<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Tenney, Charles N.</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Tenney, Charles N.</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">tenney charles n</field>
      <field name="author_text">Tenney, Charles N.</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">legacy_mss/uvaBook/tei/adelaide_case_letters/NC62b27.xml</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">The Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">The Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="full_title_text">Letter from Charles N. Tenney to "Messrs Editors", 1862 February 27</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:501587</field>
      <field name="langauge_display">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_facet">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_text">English</field>
      <field name="location_facet">Internet materials</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Letter from Charles N. Tenney to "Messrs Editors", 1862 February 27</field>
      <field name="note_display">Source copy consulted: Manuscript letter, Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection, Department of Special Collections, Alderman Library, UVa.</field>
      <field name="note_display"/>
      <field name="note_text">Source copy consulted: Manuscript letter, Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection, Department of Special Collections, Alderman Library, UVa.</field>
      <field name="note_text"/>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod02.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">UVA Library Digital Repository</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="heading_text">Letter from Charles N. Tenney to "Messrs Editors", 1862 February 27</field>
      <field name="fulltext">man more must know a word. Camp Tyler, near Paw-Paw Tunnel Feby. 27 th 1862 Messrs Editors;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Am I presuming too much if I request the insertion of a few lines, from a soldier in your valuable paper? I would like to propose a few questions, hoping some one will consider them of sufficient importance to answer.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">It is a well known fact that that no better regiment ever left the state of Ohio than the Seventh. When organized as a three year Regiment we considered ourselves as well officered, from Col= onel to Second Lieutenant. We went into the field, the hope and pride of the Reserve. Our friends were proud of having Sons and brothers in the Seventh. Has our title, that of the "Noble Seventh" been sustained? Do our friends still consider us the pride of Ohio? "How is the mighty fallen!" Where does the cause lie? The question has often been asked by different members of this Reg't. and I repeat it now. " Why are all of our best officers resigning ?" Well do we remember our loved and noble Chaplain, Mr. Brown. Need I ask why he left us? We have a Chaplain now, I suppose, but where is he? I believe he has called the Regt once . then at Patterson's Crk. I have not seen him nor heard of him since. I suppose I need not ask why Lieut. Case resigned, as his reasons have already been given in your paper. Thus two as noble men as ever lived we have been deprived of. But this is but the beginning of the end.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Scarcely has the excitement caused by the withdrawal of Lieut. Case cooled subsided, when we are informed that Adjt. DeForest has resigned, following in the same steps as Lieut Kimball of Co A. has signed , "But the end is not yet." It is whispered among those who know, that our Major Casement, has tendered his resignation and will go home in a few days. Will Col. Creighton go? Will Col Tyler go ? ( Echo answers " go ".)</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Why is it? Is there something wrong Must we lose all that we hold dear, our reputation, our honor , and remain ignorant of the cause? Will Evidently a screw is loose some where, for we certainly percieve a defect in the working of our internal machinery though-- well, we must ask " where ?"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Will not some of your numerous readers tell us where the difficulty lies? What is the cause of our losing so many of our best officers? Will Col. Tyler also resign? Echo answers ominously " resign ".</field>
      <field name="fulltext">If some one will answer these, to us, important questions, they will confer a favor upon the entire regiment.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">I am yours truly . Private .</field>
      <field name="title_display">Letter from Charles N. Tenney to "Messrs Editors", 1862 February 27</field>
      <field name="title_facet">Letter from Charles N. Tenney to "Messrs Editors", 1862 February 27</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">letter from charles n tenney to messrs editors 1862 february 27</field>
      <field name="title_text" boost="1.0">Letter from Charles N. Tenney to "Messrs Editors", 1862 February 27</field>
      <field name="year_display">1862-02-27</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1862</field>
   </doc>
</add>
