<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Case, Adelaide E.</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Case, Adelaide E.</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">case adelaide e</field>
      <field name="author_text">Case, Adelaide E.</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">legacy_mss/uvaBook/tei/adelaide_case_letters/NA61j03.xml</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">The Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">The Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="full_title_text">Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, 3 October 1861</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:501506</field>
      <field name="langauge_display">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_facet">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_text">English</field>
      <field name="location_facet">Internet materials</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, 3 October 1861</field>
      <field name="note_display">Source copy consulted: Manuscript letter, Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection, Department of Special Collections, Alderman Library, UVa.</field>
      <field name="note_display"/>
      <field name="note_text">Source copy consulted: Manuscript letter, Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection, Department of Special Collections, Alderman Library, UVa.</field>
      <field name="note_text"/>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod02.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">UVA Library Digital Repository</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="heading_text">Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, 3 October 1861</field>
      <field name="fulltext">At Home October 3 rd 1861 Dear Charlie</field>
      <field name="fulltext">I have heard gentlemen make the remark that when ladies began to write with a lead pencil to them, they guessed she wished to discontinue their correspondence But when you receive this, written with a pencil and on such paper I imagine that you will think worse than that, but do not harbor the thought for one instan dear Charlie that my feelings are such for indeed they are not I have no other paper, and my pens have all “got poor” therefore you will excuse this will you not? for I thought it necessary to write immediately as Capt. Aspen is in Warren and I do not know as I will get a chance to send again, nor do I know when he returns to war. Where are you to day are you engaged in some bloody battle or are you reposing in security in your tent or on some bed of sickness. How often my thoughts thoughts been with you to day There seems to be a presentiment of evil hovering round me, and my thoughts are with Hal and yourself, Can it be that you are in danger and some rebel strike — God forbid . I must dispel such thoughts. But would that I were near you. then I could feel that let come what might I would know all. I have a sad and gloomy spirit to day not much like the gay and joyous Addie that Hal used to tell about but last eve I was to a sewing bee for the soldiers. and I caused a strange feeling to thrill through me which is hard to dispel</field>
      <field name="fulltext">What a beautiful evening, the sun has just sunk beneath the western horizon and the day is gently falling as if shedding silent tears over the green robed earth. The pretty feathered warblers have retired to rest and the stealing twilight finds me seated at my window scribbling away as fast as my poor tallent and ability will admit Dora has just left she and I miss my light hearted joyous friend very much indeed. We have been very busy completing some triffling work which you will see when you receive this. It consists of some bachelor needle books, She has made one for one of her friends in the army and I for one of mine. will you accep it dear Charlie, as a slight testimony of my friendship and in honor of the cause in which you are engaged? I know it is but a trifle but perhaps you will make it useful I was in hopes that you would come home so that I could deliver it in person but I have looked so long in vain that I will now send it with Capt, Aspen I do hope that Hal will come home soon for I wish to see him very much Do not fail to accompany him when he comes for I do not relish disappointment in anticipated pleasure Tell Hal that two weeks have passed since we received a letter from him. If I had not heard from you in less time than that I should feel quite anxious But I must close</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Please excuse all mistakes Write soon and often and oblige your friend Addie</field>
      <field name="title_display">Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, 3 October 1861</field>
      <field name="title_facet">Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, 3 October 1861</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">letter from adelaide e case to charles n tenney 3 october 1861</field>
      <field name="title_text" boost="1.0">Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, 3 October 1861</field>
      <field name="year_display">1861-10-03</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1861</field>
   </doc>
</add>
