<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">James Booker</field>
      <field name="author_facet">James Booker</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">james booker</field>
      <field name="author_text">James Booker</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">legacy_mss/uvaBook/tei/booker_letters/Boo2c15.xml</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="full_title_text">Letter to Chloe Unity Blair [a machine-readable transcription]</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:501638</field>
      <field name="langauge_display">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_facet">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_text">English</field>
      <field name="location_facet">Internet materials</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Letter to Chloe Unity Blair [a machine-readable transcription]</field>
      <field name="note_display">Manuscript copy consulted: 11237</field>
      <field name="note_display">James and John Booker tend to use commas instead of periods to end a sentence. In the modernized version of this letter, we have regularized the punctuation in unambiguous cases.</field>
      <field name="note_text">Manuscript copy consulted: 11237</field>
      <field name="note_text">James and John Booker tend to use commas instead of periods to end a sentence. In the modernized version of this letter, we have regularized the punctuation in unambiguous cases.</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod02.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">UVA Library Digital Repository</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="fulltext">24-bit color, 400 dpi</field>
      <field name="heading_text">1862-03-15</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Greaner Hospital Richmond Va March the, 15, 1862 Dear Cousin</field>
      <field name="fulltext">I havent the least doubt but what you th think that I have for gotten you if so, I can assure you that it is not so, I have nig lected answering your letters for some time tho I think I can offer good excuses for so doing,</field>
      <field name="fulltext">I was so unwell when I got the letters that I was not able to write, I was sick about three weeks in camp before I was sent to the Hospital [1] I was mending when I left camp and I have improved very fast sence I have bin here, [2] I bin here too week to marrow, I would have writen to you soon after I got here tho I expected to go home soon and thought it un nessary to write as I was going soon my self, after I got here thay told me that I would have to get a furlow from my Col [3] be fore I cud go, the Regiment has moved sence I left them and I dont know whare thay are nor thay dont know whare I am, so it s is doubtful about my geting home soon, [4] you must write to me as soon as you get this and let me know whether you know whare the Regiment is or not,</field>
      <field name="fulltext">our fair is very rough here far sick folks I see some of my acquantance nearly every day coming down on the Cars</field>
      <field name="fulltext">all of the recruits and those that have bin home on furlows and on thar way back to the Regiment, have to wait here until thay hear whare the Regiment is, I have no news worth writeing so I will close write to me soon and gave me all the news, Direct your letters to Greaners Hospital in care of surg R, G, Banks</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Nothing more but remain your affectionate Cousin until Death James Booker to Miss C, U, Blair</field>
      <field name="title_display">James Booker, in Greaner Hospital, Richmond, Virginia to Chloe Unity Blair</field>
      <field name="title_facet">James Booker, in Greaner Hospital, Richmond, Virginia to Chloe Unity Blair</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">letter to chloe unity blair a machine readable transcription</field>
      <field name="title_text" boost="1.0">James Booker, in Greaner Hospital, Richmond, Virginia to Chloe Unity Blair</field>
      <field name="year_display">1862-03-15</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1862</field>
   </doc>
</add>