<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">William Francis Brand</field>
      <field name="author_facet">William Francis Brand</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">william francis brand</field>
      <field name="author_text">William Francis Brand</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">legacy_mss/uvaBook/tei/brand_letters/B671201.xml</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">University of Virginia Civil War Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">University of Virginia Civil War Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="full_title_text">Brand Civil War Collection: Letter from William Francis Brand to Amanda Catherine Armentrout, 1867 December 01</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:501690</field>
      <field name="langauge_display">English </field>
      <field name="langauge_facet">English </field>
      <field name="langauge_text">English </field>
      <field name="location_facet">Internet materials</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Brand Civil War Collection: Letter from William Francis Brand to Amanda Catherine Armentrout, 1867 December 01</field>
      <field name="note_display">Source copy consulted: MSS 11332, Special Collections, Alderman Library, University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="note_display"/>
      <field name="note_text">Source copy consulted: MSS 11332, Special Collections, Alderman Library, University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="note_text"/>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod02.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">UVA Library Digital Repository</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="heading_text">Letter from William Francis Brand to Amanda Catherine Armentrout Brand, December 01, 1867</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Alone Mills Dec. 1 st My dear wife</field>
      <field name="fulltext">As I expect to go to Lexington tomorrow morning if noting occures to detain me. I have been very well since I parted with you, &amp; very busy grinding up to late last night. I hope that I may have more leasure this week as I have a good eal to do. I intend to try &amp; sell Dixie tomorrow I w road her to Preac hing this eavning &amp; she came very near running away with me. I pricked up &amp; old bridle that had no curb. I am writing at the house &amp; Rash &amp; Marion are making so much fuſs that I can not keep my mind on any subject more than a second. thare was a letter here to Mrs Willie B wich I took the privalige of opening. it was from Cous Joe I will sende it with this note I hope that it may find you enjoying good health. I have often though about your pains. I hope you do not suffer any more with them. I have so much to do this week that I think it will be imposible for me to get down before Saturday week. The time will appear very long to me I am sure. But it will soon run round as I have a good eal to attend to. I hope my darling will try &amp; be hapy cheerfull &amp; sadisfied. oh how often I think of a sigh that escaped you while I was down last. I hope &amp; pray that some day I may be able to command any thing you desire. I will close by asking God to protect us from all harm I will write again &amp; a longer letter before I come down. I received a letter from Bro C he is well &amp; sent his love to you I will look for a letter in a day or two</field>
      <field name="fulltext">nothing more but remain your loving husband, Willie</field>
      <field name="title_display">Brand Civil War Collection: Letter from William Francis Brand to Amanda Catherine Armentrout, 1867 December 01</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">brand civil war collection: letter from william francis brand to amanda catherine armentrout, 1867 december 01</field>
      <field name="title_facet">Brand Civil War Collection: Letter from William Francis Brand to Amanda Catherine Armentrout, 1867 December 01</field>
      <field name="title_text" boost="1.0">Brand Civil War Collection: Letter from William Francis Brand to Amanda Catherine Armentrout, 1867 December 01</field>
      <field name="year_display">1867-12-01</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1867</field>
   </doc>
</add>
