<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Thad Donely</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Thad Donely</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">thad donely</field>
      <field name="author_text">Thad Donely</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">legacy_mss/uvaBook/tei/bitner_letters/BitDon2.xml</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Henry Bitner Letters Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Henry Bitner letters</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Bitner collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Letters written to Henry A. Bitner</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="full_title_text">Letter to Henry A. Bitner</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:501617</field>
      <field name="langauge_display">English </field>
      <field name="langauge_facet">English </field>
      <field name="langauge_text">English </field>
      <field name="location_facet">Internet materials</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Letter to Henry A. Bitner</field>
      <field name="note_display">Manuscript copy consulted: University of Virginia, Alderman Library, Special Collections MSS 11395</field>
      <field name="note_display">Two postscripts appear in the upper margins of Donely's letter; the first is written upside down on page 3, and the second is written upside down on page 4. To make the text as coherent as possible, we have included these postscripts at the end of the letter.</field>
      <field name="note_text">Manuscript copy consulted: University of Virginia, Alderman Library, Special Collections MSS 11395</field>
      <field name="note_text">Two postscripts appear in the upper margins of Donely's letter; the first is written upside down on page 3, and the second is written upside down on page 4. To make the text as coherent as possible, we have included these postscripts at the end of the letter.</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod02.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora</field>
      <field name="series_title_display">Henry Bitner letters</field>
      <field name="series_title_display">Bitner collection</field>
      <field name="series_title_display">Letters written to Henry A. Bitner</field>
      <field name="series_title_facet">Henry Bitner letters</field>
      <field name="series_title_facet">Bitner collection</field>
      <field name="series_title_facet">Letters written to Henry A. Bitner</field>
      <field name="series_title_text">Henry Bitner letters</field>
      <field name="series_title_text">Bitner collection</field>
      <field name="series_title_text">Letters written to Henry A. Bitner</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">UVA Library Digital Repository</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="fulltext">72 dpi; 24-bit color</field>
      <field name="heading_text">1863-01-07</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Camp near Falmouth, Va Jan. 7 1863 Dear Brother</field>
      <field name="fulltext">I take this oppertunity to write you a few to let you no that I am well and get along well their is not sine of a move at this time the weather here has been fine. yesterday their was some rain but did last long. I received John letter a few Days ago I though I was not going to get any word from home and was much peased to here and was much obliged to John for for the stamp and sheat of paper I cant neathe paper or stamp here and I want you to write and send them to me accationaly I can by paper at 2 cents a sheat I think I can't stand them prices well their was some talk a few days ago of our being sent back to Washington but I think their is nothing of it if whe are moved it will be towards the river it takes a good Deal of figering to live here as the feed is hard to eat but by taking cair in the cooking whe still make it go down. If I had som of the apples that are at home I would have some fine dishes of saws and apple fliters I have been very hungry since I have been here by time but I think I will be able to see it through as their is but about 3 &amp; 1/2 months illeg. has just been here and say I shall tell you he is will but times are tuff and sends his respects to all is a good thing the health of the company is good thare have been some of thoes sent to the hospital that have been sent on here are going at convalesant camp at Alaxandria. I hope they will stay their as the hardships is hard to get through and their is more in the company that wants to go home . I suppose you have been enjoying yoursalf fine but if their is no more snow their than their is here the sleigh wont mount to much this Regt is very much cut Down at prisant their is but 315 men in it my paper is most full and I must stop I got some Tobacco seed whe I was out in picket the other Day I will send it in this and I want you tents which are some protection but the weather has been fine I think I never saw such good weather this time a year Their was some talk that in camp that this Brigade would be sent back but their has been nothing said the last few days so I dont think their is much in it I wish whe would go back a piece for their would be some chance to By something to eat their is no chance to get any thing here neathe paper nor postage stamps as you will see this is ritten on an old piece of copy book that was picked up [illeg.] main and if I have to maile this and leave you the postage to pay you must excuse me or else I [illeg.] change our position Their is several that I would like to write to if I had the paper their is no sutlers supplies alowed to be shiped as the armies is so large that it require all the transportation the government can raise to bring up supplys their is no much chance for a forward move from here as the Rebels seam to bee very well Situated on the other side of the the Rappahanook is but a Small river some paces it is so shalow that it is easely forded the pickets talk to each other from the banks of the stream their is no firing amonkst the pickets but a few evenings they wer Driven in which put the officers on their gard I think I will stop writing about the armie and tell you that what part of Virginia I have seen it looks offel hard it is nothing but a lot of hill and the poorist land I have most ever seen their is a great deal of this scruby Pine and seder grows here most all the farms are vacated the inhabitants gon south with the exception of some few Negros that are scatered about I wish I who could have been at home to have tended singing the last three evenings as they have been fine and I suppose you had a good time I want you to write to me and give me all the new and let me no how the singing is going geting along I wrote to David Early some time ago have not herd from him yet my paper is most full my best Respects to your Parents and all that inquire and I Remain</field>
      <field name="fulltext">yours Truly Thad Donely Excus all mistake as it is the best I can do under the surcumstances Dont forget to give me a hole sheet full of news [1] Adres Washington D.C. 130 Regt Co D PV [2]</field>
      <field name="title_display">Letter to Henry A. Bitner</field>
      <field name="title_facet">Letter to Henry A. Bitner</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">letter to henry a bitner</field>
      <field name="title_text" boost="1.0">Letter to Henry A. Bitner</field>
      <field name="year_display">1863-01-07</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1863</field>
   </doc>
</add>
