<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">John P. Lightner</field>
      <field name="author_facet">John P. Lightner</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">john p lightner</field>
      <field name="author_text">John P. Lightner</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">legacy_mss/uvaBook/tei/brand_letters/A9615.xml</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">University of Virginia Civil War Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">University of Virginia Civil War Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="full_title_text">John P. Lightner to Kate Armentrout, December 15, 1860</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:502777</field>
      <field name="langauge_display">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_facet">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_text">English</field>
      <field name="location_facet">Internet materials</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">John P. Lightner to Kate Armentrout, December 15, 1860</field>
      <field name="note_display">Source copy consulted: William Brand Papers, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="note_display"/>
      <field name="note_text">Source copy consulted: William Brand Papers, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="note_text"/>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod02.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">UVA Library Digital Repository</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="heading_text">Dec. 15 th , 1860</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Dec. 15 th , 1860 Washington College Dear Friend;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">I hope you have not become impatient, as I have been somewhat remiss in not answering your very welcomed epistle.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">I was very glad to receive a letter from you so replete, with good sentiments, &amp; also exemplary.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">I suppose you hail the new world this morning, as well as myself. I was rather surprised, when I saw the earth robed in white. I am afraid it will blast my hopes, for I anticipated a fine time on Christmas, if I get out of this prison. I expect to leave here next Saturday or whip some of the Profs. as you know I am a great fighting character speaking ironically. I have not been very well for the last week or two. I had a very bad cold, but I think so much about Christmas, I believe it has nearly left me. I think leap year must be doing its duty, &amp; its whole duty, from the number of weddings you have attended, or rather the number of marriages that have taken place, in your immediate vicinity. I was rather surprised when you told me of J. Rubush's marriage. I hope they will have a happy sail on the Sea of life. Miss R.P. is not married yet. I think the report must have been without foundation. I would be a great looking somebody to get married would'nt I? Any one that is so diffident as I am, should never think of such a thing.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">I ask pardon for inviting you to the fair &amp; not telling you when it was to be. It was certainly oversight in me, but I hope you will grant my request.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Miss R.P. was not there very unfortunately, but there were some others present, who ich pleased me very much, but I was so bashful , I did not do more than speak to them.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">I have never been a visiting but once, since I returned to college, &amp; then I thought every body was looking at me.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">I intended going a visiting to night, but the snow, has broken my arrangements.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">How is cousin S.P. getting along at C.C. School. I suppose you have a singing-school there, this winter. I used to have some fine times at that beloved spot, but I declare I don't have them here. But one year longer, then I'll be through, after this I expect to go South &amp; whip S.C. back into the Union. I am opposed to Disunion in lots. I have been wishing all day for a good sleigh. I saw one or two pass by my window. I thank you for ever wishing me success, if I should, by the grace of God, enter upon the mission I spoke to you of, which I wished to be kept secret, for special reason.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">We have a very good band of students this year, no drinking which was as common last year, as it well could be.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Well you must excuse me for this short &amp; badly written letter. I beg to be excused for tardiness in writing. I'm glad to hear that Nicholas is improving so fast.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">I remain your Friend, J.P.L. I'll send you a ticket to the Anniversary of our Society if I can get one.</field>
      <field name="title_display">John P. Lightner to Kate Armentrout, December 15, 1860</field>
      <field name="title_facet">John P. Lightner to Kate Armentrout, December 15, 1860</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">john p lightner to kate armentrout december 15 1860</field>
      <field name="title_text" boost="1.0">John P. Lightner to Kate Armentrout, December 15, 1860</field>
      <field name="year_display">1860-12-15</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1860</field>
   </doc>
</add>
