<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">William Francis Brand</field>
      <field name="author_facet">William Francis Brand</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">william francis brand</field>
      <field name="author_text">William Francis Brand</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">legacy_mss/uvaBook/tei/brand_letters/B630407.xml</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">University of Virginia Civil War Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">University of Virginia Civil War Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="full_title_text">Brand Civil War Collection: Letter from William Francis Brand to Amanda Catherine Armentrout, 1863 April 7</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:501664</field>
      <field name="langauge_display">English </field>
      <field name="langauge_facet">English </field>
      <field name="langauge_text">English </field>
      <field name="location_facet">Internet materials</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Brand Civil War Collection: Letter from William Francis Brand to Amanda Catherine Armentrout, 1863 April 7</field>
      <field name="note_display">Source copy consulted: MSS 11332, Special Collections, Alderman Library, University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="note_display"/>
      <field name="note_text">Source copy consulted: MSS 11332, Special Collections, Alderman Library, University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="note_text"/>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod02.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">UVA Library Digital Repository</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="heading_text">Letter from William Francis Brand to Amanda Catherine Armentrout, April 7, 1863</field>
      <field name="fulltext">At Home April 7th 1863 Dear Friend</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Truly time has seen many days paſs &amp; your letter remained unanswered, I have procrastinated untill I am aschamed to seat my self to write eaven to the kindest of friends. One request I will ask of you that is to forgive &amp; forget, I intended writing before I left camp. But after I had a chance for a furlough I thought I would wait untill I got home &amp; then I might come down, But alas it seems that I can never get away from home, I have had very bad health ever since I came home. Some days I suffer with chills &amp; fevers with violent headeache &amp; pains in my limbs. Father is very ill with the mumps, though I think he is getting better, It will be my time to have them next, as I never had them, I have had chances to have taken them before,Pro p b erably I may miſs them this time, I wou,nt care if I ware so fortunate Well I reckon you think, “What have I been doing towards enjoying myself” since I came home, The blues have been my most constant companion I declair I never was as lonesome in my life Time seems to stand still on her wheels, Tom is busy blowing so if I wanted to go anywhare I have no horse to wride. I formed a slight acquaintance with your friend Fannie Seems to be a very nice girl, Kind I think would make a noble coquet, But you must not tell her that I ever thought such a thing, well you know that it is natural for self willed man to form an opinion of the fairer sext on first sight. Well I do not know what to write to interrest you I promist to answer the questions that I asked in my last letter in ref erence to your Cousin Lizzie, But I will wait hoping that I may see you before long. Then I can answer you verbaly, I know that I can sadisfy you in that way better than by writing I suppose you have already form some idea of my reason for asking you I hope that I may soon get my health &amp; be able to help work some on the farm as we will be late with the spring crop I suppose you ware surprised to hear of me coming home as you wrote that I wou'nt come home for six months. Thare if I could get a furlough, Tharefore do'nt suppose you are very ancious to see me, But for my part I never was as ancious to see you in my life Though you may think my action s do not prove it, Well you must recolect my health &amp; more I have no way of getting about, Dispair not I will be down ear long, And then my long absence will make it a hapier meet- ing, Often you are by my side in my nightly dreams them it seemes that I am happy, But I wake up &amp; find it all delusion I must bring this uninterres ing letter to a close I hope this may find you enjoying your usual good health if I have written anything in this letter to mar your feeling your parden I crave</field>
      <field name="fulltext">From your attached friend. (Willie-</field>
      <field name="title_display">Brand Civil War Collection: Letter from William Francis Brand to Amanda Catherine Armentrout, 1863 April 7</field>
      <field name="title_facet">Brand Civil War Collection: Letter from William Francis Brand to Amanda Catherine Armentrout, 1863 April 7</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">brand civil war collection letter from william francis brand to amanda catherine armentrout 1863 april 7</field>
      <field name="title_text" boost="1.0">Brand Civil War Collection: Letter from William Francis Brand to Amanda Catherine Armentrout, 1863 April 7</field>
      <field name="year_display">1863-04-07</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1863</field>
   </doc>
</add>
