<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Mark Twain, pseud. Samuel Langhorne Clemens</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Mark Twain, pseud. Samuel Langhorne Clemens</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">mark twain pseud samuel langhorne clemens</field>
      <field name="author_text">Mark Twain, pseud. Samuel Langhorne Clemens</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">legacy_mss/uvaBook/tei/misc/TwaTrue.xml</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="full_title_text">A True Story, Repeated Word for Word as I Heard It [a machine-readable transcription]</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:501898</field>
      <field name="langauge_display">English 
</field>
      <field name="langauge_facet">English 
</field>
      <field name="langauge_text">English 
</field>
      <field name="location_facet">Internet materials</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">A True Story, Repeated Word for Word as I Heard It [a machine-readable transcription]</field>
      <field name="note_display">Print copy consulted: Original manuscript in Special Collections, University of Virginia Library: Papers of Mark Twain 1862-1946, bulk 1872-1910; 6314; AMs 1874.</field>
      <field name="note_display">First published in the Atlantic Monthly, November, 1874.</field>
      <field name="note_text">Print copy consulted: Original manuscript in Special Collections, University of Virginia Library: Papers of Mark Twain 1862-1946, bulk 1872-1910; 6314; AMs 1874.</field>
      <field name="note_text">First published in the Atlantic Monthly, November, 1874.</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod02.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">UVA Library Digital Repository</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="heading_text">A Perfectly A True Story, re- peated word for word as I heard it.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">—</field>
      <field name="fulltext">It was summer time, &amp; twilight. We were sitting on the porch of the farm-house, on the summit of the hill, &amp; &amp; "Aunt Rachel" was sit- ting respectfully below our level , on the steps, —for she was our servant, &amp; colored. She was of mighty frame &amp; stature; she was sixty years old, but her eye was undimmed ∧ her strength unabated. She was a cheerful, hearty soul, &amp; it was no more trouble for her to laugh than it is for a bird to sing. She was under fire, now, as usual when the day was done. That is to say, she was being chaffed without mercy, and was enjoying it. She would let off peal after peal of laughter, &amp; then sit with her face in her hands &amp; shake with throes of enjoyment which she could no longer get breath enough to express. At such a moment as this a thought happened to occur red to me, ∧ I said:</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Aunt Rachel, how is it that you've lived sixty years &amp; never had any trouble?"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">She stopped quaking. She paused, &amp; there was a moment of still silence. She turned her face over her shoulder toward me, &amp; said, with- out even a smile in her voice:</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Misto C., is you in arnest?"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">It surprised me quite a good deal—&amp; it sobered my manner &amp; my speech, too. I said:</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Why, I thought—that is, I meant—why, you can't have had any trouble. I've never heard you sigh, and never seen your eye when there wasn't a laugh in it."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">She faced fairly around, now, &amp; was full of earnestness.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">" Has I had any trouble? Misto C., I's gwyne to tell you, den I leave it to you. I was bawn down mongst de slaves —I knows all 'bout slavery, 'cause 'case I ben one of 'em my own se l ' f. Well, sah, my ole man—dat's my husban'— he was lovin' an' kind to me— jus jist as kind as you is to yo' own wife. An' we had chil'en—seven chil'en — &amp; we loved loved dem chil'en jist de same as you loves yo' chil'en. Dey was black, but de Lord can't make no chil'en so black but what dey mother loves 'em an' wouldn't give 'em up, no, not for anything dat's in dis whole world.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">" Well, sah, I was raised in ole Fo'ginny, but my mother she was raised in Maryland; an' my souls! she was turrible when she'd git started! My lawd lan'! but she'd make de fur fly! When she'd git into dem tantrums, she d always had one word dat she said. She'd straighten herse'f up &amp; put her fists in her hips &amp; say, "I want you to understan ' d dat I ain't no houn'-dog mash; I wa'nt bawn in de mash to be fool' by trash! to be trod on by common trash! I's one o' de ole Blue Hen's Chickens, I is!"—'case you see, dat's what folks dat's bawn in Maryland calls dey- selves, an' dey's proud of it. Well dat was her word. I don't ever for- git it, becase she said it so much, an' becase she said it one day when my little Henry tore his wris', awful, a n' most busted his head, right up at the de top of his forehead, an' de niggers didn't fly aroun ' d fas' enough to 'tend to him. An' when dey talk ' ed back at her, she up an' she says, "Look-a-heah!" she says, "I want you niggers to understan' dat I wa'nt bawn in de mash to be fool' by trash!—I's one o' de ole Blue Hen's Chickens, I is!" an' den she clar' dat kitchen an' bandage' up de chile hers ' e'f. So I says dat word, too, when I's riled.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Well, bymeby my ole mistis say she's broke, an' she got to sell all de nig- gers on de place. An' when I heah dat dey gwyne to sell us all off at oction in Richmon', O de good God gracious I know what dat mean! "</field>
      <field name="fulltext">[Aunt Rachel had gradually risen, while she warmed to her sub- ject, &amp; now she towered above us, huge ∧ black against the stars.]</field>
      <field name="fulltext">" Dey put chains on us an' put us on a stan' as high as dis poach— twenty foot high—an all de people stood a- roun' —crowds an crowds. An' dey'd come up dah an' 'zamine look at us all roun ' d , an' squeeze our arm, an' make us git up an' walk, an' den say, "Dis one too ole," or "Dis one lame," or "Dis one don't 'mount to much." An' dey sole my ole man, an' took him away, an' dey begin to sell my chil'en an' take dem away, an' I begin to cry; an' de man say "Shet up yo' darn blubberins," an hit me on de mouf wid his han'. An' when de las' one was gone but my little Henry, I grab ' bed him clos e t up to my breas', so, an' I ris up an' says, "You shan't take him a- way !" I says; "I'll kill de man dat tetches him!" I says. But my little Henry whis- per an' say, "I gy gwyne to run away, an' den I work an' buy yo' freedom." O, bless de chile, it mos' broke my heart, he so he always so good. But dey got him— dey got him, de men did—but I took &amp; tear de cloes most de cloes mos' off of 'em an' beat 'em over de head wid my chain; an' dey give it to me , too, but I didn't min d e mine dat.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">" Well, dah was my ole man gone, an' all my chil'en , — all my seven chil'en—an' six of 'em I hain't set eyes on agin to dis day , — an' dats twenty- two year s ago las' Easter. De man dat bought me b'long ' ed in Norfolk Newbern, an' he took me dah. Well, bymeby de years roll on ∧ de an' de waw come. My marster he was a Confedrit Colonel, an' I was his family's cook. So when de Unions took dat town, dey all run away an' lef' me all by myse l ' f wid de other niggers in dat mon'sus big house. So de big Union officers move in dah an' dey ask me would I cook for dem , . for money. "Lord bless you," says I, "dat's what s I's for ."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">" Dey wa' nt nt no small- fry officers, mine you, dey was de biggest dey is; an' de way dey made dem so g j ers mosey roun'! Well I thinks De Gen'l he tole me to boss dat kitchen; an' he say s , ' i f anybody come s meddlin' wid you, you jist come an tell me; make 'em walk chalk; don't you be afeard, ' he say, ' you's 'mong frens, now.'</field>
      <field name="fulltext">¶ Well, I thinks to myself, if my little Henry ever got an got a chance to run away, he'd ma d k e to de Norf, o'course. So one day I comes in dah whah de big officers was, in de parlor, an' I drops a kurtchy, so, an' I says, to de Gen'l, says I, up an' tole 'em 'bout my Henry, dey a listenin' to my troubles jus jist de same as if I was white folks; ; an' I says, "What I come for is becase dat if he got away &amp; got up Norf whah you gemmen comes from, you might a seen him, maybe, ∧ an' could tell me so as I could fine him agin; he was very little, an' he had a sk-yar on his lef' wris', an' at de top of his forehead." Den dey look mournful, &amp; de Gen'l say, "How long sence you los' him him?" an' I say "Thirteen year." Den de Gen'l say, "He wouldn't be little no mo', now—he's a man!"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">" [ I never thought o o' dat befor befo'! He was only dat little feller to me , yit. I never thought 'bout him growin' up an' bein' big. But I see it den. None o' de gemmen had run acrost him, so dey couldn't do nothin' for me. ¶ But all dat time, do' I didn't know it, my Henry was run off to de Norf, years &amp; years, an' he was a barber, too, an' worked for hisse'f. An ' d bymeby when de waw come, he ups an' he says, "I's done barberin," he says; "I's gwyne to fine my ole mammy, less'n she's dead." So he sole out an' went to whah dey was re- cruitin', an' hired hisse'f out to de Colonel for his servant; an' den he went all froo de battles everywhah, huntin' for his ole mammy; yes in- deedy, he'd hire to fust one officer an' den an- other, tell he'd ransacked de whole Souf—but you see I didn't know nuffin' 'bout dis . How could I know it. was I gwyne to know it?</field>
      <field name="fulltext">" Well, one night, we had a big sojer ball— de sojers dah at New- bern was always havin' balls an' carryin' on. Dey had 'em in my kitch- en, heaps o' times, 'case it was so big. Mine you, I didn't I was down on sich doins; becase my place was wid de officers, an' it rasp' me to have dem common sojers cavortin' roun' my kitchen like dat. But I all always stood aroun' an' kep' things straight, I did; an' some- times dey'd git my dander up, an' den I'd make 'em clar dat kitchen, mine I tell you!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">" Well, one night—it was a Friday night d —dey comes a whole plattoon fr f'm a nigger ridgment dat was on guard at de house—de house was headquarters, you know—an' den I was jist a bilin'! Mad? Well honey I was jist a boomin'! I swelled aroun', an' swelled aroun',—I jist was a itchin' for 'em to do somefin' for to start me. An' dey was a waltzin' an' a dan- cin'! — my! but dey was havin' a time!—an' I jist a swellin' an' a swellin' up! Pooty soon, 'long comes sich a de spruce st young nigger a-sailin' down de room wid a yaller wench roun' de wais'; an' roun' an' roun' an' roun' dey went, enough 'nuff to make a body drunk to look at 'em; an' when dey got abreas' o' me, dey went to kin' o' balan- cin' aroun', fust on one leg an' den on tother, an' smilin' at my big red turban, an' makin' fun', an' I ups an' says, " Git along wid you!— rub- bage!" De young man's face kin' o' changed, all of a sudden, for 'bout a second, but den he went to smilin' agin same as he was befo'. Well, 'bout dis time, in comes some niggers dat played mu- sic an' b'long' to de ban', an dey never could git along widout puttin' on airs. An' de very fust air dey put on dat night, I lit into 'em! Dey laughed, an' dat made me wuss. De res' o' de niggers got to laughin ' g , an' den my soul alive but I was hot! My eye was jist a blazin ' g ! I jist straight- ened myself up, so , — jist as I am is now , — plum to de ceilin', mos' , — an' I digs my fists into my hips, an' I says, " Look-a- heah !" I says, "I want you niggers to understan' dat I ain't no houn' dat I wa'nt bawn in de mash to be fool' dog mash to be trod on by cousins o by trash by trash! I's one o' de ole Blue Hen's Chickens, I is!" — an' den I see dat young man stan' a-starin' an' stiff, like lookin' kin' o' up at de ceilin' like he fogot somefin', an' couldn't 'member it no mo'. Well , I jist march' on dem niggers , —so, — lookin ' g like a Gen'l , a goin into battle— an' dey jist cave' away befo' me an' out at de do'. An' as dis young man was a goin' went out, I heah him say to another nig- ger, "Jim," he says, "you go 'long an' tell de Cap'n I be on han' 'bout eight o'clock in de mawnin'; dey's somefin on my mine," he says; "I don't sleep no mo' dis night. ' You go 'long," he says, "an' leave me by my own se'f."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">" Dis was 'bout one o'clock in de mawnin'. Well, 'bout seven I was up an' on han', gittin' de officers' breakfast. I was a - stoopin' down by de stove , —jist so , — same as if yo' foot was de stove , —an' I'd opened de stove do' wid my right han',—so, pushin' it back, jist as I pushes yo' foot , —an' I'd jist got de pan o' hot biscuits in my han' an' was 'bout to raise up, when I see a black face come aroun' under my mine, an' de eyes a - lookin' up into mine, jist as I' s m a lookin' up clost under yo' face now ; — an' I jist stopped right dah , an' never budged! — jist gazed, an' gazed, — so ; — an' de pan begin to tremble, an' all of a sudden I knowed! De pan drop' on de flo' an' I grab his lef' han' an' shove back his sleeve , —jist so, as I' s m doin' to you , —an' den I went goes for his forehead an' push de hair back , — so , — an' "Boy!" I says, "if you ain't my Henry, what is you doin' wid dis welt on yo' wris' an' dat sk-yar on yo' forehead! — d e Lord God of ob Heaven be praise', I got my own agin!"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"O, no, Mr. C., I ain't had no trouble. An' no joy! "</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Mark Twain.</field>
      <field name="title_display">A True Story, Repeated Word for Word as I Heard It</field>
      <field name="title_facet">A True Story, Repeated Word for Word as I Heard It</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">true story repeated word for word as i heard it a machine readable transcription</field>
      <field name="title_text" boost="1.0">A True Story, Repeated Word for Word as I Heard It</field>
      <field name="year_display">1874</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1874</field>
   </doc>
</add>