<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">James Carmichael</field>
      <field name="author_facet">James Carmichael</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">james carmichael</field>
      <field name="author_text">James Carmichael</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">legacy_mss/uvaBook/tei/misc/Fev1819.xml</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="editor_display">Health Sciences Center, University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="editor_display">Health Science Center</field>
      <field name="editor_text">Health Sciences Center, University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="editor_text">Health Science Center</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="full_title_text">Selected Papers of Dr. James Carmichael of Fredericksburg, Va., 1819</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:501809</field>
      <field name="langauge_display">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_facet">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_text">English</field>
      <field name="location_facet">Internet materials</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Selected Papers of Dr. James Carmichael of Fredericksburg, Va., 1819</field>
      <field name="note_display">Source copy consulted: Dr. James Carmichael, Papers, 1816-1830 and n.d., Accession #11373, Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville, VA 22903.</field>
      <field name="note_text">Source copy consulted: Dr. James Carmichael, Papers, 1816-1830 and n.d., Accession #11373, Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville, VA 22903.</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod02.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">UVA Library Digital Repository</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Letter, from Wethers Waller to Gentlemen, February 2, 1819 Aquia 2nd Feb.y 1819 Gentlemen My powders will all be used to morrow evening; please furnish me with a further supply. I think I am gradually mending, my right ancle in which I had violent pain some time since has swoled very much the last two or three days, which prevents me from walking. I hope when the winter breaks I shall be able [ride out]; as yet I have not been down [there] Respectfully y.obliged Servant Wethers Waller Mess.rs Carmichael &amp;Son Fredericksb.g</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Letter, from Dr. James Carmichal to Thomas Wright, March 7, 1819 [23 January 1822] 7 March 1819 [?] Dr James Carmichal To Thos Wright for 1 P Boots — $9..00 July 2th 1820 to bottoming boots — 2..50 $11..50 23 January 1822 paid [?] Dr. James Carmichael $9.00 $52.00 $10.00 B[ ] 7.75 Shop Balance $32.25</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Letter, from Lau. Battaile to Gentlemen, March 31, 1819 Prospect Hill March 31st. 1819 Gentlemen, Soon after Dr. Brown left us we ap -plied the blister which drew remarkably well But I am sorry to inform you that our little boy is worse. He appeared to grow worse last night before supper. His fever rose, he breathed hard, and complained of pain in his belly, or breast -He has so continued ever since and I am now much alarmed at his situation -You will please send by the bearer such Medicine as you think necessary &amp; you will oblige yr. ob.t hum: Ser.t Lau: Battaile</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Letter, from Cary Selden to Doctor [?], November 2, 1819 Belle Plain 2nd Nov. 1819 Dr. Sir Riding down here to see Mr. Wishart I found him confined to his Bed. He express'd some desire to send for you if he thought you would come, I observed that I had no doubt but that you would ride out and see him; and as he can not write himself, (at Mrs. Wisharts desire) I have to request you would ride and see him today if possible — I am Dr. yrs very respectfully Cary Selden</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Letter, from [?]Taliaferro to [?], December 23, 1819 Doct.r Carmichael will do me the favor to examine the Girl who will hand him this &amp; do for her what he may deem proper, her knee has been swelled [word effaced] &amp; much inflamed &amp; very painful for some time, &amp; has within a few days assumed a hardness which did not attend the case before The case has been treated as the Rheumatism,— Her face has sometimes swelled.— It may not be improper to add that she is 15 years of age &amp; has not as yet I am informd had the monthly, [word effaced] disease incidental to women [?] Taliaferro 23.d Dec.er 1819</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Letter, from James Mitchell to Doctor [?], December 25, 1819 [ 25 December 1819 ] Dear Sir Mrs. Mitchell was attacked with a voilent pain in her left Breast about 4 weeks agoe. So much that She was confined to bed for 24 hours — it at first Seemd to be a hard lump but Soon went away but the breast Seemd much biger than the other -at the comencement of this attack She had a Severe ague afterwards a voilent fever &amp; Sever pain in her head &amp; back Since that time -it has been troublesome at times untill yeasterday when She was again attacked voilently it is imposable for me to Describe her Situation if you would come up with the bearer of this I Shall be glad if not try if you can Send Something that will give her Some Relif — the pain at this time in her Br -east is so Severe that She cannot move her body I am Dear Sir your obdt Jas Mitchill Decr 25 1819</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Letter, from Wethers Waller to Doctor Carmichael, December 28, 1819 Aquia 28th December 1819 Doct. Carmichael Sir I am in want of Some more of the tincture of Bark tincture of Gum goacum and the ointment that I am now using. I am no better than when I last wrote you and am in hopes that you will have it in your power to See me in a few days. Please Send the articles if you think it necessary that I should continue to take them I remain yours &amp;c Wethers Waller</field>
      <field name="title_display">Selected Papers of Dr. James Carmichael of Fredericksburg, Va., 1819</field>
      <field name="title_facet">Selected Papers of Dr. James Carmichael of Fredericksburg, Va., 1819</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">selected papers of dr james carmichael of fredericksburg va 1819</field>
      <field name="title_text" boost="1.0">Selected Papers of Dr. James Carmichael of Fredericksburg, Va., 1819</field>
      <field name="year_display">1819</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1819</field>
   </doc>
</add>