<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Andrew Brooks</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Andrew Brooks</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">andrew brooks</field>
      <field name="author_text">Andrew Brooks</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">legacy_mss/uvaBook/tei/brooks_letters/Bro1e28.xml</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="full_title_text">Letter to James Brooks</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:501699</field>
      <field name="langauge_display">English
</field>
      <field name="langauge_facet">English
</field>
      <field name="langauge_text">English
</field>
      <field name="location_facet">Internet materials</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Letter to James Brooks</field>
      <field name="note_display">Manuscript copy consulted: Private collection of Andrew Brooks Booker, Waynesboro Va.</field>
      <field name="note_display"/>
      <field name="note_text">Manuscript copy consulted: Private collection of Andrew Brooks Booker, Waynesboro Va.</field>
      <field name="note_text"/>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod02.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">UVA Library Digital Repository</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="fulltext">8 bit color; 150 dpi</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Manuscript Civil War letter, from Andrew Brooks to James Brooks, dated May 28, 1861. Image of recto contains pages 1 and 4, originally folded in half.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Manuscript Civil War letter, from Andrew Brooks to James Brooks, dated May 28, 1861. Image of verso contains pages 2 and 3, originally folded in half.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Lexington May 28, 1861 Dear Father,</field>
      <field name="fulltext">When I wrote home last week I believed that our company would not be ordered out, but now we think we will be.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Two or three weeks ago, we determined to write to the Governor (before we would get coats) to know whether he would order us out or not. After waiting two weeks, Mr. Jas Davidson of this place came home from Richmond , bringing us word that the Governor would not call us out under any circumstances. [1] Saturday night Capt. Nelson received an official answer from S. Rafael French , Aid de Camp to the Governor requiring him to ascertain the consent of the parents of the boys and to report to the Governor , and he would then "decide the matter." By the same mail Prof. White received a letter from Greenlee Davidson (son of the above and clerk in the Executive department) telling him to ascertain the consent of the parents of the boys, and that the Governor "would order us to Harpers Ferry or the Manasas Junction" [2] . A good many of the boys had gone home. They have been written to, to return. The parents of a few of the boys will keep them at home, but we have been getting some recruits to fill their places. There is no doubt but that the company will be filled out, in a day or two. We are drilling four times a day. Recitations suspended.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The captain ordered us to get flannel shirts or jackets. We have no coat.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">We are out of money and would like to have some this week if you can send it. The County Court appropriated $25,000 to equip volunteers, allowing $25 per man. An effort will be made to have ou the remainder of our uniform knapsacks paid &amp;c -paid for out of this fund. Some of the court object to it, because we do not all belong to the county. We have heard a great many reports about the fighting at Hampton Harpers Ferry illeg. , but they are too favorable to our side to be believed. I heard this evening that 7 houses in the upper end of Waynesborough were burning yesterday as the cars came by, couldn't hear whether it was by accident or had been set on fire [3] . In consequence of so many boys leaving, the Faculty has called a meeting of the Trustees, next Saturday, to graduate the Senior Class and suspend College. Whether the company goes or not it is not probable we will have any more College duties this session.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">We will write again as soon as we hear from the Governor.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">I would like to have two new pair of woolen stockings. William &amp; I both want a new strong cotton shirt. We have one apiece, our sleeping shirts which have never been used. You need not send them here, as we will go to Staunton and most likely by Waynesboro of which we will give you notice. Has Ma gotten home? and has she improved? Write to us soon.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">As ever your son, Andrew Brooks</field>
      <field name="title_display">Letter to James Brooks</field>
      <field name="title_facet">Letter to James Brooks</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">letter to james brooks</field>
      <field name="title_text" boost="1.0">Letter to James Brooks</field>
      <field name="year_display">1861-05-28</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1861</field>
   </doc>
</add>