<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">William F. Brand</field>
      <field name="author_facet">William F. Brand</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">william f brand</field>
      <field name="author_text">William F. Brand</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">legacy_mss/uvaBook/tei/brand_letters/A2974.xml</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">University of Virginia Civil War Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">University of Virginia Civil War Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="full_title_text">William F. Brand to Amanda C. Armentrout, January 9, 1866</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:502144</field>
      <field name="langauge_display">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_facet">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_text">English</field>
      <field name="location_facet">Internet materials</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">William F. Brand to Amanda C. Armentrout, January 9, 1866</field>
      <field name="note_display">Source copy consulted: William F. Brand Papers</field>
      <field name="note_display"/>
      <field name="note_text">Source copy consulted: William F. Brand Papers</field>
      <field name="note_text"/>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod02.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">UVA Library Digital Repository</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="heading_text">Miss Kate Armentrout Greenville Augusta County Virginia Miss Kate Armentrout</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jan 9th '66 Alone Mills Dear Kate</field>
      <field name="fulltext">I recieved your letter yesterday. after reading &amp; rereading it my feelings ware tinged with a degree of sadness now I have taken your letter before me, for the purpose of trying to answer its details something I never tried before &amp; believe it imposible now. While I gaze on you epistle my mind wanders &amp; I cannot senter it on no one subject. Now believe me I am going to try to write what my heart shall dictate. You are well aware I once loved you devotedly yes passionately up to the time of our first enstrangement Since then I have never have seaced to love you. But I cannot confine it to the burning love I once enjoyed. Can I help it that I changed, I withdrew my affections at a time when I thought all was lost that was dear to me. Oftimes since then I have tried to be the same loving Willie I once was, but it seems that I have failed Now dont belive that you are forgotten for no other woman has ever tuched a tender cord within my breast. You are in my mind from morning till eve, yes my only desire to live is to perpetuate your hapiness , give your hand to annother &amp; I will leave this country wich will be a proof of my feelings for you I am so carless my bright visions of the future may soon fade your mind must have been pushed to an unusual degree of temperment when you wrote I dont belive I could commit to memory all the charges you prefered , I will not attempt to excuse my self of any for very probaly I am gilty of all I spent a Mery Christmas &amp; a plesent New Year, Evry girl that fell to my lot to entertain was flatered to a limited extent So you may term me a cold carless flaterer &amp; of the world worldly my early landmarks have all nearly been erased, what do I live for. My heart says thee while my actions do not prove it you may doubt this writing put it is the truth What more shall I say shall I fill this page with loving ephithets or with the sad realities of my changed nature. You once knew me as a devout flolower of our meek &amp; generous Savoir. But alas for a long time I had only a name to live while dead. This may be the sadest letter you ever recieved from me I never intend to hide any of my faults from you. I know not what kind of a reply this may bring be what it may I hope it may have its desired effect. Alas you will say Willie will soon be a ruined youth it may be so, but I hope to the contrary I am certain the intoxicating cup shall never drag me down in its ruinous path of misery. Since I left Augusta The grate I am has called for some of her fairest duels. It seems that the fairest flowers are always smitten first. I recieved a letter some time ago from my darling sister oh how I long for her emprace . Brother C was up to see me last night got here late yesterday eavning &amp; started early this morn. He is looking quite well, dont seem to take it very hard about loosing Bette, mans hard heart is hard to brake Dear Kate I pick up your letter and look at it. Then say I cannot answer it, do not know how to commence so I will wait hoping I may soon see you, when I can answer it more satis factorily than by writing I expect to make my apperance in old Aug Sadurday week will call on you unless sooner prohibited Do not let this uninteligible letter give you any truble . If your hand is given to another before I get down I hope you will let me have the plasure of thaking it once more Bro C told me that J.V. &amp; J.H. was at a party at your house some time ago very good joke on them</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Please write soon I will promise to try and do petter next time If I have written any thing to hurt your feelings please excuse I remain yours in hope in love &amp; untill death shall us divide</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Your Willie</field>
      <field name="heading_text">Envelope</field>
      <field name="title_display">William F. Brand to Amanda C. Armentrout, January 9, 1866</field>
      <field name="title_facet">William F. Brand to Amanda C. Armentrout, January 9, 1866</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">william f brand to amanda c armentrout january 9 1866</field>
      <field name="title_text" boost="1.0">William F. Brand to Amanda C. Armentrout, January 9, 1866</field>
      <field name="year_display">1866-01-09</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1866</field>
   </doc>
</add>
