<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Edgar Allan Poe</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Edgar Allan Poe</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">edgar allan poe</field>
      <field name="author_text">Edgar Allan Poe</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">legacy_mss/uvaBook/tei/misc/PoeP465A.xml</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="full_title_text">Poe Collection: Frances Sargent Osgood / Edgar Allan Poe</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:501830</field>
      <field name="langauge_display">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_display">French</field>
      <field name="langauge_facet">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_facet">French</field>
      <field name="langauge_text">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_text">French</field>
      <field name="location_facet">Internet materials</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Poe Collection: Frances Sargent Osgood / Edgar Allan Poe</field>
      <field name="note_display">Source copy consulted: Poe Museum manuscript, Richmond, VA</field>
      <field name="note_display">This fragment represents the first two pages of a manuscript written by Edgar Allan Poe. The complete manuscript, a review of poetry by Frances Osgood, was published in Southern Literary Messenger in August of 1849 as "Frances Osgood."</field>
      <field name="note_text">Source copy consulted: Poe Museum manuscript, Richmond, VA</field>
      <field name="note_text">This fragment represents the first two pages of a manuscript written by Edgar Allan Poe. The complete manuscript, a review of poetry by Frances Osgood, was published in Southern Literary Messenger in August of 1849 as "Frances Osgood."</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod02.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">UVA Library Digital Repository</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="heading_text">Frances Sargent Osgood Poe Museum manuscript, Richmond, VA</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Mrs Osgood , for the last three or four years, has been rapidly attain- ing distinction; and this, evidently, with no effort at attaining it. She seems, in fact, to have no object in view beyond that of giving voice to the fancies or the feelings of the moment. "Necessity", says the proverb, "is the mother of Invention"; and the invention of Mrs O. , at least, springs plainly from ne- cessity — from the necessity of invention. Not to write poetry — not to act it, think it, dream it, and be it, is entirely out of her power.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">It may be questioned whether with more industry, more method, more definite purpose, more ambition, Mrs Osgood would have made a more de- cided impression on the public mind. She might, upon the whole, have written better poems ; but the chances are that she would have failed in con- veying so vivid and so just an idea of her powers as poet. The warm ab- andownement of her style — that charm which now so captivates — is but a portion and a consequence of her unworldly nature in her disregard of mere fame; but it affords us glimpses, which we could not otherwise have obtained, of a capacity for accomplishing what she has not accomplished and in all probability never will. In the world of poetry, however, there is already more than enough of uncongenial ambition and pretence.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Mrs Osgood has taken no care whatever of her literary fame. A great number of her finest compositions, both in verse and prose, have been writ- ten anonymously, and are now lying perdus 1 about the country, in out-of- the way nooks and corners. Many a goodly reputation has been reared upon a far more unstable basis than her unclaimed and uncollected "fugitive pieces."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Her first volume, I believe, was published, seven or eight years ago, by Edward Churton , of London , during the residence of the poetess in that city. I have now lying before me a second edition of it, dated 1842 — a beautifully printed book, dedicated to the Reverend Hobart Cautier . It con- tains a number of what the Bostonians call "juvenile" poems written when Mrs. O. (then Miss Locke ) could not have been more than thirteen, and e- vincing unusual precosity. The leading piece is " Elfrida , a Dramatic Po- em", but in many respects well entitled to the appellation, "drama". I allude chiefly to the passionate expression of particular portions, to delineation of character, and to occasional scenic effect: — in construction, or plot — in — general conduct and plausibility, the play fails, comparatively, of course — for the hand of genius is evinced throughout.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The story is the well known one of Edgar , Elfrida , and Earl Athelwood . The king, hearing of Elfrida 's extraordinary beauty, commissions his favorite, Athelwood , to visit her and ascertain if report speaks truly of her charms. The earl, becoming himself enamored, represents the lady as anything but beau- tiful or agreeable. The king is satisfied. Athelwood soon afterward woos and weds Elfrida — giving Edgar to understand that the heiress' wealth is the ob- ject. The true state of the case, however, is betrayed by an enemy; and the monarch resolves to visit the earl at his castle and to judge for himself. Hearing of this resolve, Athelwood , in despair, confesses to his wife his du- plicity, and entreats her to render as far as possible the effect of her charms by dressing with unusual plainness. This the wife promises to do; but, fired with ambition and resentment at the wrong done her, arrays her- self in her most magnificent and becoming costume. The king is charmed, and the result is the destruction of Athelwood and the elevation of Elfrida to the throne.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">These incidents are well adapted to dramatic purposes, and with more of that art which Mrs Osgood does not possess, she might have woven them into a tragedy which the world would not have willingly let die. As it is, she has merely succeeded in showing what she might, should, should and could have done, and yet, unhappily, did not.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The character of Elfrida is the bright point of the play. Her beauty and consciousness of it — her indignation and uncompromising ambition — are de- picted with power. There is a fine blending of the poetry of passion and of the passion of poetry, in the lines which follow:</field>
      <field name="fulltext">— Why even know he bends In courtly reverence to some mincing dame, Haply the star of Edgar 's festival, While I, with this high heart and queenly form, Time in neglect and solitude. Shall it be ? Shall I not rend my feters and be free? Ay! — be the cooing turtle-dove content, Safe in her own loved nest! — the eagle soars On restless plumes to meet the imperial sun.</field>
      <field name="title_display">Poe Collection: Frances Sargent Osgood / Edgar Allan Poe</field>
      <field name="title_facet">Poe Collection: Frances Sargent Osgood / Edgar Allan Poe</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">poe collection frances sargent osgood edgar allan poe</field>
      <field name="title_text" boost="1.0">Poe Collection: Frances Sargent Osgood / Edgar Allan Poe</field>
      <field name="year_display">1849-08-01</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1849</field>
   </doc>
</add>