<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">James Booker</field>
      <field name="author_facet">James Booker</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">james booker</field>
      <field name="author_text">James Booker</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">legacy_mss/uvaBook/tei/booker_letters/Boo1l15.xml</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Online Manuscripts</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="full_title_text">Letter to Chloe Unity Blair [a machine-readable transcription]</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:501636</field>
      <field name="langauge_display">English </field>
      <field name="langauge_facet">English </field>
      <field name="langauge_text">English </field>
      <field name="location_facet">Internet materials</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Letter to Chloe Unity Blair [a machine-readable transcription]</field>
      <field name="note_display">Manuscript copy consulted: 11237</field>
      <field name="note_display">James and John Booker tend to use commas instead of periods to end a sentence. In the modernized version of this letter, we have regularized the punctuation in unambiguous cases.</field>
      <field name="note_text">Manuscript copy consulted: 11237</field>
      <field name="note_text">James and John Booker tend to use commas instead of periods to end a sentence. In the modernized version of this letter, we have regularized the punctuation in unambiguous cases.</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod02.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">UVA Library Digital Repository</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="fulltext">24 bit color, 400 dpi</field>
      <field name="heading_text">1861-12-15</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Manassas Junction Va Dec the 15 1861 Dear Cousin</field>
      <field name="fulltext">I received your kind and interresting letter a few days ago, I was verry glad to hear from you all and also to hear from my sweat hearts I wan to see them verry bad indeed tho I dont think thare is eny chance for me to git a furlow, the Col [1] has prom ised to let the married men go t home when he gets in to winterquarters, I hird this morning that our Regiment was going to move to Gainesville this week to fix thar winter quarters, that is about 12 miles from here back to wards Wincher ter rite on the Rail Road [2] I expect to stay here until thay get fixed up, and then thay will move the bag age to the Regiment I like ve to stay here verry well I get extra pay and have a lighter task than I would if I were at the Regiment [3]</field>
      <field name="fulltext">I think thay have given aut fighting at Centrevill this win ter, I saw a gentle man the other day just from Washington he said he did not think the yankees would try us at here eny more, the yankees took him prisner the 13 of last July and kept him until last week, he said his fair was verry rough indeed, and he said thay was 60,000 sick yankees in Washington thar was too men shot at Centreville last week for trying to kill thar Com manding affesers, thay I understood thay gave the Romancatholic Priest 25 dollars apeace to save thar souls,</field>
      <field name="fulltext">I cant think of eny thing to write that will interest you so I will come to a close write soon, gave my best respects to all inquiring frends and share a good portion for your self</field>
      <field name="fulltext">tel cousin Eliza ann Williams to write to me,</field>
      <field name="fulltext">you must speak aheap er good words to the ladies for me in the Crismas,</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Write soon to your Cousin miss James Booker miss to miss C U Blair</field>
      <field name="title_display">Letter to Chloe Unity Blair</field>
      <field name="title_facet">Letter to Chloe Unity Blair</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">letter to chloe unity blair a machine readable transcription</field>
      <field name="title_text" boost="1.0">Letter to Chloe Unity Blair</field>
      <field name="year_display">1861-12-15</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1861</field>
   </doc>
</add>