<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Stephen Crane</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Stephen Crane</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">stephen crane</field>
      <field name="author_text">Stephen Crane</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">legacy/uvaBook/tei/CraSham.xml</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Online Texts</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Online Texts</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="full_title_text">Shame: Whilomville Stories VI.</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:476834</field>
      <field name="langauge_display">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_facet">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_text">English</field>
      <field name="location_facet">Internet materials</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Shame: Whilomville Stories VI.</field>
      <field name="note_display">Slang and dialect in dialogue.</field>
      <field name="note_text">Slang and dialect in dialogue.</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod02.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">UVA Library Digital Repository</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="heading_text">Crane, Stephen. "Shame." Harper's New Monthly Magazine 100 (Jan. 1900): 320-325.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"WHILOMVILLE STORIES BY STEPHEN CRANE" A street lined with trees. Illustration by Edward B. Edwards</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"DON'T come in here botherin' me," said the cook, intolerantly. "What with your mother bein' away on a visit, an' your father comin' home soon to lunch, I have enough on my mind — and that without bein' bothered with you . The kitchen is no place for little boys, anyhow. Run away, and don't be interferin' with my work." She frowned and made a grand pretence of being deep in herculean labors; but Jimmie did not run away.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Now — they're goin' to have a picnic," he said, half audibly.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"What?"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Now — they're goin' to have a picnic."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Who's goin' to have a picnic?" demanded the cook, loudly. Her accent could have led one to suppose that if the projectors did not turn out to be the proper parties, she immediately would forbid this picnic.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jimmie looked at her with more hopefulness. After twenty minutes of futile skirmishing, he had at least succeeded in introducing the subject. To her question he answered, eagerly:</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Oh, everybody! Lots and lots of boys and girls. Everybody."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Who's everybody?"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">According to custom, Jimmie began to singsong through his nose in a quite indescribable fashion an enumeration of the prospective picnickers: "Willie Dalzel an' Dan Earl an' Ella Earl an' Wolcott Margate an' Reeves Margate an' Minnie Phelps an' — oh — lots more girls an' — everybody. An' their mothers an' big sisters too." Then he announced a new bit of information: "They're goin' to have a picnic."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Well, let them," said the cook, blandly.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jimmie fidgeted for a time in silence. At last he murmured, "I — now — I thought maybe you'd let me go."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The cook turned from her work with an air of irritation and amazement that Jimmie should still be in the kitchen. "Who's stoppin' you?" she asked, sharply. "I ain't stoppin' you, am I?"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"No," admitted Jimmie, in a low voice.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Well, why don't you go, then? Nobody's stoppin' you."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"But," said Jimmie, "I — you — now — each feller has got to take somethin' to eat with 'm."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Oh ho!" cried the cook, triumphantly. "So that's it, is it? So that's what you've been shyin' round here fer, eh? Well, you may as well take yourself off without more words. What with your mother bein' away on a visit, an' your father comin' home soon to his lunch, I have enough on my mind — an' that without being bothered with you ."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jimmie made no reply, but moved in grief toward the door. The cook continued: "Some people in this house seem to think there's 'bout a thousand cooks in this kitchen. Where I used to work b'fore, there was some reason in 'em. I ain't a horse. A picnic!"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jimmie said nothing, but he loitered.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Seems as if I had enough to do, without havin' you come round talkin' about picnics. Nobody ever seems to think of the work I have to do. Nobody ever seems to think of it. Then they come and talk to me about picnics! What do I care about picnics?"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jimmie loitered.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Where I used to work b'fore, there was some reason in 'em. I never heard tell of no picnics right on top of your mother bein' away on a visit an' your father comin' home soon to his lunch. It's all foolishness."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Little Jimmie leaned his head flat against the wall and began to weep. She stared at him scornfully. "Cryin', eh? Cryin'? What are you cryin' fer?"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"N-n-nothin'," sobbed Jimmie.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">There was a silence, save for Jimmie's convulsive breathing. At length the cook said: "Stop that blubberin', now. Stop it! This kitchen ain't no place fer it. Stop it! . . . Very well! If you don't stop, I won't give you nothin' to go to the picnic with — there!"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">For the moment he could not end his tears. "You never said," he sputtered — "you never said you'd give me anything."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"An' why would I?" she cried, angrily. "Why would I — with you in here a-cryin' an' a-blubberin' an' a-bleatin' round? Enough to drive a woman crazy! I don't see how you could expect me to! The idea!"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Suddenly Jimmie announced: "I've stopped cryin'. I ain't goin' to cry no more 'tall."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Well, then," grumbled the cook — "well, then, stop it. I've got enough on my mind." It chanced that she was making for luncheon some salmon croquettes. A tin still half full of pinky prepared fish was beside her on the table. Still grumbling, she seized a loaf of bread and, wielding a knife, she cut from this loaf four slices, each of which was as big as a six-shilling novel. She profligately spread them with butter, and jabbing the point of her knife into the salmon-tin, she brought up bits of salmon, which she flung and flattened upon the bread. Then she crashed the pieces of bread together in pairs, much as one would clash cymbals. There was no doubt in her own mind but that she had created two sandwiches.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"There," she cried. "That'll do you all right. Lemme see. What'll I put 'em in? There — I've got it." She thrust the sandwiches into a small pail and jammed on the lid. Jimmie was ready for the picnic. "Oh, thank you, Mary!" he cried, joyfully, and in a moment he was off, running swiftly.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The picnickers had started nearly half an hour earlier, owing to his inability to quickly attack and subdue the cook, but he knew that the rendezvous was in the grove of tall, pillarlike hemlocks and pines that grew on a rocky knoll at the lake shore. His heart was very light as he sped, swinging his pail. But a few minutes previously his soul had been gloomed in despair; now he was happy. He was going to the picnic, where privilege of participation was to be bought by the contents of the little tin pail.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">When he arrived in the outskirts of the grove he heard a merry clamor, and when he reached the top of the knoll he looked down the slope upon a scene which almost made his little breast burst with joy. They actually had two camp fires! Two camp fires! At one of them Mrs. Earl was making something — chocolate, no doubt — and at the other a young lady in white duck and a sailor hat was dropping eggs into boiling water. Other grown-up people had spread a white cloth and were laying upon it things from baskets. In the deep cool shadow of the trees the children scurried, laughing. Jimmie hastened forward to join his friends.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Homer Phelps caught first sight of him. "Ho!" he shouted; "here comes Jimmie Trescott! Come on, Jimmie; you be on our side!" The children had divided themselves into two bands for some purpose of play. The others of Homer Phelps's party loudly endorsed his plan. "Yes, Jimmie, you be on our side." Then arose the usual dispute. "Well, we got the weakest side."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"'Tain't any weaker'n ours."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Homer Phelps suddenly started, and looking hard, said, "What you got in the pail, Jim?"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jimmie answered somewhat uneasily, "Got m' lunch in it."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Instantly that brat of a Minnie Phelps simply tore down the sky with her shrieks of derision. "Got his lunch in it! In a pail!" She ran screaming to her mother. "Oh, mamma! Oh, mamma! Jimmie Trescott's got his picnic in a pail!"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Now there was nothing in the nature of this fact to particularly move the others — notably the boys, who were not competent to care if he had brought his luncheon in a coal-bin; but such is the instinct of childish society that they all immediately moved away from him. In a moment he had been made a social leper. All old intimacies were flung into the lake, so to speak. They dared not compromise themselves. At safe distances the boys shouted, scornfully: "Huh! Got his picnic in a pail!" Never again during that picnic did the little girls speak of him as Jimmie Trescott. His name now was Him.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">His mind was dark with pain as he stood, the hang-dog, kicking the gravel, and muttering as defiantly as he was able, "Well, I can have it in a pail if I want to." This statement of freedom was of no importance, and he knew it, but it was the only idea in his head.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">He had been baited at school for being detected in writing a letter to little Cora, the angel child, and he had known how to defend himself, but this situation was in no way similar. This was a social affair, with grown people on all sides. It would be sweet to catch the Margate twins, for instance, and hammer them into a state of bleating respect for his pail; but that was a matter for the jungles of childhood, where grown folk seldom penetrated. He could only glower.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The amiable voice of Mrs. Earl suddenly called: "Come, children! Everything's ready!" They scampered away, glancing back for one last gloat at Jimmie standing there with his pail.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">He did not know what to do. He knew that the grown folk expected him at the spread, but if he approached he would be greeted by a shameful chorus from the children — more especially from some of those damnable little girls. Still, luxuries beyond all dreaming were heaped on that cloth. One could not forget them. Perhaps if he crept up modestly, and was very gentle and very nice to the little girls, they would allow him peace. Of course it had been dreadful to come with a pail to such a grand picnic, but they might forgive him.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Oh no, they would not! He knew them better. And then suddenly he remembered with what delightful expectations he had raced to this grove, and self-pity overwhelmed him, and he thought he wanted to die and make every one feel sorry.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The young lady in white duck and a sailor hat looked at him, and then spoke to her sister, Mrs. Earl. "Who's that hovering in the distance, Emily?"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Mrs. Earl peered. "Why, it's Jimmie Trescott! Jimmie, come to the picnic! Why don't you come to the picnic, Jimmie?" He began to sidle toward the cloth.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">But at Mrs. Earl's call there was another outburst from many of the children. "He's got his picnic in a pail! In a pail! Got it in a pail!"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Minnie Phelps was a shrill fiend. "Oh, mamma, he's got it in that pail! See! Isn't it funny? Isn't it dreadful funny?"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"What ghastly prigs children are, Emily!" said the young lady. "They are spoiling that boy's whole day, breaking his heart, the little cats! I think I'll go over and talk to him."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Maybe you had better not," answered Mrs. Earl, dubiously. "Somehow these things arrange themselves. If you interfere, you are likely to prolong everything."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Well, I'll try, at least," said the young lady.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">At the second outburst against him Jimmie had crouched down by a tree, half hiding behind it, half pretending that he was not hiding behind it. He turned his sad gaze toward the lake. The bit of water seen through the shadows seemed perpendicular, a slate-colored wall. He heard a noise near him, and turning, he perceived the young lady looking down at him. In her hands she held plates. "May I sit near you?" she asked, coolly.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jimmie could hardly believe his ears. After disposing herself and the plates upon the pine needles, she made brief explanation. "They're rather crowded, you see, over there. I don't like to be crowded at a picnic, so I thought I'd come here. I hope you don't mind."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jimmie made haste to find his tongue. "Oh, I don't mind! I like to have you here." The ingenuous emphasis made it appear that the fact of his liking to have her there was in the nature of a law-dispelling phenomenon, but she did not smile.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"How large is that lake?" she asked.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jimmie, falling into the snare, at once began to talk in the manner of a proprietor of the lake. "Oh, it's almost twenty miles long, an' in one place it's almost four miles wide! an' it's deep , too — awful deep — an' it's got real steamboats on it, an' — oh — lots of other boats, an' — an' — an' — "</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Do you go out on it sometimes?"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Oh, lots of times! My father's got a boat," he said, eying her to note the effect of his words.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">She was correctly pleased and struck with wonder. "Oh, has he?" she cried, as if she never before had heard of a man owning a boat.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jimmie continued: "Yes, an' it's a grea' big boat, too, with sails, real sails; an' sometimes he takes me out in her, too; an' once he took me fishin', an' we had sandwiches, plenty of 'em, an' my father he drank beer right out of the bottle — right out of the bottle!"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The young lady was properly overwhelmed by this amazing intelligence. Jimmie saw the impression he had created, and he enthusiastically resumed his narrative: "An' after, he let me throw the bottles in the water, and I throwed 'em 'way, 'way, 'way out. An' they sank, an' — never comed up," he concluded, dramatically.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">His face was glorified; he had forgotten all about the pail; he was absorbed in this communion with a beautiful lady who was so interested in what he had to say.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">She indicated one of the plates, and said, indifferently: "Perhaps you would like some of those sandwiches. I made them. Do you like olives? And there's a deviled egg. I made that also."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Did you really?" said Jimmie, politely. His face gloomed for a moment because the pail was recalled to his mind, but he timidly possessed himself of a sandwich.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Hope you are not going to scorn my deviled egg," said his goddess. "I am very proud of it." He did not; he scorned little that was on the plate.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Their gentle intimacy was ineffable to the boy. He thought he had a friend, a beautiful lady, who liked him more than she did anybody at the picnic, to say the least. This was proved by the fact that she had flung aside the luxuries of the spread cloth to sit with him, the exile. Thus early did he fall a victim to woman's wiles.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Where do you live?" he asked, suddenly.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Oh, a long way from here! In New York."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">His next question was put very bluntly. "Are you married?"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Oh, no!" she answered, gravely.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jimmie was silent for a time, during which he glanced shyly and furtively up at her face. It was evident that he was somewhat embarrassed. Finally he said, "When I grow up to be a man — "</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Oh, that is some time yet!" said the beautiful lady.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"But when I do , I — I should like to marry you."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Well, I will remember it," she answered; "but don't talk of it now, because it's such a long time, and — I wouldn't wish you to consider yourself bound." She smiled at him.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">He began to brag. "When I grow up to be a man, I'm goin' to have lots an' lots of money, an' I'm goin' to have a grea' big house an' a horse an' a shotgun, an' lots an' lots of books 'bout elephants an' tigers, an' lots an' lots of ice-cream an' pie an' — caramels." As before, she was impressed; he could see it. "An' I'm goin' to have lots an' lots of children — 'bout three hundred, I guess — an' there won't none of 'em be girls. They'll all be boys — like me."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Oh, my!" she said.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">His garment of shame was gone from him. The pail was dead and well buried. It seemed to him that months elapsed as he dwelt in happiness near the beautiful lady and trumpeted his vanity.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">At last there was a shout. "Come on! we're going home." The picnickers trooped out of the grove. The children wished to resume their jeering, for Jimmie still gripped his pail, but they were restrained by the circumstances. He was walking at the side of the beautiful lady.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">During this journey he abandoned many of his habits. For instance, he never travelled without skipping gracefully from crack to crack between the stones, or without pretending that he was a train of cars, or without some mumming device of childhood. But now he behaved with dignity. He made no more noise than a little mouse. He escorted the beautiful lady to the gate of the Earl home, where he awkwardly, solemnly, and wistfully shook hands in good-by. He watched her go up the walk; the door clanged.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">On his way home he dreamed. One of these dreams was fascinating. Supposing the beautiful lady was his teacher in school! Oh, my! wouldn't he be a good boy, sitting like a statuette all day long, and knowing every lesson to perfection, and — everything. And then supposing that a boy should sass her. Jimmie painted himself waylaying that boy on the homeward road, and the fate of the boy was a thing to make strong men cover their eyes with their hands. And she would like him more and more — more and more. And he — he would be a little god.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">But as he was entering his father's grounds an appalling recollection came to him. He was returning with the bread-and-butter and the salmon untouched in the pail! He could imagine the cook, nine feet tall, waving her fist. "An' so that's what I took trouble for, is it? So's you could bring it back? So's you could bring it back?" He skulked toward the house like a marauding bush-ranger. When he neared the kitchen door he made a desperate rush past it, aiming to gain the stables and there secrete his guilt. He was nearing them, when a thunderous voice hailed him from the rear:</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Jimmie Trescott, where you goin' with that pail?"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">It was the cook. He made no reply, but plunged into the shelter of the stables. He whirled the lid from the pail and dashed its contents beneath a heap of blankets. Then he stood panting, his eyes on the door. The cook did not pursue, but she was bawling,</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Jimmie Trescott, what you doin' with that pail?"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">He came forth, swinging it. "Nothin'," he said, in virtuous protest.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"I know better," she said, sharply, as she relieved him of his curse.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">In the morning Jimmie was playing near the stable, when he heard a shout from Peter Washington, who attended Dr. Trescott's horses:</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Jim! Oh, Jim!"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"What?"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Come yah."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jimmie went reluctantly to the door of the stable, and Peter Washington asked,</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Wut's dish yere fish an' brade doin' unner dese yer blankups?"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"I don't know. I didn't have nothin' to do with it," answered Jimmie, indignantly.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Don' tell me!" cried Peter Washington as he flung it all away — "don' tell me! When I fin' fish an' brade unner dese yer blankups, I don' go an' think dese yer ho'ses er yer pop's put 'em. I know . An' if I caitch enny more dish yer fish an' brade in dish yer stable, I'll tell yer pop."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"JIMMIE TRESCOTT'S GOT HIS PICNIC IN A PAIL." A shouting girl running from an astonished boy carrying a pail. Other children gather around laughing. Lakeshore and mountains are in the distance. Illustration by Peter Newell</field>
      <field name="title_display">Whilomville Stories: VI. — Shame</field>
      <field name="title_facet">Whilomville Stories: VI. — Shame</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">shame whilomville stories vi</field>
      <field name="title_text" boost="1.0">Whilomville Stories: VI. — Shame</field>
      <field name="year_display">1900-01</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1900</field>
   </doc>
</add>