<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">William Wyman Jacobs</field>
      <field name="author_facet">William Wyman Jacobs</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">william wyman jacobs</field>
      <field name="author_text">William Wyman Jacobs</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">legacy/uvaBook/tei/JacMonk.xml</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Online Texts</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Online Texts</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="full_title_text">The Monkey's Paw.</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:477076</field>
      <field name="langauge_display">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_facet">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_text">English</field>
      <field name="location_facet">Internet materials</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Monkey's Paw.</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod02.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">UVA Library Digital Repository</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="heading_text">I</field>
      <field name="fulltext">WITHOUT, the night was cold and wet, but in the small parlor of Lakesnam Villa the blinds were drawn and the fire burned brightly. Father and son were at chess, the former, who possessed ideas about the game involving radical changes, putting his king into such sharp and unnecessary perils that it even provoked comment from the white-haired old lady knitting placidly by the fire.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Hark at the wind," said Mr. White, who, having seen a fatal mistake after it was too late, was amiably desirous of preventing his son from seeing it.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"I'm listening," said the latter, grimly surveying the board as he stretched out his hand. "Check."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"I should hardly think that he'd come to-night," said his father, with his hand poised over the board.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Mate," replied the son.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"That's the worst of living so far out," bawled Mr. White, with sudden and unlooked-for violence; "of all the beastly, slushy, out-of-the-way places to live in, this is the worst. Pathway's a bog, and the road's a torrent. I don't know what people are thinking about. I suppose because only two houses on the road are let, they think it doesn't matter."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Never mind, dear," said his wife, soothingly; "perhaps you'll win the next one."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Mr. White looked up sharply, just in time to intercept a knowing glance between mother and son. The words died away on his lips, and he hid a guilty grin in his thin gray beard.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"There he is," said Herbert White, as the gate banged to loudly and heavy footsteps came towards the door.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The old man rose with hospitable haste, and opening the door, was heard condoling with the new arrival. The new arrival also condoled with himself, so that Mrs. White said, "Tut, tut!" and coughed gently as her husband entered the room, followed by a tall burly man, beady of eye and rubicund of visage.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Sergeant-Major Morris," he said, introducing him.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The sergeant-major shook hands, and taking the proffered seat by the fire, watched contentedly while his host got out whiskey and tumblers and stood a small copper kettle on the fire.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">At the third glass his eyes got brighter, and he began to talk, the little family circle regarding with eager interest this visitor from distant parts, as he squared his broad shoulders in the chair and spoke of strange scenes and doughty deeds, of wars and plagues and strange peoples.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Twenty-one years of it," said Mr. White, nodding at his wife and son. "When he went away he was a slip of a youth in the warehouse. Now look at him."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"He don't look to have taken much harm," said Mrs. White, politely.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"I'd like to go to India myself," said the old man, "just to look round a bit, you know."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Better where you are," said the sergeant-major, shaking his head. He put down the empty glass, and sighing softly, shook it again.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"I should like to see those old temples and fakirs and jugglers," said the old man. "What was that you started telling me the other day about a monkey's paw or something, Morris?"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Nothing," said the soldier, hastily. "Leastways nothing worth hearing."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Monkey's paw?" said Mr. White, curiously.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Well, it's just a bit of what you might call magic, perhaps," said the sergeant-major, off-handedly.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">His three listeners leaned forward eagerly. The visitor absent-mindedly put his empty glass to his lips and then set it down again. His host filled it for him.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"To look at," said the sergeant-major, fumbling in his pocket, "it's just an ordinary little paw, dried to a mummy."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">He took something out of his pocket and proffered it. Mrs. White drew back with a grimace, but her son, taking it, examined it curiously.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"And what is there special about it?" inquired Mr. White as he took it from his son, and having examined it, placed it upon the table.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"It had a spell put on it by an old fakir," said the sergeant-major, "a very holy man. He wanted to show that fate ruled people's lives, and that those who interfered with it did so to their sorrow. He put a spell on it so that three separate men could each have three wishes from it."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">His manner was so impressive that his hearers were conscious that their light laughter jarred somewhat.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Well, why don't you have three, sir?" said Herbert White, cleverly.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The soldier regarded him in the way that middle age is wont to regard presumptuous youth. "I have," he said, quietly, and his blotchy face whitened.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"And did you really have the three wishes granted?" asked Mrs. White.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"I did," said the sergeant-major, and his glass tapped against his strong teeth.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"And has anybody else wished?" inquired the old lady.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"The first man had his three wishes, yes," was the reply. "I don't know what the first two were, but the third was for death. That's how I got the paw."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">His tones were so grave that a hush fell upon the group.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"If you've had your three wishes, it's no good to you now, then, Morris," said the old man at last. "What do you keep it for?"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The soldier shook his head. "Fancy, I suppose," he said, slowly. "I did have some idea of selling it, but I don't think I will. It has caused enough mischief already. Besides, people won't buy. They think it's a fairy-tale, some of them, and those who do think anything of it want to try it first and pay me afterwards."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"If you could have another three wishes," said the old man, eying him keenly, "would you have them?"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"I don't know," said the other. "I don't know."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">He took the paw, and dangling it between his front finger and thumb, suddenly threw it upon the fire. White, with a slight cry, stooped down and snatched it off.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Better let it burn," said the soldier, solemnly.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"If you don't want it, Morris," said the old man, "give it to me."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"I won't," said his friend, doggedly. "I threw it on the fire. If you keep it, don't blame me for what happens. Pitch it on the fire again, like a sensible man."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The other shook his head and examined his new possession closely. "How do you do it?" he inquired.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Hold it up in your right hand and wish aloud," said the sergeant-major, "but I warn you of the consequences."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Sounds like the Arabian Nights ," said Mrs. White, as she rose and began to set the supper. "Don't you think you might wish for four pairs of hands for me?"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Her husband drew the talisman from his pocket, and then all three burst into laughter as the sergeant-major, with a look of alarm on his face, caught him by the arm.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"If you must wish," he said, gruffly, "wish for something sensible."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Mr. White dropped it back into his pocket, and placing chairs, motioned his friend to the table. In the business of supper the talisman was partly forgotten, and afterwards the three sat listening in an enthralled fashion to a second instalment of the soldier's adventures in India.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"If the tale about the monkey paw is not more truthful than those he has been telling us," said Herbert, as the door closed behind their guest, just in time for him to catch the last train, "we sha'n't make much out of it."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Did you give him anything for it, father?" inquired Mrs. White, regarding her husband closely.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"A trifle," said he, coloring slightly. "He didn't want it, but I made him take it. And he pressed me again to throw it away."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Likely," said Herbert, with pretended horror. "Why, we're going to be rich, and famous, and happy. Wish to be an emperor, father, to begin with; then you can't be henpecked."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">He darted round the table, pursued by the maligned Mrs. White armed with an antimacassar.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Mr. White took the paw from his pocket and eyed it dubiously. "I don't know what to wish for, and that's a fact," he said, slowly. "It seems to me I've got all I want."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"If you only cleared the house, you'd be quite happy, wouldn't you?" said Herbert, with his hand on his shoulder. "Well, wish for two hundred pounds, then; that'll just do it."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">His father, smiling shamefacedly at his own credulity, held up the talisman, as his son, with a solemn face somewhat marred by a wink at his mother, sat down at the piano and struck a few impressive chords.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"I wish for two hundred pounds," said the old man, distinctly.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">A fine crash from the piano greeted the words, interrupted by a shuddering cry from the old man. His wife and son ran towards him.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"It moved," he cried, with a glance of disgust at the object as it lay on the floor. "As I wished, it twisted in my hands like a snake."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Well, I don't see the money," said his son as he picked it up and placed it on the table, "and I bet I never shall."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"It must have been your fancy, father," said his wife, regarding him anxiously.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">He shook his head. "Never mind, though; there's no harm done, but it gave me a shock all the same."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">They sat down by the fire again while the two men finished their pipes. Outside, the wind was higher than ever, and the old man started nervously at the sound of a door banging upstairs. A silence unusual and depressing settled upon all three, which lasted until the old couple rose to retire for the night.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"I expect you'll find the cash tied up in a big bag in the middle of your bed," said Herbert, as he bade them good-night, "and something horrible squatting up on top of the wardrobe watching you as you pocket your ill-gotten gains."</field>
      <field name="heading_text">II</field>
      <field name="fulltext">In the brightness of the wintry sun next morning as it streamed over the breakfast table Herbert laughed at his fears. There was an air of prosaic wholesomeness about the room which it had lacked on the previous night, and the dirty, shrivelled little paw was pitched on the sideboard with a carelessness which betokened no great belief in its virtues.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"I suppose all old soldiers are the same," said Mrs. White. "The idea of our listening to such nonsense! How could wishes be granted in these days? And if they could, how could two hundred pounds hurt you, father?"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Might drop on his head from the sky," said the frivolous Herbert.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Morris said the things happened so naturally," said his father, "that you might if you so wished attribute it to coincidence."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Well, don't break into the money before I come back," said Herbert as he rose from the table. "I'm afraid it'll turn you into a mean, avaricious man, and we shall have to disown you."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">His mother laughed, and following him to the door, watched him down the road, and returning to the breakfast table, was very happy at the expense of her husband's credulity. All of which did not prevent her from scurrying to the door at the postman's knock, nor prevent her from referring somewhat shortly to retired sergeant-majors of bibulous habits when she found that the post brought a tailor's bill.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Herbert will have some more of his funny remarks, I expect, when he comes home," she said as they sat at dinner.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"I dare say," said Mr. White, pouring himself out some beer; "but for all that, the thing moved in my hand; that I'll swear to."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"You thought it did," said the old lady, soothingly.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"I say it did," replied the other. "There was no thought about it; I had just— What's the matter?"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">His wife made no reply. She was watching the mysterious movements of a man outside, who, peering in an undecided fashion at the house, appeared to be trying to make up his mind to enter. In mental connection with the two hundred pounds, she noticed that the stranger was well dressed and wore a silk hat of glossy newness. Three times he paused at the gate, and then walked on again. The fourth time he stood with his hand upon it, and then with sudden resolution flung it open and walked up the path. Mrs. White at the same moment placed her hands behind her, and hurriedly unfastening the strings of her apron, put that useful article of apparel beneath the cushion of her chair.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">She brought the stranger, who seemed ill at ease, into the room. He gazed furtively at Mrs. White, and listened in a preoccupied fashion as the old lady apologized for the appearance of the room, and her husband's coat, a garment which he usually reserved for the garden. She then waited as patiently as her sex would permit for him to broach his business, but he was at first strangely silent.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"I—was asked to call," he said at last, and stooped and picked a piece of cotton from his trousers. "I come from 'Maw and Meggins.'"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The old lady started. "Is anything the matter?" she asked, breathlessly. "Has anything happened to Herbert? What is it? What is it?"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Her husband interposed. "There, there, mother," he said, hastily. "Sit down, and don't jump to conclusions. You've not brought bad news, I'm sure, sir," and he eyed the other wistfully.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"I'm sorry—" began the visitor.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Is he hurt?" demanded the mother.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The visitor bowed in assent. "Badly hurt," he said, quietly, "but he is not in any pain."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Oh, thank God!" said the old woman, clasping her hands. "Thank God for that! Thank—"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">She broke off suddenly as the sinister meaning of the assurance dawned upon her and she saw the awful confirmation of her fears in the other's averted face. She caught her breath, and turning to her slower-witted husband, laid her trembling old hand upon his. There was a long silence.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"He was caught in the machinery," said the visitor at length in a low voice.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Caught in the machinery," repeated Mr. White in a dazed fashion, "yes."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">He sat staring blankly out at the window, and taking his wife's hand between his own, pressed it as he had been wont to do in their old courting days nearly forty years before.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"He was the only one left to us," he said, turning gently to the visitor. "It is hard."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The other coughed, and rising, walked slowly to the window. "The firm wished me to convey their sincere sympathy with you in your great loss," he said, without looking round. "I beg that you will understand I am only their servant and merely obeying orders."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">There was no reply; the old woman's face was white, her eyes staring, and her breath inaudible; on the husband's face was a look such as his friend the sergeant might have carried into his first action.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"I was to say that Maw and Meggins disclaim all responsibility," continued the other. "They admit no liability at all, but in consideration of your son's service they wish to present you with a certain sum as compensation."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Mr. White dropped his wife's hand, and rising to his feet, gazed with a look of horror at his visitor. His dry lips shaped the words, "How much?"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Two hundred pounds," was the answer.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Unconscious of his wife's shriek, the old man smiled faintly, put out his hands like a sightless man, and dropped, a senseless heap, to the floor.</field>
      <field name="heading_text">III</field>
      <field name="fulltext">In the huge new cemetery, some two miles distant, the old people buried their dead, and came back to a house steeped in shadow and silence. It was all over so quickly that at first they could hardly realize it, and remained in a state of expectation as though of something else to happen—something else which was to lighten this load, too heavy for old hearts to bear.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">But the days passed, and expectation gave place to resignation—the hopeless resignation of the old, sometimes miscalled apathy. Sometimes they hardly exchanged a word, for now they had nothing to talk about, and their days were long to weariness.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">It was about a week after that that the old man, waking suddenly in the night, stretched out his hand and found himself alone. The room was in darkness, and the sound of subdued weeping came from the window. He raised himself in bed and listened.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Come back," he said, tenderly. "You will be cold."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"It is colder for my son," said the old woman, and wept afresh.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The sound of her sobs died away on his ears. The bed was warm, and his eyes heavy with sleep. He dozed fitfully, and then slept until a sudden wild cry from his wife awoke him with a start.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"The monkey's paw!" she cried, wildly. "The monkey's paw!"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">He started up in alarm. "Where? Where is it? What's the matter?"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">She came stumbling across the room towards him. "I want it," she said, quietly. "You've not destroyed it?"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"It's in the parlor, on the bracket," he replied, marvelling. "Why?"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">She cried and laughed together, and bending over, kissed his cheek.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"I only just thought of it," she said, hysterically. "Why didn't I think of it before? Why didn't you think of it?"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Think of what?" he questioned.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"The other two wishes," she replied, rapidly. "We've only had one."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Was not that enough?" he demanded, fiercely.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"No," she cried, triumphantly; "we'll have one more. Go down and get it quickly, and wish our boy alive again."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The man sat up in bed and flung the bedclothes from his quaking limbs. "Good God, you are mad!" he cried, aghast.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Get it," she panted; "get it quickly, and wish— Oh, my boy, my boy!"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Her husband struck a match and lit the candle. "Get back to bed," he said, unsteadily. "You don't know what you are saying."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"We had the first wish granted," said the old woman, feverishly; "why not the second?"</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"A coincidence," stammered the old man.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Go and get it and wish," cried the old woman, and dragged him towards the door.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">He went down in the darkness, and felt his way to the parlor, and then to the mantel-piece. The talisman was in its place, and a horrible fear that the unspoken wish might bring his mutilated son before him ere he could escape from the room seized upon him, and he caught his breath as he found that he had lost the direction of the door. His brow cold with sweat, he felt his way round the table, and groped along the wall until he found himself in the small passage with the unwholesome thing in his hand.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Even his wife's face seemed changed as he entered the room. It was white and expectant, and to his fears seemed to have an unnatural look upon it. He was afraid of her.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Wish!" she cried, in a strong voice.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"It is foolish and wicked," he faltered.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Wish!" repeated his wife.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">He raised his hand. "I wish my son alive again."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The talisman fell to the floor, and he regarded it shudderingly. Then he sank trembling into a chair as the old woman, with burning eyes, walked to the window and raised the blind.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">He sat until he was chilled with the cold, glancing occasionally at the figure of the old woman peering through the window. The candle end, which had burnt below the rim of the china candlestick, was throwing pulsating shadows on the ceiling and walls, until, with a flicker larger than the rest, it expired. The old man, with an unspeakable sense of relief at the failure of the talisman, crept back to his bed, and a minute or two afterwards the old woman came silently and apathetically beside him.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Neither spoke, but both lay silently listening to the ticking of the clock. A stair creaked, and a squeaky mouse scurried noisily through the wall. The darkness was oppressive, and after lying for some time screwing up his courage, the husband took the box of matches, and striking one, went down stairs for a candle.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">At the foot of the stairs the match went out, and he paused to strike another, and at the same moment a knock, so quiet and stealthy as to be scarcely audible, sounded on the front door.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The matches fell from his hand. He stood motionless, his breath suspended until the knock was repeated. Then he turned and fled swiftly back to his room, and closed the door behind him. A third knock sounded through the house.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">" What's that?" cried the old woman, starting up.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"A rat," said the old man in shaking tones—"a rat. It passed me on the stairs."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">His wife sat up in bed listening. A loud knock resounded through the house.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"It's Herbert!" she screamed. "It's Herbert!" "WHAT'S THAT?" CRIED THE OLD WOMAN</field>
      <field name="fulltext">She ran to the door, but her husband was before her, and catching her by the arm, held her tightly.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"What are you going to do?" he whispered hoarsely.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"It's my boy; it's Herbert!" she cried, struggling mechanically. "I forgot it was two miles away. What are you holding me for? Let go. I must open the door."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"For God's sake don't let it in," cried the old man, trembling.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"You're afraid of your own son," she cried, struggling. "Let me go. I'm coming, Herbert; I'm coming."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">There was another knock, and another. The old woman with a sudden wrench broke free and ran from the room. Her husband followed to the landing, and called after her appealingly as she hurried down stairs. He heard the chain rattle back and the bottom bolt drawn slowly and stiffly from the socket. Then the old woman's voice, strained and panting.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"The bolt," she cried loudly. "Come down. I can't reach it."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">But her husband was on his hands and knees groping wildly on the floor in search of the paw. If he could only find it before the thing outside got in. A perfect fusillade of knocks reverberated through the house, and he heard the scraping of a chair as his wife put it down in the passage against the door. He heard the creaking of the bolt as it came slowly back, and at the same moment he found the monkey's paw, and frantically breathed his third and last wish.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The knocking ceased suddenly, although the echoes of it were still in the house. He heard the chair drawn back and the door opened. A cold wind rushed up the staircase, and a long loud wail of disappointment and misery from his wife gave him courage to run down to her side, and then to the gate beyond. The street lamp flickering opposite shone on a quiet and deserted road.</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Monkey's Paw</field>
      <field name="title_facet">The Monkey's Paw</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">monkey s paw</field>
      <field name="title_text" boost="1.0">The Monkey's Paw</field>
      <field name="year_display">1902</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1902</field>
   </doc>
</add>