<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">D. H. Lawrence</field>
      <field name="author_facet">D. H. Lawrence</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">d h lawrence</field>
      <field name="author_text">D. H. Lawrence</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">legacy/uvaBook/tei/LawApos.xml</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Online Texts</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Online Texts</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="full_title_text">The Apostolic Beasts</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:477121</field>
      <field name="langauge_display">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_facet">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_text">English</field>
      <field name="location_facet">Internet materials</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Apostolic Beasts</field>
      <field name="note_display">Print copy consulted: University of Virginia Library call number AP2.D48</field>
      <field name="note_text">Print copy consulted: University of Virginia Library call number AP2.D48</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod02.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">UVA Library Digital Repository</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="heading_text">Saint Mark</field>
      <field name="fulltext">There was a lion in Judah Which whelped, and was Mark.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">But winged— A lion with wings— At least at Venice, Even as late as Daniele Manin.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Why should he have wings? Is he to be a bird also? Or a spirit? Or a winged thought? Or a soaring consciousness?</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Evidently he is all that, The lion of the spirit.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Ah, Lamb of God, Would a wingless lion lie down before Thee, as this winged lion lies?</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The lion of the spirit.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Once he lay in the mouth of a cave And sunned his whiskers, And lashed his tail slowly, slowly, Thinking of voluptuousness, Even of blood.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">But later, in the sun of the afternoon, Having tasted all there was to taste, and having slept his fill, He fell to frowning, as he lay with his head on his paws And the sun coming in through the narrowest fibril of a slit in his eyes. So, nine-tenths asleep, motionless, bored and statically angry, He saw in a shaft of light a lamb on a pinnacle, balancing a flag on its foot, And he was thoroughly startled.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Going out to investigate, He found the lamb beyond him, on the inaccessible pinnacle of light. So he put his paw to his nose and pondered.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Guard my sheep," came the silvery voice from the pinnacle, "And I will give thee the wings of the morning." So the lion of the senses thought it was worth it.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Hence he became a curly sheep-dog with dangerous propensities, As Carpaccio will tell you: Ramping round, guarding the flock of mankind, Sharpening his teeth on the wolves, Ramping up through the air like a kestrel And lashing his tail above the world And enjoying the sensation of heaven and righteousness and voluptuous wrath.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">There is a new sweetness in his voluptuously licking his paw Now that it is a weapon of heaven. There is a new ecstasy in his roar of desirous love Now that it sounds self-conscious through the unlimited sky. He is well aware of himself, And he cherishes voluptuous delights, and thinks about them, And ceases to be a blood-thirsty king of beasts, And becomes the faithful sheep-dog of the Shepherd, thinking of his voluptuous pleasures of chasing the sheep to the fold, And increasing the flock, and perhaps giving a real nip here and there, a real pinch, but always well meant.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">And somewhere there is a lioness, The she-mate. Whelps play between the paws of the lion, The she-mate purrs; Their castle is impregnable, their cave, The sun comes in their lair, they are well-off, A well-to-do family.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Then the proud lion stalks abroad, alone, And roars to announce himself to the wolves And also to encourage the red-cross Lamb And also to ensure a goodly increase in the world.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Look at him, with his paw on the world, At Venice and elsewhere. Going blind at last.</field>
      <field name="heading_text">Saint Luke</field>
      <field name="fulltext">A wall, a bastion. A living forehead with its slow whorl of hair And a bull's large, sombre, glancing eye And glistening, adhesive muzzle With cavernous nostrils, where the winds run hot, Snorting defiance Or greedily snuffling behind the cows.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Horns, The golden horns of power, Power to kill, power to create, Such as Moses had, and God.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Shall great wings flame from his shoulder sockets, Assyrian-wise? It would be no wonder.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Knowing the thunder of his heart, The massive thunder of his dew-lapped chest, Deep and reverberating, It would be no wonder if great wings, like flame, fanned out from the furnace-cracks of his shoulder-sockets.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Thud! Thud! Thud! And the roar of black bulls' blood in the mighty passages of his chest.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Ah, the dewlap swings pendulous with excess, The great, roaring weight above Like a furnace dripping a molten drip.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The urge, the massive, burning ache Of the bull's breast; The open furnace-doors of his nostrils.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">For what does he ache and groan?</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Is his breast a wall?</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Nay, once it was also a fortress wall, and the weight of a vast battery; But now it is a burning hearthstone only, Massive old altar of his own burnt offering.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">It was always an altar of burnt offering; His own black blood poured out like a sheet of flame over his fecundating herd As he gave himself forth.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">But also it was a fiery fortress frowning shaggily on the world And announcing battle ready.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Since the Lamb bewitched him with that red-struck flag His fortress is dismantled, His fires of wrath are banked down, His horns turn away from the enemy.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">He serves the Son of Man.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">And hear him bellow, after many years, the bull that serves the Son of Man. Moaning, booing, roaring hollow, Constrained to pour forth all his fire down the narrow sluice of procreation Through such narrow loins, too narrow.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Is he not overcharged by the dammed-up pressure of his own massive black blood, Luke, the Bull, the father of substance, after two thousand years? Is he not overfull of offering, a vast, vast offer of himself Which must be poured through so small a vent?</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Too small a vent.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Let him remember his horns, then. Seal up his forehead once more to a bastion, Let it know nothing. Let him charge like a mighty catapult on the red-cross flag, let him roar out challenge on the world, And throwing himself upon it, throw off the madness of his blood; Let it be war.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">And so it is war.</field>
      <field name="heading_text">Saint John</field>
      <field name="fulltext">John, oh John, Thou honorable bird, Sun-peering eagle.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Taking a bird's-eye view Even of Calvary and Resurrection, Not to speak of Babylon's whoredom.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">High over the mild effulgence of the dove, Hung all the time, did we but know it, the all-knowing shadow Of John's great gold-barred eagle.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">John knew all about it, Even the very beginning.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"In the beginning was the Word, And the Word was God, And the Word was with God."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Having been to school, John knew the whole proposition. As for innocent Jesus, He was one of Nature's phenomena, no doubt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Oh that mind-soaring eagle of an Evangelist, Staring creation out of countenance And telling it off As an eagle staring down on the Sun!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Logos, the Logos! "In the beginning was the Word."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Is there not a great Mind preordaining? Does not a supreme Intellect ideally procreate the Universe? Is not each soul a vivid thought in the great conscious-stream of God?</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Put salt on his tail, The sly bird of John.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Proud intellect, high-soaring Mind Like a king eagle, bird of the most High, sweeping the round of heaven And casting the cycles of creation On two wings, like a pair of compasses; Jesus' pale and lambent dove, cooing in the lower boughs On sufferance.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">In the beginning was the Word, of course; And the Word was the first offspring of the almighty Johannine mind, Chick of the intellectual eagle.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Yet put salt on the tail of the Johannine bird, Put salt on its tail, John's eagle.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Shoo it down out of the empyrean Of the all-seeing, all fore-ordaining ideal; Make it roost on bird-spattered, rocky Patmos, And let it moult there, among the stones of the bitter sea.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">For the almighty eagle of the fore-ordaining Mind Is looking rather shabby and island-bound these days; Moulting, and rather nak'd about the rump, and down in the beak, Rather dirty, on dung-whitened Patmos.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">From which we are led to assume That the old bird is weary and almost willing That a new chick should chip the extensive shell Of the mundane egg.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The poor old golden eagle of the creative spirit Moulting and moping and waiting, willing at last For the fire to burn it up, feathers and all, So that a new conception of the beginning and end Can rise from the ashes.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Ah Phoenix, Phoenix, John's Eagle!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Phoenix, Phoenix, The nest is in flames, Feathers are singeing, Ashes flutter flocculent, like down on a blue, wan fledgeling.</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Apostolic Beasts</field>
      <field name="title_facet">The Apostolic Beasts</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">apostolic beasts</field>
      <field name="title_text" boost="1.0">The Apostolic Beasts</field>
      <field name="year_display">1921</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1921</field>
   </doc>
</add>
