<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Robinson, Roger, editor</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Robinson, Roger, editor</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">robinson roger editor</field>
      <field name="author_text">Robinson, Roger, editor</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">legacy/uvaBook/tei/RobWrit.xml</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Online Texts</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Online Texts</field>
      <field name="editor_display">Roger Robinson</field>
      <field name="editor_text">Roger Robinson</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="full_title_text">Writing Wellington: Twenty Years of Victoria University Writing Fellows</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:477341</field>
      <field name="langauge_display">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_facet">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_text">English</field>
      <field name="location_facet">Internet materials</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Writing Wellington: Twenty Years of Victoria University Writing Fellows</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod02.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">UVA Library Digital Repository</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="heading_text">1979 Joseph Musaphia 1979 Joseph Musaphia</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Charlie Wellman Pale bony fingers gripped the top rail on B deck as he surveyed the houses perched on the steep green hills surrounding Wellington's inner harbour. Chaim Walkowitz was not afraid of falling overboard. He was afraid of missing something that would reveal whether or not New Zealand was a suitable home for a twelve-year-old Polish orphan. The SS Ormonde steamed through the heads on a clear day in January 1946. A brisk warm northerly chopped the harbour waters , but the elements were irrelevant as Chaim studied this strange city on the opposite side of the planet to the malevolence that had devastated his childhood. Goats would find it easier using those houses . The youngster's height when standing erect meant the top rail was at eye level and obscuring his line of sight. He had to bend his knees to get a better view. Except that pushing his head forward to increase the angle of his vision bumped the peak of the grey cloth cap against the rail and down over his sad brown eyes, forcing him to bend even more and tilt his face upwards to observe the new world passing the ship's port side. Chaim's discomfort was as irrelevant as the elements. Baggy brown woollen shorts accentuated thin legs with one grey sock up and one grey sock down. The oversize grey jacket had been given to him by a Salvation Army woman at the London refugee centre, hoping her gesture might somehow alleviate the horrors this pathetic little boy must have endured. It covered a short-sleeved white shirt that Mrs Polikoff had ironed at five-thirty that morning for their apprehensive arrival on these distant South Pacific islands. The jacket's sleeves had fallen back from his gaunt wrists to reveal the last three digits of the number '138521' tattooed on his left forearm. The stocky figure of Mrs Polikoff stood bravely against the railing alongside young Chaim. A black woollen scarf covered her head and she clutched a dark blue overcoat about her ample body. Pure habit. January in the South Pacific bore no resemblance to Januaries in Europe. Her soft face was never far from smiling. No matter what confronted her or her family she always held to the belief that, 'everything will be alright'. Never mind that for the past decade life had been appalling. Her fortitude depended upon hoping for the best, so she said 'everything will be alright' as if it answered for every tribulation. Husband Victor was searching for their daughters. At seven and nine years old they were otherwise engaged during this historic moment with two Greek girls who had become their playmates during the five-and-a-half week journey. The ship's nooks and crannies made for endless games of hide and seek with squeals and giggles transcending the language barrier. Mrs Polikoff's bravery was vital, as the 120 European refugees on the ship knew what they had lost but not what they would gain. They had survived pogroms, war and the death camps, but as New Zealand loomed closer by the minute there was the fear of the unknown. The feeling they were landing on with alien flora and fauna, not to mention alien rules, regulations, laws and commandments. The Polikoffs had spent many shipboard hours discussing their future in this country. A discussion made all the more difficult by having no real idea what life was like in this far-flung corner of the British Empire. As far as distance goes this was surely the ultimate diaspora and they were all familiar with the story of the refugee in a European transit camp asked to which country he would like to emigrate. 'New Zealand,' was the unenthusiastic reply. 'Why so far?' enquired the official. 'Far?' The refugee shrugged. 'From where?' Still, one indisputable fact overshadowed their discussions about New Zealand being better or worse than Europe—unlike millions of others they were alive to start anew. Victor Polikoff was even luckier. He had the most wonderful cousin already living in New Zealand waiting to welcome them with a home and a job. Chaim had been chosen along with eleven other orphans to start a new life at a Wellington establishment set up by a couple who had escaped Tsarist Russia and now offered shelter to as many Jewish orphans as the New Zealand government would allow into the country. The Polikoffs were Chaim's chaperones on the journey from London. On the journey from his home town to the death camp he had been in the company of his mother and three sisters, his father having died in 1939. A blessing he would not have envisaged in his worst nightmare. The youngest Walkowitz was the only survivor. When the family arrived at the camp males and females had been separated. He never saw his mother and sisters again, but even at ten years old he did not have to see them die to know one's ordered fate in a death camp. Innocence was not an extenuating circumstance when the capital offence was your birth. One of the many seagulls that had joined the ship in Cook Strait swooped down and up again directly in front of them. It could not divert his scrutiny of New Zealand. Mrs Polikoff followed the flight of the seagull and it brought her gaze down to the forlorn twelve-year-old beside her. She noticed the button on his jacket was through the wrong buttonhole and bent down to correct it, as if this sartorial fault might have a negative influence on whatever bureaucracy processed their arrival in this country. Chaim did not notice her fussing with his jacket. They all wore second-hand clothing that accentuated their refugee status, with Chaim's the baggiest and saddest. He had said little since they first met in London seven weeks ago. Most of that had been for an English-speaking Polish schoolteacher who had organised daily language classes on the ship. A few of the refugees had dropped out of these two-hour lessons in frustration, but most of them had been glad of the opportunity for some sort of head start on whatever it was they would encounter 'down under'. Chaim had been the keenest, always seeking out the teacher as the time approached for the next lesson, making sure that he at least was on hand. His dedication had been rewarded last night when the teacher announced that he had used the five and a half weeks of lessons to the best advantage and had picked up a sizeable vocabulary. Though she warned all of them that this difficult new language contained a host of unique words and phrases. Unfortunately, warning them that the little they had learnt could be easily misinterpreted made them doubt the little they had learnt, resulting in most of them retreating to 'please' and 'thank you', in the hope that at the very least the citizens of this country would recognise if not appreciate good manners. They had survived a master plan wherein the lucky ones were designated infinitely superior and the unlucky ones manifestly inferior, so being polite could be the difference between life and death. Someone pointed out a car driving along the sea-level road separating the urbanised hills from the white-capped waters. They studied the dark vehicle's progress in silence until it disappeared round a bend in one of the harbour's many small bays, leaving only the seagulls to show there was life in these islands. By the time the ship docked they had a better idea of the local fauna. Everyone—including Victor Polikoff and his daughters—crowded the railings to watch the harbour workers bring the ship alongside the wharf. They could have joined the bustling crowd downstairs waiting to disembark as soon as the ship tied up, but after five and a half weeks the ship had become familiar, whereas New Zealand was as mysterious as life after death. One of the harbour workers waved to the refugees. None waved back. Chaim studied the strength, the competence of the big man tying a thick yellow rope to a rusty bollard and imagined himself having leapt ahead in time. Me down there doing what that man's doing. Talking New Zealandese as if it's my only language. Living like I was born in New Zealand. Like my life was someone else's and that man was on B deck watching me with my New Zealand muscles tie my New Zealand ship to my New Zealand wharf .    *     *    * Queuing before Customs officers and their wide wooden tables in a cavernous waterfront shed was a ludicrous formality, as the refugees had nothing but bundles of second-hand clothing. The two senior Polikoffs spent most of their time waving and calling out in Yiddish to Victor's cousin and family waiting in the crowd roped off from the new arrivals. The two Polikoff daughters clung dumbfounded to their mother's rough woollen skirt while dark-uniformed New Zealanders went about the task of checking, stamping and signing pieces of paper as if a misplaced comma heralded Armageddon. Occasionally an official would proffer a friendly greeting in English to a shabby newcomer. Usually this was met with a blank stare, but some responded with a nod or an apologetic smile. Like spectators at a tennis match, the children looked from the official to his target in the queue to see if what was said was understood, then back again to see what resulted when it clearly was not understood. Chaim clung to no one. In the midst of this regimented bustle he was left where he wanted to be left. Alone. He might look like a child, they might treat him like a child, but the death camp had culled the bewildered from the shrewd, the weak from the strong, the boys from the men and the unlucky from the lucky. 'This way!' An official unhooked the rope and beckoned the Polikoffs away from the wooden tables and into the tearful embrace of their relatives. Chaim avoided this fuss and stayed in the background until Mr and Mrs Davis, who owned the orphanage,stepped out of the crowd and made him the centre of attention. 'Chaim Walkowitz?' Mrs Davis beamed fierce blue eyes and a gold tooth down at the hapless child from atop her black, ankle-length astrakhan coat. He nodded and stared blankly into the faces of those responsible for his presence in New Zealand. The Polikoff family having fulfilled their obligation to chaperone him to the other side of the world, hugged the pale little boy goodbye and departed from his life forever. Mr Davis was a short, round man prone to breathlessness at the slightest exertion. He always deferred to his wife who squatted to bring her face level with Chaim's and gripped his shoulders as if he must not escape, though the compassion in her voice belied any such intent. Holding him in this position she spoke quietly in Yiddish, to which he listened but did not react. I spoke Yiddish on the other side of the world where it marked you out as an alien enemy, but here I'll speak New Zealandese or I'll speak nothing . She explained about 'the Sterns'. A New Zealand Jewish couple who wanted to be his foster parents. They had a thirteen-year-old son and a twelve-year-old daughter. How did he feel about staying a week at their 'lovely home' with the promise that if he did not like it he was free to come and live at the orphanage, where he would be taken care of as if it was his own home? Where Mr and Mrs Davis would treat him as if he were their own son?</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Joseph Musaphia, born in 1935 in London, was one of the most successful and prolific New Zealand playwrights of the 1970s—80s, his best-known stage plays being Victims (1973), Mothers and Fathers (1975) and Hunting (1979) . He had previously written more than 120 rsdio scripts, screenplays, lyrics and work for television. Since 1980 he has worked mainly as a journalist. 'Charlie Wellman', from which this extract is taken, is his second novel; his first, Let Us Be Naked , was published by Quoin Press in 1997.</field>
      <field name="heading_text">1980 Louis Johnson 1980 Louis Johnson</field>
      <field name="fulltext">City Sunday The jaunty straws, the Sunday hats Stroll blandly from the Government flats, Their plastic fruit and flowers of glass On heads as dark as beaten brass Gleam in the sun: sedate beside Blue suits, white collars, quietly stride. Ahead of them, like nylon fawns, Two skirted children eye the lawns For weekday running: now green grass Wears an ironshod word—'Trespass.' But like cicadas in the trees The band ahead has news to please. Its solemn notes rise thin and clear Upon the neutral Sunday air Where even buses learn to mute The rancour of their usual route And rising bush absorbs all sound Before it gets above the ground. One pair of high heels on the path Creates the only hint of wrath To crack the windows of this view As goes a girl, all limbs, and new To old designs and repetitions That may restore the lost positions. But she has vanished through the trees And eyes revert through stone degrees As the band turns the page to surge Onwards through its ponderous dirge, And suits and hats arise, resume Their walk, then home to habit's room.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Holidays Home from play: Miranda bearing the day's takings—a minute hedgehog. One of the three, she explains, fallen into holes dug by the other father for posts: and this prize, as she places it to feed from the bowl of slops on the lawn, lurches, dragging a back leg so sickeningly I know something is much broken like my own peace for another unreasoning avalanche of the sense of hurt that always unbalances. And damn language fails again: only the hurt speaks plunging to pity when the language of size adds its diminutions. It all depends on definition and training. Were it vermin . . . I have kicked rats to death           crushed spiders and crawlies, ticklers of another trade and conscience. This small one agonises towards the ward of shrubs to lie from sight so slow I ambulance it with the fireshovel bristling with pain like a hot coal           and burns among dry leaves and twigs (while the heedless grandeur of nature knives away at lusts and possessions) its faint side suspiring while we all die into ourselves as night falls.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Kapiti Coast You do not need to depend on the location to gain the poem: it is, perhaps, enough that a general sense of sea or sky persist or nag the memory to put you here in the mind's eye, gazing out on the specific ominous island you are told rises like ruin from an ocean haze of blood-soaked history. Interpretation begins. You can close your eyes if it helps to establish earshot and anguish, the heard and tasted tears that were real as stone and as hard to swallow. Not only a place, but what happened here. Each detail part of a map of pity you need not be intimate with because you have domesticated hurt. And yet you know. There is that current of water and air, electric, conducting the sense a louring sky might attempt to conceal. Houses whose inmates look out for the stranding of stories, miraculous mammals beached for their glory and anticipation. All to be handled and put away at day's end with bloodsports and entertainment. The place does not matter in detail if you remember there is terror best not recalled when nightfall crackles and flame blinds the beaches. Black stones from former feasting, and a set of kneecaps for cupping the springwater. Drink deep. Look again. Pray that rain might squall; obliterate: memory be cleansed. Hope to reopen eyes, and see.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Louis Johnson (1924—88) was a central figure in New Zealand poetry for over thirty years, despite spending the 1970s in Australia. In the 1950s he was the key figure in the innovative 'Wellington Group' and in the 1980s provided support for younger writers through his Antipodes Press. He founded and edited New Zealand Poetry Yearbook 1951— 54 He died during his tenure of the Katherine Mansfield Fellowship at Menton.</field>
      <field name="heading_text">1981 Vincent O'Sullivan 1981 Vincent O'Sullivan</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Three Pieces for Academe Setting it right Dr W.C. Williams couldn't think less of those high-falutin' cherubs slopped across human sky—space, mafiosi with the monikers of classic hoods elbowing every bar minute a book's mentioned. Cut loose, the doctor said. How Columbus, C. (capitano) didn't plot out West for a propped Louis Quatorze mirror. It was black plug, cowboy movies, that's what he was after, 'poetry for cats and dogs', wasn't that New Jersey? The zebras, the gazelles, who's got them out back? Dr Williams couldn't bandage a finger without thinking, say it simpler , it's not vaticano brushwork makes it a joint worth saving, worth setting right. Contented, he leaned on his icebox and wrote a note and walked out on the stoop to watch a late sky burl in from the Atlantic, god-damned sure things were on the mend. To let puss know for one thing fat drops like flattened dimes fell for cats as far as Frisco. No Nostalgia on This Site The professor in retirement constructed an aviary which he filled with birds of diverse plumage, cordant and discordant com- municative systems, with habits, one or two, of droll sibilant mimicry, all eager for the palm dispensing top-quality seed as classes once had been, their essays fanned in his hand; each bird nomenclatured from the classics of his hey-day, Desdemona a canary of particular plangency, Burns a Scots cock after more than his share, Ezra, rifling at other avine nests. Yet the teacher famous for capacious wells of ready quotation declined, alas, swiftly forgetting their names, then the birds themselves. Within weeks the fluent rainbows, ethereal shimmers, mulched sloppy brilliance in random corners—does one need to describe it? Nurse said how he perked some days, grinned at a quick blur high up, was inclined to talk peculiar. To which his wife said, 'Yes, poetry. He always has.' Quaintly his mind closed down, like a parrot under its hood. Well, there's nothing nice about this story, the widow's house razed for quick investment, the bull- dozer grossly demolishing the lot, so that weeks before term a disco rises, The Shagged Phoenix , students asking 'Who? Old what's it?', even the young S/M professor they fall for, cool as, not a discourse he couldn't plait through discursive octaves, semantic conundra descanted on at the drop of whatever. Yet lo! how a hyped dude carries in from a scrap of surviving garden a feather the size of a thumb so it's like his thumb's on fire. On the beak of a stuffed toucan someone smartly graffiting, Entropy, Right On ! Going Down for Air Mole, who is not the brightest creature but industrious and mildly droll, dug and dug against the day of definitions, worked tunnel to tunnel, stroked a paw across honest sweat, sentimentally thought on the odd evening, sipping a lager, how beneath the entire city ran another city which was his, Moles- ville . The suave chatty professor he sometimes drank with liked to hear the stories of how the galleries connected and shafts bucketed down light and the double doors made it impossible, virtually, to be pursued or even discovered. Mole perfected the city that was like a more splendid city on the other side of a mirror laid where the skyscrapers rose and rose while his went down. The suave professor let him see the bullet he laughingly called a pellet from the orifice of Correctness. 'It's silver, you know,' he said. Then shot the Mole. The deepest, nicest, safest place you could imagine ready to be moved into, spick, complete. But a disappointment, to say the least, when his morning coffee on the inverted heights, even his Croix du Sud croissant , reeked of rankest mole.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Vincent O'Sullivan (b. 1937) is Director of the Stout Research Centre and Professor of English at Victoria University. A leading New Zealand figure in poetry, fiction and drama, as well as anthologist and critic, his best known works are The Butcher Papers (1982) , Palms and Minarets: Selected Stories (1992), Shuriken (1983), Let the River Stand (1993) (winner of the Montana Book Award) and the Collected Letters of Katherine Mansfield (ed., with Margaret Scott, 1984—). His novel Believers to the Bright Coast was published in 1998.</field>
      <field name="heading_text">1982 Witi Ihimaera 1982 Witi Ihimaera</field>
      <field name="fulltext">A History of New Zealand Literature Through Selected Texts (An abstract for a paper to be presented at the LALALAND Conference.) My paper will explore the various texts of identity, representation and construction as presented in eighteen selected New Zealand novels, films and poetic works. In so doing it will try to engage with the semiotics of contact and the various diasporic, immigrant, exilic and expatriate notions of this country, alternatively known as the Land of the Wrong White Crowd. The alternative realities, asymmetries and linguistic aesthetics of Pakeha New Zealand and their textual collisions with the Maori race will also be explored, much as Shashi Tharoor has done for India in his seminal revisionist, eclectic and postmodernist work, The Ingrate's Indian Novel . My paper is offered in homage from one subversive to another. The selected New Zealand texts are: Nohwere This great New Zealand title belongs to an ancestral Pakeha settler society text, elevated to canonical heights by people who have, actually, never read it. The paper will examine the reasons for the deplorable level of English transported to this virgin country from Great Britain, especially the bad spelling. Sold New Zealand Another canonical text in New Zealand literature, Sold New Zealand considers the truths about the Pakeha settler society from the perspective of a so-called Pakeha-Maori. Ostensibly a tract defending Maori, Sold New Zealand turns out to provide not the mediation between two binaries but rather the rationale for Pakeha to take over Maori New Zealand. Maori should never have signed the Treaty of Waitangi or in any way trusted the buggers. The Greenstone Flaw The paper will offer a critique on this rip-roaring yarn, a prototype of the romantic heroic settler novel of the mid-to late-nineteenth century. It is typical of those constructs of White hegemony, involving such characters as the White hero, friendly Maori sidekick, Maori princess who saves the White hero from the usual volcanic eruption or earthquake presumably so he can go back home to marry the (White) woman who has been waiting for him all along. Freire, Said, Ghandi, Spivak, Marx, Foucault, the Spice Girls and aspects of the film Titanic will be invoked in the paper to provide an utterly useless (con)text to text. The Pardon Garty Acknowledgment is made of one of New Zealand's greatest short story writers in the paper and the curious dichotomous ambivalent position she holds in New Zealand letters. The author disliked New Zealand, left it to its own devices, never came back and wrote all her major stories about New Zealand while living in France. The paper will propose this trailing of skirts through colonial space as being a metaphor for the meta-schizophrenic nature of the New Zealand psyche. Land Brawl in Unknown Trees One of the great verse sequences of New Zealand literature, Land Brawl in Unknown Trees lends itself to questions of power, resistance, indigenous essence, Fatal Contact, antipodean vision and the mapping out of Maori and Pakeha dialogical space. If you can understand what all this gobbledegook means please email the author of this paper w.ihimaera@wellington.ac.nz Children of the Whore and Once Were Worriers The paper will posit Britannia as prostitute and consider the sorry plight of her children, seeking diasporical haven in the new colonial space of New Zealand. The bifurcated problematics of the two books listed above will be compared and contrasted in one of those stupid and futile intellectual exercises beloved of academics and find contrasts and commonalities that don't exist. Bowels Do Dry A Bakhtinian Perspective will explore the Architectonic Self implicit in the main character, Daphne Withers, of this brilliant New Zealand novel. Random and totally inappropriate parallels with Arundhati Roy, Margaret Forster, classical Tamil poetry, Caribbean hybrid literature and Hindu sacred cow beliefs will reveal that when bowels do dry you can always rely on Janet Frame to provide superb discourse. All Visitors Aboard and Dumb These two novels from the White, male and realist tradition reveal that the Pakeha male writer is still very much alive and kicking—is he what . The paper will explore how men have been empowered and disempowered and include discussion on the sexual politics implicit in other such seminal male gender texts as Man Can Do It Alone, The Odd Boy, The Good Keen Ram and so on. When the time comes would the last White (straight) male, realist writer still standing in New Zealand please close the door before he leaves? A Creed for Women Just when Pakeha male writers thought they were home and scot-free along came the feminist revolution to stop them in their hobnail boot tracks and Swandris. The paper will explore the feminist imperative in New Zealand literature, the whinges and whines of women and why it is that this imperative has resulted in some really awful first person narratives by the New Zealand sisterhood. This part of the paper could otherwise be titled Save The Males/Whales. No Ordinary Son and The Clone People By comparison, really excellent writing of a quality only matched by the Kalyani tribe of the Hindu Kush Mountains, a tribe only slightly lower than the Maori are to Heaven, is to be obtained in the texts written by Maori authors. Descended from the Gods, the poet of No Ordinary Son and the great Wordweaver of the West Coast, really do show that the Empire has indeed Struck Back. The paper will consider the negative aspects of global English on the sacred Sanskrit-Maori language and how the sterling battle has been waged by Xena and her Maori literary warriors to combat further marginalisation, invisibilisation, appropriation of text (cf Season of the Stew and The Sinking Pukkah-Papa ) and demonising of the Maori people by the villainous Pakeha. Discussion will also focus on essentialism vs synthesis, post-nativism and indigenous essence, and the upturning of notions of Centre and Rim in other (r)evolutionary Polynesian texts such as Cuzzies and Leave Us the Banyan Trees . The paper will also disclose the great literary secret, actually known to Maori all along, but only confirmed by the discovery of gold tablets on sacred Hikurangi Mountain, that Shakespeare's mother was a Maori. The implications of post-Shakespearian literature in English being a long lost branch of the Ngati Porou oral tradition (Shakespeare's appropriation is being contested in an action currently before the Waitangi Tribunal which seeks to reclaim him as a taonga) will be particularly highlighted in the paper. Na reira, kia kaha, kia manawanui, kia toa ki o tatou mahi tuhituhi i te Ao, ka mate ka mate ka ora ka ora etc etc. (Author's Note: This magical and spiritual ritualistic karakia or prayer must remain untranslated to preserve the very sacred nature of Maori textuality, all praise be to Allah, and to recognise the primacy of the reo.) Good Fry Pork Pie, The Abrogator and The Piano Finger These three texts exist in New Zealand film and the filmic intersections with literary equivalents show that postmodernism, postcolonialism and neocolonialism are structures which are perpetuated in film as well as literature. The first film indicates that New Zealanders are able to laugh at themselves—as long as the film involves a Mini—but the other two show that Pakeha unease and dis-ease still intersect with Pakeha New Zealand Lit. Questions of anxiety, uncertainty, evasion, ambiguity, ambivalence, deceptions, disclosures and the slipperiness evident in the Pakeha sense of self indicate that the post-settler identity of the New Zealand Pakeha is still in a whole heap of trouble. This is evidenced in the sidelining of Maori characters to the margins of discourse and, in particular, the metaphoric cutting off of the finger in the award-winning film, Piano . Thus, the paper will also discuss dismemberment as a Pakeha response to having no culture, genital mutilation, pornographic culture, the conflicting discourses of homo-erotic and hetero-erotic narratives in the film concerned—and the crucial question of what happened to the finger? It was not, as far as the author of this paper is aware, thrown out of a plane. Faking Peoples and The Fake-triach Finally, these last two texts, one historical and the other creative, confirm the rhyzomic nature of myth-making (and, incidentally, the continued invisibilising of gay, lesbian, transgender and bisexual people in New Zealand history indicative of the failure in 1997 of the Auckland City Council to recognise the liberating effects of the Hero Parade). Primarily, the paper will propose that all history is lies and all lies can be made into suspect novels or histories. The paper considers these two texts as both salvation of and destruction of myth-making and that, in New Zealand, it doesn't matter what the myth, demolish it (especially if it's Maori) and you may end up with a knighthood. The novel under discussion is the last of all the texts to be considered in the paper and should not in fact be included. However, rather than face accusations of being a spoilsport, the author—who is also the presenter of the paper to the LALALAND Conference—includes it as an indication that he can take the piss out of himself. To be frank, why critics have considered The Fake-triach aka Kiss of the Spider Woman Part 2 aka Magic Realism's Last Gasp as an impossible and unbelievable cybertext is beyond his comprehension. Many beautiful Maori grandmothers existed who once lived in Italy, sang arias by Verdi while fighting the Pakeha, and were pursued by vengeful mothers who could swim through the universe. The paper, as above, will be presented in the Atrium of the Peking Cluck Hotel at 5.30pm on Thursday. Those students wishing to get A+'s in the author's Masters Papers at Victoria University of Wellington, and other members of the public lucky enough to find a seat in the packed hall should attend. Please note that the paper is programmed to deconstruct five minutes after presentation. The author exerts his moral rights and, to pre-empt those who wish to take out a fatwa against his pure and innocent intentions, asserts that any resemblance to any New Zealand writer or to the proceedings of the 11th Triennial ACLALS Conference, December 1—6, Kuala Lumpur, 1998, is entirely coincidental.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Witi Ihimaera was born in Gisborne, graduated BA from Victoria University of Wellington and now lives in Auckland. His titles include Pounamu, Pounamu, Tangi, The Matriarch, Bulibasha, Nights in the Gardens of Spain and The Dream Swimmer . As librettist, he has worked in opera, song cycle and symphony with narration. As editor, his books include Growing Up Maori, Mataora: Contemporary Maori Art and the five-volume Te Ao Marama series. He has just completed his second play, Woman Far Walking , and a biography of the soprano Virginia Zeani.</field>
      <field name="heading_text">1983 Michael King 1983 Michael King</field>
      <field name="fulltext">On the Purchase of Oysters, Terakihi and Trollopes It was John Beaglehole who spoke, somewhere, of 'the Regent Street curve of Lambton Quay'. He was lamenting the loss of a harmony of architectural styles that had characterised Wellington's best-known thoroughfare up to the era of gouging and rebuilding that began in the late 1950s. The comment was pure Beaglehole, apt and felicitous. It arose out of a love for his home city; and it reflected his brand of erudition, and that of his generation of scholars, which viewed so many features of New Zealand life from a perspective conditioned by a thorough knowledge of English history. That same erudition ensured that Beaglehole would have known the identity of Edward Gibbon Wakefield's patron John Lambton, Lord Durham, for whom the street had been named; and, of course, he was aware of its origin as a genuine quay running alongside the mid-nineteenth-century Wellington waterfront, before the uplift of earthquakes and the process of reclamation banished the sea some hundreds of metres to the east. It was the curve of that original beachfront that was responsible for what seemed like a glacier swerve once buildings loomed on both sides of the street. All of this I now know and understand. In my childhood, however, I had a more elementary view. Then, visiting Lambton Quay was a matter of going to town; and Lambton Quay, I believed, was the whole of that place called 'town'. I have no recollection of venturing beyond it up to the age of nine. There was no need. The Quay contained all the places that, for us, 'going to town' implied. My father's office at the advertising agency Carlton Carruthers du Chateau and King was in the South British Insurance Company Building down the Plimmer Steps end. The Bank of New South Wales, where my father persuaded a senior staff member to put aside Victorian and Edwardian currency for my collection of old coins, stood next door. The booksellers and stationers Whitcombe and Tombs, where we bought family copies of New Zealand classics (Oliver's New Zealand Birds , Graham's A Treasury of New Zealand Fishes , and Powell's Native Animals of New Zealand ) was close by. Right alongside Plimmer Steps was the fish shop run by the Barnao family where, like all good Catholics, we bought seafood on Fridays. This last was the subject of what would now be judged a politically incorrect song that my father would sing on the way home in the car, to the tune of 'O Solo Mio'. Bartolo Barnao Of Lambton Quay, He sella da oyster, Da teraki . . . This, I found out later, was a variant on a song sung about an even earlier fish shop owner, Nick Fernando. And there was more. Tony Paino and Vince Criscillo's fruit and vegetable shop, bursting with an unimaginable selection of produce. The man with a basket of flowers down the Woodward Street end who called out, 'Aaa, lovely Otaki violets . . .' The DIC and Kirkcaldie and Stains department stores, where we did Christmas and birthday shopping and were served by immaculately dressed women in black skirts and white blouses. And the Quay was the last domain of that now extinct breed, the street photographer, who took our pictures in a variety of family combinations as we strode along verandah-covered footpaths. The reason that 'going to town' provided such a sense of occasion, and that all these sights seemed so exotic, was that we lived on the then rural arm of the Pauatahanui inlet, where there was nothing remotely urban or suburban (Cambourne and Whitby were later intrusions). Getting to town, by train or by car, not only involved transporting ourselves to a different landscape; it was very often a different weather system too by the time we emerged from the second train tunnel or from the bottom of the Ngauranga Gorge and saw what Wellington and its colosseum of hills had in store for us. The meteorological transformation often seemed as complete as it would have been were we visiting another country. My first recollections of the Quay itself are shadowy and generic—just an awareness of being in a canyon of high grey and brown buildings, of trams rattling past down the centre of the road, and of being jostled by the constant movement of pedestrians. There was a touch of fear in that experience, and a need to keep a firm hold on my mother's or my grandmother's hand. But the dominant memory is one of excitement at the sight of so much mobile and noisy humanity. The same set of feelings came back to me when I walked for the first time down Fifth Avenue, which was cavernous and crowded to an extent Lambton Quay never was—but my perspective as an adult in New York in the 1970s matched that of a small child in Wellington in the late 1940s. My second memory is highly specific. On 15 December 1950, my fifth birthday, fulfilling a promise made one year earlier, my mother and grandmother took me to afternoon tea at Kirkcaldie and Stains. It's not the tea itself I recall vividly, though I do remember the cake-stand, its tiers of plates loaded with miniature sandwiches, scones and cakes on doilies. What I remember with absolute clarity is what we trooped to the window to watch passing in the street below us: Peter Fraser's funeral cortege. I knew nothing of bereavements, nor of the rituals and pageantry surrounding death, let alone the death of a wartime prime minister. And so I was intensely interested. The slow procession was led by an armoured personnel carrier hauling a gun carriage. On that carriage lay the coffin, covered with a kiwi-feather cloak, a symbol of leadership whose warm earth colour and soft texture contrasted with the cold steel of the war machines. Fraser's former colleagues walked in dark suits on either side of the carriage, divided by death as they were in life. The Labour members, who included a family friend, Phil Connolly, were on our side of the Quay. My mother identified them for me as they passed in single file. Walter Nash out front, now Leader of the Opposition, his square face set in granite solemnity. Behind him Arnold Nordmeyer, whose egglike head was so like the cartoonists' caricatures that he seemed to be imitating them. Then Eruera Tirikatene, tall, silver-haired, handsome in a cloak, not third in party seniority but in that position as chief mourner for the Maori people. Then the rest, unrecognisable and unmemorable to me. By the time they had passed, the government members on the far side, led by the Prime Minister Sid Holland, were too far off to be distinguishable from one another. Behind the mourners came a line of black limousines. Then lorries loaded with what, at funerals, are always called floral tributes, a blaze of colour in an otherwise sombre sequence. Then an army of trade unionists marching in ranks, shoulder to shoulder. They seemed soldierlike: not because they were in uniform—on the contrary, they were variously dressed in open-necked shirts and tattered sports coats—but because of their numbers, their formation and, most of all, their grim determination. All this was watched over by the largest crowd I had ever seen, lining both sides of the Quay, crammed on to shop verandahs, leaning out of windows of buildings such as Kirkcaldie and Stains. Strangely, there was no sound, no audible expression of emotion. The effect was one of solemnity rather than grief—a farewell to a man respected rather than loved. My grandmother, however, who lived then in the railway settlement at Ngaio, dabbed her eyes and announced that he had been a good and a great man and a friend to working people. The years passed. I grew up. Lambton Quay no longer seemed so cavernous at street level. And I learned about other parts of the city: Willis Street, beyond Stewart Dawson's corner, where the handwritten headlines of that day's Evening Post were displayed in the street-level window; Manners Street, home of the left-wing bookshop Modern Books; Mercer Street, where Dick Reynolds presided over that marvellous second-hand emporium, Smith's Bookshop; Courtenay Place, with the best of the cinemas and Chinese restaurants; and Boulcott Street, with St Mary of the Angels, where we attended midnight mass at Christmas and Easter and revelled in the sound of Maxwell Fernie's choir. In every sense that mattered, however, Lambton Quay was still 'town'. In the course of my rare visits to the city from boarding school in the Hutt Valley, my mother would meet me at the railway station. From there, to allow me to experience something called 'coffee bar culture', whose major features seemed to be candles in Chianti bottles and heavily mascara'd women in bouffant hair-dos and fishnet stockings, she would take me to the Rendez-Vous coffee shop near the entrance to Cable Car Lane. (It was a sine qua non that such establishments had to have French names: there was also the Chez Paree and the Monde Marie; even the one that did not was still called The French Maid.) On one such occasion at the Rendez-Vous, told that the premises had a newly opened upstairs gallery, my mother led me with our cups of coffee and plates of cream cakes into the adjacent and plush office of a prominent accountant, who was just as startled to see us as we were to encounter him. Later still, when I was a university student in the mid-sixties, I always took the Kelburn cable car to and from town, so that Lambton Quay was invariably my point of access and egress. It was in these years that I began to haunt Roy Parsons' sparsely elegant bookshop, by this time established in the Ernst Plischke-designed Massey House. An additional attraction there was the coffee bar that Harry Seresin and his mother had opened on the mezzanine floor, which, among many other attractions, was the first Wellington eatery to make and sell yoghurt. Further along the Quay were the Parsons' shabby but enticing bookseller neighbours, Ferguson and Osborn. The business was run by the eccentric and bad-tempered siblings Harold and Vera Osborn, who seemed to have an inexhaustible supply of unopened first editions selling at their original, pre-inflation prices, and who, right to the end, parcelled all purchases in brown paper tied with string. In those years too I evolved a routine of Friday night drinking. In the case of the crowd I had fallen in with, this meant heading for the first-floor lounge bar of the Midland Hotel. From that genteel den of iniquity other rites of passage followed: the courtship of members of the fairer sex who joined us there, or floated provocatively on our periphery (of the latter, I recall in particular a pair of blonde Dutch-Jewish twins, with plunging necklines and Stars of David on silver chains); the purchase and subsequent juggling of bottles to have in hand for whatever entertainment would complete the evening; the post-six o'clock meals at the steak bar over the road whose name I no longer recall; and the subsequent converging on taxi ranks for transport to the scene of that night's party in Kelburn, Wadestown or Tinakori Road. Memories of later years speed up, the way recollections do as they approach the present, and are less vivid. In my journalism days, after the abolition of six o'clock closing, there were regular drinking sessions with journalists at Barrett's Hotel (primarily Evening Post staffers—Keith Gunn, Doug McNeil, Donald McDonald). And there was an entirely different school at De Brett's made up of the city's Maori professionals (Koro Dewes, Waka Vercoe, Ross White). The writers Alistair Campbell and Harry Orsman gathered for a time with musicians at the Dungeon Bar of the Royal Tavern, then abandoned it for some pub in Willis Street. Twenty years earlier, my father had drunk with Denis Glover, Jim Baxter, Tony Vogt and Lou Johnson in the old Royal Hotel on the same site. In the early 1970s there was the welcome appearance on Plimmer Steps of John Quilter's bookshop, eventually to shift down to the Quay proper. It was in the original location that I overheard the kind of conversation one dines out on for years afterwards. A flushed gentleman in tweeds burst into the shop and hurtled to the counter, where he asked in a loud voice, 'I say, do you have any Trollopes?' There was a silence while the proprietor considered the implications of the question. Then a customer intervened. 'Wrong place, mate,' he said. 'You want Vivian Street.' In 1980 I turned my back on the Wellington district in favour of the winterless north and have made only sporadic return visits. When I am back, I am frequently surprised at ways in which Lambton Quay has improved: the pavement cafes, the renovations of such treasures as the Public Trust Building, the extent to which even the buildings which John Beaglehole regarded as intrusions now look as if they belong. I am grateful too for landmarks and reference points that survive, like Parsons' and Quilter's. But I am also aware of the 'silences between'—the businesses and buildings that have entirely disappeared along with the trams: Ferguson and Osborn, the Cadeau giftshop, the Rendez-Vous, the Midland, De Brett's, Barrett's. The Quay is simultaneously familiar and unfamiliar to me as it sheds old skins and acquires new ones. In one important respect it doesn't change, however. If I ever want to recapture the feeling of belonging to a town, of casting off anonymity, I do it there. In ten minutes at Bowen Street corner, or at the bottom of Woodward Street, I can be sure of sighting and talking to at least half-a-dozen people I know: old school friends, acquaintances from university, current and retired journalists, civil servants, politicians. Lambton Quay is not, was not and never will be my place of residence. But it brings me as near as I shall ever come in my life to feeling part of an urban community; and it connects my past to my present.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Michael King (b. 1945), biographer and historian, was awarded an Honorary DLitt by Victoria University in 1997. His Whina, a biography of Whina Cooper, won the Wattie Book of the Year Award. Other major publications include Te Puea (1977), Maori: A Photographic and Social History (written during his Victoria University Fellowship) , Moriori: A People Rediscovered ( 1989) and Frank Sargeson (1995). In 1999, as Burns Fellow at Otago University, he is writing a life of Janet Frame .</field>
      <field name="heading_text">1984 Ian Wedde 1984 Ian Wedde</field>
      <field name="fulltext">My Victorian Year The record shows that in 1984 when I had the writing fellowship at Victoria, I completed a big historical novel, a short comic novel, a book of selected poems, an anthology of New Zealand poetry, and a new book of poems called Tendering . An output of such heroic proportions needs to be treated with kindly scepticism. Nineteen-eighty-four was indeed a good year for me: a year whose garrulous tides went in and out. It allowed me to complete much that was not, and to commit much that would not otherwise have got past the warm-up. Symmes Hole , a big 'hysterical' novel, was published in 1986: what happened to it in 1984 was the application of bromides. Survival Arts , described as a 'comic novel', was published in 1988: the crippled weka that limps out the tragic rhythm of the book's heart was one I'd seen when, self-marooned in the Sounds, I was finishing the first draft of Symmes Hole . It's hard for me to find the place of my Victorian year within these continuities. I guess, and could check, but do not remember, that the Survival Arts story that continued where Symmes Hole stopped, began to be written in 1984. The note at the front of Driving into the Storm: selected poems says, 'Much of the work was done while I had the writing fellowship at Victoria University, and would have been difficult without that time.' The book was published in 1987, which suggests delays. It went through a hesitant development that was steadied at the editorial end by Michele Leggott who gave me the nerve to select and probably did most of it. At the production end, a set of brilliant cover designs by Gavin Chilcott, now in the collection of the Hocken Library in Dunedin, and not viewed by me until 1998, annotate a difficult birth. It was not during my Victorian year that these lovely designs were made. I saw smudged photocopies of a couple of them, which were not used. I never bonded with the hideous factory production that eventuated. I also, now, rediscover another phrase from the introduction: 'This selection stops at a point where I'd begun to reconsider what I was doing in writing.' A mild sense of the ominous enters at this 'point', shepherded by a book that gave way to production what it owed to integrity—a 'point' which is also the point at which the end of one novel became the beginning of another. This flow-on I cannot find in my memory of the Victorian year. What I do remember very clearly, is the final stage of the co-editing of the Penguin Book of New Zealand Verse , published in 1985. What this involved for me, at the most personal level, was the discovery of a scepticism about what I was doing with writing, which would evolve into dislike, and subsequently into a decision to step away from the burbling storm-drain of narrative out of which books came by means of a process more like bucketing than thinking. The work of editing a large anthology is profoundly humbling. You encounter not only the few, piercing moments of great writing, highly individual and remembered as absolutely specific, but also the immense emotional force of the collective minor. There is nothing wrong with the innate elitism of all writing with pretensions to individuality. But what I began to encounter in myself, as I looked into the mirror of the anthology, was more like snobbery: the critically endorsed belief that much of the value of what I wrote consisted in its individuality, in stylistic skiting. This beginning of disenchantment; this first stirring of a sense of fraudulence; this desire to 'collect' the poems I'd written mostly in order to be able to start again—what was happening, was that my Victorian year with its surging tides of production was also the year in which I began, not yet deliberately, to stop writing. What I remember most clearly of all about the year, with immense nostalgic anticipation (and apart from the dreamlike, fabulous, infantile, corrupting fantasy of earning money without any sense of transaction), is the writing of most of the poems in Tendering , presumably at the 'point where I'd begun to reconsider what I was doing in writing'. The writing of much of this book came out of the evolutionary crisis of my Victorian year. It happened on the evolved side of my doubts, over the fence of Driving into the Storm . The key poem in it was 'The Relocation of Railway Hut 49', in which the tale of my writing shed at home was interwoven with the tale of my great-grandfather, Heinrich Augustus Wedde, and with The Tempest . I still enjoy the way the language of this poem, and of the others in the book, stirs up 'the dutiful oil of narrative' (a grizzling phrase from the introduction to Driving into the Storm ). There's a reference in 'The Relocation' to 'contenders' who are 'shooting up katipo venom'—they would crop up again in Survival Arts as one of that novel's insane variations on nationalism, which I do remember writing a lot of in the '49' shed, after my Victorian year. I particularly remember enjoying sitting in the scruffily bucolic haven of the shed, reading up about tank warfare in Vietnam (not in the University library) and the bizarre history of tarantula cults (deep in the cobwebby parts of the University library, which I visited with a mild sense of post-Victorian trespass). The mercilessly mechanical narrative structure of this 'comic novel', together with its manifest loathing of exposition, and its relish of mundane melodrama (I love the book)—these character traits also give notice of advancing scepticism and even boredom, and indeed the large novel about Chinese Opera that followed is, to this day, on hold pending my return to the writing I began to stop doing in 1984. This is not to say my Victorian year was the one that stopped me writing. On the contrary, it was the one that made it possible for me to start again, which, fifteen years later, I eagerly look forward to doing. This is a paradox that will be recognised by other writers whose shit-detectors have been given the time to assist them grow out of their own needy relationship with writing. And let's be a little more frank—I didn't really 'stop', with all the chaste melodrama that implies. I relocated the effort, much as I'd relocated the Railways shed. My Victorian year helped me to start that process. It was a life-saver. 'The Relocation' is my testimonial.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Relocation of Railway Hut 49 1 Yet why shouldn't I aim with 'tender' the best stories begin 'you're not going to believe this but' I'm still just a taut sailor on shore leave in life (time to get back in the tender) like my tempest tossed great-grandfather before me 'Tend to th' master's whistle' two white doves flirt by the water Heinrich Augustus and Maria Van Reepen Barnacle Bill and the Scandinavian Princess I couldn't either live away from how light stirs in the surface (time to attend to the water) sounds bound once in the braids and weeds of seas or how the waves wash my spring head in sun fishscales glittering on my dead father's arms through how may lives' gentle propulsion his sea man ship escorted me here (pit ease sake against sea men) and you can see how the pitted concrete face of the city begins to show the short history of an early disenchantment (certain material securities have not stood up) drown the books let purpose buckle against something of no substance the rainbows that fall into our open mouths our legal tender of breath (here's just a pet food kingdom) and the kids in Fun City aren't going to walk in one day and say 'Enough Space Invaders, it's the revolution' (it's just a dog food factory) it's the first few ships Cooked Breakfast, Bad Karma and Gaga in Toto stirring light into the water whatever acids history serves us to fling that I can't live away from (imaginary mountains won't budge either) just heave to live ear listen see man pen meander the moon drips light through my roof wind croons in my ear wherever I am there's no where to go (chance is just another iron butterfly) 2 And you easy mark for the sick vertigo of underemployed responsibility better look out! Know where to go! Is the light fading will the Cruise Ship ram the atoll how do you read your musical watch in the dark and what happens next? Way out west among the black iron dunes contenders are shooting up katipo venom— now there's nationalism for you! Heinrich Augustus sailed through the Dangerous Archipelago beneath unfamiliar stars— hanged if he was born to drown on an acre of barren ground. No vertigo. Mid ocean reek of reef mermaid's braids uncharted smell of weed stellar sound of grief's wreck passion's gentle helm 'Must our mouths be cold?' 3 Nose to tail in the pool the swimmers turning and turning I enter the tainted bowl of my affections my chemical chalice eyes grape pulped by chlorine Through how many lives' genital propulsion his sea man's tender helm engendered to end here to prosper This line I heave to Heinrich Augustus This mouth I warm for him 4 As ship-rig pilot to this harbour that the craft not founder as reef and bar tender I sköl him founder of my line disenchantment and an end of meandering here he found her by sea man's nurture to tend her his delicate dove by the wind's waves shoving moonlight up the bay outside the door of 49 the fast clouds roar their shadow steers the sea I tendered for the relocation of hut 49 single men's quarters Thorndon Quay Railway Yards you're not going to believe this but $50 and got it. 5 Outside the door of 49 will be a slender almond tree pohutukawas will scratch the panes Past all realism the pet food kingdoms green ache of barren drowned broken knowledge of disenchanter's art grave few whirled The nearby smokehouse leaking mists: eels, trout, chicken 49 dim in smoke and autumn dusk the delicate almond whirling its leaves Ships tended for weather tides turn keeping tides to leeward of their pick and 49's the bower I line on while everything under the moon swings Heart's vanity to prosper brave new pastoral acre in tended 49 my praise pilots the smoky light through pain. 6 der Fischer Hanging today the glass door in 49 Heinrich Augustus born in 1840 balance and an easy swing out spliced his own tackle with a sewing needle light casting its lures in fouled the line and plunged in after it sound of rain squall on the pane double pneumonia in Blenheim in 1916 jammed any door I ever tried to hang appropriate death for an old sea man balance and illumination I can't do it only thing missing was salt in the water tomorrow, windows 7 Disenchanted city of few lights and less music stand by pilot for ship rig these clear stars of an Indian summer one border your breath won't passport harbour night watch man later here in the dark no man's land you draw breath like credit how long can that last? Steered clear of the army ran to sea at fourteen and never been home tending the tension right on pension night schnapps intoning enlightenment how much equity left in your barren domes or hope in your heart pumping its orders? My glittering dead father now watch man pilot on his own death ship remembered Heinrich's lone order and schnapps 'above all I respect his memory' and all unnoticed by those armies camped among their dazzling constellations. Unnoticed Heinrich intoning Goethe light entertainment between their watch towers the wasteful panting of your lover's breath Hello goodbye I'm here I'm gone hello. 8 By the brave sail to prosper on the strange sixth hour down under drinking the new autumn air before me amazing kitchenettes all sun set kissed discover the world lovers at play past all real ache men trod. Spitting seeds from hut 49 orange's sweet cold cramps sun kissed and tempest tossed my little residence my making sense the only conclusions ever reached just heave to live there.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Ian Wedde (b. 1946) is a poet, fiction writer, critic, art critic and arts administrator. His major publications include Made Over (1974), Earthly: Sonnets for Carlos (1975), Spells for Coming Out (1977), Driving into the Storm: Selected Poems (1987), Tendering (1988), the novel Symmes Hole(1986), the Penguin Book of New Zealand Verse (ed., with Harvey McQueen, 1985) , How to be Nowhere (1995) an d Fomison:what shall we tell them? (1994). He is a curator at Te Papa Tongarewa The Museum of New Zealand.</field>
      <field name="heading_text">1985 Patricia Grace 1985 Patricia Grace</field>
      <field name="fulltext">When the Lights Go On Again All Over the World While it was still dark Mereana went up to the front bedroom and waited with her mother by the window, looking down. 'There's a southerly coming up,' her mother said. If it had been daylight they would have seen the rooftops of the other houses layered down the hillside below them. They'd have seen the road curving down, the terraces and crescents, the zigzag paths and the white handrails. On the flats at the base of the hill, they'd have seen more housetops, in rows with roads between, where trams followed each other back and forth, small, far away. Beyond the houses and roads she knew there was the aerodrome where, in the daytime, planes dawdled about like bees before facing on to the runway, picking up speed and suddenly lifting to fly. Or they came out of the sky above the sea, dropping, roaring along the dark strip, stopping, turning, and making their slow way towards the sheds or the hangar. At one end of the aerodrome was Lyall Bay and the coloured ocean where they saw ships come out from behind the hills and move across the water, becoming smaller and smaller until they went from sight. At the other end was Evans Bay and a shaped sea, which seemed to be enclosed by roads and houses, the distant city, the cut-out hills. On the far side of the 'drome were more houses on more hillsides, and way back, where there were no more houses, were the faraway hills, dark and sharp. Between them, here and there, were glimpses of the sea. Some mornings, when there was a moon, they could make out the two silver patches of water and the ghosts of houses, the shapes of buildings and hills. But this morning, there in the dark, it was as though there was nothing about or below them at all, apart from the rattling wind. It was as though she and her mother, her brother who was asleep, and their father on his way to work, were the only people in the world, living in the one and only house. Sometimes Mereana's mother would say, 'One day the lights will come on. There'll be lights in the streets again. People will let their blinds up and take the blackouts down. We'll look out and see everything lit for miles.' Now, kneeling on the big bed in the dark, there was just one light that they waited to see as they looked down to where they knew the road to be. 'There,' her mother said, and she saw the faint, bobbing light, knowing it was her father with a shade on his torch and his lunch in a tin bag, going to his job at the freezing works. They watched, and at the place down there where they knew the corner to be, they saw the little light stop a moment, jig from side to side as her father waved goodbye, then it was gone. She got into bed with her mother who said, 'He'll be at the top of the road already.' After a moment she said, 'He'll be on his way down the hill.' Running past all the animals asleep in their cages—Nellikutha in her concrete house; the scabby polar bear who walked back and forth, back and forth all day in front of the white painted rocks by a pool of bright green water, while people waited for him to dive and swim; parrots, budgies, canaries, finches, cockatoos, and old vultures that looked like nothing but dusty brooms hanging up against the wires; bison that rubbed themselves into strips and patches against the barbed wire fences; tigers, monkeys, lions; old horses. Sometimes on Saturdays she would go with her father over the hills at the back of the zoo to collect horse dung for the garden. He'd take his spade and sack and she'd take the hearth shovel. They'd make their way through the gorse and broom to the clearings, and the old horses would snort and walk away, whacking their big feet down, their tails and manes lifting and falling. 'They're for the lions,' her father told her. 'They're lion tucker.' When they'd filled the sack they would walk back to the slope above their house and her father, with her on his back, and pulling the sack and shovel, would run down through the prickles and broom to the fence. When they'd climbed through it they could almost have stepped on to the roof of their house which was set right up close to the bank. The southerly was flapping the blinds, banging the windows, rattling the dustbin that had a brick on its lid; rattling the chimney pot which sometimes came apart, clattered down the roof and dropped on to the square of lawn before bouncing down on to the square of garden. Sometimes at night, when she was supposed to be going to sleep, she'd get out of bed and watch the searchlights, like long, blue arms, reaching, criss-crossing, looking for enemy planes that could be in the sky. She'd wait, hoping to see an enemy plane trapped in the light, but after a while she'd feel tired of waiting and get back into bed wondering what an enemy plane looked like, what an enemy looked like. What was an enemy? In one of her books there was a story of Bertie Germ who lived in a rubbish bin. You had to fight against him with soap and toothbrushes. Her brother was still asleep, she thought her mother could be asleep too, and her father was in a dark tram, on his way to catch a train with blinds down over its windows, taking him to the meatworks. But what would it be like when all the lights came on again, lighting everything for miles? Would there be no night at all then? Would she play and play in an everlasting daytime, up and down all the lit-up streets, in and out of houses that would now have their lights on, their blinds up, their blackouts taken down? 'This week, or next,' her mother said, 'his call-up papers'll come. He'll be off to war.'</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Patricia Grace (b. 1937) has won awards for her novels, short fiction and children's writing. Potiki (1987), which she wrote during her Victoria University Fellowship, won the New Zealand Book Award for Fiction and international awards. Her most recent publication is the novel Baby No-Eyes (1999). She is of Ngati Toa, Ngati Raukawa and Te Ati Awa descent. She was awarded an Honorary DLitt by Victoria University in 1989.</field>
      <field name="heading_text">1986 Stevan Eldred-Grigg 1986 Stevan Eldred-Grigg</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Literary, Literally Wellington for me first took shape on paper. Wellington—a word in my early readings. Two other words—Christchurch, Canterbury—at the same time were offered by this or that source as ostensible synonyms for the word home. Words for want of a better word. My homeland felt pretty fugitive, needless to say, seemed more readily defined by emblems, by written script, than by any lifting of eyes or fingers away from pages to find or feel for something more—or less?—palpable. Alienation, anomie, intellectual precocity blended with anal retention—more or less par for the course on the mown links, the tidily weeded and chemically fertilised greens, the stereotyped sandtraps, the nineteenth hole, mapped inside the smartish cerebral cortex of a white suburban child anywhere in the world during the decades of the fifties and sixties. Merely happened to be Christchurch. Wellington—would it have been any different in Wellington? Wellington, one day, would start to wriggle its meaning sideways inside that cortex. The holes on the course would sprout tufts of gorse. The gorse in turn would shoot out spikes, and bright yellow blossoms. Wellington would prove the first of a long list of placenames found in literature during my younger years and later turned into something different, something I hadn't counted on. Curnow yielded a lot of pliable linguistic parts, of course. Parts willingly grasped. Moveable signs for a young writer wanting to write away towards some sort of homeland. My first decade offered not so many pointers. The first memorable literature about the windy city to come my way was a product of commercial copywriting, a leaflet handed to me during my fifth or sixth year by an uncle who knew I was 'keen about boats and that'. A leaflet published by the Union Steamship Company. Wellington, thanks to the copywriter, came to mean a port. A port to be found at the end of a charted line not to be seen on the surface of our planet yet ploughed each night by two trim little liners. 'Interisland Express'—that was the name of the 'class of vessel'—while the individual names of the liners were Maori and Hinemoa . A map inside the leaflet outlined the two chief islands of the national state in the shape of tiny, meticulously inked silhouettes of the fleet owned by Union. Marvellous! My picture of a port at the other end of the Interisland Express was soon complicated by new readings. Readings that came to hand during my early teens when a quickening curiosity about the nineteenth century as a possible homeland led me to look at all sorts of bits and pieces of text about colonial Wellington. 'At first I thought the shops very handsome,' I was told by Lady Barker, 'but I found, rather to my disgust, that generally the fine, imposing frontage was all a sham; the actual building was only a little hut at the back, looking all the meaner for the contrast to the cornices and show windows in front.' Mean sham blended with dark bleakness to mark the place in the work of Henry Lawson. 'The great black hills they seemed to close and loom above the town.' Arthur H Adams gritted his teeth about a 'rudely fashioned' town on a 'wounded hill-side steep.' The word 'rude' was similarly serviceable for the scripts of David McKee Wright. 'Rudely scarred', the dark hills of the capital 'encircle her pent streets'. Robin Hyde was the first writer to fill out my portrait of the town with anything in the way of circumstantial detail. Her readings seemed slightly to shift my acquired literary—or sub-literary—sense of Wellington. I 'bonded' intensely with Hyde, as we would say in a later decade, though that intensity owed more to biography and psychopathology than geography. 'There are dark, slanting hills, and those enormous crystal-green waves which pour in, translucent hillocks,' says the narrative voice in Passport to Hell . 'If you can once be perfectly alone with the hills and sea of Wellington, you have something they can't take away from you, no matter where and why they lock you up.' Not that the narrator seemed too trustworthy to a bookishly troubled teenager inside a suburban lounge on one of the numberless orderly streets of Christchurch. 'Blowy old place, isn't it?' says a secondary character in Nor the Years Condemn . 'Windy Wellington . . . But I like the wind.' 'Smells of ships, doesn't it?' says Starkie. 'Ships coming in the whole time. I can't stand a place that smells dead.' Working my way through other writings seemed to add little to my stock literary knowledge of Wellington. A knowledge that the capital was a lot of rusty shanties dumped onto steep, dripping, windy hillsides. Wooden houses on posts—a sort of cross between the towns of Appalachia and Ireland. Damp, drizzling. Poor. The sort of place where kids played barefoot in gutters while grey warmish clouds streamed ceaselessly across the sky—a sort of northern West Coast. WH Oliver confirmed my stereotype by versifying about 'iron rust roof slums' on 'green, sullen hills'. Ruth France afforded a creepy feeling when she wrote that the city caused her to think of death, of a caged creature, of weeping women: . . . we have mucked With the rake of time over the tamed Foreshore. Battering trams; Lambton, lamed With concrete, has only a hint of ghost waters On the Quay stranded among elevators. Swinging, however, from the sixties into the seventies of the twentieth century, we come to a lucid day of late summer. Sun, water, a small ship. A young man stands at a railing and scans a strait. Myself, standing and scanning. Ready for my first sighting of the literal Wellington. Myself, dressed in flared blue jeans and a yellow muslin body shirt, braced on board the Maori . No longer so trim, that small, honest ship. Tired, one might say. Tiredness inside her steel plates, but not my mind—my mind at full alert, aware that my sighting of the city, so far unseen, will be a sighting from out at sea, from the deck of a vessel—the traditional first sighting by any outsider of the City of the Strait. A would-be writer stands on top of a mildly vibrating promenade deck. He squints across a wide stretch of hard glittering water. At last—headlands! Yet—what? Not what I have been taught by my reading to find. The light and colours cause discomfort. White light. Bright white light. Yellow headlands—tawny? Clear air, calm air. A windless windy city. A wonderful city whose seaward slopes seem to climb an escalator of light from what one knows to be the unstable basement of Cook Strait. Water swelling subtly on all sides as the bow of the Maori cuts past Pencarrow Head. The colour of the water, all wrong. Turquoise? A true turquoise! Wellington—brilliant! A place of beauty! Bewilderment is what I feel, needless to say, leaning forward into the wonderful landscape, bewilderment because, of course, the texts—the texts have not told me. And now, now what sort of place will it prove to be, the literal city? What am I about to find, once our bows have rounded Point Halswell and veered towards the wharves? The would-be writer frowns, and wonders. What sort of city?</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Stevan Eldred-Grigg (b. 1952) is a fiction writer, autobiographer and social historian, especially of Canterbury. Historical works such as A Southern Gentry ( 1980) and Pleasures of the Flesh: Sex and Drugs in Colonial New Zealand (1984) were followed by the award-winning novel Oracles and Miracles (1987) , The Shining City (1991) , Blue Blood (1997) and others, all drawing on the social, cultural and literary history of Canterbury. My History, I think (1994) is a memoir.</field>
      <field name="heading_text">1987 Lauris Edmond 1987 Lauris Edmond</field>
      <field name="fulltext">'Silent Tears' A windy autumn night. We've lost our way in the distant Wellington suburb of Tawa. Here's a lit-up petrol station—we'll go there, they always know. But will they? This isn't any ordinary address, a house in a street. Will they draw back from us, shaking their heads, not wanting to know, or to be seen to know? How do people regard a prison in their neighbourhood? Arohata Women's Prison as it turns out is a bit off the main road, up a curving drive that climbs to the top of the hill where there are large dark buildings, and a car park. No real directions, however; we follow a group which itself gets lost in the darkness, turns, tries again . . . Eventually we find ourselves waiting in a little enclosure, a kind of open porch, for a door to be unlocked. We form a queue, pay someone our money, wait again. In the end we are invited to take our seats in an informal semi-circle round a large open floor. It looks like a decorated gym (and it is). It is April 1996. We have come to see Kia Marama , the Arohata Women's Prison performance. It is a collage of different kinds of presentation—song, dance, guitar music, chorus, talking. Towards the end of the evening a small fair-headed Pakeha woman comes forward from the chorus line. She takes a chair, turns it round and sits on it, leaning on the back; a silence, then slowly she begins to tell us about her 'Silent Tears'. She pauses often, and there is a long silence at the end of her words. Then she stands up and sings, without accompaniment, in a sweet, throaty voice, 'All You've Got is Your Soul'. Silence again, then she turns back to join the group, and they move into their final chorus. This is Pauline Brown. Weeks later she still haunts me; that pale intense face and curly fair hair, the clasped hands as she leans forward. Her direct appeal—no, it was not an appeal. 'Here I am,' she said, 'a mother of three children sitting in prison . . . because I killed a man . . .' But she did not condone her crime. 'I'm not sorry he's no longer around, but I am sorry I'm the one who took his life. I will never be able to forgive myself . . .' Mostly she'd talked about her children; she tried to protect them, and now the law decreed she should be denied all access to them. What kind of history could it be, looming up behind that brief revelation? But then, who am I to wonder, to enquire? A stranger, someone from another world . . . yet I live in the same town, share the same windy sky, the same jutting Wellington hills; our local spring storms and occasional mellow afternoons . . . Is the gap between us really uncrossable? I sense there is something I could do to traverse it, but at first I don't know what it is; I just know the idea won't leave me alone. I consider the oppressive contrast between my life and hers, my daily freedom of choice and the unrelenting restrictions of hers. I go out, come in, pick up the phone, drive to town or into the country, visit friends and family. And Pauline, this young woman? My God, she's young enough to be my daughter . . . what has the world done to her, taught her, given her and taken away? One day, weeks after the performance, I know what I must do. I write a careful letter, post it, prepare to wait. It's not for long. 'I wanted to write it myself,' she says, 'but I couldn't: growing up—the booze, and beatings—those men I married—I'll tell you—' Wednesday. My morning with Pauline. I drive the twenty kilometres or so along the urban motorway, turn oV and up past a mowed slope on which TAWA is planted in low bushes, then up a curved drive to the prison. Lawns edged by tidy gardens, a row of parked cars, the entrance to the Guard Room. There's quite a ritual about unlocking and signing in. Door It comes up to you and leans close glowering, it stands over you it is dressed in armour steel bars forged in old furnaces paint shining with a malevolent glitter beyond it the nameless rumpus footfalls, dim whistles, a banging— while it stares impassive, not rude merely doing its duty that famous excuse— its handle juts out, in its thick way it gives you the fingers. The door holds the weight of the world, cringe before it: they do. It steals days and years of their lives. We meet in a small interview room. When Pauline arrives she is carrying an electric jug, milk, a mug for each of us, coffee and her own smokes. One day she comes empty-handed. It's a new guard, doesn't believe her story, confiscated her things—'Arsehole,' snorts Pauline, 'having a bad day, and takes it out on me—' Sometimes we gossip. Like the time we'd both seen the film on TV showing murder victims dressing up to go and watch an execution. We agree we wouldn't want to live in America. 'It's just revenge,' she says. 'Can't see the point. You have to forgive—everyone does. I mean, am I going to go on for ever blaming my mother? or Bill, bastard as he was? I have to be responsible for myself, for what I've done.' Other occasions come and go. At home I write to the woman I now know, the silent archetype who endures Pauline's sufferings. Turning Forty Most of us get there, some stumble into it a few are afraid; those with friends say they glory in it, the language is ready: 'in your prime' 'the best years' 'life begins . . .' No one will say to you 'This time next year' or 'Where were you for the last—?' They know. Ten years; they call it Life and you're only half way through. Last year you were a youngster—thirty-eight, nothing. Next year Miss Black you'll be thinner, that small frown will be deeper you'll cry less often already you're good at advice for the new lags your children will grow more strange you won't sleep any better . . . Oh my dear friend, think of another story, find cracks in the pressed steel of the bars, locks, regulations—go on, do; make yourself up, give it a go, take your dream for a walk. I've discovered that the differences between us don't magically disappear just because we're friends. There is something else though that binds us together; perhaps it's common cause. We do agree on almost everything—but then we mostly talk about 'the system', meaning the law; and it's true that it has ignored the real lives of women like Pauline for hundreds of years, and is very hard to change. Sometimes I go away, and we miss our weekly talks. But I think of her, she's part of me now. Even sitting in a garden in the early morning, she's there. Letter to Miss Black This is the morning shift of the universe a brief autumn sun bustles around the house and into my corner—there are bees too nosing into the slim trumpets of the purple sage bush brushing my elbow children shout faintly in the distance somewhere a hammer pecks at its wood a dog barks; ants secretly creep round my feet. There'll be a woman in tears in one of the plain painted units down the road, or the careful bungalows; perhaps a rough bloke having a go at her; a child squealing; in the city a dark suit by a handsome window will be promoting a deal; a boy breaks his heart alone in a shed at the back of a farm. And you Miss Black— are you on kitchen or laundry or floors or maybe the garden . . . did you answer him back, the fat guard who winds you up with his lazy smile? Did you write the thousandth letter in your tossing dream last night and wake to the same denial? The morning rolls its warm body over towards the day. Look Miss Black, we're all history, we're the Twentieth Century, you and I are in the programme; trouble is, we never seem to find out who it was wrote the script.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Lauris Edmond published her first volume of poetry at fifty-one, and has since sustained a prolific output of poetry, fiction, autobiography and critical/editorial work, winning the Commonwealth Poetry Prize in 1986. Her most recent volumes are A Matter of Timing ( 1996) and a celebratory seventy-fifth birthday selection (1999). She is an Honorary DLitt of Massey University.</field>
      <field name="heading_text">1988 Fiona Kidman 1988 Fiona Kidman</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Speaking With My Grandmothers Lines Every day the sea grandmother the last fringe of light lies beneath a banner of storm clouds the burden of hills presses against air from out of my window I touch the leaves of kowhai we planted a whole quarter of a century ago such an accumulation of years how we guarded those saplings from hurricanes     nothing much changes lights aeroplane a tangle of cable wire but the outlines of the place we've both called home are still here I know you through these hills, this horizon, tonight's wild dark, our summer         days because you are my grandmother (great to be exact) your picture hangs in the passage way I like the way you stand, fingers trailing over the back of a chair before a velvet curtain looped with braid, your eyes fierce and direct, a hat like a guardsman's helmet tilting on your brow, a tell-tale ruffle of lace at the wrists because you are my grandmother fluted silver vases stand poised above my bookshelves because you are my grandmother I wear old fine gold and mother-of-pearl because, because of this, I wear this hair shirt of guilt the settlers' shame     * A little history: they left Badbea, the Sutherlands, Bartons and Sinclairs, making their way to Broro, a small town on the sea coast in Sutherlandshire, here to connect with the passenger boat trading from the far north of Scotland to the south. Picture them waiting with relatives one early morning near the mouth of the Broro River. All ready at last, the final goodbyes, the menfolk take their places. But wait, at that moment as the keening rises, the wife of Alexander Sutherland, holding her youngest child in her arms, breaks down and refuses to enter the boat, to go one step further. We see Alexander leave the boat, walk to where his wife stands, surrounded by her people. See how he seizes the child from her arms and turns back to the boat. She follows; she takes her place. Going, going. Gone to New Zealand.     * Did she ever flinch again?     * The Oriental put down at Petone from where you were taken by whaleboat to Evans Bay that spot where merry ducks paddle their own canoes and darken the clear shallows with their shit your father brought some books a Gaelic bible one or two willow pattern jugs a blue embossed milk jug a mahogany table he took one hundred acres of country and one town acre fifty chains of seafront at Lyall Bay for some sovereigns and blankets and beads and hatchets and there's the rub your legacy a ring a vase or two and a label you couldn't have dreamed I'd wear and I've found only of late like a child discovering illegitimacy in a certificate hidden in the bottom of a knickers drawer, the contrivances of that rush for the great land grab before the Treaty of Waitangi was signed; we can thank Gibbon Wakefield for that, the sailing ship rushing down to Cape Verde Islands past the Cape of Good Hope and on and on through the harbour mouth arrival: 30 January 1840 what a gasp of relief in the salons of London we beat the bastards with seven days up our sleeves look, you'd laugh if it wasn't serious, as they say, the city mapped out in tidy lines across a terrain as yet unseen by its planners up hill and down dale well, no, up mountainsides and down passes, this town of ours kind of flattened across the creases of an imaginary map a touch of parchment surrealism here no wonder the lights are wavering all over the place tonight not a straight town at all     * All the same grandmother how many hills are there left to stand on because I'll tell you, it's getting quite lonely on this high moral ground and now that I've found you, guilty secrets and all, I can't keep away, can't stop looking at your picture on the wall can't stay away from the green field I've found up the line where sheep may safely graze between each tombstone, private people in private graves; I always mean to bring bunches of flowers but they end up time and again rusty hydrangeas plucked from the side of the road to lay on slabs stretching in perfect line grandmother by grandmother all the way back to those ships     * And I whisper to you. I tell you you must not mind this foreign soil. You must not mind for me. I am the robber's bride as my mother was before me. I have found my own way. I am the ordinary face of strangeness. You would not know me if you saw me. We have bitten the white throats of roses and ridden wild horses bare backed. I live here. There is no turning back. Do not call me now. Stay just where you are. Tonight I want to sit quietly by this window. There is so little silence, so many voices.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Fiona Kidman (b. 1940) began to write seriously when she was twenty-two, combining her early writing life with motherhood. Later, she worked in radio and television, but is now primarily a writer of fiction. Her novels include A Breed of Women (1979), The Book of Secrets (1987 ), Mandarin Summer (1989) (shortly to be a feature film) , True Stars (1990) (written during tenure of the Writer's Fellowship) and Ricochet Baby (1996). Her most recent book is The Best of Fiona Kidman's Short Stories . She has received numerous awards and in 1998 became Dame Companion of the New Zealand Order of Merit (DNZM).</field>
      <field name="heading_text">1989 Maurice Gee 1989 Maurice Gee</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Waterfront After his wife's death John began to fall in love again. It came on him steadily, drawing energy from his grief until that dried up and blew away and she could walk beside him speaking silently and touching his arm. He remembered that she had been the first to say, 'I love this place.' He had not shared that with her until she was gone. He thought of her less frequently after several years but was glad of her presence when she came. He looked up from his gardening and saw red cattle moving through the gorse on the hill and no longer heard her telling him to see. A morepork calling woke him in the night and he heard alone, and hearing made him part of the nature of the place; as the cattle did, as the pair of horses on the skyline, as the steeplejack on the TV mast with a helicopter lowering parts to him. He took the yellow unit down the gorge—nine minutes to the central station—and walked along the waterfront in his parka and sneakers and cheese-cutter hat. They had made that walk each Sunday—and now less frequently he heard her say, Listen, see: the hum of yacht rigging in the wind, a shag on a mooring line drying its wings. He saw for himself and he showed her, easy now, smiling with the union he made. He did not believe she would have been jealous. The wind wrinkled the water on the artificial lake by the museum and sped a plastic bottle on the surface like a canoe. A black-backed gull with a broken wing flapped and scrambled on the sloping lawn by the marina. 'My husband's phoning the animal ambulance,' a woman cried. The wind gusted. A fat sloop hung in slings by the overseas terminal while two men scrubbed her down with wire brooms. After the murders in the Sounds was there anyone in New Zealand who could not tell a sloop from a ketch? John walked on, not wanting to remember, only to see: fathers jogging with pushchairs in which tiny frowning buddhas slept: a man 'released into the community'—fingerless gloves, broken shoes, a New World shopping bag full of ravelled jerseys and bitten loaves of bread. He jabbed a fence paling at a council dustman wanting to sweep the corner where he slept. Beyond the Hotel Raffaele an Air New Zealand jetliner slid into the opening between Point Jerningham and Point Halswell. John walked as far as the Raffaele, past labradors and schnauzers and a muzzled pit bull; past cars splashed with birdshit from starlings overnighting in the Norfolk pines; past vandalised bus shelters and million dollar apartments on the hill; and was still able to say, with a happy melancholy, This is mine. The city of mirrors and chessboards strove for size underneath the hills it would never climb. The Beehive, a pancake stack, remained complacent. He would have liked to see it sooty and scarred. The sound of a piledriver came across the water from the Railyard Stadium and made him think of Jael nailing Sisera to the ground. Away in its suburb, under the mast, his house would be steaming in the sun. Others, across the valley, were jammed in dark creases in the hill. Roads dived and climbed and turned back on themselves. Steps went up like ladders, their handrails sprung or skewed. He loved it all. Loved the wind in the gullies, the sound of gusts approaching like trains. He had gone up through the manhole to mend the tile that rattled at the eighty kilometre level but all the wires were tight. He found a poisoned beehive, the bees as light as air, and the mummified body of a mouse, and thought that he might crawl into a corner and dry out too, on the pink Batts, while a new family lived down below. Tiles would rattle, rain would splash inches from his face. He saw himself drifting on the hills, as natural as the weather there. A shag dived, sped eel-like and vanished; came up with a fish in its beak. Silver flashed from the mirror glass. Red grew dull as the sun went out. He might be watching himself, if time were nothing, from that building on the hill where he had worked. He rode up every two or three weeks in the cable car, by-passed Von Zedlitz, found the library instead and leafed through the TLS and the London Review of Books , keeping in touch although he no longer needed to. Went into the stairwell to see the painting when he was done. That figure made of earth and air was what he really came for. He wanted to take it with him when he left, under his arm—had never seen a student even pause. He watched it now, on the hills, and joined it. He did not know what it was doing there, or what he was doing. The harbour waited, level and patient; it darkened, then lit up from inside itself. A painter might see a shape in the water between Somes Island and Oriental Bay—a giant ray beating its wings—or see a bird on the grey wind, an albatross that darkened the city with its shadow. Would someone reveal them one day, while the kayakers paddled and the joggers ran? He hummed with fear at his vision, then let it go. Walked back to the station the way he had come: the chlorine stink at the Freyburg Pool, the ketches and sloops, the floating crane. Listen, he said to his wife: the wind was coming. Ropes on the charter yacht slapped against the mast with the sound she had made beating eggs. Black-backed gulls side-slipped in the sky. Tonight the tiles would rattle. He frowned at it. He smiled at it.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Maurice Gee (b. 1931) achieved early success as a fiction writer with such titles as the novels The Big Season (1962) and In My Father's Den (1972) and the short story collection A Glorious Morning, Comrade (1975). Plumb (1978) brought a new level of acclaim, sustained by such later books as Meg (1981), The Burning Boy (1990), Going West (1992) and his most recent, Live Bodies (1998) (winner of the Montana New Zealand Book Award). He is also a successful children's writer, with Under the Mountain (1979) and others. He was awarded an Honorary DLitt of Victoria University in 1987.</field>
      <field name="heading_text">1990 Marilyn Duckworth 1990 Marilyn Duckworth</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Camping on the Fault-line Olive-green houses had had their day. Now, in the late sixties, psychedelic dwellings had sprung up in Kelburn and on the Thorndon hillside. Chocolate brown with dazzling yellow or orange trim, dark rusty red with turquoise window frames. I looked at them and shone back, quaintly cheered. I bought some dark rust-coloured paint and set to work on the asbestos sidings of our house. My stepladder wouldn't reach as far as the eaves and I had to get help from a neighbour to complete the top half. Then the paint ran out. The wall alongside the church would remain a watery green. Harry (Seresin) was appalled at the way we were living and at once organised me a job doing publicity for Downstage Theatre for twice as much money as I earned at the Observer ; which was fortuitous because the Observer was about to become defunct. The advertising salesman had failed to sell space. Young Helen and Sarah began accompanying me to Downstage opening nights. Pinter's Birthday Party , Christopher Hampton's The Philanthropist . When KB Laffa's exuberant comedy, Zoo Zoo, Widdershins Zoo , was showing my father rang up and warned me—'If you're thinking of taking the girls to Zoo Zoo I thought you should know there's a scene of simulated intercourse.' The play was about six young people in a Midlands flat, one of them an American draft dodger and all of them busily making love not war. My girls had already seen it and loved it. I didn't, however, think of taking them to the Late Night Show— Knackers and later Knockers , starring Paul Holmes, John Banas and John Clarke. Downstage was then in the draughty Star Boating Club. Harry's tiny office gave onto the storeroom of the kitchen. He told me he had to stamp his feet before he went through this room at night, to discourage the rats. The food was protected in cages. Downstage had begun life in an old café on the corner of Courtenay Place, the brain child of actors Tim Elliott and Martyn Sanderson, poet and actor Peter Bland, and Harry, who had promoted the idea of serving dinner before the show. It caused some headaches not usually associated with theatre management but made Downstage certainly unique. One of the pleasures of doing publicity for Downstage was being allowed to attend rehearsals. For years I had borrowed playscripts from the library because I found them as rewarding to read as novels. Now I watched them come to life, beginning to hatch like peacocks. You Know I Can't Hear You While the Water's Running . The Bacchae . Eduardo Manet's The Nuns . Three Months Gone . I tried to make myself invisible. Sunny Amey would hover, one hand poised above her script like a baton. Nola Millar sat, watchful under her beret, with a bag of humbugs on the seat beside her. Bill Austin, head of Radio and Television Drama, bought another TV play I had called A Jelly Fish in Summer —but told me they didn't currently have the actresses capable of doing it justice. '. . . is the kind of play that would be very hazardous to present just at this time. However, it could very easily be a viable proposition at some time in the future.' I wondered if it was a little raunchy for the times. They had looked askance at my suggestion for a series set in a venereal diseases clinic. I went on to write a number of television scripts, for Section Seven, and for a series that never eventuated, but which brought me in some substantial money. Harry loved my children and said so, but I wasn't ready to be charmed by this approach a second time. Harry and I became lovers and the best of friends, always, but it didn't happen in a hurry. Meanwhile he courted me with cases of peaches, driving me in his Triumph two-seater, telling me the stories of his life while I hung washing on the line. I told him some of my stories and he listened with mournful attention, sometimes exploding with sympathetic laughter. He took the children to the park so that I could do some writing. I learned that he was a special person, thoughtful and brimming with ideas. He could see what was good about living in New Zealand, his adopted country, and yet he was sometimes dejected by the same drabness which had depressed me when I came back to Wellington after living in London. He talked nostalgically about 'dancing and singing in the streets', which there was none of in Wellington in the sixties, and he yearned for more non-conformist behaviour. I remembered an occasion back in 1962 when he had made his coffee gallery available for a special meeting organised by poet Tony (Anton) Vogt, who shared the same disappointment as Harry in our 'welfare society'. Tony had invited writers, musicians, artists, to this meeting with the intention of starting an exciting new magazine. There must have been about thirty of us. Jim Baxter, musician Douglas Lilburn, myself and others, ranging from humble to smug. We had been surprised and disappointed when Tony Vogt decided within weeks to leave the country and the project died. A lot of people were angry at the critical views Tony expressed in a farewell radio interview. Monte Holcroft wrote in a Listener editorial: 'Mr Vogt will no doubt be able to find a place where the people are joyful and where his own ebullience will cause no surprise. But he may need to be careful. In New Zealand he has been free to speak his mind on a variety of subjects; indeed we are all richer because he has had strong opinions and has expressed them vigorously . . .' I enjoyed the vigour of Harry's expression. I wrote to Fleur expressing my surprise that I had become involved with him. He was so different from the kind of man I had been attracted to in the past. I was pleased with myself for not repeating old patterns—if this was a mistake, it was a new one. Harry and I went with Sunny Amey and Bob Lord to a satirical revue at the university— One In Five . The title was based on a provocative statement by psychiatrist Fraser MacDonald that 'one in five New Zealanders are mad'. Dave Smith had written the catchy title song. He and Roger Hall and John Clarke were responsible for most of the skits. Watching this revue I suddenly recognised that I had become a genuine New Zealander without really noticing. I wrote an article in the Listener : '. . . leaning back in laughter at this country which I had never quite acknowledged, like a de facto relationship, I had a new feeling about it . . . Because I have lived [in Wellington] for more than 20 years, the place is full of ghosts for me, some of them malignant but mostly not. With the coming of the motorway the city seems to move under me like a quicksand—streets removing themselves overnight, buildings enlarging and soaring. While the bulldozers busily erase I superstitiously mark the spot, until the city becomes a kind of private scrapbook. The people—they are another thing. I cannot relegate them to a scrapbook. My shared experiences of their peculiarities joins me in a bond with the rest of the Wellington population . . . not until now had I recognised in [New Zealand]'s familiar, sometimes drab landscapes—myself. What tremendous cheek led me to set myself apart from all this?' Wellington had had its eccentric personalities as long as I had lived there. There was the Eccles family, wizen-faced Mum and the two grown-up sons who didn't seem to work but had money to go to the continuous 'pictures'. They shambled in long, shabby, mud-coloured coats and worn shoes, like creatures from the lost lagoon. There was the gentleman who always wore a hat and pin-striped suit and twirled a walking stick. He talked to himself in plummy tones and would stop to salute the DIC. Lizzie and I as schoolgirls would encounter 'the birdman' who would put his hands together and warble like a canary. He was delighted when we stopped to listen and began to sing: 'Two little girls in blue!' We were wearing our Queen Margaret College royal blue uniforms. These were all personalities we indulged with a fondness which was possessive. They were ours. 'Camping on the Faultline' is an extract from an autobiography in progress.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Marilyn Duckworth, OBE, fiction writer and poet, was born in Auckland but has lived mainly in Wellington. Her first novel, A Gap in the Spectrum (1959), was published when she was twenty-three; her fifth, Disorderly Conduct (1984), won a New Zealand Book Award. She has been awarded the Scholarship in Letters three times, the Katherine Mansfield Fellowship in 1980 and a Fulbright Scholarship in 1987. She has held fellowships at Victoria and Auckland universities. In 1996 Leather Wings was shortlisted for a Commonwealth Writers Prize. In that year she edited a book on New Zealand writing sisters— Cherries on a Plate. Her thirteenth novel, Studmuffin , appeared in 1997.</field>
      <field name="heading_text">1991 Barbara Anderson 1991 Barbara Anderson</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CLAT Daniel Manders was not happy. Rage engulfed him, seared his ego like a naked flame. His ego, he was prepared to admit, was as big as the next man's, if not bigger. But even so, even so. Not only had the Head turned down his request for Paris. The man had popped his arse against the window-sill, and, between the flick of the Bic and the first drag, had dropped his bombshell. Manders, DGR was to be seconded from Foreign Affairs to the Ministry of Cultural Links and Trade. Manders of all people; brilliant track record, bilingual and judgement to burn was to remain in Wellington to hold the hand of the Minister for CLAT. To make the path smooth for a man known to be an incompetent bumbler and disloyal to his staff. A Valley of the Bones type boss. This was the fact that enraged Manders, not the job itself. He had nothing against Trade. Trade was essential and he could do it. And he could certainly do Culture. Like any self-respecting thruster in Foreign Affairs, Manders collected New Zealand art. Or had. He read New Zealand literature, especially history, which was even more interesting nowadays. He had always been conversant with the customs and culture of its indigenous people. One or two of his friends were Maori. And he loved his country, loved it dearly. There was nothing wrong with his homeland. Beautiful. Beautiful. Or with its people. Or was there? He stared out the window at two large water tanks on the flat grey roof below, at air-conditioning ducts and a pigeon standing in a large and rippling puddle. Did he, in fact, like his fellow countrymen and women? Did he, in fact, like anyone? And this, this was the point. Did it show? Manders was a reasonably honest man. If he didn't like his compatriots then it bloody well should show. Esse quam videre . To be rather than to seem. A good motto, he had always thought so. One that should be framed above the beds of leaders and force-fed to frauds. The clerical-grey pigeon had been replaced by a streetkid sparrow. The reflections of surrounding high buildings, slabs of cream, brown and blue, shuddered about its feet in the chilly-looking puddle. Manders pulled a yellow legal pad towards him and wrote. Appreciation of Situation. a)   I have become a supercilious shit. b)   It shows. c)   Is this why I have been seconded to a job in Cultural Links and Trade? d)   Unlikely. Both CL and T need charm and bonhomie. e)   So does an overseas posting. f)   An overseas posting at this stage is essential for my career, let alone vis-à-vis Caroline. He made a new heading. Options/Action 1)   Do the CLAT job superbly and get sent back to FA for overseas posting as soon as possible. 2)   How else to achieve desired posting? a.   Get charming. You used to charm. Get charming. b.   What about EQV? c.   Bugger EQV. d.   Practise on someone. e.   Who? He snatched the yellow page, screwed it up and threw it in the wastepaper bin. Then reconsidered and tore it into small pieces. No point in advertising angst at this stage. The sparrow had disappeared. Cold feet perhaps. The telephone rang. Daniel snatched it to him. 'Manders,' he barked. 'Is that Daniel Manders?' 'Yes.' Who else, chucky, who else. 'Daniel, this is Tania Webster, Mr Carew's personal assistant speaking. Mr Carew wants to see you as soon as possible about arrangements for the ASEAN trip.' 'Trip. When?' 'After you join CLAT.' Sweet Christ. One of those balls-aching chatting and shopping Ministerial swing arounds, dreaded by High Commissions, Embassies and handlers alike. And I'll be one of them , the Minister's bear leader, there to dance with the enemy and piss on my colleagues. He drew a deep breath. 'Thank you, Ms Webster.' 'Mrs.' 'Mrs. Shall I come over forthwith?' (A bit much, forthwith, but let her swing.) 'No, no, the Minister is completely tied up till Thursday.' The old game. I'll show you my diary if you show me yours and mine will be bigger and fatter and packed full of meaty interest because my boss is the biggest fucker in the forest and you're ground cover. 'Thursday,' he muttered, 'will be fine.' He put down the receiver with care. The future did not beckon. He would go and see Steve Roper on the Asian desk. Steve might know something, some hidden and hopeful agenda, some gleam of light, some sense behind this grisly scenario, this deliberate seconding of brilliance. He loped along the corridor in search of help he knew he was unlikely to receive. Friends, even good friends like Steve, never get the consoling thing right. They listen for a few moments, tell you where you went wrong, tell you what intelligent action they would have taken in similar circumstances, which is usually the exact opposite of that taken by you, then slide gently into their problems which are invariably serious and far-reaching in their effects unlike your sweaty little quibbles against fate. Your bad luck, they intimate, lies within yourself. They are the ones whose misfortunes are determined by malevolent stars. Steve, as expected, was useless, worse than useless. He said that you have to expect bum postings occasionally, and that Daniel's trouble was he'd always been so bloody brilliant he thought the department owed him a living which it didn't, and that Daniel should wait until he landed a really shitty job like Steve's, and a boss like Stormin' Norman. Then he would have something to moan about. Oh, and had he seen the photos of the shindig at the Mendezes the other night? 'No.' Steve produced an album with the word 'Photographs' embossed in gold letters on the cover and a handwritten inscription inside. 'With the compliments of Ambassador Constantine Mendeze and Mrs Mendeze on the occasion of the visit of General Alsarvo d'Riva.' From the evidence of the photographs the party had been an outstanding success. Most of the participants appeared to have spent the evening shrieking with joy, except for one unfortunate shot of a saffron-suited Minister clutching his groin beside a vast floral arrangement of red Kniphofias, Birds of Paradise and giant Pampas Grass. 'Why've you got one?' said Daniel. 'Every desk has. Asian, French, the States. The lot.' 'Very generous.' 'They are very generous, the Peruvians. They gave Daphne and me a set of coasters when they came for a meal. Sort of mottled stone, brown and white like a cow.' 'Brindled.' 'As you say. Rather attractive in a weird sort of way.' 'Caroline and I got them too. God knows where they are now.' 'Well, you would, wouldn't you? Same seniority.' 'Seventy-seven, wasn't it?' 'Nnn. Seventy-seven.' 'Twenty-one years.' 'Yeah.' They stared at each other bleakly. 'Probably,' continued Daniel, 'she took them with her.' Steve's head moved sadly from side to side. 'God, you're a supercilious bastard. What would Caroline, an independent front runner like Caroline, want with four joint matrimonial stone coasters in Paris?'</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Barbara Anderson (b. 1926) gained her international standing as a novelist and short story writer in her sixties. Having already published stories, she included Victoria University's Creative Writing paper in her BA, completed in 1984, and published her first collection, I Think We Should Go Into the Jungle , in 1989. Successful subsequent titles include Girls High (1990), Portrait of the Artist's Wife (1992), which won the Wattie Book of the Year Award, The House Guest (1995) and Proud Garments (1996). Her new novel, Long Hot Summer , will be published this year.</field>
      <field name="heading_text">1992 Alistair Te Ariki Campbell 1992 Alistair Te Ariki Campbell</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Utu 1 Haunui Haunui's the name—Big Wind,     at your service. Caught them         at it, didn't I? My woman and Weku, my best mate—     not any more, he's not.         Trusted them, you know—him and her who brought me so much     pain. Caught them red-handed—if         you'll pardon the expression— at Waimapihi, a sacred spring     whose waters immediately drained         away for shame, for shame. 2 Weku He'd a stupid grin, like he was     making out some other lecher—         may he rot in hell!—could be the culprit. Should have     heard the piwakawaka!         The leaves concealing them rippled with their merriment.     Any other time I'd have       not when I'm sporting the pair     of horns he put on me.         Couldn't let it pass, could I? when my pride and honour,     yeah, and dignity         as a man, were at stake. 3 Te Ana o Hau He hid in a towering bluff,     but with one blow of my fist         it became an archway down which he dropped, abseiling     for dear life—a katipo, God         damn it! He hit the beach running, but I was swifter,     squashing him flat with my foot.         It was goodbye, Weku boy. His soul, snatched up by a lizard,     howled all the way to Te Po.         Will miss him all the same when fishing—him and his whoppers.     That big one out there,         yeah, Kapiti. It's one that didn't get away. We fished it up—     not that trickster Maui,         with his impudent claims. 4 Maui He lolled against the archway     to the Underworld, murmuring         how Wairaka's ghost brushed past him, eyes and mouth agape     in a soundless scream. A liar         he may have been, but he wasn't all bad. Trying to abolish     death at great personal         risk showed real nobility, but try telling that to the     piwakawaka, who fell out of         their tree with laughter, when Hinenuitepo turned massively     in her sleep, closed her thighs,         crushing his skull like eggshell. 5 Wairaka She had to be punished. Couldn't     live with the humiliation.         She beat it south, squawking like a weka, and where the coast     baulks at the corner, she looked         back and tripped, her feet ensnared by seaweed. The little     bush birds, attending her,         begged me to forgive her, but my heart was stone. It wasn't     good the thing I had to do—         turned her into the monstrous rock of ill omen that's named     for her—Wairaka. Sort         of miss her, though, glowing black eyes, black hair tumbling to her     bottom—lovely, that. Could         weep, thinking of her and how it used to be . . . Ah, well,     that about wraps it up,         yeah, that's about it. Kia ora .</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Alistair Te Ariki Campbell (b. 1925) has a long association with Victoria University throughout his career as a poet, playwright, novelist and autobiographer. He was a student when Mine Eyes Dazzle achieved early success in 1950, and his most recent volume of new poems, Death and the 'Tagua' , was published in a fine-print edition by the University's Wai-te-ata Press in 1996. Other significant titles include Wild Honey ( 1964), The Dark Lord of Savaiki (1980) and Pocket Collected Poems (1996). He was awarded an Honorary DLitt in Victoria University's Centennial Year, 1999.</field>
      <field name="heading_text">1993 Jack Lasenby 1993 Jack Lasenby</field>
      <field name="fulltext">This Strange Cold Town I stuck my feet in the oven of the coal stove and opened my book. I was renting an old house in a strange, cold town. My daughter was asleep in her bedroom off the kitchen. She was five. Her mother had just killed herself. I like a coal stove. You can dry your clothes on the rack, warm your feet in the oven, and keep the teapot hot. I looked at the red glow in the grate, heard the ashes falling soft into the pan. The kettle began to sing. I shoved it to the back where it fell quiet, a violin string winding down. My daughter called out in her sleep. I tiptoed into her room. She had one arm outside the blanket. I tucked it in. I'd had a go at making cheerful curtains for her window, but they didn't fit too well. When I drew them tighter, the night outside was dark; the glass was cold on my knuckles. I put the kettle over the ring, made a cup of tea, read for an hour or two, and woke. The book was in my lap. I had gone to sleep in my comfortable chair in front of the stove, feet in the oven. My daughter must have called me. She often did that, or she'd pad out and stand silent beside my bed till I woke and found her there, feet cold as linoleum. I'd pop her into bed beside me, put her feet on the hot water bottle and, in the morning, she wouldn't remember how she got there. But she hadn't called out. Or she'd gone back to sleep. I found where I'd been reading and heard the sound again. The kitchen door into the gloomy front passage was closed. As I looked the doorknob turned. I tiptoed across. The doorknob turned further. I put my foot against the door, kicked it hard. A neigh of agony. I shouted with fright and rage. A tall man stood in the passage, a black stocking over his head, holding his nose in both hands. He'd sneaked in through the unlocked front door. He'd gone through the two front rooms and was trying the kitchen door, turning the knob slowly, when it flew open and smashed his nose. He ran, whinnying in pain. I ran after, shouting. He jumped the front gate. I jumped after. He ran down the street, across Tinakori Road, down the asphalt zigzag between the pohutakawas and Thorndon Quay and, shouting for help, I ran after. He dodged between cars going home from the pictures, and I dodged after him. The neighbours must have heard me yelling. Somebody in the cars would see me chasing the man in the mask. He ran under the flyover being built across Thorndon, part of the new motorway. In the gritty air beneath that concrete sky he turned, stood his ground, and hefted a length of reinforcing steel like a spear. 'Come and get me! Try your luck . . .' Voice nasal and muffled by the stocking, he took aim. Behind him I could see the huts and lights of the single men's camp in the railway yards, the other side of the flyover. He was on his territory. As I was off mine. The lights of the cars were a solid white band. None of the neighbours had come to help. Nobody stopped their car. I thought of my daughter alone inside the house, its front door wide open in this strange, cold town. I looked down, saw I was in my socks and was scared. I turned and ran. The man in the mask snorted and flung the reinforcing steel. I heard the whicker as it flexed through the dark air, the whine as it clanked off something and buried itself, grating into a heap of shingle beside me. I whirled, pulled it out, spun myself around a couple of times and let go. Whop! whop! whop! like a chopper coming up a valley. There was a flump and the second shriek I'd heard that night. I didn't wait to see if he was injured, nor if he was going to throw it back. I didn't want to be killed under a half-built flyover in a strange town. Just wanted to make sure my daughter was safe. I ran between the cars. Several swerved. A couple tooted. None stopped. I ran up the zigzag, across Tinakori Road, up the street to where light poured through the front door, spilled across the road. My daughter lay asleep, one arm outside her blanket. I tucked it in, put a shovel of coal on the fire, shoved the kettle over the ring, made some tea. What if the man had speared me? What if a car hit me? What if somebody else sneaked in the open door, my daughter asleep and alone? I stood at the front door and stared at the other houses in the narrow, elbowed street. Not one neighbour had come to help. I glared at their windows, locked the door, took my daughter out of her bed, and put her into mine. I filled the hot water bottle from the kettle, wrapped it in my pullover, put her feet on it, and went to bed myself. I lay beside my daughter, looked through the dark, and thought about our life in the strange town. On Thorndon Quay below, a siren screamed. Next morning, I took my daughter down the asphalt zigzag between the pohutukawas, across the road, and along the footpath beside the flyover where last night I had turned and run from the man in the mask. There was frost on the pavement and, tingeing the white crystals, a swathe of what looked like blood. My daughter held my hand. The wind was from the south, wolfish as we walked through the strange town. 'We'll get to know the place better,' I said. 'I read a story last night about the zigzag we just came down, a story by a girl who lived just up the road from us. Come on, we'll look for a park.' My daughter held my hand and skipped. 'Will there be a slide and swings?' she said. 'Will there be friends?' 'There's bound to be,' I told her. Already, she was getting used to this town.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jack Lasenby (b. 1931) is a leading writer of children's fiction, which draws on his wide experience of the New Zealand bush. His successful titles include The Lake (1987), Dead Man's Head (1994), The Waterfall (1995) and his several collections of 'Uncle Trev' stories. He has worked as a deer culler and as a lecturer at Wellington Teachers' College.</field>
      <field name="heading_text">1994 Christopher Pugsley 1994 Christopher Pugsley</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Wellington City, a Career Choice Living in Wellington was a career choice. It was 1987. I was in Singapore and decided against some family opposition to become a freelance historian. I enjoyed my twenty-two years in the New Zealand Army, and was content enough, but had the itch to write. That came from writing Gallipoli: The New Zealand Story , published in 1984, and working on the television documentary of the same name. If I left writing until I retired I believed I would always be an amateur so I left the world of an Infantry Officer and took the plunge. Wellington had to be our base. From Waiouru and then Auckland I had found the difficulty of mounting smash and grab raids to National Archives and the Alexander Turnbull Library, bunking over in Mike Wickstead's flat in Hobson Court. So Wellington had to be home. The family home in Sefton Street is a typical Wadestown house looking to the western hills bathed in afternoon sunlight, the downside being the northerly winds. In my first years I wrote there each morning. Walking David to school with Blue the dog, then writing from nine till one. The Maurice Shadbolt routine, 1000 words then stop even if I had more to say. Just let it come, good days, bad days, the next time through it would get better. My draft was my file, layering in the research as I went, writing early, writing often, just like tennis, practising my craft every day. The Army gave me three months resettlement leave on full pay and I offered my services to the National Archives checking and listing the First World War holdings. It was letting loose a child in a lolly shop. Sheer marvellous indulgence, being allowed to look into every War Archives box in the bowels of the Air New Zealand building in Vivian Street. After the three months finished I kept on with it. No money coming in, living on what we had put aside to get me started. Dee at university, the kids at school, enjoying every day. I got involved in the War Art collection. Tony Murray-Oliver had done wonders in gathering the Second World War collection from RSAs various. But on his death, little had been done with the First World War collection. Sorting them out was difficult, the records messy, and identification uncertain. That's where I came in. I could not tell how it was painted, but I could identify scenes and individuals. One thing led to another. The 1990 sesqui-centennial exhibitions: The Honorary Rank of Captain, A Loss of Innocence, and Crete: A Tribute from New Zealand and I was now earning money. Archives were also good company, Ray Grover and his team endured my singing. Georgina Christensen administering each exhibition with me as curator. Walking daily from Wadestown to Vivian Street. Lunchtimes in the Cuba Street galleries and second-hand bookshops. Jazz 78s in Slow Boat Records, sheer delight. Archives led me to the New Zealand Film Archive identifying and cataloguing official New Zealand First World War documentaries and newsreels, equally good company and equally enjoyable. I was also writing a history of the New Zealand Division on the Western Front which ten years on is still in draft. One chapter on discipline was giving me trouble. Wherever I put it in the draft, it did not fit and seemed better as a stand-alone project. In Archives I came across the court-martial register of the New Zealand Division. Defence Headquarters Legal Branch and Base Records threw up the records of those New Zealanders sentenced to death, but not executed in the First World War, and the Judge Advocate General Sir John White gave me access to the records of the five New Zealanders executed. What started out being a 'quickie' took two years. It became my D Phil thesis. Laurie Barber at Waikato encouraged me to apply to complete a doctorate, despite no formal academic qualifications, on the strength of my writing and publications. On the Fringe of Hell: New Zealanders and Military Discipline in the First World War was the result. I also got a contract to write the official history of New Zealanders in South East Asia working to both Historical Branch and Headquarters New Zealand Defence Force. It gave me an office in Defence House, access to files, research trips overseas, and a project that I have only just finished many years on. Writing a contract history has been a salutary experience. You have to anticipate where you are going and stick to it. That was the difficult part. At times, in despair, I sought and enjoyed distraction. Books, two during my time as Writer in Residence at Victoria, feature articles for Kate Coughlan at the Evening Post , being one of the team that started the New Zealand Defence Quarterly magazine, now five years old and going strong. Curator and then Creative Director of Scars on the Heart at the Auckland War Memorial Museum, commuting to Auckland every second week for two years. It is only in the last two years that I fell in love with Fighting a Jungle War , as I have with all my other books. Looking forward to 5.30 or 6.00 am starts, writing the daily quota, finally doing it justice. Wellington is an inextricable part of all this. Meeting everybody on Lambton Quay. Long café discussions with Ray Grover and Oliver Riddell. DQM breakfasts and lunches with Jim Rolfe and Lindsay Missen. Art gallery afternoons and coffee with Christopher Moore when punch-drunk from writing. I am typing this in Armidale in northern New South Wales. Our delight during the two years here have been the weeks we have stolen in Balmain. Last week I rang my wife, back visiting family, and asked Dee how Wellington struck her after Australia. Her reply: 'A windy Balmain.' But really, it's the other way round. Balmain reminds me of Wellington and it's time to go home. Night Attack (from Anzac: The New Zealanders at Gallipoli , 1998) The assault began at 9.30 pm, 6 August 1915. The Auckland Mounteds seized Old No 3 Outpost, the Otago Mounteds and the Canterbury Mounteds took Bauchop Hill, and the Wellington Mounteds stormed Table Top. Reinforced by the Maori Contingent, they attacked with rifle and bayonet. The flash of rifles and the Maori war cry indicated progress. At 11 am on 7 August, the Auckland Infantry Battalion attacked and lost 300 men in twenty minutes for a gain of 100 metres. The Wellington Infantry Battalion were ordered to continue the attack but Malone refused to send his men 'to commit suicide'. In the early morning of 8 August, Malone's battalion occupied the Turkish trench on the crest of Chunuk Bair, and dug a supporting trench behind it. The Turks' dawn counter-attack saw the British battalions, with the Wellingtons, break and run. The trench on the crest was lost and the fight continued on the seaward slopes. Men dug trenches behind the original support line as it filled with dead and wounded. Turkish grenades were hurled back, and even stones were thrown. All day the Wellingtons, reinforced by the Auckland Mounted Rifles, fought off Turkish attacks that were announced with a shower of grenades. By nightfall Malone was dead, killed by New Zealand artillery fire. The Otago Infantry Battalion and the Wellington Mounted Rifles, led by Lieutenant Colonel Meldrum, replaced the Wellingtons. Throughout 9 August, the Wellington Mounted Rifles desperately held on to a line just below the crest of Chunuk Bair. But by evening they had no more to give. Out of 3000 men, the New Zealand Infantry Brigade had 1700 casualties; both New Zealand brigades were exhausted. The position on Chunuk Bair was taken over by two British battalions, with Meldrum leaving the best of his scouts. On the morning of 10 August, a Turkish counter-attack panicked the raw British infantry, and the New Zealanders were recalled. But the effort required was too much for exhausted men and the Turks regained the slopes, so determining the fate of the Gallipoli Campaign. If New Zealanders have a day that is uniquely ours, it is 8 August 1915. For thirty-six hours, the New Zealanders at Chunuk Bair on the Gallipoli Peninsula held an opportunity to directly influence the course of world events. Had they held on to the crest of Chunuk Bair, the First World War may have ended some two years before it finally did. But the heights seized by the New Zealand battalions were surrendered by those who relieved them, and a priceless opportunity lost. No country went so far to fight in this campaign, nor suffered as much, for the size of its force. But the real casualties were those who lived. Racked with guilt at having survived when their mates had died, they returned to an uncomprehending New Zealand and had to fit back in as if they had never been away.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Christopher Pugsley was a career army officer before becoming a full-time military historian. His books include On the Fringe of Hell: New Zealanders and Military Discipline (1991), Te Hokowhitu a Tu: the Maori Battalion in the First World War (1995) and Gallipoli: the New Zealand Story (1984, 1990, 1998). From 1996 to 1999 he was at the University of New England, Armidale.</field>
      <field name="heading_text">1995 Gregory O'Brien 1995 Gregory O'Brien</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Contents of a Breeze, Wellington I Elaborate forms of urban life, Wellington: swirling trees aeroplanes pass between, a freshly mown lawn arriving from three blocks away. As Eastern Europe heads west, school parties raise and lower the Green Belt, a tour bus vacates the mountainside and our rubbish bin which disappeared southwards five days ago returns, clattering, rolling in from the north-east. II Where in the wind's high or low room we might find a child's wind-sock, wooden pigeon or 737, the paddling pool uplifted from our lawn. This the southerly's argument: snow in the middle of summer, the departed Flann O'Brien tee-shirt, Golden Boy deck- chair, Mondrian teatowel, leaves the shape of every country of a rearranged world, all headed upwards, to god, Saint Augustine,              someone . III In the absence of a whistling stairwell, all we have is air, air's whistling. Two weeks after Guy Fawkes, a Crimson Starburst finally flutters back to earth, landing among burnt-out Double Happies, Mighty Cannons, Foxton Fizz. Considering, late November, the wind's freight of trees and parts of trees, everlasting debris. And further north the southerly. Petone foreshore. Where the striped tent went. (September —December 1990)</field>
      <field name="fulltext">View of Wellington from Marahau Every tract of land has its title, or so Mein Smith sizing up the Wellington Harbour periphery would have maintained—in either role surveyor or watercolourist. I think of him now, not often, some miles south amidst the breezy constellations of Marahau 'a garden where wind is grown', hatching ground for the storms that cross Cook Strait to rip up Wellington Harbour, imagine him here uprooted, transplanted, gridding up the tilted and irrational properties of wind and water, struggling with the meandering tides, eddying bulbs, their crazy intelligence. Then finally being thrown clear of his fastidious paperwork into unimpeded space. As titles are given and grown beyond, like him we're all churned up, steered into harbours not our own, or left to languish in this storm-tossed garden where, on its windy stem, one bud is a washed out moon, another a fishing buoy bobbing, the one streetlamp of the nearest town or a gong-like bubble of sound that opens the first waking eye of the not yet born another bud swaying on its necessary stem.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Gregory O'Brien (b. 1961) is a poet, fiction writer, painter, writer on art and anthologist. His collections of poems and drawings include Location of the Least Person (1987), Great Lake (1991), Days Beside Water (1993) and Winter I Was (1999). Diesel Mystic (1989) is an illustrated novel. He has edited a collection of New Zealand love poems, and co-edited An Anthology of New Zealand Poetry in English (OUP, 1997).</field>
      <field name="heading_text">1996 Jane Tolerton 1996 Jane Tolerton</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Getting over Ettie Just after I had finished Ettie , my biography of Ettie Rout, I felt as if I had walked into a room which was my life—and switched on the light. Suddenly I was back in the middle of my own life. For almost a decade, almost a third of my life, almost all of my adult life, someone else had been there. Ettie had been my focus—as I had been trying to get her into focus. I came back to Wellington to write the book. Wellington is the place to write such a book—with the Alexander Turnbull Library; the General Assembly Library, where I copied out articles from old, unphotocopyable newspapers; the National Archives where Ettie's banned letters lay in folders; Victoria University, where I spent time at the Stout Research Centre; and the spirit of the place—brisk and thinking and collegial for a writer. I had left eight years before, to go to university in Christchurch and had stayed away for a newspaper job in a provincial city. There I had won the news award of the day which, ironically, saved me from having to do news reporting—something I found it hard to get a grip on; it was so transient and mindless of past or future. So I could go off into the past and my future, knowing that if I ever had to come back to the present and a job, I had a piece of paper which made me look attractive to a newspaper editor. But having come to my own time and place (I always wanted to be in Wellington; circumstances had led me out and kept me away), I was never quite in either. How could I live properly in my own time when I read more newspapers from her time than I did from my own? When I was more interested in any account of any social function she had gone to than to go to one myself? When no visitor was the one I most wanted to see and never could—just for five minutes, to ask questions no one but Ettie could answer, to which I needed answers to make sense of the rest. And when almost any living person was less interesting than the dead people who populated my mind. On the occasions when I met up with others who had known these people, we fell to what seemed like gossiping about mutual friends and relatives, while to the living I was quite capable of saying, 'Oh, but I do not have a social life' meaning, don't bother asking me. The social mores and social arguments I was thinking my way round were not those of my own day—to which I paid little attention. I actively avoided things that would excite my mind in other directions. I often did not go to a movie because I didn't want it in my mind. I read few novels, watched little television, and had practically no interest in the 'news' I had once made my living by. HG Wells (who was one of those who populated my mind as he had been a friend of Ettie's) once said of his wife that she stuck to him so hard that in the end he stuck to himself. And I felt like that about Ettie. It was only when I became riveted to her, at the expense of practically everything else, that the project stuck to me and flowed in my head and onto the paper. When I went out to earn money—in journalism, publishing and teaching—or tried in other ways to live my own life, it just didn't happen. Writing a book is hard, but not writing it is worse. At those times when I was trying to do something else, I felt as if there was a child I should have been attending to, but had locked in a cupboard in the meantime. Did I have the key to the cupboard safely in my pocket? What if I could not get back in? For lack of my active attention, it could die. A piece of written work can die—just go cold on you, to the point where you cannot resuscitate it. So active attention, feeding it every day, was the only way. The analogy I thought of at the time was a bath. You can stand in it with the water around your ankles, but it won't do any good until you have lowered yourself into it and the water is all round you. With a book you have to immerse yourself in it to a certain level before it will flow. You are in it, it is in you. For me, going to sleep with it and waking up with it was important because that's when I found ideas came, especially the ones that made links. Making the links is what fires the whole thing. You could put all the facts of a person's life in date order and join them together with dots—but you wouldn't have a biography. You start with hundreds of bits of paper all containing clues—often indecipherable and contradictory—which have to be studied, deciphered, understood, and then stuck together, not in order necessarily, but married one bit to another to include explanation and background and give a bigger meaning than the sum of the parts. To do this I had to have the whole thing in my head, so that I was able to scan backwards and forwards. There's endlesschoice about where to say what. I was constantly swapping bits of information from the beginning to the summing up at the end. With someone about whom the reader will know very little, as in Ettie's case, you need information at the beginning which forms an argument as to why the reader should bother even knowing about the subject. With Ettie an additional problem was that for many years—between her time and ours—the great issue of her life, the spread of venereal disease, was a non-issue. Unfortunately for the world, but fortunately for making Ettie's life a relevant story, AIDS appeared just before I began the book. Not only had the cause that fuelled her life become a non-issue in the meantime, even in her own day it had been studiously ignored or concealed —there were not, for example, adequate figures on how many New Zealand soldiers had contracted venereal diseases in World War One when she staged her campaign so there was an enormous amount of research to do even to understand what she had been on about. And even if you could discern 'the facts', you had to understand the thinking of the time. You had to know the odds to see how desperate was her bid to beat them. It was the thinking of the time, the strength of views of those who opposed her that cornered her into tragedy. But how much of a mountain of research do you put in? How can you make that tip of the iceberg stand out clearly for the reader without freezing them to death with the huge bit hidden in the research sea? Grappling with such things was misery-inducing at first. But when I was feeding the child in the cupboard daily, immersed in the bath which had been cold around my ankles but was now warm and up to my neck, the project became a delight. I was in the project; it was in me. I had no choice about what I did, and I didn't want to do anything else anyway. If you are actively engaged on a creative endeavour, I learnt, you have to do the creative thing first—and everything else comes last. I trained myself out of housework and administrative tasks that did not have to do with the biography. (There's a lot of admin in a biography: writing and answering letters to and from informants and potential informants and libraries holding archives of other players in the story, setting up interviews, paying for photographs, asking an MP for a signature to get a card for the British Library's manuscripts section, filing . . .) You could tidy up first—but that could go on forever. You could do all the research first—and never write the book because there's no end to how much research you could do. If I sound sentimental or self-sacrificing, don't read me that way. I was living an adventure. I knew I was sacrificing things—such as what is generally referred to as 'making a living'. But I did not keep count of the cost. (When I did do the roughest add-up later I decided the sum of the relatively small grants I'd had and the award I won and the royalties for the book would have covered only the cost of materials and travel—no wages for time spent.) And next to what Ettie had sacrificed for her project I wasn't losing much. Money was the least of what she spent in her campaign; she lost reputation and the chance of remaking a life in New Zealand afterwards. Actually my reputation seemed to be on a downward spiral as the years rolled by. More people asked me in that time, 'How's Ettie ?' than asked, 'How are you?' as if I were to be judged solely on production of the book, as if they were somehow put out by the fact that it wasn't out last year. I was cheered to find when I picked up biographies that their authors had often taken between eight and ten years. (I took nine—and did another book in between: an oral history of World War One, which allowed me to ask old soldiers for the information I couldn't have found out any other way). I loved the time I spent fixated. I learnt an enormous amount about myself, being riveted to Ettie , and not only how to write outraged letters—for which I borrowed Ettie's sarcastic style. Any big project teaches a lot—and so does trying to see the world through someone else's eyes. There was never a time when I felt all the decisions had been made. I had no feeling of fait accompli—always of fait en progres. But I did finally call a halt and so came to a point where, having delivered it to the publisher myself (by hand, via car journey, with breakdown so that after a night in the Cambridge Hotel I walked the streets hugging my manuscript to my bosom, waiting for the mechanic to let me go on) I walked back into that room which was my life, and put the light on. I did my tax for the first time in three years and went out in search of income, lurching to the opposite end of the work-income spectrum, by going down to The Terrace and taking a public relations job for a corporate. When I left that job, I had an 'exit interview' with a young woman from Human Resources. 'Before I came here,' I told her, 'I never would have thought that looking the part and playing the game could be more important than doing the work.' She gave me a look that said, 'My God, where have you been?' Well, I'd been in my own house, but in other decades, and with someone whose integrity would have staggered her much more than my statement seemed to. I was not a candidate for life in the corporate world. I had lasted nine months there before I was caught by the need to produce something myself again. For when you've done a book, you've tasted a narcotic. But the books I've done since— Convent Girls and Sixties Chicks Hit the Nineties —have been short, swift pieces of work compared with Ettie . So would I enter the fray of another biography? Oh, yes. But I'd be putting up a stiffer battle in fighting for my own life next time round, trying harder to keep the light on in that room which is my life.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jane Tolerton (b. 1957) is a biographer, journalist and teacher of journalism, whose life of Ettie Rout, Ettie ( 1992), won the New Zealand Book Award for non-fiction. Her other books include Convent Girls (1994) and Sixties Chicks Hit the Nineties (1997).</field>
      <field name="heading_text">1997 Elizabeth Knox 1997 Elizabeth Knox</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Assemble in Bunny Street While I was Writer in Residence in 1997 there was one blustery, sunny day, coming into spring, when we stood at the north-facing windows of Von Zedlitz and watched a large group of marchers set off down Kelburn Parade towards town. They were protesting a rise in fees, of course. We were a Writer in Residence, two of the job-sharing English Department receptionists, and the department secretary, Helen—and maybe one of Bill Manhire's MA students, lured out of the writing room by the irresistible sound of more than two voices in conversation. We stood watching the protest because it was not just a spectacle but a novelty. People just didn't do that any more. I told the others some stories about protests. Eighty-three and eighty-four there were sometimes two marches a day—at lunchtime and early evening. Often they were for the same cause, and you could take your choice—'Is there a matinee?' Most were anti-nuclear, but there was also Homosexual Law Reform, and the H-Block and Latin American Committees, and marches for Women Reclaim the Night. My friends stopped meeting in pubs—instead we went out walking together, ambled along in our op-shop overcoats or Swandris, or our thick men's jerseys under XOS black woollen shearers' singlets. I'd lend some burlier person my fingerless gloves so that they could carry one end of a banner, or one pole of a litter bearing a huge Debra Bustin Uncle Sam—indecently exposing his tumescent warhead. We heard 'Assemble in Bunny Street', or 'Assemble in Pigeon Park'. And there were chants: 'What do we want?' 'No Nukes!' 'When do we want it?' 'Now!' (less grammatical than a Marines marching song). My sister, Sara, would produce her own versions. On one marathon march for Women Reclaim the Night, we wandered around the smaller streets of Mount Victoria, till Sara began chanting, 'Two four six eight; where are we going, it's getting late?' And there were times she'd offer helpful advice, 'Two four six eight; don't sit on a spiked gate!' Because I was nosy I worked those marches. There were so many people I knew —my friend from design school at the polytechnic, a 'mature student' friend with her daughter in a pushchair; all of Sara's tribal Rugby Street flat; or Women Against Pornography, with one woman's white husky trotting among them; and the good-looking English guy from Greenpeace, possibly without his latest girlfriend; the bow-legged Chilean from the Latin American Committee; and members of PAN—our writer's club, an offshoot of the English Club—two male poets and a protean novelist raising a sweat by carrying some giant papier-mache puppet from the Nuclear Horror Show. My dashing about was noticed, I was sent back against the current to find people—people would ask, 'So, who is here, Elizabeth?' Once I was sent off with money to buy a big bucket of Kentucky Fried Chicken (this is back before it became today's sourceless, global 'K', health-conscious 'F', and hedging-their-bets 'C'). Sometimes there was violence, almost always offered by passers-by. Well—it isn't advisable to suggest to a homophobe that he's a repressed homosexual, especially if he's amongst friends, and they've all just reeled out of the Abel T. My sister took up a new sport—eyeballing the police—and once she slugged a distracted blue giant outside the Michael Fowler Centre (at either Miss New Zealand or the National Party Conference). I hauled her away, backwards and flailing, by grabbing her jacket hood, and drawing her through the crowd, out of the giant's sight and reach. She plunged like a furious but collared dog, then spun around and nearly landed one before recognising me. Once, during a protest on Budget Night, I saw my sister on TV being marched off with an arm twisted up her back. She arrived home hours late, tearful and shaken, and said she'd been put in a van and photographed —but had 'talked her way out of it . . .' On Bastille Day we gathered outside the Saint George, where the French Embassy was holding a banquet. It was a silent protest. We stood peacefully, our candles reflected in the wet asphalt. But the police decided to keep us moving, so that we wouldn't be blocking the traffic. We were directed to go single-file (an order that, whenever it was given by the police, usually elicited memories of Molesworth Street in '81). I wasn't one for single-file. I was talking to a friend, trailing her at her ear. A policeman caught me by the arms to slow me and we spun around several times till I chimed at him sweetly, 'Thank you for this dance.' And he gave a winded laugh, and lost his grip. Unlike Sara, I had no unshared moments of fear. The worst thing that happened to me—other than swollen feet and fingers after the Wellington test day march in '81—was eczema from the face paint, a patch of red blisters in the shape of a skull. Some acquaintances who didn't go on the marches would say, 'Aren't you afraid of being hurt?' Or even, 'You can't change anything that way.' (Male homosexuality was illegal; there was no rape in marriage; nuclear-powered and -armed ships sailed into our harbours; and Nelson Mandela was in prison.) These acquaintances claimed to 'express their political opinions differently'. Probably they wrote submissions to commissions, or letters to MPs, probably they voted every three years—though I know some didn't do that either, were so suspicious of political opinions they were also suspicious of the democratic process. 'But how can you be so sure of yourselves?' they'd say, disapproving. Well—we were doing ourselves that favour—giving ourselves a certain look. 'What are you complaining about?' they wanted to know. 'Don't we live in a comfortable society?' Relatively, yes, but our rights weren't conferred by nature, didn't drop like the gentle dew. Someone, at some time, fought for our rights. Perhaps these people thought that being counted-in was the same as being co-opted? They did express fears for their identity. We were the conformists, they said. We were 'sheep' or 'ideologues'. (At this point in the argument my friend jumped up on our couch and yelled, 'I'm going to sweep myself out with an iron broom!') On the other hand, J, from Socialist Unity, thought we hadn't sacrificed enough for our political beliefs. We were at University, while there were people working 'forty hours a week in the biscuit factory'—which didn't quite have the ring of 't'mill' or 'at the coalface'. I quarrelled with another friend eye-to-eye across the catalogue in the library. She said that my wanting to be a writer was 'bourgeois dilettantism'. (She is now a homebirth midwife.) Some of us thought we were revolutionaries; and some of us joked about our 'black balaclava knitting circle'. I decided not to buy suede walking boots because of all the occasions on which protests required me to stand in the rain. In July of '84 the ranks—our ranks—parted to let through the real revolutionaries, with their rarefied language, their market forces, their jet-stream high-and-dry clouds of capital, their promises of wealth.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Elizabeth Knox (b. 1959), fiction writer, is a Victoria University graduate in English and Creative Writing. She came to early prominence with After Z-Hour (1987) and has since published Treasure (1992), Glamour and the Sea (1996), a trilogy of Wellington novellas, and the internationally successful The Vintner's Luck (1998). She is the 1999 Katherine Mansfield Fellow at Menton.</field>
      <field name="heading_text">1998 Lorae Parry 1998 Lorae Parry</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Scene from 'Vagabonds' Scene 2: Wellington Wharf—1863 Sound of a ship's horn. An English PORTER enters, carrying a large theatrical trunk and a basket. Behind him, in full sail, is the actress, MRS ADELAIDE FOLEY—an elegant woman in her mid fifties. A newspaper billboard reads, 'Escaped Convict. Whipped Sea Captain. Resighted in Manukau.' PORTER Do you require a horse and cart Ma'am? ADELAIDE I do indeed. And could you recommend a decent hotel? Something capacious. Last time I stayed here, I ended up in either an opium den or a brothel! In any case it was inconsolably small! PORTER There's the Thistle Inn, Ma'am. Just opposite the public stocks, but that's not especially commodious. I would personally recommend The Empire Hotel, up on Willis Street, Dicky Dwyer's place. Reading room, billiard room, nicer class of clientele. ADELAIDE Dicky's sounds divine! And could you also direct me to the portrait gallery of a Mr Richard Swan? We have some business together. PORTER Ah! Now that's easy Ma'am. Mr Swan has premises over on Clay Point. Just a stone's throw away from the hotel. ADELAIDE Magnificent! PORTER Have you any more baggage Ma'am? ADELAIDE I have an entire wardrobe, Sir. Not to mention a couple of infuriatingly late performers, who've managed to get themselves lost on a gangplank. Thank God I can see one of them now. The other one's probably fallen in the drink! Do come and see our performance. Royal Olympic Theatre, behind the Ship Hotel. One week only. PORTER I don't approve of theatricals Ma'am. Devillism enacted onstage. This settlement has had a constant stream of vagabond vaudevillians passing through it of late, creating all manner of licentious behaviour! What with liquor being passed around the pit and foul-mouthed debauchery, it's become offensive to ladies and gentlemen of the first quality. ADELAIDE My good man, let me inform you that my company could not be described as vaudevillian. We have enacted our theatricals before the Queen herself! Not to mention the Princess Royal. We perform Shakespeare, the most beautiful language in the world. I sing opera, superbly well I might add. And in addition, we delight with a small menagerie of animals. Everything, Sir, from the wild and ferocious Bengal leopard, to the twelfth wonder of the world, the Double-Headed Goat! So you see, Sir, it is manifestly absurd that you should find The Foley Theatrical Company threatening! Rather you should be fighting for a good seat! PORTER Forgive me, Madam. Heaven implore us. I had not recognised you. I most humbly beg your pardon, Mrs Foley. ADELAIDE smiles charmingly. ADELAIDE Forgiven. PORTER My dear Mrs Foley, I have seen you perform on two marvellous occasions, and each time you added considerable class to our young colony. ADELAIDE smiles charmingly. ADELAIDE How kind. Now run along and help that leading man of mine off the gangplank. He looks as if he's about to fall over his wig box! PORTER Pleasure, Mrs Foley. Truly a pleasure. ADELAIDE I'm so glad. CAMERON CARRUTHERS, a handsome actor in his forties, struggles on with several small cases. ADELAIDE Good God, Cameron, you look as if you're about to expire! CAMERON Concerts in the colonies, Adelaide, are not my idea of a capital time. Bloody idiot I was to be talked into this. And if I never saw the SS Stormbird again, I'd be damn grateful. Ghastly crossing and the digs are downright common! ADELAIDE Come, come, where's your sense of adventure? CAMERON Back in England with a weekly repertory and a decent bit of Yorkshire pud! Good God, look at that landscape. Not a soul alive and hedged in by hills. Bottom of the bloody world! The Porter relieves CAMERON of his bags. CAMERON Don't know what's happened to Kathryn. Last time I saw her, she was surrounded by six randy sailors. ADELAIDE That's a fine predicament to leave your fiancée in! You might at least have acted the gentleman and fought them off. CAMERON Kathryn's more than capable of shoving them overboard. ADELAIDE And don't think I didn't see you eyeing up a young colonial thing yourself. CAMERON Adelaide, Adelaide, you don't miss a trick do you? I was admiring her hair. ADELAIDE You were admiring her bosom. CAMERON smiles charmingly. CAMERON And I'm admiring yours now. ADELAIDE You never change do you? CAMERON Would you want me to? She smiles despite herself. ADELAIDE Probably not. He taps his pockets. CAMERON Where'd I put that damn flask? He pulls out a whisky flask and takes a swig. ADELAIDE That's your trouble, Cameron. Too much spirit and not enough pluck! CAMERON You do go on, Adelaide. ADELAIDE Precious little good it does. CAMERON Ah, here she is. KATHRYN enters. She is a beautiful woman in her late thirties. Her clothes have a look of fashion, theatricality and flair. ADELAIDE Kathryn, where have you been? We're forever waiting, it's maddening. KATHRYN looks around, delighted. KATHRYN Oh, what light! What exquisite light! We have arrived in heaven surely! CAMERON Kathryn, your brain is sodden from that cheerless little boat ride. What nautical nonsense! Mind you, after that turbulent tossing, any bit of land would be a blessing. Talk about tempests! KATHRYN 'When the shore is won at last, who can remember the billows past!' CAMERON No use quoting Swinburne at me. It was a horrid little hulk and I hope I never have to see it again. KATHRYN Oh, Cammy, how can you be so cruelly ungrateful to that virtuous vessel? That gallant little barque that bore us here. She rose against the salt like a lioness protecting her young. You really are a philistine. CAMERON Yes, but a very charming one. ADELAIDE Perhaps we could attempt to meet Mr Swan before midnight. CAMERON Yes, and I do hope he's not another vapid, talent-free, vanity queen who can't act his way out of a paper bag. ADELAIDE Cameron darling, every support actor I've ever had can act. Eventually. CAMERON I rest my case! ADELAIDE Shall we go? CAMERON Yes, let us depart this shapeless shore. KATHRYN Farewell then, thou dark and deep blue ocean. Ta-ta my tireless little tugboat. Parting is such sorrow, sorrow. God I'm absolutely starving. What are we waiting for? She smiles delightfully at CAMERON and ADELAIDE who walk off. The PORTER is left to pick up a mountain of luggage. KATHRYN picks up a couple of small bags. She stops at the newspaper stand and reads the headlines of The Independent. KATHRYN Oh look, how exciting! 'Escaped Convict. Whipped Sea Captain. Resighted at Manukau!' How very dramatic! PORTER Yes, they've been looking for that felon for a long time, Miss. Very depraved piece of work. Murderer, thief, prostitute. You name it! They say she's been hiding out among the Maoris, and apparently she actually stripped the Captain and whipped his bare . . . his bare . . . He can't quite say the word. Pause. KATHRYN Bare what? PORTER Bottom. KATHRYN can't help but find this amusing. KATHRYN Oh really? PORTER Yes, she stripped him of his clothes and then she used them to outfit herself. KATHRYN How very Shakespearian! She smiles charmingly and exits. The PORTER is left standing there with a mountain of luggage. He calls after her. PORTER Oh, Miss! Are there any seats left for tonight's performance?</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Lorae Parry (b. 1955) is a playwright, actor and director. Her plays include the sell-out Frontwomen (1993), Cracks (1994) and Eugenia (1996) which has been performed in New Zealand and internationally. She was the founder of the Women's Play Press, and has performed with the women's comedy company 'Hen's Teeth'. She is celebrated for her comic characterisations on both television and stage, including her representations of Labour Leader Helen Clark.</field>
      <field name="title_display">Writing Wellington: Twenty Years of Victoria University Writing Fellows</field>
      <field name="title_facet">Writing Wellington: Twenty Years of Victoria University Writing Fellows</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">writing wellington twenty years of victoria university writing fellows</field>
      <field name="title_text" boost="1.0">Writing Wellington: Twenty Years of Victoria University Writing Fellows</field>
      <field name="year_display">copyright 2001, Victoria University Press</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">2001</field>
   </doc>
</add>