<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Beatrix Potter</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Beatrix Potter</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">beatrix potter</field>
      <field name="author_text">Beatrix Potter</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">legacy/uvaBook/tei/PotNutk.xml</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Online Texts</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Online Texts</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="full_title_text">The Tale of Squirrel Nutkin</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:477315</field>
      <field name="langauge_display">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_facet">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_text">English</field>
      <field name="location_facet">Internet materials</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Tale of Squirrel Nutkin</field>
      <field name="note_display">Source copy consulted: Longwood College Library call no: Juv. P866SQ</field>
      <field name="note_text">Source copy consulted: Longwood College Library call no: Juv. P866SQ</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod02.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">UVA Library Digital Repository</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Watercolor of a squirrel on top of a tree eating nuts</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THIS is a Tale about a tail— a tail that belonged to a little red squirrel, and his name was Nutkin.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">He had a brother called Twinkleberry, and a great many cousins: they lived in a wood at the edge of a lake.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">IN the middle of the lake there is an island covered with trees and nut bushes; and amongst those trees stands a hollow oak-tree, which is the house of an owl who is called Old Brown.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Watercolor of a hollow oak tree and Old Brown, the owl, flying to it.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Watercolor of lots of squirrels at the edge of the lake with trees.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ONE autumn when the nuts were ripe, and the leaves on the hazel bushes were golden and green—Nutkin and Twinkleberry and all the other little squirrels came out of the wood, and down to the edge of the lake.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THEY made little rafts out of twigs, and they paddled away over the water to Owl Island to gather nuts.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Each squirrel had a little sack and a large oar, and spread out his tail for a sail.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Watercolor of squirrels sailing across the lake with their tails on rafts of twigs.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Watercolor of squirrels pleading and bargaining with Old Brown, the owl.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THEY also took with them an offering of three fat mice as a present for Old Brown, and put them down upon his door-step.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Then Twinkleberry and the other little squirrels each made a low bow, and said politely—</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Old Mr. Brown, will you favour us with permission to gather nuts upon your island?''</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">BUT Nutkin was excessively impertinent in his manners. He bobbed up and down like a little red cherry , singing— "Riddle me, riddle me, rot-tot-tote! A little wee man, in a red red coat! A staff in his hand, and a stone in his throat; If you'll tell me this riddle, I'll give you a groat.''</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Now this riddle is as old as the hills; Mr. Brown paid no attention whatever to Nutkin.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">He shut his eyes obstinately and went to sleep.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Watercolor of Squirrel Nutkin singing to Old Brown, the owl.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Watercolor of squirrels filling their sacks with nuts from the oak tree</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE squirrels filled their little sacks with nuts, and sailed away home in the evening.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">BUT next morning they all came back again to Owl Island; and Twinkleberry and the others brought a fine fat mole, and laid it on the stone in front of Old Brown's doorway, and said—</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Mr. Brown, will you favour us with your gracious permission to gather some more nuts?''</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Watercolor of squirrels paying more homage to Old Brown the owl for nuts</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Squirrel Nutking tickling Old Brown, the owl, with a nettle. Watercolor.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">BUT Nutkin, who had no respect, began to dance up and down, tickling old Mr. Brown with a nettle and singing— "Old Mr. B! Riddle-me-ree! Hitty Pitty within the wall, Hitty Pitty without the wall; If you touch Hitty Pitty, Hitty Pitty will bite you!''</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Mr. Brown woke up suddenly and carried the mole into his house.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">HE shut the door in Nutkin's face. Presently a little thread of blue smoke from a wood fire came up from the top of the tree, and Nutkin peeped through the key-hole and sang— "A house full, a hole full! And you cannot gather a bowl-full!''</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Squirrel Nutkin singing through a keyhole of a door in the oak tree.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Watercolor of Squirrel Nutkin playing marbles with oak-apples in front of the owl's door.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE squirrels searched for nuts all over the island and filled their little sacks.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">But Nutkin gathered oak-apples —yellow and scarlet—and sat upon a beech-stump playing marbles, and watching the door of old Mr. Brown.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ON the third day the squirrels got up very early and went fishing; they caught seven fat minnows as a present for Old Brown.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">They paddled over the lake and landed under a crooked chestnut tree on Owl Island.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Watercolor of squirrels fishing</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Watercolor of squirrels marching to the owl's through the grove with Nutkin leading them</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">TWINKLEBERRY and six other little squirrels each carried a fat minnow; but Nutkin, who had no nice manners, brought no present at all. He ran in front, singing— "The man in the wilderness said to me, `How may strawberries grow in the sea?' I answered him as I thought good— `As many red herrings as grow in the wood.’''</field>
      <field name="fulltext">But old Mr. Brown took no interest in riddles—not even when the answer was provided for him.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ON the fourth day the squirrels brought a present of six fat beetles, which were as good as plums in plum-pudding for Old Brown. Each beetle was wrapped up carefully in a dock-leaf, fastened with a pine-needle pin.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">But Nutkin sang as rudely as ever— "Old Mr. B! riddle-me-ree! Flour of England, fruit of Spain, Met together in a shower of rain; Put in a bag tied round with a string, If you'll tell me this riddle, I'll give you a ring!''</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Which was ridiculous of Nutkin, because he had not got any ring to give to Old Brown.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Watercolor of a plate full of dock-leaf wrapped beetles that squirrels are giving to Old Brown, the owl</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Watercolor of Squirrel Nutkin gathering robin's pin-cushions and sticking them full of pine-needle pins.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE other squirrels hunted up and down the nut bushes; but Nutkin gathered robin's pin- cushions off a briar bush, and stuck them full of pine-needle pins.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ON the fifth day the squirrels brought a present of wild honey; it was so sweet and sticky that they licked their fingers as they put it down upon the stone. They had stolen it out of a bumble bees ' nest on the tippity top of the hill.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">But Nutkin skipped up and down, singing— "Hum-a-bum! buzz! buzz! Hum-a-bum buzz! As I went over Tipple-tine I met a flock of bonny swine; Some yellow-nacked, some yellow backed! They were the very bonniest swine That e'er went over the Tipple-tine.''</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Watercolor of squirrels with wild honey</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Watercolor of Old Brown, the owl, eating honey on his plate in the oak-tree hollow and turning in disgust from Squirrel Nutkin.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">OLD Mr. Brown turned up his eyes in disgust at the impertinence of Nutkin.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">But he ate up the honey!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE squirrels filled their little sacks with nuts.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">But Nutkin sat upon a big flat rock, and played ninepins with a crab apple and green fir-cones.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Watercolor of Squirrel Nutkin bowling and playing ninepins with a crab apple and fir-cones.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Watercolor of squirrels with a new-laid egg. Nutkin jumps in front.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ON the sixth day, which was Saturday, the squirrels came again for the last time; they brought a new-laid egg in a little rush basket as a last parting present for Old Brown.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">But Nutkin ran in front laughing, and shouting— "Humpty Dumpty lies in the beck, With a white counterpane round his neck, Forty doctors and forty wrights, Cannot put Humpty Dumpty to rights!''</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">NOW old Mr. Brown took an interest in eggs; he opened one eye and shut it again. But still he did not speak.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Watercolor of squirrels showing Old Brown, the owl, the egg.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Watercolor of squirrels and Nutkin dancing and jeering Old Brown, the owl.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">NUTKIN became more and more impertinent— "Old Mr. B! Old Mr. B! Hickamore, Hackamore, on the King's kitchen door; All the King's horses, and all the King's men, Couldn't drive Hickamore, Hackamore, Off the King's kitchen door!''</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Nutkin danced up and down like a sunbeam ; but still Old Brown said nothing at all.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">NUTKIN began again— "Authur O'Bower has broken his band, He comes roaring up the land! The King of Scots with all his power, Cannot turn Arthur of the Bower!''</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Nutkin made a whirring noise to sound like the wind , and he took a running jump right onto the head of Old Brown! . . . .</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Then all at once there was a flutterment and a scufflement and a loud "Squeak!''</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The other squirrels scuttered away into the bushes.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Watercolor of squirrels running and Old Brown, the owl, really angry and Nutkin flying through the air.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Watercolor of squirrels peering around the tree at Old Brown, the owl.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">WHEN they came back very cautiously, peeping round the tree—there was Old Brown sitting on his door-step, quite still, with his eyes closed, as if nothing had happened.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">* * * * *</field>
      <field name="fulltext">But Nutkin was in his waist- coat pocket!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THIS looks like the end of the story; but it isn't.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Watercolor of Old Brown, the owl, with his talon on Squirrel Nutkin.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">OLD BROWN carried Nutkin into his house, and held him up by the tail, intending to skin him; but Nutkin pulled so very hard that his tail broke in two, and he dashed up the staircase and escaped out of the attic window.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Watercolor of Old Brown, the owl, looking out of the hollow in his oak tree as Nutkin flies over without his tail.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Watercolor of tailless Squirrel Nutkin scolding the other squirrels on a tree branch.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">AND to this day, if you meet Nutkin up a tree and ask him a riddle, he will throw sticks at you, and stamp his feet and scold, and shout—</field>
      <field name="fulltext">"Cuck-cuck-cuck-cur-r-r- cuck-k-k!''</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE END</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Tale of Squirrel Nutkin</field>
      <field name="title_facet">The Tale of Squirrel Nutkin</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">tale of squirrel nutkin</field>
      <field name="title_text" boost="1.0">The Tale of Squirrel Nutkin</field>
      <field name="year_display">1903</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1903</field>
   </doc>
</add>