<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Beatrix Potter</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Beatrix Potter</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">beatrix potter</field>
      <field name="author_text">Beatrix Potter</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">legacy/uvaBook/tei/PotJemi.xml</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Online Texts</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Online Texts</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="full_title_text">The Tale of Jemima Puddle-Duck</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:477311</field>
      <field name="langauge_display">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_facet">English</field>
      <field name="langauge_text">English</field>
      <field name="location_facet">Internet materials</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Tale of Jemima Puddle-Duck</field>
      <field name="note_display">Source copy consulted: Uva, Alderman Library call no: PZ10.3.P47 Taj 1908</field>
      <field name="note_text">Source copy consulted: Uva, Alderman Library call no: PZ10.3.P47 Taj 1908</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod02.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">UVA Library Digital Repository</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="heading_text">THE TALE OF JEMIMA PUDDLE-DUCK</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Farmer's wife feeding chicks and ducks in the farmyard.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">WHAT a funny sight it is to see a brood of ducklings with a hen! —Listen to the story of Jemima Puddle-duck, who was annoyed because the farmer's wife would not let her hatch her own eggs.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">HER sister-in-law, Mrs. Rebeccah Puddle-duck, was perfectly willing to leave the hatching to some one else —“I have not the patience to sit on a nest for twenty-eight days; and no more have you, Jemima. You would let them go cold; you know you would!”</field>
      <field name="fulltext">“I wish to hatch my own eggs; I will hatch them all by myself,” quacked Jemima Puddle-duck.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">In the barn, a cow, roosters, chickens, and other ducks and Jemima.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Blank Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Blank Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jemima Puddle-Duck getting her eggs stolen from a little boy standing in front of a gate as his mother looks at him in the garden.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SHE tried to hide her eggs; but they were always found and carried off.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jemima Puddle-duck became quite desperate. She determined to make a nest right away from the farm.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SHE set off on a fine spring afternoon along the cart- road that leads over the hill.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">She was wearing a shawl and a poke bonnet.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jemima Puddle-Duck wearing a shawl and a poke blue bonnet setting off along the cart-road over a hill through trees..</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Blank Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Blank Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jemima Puddle-Duck wearing a shawl and a poke blue bonnet setting off along the cart-road over a hill through trees.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">WHEN she reached the top of the hill, she saw a wood in the distance.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">She thought that it looked a safe quiet spot.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">JEMIMA PUDDLE-DUCK was not much in the habit of flying. She ran downhill a few yards flapping her shawl, and then she jumped off into the air.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jemima Puddle-Duck running down the hill with her shawl and bonnet flapping in the wind..</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Blank Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Blank Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jemima Puddle-Duck flying in the air above the trees.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SHE flew beautifully when she had got a good start.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">She skimmed along over the tree-tops until she saw an open place in the middle of the wood, where the trees and brushwood had been cleared.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">JEMIMA alighted rather heavily, and began to waddle about in search of a convenient dry nesting-place. She rather fancied a tree-stump amongst some tall fox-gloves.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">But—seated upon the stump, she was startled to find an elegantly dressed gentleman reading a newspaper.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">He had black prick ears and sandy coloured whiskers.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">“Quack?” said Jemima Puddle-duck, with her head and her bonnet on one side— “Quack?”</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jemima Puddle-Duck coming upon the fox amidst the fox-gloves and trees.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Blank Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Blank Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jemima Puddle-Duck talking with the fox, as he sits and reads his newspaper.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE gentleman raised his eyes above his newspaper and looked curiously at Jemima—</field>
      <field name="fulltext">“Madam, have you lost your way?” said he. He had a long bushy tail which he was sitting upon, as the stump was somewhat damp.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jemima thought him mighty civil and handsome. She explained that she had not lost her way, but that she was trying to find a convenient dry nesting-place.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">“AH! is that so? indeed!” said the gentleman with sandy whiskers, looking curiously at Jemima. He folded up the newspaper, and put it in his coat-tail pocket.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jemima complained of the superfluous hen.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">“Indeed! how interesting! I wish I could meet with that fowl. I would teach it to mind its own business!”</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jemima Puddle-Duck and the fox, talking in the wood— the fox wears a green coat and his big bushy red tail sticks out the back.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Blank Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Blank Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The fox, leads Jemima Puddle-Duck to his ramshackle house of faggots amongst the fox-gloves.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">“BUT as to a nest—there is no difficulty: I have a sackful of feathers in my wood- shed. No, my dear madam, you will be in nobody's way. You may sit there as long as you like,” said the bushy long- tailed gentleman.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">He led the way to a very retired, dismal-looking house amongst the fox-gloves.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">It was built of faggots and turf, and there were two broken pails, one on top of another, by way of a chimney.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">“THIS is my summer residence; you would not find my earth—my winter house—so convenient,” said the hospitable gentleman.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">There was a tumble-down shed at the back of the house, made of old soap-boxes. The gentleman opened the door, and showed Jemima in.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The fox showing Jemima Puddle-Duck into his wood-shed to nest, the fox snickers as he shuts the door.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Blank Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Blank Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jemima Puddle-Duck nestles amongst feathers in the wood shed to lay her eggs while the fox peers in through the door .</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE shed was almost quite full of feathers—it was almost suffocating; but it was comfortable and very soft.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jemima Puddle-duck was rather surprised to find such a vast quantity of feathers. But it was very comfortable; and she made a nest without any trouble at all.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">WHEN she came out, the sandy whiskered gentleman was sitting on a log reading the newspaper—at least he had it spread out, but he was looking over the top of it.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">He was so polite, that he seemed almost sorry to let Jemima go home for the night. He promised to take great care of her nest until she came back again next day.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">He said he loved eggs and ducklings; he should be proud to see a fine nestful in his wood-shed.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jemima Puddle-Duck speaking with the fox gentleman again as he reads his newspaper.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Blank Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Blank Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The fox, without his green coat, walks into the wood-shed and peers and paws at all the eggs amongst the feathers.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">JEMIMA PUDDLE-DUCK came every afternoon; she laid nine eggs in the nest. They were greeny white and very large. The foxy gentleman admired them immensely. He used to turn them over and count them when Jemima was not there.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">At last Jemima told him that she intended to begin to sit next day—“and I will bring a bag of corn with me, so that I need never leave my nest until the eggs are hatched. They might catch cold,” said the conscientious Jemima.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">“MADAM, I beg you not to trouble yourself with a bag; I will provide oats. But before you commence your tedious sitting, I intend to give you a treat. Let us have a dinner-party all to ourselves!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">“May I ask you to bring up some herbs from the farm- garden to make a savoury omelette? Sage and thyme, and mint and two onions, and some parsley. I will provide lard for the stuff-lard for the omelette,” said the hospitable gentleman with sandy whiskers.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The fox in green waistcoat talking with Jemima Puddle-Duck in front of a white farm gate.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Blank Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Blank Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jemima Puddle-Duck nipping off herbs in the garden with latice in the background.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">JEMIMA PUDDLE-DUCK was a simpleton: not even the mention of sage and onions made her suspicious.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">She went round the farm- garden, nibbling off snippets of all the different sorts of herbs that are used for stuffing roast duck.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">AND she waddled into the kitchen, and got two onions out of a basket.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The collie-dog Kep met her coming out, “What are you doing with those onions? Where do you go every afternoon by yourself, Jemima Puddle-duck?”</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jemima was rather in awe of the collie; she told him the whole story.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The collie listened, with his wise head on one side; he grinned when she described the polite gentleman with sandy whiskers.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jemima Puddle-Duck, two onions, and explaining to Kep, the collie, her whole story.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Blank Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Blank Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Kep the collie walks up to two fox-hound puppies and a horse-drawn carriage in front of a village shop.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">HE asked several questions about the wood, and about the exact position of the house and shed.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Then he went out, and trotted down the village. He went to look for two fox-hound puppies who were out at walk with the butcher.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">JEMIMA PUDDLE-DUCK went up the cart-road for the last time, on a sunny afternoon. She was rather burdened with bunches of herbs and two onions in a bag.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">She flew over the wood, and alighted opposite the house of the bushy long-tailed gentleman.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jemima Puddle-Duck laden down with a bag of herbs and onions, walking up the cart-path.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Blank Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Blank Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jemima Puddle-Duck and the fox talking with Kep, the collie, and the two puppies hiding behind the brush.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">HE was sitting on a log; he sniffed the air, and kept glancing uneasily round the wood. When Jemima alighted he quite jumped.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">“Come into the house as soon as you have looked at your eggs. Give me the herbs for the omelette. Be sharp!”</field>
      <field name="fulltext">He was rather abrupt. Jemima Puddle-duck had never heard him speak like that.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">She felt surprised, and uncomfortable.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">WHILE she was inside she heard pattering feet round the back of the shed. Some one with a black nose sniffed at the bottom of the door, and then locked it.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jemima became much alarmed.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Kep the collie running towards the fox's wood-shed.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Blank Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Blank Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The fox-hound puppies and the collie chase the fox and we see the fox's hind legs and tail as it runs out of the picture.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">A MOMENT afterwards there were most awful noises—barking, baying, growls and howls, squealing and groans.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">And nothing more was ever seen of that foxy-whiskered gentleman.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PRESENTLY Kep opened the door of the shed, and let out Jemima Puddle-duck.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Unfortunately the puppies rushed in and gobbled up all the eggs before he could stop them.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">He had a bite on his ear and both the puppies were limping.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Kep, the collie dog, letting Jemima Puddle-Duck out of the woodshed and the fox-hound puppies unfortunately eat up the eggs.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Blank Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Blank Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">JEMIMA PUDDLE-DUCK was escorted home in tears on account of those eggs.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jemima Puddle-Duck escorted home by the dogs in tears along the cart-path back to the farm</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Blank Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Blank Page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Cows, a barn, and Jemima Puddle-Duck with her four chicks.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Text page.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SHE laid some more in June, and she was permitted to keep them herself: but only four of them hatched.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Jemima Puddle-duck said that it was because of her nerves; but she had always been a bad sitter.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE END</field>
      <field name="title_display">Tale of Jemima Puddle-Duck</field>
      <field name="title_facet">Tale of Jemima Puddle-Duck</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">tale of jemima puddle duck</field>
      <field name="title_text" boost="1.0">Tale of Jemima Puddle-Duck</field>
      <field name="year_display">1908</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1908</field>
   </doc>
</add>