<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">University of Virginia, Board of Visitors</field>
      <field name="author_facet">University of Virginia, Board of Visitors</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">university of virginia board of visitors</field>
      <field name="author_text">University of Virginia, Board of Visitors</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1970's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/2006_01/uvaGenText/tei/bov_1979-10-06.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240342</field>
      <field name="date_text">October 6, 1979</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Board of Visitors Minutes, 1817-2002</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Board of Visitors Minutes, 1817-2002</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:183706</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Board of Visitors minutes. October 6, 1979</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Minutes</field>
      <field name="subject_text">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Minutes</field>
      <field name="title_display">Board of Visitors minutes.  October 6, 1979</field>
      <field name="title_facet">board of visitors minutes</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">board of visitors minutes</field>
      <field name="title_text">Board of Visitors minutes.  October 6, 1979</field>
      <field name="year_display">October 6, 1979</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1979-10-06</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1979</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:183706&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;public&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:183706&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;serial volume&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;University of Virginia, Board of Visitors&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;university of virginia, board of visitors&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Board of Visitors minutes. October 6, 1979&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;board of visitors minutes&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;October 6, 1979&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1979-10-06&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="corpname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia, Board of Visitors&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Board of Visitors minutes&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;October 6, 1979&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="edition"&gt;Public minutes&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa call number"&gt;Accession# RG-1/1/&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;a2846310&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;1 v.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="AAT"&gt;Minutes&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;The official minutes contain salary information. Access to minutes containing salary information will be granted only under the procedures of the Virginia Freedom of Information Act (Code of Virginia-2.1-340 ff.) or if permission is granted by the Secretary of the Board. Researchers interested in obtaining access to these records should direct a request in writing to the Office of the Legal Adviser, Madison Hall, University of Virginia. These public minutes have had salary information deleted and bear no restrictions.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Board of Visitors' minutes, Accession # RG-1/1/, Special Collections Dept., University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Minutes of meetings of the university's governing body which is the legal owner and operator of the institution. Recorded in the minutes are appointments and other personnel decisions concerning faculty, decisions about construction of facilities, gifts to the university, and all other board actions, decisions and resolutions.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Board of Visitors minutes&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;1979-10-06&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville, Virginia&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia Library&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;2005&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©2005 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Publicly accessible&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 125 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-BoardOfVisitorsMinutes"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">OFFICIAL MINUTES - TENTATIVE Subject to the Approval of the Board of Visitors THE RECTOR AND VISITORS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA October 6, 1979 The Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia met at 9:00 a.m., on October 6, 1979, in the Dome Room of the Rotunda with the following persons present: Rector William L. Zimmer, III, President Frank L. Hereford, Jr.; and Visitors William C. Battle, William M. Dudley, Warren B. French, Jr., DuPont Guerry, III, Robert V. Hatcher, Jr., Mrs. Linwood Holton, William E. Leggett, Stephen C. Mahan, George C. Palmer, II, Frank S. Royal, D. French Slaughter, Jr., Glenn B. Updike, Jr., and E. Massie Valentine. Absent: Robert P. Buford and Howard W. McCall, Jr. Messrs. George G. Grattan, IV, David A. Shannon, Ray C. Hunt, Jr., Avery Catlin, John J. Owen, Ernest H. Ern, and William H. Muller were presented throughout the meeting. The Minutes of the meeting of June 2, 1979, previously distributed, were approved as corrected.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">MOTIONS FOR EXECUTIVE SESSIONS The following motions were unanimously adopted by vote of all Visitors present: (a) That the Finance Committee and the Buildings and Grounds Committee of the Board of Visitors go into Executive Session for discussion and consideration of the acquisition and use of real property for public purposes. (b) That the Buildings and Grounds Committee and the Finance Committee of the Board of Visitors go into Executive Session to discuss and consider the investing of public funds where competition and bargaining are involved, where if made public initially the University's financial interests would be adversely affected. (c) That the Educational Policy Committee of the Board of Visitors go into Executive Session for the purpose of discussion and consideration of personnel matters involving the appointment, assignment, promotion, salaries and resignation of public employees. (d) That the Educational Policy Committee of the Board of Visitors go into Executive Session for discussion of legal matters which are within the University's jurisdiction. (e) That the Finance Committee of the Board of Visitors go into Executive Session for discussion of a legal matter which is within the University's jurisdiction. (f) That the Health Affairs Committee of the Board of Visitors go into Executive Session for discussion of legal matters relating to the Health Services Foundation, which are within the University's jurisdiction. (g) That the Board of Visitors go into Executive Session for the discussion of legal matters which are within the University's jurisdiction. Following the adoption of these motions, the Board of Visitors meeting was recessed at 9:07 a.m. The Board of Visitors reconvened in open session on Saturday, October 6, 1979, at 10:47 a.m.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ELECTIONS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED by The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia that the following persons be and they are hereby elected to the faculty: Mrs. Judith S. Allen as Assistant Professor of Music, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Ms. Lisa A. Anderson as Instructor in Nursing, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Dr. Jaafar I. Aouad as Instructor, General Medical Faculty, Vivarium, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. Mr. George S. Avrunin as Visiting Assistant Professor of Mathematics, for one semester, effective January 16, 1980. Mr. David A. Badertscher as Instructor, General Faculty, Clemons Library, for the period August 16, 1979, through June 30, 1980. Mr. Gary Balian as Associate Professor of Orthopedics and Biochemistry, for three years, effective August 1, 1979. Dr. James C. Ballenger as Associate Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, for three years, effective August 16, 1979. Mr. Robert M. Beckstead as Assistant Professor of Anatomy, for three years, effective August 16, 1979. Dr. Bruce C. Berger as Instructor in Medicine, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. Mr. John A. Blackburn as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, for three years, effective September 10, 1979. Dr. Peter A. Blasco as Assistant Professor of Pediatrics, for three years, effective October 16, 1979. Miss Eve Borsook as Professor of Art History, for one semester, effective January 16, 1980. Miss Bonnie L. Bowman as Instructor in English, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Stephen D. Bruck as Research Professor of Biomedical Engineering, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. Mr. Warren T. Byrd, Jr., as Visiting Lecturer of Landscape Architecture, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Dr. Blase A. Carabello as Assistant Professor of Medicine, for three years, effective July 1, 1979. Mr. Rion A. Causey as Assistant Professor of Nuclear Engineering, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Roger A. Chevalier as Associate Professor of Astronomy, effective September 1, 1979. Ms. Ellen R. Clore as Assistant Professor of Nursing, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Giovanni Costa as Visiting Professor of Physics, for one semester, effective January 16, 1980. Mr. Michael J. Cronin as Assistant Professor of Physiology, for three years, effective November 1, 1979. Ms. Mary Culnan as Acting Assistant Professor of Commerce, for the periods January 16, 1980, through May 31, 1980, and September 1, 1980, through January 15, 1981. Mr. Terrence M. Dempsey as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, School of Education, for the period September 15, 1979, through June 30, 1980. Mr. Hollis A. Dixon as Carman Blough Professor of Accounting, for one semester, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Robert G. Dixon, Jr., as Visiting Professor of Law, for one semester, effective January 16, 1980. Lieutenant Joseph W. Doswell, Jr., as Assistant Professor of Naval Science, for two years, effective September 1, 1979. Mrs. Marsha Dowell as Instructor in Nursing, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Winston L. Edmunds as Lecturer, General Faculty, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. Mr. Charles H. W. Edwards as Lecturer in Business Administration, The Darden School, for the period July 1, 1979, through January 31, 1980. Mr. Mark D. Ericson as Assistant Professor of History, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Dr. Jerry A. Fogle as Assistant Professor of Ophthalmology, for three years, effective July 1, 1980. Mr. M. P. Fontana as Visiting Professor of Physics, for the period August 1, 1979 through January 31, 1980. Mr. Alastair Fowler as Visiting Professor of English, for one semester, effective September 1, 1979. Miss Jacqueline R. Fox as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, Law Library, for one year, effective October 1, 1979. Mr. Jeffrey B. Freyman as Acting Assistant Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979, Mrs. Anne L. Furno as Visiting Assistant Professor of Mathematics, for one semester, effective September 1, 1979. Dr. John D. Gaare as Instructor in Anatomy, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. Mr. Angus William M. Gavin as Visiting Associate Professor of Architecture, for one semester, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Romaldo Giurgola as Thomas Jefferson Professor of Architecture, for the period September 1, 1979, through October 15, 1979. Lieutenant Patrick O. Gottschalk as Assistant Professor of Naval Science, for two years, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Jonathan F. Greig as Visiting Assistant Professor of Architecture, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. John B. Guerard as Acting Assistant Professor of Commerce, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mrs. Mary Alice Gunter as Assistant Professor of Education, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Robin J. Haack as Visiting Associate Professor of Philosophy, for one semester, effective January 16, 1980. Mrs. Susan Haack as Visiting Associate Professor of Philosophy, for one semester, effective January 16, 1980. Mr. Robert W. Haigh as Professor of Business Administration, for five academic years, effective September 1, 1979. Mrs. Maureen R. Hanson as Assistant Professor of Biology, for four academic years, effective September 1, 1979. Dr. Gregory F. Hayden as Assistant Professor of Pediatrics, for three years, effective July 1, 1979. Mr. Alvin J. Hill as Assistant Professor of Psychology, for one semester, effective September 1, 1979. Mrs. Pamela Holley-Wilcox as Acting Assistant Professor of Psychology, for one semester, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Kenneth O. Horner as Assistant Professor of Biology, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Robert B. Howsam as Visiting Professor of Education, for the period September 1, 1979, through January 15, 1980. Mr. Dennis Ting-pong Hu as Assistant Professor of Chinese, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mrs. Dana C. Hughes as Assistant Professor of Nursing, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Jon K. Hutchison as Assistant Professor of Planning, for two academic years, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. David H. Ibbeken as Professor, General Faculty, School of Law, for three years, effective September 1, 1979. Mrs. Karen L. Jacobs as Instructor in Nursing, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Peter J. Kenny as Lecturer in Law, for one year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Yong I. Kim as Assistant Professor of Biomedical Engineering and Neurology, for three years, effective August 1, 1979. Mr. Wolfgang O. Kimmerle as Visiting Assistant Professor of Mathematics, for one semester, effective January 16, 1980. Mr. Martin Klaus as Visiting Assistant Professor of Mathematics, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Christopher K. Kohlmiller as Instructor in Chemistry, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. John S. Land as Instructor, General Faculty, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. Mrs. Virginia K. Lee as Instructor in Nursing, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Dr. Nicholas J. Lenn as Associate Professor of Neurology and Pediatrics, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. William B. Levy as Research Assistant Professor of Neurosurgery, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. Mr. Dov A. Lichtenberg as Visiting Assistant Professor of Biochemistry, for the period July 1, 1979, through August 31, 1980. Mr. Joel M. Linden as Research Assistant Professor of Physiology and Pharmacology, for one year, effective January 1, 1980. Dr. Kathleen M. Link as Instructor in Pediatrics, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. Mr. John E. Logan as Visiting Associate Professor of Commerce, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Dr. Ivan S. Login as Research Assistant Professor of Neurology, for three years, effective July 1, 1979. Miss Elizabeth B. Lowe as Acting Assistant Professor, General Faculty, for one year, effective August 16, 1979. Mr. David E. Ludden as Assistant Professor of History, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Charles G. MacDonald as Visiting Assistant Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Charles J. Maffeo as Assistant Professor of Biomedical Engineering and Anesthesiology, for three years, effective August 1, 1979. Mr. David B. Magleby as Acting Assistant Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs, for one year, effective September 1, 1979. Ms. Lois Mansfield as Visiting Associate Professor of Applied Mathematics, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Dr. Steven A. Meixel as Assistant Professor, Family Practice, Student Health, for three years, effective August 16, 1979. Mr. Gary B. Melton as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, School of Law, for one year, effective August 16, 1979. Dr. Paul D. Mintz as Assistant Professor of Pathology, for three years, effective September 16, 1979. Miss Anne Mustain as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, Law Library, for one year, effective August 1, 1979. Ms. Kathryn A. Neeley as Instructor in Humanities, School of Engineering and Applied Science, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. James W. Nicholson as Acting Assistant Professor of Applied Mathematics, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Frank D. Nidiffer, Jr., as Assistant Professor of Pediatrics, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Lawrence Noriega as Instructor in Nursing, General Nursing Faculty, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. Lieutenant Leonard K. Payne, III, as Assistant Professor of Naval Science, for two years, effective September 1, 1979. Miss Patricia Plovanich as Acting Assistant Professor of Religious Studies, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mrs. Katharine S. Popp as Assistant Professor of Education, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Gregory L. Powers as Acting Assistant Professor of Chemical Engineering, for one semester, effective January 1, 1980. Miss Rosemarie F. Raimo as Assistant Professor, Division of Medical Center Social Work, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective September 16, 1979. Mr. M.S.A. Rao as Visiting Professor of Anthropology, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Miss Carmela A. Rehtz as Assistant Professor of Nursing, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Russell M. Reid as Acting Assistant Professor of Applied Mathematics, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mrs. Christine M. Reppucci as Associate Professor of Psychology, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Patrik Reutersward as Professor of Art History, for one semester, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Stephen P. Reynolds as Acting Assistant Professor of Astronomy, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979, Mr. Robert J. Ribando as Assistant Professor of Mechanical Engineering, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Joseph M. Robertson as Professor of Human Relations, Industrial Relations Counselors, The Darden School, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979, Dr. Charles E. Rose as Assistant Professor of Medicine, for three years, effective July 1, 1979. Mr. Alvin Z. Rubinstein as Visiting Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs, for one semester, effective January 16, 1980. Dr. James C. Sackellares as Research Assistant Professor of Neurology, for three years, effective July 1, 1979. Dr. William M. Scheld as Assistant Professor of Medicine, for two years, effective July 1, 1979. Mrs. Elizabeth S. Scott as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, Law School, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. Mr. David A. Sensabaugh as Acting Assistant Professor of Art History, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979, Mr. Michael C. Sharrett as Instructor, General Faculty, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. Mr. Arthur R. Shelley, Jr., as Lecturer in Law, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Peter A. Stark, Jr., as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1979. Miss Frances A. Stephenson as Research Assistant Professor of Pediatrics, for one year, effective July 1, 1979, Mr. Gerald A. Strand as Assistant Professor of Education, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Graham B. Strong as Lecturer in Law, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Hugh A. Stubbins as Thomas Jefferson Professor of Architecture, for the period October 16, 1979, through November 30, 1979. Mr. Randolph S. Tipps as Acting Assistant Professor of Education, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Dr. Paul B. Underwood, Jr., as Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology, effective October 1, 1979. (Dr. Underwood will be part-time for the month of September 1979.) Captain Evan J. Vaughan, Jr., as Professor of Naval Science, for three years, effective July 1, 1979. Mrs. Renate L. Voris as Assistant Professor of German, for four academic years, effective September 1, 1979. Dr. Robert L. Wangelin as Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, for three years, effective July 1, 1979. Mr. John H. A. Watson as Visiting Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs, for two years, effective January 16, 1980. Miss Barbara L. Wells as Assistant Professor of Education, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. William W. Wells, Jr., as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, Law Library, for one year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. K. Preston White as Assistant Professor of Engineering Science and Systems, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Melvin N. Wilson as Assistant Professor of Psychology, for four academic years, effective September 1, 1979. Dr. William G. Wilson as Assistant Professor of Pediatrics, for three years, effective July 1, 1979. Mr. Charles H. Wolfgang as Visiting Associate Professor of Education, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Larry A. Wolfe as Assistant Professor of Education, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ELECTION OF PART-TIME FACULTY Miss Sharon G. Berk as Visiting Assistant Professor of Environmental Sciences, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Dr. Charles H. Boggs, Jr., as Assistant Professor of Surgery, Roanoke Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1979. Miss Patricia C. Click as Acting Assistant Professor of Humanities, for one semester, effective September 1, 1979. Dr. Placido H. DeGuzman as Assistant Professor of Radiology, Roanoke Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1979. Dr. R. Jack Eastham, III, as Clinical Instructor in Otolaryngology, for one year, effective April 1, 1979. Mr. Jimell Erwin as Acting Assistant Professor of Chemical Engineering, for one semester, effective September 1, 1979. Mrs. Uliana Gabara as Lecturer in Slavic Languages and Literatures, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Oscar M. Garibaldi as Lecturer in Law, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mrs. Julia H. Green as Acting Assistant Professor of Education, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Dr. Raphael H. Greenstein as Associate Professor of Internal Medicine, Roanoke Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1979. Mr. John M. Gusdorf as Lecturer in Planning, for one semester, effective January 16, 1980. Mr. James G. Hallett as Assistant Professor of Environmental Sciences, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mrs. Frances Halsband as Lecturer in Architecture, for the period November 1, 1979, through January 15, 1980. Mr. Tawfig Y. Hasou as Assistant Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Ross A. Howell, Jr., as Lecturer in English, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. David K. Jemiolo as Acting Assistant Professor of Biology, for one semester, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. George W. Kester as Lecturer in Commerce, for one academic year, effective September 2, 1979. Mr. Donald E. Nuechterlein as Lecturer in Government and Foreign Affairs, for one semester, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Charles G. King as Lecturer in Commerce, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Robert M. Kliment as Lecturer in Architecture, for the period September 1, 1979, through November 15, 1979. Mr. Calder C. Loth as Lecturer in Architectural History, for one semester, effective September 1, 1979. Dr. Nina G. Magier as Associate Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Roanoke Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1979. Dr. Victor F. Marshall as Professor of Urology, for one year, effective August 1, 1979. Mr. Jeffrey H. McCormack as Assistant Professor of Biology, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Paul R. V. Pawlowski as Visiting Lecturer of Landscape Architecture, for one semester, effective September 1, 1979. Miss Cynthia J. Phifer as Visiting Assistant Professor of Architecture, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Robert L. Plavnick as Lecturer in Planning, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. G. Carleton Ray as Research Professor of Environmental Sciences, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1979. Miss Margo L. Reid as Lecturer in Speech Communication, for one semester, effective September 1, 1979. Mrs. Betty H. Sapir as Lecturer in French, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Lon D. Shackelford as Lecturer in Education, for the period September 1, 1979, through January 15, 1980. Dr. Robert B. Sharp as Associate Professor of Internal Medicine, for three years, effective July 1, 1979. Mr. Steven A. Sharp as Lecturer in Law, for one semester, effective September 1, 1979. Mrs. Roberta W. Shell as Lecturer in English, one-half time, for one semester, effective September 1, 1979, and full-time, for one semester, effective January 15, 1980. Mr. Christopher Slobogin as Lecturer in Law, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Dr. Richard A. Tomasulo as Assistant Professor of Neurology, Roanoke Program, for the period August 1, 1979, through June 30, 1982. Mr. Dell Upton as Lecturer in Architectural History, for one semester, effective September 1, 1979. Dr. Hugh H. Wells as Assistant Professor of Pediatrics, Roanoke Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1979. Dr. Suk-Chul Yoon as Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Roanoke Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1979. Mrs. Ann M. Young-Anawaty as Lecturer in Law, for one semester, effective September 1, 1979.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ELECTION OF NON-SALARIED FACULTY Mr. Peter Boyce as Visiting Scholar in Government and Foreign Affairs, for three months, effective September 12, 1979. Mr. Warren Chappell, Artist-in-Residence, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Javier Coy as Visiting Scholar in English, for the period January 16, 1980, through August 15, 1980. Mr. Lee L. Davenport as Visiting Lecturer, The Darden School, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Allen R. Douglas as Scholar-in-Residence in History, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Soon-Yung Hong as Visiting Scholar in Chemistry, for the period September 1, 1979, through August 31, 1980. Mr. Takeshi Igarashi as Scholar-in-Residence, Department of History, for two years, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Momoyo Ishibashi as Visiting Scholar in Government and Foreign Affairs, for one semester, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Mladen Jovanovic as Visiting Scholar in English, for the period June 12, 1979, through September 11, 1979. Mr. Tsutomu Kanashiki as Visiting Scholar in English, for the period September 1, 1980, through June 30, 1981. Mr. John H. Kareken as Scholar-in-Residence, Department of Economics, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Theodore M. Kellogg as Scholar-in-Residence, Office of the Vice-President and Provost, for one academic year, effective August 27, 1979. Mr. Rolf Lunden as Visiting Scholar in English, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. William L. Lurie as Visiting Lecturer, The Darden School, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. William R. Matthews as Visiting Scholar in English, for the period January 15, 1980, through May 31, 1980. Dr. George C. Newman as Research Assistant Professor of Biochemistry, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. Mr. L. Anderson Orr as Visiting Scholar in English, for one academic year, effective September 15, 1979. Mr. Richie Ovendale as Visiting Scholar in Government and Foreign Affairs, for the period July 1, 1979, through December 31, 1979. Mr. David A. Schlueter as Lecturer in Law, for one semester, effective September 1, 1979. Dr. W. Conrad Stone as Clinical Associate Professor of Ophthalmology, Roanoke Program, for the period September 1, 1979, through June 30, 1982. Mr. Akiko Sumimoto as Visiting Scholar in English, for the period September 1, 1979, through February 29, 1980.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ELECTION OF CLINICAL FACULTY Dr. Walter B. Beverly as Clinical Assistant Professor of Family Practice, for three years, effective July 1, 1979. Dr. David B. Flannery as Clinical Instructor in Pediatrics, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. Dr. Larry W. Lawhorne as Clinical Assistant Professor of Family Practice, for three years, effective July 1, 1979. Dr. Alan J. LePeter as Clinical Associate Professor of Ophthalmology, Roanoke Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1979. Dr. Robert F. McGrail as Visiting Clinical Instructor in Dentistry (Periodontology), for one year, effective September 1, 1979. Dr. Lawrence K. Monahan as Clinical Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, Roanoke Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1979. Dr. George T. Sproul as Clinical Assistant Professor of Pediatrics, for one year, effective July 1, 1979.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHANGE IN THE EFFECTIVE DATE OF ELECTION OF MR. KENNETH E. PEACOCK The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED by The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia that the effective date of the election of Mr. Kenneth E. Peacock as Acting Assistant Professor of Commerce, as approved by the Board on June 2, 1979, be changed to read as follows: Mr. Kenneth E. Peacock as Acting Assistant Professor of Commerce, for one academic year, effective January 16, 1980.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACTIONS RELATING TO CHAIRHOLDERS (a) Election to Chairs: The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED by The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia that the following persons be and they are hereby elected to the named chairs as shown below: Mr. Elmer L. Gaden, Jr., as Wills Johnson Professor of Chemical Engineering, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. W. Dexter Whitehead as Alumni Professor of Physics, effective July 1, 1979. (b) Leave of Absence: The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED by The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia that the following faculty member be and he is hereby granted leave of absence: Mr. Edwin S. Cohen, Joseph M. Hartfield Professor of Law, for the period September 1, 1979, to May 31, 1980, one-half time, to be retained part-time as Counsel to the Covington and Burling Law Firm of Washington, D. C.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RE-ELECTIONS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED by The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia that the following persons be and they are hereby reelected to the faculty: Dr. Thomas Abel as Assistant Professor of Medicine, for one year, effective September 16, 1979. Mr. Frank E. Barham as Assistant Professor of Education, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Richard Q. Bell as Professor of Psychology and Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, for three years, effective January 1, 1979. Mr. Clifford T. Bennett as Assistant Professor of Education, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. William J. Berman as Assistant Professor of Computer Science, for the period June 1, 1979, through July 31, 1979. Mr. Clifford E. Brubaker as Associate Professor of Education and Assistant Professor of Orthopedics, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Glen L. Bull as Assistant Professor of Education, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Steven L. Carter as Assistant Professor of Physics, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Alexander N. Christakis as Associate Professor of Engineering Science and Systems, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1979. Mrs. Anne G. Cooke as Assistant Professor, Division of Medical Center Social Work, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. Ms. Patricia R. Crook as Assistant Professor of Education, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Bruce P. Gaber as Research Associate Professor of Biochemistry, for one year, effective October 1, 1979. Mrs. Jean Wallace Gillett as Assistant Professor of Education, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Ms. Barbara A. Graham as Assistant Professor of Nursing, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. C. Scott Greene as Assistant Professor of Commerce, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Dr. John E. Greenlee as Assistant Professor of Neurology, for three years, effective July 1, 1979. Mr. John T. Hackett as Associate Professor of Physiology, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. Mr. Robert J. Hall as Assistant Professor of Education, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Daniel P. Hallahan as Associate Professor of Education, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Philip E. Hardee as Assistant Professor of Astronomy, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Ronald M. Hartwell as Professor of Economics, part-time, for the Fall terms of 1980, 1981, 1982, 1983, 1984, and 1985, effective September 1, 1980. Ms. Mary S. Hasenstab as Assistant Professor of Education, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Steven J. Hillenius as Assistant Professor of Physics, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Charles F. Hobson as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, Papers of James Madison, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. Ms. Priscilla O. Jobe as Assistant Professor of Nursing, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1979. Ms. Karen R. Johnson as Associate Professor of Nursing, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Lewis Johnson as Research Professor of Materials Science, for one year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Donald A. Keefer as Assistant Professor of Anatomy, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1979. Ms. Rebecca D. Kneedler as Assistant Professor of Education, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Ms. Sherry P. Kraft as Assistant Professor of Education, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1979. Ms. Susan G. Landin as Assistant Professor of Nursing, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1979. Ms. Suzanne C. Lareau as Assistant Professor of Nursing, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Dr. Michael G. Levien as Assistant Professor of Pediatrics, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. Mr. John Lloyd as Assistant Professor of Education, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Ms. Ann B. Loper as Assistant Professor of Education, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Thomas D. O'Sullivan as Assistant Professor of History, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Dr. Elsa P. Paulsen as Associate Professor of Pediatrics, and Assistant Professor of Biochemistry, for three years, (term for Biochemistry only), effective July 1, 1979. Mrs. Joanne H. Peach as Assistant Professor of Nursing, for the period September 1, 1979, through January 15, 1980. Mr. Stephen P. Plaskon as Assistant Professor of Education, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1979. Ms. Adelle M. Renzaglia as Assistant Professor of Education, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Michael J. Robinson as Visiting Associate Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Ms. Terry A. Schwartz as Assistant Professor of Education, for three years, effective July 1, 1979. Dr. Covie E. See as Assistant Professor of Dentistry, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. Ms. Suzanne E. Tatro as Assistant Professor of Nursing, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. David W. Thompson as Visiting Morris Professor of Commerce, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Ms. Paula J. Thompson as Assistant Professor of Biology, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Willem Antonius H. Thissen as Assistant Professor of Engineering Science and Systems, for one semester, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Madan M. Varma as Research Assistant Professor of Pediatrics, for the period August 1, 1979, through November 1, 1979. Miss Diane K. Wakat, as Assistant Professor of Nursing, part-time, General Nursing Faculty, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. David E. Winter as Assistant Professor of Art, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Jerry O. Wolff as Assistant Professor of Biology, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PROMOTIONS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED by The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia that the following promotions be and they are hereby made: Mr. Robert S. Brown, Associate Professor of Education, to Visiting Professor of Education, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Philip A. Ianna, Assistant Professor of Astronomy, to Associate Professor, General Faculty, effective September 1, 1979. Dr. Hubert A. Marshall, Clinical Assistant Professor of Ophthalmology, part-time, to Clinical Associate Professor of Ophthalmology, part-time, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. Mr. C. Michael Sheppa, Instructor, to Assistant Professor of Medicine, for three years, effective September 1, 1979. Ms. Sondra F. Stallard, Lecturer in Education, to Assistant Professor, General Faculty, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. Dr. Christopher Zazakos, Clinical Instructor in Medicine, to Clinical Assistant Professor of Medicine, for three years, effective July 1, 1979.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CORRECTION IN THE PROMOTION OF DR. WALLACE C. NUNLEY, JR. The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED by The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia that the promotion of Dr. Wallace C. Nunley, Jr., to Assistant Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology, as approved by the Board on March 31, 1979, be changed to read as follows: Dr. Wallace C. Nunley, Jr., Instructor in Obstetrics and Gynecology, to Assistant Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology, for three years, effective July 1, 1979.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">LEAVES OF ABSENCE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED by The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia that the following faculty members be and they are hereby granted leave of absence: Mr. Benjamin K. Bennett, Associate Professor of German, for one year, effective September 1, 1979, to accept a Guggenheim Fellowship. Mr. Ronald Biondini, Research Associate Professor of Environmental Sciences, for the period September 1, 1979, through December 31, 1979, to work on NOAA project. Mrs. Jane K. Brown, Associate Professor of German, for one year, effective September 1, 1979, to be a Visiting Professor at the University of Colorado. Mr. Edwin S. Cohen, Joseph M. Hartfield Professor of Law, for the period September 1, 1979, to May 31, 1980, one-half time, to be retained part-time as Counsel to the Covington and Burling Law Firm of Washington, D. C. Mr. Randall Collins, Professor of Sociology and Member of the Center for Advanced Studies, for the period January 16, 1980, to May 31, 1980, to serve as a Visiting Professor of Sociology, at the University of California at Riverside. Dr. Eugene C. Corbett, Jr., Assistant Professor of Medicine, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective July 1, 1979, to enter private practice. Mrs. Eleanor C. Crocker, Assistant Professor, Division of Medical Center Social Work, General Medical Faculty, and Assistant Professor of Psychiatry, General Medical Faculty, for the period July 6, 1979, through August 10, 1979, to join her husband in France for the last month of his leave from the University of Virginia Department of Anthropology. Ms. Martine Duchatelet, Assistant Professor of Economics, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979, to accept a visiting teaching position at the Graduate School of Business of Columbia University. Mr. Charles H. Giffen, Associate Professor of Mathematics, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979, to be a visitor on the faculty at Northwestern University. Mr. A. Robert Kuhlthau, Professor of Civil Engineering, for the period January 16, 1980, to May 31, 1980, to work with state, local communities and airlines implementing new concepts in air transportation systems. Mr. Ralph Lerner, Assistant Professor of Architecture, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979, to accept a visiting position at the Polytechnic of Central London. Mr. Richard W. Mintel, Assistant Professor of Biology, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979, to accept a temporary faculty position in the School of Medical Sciences, University of Illinois. Mr. Garland Okerlund, Associate Professor of Landscape Architecture, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979, to pursue consulting work. Mr. Brian Parshall, Associate Professor of Mathematics, for the period January 16, 1980, through May 31, 1980, to pursue research at Northwestern University in Illinois. Mrs. Lola D. Pelliccia, Lecturer in Italian, part-time, for the period September 1, 1979, through January 15, 1980, because of illness. Mr. Larry Sabato, Assistant Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs, for one year, effective January 16, 1980, to accept a Fellowship from the National Endowment for the Humanities. Mr. Robert J. Sheehan, Assistant Professor of Education, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979, to accept a position as Visiting Scholar at the University of California, Los Angeles. Ms. Joanne Simpson, Professor of Environmental Sciences, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979, to accept a position with NASA. Ms. Renate Voris, Assistant Professor of German, for one month, effective September 1, 1979, for medical reasons. Mrs. Libby R. Wyatt, Assistant Dean of Admissions, for the period June 1, 1979, through July 31, 1979, for personal reasons.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHANGES OF TITLE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED by The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia that the following changes of title be and they are hereby made: Mr. Antharvedi Anne, from Associate Professor of Biomedical Engineering, to Associate Professor of Biomedical Engineering, School of Engineering and Applied Science and Associate Professor of Biomedical Engineering, School of Medicine, effective September 1, 1979. Miss Varnell Armstrong, from Assistant Professor of Nursing, to Assistant Professor of Nursing, General Nursing Faculty, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. Mr. Amir H. Assadi, from Acting Assistant Professor of Mathematics, to Assistant Professor of Mathematics, for four years, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Manfred Bansleben, from Acting Assistant Professor of German, to Assistant Professor of German, for four academic years, effective September 1, 1979. Dr. William L. Clarke, from Assistant Professor of Pediatrics, General Medical Faculty, to Assistant Professor of Pediatrics, for two years, effective July 1, 1979. Ms. Bella M. DePaulo, from Acting Assistant Professor of Psychology, to Assistant Professor of Psychology, for four academic years, effective September 1, 1979. Miss Marjorie L. Girth, from Visiting Associate Professor of Law, to Visiting Professor of Law, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Dr. Peter W. Heymann, from Assistant Professor of Pediatrics, General Medical Faculty, to Assistant Professor of Pediatrics, for two years, effective July 1, 1979. Mr. Jack A. Holt, from Acting Assistant Professor of Commerce, to Assistant Professor of Commerce, for three years, effective September 1, 1979. Dr. Karen S. Kuehl, from Research Assistant Professor of Biochemistry, to Assistant Professor of Pediatrics, General Medical Faculty and Assistant Professor of Physiology, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. Mr. Russell M. Reid, from Acting Assistant Professor of Applied Mathematics, to Assistant Professor of Applied Mathematics, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mrs. Dorothy F. Rudolph, from Clinical Assistant Professor, Division of Medical Center Social Work, General Medical Faculty, to Clinical Assistant Professor, Division of Medical Center Social Work, General Medical Faculty, and Clinical Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine, and Psychiatry, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. Mr. Arthur A. Snow, from Acting Assistant Professor of Economics, to Assistant Professor of Economics, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Neil Snyder, from Acting Assistant Professor of Commerce, to Assistant Professor of Commerce, for three years, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Mano Thubrikar, from Assistant Professor of Surgery, General Medical Faculty, to Research Assistant Professor of Surgery, for two years, effective July 1, 1979. Mr. Brian L. Wilcox, from Acting Assistant Professor of Psychology, to Assistant Professor of Psychology, for four academic years, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Brent D. Wilson, from Acting Assistant Professor of Business Administration, to Assistant Professor of Business Administration, The Darden School, for one year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Michael Yoshitsu, from Acting Assistant Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs, to Assistant Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs, for four years, effective September 1, 1979.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RESIGNATIONS The following resignations were announced: Dr. Stanley Berent, Associate Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, effective June 30, 1979, to accept a position at the University of Michigan. Mr. Jonathan W. Best, Assistant Professor of Art History, effective August 31, 1979, to accept a position at Wesleyan University. Mr. Si Brown, Assistant Professor of Planning, effective August 6, 1979, to accept employment in Canada. Dr. Justiniano F. Campa, Associate Professor of Neurology, effective September 30, 1979, to enter private practice. Dr. Robert R. Cardell, Jr., Professor of Anatomy, effective August 31, 1979, to accept another position. Mr. David H. Cohen, Professor of Physiology, effective August 31, 1979, to accept a position at the State University of New York, Stony Brook. Mrs. Suzanne Freeman, Lecturer in English, effective September 1, 1979, for personal reasons. Mr. Michael Fritsch, Research Associate Professor of Environmental Sciences, effective September 1, 1979, for personal reasons. Dr. J. William Futrell, Associate Professor of Plastic Surgery, effective June 30, 1979, to accept another position. Mr. Sanford A. Garfield, Assistant Professor of Anatomy, effective August 31, 1979, to accept another position. Mr. Michael J. Graetz, Professor of Law, effective May 31, 1979, to accept another position. Mr. Brian Greenberg, Assistant Professor of Mathematics, effective August 31, 1979, to accept another position. Mr. C. Scott Greene, Assistant Professor of Commerce, effective September 1, 1979, to accept another position. Mrs. Barbara M. Gruber, Assistant Professor of Nursing, effective May 31, 1979, for personal reasons. Mr. James A. Gundy, III, Assistant Dean of Admissions, effective July 31, 1979, to accept another position. Mr. Ken E. Handley, Assistant Professor of Dentistry, effective July 15, 1979, to accept a teaching position in Texas. Mr. Charles F. Hobson, Assistant Professor, General Faculty, Papers of James Madison, effective August 31, 1979, to accept another position. Mr. Keith A. Howell, Associate Professor of Education, effective August 31, 1979, to accept a position at Northeastern University. Mr. Steven L. Ifshin, Assistant Professor, General Medical Faculty, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, effective September 30, 1979, to accept another position. Mr. Richard N. Johnson, Associate Professor of Biomedical Engineering and Neurology, effective July 31, 1979, to accept a position at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. Mr. Paul W. Kroll, Assistant Professor of Chinese, effective May 31, 1979, to accept a position at another University. Dr. L. Jerome Krovetz, Professor of Pediatrics, effective September 30, 1979, to accept a position at the University of Florida. Mr. John S. Land, Assistant Dean, Office of Admissions, effective August 31, 1979, to accept another position. Mr. David W. Leslie, Associate Professor of Education. effective August 15, 1979, to accept another position. Mr. Gregory M. MacGregor, Assistant Professor, General Faculty, and Assistant Dean, School of Law, effective May 31, 1979, to return to private practice. Mrs. Margaret H. MacGregor, Assistant Professor of Nursing, effective May 31, 1979, to return to full-time graduate study. Mr. Stephen B. Manuck, Assistant Professor of Psychology, effective August 31, 1979, to accept a position at Bowman Gray School of Medicine in North Carolina. Mr. Richard W. Mintel, Assistant Professor of Biology, effective May 31, 1980, to accept a position at the School of Medical Sciences, University of Illinois. Mr. Michael D. Peterson, Assistant Professor, Alderman Library, effective September 5, 1979, to accept another position. Mrs. Ann Pumphrey, Assistant Professor of Nursing, effective May 31, 1979, to accept another position. Ms. Jane W. Ransom, Assistant Professor, Division of Medical Center Social Work, General Medical Faculty, and Clinical Assistant Professor of Psychiatry, General Medical Faculty, effective July 31, 1979, to pursue unsalaried activities. Dr. James C. Sackellares, Research Assistant Professor of Neurology, effective August 31, 1979, to accept a position at the University of Michigan. Mr. Thomas W. Sadler, Assistant Professor of Anatomy, effective August 31, 1979, to accept another position. Mr. Jay S. Segal, Assistant Professor of Education, effective August 31, 1979, to accept a position at Temple University. Mr. Richard T. Selden, Chairman, Department of Economics, effective September 16, 1979, to return to full-time teaching and research. (Chairmanship only) Dr. Kenneth R. Spisso, Assistant Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology, effective June 30, 1979, to accept another position. Dr. Peyton T. Taylor, Jr., Assistant Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology, effective July 31, 1979, to accept another position. Mr. Thomas C. Westfall, Professor of Pharmacology, effective July 31, 1979, to accept a position at the University of Missouri. Miss Dora Wiebenson, Chairman, Division of Architectural History, effective May 31, 1979, to devote full time to teaching. Mr. James R. Wilson, Research Assistant Professor of Physiology, effective July 31, 1979, to accept another position. Mr. Ricardo N. Zapata, Associate Professor of Engineering Science and Systems, effective May 31, 1979 to accept another position.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHANGE IN THE EFFECTIVE DATE OF THE RESIGNATION OF MR. MARTIN S. OCHS The President announced that the effective date of the resignation of Mr. Martin S. Ochs, Lecturer, General Medical Faculty, has been changed from June 30, 1979, as announced to the Board at its meeting June 2, 1979, to August 31, 1979.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHANGE IN THE EFFECTIVE DATE OF THE RESIGNATION OF MR. LAURENCE J. O'TOOLE, JR. The President announced that the effective date of the resignation of Mr. Laurence J. O'Toole, Jr., Assistant Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs, as announced to the Board at its meeting on January 27, 1979, be changed from May 31, 1979 to July 31, 1979.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPOINTMENTS The following appointments were announced: Mr. Joseph M. Bessette as Research Associate in the White Burkett Miller Center of Public Affairs, for the period July 1, 1979, through December 31, 1979. Mr. Rodney L. Biltonen as Assistant Dean, School of Medicine, for three years, effective August 1, 1979. Mr. John A. Blackburn as Associate Dean of Admissions, for three years, effective September 10, 1979. Ms. Bonnie L. Bowman as Assistant Dean, College of Arts and Sciences, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Roger A. Chevalier as a Member of the Center for Advanced Studies, for three years, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Robert F. Cook as Assistant Dean, College of Arts and Sciences, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Giovanni Costa as a Member of the Center for Advanced Studies, for the period January 16, 1980 to May 31, 1980. Mr. Ronald G. Dimberg as Assistant Dean for International Studies, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. George M. Dupuy as Director of Executive Education Programs, School of Commerce, for one year, effective July 16, 1979. Mr. Winston L. Edmunds as Director, Upward Bound Program, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. Mr. Irvin Ehrenpreis as a Member of the Center for Advanced Studies, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1979. Ms. Kathryn B. Feuer as Acting Chairman, Department of Slavic Languages and Literatures, for one year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. M. P. Fontana as a Member of the Center for Advanced Studies, for the period August 1, 1979, through January 31, 1980. Mr. Elmer L. Gaden, Jr., as a Member of the Center for Advanced Studies, for three years, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. C. Edward Good as Acting Director, Law School Foundation, and Acting Director, Alumni Association, School of Law, for the period July 1, 1979, to December 31, 1979. Ms. Vivian V. Gordon as Director, Afro-American and African Studies, for two years, effective September 1, 1979. Mrs. E. Mavis Hetherington as Chairman, Department of Psychology, for three years, effective September 1, 1980. Mr. David H. Ibbeken as Director of the Law School Foundation and Director of the Law School Alumni Association, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. John S. Land as Assistant Dean of Admissions, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. Ms. Elizabeth B. Lowe as Assistant Dean, School of Law, for one year, effective August 16, 1979. Mr. Glenn J. McGarvey as a Member of the Center for Advanced Studies, for two years, effective September 1, 1979. (Mr. McGarvey was elected as Assistant Professor of Chemistry, March 1979.) Mr. Gary B. Melton as Director of Research, Institute of Law, Psychiatry and Public Policy, for one year, effective August 16, 1979. Mr. Alvin Z. Rubinstein as a Member of the Center for Advanced Studies, for one semester, effective January 16, 1980. Mrs. Elizabeth S. Scott as Director of Forensic Psychiatry Mental Health Professionals Training Program and Assistant Director of Institute of Law, Psychiatry and Public Policy, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. Mr. Nathan A. Scott, Jr., as Acting Chairman, Department of Religious Studies, for one semester, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Michael C. Sharrett as Assistant Director, Career Planning and Placement, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. Mr. Peter A. Stark, Jr., as Assistant to the Vice-President for Student Affairs, for three years, effective July 1, 1979. Ms. Paula J. Thompson as Assistant Dean for Instructional Programs, College of Arts and Sciences, for one year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. John H. A. Watson as a Member of the Center for Advanced Studies, for the period January 16, 1980 to January 15, 1982. Mr. Richard G. Wilson as Chairman, Division of Architectural History, School of Architecture, for three years, effective September 1, 1979. Dr. Paul B. Underwood, Jr., as Chairman, Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, for five years, effective October 1, 1979. Mr. John Whitaker, Chairman, Department of Economics, for the period September 17, 1979, through August 31, 1982.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CANCELLATION OF APPOINTMENT OF MR. A. VINCENT SHEA The President announced the cancellation of the appointment of Mr. A. Vincent Shea as Acting Director of the Institute of Government, for one semester, effective September 1, 1979.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RE-APPOINTMENTS The following re-appointments were announced: Mr. Patrick J. Bird as Associate Dean for Academic and Student Affairs, School of Education, for four years, effective July 1, 1979. Ms. Miriam C. Birdwhistell as Director, Division of Medical Center Social Work, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. Dr. Robert M. Blizzard as Chairman, Department of Pediatrics, for five years, effective July 1, 1979. Ms. Linda K. Bunker as Chairman, Department of Health and Physical Education, for four years, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Jay L. Chronister as Associate Dean for Administrative Affairs, School of Education, for four years, effective July 1, 1979. Mr. H. Clifton McCleskey as Director, Institute of Government, for four academic years, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Edwin W. Pullen as Vice-Chairman, Department of Anatomy, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. Mr. Jennings L. Wagoner, Jr., as Director, Center for the Study of Higher Education, for four years, effective September 1, 1979.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DEATH OF MR. ROWLAND A. EGGER Mr. Rowland A. Egger, Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs died on July 10, 1979. Mr. Egger was a member of the Faculty from 1931 until 1964 and then returned as a Visiting Professor during the 1977-78 Session.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DEATH OF MR. RICHARD C. GARLICK Mr. Richard C. Garlick, Associate Professor of French, died September 7, 1979. Mr. Garlick had been a member of the faculty since 1929, and had retired in 1966.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DEATH OF MR. BERNARD MAYO Mr. Bernard Mayo, Professor Emeritus of History, died August 20, 1979. Mr. Mayo had been a member of the faculty since 1937 and had retired in 1972.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DEATH OF MR. WILHELM MOLL Mr. Wilhelm Moll, Executive Director, Health Sciences Communications Center, Director of the Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, died on June 16, 1979. He had been a member of the faculty since 1962.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DEATH OF MR. WILLIAM STEINBERG Mr. William Steinberg, Associate Professor of Microbiology, died on June 27, 1979. He had been a member of the faculty since 1969.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DEATH OF MR. EDWARD E. YOUNGER Mr. Edward E. Younger, Alumni Professor of History, died June 7, 1979. Mr. Younger had been a member of the faculty since 1946, and was to have retired June 30, 1979.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">REPORT ON CONSTRUCTION The President reported on the status of construction projects. The report noted that the housing project for the Executive Programs Center was accepted on August 31, 1979. Other projects essentially complete are the Primary Care Center, the North Grounds and the 12th Street Parking Lots, the Student Recreation Building and the University Hall roof repairs. In addition, there are 25 projects in the planning stages, and an additional 13 under construction.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">STUDENT COUNCIL INVITATION TO SOCIAL GATHERINGS WITH BOARD MEMBERS The Rector advised that he has received a letter from Mr. John Serpe, President of Student Council, inviting Board Members to informal gatherings on the night preceding the regular Board Committee meetings. He said that such a gathering was held on October 4, 1979. Several Members of the Board reported that the meeting was enjoyable and beneficial. It was the consensus of the meeting that Board Members would attend future social gatherings given by the Student Council when possible.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">REPORT OF THE HOSPITAL ACCOUNTS COMMITTEE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED by The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia that the Hospital Accounts Committee be and it is hereby authorized to write off as bad debts and free service accounts listed on University of Virginia Hospital Schedules numbers 340, 343, and 346, for the months of May, June, and July 1979, totaling $2,145,197.08, and Blue Ridge Hospital Division Schedule number 434 for the months of July 1978 through March 1979, totaling $976,285.02, consisting of the following: University of Virginia Hospital: Bad Debts $ 955,716.32 Free Service to Counties and Cities 1,189,480.76 -------------- Total $2,145,197.08 Blue Ridge Hospital Division: Free Service to Counties and Cities $ 976,285.02 RESOLVED FURTHER, that the above action shall not be a compromise, settlement or discharge of the debts represented by such accounts.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RESIGNATION OF JOSEPH H. MCCONNELL FROM THE COUNCIL OF THE WHITE BURKETT MILLER CENTER The President pointed out that Mr. Joseph H. McConnell has tendered his resignation as a Member of the Miller Center Council, and that Mr. McConnell had served on the Council continuously since the Center was established. The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED by The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia that the letter of resignation from the Miller Center Council tendered by Mr. Joseph H. McConnell be and it is hereby regretfully accepted, effective October 6, 1979; and RESOLVED FURTHER that expressions of appreciation to Mr. McConnell for his leadership and dedicated service to the University, be transmitted to him. The President noted that the Board will elect a replacement for Mr. McConnell at a future meeting.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">AUTHORIZATION TO WRITE-OFF UNCOLLECTIBLE PARKING FINES AND PENALTIES The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED by The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia that the Service Support Units Bad Debts Committee be and it is hereby authorized, as recommended by it, to charge off the following uncollectible parking fines and penalties listed on Schedule 42 attached to the Report of the Committee consisting of the following: Parking Fines $ 9,220.00 Parking Penalties 13,970.00 ------------ Total $ 23,190.00 RESOLVED FURTHER that the above action shall not be a compromise settlement or discharge of the debts represented by such accounts.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RENTAL RATES FOR HOUSING FACILITIES FOR THE SUMMER 1980 The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED by The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia that the following rental rates for housing facilities for Summer 1980, be and they are hereby approved: FACILITY Approved Summer 1979 Amount of Increase Percent of Increase Proposed Rate Summer, 1980 SUMMER SESSION RATES Alderman - Observatory per student, per week, double occupancy $20 $2 10% $22 per student, per week, single occupancy $26 $2 8% $28 Nurses Apartment Complex per student, per week, double occupancy $24 $3 13% $27 per student, per week, single occupancy $32 $3 9% $35 Monroe Hill Houses per student, per week, double occupancy $24 $2 8% $26 per student, per week, single occupancy $32 $2 6% $34 SUMMER CONFERENCE RATES Lambeth Field, Copeley III, and Nurses per person, per night, double occupancy $10 $1 10% $11 per person, per night, single occupancy $13 $2 15% $15 family rates, per week two bedroom apts $90 $10 11% $100 family rates, per week three bedroom apts. $100 $10 10% $110 Monroe Hill Houses per person, per night, double occupancy $ 8 $1 13% $ 9 per person, per night, single occupancy $11 $2 18% $13 Alderman/Observatory Houses per person, per night, double occupancy $6.50 $0.50 8% $ 7 per person, per night, single occupancy $9 $1.50 17% $10.50 (continued on the next page) RENTAL RATES FOR HOUSING FACILITIES - Continued Facility Approved Summer 1979 Amount of Increase Percent of Increase Proposed Rate Summer, 1980 McCormick Road Houses per person, per night, double occupancy $5.50 $0.50 9% $6 per person, per night, single occupancy $8 $1.50 19% $9.50 Graduate Advisor Suites in Alderman, McCormick Road Houses per suite, per week $40 $10 25% $50 GUEST FACILITIES McCormick Road Houses per person, for first night $7 $1 14% $8 per person, per night thereafter $5 $1 20% $6</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ESTABLISHMENT OF AN ENERGY POLICY STUDIES CENTER AT THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED by The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia that there is hereby established an Energy Policy Studies Center at the University of Virginia.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF FINANCIAL REPORT PERTAINING TO EXPENDITURE OF FUNDS FROM THE PRATT ESTATE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED by The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia that the financial report pertaining to funds received from the Estate of John Lee Pratt for the period ended June 30, 1979, be and it is hereby approved. (see the following page for the Report) UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA JOHN LEE PRATT FUNDS AS OF JUNE 30, 1979 Unexpended Balance 6/30/78 Board Approval (1) (1) : Allocations represent amount approved by Board for 1979-80. Allocations 1978-79 Expenditures Unexpended Balance 6/30/79 Arts and Sciences Biology Student Support $ 13,651.00 $ 49,200.00 $ 37,755.66 $ 25,095.34 Faculty Salary Supplement 5,124.44 0.00 3,692.50 1,431.94 Research and Equipment 147,085.24 32,100.00 34,636.56 144,548.68 $ 165,860.68 $ 81,300.00 $ 76,084.72 $ 171,075.96 Chemistry Student Support $ 22,149.18 $ 17,500.00 $ 15,479.76 $ 24,169.42 Faculty Salary Supplement 3,500.00 4,000.00 6,888.33 611.67 Research and Equipment 178,000.00 149,500.00 57,634.00 269,866.00 $ 203,649.18 $ 171,000.00 $ 80,002.09 $ 294,647.09 Mathematics Student Support $ 50,200.00 $ 28,700.00 $ 42,900.10 $ 35,999.90 Faculty Salary Supplement 30,000.00 0.00 3,750.52 26,249.48 Research and Equipment 50,000.00 (25,000.00) 0.00 25,000.00 $ 130,200.00 $ 3,700.00 $ 46,650.62 $ 87,249.38 Physics Student Support $ 62,334.44 $ 40,000.00 $ 55,941.00 $ 46,393.44 Faculty Salary Supplement 1,500.00 0.00 1,582.50 (82.50) Research and Equipment 211,000.00 74,000.00 105,644.15 179,355.85 $ 274,834.44 $ 114,000.00 $163,167.65 $ 225,666.79 School of Medicine Student Support $ 37,075.00 $ 50,000.00 $ 26,194.30 $ 60,880.70 Research and Equipment 890,076.79 312,940.00 480,956.47 722,060.32 $ 927,151.79 $ 362,940.00 $507,150.77 $ 782,941.02 $1,701,696.09 $ 732,940.00 $873,055.85 $1,561,580.24</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RESOLUTION OF THANKS TO FACULTY ADVISERS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED by The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia that expressions of thanks be and they are hereby extended to members of the faculty who have given freely of their time to act as advisers to the new and returning students of the University, providing important guidance and direction for their academic programs.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">AUTHORIZATION FOR EXECUTION OF MEMORANDUM OF UNDERSTANDING AND AFFILIATION AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE UNIVERSITY AND THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA HEALTH SERVICES FOUNDATION The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia hereby reaffirms its approval in principle of the proposed formation, by members of the Clinical Faculty of the Medical School, of a non-stock corporation, to be called "The University of Virginia Health Services Foundation," for the purposes described in the proposed Articles of Incorporation and By-Laws, copies of which were exhibited to the meeting. RESOLVED FURTHER that the appropriate University Officers are hereby authorized to execute the Memorandum of Understanding between the University and the Foundation, a copy of which was exhibited to the meeting, and such officers are further authorized to negotiate an Affiliation Agreement between the University and the Foundation as described in the Memorandum of Understanding, which Agreement would be subject to the approval of the Executive Committee.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF SALE OF PROPERTY IN NEW ORLEANS, LOUISIANA The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED by The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia that the sale of endowment property located at 3331/333 Carondelet Street and the adjoining parking lot fronting on Union Street through to Perdido Street, New Orleans, Louisiana, jointly owned by Tulane University, Trinity Church and the University of Virginia, for $750,000, be and it is hereby approved.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">AUTHORIZATION FOR INVESTMENT IN THE COMMON FUND The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED by The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia that the Vice-President for Business and Finance be and he is hereby authorized to invest such funds or securities as may from time to time be determined by the Finance Committee in the Common Fund for bond investments. The following persons are authorized to give instructions and effect transactions with the Bank, subject to the understanding that their authorization to withdraw funds from the Bank is limited to instructions to remit such withdrawals to another bank to deposit to the credit of the University of Virginia in that bank. Ray C. Hunt, Jr., Vice-President for Business and Finance Herbert R. Pickett, Treasurer Alice H. Gerow, Investment Officer</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RESOLUTION ON FACULTY HOME MORTGAGE LOAN PROGRAM The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED by The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia that effective immediately the interest rate on University faculty home mortgage loans shall be increased from 9 1/2% to 10%.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF PROPOSAL TO RETURN GIFT OF DR. PAUL DISHNER The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED by The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia that authority be, and hereby is, granted to the Treasurer of the University to refund to Dr. Paul F. Dishner the contributions which he made to the University in 1975 and 1976 together with the accrued gains and interest earned on these funds amounting to a total of approximately $28,000, as of this date.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">GIFTS, GRANTS, AND CONTRACTS The President reported on gifts, grants, and contracts for the period May 1, 1979, through August 31, 1979. The report indicated a total of $1,519,700 in gifts and $17,703,900 for sponsored programs. The Board voted to accept the gifts, grants and contracts listed in the report.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">REPORT ON FACULTY SALARIES The President reported that the average faculty salary for University of Virginia faculty has been compared to the average salary in the 47 American Association of Universities institutions for the 1978-1970 session. The University ranked 20 in faculty salary and 29 in compensation (including fringe benefits). The President said that the maintenance of the University's position with respect to faculty salaries is a matter of the greatest importance.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">REPORT BY THE RECTOR ON THE ACTION OF THE EXECUTIVE COMMITTEE REGARDING THE INCREASE IN DAILY ROOM RATES AT THE UNIVERSITY HOSPITALS The Rector reported that on June 22, 1979 the Executive Committee adopted a resolution which increased the daily care rates at the University of Virginia Hospitals by $8,00, effective July 1, 1979.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF THE ACADEMIC PLAN FOR 1979-1985 Following discussion, the following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED by The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia that the University of Virginia Plan for the period 1979-1985 be and it is hereby approved in principle.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF THE POLICY ON THE ROLE OF THE INTERNAL AUDIT DEPARTMENT The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED by The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia that the policy on the role of the Internal Audit Department, as stated in the attached document (Attachment A), be and it is hereby approved effective immediately. Mr. William Battle urged the Rector to appoint a separate audit committee which should report directly to the Board. He urged that the appointment of an audit committee be undertaken soon, since the firm that has conducted audits for the University will not be re-engaged. Audits will be conducted by State auditors. The Rector will discuss the matter with Mr. Howard W. McCall, Jr., who is the Chairman of the Finance Committee.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CLINCH VALLEY COLLEGE MATTERS ELECTIONS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED by The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia that the following persons be and they are hereby elected to the faculty: Mr. Martin F. Keena as Lecturer, General Faculty, Clinch Valley College, for the period August 16, 1979 through June 30, 1980. Mr. Shiva K. Saksena as Assistant Professor of Statistics and Mathematics at Clinch Valley College, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Paul L. Steinmarc as Assistant Professor of Sociology at Clinch Valley College, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. Mr. Jefferson L. Townsend as Associate Professor of Social Welfare at Clinch Valley College, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1979. RE-ELECTIONS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED by The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia that the following person be and he is hereby re-elected to the faculty of Clinch Valley College: Mr. Franklin T. Harrell as Assistant Professor of Physical Education at Clinch Valley College, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. APPOINTMENT The following appointment was announced: Mr. Martin F. Keena as Admissions Counselor, Clinch Valley College, for the period August 16, 1979 through June 30, 1980.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DIVISION OF CONTINUING EDUCATION MATTERS RESIGNATIONS The following resignations were announced: Mr. Paul K. Beebee, Assistant Professor of Continuing Education, Division of Continuing Education, effective July 1, 1979, to accept another position. Miss Marilyn F. Pultz, Lecturer in Continuing Education, Division of Continuing Education, effective October 6, 1979, to accept another position. RE-APPOINTMENTS The following re-appointments were announced: Mr. Emmett B. Ford, Jr., as Assistant to the Dean for Administration, Division of Continuing Education, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. Mr. Wendell M. Lewis as Assistant Dean, Division of Continuing Education, for one year, effective July 1, 1979.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CENTRAL VIRGINIA REGIONAL OFFICE OF THE DIVISION OF CONTINUING EDUCATION MATTERS ELECTION The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED by The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia that the following person be and he is hereby elected to the faculty: Mr. Gregory J. Pels as Lecturer in Continuing Education, Central Virginia Regional Office, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. APPOINTMENT The following appointment was announced: Mr. Gregory J. Pels as Assistant Director, Central Virginia Regional Office, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. RE-APPOINTMENT The following re-appointment was announced: Mr. Robert H. Crow, Jr., as Director, Central Virginia Regional Office, for one year, effective July 1, 1979.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">HAMPTON ROADS REGIONAL OFFICE OF THE DIVISION OF CONTINUING EDUCATION MATTERS RE-ELECTION The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED by The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia that the following person be and she is hereby re-elected to the faculty of the Hampton Roads Regional Office of the Division of Continuing Education: Ms. Judith D. Whittemore as Assistant Professor of Continuing Education, Hampton Roads Regional Office, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. APPOINTMENT The following appointment was announced: Ms. Judith D. Whittemore as Director, Hampton Roads Regional Office, for one year, effective July 1, 1979.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">LYNCHBURG REGIONAL OFFICE OF THE DIVISION OF CONTINUING EDUCATION MATTERS RE-APPOINTMENT The following re-appointment was announced: Mr. Robert J. Gwinn as Director, Lynchburg Regional Office, Division of Continuing Education, for one year, effective July 1, 1979.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">NORTHERN VIRGINIA REGIONAL OFFICE OF THE DIVISION OF CONTINUING EDUCATION MATTERS RE-APPOINTMENT The following re-appointment was announced: Mr. William F. Lanier as Director, Northern Virginia Regional Office, Division of Continuing Education, for one year, effective July 1, 1979.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RICHMOND REGIONAL OFFICE OF THE DIVISION OF CONTINUING EDUCATION MATTERS ELECTION The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED by The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia that the following person be and she is hereby elected to the faculty of the Richmond Regional Office of the Division of Continuing Education: Mrs. Rhonda B. Lloyd as Assistant Professor of Continuing Education, Richmond Regional Office, for the period August 1, 1979, through June 30, 1980. RE-ELECTION The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED by The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia that the following person be and he is hereby re-elected to the faculty of the Richmond Regional Office: Mr. John M. Dunnavant, Jr., as Assistant Professor of Continuing Education, Richmond Regional Office, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. APPOINTMENT The following appointment was announced: Mrs. Rhonda B. Lloyd as Assistant Director, Richmond Regional Office, for the period August 1, 1979, through June 30, 1980. RE-APPOINTMENT The following re-appointments were announced: Mr. John M. Dunnavant, Jr., as Director, Richmond Regional Office, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. Mr. Charles E. Smith as Coordinator of the F.B.I. Program, Division of Continuing Education, for one year, effective July 1, 1979.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ROANOKE REGIONAL OFFICE OF THE DIVISION OF CONTINUING EDUCATION MATTERS RE-ELECTION The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED by The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia that the following person be and he is hereby re-elected to the faculty of the Roanoke Regional Office: Mr. Gary R. Atkinson as Assistant Professor of Continuing Education, Roanoke Regional Office, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. RE-APPOINTMENT The following re-appointment was announced: Mr. Gary R. Atkinson as Director, Roanoke Regional Office, for one year, effective July 1, 1979.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SOUTHWESTERN VIRGINIA REGIONAL OFFICE OF THE DIVISION OF CONTINUING EDUCATION MATTERS RE-ELECTION The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED by The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia that the following person be and he is hereby re-elected to the faculty of the Southwestern Virginia Regional Office: Mr. Jack L. Mason as Associate Professor of Continuing Education, Southwestern Virginia Regional Office, for one year, effective July 1, 1979. RE-APPOINTMENT The following re-appointment was announced: Mr. Jack L. Mason as Director, Southwestern Virginia Regional Office, for one year, effective July 1, 1979.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">On motion, the meeting was adjourned at 11:24 a.m. Respectfully submitted, Raymond C. Bice, Jr. Secretary RCB:jb Alexander G. Gilliam, Jr. Assistant Secretary</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ATTACHMENT A INTERNAL AUDIT POLICY STATEMENT It is the policy of the University to establish and support the Audit Department for the purpose of assisting management in the effective discharge of its responsibilities for the control of University resources. The mission and objectives of the Audit Department are as follows: To perform financial audits for the purpose of assuring that (a) cash, accounts receivable, and other assets of the University are promptly and completely recorded, accounted for, authorized and adequately safeguarded against loss and misappropriation, (b) liabilities of the University have been properly incurred and are properly recorded and discharged. Audits directed to financial accountability will include a review of all records, source data, fiscal procedures and control. To perform operational audits for the purpose of assuring that University operations are conducted efficiently and in accordance with appropriate and adequately documented policies, plans, and procedures. Operational audits will encompass a review of the policies, plans, procedures, organizational structure, staffing, and output of the audited unit. These audits will be conducted in accordance with the "Guide to Operational Auditing." To provide senior management with an independent, fair and objective appraisal of the effectiveness of the University's financial accountability systems and operational performance in accordance with the priorities established by the Director of Audits in coordination with the Vice President for Business and Finance and approved by the President and The Board of Visitors. To provide management with constructive criticism and positive recommendations designed to strengthen and improve performance results and cost effectiveness of their operations. The following policies identify the responsibilities of the Audit Department and provide guidelines for its interaction with all University departments and activities. Organizational Responsibilities The Director of Audits will coordinate the department's activities with the Vice President for Business and Finance. The Director will have unrestricted access and be responsible to the President and The Board of Visitors. He is responsible for the direction of the audit function and for seeing that the results of examinations and actions taken are communicated to appropriate levels of University management and, as appropriate, the President and The Board of Visitors. The Director of Audits, with participation by the Vice President for Business and Finance, will draft an annual audit plan. The plan will be submitted to the President and The Board of Visitors for review and suggested changes in scope. The Audit Department will give full consideration to scheduling special audit requests made by any department or activity. All requests should be in writing to the Director of Audits and state the purpose and scope of the audit. Independence The Audit Department will be organizationally and functionally independent from all University operations and will have no responsibility for the departments and activities being audited while being responsive to their needs and requirements. Because the Audit Department must be independent in carrying out its responsibility to monitor and evaluate control procedures instituted by management, the extent of audit work to be performed with respect to those procedures is limited to the assessment of such procedures. The Audit Department normally performs tests of underlying records and documentary support for transactions. Accordingly, objectivity would be lost if the Audit Department participated in accumulating data or reconstructing records. Authorities and Limitations The Audit Department personnel will have complete, free, and unrestricted access to all University departments, activities, records, properties, and personnel, and is not to be restricted in their activities. Where appropriate, special arrangements will be made for the examination of confidential information. Systems Planning and Development The Audit Department will participate in the planning, development, implementation, and modification of major computer-based and manual systems to insure that (a) adequate controls are incorporated in the system; (b) thorough system testing is performed at appropriate stages; (c) system documentation is complete and accurate; and (d) the resultant system is a complete and accurate implementation of the system specifications. The Audit Department will conduct post installation evaluations of major data processing systems to assure that these systems meet their intended purpose and objectives. The department will also review computer operations supporting such systems to assure that generally accepted standards for systems integrity and security, as well as system-specific controls, are being observed. Security Investigations The Audit and University Police Departments are to be notified if assets have been lost through defalcation or other security breaches. The Audit Department will perform sufficient tests and investigations to identify the weaknesses in procedures which permitted the defalcation to occur. However, the investigation of the specific event with the objective of recovery and/or prosecution is the responsibility of the University Police Department, with the decision to prosecute being the responsibility of the appropriate Commonwealth's Attorney. Coordination with External Auditing Agencies The Director of Audits will coordinate the department's audit efforts with those of the University's independent public accountants or other external auditing agencies by participating in the planning and definition of the scope of proposed audits so the work of all auditing groups is complementary, and their combined efforts provide comprehensive, cost-effective audit coverage for the University. Duplication of work will be avoided as much as possible. Reporting Prior to the completion of a formal report, an exit conference will be conducted with the department or activity head. The conference will be a review of all findings, conclusions, and recommendations. A formal report will be issued at the conclusion of every audit which will present a concise, clear and factual review of the conditions found, together with recommendations for improvement. A memorandum shall be issued to the Director of Audits within 60 days responding to each finding, recommendation, and exception included in the audit report. This memorandum will include the department's or activity's plan for implementing the recommendations or a presentation of significant disagreement with the findings and/or recommendations. A follow-up review will be made by the Audit Department to establish that agreed-to recommendations have been adopted. A memorandum will be issued on the follow-up review to the President and Vice President for Business and Finance. Distribution of Reports Audit reports will be issued to the Vice President responsible for the department or activity involved. In addition, copies of all such reports will be distributed to the President, the Vice President for Business and Finance, and the senior fiscal administrator having a functional interest in the subject matter. All audit reports will be available for review by The Board of Visitors. A summary of significant audit findings will be prepared annually and submitted to The Board of Visitors, the President, and the Vice President for Business and Finance.</field>
   </doc>
</add>