<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">University of Virginia, Board of Visitors</field>
      <field name="author_facet">University of Virginia, Board of Visitors</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">university of virginia board of visitors</field>
      <field name="author_text">University of Virginia, Board of Visitors</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1900's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/2006_07/uvaGenText/tei/bov_19090323.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240344</field>
      <field name="date_text">March 23, 1909</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Board of Visitors Minutes, 1817-2002</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Board of Visitors Minutes, 1817-2002</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:302039</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Board of Visitors minutes. March 23, 1909</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Minutes</field>
      <field name="subject_text">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Minutes</field>
      <field name="title_display">Board of Visitors minutes.  March 23, 1909</field>
      <field name="title_facet">board of visitors minutes</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">board of visitors minutes</field>
      <field name="title_text">Board of Visitors minutes.  March 23, 1909</field>
      <field name="year_display">March 23, 1909</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1909-03-23</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1909</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:302039&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;public&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:302039&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;serial volume&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;University of Virginia, Board of Visitors&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;university of virginia, board of visitors&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Board of Visitors minutes. March 23, 1909&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;board of visitors minutes&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;March 23, 1909&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1909-03-23&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="corpname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia, Board of Visitors&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Board of Visitors minutes&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;March 23, 1909&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="edition"&gt;Public minutes&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa call number"&gt;Accession# RG-1/1/&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;a2846310&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;0 pages&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="AAT"&gt;Minutes&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;The official minutes contain salary information. Access to minutes containing salary information will be granted only under the procedures of the Virginia Freedom of Information Act (Code of Virginia-2.1-340 ff.) or if permission is granted by the Secretary of the Board. Researchers interested in obtaining access to these records should direct a request in writing to the Office of the Legal Adviser, Madison Hall, University of Virginia. These public minutes have had salary information deleted and bear no restrictions.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Board of Visitors' minutes, Accession # RG-1/1/, Special Collections Dept., University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Minutes of meetings of the university's governing body which is the legal owner and operator of the institution. Recorded in the minutes are appointments and other personnel decisions concerning faculty, decisions about construction of facilities, gifts to the university, and all other board actions, decisions and resolutions.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Board of Visitors minutes&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;1909-03-23&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville, Virginia&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia Library&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;2006&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©2006 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Publicly accessible&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 18 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-BoardOfVisitorsMinutes"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">University of Virginia, March 23, 1909. At a meeting of Board of Visitors of the University, at 2:00 P. M., on above date in the President's Office, East Lawn, Present: The Rector, Armistead C. Gordon, and Visitors White, Craddock, Harmon, Norton, Irvine, and Shackelford, The Rector having called the Board to order, the following was adopted,— Resolved: That $150.00 be appropriated out of the general funds of the University to the Debating and Oratorical Council of the Washington and Jefferson Literary Societies, to assist in defraying the expenses of the contestants in the scheduled oratorical contests and to cover the cost of a debater's medal awarded by the Board as in the past. Resolved: That the sum of $200.00 be appropriated out of the general funds of the University, to cover cost of a portrait of the late Arthur W. Austin, benefactor. Resolved: That the claim of Fuller and Pitcher for architectural plans for the Hospital, be referred to Mr. John B. Moon, attorney for the University, with the authority to make the best settlement of the same practicable. Resolved: That the action of the General Faculty suggesting the establishment of a "Department of Public Health and Sanitation" as set out in the report of the Committee of the Medical Department, be approved; and that said Department be established in the University, as recommended. The recommendation of Committee on Academic Rules and Courses, previously adopted by the Academic Faculty, was presented, and adopted by the Board as follows:- Resolved: That a sixth Academic Group be formed in which shall be placed the subjects: English Literature, Biblical History and Literature, and English Language; and that every candidate for either of the baccalaureate cultural degrees be required to select one subject from this Group. Resolved, further—that the other regulations concerning the baccalaureate degrees be unchanged, save in so far as the adoption of the above recommendations renders necessary. The following correspondence was presented to the Board by President Alderman,— University of Virginia, March 18, 1909. To the Honorable Board of Visitors, University of Virginia. Gentlemen: Learning from our honored President that you would probably meet at the University very soon for the transaction of important business, I take advantage of the opportunity to bring a personal matter of high importance to myself before you. For several years past my health has been gradually failing accompanied by a partial loss of sight induced by incessant labors in the fields of literature, the lecture-room, and research work in my chosen subjects. My ill-health has now reached such a pass that I am compelled, though with profound reluctance, to hand in my resignation of the Chair of Teutonic Languages, to take effect at the end of the scholastic year in June next. I should struggle on with my work, with the help of my able assistant; had not the Carnegie Board assured me that it would place me on its honorary list, provided I received the consent and endorsement of the President and of your honorable body. Their Board meets in May and I should be most grateful if you could make your action subject to theirs, in case of miscarriage. Singularly pleasant and instructive as my connection of nearly 43 years with the University has been, first as a student in 1866-67-68, then as closely bound alumnus at a neighboring institution, finally, as 14 years' occupant of several different chairs in the University; delightful as all this has been to me, and largely through your gracious kindness, I feel that the time has come when a younger and stronger man should take up the work of my historic chair and meet the demands urged upon us by the expansion of the institution under its far-seeing President. I shall always watch this work with the most cordial and sympathetic feeling, knowing that under a superintending hand so wonderfully gifted, Dr. Alderman's plans for the University will, if carried out, rank him as the second founder of our great Alma Mater, inferior in his wide and comprehensive knowledge of educational matters only to the Sage of Monticello himself. It is therefore with the deepest sorrow that I part from the University at this moment, unable to share in its expanding power and greatness, but wishing it Godspeed in its noble future. Thanking you gentlemen most sincerely for your toleration of my imperfect work in all this trying illness, I remain Most cordially and respectfully yours, (signed) James A. Harrison, Professor of Teutonic Languages. Office of the President. March 23rd, 1909. Dr. James A. Harrison, University of Virginia. My dear Professor Harrison:- I beg to acknowledge the receipt of your communication of the 18th inst., forwarding your letter of resignation as Professor of Teutonic Languages in the University of Virginia. I have communicated your letter to the Rector and Visitors of the University and they have commissioned me to express their profound regret at your decision. I believe you will understand how keenly and genuinely I share with the Visitors this sentiment of regret. The Visitors, however, appreciate perfectly the reasons that impel you to take this step. They accept your resignation, subject to the conditions mentioned in your letter, assuring you of their entire appreciation of the singularly able services as a teacher and as a scholar which you have rendered to this institution for the past fourteen years. As a scholar and teacher and man of letters, you have given distinction to a great department and enrolled your name among the great servants of the University of Virginia. The Rector and Visitors and the President wish for you in your retirement, health and strength sufficient for the happy continuance of the scholar's life and the scholar's work. Very sincerely yours, (signed) Edwin A. Alderman, President. In view of the foregoing, the following was adopted,— Resolved: That the resignation of Professor James A. Harrison be accepted with the sincere regret of the Board, and with an expression of their high appreciation of his services as Professor; and that President Alderman be requested to communicate the action of the Board to Dr. Harri- son. It appearing that notice having been given as required by statute of the intention of the Board to elect a Professor of English, Dr. C. Alphonso Smith having received the votes of the members of the Board present, is declared elected Professor of English, at a salary of $3,000.00 per annum, to enter upon his duties September 16th, 1909. Resolved: That Pavillion II East Lawn, now occupied by Dr. James A. Harrison, be reserved for Dr. C. Alphonso Smith, and that the Superintendent of Buildings and Grounds is authorized to make such changes in the house as may be necessary for his occupancy. It appearing that notice having been given as required by statute of the intention of the Board of Visitors to elect a Professor of Chemistry, Dr. Joseph H. Kastle having received the votes of the members of the Board present, is declared elected Professor of Chemistry, at a salary of $3,300.00 per annum, to enter upon his duties September 16th, 1909. Resolved: That all recitation rooms, laboratories and dormitories necessary for the uses of the Summer School, be placed at the disposal of the management of the Summer School during its session, under the direction of the President. Resolved: That the question of fire protection for the University be referred to the Superintendent of Grounds and Buildings, with request that he report to the next meeting of the Board, with recommendations as to what should be done in the matter of increased protection; and, in the mean time, the request of the City of Charlottesville for co-operation in the support of the City Fire Department be postponed. Resolved: That the claim of Mr. Paul J. Pelz, Architect, be referred to Mr. John B. Moon, Attorney for the Board, with authority to act. Resolved: That Section 68 of the Laws of the University, is amended so that the Adjunct Professors in the Engineering Department may do work as consulting engineers, provided their regular professorial duties be not thereby interfered with. Resolved: That the sum of $104.00 be appropriated out of the general funds of the University to defray the balance due on repairs to the University Chapel. Resolved: That the sum of $2,000.00, or as much thereof as may be necessary be hereby appropriated for the purpose of furnishing the President's house as suggested in the report of the Superintendent of Buildings and Grounds, and that the same be expended under the direction of the President. Resolved: That the thanks of this Board be tendered to President Edwin A. Alderman for the energetic, efficient and devoted part which he has taken in securing to the University of Virginia, the creation and benefits of "The Thomas Jefferson Memorial Endowment Fund" of the University. Resolved: That the Visitors coincide with and approve the resolution of the Board of Trustees of the "Thomas Jefferson Memorial Endowment Fund" with regard to the application of the income of the Fund, and the designation of the schools as therein set forth. Resolved: That Henry Martin be continued in his present position as janitor, at the same salary, but without being required to perform any of the duties of the position. This action is taken by the Board in recognition of his advanced age, and of his faithful services to the University during a period of sixty years; and the Board desires to say to him: "Well done, good and faithful servant." On motion the Board adjourned I. K. Moran, Secy. Armistead C. Gordon Rector</field>
      <field name="fulltext">University of Virginia, March 18, 1909. To the Honorable Board of Visitors, University of Virginia. Gentlemen: Learning from our honored President that you would probably meet at the University very soon for the transaction of important business, I take advantage of the opportunity to bring a personal matter of high importance to myself before you. For several years past my health has been gradually failing accompanied by a partial loss of sight induced by incessant labors in the fields of literature, the lecture-room, and research work in my chosen subjects. My ill-health has now reached such a pass that I am compelled, though with profound reluctance, to hand in my resignation of the Chair of Teutonic Languages, to take effect at the end of the scholastic year in June next. I should struggle on with my work, with the help of my able assistant; had not the Carnegie Board assured me that it would place me on its honorary list, provided I received the consent and endorsement of the President and of your honorable body. Their Board meets in May and I should be most grateful if you could make your action subject to theirs, in case of miscarriage. Singularly pleasant and instructive as my connection of nearly 43 years with the University has been, first as a student in 1866-67-68, then as closely bound alumnus at a neighboring institution, finally, as 14 years' occupant of several different chairs in the University; delightful as all this has been to me, and largely through your gracious kindness, I feel that the time has come when a younger and stronger man should take up the work of my historic chair and meet the demands urged upon us by the expansion of the institution under its far-seeing President. I shall always watch this work with the most cordial and sympathetic feeling, knowing that under a superintending hand so wonderfully gifted, Dr. Alderman's plans for the University will, if carried out, rank him as the second founder of our great Alma Mater, inferior in his wide and comprehensive knowledge of educational matters only to the Sage of Monticello himself. It is therefore with the deepest sorrow that I part from the University at this moment, unable to share in its expanding power and greatness, but wishing it Godspeed in its noble future. Thanking you gentlemen most sincerely for your toleration of my imperfect work in all this trying illness, I remain Most cordially and respectfully yours, (signed) James A. Harrison, Professor of Teutonic Languages. Office of the President. March 23rd, 1909.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Dr. James A. Harrison, University of Virginia. My dear Professor Harrison:- I beg to acknowledge the receipt of your communication of the 18th inst., forwarding your letter of resignation as Professor of Teutonic Languages in the University of Virginia. I have communicated your letter to the Rector and Visitors of the University and they have commissioned me to express their profound regret at your decision. I believe you will understand how keenly and genuinely I share with the Visitors this sentiment of regret. The Visitors, however, appreciate perfectly the reasons that impel you to take this step. They accept your resignation, subject to the conditions mentioned in your letter, assuring you of their entire appreciation of the singularly able services as a teacher and as a scholar which you have rendered to this institution for the past fourteen years. As a scholar and teacher and man of letters, you have given distinction to a great department and enrolled your name among the great servants of the University of Virginia. The Rector and Visitors and the President wish for you in your retirement, health and strength sufficient for the happy continuance of the scholar's life and the scholar's work. Very sincerely yours, (signed) Edwin A. Alderman, President.</field>
   </doc>
</add>