<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">University of Virginia, Board of Visitors</field>
      <field name="author_facet">University of Virginia, Board of Visitors</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">university of virginia board of visitors</field>
      <field name="author_text">University of Virginia, Board of Visitors</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1980's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/2006_01/uvaGenText/tei/bov_1987-01-30.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240342</field>
      <field name="date_text">January 30, 1987</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Board of Visitors Minutes, 1817-2002</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Board of Visitors Minutes, 1817-2002</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:183734</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Board of Visitors minutes. January 30, 1987</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Minutes</field>
      <field name="subject_text">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Minutes</field>
      <field name="title_display">Board of Visitors minutes.  January 30, 1987</field>
      <field name="title_facet">board of visitors minutes</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">board of visitors minutes</field>
      <field name="title_text">Board of Visitors minutes.  January 30, 1987</field>
      <field name="year_display">January 30, 1987</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1987-01-30</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1987</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:183734&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;public&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:183734&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;serial volume&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;University of Virginia, Board of Visitors&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;university of virginia, board of visitors&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Board of Visitors minutes. January 30, 1987&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;board of visitors minutes&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;January 30, 1987&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1987-01-30&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="corpname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia, Board of Visitors&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Board of Visitors minutes&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;January 30, 1987&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="edition"&gt;Public minutes&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa call number"&gt;Accession# RG-1/1/&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;a2846310&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;1 v.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="AAT"&gt;Minutes&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;The official minutes contain salary information. Access to minutes containing salary information will be granted only under the procedures of the Virginia Freedom of Information Act (Code of Virginia-2.1-340 ff.) or if permission is granted by the Secretary of the Board. Researchers interested in obtaining access to these records should direct a request in writing to the Office of the Legal Adviser, Madison Hall, University of Virginia. These public minutes have had salary information deleted and bear no restrictions.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Board of Visitors' minutes, Accession # RG-1/1/, Special Collections Dept., University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Minutes of meetings of the university's governing body which is the legal owner and operator of the institution. Recorded in the minutes are appointments and other personnel decisions concerning faculty, decisions about construction of facilities, gifts to the university, and all other board actions, decisions and resolutions.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Board of Visitors minutes&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;1987-01-30&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville, Virginia&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia Library&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;2005&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©2005 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Publicly accessible&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 114 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-BoardOfVisitorsMinutes"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE RECTOR AND VISITORS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA January 30, 1987 The Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia met at 1:00 p.m., in Open Session on January 29, 1987, in the East Oval Room of the Rotunda with the following persons present: Rector Fred G. Pollard, President Robert M. O'Neil, John S. Battle, Jr., Angela L. Cleveland, Mrs. George M. Cochran, James S. Cremins, Joshua P. Darden, Jr., Henry A. Dudley, Edward E. Elson, Lemuel E. Lewis, Carl W. Smith, James L. Trinkle, E. Massie Valentine, Edgar N. Weaver, Jesse B. Wilson, III, and Thomas E. Worrell, Jr. Absent: Charles L. Brown and William M. Camp, Jr. Messrs. Ray C. Hunt, Jr., Ernest H. Ern, Raymond M. Haas, Marion B. Peavey, William H. Muller and George G. Grattan, IV, were also present. The Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia met at 2:50 p.m., in Open Session on January 30, 1987, in the East Oval Room of the Rotunda with the following persons present: Rector Fred G. Pollard, President Robert M. O'Neil, John S. Battle, Jr. Angela L. Cleveland, Mrs. George M. Cochran, James S. Cremins, Henry A. Dudley, Edward E. Elson, Lemuel E. Lewis, Carl W. Smith, James L. Trinkle, E. Massie Valentine, Edgar N. Weaver, Jesse B. Wilson, III, and Thomas E. Worrell, Jr. Absent: Charles L. Brown, William M. Camp, Jr., and Joshua P. Darden, Jr. Messrs. Ray C. Hunt, Jr., Ernest H. Ern, Raymond M. Haas, Marion B. Peavey, Paul R. Gross, and George G. Grattan, IV, were also present. The Minutes of the meeting of October 3, 1986, previously distributed were approved as corrected.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">MOTIONS FOR EXECUTIVE SESSIONS The following motions were unanimously adopted by vote of all Visitors present: (a) That the Educational Policy Committee of the Board of Visitors go into Executive Session for Item Number 11 on that Committee's agenda for the discussion and evaluation of the performance of University departments or schools if individual employees might be affected by the evaluation. (b) That the Finance Committee of the Board of Visitors go into Executive Session for Item Number 22 on that Committee's agenda for the following reason: to discuss the investing of public funds where competition or bargaining is involved when if made public initially the University's financial interests would be adversely affected as provided for in Section 2.1-344 (a) (5) of the Virginia Code. (c) That the Finance Committee of the Board of Visitors go into Executive Session for Item Number 23 on that Committee's agenda for the following reason: to discuss or consider the acquisition or disposition of real property for a public purpose if that discussion could affect the value of property owned by or desirable for ownership by the University as provided for in Section 2.1-344 (a) (2) of the Virginia Code. (d) That the Board of Visitors go into Executive Session for consultation with legal counsel pertaining to actual and potential litigation, or other legal matters within the jurisdiction of the Board, as provided for in Section 2.1-344 (a) (6) of the Virginia Code. Following a recess for an Executive Session of the Board of Visitors, the Open Session continued at 2:50 p.m., on January 30, 1987.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ELECTIONS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following persons be and they are hereby elected to the faculty: Ms. Catherine S. Anas as Instructor, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Steven N. Applegate as Instructor in Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective November 16, 1986. Mr. David G. Aubrey as Visiting Associate Professor of Environmental Sciences, for one semester, effective January 16, 1987. Ms. Patricia A. Babe as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, for the period October 1, 1986 through June 30, 1989. Mr. David A. Badertscher as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, Alderman Library, for the period November 1, 1986 through June 30, 1989. Mr. C. David Benson as Visiting Professor of English, for one semester, effective January 16, 1987. Ms. Donna R. Buck as Lecturer in Law, for the period October 13, 1986 through June 30, 1987. Dr. Jorn Carlsen as Research Assistant Professor of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, for the period September 1, 1986 through December 15, 1986. Ms. Patricia A. Connelly as Research Assistant Professor of Pharmacology, for one year, effective October 1, 1986. Ms. Janet I. Crayne as Instructor, General Faculty, Alderman Library, for the period January 1, 1987 through June 30, 1987. Mr. Imre Csiszar as Visiting Professor of Mathematics, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1986. Dr. Stephen B. Edge as Assistant Professor of Surgery, for three years, effective October 1, 1986. Dr. Robert D. Ferguson as Assistant Professor of Radiology, for three years, effective November 1, 1986. Mr. Gideon Fishelson as Visiting Professor of Economics, for one semester, effective September 1, 1986. Ms. Ellen K. Fitzgerald as Instructor in Surgery, for one year, effective September 1, 1986. Dr. Ted R. Galbraith as Instructor in Dentistry, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective October 1, 1986. Mr. Martin S. Green as Lecturer, General Faculty, for the period August 18, 1986 through June 30, 1987. Ms. Diane B. Hamilton as Assistant Professor of Nursing, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1986. Ms. Sandra D. Hobbs as Lecturer, General Faculty, for the period September 1, 1986 through June 30, 1987. Mr. Dell H. Hymes as Professor of Anthropology, effective July 1, 1987. Mr. Robert M. Jordan as Visiting Professor of English, for one semester, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Theodore Kuzen as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, Alderman Library, for the period June 16, 1987 through June 30, 1990. Mr. Nicholas L. Lash as Lecturer in Religious Studies, for one semester, effective September 1, 1986. Ms. Susan M. Leatherman as Instructor in Internal Medicine, General Medical Faculty, for the period September 1, 1986 through June 30, 1987. Dr. Charles Y. Lui as Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, Veterans Administration Medical Center, Salem Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1986. Mr. A. Jon Megibow as Lecturer, General Faculty, for the period September 15, 1986 through June 30, 1987. Mr. George Mentore as Assistant Professor of Anthropology, for four academic years, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Theodore E. Mifflin as Research Assistant Professor of Pathology and Research Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, for one year, effective September 16, 1986. Ms. Farzaneh M. Milani as Assistant Professor of Persian, for four academic years, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. James P. Mitchell as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, for three years, effective January 1, 1987. Mr. E. Edmund Moomaw as Visiting Professor, General Faculty, for the period January 5, 1987 through June 30, 1988. Mr. James Morganstern as Visiting Lecturer in Architectural History, for one semester, effective January 16, 1987. Ms. Noriko Narita as Instructor in Japanese, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1986. Ms. Lynda A. Nelson as Assistant Professor of Education, for the period January 16, 1987 through May 31, 1987. Mr. Robert L. Payton as Scholar in Residence, the Miller Center of Public Affairs, for the period May 1, 1987 through May 31, 1990. Ms. Susan B. Piepho as Visiting Professor of Chemistry, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1986. Ms. Mary E. Seeley as Instructor in Education, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Bellave S. Shivaram as Assistant Professor of Physics, for the period January 16, 1987 through January 15, 1991. Dr. Delmar D. Short as Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Salem Program, for the period September 1, 1986 through June 30, 1989. Ms. Johnnie R. Simpson as Lecturer, General Faculty, for the period September 1, 1986 through June 30, 1987. Mr. Thomas C. Skalak as Assistant Professor of Biomedical Engineering, for the period November 16, 1986 through May 31, 1989. Mr. Wayne L. Smith as Assistant Professor, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective November 1, 1986. Mr. Peter A. Stoudt as Instructor, General Faculty, for the period October 1, 1986 through June 30, 1987. Ms. Valerie O. Sutter as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Amparo Urbana as Lecturer in Economics, for one semester, effective September 1, 1986. Ms. Carolyn C. Walker as Research Assistant Professor of Otolaryngology, for one year, effective September 1, 1986. Dr. George W. Ward, Jr. as Associate Professor of Internal Medicine, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective September 16, 1986. Mr. Richard P. Warner as Assistant Professor of Drama, for four academic years, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Terry G. Wood as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, for the period November 16, 1986 through June 30, 1989. Ms. Eunice A. Woode as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, Alderman Library, for the period November 3, 1986 through May 27, 1988. Ms. A. Pamela Woodie as Lecturer, General Faculty, for three years, effective October 1, 1986. Mr. Zhongxin Zhao as Lecturer in Mathematics, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1986.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ELECTION OF PART-TIME FACULTY Mr. John S. Barrett as Lecturer in Commerce, for one semester, effective January 16, 1987. Mr. Mohamad N. Bassim as Visiting Professor of Materials Science, for the period December 1, 1986 through February 28, 1987. Mr. Larry W. Burton as Instructor in English, for one semester, effective January 16, 1987. Mr. Warner D. Chapman as Lecturer in Commerce, for one semester, effective January 16, 1986. Ms. Sharon E. Chilcote-Doner as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Gongpil Choi as Instructor in Economics, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. B. Waugh Crigler as Lecturer in Law, for one semester, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Thomas O. Cushman as Instructor in Sociology, for one semester, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Guru V. Dass as Visiting Research Professor in the Institute of Nuclear and Particle Physics, for the period December 1, 1986 through February 28, 1987. Mr. David J. DeMoss as Instructor in Philosophy, for one semester, effective January 16, 1987. Mr. James P. Fulton as Instructor in Applied Mathematics, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Johan V. Galtung as Visiting Professor of Sociology, for one semester, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Joseph V. Gartlan as Lecturer in Law, for one semester, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. J. Richard Gott, III as Visiting Associate Professor of Astronomy, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. John M. Grammer as Instructor in English, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1986. Ms. Elizabeth A. Griffith as Instructor in Business Administration, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1986. Ms. Mary E. Haas as Instructor in Mathematics, for one semester, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Hurst Hannum as Lecturer in Law, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Thomas P. Helscher as Instructor in English, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Robert A. Hickerson as Instructor in English, for one semester, effective September 1, 1986. Ms. Maura C. Ives as Instructor in English, for one semester, effective January 16, 1987. Mr. Joseph A. Kechichian as Lecturer in Government and Foreign Affairs, for one semester, effective September 1, 1986. Ms. Tsukio Kucinskas as Instructor in Japanese, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Charles H. Levine as Visiting Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs, for one semester, effective January 16, 1987. Mr. Dov A. Lichtenberg as Visiting Associate Professor of Biochemistry, for one year, effective September 16, 1986. Ms. Cassandra Linde as Instructor in Mathematics, for one semester, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Douglas E. Loyd as Lecturer in Sociology, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Michael B. Marzolf as Lecturer in Education, for one semester, effective January 16, 1987. Mr. Raymond P. McDermott as Visiting Professor of Education, for the period January 16, 1987 through May 31, 1987. Mr. Philip F. McEldowney as Lecturer in History, for one semester, effective January 16, 1987. Mr. Joseph E. Myers as Lecturer in Anthropology, for an academic year, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Eric R. Olsen as Instructor in Economics, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Richard A. Patterson as Lecturer in Computer Science, for one semester, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Donald E. Priest as Lecturer in Planning, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Christian P. Roberts as Instructor in Applied Mathematics, for one semester, effective January 16, 1987. Ms. Virginia G. Rovnyak as Lecturer in Mathematics, for one semester, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Treadwell Ruml, II as Instructor in English, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1986. Mr, Kurt R. Schaefer as Instructor in Economics, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1986. Ms. Rita K. Scott as Lecturer in Commerce, for one semester, effective January 16, 1987. Ms. Elizabeth L. Ward as Lecturer in Commerce, for one semester, effective January 16, 1987. Ms. Patricia A. Welsch as Instructor in English, for one semester, effective September 1, 1986. Ms. Maureen R. Worth as Assistant Professor of Education, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1986. Ms. Laurie U. deBettencourt as Assistant Professor of Education, for the period January 16, 1987 through May 31, 1987.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ELECTION OF NON-SALARIED FACULTY Mr. Robert D. Billinger, Jr. as Scholar in Residence in History, for one semester, effective January 16, 1987. Mr. Hei-yuan Chiu as Visiting Professor of Sociology, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Dennis C. Donat as Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Western State, for three years, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Alex N. Dragnich as Visiting Scholar in the Center for Russian and East European Studies, for the period November 1, 1986 through August 31, 1987. Ms. Ruth D. Gaare as Scholar in Residence in Religious Studies, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Vladimir G. Gelnovatch as Visiting Professor of Electrical Engineering, for one year, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Paul W. Glover as Visiting Lecturer in Business Administration, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1986. Dr. M. Anthony Graham as Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Southwestern State Hospital, for three years, effective December 1, 1986. Ms. Elizabeth M. Hairfield as Visiting Scholar in Chemistry, for the period September 1, 1986 through January 15, 1987. Mr. Gary L. Hawk as Research Assistant Professor of Psychology, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Takeo Iguchi as Visiting Lecturer in Business Administration, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. James B. Kobak, Jr. as Lecturer in Law, for one semester, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Zi F. Ma as Visiting Scholar in History, for the period August 1, 1987 through August 31, 1988. Ms. Meenakshi Munshi as Visiting Scholar in the Center for South Asian Studies, for the period December 11, 1986 through August 14, 1987. Mr. Kiyoyuki Ono as Visiting Scholar in English, for the period October 12, 1986 through November 30, 1987. Ms. Karen V. Parshall as Scholar in Residence in History, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Pierre Perez as Visiting Assistant Professor of French, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Russell C. Petrella as Research Associate Professor of Psychology, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Nicholas C. Sanders as Visiting Lecturer in Business Administration, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1986. Ms. Stephanie J. Shaw as Scholar in Residence in History, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Stephen J. Suomi as Research Professor of Psychology, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1986. Dr. Joel M. Trugman as Research Assistant Professor of Neurology, for one year, effective July 1, 1986. Mr. Charles E. Vernoff as Visiting Scholar in Religious Studies, for the period October 27, 1986 through November 7, 1986. Mr. Robert W. Ward as Visiting Research Scholar, for the period January 1, 1987 through June 30, 1987.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ELECTION OF CLINICAL FACULTY Mrs. Jann T. Balmer as Clinical Assistant Professor of Nursing, for the period January 1, 1987 through June 30, 1988. Ms. Joanne T. Banks as Clinical Professor of Internal Medicine, for the period October 16, 1986 through June 30, 1988. Dr. A. Norman A.G. Brenbridge as Clinical Associate Professor of Radiology, for three years, effective January 9, 1987. Dr. Placido H. DeGuzman as Clinical Assistant Professor of Radiology, Salem Program, for the period September 1, 1986 through June 30, 1989. Ms. Diana L. Deputy as Clinical Instructor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, for one year, effective October 1, 1986. Mrs. Mahone I. Heppner as Clinical Instructor in Nursing, for the period January 1, 1987 through June 30, 1990. Dr. Demetrios A. Julius as Clinical Associate Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, for three years, effective October 1, 1986. Mrs. Kathy J. Mitchell as Clinical Instructor in Nursing, for the period January 1, 1987 through June 30, 1990. Ms. Judith L. Mulligan as Clinical Assistant Professor of Nursing, for the period September 1, 1986 through June 30, 1989. Mrs. Susan K. Regi as Clinical Instructor in Nursing, for the period September 1, 1986 through June 30, 1989. Ms. Laurie L. Walker as Clinical Instructor in Nursing, for the period January 1, 1987 through June 30, 1990. Mr. Gordon J. Walker as Clinical Instructor in Nursing, for the period September 1, 1986 through June 30, 1989.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CORRECTION IN THE ELECTION OF MR. DOUGLAS E. DEGOOD The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the election of Mr. Douglas E. DeGood as approved by the Board on October 3, 1986, be changed to read as follows: Mr. Douglas E. DeGood as Associate Professor of Anesthesiology and Associate Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, for one year, effective July 1, 1986.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CORRECTION IN THE ELECTION OF DR. CHARLES G. DRAKE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the election of Dr. Charles G. Drake, as approved by the Board on October 3, 1986, be changed to read as follows: Dr. Charles G. Drake as Visiting Professor of Neurosurgery, for one year, effective November 1, 1986.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CORRECTION IN THE ELECTION OF MS. MARILYN FISHER The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the election of Ms. Marilyn Fisher as approved by the Board on October 3, 1986, be changed to read as follows: Ms. Marilyn Fisher as Assistant Professor of Anatomy and Cell Biology and Assistant Professor of Neuroscience, for three years, effective October 1, 1986.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CORRECTION IN THE EFFECTIVE DATE OF THE ELECTION OF MR. KAZUO ICHIKAWA The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the election of Mr. Kazuo Ichikawa as approved by the Board on October 3, 1986, be changed to read as follows: Mr. Kazuo Ichikawa as Visiting Scholar in English, for the period April 30, 1987 through May 11, 1987.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACTIONS RELATING TO CHAIRHOLDERS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the actions relating to chairholders be and they are hereby approved as shown below: (a) Elections of Chairholders Mr. Richard J. Bonnie as John S. Battle Professor of Law, effective February 1, 1987. Mr. Michael D. Dennis as Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation Professor of Architecture, for the period October 15, 1986 through December 15, 1986. Mr. John C. Jeffries, Jr., as Emerson G. Spies Professor of Law, effective February 1, 1987. Mr. John C. McCoid as O. M. Vicars Professor of Law, effective February 1, 1987. Mr. Michael Menaker as Commonwealth Professor of Biology, effective January 1, 1987. Mr. Stephen A. Saltzburg as Class of 1962 Professor of Law, effective February 1, 1987. Mr. Tsung Y. Shen as Alumni Professor of Chemistry, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. William B. Spong as John A. Ewald, Jr., Distinguished Visiting Professor of Law, effective January 16, 1987, for one semester. Dr. Peyton T. Taylor, Jr., as Richard N. and Louise R. Crockett Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology, effective February 1, 1987. Mr. Douglas J. White as Mac Wade Professor of Engineering, effective January 1, 1987. Mr. G. Edward White as John Barbee Minor Professor of Law, effective February 1, 1987. (b) Change of Title of Chairholder Dr. Robert M. Epstein, from Alumni Professor of Anesthesiology to Distinguished Professor of Anesthesiology, effective February 1, 1987. (c) Leave of Absence of Chairholder Mr. Richard M. Rorty, William R. Kenan, Jr., Professor of Humanities, for the period September 1, 1986 through May 31, 1987, without pay, to teach and do research in Germany. (d) Correction in the Leave of Absence of Mr. Roland N. McKean Correct the leave of absence of Mr. Roland N. McKean as shown in the Minutes of the meeting of May 30, 1986 to read as follows: Mr. Roland N. McKean, Paul Goodloe McIntire Professor of Economics, for the period September 1, 1986 through May 31, 1987, with partial pay, to do research.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RE-ELECTIONS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following persons be and they are hereby re-elected to the faculty: Dr. Martin P. Albert as Clinical Assistant Professor of Nursing, for three years, effective July 1, 1986. Mr. Gary R. Allen as Visiting Associate Professor of Economics, part time, for one semester, effective January 16, 1987. Dr. Robert W. Allen as Assistant Professor of Pediatrics, Roanoke Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1986. Dr. Willie A. Andersen as Associate Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1987. Ms. Francoise M. Attinger as Assistant Professor of Pediatrics, General Medical Faculty and Assistant Professor of Physiology, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective January 1, 1987. Ms. Arlene Aveno as Research Assistant Professor of Education, for the period October 1, 1986 through August 31, 1987. Ms. Janet L. Beizer as Assistant Professor of French, for two academic years, effective September 1, 1987. Mr. Patrick K. Bender as Research Assistant Professor of Biology, for one year, effective September 1, 1986. Dr. Donald E. Bley as Clinical Associate Professor of Nursing, for two years, effective July 1, 1986. Ms. Linda K. Blum as Research Assistant Professor of Environmental Sciences, part time, for one year, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Ralph C. Bralley as Associate Professor of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, for three years, effective April 1, 1985. Mr. Herbert Braun as Assistant Professor of History, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1987. Mr. Charles L. Cappell as Assistant Professor of Sociology, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1987. Ms. Madeleine B. Chandler as Assistant Professor of Nursing, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Martin D. Chapman as Research Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine and Research Assistant Professor of Microbiology, for the period October 1, 1987 through September 30, 1988. Dr. William C. Constable as Professor of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, for three years, effective April 1, 1985. Mrs. Deborah C. Conway as Assistant Professor of Nursing, part time, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1986. Dr. Philip H. Cooper as Professor of Dermatology, for three years, effective July 1, 1987. Mr. Michael B. Cornfield as Acting Assistant Professor of Rhetoric and Communication Studies, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1987. Dr. Alfred B. Cramer, III as Clinical Associate Professor of Nursing, for three years, effective July 1, 1986. Mr. Scott K. DeVeaux as Assistant Professor of Music, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1987. Dr. Pilar C. Dizon as Clinical Associate Professor of Nursing, for two years, effective July 1, 1986. Mr. Jonathan F. Doner as Research Assistant Professor of Biomedical Engineering, for the period January 1, 1987 through June 30, 1987. Mr. Marc J. Feldman as Research Associate Professor of Electrical Engineering, for the period January 16, 1987 through June 30, 1988. Mr. Arthur E. Freedlender as Research Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, for the period October 1, 1986 through June 30, 1987. Mr. Irving R. Friedman as Visiting Lecturer in Business Administration, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1986. Ms. Nancy J. Gansneder as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1987. Mr. John C. Garnett as Visiting Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs, for one semester, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Joseph H. Gieck as Associate Professor of Education, General Faculty and Assistant Professor of Orthopaedics and Rehabilitation, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective July 1, 1986. Ms. Linda A. Gonder-Frederick as Research Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, for one year, effective January 1, 1987. Ms. Fraunces M. Hardy as Clinical Assistant Professor of Nursing, for three years, effective July 1, 1986. Ms. Marilyn P. Hess as Clinical Assistant Professor of Nursing, for three years, effective July 1, 1986. Mr. Roger G. Hood as Visiting Professor of Law, for the period March 16, 1986 through April 24, 1987. Mr. Roger G. Hood as Visiting Professor of Law, for the period October 25, 1986 through November 1, 1986. Mr. John S. Horner as Professor of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, for three years, effective April 1, 1985. Mr. James D. Hunter as Assistant Professor of Sociology, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1987. Ms. Marylin S. James as Assistant Professor, General Medical Faculty, The Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, for the period December 9, 1986 through December 8, 1987. Dr. David Johnson as Clinical Assistant Professor of Nursing, for two years, effective July 1, 1986. Mr. Harold B. Johnson, Jr. as Scholar in Residence in History, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1987. Mr. Daniel P. Jordan as Scholar in Residence in History, for one academic year, effective July 1, 1987. Dr. William E. Kelly as Visiting Scholar in Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, for one year, effective January 16, 1987. Dr. Thaddeus E. Kelly as Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, for three years, effective September 1, 1986. Dr. Stephen M. Krenytsky as Clinical Assistant Professor of Nursing, for three years, effective July 1, 1986. Mr. Richard A. Lindgren as Research Professor of Physics, for two academic years, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. John W. Lloyd as Research Associate Professor of Education, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Ignacio J. Lopez as Assistant Professor of Spanish, for four academic years, effective September 1, 1987. Ms. Catherine L. Macklin as Assistant Professor of Anthropology, for three years, effective September 1, 1986. Ms. Claudine B. Malone as Visiting Professor of Business Administration, for one semester, effective September 1, 1986. Ms. Marjorie B. McElroy as Visiting Professor of Economics, for one semester, effective January 16, 1987. Mr. Patrick J. Michaels as Research Associate Professor of Environmental Sciences, for two years, effective July 1, 1989. Ms. Susan L. Mintz as Assistant Professor of Education, for the period November 1, 1986 through May 31, 1987. Dr. Raymond F. Morgan as Associate Professor of Orthopaedics and Rehabilitation and Associate Professor of Plastic and Maxillofacial Surgery, for the period September 1, 1986 through June 30, 1988. Ms. Anne Mustain as Assistant Professor. General Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1986. Mr. Frank D. Nidiffer, Jr. as Assistant Professor of Pediatrics, General Medical Faculty, and Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Thomas L. Pearce as Associate Professor, General Faculty and Lecturer in Biology, for the period August 16, 1986 through June 30, 1989. Mr. Marion B. Peavey as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, for five years, effective April 1, 1986. Mr. Gustavo Pellon as Assistant Professor of Spanish, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1987. Mr. Vojislav Radojevic as Visiting Associate Professor of Physics, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Prem veer G. Reddy as Assistant Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology, and Assistant Professor of Biochemistry, for three years, effective October 15, 1986. Ms. Marion W. Ross as Assistant Professor of Anthropology and Assistant Professor of French, part-time, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1987. Dr. J. Thomas Ryan as Clinical Assistant Professor of Nursing, for two years, effective July 1, 1986. Mr. Richard M. Scowcroft as Assistant Professor of English, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1987. Dr. Kiritkumar N. Shah as Clinical Associate Professor of Nursing, for two years, effective July 1, 1986. Ms. Eileen M. Stephens as Research Assistant Professor of Physiology, for one year, effective January 1, 1987. Mr. Graham B. Strong as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1986. Dr. Siva Thiagarajah as Associate Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology, General Medical Faculty and Associate Professor of Radiology, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1987. Ms. Maria-Michaela Thompson as Research Assistant Professor of Physiology, for one year, effective January 1, 1987. Mr. George B. Vaughan as Visiting Professor of Education, part time, for the period January 16, 1987 through May 31, 1987. Mr. Van D. Westervelt as Assistant Professor of Pediatrics, for one year, effective September 1, 1986.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CORRECTION IN THE EFFECTIVE DATE OF THE RE-ELECTION OF MR. JOSEPH H. GIECK The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the re-election of Mr. Joseph H. Gieck, as approved by the Board on October 3, 1986, be changed to read as follows: Mr. Joseph H. Gieck as Assistant Professor of Orthopedics and Rehabilitation, General Medical Faculty, for the period September 1, 1985 through June 30, 1986.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PROMOTIONS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following faculty members be and they are hereby promoted: Dr. Sam D. Graham from Clinical Associate Professor of Urology to Clinical Professor of Urology, for three years, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Gary W. Ives from Instructor, General Medical Faculty, The Claude Moore Health Sciences Library to Assistant Professor, General Medical Faculty, The Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, for three years, effective January 1, 1987.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">LEAVES OF ABSENCE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following faculty members be and they are hereby granted leave of absence: Mr. Daniel T. Devereux, Associate Professor of Philosophy, for the period January 16, 1987 through May 31, 1987, with partial pay, to conduct a graduate research seminar at The Catholic University, Washington, D.C.. Ms. Jessica R. Feldman, Assistant Professor, General Faculty, for the period September 1, 1986 through January 15, 1987, with partial pay, to write a book. Ms. Grace E. Fielder, Assistant Professor of Slavic Languages and Literatures, for the period September 1, 1987 through May 31, 1988, with partial pay, to do research. Mr. Ronald M. Hartwell, Professor of Economics, for the period January 16, 1987 through May 31, 1987, without pay, to visit the University of Sydney. Mr. Walter Hauser, Associate Professor of History, for the period January 16, 1987 through January 15, 1988, without pay, to do research. Mr. Hugh S. Landes, Associate Professor of Electrical Engineering, for the period January 16, 1988 through May 31, 1988, without pay, to qualify for the early retirement plan as approved by the Board of Visitors. Dr. Thomas A. Massaro, Associate Professor of Pediatrics and Associate Professor of Anesthesiology, for the period December 1, 1986 through April 30, 1987, without pay, to do research. Mr. Edward E. Oliphant, Associate Professor of Anatomy and Cell Biology, for the period October 1, 1986 through August 15, 1987, without pay, to do research. Mr. Terrance W. Pratt, Research Professor of Computer Science, for the period September 1, 1986 through May 31, 1987, with partial pay, to write textbooks. Mr. S. Frederick Singer, Professor of Environmental Sciences, for the period September 1, 1986 through January 15, 1987, without pay, to serve the federal government. Mr. Graham B. Strong, Assistant Professor, General Faculty, for the period September 1, 1986 through May 31, 1987, without pay, to be visiting professor at the University of Californi Los Angeles. Mr. Carlos Villar-Palasi, Professor of Pharmacology, for the period January 1, 1987 through December 31, 1987, with partial pay, to do research. Ms. Dora Wiebenson, Professor of Architectural History, for the period September 1, 1987 through May 31, 1988, without pay, to co-author a catalog for the National Gallery. Ms. Virginia H. Young, Lecturer in Anthropology, for the period January 16, 1987 through May 31, 1987, without pay, to write.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CORRECTION IN THE LEAVE OF ABSENCE OF MS. JEANNE C. BIGGAR The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the leave of absence of Ms. Jeanne C. Biggar, as approved by the Board on October 3, 1986, be changed to read as follows: Ms. Jeanne C. Biggar, Associate Professor of Sociology, for the period September 1, 1986 through May 31, 1987, with partial pay, to do research.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CORRECTION IN THE EFFECTIVE DATE OF THE LEAVE OF ABSENCE OF MR. CHARLES A. HOLT The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the leave of absence of Mr. Charles A. Holt, as approved by the Board on May 30, 1986, be changed to read as follows: Mr. Charles A. Holt, Associate Professor of Economics, for the period January 16, 1987 through May 31, 1987, without pay, to do research.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CORRECTION IN THE EFFECTIVE DATE OF THE LEAVE OF ABSENCE OF MR. TSUNG Y. SHEN The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the leave of absence of Mr. Tsung Y. Shen, as approved by the Board on October 3, 1986, be changed to read as follows: Mr. Tsung Y. Shen, Professor of Chemistry, for the period September 1, 1986 through November 30, 1986, without pay, for temporary employment at Merck, Sharp and Dohme Research Laboratories.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHANGES OF TITLE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following changes of title be and they are hereby made: Mr. Charles P. Baril from Acting Assistant Professor of Commerce to Assistant Professor of Commerce, for two years, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. F. John Bourgeois from Assistant Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology to Assistant Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective October 1, 1986. Mr. Douglas E. DeGood from Associate Professor of Anesthesiology and Associate Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry to Associate Professor of Anesthesiology, General Medical Faculty, and Associate Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1986. Mr. Robyn M. Kerler from Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Western State to Clinical Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Western State, for the period December 1, 1986 through June 30, 1988. Ms. Marilyn K. Nations from Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine and Instructor in Anthropology to Clinical Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, for one year, effective July 1, 1986. Mr. John G. Papovich from Lecturer in English, General Faculty to Lecturer in English, for one year, effective September 1, 1986. Dr. Lawrence H. Phillips from Assistant Professor of Neurology to Assistant Professor of Neurology, General Medical Faculty, for the period January 1, 1987 through June 30, 1987. Mr. Terrance W. Pratt from Professor of Computer Science to Research Professor of Computer Science, for the period September 1, 1986 through August 31, 1989. Mr. Eric N. Turkheimer from Acting Assistant Professor of Psychology to Assistant Professor of Psychology, for four academic years, effective September 1, 1986. Miss Mary F. Yeager, from Assistant Professor of Pediatrics General Medical Faculty and Clinical Assistant Professor of Nursing (term is July 1, 1985 through June 30, 1988), to Assistant Professor of Pediatrics, General Medical Faculty (July 1, 1985 through June 30, 1988) and Assistant Professor of Nursing, General Nursing Faculty, for the term October 1, 1986 through June 30, 1987.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CORRECTION IN THE CHANGE OF TITLE OF DR. MARY W. CLARK The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the change of title of Dr. Mary W. Clark, as approved by the Board on October 3, 1986, be changed to read as follows: Dr. Mary W. Clark, from Associate Professor of Orthopedics and Associate Professor of Pediatrics to Associate Professor of Orthopedics and Associate Professor of Pediatrics, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective September 1, 1986.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ELECTION OF PROFESSOR EMERITI The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following person be and he is hereby elected Professor Emeriti: Dr. William Parson resigned September 30, 1966 as Professor of Internal Medicine. He had been a member of the faculty since February 1, 1949. the effective date of this action is November 1, 1986.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RESIGNATIONS The following resignations were announced: Mr. Steven N. Applegate, Clinical Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, effective November 15, 1986. to become full time faculty member as an Instructor. Dr. George B. Batchelor, Clinical Assistant Professor of Otolaryngology, Roanoke Program, effective September 30, 1985, for personal reasons. Mr. Richard J. Becherer, Assistant Professor of Architecture, effective May 31, 1986, to accept another position. Dr. Martin E. Bloch, Assistant Professor of Plastic and Maxillofacial Surgery and Assistant Professor of Dentistry, effective September 30, 1986, for personal reasons. Mr. Thomas M. Boyd, Clinical Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, effective December 31, 1986, for personal reasons. Dr. Donald G. Branson, Associate Professor of Family Medicine, Lynchburg Program, effective September 30, 1986, to accept another position. Dr. Norman A.G. Brenbridge, Associate Professor of Radiology, General Medical Faculty and Associate Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology, General Medical Faculty, effective January 8, 1987, for personal reasons. Dr. Placido H. DeGuzman, Assistant Professor of Radiology, effective August 31, 1986, to accept a position as Clinical Assistant Professor of Radiology. Ms. Elizabeth A. Demers, Instructor in Orthopaedics and Rehabilitation, General Medical Faculty, effective January 2, 1987, to accept another position. Ms. Anne H. Freeman, Lecturer in English, part time, effective January 15, 1987, to finish a book. Ms. Jane J. Jacobs, Assistant Professor of Landscape Architecture, effective August 25, 1986, for personal reasons. Mr. Samuel B. Long, III, Assistant Professor, General Faculty, effective December 31, 1986, to accept another position. Miss Sara J. Mapstone, Assistant Professor of Nursing, General Nursing Faculty, effective March 31, 1987, for personal reasons. Dr. Vicente F. Maza, Assistant Professor of Radiology, Salem Program, part time, effective December 16, 1986, for personal reasons. Ms. Anne K. Myers, Assistant Professor, General Faculty, effective January 27, 1987, to accept another position. Ms. Margaret M. O'Bryant, Assistant Professor, General Faculty, Alderman Library, effective November 7, 1986, for personal reasons. Mr. Edward A. Parrish, Jr., Professor of Electrical Engineering, effective December 31, 1986, to accept another position. Ms. Ann P. Pollard, Assistant Professor, General Faculty, University of Virginia Hospital, effective January 16, 1987, for personal reasons. Mr. Terrance W. Pratt, Professor of Computer Science, effective August 31, 1986, to be appointed as Research Professor. Mr. Donald E. Priest, Lecturer in Planning, effective January 15, 1987, to accept another position. Mr. Michael B. Prince, Instructor in English, part time, effective January 15, 1987, to teach as a graduate instructor. Dr. William D. Routh, Clinical Assistant Professor of Medicine, Roanoke Program, effective June 30, 1984, for personal reasons. Mr. Steven M. Sanders, Assistant Professor, General Medical Faculty, The Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, effective November 30, 1986, to accept another position. Dr. Ellen B. Smith, Assistant Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology, effective February 14, 1987, for personal reasons. Mr. Michael Sochat, Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, General Medical Faculty, effective December 31, 1986, to accept another position. Mr. Zhi-Fu Wang, Visiting Professor of Physics, effective September 1, 1986, to continue on a consulting basis. Ms. Lynn Wichern, Assistant Professor of Drama, effective May 31, 1987, for personal reasons.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CANCELLATION OF THE RESIGNATION OF MRS. AMY L. FELDMAN The President announced that the resignation of Mrs. Amy L. Feldman, as Clinical Instructor in Nursing, effective June 30, 1986, as announced to the Board on October 3, 1986, be and it is hereby cancelled.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPOINTMENTS The following appointments were announced: Ms. Rosalyn W. Berne as Director of Admissions, The Darden School, for one year, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Robert P. Cook as Chairman, Department of Computer Science, for the period January 16, 1987 through May 31, 1987 Mr. Dell H. Hymes as Member of the Center for Advanced Studies, for three years, effective July 1, 1987. Miss Sara J. Mapstone as Assistant Dean for In-Hospital Services, for the period July 1, 1986 through March 31, 1987 Mr. Robert J. Mattauch as Chairman, Department of Electrical Engineering, for five years, effective January 1, 1987. Mr. A. Jon Megibow as Assistant Director of Admissions, Darden School, for the period September 15, 1986 through June 30, 1987 Mr. Robert L. Payton as Associate Director of the Miller Center of Public Affairs, for three years, effective May 1, 1987. Mr. Leonard L. Scott as Member of the Center for Advanced Studies, for one year, effective September 1, 1986. Mr. Douglas J. White as Member of the Center for Advanced Studies, for one year, effective January 1, 1987. Mr. Terry G. Wood as Associate Vice President and Director of University Development, for the period November 16, 1986 through June 30, 1989 Ms. A. Pamela Woodie as Director of the Budget, for three years, effective October 1, 1986. Mr. John J. Yiannias as Acting Chairman, Department of Art, for one semester, effective January 16, 1987. Ms. Mair J. de Voursney as Assistant to the Vice President and Provost, for one year, effective November 1, 1986.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RE-APPOINTMENTS The following re-appointments were announced: Mr. Jules I. Levine as Assistant Vice President for Health Affairs, for five years, effective October 1, 1986. Mr. Thomas L. McKeon as Acting Dean, Division of Continuing Education, for the period December 1, 1986 through June 30, 1987 Mr. Bernard A. Morin as Associate Provost for Public Service, for the period January 16, 1987 through August 30, 1987 Mr. William J. Thurneck as Assistant Dean for Academic Affairs, School of Engineering and Applied Science, for the period November 1, 1986 through December 31, 1989 Mr. Miles A. Townsend as Chairman, Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering, for five years, effective January 1, 1987.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ESTABLISHMENT OF THE RICHARD N. AND LOUISE R. CROCKETT PROFESSORSHIP IN OBSTETRICS AND GYNECOLOGY The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that there is hereby established in the School of Medicine a Chair to be known as the Richard N. and Louise R. Crockett Professorship in Obstetrics and Gynecology. The Board is grateful to the late Louise R. Crockett who made the establishment of this Chair possible.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ESTABLISHMENT OF THE THOMAS JEFFERSON PROFESSORSHIP IN THE COLLEGE AND GRADUATE SCHOOL OF ARTS AND SCIENCES The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that there is hereby established in Arts and Sciences a Chair to be known as the Thomas Jefferson Professorship in the College and Graduate School of Arts and Sciences. The Board is grateful to Ruth Robinson Smith, James Beverly Robinson, George C. Seward, William R. Piper and Fitzgerald and Company who made the establishment of this Chair possible.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ESTABLISHMENT OF THE SOUDER FAMILY PROFESSORSHIP IN ARTS AND SCIENCES The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that there is hereby established in Arts and Sciences a Chair to be known as the Souder Family Professorship in Arts and Sciences. The Board is grateful to William F. Souder, Jr., who made the establishment of this Chair possible.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ESTABLISHMENT OF THE JOHN V. RAY PROFESSORSHIP IN LAW The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that there is hereby established in the School of Law a Chair to be known as the John V. Ray Professorship in Law. The Board is grateful to John L. Ray and Olivia R. Singleton who made the establishment of this Chair possible.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ESTABLISHMENT OF THE JAN LANGMAN PROFESSORSHIP IN BIO-MEDICAL GENETICS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that there is hereby established in the School of Medicine a Chair to be known as the Jan Langman Professorship in Bio-Medical Genetics. This Chair is to become effective on such date as its funding is complete. The Board is grateful to Ronald H. J. Langman and M.W. Langman who made the establishment of this Chair possible.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHANGE IN THE NAME OF THE HENRY B. MULHOLLAND PROFESSORSHIP IN MEDICINE TO THE HENRY B. MULHOLLAND PROFESSORSHIP IN INTERNAL MEDICINE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the name of the Henry B. Mulholland Professorship in Medicine be and it is hereby changed to the Henry B. Mulholland Professorship in Internal Medicine.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">REPORT OF THE HOSPITAL ACCOUNTS COMMITTEE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the Hospital Accounts Committee be and it is hereby authorized to write off as bad debts and free service accounts included in the University of Virginia Hospitals Accounts Committee Reports for the meetings of September 15, 1986, October 20, 1986, November 17, 1986, and December 15, 1986, totaling $15,298,913.39 and consisting of the following: Bad Debts $ 2,208,056.28 Indigent Care 13,090,857.11 ------------- Total $15,298,913.39 RESOLVED FURTHER, that the above action shall not be a compromise, settlement or discharge of debts represented by such accounts.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF AMENDMENT TO FACULTY MORTGAGE LOAN PROGRAM The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that effective January 30, 1987, the interest rate on University faculty home mortgage loans shall be decreased from 9 1/2% to 8 1/2%.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF EASEMENT FOR OLD DOMINION POWER COMPANY ACROSS CLINCH VALLEY COLLEGE PROPERTY The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the deed of easement dated December 1, 1986 between The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia and the Old Dominion Power Company, which grants a 30 foot easement of right-of-way to bury electrical lines across property owned by The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia and located at various points throughout the campus of Clinch Valley College, be and it is hereby approved; and RESOLVED FURTHER that the appropriate officers of the University be and they are hereby authorized to execute and deliver said deed of easement.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF EASEMENT FOR OLD DOMINION POWER COMPANY ACROSS CLINCH VALLEY COLLEGE PROPERTY The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the deed of easement dated December 1, 1986 between The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia and the Old Dominion Power Company, which grants a 30 foot easement of right-of-way to Street Lighting Circuitry lines across property owned by The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia and located at various points throughout the campus of Clinch Valley College, be and it is hereby approved; and RESOLVED FURTHER that the appropriate officers of the University be and they are hereby authorized to execute and deliver said deed of easement.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF EASEMENT FOR RIVANNA WATER AND SEWER AUTHORITY ACROSS UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA PROPERTY The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the deed of easement dated December 15, 1986 between The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia and the Rivanna Water and Sewer Authority, which grants a 20 foot easement of right-of-way to install pipe lines across property owned by The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia and located on Observatory Mountain in the southwestern portion of the Grounds, be and it is hereby approved; and RESOLVED FURTHER that the appropriate officers of the University be and they are hereby authorized to execute and deliver said deed of easement.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">INCREASE IN SUMMER TUITION AND FEES FOR 1987 The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the Summer Session fees for the University Division be and they are hereby increased as follows, effective beginning with the Summer Session of 1987: Actual 1986 Amount of Increase Percent Increase Proposed 1987 FULL TIME COMPREHENSIVE FEE Class Affiliation $ 1.00 $-0- -- $ 1.00 Intramurals 7.00 2.00 28.6% 9.00 Newcomb Hall 10.00 1.00 10.0% 11.00 Drama 1.50 -0- -- 1.50 Student Health 32.00 2.00 6.3% 34.00 Transportation 9.50 -0- -- 9.50 TOTAL $61.00 $5.00 8.2% $66.00 PART TIME COMPREHENSIVE FEE Class Affiliation $ 1.00 $-0- -- $ 1.00 Intramurals 6.75 2.25 33.3% 9.00 Newcomb Hall 5.00 0.50 10.0% 5.50 Drama 1.00 0.25 25.0% 1.25 Student Health 32.00 2.00 6.3% 34.00 Transportation 4.25 -0- -- 4.25 TOTAL $50.00 $5.00 10.0% $55.00 TUITION Virginian (per semester hour) $ 60.00 $ 7.00 11.7% $ 67.00 Non-Virginian (per semester hour) 150.00 24.00 16.0% 174.00 Thesis/Dissertation Research 165.00 30.00 18.2% 195.00 Appellate Judges Program 540.00 63.00 11.7% 603.00 Non-Resident Fee 40.00 5.00 12.5% 45.00 Late Payment Fee 25.00 -0- -- 25.00 The Summer Session registration fee and tuition rates also apply to Mt. Lake Biological Station. In addition the following special fees apply to Mt. Lake Biological Station. Actual 1986 Amount of Increase Percent Increase Proposed 1987 Lab Fee and Field Trip $ 45.00 $ 5.00 11.1% $ 50.00 Pre-Doctoral Research Fee Per Term: Virginian 165.00 30.00 18.2% 195.00 Non-Virginian 330.00 60.00 18.2% 390.00 Post doctoral Laboratory: Fee per week 66.00 12.00 18.2% 78.00 MT. LAKE BOARD RATES PER TERM (5) WEEKS) Each Person 17 years of age &amp; older $260.00 $ 40.00 15.4% $300.00 Each Person 10-16 years of age 175.00 25.00 14.3% 200.00 Each Person 9 years of age &amp; younger 110.00 15.00 13.6% 125.00 MT. LAKE HOUSING RATES PER TERM (5 WEEKS) Dormitories $ 63.00 $ 6.00 9.5% $ 69.00 Cottages Laing Singles 63.00 6.00 9.5% 69.00 Laing Center 100.00 10.00 10.0% 110.00 North 85.00 9.00 10.6% 94.00 South 85.00 9.00 10.6% 94.00 Northwest 85.00 9.00 10.6% 94.00 West 100.00 10.00 10.0% 110.00 Hentz-Mohr 130.00 13.00 10.0% 143.00 With Kitchen 160.00 16.00 10.0% 176.00 Clayton 130.00 13.00 10.0% 143.00 Catesby 110.00 11.00 10.0% 121.00 Gattinger 110.00 11.00 10.0% 121.00 Michaux 130.00 13.00 10.0% 143.00 With Kitchen 160.00 16.00 10.0% 176.00 Washington 115.00 12.00 10.4% 127.00 Banister 115.00 12.00 10.4% 127.00 LeConte 115.00 12.00 10.4% 127.00 Hariot 115.00 12.00 10.4% 127.00 Schoew 115.00 12.00 10.4% 127.00 Mapnis 115.00 12.00 10.4% 127.00 Holbrook 115.00 12.00 10.4% 127.00 Mitchell 115.00 12.00 10.4% 127.00 Burns 115.00 12.00 10.4% 127.00 Rafinesque 100.00 10.00 10.0% 110.00 Other Rental Plans Rafinesque - September - May: $17/night for 1 or 2 persons or $99/week; $5/night for each additional person. September-November and March-May: $325/month December - February: $363/month</field>
      <field name="fulltext">INCREASE IN STUDENT HOUSING RATES FOR 1987-1988 The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that rental increases for student housing facilities be and they are hereby approved as shown below, effective beginning with the Session 1987-1988: Facility Actual 1986-87 Per Student Per Session Amt of Incr Percent Incr Proposed 1987-88 Per Student Per Session DORMITORIES Alderman/Observatory Houses Double Room $1190 $ 50 4.20% $1,240 Monroe Hill Double Room $1385 $ 55 3.97% $1,440 Triple Room N/A N/A N/A $1,150 McCormick Road Double Room $1125 $ 45 4.00% $1,170 Small Double Room $ 985 $ 40 4.06% $1,025 Lawn Small Single $1290 $ 50 3.88% $1,340 Regular Single $1355 $ 55 4.06% $1,410 Small Single (no fireplace) $1250 $ 50 4.00% $1,300 Range Regular Single $1315 $ 55 4.18% $1,370 Crackerbox Double Room $1245 $ 55 4.42% $1,300 Mary Munford/Roberta Gwathmey Double Room $1190 $ 50 4.20% $1,240 Single Room $1315 $ 55 4.18% $1,370 Sprigg (Lewis/Hoxton) Double Room $1350 $ 55 4.07% $1,405 Single Room $1470 $ 60 4.08% $1,530 Single Room (Private Bath) $1525 $ 60 3.93% $1,585 Stadium Road (Gooch/Dillard) Double Room $1355 $ 55 4.06% $1,410 Single Room $1470 $ 60 4.08% $1,530 Facility Actual 1986-87 Per Student Per Session Amt of Incr Percent Incr Proposed 1987-88 Per Student Per Session APARTMENTS - SINGLE STUDENT Copeley Hill Phase III &amp; IV, Nurses, Lambeth Field Two Bedroom $1410 $ 55 3.90% $1,465 Three Bedroom $1345 $ 55 4.09% $1,400 Faulkner (Hench/Mitchell/Younger) Two Bedroom $1455 $ 60 4.12% $1,515 One Bedroom $1525 $ 65 4.26% $1,590 Actual 1986-87 Per Student Per Month Amt of Incr Percent Incr Proposed 1987-88 Per Student Per Month APARTMENTS - FAMILY Copeley Hill Phases I &amp; II One Bedroom $ 290/Mo. $ 12 4.14% $ 302 Two Bedroom $ 320/Mo. $ 13 4.06% $ 333 Three Bedroom $ 350/Mo. $ 14 4.00% $ 364 University Gardens One Bedroom $ 280/Mo. $ 11 3.93% $ 291 Two Bedroom $ 310/Mo. $ 12 3.87% $ 322 These rates include all utility costs, TV cable in apartments and post office box rental where applicable.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RENTAL RATES FOR HOUSING FACILITIES FOR THE SUMMER 1987 The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following rental rates for housing facilities for Summer, 1987, be and they are hereby approved: FACILITY Actual Summer 1986 Amt of Incr Percent Incr Proposed Rate Summer 1987 SUMMER SESSION RATES (Including PHD Institute) Alderman-Observatory Per student, per week, double occup $ 30.00 $ 1.00 3.33% $ 31.00 Per student, per week, single occup $ 38.00 $ 2.00 5.26% $ 40.00 Nurses Apartment Complex Per student, per week, double occup $ 38.00 $ 2.00 5.26% $ 40.00 Per student, per week, single occup $ 48.00 $ 2.00 4.17% $ 50.00 Munford/Gwathmey Per student, per week, double occup $ 30.00 $ 1.00 3.33% $ 31.00 Per student, per week, single occup $ 38.00 $ 2.00 5.26% $ 40.00 Sprigg Lane Per student, per week, double occup $ 34.00 $ 1.00 2.94% $ 35.00 Per student, per week, single occup $ 42.00 $ 2.00 4.76% $ 44.00 Stadium Road Per student, per week, double occup N/A N/A N/A $ 35.00 Per student, per week, single occup N/A N/A N/A $ 44.00 SUMMER CONFERENCE RATES (A) FULL SERVICE - All linens provided; full, daily maid service. Lambeth Field Per person, per night, double occup $ 13.50 $ 0 0% $ 13.50 Per person, per night, single occup $ 19.00 $ 0 0% $ 19.00 Monroe Hill Houses Per person, per night, double occup $ 12.00 $ 0 0% $ 12.00 Per person, per night, single occup $ 17.00 $ 0 0% $ 17.00 Alderman/Observatory Houses Per person, per night, double occup $ 9.50 $ 0 0% $ 9.50 Per person, per night, single occup $ 13.00 $ 0 0% $ 13.00 McCormick Road Houses Per person, per night, double occup $ 8.50 $ 0 0% $ 8.50 Per person, per night, single occup $ 12.00 $ 0 0% $ 12.00 Copeley Hill, Phase III &amp; IV Per person, per night, double occup $ 15.00 $ 0 0% $ 15.00 Per person, per night, single occup $ 22.00 $ 0 0% $ 22.00 FACILITY Actual Summer 1986 Amt of Incr Percent Incr Proposed Rate Summer 1987 (A) FULL SERVICE - (cont) Faulkner Per person, per night, double occup $ 14.50 $ 0 0% $ 14.50 Per person, per night, single occup $ 21.00 $ 0 0% $ 21.00 Stadium Road (Gooch/Dillard) Per person, per night, double occup $ 12.00 $ 0 0% $ 12.00 Per person, per night, single occup $ 17.00 $ 0.50 2.94% $ 17.50 (B) PARTIAL SERVICE - Most linens provided; common areas serviced moderately. Lambeth Field Per person, per night, double occup $ 11.00 $ 0 0% $ 11.00 Per person, per night, single occup $ 16.00 $ 0 0% $ 16.00 Family rates, per week 2 bdrm apt $165.00 $ 5.00 3.03% $170.00 Family rates, per week 3 bdrm apt $220.00 $ 5.00 2.27% $225.00 Monroe Hill Houses Per person, per night, double occup $ 10.00 $ 0 0% $ 10.00 Per person, per night, single occup $ 14.00 $ 0 0% $ 14.00 Alderman/Observatory Houses Per person, per night, double occup $ 8.50 $ 0 0% $ 8.50 Per person, per night, single occup $ 10.00 $ 0 0% $ 10.00 McCormick Road Houses Per person, per night, double occup $ 7.50 $ 0 0% $ 7.50 Per person, per night, single occup $ 8.00 $ 0 0% $ 8.00 Stadium Road (Gooch/Dillard) Per person, per night, double occup $ 10.00 $ 0 0% $ 10.00 Per person, per night, single occup $ 12.00 $ 0 0% $ 12.00 (C) NO LINEN SERVICE Lambeth Field Per person, per night, double occup $ 9.00 $ 0 0% $ 9.00 Monroe Hill Houses Per person, per night, double occup $ 9.00 $ 0 0% $ 9.00 Alderman/Observatory Houses Per person, per night, double occup $ 7.50 $ 0 0% $ 7.50 McCormick Road Houses Per person, per night, double occup $ 6.50 $ 0 0% $ 6.50 FACILITY Actual Summer 1986 Amt of Incr Percent Incr Proposed Rate Summer 1987 OTHER CONTRACTED per person group rates approved on a basis consistent with University contracting policies and procedures. GRADUATE SUITES Graduate Advisor Suites in Alderman and McCormick Road Houses Per suite, per week $ 74.00 $ 3.00 4.05% $ 77.00 GUEST FACILITIES McCormick Road Houses Per person, per first night $ 11.10 $ 0.40 3.60% $ 11.50 Per person, for night thereafter $ 9.10 $ 0.40 4.40% $ 9.50</field>
      <field name="fulltext">AUTHORIZATION TO EFFECT TRANSFER OF STOCK OF THE HISTORIC RENOVATION CORPORATION TO THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA REAL ESTATE FOUNDATION The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED, that the Vice President for Business and Finance be and he is hereby authorized to effect the transfer effective as of January 1, 1987 to the University of Virginia Real Estate Foundation (the "Foundation") of all of the issued and outstanding capital stock of the Historic Renovation Corporation, a Virginia stock corporation, in consideration for the obligation of the Foundation in the amount of $300,000. BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED that the obligation of the Foundation to the University shall be evidenced by a Demand Note in substantially the form attached hereto, (Attachment A), provided that the Vice President for Business and Finance is hereby authorized to revise, amend, alter or supplement the terms of such Demand Note in his discretion. RESOLVED, that the Vice President for Business and Finance is authorized to take such further actions in the name and on behalf of the University, including, without limitation, the preparation, execution, acknowledgement and delivery of such additional agreements, documents and certificates made in connection with the transfer of Historic Renovation Corporation stock to the Foundation, as he may deem necessary or appropriate to carry out the intent and purpose of the foregoing resolutions.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF THE FIRM OF HELLMUTH, OBATA AND KASSABAUM OF KANSAS CITY, MISSOURI, FOR THE PERFORMANCE OF A MASTER PLAN STUDY FOR UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA ATHLETIC DEPARTMENT FACILITIES The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the firm of Hellmuth, Obata and Kassabaum of Kansas City, Missouri, be approved for the performance of a Master Plan Study for University of Virginia Athletic Department Facilities. At the option of the University administration, the firm may later be continued for the preparation of one or more pre-planning studies pertaining to individual new construction projects which may develop from this study, and for full architectural and engineering services for one or more of these projects upon approval by State government.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF THE FIRM OF MARCELLUS, WRIGHT, COX AND SMITH OF RICHMOND, VIRGINIA, FOR THE PERFORMANCE OF A PRE-PLANNING STUDY FOR THE MILLER CENTER ADDITION The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the firm of Marcellus, Wright, Cox and Smith of Richmond, Virginia, be approved for the performance of a pre-planning study for the Miller Center Addition. At the option of the University administration, the firm may later be continued for full architectural design services upon approval of the project by State government.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF 1987 INTERNAL AUDIT SCHEDULE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the 1987 Internal Audit Schedule as presented by the Director of Audits be and it is hereby approved as recommended by the Audit Committee.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF SUMMARY OF AUDIT REPORTS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the Summary of Audit Reports for the period September 13, 1986, through January 16, 1987, as presented by the Director of Audits, be and it is hereby approved as recommended by the Audit Committee.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF UNIVERSITY AND HOSPITAL FINANCIAL REPORTS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the University of Virginia 1985-1986 consolidated Financial Report and the University of Virginia Hospitals Financial Report be and they are hereby approved as recommended by the Audit Committee.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF DIRECTIVE TO REQUEST REVIEW OF ARCHITECTURAL OR STRUCTURAL CHANGES TO BUILDINGS IN THE HISTORIC DISTRICT BY THE JEFFERSONIAN RESTORATION ADVISORY BOARD The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the Board of Visitors directs the Buildings and Grounds Committee to request review by the Design Committee of the Jeffersonian Restoration Advisory Board before approving architectural renovation or structural changes to buildings in the historic district. This is not to include routine maintenance. Major changes in landscaping within the historic district should also have review by this same Design Committee.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RECOMMENDATION OF THE JANUARY - JUNE 1987 SALARY FOR ACTING CHANCELLOR JERRY D. CARDWELL The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the Rector of the University of Virginia be and he is hereby authorized to submit the following January - June 1987 salary recommendation for the Acting Chancellor of Clinch Valley College to the Governor for approval: Proposed for Acting Chancellor Jerry D. Cardwell, in addition to State salary, a local supplement of $4,212 for the period January - June 1987.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">REPORT BY THE RECTOR ON THE ACTION OF THE EXECUTIVE COMMITTEE REGARDING THE NOMINATION OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA HISTORIC DISTRICT FOR THE WORLD HERITAGE LIST The Rector reported that the Executive Committee, acting for the Board of Visitors as provided for under Section 3.1 of The Manual adopted the following resolution on November 15, 1986: RESOLVED by the Executive Committee of the Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia that the Board of Visitors concurs in the nomination of the University of Virginia Historic District for the World Heritage List, and authorizes the President to inform the National Park Service of its concurrence.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">GIFTS, GRANTS AND CONTRACTS The President reported that for the period July 1, 1986 to December 31, 1986, private gifts in the amount of $7,690,300 had been received. For the same period, restricted grants and contracts amounted to $30,703,697.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">REPORT ON LEGISLATIVE MATTERS The President reported that hearings are being held this week, and by the end of the week, all essential items will be in process to go before the General Assembly.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">REPORT ON CONSTRUCTION The President reported that the replacement hospital is, of course, the largest construction project now in progress. It is within budget and right on schedule. The other projects described in the quarterly report are going along well.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CLINCH VALLEY COLLEGE MATTERS ELECTION The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following person be and he is hereby elected to the faculty: Mr. David B. Jodrey, Jr. as Assistant Professor of Psychology, Clinch Valley College, for one semester, effective January 16, 1987.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">LEAVES OF ABSENCE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following faculty members be and they are hereby granted leave of absence: Mr. David M. Donathan, Associate Professor of Music, Clinch Valley College, for the period January 15, 1987 through May 31, 1987, with partial pay, for personal reasons. Mr. W. Edmund Moomaw, Professor of Political Science, Clinch Valley College, for the period January 5, 1987 through June 30, 1988, without pay, to do research at the University of Virginia.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RETIREMENT The following retirement was announced: Mr. Harold L. Gilbert, Assistant Professor of Psychology, Clinch Valley College, effective May 31, 1986. Mr. Gilbert has been a member of the faculty since September 1, 1966.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RESIGNATIONS The following resignations were announced: Ms. Bonnie P. Elosser, Assistant Professor of Speech, Clinch Valley College, effective October 10, 1986, for personal reasons. Ms. Deborah H. Frazier, Lecturer, General Faculty, Clinch Valley College, effective September 2, 1986, for personal reasons. Mr. W. Edmund Moomaw, Chancellor, Clinch Valley College, effective January 5, 1987, to do research at the University of Virginia.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPOINTMENTS The following appointments were announced: Mr. Jerry D. Cardwell as Acting Chancellor, Clinch Valley College, for the period January 5, 1987 through June 30, 1987 Mr. Mark A. Foster as Chairman, Department of Social and Behavioral Sciences, Clinch Valley College, for one semester, effective January 16, 1987. On motion, the meeting adjourned at 3:02 p.m. Respectfully submitted, Raymond C. Bice, Jr. Secretary RCB:jb</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ATTACHMENT A DEMAND NOTE $ 300,000.00 Charlottesville, Virginia _______________, 1987 FOR VALUE RECEIVED, the undersigned promises to pay to the order of THE RECTOR AND VISITORS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA, upon demand made after date, the sum of three hundred thousand DOLLARS ($ 300,000) WITH NO INTEREST THEREON, c/o Mr. Ray C. Hunt, Jr., Vice President for Business and Finance, Madison Hall, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Virginia, 22903. This note may be prepaid by the maker hereof in whole or in part at any time and from time to time without penalty. WITNESS the following signature: UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA REAL ESTATE FOUNDATION By: Title:</field>
   </doc>
</add>