<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">University of Virginia, Board of Visitors</field>
      <field name="author_facet">University of Virginia, Board of Visitors</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">university of virginia board of visitors</field>
      <field name="author_text">University of Virginia, Board of Visitors</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1860's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/2006_06/uvaGenText/tei/bov_18670904.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240343</field>
      <field name="date_text">September 4, 1867</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Board of Visitors Minutes, 1817-2002</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Board of Visitors Minutes, 1817-2002</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:270563</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Board of Visitors minutes. September 4, 1867</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Minutes</field>
      <field name="subject_text">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Minutes</field>
      <field name="title_display">Board of Visitors minutes.  September 4, 1867</field>
      <field name="title_facet">board of visitors minutes</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">board of visitors minutes</field>
      <field name="title_text">Board of Visitors minutes.  September 4, 1867</field>
      <field name="year_display">September 4, 1867</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1867-09-04</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1867</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:270563&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;public&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:270563&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;serial volume&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;University of Virginia, Board of Visitors&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;university of virginia, board of visitors&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Board of Visitors minutes. September 4, 1867&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;board of visitors minutes&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;September 4, 1867&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1867-09-04&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="corpname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia, Board of Visitors&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Board of Visitors minutes&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;September 4, 1867&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="edition"&gt;Public minutes&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa call number"&gt;Accession# RG-1/1/&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;a2846310&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;6 pages&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="AAT"&gt;Minutes&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;The official minutes contain salary information. Access to minutes containing salary information will be granted only under the procedures of the Virginia Freedom of Information Act (Code of Virginia-2.1-340 ff.) or if permission is granted by the Secretary of the Board. Researchers interested in obtaining access to these records should direct a request in writing to the Office of the Legal Adviser, Madison Hall, University of Virginia. These public minutes have had salary information deleted and bear no restrictions.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Board of Visitors' minutes, Accession # RG-1/1/, Special Collections Dept., University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Minutes of meetings of the university's governing body which is the legal owner and operator of the institution. Recorded in the minutes are appointments and other personnel decisions concerning faculty, decisions about construction of facilities, gifts to the university, and all other board actions, decisions and resolutions.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Board of Visitors minutes&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;1867-09-04&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville, Virginia&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia Library&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;2006&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©2006 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Publicly accessible&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 15 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-BoardOfVisitorsMinutes"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Adjourned Meeting September 4th 1867 Present B. Johnson Barbour, Rector, Samuel Watts, Thomas J. Pretlow, Marmaduke Johnson, Thomas L. Preston, John R. Woods, W. E. M. Word, Samuel H. Lewis and Rob. W. Hughes. The Board having been called to order by the Rector, it was ordered that the Secretary proceed to read the testimonials of the applicants for the Chair of Medicine; before completing the reading of the testimonials. On motion The Board adjourned to meet again tomorrow morning at 9 Oclock. Wm. Wertenbaker Secretary B. Johnson Barbour Rector of Univ. of Virg September 5th 1867 The Board met pursuant to adjournment. Present the same members as on yesterday. The Rector laid before the Board a letter from Capt. M. F. Maury in answer to a communication sent to him by the Rector pursuant to resolutions passed September 10th 1866 and June 29th 1867. Whereupon Resolved that Capt Maury's letter be referred to a committee consisting of Messrs. Johnson, Hughes &amp; Word On motion, it was resolved that the Rector be added to the Committee. On motion Resolved, unanimously that Dr. James F. Harrison be appointed Professor of Medicine in place of Dr. Henry Howard whose resignation takes effect October 1st. Resolved, unanimously, that J. William Mallet be appointed Professor of Technology &amp; Agricultural Science, and that his Salary commence when he enters upon the discharge of his duties. Resolved that the Pavilion recently occupied by Professor Howard together with the garden and grounds attached thereto, be assigned to Professor Peters. Resolved That in view of the fact that the use of the Laboratory will be essential to Prof. Mallet, the Board suggests a conference between himself and the Professor of Chemistry that such arrangements may be made as will avoid all interference, and make its joint occupancy convenient and agreeable to both parties. Resolved that the Rector be requested to address a letter to the proper authorities of the Medical University of Louisana, requesting them to release Prof. J. W. Mallet from his obligation to deliver a course of Lectures at that institution during the ensuing winter, in order that he may enter at once upon his duties as Professor of Technology &amp; Agricultural Science. The Rector and Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia desiring at all times and in every appropriate manner to fulfil the designs, and honor the memory of its illustrious Founder, do hereby make a standing appropriation of not exceeding $75 for the periodical purchase of a Golden Medal to be entitled the Jefferson Medal of the University of Virginia-and to be awarded in future to the most distinguished student of those who in each session shall take the Degree of Master of Arts. This Medal shall only be awarded under the rigid application of the following tests and requisitions. 1. When a number of students take the Degree of A.M. it shall be the duty of the Faculty in full session after a thorough discussion of the merits of all the competitors to decide which is entitled (if any) to this, the highest honor of the University- but it is further provided that if there be only one student taking the Degree of A.M. in any session it shall still be competent for the Faculty to award this medal if deserved. 2. No one shall receive this medal unless to high Scientific and Literary attainments and systematic habits of study he adds the essential qualifications of good general deportment and high moral character- the true intent and purpose of the Board being to make this prize not only the reward of superior mental culture, but an incentive to moral improvement and elevation- and the Faculty is hereby again cautioned and enjoined not to award this medal (no matter how large the number of applicants) unless that high standard of education and character (of which it is meant to be the token and pledge to society) has been attained. 3. The Device of this medal shall be as follows- On the obverse, the inscription "Jefferson Medal of the University of Virginia awarded to (name of student) session of ——" On the Reverse shall be inscribed the words "Detur Digniori" both faces marked with Laurel wreaths. 4. The Chairman of the Faculty is charged with the duty of contracting for this medal whenever required- or if he finds it more advisable to have Dies made for it- so that no hand work except the engraving of the date and name will be necessary- The case of the Dies to be separate. Resolved That the Professor of Modern Languages be and he is hereby authorized at his descretion to appoint an assistant in his department, whose duties and compensation shall be defined and settled by him- provided however that in no event shall the University be subject to any charge for the services rendered by the Assistant. Resolved that hereafter the Salary of the Commissioner of Accounts be fixed at $200 per annum. General S. H. Lewis moved that the order made at the annual meeting in June giving the use of the chapel to the Washington Society be rescinded- The question on this motion was decided in the negative. Resolved that the Proctor be authorized to appropriate $150 per annum for the purpose of employing a clerk to assist him in the duties of his office at the commencement &amp; also at the close of the session. The Rector laid before the Board a communication from the Superintendent of Grounds &amp; Buildings made in pursuance of a resolution passed June 28th 1867 instructing him to make out estimates for constructing a Dam in the Ravine of the Observatory Mountain, at the highest advisable level, and for extending the present main to said Dam- On motion Resolved that said communication be referred to the Executive Committee. The Rector laid before the Board a report from the Faculty on the subject of Licentiates- On motion Resolved that for want of time to consider it, said report be laid on the table. On motion Resolved that the Janitor's salary be raised to four hundred dollars per annum. Resolved that the communication of Dr. James Bolton be referred to the members of the Medical department of the Faculty and that they be requested to communicate to the Board of Visitors thereon at their next meeting. Ordered That the execution by the Rector under date of July 1st 1867, of five notes to Addison Maupin, for two thousand dollars each, bearing lawful interest from the fisrt day of July 1867, interest payable semi- annually, being for the purchase-money of the premises known as "Carr's Hill", and the execution of a deed of trust on said premises to secure the said purchase-money, which deed is signed by the Rector, and sealed with the corporate seal of the Rector &amp; Visitors of the University of Virginia, be and is hereby recognized, ratified &amp; adopted as done by the authority, and conformably to the order of this Board, and that the said notes and deed of trust are intended to have and shall have the same validity force &amp; effect as if the same had been made and executed in the prescence, and by the immediate personal direction of the Board. The Board then adjourned. Wm. Wertenbaker, Secretary B. Johnson Barbour. Rector of Univ. of Virg.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Adjourned Meeting September 4th 1867 Present B. Johnson Barbour, Rector, Samuel Watts, Thomas J. Pretlow, Marmaduke Johnson, Thomas L. Preston, John R. Woods, W. E. M. Word, Samuel H. Lewis and Rob. W. Hughes. The Board having been called to order by the Rector, it was ordered that the Secretary proceed to read the testimonials of the applicants for the Chair of Medicine; before completing the reading of the testimonials. On motion The Board adjourned to meet again tomorrow morning at 9 Oclock. Wm. Wertenbaker Secretary B. Johnson Barbour Rector of Univ. of Virg</field>
      <field name="fulltext">September 5th 1867 The Board met pursuant to adjournment. Present the same members as on yesterday. The Rector laid before the Board a letter from Capt. M. F. Maury in answer to a communication sent to him by the Rector pursuant to resolutions passed September 10th 1866 and June 29th 1867. Whereupon Resolved that Capt Maury's letter be referred to a committee consisting of Messrs. Johnson, Hughes &amp; Word On motion, it was resolved that the Rector be added to the Committee. On motion Resolved, unanimously that Dr. James F. Harrison be appointed Professor of Medicine in place of Dr. Henry Howard whose resignation takes effect October 1st. Resolved, unanimously, that J. William Mallet be appointed Professor of Technology &amp; Agricultural Science, and that his Salary commence when he enters upon the discharge of his duties. Resolved that the Pavilion recently occupied by Professor Howard together with the garden and grounds attached thereto, be assigned to Professor Peters. Resolved That in view of the fact that the use of the Laboratory will be essential to Prof. Mallet, the Board suggests a conference between himself and the Professor of Chemistry that such arrangements may be made as will avoid all interference, and make its joint occupancy convenient and agreeable to both parties. Resolved that the Rector be requested to address a letter to the proper authorities of the Medical University of Louisana, requesting them to release Prof. J. W. Mallet from his obligation to deliver a course of Lectures at that institution during the ensuing winter, in order that he may enter at once upon his duties as Professor of Technology &amp; Agricultural Science. The Rector and Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia desiring at all times and in every appropriate manner to fulfil the designs, and honor the memory of its illustrious Founder, do hereby make a standing appropriation of not exceeding $75 for the periodical purchase of a Golden Medal to be entitled the Jefferson Medal of the University of Virginia-and to be awarded in future to the most distinguished student of those who in each session shall take the Degree of Master of Arts. This Medal shall only be awarded under the rigid application of the following tests and requisitions. 1. When a number of students take the Degree of A.M. it shall be the duty of the Faculty in full session after a thorough discussion of the merits of all the competitors to decide which is entitled (if any) to this, the highest honor of the University- but it is further provided that if there be only one student taking the Degree of A.M. in any session it shall still be competent for the Faculty to award this medal if deserved. 2. No one shall receive this medal unless to high Scientific and Literary attainments and systematic habits of study he adds the essential qualifications of good general deportment and high moral character- the true intent and purpose of the Board being to make this prize not only the reward of superior mental culture, but an incentive to moral improvement and elevation- and the Faculty is hereby again cautioned and enjoined not to award this medal (no matter how large the number of applicants) unless that high standard of education and character (of which it is meant to be the token and pledge to society) has been attained. 3. The Device of this medal shall be as follows- On the obverse, the inscription "Jefferson Medal of the University of Virginia awarded to (name of student) session of ——" On the Reverse shall be inscribed the words "Detur Digniori" both faces marked with Laurel wreaths. 4. The Chairman of the Faculty is charged with the duty of contracting for this medal whenever required- or if he finds it more advisable to have Dies made for it- so that no hand work except the engraving of the date and name will be necessary- The case of the Dies to be separate. Resolved That the Professor of Modern Languages be and he is hereby authorized at his descretion to appoint an assistant in his department, whose duties and compensation shall be defined and settled by him- provided however that in no event shall the University be subject to any charge for the services rendered by the Assistant. Resolved that hereafter the Salary of the Commissioner of Accounts be fixed at $200 per annum. General S. H. Lewis moved that the order made at the annual meeting in June giving the use of the chapel to the Washington Society be rescinded- The question on this motion was decided in the negative. Resolved that the Proctor be authorized to appropriate $150 per annum for the purpose of employing a clerk to assist him in the duties of his office at the commencement &amp; also at the close of the session. The Rector laid before the Board a communication from the Superintendent of Grounds &amp; Buildings made in pursuance of a resolution passed June 28th 1867 instructing him to make out estimates for constructing a Dam in the Ravine of the Observatory Mountain, at the highest advisable level, and for extending the present main to said Dam- On motion Resolved that said communication be referred to the Executive Committee. The Rector laid before the Board a report from the Faculty on the subject of Licentiates- On motion Resolved that for want of time to consider it, said report be laid on the table. On motion Resolved that the Janitor's salary be raised to four hundred dollars per annum. Resolved that the communication of Dr. James Bolton be referred to the members of the Medical department of the Faculty and that they be requested to communicate to the Board of Visitors thereon at their next meeting. Ordered That the execution by the Rector under date of July 1st 1867, of five notes to Addison Maupin, for two thousand dollars each, bearing lawful interest from the fisrt day of July 1867, interest payable semi- annually, being for the purchase-money of the premises known as "Carr's Hill", and the execution of a deed of trust on said premises to secure the said purchase-money, which deed is signed by the Rector, and sealed with the corporate seal of the Rector &amp; Visitors of the University of Virginia, be and is hereby recognized, ratified &amp; adopted as done by the authority, and conformably to the order of this Board, and that the said notes and deed of trust are intended to have and shall have the same validity force &amp; effect as if the same had been made and executed in the prescence, and by the immediate personal direction of the Board. The Board then adjourned. Wm. Wertenbaker, Secretary B. Johnson Barbour. Rector of Univ. of Virg.</field>
   </doc>
</add>