<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">University of Virginia, Board of Visitors</field>
      <field name="author_facet">University of Virginia, Board of Visitors</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">university of virginia board of visitors</field>
      <field name="author_text">University of Virginia, Board of Visitors</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1990's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/2006_01/uvaGenText/tei/bov_1993-02-06.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240342</field>
      <field name="date_text">February 6, 1993</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Board of Visitors Minutes, 1817-2002</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Board of Visitors Minutes, 1817-2002</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:183763</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Board of Visitors minutes. February 6, 1993</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Minutes</field>
      <field name="subject_text">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Minutes</field>
      <field name="title_display">Board of Visitors minutes.  February 6, 1993</field>
      <field name="title_facet">board of visitors minutes</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">board of visitors minutes</field>
      <field name="title_text">Board of Visitors minutes.  February 6, 1993</field>
      <field name="year_display">February 6, 1993</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1993-02-06</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1993</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:183763&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;public&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:183763&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;serial volume&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;University of Virginia, Board of Visitors&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;university of virginia, board of visitors&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Board of Visitors minutes. February 6, 1993&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;board of visitors minutes&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;February 6, 1993&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1993-02-06&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="corpname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia, Board of Visitors&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Board of Visitors minutes&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;February 6, 1993&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="edition"&gt;Public minutes&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa call number"&gt;Accession# RG-1/1/&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;a2846310&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;1 v.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="AAT"&gt;Minutes&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;The official minutes contain salary information. Access to minutes containing salary information will be granted only under the procedures of the Virginia Freedom of Information Act (Code of Virginia-2.1-340 ff.) or if permission is granted by the Secretary of the Board. Researchers interested in obtaining access to these records should direct a request in writing to the Office of the Legal Adviser, Madison Hall, University of Virginia. These public minutes have had salary information deleted and bear no restrictions.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Board of Visitors' minutes, Accession # RG-1/1/, Special Collections Dept., University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Minutes of meetings of the university's governing body which is the legal owner and operator of the institution. Recorded in the minutes are appointments and other personnel decisions concerning faculty, decisions about construction of facilities, gifts to the university, and all other board actions, decisions and resolutions.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Board of Visitors minutes&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;1993-02-06&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville, Virginia&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia Library&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;2005&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©2005 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Publicly accessible&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 203 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-BoardOfVisitorsMinutes"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE RECTOR AND VISITORS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA February 6, 1993 The Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia met at 10:00 a.m., in Open Session, on Friday, February 5, 1993, in the East Oval Room of the Rotunda with the following persons present: Hovey S. Dabney, Rector, J. Scott Ballenger, W. L. Lyons Brown, Jr., Robert G. Butcher, Jr., Mortimer M. Caplin, N. Thomas Connally, Warner N. Dalhouse, Daniel A. Hoffler, J. Thomas Hulvey, Evans B. Jessee, Patricia M. Kluge, Arnold H. Leon, Leigh B. Middleditch, Jr., Mrs. Elizabeth D. Morie, Freddie W. Nicholas, Sr., S. Buford Scott and Albert H. Small. Messrs. John T. Casteen, III, James J. Mingle, Leonard W. Sandridge, Jr., Thomas H. Jackson, Don E. Detmer, Ernest H. Ern, Robert D. Sweeney, Alexander G. Gilliam, Jr., and Jeanne F. Bailes were also present. The Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia met at 1:30 p.m., in Open Session, on Saturday, February 6, 1993, in the East Oval Room of the Rotunda with the following persons present: Rector Hovey S. Dabney, J. Scott Ballenger, W. L. Lyons Brown, Jr., Robert G. Butcher, Jr., Mortimer M. Caplin, N. Thomas Connally, Warner N. Dalhouse, Daniel A. Hoffler, J. Thomas Hulvey, Evans B. Jessee, Patricia M. Kluge, Arnold H. Leon, Leigh B. Middleditch, Jr., Mrs. Elizabeth D. Morie, Freddie W. Nicholas, Sr., S. Buford Scott and Albert H. Small. Messrs. John T. Casteen, III, James J. Mingle, Leonard W. Sandridge, Jr., Thomas H. Jackson, Don E. Detmer, Robert D. Sweeney, Ernest H. Ern, Jr., and Jeanne F. Bailes were also present. The Minutes of the meeting of October 9, 1992, previously distributed, were approved as corrected.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">MOTIONS FOR EXECUTIVE SESSION The following motions were adopted unanimously by the vote of all Visitors present: (a) That the Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia go into Executive Session for the purpose of consulting with the General Counsel concerning certain pending and potential litigation involving the University, as well as specific legal matters requiring the advice of counsel, as provided for in Section 2.1-344 (A) (7) of The Code of Virginia. (b) That the Audit Committee of the Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia go into Executive Session for the purpose of discussing and considering reports and recommendations of the Internal Auditor related to the recently completed fiscal audits and performance evaluations of certain University departments and programs, including the Clinch Valley College, Information Technology and Communication/Administrative Computing Services - Data Control, Department of Parking and Transportation Services (Follow-up), Medicare Administrative Costs, Nephrology, Ambulatory Care Services and the Kluge Children's Rehabilitation Center (Follow-up) as provided for in Section 2.1-344 (A)(1) of The Code of Virginia. (c) That the Audit Committee of the Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia go into Executive Session for the purpose of discussing and considering a Report and Recommendations of the Department of the State Internal Auditor related to the recently completed Quality Assurance Review of the University of Virginia Audit Department as provided for in Section 2.1-344 (A)(1) of The Code of Virginia. (d) That the Educational Policy Committee of the Board of Visitors go into Executive Session for the purpose of discussing personnel matters pertaining to the appointment, assignment, reappointment, promotion, performance, compensation, separation and resignation of specific faculty members of the University of Virginia, as provided for in Section 2.1-344 (A) (1) of The Code of Virginia.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">STATEMENT BY THE PRESIDENT The President told the Board he wanted to bring two matters, not on the Agenda, to its attention. The first concerned an incident which, he said, took place at the Corner about ten days before in which two students were assaulted by a group of students from the University of Mississippi, in Charlottesville on a fraternity trip. Although it was clear that racial insults were part of the assault, it was not known for several days that the persons assaulted are students at the University. Several of the University of Mississippi students were arrested by the City Police and they are to appear in court later this month. The President said the incident was of grave concern to him and to the Administration. He has conferred with the Chancellor of the University of Mississippi which has taken action against the fraternity and will take action against the students once the civil charges have been resolved. There will be a rally this evening (Friday, February 5), on the Grounds, across the street from the restaurant where the incident occurred, the President said, and he and the Rector will attend. The second matter, the President reported, concerns a statue of Thomas Jefferson which the Board authorized the University to present to the College of William and Mary to commemorate the 300th anniversary of the founding of the College. The statue was done by the sculptor of the Jefferson statue which stands between the Law School and the Darden School, and is very similar to it. It has been so well placed at the College that one has the impression of coming up on a living person dressed in 18th century clothes. The statue was dedicated several months ago and the President showed the Board a copy of the William and Mary alumni magazine with pictures of it.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">STATEMENT OF APPRECIATION TO MR. DAVID A. HARRISON, III FOR AN UNPRECEDENTED GIFT TO THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA Rector Hovey S. Dabney read the following statement: I am pleased to announce that one of our most loyal alumni and friends, David A. Harrison, III, has made an unprecedented gift to the University of Virginia. As many of you know, Mr. Harrison is part of a four-generation family tradition at the University. A native of Petersburg, he graduated in 1939 from the College of Arts and Sciences and in 1941 from the School of Law. He has been a rare friend to us, indeed. Despite living and working in New York as an attorney and investment banker for the bulk of his career, his relationship with the University has been marked by continuity and loyalty. He reminisces fondly about his six years in Charlottesville, including long-term friends and the professors who influenced him - especially Dobie, Ribble, Glenn and Ritchie. His affection for the University of Virginia is matched by his interest in the history of early Virginia plantation life. In the 1960s, he and his wife, Mary Anderson Harrison, acquired the 1,400 acre Flowerdew Hundred Plantation along the south bank of the James River near Hopewell. In addition to being a working farm, it now houses a major archaeological research program on early 17th century America. A recent Smithsonian exhibit focused on Flowerdew's artifacts. From his Flowerdew office, Mr. Harrison still manages the farm and several businesses around Virginia, and lends us his counsel and talents whenever we call on him. He has served as a member of the Alumni Board of Managers and the Health Sciences Council, and will serve on the board of the new University of Virginia Foundation. Over the years, Mr. Harrison has generously supported the establishment of several chairs in the Schools of Law and Medicine. All of these chairs were donated to underscore one of his principal tenets - the importance of teaching. He has often said that "a university is no better than its professors. For the University to be at the top, the faculty has to be at the top." I am therefore pleased to announce that Mr. Harrison has made a gift remarkable in reach and spirit. It totals approximately $6.7 million, the bulk of the assets available from the liquidation of the Harrison Foundation. This gift will provide $4.5 million for the School of Law building campaign, more than $1.7 million for professorships in the School of Medicine, $400,000 for an endowed professorship in archaeology, and $100,000 for the Department of Athletics. Mr. Harrison's gift answers vital and immediate needs for the University. It helps position us to address challenges we will face in the new century by providing financial support that will attract renowned teachers and scholars to the University. Mr. Harrison's generosity marks a leadership gift for the University's upcoming capital campaign. This gift will set the standard by which all other generosity will be measured. We are deeply honored to announce this magnificent gift as further evidence of David Harrison's continued support.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">STATEMENT BY THE RECTOR Mr. Dabney reported that Mr. Butcher, Chair of the Finance Committee, will call a meeting of that Committee before the end of the spring semester in order that students will have an opportunity to have input regarding tuition. Mr. Dabney said that the other members of the Board will also be invited to the Finance Committee meeting. Following Committee meetings and a recess for an Executive Session of the Board of Visitors, the Open Session of the full Board resumed at 3:00 p.m., on Saturday, February 6, 1993.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Elections The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following persons be and they are hereby elected to the faculty: Dr. John F. Angle as Assistant Professor of Radiology, for three years, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. Richard S. Becker as Lecturer, General Faculty, for three years, effective December 1, 1992. Ms. Mary K. Bednar as Lecturer, General Medical Center Faculty, for the period November 1, 1992 through June 30, 1994. Mr. Julian M. Bivins, Jr. as Lecturer, General Faculty, for one year, effective August 16, 1992. Mr. H. Julian Bond as Lecturer in History, for the period January 16, 1993 through May 31, 1996. Dr. John Broderick-Cantwell as Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, for three years, effective October 1, 1992. Ms. June N. Campbell as Lecturer, General Faculty, for the period September 1, 1992 through June 30, 1995. Ms. Anne W. Chalam as Lecturer, General Medical Center Faculty, for the period November 1, 1992 through June 30, 1994. Mr. Harsha K. Chelliah as Assistant Professor of Mechanical Engineering, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. Patrick L. Chester as Lecturer, General Faculty, for the period August 17, 1992 through June 30, 1993. Ms. Reba M. Childress as Instructor in Nursing, General Nursing Faculty, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1992. Ms. Sandra R. Ciocci as Acting Assistant Professor, General Faculty, for the period January 16, 1993 through June 30, 1993. Mr. George M. Cohen as Visiting Assistant Professor of Law, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1992. Ms. Stacy L. Dahlstrom as Lecturer, General Medical Center Faculty, for one year, effective July 1, 1992. Dr. Mark O. Daugherty as Assistant Professor of Anesthesiology, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective November 1, 1992. Mr. James A. Doyle as Lecturer in Philosophy, for one semester, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. Clarence M. Dunlap, III as Lecturer, General Medical Center Faculty, for the period September 1, 1992 through June 30, 1993. Dr. Robert G. Dussault as Professor of Radiology, effective October 1, 1992. Mr. Samuel J. Dwyer, III as Professor of Radiology, effective October 1, 1992. Ms. Jane-Ashley Everett as Lecturer, General Faculty, for one year, effective December 1, 1992. Mr. Walter J. Farrell as Lecturer, General Medical Center Faculty, for the period September 1, 1992 through June 30, 1993. Mr. Gregory N. Fife as Instructor, General Faculty, for one year, effective October 1, 1992. Mr. John B. Gonnella as Lecturer, General Medical Center Faculty, for one year, effective October 19, 1992. Ms. Rosel F. Halle as Lecturer, General Faculty, for one year, effective September 8, 1992. Ms. Susan Hamburger as Lecturer, General Faculty, Alderman Library, for the period October 16, 1992 through September 30, 1993. Mr. John C. Harrison as Associate Professor of Law, for five academic years, effective September 1, 1993. Mr. Joseph L. Hoffmann as Visiting Professor of Law, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. W. Nathaniel Howell as Lecturer, General Faculty, for one year, effective January 1, 1993. Ms. Julia W.P. Hsu as Assistant Professor of Physics, for four academic years, effective January 16, 1993. Ms. Betty Jolly as Lecturer, General Medical Center Faculty, for the period August 1, 1992 through February 28, 1993. Mr. Robert R. Jones, Jr. as Assistant Professor of Physics, for four academic years, effective September 1, 1993. Dr. Sara A. Kaltreider as Associate Professor of Ophthalmology, for three years, effective November 1, 1992. Dr. Phoebe A. Kaplan as Professor of Radiology, effective October 1, 1992. Dr. Michael A. Kligman as Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, for three years, effective September 16, 1992. Ms. Anne C.M. Kromkowski as Lecturer, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective November 1, 1992. Mr. Mark Lee as Assistant Professor of Physics, for four academic years, effective January 16, 1993. Ms. Mary F. Marshall as Assistant Professor of Neurosurgery, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective September 1, 1992. Ms. Alice L. Mason as Lecturer, General Medical Center Faculty, for the period October 1, 1992 through June 30, 1994. Dr. Eugene D. McGahren, III as Assistant Professor of Surgery, for three years, effective August 16, 1992. Ms. Maureen F. McKone as Instructor in Nursing, General Nursing Faculty and Instructor in Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. Gregory Newman as Lecturer, General Medical Center Faculty, for the period October 1, 1992 through June 30, 1994. Ms. Donna A. Oliver as Lecturer, General Faculty, for three years, effective October 15, 1992. Ms. Carol Aline Otey as Assistant Professor of Anatomy and Cell Biology, for three years, effective January 1, 1993. Dr. Shashank C. Parekh as Instructor in Radiology, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective October 1, 1992. Mr. John H. Payne, III as Lecturer, General Faculty, for one year, effective January 1, 1993. Mr. Jeffrey Plank as Lecturer, General Faculty, for three years, effective January 1, 1993. Mr. Ronnie J. Price as Lecturer, General Faculty, for two years, effective September 1, 1992. Ms. Cornelia A. Ramsey as Lecturer, General Medical Center Faculty, for the period October 1, 1992 through June 30, 1994. Ms. Abigail Reed as Lecturer, General Faculty, for one year, effective September 15, 1992. Mr. David B. Reid as Instructor in Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation, for one year, effective September 1, 1992. Dr. Lawrence I. Rosenberg as Instructor in Surgery, General Medical Faculty, for the period August 1, 1992 through June 30, 1993. Ms. Marjorie L. Sidebottom as Lecturer, General Medical Center Faculty, for the period November 1, 1992 through June 30, 1994. Mr. John W. Smith as Lecturer, General Faculty, for one year, effective October 5, 1992. Ms. Mary D. Smith as Lecturer, General Faculty, for three years, effective October 1, 1992. Ms. Lisa L. Spooner as Instructor, General Faculty, for one year, effective August 1, 1992. Mr. Martin Straume as Research Associate Professor of Internal Medicine, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective October 6, 1992. Ms. Sally H. Thomas as Lecturer, General Faculty, for the period October 1, 1992 through June 30, 1995. Ms. Mary A. Thompson as Lecturer, General Medical Center Faculty, for the period August 1, 1992 through June 30, 1993. Dr. Kelly L. Vollmer as Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective August 1, 1992. Mr. Terrance R. Williams as Lecturer, General Faculty, for three years, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. Mark C. Wolff as Assistant Professor of Neurosurgery, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective November 1, 1992. Ms. Arlene F. Yuan as Instructor in Nursing, General Nursing Faculty, for one year, effective August 24, 1992. Ms. Anne E. Zintl as Lecturer, General Faculty, for one year, effective September 1, 1992. Dr. Pedro A. de Alarcon as Professor of Pediatrics, for five years, effective December 1, 1992.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Election of Part-Time Faculty Mr. Gary R. Allen as Lecturer in Civil Engineering, for one semester, effective September 1, 1992. Ms. Catherine D. Baritaud as Instructor in Humanities, for one semester, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. Suketu P. Bhavsar as Visiting Associate Professor of Theoretical Astronomy, for the period August 1, 1992 through June 30, 1993. Ms. Suzanne C. Bischoff as Lecturer in Government and Foreign Affairs, for one semester, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. William A. Booth as Lecturer in Medical Education, General Medical Faculty, for the period September 1, 1992 through February 28, 1993. Mr. Douglas B. Chambers as Instructor in History, for one semester, effective January 16, 1993. Ms. Helene Cixous as Lecturer in the Commonwealth Center for Literary and Cultural Change, for the period September 14, 1992 through September 26, 1992. Mr. Richard H. Clarida as Visiting Associate Professor of Economics, for one semester, effective January 16, 1993. Ms. Mary A. Coy as Lecturer in Drama, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. Marshall F. Coyle as Instructor in Mechanical Engineering, for the period September 1, 1992 through January 15, 1993. Ms. Amy D. Crews as Instructor in Economics, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. Dennis C. Donat as Lecturer in Education, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1992. Ms. Beth K. Dougherty as Instructor in Government and Foreign Affairs, for one semester, effective January 16, 1992. Ms. Rebecca B. Edwards as Instructor in History, for one semester, effective January 16, 1993. Mr. William G. Evans as Lecturer in Music, for one semester, effective January 16, 1993. Ms. Christine A. Flanagan as Lecturer in Environmental Sciences, for one year, effective November 1, 1992. Mr. Lawrence R. Fullerton as Lecturer in Law, for one semester, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. Russell J. Ganim as Lecturer in French, for one semester, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. Edmund Ghareeb as Visiting Associate Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs, for one semester, effective September 1, 1992. Ms. Julie J. Grossman as Instructor in Business Administration, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1992. Ms. Karen Guest as Instructor in History, for one semester, effective January 16, 1993. Mr. Jonathan C.R. Hall as Lecturer in Classics, for one semester, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. Mark D. Hall as Lecturer in Government and Foreign Affairs, for one semester, effective September 1, 1992. Dr. Daniel P. Harrington as Associate Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Roanoke Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1992. Mr. Jeffrey Hause as Lecturer in Philosophy, for one semester, effective January 16, 1992. Mr. Brian Healy as Lecturer in Architecture, for the period September 1, 1992 through October 16, 1992. Ms. A'Lelia R. Henry as Instructor in the Carter G. Woodson Institute, for one semester, effective September 1, 1992. Ms. Ivora D. Hinton as Instructor in Psychology, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. Eric Hooglund as Lecturer in Government and Foreign Affairs, for one semester, effective January 16, 1993. Ms. Edna J. Johnston as Instructor in History, for the period October 21, 1992 through November 5, 1992. Mr. Steven R. Koerner as Instructor in History, for one semester, effective January 16, 1993. Ms. Linda Krag as Lecturer, General Faculty, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. Russell M. Lafferty as Lecturer in Electrical Engineering, for one semester, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. Arthur Lessac as Lecturer in Drama, for the period October 12, 1992 through December 11, 1992. Mr. Michael E. Levinshtein as Visiting Professor of Electrical Engineering, for the period October 17, 1992 through December 17, 1992. Mr. Murray H. Loew as Visiting Professor of Radiology, for the period September 1, 1992 through December 31, 1992. Mr. Robert D. Luskin as Lecturer in Law, for one semester, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. Peter B. MacKeith as Lecturer in Architecture, for one semester, effective January 16, 1993. Ms. Julia A. McDonough as Instructor in the Carter G. Woodson Institute, for one semester, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. Michael S. McKenna as Instructor in Philosophy, for one semester, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. Robert J. Myers as Lecturer in Government and Foreign Affairs, for one semester, effective September 1, 1992. Ms. Cynthia R. O'Donoghue as Lecturer in Education, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1992. Ms. Carmen M. Pancerella as Instructor in Computer Science, for one semester, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. Rosser H. Payne, Jr. as Lecturer in Planning, for one semester, effective January 16, 1993. Ms. Marjorie E. Plummer as Instructor in History, for one semester, effective January 16, 1993. Mr. Jeff O. Prudhomme as Lecturer in Religious Studies, for one semester, effective January 16, 1993. Ms. Lisa K. Rollins as Lecturer in Education, for the period September 1, 1992 through January 15, 1993. Ms. Virginia Rovnyak as Lecturer in Mathematics, for one semester, effective January 16, 1993. Mr. Stephen F. Schneck as Visiting Associate Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs, for one semester, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. Simon H. Serfaty as Visiting Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs, for one semester, effective September 1, 1992. Ms. Neeta Sinha as Instructor in Economics, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. Robert E. Troxell as Lecturer in Architecture, for one semester, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. Robert W. Tucker, Jr. as Lecturer in Planning, for one semester, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. Paul M. Walker as Lecturer in Music, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1992. Ms. Laura Weiss as Lecturer in Architecture, for one semester, effective January 16, 1993. Mr. Andrew K. Wise as Instructor in History, for one semester, effective January 16, 1993. Ms. Constanze M. Witt as Instructor in Art History, for one semester, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. Richard E. Zody as Visiting Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs, for one semester, effective January 16, 1993.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Election of Non-Salaried Faculty Dr. Gayle S. Ackerman as Assistant Professor of Surgery, Roanoke Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1992. Dr. Clinton M. Cavett as Assistant Professor of Surgery, Roanoke Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1992. Mr. William G. Cooper as Visiting Professor of Medical Education, for one year, effective October 1, 1992. Dr. G. Rees Cosgrove as Visiting Assistant Professor of Neurosurgery, for the period September 2, 1992 through June 30, 1993. Dr. Ross S. Davies as Associate Professor of Surgery, Roanoke Program, for three years, effective October 1, 1992. Mr. Thomas E. Doyle as Lecturer in Mechanical, Aerospace and Nuclear Engineering, for the period September 1, 1992 through January 15, 1993. Ms. Penelope B. Finn as Assistant Professor of Psychiatric Medicine, Salem Program, for the period October 1, 1992 through June 30, 1995. Mr. Eckhardt Fuchs as Visiting Scholar in History, for one year, effective December 1, 1992. Mr. Jerome D. Gilmore as Assistant Professor of Psychiatric Medicine, Salem Program, for the period October 1, 1992 through June 30, 1995. Mr. William P. Glasheen as Visiting Assistant Professor of Plastic Surgery, for three years, effective October 1, 1992. Dr. Margaret S. Gorbatenko as Assistant Professor of Psychiatric Medicine, Salem Program, for the period October 1, 1992 through June 30, 1995. Mr. Paul F. Gorman as Visiting Professor of Computer Science, for two years, effective September 1, 1992. Ms. Mary K. Johnson as Assistant Professor of Psychiatric Medicine, Salem Program, for the period October 1, 1992 through June 30, 1995. Mr. Steven J. Lash as Assistant Professor of Psychiatric Medicine, Salem Program, for the period October 1, 1992 through June 30, 1995. Mr. Jon E. Lendon as Visiting Scholar in History, for the period October 15, 1992 through August 1, 1993. Mr. Gerald C. Mattran as Visiting Scholar in History, for the period October 1, 1992 through September 1, 1993. Mr. Randy R. Mosele as Assistant Professor of Military Science, for four academic years, effective May 1, 1993. Dr. Thomas Mulligan as Visiting Associate Professor of Internal Medicine, for the period August 6, 1992 through May 5, 1993. Mr. Christopher B. Nye as Assistant Professor of Family Medicine, for the period November 1, 1992 through June 30, 1993. Mr. James A. Pardo, Jr. as Lecturer in Law, for one semester, effective September 1, 1992. Dr. Joseph B. Philips, III as Visiting Associate Professor of Physiology, for one year, effective August 17, 1992. Mr. Robert D. Phillips as Visiting Scholar in Education, for the period September 1, 1992 through November 15, 1992. Dr. Peter J. Quesenberry as Professor of Internal Medicine, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective January 1, 1993. Ms. Kim G. Ragsdale as Assistant Professor of Psychiatric Medicine, Salem Program, for the period October 1, 1992 through June 30, 1995. Dr. Michael Rauchenwald as Visiting Assistant Professor of Urology, for one year, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. Fritz L. Schuermeyer as Visiting Professor of Electrical Engineering, for one year, effective September 1, 1992. Ms. Paulina Shur as Lecturer in Drama, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. Gregory B. Tait as Visiting Assistant Professor of Electrical Engineering, for one year, effective September 1, 1992. Dr. Randolph L. Turner as Visiting Assistant Professor of Dentistry, for the period September 1, 1992 through June 30, 1993. Dr. Hiroshi Ueno as Visiting Assistant Professor of Urology, for one year, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. Jiqing Xu as Visiting Scholar in Chemistry, for the period September 28, 1992 through March 28, 1993.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Election of Clinical Faculty Dr. Roberto A. Auffant as Clinical Assistant Professor of Anesthesiology, for the period October 1, 1992 through November 30, 1992. Ms. Glenda B. Ball as Clinical Instructor in Nursing, for three years, effective October 1, 1992. Mr. Michael A. Chiglinsky as Clinical Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Roanoke Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1992. Ms. Maureen M. Cunningham as Clinical Assistant Professor of Nursing, for three years, effective October 1, 1992. Ms. Susan Del Gobbo as Clinical Instructor in Medical Education, for one year, effective May 1, 1992. Dr. Jitendra S. Desai as Clinical Associate Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Roanoke Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1992. Dr. Kurtis S. Elward as Clinical Assistant Professor of Family Medicine, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective July 1, 1992. Dr. Richard W. Graham as Clinical Assistant Professor of Urology, for three years, effective August 1, 1992. Dr. Sumandeep Groh as Clinical Assistant Professor of Pediatrics, for one year, effective August 1, 1992. Mr. A. David Hamilton as Clinical Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Roanoke Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1992. Dr. Alden L. Hostetter as Clinical Assistant Professor of Pathology, for three years, effective October 1, 1992. Dr. Richard W. Lord, Jr. as Clinical Assistant Professor of Family Medicine, for the period November 1, 1992 through June 30, 1993. Dr. Jarlath MacKenna as Clinical Assistant Professor of Family Medicine, Lynchburg Program, for one year, effective September 1, 1992. Ms. Yvonne G. Newberry as Clinical Assistant Professor of Nursing, for three years, effective November 1, 1992. Dr. Neal R. Nygard as Clinical Instructor in Internal Medicine, for the period August 1, 1992 through August 31, 1992. Mr. Bryan D. Parsons as Clinical Instructor in Medical Education, for one year, effective May 1, 1992. Dr. Glen L. Portwood as Clinical Instructor in Internal Medicine, for the period November 1, 1992 through June 30, 1993. Ms. Rebecca H. Reeve as Clinical Instructor in Medical Education, for one year, effective May 1, 1992. Dr. Hendra A. Sanusi as Clinical Assistant Professor of Family Medicine, for the period October 1, 1992 through June 30, 1994. Dr. Narendra C. Shah as Clinical Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Roanoke Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1992.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Actions Relating to Chairholders The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the actions relating to chairholders be and they are hereby approved as shown below: (a) Election of Chairholder(s) Mr. Gene D. Block as Alumni Council Thomas Jefferson Professor of Biology, effective January 1, 1993. Ms. Maryse Conde as University Professor, effective January 16, 1993. Mr. Brian R. Duling as Robert M. Berne Professor of Cardiovascular Research, effective October 1, 1992. Mr. Duling will continue as Professor of Physiology without term. Ms. Marie-Helene Huet as Commonwealth Professor of French, effective January 16, 1993. Mr. Michel J. Lebas as Eleanor F. and Philip G. Rust Visiting Professor of Business Administration, for the period December 1, 1992 through May 31, 1993. Mr. Allen Lynch as White Burkett Miller Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs, for one year, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. Lynch will continue as Associate Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs, without term. Dr. James Q. Miller as Alumni Professor in Neurology, effective August 1, 1992. Mr. Laurie Olin as Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation Professor of Architecture, for the period October 21, 1992 through December 18, 1992. Mr. Peter Onuf as Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation Professor of History, effective December 1, 1992. Dr. Eric R. Powers as Donald C. Barnes Professor of Cardiology in Internal Medicine, effective October 1, 1992. (b) Leaves of Absence of Chairholder(s) Mr. Carl T. Herakovich, Henry L. Kinnier Professor of Civil Engineering, with partial pay, for the period January 1, 1993 through May 31, 1993, to do research as part of a sesquicentennial award. (c) Changes of Title of Chairholder Mr. Jerome J. McGann from Commonwealth Professor of English to John Stewart Bryan Professor of English, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. Tsung Y. Shen from Alumni Professor of Chemistry to Alfred Burger Professor of Biological and Medicinal Chemistry, effective September 1, 1992. (d) Resignations of Chairholder(s) Mr. William B. Taylor, Commonwealth Professor of History, effective May 31, 1993, to accept another position. (e) Re-appointments of Chairholder(s) Dr. R. Scott Jones as Chair, Department of Surgery, for the period January 1, 1992 through June 30, 1993.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Re-elections The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following persons be and they are hereby re-elected to the faculty: Dr. John T. Ashley as Professor of Internal Medicine, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective August 1, 1992. Mr. James R. Barrett as Assistant Professor of Biomedical Engineering, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective September 1, 1992. Dr. J. Clark Bates as Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, DeJarnette Center, for three years, effective August 14, 1992. Dr. G. Randall Bond as Assistant Professor of Pediatrics, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective November 1, 1992. Ms. Patricia Camacho as Research Assistant Professor of Neuroscience, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective October 1, 1992. Mr. Jiande Chen as Research Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, for the period November 1, 1992 through June 30, 1993. Ms. Nancy M. Coddington as Research Assistant Professor of Physiology, for one year, effective September 1, 1992. Dr. Eugene C. Corbett, Jr. as Associate Professor of Internal Medicine, General Medical Faculty and Assistant Professor of Nursing, General Nursing Faculty, for two years, effective July 1, 1992. Mr. Bernard J. Cosby as Research Associate Professor of Environmental Sciences, for one year, effective October 1, 1992. Dr. Claudette E. Dalton as Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, General Medical Faculty, for the period December 1, 1992 through March 31, 1993. Dr. Neto E. De Arruda as Research Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, for one year, effective September 1, 1992. Dr. Margarete Di Benedetto as Professor of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation, for three years, effective October 15, 1992. Mr. Pieter A. Dijkwel as Research Assistant Professor of Biochemistry, for the period September 1, 1992 through February 28, 1993. Mr. Dennis C. Donat as Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Western State Hospital, for three years, effective September 1, 1992. Dr. Stephen W. Ely as Research Assistant Professor of Physiology, for one year, effective July 1, 1992. Mr. Daniel A. Engel as Assistant Professor of Microbiology, for three years, effective September 1, 1992. Ms. Jonquil D. Feldman as Assistant Professor, General Medical Faculty, The Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, for one year, effective October 16, 1992. Mr. Tor A. Fjeldly as Visiting Professor of Electrical Engineering, for the period September 1, 1992 through August 31, 1993. Mr. John C. Fletcher as Professor of Religious Studies, for three years, effective July 1, 1992. Mr. Fletcher will continue as Professor of Biomedical Ethics, without term. Mr. James B. Garrett, Jr. as Assistant Professor of Psychiatric Medicine, Western State Hospital, for the period January 1, 1993 through June 30, 1995. Mr. Edmund Ghareeb as Visiting Associate Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs, for one semester, effective January 16, 1993. Mr. Eliezer Gileadi as Visiting Professor of Materials Science, part time, for the period September 1, 1992 through December 31, 1992. Mr. Chang S. Hahn as Research Assistant Professor of Microbiology, for one year, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. W. Dean Harman as Assistant Professor of Chemistry, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1993. Mr. Max R. Harris as Assistant Professor of Psychiatric Medicine, General Medical Faculty and Lecturer in Religious Studies, for one year, effective January 1, 1993. Mr. Ian Harrison as Assistant Professor of Chemistry, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1993. Mr. David J. Hudson as Associate Professor, General Faculty, for four academic years, effective September 1, 1992. Ms. Marylin S. James as Assistant Professor, General Medical Faculty, The Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, for one year, effective December 9, 1992. Mr. James S. Kennan as Assistant Professor, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective January 1, 1993. Mr. Michael T. Kinter as Research Assistant Professor of Microbiology, for the period October 1, 1992 through June 30, 1993. Ms. Elisabeth Ladenson as Acting Assistant Professor of French, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. Mark G. Lupher as Assistant Professor of Sociology, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1993. Ms. Bernice A. Marcopulos as Assistant Professor of Psychiatric Medicine, Western State Hospital, for the period January 1, 1993 through June 30, 1995. Mr. Robert E. Matson as Professor, General Faculty, for two academic years, effective September 1, 1992. Ms. Janice L. McMillan as Assistant Professor of Education, for the period January 16, 1993 through May 31, 1993. Mr. George Mentore as Assistant Professor of Anthropology, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. Drake C. Mitchell as Research Assistant Professor of Biochemistry, for one year, effective January 1, 1993. Mr. W. Edmund Moomaw as Professor, General Faculty, for the period December 1, 1992 through June 30, 1996. Mr. Thomas F. Oltmanns as Professor of Psychiatric Medicine, for three years, effective November 1, 1992. Mr. Oltmanns will continue as Professor of Psychology, without term. Ms. Angela D. Otero as Research Assistant Professor of Physiology, for three years, effective October 1, 1992. Ms. Joyce G. Pastors as Research Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, for the period December 1, 1992 through June 30, 1993. Mr. Jeffrey L. Phillips as Assistant Professor of Psychiatric Medicine, Western State Hospital, for the period January 1, 1993 through June 30, 1995. Mr. Roger O. Printup as Associate Professor, General Faculty, for one year, effective September 1, 1992. Dr. Timothy L. Pruett as Associate Professor of Surgery, for the period July 1, 1992 through January 1, 1993. Mr. James D. Rawls as Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Western State, for two years, effective October 1, 1992. Mr. Prem-Veer G. Reddy as Assistant Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology, General Medical Faculty, for the period October 15, 1992 through June 30, 1993. Mr. Mark Reisler as Associate Professor, General Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1993. Ms. Diane L. Rosin as Research Assistant Professor of Pharmacology, for one year, effective September 1, 1992. Ms. Cynthia W. Sanborn as Research Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, for the period December 1, 1992 through June 30, 1993. Ms. Betty H. Sapir as Assistant Professor of French, part time, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1993. Mr. Jon T. Saunders as Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, General Medical Faculty, for the period December 1, 1992 through June 30, 1993. Mr. Simon H. Serfaty as Visiting Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs, for one semester, effective January 16, 1992. Mr. Theodore R. Simons as Research Assistant Professor of Environmental Sciences, for one year, effective January 1, 1993. Mr. John P. Slattery as Research Associate Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, for the period August 29, 1992 through January 14, 1994. Ms. Allison M. Sleeman as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, Alderman Library, for the period September 16, 1992 through June 30, 1995. Mr. Douglas B. Smith as Lecturer, General Medical Center Faculty, for the period December 7, 1992 through June 30, 1994. Dr. Edward M. Spencer as Assistant Professor of Pediatrics, General Medical Faculty, for the period October 1, 1992 through June 30, 1993. Dr. William C. Stevenson as Assistant Professor of Surgery, for three years, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. Christopher L. Vaughan as Associate Professor of Orthopaedics and Rehabilitation and Associate Professor of Education, for one year, effective August 16, 1992. Ms. Susan M. VerSchneider as Instructor in Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective August 1, 1992. Ms. Elizabeth B. Waters as Lecturer in Planning, for one semester, effective September 1, 1992. Ms. Margot L. White as Assistant Professor of Medical Education, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective October 1, 1992. Ms. Patricia L. Wiberg as Assistant Professor of Environmental Sciences, for three academic years, effective January 16, 1994. Mr. Richard M. Wright as Research Assistant Professor of Anatomy and Cell Biology, for one year, effective December 1, 1992. Mr. Yongbo Xu as Visiting Research Associate Professor of Materials Science, for the period October 1, 1992 through December 31, 1992. Mr. Chenggui Zhang as Visiting Research Assistant Professor of Pharmacology, for one year, effective October 1, 1992.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Promotions The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following faculty members be and they are hereby promoted: Dr. David M. French from Clinical Assistant Professor of Family Medicine to Clinical Professor of Family Medicine, for three years, effective November 1, 1992.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Leaves of Absence The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following faculty members be and they are hereby granted leave of absence: Mr. Gib Akin, Associate Professor of Commerce, with pay, for the period January 16, 1993 through May 31, 1993, to do research as part of a sesquicentennial award. Ms. Sara B. Blair, Assistant Professor of English, without pay, for the period September 1, 1992 through January 15, 1993, to do research. Ms. Linda K. Blum, Research Assistant Professor of Environmental Sciences, without pay, for the period September 1, 1992 through July 31, 1993, due to insufficient research funds. Ms. Mary L. Bun, Assistant Professor of Slavic Languages and Literatures, without pay, for the period September 1, 1992 through May 31, 1993, for medical reasons. Mr. Reginald D. Butler, Assistant Professor of History, without pay, for the period January 16, 1993 through May 31, 1993, to do research. Mr. James W. Ceaser, Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs, without pay, for the period September 1, 1992 through May 31, 1993, for educational purposes. Dr. Robert L. Chevalier, Professor of Pediatrics, with pay, for the period July 1, 1992 through June 30, 1993, for educational purposes. Mr. M. G. Finn, Assistant Professor of Chemistry, with partial pay, for the period September 1, 1992 through August 31, 1995, to do research. Ms. Janet S. Herman, Associate Professor of Environmental Sciences, with partial pay, for the period January 16, 1993 through May 31, 1993, to do research. Mr. Charles R. Kaut, Associate Professor of Anthropology, with partial pay, for the period September 1, 1992 through May 31, 1993, to continue to qualify for the incentive retirement plan as approved by the Board of Visitors. Mr. John F. Leahy, Professor of Education, with pay, for one year, effective January 16, 1993, to do research. Mr. David Lewis, Professor of Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering, with partial pay, for the period September 1, 1992 through May 31, 1993, to continue to qualify for the phased retirement plan as approved by the Board of Visitors. Mr. William A. Little, Professor of German, with partial pay, for the period September 1, 1992 through May 31, 1993, to continue to qualify for the incentive retirement plan as approved by the Board of Visitors. Mr. Robert M. MacLeod, Professor of Internal Medicine, with pay, for the period January 1, 1993 through June 30, 1993, to do research. Ms. Felicia C. Marston, Assistant Professor of Commerce, with pay, for the period January 16, 1993 through May 31, 1993, to do research as part of a sesquicentennial award. Mr. Donald McGrady, Professor of Spanish, Italian and Portuguese, with partial pay, for one year, effective January 16, 1993, to do research as part of a sesquicentennial award. Mr. Harold S. Morton, Associate Professor of Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering, without pay, for the period September 1, 1992 through January 15, 1993, to continue to qualify for the incentive retirement plan as approved by the Board of Visitors. Ms. Justine E. Owens, Research Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, with partial pay, for the period September 1, 1992 through May 31, 1993, to do research. Mr. Laurence C. Pettit, Professor of Commerce, with pay, for the period September 1, 1992 through January 15, 1993, to do research as part of a sesquicentennial award. Mr. G. Carleton Ray, Research Professor of Environmental Sciences, with partial pay, for the period February 1, 1993 through May 31, 1993, due to insufficient research funds. Ms. Karen L. Ryan-Hayes, Assistant Professor of Slavic Languages and Literatures, with pay, for the period October 6, 1992 through November 17, 1992, for maternity leave. Mr. Abdulaziz A. Sachedina, Professor of Religious Studies, without pay, for the period January 16, 1993 through May 31, 1993, to do research. Mr. Mantripragada B. Sankaram, Research Assistant Professor of Biochemistry, without pay, for one year, effective September 1, 1992, to do research. Mr. S. Fred Singer, Research Professor of Environmental Sciences, without pay, for the period September 1, 1993 through May 31, 1994, for personal reasons. Mr. John W. Stewart, Associate Professor of Physics, without pay, for the period September 1, 1993 through January 15, 1994, to continue to qualify for the incentive retirement plan as approved by the Board of Visitors. Mr. Ralph J. Stoudt, Associate Professor of Education, with partial pay, for the period October 1, 1992 through May 31, 1995, to continue to qualify for the incentive retirement plan as approved by the Board of Visitors. Mr. Robert L. Vickery, Professor of Architecture, with partial pay, for the period January 16, 1993 through May 31, 1993, to teach at a premier Architecture School in Helsinki, Finland and to accept a Fulbright Traveling Grant.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Changes of Title The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following changes of title be and they are hereby made: Mr. Matthew Ando from Acting Assistant Professor of Mathematics to Assistant Professor of Mathematics, for four years, effective September 1, 1992. Ms. Rosalyn W. Berne from Research Assistant to Instructor in Business Administration, for the period January 1, 1993 through June 30, 1993. Ms. Marilyn Fisher from Assistant Professor of Anatomy and Cell Biology to Assistant Professor of Anatomy and Cell Biology, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective October 1, 1992. Mr. David F. Germano from Lecturer in Religious Studies to Assistant Professor of Religious Studies, for three years, effective September 1, 1993. Ms. Cheryl L. Krueger from Acting Assistant Professor of French to Assistant Professor of French, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1992. Ms. Mary P. Martin from Acting Assistant Professor of English to Assistant Professor of English, for two years, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. Thomas J. O'Leary from Assistant Professor of Medical Education, General Medical Faculty to Assistant Professor of Medical Education, General Medical Faculty and Lecturer in Sociology, for the period September 1, 1992 through January 15, 1993. Dr. Timothy L. Pruett from Associate Professor of Surgery to Associate Professor of Surgery, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective January 1, 1993. Mr. Ethan N. Saliba from Instructor, General Faculty to Assistant Professor, General Faculty, for one year, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. Thomas J. Scanlan from Acting Assistant Professor of English to Assistant Professor of English, for four academic years, effective September 1, 1992. Ms. Prudence H. Thorner from Lecturer, General Medical Faculty to Lecturer, General Faculty, for three years, effective December 1, 1992. Mr. Jeremy B. Tuttle from Research Assistant Professor of Neuroscience to Assistant Professor of Urology, General Medical Faculty and Assistant Professor of Neuroscience, General Medical Faculty, for the period November 1, 1992 through June 30, 1993. Ms. Jacqueline A. Young from Instructor in Internal Medicine, General Medical Faculty to Instructor, General Medical Center Faculty, for one year, effective July 1, 1992.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Resignations The following resignations were announced: Mr. Steven N. Applegate, Instructor in Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, General Medical Faculty, effective November 2, 1992, to accept another position. Ms. Terry A. Astuto, Associate Professor of Education, effective August 31, 1992, to accept another position. Mr. Christopher Barton, Lecturer, General Faculty, effective August 14, 1992, to accept another position. Ms. Mary K. Bednar, Lecturer, General Faculty, effective November 1, 1992, to accept another position. Mr. Robert L. Blackburn, Assistant Professor of Electrical Engineering, effective August 31, 1992, to accept another position. Mr. Philip J. Bushman, Lecturer in Architecture, effective December 21, 1992, to accept another position. Mr. John D. Casey, Professor of English, effective December 31, 1992, to accept another position. Ms. Bethany J. Christenson, Lecturer in Architecture, effective January 15, 1993, to accept another position. Ms. Nancy M. Coddington, Research Assistant Professor of Physiology, effective December 31, 1992, to accept another position. Dr. G. Rees Cosgrove, Assistant Professor of Neurosurgery, effective September 1, 1992, to accept another position. Ms. Marcia A. Delcourt, Research Assistant Professor of Education, effective March 31, 1993, to accept another position. Dr. Jitendra S. Desai, Clinical Associate Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Roanoke Program, effective June 30, 1992, to accept another position. Ms. Teresa A. Deturo, Instructor, General Faculty, effective December 31, 1992, for personal reasons. Ms. Jin Dewen, Visiting Professor of Mechanical Engineering, effective October 31, 1992, for personal reasons. Dr. Kurtis S. Elward, Clinical Assistant Professor of Family Medicine, effective June 30, 1992, to accept another position. Ms. Deborah A. Gideon, Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Western State Hospital, effective July 29, 1992, to accept another position. Ms. Mary L. Glover, Assistant Professor of Nursing, General Nursing Faculty, effective December 31, 1992, for personal reasons. Dr. Daniel P. Harrington, Associate Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Roanoke Program, effective June 30, 1992, to accept another position. Dr. Mark M. Harris, Associate Professor of Anesthesiology, General Medical Faculty, effective September 15, 1992, to enter private practice. Mr. Donald P. Holmes, Lecturer, General Medical Center Faculty, effective October 31, 1992, for personal reasons. Dr. Ismail H. Ihmeidan, Assistant Professor of Radiology, effective November 9, 1992, for personal reasons. Dr. Sheila M. Johnson, Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Salem Program, effective August 11, 1992, to accept another position. Ms. Jane R. Maggard, Lecturer, General Faculty, effective October 1, 1992, due to a change in the relationship between the Virginia Engineering Foundation and the University of Virginia. Ms. Carol A. Manning, Research Assistant Professor of Psychology, effective September 1, 1992, due to insufficient research funds. Ms. Stephanie McElhone, Instructor, General Faculty, effective September 1, 1992, for personal reasons. Mr. James P. Mitchell, Assistant Professor, General Faculty, effective August 31, 1992, to accept another position. Mr. George A. Nowacek, Associate Professor of Medical Education, General Medical Faculty, effective October 31, 1992, to accept another position. Ms. Debra L. Nystrom, Lecturer in English, effective January 15, 1993, for personal reasons. Dr. John A. Persing, Professor of Plastic Surgery, effective August 31, 1992, to accept another position. Dr. John M. Plewes, II, Clinical Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, effective September 30, 1992, to accept another position. Mr. Terrance W. Pratt, Research Professor of Computer Science, effective September 30, 1992, to accept another position. Dr. Peter J. Quesenberry, Professor of Internal Medicine and Professor of Otolaryngology, effective December 31, 1992, to accept another position. Ms. Mary E. Ropka, Assistant Professor of Nursing, General Nursing Faculty, effective August 31, 1992, for personal reasons. Dr. Julia P. Roulier, Clinical Assistant Professor of Family Medicine, effective September 30, 1992, for personal reasons. Dr. Hilary A. Sanfey, Assistant Professor of Surgery, General Medical Faculty, effective September 2, 1992, to accept another position. Ms. Evelynne B. Scarboro, Lecturer, General Faculty, effective December 11, 1992, to accept another position. Mr. Peter M. Scharf, Lecturer in Religious Studies, effective September 1, 1992, to accept another position. Dr. John B. Selby, Associate Professor of Radiology, effective October 2, 1992, to enter private practice. Mr. Douglas B. Smith, Lecturer, General Medical Center Faculty, effective December 6, 1992, to accept another position. Mr. Kotteazeth Srikumar, Research Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, effective December 31, 1992, to accept another position. Dr. Forrest M. Stewart, Associate Professor of Internal Medicine, effective December 31, 1992, to accept another position. Ms. Clover C. Taylor, Instructor in Humanities, effective September 10, 1992, to accept another position. Mr. James C. Thompson, Lecturer, General Faculty, effective April 1, 1993, for personal reasons.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Retirements The following Retirements were announced: Mr. Donald G. Baker, Professor of Radiology, General Medical Faculty, effective December 31, 1992. Mr. Baker has been a member of the faculty since October 1, 1977. Mr. John S. Horner, Professor of Education, effective May 31, 1992. Mr. Horner has been a member of the faculty since September 1, 1964. Dr. William B. Looney, Professor of Biomedical Engineering, effective October 31, 1992. Dr. Looney has been a member of the faculty since January 16, 1961. Dr. Cary N. Moon, Jr., Clinical Professor of Otolaryngology, Head and Neck Surgery, effective March 31, 1992. Dr. Moon has been a member of the faculty since July 1, 1950. Mr. James O. West, Associate Professor, General Faculty, effective September 30, 1992. Mr. West has been a member of the faculty since September 1, 1959. Dr. Arthur W. Wyker, Jr., Professor of Urology, effective December 31, 1992. Dr. Wyker has been a member of the faculty since July 1, 1960.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Appointments The following appointments were announced: Mr. Patrick L. Chester as Assistant Dean for Afro-American Affairs, for the period August 17, 1992 through June 30, 1993. Mr. W. Edmund Moomaw as Executive Director of Assessment, Planning, and Studies, for the period December 1, 1992 through June 30, 1996. Ms. Prudence H. Thorner as Executive Assistant to the Provost, for three years, effective December 1, 1992. Ms. Anne E. Zintl as Assistant to the President, for one year, effective September 1, 1992.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Re-appointments The following re-appointments were announced: Dr. Margarete Di Benedetto as Chair, Department of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation, for one year, effective October 15, 1992. Mr. John B. Hightower as Director of Planning and Development for the Arts, for one year, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. Roger O. Printup as University Registrar, for one year, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. Carl O. Trindle as Assistant Dean, College of Arts and Sciences, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1992.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Election of Professors Emeritus The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following person(s) be and they are hereby elected Professor Emeritus: Mr. John S. Horner, Professor of Education, effective May 31, 1992. Dr. William B. Looney, Professor of Biomedical Engineering, effective October 31, 1992. Dr. Arthur W. Wyker, Jr., Professor of Urology, effective December 31, 1992.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">TERMINATION Dr. Larry D. Edwards, Professor of Internal Medicine, Salem Program, effective September 22, 1992, due to termination by the Veteran's Administration Medical Center.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHANGE IN RESIGNATION OF DR. DEBRA J. GROSSMAN The President announced that the resignation of Dr. Debra J. Grossman, Assistant Professor of Dermatology, effective June 30, 1990, to return to private practice, as shown in the Minutes of the meeting of October 5, 1990, be changed to read as follows: Dr. Debra J. Grossman, Assistant Professor of Dermatology, effective July 31, 1990, to return to private practice.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHANGE IN RETIREMENT OF MR. JACK A. HOLT The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the retirement of Mr. Jack A. Holt, Associate Professor of Commerce, effective December 31, 1992, as shown in the Minutes of the Meeting of March 28, 1992, be changed to read as follows: Mr. Jack A. Holt, Associate Professor of Commerce, effective January 15, 1993. Mr. Holt has been a member of the faculty since September 1, 1977.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHANGE IN THE ELECTION OF MR. CARL W. STENBERG, III The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the election of Mr. Carl W. Stenberg, III as Distinguished Professor for the Director of the Center for Public Service, effective September 1, 1990, as shown in the Minutes of the Meeting of February 1, 1991, be corrected to read as follows: Mr. Carl W. Stenberg, III as Distinguished Professor for the Director of the Center for Public Service, for the period September 1, 1990 through September 30, 1994.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHANGE IN THE ELECTION OF MR. RUSSELL S. VALENTINO The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the election of Mr. Russell S. Valentino as Lecturer in Slavic Languages and Literatures, for one semester, effective September 1, 1992, as shown in the Minutes of the Meeting of October 9, 1992, be changed to read as follows: Mr. Russell S. Valentino, as Lecturer in Slavic Languages and Literatures, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1992.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHANGE IN THE APPOINTMENT OF MR. MOSES K. WOODE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the appointment of Mr. Moses K. Woode as Associate Dean for Academic Support, School of Medicine, for three years, effective January 1, 1992, as shown in the Minutes of the meeting of January 24, 1992, be changed to read as follows: Mr. Moses K. Woode as Associate Dean for Student Academic Support, School of Medicine, for three years, effective January 1, 1992.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CLINCH VALLEY COLLEGE Elections The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following persons be and they are hereby elected to the faculty: Ms. Marcia Y. Brown as Lecturer, General Faculty, Clinch Valley College, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1992. Mr. Kenneth K. Frank as Assistant Professor of Management, Clinch Valley College, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1992. Ms. Mary Lou B. Frank as Associate Professor of Psychology, Clinch Valley College, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1992. Ms. Delores A. Gibson as Lecturer, General Faculty, Clinch Valley College, for the period September 1, 1992 through June 30, 1994. Mr. Peter A. Mangan as Assistant Professor of Psychology, Clinch Valley College, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1992. Ms. Kelly R. McBride as Lecturer, General Faculty, Clinch Valley College, for the period October 1, 1992 through June 30, 1994. Ms. Marcia K. Quesenberry as Lecturer, General Faculty, Clinch Valley College, for the period October 1, 1992 through June 30, 1994. Ms. Elizabeth E. Ryan as Assistant Professor of Mathematics, Clinch Valley College, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1992.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Re-elections The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following person be and he is hereby re-elected to the faculty: Mr. Clifford A. Edwards as Assistant Professor of Computer Science, Clinch Valley College, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1992.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Appointments The following appointments were announced: Ms. Marcia K. Quesenberry as Director, Southwest Virginia Public Education Consortium, Clinch Valley College, for the period October 1, 1992 through June 30, 1994.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ESTABLISHMENT OF THE ELIZABETH D. AND RICHARD A. MERRILL PROFESSORSHIP IN LAW The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that there is hereby established a Chair to be known as the Elizabeth D. and Richard A. Merrill Professorship in Law. The Board is grateful to Mr. David Lurton Massee, Jr., who made the establishment of this Chair possible.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ESTABLISHMENT OF THE CADDELL &amp; CONWELL PROFESSORSHIP IN LAW The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that there is hereby established a Chair to be known as the Caddell &amp; Conwell Professorship in Law, this Chair to become effective at such time as its funding is complete. The Board is grateful to Mr. Michael A. Caddell and Ms. Tracey Conwell who made the establishment of this Chair possible.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ESTABLISHMENT OF THE H. WILLIAM PORTERFIELD, M.D. &amp; LINDA OBENAUF PORTERFIELD PROFESSORSHIP IN BIOMEDICAL ETHICS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that there is hereby established a Chair to be known as the H. William Porterfield, M.D., and Linda Obenauf Porterfield Professorship in Biomedical Ethics in the College of Arts and Sciences. The Board is grateful to Dr. and Mrs. H. William Porterfield who made the establishment of this Chair possible.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ELECTION OF DR. DON E. DETMER AS VICE PRESIDENT AND PROVOST FOR HEALTH SCIENCES The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that Dr. Don E. Detmer be and he is hereby elected Vice President and Provost for Health Sciences, for five years, effective July 1, 1993.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RESOLUTION REGARDING FACULTY GRIEVANCE APPEAL The following resolution was adopted: WHEREAS, a faculty member has appealed to the Board of Visitors adverse findings of a faculty hearing board and of the President, in connection with a grievance proceeding conducted pursuant to the Faculty Relations Committee's Policies and Procedures in which the faculty member contested disciplinary sanctions imposed by the Dean of the School; WHEREAS, Section 5.1 of theManual of the Board of Visitorsprovides that the "Board at its discretion shall consider such appeals as are provided for in the University regulations . . . ;". RESOLVED that the Board of Visitors denies the faculty member's appeal; RESOLVED FURTHER that Board review of the merits of faculty grievances pursuant to the Faculty Relations Committee's Policies and Procedures should be reserved for appeals of extraordinary cases.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF SUMMARY OF AUDIT REPORTS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the Summary of Audit Reports for the period September 1, 1992, through December 31, 1992, as presented by the Director of Audits, be and it is hereby approved as recommended by the Audit Committee.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF THE 1993 AUDIT SCHEDULE FOR THE REMAINDER OF FISCAL YEAR 1993 The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the Audit Schedule for the remainder of Fiscal Year 1993, as presented by the Director of Audits, be and it is hereby approved as recommended by the Audit Committee.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF EASEMENT FOR THE VIRGINIA DEPARTMENT OF TRANSPORTATION ON FONTAINE AVENUE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the deed of easement to be executed on or about February 5, 1993, between The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia and the Department of Transportation which allows for widening of Fontaine Avenue across from the Real Estate Foundation's Fontaine Research Park located east of the 250 By-pass on the north side of Fontaine Avenue in Albemarle County, be and it is hereby approved; RESOLVED FURTHER that the appropriate officers of the University be and they are hereby authorized to execute said deed of easement.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF THE ARCHITECT/ENGINEER SELECTION FOR THE AMBULATORY CARE AND RELATED FACILITIES PROJECT The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the joint venture firm of Metcalf/Tobey, Davis Brody, Hansen Lind Meyer (HLM) of Reston, Virginia, and New York, New York, be and it is hereby approved for the performance of architectural and engineering services for programming and functional planning for the Ambulatory Care and Related Facilities project; RESOLVED FURTHER that at the option of the University administration, the joint venture firm may later be continued to perform full architectural design services upon approval of the project by State Government.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF THE ENGINEER SELECTION FOR THE NORTH GROUNDS ELECTRIC SUBSTATION PROJECT The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the firm of The Greenwood Partnership, Engineers/Architects of Lynchburg, Virginia, be and it is hereby approved for the performance of architectural and engineering services for the North Grounds Electrical Substation project.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF THE ENGINEER SELECTION FOR THE JORDAN HALL CHILLED WATER SYSTEM The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the firm of the Greenwood Partnership, Engineers/Architects of Lynchburg, Virginia, be and it is hereby approved for the performance of engineering and architectural services for the design and construction of the Jordan Hall Chilled Water System upon approval of the project by State Government.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF THE INDIVIDUAL BUILDING PRELIMINARY DESIGNS FOR THE CONSTRUCTION OF THE DARDEN BUILDING PROJECT The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the individual building preliminary designs for the construction of the Darden Building Project as illustrated on drawings dated February 5, 1993, by the Architect of Record, Ayers/Saint/Gross, Inc., of Baltimore, Maryland, and the design architect, Robert A.M. Stern, Architects of New York City, New York, and presented on drawings titled 1. Site Plan, 2. Building Elevations and Sections - Library/Commons/Future Auditorium, 3. Building Elevations and Sections - Classroom/Commons/Faculty Office, 4. Building Elevations and Sections - Faculty Office/ Commons/Library, 5. Building Elevations and Sections - Sponsors Hall, 6. Building Plans - Ground Floor Plan: Library/Commons/Classroom/Faculty Office, 7. Building Plans - Commons Level Floor Plan: Library/Commons/ Classroom/Faculty Office, 8. Building Plans - Upper Level Floor Plan; Library/Commons/Classroom/Faculty Office, 9. Building Plans - Sponsors Hall Floor Plans: Three Levels, 10. Details - Commons-Partial Elevation, 11. Details - Library - Partial Elevation, 12. Details - Classroom/Faculty Office - Typical Pavilion Front, 13. Details - Doors/Windows, be and they are hereby approved for further development.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF THE SITING FOR THE CONSTRUCTION OF THE ALDERMAN LIBRARY SOUTH ACCESSIBILITY IMPROVEMENT PROJECT The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the siting for the construction of the Alderman Library South Accessibility Improvement project as illustrated on the site map dated November 1992, prepared by the Facilities Management Landscape Architecture Division, be and it is hereby approved.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF THE ARCHITECTURAL DESIGN GUIDELINES FOR THE CONSTRUCTION OF THE ALDERMAN LIBRARY SOUTH ACCESSIBILITY IMPROVEMENT PROJECT The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the architectural design guidelines prepared by the Architect for the University, dated January 15, 1993, for the construction of the Alderman Library South Accessibility Improvement Project, be and they are hereby approved; RESOLVED FURTHER that the project design shall be presented for further review at the schematic design level of development.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF THE SCHEMATIC DESIGN FOR THE CONSTRUCTION OF THE ALDERMAN LIBRARY SOUTH ACCESSIBILITY IMPROVEMENT PROJECT The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the schematic design for the construction of the Alderman Library South Accessibility Improvement Project as illustrated on drawing A-1 Site Plan and Elevation dated January 15, 1993, and prepared by Mitchell, Matthews and Associates, Ltd., be and it is hereby approved; RESOLVED FURTHER that the project design shall be presented for further review at the preliminary design level of development.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF THE 1994-1996 CAPITAL BUDGET PROGRAM FOR FINAL DEVELOPMENT BY THE UNIVERSITY ADMINISTRATION AND SUBMITTAL TO THE STATE GOVERNMENT The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the 1994-1996 Capital Budget Program for the University Academic Division (Agency 207), University Medical Center (Agency 209), and Clinch Valley College (Agency 246), as presented to the Board of Visitors on February 5, 1993, be and it is hereby approved for final development by the University Administration and submittal to the State Government.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">WRITE-OFF OF BAD DEBTS AND FREE SERVICE FOR THE MEDICAL CENTER The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the Medical Center Accounts Committee be and it is hereby authorized to write off as bad debts and free service accounts included in the University of Virginia Medical Center Accounts Committee Reports for the October 19, 1992, and December 14, 1992, meetings which include the write-offs for the months of August 1992, through November 1992, totaling $26,683,926.26, and consisting of the following: Bad Debts $ 3,425,736.24 Indigent Care 23,258,190.02 ---------- Total $26,683,926.26 RESOLVED FURTHER that the above action shall not be a compromise, settlement or discharge of debts represented by such accounts.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF INCREASE IN SUMMER SESSION, CONFERENCE, AND SPECIAL PURPOSE FACILITIES RATES FOR 1993-1994 The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the Summer Session fees for the Academic Division be and they are hereby increased as follows, effective beginning with the Summer Session of 1993: Actual 1992 Amount of Increase Percent Increase Proposed 1993 TUITION Virginian (per semester hour) $105.00 $19.00 18.1% $124.00 Non-Virginian (per semester hour) $326.00 $64.00 19.6% $390.00 Thesis/Dissertation Research $318.00 $55.00 17.3% $373.00 Appellate Judges Program $945.00 $171.00 18.1% $1,116.00 Non-Resident Fee $50.00 $5.00 10.0% $55.00 COMPREHENSIVE FEE Newcomb Hall $9.00 $0.00 0.0% $9.00 Student Health $45.00 $0.00 0.0% $45.00 Transportation $10.00 $0.00 0.0% $10.00 TOTAL $64.00 $0.00 0.0% $64.00 OTHER FEES Late Payment Fee $25.00 $0.00 0.0% $25.00 Summer Foreign Language Institute Fee $30.00 $0.00 0.0% $30.00 The Summer Session registration fee and tuition rates also apply to Mt. Lake Biological Station. In addition the following special fees apply to Mt. Lake Biological Station Actual 1992 Amount of Increase Percent Increase Proposed 1993 Lab Fee and Field Trip $65.00 $2.00 3.1% $67.00 Pre-Doctoral Research Fee Per Term: Virginian $318.00 $55.00 17.3% $373.00 Non-Virginian $636.00 $110.00 17.3% $746.00 Post Doctoral Laboratory: Fee per week $100.00 $10.00 10.0% $110.00 MT. LAKE BOARD RATES PER TERM (5 WEEKS) Each Person 17 years of age &amp; older $390.00 $0.00 0.0% $390.00 Each Person 10-16 years of age $250.00 $0.00 0.0% $250.00 Each Person 9 years of age &amp; younger $155.00 $0.00 0.0% $155.00 MT. LAKE HOUSING RATES PER TERM (5 WEEKS) Dormitories $90.00 $3.00 3.3% $93.00 Cottages Laing Singles $90.00 $3.00 3.3% $93.00 Laing Center $125.00 $4.00 3.2% $129.00 North $122.00 $4.00 3.3% $126.00 South $122.00 $4.00 3.3% $126.00 Northwest $122.00 $4.00 3.3% $126.00 West $125.00 $4.00 3.2% $129.00 Hentz-Mohr $180.00 $6.00 3.3% $186.00 With Kitchen $225.00 $6.00 2.7% $231.00 Clayton $180.00 $6.00 3.3% $186.00 Catesby $150.00 $5.00 3.3% $155.00 Gattinger $150.00 $5.00 3.3% $155.00 Michaux $180.00 $6.00 3.3% $186.00 With Kitchen $225.00 $6.00 2.7% $231.00 Burns $168.00 $5.00 3.0% $173.00 With Kitchen $213.00 $5.00 2.3% $218.00 Washington $160.00 $5.00 3.1% $165.00 Banister $160.00 $5.00 3.1% $165.00 LeConte $160.00 $5.00 3.1% $165.00 Hariot $160.00 $5.00 3.1% $165.00 Schoew $160.00 $5.00 3.1% $165.00 Mapnis $160.00 $5.00 3.1% $165.00 Holbrook $160.00 $5.00 3.1% $165.00 Mitchell $160.00 $5.00 3.1% $165.00 Rafinesque $140.00 $5.00 3.6% $145.00 New Dorm Singles NA NA NA $100.00 Apartments NA NA NA $150.00 AND BE IT RESOLVED that the following rental rates for housing facilities for summer, 1993, be and they are hereby approved: Actual Summer 1992 Amount of Increase Percent Increase Proposed Rate Summer 1993 FACILITY SUMMER SESSION RATES* * The New College will be the only facility utilized for the 1993 Summer Session. Alderman/Observatory Houses Per student, per week, double occupancy $42.00 N/A N/A N/A Per student, per week, single occupancy $52.00 N/A N/A N/A Brandon Apartment Complex Per student, per week, double occupancy $52.00 N/A N/A N/A Per student, per week, single occupancy $68.00 N/A N/A N/A Munford/Gwathmey Per student, per week, double occupancy $42.00 N/A N/A N/A Per student, per week, single occupancy $52.00 N/A N/A N/A Sprigg Lane Per student, per week, double occupancy $46.00 N/A N/A N/A Per student, per week, single occupancy $58.00 N/A N/A N/A Stadium Road (Gooch/Dillard) Per student, per week, double occupancy $46.00 N/A N/A N/A Per student, per week, single occupancy $58.00 N/A N/A N/A New College Per Student, per week, double occupancy N/A N/A N/A $48.00 Per student, per week, single occupancy N/A N/A N/A $60.00 SUMMER CONFERENCE RATES * * Five percent discount for reservations received for the period of August 8 through August 15 (A) FULL SERVICE - All linens provided; full, daily maid service Lambeth Field Per person, per night, double occupancy $18.00 $0.50 2.8% $18.50 Per person, per night, single occupancy $24.75 $0.75 3.0% $25.50 Monroe Hill Houses Per person, per night, double occupancy $15.50 $0.50 3.2% $16.00 Per person, per night, single occupancy $21.25 $0.75 3.5% $22.00 Copeley Hill, Phase III &amp; IV Per person, per night, double occupancy $19.50 $0.50 2.6% $20.00 Per person, per night, single occupancy $28.50 $0.75 2.6% $29.25 Lawn Per person, per night, double occupancy $16.00 $0.50 3.1% $16.50 Per person, per night, single occupancy $22.25 $0.75 3.4% $23.00 FACILITY Actual Summer 1992 Amount of Increase Percent Increase Proposed Rate Summer 1993 (A) FULL SERVICE - (cont) Faulkner Per person, per night double occupancy $18.00 $0.50 2.8% $18.50 Per person, per night, single occupancy $27.00 $0.75 2.8% $27.75 New College Per person, per night, double occupancy $15.50 $0.50 3.2% $16.00 Per person, per night, single occupancy $23.00 $0.00 0.0% $23.00 Stadium Road (Gooch/Dillard) Per person, per night, double occupancy $15.50 $0.50 3.2% $16.00 Per person, per night, single occupancy $23.00 $0.00 0.0% $23.00 (B) PARTIAL SERVICE - Most linens provided; common areas served moderately. Lambeth Field Per person, per night, double occupancy $15.00 $0.00 0.0% $15.00 Per person, per night, single occupancy $20.50 $0.75 3.7% $21.25 Family rates, per week 2 bedroom apartment $210.00 $5.00 2.4% $215.00 Family rates, per week 3 bedroom apartment $280.00 $10.00 3.6% $290.00 Monroe Hill Houses Per person, per night, double occupancy $13.50 $0.50 3.7% $14.00 Per person, per night, single occupancy $17.75 $0.50 2.8% $18.25 Alderman/Observatory Houses Per person, per night, double occupancy $11.00 $0.50 4.5% $11.50 Per person, per night, single occupancy $13.50 $0.50 3.7% $14.00 McCormick Road Houses Per person, per night, double occupancy $10.00 $0.25 2.5% $10.25 Per person, per night, single occupancy $11.50 $0.25 2.2% $11.75 Stadium Road (Gooch/Dillard) Per person, per night, double occupancy $13.00 $0.50 3.8% $13.50 Per person, per night, single occupancy $16.00 $0.50 3.1% $16.50 New College Per person, per night, double occupancy $13.00 $0.50 3.8% $13.50 Per person, per night, single occupancy $16.00 $0.50 3.1% $16.50 Faulkner Per person, per night, double occupancy $15.00 $0.50 3.3% $15.50 Per person, per night, single occupancy $20.50 $0.50 2.4% $21.00 Sprigg Lane Per person, per night, double occupancy $13.00 $0.50 3.8% $13.50 Per person, per night, single occupancy $16.00 $0.50 3.1% $16.50 FACILITY Actual Summer 1992 Amount of Increase Percent Increase Proposed Rate Summer 1993 (C) NO LINEN SERVICE Lambeth Field Per person, per night, double occupancy $11.00 $0.50 4.5% $11.50 Monroe Hill Houses Per person, per night, double occupancy $11.00 $0.50 4.5% $11.50 Munford/Gwathmey Per person, per night, double occupancy $9.00 $0.00 0.0% $9.00 Alderman/Observatory Per person, per night, double occupancy $9.50 $0.25 2.6% $9.75 McCormick Road Houses Per person, per night, double occupancy $8.25 $0.25 3.0% $8.50 Brandon Apartment Complex Per person, per night, double occupancy $11.00 $0.50 4.5% $11.50 Sprigg Lane Per person, per night, double occupancy $11.00 $0.50 4.5% $11.50 Stadium Road (Gooch/Dillard) Per person, per night, double occupancy $11.00 $0.50 4.5% $11.50 New College Per person, per night, double occupancy $11.00 $0.50 4.5% $11.50 OTHER CONTRACTED per person group rates approved on a basis consistent with University contracting policies and procedures. GRADUATE SUITES Graduate Advisor Suites in Alderman and McCormick Road Houses Per suite, per week $100.00 $0.00 0.0% $100.00 GRADUATION GUESTS Alderman/Observatory Graduation Guests Per person, per night $16.00 $0.00 0.0% $16.00 AND BE IT RESOLVED that rate increases for summer conference meals be and they are hereby approved as shown below effective July 1, 1993: BREAKFAST BRUNCH LUNCH DINNER Actual 1992-93 Rate Adult Conferences Conference rate $4.55 $4.85 $5.75 $6.90 Guest rate $4.95 $5.30 $6.05 $7.20 Camps &amp; Children Conference rate $3.25 $3.85 $4.40 $5.25 Guest rate $3.60 $4.20 $4.80 $5.60 Amount of Increase Adult Conferences Conference rate $0.10 $0.10 $0.20 $0.25 Guest rate $0.15 $0.10 $0.20 $0.25 Camps &amp; Children Conference rate $0.10 $0.15 $0.15 $0.20 Guest rate $0.10 $0.15 $0.15 $0.20 Percent Increase Adult Conference Conference rate 2.2% 2.1% 3.5% 3.6% Guest rate 3.0% 1.9% 3.3% 3.5% Camps &amp; Children Conference rate 3.1% 3.9% 3.4% 3.8% Guest rate2.8% 3.6% 3.1% 3.6% Proposed 1993-94 Rate Adult Conference Conference rate $4.65 $4.95 $5.95 $7.15 Guest rate $5.10 $5.40 $6.25 $7.45 Camps &amp; Children Conference rate $3.35 $4.00 $4.55 $5.45 Guest rate $3.70 $4.35 $4.95 $5.80 AND BE IT RESOLVED that the Birdwood Pavilion overnight accommodation and the International Center room rates be and they are hereby approved as indicated, effective July 1, 1993: Actual 1992-93 Amount of Increase Percent Increase Proposed Rate 1993-94 Birdwood Pavilion Single, per night $50.00 $0.00 0.0% $50.00 Double, per night $65.00 $0.00 0.0% $65.00 International Center - Public Rooms Use of Rooms &amp; Functions Rooms Main rooms for Main rooms $17.00 ($2.00) -11.8% $15.00 social occasions Living room Dining room Porch/pantry Grounds Main rooms for Main rooms $20.00 $0.00 0.0% $20.00 social occasions Living room with use of Dining room kitchen Porch/pantry Use of kitchen Grounds Use of grounds (only) $20.00 $0.00 0.0% $20.00 Wedding receptions Main rooms $200.00 $0.00 0.0% $200.00 Living room Dining room Porch/pantry Use of kitchen Rehearsal dinners Main rooms $100.00 $0.00 0.0% $100.00 and/or large parties Living room over 80 persons Dining room Porch/pantry Use of kitchen Rain site for Main rooms $35.00 $0.00 0.0% $35.00 wedding receptions Living room Dining room Porch/pantry Use of kitchen Security deposit $35.00 $0.00 0.0% $35.00 Actual 1992-93 Amount of Increase Percent Increase Proposed Rate 1993-94 International Center - Guest Rooms Single per night $18.00 $0.00 0.0% $18.00 per week $92.00 $4.60 5.0% $96.60 per month $285.00 $14.25 5.0% $299.25 Couple per night $25.90 $0.00 0.0% $25.90 per week $129.00 $6.45 5.0% $135.45 per month $397.50 $19.85 5.0% $417.35 Children under 16 (cot) per night $5.00 $0.00 0.0% $5.00 per week $15.00 $0.00 0.0% $15.00 per month $50.00 $0.00 0.0% $50.00 Children in crib per night $2.00 $0.00 0.0% $2.00 per week $10.00 $0.00 0.0% $10.00 per month $25.00 $0.00 0.0% $25.00</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF STUDENT HOUSING RATES FOR 1993-1994 FOR THE ACADEMIC DIVISION The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that rental increases for student housing facilities be and they are hereby approved as shown below, effective beginning with the Session 1993-1994: Facility Actual 1992-93 Per Student Per Session Amount of Increase Percent Increase Proposed 1993-94 Per Student Per Session DORMITORIES Alderman/Observatory Houses Double Room $1,630 $64 3.93% $1,694 Monroe Hill Double Room $1,976 $78 3.95% $2,054 McCormick Road Double Room $1,548 $174 11.24% $1,722 Small Double Room $1,394 $168 12.05% $1,562 Single $1,548 $270 17.44% $1,818 Per Day Rate $8 $0 0.00% $8 (1993-94 rates include new data line service charges: $112 double, $210 single. Excluding this service, the rate increases would be: 4.01% double; 4.02% small double; and 3.88% single) Lawn Small Single $1,860 $74 3.98% $1,934 Regular Single $1,860 $74 3.98% $1,934 Small Single (no fireplace) $1,808 $72 3.98% $1,880 Range Regular Single $1,860 $74 3.98% $1,934 Crackerbox Single Room $1,860 $74 3.98% $1,934 Mary Munford/Roberta Gwathmey Double Room $1,630 $64 3.93% $1,694 Single Room $1,860 $74 3.98% $1,934 Sprigg (Lewis/Hoxton) Double Room $1,860 $74 3.98% $1,934 Single Room $2,016 $80 3.97% $2,096 Single Room (Private Bath) $2,116 $84 3.97% $2,200 New College Double Room $2,094 $76 3.63% $2,170 Single Room $2,248 $80 3.56% $2,328 TWELVE MONTH RATE: Double Room N/A N/A N/A $3,254 Single Room N/A N/A N/A $3,492 Facility Actual 1992-93 Per Student Per Session Amount of Increase Percent Increase Proposed 1993-94 Per Student Per Session Stadium Road (Gooch/Dillard) Double Room $1,860 $186 10.00% $2,046 Single Room $2,016 $290 14.38% $2,306 TWELVE MONTH RATE: Double Room $2,788 N/A N/A N/A Single Room $2,946 N/A N/A N/A (1993-94 rates include new data line service charges: $112 double, $210 single. Excluding this service, the rate increase would be: 3.98% double; and 3.97% single). Barringer House Triple Room $1,800 $72 4.00% $1,872 Double Room $1,900 $76 4.00% $1,976 Single Room $2,100 $84 4.00% $2,184 Max Kade House Single Room $1,800 $70 3.89% $1,870 APARTMENTS - SINGLE STUDENT Copeley Hill Phase III &amp; IV, Brandon, Lambeth Field Two Bedroom $1,928 $76 3.94% $2,004 Three Bedroom $1,850 $74 4.00% $1,924 Faulkner (Hench/Mitchell/Younger) Double $2,000 $80 4.00% $2,080 Single $2,092 $84 4.02% $2,176 Actual 1992-93 Per Month Amount of Increase Percent Increase Proposed 1993-94 Per Month APARTMENTS - FAMILY Copeley Hill Phases I &amp; II One Bedroom $406 $16 3.94% $422 Two Bedroom $450 $18 4.00% $468 Three Bedroom $486 $19 3.91% $505 University Gardens One Bedroom $392 $16 4.08% $408 Two Bedroom $426 $17 3.99% $443 These rates include all utility costs, TV cable in apartments, and post office box rental where applicable.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF INCREASE IN STUDENT HOUSING RATES FOR 1993-1994 FOR CLINCH VALLEY COLLEGE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the dormitory room charges applicable to Clinch Valley College be and they are hereby approved as shown below, effective July 1, 1993: Actual 1992-93 Amt. of Inc. Percent of Inc. Proposed 1993-94 Dormitory Rent Dorms $1,600 $ 80 5.0% $1,680 Apt. House $1,850 $ 90 4.9% $1,940</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF MARKET ADJUSTMENTS FOR HEALTH CARE PROFESSIONALS The following resolution was adopted: WHEREAS legislation enacted by the 1990 General Assembly authorized the Board of Visitors to establish competitive compensation programs for Health Care Professionals employed in the UVA Medical Center; and WHEREAS the Department of Human Resources conducted its semi-annual compensation survey of comparable hospitals in the Northeast, Southeast and Midwest; and WHEREAS the survey results illustrate that compensation for UVA Health Care Professionals is below the compensation provided for similar positions at the hospitals surveyed; RESOLVED that the accompanying Market Adjustments for Health Care Professionals (See Attachment A), be and it is hereby approved, subject to the concurrence of the Secretary of Education of the Commonwealth of Virginia, to become effective on or after April 1, 1993.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF DELEGATION OF AUTHORITY TO APPROVE CERTAIN TRANSACTIONS TO THE SENIOR VICE PRESIDENT AND CHIEF FINANCIAL OFFICER The following resolution was adopted: WHEREAS the Board of Visitors has by previous resolutions, delegated signatory authority to certain University of Virginia officials to approve and execute particular types of agreements and documents on behalf of The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia; WHEREAS the Board desires to amend the delegated signatory authority by increasing the monetary limit relating to contracts for goods and services that require the Board's prior approval; and WHEREAS the Board of Visitors also desires to extend the authority of the Senior Vice President and Chief Financial Officer to act on its behalf with respect to certain types of other transactions which have been routinely presented to the Board for action; RESOLVED that subparagraphs 1(f) and 1(g) of the current policy on delegated signatory authority be and hereby is amended to read as follows: (f) Contracts and any other documents by which the University acquires, or contracts to acquire, by purchase, lease or otherwise, goods for an amount exceeding $5,000,000 in any one year or over the term of the contract; (g) Contracts and any other documents by which the University acquires, or contracts to acquire, services for an amount exceeding $5,000,000 in any one year or over the term of the contract; RESOLVED FURTHER that the Senior Vice President and Chief Financial Officer be and hereby is authorized to approve, with the President's concurrence, the following types of transactions and report them to the Board of Visitors at its next meeting following the action: (1) The write-off of bad debts and free service for the Medical Center, and the write-off of bad debts for the Academic Division and Clinch Valley College; (2) The allocation of funds for debt service, capital outlay and other purposes from unrestricted quasi-endowment income; (3) Acceptance of the financial report pertaining to expenditure of funds from the Pratt Estate; and (4) Establishment of summer conference rates for housing facilities and for meals, overnight accommodation rates for the Birdwood Pavilion, and room rates for the International Center.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DECLARATION OF OFFICIAL INTENT TO ISSUE BONDS TO REIMBURSE EXPENDITURES FOR AMOUNTS NEEDED FOR PLANNING COSTS, ISSUANCE COSTS, RESERVE FUNDS AND OTHER FINANCING EXPENSES ASSOCIATED WITH THE ACQUISITION, CONSTRUCTION, AND EQUIPPING OF THE GILMER FIELD RECREATION CENTER AND THE CHEMISTRY BUILDING ADDITION The following resolution was adopted: WHEREAS, the United States Department of the Treasury has promulgated final regulations in 26 CFR Section 1.103-18 (the "Regulations") governing when the allocation of bond proceeds to reimburse expenditures previously made by an issuer shall be treated as an expenditure of the bond proceeds; and WHEREAS, the IRS Regulations, which are effective for bonds issued after March 2, 1992, require a declaration of official intent by an issuer to provide evidence that, on or prior to the date of payment of expenditures, the issuer intended to reimburse such expenditures with proceeds of its bonds; and WHEREAS, The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia (the "University") issues bonds, from time to time, pursuant to Article X, Section 9(d) of the Constitution of Virginia (the "9(d) Bonds"); and WHEREAS, the University now desires to make such a declaration of official intent as required by the Regulations. NOW THEREFORE, BE IT RESOLVED THAT, pursuant to the Regulations the University hereby declares its intent to reimburse expenditures in accordance with the following: 1. The University reasonably expects to reimburse expenditures incurred for the construction of the Gilmer Field Recreation Center and the Chemistry Building Addition with proceeds of 9(d) Bonds to be issued by the University through the Treasury Board. 2. This resolution is a declaration of official intent under Section 1.103-18 of the Regulations. 3. The maximum principal amount of bonds expected to be issued for the purpose of reimbursing expenditures relating to the Gilmer Field Recreation Center project is $14,000,000 and the maximum principal amount of bonds expected to be issued for the purpose of reimbursing expenditures relating to the Chemistry Building Addition project is $7,706,000. 4. This declaration of intent shall be available for public inspection at the principal office of the University's Office of the Treasurer immediately after the date hereof and shall remain available for public inspection on a reasonable basis until the date of issue of all reimbursement bonds pursuant hereto.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF TECHNICAL AMENDMENT TO PRIOR RESOLUTION ADOPTING THE POLICY ON UNIVERSITY-RELATED FOUNDATIONS The following resolution was adopted: WHEREAS by resolution adopted on October 9, 1992, the Board of Visitors approved the revised Policy on University-Related Foundations ("Policy"); and WHEREAS the Board desires to clarify and confirm the extent of the President's delegated authority to adjust specific Policy requirements in exceptional circumstances; RESOLVED that the delegation provision of the prior resolution be and it is hereby amended in the following respect: "the President be and he is hereby delegated the authority . . . . (2) to adjust the sequence or substance of specific reporting or other requirements of the Policy in order to minimize any undue burden on, or otherwise to accommodate the unique circumstances of, particular foundations . . . ." RESOLVED FURTHER that the President shall confirm any such agreed-upon adjustments of specific Policy requirements in a memorandum to the president of the affected foundation, with copies provided to the Rector, and the Chairs of the Finance and the External Affairs Committees.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">GIFTS, GRANTS AND CONTRACTS The President reported on gifts, grants and contracts. The report was accepted by the Board.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF THE SITING FOR THE CONSTRUCTION OF THE CLINCH VALLEY COLLEGE EDUCATION AND DEVELOPMENT CENTER PROJECT The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the siting for the construction of the Clinch Valley College Education and Development Center project, as illustrated on the site map dated January 15, 1993, prepared by the Office of the Architect for the University, be and it is hereby approved.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF THE ARCHITECTURAL DESIGN GUIDELINES FOR THE CONSTRUCTION OF THE CLINCH VALLEY COLLEGE EDUCATION AND DEVELOPMENT CENTER PROJECT The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the architectural guidelines prepared by the Architect for the University, dated January 15, 1993, for the construction of the Clinch Valley College Education and Development Center project, be and they are hereby approved; RESOLVED FURTHER that the project design shall be presented for further review at the schematic design level of development.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF THE SITING FOR THE CONSTRUCTION OF THE CLINCH VALLEY COLLEGE LIBRARY ADDITION PROJECT The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the siting for the construction of the Clinch Valley College Library Addition project as illustrated on the site map dated January 15, 1993, prepared by the Office of the Architect for the University, be and it is hereby approved.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF THE ARCHITECTURAL DESIGN GUIDELINES FOR THE CONSTRUCTION OF THE CLINCH VALLEY COLLEGE LIBRARY ADDITION PROJECT The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the architectural guidelines prepared by the Architect for the University, dated January 15, 1993, for the construction of the Clinch Valley College Library Addition project be and they are hereby approved; RESOLVED FURTHER that the project design shall be presented for further review at the schematic design level of development.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF EASEMENT FOR VIRGINIA ELECTRIC AND POWER COMPANY ON FONTAINE AVENUE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the deed of easement to be executed on or about February 5, 1993, between Virginia Electric and Power Company (Virginia Power) and The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia, in support of the project to widen Fontaine Avenue across from the Real Estate Foundation's Fontaine Research Park in Albemarle County, be and it is hereby approved; RESOLVED FURTHER that the appropriate officers of the University be and they are hereby authorized to execute said deed of easement.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF THE ARCHITECT SELECTION FOR THE CLINCH VALLEY COLLEGE LIBRARY ADDITION PROJECT The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the firm of Motley + Associates, P.C. of Roanoke, Virginia, be and it is hereby approved for the performance of architectural and engineering services for the design and construction of the Clinch Valley College Library Addition project.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF THE ARCHITECT SELECTION FOR THE CLINCH VALLEY COLLEGE EDUCATION AND DEVELOPMENT CENTER PROJECT The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the firm of Balzer and Associates of Roanoke, Virginia, with design consultants Pasanella + Klein Stolzman + Berg Architects, P.C. of New York, New York, be and it is hereby approved for the performance of architectural and engineering services for the design and construction of the Clinch Valley College Education and Development Center project.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF THE ARCHITECT SELECTION FOR THE CLINCH VALLEY COLLEGE ZEHMER BUILDING RENOVATION PROJECT The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the firm of Thompson &amp; Litton, Inc., of Wise, Virginia, be and it is hereby approved for the performance of architectural and engineering services for the design and construction of the Clinch Valley College Zehmer Building Renovation project.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF BOARD OF VISITORS REPRESENTATIVES TO GOVERNING BOARDS OF UNIVERSITY-RELATED FOUNDATIONS The following resolution was adopted: WHEREAS by prior resolution adopted on October 9, 1992, the Board of Visitors approved the Policy on University-Related Foundations; RESOLVED that the following persons be and they are hereby approved as representatives of the Board of Visitors to the governing boards of the following University-related foundations: APPROVAL OF BOARD OF VISITORS REPRESENTATIVES TO GOVERNING BOARDS OF UNIVERSITY-RELATED FOUNDATIONS - CONTINUED Alumni Patents Foundation Robert J. Mattauch Boar's Head Enterprises, Inc. Robert G. Butcher, Jr. Curry School of Education Foundation Elizabeth D. Morie Darden School Foundation Wallace Stettinius Health Services Foundation Leigh B. Middleditch, Jr. Historic Renovation Corporation Tim R. Rose Law School Foundation Mortimer M. Caplin McIntire School of Commerce Foundation William R. Wilkerson Medical School Foundation Charles W. Miller, M.D. Miller Center Foundation Hovey S. Dabney University of Virginia Foundation Hovey S. Dabney Virginia Auxiliary Services Foundation William S. Battle Virginia Engineering Foundation Patricia M. Kluge Virginia Student Aid Foundation W. James Copeland, Jr.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RESOLUTION REGARDING THE NEUROLOGICAL INSTITUTE OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA AND COMMISSIONING THE PRESIDENT TO DEVELOP A PLAN FOR THE INSTITUTE The following resolution was adopted: WHEREAS the President and the Board of Visitors have been requested to consider the creation of the Neurological Institute of the University of Virginia so that the treatment of neurological disorders and the teaching and research of the neurological sciences may be conducted within a more efficient organizational framework; and WHEREAS the proposal to establish such an Institute is worthy of serious consideration; RESOLVED that The Rector and Visitors request the President to develop a plan for the creation, operation, and management of a Virginia Neurological Institute that is consistent with the purposes, responsibilities, and mission of the University of Virginia; RESOLVED FURTHER that the President present such a plan to the Health Affairs Committee and other appropriate Committee of the Board of Visitors for their review and recommendations to the full Board.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RESOLUTION AUTHORIZING THE SENIOR VICE PRESIDENT AND CHIEF FINANCIAL OFFICER TO ENTER INTO AN AGREEMENT WITH THE DARDEN SCHOOL FOUNDATION FOR THE CONSTRUCTION OF THE NEW DARDEN SCHOOL AND THE ADDITION TO SPONSORS HALL The following resolution was adopted: WHEREAS, the Darden School Foundation wishes to construct a new academic facility for use by the Darden School and a new facility for expansion of Sponsors Hall (collectively, the "Projects"); WHEREAS, by resolution dated January 23, 1992, the Board of Visitors authorized the Senior Vice President and Chief Financial Officer, with the concurrence of the President and the Finance Committee of the Board of Visitors, to enter into a ground lease between the University and the Darden School on certain terms contained within that resolution; WHEREAS, by resolution dated October 31, 1992, the Finance Committee authorized the Senior Vice President and Chief Financial Officer, with the concurrence of the President and Rector, to enter into a lease subject to the terms of the January 23, 1992, resolution of the Board and Visitors and subject to appropriate terms on certain issues addressed in that resolution; WHEREAS, the nature of the transaction has changed and the University now plans to hire the Darden School Foundation as developer and issue up to $40 million in tax-exempt bonds to construct the Projects; WHEREAS, the Darden School Foundation wishes to pay the costs of constructing the Projects in the form of contractual payments over a term not to exceed thirty years; RESOLVED that the Senior Vice President and Chief Financial Officer, with the concurrence of the President and Rector, be and is hereby authorized to execute and deliver such documents, including without limitation a Letter of Understanding or other agreement, and take such action as may be necessary or desirable in connection with the authorization to issue up to $40 million in general revenue bonds to finance the cost of the Projects.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DECLARATION OF OFFICIAL INTENT TO ISSUE BONDS TO REIMBURSE EXPENDITURES FOR AMOUNTS NEEDED FOR PLANNING COSTS, ISSUANCE COSTS, RESERVE FUNDS AND OTHER FINANCING EXPENSES ASSOCIATED WITH THE ACQUISITION, CONSTRUCTION, AND EQUIPPING OF THE DARDEN SCHOOL REPLACEMENT FACILITY AND SPONSORS HALL ADDITION PROJECT The following resolution was adopted: WHEREAS, the United States Department of the Treasury has promulgated final regulations in 26 CFR Section 1.103-18 (the "Regulations") governing when the allocation of bond proceeds to reimburse expenditures previously made by an issuer shall be treated as an expenditure of the bond proceeds; and WHEREAS, the IRS Regulations, which are effective for bonds issued after March 2, 1992, require a declaration of official intent by an issuer to provide evidence that, on or prior to the date of payment of expenditures, the issuer intended to reimburse such expenditures with proceeds of its bonds; and WHEREAS, The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia (the "University") issues bonds, from time to time, pursuant to Article X, Section 9(d) of the Constitution of Virginia (the "9(d) Bonds"); and WHEREAS, the University now desires to make such a declaration of official intent as required by the Regulations. NOW THEREFORE, BE IT RESOLVED THAT, pursuant to the Regulations the University hereby declares its intent to reimburse expenditures in accordance with the following: 1. The University reasonably expects to reimburse expenditures incurred for the construction of the Darden School Replacement Facility and Sponsors Hall Addition Project with proceeds of 9(d) Bonds to be issued by the University through the Treasury Board. 2. This resolution is a declaration of official intent under Section 1.103-18 of the Regulations. 3. The maximum principal amount of bonds expected to be issued for the purpose of reimbursing expenditures relating to the Darden School Replacement Facility and Sponsors Hall Addition Project is $45,000,000. 4. This declaration of intent shall be available for public inspection at the principal office of the University's Office of the Treasurer immediately after the date hereof and shall remain available for public inspection on a reasonable basis until the date of issue of all reimbursement bonds pursuant hereto.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RESOLUTION APPROVING THE ESTABLISHMENT OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA FOUNDATION The following resolution was adopted: WHEREAS, it is proposed a new foundation be established to perform the functions of the University of Virginia Real Estate Foundation among other prescribed purposes: WHEREAS, it is proposed that the new foundation be named the "University of Virginia Foundation," be organized as a Section 501(c)(3) Virginia nonstock corporation solely and exclusively for the benefit of the University of Virginia, and be operated to fulfill the following purposes: ? provide administration services to University entities, University-related foundations, or other entities which are involved in activities in support of the University; ? engage in any and all matters pertaining to real property for the benefit of the University; ? use and administer gifts, grants, bequests and devises for the benefit of the University; and ? engage in any and all lawful activities consistent with the corporate charter; WHEREAS, it is further proposed that the University of Virginia Real Estate Foundation become a subsidiary of the newly-created University of Virginia Foundation; and WHEREAS, in accordance with the Policy on University-Related Foundations, the Board of Visitors has reviewed the purposes of the University of Virginia Foundation, its proposed organizational format, the scope of its activities, and the provision for representation of the Board and of the President on the Foundation's governing board; RESOLVED that the establishment of the University of Virginia Foundation be and is hereby approved subject to the Foundation's and its subsidiary's continued compliance with the requirements of the Policy on University-Related Foundations; and RESOLVED FURTHER that the organization and operation of the University Real Estate Foundation as a subsidiary of the University of Virginia Foundation be and is hereby approved. On motion, the meeting adjourned at 3:30 p.m. Respectfully submitted, Alexander G. Gilliam, Jr. Secretary AGG:jb</field>
      <field name="fulltext">(ATTACHMENT A) University of Virginia Medical Center Proposed Salary Ranges * * Ranges will be adjusted by the increase amount. Actual employee salary increases may differ based upon salary compression and equity considerations. The Medical Center will optimize retention and recruitment of HCP's by applying relocation assistance which is competitive with types of assistance offered by others in the tertiary care labor market. Class Code Class Title Proposed Range Increase Proposed Minimum Maximum 95131 HCP-Administrative Practical Nurse 3.0 19458 29709 95051 HCP-Anesthetist 5.0 49399 75428 95052 HCP-Anesthetist Asst Head 5.0 54004 82454 95053 HCP-Anesthetist Head 5.0 54004 82454 95045 HCP-Asst. Dir, Respir Care Services 4.0 31728 48445 95055 HCP-Audiologist 3.0 25924 39581 95086 HCP-Autopsy Pathologist's Assist 3.0 31575 48211 95109 HCP-Bone Marrow Trans Tech 3.0 23256 35511 95118 HCP-Bone Marrow Trans Tech Sr 3.0 27795 42438 95115 HCP-Cardiac Cath Tech 3.0 21276 32482 95116 HCP-Cardiac Cath Tech Sr 3.0 23256 35511 95119 HCP-Cast Tech 3.0 21276 32482 95146 HCP-Cert Nurse Pract (Inpat) 3.0 34042 51976 95157 HCP-Cert Nurse Pract (OP) 3.0 32703 49932 95158 HCP-Cert Nurse Practitioner Sr 3.0 35750 54584 95003 HCP-Clin Perfusion Assistant 3.0 23257 35511 95001 HCP-Clinical Perfusionist 3.0 0 85696 95002 HCP-Clinical Perfusionist Chief 3.0 0 91052 95094 HCP-Clinical Pharmacy Specialist 4.0 42972 65610 95063 HCP-Clinical Social Work Supv 3.0 27794 42438 95061 HCP-Clinical Social Worker 3.0 21275 32483 95062 HCP-Clinical Social Worker Sr 3.0 25425 38820 95123 HCP-CV Monitor Tech 3.0 20859 31846 95124 HCP-CV Monitor Tech Sr 3.0 22800 34815 95125 HCP-CV Monitor Tech Supv 3.0 27250 41606 95104 HCP-Cytotechnologist 3.0 26303 40163 95105 HCP-Cytotechnologist Senior 3.0 29723 45384 95106 HCP-Cytotechnologist Supervisor 3.0 32486 49604 95007 HCP-Dental Hygienist 3.0 23827 36382 95019 HCP-Echocardiography Spec, Chief 3.0 28340 43270 95018 HCP-Echocardiography Spec, Sr 3.0 25924 39581 95017 HCP-Echocardiography Spec, Staff 3.0 23712 36208 95107 HCP-EEG Tech 3.0 17802 27181 95108 HCP-EEG Tech Supv 3.0 21276 32482 95112 HCP-EKG Supv 3.0 17802 27181 95111 HCP-EKG Tech 3.0 14896 22745 University of Virginia Medical Center Proposed Salary Ranges* Class Code Class Title Proposed Range Increase Proposed Minimum Maximum 95079 HCP-Electrocard Stress Test Tch Sr 3.0 23256 35511 95054 HCP-Electrocard Stress Test Tech 3.0 17802 27181 95102 HCP-Emer Med Tech Spec 3.0 18713 28572 95103 HCP-Emer Med Tech Sr 3.0 20457 31234 95114 HCP-Epidemiology Tech Adv 3.0 27795 42438 95113 HCP-Epidemiology Tech Sr 3.0 23256 35511 95189 HCP-Histo Tech 2.0 22362 34146 95193 HCP-Histo Tech Manager 0.0 31938 48764 95191 HCP-Histo Tech Senior 2.0 26725 40805 95192 HCP-Histo Tech Supv. (incl regrade) 11.5 29214 44606 95065 HCP-Laboratory Specialist 3.0 21276 32482 95067 HCP-Laboratory Specialist Adv 3.0 27795 42438 95068 HCP-Laboratory Specialist Mgr 3.0 33216 50716 95066 HCP-Laboratory Specialist Sr 3.0 23256 35511 95069 HCP-Lithotripter Technologist 3.0 25426 38820 95071 HCP-Med Tech 3.0 23033 35170 95075 HCP-Med Tech Lab Admn 3.0 39312 50024 95074 HCP-Med Tech Mgr 3.0 32896 50227 95072 HCP-Med Tech Sr 3.0 27527 42029 95073 HCP-Med Tech Supv 3.0 30091 45946 95221 HCP-Nonregistered Rad Tech 3.0 21275 32483 95174 HCP-Nutrition Program Dir 3.0 32564 49721 95172 HCP-Nutritionist Specialist 3.0 24927 38059 95173 HCP-Nutritionist Specialist Sr 3.0 29788 45482 95011 HCP-Occupational Ther Asst 4.5 18858 28794 95012 HCP-Occupational Therapist 4.5 29595 45187 95013 HCP-Occupational Therapist Sr 4.5 32353 49397 95016 HCP-Occupational Therapy Dir 4.5 41456 6297 95014 HCP-Occupational Therapy Supv 4.5 35368 54001 95088 HCP-Operating Room Tech 3.0 16285 24865 95165 HCP-Ophthalmic Asst (certified) 3.0 19461 29715 95048 HCP-Ophthalmic Tech Trainee 3.0 19461 29715 95166 HCP-Ophthalmic Tech (certified) 3.0 21276 95049 HCP-Ophthalmic Technologist 3.0 23256 95122 HCP-Organ Transplant Coord Sr 3.0 27795 95121 HCP-Organ Transplant Coordinator 3.0 23256 95089 HCP-Orthoptist 3.0 19080 95117 HCP-Pain Mgmt Med Tech 3.0 21276 95164 HCP-Patient Care Specialist 3.0 19462 95081 HCP-Pharmacist 4.0 35958 95082 HCP-Pharmacist Senior 4.0 39309 95083 HCP-Pharmacist Supv 4.0 42972 95084 HCP-Pharmacy Assistant Director 4.0 46976 95022 HCP-Physical Therapist 4.5 30460 95021 HCP-Physical Therapist Asst 4.5 19221 29347 University of Virginia Medical Center Proposed Salary Ranges* Class Code Class Title Proposed Range Increase Proposed Minimum Maximum 95023 HCP-Physical Therapist Sr 4.5 33296 50842 95025 HCP-Physical Therapy Asst Dir 4.5 38652 59015 95026 HCP-Physical Therapy Director 4.5 42253 64515 95024 HCP-Physical Therapy Supv 4.5 36401 55578 95087 HCP-Physician's Assistant 3.0 31575 48211 95147 HCP-Practical Nurse 3.0 16285 24865 95148 HCP-Practical Nurse Sr 3.0 17802 27182 95077 HCP-Prosthetic/Orthotic Assistant 3.0 22580 34477 95078 HCP-Prosthetic/Orthotic Certified 3.0 29499 45041 95064 HCP-Prosthetic/Orthotic Cert. Supv 3.0 34711 52761 95076 HCP-Prosthetic/Orthotic Tech 3.0 19843 30298 95091 HCP-Psychologist 3.0 27250 41606 95127 HCP-Pulmonary Lab Tech 3.0 21693 33119 95128 HCP-Pulmonary Lab Tech Sr 3.0 23712 36208 95129 HCP-Pulmonary Lab Tech Supv 3.0 28340 43270 95231 HCP-Rad Dosimetrist-RT 15.0 33362 50940 95246 HCP-Rad Educ Asst Dir 3.0 30384 46392 95187 HCP-Rad Tech Asst Chief-CT 4.0 30679 46842 95197 HCP-Rad Tech Asst Chief-Diag 3.0 30384 46392 95207 HCP-Rad Tech Asst Chief-MRI 4.0 30679 46842 95217 HCP-Rad Tech Asst Chief-NM 4.0 30679 46842 95227 HCP-Rad Tech Asst Chief-RT 15.0 33579 51269 95237 HCP-Rad Tech Asst Chief-SP 4.0 30679 46842 95243 HCP-Rad Tech Asst Chief-US 4.0 30679 46842 95188 HCP-Rad Tech Chief-CT 4.0 33538 51207 95198 HCP-Rad Tech Chief-Diag 3.0 33216 50715 95218 HCP-Rad Tech Chief-NM 4.0 33538 51207 95228 HCP-Rad Tech Chief-RT 15.0 36708 56046 95238 HCP-Rad Tech Chief-SP 4.0 33538 51207 95186 HCP-Rad Tech Sr-CT 4.0 26679 40734 95196 HCP-Rad Tech Sr-Diag 3.0 25799 39391 95206 HCP-Rad Tech Sr-MRI 4.0 26679 40734 95216 HCP-Rad Tech Sr-NM 4.0 28476 43479 95226 HCP-Rad Tech Sr-RT 15.0 33362 50940 95236 HCP-Rad Tech Sr-SP 4.0 28476 43479 95242 HCP-Rad Tech Sr-US 4.0 28476 43479 95185 HCP-Rad Tech Staff-CT 4.0 24403 37262 95195 HCP-Rad Tech Staff-Diag 3.0 23599 36034 95205 HCP-Rad Tech Staff-MRI 4.0 24403 37262 95215 HCP-Rad Tech Staff-NM 4.0 26049 39774 95225 HCP-Rad Tech Staff-RT 15.0 30520 46597 95235 HCP-Rad Tech Staff-SP 4.0 26049 39774 95241 HCP-Rad Tech Staff-US 4.0 26049 39774 95219 HCP-Rad Tech Sup-Nuclear 4.0 30679 46842 95249 HCP-Radiology Education Dir 3.0 33216 50715 University of Virginia Medical Center Proposed Salary Ranges* Class Code Class Title Proposed Range Increase Proposed Minimum Maximum 95181 HCP-Radiology Manager 4.0 38100 58173 95183 HCP-Radiology Physics Spec Sr 4.0 26679 40734 95244 HCP-Radiology School Dir (RT) 3.0 32192 49153 95247 HCP-Radiology School Director 3.0 30384 46392 95034 HCP-Recreation Therapist Supv 3.0 25924 39581 95032 HCP-Recreational Therapist 3.0 19843 30298 95033 HCP-Recreational Therapist Sr 3.0 23712 36208 95142 HCP-Reg Nurse Clin A (InPat) 3.0 29354 44819 95152 HCP-Reg Nurse Clin A (OutPat) 3.0 27192 41519 95161 HCP-Reg Nurse Clin A (staff ed) 3.0 28590 43654 95143 HCP-Reg Nurse Clin B (InPat) 3.0 32089 48996 95153 HCP-Reg Nurse Clin B (OutPat) 3.0 29726 45388 95162 HCP-Reg Nurse Clin B (staff ed) 3.0 31254 47721 95144 HCP-Reg Nurse Coord (InPat) 0.0 34713 53001 95154 HCP-Reg Nurse Coord (OutPat) 3.0 32497 49617 95145 HCP-Reg Nurse Mgr (InPat) 3.0 42729 65238 95155 HCP-Reg Nurse Mgr (OutPat) 3.0 38835 59294 95156 HCP-Registered Clin Nurse Spec 3.0 39694 60606 95169 HCP-Registered Nurse, Transplant 3.0 31279 47763 95163 HCP-Registered Nurse Coord (staff 3.0 34167 52167 95141 HCP-Registered Nurse (InPat) 3.0 26852 40998 95151 HCP-Registered Nurse (OutPat) 3.0 24874 37979 95159 HCP-Registered Nurse (staff ed) 3.0 26153 39931 95132 HCP-Renal Dialysis Tech 3.0 20457 31234 95133 HCP-Renal Dialysis Tech Sr 3.0 22362 34146 95134 HCP-Renal Dialysis Tech Supv 3.0 26725 40806 95201 HCP-RN Clin 1 Salaried 3.0 29252 44665 95202 HCP-RN Clin 2 Salaried 3.0 31979 48828 95203 HCP-RN Clin 3 Salaried 3.0 34959 53377 95095 HCP-RN Clinician 1 3.0 26594 40604 95096 HCP-RN Clinician 2 3.0 29072 44388 95097 HCP-RN Clinician 3 3.0 31780 48525 95098 HCP-RN Clinician 4 3.0 37259 56887 95099 HCP-RN Clinician 5 3.0 40723 62178 95177 HCP-Speech Pathologist 3.0 25924 39581 95179 HCP-Speech Pathologist Supv 3.0 28340 43270 95041 HCP-Staff Technician-Respir Care Se 4.0 19040 29070 95042 HCP-Staff Therapist-Respir Care Ser 4.0 24286 37084 95044 HCP-Supervisor, Respir Care Service 4.0 29024 44315 95043 HCP-Therapist Sr, Respir Care Servi 4.0 26550 40539 95149 HCP-UVA POOL RN (hourly rate) 0.0 18 22 95139 HCP-Venipuncture Manager 3.0 23256 35511 95136 HCP-Venipuncture Tech 3.0 16285 24865 95138 HCP-Venipuncture Tech Supv 3.0 21276 32482 University of Virginia Medical Center Proposed Salary Ranges* Class Code Class Title Proposed Range Increase Proposed Minimum Maximum 95027 HCP-Administr Resident - 1st Year 5.0 0 23611 95046 HCP-Administr Resident - 2nd Year 5.0 0 24792 95028 HCP-Resident - First Year 5.0 0 27072 95029 HCP-Resident - Second Year 5.0 0 28579 95031 HCP-Resident - Third Year 5.0 0 30092 95035 HCP-Resident - Fourth Year 5.0 0 31417 95036 HCP-Resident - Fifth Year 5.0 0 33107 95037 HCP-Resident - Sixth Year 5.0 0 34664 95038 HCP-Resident - Seventh Year 5.0 0 36823 95039 HCP-Resident - Eighth Year 5.0 0 38951 95008 HCP-Dentistry Resident 3.0 25329 27934 95047 HCP-Eye Clinic Extern 3.0 4255 4255 95057 HCP-NETS Resident 3.0 0 11586 95058 HCP-Patient &amp; Fam Couns Resident 3.0 17139 19282 95059 HCP-Counseling Center Intern 3.0 12854 14140 95092 HCP-Clinical Psychology Resident 3.0 0 12794 95093 HCP-Pharmacy Resident 3.0 0 24638</field>
      <field name="fulltext">At a meeting of the Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia held on February 6, 1993 a roll call vote was taken immediately following an executive session. Members voting "yes" certify that to the best of the Member's knowledge (1) only public business matters lawfully exempted were discussed in closed session; and (2) only public business matters identified in the public motion by which the executive or closed meeting were discussed. In accordance with the law, any member of the public body who believes that there was a departure from the foregoing shall so state prior to the vote indicating "the substance of the departure". Any such statements are recorded below under "comments". NAME VOTE (yes or no) COMMENTS W. L. Lyons Brown, Jr. yes Robert G. Butcher, Jr. yes Mortimer M. Caplin yes N. Thomas Connally yes Hovey S. Dabney yes Warner N. Dalhouse yes Daniel A. Hoffler yes J. Thomas Hulvey yes Evans B. Jessee yes Mrs. Patricia M. Kluge yes Arnold H. Leon yes Leigh B. Middleditch, Jr. yes Mrs. Elizabeth D. Morie yes Freddie W. Nicholas, Sr. yes S. Buford Scott yes Albert H. Small yes J. Scott Ballenger yes</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ADDENDUM TO THE OFFICIAL MINUTES OF THE MEETING OF THE BOARD OF VISITORS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA Meeting Date: February 6, 1993 CERTIFICATION OF EXECUTIVE MEETING WHEREAS, the Board of Visitors has convened an executive meeting on this date pursuant to an affirmative recorded vote and in accordance with the provisions of The Virginia Freedom of Information Act; and WHEREAS, Section 2.1-344.1 of the Code of Virginia requires a certification by this Board of Visitors that such executive meeting was conducted in conformity with Virginia law; NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED that the Board of Visitors hereby certifies that, to the best of each member's knowledge, (i) only public business matters lawfully exempted from open meeting requirements by Virginia law were discussed in the executive meeting to which this certification resolution applies, and (ii) only such public business matters as were identified in the motion convening the executive meeting were heard, discussed or considered by the Board of Visitors. VOTE AYES: 17 NAYS: 0 [For each nay vote, the substance of the departure from the requirements of the Act should be described] ABSENT DURING VOTE: 0 ABSENT DURING MEETING: 0 Alexander G. Gilliam, Jr. Secretary, Board of Visitors, University of Virginia</field>
   </doc>
</add>