<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">University of Virginia, Board of Visitors</field>
      <field name="author_facet">University of Virginia, Board of Visitors</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">university of virginia board of visitors</field>
      <field name="author_text">University of Virginia, Board of Visitors</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1980's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/2006_01/uvaGenText/tei/bov_1985-03-29.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240342</field>
      <field name="date_text">March 29, 1985</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Board of Visitors Minutes, 1817-2002</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Board of Visitors Minutes, 1817-2002</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:183728</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Board of Visitors minutes. March 29, 1985</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Minutes</field>
      <field name="subject_text">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Minutes</field>
      <field name="title_display">Board of Visitors minutes.  March 29, 1985</field>
      <field name="title_facet">board of visitors minutes</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">board of visitors minutes</field>
      <field name="title_text">Board of Visitors minutes.  March 29, 1985</field>
      <field name="year_display">March 29, 1985</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1985-03-29</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1985</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:183728&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;public&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:183728&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;serial volume&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;University of Virginia, Board of Visitors&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;university of virginia, board of visitors&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Board of Visitors minutes. March 29, 1985&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;board of visitors minutes&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;March 29, 1985&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1985-03-29&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="corpname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia, Board of Visitors&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Board of Visitors minutes&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;March 29, 1985&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="edition"&gt;Public minutes&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa call number"&gt;Accession# RG-1/1/&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;a2846310&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;1 v.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="AAT"&gt;Minutes&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;The official minutes contain salary information. Access to minutes containing salary information will be granted only under the procedures of the Virginia Freedom of Information Act (Code of Virginia-2.1-340 ff.) or if permission is granted by the Secretary of the Board. Researchers interested in obtaining access to these records should direct a request in writing to the Office of the Legal Adviser, Madison Hall, University of Virginia. These public minutes have had salary information deleted and bear no restrictions.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Board of Visitors' minutes, Accession # RG-1/1/, Special Collections Dept., University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Minutes of meetings of the university's governing body which is the legal owner and operator of the institution. Recorded in the minutes are appointments and other personnel decisions concerning faculty, decisions about construction of facilities, gifts to the university, and all other board actions, decisions and resolutions.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Board of Visitors minutes&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;1985-03-29&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville, Virginia&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia Library&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;2005&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©2005 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Publicly accessible&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 190 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-BoardOfVisitorsMinutes"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">OFFICIAL MINUTES - TENTATIVE Subject to the Approval of the Board of Visitors THE RECTOR AND VISITORS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA March 29, 1985 The Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia met at 1:00 p.m., in Open Session on March 28, 1985, in the East Oval Room of the Rotunda with the following persons present: Rector Fred G. Pollard, President Frank L. Hereford, Jr., President-Elect Robert M. O'Neil, and John S. Battle, Jr., William M. Camp, Jr., Mrs. George M. Cochran, James S. Cremins, Joshua P. Darden, Jr., Henry A. Dudley, Edward E. Elson, William R. Harvey, Carl W. Smith, James L. Trinkle, E. Massie Valentine, Neal O. Wade, Jr., Edgar N. Weaver, Gregory C. Whitehead, Jesse B. Wilson, III, and Thomas E. Worrell, Jr. Messrs. Ray C. Hunt, Jr., Ernest H. Ern, Raymond M. Haas, Edwin E. Floyd, William H. Muller, Marion B. Peavey, and George G. Grattan, IV, were also present. The Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia reconvened in Open Session on March 29, 1985, at 2:30 p.m., in the East Oval Room of the Rotunda with the following persons present: Rector Fred G. Pollard, President Frank L. Hereford, Jr., President-Elect Robert M. O'Neil, John S. Battle, Jr., William M. Camp, Jr., Mrs. George M. Cochran, James S. Cremins, Joshua P. Darden, Jr., Edward E. Elson, Carl W. Smith, James L. Trinkle, Neal O. Wade, Jr., Edgar N. Weaver, Gregory C. Whitehead, Jesse B. Wilson, III, and Thomas E. Worrell. Absent: Henry A. Dudley, William R. Harvey, and E. Massie Valentine. Messrs. Ray C. Hunt, Jr., Raymond M. Haas, William H. Muller, Marion B. Peavey, and George G. Grattan, IV, were also present. The Minutes of the meeting of January 25, 1985, previously distributed were approved as corrected.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">MOTIONS FOR EXECUTIVE SESSIONS The following motions were unanimously adopted by vote of all Visitors present: (a) That the Educational Policy Committee of the Board of Visitors go into Executive Session for Item Number 13 on that Committee's agenda for the discussion and evaluation of the performance of University departments or schools if individual employees might be affected by the evaluation. (b) That the Buildings and Grounds Committee of the Board of Visitors go into Executive Session for Item Number 6 on that Committee's agenda for the following reason: to discuss or consider the acquisition or disposition of real property for a public purpose if that discussion could affect the value of property owned by or desirable for ownership by the University as provided for in Section 2.1-344 (a) (2) of the Virginia Code. (c) That the Board of Visitors go into Executive Session for consultation with legal counsel pertaining to actual and potential litigation, or other legal matters within the jurisdiction of the Board, as provided for in Section 2.1-344 (a) (6) of the Virginia Code. Following a recess for Executive Session of the Board of Visitors, the Open Session continued at 2:30 p.m., on March 29, 1985.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ELECTIONS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following persons be and they are hereby elected to the faculty: Mr. Donald E. Brown as Acting Assistant Professor of Systems Engineering, for the period of January 1, 1985 through December 31, 1985. Mr. John M. Duva as Acting Assistant Professor of Applied Mathematics, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1985. Mr. William J. Finan as Lecturer in Religious Studies, for one semester, effective January 16, 1985. Dr. Henry F. Frierson, Jr. as Instructor in Pathology, for one year, effective July 1, 1985. Ms. Alyson C. Hagy as Lecturer in English, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1985. Mr. Paul Hansma as Visiting Professor of Physics, for the period April 1, 1985 through April 30, 1985. Miss Cassandra F. Harding as Instructor in Nursing, for one semester, effective January 16, 1985. Mr. Marian L. Kostecki as Lecturer in Sociology, for one semester, effective January 16, 1985. Mr. Richard A. Kovatch as Lecturer, General Faculty, for three years, effective January 1, 1985. Dr. Marguerite C. Lippert as Assistant Professor of Urology, for three years, effective January 1, 1985. Mr. Thomas J. Loving as Lecturer, General Faculty, for three years, effective January 1, 1985. Ms. Jere K. Mundy as Instructor, General Medical Faculty, for the period March 16, 1985 through June 30, 1986. Mr. Kwong-Tai Ng as Research Assistant Professor of Electrical Engineering, for the period January 16, 1985 through May 31, 1985. Mr. John A. Norton as Acting Assistant Professor of Business Administration, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1985. Mr. John F. Plummer, III as Visiting Associate Professor of English, for one semester, effective January 16, 1985. Mr. Trilochan Pradhan as Visiting Professor of Physics, for one semester, effective January 16, 1985. Ms. Mary L. Price as Instructor in Internal Medicine, General Medical Faculty, for the period January 16, 1985 through June 30, 1985. Dr. R. Beverly Raney, Jr. as Professor of Pediatrics, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Wilfrid J. Rollman as Lecturer in History, for one academic year, effective January 16, 1985. Mr. Gordon Slade as Lecturer in Mathematics, for one semester, effective January 16, 1985. Ms. Nancy J. Smith as Assistant Professor, General Medical Faculty, The Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, for the period February 16, 1985 through February 15, 1986. Dr. William D. Spotnitz as Assistant Professor of Surgery, for three years, effective February 1, 1985. Ms. Eileen M. Stephens as Research Assistant Professor of Physiology, for one year, effective January 1, 1985. Mr. John A. Wert as Associate Professor of Materials Science, for three years, effective January 1, 1985.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ELECTION OF PART-TIME FACULTY Mr. Michael D. Aeschliman as Lecturer in English, for one semester, effective January 16, 1985. Mr. Richard C. Bausch as Lecturer in English, for one semester, effective January 16, 1985. Mr. John W. Bebout as Lecturer in Environmental Sciences, for one semester, effective January 16, 1985. Ms. Margaret W. Bemiss as Lecturer in Architecture, for one semester, effective January 16, 1985. Mr. Carl H. Cofer as Visiting Lecturer, for one semester, effective January 16, 1985. Mr. John L. Crawford as Visiting Professor of Materials Science, for the period December 1, 1984 through April 15, 1985. Ms. Tannis Gibson as Lecturer in Music, for one semester, effective September 1, 1984. Ms. Martha D. Goebel as Lecturer in Education, for one semester, effective January 16, 1985. Ms. R. Claire Guthrie as Lecturer in Law, for one semester, effective January 16, 1985. Mr. Harry L. Gutman as Visiting Professor of Law, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1984. Ms. Cathryn A. Hankla as Lecturer in English, for one semester, effective January 16, 1985. Ms. Marlene E. Heck as Lecturer in Architectural History, for one semester, effective January 16, 1985. Mr. David L. Heilberg as Lecturer in Law, for the period January 1, 1985 through May 31, 1986. Ms. Rebekah B. Karp as Instructor, General Faculty, for the period January 2, 1985 through April 5, 1985. Ms. Nancy C. Kern as Lecturer in Law, for the period January 1, 1985 through May 31, 1986. Mr. Steven J. Klein as Instructor, General Faculty, for the period January 2, 1985 through April 5, 1985. Mr. Om Prakash as Visiting Professor of Economics, for one semester, effective January 16, 1985. Ms. Hollace H. Quarles as Instructor, General Medical Faculty, The Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, for the period February 21, 1985 through August 31, 1985. Ms. Lisa C. Rose as Instructor, General Faculty, for the period January 2, 1985 through April 5, 1985. Mr. Patrick F. Ryan as Instructor in Environmental Sciences, for one semester, effective January 16, 1985. Ms. Laurie Shaul as Lecturer in Commerce, for one semester, effective January 16, 1985. Ms. Barbara Steinberg as Instructor in Economics, for one semester, effective January 16, 1985.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ELECTION OF NON-SALARIED FACULTY Mr. Dennis R. Browne as Lecturer in Slavic Languages and Literatures, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1984. Mr. Marc J. Feldman as Research Associate Professor of Electrical Engineering, for the period January 16, 1985 through January 15, 1986. Mr. Pricha Hongskrailers as Visiting Scholar in Government and Foreign Affairs, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1985. Mr. Michael S. Hopkins as Visiting Scholar in Environmental Sciences, for the period February 15, 1985 through October 31, 1985. Mr. Paul L. Hundley as Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Western State, for three years, effective March 1, 1985. Dr. William E. Kelly as Visiting Scholar, Department of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, for one year, effective January 16, 1985. Mr. Everett M. Ressler as Scholar in Residence in Sociology, for the period March 1, 1985 through July 31, 1986. Mr. Mark Rush as Lecturer in Music, for one semester, effective September 1, 1984. Mr. Robert E. Stroud as Lecturer in Law, for one semester, effective January 16, 1985. Mr. Hisao Tanaka as Visiting Scholar in English, for the period August 15, 1985 through August 14, 1986. Mr. Jos C. Van Meurs as Visiting Scholar in English, for the period July 1, 1985 through December 31, 1985. Mr. Michael J. Wirtz as Instructor in Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering, for one semester, effective January 16, 1985. Mr. James B. Wolff as Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Western State, for three years, effective March 1, 1985. Mr. Hiroto Yamagami as Visiting Scholar in Economics, for one year, effective April 1, 1985. Mr. Richard C. York as Research Associate Professor of Engineering Physics, for three academic years, effective January 16, 1985. Mr. Yoshihide Yoshizu as Visiting Scholar in Religious Studies, for one semester, effective January 16, 1985. Dr. Joseph J. Zealberg as Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Southwestern State Hospital, for three years, effective July 1, 1985.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ELECTION OF CLINICAL FACULTY Mrs. Brenda C. Carper as Clinical Instructor in Nursing, for the period January 1, 1985 through June 30, 1988. Miss Marilu Dixon as Clinical Instructor in Nursing, for the period February 1, 1985 through June 30, 1988. Mrs. Maria L. Knapp as Clinical Instructor in Nursing, for the period February 1, 1985 through June 30, 1986. Dr. John M. Mathis as Clinical Assistant Professor of Radiology, Veterans Administration Medical Center, Salem Program, for the period April 1, 1985 through June 30, 1987. Dr. David B. Moga as Clinical Assistant Professor of Orthopaedics and Rehabilitation, for one year, effective March 1, 1985. Ms. Kathleen M. Powers as Clinical Instructor in Nursing, for the period January 1, 1985 through June 30, 1988. Mrs. Elaine S. Venn as Clinical Instructor in Nursing, for the period February 1, 1985 through June 30, 1986.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CANCELLATION OF THE ELECTION OF MR. HAFIZ M. AYOUB The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the election of Mr. Hafiz M. Ayoub as Visiting Professor of Internal Medicine, for the period October 16, 1984 through November 15, 1984, as approved by the Board on January 25, 1985, be and it is hereby cancelled.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CANCELLATION OF THE ELECTION OF MR. KENNETH I. KELLERMANN The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the election of Mr. Kenneth I. Kellermann as Research Professor of Astronomy, for one year, effective September 1, 1984, as approved by the Board on January 25, 1985, be and it is hereby cancelled.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CORRECTION IN THE ELECTION OF DR. JORGE R. RIVERA-IRIAS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the election of Dr. Jorge R. Rivera-Irias as approved by the Board on January 25, 1985, be changed to read as follows: Dr. Jorge R. Rivera-Irias as Assistant Professor of Surgery, Salem Program, for the period October 1, 1984 through June 30, 1987.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACTIONS RELATING TO CHAIRHOLDERS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the actions relating to chairholders be and they are hereby approved as shown below: (a) Elections of Chaired Professors Mr. Edward J. Logue as Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation Professor of Architecture, for the period February 16, 1985 through April 12, 1985. Mr. Richard W. McEnally as Arthur J. Morris Visiting Professor of Commerce, for one semester, effective January 16, 1986. Mr. Richard L. Rubenstein as Edgar M. Bronfman Visiting Professor of Modern Judaic Studies, effective September 1, 1985, for one semester. Dr. David D. Stone as Distinguished Professor of Internal Medicine, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Robert L. Wilken as Commonwealth Professor of the History of Christianity, effective September 1, 1985. (b) Re-election of Chaired Professor Mr. Walter J. Wadlington, III, James Madison Professor of Law, and Professor of Legal Medicine, School of Medicine, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. (c) Retirements of Chaired Professors Dr. Harold Carron, Distinguished Professor of Anesthesiology, effective December 31, 1984. He has been a member of the faculty since August 17, 1970. Mr. Edwin S. Cohen, Joseph M. Hartfield Professor of Law, effective May 31, 1985. He has been a member of the faculty since September 1, 1963. Mr. Frank W. Finger, alumni Professor of Psychology, effective May 31, 1985. He has been a member of the faculty since March 1, 1942. Mr. Emerson G. Spies, Mary and Daniel Loughran Professor of Law, effective May 31, 1985. He has been a member of the faculty since April 1, 1946. Mr. David Thompson, Frank S. Kaulback, Jr., Professor of Commerce, effective May 31, 1985. He has been a member of the faculty since September 1, 1976.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RE-ELECTIONS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following persons be and they are hereby re-elected to the faculty: Ms. Janet H. Allaire as Assistant Professor of Pediatrics, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Elias Awad as Professor of Commerce, effective September 1, 1985. Mr. Alex J. Baertschi as Associate Professor of Physiology, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Nissim Bar Yaacov as Scholar in Residence, Department of Government and Foreign Affairs, for one semester, effective January 16, 1985. Ms. Ann L. Bayer as Assistant Professor of Microbiology, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Ms. Sharon J. Beckman-Brindley as Assistant Professor of Pediatrics, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Richard S. Benner as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1985. Mr. Bruce C. Black as Research Assistant Professor of Biology, for one year, effective March 1, 1985. Dr. Charles M. Boggs as Assistant Professor of Surgery, Salem Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Ms. Claire P. Bolfing as Acting Assistant Professor of Commerce, for one academic year, effective January 16, 1985. Mr. James M. Campbell as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, Alderman Library, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. James P. Cohoon as Assistant Professor of Computer Science, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1985. Ms. L. Gayle Cooper as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, Alderman Library, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. George B. Craddock as Associate Professor of Internal Medicine, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Michael J. Cronin as Associate Professor of Physiology, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Martin R. Davis as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, Alderman Library, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. Placido H. Deguzman as Assistant Professor of Radiology, Veterans Administration Medical Center, Salem Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. John P. Di Marco as Associate Professor of Internal Medicine, effective July 1, 1985. Ms. Mary C. Dunnigan as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, Alderman Library, for one year, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Mark W. Edmundson as Acting Assistant Professor of English, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1985. Mr. Carlos M. Eire as Assistant Professor of Religious Studies, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1985. Dr. Sharon A. Esau as Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. Amando V. Esguerra as Assistant Professor of Pathology, Veterans Administration Medical Center, Salem Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. David S. Fedson as Associate Professor of Internal Medicine, for three years, effective October 1, 1985. Dr. Philip S. Feldman as Associate Professor of Pathology, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. Fred Felton as Assistant Professor of Radiology, Veterans Administration Center, Salem Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Ms. Betty A. Fletcher as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1985. Dr. Philip S. Fogg as Associate Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Veterans Administration Medical Center, Salem Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Michael S. Forbes as Research Assistant Professor of Physiology, for one year, effective April 1, 1985. Ms. Lydia Gasman as Assistant Professor of Art History, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1985. Mr. Thomas J. Gates as Associate Professor, General Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. Robert S. Gibson as Associate Professor of Internal Medicine, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Earl A. Glosser as Associate Professor, General Faculty, for three years, effective September 1, 1985. Mr. Charles R. Hagwood as Assistant Professor of Mathematics, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1985. Mr. Michael J. Halseth as Assistant Professor, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective January 1, 1985. Mr. John M. Hamrick as Assistant Professor of Civil Engineering, for the period January 16, 1985 through May 31, 1987. Mr. John F. Harlan, Jr. as Assistant Professor, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. William R. Hobbs, Associate Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, General Medical Faculty, and Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, General Medical Faculty, for the period December 16, 1984 through June 30, 1987. Dr. Robert H. Hodge, Jr. as Associate Professor of Internal Medicine, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Ms. Anne M. Hogg as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, Alderman Library, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Philip A. Ianna as Associate Professor, General Faculty, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1985. Mr. Robert E. Ingham as Assistant Professor of Drama, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1985. Ms. Marcia A. Invernizzi as Assistant Professor of Education, for one semester, effective January 16, 1985. Ms. Barbara A. Jackson as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, Alderman Library, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. Richard P. Keeling as Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, for the period April 1, 1985 through June 30, 1985. Ms. Cornelia A. Kelley as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, Alderman Library, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Ms. Karen H. Knierim as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, part time, for one year, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. John C. Knight as Associate Professor of Computer Science, effective September 1, 1985. Ms. Evelyn A. Knight as Assistant Professor of Education, for two academic years, effective September 1, 1985. Dr. Gregg A. Korbon as Assistant Professor of Anesthesiology, for three years, effective February 1, 1985. Mr. Roman Krzystofowicz as Associate Professor of Systems Engineering, effective September 1, 1985. Dr. Thomas P. Kuhlmann as Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Ms. Yun-fun Lai as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, Alderman Library, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Ms. Karen C. Lang as Assistant Professor of Religious Studies, for four academic years, effective September 1, 1985. Ms. Edith C. Lawrence as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1985. Mr. Roger M. Leachman as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, Alderman Library, for one year, effective July 1, 1985. Ms. Linda L. Lester as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, Alderman Library, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Ms. Jacqueline Lichtman as Associate Professor, General Faculty, for the period August 16, 1984 through June 15, 1985. Ms. Janet R. Linde as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, Alderman Library, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. Allen D. Majewski as Assistant Professor of Family Medicine, Lynchburg Program, for three years, effective February 1, 1985. Ms. Elizabeth A. Margutti as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, Alderman Library, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Worthy Martin as Assistant Professor of Computer Science, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1985. Mr. Louis Martsolf as Associate Professor, General Faculty, for the period July 1, 1985 through June 30, 1988. Mr. Robert S. Marvin, II as Assistant Professor of Pediatrics, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Paul D. McKinnon as Assistant Professor of Business Administration, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1985. Mr. Patrick J. Michaels as Research Assistant Professor of Environmental Sciences, for one year, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. John F. O'Bryant as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, Alderman Library, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Ranajit Pal as Research Assistant Professor of Microbiology, for one year, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Ronny B. Panerai as Visiting Research Associate Professor of Biomedical Engineering, for the period January 1, 1985 through June 30, 1985. Ms. Sarah J. Parsons as Assistant Professor of Microbiology, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. James W. Ramsey, Jr. as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. G. Carleton Ray as Research Professor in Environmental Sciences, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1985. Dr. David W. Robinson as Associate Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Veterans Administration Medical Center, Salem Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. George T. Rodeheaver as Associate Professor of Plastic and Maxillofacial Surgery, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. C. Edward Rose, Jr. as Associate Professor of Internal Medicine, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Mitchel Rosen as Research Assistant Professor of Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering, for the period January 16, 1985 through December 31, 1985. Mr. Fred Rosi as Research Professor of Materials Science and Electrical Engineering, for the period June 1, 1985 through June 30, 1986. Ms. Julianne J. Sando as Assistant Professor of Pharmacology, for one year, effective January 1, 1985. Ms. Betty H. Sapir as Assistant Professor of French, part time, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1985. Dr. Frank T. Saulsbury as Associate Professor of Pediatrics, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. R. Michael Schafer as Assistant Professor of Electrical Engineering, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1985. Mr. Richard D. Schultz as Professor, General Faculty, for five years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Jorge E. Secada as Assistant Professor of Philosophy, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1987. Mr. David W. Sedgwick as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1985. Dr. Hubert A. Shaffer, Jr. as Associate Professor of Radiology, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Thomas A. Shannon as Visiting Professor of Education, for one academic year, effective January 16, 1985. Dr. Robert B. Sharp as Associate Professor of Internal Medicine, Salem Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. Mark L. Smucker as Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Kenneth M. Sosnowski as Assistant Professor of Pathology, Veterans Administration Medical Center, Salem Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. Aubrey L. Stafford as Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Veterans Administration Medical Center, Salem Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Peter A. Stark, Jr. as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Ms. Christie D. Stephenson as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, Alderman Library, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Kanubhai D. Suthar as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, Alderman Library, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Ms. Sybil R. Todd as Associate Professor, General Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Nicolaos S. Tzannes as Visiting Professor of Electrical Engineering, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1985. Mr. George B. Vaughan as Visiting Professor of Education, for one semester, effective January 16, 1985. Mr. Franklin E. Wawner as Research Professor of Materials Science, for the period June 1, 1985 through June 30, 1988. Dr. Wayne H. Wilson as Associate Professor of Surgery, Salem Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Ms. Mary F. Yeager as Assistant Professor of Pediatrics, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. Tatsuo Yoneyama as Associate Professor of Pathology, Veterans Administration Medical Center, Salem Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1985.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PROMOTIONS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following faculty members be and they are hereby promoted: Ms. Judith S. Allen from Assistant Professor of Music to Associate Professor of Music, effective September 1, 1985. Mr. Ralph O. Allen from Associate Professor of Chemistry to Professor of Chemistry, effective September 1, 1985. Mr. Amir H. Assadi from Assistant Professor of Mathematics to Associate Professor of Mathematics, effective September 1, 1985. Mr. Gary Balian from Associate Professor of Orthopaedics and Biochemistry, General Medical Faculty to Professor of Orthopaedics and Biochemistry, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Theodore E. Batchman from Associate Professor of Electrical Engineering to Professor of Electrical Engineering, effective September 1, 1985. Mr. Robert M. Beckstead from Assistant Professor of Anatomy to Associate Professor of Anatomy, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. Luiz Belardinelli from Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine and Assistant Professor of Physiology to Associate Professor of Internal Medicine and Associate Professor of Physiology, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. William H. Bennett from Assistant Professor of Art to Associate Professor of Art, effective September 1, 1985. Mr. Bennett I. Bertenthal from Assistant Professor of Psychology to Associate Professor of Psychology, effective September 1, 1985. Dr. William C. Black from Instructor in Radiology to Assistant Professor of Radiology, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. Peter A. Blasco, Jr. from Assistant Professor of Pediatrics, General Medical Faculty to Associate Professor of Pediatrics, General Medical Faculty, for five years, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. W. Kline Bolton from Associate Professor of Internal Medicine to Professor of Internal Medicine, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. Robert J. Boyle from Assistant Professor of Pediatrics to Associate Professor of Pediatrics, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Michael F. Brown from Assistant Professor of Chemistry to Associate Professor of Chemistry, effective September 1, 1985. Mr. Robert F. Bruner from Assistant Professor of Business Administration to Associate Professor of Business Administration, for three years, effective September 1, 1985. Ms. M. Elizabeth Bruns from Assistant Professor of Pathology and Research Assistant Professor of Biochemistry to Research Associate Professor of Pathology and Research Associate Professor of Biochemistry, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. George Cahen from Research Assistant Professor of Materials Science to Research Associate Professor of Materials Science, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. Wayne D. Cail from Assistant Professor of Radiology to Associate Professor of Radiology, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Paul A. Cantor from Associate Professor of English to Professor of English, effective September 1, 1985. Ms. Karen S. Chase from Assistant Professor of English to Associate Professor of English, effective September 1, 1985. Mr. Roger A. Chevalier from Associate Professor of Astronomy to Professor of Astronomy, effective September 1, 1985. Dr. Maximo L. Cuesta from Assistant Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Roanoke Program to Associate Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Roanoke Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. Robert A. Darnall, Jr. from Assistant Professor of Pediatrics to Associate Professor of Pediatrics, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Ms. Angela M. Davis from Assistant Professor, General Faculty to Associate Professor, General Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. James N. Demas from Associate Professor of Chemistry to Professor of Chemistry, effective September 1, 1985. Mr. Robert D. Dripps, III from Associate Professor of Architecture to Professor of Architecture, effective September 1, 1985. Dr. Kemal H. Elbirlik from Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, General Faculty to Associate Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, General Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Victor H. Engelhard from Assistant Professor of Microbiology to Associate Professor of Microbiology, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. M. Jamie Ferreira from Assistant Professor of Religious Studies to Associate Professor of Religious Studies, effective September 1, 1985. Ms. Marjorie A. Flavin from Assistant Professor of Economics to Associate Professor of Economics, effective September 1, 1985. Mr. Michael S. Forbes from Research Assistant Professor of Physiology to Research Associate Professor of Physiology, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. James C. Garrison from Associate Professor of Pharmacology to Professor of Pharmacology, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. Joseph A. Gascho from Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine to Associate Professor of Internal Medicine, for one year, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. David T. Gies from Associate Professor of Spanish to Professor of Spanish, effective September 1, 1985. Miss Jean Goeppinger from Associate Professor of Nursing to Professor of Nursing, effective September 1, 1985. Ms. Barbara A. Graham from Assistant Professor of Nursing to Associate Professor of Nursing, effective September 1, 1985. Dr. Gregory F. Hayden from Assistant Professor of Pediatrics to Associate Professor of Pediatrics, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Bruce P. Hayden from Associate Professor of Environmental Sciences to Professor of Environmental Sciences, effective September 1, 1985. Dr. Erik L. Hewlett from Associate Professor of Internal Medicine and Associate Professor of Pharmacology to Professor of Internal Medicine and Associate Professor of Pharmacology, for two years, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. William R. Hobbs from Associate Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, and Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, General Medical Faculty, to Associate Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, and Associate Professor of Internal Medicine, General Medical Faculty, for two years, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. Rajiv Jain from Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, Veterans Administration Medical Center, Salem Program to Associate Professor of Internal Medicine, Veterans Administration Medical Center, Salem Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. John A. James from Associate Professor of Economics to Professor of Economics, effective September 1, 1985. Mr. Michael L. Johnson from Assistant Professor of Pharmacology to Associate Professor of Pharmacology, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Ervin L. Jordan, Jr. from Instructor, General Faculty, Alderman Library to Assistant Professor, General Faculty, Alderman Library, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Demetrios Kazakos from Associate Professor of Electrical Engineering to Professor of Electrical Engineering, effective September 1, 1985. Dr. Richard P. Keeling from Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine to Associate Professor of Internal Medicine, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. John G. Kenney from Assistant Professor of Plastic and Maxillofacial Surgery to Associate Professor of Plastic and Maxillofacial Surgery, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. Richard W. Kesler from Associate Professor of Pediatrics to Professor of Pediatrics, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Donald F. Kettl from Assistant Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs to Associate Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs, effective September 1, 1985. Dr. Irving L. Kron from Assistant Professor of Surgery to Associate Professor of Surgery, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. Carol L. Lake from Associate Professor of Anesthesiology, General Medical Faculty to Associate Professor of Anesthesiology, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Michael H. Levenson from Assistant Professor of English to Associate Professor of English, effective September 1, 1985. Dr. Robert M. Mentzer from Assistant Professor of Surgery to Associate Professor of Surgery, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Ronald W. Michener from Assistant Professor of Economics to Associate Professor of Economics, effective September 1, 1985. Mr. Jon D. Mikalson from Associate Professor of Classics to Professor of Classics, effective September 1, 1985. Dr. Stacey E. Mills from Assistant Professor of Pathology to Associate Professor of Pathology, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. Paul D. Mintz from Assistant Professor of Pathology to Associate Professor of Pathology, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. Raymond F. Morgan from Assistant Professor of Plastic and Maxillofacial Surgery to Associate Professor of Plastic and Maxillofacial Surgery, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Raymond J. Nelson from Associate Professor of English to Professor of English, effective September 1, 1985. Mr. Thomas F. Noble from Assistant Professor of History to Associate Professor of History, effective September 1, 1985. Dr. Wallace C. Nunley from Associate Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology and Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, General Medical Faculty, to Associate Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology and Associate Professor of Internal Medicine, General Medical Faculty, for two years, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. Michael R. Paling from Assistant Professor of Radiology to Associate Professor of Radiology, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. Robert C. Patten from Assistant Professor of Family Medicine, Roanoke Program to Associate Professor of Family Medicine, Roanoke Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. James S. Payne from Associate Professor of Education to Professor of Education, effective September 1, 1985. Dr. Richard D. Pearson from Associate Professor of Internal Medicine and Pathology to Associate Professor of Internal Medicine and Pathology, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Ms. Angelika Powell from Assistant Professor, General Faculty, Alderman Library to Associate Professor, General Faculty, Alderman Library, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Dennis R. Proffitt from Assistant Professor of Psychology to Associate Professor of Psychology, effective September 1, 1985. Dr. Jonathan I. Ravdin from Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine to Associate Professor of Internal Medicine, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. R. J. Ribando from Assistant Professor of Mechanical Engineering to Associate Professor of Mechanical Engineering, effective September 1, 1985. Dr. John P. Shemo from Associate Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry and Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, General Medical Faculty, to Associate Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry and Associate Professor of Internal Medicine, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Gary J. Shiflet from Assistant Professor of Materials Science to Associate Professor of Materials Science, effective September 1, 1985. Mr. Paul B. Stephan from Associate Professor of Law to Professor of Law, effective September 1, 1985. Dr. Michael D. Sussman from Associate Professor of Orthopaedics and Pediatrics, General Medical Faculty to Associate Professor of Orthopaedics and Pediatrics, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. Lawrence H. Sutker from Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Western State to Associate Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Western State, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. Johannes D. Veldhuis from Associate Professor of Internal Medicine and Associate Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology to Professor of Internal Medicine and Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. K. Preston White from Assistant Professor of Systems Engineering to Associate Professor of Systems Engineering, effective September 1, 1985. Ms. Linda S. White from Instructor, General Faculty, Alderman Library to Assistant Professor, General Faculty, Alderman Library, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. William R. Wilkerson from Assistant Professor, General Faculty to Associate Professor, General Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Ms. Luciana G. Wlassics from Instructor, General Faculty, Alderman Library to Assistant Professor, General Faculty, Alderman Library, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. Glenn R. Yank from Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Western State to Associate Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Western State, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. J. Joe Yazel from Associate Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry and Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, General Medical Faculty, to Associate Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry and Associate Professor of Internal Medicine, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. Albert S. Yoon from Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Veterans Administration Medical Center, Salem Program to Associate Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Veterans Administration Medical Center, Salem Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1985.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">LEAVES OF ABSENCE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following faculty members be and they are hereby granted leave of absence: Mr. William Bennett, Assistant Professor of Art, for one semester, without pay, effective January 16, 1985, to pursue creative work in sculpture. Ms. Edwina Campbell, Assistant Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs, for the period September 1, 1985 through May 31, 1986, without pay, to accept a Robert Bosch Fellowship Award. Mr. Richard Crozier, Associate Professor of Studio Art, for one semester, without pay, effective January 16, 1986, to pursue professional goals in painting. Ms. Ann W. Fisher, Assistant Professor of English, for one semester, without pay, effective January 16, 1986, to do research. Mr. Gerald P. Fogarty, Associate Professor of Religious Studies, for one semester, without pay, effective January 16, 1985, to accept the Catholic Daughters of America visiting professorship at the Catholic University of America. Mr. Anthony Frankfurter, Research Assistant Professor in Biology, for the period January 1, 1985 through March 31, 1985, with partial pay, to reduce effort while writing final grant reports. Ms. Lydia Gasman, Assistant Professor of Art History, for the period September 1, 1985 through January 15, 1986, without pay, to complete a book project. Mr. Philip Geiger, Assistant Professor of Studio Art, for the period September 1, 1985 through January 16, 1986, without pay, to pursue professional goals in painting. Mr. Ronald M. Hartwell, Professor of Economics, for one semester, without pay, effective January 16, 1986, to do research. Mr. James J. Kauzlarich, Professor of Mechanical Engineering, for the period February 1, 1985 through May 31, 1985, with partial pay, to do research. Mr. David Little, Professor of Religious Studies, for the period August 31, 1985 through January 15, 1986, without pay, to be a visiting Professor at the University of Colorado. Ms. Linda M. Miller, Research Instructor, General Faculty, for the period February 1, 1985 through March 31, 1985, without pay, to work on a project for the National Endowment for the Humanities. Mr. John F. Miller, Assistant Professor of Classics, for the period September 1, 1985 through May 31, 1986, without pay, to do research at the University of Heidelberg. Mr. Theodore M. Porter, Assistant Professor of History, for the period September 1, 1985 through January 15, 1986, without pay, to do research. Mr. Craig L. Sarazin, Associate Professor of Astronomy, for the period September 1, 1985 through May 31, 1986, with partial pay, to do research. Ms. Vanessa D. Saunders, Assistant Professor of English, for the period September 1, 1985 through January 15, 1986, without pay, to do research. Mr. Peter Smith, Assistant Professor of English, for the period September 1, 1985 through May 1, 1986, without pay, to accept a visiting appointment at Stanford University. Mr. Robert L. Vickery, Professor of Architecture, for one semester, with partial pay, effective January 16, 1985, to devote more time to a major project. Dr. Richard P. Wenzel, Professor of Internal Medicine, for the period August 19, 1985 through August 18, 1986, with partial pay, to do research.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHANGES OF TITLE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following changes of title be and they are hereby made: Mr. Donald E. Brown from Acting Assistant Professor of Systems Engineering to Assistant Professor of Systems Engineering, for three years, effective January 1, 1985. Mr. Joseph A. Brown from Acting Assistant Professor of English and Religious Studies to Assistant Professor of English and Religious Studies, for the period January 1, 1985 through May 31, 1988. Ms. Marcia A. Invernizzi from Acting Assistant Professor of Education to Assistant Professor of Education, for one semester, effective January 16, 1985. Mr. Alvis W. Jeffreys, Jr. from Clinical Associate Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Western State to Associate Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Western State, for the period March 1, 1985 through December 31, 1985. Ms. Maria I. Lasaga from Acting Assistant Professor of Psychology to Assistant Professor of Psychology, for the period September 21, 1984 through May 31, 1988. Ms. Anne C. Newman from Clinical Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Western State to Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Western State, for the period March 1, 1985 through June 30, 1987. Ms. Lynne W. Olsho from Research Assistant Professor of Otolaryngology to Research Assistant Professor of Otolaryngology and Research Assistant Professor of Speech Pathology and Audiology, for one semester, effective January 16, 1985. Mr. Fernando Opere from Acting Assistant Professor of Spanish to Assistant Professor of Spanish, for the period January 11, 1985 through May 31, 1986. Mr. Reuben M. Rainey from Associate Professor of Architecture to Associate Professor of Architecture and Lecturer in Religious Studies, for two years, effective September 1, 1985. Mr. James D. Rawls from Clinical Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Western State to Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Western State, for the period March 1, 1985 through September 30, 1986. Mr. John K. Steehler from Acting Assistant Professor of Chemistry to Assistant Professor of Chemistry, for the period December 17, 1984 through May 31, 1988. Mr. Nicolaos S. Tzannes from Visiting Professor of Electrical Engineering to Professor of Electrical Engineering, for the period September 1, 1985 through May 31, 1987. Mr. David M. Veleber from Clinical Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Western State to Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Western State, for the period March 1, 1985 through January 31, 1987. Dr. Robert C. Wesley, Jr. from Research Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine to Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. Eduard E. de Lange from Visiting Assistant Professor of Radiology to Assistant Professor of Radiology, for the period April 1, 1985 through June 30, 1985.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RETIREMENTS The following retirements were announced: Dr. Stuart T. Bray, Assistant Professor of Radiology, General Medical Faculty, effective June 30, 1985. Dr. Bray has been a member of the faculty since April 1, 1978. Ms. Martha S. Carpenter, Associate Professor of Astronomy, effective May 31, 1985. Ms. Carpenter has been a member of the faculty since February 1, 1968. Dr. Harold Carron, Distinguished Professor of Anesthesiology, effective December 31, 1984. Dr. Carron has been a member of the faculty since August 17, 1970. Mr. Edwin S. Cohen, Joseph M. Hartfield Professor of Law, effective May 31, 1985. Mr. Cohen has been a member of the faculty since September 1, 1963. Mr. Frank W. Finger, alumni Professor of Psychology, effective May 31, 1985. Mr. Finger has been a member of the faculty since March 1, 1942. Dr. Bernard S. Goffen, Assistant Professor of Anesthesiology, Veterans Administration Medical Center, Salem Program, effective June 30, 1985. Dr. Goffen has been a member of the faculty since September 1, 1980. Mr. George W. Holmes, III, Professor of Education, effective January 15, 1985. Mr. Holmes has been a member of the faculty since September 15, 1958. Mr. Alwyn C. Lapsley, Research Associate Professor, Nuclear Engineering and Engineering Physics, effective June 30, 1985. Mr. Lapsley has been a member of the faculty since September 12, 1960. Mr. Wendell M. Lewis, Lecturer, General Faculty, effective June 30, 1985. Mr. Lewis has been a member of the faculty since September 1, 1967. Mr. Carlos Ramos-Gil, Professor of Spanish, effective June 30, 1985. He has been a member of the faculty since February 1, 1970. Mr. Steve Sebo, Professor of Physical Education, effective June 30, 1985. Mr. Sebo has been a member of the faculty since March 1, 1962. Mr. Emerson G. Spies, Mary and Daniel Loughran Professor of Law, effective May 31, 1985. Mr. Spies has been a member of the faculty since April 1, 1946. Mr. David Thompson, Frank S. Kaulback, Jr., Professor of Commerce, effective May 31, 1985. Mr. Thompson has been a member of the faculty since September 1, 1976. Mr. Theodore R. Turner, Associate Professor of Studio Art, effective May 31, 1985. Mr. Turner has been a member of the faculty since September 15, 1952. Mr. Vincent W. Uhl, Professor of Chemical Engineering, effective January 16, 1985. Mr. Uhl has been a member of the faculty since September 1, 1963.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ELECTION OF PROFESSORS EMERITI The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following persons be and they are hereby elected Professor Emeritus: Dr. Harold Carron, Distinguished Professor of Anesthesiology. Mr. Edwin S. Cohen, Joseph M. Hartfield Professor of Law. Mr. Frank W. Finger, Alumni Professor of Psychology. Mr. George W. Holmes, III, Professor of Education. Mr. Carlos Ramos-Gil, Professor of Spanish. Mr. Steve Sebo, Professor of Physical Education. Mr. Emerson G. Spies, Mary and Daniel Loughran Professor of Law. Mr. David Thompson, Frank S. Kaulback, Jr., Professor of Commerce. Mr. Vincent W. Uhl, Professor of Chemical Engineering.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RESIGNATIONS The following resignations were announced: Ms. Frances F. Ash, Instructor in French, part-time, effective May 31, 1985, to accept fellowship award. Mr. Paul Benneche, Instructor in Nuclear Engineering, effective February 8, 1985, for cancellation of overload duties. Dr. Carol A. Bryant, Assistant Professor of Surgery, effective June 30, 1985, for personal reasons. Mr. William J. Burns, Associate Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Western State, effective January 31, 1985, for personal reasons. Dr. James P. Caldwell, Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, Salem Program, effective June 30, 1985, for personal reasons. Miss Beth A. Collins, Instructor in Nursing, effective May 31, 1985, for personal reasons. Ms. Nancy A. Crowell, Clinical Assistant Professor of Nursing, effective January 18, 1985, for personal reasons. Mrs. Sarah P. Farrell, Instructor in Nursing, effective May 31, 1985, for personal reasons. Dr. Mihai Gheorghiade, Associate Professor of Internal Medicine, Salem Program, effective February 28, 1985, to accept another position. Mrs. Kathryn H. Haugh, Instructor in Nursing, effective May 31, 1985, to accept another position. Mr. William W. Kerrigan, Associate Professor of English, effective May 31, 1985, to accept another position. Mr. Scott E. Masten, Assistant Professor of Economics, effective May 31, 1985, to accept another position. Ms. Linda A. Moore, Assistant Professor of Nursing, effective May 31, 1985, for personal reasons. Dr. Stuart A. Rosenberg, Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, effective April 30, 1985, to accept another position. Dr. Tomio Sasaki, Assistant Professor of Neurosurgery, effective March 31, 1985, for personal reasons. Mr. Steven E. Sayre, Clinical Assistant Professor, Division of Medical Center Social Work, General Medical Faculty, effective June 30, 1985, to accept another position. Mr. Rudolf Schneck, Instructor in Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering, effective January 16, 1985, for personal reasons. Mr. David P. Schwartz, Research Assistant Professor of Anesthesiology, effective March 31, 1985, for personal reasons. Ms. Elizabeth A. Weiss, Instructor in Nursing, effective May 31, 1985, to accept another position. Ms. Christina T. Wilhelm, Instructor, General Medical Faculty, effective March 29, 1985, for personal reasons. Ms. Donna D. Wilson, Assistant Professor, General Faculty, Alderman Library, effective June 14, 1985, for personal reasons. Mr. Michael Yoshitsu, Assistant Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs, effective May 31, 1985, to accept another position.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPOINTMENTS The following appointments were announced: Mr. John A. Blackburn as Dean of Admissions, for five years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Elmer L. Gaden, Jr. as Chairman, Department of Chemical Engineering, for two years, effective September 1, 1985. Mr. Paul Hansma as Member of the Center for Advanced Studies, for one month, effective April 1, 1985. Mr. Hugh P. Kelly as Dean of the Faculty of Arts and Sciences, for five years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Verdel A. Kolve as Member of the Center for Advanced Studies, for three years, effective September 1, 1985. Mr. Richard A. Kovatch as Director of Audits, for three years, effective January 1, 1985. Mr. Bernard A. Morin as Associate Provost for Public Service, for the period April 1, 1985, through January 15, 1987. Ms. Jere K. Mundy as Director of Medical Records, for the period March 16, 1985 through June 30, 1986 Mr. Alexander Sedgwick as Dean of the College of Arts and Sciences, for five years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Robert L. Wilken as Member of the Center for Advanced Studies, for two years, effective September 1, 1985.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CORRECTION IN THE APPOINTMENT OF MR. JAMES M. COOPER The President announced that the term of the appointment of Mr. James M. Cooper, as announced to the Board on June 1, 1984, has been changed to read as follows: Mr. James M. Cooper as Dean of the School of Education, for five years, effective July 1, 1984.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RE-APPOINTMENTS The following re-appointments were announced: Mr. Terry Appolonia as Assistant Dean of Students, for one year, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Richard S. Benner as Assistant Director, Office of Career Planning and Placement, for one year, effective September 1, 1985. Ms. Rosalyn W. Berne as Assistant Director, Office of Career Planning and Placement, for one year, effective July 1, 1985. Ms. Karen A. Chandler as Director of Afro-American Cultural Center, for one year, effective September 1, 1985. Ms. Angela M. Davis as Assistant Dean of Students, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Ms. Alexandria J. DeLoatch as Assistant Dean of Afro-American Affairs, for one year, effective August 1, 1985. Dr. Byard S. Deputy as Chairman, Department of Dentistry, for five years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Thomas J. Gates as Director of the Counseling Center, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Ms. Annette Gibbs as Associate Dean of Students, for the period July 1, 1985 through August 31, 1985 Mr. Thomas I. Grexa as Assistant Dean of Admissions, for two years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Michael J. Halseth as Director of Operations, University Hospital, for three years, effective January 1, 1985. Mr. John F. Harlan, Jr. as Assistant Vice President for Allied Health Affairs, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Ms. Hortense B. Hinton as Associate Dean of Afro-American Affairs, for the period August 1, 1985 through July 31, 1986 Mr. James E. Kinard as University History Officer, for one year, effective July 1, 1985. Ms. Karen H. Knierim as Associate Director, Office of Career Planning and Placement, part time, for one year, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Phillip P. Muth as Assistant Dean of Admissions, for two years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. James W. Ramsey, Jr. as Associate Director of Financial Aid, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Wayne A. Reschke as Assistant Director, Office of Career Planning and Placement, part time, for one year, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Jaquelin T. Robertson as Dean, School of Architecture, for five years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Arthur I. Schulman as Assistant Dean, College of Arts and Sciences, for one year, effective September 1, 1985. Mr. Richard D. Schultz as Director, University Athletic Programs, for five years, effective July 1, 1985. Dr. Nickolas J. Sojka as Chairman, Department of Comparative Medicine, for five years, effective July 1, 1985. Mr. Peter A. Stark, Jr. as Assistant Vice President for Student Affairs, for three years, effective July 1, 1985. Ms. Sybil R. Todd as Associate Dean of Students, for three years, effective July 1, 1985.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DEATH OF DR. THOMAS E. DONNELLY Dr. Thomas E. Donnelly, Clinical Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, Roanoke Program, died February 2, 1985. He had been a member of the faculty since January 1, 1976.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCHEDULE OF MEETING DATES FOR 1986 The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following dates for the 1986 meetings of the Board be and they are hereby approved: January 30, 31, and February 1, 1986 Charlottesville March 20, 21, and 22, 1986 Charlottesville May 29, 30, and 31, 1986 Charlottesville October 2 and 3, 1986 Charlottesville</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ESTABLISHMENT OF THE LEONE REAVES AND GEORGE W. SPICER PROFESSORSHIP IN THE WOODROW WILSON DEPARTMENT OF GOVERNMENT AND FOREIGN AFFAIRS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that there is hereby established in the Faculty of Arts and Sciences a Chair to be known as the Leone Reaves and George W. Spicer Professorship in the Woodrow Wilson Department of Government and Foreign Affairs. The Board is grateful to the late Leone Reaves and George W. Spicer whose generosity made this Chair possible.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ESTABLISHMENT OF THE HUNTON AND WILLIAMS PROFESSORSHIP IN LAW The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that there is hereby established in the School of Law a Chair to be known as the Hunton and Williams Professorship in Law. This Chair for a distinguished scholar is established in memory of Thomas Benjamin Gay and Eppa Hunton, IV, and shall become effective at such time as its funding is complete. The Board is grateful to the Law School Foundation and particularly to the families of Mr. Gay and Mr. Hunton, the firm of Hunton and Williams, and the many graduates of the Law School practicing there, whose contributions made the establishment of this Chair possible.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ESTABLISHMENT OF THE EMERSON G. SPIES PROFESSORSHIP IN LAW The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that there is hereby established in the School of Law a Chair to be known as the Emerson G. Spies Professorship in Law. This Chair is to become effective at such time as its funding is complete. The Board is grateful to the Law School Foundation and particularly to the many friends, admirers, and former students of Professor Spies whose contributions made the establishment of this Chair possible.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ESTABLISHMENT OF THE DOROTHY DANFORTH COMPTON PROFESSORSHIP AT THE WHITE BURKETT MILLER CENTER OF PUBLIC AFFAIRS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that there is hereby established the Dorothy Danforth Compton Professorship in Public Affairs in an academic department to be designated by the Vice President and Provost, as appropriate to the incumbent's activities and participation in the White Burkett Miller Center of Public Affairs. The Board is grateful to the Compton Foundation, Incorporated, which made the establishment of this Chair possible.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ESTABLISHMENT OF THE MARY MUILENBURG STAMP PROFESSORSHIP IN ORTHOPEDIC RESEARCH IN THE SCHOOL OF MEDICINE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that there is hereby established in the School of Medicine a Chair to be known as the Mary Muilenburg Stamp Professorship in Orthopedic Research. The Board is grateful to Dr. Charles J. Frankel and others whose generosity made possible the establishment of this Chair.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RENAMING OF THE DISTINGUISHED PROFESSORSHIP IN ORTHOPEDICS AND REHABILITATION THE CHARLES J. FRANKEL PROFESSORSHIP IN ORTHOPEDICS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the Chair known as the Distinguished Professorship in Orthopedics and Rehabilitation be and it is hereby renamed the Charles J. Frankel Professorship in Orthopedics established by the University of Virginia Medical School Foundation.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">AUTHORIZATION TO NAME MORE THAN ONE CHAIRHOLDER TO THE LAWRENCE R. QUARLES PROFESSORSHIP The following resolution was adopted: WHEREAS; the Board of Visitors previously created the Lawrence R. Quarles Professorship in Engineering and Applied Science; and WHEREAS, the available resources now are sufficient to support more than one chairholder; and WHEREAS, the support of more than one chairholder is not inconsistent with the restrictions applicable to the Lawrence R. Quarles Professorship; NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED that more than one chairholder may be named to the Lawrence R. Quarles Professorship in Engineering and Applied Science.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">REPORT ON CONSTRUCTION A detailed construction report was distributed to Members of the Board which included 33 active construction projects for the University Division, 22 for the Medical Center and two for Clinch Valley College. Projects in the University Division represent costs of $87,448,148, for the Medical Center Division costs of $227,900,369, and for Clinch Valley College costs of $1,261,900.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RESOLUTION CHANGING THE NAME OF THE SCHOOL OF EDUCATION FROM THE CURRY MEMORIAL SCHOOL OF EDUCATION TO CURRY SCHOOL OF EDUCATION The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the name of the Curry Memorial School of Education be and it is hereby changed to Curry School of Education.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">INCREASE IN TUITION AND REQUIRED FEES AND OTHER CHARGES FOR THE UNIVERSITY DIVISION The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the tuition and required fees and other charges applicable to the University Division be and they are hereby approved as shown below, effective July 1, 1985: REGULAR SESSION: Virginian Non-Virginian Actual 1984-85 Amt. Inc. Percent of Inc. Proposed 1985-86 Actual 1984-85 Amt. Inc. Percent of Inc. Proposed 1985-86 Tuition and Required Fees Undergraduate and Graduate Schools-Full Time $1,810 $210 11.6% $2,020 $4,320 $550 12.7% $4,870 Medical Technology 990 70 7.1% 1,060 990 70 7.1% 1,060 Professional Schools Graduate Bus.- MBA 3,320 240 7.2% 3,560 6,820 620 9.1% 7,440 Law-JD 2,750 240 8.7% 2,990 5,770 620 10.7% 6,390 Medicine - MD 4,870 240 4.9% 5,110 9,690 620 6.4% 10,310 Activity Fees General-All Students 16 -- -- 16 16 -- -- 16 Architecture 10 -- -- 10 10 -- -- 10 Commerce 5 5 100.0% 10 5 5 100.0% 10 Darden 20 5 25.0% 25 20 5 25.0% 25 Education 2 2 100.0% 4 2 2 100.0% 4 Engineering 4 -- -- 4 4 -- -- 4 Law School 28 -- -- 28 28 -- -- 28 Medicine 32 -- -- 32 32 -- -- 32 Nursing 10 -- -- 10 10 -- -- 10 CONTINUING EDUCATION: Current 1984-85 Amount of Increase Percent Increase Proposed 1985-86 Undergrad. and Grad. Per Semester Hour $ 55 $ 8 14.5% $ 63 Special Students Registering through and admitted by the Division of Continuing Education in On-Grounds Courses per semester hour 75 -- -- 75 INCREASE IN TUITION AND REQUIRED FEES AND OTHER CHARGES FOR THE UNIVERSITY DIVISION (continued) CONTINUING EDUCATION (continued): Current 1984-85 Amount of Increase Percent Increase Proposed 1985-86 Admission Fee in Certificate and Special Programs $10 -- -- $10 Registration Fee - Northern Virginia Only 5 -- -- 5 Change of Status Fee 5 -- -- 5 Transcript Fee 2 -- -- 2 Late Exam Fee 5 -- -- 5 TIAA Fee for Students Registered in Off-Campus Degree Programs Per Registration 10 -- -- 10 Other Miscellaneous Fees as Established to Recover Expenses such as Laboratory, Materials, etc., on a Basis of Estimated Cost. OTHER: Other contracted course and cooperative program tuition and required fee rates approved on a basis consistent with University contracting policies and procedures by the Associate Vice President for Budget and Planning.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">INCREASE IN TUITION AND REQUIRED FEES AND OTHER CHARGES FOR CLINCH VALLEY COLLEGE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the tuition and required fees and other charges applicable to Clinch Valley College be and they are hereby approved as shown below, effective July 1, 1985: Virginian Non-Virginian Actual 1984-85 Amt. of Inc. Percent of Inc. Proposed 1985-86 Actual 1984-85 Amt. of Inc. Percent of Inc. Proposed 1985-86 Tuition and Required Fees Full-time Students (12 semester hours or more per semester) Session Rate $1,200 $48 4.0% $1,248 $1,848 $120 6.5% $1,968 Students taking more than 18 credit hours per semester must pay for the additional hours at the part-time tuition rates listed below. Part-time Students (less than 12 semester hrs per semester) Rate per semester hour $ 40 $ 2 5.0% $ 42 $ 67 $ 5 7.5% $ 72 Off-Campus Instruction Credit Courses - Rate per semester hour $ 40 $ 2 5.0% $ 42 $ 67 $ 5 7.5% $ 72 Non-Credit Courses - Rate per CEU $ 14 $ 1 7.1% $ 15 $ 24 $ 2 8.3% $ 26 Dormitory Rent $ 736 $224 30.4% $ 960 $ 736 $224 30.4% $ 960 Board 15 meals per week $1,200 0 0 $1,200 $1,200 0 0 $1,200 12 meals per week 1,000 0 0 1,000 1,000 0 0 1,000 10 meals per week 850 0 0 850 850 0 0 850 Meal ticket for a la carte meals 100 0 0 100 100 0 0 100 Other Fees Application Fee $ 15 0 0 $ 15 $ 15 0 0 $ 15 Applied Music Fee-Rate per semester hour $ 75 0 0 $ 75 $ 75 0 0 $ 75 The Applied Music Fee is applicable to Applied Music Courses 104, 105, 108, 109, 204, 205, 304, 305, 404, and 405 and is in addition to all other tuition and required fees. Part-time students will pay a $5 registration fee for a one-hour course, $10 for a two-hour course, and $15 for three hours or more. CEU courses will pay a $5 registration fee.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ALLOCATION OF REQUIRED FEES The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the fee component of the tuition and required fees be and it is hereby established, effective July 1, 1985, in the amount of $460; BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED that the fee component be allocated for the 1985-86 Session as follows: Actual 1984-85 Amount of Increase Percent of Increase Proposed 1985-86 Pledged for amortization bond issue for University Hall $ 15.00 $ -0- -- $ 15.00 University Transit 48.00 -0- -- 48.00 Auxiliary Services Fee (including debt service) 42.00 14.00 33.3% 56.00 Fringe Benefits 105.00 -0- -- 105.00 Athletics 64.00 -0- -- 64.00 Student Health 123.00 5.00 4.1% 128.00 University Union 29.00 1.00 3.4% 30.00 University Union Programs 10.00 -0- -- 10.00 Class Affiliation 4.00 -0- 4.00 TOTAL $440.00 $20.00 4.5% $460.00</field>
      <field name="fulltext">INCREASE IN THE FACULTY SALARY SCALE FOR THE UNIVERSITY The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following compensation plans applicable to the teaching and research staff in the University Division be and they are hereby approved, effective July 1, 1985: 1984-85 Normal Entrance Rate (1) (1) Amounts are stated on a session basis unless otherwise indicated. 1985-86 Proposed Normal Entrance Rate (1) Normal Increment Amount Interval General Faculty Professor $30,400 $33,400 (2) (2) 0-15%; amounts in excess of 15% are approved as special salary actions. 1 year Associate Professor 24,900 27,400 (2) 1 year Assistant Professor 20,200 22,200 (2) 1 year Instructor 14,300 15,700 (2) 1 year Pre-Clinical Faculty (3) (3) Amounts in this category are stated on an annual (12-month) basis. Department Head 40,300 44,300 (2) 1 year Professor 35,200 38,700 (2) 1 year Associate Professor 29,000 31,900 (2) 1 year Assistant Professor 23,300 25,600 (2) 1 year Instructor 18,300 20,100 (2) 1 year Junior Staff (3) Research Assistant 14,100 15,000 (2) 1 year Research Associate 14,700 16,000 (2) 1 year Senior Astronomy &amp; Physics Research Assistant 16,900 18,000 (2) 1 year Sponsored Programs (3) Research Scientist 21,100 22,800 (2) 1 year Senior Scientist 27,300 28,000 (2) 1 year Principal Scientist 42,900 43,000 (2) 1 year</field>
      <field name="fulltext">INCREASE IN FACULTY SALARY SCALE FOR CLINCH VALLEY COLLEGE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following compensation plan applicable to the teaching and research staff of Clinch Valley College be and it is hereby approved, effective July 1, 1985: 1984-85 Normal Entrance Rate (1) (1) Amounts are stated on a session basis. Proposed 1985-86 Normal Entrance Rate (1) Normal Increment Rank Amount Interval Professor $23,600 $25,000 (2) (2) 0-15%; amounts in excess of 15% are approved as special salary actions. 1 year Associate Professor $20,400 $22,000 (2) 1 year Assistant Professor $16,800 $18,000 (2) 1 year Instructor $13,400 $15,000 (2) 1 year</field>
      <field name="fulltext">INCREASE IN CONTRACT RATES FOR FOOD SERVICE, 1985-1986 The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the student contract rates for food services be and they are hereby approved as shown below, effective beginning with the Session 1985-1986: Food Service Contract Actual 1984-85 Amount of Increase Percent Increase Proposed 1985-86 7-Day (19 meals) $1,278 $ 64 5.0% $1,342 6-Meals per week $ 600 $ 0 -- $ 600 12-Meals per week $1,078 $ 54 5.0% $1,132 Flex (15 meals) $1,218 $ 60 4.9% $1,278</field>
      <field name="fulltext">INCREASE IN CLINICAL AND PATHOLOGY FACULTY SALARY CEILINGS FOR THE SCHOOL OF MEDICINE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that subject to the approval of the Governor, the full-time Clinical and Pathology Faculty Salary Ceilings shall be as follows, effective July 1, 1985: Current Scale 1984-85 Proposed Scale 1985-86 Rank State Maximum Ceilings State Maximum Ceilings Professor and Department Head $56,200 $147,500 $61,800 $156,400 Professor and Division Head 53,600 132,300 59,000 140,200 Professor 48,800 127,900 53,700 135,600 Associate Professor and Division Head 46,900 120,200 51,600 127,400 Associate Professor 42,200 114,800 46,400 121,700 Assistant Professor 35,600 102,700 39,200 108,900 Instructor 31,000 85,000 34,100 90,100</field>
      <field name="fulltext">INCREASE IN RESIDENTIAL HOUSING RATES FOR 1985-1986 The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the residential housing rates be and they are hereby approved as indicated, effective July 1, 1985: Utilities Furnished by UVA Facility WS (Water, Sewer) E (Electricity) O (Fuel Oil) G (Gas) HP (Heating Plant) Rents 1984-85 per Month Amount of Increase Percent of Increase Proposed Rents 1985-86 per Month Utilities Paid By Occupant Piedmont Estates 1 Bedroom Apt. (7) WS, E, O $275 $15 5.45% $290 2 Bedroom Apt. (16) WS, E, O $310 $15 4.83% $325 3 Bedroom Houses (16) WS, E $350 $25 7.14% $375 O Townhouses (10) 3 BR WS, E $400 $25 6.25% $425 Farmhouse (121 Mimosa) Apt. 1, 1 Bedroom WS, E, O $220 $25 11.36% $245 Apt. 2, 3 Bedrooms WS, E, O $245 $25 10.20% $270 Apt. 3, 1 Bedroom WS, E, O $215 $25 11.62% $240 Apt. 4, 2 Bedrooms WS, E, O $230 $25 10.86% $255 Gildersleeve/Snowden Monroe Lane 1 Bedroom (16) WS, G, E $230 $20 8.69% $250 2 Bedroom (1) WS, G, E $295 $25 8.47% $320 Efficiency (2) WS, G, E $200 $15 7.50% $215 Snowden Apt. 1 (1 BR) WS, G, E $240 $15 6.25% $255 Apt. 2 (1 BR) WS, G, E $240 $15 6.25% $255 Apt. 6 (Efficiency) WS, G, E $200 $15 7.50% $215 Apt. 101 (3 BR) WS, G, E $360 $25 6.94% $385 Apt. 103 (2 BR) WS, G, E $295 $25 8.47% $320 Apt. 201 (1 BR) WS, G, E $240 $15 6.25% $255 Apt. 202 (1 BR) WS, G, E $240 $15 6.25% $255 Apt. 203 (2 BR) WS, G, E $295 $25 8.47% $320 Sundry Vyssotsky Cottage (3 BR) WS $250 $20 8.00% $270 E, O Upper Alden (3 BR) WS, O $275 $25 9.09% $300 E Lower Alden (3 BR) WS, O $250 $25 10.00% $275 E South Cottage (3 BR) WS $130 $10 7.69% $140 E, O Carr's Hill (2 BR) WS, E, HP $105 $15 14.28% $120 McGuffey Cottage (Eff) HP, E, WS $180 $15 8.33% $195 Farmhouse 250 Bypass (3BR) -- $120 $10 8.33% $130 WS, E, O 2400 Stadium Rd (3 BR) E $330 $25 7.57% $355 WS, G Upper Mews (1 BR) HP, E. WS $205 $20 9.75% $225 Lower Mews (1 BR) HP, E, WS $205 $20 9.75% $225 Monroe Hill House (2BR) HP, E, WS $185 $15 8.10% $200 INCREASE IN RESIDENTIAL HOUSING RATES FOR 1985-86 Utilities Furnished by UVA Facility WS (Water, Sewer) E (Electricity) O (Fuel Oil) G (Gas) HP (Heating Plant) Rents 1984-85 per Month Amount of Increase Percent of Increase Proposed Rents 1985-86 per Month Utilities Paid By Occupant Birdwood Properties Cottage (1 BR) WS, E $245 $25 10.20% $270 Garage Apt. (2 BR) WS, E, O $300 $25 8.33% $325 Cash House (3 BR) WS, E, O $290 $30 10.34% $320 Faulkner Property Holly House (2 BR) WS, E, O $255 $25 9.80% $280 Holly House Lower (1RM) WS, E, O $115 $ 5 4.34% $120 Hedge House (2 BR) WS $185 $15 8.10% $200 E, O Orchard House (5SRMS) WS, E, O $115 $ 5 4.34% $120 Carriage House (4 BR) WS $210 $20 9.52% $230 E, O 118 Oakhurst Circle Upper (2 BR) WS, G $255 $20 7.84% $275 E Lower (2 BR) WS, G $290 $25 8.62% $315 E Valley Road Property 409 Valley Road (2 BR) -- $240 $20 8.33% $260 WS,E,O 411 Valley Road (2 BR) -- $240 $20 8.33% $260 WS,E,G 503 Valley Road (1 BR) -- $200 $15 7.50% $215 WS,E,G Faculty Apartments Apt. 11 (2 BR) WS, E, O $260 $25 9.61% $285 Apt. 12 (2 BR) WS, E, O $260 $25 9.61% $285 Apt. 14 (2 BR) WS, E, O $250 $25 10.00% $275 Apt. 15 (2 BR) WS, E, O $250 $25 10.00% $275 Apt. 21 (1 BR) WS, E, O $195 $20 10.25% $215 Apt. 22 (1 BR) WS, E, O $195 $20 10.25% $215 Apt. 23 (Eff) WS, E, O $185 $15 8.10% $200 Apt. 24 (1 BR) WS, E, O $190 $20 10.52% $210 Apt. 25 (1 BR) WS, E, O $200 $20 10.00% $220 Apt. 26 (1 BR) WS, E, O $200 $20 10.00% $220 Apt. 27 (1 BR) WS, E, O $200 $20 10.00% $220 Apt. 28 (1 BR) WS, E, O $200 $20 10.00% $220 Apt. 31 (1 BR) WS, E, O $205 $20 9.75% $225 Apt. 32 (1 BR) WS, E, O $200 $20 10.00% $220 Apt. 33 (2 BR) WS, E, O $225 $20 8.88% $245 Apt. 34 (2 BR) WS, E, O $225 $20 8.88% $245 Apt. 35 (2 BR) WS, E, O $220 $20 9.09% $240 Apt. 36 (2 BR) WS, E, O $220 $20 9.09% $240 INCREASE IN RESIDENTIAL HOUSING RATES FOR 1985-86 Utilities Furnished by UVA Facility WS (Water, Sewer) E (Electricity) O (Fuel Oil) G (Gas) HP (Heating Plant) Rents 1984-85 per Month Amount of Increase Percent of Increase Proposed Rents 1985-86 per Month Utilities Paid By Occupant E. &amp;G. Property: Montebello (3 BR) O $230 $20 8.69% $250 WS,E,G Big Morea (4 BR) WS, E, O $230 $20 8.69% $250 Little Morea (1 BR) WS, E, O $210 $15 7.14% $225 Sunnyside (4 BR) O $330 $30 9.09% $360 WS,E Hotel D (2 BR) WS, E, HP $200 $15 7.50% $215 Pavilions Pavilion I WS, HP $275 $20 7.27% $295 E Pavilion II WS, HP $275 $20 7.27% $295 E Pavilion III WS, HP $275 $20 7.27% $295 E Pavilion IV WS, HP $275 $20 7.27% $295 E Pavilion V WS, HP $275 $20 7.27% $295 E Pavilion V Annex WS, HP $275 $20 7.27% $295 E Pavilion VI WS, HP $275 $20 7.27% $295 E Pavilion IX WS, HP $275 $20 7.27% $295 E Pavilion X (3 BR) WS, HP $275 $20 7.27% $295 E Blue Ridge Properties Bldg 927 (4 BR House) WS $305 $25 8.19% $330 E,O Bldg 925 (2 BR House) WS, E $245 $20 8.16% $265 O Bldg 924 (2 BR House) WS, E $245 $-- -- $ 0 O Bldg 921 (3 BR House) WS, E $270 $-- -- $ 0 O Bldg 919 (4 BR House) HP, WS, E $305 $25 8.19% $330 Bldg 918A (1 BR Apt) HP, WS, E $200 $15 7.50% $215 Bldg 918B (1 BR Apt) HP, WS, E $200 $15 7.50% $215 Bldg 917 (2 BR House) HP, WS, E $245 $20 8.16% $265 Bldg 916 (4 BR House) HP, WS, E $305 $25 8.19% $330 Bldg 915A (1 BR Apt) HP, WS, E $185 $-- -- $ 0 Bldg 915B (1 BR Apt) HP, WS, E $185 $-- -- $ 0 Bldg 915C (1 BR Apt) HP, WS, E $185 $15 8.10% $200 Bldg 915D (1 BR Apt) HP, WS, E $185 $15 8.10% $200 Bldg 913A (2/3 BR Apt) HP, WS, E $230 $20 8.69% $250 Bldg 913B (2/3 BR Apt) HP, WS, E $230 $20 8.69% $250 Bldg 913C (2/3 BR Apt) HP, WS, E $230 $20 8.69% $250 Bldg 913D (2/3 BR Apt) HP, WS, E $230 $20 8.69% $250 Bldg 912A (2 BR Apt) HP, WS, E $230 $20 8.69% $250 Bldg 912B (2 BR Apt) HP, WS, E $230 $20 8.69% $250 Bldg 903 Dorm Rooms 6 Doubles HP, WS, E $ 61 $14 23.00% $ 75 Bldg 903 Dorm Rooms 9 Singles HP, WS, E $ 75 $ 0 0.00% $ 75</field>
      <field name="fulltext">INCREASE IN RESIDENTIAL HOUSING RATES FOR CLINCH VALLEY COLLEGE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the residential housing rates applicable to Clinch Valley College be and they are hereby approved as shown below, effective September 1, 1985: Utilities Furnished By Clinch Valley College Facility WS (Water, Sewer) G (Gas) Rents 1984-85 Per Month Amount of Increase Percent of Increase Proposed Rents 1985-86 Per Month Houses (6) WS $ 240 $ 15 6.3% $ 255 2 Bedroom Apt. (2) WS, G 240 15 6.3% 255 1 Bedroom Apt. (2) WS, G 210 15 7.1% 225</field>
      <field name="fulltext">INCREASE IN TIAA/CREF CEILING TO $60,000 The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the TIAA/CREF retirement plan be amended as follows: The maximum amount of salary on which the University contribution to TIAA/CREF is based be increased from the present $54,000 to $60,000 for 1985-1986.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">REPORT OF THE HOSPITAL ACCOUNTS COMMITTEE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the Hospital Accounts Committee be and it is hereby authorized to write off as bad debts and free service accounts listed on University of Virginia schedule numbers 539 through 547, meetings for the months of December 14, 1984, January 25, 1985, and February 22, 1985, totaling $10,040,087.66 and Blue Ridge Hospital Division schedule numbers 604 through 615, meetings for the months of December 14, 1984, January 25, 1985, and February 22, 1985, totaling $407,013.56 consisting of the following: Bad Debts $ 3,038,390.80 Indigent Care 7,408,710.42 --------------------- Total $10,447,101.22 RESOLVED FURTHER, that the above action shall not be a compromise, settlement or discharge of debts represented by such account.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">NAMING OF THE FORMER SEARS BUILDING JOHN M. STACEY HALL The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the former Sears Building on West Main Street be and it is hereby named John M. Stacey Hall.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">NAMING OF THE NEW FACILITY AT THE SOUTH END OF SCOTT STADIUM J. C. HERBERT BRYANT HALL The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the structure erected at the south end of Scott Stadium be and it is hereby named J. C. Herbert Bryant Hall.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF BACHELOR OF SCIENCE IN ACCOUNTING DEGREE AT CLINCH VALLEY COLLEGE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the Bachelor of Science in Accounting Degree at Clinch Valley College be and it is hereby approved, subject to final approval by the State Council of Higher Education.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">GIFTS, GRANTS, AND CONTRACTS A January 1, 1985 to February 28, 1985 report of private gifts in the amount of $2,298,100, and sponsored programs in the amount of $3,093,700 was accepted by the Board. The overall cash total gifts to the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia and gifts through University related foundations designated for the Rector and Visitors amounted to $10,621,300 for the period. Also $7,527,600 in cash gifts to the Rector and Visitors and gifts to University related foundations designated for the Rector and Visitors were received during the period December 1, 1984 through December 30, 1984.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF THE FIRM OF THE ARCHITECTS DESIGN GROUP, OF ROANOKE, VIRGINIA, FOR THE PERFORMANCE OF ARCHITECTURAL DESIGN FOR THE STORES WAREHOUSE RENOVATION PROJECT The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the firm of The Architects Design Group, of Roanoke, Virginia, be approved for the performance of architectural design for the Stores Warehouse renovation project.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF UNIVERSITY HOSPITALS CONTRACTS WITH IBM AND SMS SYSTEMS The following resolution was adopted: WHEREAS, the Board of Visitors at its October 1981 and its March 1983 meetings approved contracts for a Hospital Information System with SMS Systems and Technicon; and WHEREAS, the Board of Visitors approved at its January 1985 meeting a contract with IBM for the necessary hardware and software to operate the healthcare portion of the Hospital Information System provided by Technicon; and WHEREAS, the University has decided to contract with IBM and SMS Systems to obtain the necessary hardware and software to convert the financial portion of the Hospital Information System from a shared basis with SMS System licensed software; NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED that the terms of the proposed contracts between the University, IBM, and SMS Systems in the anticipated amount of $3,256,000 for a processor, peripherals and software as outlined in the attached summary exhibited to the meeting be and they are hereby approved, and the appropriate officers of the University are hereby authorized to execute such contracts after they are in final form and approved by the Legal Adviser's Office.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DESCRIPTION OF PROPOSED CONTRACTS BETWEEN THE RECTOR AND VISITORS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA AND INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS MACHINES, CORPORATION ARMONK, N.Y. 10504 AND SMS SYSTEMS Malvern, P.A. 19355 BACKGROUND In August 1981 the University of Virginia issued a Request for Proposal for a Hospital Information System to improve operating efficiency and the availability of management information. University Management, in cooperation with the State's Office of Management Analysis and Systems Development (MASD) reviewed proposals received in October 1981 from six major healthcare system vendors. The selection committee determined that no one vendor offered an acceptable comprehensive system. Two firms were selected in October 1982 to meet the system needs of the Hospital: SMS Systems for the financial systems and Technicon Data Systems for the healthcare systems. The State Health Commission approved a Certificate of Need for the procurement of a Hospital Information System. A contract with SMS Systems was negotiated by the University and approved by the Board of Visitors in March 1983. The projected value of the SMS contract was $4.5 million. A contract with Technicon Data systems was negotiated by the University and approved by the Board of Visitors in August 1984. The projected value of the Technicon contract was $5.4 million. A contract with IBM for hardware and software to support the Technicon software was approved by the Executive Committee of the Board of Visitors in November 1984 and ratified by the January 1985 Board of Visitors Meeting. The total amount of the IBM contract was $1,114,000. IBM Corporation Agreement Page 2 March 27, 1985</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CONVERSION FROM SHARED TO UNIVERSITY OPERATED FINANCIAL SYSTEM The contract with SMS Systems provided that the University Hospital would initially operate its financial systems on a shared basis using systems located at SMS Systems corporate headquarters. The University Hospital pays a monthly fee to SMS Systems based upon the volume of transactions and reports. The contract also allows for a conversion from a shared basis to an "in-house" option whereby SMS System licensed software is run on a University owned computer. Due to the potential savings derived by the in-house option, University management recommends that the University Hospital financial systems be converted from a shared to University operated basis at this time. PRICE The estimated operating savings which would result from the conversion of the University Hospital's financial systems from a shared to University operated basis is $1,150,000 per year. The total cost of acquiring the necessary hardware and software is approximately $3,256,000 as follows: IBM 4381 Group III Processors and Required Peripherals $2,252,000 IBM Operating System Software 177,000 SMS Systems Software 827,000 Total $3,256,000 APPROVAL The University requests Board of Visitors approval to contract with IBM and SMS Systems subject to the review and approval of contract documents by the Legal Adviser's Office and University Management.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF SUMMARY OF AUDIT REPORTS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the Summary of Audit Reports for the period January 11, 1985 through March 15, 1985, as presented by the Director of Audits, be and it is hereby approved as recommended by the Audit Committee.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHARGE TO THE PROXY ADVISORY COMMITTEE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the Proxy Advisory Committee be and it is charged with the following responsibilities: 1. Review of the Vice President for Business and Finance's designation of upcoming proxy resolutions as being "social" or "business" and either concurring or recommending changes in such designations to the President. 2. Recommend to the President from the pool of "social" issues those which are of such major import that they require further study and should not routinely be voted as an "abstention." 3. Study those issues so approved by the President with particular emphasis focused on the effects of the proxy resolution involved on the company, society and the University. 4. Study other related issues as the President may direct from time to time. 5. Accept petitions from the community allowing oral presentations if requested. 6. Prepare a written report substantiating the majority of the Committee's specific recommendations by including a description of the Committee's procedure, research findings, analysis and conclusions. Committee members may also submit separate reports of concurring or dissenting recommendations. 7. Appear before the President, Vice President for Business and Finance or Finance Committee upon request to answer questions about a particular report or the Committee's activities in general. 8. Report back to University community such Finance Committee decisions as the President may direct.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">AUTHORIZATION FOR ISSUANCE OF HOSPITAL REVENUE REFUNDING BONDS - SERIES C The following resolution was adopted: WHEREAS, by Article 2, Chapter 9, Title 23, Code of Virginia, 1950, as amended, there is created a corporation under the name and style of The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia (hereinafter sometimes called the "University"), which University is governed by a Board of Visitors (hereinafter sometimes called the "Board") and WHEREAS, by Chapter 3, Title 23, Code of Virginia, 1950, as amended (hereinafter sometimes called the "Act"), the University is classified as an educational institution, is declared to be a public body and is constituted a governmental instrumentality for the dissemination of education; and WHEREAS, by virtue of the Act, the University, with the consent and approval of the General Assembly of the Commonwealth of Virginia and the Governor of the Commonwealth of Virginia, is authorized and empowered (a) to build, construct, reconstruct, erect, extend, better, equip and improve any building, facility, addition, extension or improvement of a capital nature required by or convenient for the purposes of the University, including, without limitation, administration, teaching, lecture and exhibition halls, libraries, dormitories, student apartments, faculty dwellings, dining halls, cafeterias, snack bars, laundries, hospitals, laboratories, research centers, infirmaries, field houses, gymnasiums, auditoriums, student unions, recreation centers, stadiums, athletic facilities, garages, parking facilities, warehouses and storage buildings, book and student supplies centers and all buildings, land and any other appurtenances and equipment necessary or desirable in connection therewith or incidental thereto, (b) to borrow money and make, issue and sell bonds of the University for any of such purposes, such bonds to be issued and sold through the Treasury Board of the Commonwealth of Virginia (hereinafter sometimes called the "Treasury Board") and to be payable only from any one or more of the revenue sources provided therefor in the Act and pledged for their payment, and (c) to fix and revise from time to time and to charge and collect (i) fees, rents and charges for or in connection with the use, occupation or services of each project for which bonds are issued and increases in fees, rents and charges for or in connection with the use, occupation or services of any existing facilities a the University, and (ii) fees, rents and charges for or in connection with the use, occupation or services of any existing facilities at the University. and to pledge the same to payment of the principal of and the interest on such bonds; and WHEREAS, under date of November 1, 1984, the University issued $40,000,000 Fixed Rate Insured Hospital Revenue Bonds (Series A) (the "Series A Bonds") and $110,000,000 Fixed/Adjustable Rate Hospital Revenue Bonds (Series B) (the "Series B Bonds") for the purpose of providing funds, with any other available funds, to finance the cost of constructing and equipping a hospital to replace the existing University of Virginia Hospital, renovating the existing hospital, constructing additional parking facilities and enlarging, improving and expanding the power plant and other portions of the existing hospital (collectively, the "Project"); and WHEREAS, the Board has determined to provide for the issuance of additional bonds of the University for the purpose of refunding all of the outstanding Series A Bonds, $30,000,000 Series B Bonds maturing December 1, 2014, and $40,000,000 Series B Bonds maturing December 1, 2018; and WHEREAS, there have been presented to the Board by officers of the University a plan of finance for providing funds to refund the outstanding bonds described above and documents related thereto, all of which have been filed in the records of the Board; now, therefore, BE IT RESOLVED BY THE BOARD OF VISITORS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA: 1. AUTHORIZATION OF BONDS. The Board hereby authorizes, pursuant to the Act, the issuance, execution and sale of bonds of the University (the "Series C Bonds") to finance, together with other available funds, the costs of refunding all of the Series A Bonds, the $30,000,000 Series B Bonds maturing December 1, 2014, and the $40,000,000 Series B Bonds maturing December 1, 2018 (including the funding of interest, reserves and costs of issuance) and pursuant to Section 23-19 of the Act hereby provides that the terms and conditions of the Series C Bonds shall be specified by the Executive Committee of the Board (the "Executive Committee") subject to the following limitations: a. Maximum principal amount: $110,000,000. b. Maturity: On any date not later than December 1, 2025. c. Interest Rate: Any fixed rate not to exceed 11% per annum. d. Number of series: One or more not to exceed three. e. Date of Series C Bonds: Any date not later than July 1, 1985. f. Interest payment dates: On any date not more frequently than monthly. g. Denominations: Any multiple of $1,000. h. Form of Series C Bonds: Registered. i. Execution; Medium and Place of Payment: As approved by the Executive Committee consistent with the laws of the Commonwealth. j. Redemption: On any date approved by the Executive Committee with a premium not to exceed 4%. k. Sale price: At least par minus (1) a bond discount to underwriters not to exceed 3 1/2%, plus (2) if deemed advisable in connection with the marketing of the Series C Bonds, a discount to investors in an amount to be determined by the Executive Committee. l. Amount of bond proceeds used to purchase bond insurance, letters of credit and other credit enhancements: Not more than 4% of original principal amount of Series C Bonds. m. Security: The Series C Bonds, together with the outstanding Series B Bonds not being refunded and any additional bonds issued pursuant to the Master Resolution adopted by the Executive Committee on November 30, 1984, will be secured by a pledge of the Net Revenues (as defined in said Master Resolution). 2. AUTHORIZATION OF RESOLUTIONS. The Board hereby authorizes the Executive Committee (a) to adopt one or more appropriate series resolutions in substantially the form submitted to the Board at this meeting or such other forms approved by the Executive Committee consistent with the terms and conditions set forth in Paragraph 1 above and (b) to execute and deliver such other documents, including reimbursement agreements with one or more foreign or domestic banking institutions, agreements with one or more bond insurers, and an escrow deposit agreement with Bank of Virginia Trust Company and/or the Treasurer of the Commonwealth of Virginia, and take such action as may be necessary or desirable in connection with the issuance and sale of the Series C Bonds. 3. AUTHORIZATION TO OFFICERS. The Board hereby authorizes all officers and employees of the University to take all action necessary or desirable in connection with the issuance or sale of the Series C Bonds as may be approved by the Rector, President, Vice President for Business and Finance or the Assistant Vice President for Finance.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">AUTHORIZATION TO PARTICIPATE IN COMMONWEALTH OF VIRGINIA 9-C BOND ISSUE The following resolution was adopted: WHEREAS, there has been enacted by the General Assembly of Virginia of 1985 an act entitled "Commonwealth of Virginia Higher Educational Institutions Bond Act of 1985" (the "Act"); WHEREAS, subject to the approval of the Governor, the Treasury Board of the Commonwealth of Virginia shall be authorized to sell and issue bonds of the Commonwealth of Virginia in an aggregate principal amount not currently exceeding $31,109,000 pursuant to the Act, for the purpose of providing funds, with any other available funds, for paying the cost of acquiring, constructing and equipping revenue producing capital projects, including the enlarging and improving thereof, at institutions of higher learning in the Commonwealth, all in accordance with the provisions of Section 9(c) of Article X of the Constitution of Virginia; WHEREAS, said revenue producing capital projects under the Act include the construction of an addition to the Observatory Dining Hall (the "Dining Hall Project"), the construction of an addition to Sponsors Hall (the "Sponsors Hall Project") and the construction of a student activity building (the "Student Activity Building Project") for the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia (the "University") at costs now estimated to equal or exceed $870,000, $2,200,000 and $564,000, respectively (the Dining Hall Project, the Sponsors Hall Project and the Student Activity Building Project are collectively called the "Projects"); WHEREAS, the Treasury Board proposes to sell a portion of the above bonds to be designated "Higher Educational Institutions Bonds, Series 1985" (the "Bonds") which will include an amount not to exceed $3,634,000 for the purpose of financing the cost of the Projects; NOW, THEREFORE, BE IT RESOLVED BY THE BOARD OF VISITORS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA: Section 1. The Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia (the "Board") (a) covenants to fix, revise, charge and collect food service contract fees for or in connection with all of the University-owned student dining facilities, including the Dining Hall Project, and (b) pledges such fees to the payment of the principal of, premium, if any, and interest on that portion of the Bonds issued to finance the Dining Hall Project; provided that the current expenses of operating all of the University-owned student dining facilities, including the Dining Hall Project (the "Dining Facilities Current Expenses") shall be a first charge on such fees. The Board further covenants that such fees will be fixed, revised, charged and collected so that the net revenues received from or for the use of the University-owned student dining facilities, including the Dining Hall Project, after payment of the Dining Facilities Current Expenses, will at all times be sufficient to pay the principal of, premium, if any, and interest on that portion of the Bonds issued to finance the Dining Hall Project as and when the same become due, and to pay debt service on any outstanding obligations that have been previously issued to provide funds for University-owned student dining facilities, that portion of the Bonds issued to finance the Dining Hall Project to be secured on a parity with such obligations. Any such revenues in excess of the amounts required for the payment of the Dining Facilities Current Expenses, the payment of the principal of, premium, if any, and interest on that portion of the Bonds issued to finance the Dining Hall Project when due, and debt service on any outstanding obligations that have been issued to provide funds for University-owned student dining facilities may be used by the University for any other proper purpose. Section 2. It is hereby found, determined, and declared that, based upon responsible engineering and economic estimates and advice of appropriate officials of the University as shown on Exhibit A hereto, the anticipated net revenues received from the food service contract fees pledged above will be sufficient to pay the Dining Facilities Current Expenses, the principal of, premium, if any, and interest on that portion of the Bonds issued to finance the Dining Hall Project as the same become due, and debt service on any outstanding obligations that have been issued to provide funds for University-owned student dining facilities, so long as (i) the effective true interest cost on the Bonds does not exceed 12% per annum and (ii) the aggregate amount of debt service actually payable on that portion of the Bonds issued to finance the Dining Hall Project from their date of issue to the end of any bond year does not exceed the estimated aggregate amount of debt service for the corresponding period as shown on Exhibit A, or the Vice President for Business and Finance provides the Governor and the Treasury Board of the Commonwealth of Virginia with satisfactory evidence that the revenues pledged in Section 1 above will also be sufficient to pay the additional amount of actual debt service which for any such period exceeds the estimated amount shown on Exhibit A. Section 3. The Board (a) covenants to fix, revise, charge and collect fees and rents, including rents payable under a lease between the University and the Darden School Sponsors and a payment due to the University each year from the Darden School Sponsors for or in connection with the entire Sponsors Hall facility, including the Sponsors Hall Project, and (b) pledges said fees and rents to the payment of the principal of, premium, if any, and interest on that portion of the Bonds issued to finance the Sponsors Hall Project; provided that the current expenses of operating the entire Sponsors Hall facility (the "Sponsors Hall Current Expenses") shall be a first charge on such fees and rents. The Board further covenants that such fees and rents will be fixed, revised, charged and collected so that the net revenues from or for the use or otherwise received on behalf of the entire Sponsors Hall facility, including the Sponsors Hall Project, after payment of the Sponsors Hall Current Expenses, will at all times be sufficient to pay the principal of, premium, if any, and interest on that portion of the Bonds issued to finance the Sponsors Hall Project as and when the same become due, and to pay debt service on any outstanding obligations that have been previously issued to provide funds for the Sponsors Hall facility, that portion of the Bonds issued to finance the Sponsors Hall Project to be secured on a parity with such obligations. Any such revenues in excess of the amounts required for the payment of the Sponsors Hall Current Expenses, the payment of the principal of, premium, if any, and interest on that portion of the Bonds issued to finance the Sponsors Hall Project when due, and debt service on any outstanding obligations issued to provide funds for the Sponsors Hall facility may be used by the University for any other proper purpose. Section 4. It is hereby found, determined, and declared that, based upon responsible engineering and economic estimates and advice of appropriate officials of the University as shown on Exhibit B hereto, the anticipated net revenues received from the fees, rents and payments pledged above will be sufficient to pay the Sponsors Hall Current Expenses, the principal of, premium, if any, and interest on that portion of the Bonds issued to finance the Sponsors Hall Project as the same become due, and debt service on any outstanding obligations issued to provide funds for the Sponsors Hall facility, so long as (i) the effective true interest cost on the Bonds does not exceed 12% per annum, and (ii) the aggregate amount of debt service actually payable on that portion of the Bonds issued to finance the Sponsors Hall Project from their date of issue to the end of any bond year does not exceed the estimated aggregate amount of debt service for the corresponding period as shown on Exhibit B, or the Vice President for Business and Finance provides the Governor and the Treasury Board of the Commonwealth of Virginia with satisfactory evidence that the revenues pledged in Section 3 above will also be sufficient to pay the additional amount of actual debt service which for any such period exceeds the estimated amount shown on Exhibit B. Section 5. The Board (a) covenants to fix, revise, charge, and collect that component of the comprehensive student fee known as the "Auxiliary Services Fee" for or in connection with the Student Activity Building Project and other auxiliary enterprise facilities supported by the Auxiliary Services Fee, and (b) pledges the Auxiliary Services Fee to the payment of the principal of, premium, if any, and interest on that portion of the Bonds issued to finance the Student Activity Building Project, provided that the current expenses of operating the Student Activity Building Project and the other auxiliary enterprise facilities supported by the Auxiliary Services Fee (the "Auxiliary Services Current Expenses") shall be a first charge on such Auxiliary Services Fee. The Board further covenants that such Fee will be fixed, revised, charged, and collected so that the net revenues therefrom, after payment of the Auxiliary Services Current Expenses will at all times be sufficient to pay the principal of, premium, if any, and interest on that portion of the Bonds issued to finance the Student Activity Building Project as and when the same become due, and to pay debt service on any outstanding obligations that have been previously issued to provide funds for auxiliary enterprise facilities supported by the Auxiliary Services Fee, that portion of the Bonds issued to finance the Student Activity Building Project to be secured on a parity with such obligations. Any such revenues in excess of the amounts required for the payment of the Auxiliary Services Current Expenses, the payment of principal of, premium, if any, and interest on that portion of the Bonds issued to finance the Student Activity Building Project when due, and debt service on any outstanding obligations issued to provide funds for auxiliary enterprise facilities supported by the Auxiliary Services Fee may be used by the University for any other proper purpose. Section 6. It is hereby found, determined, and declared that, based upon responsible engineering and economic estimates and advice of appropriate officials of the University as shown on Exhibit C hereto, the anticipated net revenues from the Auxiliary Services Fee pledged above will be sufficient to pay the Auxiliary Services Current Expenses, the principal of, premium, if any, and interest on that portion of the Bonds issued to finance the Student Activity Building Project as the same become due, and debt service on any outstanding obligations issued to provide funds for auxiliary enterprise facilities supported by the Auxiliary Services Fee, so long as (i) the effective true interest cost on the Bonds does not exceed 9.5% per annum, and (ii) the aggregate amount of debt service actually payable on that portion of the Bonds issued to finance the Student Activity Building Project from their date of issue to the end of any bond year does not exceed the estimated aggregate amount of debt service for the corresponding period as shown on Exhibit C, or the Vice President for Business and Finance provides the Governor and the Treasury Board of the Commonwealth of Virginia with satisfactory evidence that the revenues pledged in Section 5 above will also be sufficient to pay the additional amount of actual debt service which for any such period exceeds the estimated amount shown on Exhibit C. Section 7. The Board covenants that so long as the Bonds are outstanding, the University will pay to the Treasurer of Virginia not less than 30 days before each interest or principal and interest payment date, the amount certified by the Treasurer of Virginia to be due and payable on such date as principal and interest on that portion of the Bonds issued on behalf of the University to finance the Projects. Section 8. The Board covenants that the University will pay from time to time its proportionate share of all expenses incurred in connection with the sale and issuance of the Bonds and all expenses thereafter incurred in connection with the payment of the principal of, premium, if any, and interest on the Bonds all as certified by the Treasurer of Virginia to the University.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Exhibit A UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA Preliminary Feasibility Study for Addition to Observatory Dining Hall, Approximately 200 Seats Prepared by The University of Virginia Budget Office In Consultation with the Director of Business Operations December 1, 1981 UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA Addition to Observatory Dining Hall, Approximately 200 Seats Project Description The University is planning to construct an addition to Observatory Dining Hall. The project is expected to be completed in July, 1984 at a cost of $871,500 including utilities. We have requested approval of the total project by the General Assembly, and we would like the project to be included in a revenue bond issue for permanent financing. In the vicinity of Observatory Dining Hall, the University is constructing housing for 650 students. Since the present contract facilities are operating at capacity, additional dining space is needed at Observatory Dining Hall to accommodate the students residing in the new housing. The addition will include space for approximately 200 seats, another hot service line, a walk-in cooler and/or freezer and a small storage area for additional volumes of foodstuffs. Payment of the debt will be from food service contract sales. In calculating the debt payment schedule, an interest rate of 12% was used and the payments were extended over 20 years which resulted in coverage of approximately 110%. UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA Addition to Observatory Dining Hall, Approximately 200 Seats Estimated Annual Net Revenue Available for Debt Service for $871,500 Bond Issue Estimated Revenues Food Service Contract Sales (indicates that portion of increased contract sales which are reserved for operating costs and debt service on the new facility) $167,350 Total Estimated Revenues $167,350 Estimated Expenditures Personnel Salaries &amp; Fringe Benefits $ 16,650 Maintenance 19,450 Supplies &amp; Other Contractual Services 2,250 Total Estimated Expenditures $ 38,350 Total Estimated Net Revenues $129,000 UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA DEBT SERVICE SCHEDULE ADDITION TO OBSERVATORY DINING HALL, APPROXIMATELY 200 SEATS INTEREST RATE 12 % YEAR REMAINING PRINCIPAL PRINCIPAL PAYMENT INTEREST PAYMENT TOTAL DEBT SERV PAYT REVENUE COVERAGE 871,500.00 1985 861,500.00 10,000.00 104,580.00 114,580.00 129,000.00 1.13 1986 846,500.00 15,000.00 103,380.00 118,380.00 129,000.00 1.09 1987 831,500.00 15,000.00 101,580.00 116,580.00 129,000.00 1.11 1988 816,500.00 15,000.00 99,780.00 114,780.00 129,000.00 1.12 1989 796,500.00 20,000.00 97,980.00 117,980.00 129,000.00 1.09 1990 776,500.00 20,000.00 95,580.00 115,580.00 129,000.00 1.12 1991 751,500.00 25,000.00 93,180.00 118,180.00 129,000.00 1.09 1992 726,500.00 25,000.00 90,180.00 115,180.00 129,000.00 1.12 1993 696,500.00 30,000.00 87,180.00 117,180.00 129,000.00 1.10 1994 661,500.00 35,000.00 83,580.00 118,580.00 129,000.00 1.09 1995 626,500.00 35,000.00 79,380.00 114,380.00 129,000.00 1.13 1996 586,500.00 40,000.00 75,180.00 115,180.00 129,000.00 1.12 1997 541,500.00 45,000.00 70,380.00 115,380.00 129,000.00 1.12 1998 491,500.00 50,000.00 64,980.00 114,980.00 129,000.00 1.12 1999 431,500.00 60,000.00 58,980.00 118,980.00 129,000.00 1.08 2000 366,500.00 65,000.00 51,780.00 116,780.00 129,000.00 1.10 2001 291,500.00 75,000.00 43,980.00 118,980.00 129,000.00 1.08 2002 211,500.00 80,000.00 34,980.00 114,980.00 129,000.00 1.12 2003 121,500.00 90,000.00 25,380.00 115,380.00 129,000.00 1.12 2004 0.00 121,500.00 14,580.00 136,080.00 129,000.00 0.95 TOTAL 871,500.00 1,476,600.00 2,348,100.00</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Exhibit B UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA Preliminary Feasibility Study for Addition to Sponsors Hall Prepared by The University of Virginia Budget Office December 1, 1981 UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA Addition to Sponsors Hall Project Description The University is planning construction of an addition to Sponsors Hall. This addition will provide additional on-grounds housing facilities for participants in Darden's Executive Programs. The structure is expected to be completed in 1984-85 at a cost of $2,305,500 including utilities. We have requested approval of the total project by the General Assembly, and we would like the project to be included in a revenue bond issue for permanent financing. One of the objectives of the Darden School is to conduct intensive short courses, conferences, and executive training programs for individuals in business. It is most desirable to have eating and living facilities integral with the academic classrooms for these programs. In September .1979, our present facility consisting of Sponsors Hall and Program Center housing (36 units) was opened. When the Darden School planned for Executive Programs housing, it was felt that 36 units would be adequate for the size of class we would attract. The attractiveness of the offerings has been so great that it has been impossible to house all the participants in Sponsors Hall facilities. It is anticipated that the program will not expand to more than 60 participants per program; therefore to avoid the undesirable condition of having a portion of the program participants in other areas, an additional 24 units are needed. The dining area will also be enlarged in order to accommodate the increased number of participants staying in Sponsors Hall facilities. Also, included in the project is a general purpose room which will be used as a meeting room for introductory, evening, and final sessions. Sponsors Hall and Executive Programs Housing are totally self-supporting. Payment of the debt on the additional 24 housing units will be from revenues received from overnight room rent. Rental rates for the addition are expected to be $35 per night. The charge per person per night is at the discretion of the Executive Program and can be varied to meet whatever costs are incurred. In calculating the debt payment schedule, an interest rate of 12% was used and payments were extended over 20 years resulting in coverage of approximately 110%. UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA Addition to Sponsors Hall Estimated Annual Net Revenue Available for Debt Service for $2,305,500 Bond Issue Estimated Revenues Rent: 24 units X $35 per night X 240 days occupancy $201,600 Total Estimated Revenues $201,600 Estimated Expenditures Personal Services &amp; Fringe Benefits $ 23,150 Contractual Services (Utilities, etc.) 29,800 Maintenance 48,100 Total Estimated Expenditures $101,050 Subtotal Net Revenues 100,550 Subsidy from Darden School Sponsors (Supported by a contract with the independent Darden School Sponsors Foundation) 239,450 Total Estimated Net Revenues $340,000 UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA DEBT SERVICE SCHEDULE ADDITION TO SPONSORS HALL INTEREST RATE 12 % YEAR REMAINING PRINCIPAL PRINCIPAL PAYMENT INTEREST PAYMENT TOTAL DEBT SERV PAYT REVENUE COVERAGE 2,305,500.00 1984 2,275,500.00 30,000.00 276,660.00 306,660.00 340,000.00 1.11 1985 2,240,500.00 35,000.00 273,060.00 308,060.00 340,000.00 1.10 1986 2,200,500.00 40,000.00 268,860.00 308,860.00 340,000.00 1.10 1987 2,155,500.00 45,000.00 264,060.00 309,060.00 340,000.00 1.10 1988 2,105,500.00 50,000.00 258,660.00 308,660.00 340,000.00 1.10 1989 2,050,500.00 55,000.00 252,660.00 307,660.00 340,000.00 1.11 1990 1,985,500.00 65,000.00 246,060.00 311,060.00 340,000.00 1.09 1991 1,915,500.00 70,000.00 238,260.00 308,260.00 340,000.00 1.10 1992 1,835,500.00 80,000.00 229,860.00 309,860.00 340,000.00 1.10 1993 1,745,500.00 90,000.00 220,260.00 310,260.00 340,000.00 1.10 1994 1,645,500.00 100,000.00 209,460.00 309,460.00 340,000.00 1.10 1995 1,535,500.00 110,000.00 197,460.00 307,460.00 340,000.00 1.11 1996 1,410,500.00 125,000.00 184,260.00 309,260.00 340,000.00 1.10 1997 1,270,500.00 140,000.00 169,260.00 309,260.00 340,000.00 1.10 1998 1,115,500.00 155,000.00 152,460.00 307,460.00 340,000.00 1.11 1999 940,500.00 175,000.00 133,860.00 308,860.00 340,000.00 1.10 2000 745,500.00 195,000.00 112,860.00 307,860.00 340,000.00 1.10 2001 525,500.00 220,000.00 89,460.00 309,460.00 340,000.00 1.10 2002 280,500.00 245,000.00 63,060.00 308,060.00 340,000.00 1.10 2003 0.00 280,500.00 33,660.00 314,160.00 340,000.00 1.08 TOTAL 2,305,500.00 3,874,200.00 6,179,700.00</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Exhibit C UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA Feasibility Study for Student Activity Building Prepared by the University Budget Office March 13, 1985 UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA Student Activity Building Project Description The University has constructed a Student Activity Building which will accommodate approximately 800 persons. The structure will provide activity space for large meetings and social activities for both on-Grounds and off-Grounds students. The project was completed in November 1984 at a cost of $564,700 including utilities and sitework. The General Assembly authorized the inclusion of this project in a revenue bond issue for permanent financing. For a significant period of time student groups and organizations have faced a scarcity of activity space for large meetings and social activities which would protect them from the elements. Currently, there are approximately 150 student organizations that are in need of activity space. In addition, there are approximately 50 fraternities and sororities that on occasion are in need of space. One of the three buildings previously being used for social activities, Halsey Hall, is being converted to academic space. Since they are smaller in size, the other two facilities do not fully meet the needs of the student body. Payment of the debt will be from a student fee to be assessed to all full-time, regular session students in the amount of $7 per session. In calculating the debt payment schedule, an interest rate of 9.5% was used and the payments were extended over 20 years resulting in coverage of approximately 117%. UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA Student Activity Building Estimated Annual Net Revenue Available for Debt Service of $564,700 Bond Issue Estimated Revenues Student Fees $7 per full-time student x 15,000 students $105,000 Total Estimated Revenues $105,000 Estimated Expenditures Maintenance Services $30,000 Total Estimated Expenditures $30,000 Total Estimated Net Revenue $75,000 UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA DEBT SERVICE SCHEDULE STUDENT ACTIVITY BUILDING INTEREST RATE 9.50% Year Remaining Principal Principal Payment Interest Payment Total Debt Serv Payt Revenue Coverage 564,700 1985-86 554,700 10,000 53,647 63,647 75,000 1.18 1986-87 544,700 10,000 52,697 62,697 75,000 1.20 1987-88 534,700 10,000 51,747 61,747 75,000 1.21 1988-89 519,700 15,000 50,797 65,797 75,000 1.14 1989-90 504,700 15,000 49,372 64,372 75,000 1.17 1990-91 489,700 15,000 47,947 62,947 75,000 1.19 1991-92 469,700 20,000 46,522 66,522 75,000 1.13 1992-93 449,700 20,000 44,622 64,622 75,000 1.16 1993-94 429,700 20,000 42,722 62,722 75,000 1.20 1994-95 404,700 25,000 40,822 65,822 75,000 1.14 1995-96 379,700 25,000 38,447 63,447 75,000 1.18 1996-97 349,700 30,000 36,072 66,072 75,000 1.14 1997-98 319,700 30,000 33,222 63,222 75,000 1.19 1998-99 284,700 35,000 30,372 65,372 75,000 1.15 1999-00 249,700 35,000 27,047 62,047 75,000 1.21 2000-01 209,700 40,000 23,722 63,722 75,000 1.18 2001-02 164,700 45,000 19,922 64,922 75,000 1.16 2002-03 114,700 50,000 15,647 65,647 75,000 1.14 2003-04 59,700 55,000 10,897 65,897 75,000 1.14 2004-05 0 59,700 5,672 65,372 75,000 1.15 564,700 721,905 1,286,605</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CLINCH VALLEY COLLEGE MATTERS ELECTION The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following person be and she is hereby elected to the faculty at Clinch Valley College: Ms. Deborah S. Rouse as Lecturer, General Faculty, for the period February 1, 1985 through June 30, 1985.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RETIREMENT The following retirement was announced: Mr. Stanley H. Botts, Professor of Commerce, Clinch Valley College, effective December 31, 1984. Mr. Botts has been a member of the faculty at Clinch Valley College since September 15, 1955.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ELECTION OF PROFESSOR EMERITUS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following person be and he is hereby elected Professor Emeritus at Clinch Valley College: Mr. Stanley H. Botts, Professor of Commerce at Clinch Valley College.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPOINTMENT The following appointment was announced: Ms. Deborah S. Rouse as Director of Public Relations and Publications at Clinch Valley College, for the period February 1, 1985 through June 30, 1985. On motion, the meeting adjourned at 2:50 p.m. Respectfully submitted, Raymond C. Bice, Jr. Secretary RCB: jb</field>
   </doc>
</add>