<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">University of Virginia, Board of Visitors</field>
      <field name="author_facet">University of Virginia, Board of Visitors</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">university of virginia board of visitors</field>
      <field name="author_text">University of Virginia, Board of Visitors</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1980's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/2006_01/uvaGenText/tei/bov_1989-03-31.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240342</field>
      <field name="date_text">March 31, 1989</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Board of Visitors Minutes, 1817-2002</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Board of Visitors Minutes, 1817-2002</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:183743</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Board of Visitors minutes. March 31, 1989</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Minutes</field>
      <field name="subject_text">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Minutes</field>
      <field name="title_display">Board of Visitors minutes.  March 31, 1989</field>
      <field name="title_facet">board of visitors minutes</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">board of visitors minutes</field>
      <field name="title_text">Board of Visitors minutes.  March 31, 1989</field>
      <field name="year_display">March 31, 1989</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1989-03-31</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1989</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:183743&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;public&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:183743&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;serial volume&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;University of Virginia, Board of Visitors&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;university of virginia, board of visitors&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Board of Visitors minutes. March 31, 1989&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;board of visitors minutes&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;March 31, 1989&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1989-03-31&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="corpname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia, Board of Visitors&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Board of Visitors minutes&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;March 31, 1989&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="edition"&gt;Public minutes&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa call number"&gt;Accession# RG-1/1/&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;a2846310&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;1 v.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="AAT"&gt;Minutes&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;The official minutes contain salary information. Access to minutes containing salary information will be granted only under the procedures of the Virginia Freedom of Information Act (Code of Virginia-2.1-340 ff.) or if permission is granted by the Secretary of the Board. Researchers interested in obtaining access to these records should direct a request in writing to the Office of the Legal Adviser, Madison Hall, University of Virginia. These public minutes have had salary information deleted and bear no restrictions.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Board of Visitors' minutes, Accession # RG-1/1/, Special Collections Dept., University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Minutes of meetings of the university's governing body which is the legal owner and operator of the institution. Recorded in the minutes are appointments and other personnel decisions concerning faculty, decisions about construction of facilities, gifts to the university, and all other board actions, decisions and resolutions.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Board of Visitors minutes&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;1989-03-31&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville, Virginia&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia Library&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;2005&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©2005 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Publicly accessible&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 140 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-BoardOfVisitorsMinutes"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">OFFICIAL MINUTES - TENTATIVE Subject to the Approval of the Board of Visitors THE RECTOR AND VISITORS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA March 31, 1989 The Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia met at 10:10 a.m., in Open Session on March 30, 1989, in the East Oval Room of the Rotunda with the following persons present: Rector Joshua P. Darden, Jr., President Robert M. O'Neil, John S. Battle, Jr., Charles L. Brown, W. L. Lyons Brown, Jr., Robert G. Butcher, Jr., William M. Camp, Jr., Mrs. George M. Cochran, Waller H. Horsley, Glynn D. Key, Lemuel E. Lewis, Mrs. Elizabeth D. Morie, James L. Trinkle, Edgar N. Weaver, Jesse B. Wilson, III, and Thomas E. Worrell, Jr. Absent: Edward E. Elson and S. Buford Scott. Messrs. Ray C. Hunt, Jr., Don E. Detmer, Ernest H. Ern, Raymond M. Haas, Marion B. Peavey, and James J. Mingle were also present. The Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia met at 2:15 p.m., in Open Session on March 31, 1989, in the East Oval Room of the Rotunda with the following persons present: Rector Joshua P. Darden, Jr., President Robert M. O'Neil, John S. Battle, Jr., Charles L. Brown, W. L. Lyons Brown, Jr., Robert G. Butcher, Jr., William M. Camp, Jr., Mrs. George M. Cochran, Edward E. Elson, Waller H. Horsley, Glynn D. Key, Lemuel E. Lewis, S. Buford Scott, James L. Trinkle, Edgar N. Weaver, Jesse B. Wilson, III, and Thomas E. Worrell, Jr. Absent: Mrs. Elizabeth D. Morie. Messrs. Ray C. Hunt, Jr., James J. Mingle, Don E. Detmer, Ernest H. Ern, Raymond M. Haas, Marion B. Peavey, and Paul R. Gross were also present. The Minutes of the meeting of January 27, 1989, previously distributed, were approved as corrected.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">MOTIONS FOR EXECUTIVE SESSION The following motions were unanimously adopted by the vote of all Visitors present: (a) That the Board of Visitors go into Executive Session for consultation with legal counsel pertaining to actual or potential litigation, or other legal matters within the jurisdiction of the Board, as provided for in Section 2.1-344 A. (7) of the Code of Virginia. (b) That the Educational Policy Committee of the Board of Visitors go into Executive Session for Item Number 8 on that Committee's agenda for the discussion or consideration of personnel matters involving University appointees including employment, assignment, appointment, promotion, performance, demotion, salaries, discipling or resignation of public officers, appointees or employees of the University as provided for in Section 2.1-344 A. (1) of the Code of Virginia. (c) That the Finance Committee of the Board of Visitors go into Executive Session for Item Number 20 on that Committee's agenda for the discussion or consideration of the condition, acquisition or use of real property for public purpose, or of the disposition of publicly held property, or of plans for the future of a state institution of higher education which could affect the value of property owned or desirable for ownership by such institution as provided for in Section 2.1-344 A. (3) of the Code of Virginia.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RESOLUTION DESIGNATING THE MARCH 1989 MEETING OF THE BOARD OF VISITORS AS THE ANNUAL MEETING The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the March 1989 meeting of the Board be and it is hereby designated as the Annual Meeting, on recommendation of the Rector and the President. All matters normally taken up in the Annual Meeting will be considered at the March meeting except for the approval of the Annual Budget which will be considered at the May meeting. Following a recess for an Executive Session of the Board of Visitors, the Open Session continued at 2:15 p.m., on March 31, 1989.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPOINTMENT OF STANDING COMMITTEES The Rector announced his appointments to the Standing Committees to serve until the Annual Meeting in May 1990. The Committee assignments are as follows: FINANCE COMMITTEE Mr. John S. Battle, Jr., Chairman Mr. Charles L. Brown Mr. W. L. Lyons Brown, Jr. Mr. Edward E. Elson Mr. Lemuel E. Lewis Mr. S. Buford Scott Mr. Thomas E. Worrell, Jr. STUDENT AFFAIRS AND ATHLETICS COMMITTEE Mr. Jesse B. Wilson, III, Chairman Mr. Robert G. Butcher, Jr. Mr. William M. Camp, Jr. Mrs. George M. Cochran Mr. Waller H. Horsley Miss Glynn D. Key Mr. Lemuel E. Lewis HEALTH AFFAIRS COMMITTEE Dr. Edgar N. Weaver, Chairman Mr. Edward E. Elson Mr. Waller H. Horsley Mrs. Elizabeth D. Morie Mr. James L. Trinkle Mr. Thomas E. Worrell, Jr. BUILDINGS AND GROUNDS COMMITTEE Mrs. George M. Cochran, Chairman Mr. John S. Battle, Jr. Mr. Charles L. Brown Mr. Robert G. Butcher, Jr. Mr. S. Buford Scott Mr. Thomas E. Worrell, Jr. EDUCATIONAL POLICY COMMITTEE Mr. James L. Trinkle, Chairman Mr. W. L. Lyons Brown, Jr. Mr. William M. Camp, Jr. Miss Glynn D. Key Mrs. Elizabeth D. Morie Dr. Edgar N. Weaver Mr. Jesse B. Wilson, III AUDIT COMMITTEE Mr. Charles L. Brown, Chairman Mr. Robert G. Butcher, Jr. Mr. Lemuel E. Lewis Mr. Jesse B. Wilson, III The Rector, Mr. Joshua P. Darden, Jr., is an ex officio member of all Committees.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ELECTION OF THE EXECUTIVE COMMITTEE In compliance with Section 3.1 of the 1985 Manual of the Board of Visitors, the following members were elected to serve on the Executive Committee until the next Annual Meeting in May 1990: Joshua P. Darden, Jr., Chairman, John S. Battle, Jr., Charles L. Brown, Mrs. George M. Cochran, and James L. Trinkle.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ELECTION OF WENDELIN L. "WENDY" WHITE AS NON-VOTING STUDENT MEMBER On the motion of Mr. Jesse B. Wilson, III, Chairman of the Special Committee on Nominating a Non-Voting Student on the Board of Visitors, the Board elected Miss Wendelin L. "Wendy" White as a non-voting student member of the Board of Visitors for the period July 1, 1989 through June 30, 1990 as prescribed in Section 2.21 of The Manual.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCHEDULE OF MEETING DATES FOR 1990 The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following dates for the 1990 meetings of the Board be and they are hereby approved: January 25 and 26, 1990 Charlottesville March 29 and 30, 1990 Charlottesville May 24 and 25, 1990 Charlottesville October 4 and 5, 1990 Charlottesville</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF AMENDMENTS TO THE MANUAL The Manual provides in Section 5.9 that amendments to The Manual may be made at any regular meeting by a majority vote of all of the members of the Board provided that the proposed amendments are included in the notice of the meeting and that the views of the Executive Committee are submitted to the Board. Notice of the following proposed amendments was duly given, along with the statement that the Executive Committee views with favor the amendments set forth in the following resolution: RESOLVED that the following amendments to The Manual be and they are hereby made: A. Introduction to Chapter 4, page 15, shall be changed to read: "The Officers of the Board shall consist of the Rector of the University of Virginia, the President of the University, the Comptroller of the University, the General Counsel of the University, and the Secretary and Assistant Secretary to the Board of Visitors." B. Section 4.6 shall be changed to read "General Counsel of the University". C. Section 4.61 shall be changed to read as follows: "On nomination of the President, the Board shall elect a General Counsel of the University to serve at its pleasure." D. Section 4.62 shall be changed to read as follows: "As the chief legal officer of the University, the General Counsel shall advise the Board and the President, under whose immediate direction he shall be, on all legal matters affecting the University. He shall perform such other duties as may be assigned to him by the Board or the President."</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHANGE IN THE TITLE AND THE EFFECTIVE DATE OF THE ELECTION OF MR. JAMES J. MINGLE AS LEGAL ADVISER OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the effective date of the election of Mr. James J. Mingle, as approved by the Board of Visitors at its meeting on January 27, 1989, be changed to read as follows: Mr. James J. Mingle be and he is hereby elected to the position of Legal Adviser of the University of Virginia, effective March 1, 1989, at a salary for the 1988-1989 year of $80,000; BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED that pursuant to The Manual, his title be and and it is hereby changed to General Counsel of the University, effective March 31, 1989.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ELECTIONS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following persons be and they are hereby elected to the faculty: Dr. David L. Bogdonoff as Assistant Professor of Anesthesiology, for three years, effective July 1, 1989. Ms. Dyanne S. Bostain as Lecturer, General Faculty, Division of Continuing Education, for the period January 1, 1989 through June 30, 1989. Ms. Kay A. Cutler as Lecturer, General Faculty, Alderman Library, for the period February 1, 1989 through June 30, 1991. Dr. Claudette E. Dalton as Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, General Medical Faculty, for the period January 1, 1989 through December 31, 1989. Mr. Russell M. Dancy as Visiting Professor of Philosophy, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Mr. Antonio Ferres as Visiting Professor of Spanish, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Ms. Marie H. Hanigan as Research Instructor in Anatomy and Cell Biology, for one year, effective December 1, 1988. Mr. James P. Holloway as Research Assistant Professor of Engineering Physics and Applied Mathematics, for the period January 1, 1989 through December 31, 1989. Dr. Christopher J. Lander as Assistant Professor of Anesthesiology, for three years, effective July 1, 1989. Dr. Robert B. Lechner as Assistant Professor of Anesthesiology, for three years, effective July 1, 1989. Ms. Jeanne W. Lovelock as Instructor, General Faculty, for one year, effective January 16, 1989. Mr. Douglas A. Lutz as Lecturer in Biology, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Mr. Joseph N. Mait as Visiting Assistant Professor of Electrical Engineering, for the period January 16, 1989 through January 15, 1990. Dr. Paul M. Martha as Research Assistant Professor of Pediatrics, for the period December 1, 1988 through June 30, 1989. Mr. David W. Martin as Lecturer, General Faculty, for three years, effective January 16, 1989. Mr. Robert E. Matson as Professor, General Faculty, for three academic years, effective January 15, 1989. Dr. Russell B. McKelway as Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, for three years, effective July 1, 1989. Mr. James J. Mingle as Lecturer, General Faculty, for five years, effective March 1, 1989. Ms. Jacquelin S. Neatherlin as Instructor, General Faculty, for the period January 3, 1989 through January 1, 1990. Dr. Laura L. Norling as Assistant Professor of Pediatrics, for the period January 16, 1989 through January 15, 1992. Dr. George F. Rich as Assistant Professor of Anesthesiology, for three years, effective January 1, 1989. Ms. Judith G. Robinson as Assistant Professor, General Medical Faculty, The Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, for the period February 1, 1989 through January 31, 1992. Mr. Tim R. Rose as Lecturer, General Faculty, for the period December 19, 1988 through August 31, 1989. Mr. Mantripragda B. Sankaram as Visiting Research Assistant Professor of Biochemistry, for one year, effective February 1, 1989. Dr. David J. Scheiderer as Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, for three years, effective July 1, 1989. Mr. Dennis Slon as Lecturer, General Faculty, for three years, effective February 1, 1989. Mr. Bryan L. Spangelo as Research Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, for the period December 1, 1988 through November 30, 1989. Mr. Gary H. Toops as Lecturer in Slavic Languages and Literatures, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Mr. Enrique R. Torre as Visiting Research Assistant Professor of Neuroscience, for one year, effective December 16, 1988. Ms. Jane F. Walsh as Instructor in Pharmacology, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective December 19, 1988. Ms. Patricia J. Young as Lecturer, General Faculty, Division of Continuing Education, for the period February 1, 1989 through June 30, 1989.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ELECTION OF PART-TIME FACULTY Mr. Michael F. Berube as Instructor in English, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Mr. Herbert L. Beskin as Lecturer in Commerce, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Mr. Robert A. Booth, Jr. as Lecturer in Education, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Mr. William L. Clement as Instructor in Electrical Engineering, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Mr. Malcolm L. Crystal as Instructor in History, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Mr. John E. Dearth as Lecturer in Music, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1988. Mr. William A. Dobrovir as Lecturer in Law, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Ms. Nina H. Dorrance as Instructor in English, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Mr. George H. Fenwick as Lecturer in Planning, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Mr. Danny L. Hawley as Instructor in Oriental Languages, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Mr. Stephen H. Helvin as Lecturer in Law, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Mr. Barry P. Hollar as Lecturer in Commerce, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Ms. Suzanne R. Johnson as Instructor in English, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Mr. John R. Kirk as Lecturer in Architecture, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Mr. John F. Kirn as Instructor in History, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Mr. Francis M. Lawrence as Lecturer in Law, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Mr. Edward A. Lynch as Instructor in Government and Foreign Affairs, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Mr. Jay I. Minnix as Instructor in Electrical Engineering, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Ms. Beverly M. Momsen-Palmore as Lecturer in Education, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Ms. Amy L. Neff as Instructor in Art History, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Ms. Margaret E. Newell as Instructor in History, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Mr. Robert L. O'Connell as Lecturer in History, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Mr. Lawrence E. Payne as Visiting Professor of Applied Mathematics, for the period January 1, 1989 through April 30, 1989. Mr. John B. Rhinelander as Lecturer in Law, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Ms. Kate A. Ritson as Instructor in Studio Art, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Mr. Gregory L. Roper as Instructor in English, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Mr. Joel Schwartz as Lecturer in Government and Foreign Affairs, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Mr. Peter Sebastian as Lecturer in Government and Foreign Affairs, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Ms. Charlotte J. Shelton as Lecturer in Commerce, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Mr. Donald K. Sill as Instructor in Economics, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Ms. Elisabeth W. Sommer as Instructor in History, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Mr. Timothy L. Stenson as Lecturer in Architecture, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Mr. Daniel J. Stuver as Lecturer in Architecture, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Ms. June L. Triplett as Visiting Professor of Nursing, for the period January 1, 1989 through May 31, 1989. Mr. Kunchok Tsering as Visiting Scholar in Religious Studies, for the period January 21, 1989 through April 21, 1989. Mr. David L. Veasey as Instructor in Electrical Engineering, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Mr. Edwin M. Vergason as Lecturer in Landscape Architecture, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Ms. Mary B. Warinner as Lecturer in Landscape Architecture, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Mr. Charles O. Wood as Lecturer in Sociology, for one semester, effective September 1, 1988.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ELECTION OF NON-SALARIED FACULTY Ms. Jean-Marie M. Cook as Visiting Scholar in English, for the period July 15, 1989 through September 30, 1989. Mr. Dongchul Han as Visiting Scholar in Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering, for the period January 9, 1989 through March 31, 1989. Mr. Tetsuya Ishido as Visiting Scholar in English, for the period April 15, 1989 through January 4, 1990. Dr. Thomas M. Kayrouz as Assistant Professor of Pediatrics, Roanoke Program, for the period January 1, 1989 through June 30, 1991. Mr. Franklin G. Miller as Instructor in Biomedical Ethics in Internal Medicine, for the period February 1, 1989 through June 30, 1990. Ms. Jennie L. Moody as Visiting Scholar in Environmental Sciences, for one academic year, effective January 1, 1989. Dr. Lawrence H. Nabors as Assistant Professor of Surgery, Roanoke Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1988. Ms. Claudina I. Rodrigues as Visiting Scholar in Mathematics, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. Luc Sirois as Visiting Scholar in Environmental Sciences, for one year, effective January 1, 1989. Mr. Erik Skibsted as Visiting Scholar in Mathematics, for the period February 1, 1989 through July 31, 1989. Mr. John M. Trischuk as Visiting Professor of Physics, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1989. Captain Donna M. Zerbato as Assistant Professor of Air Science, for the period June 1, 1989 through May 31, 1992.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ELECTION OF CLINICAL FACULTY Dr. E. Virginia Bayliss as Clinical Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, for the period February 1, 1989 through June 30, 1991. Mr. William R. Carter as Clinical Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, for one year, effective January 1, 1989. Dr. Maura K. Dollymore as Clinical Assistant Professor of Nursing, for three years, effective July 1, 1988. Ms. Marylou W. Downs as Clinical Instructor in Nursing, for three years, effective July 1, 1988. Dr. Thomas M. Ehlinger as Clinical Assistant Professor of Nursing, for three years, effective July 1, 1988. Dr. J. Blaine Fitzgerald as Clinical Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, for three years, effective January 1, 1989. Dr. Snowden C. Hall as Clinical Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, for the period March 1, 1989 through June 30, 1991. Dr. Charles L. Halstead as Clinical Professor of Dentistry, for one year, effective January 1, 1989. Ms. Rebecca B. Harmon as Clinical Instructor in Nursing, for three years, effective July 1, 1988. Ms. Annelle V. Hodges as Clinical Instructor in Otolaryngology, for one year, effective January 1, 1989. Dr. Lee R. Jones as Clinical Assistant Professor of Dentistry, Roanoke Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1989. Dr. Phillip J. Klemmer as Clinical Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, for the period February 1, 1989 through January 31, 1992. Dr. Thomas G. Langer as Clinical Assistant Professor of Radiology, for the period February 1, 1989 through June 30, 1991. Dr. Daryl M. Larusso as Clinical Assistant Professor of Nursing, for three years, effective July 1, 1988. Dr. John C. Lystash as Clinical Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, Roanoke Program, for the period February 1, 1989 through June 30, 1991. Ms. Ruth M. Mahler as Clinical Instructor in Nursing, for three years, effective July 1, 1988. Ms. Christine L. Palank as Clinical Instructor in Nursing, for three years, effective July 1, 1988. Dr. Robert A. Schwab as Clinical Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, for the period June 1, 1989 through June 30, 1989.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CORRECTION IN THE SALARY OF THE ELECTION OF MR. CHRISTIAN LINDTNER The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the election of Mr. Christian Lindtner, as Visiting Professor of Religious Studies, as approved by the Board on January 27, 1989, be and it is hereby changed to read as follows: Mr. Christian Lindtner as Visiting Professor of Religious Studies, for the period October 14, 1988 through May 31, 1989.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACTIONS RELATING TO CHAIRHOLDERS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the actions relating to chairholders be and they are hereby approved as shown below: (a) Election of Chairholders Mr. Anthony M. Ames as Harry Shure Visiting Professor of Architecture, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Mr. Jonathan Eaton as Merrill H. Bankard Professor of Economics, effective July 1, 1989. Mr. David Novak as Edgar M. Bronfman Professor of Modern Judaic Studies, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. Henry H. Smith-Miller as Thomas Jefferson Professor of Architecture, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Mr. James A. Verbrugge as Visiting Virginia Bankers Association Professor of Bank Management, for one semester, effective September 1, 1989. (b) Leave of Absence of Chairholder Mr. Douglas J. White, Mac Wade Professor of Engineering, for the period January 1, 1989 through December 31, 1989, without pay, for personal reasons. (c) Change of Title of Chairholder Mr. Hugh P. Kelly from Commonwealth Professor of Physics to Alumni Council Thomas Jefferson Professor of Physics, effective July 1, 1989. (d) Resignation of Chairholder Mr. William B. Spong, John A. Ewald, Jr., Distinguished Visiting Professor of Law, part-time, effective January 16, 1989, to accept the presidency of Old Dominion University.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RE-ELECTIONS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following persons be and they are hereby re-elected to the faculty: Mr. William H. Anderson, Jr. as Associate Professor, General Faculty, for three years, effective September 1, 1989. Ms. Arlene Aveno as Research Assistant Professor of Education, for the period December 1, 1988 through August 31, 1989. Ms. Margaret A. Aycock as Associate Professor, General Faculty, Law Library, for three years, effective July 1, 1989. Ms. Patricia A. Babe as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, Law Library, for three years, effective July 1, 1989. Mr. Michael Bowermaster as Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Western State, for the period March 1, 1989 through June 30, 1991. Mr. Robert T. Canevari as Associate Professor, General Faculty, for five years, effective July 1, 1989. Mr. Zhang Chenggui as Visiting Research Assistant Professor of Pharmacology, for one year, effective February 1, 1989. Ms. Sharon E. Chilcote-Doner as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, part time, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1989. Ms. Patricia F. Coopersmith as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, part time, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. Dewey G. Cornell as Assistant Professor of Education, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. O. Carlton Deale as Research Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, for the period June 1, 1989 through June 30, 1989. Ms. Ellen B. Dunham-Jones as Assistant Professor of Architecture, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. Edward R. Ford as Associate Professor of Architecture, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1989. Ms. Mary C. Gilliam as Associate Professor, General Faculty, Law Library, for three years, effective July 1, 1989. Dr. Linda S. Godleski as Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Western State, for the period January 18, 1989 through June 30, 1989. Mr. Theodore W. Graves, Jr. as Assistant Professor of Nursing, General Nursing Faculty, part time, for one year, effective July 1, 1989. Ms. Helen C. Hamman as Research Assistant Professor of Pharmacology, for one year, effective February 1, 1989. Dr. Marion D. Hargrove as Visiting Professor of Internal Medicine, for the period June 1, 1989 through June 30, 1989. Ms. Audrey A. Irvine as Research Assistant Professor of Nursing, for the period March 1, 1989 through May 31, 1989. Ms. Betty M. Johnson as Visiting Professor of Nursing, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. Harold B. Johnson, Jr. as Scholar in Residence in History, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. Daniel P. Jordan as Scholar in Residence in History, for one academic year, effective July 1, 1989. Mr. Allan M. Judd as Research Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, for the period February 1, 1989 through June 30, 1990. Ms. Julie A. Kaplan as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1989. Dr. William E. Kelly as Visiting Scholar in Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, for the period January 16, 1989 through June 30, 1989. Mr. James R. Klein as Assistant Professor of Landscape Architecture, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1989. Ms. Karen H. Knierim as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, part time, for three years, effective July 1, 1989. Mr. W. Jude LeBlanc as Assistant Professor of Architecture, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. Jechiel Lichtenstadt as Visiting Research Professor of Physics, for the period February 16, 1989 through October 15, 1989. Ms. Jacqueline Lichtman as Associate Professor, General Faculty, Law Library, for the period August 16, 1989 through May 15, 1992. Ms. Catherine L. Macklin as Assistant Professor of Anthropology, for two academic years, effective September 1, 1989. Ms. Lorna Martens as Associate Professor of German, effective September 1, 1989. Ms. Cassandra Maxwell-Simmons as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1989. Mr. Raymond P. McDermott as Visiting Professor of Education, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Mr. Colin A. McLaurin as Research Professor of Biomedical Engineering, part time, for the period February 1, 1989 through January 31, 1992. Mr. George P. Mentore as Assistant Professor of Anthropology, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1989. Ms. Barbara G. Murphy as Associate Professor, General Faculty, Law Library, for three years, effective July 1, 1989. Ms. Anne Mustain as Associate Professor, General Faculty, Law Library, for three years, effective July 1, 1989. Mr. Daniel R. Ortiz as Assistant Professor of Law, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. George A. Overstreet Jr. as Associate Professor of Commerce, effective September 1, 1989. Ms. Joanne H. Peach as Assistant Professor of Nursing, General Nursing Faculty, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. David H. Perrin as Assistant Professor of Education, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. Robert C. Pianta as Assistant Professor of Education, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. William J. Randolph as Assistant Professor, General Medical Faculty, for the period April 1, 1989 through March 31, 1991. Mr. Hans-Peter Roeser as Visiting Associate Professor of Electrical Engineering, for the period March 1, 1989 through March 31, 1989. Ms. Julie A. Roin as Assistant Professor of Law, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1989. Ms. Mary E. Ropka as Assistant Professor of Nursing, part time, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. Arunava Saha as Research Assistant Professor, Institute of Nuclear and Particle Physics, for one year, effective June 1, 1989. Dr. Hidayet Sari as Visiting Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, for the period January 1, 1989 through June 30, 1989. Mr. David W. Sedgwick as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, part time, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1989. Ms. Charlene M. Sedgwick as Associate Professor of English, General Faculty, for five academic years, effective September 1, 1989. Ms. Ellen P. Soroka as Assistant Professor of Architecture, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. Wayne M. Sparks as Associate Professor, General Faculty, for five years, effective July 1, 1989. Dr. Imadeddine A. Tabbara as Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective January 1, 1989. Ms. Sylvia V. Terry as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1989. Mr. Theodore S. Thomas as Assistant Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology, for three years, effective March 16, 1989. Ms. Maria-Michaela Thompson as Research Assistant Professor of Physiology, for the period January 1, 1989 through December 31, 1989. Mr. Rizwan Uddin as Research Assistant Professor of Nuclear Engineering, for the period January 16, 1989 through July 15, 1989. Mr. George B. Vaughan as Visiting Professor of Education, for one semester, effective January 16, 1989. Mr. Arthur L. Weltman as Associate Professor of Education, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. D. Mark Whittle as Assistant Professor of Astronomy, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. A. Bennett Wilson, Jr. as Associate Professor of Orthopaedics and Rehabilitation, General Medical Faculty, for the period February 16, 1989 through April 30, 1989. Mr. Terry G. Wood as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1989.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DELETION OF THE RE-ELECTION OF MR. CARL O. TRINDLE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the re-election of Mr. Carl O. Trindle as Associate Professor, for three years, be deleted from the January 27, 1989 Minutes of the Board of Visitors since Mr. Trindle is already an Associate Professor of Chemistry, without term.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PROMOTIONS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following faculty members be and they are hereby promoted: Mr. James H. Aylor from Associate Professor of Electrical Engineering to Professor of Electrical Engineering, effective July 1, 1989. Mr. Gene D. Block from Associate Professor of Biology to Professor of Biology, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. Herbert Braun from Assistant Professor of History to Associate Professor of History, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. Charles E. Brownell from Assistant Professor of Architectural History to Associate Professor of Architectural History, for three years, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. Clifford E. Brubaker from Associate Professor of Education and Assistant Professor of Orthopedics, to Associate Professor of Education (already without term), and Research Associate Professor of Biomedical Engineering, for the period October 1, 1988 through May 31, 1991. Mr. Giorgio Carta from Assistant Professor of Chemical Engineering to Associate Professor of Chemical Engineering, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. John D. Casey from Associate Professor of English to Professor of English, effective September 1, 1989. Ms. Patricia C. Click from Assistant Professor of Humanities to Associate Professor of Humanities, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. James P. Cohoon from Assistant Professor of Computer Science to Associate Professor of Computer Science, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. Donal B. Day from Research Assistant Professor of Physics to Research Associate Professor of Physics, for the period September 1, 1989 through May 31, 1991. Mr. Scott K. Deveaux from Assistant Professor of Music to Associate Professor of Music, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. Maxim P. Engers from Assistant Professor of Economics to Associate Professor of Economics, effective September 1, 1989. Ms. Grace E. Fielder from Assistant Professor of Slavic Languages and Literatures to Associate Professor of Slavic Languages and Literatures, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. Philip N. Geiger from Assistant Professor of Art to Associate Professor of Art, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. Robert M. Grainger from Associate Professor of Biology to Professor of Biology, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. Jeffrey L. Hantman from Assistant Professor of Anthropology to Associate Professor of Anthropology, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. David Hill from Assistant Professor of Psychology to Associate Professor of Psychology, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. Charles A. Holt from Associate Professor of Economics to Professor of Economics, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. P. Jeffrey Hopkins from Associate Professor of Religious Studies to Professor of Religious Studies, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. James D. Hunter from Assistant Professor of Sociology to Associate Professor of Sociology, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. Barry W. Johnson from Assistant Professor of Electrical Engineering to Associate Professor of Electrical Engineering, effective July 1, 1989. Mr. Alex M. Johnson Jr. from Assistant Professor of Law to Professor of Law, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. Walter P. Jost III from Assistant Professor of Rhetoric and Communication Studies to Associate Professor of Rhetoric and Communication Studies, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. George Klosko from Assistant Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs to Associate Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. David W. LaRue from Assistant Professor of Commerce to Associate Professor of Commerce, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. Malcolm H. Lathan Jr. from Assistant Professor of Commerce to Associate Professor of Commerce, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. Martin D. Levan from Associate Professor of Chemical Engineering to Professor of Chemical Engineering, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. Timothy L. MacDonald from Associate Professor of Chemistry to Professor of Chemistry, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. David M. Maloney from Assistant Professor of Commerce to Associate Professor of Commerce, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. Jack McArdle from Assistant Professor of Psychology to Associate Professor of Psychology, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. James C. McDaniel from Assistant Professor of Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering to Associate Professor of Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. Robert F. McNergney from Associate Professor of Education to Professor of Education, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. Peter A. Metcalf from Associate Professor of Anthropology to Professor of Anthropology, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. David E. Mills from Associate Professor of Economics to Professor of Economics, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. David M. O'Brien from Associate Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs to Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. Gustavo Pellon from Assistant Professor of Spanish, Italian and Portuguese to Associate Professor of Spanish, Italian and Portuguese, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. Larry G. Richards from Research Associate Professor of Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering to Associate Professor of Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering, General Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1989. Dr. Marta C. Sayers from Clinical Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, Roanoke Program to Clinical Associate Professor of Internal Medicine, Roanoke Program, for the period January 1, 1989 through June 30, 1991. Mr. A. John Simmons from Associate Professor of Philosophy to Professor of Philosophy, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. Willis J. Spaulding from Assistant Professor, General Faculty to Associate Professor, General Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1989. Ms. Alison P. Weber from Assistant Professor of Spanish, Italian and Portuguese to Associate Professor of Spanish, Italian and Portuguese, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. Joseph C. Zieman from Associate Professor of Environmental Sciences to Professor of Environmental Sciences, effective September 1, 1989.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">LEAVES OF ABSENCE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following faculty members be and they are hereby granted leave of absence: Mr. Shmuel Agmon, Professor of Mathematics, for the period January 16, 1989 through May 31, 1989, without pay, to teach at the Hebrew University, Israel. Mr. Ronald M. Hartwell, Professor of Economics, for the period January 16, 1989 through May 31, 1989, without pay, to do research. Mr. Hugh S. Landes, Associate Professor of Electrical Engineering, for the period January 16, 1989 through January 15, 1990, with partial pay, to qualify for the early retirement plan as approved by the Board of Visitors. Ms. Catherine L. Macklin, Assistant Professor of Anthropology, for the period November 1, 1988 through January 15, 1989, without pay, for personal reasons. Mr. Edward J. White, Associate Professor of Electrical Engineering, for the period January 16, 1989 through January 15, 1990, without pay, to continue leave of absence.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHANGES OF TITLE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following changes of title be and they are hereby made: Ms. Alice H. Cooper from Acting Assistant Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs to Assistant Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs, for the period January 16, 1989 through January 15, 1993. Dr. William S. Erwin Jr. from Clinical Professor of Internal Medicine, Roanoke Program to Professor of Internal Medicine, Roanoke Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1989. Ms. Susan D. Fraiman from Acting Assistant Professor of English to Assistant Professor of English, for the period December 1, 1988 through May 31, 1991. Mr. Mark Garrison from Instructor in Art History to Lecturer in Art History, for the period November 1, 1988 through May 31, 1989. Dr. Margaret E. Gutgesell from Associate Professor of Pediatrics to Associate Professor of Pediatrics, General Medical Faculty, for the period September 1, 1989 through June 30, 1990. Mr. James S. Kennan from Clinical Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry and Assistant Professor, General Medical Faculty to Assistant Professor, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective January 1, 1989. Ms. Elizabeth A. Meyer from Acting Assistant Professor of History to Assistant Professor of History, for the period January 1, 1989 through May 31, 1992. Mr. Mark E. Parry from Acting Assistant Professor of Business Administration to Assistant Professor of Business Administration, for the period January 16, 1989 through May 31, 1991. Mr. Gary Peller from Associate Professor of Law to Professor of Law, effective January 16, 1989. Mr. Bryan Pfaffenberger from Assistant Professor of Humanities, School of Engineering and Applied Science to Lecturer, General Faculty, for three years, effective September 1, 1989. Ms. Mildred W. Robinson from Associate Professor of Law to Professor of Law, effective January 16, 1989. Mr. Charles F. Schwartz from Research Assistant Professor of Pharmacology to Assistant Professor of Surgery, for three years, effective February 1, 1989. Mr. Jonathan Shiff from Acting Assistant Professor of Italian to Assistant Professor of Italian, for the period December 2, 1988 through May 31, 1992. Ms. Eileen M. Stephens from Research Assistant Professor of Physiology to Assistant Professor of Surgery, for three years, effective February 1, 1989. Mr. Steven P. Wartik from Assistant Professor of Computer Science to Visiting Research Assistant Professor, for the period January 1, 1989 through December 31, 1989. Ms. Patricia A. Yasenchak from Instructor in Orthopaedics and Rehabilitation to Instructor in Orthopaedics and Rehabilitation, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective January 1, 1989.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RETIREMENTS The following retirements were announced: Mr. Julius P. Barclay, Associate Professor, Alderman Library, effective June 30, 1989. Mr. Barclay has been a member of the faculty since September 1, 1973. Mr. Richard O. Bell, Professor of Psychology, effective May 31, 1989. Mr. Bell has been a member of the faculty since September 1, 1974. Dr. Johnson T. Carpenter, Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, effective June 30, 1989. Dr. Carpenter has been a member of the faculty since July 1, 1961. Mr. Piet C. Gugelot, Professor of Physics, effective May 31, 1989. Mr. Gugelot has been a member of the faculty since April 1, 1967. Mr. John F. Hahn, Professor of Psychology, effective May 31, 1989. Mr. Hahn has been a member of the faculty since September 15, 1952. Mr. Robert H. Owens, Professor of Applied Mathematics, effective May 31, 1989. Mr. Owens has been a member of the faculty since September 1, 1964. Mr. Yale Rabin, Professor of Planning, School of Architecture, effective May 31, 1989. Mr. Rabin has been a member of the faculty since September 1, 1975. Dr. Donald H. Shotton, Associate Professor of Internal Medicine and Professor of Family Medicine, Lynchburg Program, effective March 31, 1989. Dr. Shotton has been a member of the faculty since July 1, 1970. Mr. Richard F. Shutts, Professor, General Faculty, effective July 1, 1989. Mr. Shutts has been a member of the faculty since January 1, 1977.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RESIGNATIONS The following resignations were announced: Dr. Charles F. Ballou, III, Clinical Associate Professor of Internal Medicine, effective December 31, 1988, for personal reasons. Ms. Mina H. Braun, Lecturer, General Faculty, Alderman Library, part time, effective May 31, 1989, for personal reasons. Mr. William R. Carter, Research Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, effective December 31, 1988, to enter private practice and be Clinical Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry. Ms. Patricia E. Dix, Instructor in Nursing, General Nursing Faculty, effective May 31, 1989, for personal reasons. Mr. Timothy S. Good, Instructor in English, part time, effective January 15, 1989, to accept a position as graduate instructor. Dr. Debra J. Grossman, Assistant Professor of Dermatology, effective June 30, 1989, for personal reasons. Mr. Mark E. Hawley, Assistant Professor of Environmental Sciences, effective January 15, 1989, to accept another position. Mr. John W. Howard, Lecturer, General Faculty, effective June 30, 1989, for personal reasons. Mr. George C. Jones, Lecturer, General Faculty, effective January 20, 1989, to return to graduate school. Mr. John H. King, Professor, General Faculty, effective January 31, 1989, to accept another position. Dr. DeAnn K. Kutzner, Instructor in Obstetrics and Gynecology, effective June 30, 1989, for personal reasons. Ms. Karen D. Little, Instructor, General Faculty, Alderman Library, effective May 31, 1989, to accept another position. Mr. Roger S. Martin, Lecturer, General Faculty, effective March 15, 1989, to pursue a non-University career. Mr. Xiao-Fan Meng, Visiting Associate Professor of Engineering, effective December 1, 1988, to be Research Associate in Physics. Mr. P. Keith Moxey, Professor of Art History, effective May 31, 1989, to accept another position. Mr. James C. Peterson, Lecturer in Internal Medicine, effective December 31, 1988, to enter private practice. Mr. Charles D. Piot, Lecturer, General Faculty, effective December 31, 1988, to accept another position. Dr. Thomas L. Pope, Jr., Associate Professor of Radiology, effective June 15, 1989, to accept another position. Dr. Michael R. Redler, Instructor in Orthopaedics and Rehabilitation, effective December 31, 1988, to enter private practice. Ms. Susan M. Schultz, Instructor in English, part time, effective January 15, 1989, to accept another position. Mr. Michael A. Thompson, Assistant Professor, General Faculty, effective July 31, 1989, to accept another position. Mr. Sander Weinreb, Visiting Professor of Electrical Engineering, effective December 31, 1988, to accept another position. Dr. William F. Weller, Clinical Assistant Professor of Radiology, Roanoke Program, effective December 31, 1988, to retire from practice. Mr. Daniel F. Wiener, II, Lecturer, General Faculty, effective January 31, 1989, for personal reasons. Dr. Benjamin H. Word, Jr., Clinical Assistant Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology, effective February 15, 1989, for personal reasons.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPOINTMENTS The following appointments were announced: Mr. John D. Lyons as Chairman, Department of French Language and Literature, for three years, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. A. John Simmons as Chairman, Department of Philosophy, for three years, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. Lawrence E. Thomas as Chairman, Department of Mathematics, for three years, effective July 1, 1989. Mr. Chelsea C. White as Chairman, Systems Engineering and Member of the Center for Advanced Studies, for one year, effective January 1, 1989.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RE-APPOINTMENTS The following re-appointments were announced: Mr. Robert T. Canevari as Dean of Students, for five years, effective July 1, 1989. Mr. James F. Childress as Chairman, Department of Religious Studies, for three years, effective July 1, 1989. Mr. William E. Odum as Chairman, Department of Environmental Sciences, for the period July 1, 1989 through June 30, 1990. Mr. Austin E. Quigley as Chairman, Department of English, for four years, effective September 1, 1989. Ms. Sylvia V. Terry as Assistant Dean of Admissions, for three years, effective July 1, 1989. Mr. Terry G. Wood as Associate Vice President and Director of University Development, for three years, effective July 1, 1989.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ELECTION OF PROFESSORS EMERITI The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following persons be and they are hereby elected Professor Emeritus: Mr. Richard Q. Bell, Professor of Psychology. Mr. Piet C. Gugelot, Professor of Physics. Mr. John F. Hahn, Professor of Psychology. Mr. Robert H. Owens, Professor of Applied Mathematics. Mr. Yale Rabin, Professor of Planning, School of Architecture.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DEATH OF MS. NANCY E. HILT Ms. Nancy E. Hilt, Assistant Professor of Nursing, died on February 2, 1989. Ms. Hilt had been a member of the faculty since September 1, 1983.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CLINCH VALLEY COLLEGE CORRECTION IN THE ANNOUNCEMENT OF THE RE-APPOINTMENT OF MR. JERRY D. CARDWELL The President announced that the re-appointment of Mr. Jerry D. Cardwell as Vice Chancellor of Clinch Valley College, for three years, effective July 1, 1988, as reported to the Board on May 27, 1988, be changed to read as follows: Mr. Jerry D. Cardwell as Vice Chancellor, Clinch Valley College, for one year, effective July 1, 1988.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ESTABLISHMENT OF THE HARRY SHURE VISITING PROFESSORSHIP IN ARCHITECTURE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that there is hereby established in the School of Architecture a Chair to be known as the Harry Shure Visiting Professorship in Architecture, this Chair to become effective January 1, 1989. The Board is grateful to Mr. Michael Shure who made the establishment of this Chair possible.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ESTABLISHMENT OF THE NANCY AND NEAL WADE PROFESSORSHIP IN ENGINEERING AND APPLIED SCIENCE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that there is hereby established in the School of Engineering and Applied Science a Chair to be known as the Nancy and Neal Wade Professorship in Engineering and Applied Science. The Board is grateful to Mr. Neal O. Wade, Jr., who made the establishment of this Chair possible.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ESTABLISHMENT OF THE BARRON F. BLACK RESEARCH PROFESSORSHIP IN LAW The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that there is hereby established in the School of Law a Chair to be known as the Barron F. Black Research Professorship in Law. The Board is grateful to Mrs. Aileen T. Black who made the establishment of this Chair possible.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RESCINDING ACTION OF AUGUST 1, 1973 WITH RESPECT TO THE ESTABLISHMENT OF THE DISTINGUISHED PUBLIC SERVICE PROFESSORSHIP OF GOVERNMENT The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the action of the Executive Committee for the Board of Visitors of August 1, 1973, establishing the Distinguished Public Service Professorship of Government, be and it is hereby rescinded.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ESTABLISHMENT OF THE WALKER COWEN MEMORIAL PRIZE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that there is hereby established in memory of the late Walker Cowen an award to be known as The Walker Cowen Memorial Prize, which is to take the form of a cash award (amount to be determined) and an appropriately inscribed certificate. The award is to be made for an outstanding original work of scholarship in Eighteenth Century Studies in history, literature, philosophy, or the arts published by the University Press of Virginia. The award shall be made on a biennial basis and will be withheld unless original scholarship meriting the award is offered to the University Press of Virginia and accepted for publication during the biennium. The original work of scholarship for which the award is to be made will be determined by a distinguished panel of three scholars appointed by the Provost at least one of whom should not be affiliated with Virginia institutions of higher education, none of whom are members of the Committee for the University Press of Virginia during the biennium for which the selection is made, and all of whom have an interest in Eighteenth Century Studies. The members of the panel shall receive reasonable compensation for their work. Manuscripts to be submitted to the panel for its consideration should be selected by the Director of the University Press of Virginia.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF THE REVISION OF THE RESOLUTION REGARDING HEALTH INSURANCE FOR STUDENTS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that effective September 1, 1989, it shall be the policy of the University to require all University of Virginia students (except those enrolled in the Division of Continuing Education) and all Clinch Valley College students to carry health insurance and that, in selecting an insurance plan, the student shall have a choice between an insurance plan sponsored by the University of Virginia Student Council or one that the student or his/her parents considers comparable to that plan.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">REPORT OF THE HOSPITAL ACCOUNTS COMMITTEE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the Hospital Accounts Committee be and it is hereby authorized to write off as bad debts and free service accounts included in the University of Virginia Hospital Accounts Committee Reports for the meeting of January 20, 1989 which includes the write-offs for the months of December 1988 and January 1989 totaling $10,434,858.89 and consisting of the following: Bad Debt $1,945,914.73 Indigent Care 8,488,944.16 ------------ $10,434,858.89 RESOLVED FURTHER, that the above action shall not be a compromise, settlement or discharge of debts represented by such accounts.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">REPORT ON CONSTRUCTION The President reported that in the University Division, there are contracts totaling $84 million from general funds. In the Hospital Division, contracts total $28 million from general funds. Contracts for Clinch Valley College total $1 million from general funds.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF INCREASE IN INTEREST RATE ON UNIVERSITY FACULTY HOME MORTGAGE LOANS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that effective March 31, 1989, the interest rate on University faculty home mortgage loans shall be increased from 9 1/2% to 10 1/4%.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF THE FIRM OF THOMPSON &amp; LITTON, INCORPORATED, FOR THE PERFORMANCE OF A PREPLANNING STUDY FOR RENOVATION OF THE ZEHMER BUILDING AT CLINCH VALLEY COLLEGE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the firm of Thompson &amp; Litton, Incorporated, of Wise, Virginia, be approved for the performance of a preplanning study for renovation of the Zehmer Building at Clinch Valley College. At the option of the University administration, the firm may later be continued for full architectural design services upon approval of the project by State government.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF THE FIRM OF DEWBERRY &amp; DAVIS FOR THE PERFORMANCE OF A PREPLANNING STUDY FOR NEW CONSTRUCTION OF A CLASSROOM BUILDING AND OUTSIDE UTILITIES AT CLINCH VALLEY COLLEGE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the firm of Dewberry &amp; Davis of Marion, Virginia, be approved for the performance of a preplanning study for new construction of a classroom building and outside utilities at Clinch Valley College. At the option of the University administration, the firm may later be continued for full architectural design services upon approval of the project by State government.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF THE FIRM OF DEWBERRY &amp; DAVIS FOR THE PERFORMANCE OF A PREPLANNING STUDY FOR RENOVATION OF THE MARTHA RANDOLPH HALL AT CLINCH VALLEY COLLEGE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the firm of Dewberry &amp; Davis of Marion, Virginia, be approved for the performance of a preplanning study for renovation of the Martha Randolph Hall at Clinch Valley College. At the option of the University administration, the firm may later be continued for full architectural design services upon approval of the project by State government.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF THE FIRM OF MICHAEL DENNIS, JEFFREY CLARK AND ASSOCIATES FOR THE PERFORMANCE OF A PREPLANNING STUDY FOR THE FINE ARTS FACILITIES, SCHOOL OF ARCHITECTURE ADDITION AND OUTSIDE UTILITIES/MCINTIRE DEPARTMENT OF ART FACILITIES AND OUTSIDE UTILITIES The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the firm of Michael Dennis, Jeffrey Clark and Associates of Boston, Massachusetts, be approved for the performance of a preplanning study for the Fine Arts Facilities, School of Architecture Addition and Outside Utilities/McIntire Department of Art Facilities and Outside Utilities. At the option of the University administration, the firm may later be continued for full architectural design services upon approval of the project by State government.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF THE FIRM OF VMDO IN ASSOCIATION WITH WILLIAMS, TSEIN AND ASSOCIATES FOR THE PERFORMANCE OF A PREPLANNING STUDY FOR THE STUDENT DINING FACILITY AND ARCHITECTURAL DESIGN OF STUDENT HOUSING FOR 500 The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the firm of VMDO of Charlottesville, Virginia, in association with Williams, Tsein and Associates of New York, New York, be approved for the performance of a preplanning study for the Student Dining Facility and architectural design of Student Housing for 500. At the option of the University administration, the firm may later be continued for full architectural design services of the dining facility upon approval of the project by State government.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ANNOUNCEMENT OF ARCHITECTURAL SELECTIONS FOR THE RENOVATION OF RESEARCH SPACES The President announced the following architectural selections for renovation of research spaces: The CEGG Partnership Virginia Beach, Virginia Ekstrom and Associates Richmond, Virginia Ayers/Saint/Gross Baltimore, Maryland Cooper Lecky Architects Washington, D. C. (This is an "umbrella" project for miscellaneous minor renovations. Architects have been selected and projects will be assigned to an appropriate firm from the slate selected.)</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SETTLEMENT OF CLAIMS FOR SERVICES RENDERED BY THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA MEDICAL CENTER The following resolution was adopted: WHEREAS, Section 2.1-127 of the Code of Virginia states that the Attorney General shall have the authority to settle any dispute, claim or controversy involving the interests of the Commonwealth, provided that such action has first been approved by the head of the department, institution, division, board or bureau which is interested; WHEREAS, the Medical Center is now working directly with the Office of the Attorney General in matters of settlement related to debts owed for patient care services; NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED that for the purpose of complying with this Section, the Executive Director of the University of Virginia Medical Center is granted the authority to act on behalf of the University of Virginia to negotiate settlements related to the Medical Center's billing for goods and services that it has rendered, subject to final approval by the Attorney General or, in certain cases, the Governor.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">INCREASE IN APPLICATION FEES FOR THE ACADEMIC DIVISION The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following schedule of application fees be and they are hereby approved, effective July 1, 1989: Fees Collected After Present July 1, 1989 Undergraduate $25 $30 Graduate (except Law and Darden) $20 $30 Law (including Graduate Law) $30 $40 Darden (including DBA) $30 $50 Medicine $50 $50</field>
      <field name="fulltext">INCREASE IN TUITION AND REQUIRED FEES AND OTHER CHARGES FOR THE ACADEMIC DIVISION The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the tuition and required fees and other charges applicable to the Academic Division be and they are hereby approved as shown below, effective July 1, 1989: REGULAR SESSION: Virginian Non-Virginian Actual 1988-89 Amt. Inc. Percent of Inc. Proposed 1989-90 Actual 1988-89 Amt. Inc. Percent of Inc. Proposed 1989-90 Tuition and Required Fees Undergraduate and Graduate Schools-Full Time $2,500 $180 7.2% $2,680 $6,310 $750 11.9% $7,060 Medical Technology 1,280 80 6.3% 1,360 1,280 80 6.3% 1,360 Professional Schools Graduate Bus.- MBA 4,350 290 6.7% 4,640 9,230 890 9.6% 10,120 Law-JD 3,710 350 9.4% 4,060 8,030 890 11.1% 8,920 Medicine - MD 6,070 370 6.1% 6,440 12,340 980 7.9% 13,320 Activity Fees General-All Students 26 2 7.7% 28 26 2 7.7% 28 Architecture 10 10 100.0% 20 10 10 100.0% 20 Commerce 10 -- -- 10 10 -- -- 10 Darden 32 -- -- 32 32 -- -- 32 Education 4 -- -- 4 4 -- -- 4 Engineering 4 6 150.0% 10 4 6 150.0% 10 Law School 28 -- -- 28 28 -- -- 28 Medicine 70 -- -- 70 70 -- -- 70 Nursing 10 -- -- 10 10 -- -- 10 Residential College Programming Fee 100 -- -- 100 100 -- -- 100 INCREASE IN TUITION AND REQUIRED FEES AND OTHER CHARGES FOR THE ACADEMIC DIVISION (continued) CONTINUING EDUCATION: Current 1988-89 Amount of Increase Percent Increase Proposed 1989-90 Undergrad. and Grad. (Non-Degree Programs) Per Semester Hour Virginian $ 80.00 $ 8.00 10.0% $ 88.00 Non-Virginian 90.00 14.00 15.6% 104.00 Special Students Registering through and admitted by the Division of Continuing Education in On-Grounds Courses Per semester hour Virginian 110.00 10.00 9.1% 120.00 Non-Virginian 110.00 226.00 205.5% 336.00 Masters Degree Programs Per semester hour Virginian 90.00 8.00 8.9% 98.00 Non-Virginian 90.00 24.00 26.7% 114.00 Graduate Televised Engineering Per Semester Hour Virginian 132.00 -- -- 132.00 Non-Virginian 252.00 46.00 18.3% 298.00 Admission Fee in Certificate and Special Programs 10.00 -- -- 10.00 Late Registration Fee 10.00 -- -- 10.00 Change of Course Fee 10.00 -- -- 10.00 Transcript Fee 2.00 -- -- 2.00 Late Exam Fee 5.00 -- -- 5.00 TIAA Fee for Students Registered in Off-Campus Degree Programs Per Course 10.00 (10.00) -- 0.00 Other Miscellaneous Fees as Established to Recover Expenses such as Laboratory, Materials, etc., on a Basis of Estimated Cost. OTHER: Other contracted course and cooperative program tuition and required fee rates approved on a basis consistent with University contracting policies and procedures by the Associate Vice President for Budget and Planning.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">INCREASE IN TUITION AND REQUIRED FEES AND OTHER CHARGES FOR CLINCH VALLEY COLLEGE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the tuition and required fees and other charges applicable to Clinch Valley College be and they are hereby approved as shown below, effective July 1, 1989: Virginian Non-Virginian Actual 1988-89 Amt. of Inc. Percent of Inc. Proposed 1989-90 Actual 1988-89 Amt. of Inc. Percent of Inc. Proposed 1989-90 Tuition and Required Fees Full-time Students (12 semester hours or more per semester) Session Rate $1,574 $296 18.8% $1,870* * Tuition $1,468 + Fees $402 = $1,870 $2,534 $804 31.7% $3,338** ** Tuition $2,936 + Fees $402 = $3,338 Students taking more than 18 credit hours per semester must pay for the additional hours at the part-time tuition rates listed below. Part-time Students (less than 12 semester hrs per semester) Rate per semester hour $52 $8 15.4% $60 $92 $28 30.4% $120 Off-Campus Instruction Credit Courses - Rate per semester hour $52 $8 15.4% $60 $92 $28 30.4% $120 Non-Credit Courses - Rate per CEU $18 $2 11.1% $20 $32 $8 25.0% $40 Dormitory Rent Dorms $1,180 $140 11.9% $1,320 $1,180 $140 11.9% $1,320 Apt. House $1,340 $160 11.9% $1,500 $1,340 $160 11.9% $1,500 Meal Plan 19 meals per week $1,340 $80 6.0% $1,420 $1,340 $80 6.0% $1,420 Other Fees Application Fee $15 $0 0% $15 $15 $0 0% $15 Applied Music Fee $120 $0 0% $120 $120 $0 0% $120 The Applied Music Fee is applicable to Applied Music Courses 104, 105, 108, 109, 204, 205, 304, 305, 404, and 405 and is in addition to all other tuition and required fees. A registration fee for part-time students will be $15 per semester hour. There will be no registration fee for off-campus courses. The graduation fee will be $35 per year.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ALLOCATION OF REQUIRED FEES The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the fee component of the tuition and required fees be and it is hereby established, effective July 1, 1989, in the amount of $540.00; RESOLVED FURTHER that the fee component be allocated for the 1989-90 Session as follows: Actual 1988-89 Amount of Inc/(Decr) Percent of Inc/(Decr) Proposed 1989-90 Pledged for Facilities - University Hall $ 15.00 ---- ----- $ 15.00 University Transit 52.00 ---- ----- 52.00 Auxiliary Services Fee (including debt service) 56.00 $ 42.00 75.0% 98.00 Fringe Benefits 105.00 (42.00) (40.0%) 63.00 Athletics 80.00 8.00 10.0% 88.00 Student Health 151.00 12.00 8.0% 163.00 University Union 41.00 4.00 9.8% 45.00 University Union Programs 16.00 ----- ----- 16.00 Class Affiliation 4.00 (4.00) (100.0%) 0.00 TOTAL $520.00 $ 20.00 3.8% $540.00</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CONTRACT RATES FOR DINING SERVICES, 1989-1990 The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the student contract rates for dining services be and they are hereby approved as shown below, effective beginning with the Session 1989-1990: Dining Service Contract Actual 1988-89 Amount of Increase Percent Increase Proposed 1989-90 7-Day (19 meals) $1,518 $ 0 0% $1,518 6 Meals per week $ 664 $ 0 0% $ 664 12 Meals per week $1,306 $ 0 0% $1,306 Flex (15 meals) $1,428 $ 0 0% $1,428 Residential College 7-Day (19 meals) $1,668 $ 0 0% $1,668 6 Meals per week $ 814 $ 0 0% $ 814 12 Meals per week $1,456 $ 0 0% $1,456 Flex (15 meals) $1,578 $ 0 0% $1,578 Athletics 12 Meals per week $1,392 $ 0 0% $1,392 19 Meals per week $1,604 $ 0 0% $1,604 French House 4 Meal Dinners $ 578 $ 0 0% $ 578 Rates for alternate meal plans proposed by ARA Services are subject to approval of the Associate Vice President for Budget and Planning.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">INCREASE IN FACULTY AND STAFF HOUSING RATES FOR 1989-1990 The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the faculty and staff housing rates be and they are hereby approved as indicated, effective July 1, 1989: Utilities Furnished by UVA Facility WS (Water, Sewer) E (Electricity) O (Fuel Oil) G (Gas) HP (Heating Plant) Rents 1988-89 per Month Amount of Increase Percent of Increase Proposed Rents 1989-90 per Month Utilities Paid By Occupant Piedmont Estates 1 Bedroom Apt. (7) WS, E, O $305 $ 15 4.9% $320 2 Bedroom Apt. (16) WS, E, O $355 $ 25 7.0% $380 3 Bedroom Houses (16) WS $370 $ 30 8.1% $400 O, E Townhouses (10) 3 BR WS $370 $ 30 8.1% $400 E Farmhouse (121 Mimosa) Apt. 1, 1 Bedroom WS, E, O $280 $ 30 10.7% $310 Apt. 2, 3 Bedrooms WS, E, O $315 $ 30 9.5% $345 Apt. 3, 1 Bedroom WS, E, O $280 $ 30 10.7% $310 Apt. 4, 2 Bedrooms WS, E, O $290 $ 30 10.3% $320 Gildersleeve/Snowden Monroe Lane 1 Bedroom (15) WS, G $260 $ 20 7.7% $280 E Efficiency (1) WS, G $225 $ 15 6.7% $240 E 404 Monroe Lane (2BR) WS, G $300 $ 30 10.0% $330 E 412A Monroe Lane (2BR) WS, G $330 $ 25 7.6% $355 E 412B Monroe Lane (Eff) WS, G $220 $ 20 9.1% $240 E Snowden Apt. 1 (1 BR) WS, G $265 $ 20 7.6% $285 E Apt. 2 (1 BR) WS, G $265 $ 20 7.6% $285 E Apt. 6 (Efficiency) WS, G $225 $ 15 6.7% $240 E Apt. 101 (3 BR) WS, G $390 $ 30 7.7% $420 E Apt. 103 (2 BR) WS, G $330 $ 25 7.6% $355 E Apt. 201 (1 BR) WS, G $265 $ 20 7.6% $285 E Apt. 202 (1 BR) WS, G $265 $ 20 7.6% $285 E Apt. 203 (2 BR) WS, G $330 $ 25 7.6% $355 E Sundry Vyssotsky Cottage (3BR) WS $315 $ 30 9.5% $345 E, O Upper Alden (3 BR) WS, O $340 $ 40 11.8% $380 E Lower Alden (2 BR) WS, O $305 $ 30 9.8% $335 E South Cottage (3 BR) WS $165 $ 15 9.1% $180 E, O Carrs Hill (2 BR) WS, E, HP $310 $ 30 9.7% $340 McGuffey Cottage (Eff) HP, E, WS $215 $ 25 11.6% $240 2400 Stadium Rd (4 BR) $425 $ 25 5.9% $450 WS, G, E Upper Mews (1 BR) HP, E, WS $255 $ 25 9.8% $280 Lower Mews (1 BR) HP, E, WS $300 $ 35 11.7% $335 Monroe Hill Range (2BR) HP, WS $375 $ 25 6.7% $400 E Monroe Hill Apts. (2BR) HP, E, WS $310 $ 30 9.7% $340 Milton Airport (1BR) $150 $ 15 10.0% $165 WS,E INCREASE IN FACULTY AND STAFF HOUSING RATES FOR 1989-90 Utilities Furnished by UVA Facility WS (Water, Sewer) E (Electricity) O (Fuel Oil) G (Gas) HP (Heating Plant) Rents 1988-89 per Month Amount of Increase Percent of Increase Proposed Rents 1989-90 per Month Utilities Paid By Occupant Birdwood Properties Cottage (1 BR) WS, $240 $20 8.3% $260 E Garage Apt. (2 BR) WS, E, O $360 $30 8.3% $390 Cash House (3 BR) WS, E, O $370 $40 10.8% $410 Faulkner Property Holly House (2 BR) WS, E, O $310 $20 6.5% $330 Holly House Lower (1RM) WS, E, O $140 $20 14.3% $160 Hedge House (2 BR) WS $250 $50 20.0% $300 E, O Orchard House (5SRMS) WS, E, O $140 $20 14.3% $160 Carriage House (4 BR) WS $300 $50 16.7% $350 E, O 118 Oakhurst Circle Upper (2 BR) WS, G $315 $30 9.5% $345 E Lower (2 BR) WS, G $355 $35 9.9% $390 E Valley Road Property 409 Valley Road (2 BR) -- $300 $30 10.0% $330 WS,E,O 411 Valley Road (2 BR) -- $300 $30 10.0% $330 WS,E,G 503 Valley Road (1 BR) -- $245 $25 10.2% $270 WS,E,G Faculty Apartments Apt. 11 (2 BR) WS, E, G $325 $35 10.8% $360 Apt. 12 (2 BR) WS, E, G $325 $35 10.8% $360 Apt. 14 (2 BR) WS, E, G $325 $35 10.8% $360 Apt. 15 (2 BR) WS, E, G $325 $35 10.8% $360 Apt. 21 (Eff) WS, E, G $245 $25 10.2% $270 Apt. 22 (1 BR) WS, E, G $250 $25 10.0% $275 Apt. 23 (Eff) WS, E, G $235 $25 10.6% $260 Apt. 24 (1 BR) WS, E, G $250 $25 10.0% $275 Apt. 25 (1 BR) WS, E, G $255 $25 9.8% $280 Apt. 26 (1 BR) WS, E, G $255 $25 9.8% $280 Apt. 27 (1 BR) WS, E, G $255 $25 9.8% $280 Apt. 28 (1 BR) WS, E, G $255 $25 9.8% $280 Apt. 31 (1 BR) WS, E, G $255 $25 9.8% $280 Apt. 32 (1 BR) WS, E, G $255 $25 9.8% $280 Apt. 33 (2 BR) WS, E, G $280 $30 10.7% $310 Apt. 34 (2 BR) WS, E, G $280 $30 10.7% $310 Apt. 35 (2 BR) WS, E, G $280 $30 10.7% $310 Apt. 36 (2 BR) WS, E, G $280 $30 10.7% $310 INCREASE IN FACULTY AND STAFF HOUSING RATES FOR 1989-90 Utilities Furnished by UVA Facility WS (Water, Sewer) E (Electricity) O (Fuel Oil) G (Gas) HP (Heating Plant) Rents 1988-89 per Month Amount of Increase Percent of Increase Proposed Rents 1989-90 per Month Utilities Paid By Occupant E. &amp; G. Property: Montebello (3 BR) O $390 $20 5.1% $410 WS,E,G Big Morea (4 BR) WS, E, O $290 $15 5.2% $305 Little Morea (1 BR) WS, E, O $260 $15 5.8% $275 Sunnyside (4 BR) O $500 $25 5.0% $525 WS,E Hotel D (2 BR) WS, E, HP $250 $10 4.0% $260 Monroe Hill House WS, E, HP $500 $25 5.0% $525 Pavilions Pavilion I WS, HP, E $480 $25 5.2% $505 Pavilion II WS, HP $340 $20 5.9% $360 E Pavilion III WS, HP, E $480 $25 5.2% $505 Pavilion IV WS, HP $340 $20 5.9% $360 E Pavilion V WS, HP $340 $20 5.9% $360 E * * Will be vacant during FY 1989-90. Pavilion V Annex WS, HP E * Pavilion VI WS, HP $340 E Pavilion VIII Lower WS, HP $115 $ 5 4.4% $120 E Pavilion VIII Upper WS, HP $230 $10 4.4% $240 E Pavilion IX WS, HP $340 $20 5.9% $360 E Pavilion X WS, HP $340 $20 5.9% $360 E Blue Ridge Properties Bldg 913A (2/3 BR Apt) HP, WS, E $445 $50 11.2% $495 + + Facilities have been removed from residential use. Bldg 913B (2/3 BR Apt) HP, WS, E $445 + Bldg 903 Dorm Rooms (1) HP, WS, E $102 Blandy Farm Curator's House WS $275 $10 3.6% $285 E,O Farmhouse WS $250 $20 8.0% $270 E,O ** ** Agreement of service in lieu of rent has been approved. Superintendent's House WS $ 0 -- -- $ 0 E,O</field>
      <field name="fulltext">INCREASE IN RESIDENTIAL HOUSING RATES FOR CLINCH VALLEY COLLEGE, 1989-1990 The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the Residential Housing Rates applicable to Clinch Valley College be and they are hereby approved as shown below, effective September 1, 1989: Proposed Rents 1989-90 Per Month Utilities Furnished By Clinch Valley College Rents 1988-89 per Month Facility WS (Water, Sewer) G (Gas) Amount of Increase Percent of Increase Houses (6) WS $ 300 $ 36 12.0% $ 336 2 Bedroom Apt. (2) WSG $ 300 $ 36 12.0% $ 336 1 Bedroom Apt. (2) WSG $ 270 $ 36 13.3% $ 306</field>
      <field name="fulltext">INCREASE IN THE FACULTY SALARY SCALE FOR THE UNIVERSITY The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following compensation plans applicable to the teaching and research staff in the Academic Division be and they are hereby approved, effective July 1, 1989: 1988-89 Normal Entrance Rate (1) (1) Amounts are stated on a session basis unless otherwise indicated. 1989-90 Proposed Normal Entrance Rate (1) Normal Increment Amount Interval General Faculty Professor $41,200 $42,800 (2) (2) 0-15%; amounts in excess of 15% are approved as special salary actions. 1 year Associate Professor 33,800 35,200 (2) 1 year Assistant Professor 27,500 28,600 (2) 1 year Instructor 19,400 20,200 (2) 1 year Pre-Clinical Faculty (3) (3) Amounts in this category are stated on an annual (12-month) basis. Department Head 54,700 56,900 (2) 1 year Professor 47,900 49,800 (2) 1 year Associate Professor 39,400 41,000 (2) 1 year Assistant Professor 31,700 33,000 (2) 1 year Instructor 24,800 25,800 (2) 1 year Junior Staff (3) Research Assistant 15,800 16,500 (2) 1 year Research Associate 16,000 17,000 (2) 1 year Sponsored Programs (3) Research Scientist 26,700 26,700 (2) 1 year Senior Scientist 33,500 33,500 (2) 1 year Principal Scientist 51,400 51,400 (2) 1 year</field>
      <field name="fulltext">INCREASE IN FACULTY SALARY SCALE FOR CLINCH VALLEY COLLEGE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following compensation plan applicable to the teaching and research staff of Clinch Valley College be and it is hereby approved, effective July 1, 1989: 1988-89 Normal Entrance Rate (1) (1) Amounts are stated on a session basis. Proposed 1989-90 Normal Entrance Rate (1) Normal Increment Rank Amount Interval Professor $31,400 $32,000 (2) (2) 0-15%; amounts in excess of 15% are approved as special salary actions. 1 year Associate Professor $27,000 $27,500 (2) 1 year Assistant Professor $23,000 $23,500 (2) 1 year Instructor $19,400 $20,000 (2) 1 year</field>
      <field name="fulltext">INCREASE IN CLINICAL AND PATHOLOGY FACULTY SALARY CEILINGS FOR THE SCHOOL OF MEDICINE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that subject to the approval of the Governor, the full-time Clinical and Pathology Faculty Salary Ceilings shall be as follows, effective July 1, 1989: Current Scale 1988-89 Proposed Scale 1989-90 Rank State Maximum Ceilings State Maximum Ceilings Professor and Department Head $76,200 $185,800 $81,300 $198,400 Professor and Division Head 72,200 171,900 77,100 186,600 Professor 69,400 165,200 74,100 179,400 Associate Professor and Division Head 62,800 153,100 67,000 162,300 Associate Professor 60,300 147,100 64,400 155,900 Assistant Professor 53,400 130,100 57,000 138,000 Instructor 41,600 101,400 44,700 108,300</field>
      <field name="fulltext">AUTHORIZATION FOR THE VICE PRESIDENT FOR BUSINESS AND FINANCE AND ASSISTANT VICE PRESIDENT FOR FINANCE TO SIGN CONTRACTS WITH THE VIRGINIA COLLEGE BUILDING AUTHORITY FOR LEASED EQUIPMENT NOT EXCEEDING $3.8 MILLION The following resolution was adopted: WHEREAS, the Virginia College Building Authority (the Authority) has instituted a program of purchasing scientific and technical equipment (the Equipment) for lease to public institutions of higher education in the Commonwealth of Virginia for use in teaching and research; WHEREAS, the Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia (the Institution) hereby finds it will be in the best interest of the Institution to lease Equipment having an aggregate value not exceeding $3,720,000 from the Authority; and, WHEREAS, there has been presented to the Board a form of a Lease Agreement providing for the lease of Equipment by the Institution from the Authority; BE IT RESOLVED BY THE BOARD OF VISITORS: 1. The Institution shall lease Equipment having an aggregate value not exceeding $3,720,000 from the Authority under terms and conditions substantially as set forth in the form of the Lease Agreements presented to the Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia, which is hereby approved. 2. The Vice President for Business and Finance and the Assistant Vice President for Finance of the Institution are each hereby authorized and directed to take such further action as may be necessary or desirable to effect such leases of Equipment, including executing and delivering such Lease Agreements and supplements thereto as may be necessary or desirable. 3. The Vice President for Business and Finance or the Assistant Vice President for Finance may approve such changes or modifications to the form of Lease Agreement as such officer may determine to be in the best interest of the Institution, such Officer's execution of such Lease Agreement with such changes to be conclusive evidence of approval. 4. The obligations of the Institution to pay rent for Equipment under such Lease Agreements shall be payable in such installments with interest at such rate or rates over such term or terms as the President or Vice President for Business and Finance or the Assistant Vice President for Finance shall determine to be in the best interest of the Institution.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">AUTHORITY TO APPROVE CONTRACT FOR AIR TRANSPORT SERVICES The following resolution was adopted: WHEREAS, the University seeks to renew its Air Transport contract through lease and/or purchase, and; WHEREAS, the Board of Visitors has reviewed the merits of the Medical Center's Air Transport Program and supports its continuation; NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED that following approval by the Finance Committee the Vice President for Business and Finance be authorized to approve a contract or contracts for lease and/or purchase of aero-medical transport services, effective on or around August 1, 1989, subject to approval by the Legal Adviser and compliance with all procurement requirements.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF SUMMARY OF AUDIT REPORTS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the Summary of Audit Reports for the period January 1, 1989 through March 10, 1989, as presented by the Director of Audits, be and it is hereby approved as recommended by the Audit Committee.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">AUTHORIZATION TO CONTINUE CONTINGENCY ENROLLMENT PLANNING The following resolution was adopted: WHEREAS, The Board of Visitors has heard presentations of views on enrollment growth by members of the Charlottesville-Albemarle Community, by the Faculty Senate and Student Council and by two academic Deans, the Board of Visitors wishes to express its appreciation to those who took the time to share their views on this issue; and WHEREAS, the Board has not yet reached any decision on this issue but recognizes the importance of reaching such a decision not later than the January, 1990, meeting of the Board; BE IT RESOLVED that the President of the University be asked to continue the contingency planning process which began last fall with the Biennial Planning Guidelines Memorandum, and to bring to the Board not later than its January, 1990, meeting specific options by which the University's enrollment plans could accommodate the various interests to which the Board must be sensitive in its eventual decision.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">GIFTS, GRANTS AND CONTRACTS The President distributed a list of gifts, grants, and contracts. He noted with appreciation, that private giving is up 25% over last year, and that there have been increases in the funding of projects in both the Medical School and departments in the College of Arts and Sciences. Upon motion, the Board voted to accept the gifts, grants and contracts.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">AUTHORIZATION FOR THE FINANCE COMMITTEE TO SELECT A VICE PRESIDENT FOR BUSINESS AND FINANCE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the Finance Committee be and it is hereby authorized to select from among the candidates interviewed, a Vice President for Business and Finance, such selection to be made at the Finance Committee's May 9, 1989 meeting, and subject to election by the Board at its May 23, 1989 meeting.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF REVISED RETIREMENT CONTRIBUTION FORMULA The following resolution was adopted: WHEREAS, the Tax Reform Act of 1986 necessitates that the University modify its current TIAA-CREF retirement contribution formulas; and WHEREAS, the Tax Reform Act requires that the changes be effective not later than the beginning of the Plan Year following January 1, 1989; NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED that the TIAA-CREF retirement formula be 12.5% of salary up to $100,000, effective July 1, 1989 (the beginning of the University's Plan Year). (See Attachment A) On motion, the meeting adjourned at 2:57 p.m. Respectfully submitted, Raymond C. Bice, Jr. Secretary RCB:jb</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Attachment A RETIREMENT PLAN DESIGN OBJECTIVE: To merge the University's three retirement contribution formulas under TIAA-CREF into one formula which will enable the plan to become qualified under the requirements of the Tax Reform Act. CURRENT FORMULAS: 1. Regular - 5% of $14,500; 20% of remainder to $60,000 (270 faculty) 2. Step - 10% of $14,500; 15% of remainder to $60,000 (1,206 faculty) 3. Clinical - 10% up to $60,000 (matched by HSF) (324 faculty) CONSIDERATIONS: 1. The new formula should ensure a retirement annuity of at least 66% of final salary including social security. 2. The new formula should be cost neutral or have a minimal cost impact. 3. The cap of $60,000 should be increased. 4. The University should assist the Health Services Foundation with their tax reform problems while, at the same time, ensuring that the University's program is not jeopardized. 5. The formula should be equitable for a majority of the faculty. PROPOSED FORMULA: 12-1/2% of salary up to $100,000 IMPACT OF 12-1/2% FORMULA ON RETIREMENT CONTRIBUTIONS: (Assuming all faculty receive a 7% salary increase next fiscal year) 155 faculty in the regular formula would receive less in retirement contributions next fiscal year than in the current fiscal year: $167,600 370 faculty in the step formula would receive less in retirement contributions next fiscal year than in the current fiscal year (186 of the 370 faculty have a projected decrease in their retirement contributions of less than $100): 40,256 TOTAL 207,856 RECOMMENDED APPROACH TO OFFSET DECREASE IN RETIREMENT CONTRIBUTIONS: (Applicable to individuals whose decrease in retirement contributions is $100 or greater) A special one-time adjustment to the contractual salary will be made to offset the decrease in retirement contributions. For twelve (12) month faculty, the adjustment will be made on July 1 and for nine (9) month faculty, the adjustment will be made on September 1. The adjustments to salary will be calculated by taking the total decrease in retirement contributions ($207,856) minus the retirement contributions generated by the salary increase ($25,892 = 12-1/2% of $207,856). ADVANTAGES OF PROPOSED FORMULA: ?The formula is easy to explain and understand. ?All faculty up to the contribution cap are treated equitably. ?The majority of faculty whose salaries are adjusted will have the opportunity to tax-shelter these dollars through the University's tax-deferred annuity program. ?The retirement contribution cap is increased to a more competitive level. ?The formula will accommodate the Health Sciences Foundation. ?The increased costs are minimal for the University. ?The objective of providing a retirement annuity of at least 66% of final salary plus social security can be realized.</field>
   </doc>
</add>