<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">University of Virginia, Board of Visitors</field>
      <field name="author_facet">University of Virginia, Board of Visitors</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">university of virginia board of visitors</field>
      <field name="author_text">University of Virginia, Board of Visitors</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1990's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/2006_01/uvaGenText/tei/bov_1990-03-30.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240342</field>
      <field name="date_text">March 30, 1990</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Board of Visitors Minutes, 1817-2002</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Board of Visitors Minutes, 1817-2002</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:183749</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Board of Visitors minutes. March 30, 1990</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Minutes</field>
      <field name="subject_text">University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Minutes</field>
      <field name="title_display">Board of Visitors minutes.  March 30, 1990</field>
      <field name="title_facet">board of visitors minutes</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">board of visitors minutes</field>
      <field name="title_text">Board of Visitors minutes.  March 30, 1990</field>
      <field name="year_display">March 30, 1990</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1990-03-30</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1990</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:183749&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;public&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:183749&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;serial volume&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;University of Virginia, Board of Visitors&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;university of virginia, board of visitors&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Board of Visitors minutes. March 30, 1990&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;board of visitors minutes&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;March 30, 1990&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1990-03-30&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="corpname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia, Board of Visitors&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Board of Visitors minutes&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;March 30, 1990&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="edition"&gt;Public minutes&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa call number"&gt;Accession# RG-1/1/&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;a2846310&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;1 v.&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;University of Virginia&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="AAT"&gt;Minutes&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;The official minutes contain salary information. Access to minutes containing salary information will be granted only under the procedures of the Virginia Freedom of Information Act (Code of Virginia-2.1-340 ff.) or if permission is granted by the Secretary of the Board. Researchers interested in obtaining access to these records should direct a request in writing to the Office of the Legal Adviser, Madison Hall, University of Virginia. These public minutes have had salary information deleted and bear no restrictions.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Board of Visitors' minutes, Accession # RG-1/1/, Special Collections Dept., University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Minutes of meetings of the university's governing body which is the legal owner and operator of the institution. Recorded in the minutes are appointments and other personnel decisions concerning faculty, decisions about construction of facilities, gifts to the university, and all other board actions, decisions and resolutions.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Board of Visitors minutes&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;numbering type="date"&gt;1990-03-30&lt;/numbering&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Charlottesville, Virginia&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University of Virginia Library&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;2005&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©2005 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Publicly accessible&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 180 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-BoardOfVisitorsMinutes"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE RECTOR AND VISITORS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA March 30, 1990 The Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia met at 9:00 a.m., in Open Session on March 29, 1990, in the East Oval Room of the Rotunda with the following persons present: Rector Pro Tem Edward E. Elson, President Robert M. O'Neil, W. L. Lyons Brown, Jr., Robert G. Butcher, Jr., N. Thomas Connally, Hovey S. Dabney, Waller H. Horsley, J. Thomas Hulvey, Evans B. Jessee, Patricia M. Kluge, Arnold H. Leon, Leigh B. Middleditch, Jr., Elizabeth D. Morie, Freddie W. Nicholas, Sr., S. Buford Scott, Wendelin L. White, Jesse B. Wilson, III, and Thomas E. Worrell, Jr. Messrs. James J. Mingle, Hugh P. Kelly, Don E. Detmer, Ernest H. Ern, Raymond M. Haas, Leonard W. Sandridge, Jr., and Alexander G. Gilliam, Jr., were also present. The Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia met at 2:30 p.m., in Open Session on March 30, 1990, in the East Oval Room of the Rotunda with the following persons present: Rector Edward E. Elson, President Robert M. O'Neil, W. L. Lyons Brown, Jr., Robert G. Butcher, Jr., N. Thomas Connally, Hovey S. Dabney, Waller H. Horsley, J. Thomas Hulvey, Evans B. Jessee, Patricia M. Kluge, Arnold H. Leon, Leigh B. Middleditch, Jr., Elizabeth D. Morie, Freddie W. Nicholas, Sr., S. Buford Scott, Wendelin L. White, Jesse B. Wilson, III, and Thomas E. Worrell, Jr. Messrs. James J. Mingle, Hugh P. Kelly, Don E. Detmer, Ernest H. Ern, Raymond M. Haas, and Alexander G. Gilliam, Jr. were also present. The Minutes of the meeting of January 26, 1990, previously distributed, were approved as corrected.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">MOTIONS FOR EXECUTIVE SESSION The following motions were unanimously adopted by the vote of all Visitors present: (a) That the Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia go into Executive Session for the discussion or consideration of personnel matters involving University appointees including employment, assignment, appointment, promotion, performance, demotion, salaries, discipling, or resignation of faculty, appointees or employees of the University of Virginia as provided for in Section 2.1-344 A. (1) of The Code of Virginia. (b) That the Finance Committee of the Board of Visitors go into Executive Session for discussion of Item Number 13 on that Committee's agenda for the discussion of investing public funds where competition or bargaining is involved when if made public initially the University's financial interests would be adversely affected as provided for in Section 2.1-344 A. (6) of The Code of Virginia. (c) That the Board of Visitors go into Executive Session for consultation with Legal Counsel pertaining to actual or probable litigation, or other specific legal matters requiring the provision of legal advice by Counsel, as provided for in Section 2.1-344 A.(7) of The Code of Virginia. (d) That the Educational Policy Committee of the Board of Visitors go into Executive Session for Item Number 19 on that Committee's agenda for the discussion or consideration of personnel matters involving University appointees including employment, assignment, appointment, promotion, performance, demotion, salaries, discipling or resignation of faculty, appointees or employees of the University of Virginia as provided for in Section 2.1-344 A.(1) of The Code of Virginia.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RESOLUTION PROVIDING THAT THE BOARD'S STANDING COMMITTEES OPERATE AS THE COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE BOARD ON A TEMPORARY BASIS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that until Committee memberships are announced by the Rector, each of the Board's Standing Committees shall operate as the Committee of the Whole.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">INTRODUCTION OF NEW BOARD MEMBERS The Rector introduced the newly appointed members of the Board; Mr. Hovey S. Dabney, Dr. J. Thomas Hulvey, Mr. Evans B. Jessee, Mrs. Patricia M. Kluge, Mr. Arnold H. Leon, Mr. Leigh B. Middleditch, Jr., and Mr. Freddie W. Nicholas.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ELECTION OF MR. EDWARD E. ELSON AS RECTOR OF THE UNIVERSITY In accordance with the 1985 Manual of the Board of Visitors, and in compliance with the provisions of the Code of Virginia, Section 23-74, Mr. Edward E. Elson was unanimously elected as Rector of the University of Virginia for a four year term.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ELECTION OF MR. RAYMOND C. BICE, JR., AS SECRETARY OF THE BOARD OF VISITORS In accordance with the 1985 Manual of the Board of Visitors and in compliance with the Code of Virginia, Section 23-74, Mr. Raymond C. Bice, Jr., was elected Secretary to the Board of Visitors, for a term of four years.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ELECTION OF MR. ALEXANDER G. GILLIAM, JR., AS ASSISTANT SECRETARY OF THE BOARD OF VISITORS In accordance with the 1985 Manual of the Board of Visitors and in compliance with the Code of Virginia, Section 23-74, Mr. Alexander G. Gilliam, Jr., was elected Assistant Secretary to the Board of Visitors, for a term of four years.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ELECTION OF THE EXECUTIVE COMMITTEE In accordance with the 1985 Manual of the Board of Visitors and in compliance with the Code of Virginia, Section 23-75, the following were elected to serve on the Executive Committee of the Board of Visitors until the annual meeting in May 1990: Mr. Edward E. Elson, Chair, Dr. N. Thomas Connally, Mr. Hovey S. Dabney, Mrs. Patricia M. Kluge, and Mr. Leigh B. Middleditch, Jr.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ELECTION OF JULIE G. LYNN AS NON-VOTING STUDENT MEMBER On the motion of Mr. Jesse B. Wilson, III, Chair of the Special Committee on Nominating a Non-Voting Student on the Board of Visitors, the Board elected Miss Julie G. Lynn as a non-voting student member of the Board of Visitors for the period July 1, 1990 through June 30, 1991 as prescribed in Section 2.21 of The Manual.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPOINTMENT OF STANDING COMMITTEES The Rector announced his appointments to the Standing Committees to serve until the Annual Meeting in May 1990. The Committee assignments are as follows: HEALTH AFFAIRS COMMITTEE Mr. Hovey S. Dabney, Chair Dr. N. Thomas Connally Dr. J. Thomas Hulvey Mr. Evans B. Jessee Mr. Leigh B. Middleditch, Jr. Mrs. Elizabeth D. Morie FINANCE COMMITTEE Mr. Robert G. Butcher, Jr., Chair Mr. W. L. Lyons Brown, Jr. Mr. Hovey S. Dabney Mr. Arnold H. Leon Mr. S. Buford Scott Mr. Thomas E. Worrell, Jr. BUILDINGS AND GROUNDS COMMITTEE Mrs. Elizabeth D. Morie, Chair Mr. Evans B. Jessee Mr. Arnold H. Leon Mr. S. Buford Scott Mr. Jesse B. Wilson, III Mr. Thomas E. Worrell, Jr. STUDENT AFFAIRS AND ATHLETICS COMMITTEE Mr. W. L. Lyons Brown, Jr., Chair Mr. Robert G. Butcher, Jr. Mr. Waller H. Horsley Dr. J. Thomas Hulvey Mrs. Patricia M. Kluge Mr. Freddie W. Nicholas, Sr. Miss Wendelin L. White EDUCATIONAL POLICY COMMITTEE Mr. Waller H. Horsley, Chair Dr. N. Thomas Connally Mrs. Patricia M. Kluge Mr. Leigh B. Middleditch, Jr. Mr. Freddie W. Nicholas, Sr. Miss Wendelin L. White Mr. Jesse B. Wilson, III AUDIT COMMITTEE Mr. Thomas E. Worrell, Jr., Chair Mr. Arnold H. Leon Mr. S. Buford Scott Mr. Jesse B. Wilson, III The Rector, Mr. Edward E. Elson, is an ex officio member of all Committees.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SPECIAL COMMITTEE ON ALUMNI AFFAIRS The Rector announced the establishment of the Special Committee on Alumni Affairs for the purpose of ensuring that alumni activities maintain a signal place on the agenda of the Board of Visitors. The membership consists of: Mr. S. Buford Scott, Chair Mr. W. L. Lyons Brown, Jr. Mr. Robert G. Butcher, Jr. Dr. J. Thomas Hulvey Mr. Jesse B. Wilson, III</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SPECIAL COMMITTEE ON EXTERNAL AFFAIRS The Rector announced the establishment of the Special Committee on External Affairs for the purpose of studying and assisting the University's external affairs and recommending to the Board ways to encourage an efficacious program. The membership consists of: Mr. Thomas E. Worrell, Jr., Chair Dr. N. Thomas Connally Mrs. Elizabeth D. Morie</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SPECIAL COMMITTEE ON GOVERNMENTAL AFFAIRS The Rector announced the establishment of the Special Committee on Governmental Affairs for the purpose of assisting and encouraging the governmental relations of the University with commissions and executive, administrative and legislative bodies with whom the University interfaces and reporting to the Board that information necessary to ensure full Board participation. The membership consists of: Mrs. Patricia M. Kluge, Chair Mr. Hovey S. Dabney Mr. Waller H. Horsley Mr. Leigh B. Middleditch, Jr. Mr. Freddie W. Nicholas, Sr.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SPECIAL COMMITTEE ON INTER-GROUP RELATIONS The Rector announced the establishment of the Special Committee on Inter-Group Relations for the purpose of promoting inter-group relations to assure that the sense of community of which the University is so justly proud continues and to report to the Board suggestions to further encourage and enhance pluralism on the Grounds. The membership consists of: Mr. Freddie W. Nicholas, Sr., Chair Mr. Evans B. Jessee Mr. Arnold H. Leon Miss Wendelin L. White</field>
      <field name="fulltext">EXPRESSION OF APPRECIATION TO RETIRING VISITORS The Rector expressed the deep appreciation of the Board and the University to the following members of the Board whose terms ended on March 1, 1990: Mr. Joshua P. Darden, Jr., Rector, Mr. John S. Battle, Jr., Mr. Charles L. Brown, Mr. William M. Camp, Mrs. George M. Cochran, Mr. Lemuel E. Lewis and Mr. James L. Trinkle.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DISCUSSION OF BOARD MEETING SCHEDULES The Rector said he would appoint a special committee to recommend possible changes in the scheduling of meetings. This committee will report its recommendations to the Board at the May 1990 meeting if they recommend any changes at all.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ELECTIONS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following persons be and they are hereby elected to the faculty: Mr. Yongde Bao as Research Assistant Professor of Pathology, for one year, effective January 1, 1990. Mr. Raul A. Baragiola as Associate Professor of Engineering Physics, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1990. Mr. John T. Casteen, III, as Professor of English, effective August 1, 1990. Ms. Dawn C. Chiang as Lecturer in Drama, for one semester, effective January 16, 1990. Ms. Maryse Conde as Visiting Professor of French, for one semester, effective September 1, 1990. Ms. Elizabeth A. Cooley as Lecturer, General Medical Faculty, The Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, for one year, effective January 1, 1990. Mr. W. James Copeland, Jr., Professor, General Faculty, for five years, effective September 1, 1987. Mr. Richard N. Day as Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, for two years, effective July 1, 1990. Mr. Bradford J. Eaton as Instructor in Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective December 1, 1989. Mr. Graeme C. Gerrans as Visiting Professor of Chemistry, for one semester, effective January 16, 1990. Mr. Kenneth I. Henley as Visiting Associate Professor of Philosophy, for one semester, effective January 16, 1990. Mr. Michael H. Kaplan as Lecturer, General Faculty, for three years, effective March 1, 1990. Mr. Jody S. Kraus as Assistant Professor of Law, for five academic years, effective September 1, 1990. Dr. Michael Y. Lee as Assistant Professor of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation, for three years, effective July 1, 1990. Mr. Larry L. Lowe as Visiting Research Assistant Professor of Biology, for the period January 1, 1990 through May 31, 1990. Mr. Paul G. Mahoney as Associate Professor of Law, for five academic years, effective September 1, 1990. Ms. Mary L. McBride as Lecturer, General Faculty, for the period January 1, 1990 through June 30, 1990. Mr. Eugene O. Mills as Lecturer in Philosophy, for one semester, effective January 16, 1990. Mr. Clark S. Nesbit as Lecturer, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective January 1, 1990. Mr. Roy C. Ogle as Assistant Professor of Plastic Surgery, for three years, effective February 1, 1990. Mr. Stephan Palmie as Lecturer, Carter G. Woodson Institute, for one semester, effective January 16, 1990. Dr. Robert A. Pearce as Assistant Professor of Anesthesiology, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective January 1, 1990. Mr. Laurence Schumann as Lecturer in Economics, for one semester, effective January 16, 1990. Ms. Linda T. Seeloff as Lecturer, General Faculty, for three years, effective January 1, 1990. Mr. Peter P. Swire as Associate Professor of Law, for five academic years, effective September 1, 1990. Mr. Gary L. Wilbert as Lecturer, General Faculty, for three years, effective February 1, 1990. Mr. John D. Wilkes as Visiting Professor of Applied Mathematics, for one semester, effective January 16, 1990.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Election of Part-Time Faculty Mr. Brian D. Andrews as Lecturer in Architecture, for one semester, effective January 16, 1990. Mr. Robert L. Asher as Instructor in English, for one semester, effective January 16, 1990. Mr. Stephen Bann as Lecturer in Literary and Cultural Change, for the period March 12, 1990 through April 9, 1990. Ms. Barbara M. Bruner as Instructor in Business Administration, for one semester, effective January 16, 1990. Mr. Larry W. Burton as Lecturer in English, for one semester, effective January 16, 1990. Mr. David W. Carr, Jr. as Lecturer in Planning, for one semester, effective January 16, 1990. Ms. Sharon M. Chute as Lecturer in Education, for one semester, effective January 16, 1990. Mr. Robert B. Douglass as Visiting Associate Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs, for one semester, effective January 16, 1990. Mr. Frank W. Finger as Lecturer in Psychology, for one semester, effective January 16, 1990. Mr. John H. Howland, Jr. as Lecturer in English, for one semester, effective January 16, 1990. Ms. Elizabeth M. Hull as Instructor in English, for one semester, effective January 16, 1990. Ms. Sarah P. Johnson as Lecturer, General Faculty, for the period December 1, 1989 through January 31, 1990. Ms. Franciska Koscielny as Lecturer in Music, for one semester, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. Robert M. McAnulty as Lecturer in Architecture, for one semester, effective January 16, 1990. Mr. Derek A. Neal as Instructor in Economics, for one semester, effective January 16, 1990. Mr. Gary L. Ramsey as Instructor in History, for one semester, effective January 16, 1990. Ms. Barbara D. Ranagan as Lecturer in Law, for one semester, effective January 16, 1990. Mr. John S. Rice as Instructor in Sociology, for one semester, effective January 16, 1990. Dr. Richard J. Rivers as Instructor of Anesthesiology, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective January 1, 1990. Mr. A. Peter Spaar as Lecturer in Music, for one semester, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. William J. Stockwell as Lecturer in Education, for one semester, effective January 16, 1990. Mr. Gary Thompson as Lecturer in Mathematics, for one semester, effective January 16, 1990. Mr. William H. Toel as Lecturer in Commerce, for one semester, effective January 16, 1990. Mr. Lan Vo Ky as Visiting Research Professor of Physics, for one year, effective January 15, 1990. Ms. Terri E. Welch as Lecturer in Law, for one semester, effective January 16, 1990. Ms. Janet Wolff as Lecturer in the Commonwealth Center for Literary and Cultural Change, for the period January 22, 1990 through February 15, 1990.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Election of Non-Salaried Faculty Mr. Emilio H. Arribas as Visiting Scholar in Economics, for one semester, effective January 16, 1990. Mr. Ze-Nai Chen as Visiting Scholar in Chemistry, for the period March 31, 1990 through March 30, 1991. Dr. Federico Colombo as Visiting Professor of Neurosurgery, for one year, effective February 1, 1990. Mr. James B. Garrett, Jr. as Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Western State, for three years, effective January 1, 1990. Mr. Boris Gelmont as Visiting Professor of Electrical Engineering, for the period January 7, 1990 through April 7, 1990. Mr. Gordon N. Hutner as Visiting Scholar in English, for the period January 15, 1990 through June 30, 1990. Mr. Kevin L. Keough as Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Western State, for three years, effective January 1, 1990. Mr. Yong K. Kim as Visiting Scholar in English, for the period January 1, 1990 through April 30, 1990. Mr. Antonio C. Lemgruber as Visiting Scholar in Economics, for one semester, effective January 16, 1990. Ms. Concepcion Manella Jimenez as Visiting Scholar in English, for the period January 1, 1990 through July 31, 1990. Ms. Bernice A. Marcopulos as Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Western State, for three years, effective January 1, 1990. Mr. Raymond M. Marsh as Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Catawba Hospital, for three years, effective January 1, 1990. Dr. S. Raymond Mayberry as Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Roanoke Program, for three years, effective January 1, 1990. Ms. Alexia Morrison as Lecturer in Law, for one semester, effective January 16, 1990. Mr. Kwong-Tai Ng as Visiting Assistant Professor of Electrical Engineering, for one year, effective January 1, 1990. Dr. Stephen A. Nichols as Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Western State, for three years, effective March 1, 1990. Ms. Sandra Olsen as Lecturer in Anthropology, for one semester, effective January 1, 1990. Mr. Seog Park as Visiting Associate Professor of Computer Science, for one year, effective January 1, 1990. Mr. Jeffrey L. Phillips as Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Western State, for three years, effective January 1, 1990. Mr. Scott W. Sautter as Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Western State, for three years, effective January 1, 1990. Dr. Helen E. Smith as Instructor of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Roanoke Program, for one year, effective July 1, 1989. Mr. Vijay K. Yadav as Visiting Scholar in Biology, for the period January 1, 1990 through March 31, 1990.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Election of Clinical Faculty Dr. James M. Bennett as Clinical Assistant Professor of Nursing, for the period January 1, 1990 to June 30, 1993. Dr. Benjamin T. Brown as Clinical Assistant Professor of Nursing, for the period January 1, 1990 through June 30, 1993. Mr. Gary R. Culver as Clinical Instructor in Nursing, for the period January 1, 1990 through June 30, 1993. Mr. Carlos A. De Aristizabel as Clinical Instructor in Nursing, for the period January 1, 1990 through June 30, 1993. Dr. Frank M. Eggers, II as Clinical Assistant Professor of Radiology, for the period January 16, 1990 through December 31, 1990. Ms. Linda H. Gillet as Clinical Instructor in Nursing, for the period January 1, 1990 through June 30, 1993. Mr. Michael L. Gromg as Clinical Instructor in Nursing, for the period January 1, 1990 through June 30, 1993. Ms. Jean C. Hemphill as Clinical Instructor in Nursing, for the period January 1, 1990 through June 30, 1993. Mr. Robert B. Iadeluca as Clinical Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, for one year, effective January 1, 1990. Ms. Cynthia C. Janechild as Clinical Instructor in Nursing, for the period January 1, 1990 through June 30, 1993. Ms. Nancy R. Joseph as Clinical Assistant Professor of Nursing, for the period January 1, 1990 through June 30, 1993. Ms. Virginia M. Kelly as Clinical Instructor in Nursing, for the period January 1, 1990 through June 30, 1993. Ms. Barbara J. Koster as Clinical Instructor in Nursing, for for the period January 1, 1990 through June 30, 1992. Ms. Rebecca M. Mason as Clinical Instructor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, for one year, effective February 1, 1990. Mr. Walter H. Mason as Clinical Instructor in Nursing, for the period January 1, 1990 through June 30, 1993. Ms. Deborah S. Mills as Clinical Instructor in Nursing, for the period January 1, 1990 through June 30, 1993. Ms. Claudia R. O'Neill as Clinical Instructor in Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Western State, for one year, effective July 1, 1990. Ms. Gilda H. Pegram as Clinical Instructor in Nursing, for the period January 1, 1990 through June 30, 1993. Ms. Laura E. Pole-Trafidlo as Clinical Instructor in Nursing, for the period January 1, 1990 through June 30, 1993. Ms. MaryLee Profy as Clinical Instructor in Nursing, for the period January 1, 1990 through June 30, 1993. Dr. Robert B. Walker as Clinical Assistant Professor of Nursing, for the period January 1, 1990 through June 30, 1993. Dr. Dana F. Zweig as Clinical Assistant Professor of Nursing, for the period January 1, 1990 through June 30, 1993.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CORRECTION IN THE ELECTION OF DR. KATHRYN L. WEISE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the election of Dr. Kathryn L. Weise as Assistant Professor of Pediatrics, for two years, effective September 1, 1989, as approved by the Board on January 26, 1990, be and it is hereby corrected to read as follows: Dr. Kathryn L. Weise as Assistant Professor of Pediatrics, General Medical Faculty, for two years, effective September 1, 1989.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACTIONS RELATING TO CHAIRHOLDERS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the actions relating to chairholders be and they are hereby approved as shown below: Mr. John T. Casteen, III, as George M. Kaufman Presidential Professor, effective August 1, 1990. Mr. James A. Gentry as Visiting Virginia Bankers Association Professor of Bank Management, for one semester, effective January 16, 1991. Dr. Irving L. Kron as Distinguished Professor of Surgery, effective January 1, 1990. Mr. Oswald Steward as Harrison Foundation Professor of Neuroscience, effective March 1, 1990. Dr. Morton C. Wilhelm as Joseph Helms Farrow Professor of Surgical Oncology, effective March 1, 1990. (b) Re-election of Chairholders Mr. Murray H. Finley as Eleanor F. and Philip G. Rust Visiting Professor of Business Administration, for one semester, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. Lewis F. Powell, Jr., as John A. Ewald, Jr., Distinguished Visiting Professor of Law, for the period March 19, 1990 through March 30, 1990. (c) Leave of Absence of Chairholders Mr. Murray H. Finley, Eleanor F. and Philip G. Rust Visiting Professor of Business Administration, for the period January 16, 1990 through May 31, 1990, without pay, for personal reasons. Mr. Lester A. Hoel, Janet Scott Hamilton and John Downman Hamilton Professor of Civil Engineering, for the period June 1, 1990 through December 31, 1990, with pay, to do research. Mr. Douglas J. White, Mac Wade Professor of Engineering, for the period January 1, 1990 through August 31, 1990, without pay, for personal reasons. (d) Change of Title of Chairholders Dr. Guy M. Harbert, Jr., from Mamie A. Jessup Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology to John M. Nokes Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology, effective January 1, 1990. Mr. Robert J. Mattauch, from Standard Oil Company (OHIO) Professor of Science, to BP America Professor of Science and Technology, effective November 1, 1989. (e) Death of Chairholder Mr. Ernest L. Folk, III, William S. Potter Professor of Law, died November 16, 1989. Mr. Folk had been a member of the faculty since February 1, 1968. (f) Retirement of Chairholders Mr. Neill H. Alford, Jr., Percy Brown, Jr., Professor of Law, effective May 31, 1990. Mr. Alford has been a member of the faculty since October 23, 1947. Mr. Ernst O. Attinger, Harry Douglas Forsyth Professor of Engineering and Applied Science, effective May 31, 1990. Mr. Attinger has been a member of the faculty since July 1, 1967. Mr. Richard M. Brandt, Curry Memorial Professor of Education, effective May 31, 1990. Mr. Brandt has been a member of the faculty since September 1, 1965. Mr. Hugh M. Davidson, Commonwealth Professor of French Literature, effective May 31, 1990. Mr. Davidson has been a member of the faculty since September 1, 1972. Mr. James E. Deese, Hugh Scott Hamilton Professor of Psychology, effective May 31, 1990. Mr. Deese has been a member of the faculty since September 1, 1972. Mr. William H. Harbaugh, Langbourne M. Williams Professor of American History, effective May 31, 1990. Mr. Harbaugh has been a member of the faculty since September 1, 1966. Mr. Irwin R. Konigsberg, Commonwealth Professor of Biology, effective May 31, 1990. Mr. Konigsberg has been a member of the faculty since August 1, 1966. Mr. William H. Muller, Jr., S. Hurt Watts Professor of Surgery and University Professor of Health Policy, effective June 30, 1990. Dr. Muller has been a member of the faculty since October 25, 1954. Mr. Jaquelin T. Robertson, Commonwealth Professor of Architecture, effective October 17, 1989. Mr. Robertson has been a member of the faculty since January 1, 1981. Mr. Nathan A. Scott, William R. Kenan, Jr., Professor of Religious Studies, effective May 31, 1990. Mr. Scott has been a member of the faculty since July 1, 1976.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RE-ELECTIONS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following persons be and they are hereby re-elected to the faculty: Dr. Robert C. Allen as Associate Professor of Ophthalmology, effective July 1, 1990. Ms. Susan G. Bader as Assistant Professor, General Medical Faculty, The Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, for three years, effective April 1, 1990. Dr. Daniel M. Becker as Associate Professor of Internal Medicine, effective July 1, 1990. Mr. Michael E. Brint as Assistant Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1990. Mr. Lee B. Crigler as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, for two years, effective November 1, 1989. Ms. Linda R. Davies as Assistant Professor of Nursing, General Nursing Faculty, for one year, effective July 1, 1990. Dr. Frederic De Blay as Visiting Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, for the period May 1, 1990 through April 30, 1991. Ms. Pamela D. Dennison as Assistant Professor of Nursing, General Nursing Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1990. Mr. John E. Echeverri-Gent as Assistant Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs, for three academic years, effective 30, 1990. Ms. Mary C. Ellwein as Assistant Professor of Education, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1990. Mr. Philip J. Foubert as Assistant Professor of Biomedical Ethics, General Medical Faculty, for the period May 1, 1990 through June 30, 1990. Mr. Boris Gelmont as Visiting Professor of Electrical Engineering, for the period April 8, 1990 through June 17, 1990. Mr. Theodore W. Graves, Jr. as Assistant Professor of Nursing, General Nursing Faculty, part time, for the period July 1, 1990 through January 15, 1991. Mr. Marcus W. Hastings as Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Western State, for three years, effective March 1, 1990. Mr. Yunsheng Huang as Visiting Professor of Architectural History, part time, for one semester, effective January 16, 1990. Ms. Leslie D. Hurt as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, for two years, effective November 1, 1989. Mr. Harold B. Johnson, Jr. as Scholar in Residence in History, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1990. Mr. Daniel P. Jordan as Scholar in Residence in History, for one year, effective July 1, 1990. Mr. James S. Kennan as Assistant Professor, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective January 1, 1990. Ms. Patricia M. Lampkin as Associate Professor, General Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1990. Dr. Victor C. Lee as Assistant Professor of Anesthesiology, for three years, effective February 1, 1990. Mr. Peter A. Lichtenberg as Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Western State, for three years, effective March 1, 1990. Mr. Raymond P. McDermott as Visiting Professor of Education, part time, for one semester, effective January 16, 1990. Mr. Gerald F. McKeegan as Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Western State, for three years, effective March 1, 1990. Mr. James P. Mitchell as Assistant Professor, General Faculty, for three years, effective January 1, 1990. Mr. John G. Papovich as Assistant Professor, General Faculty and Lecturer in English, for three years, effective July 1, 1990. Mr. Lawrence E. Payne as Visiting Professor of Applied Mathematics, part time, for the period January 1, 1990 through March 31, 1990. Ms. JoAnne H. Peach as Assistant Professor of Nursing, General Nursing Faculty, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1990. Ms. Deborah A. Phillips as Assistant Professor of Psychology, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1991. Dr. Timothy L. Pruett as Assistant Professor of Surgery, for three years, effective January 1, 1990. Ms. Marion W. Ross as Assistant Professor of Anthropology, part time, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1990. Mr. Michael J. Smith as Assistant Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs, for three academic years, effective January 16, 1990. Ms. Jean Sorrells-Jones as Associate Professor of Nursing, General Nursing Faculty, for one year, effective July 1, 1990. Mr. Herbert L. Stewart as Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Western State, for three years, effective March 1, 1990. Mr. Stephen J. Suomi as Research Professor of Psychology, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. Joshua H. Tonkel as Assistant Professor of Philosophy, for three academic years, effective September 1, 1990. Ms. June L. Triplett as Visiting Professor of Nursing, part time, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1990. Ms. Chenggui Zhang as Visiting Research Assistant Professor of Pharmacology, for one year, effective February 1, 1990.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DELETION OF THE RE-ELECTION OF MRS. BEVERLEY B. BUTLER The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the re-election of Mrs. Beverley B. Butler, as Assistant Professor of Pediatrics, for the period January 1, 1990 through March 31, 1990, as approved by the Board on January 26, 1990, be and it is hereby deleted. Mrs. Butler is tenured.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CORRECTION TO THE RE-ELECTION OF MR. JOSEPH H. GIECK The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the re-election of Mr. Joseph H. Gieck as Associate Professor, General Faculty, School of Education and Associate Professor of Orthopedics and Rehabilitation, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1989, as approved by the Board on October 6, 1989, be and it is hereby corrected to read as follows: Mr. Joseph H. Gieck as Associate Professor, General Faculty, School of Education, for three years, effective July 1, 1989.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHANGE IN THE EFFECTIVE DATE OF THE RE-ELECTION OF MR. ENRIQUE R. TORRE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the re-election of Mr. Enrique R. Torre, as Visiting Research Assistant Professor of Neuroscience, for one year, effective January 1, 1990, as approved by the Board on January 26, 1990, be and it is hereby changed to read as follows: Mr. Enrique R. Torre, Visiting Research Assistant Professor of Neuroscience, for the period December 16, 1989 through December 15, 1990.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PROMOTIONS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following faculty members be and they are hereby promoted: Mr. Lewis M. Armistead from Assistant Professor of Family Medicine and Behavioral Medicine, Roanoke Program to Associate Professor of Family Medicine and Behavioral Medicine, Roanoke Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1990. Dr. Alfred S. Barritt, III from Associate Professor of Internal Medicine, Salem Program to Professor of Internal Medicine, Salem Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1990. Dr. James P. Bennett from Assistant Professor of Neurology, Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, and Assistant Professor of Pharmacology to Associate Professor of Neurology, General Medical Faculty and Associate Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1990. Dr. David E. Bruns from Associate Professor of Pathology to Professor of Pathology, effective July 1, 1990. Ms. Suzanne M. Burns from Instructor in Nursing, General Nursing Faculty to Assistant Professor of Nursing, General Nursing Faculty, for one year, effective July 1, 1990. Dr. Lawrence R. Burwell from Associate Professor of Internal Medicine to Professor of Internal Medicine, effective July 1, 1990. Dr. Peter A. Campochiaro from Associate Professor of Ophthalmology to Professor of Ophthalmology, effective July 1, 1990. Dr. Thomas M. Daniel from Associate Professor of Surgery to Professor of Surgery, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1990. Ms. Wei Li Fang from Assistant Professor of Medical Education, General Medical Faculty to Associate Professor of Medical Education, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1990. Mr. Robin A. Felder from Assistant Professor of Pathology to Associate Professor of Pathology, effective July 1, 1990. Dr. James E. Ferguson, II from Assistant Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology and Assistant Professor of Radiology to Associate Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology and Associate Professor of Radiology, for three years, effective July 1, 1990. Mr. Willard L. Fitch from Assistant Professor, General Faculty to Associate Professor, General Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1990. Dr. Gary E. Glontz from Clinical Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, Roanoke Program to Clinical Associate Professor of Internal Medicine, Roanoke Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1990. Dr. Steven L. Gonias from Assistant Professor of Pathology and Assistant Professor of Biochemistry to Associate Professor of Pathology and Associate Professor of Biochemistry, for three years, effective July 1, 1990. Ms. Patrice G. Guyenet from Associate Professor of Pharmacology to Professor of Pharmacology, effective July 1, 1990. Dr. Seung S. Hahn from Assistant Professor of Radiology, General Medical Faculty to Associate Professor of Radiology, General Medical Faculty, for two years, effective July 1, 1990. Dr. Elliott C. Haley, Jr. from Assistant Professor of Neurology and Assistant Professor of Neurosurgery to Associate Professor of Neurology, General Medical Faculty and Associate Professor of Neurosurgery, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1990. Dr. John B. Hanks from Associate Professor of Surgery to Professor of Surgery, effective July 1, 1990. Dr. Frederick G. Hayden from Associate Professor of Internal Medicine and Associate Professor of Pathology to Professor of Internal Medicine (without term), and Professor of Pathology, for three years, effective July 1, 1990. Dr. Peter W. Heymann from Assistant Professor of Pediatrics, General Medical Faculty and Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine, General Medical Faculty to Associate Professor of Pediatrics (without term) and Associate Professor of Internal Medicine, for three years, effective July 1, 1990. Dr. Alan D. Jenkins from Assistant Professor of Urology to Associate Professor of Urology, effective July 1, 1990. Dr. Dearing W. Johns from Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine to Associate Professor of Internal Medicine, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1990. Dr. C. Ronald Kersh from Assistant Professor of Radiology to Associate Professor of Radiology, for two years, effective July 1, 1990. Mr. Joel M. Linden from Associate Professor of Internal Medicine and Associate Professor of Physiology to Associate Professor of Internal Medicine (without term) and Associate Professor of Physiology, for two years, effective July 1, 1990. Dr. Marguerite C. Lippert from Assistant Professor of Urology to Associate Professor of Urology, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1990. Dr. Stacey E. Mills from Associate Professor of Pathology to Professor of Pathology, effective July 1, 1990. Dr. Ravinder K. Mittal from Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine to Associate Professor of Internal Medicine, for one year, effective July 1, 1990. Dr. Steven A. Newman from Assistant Professor of Ophthalmology, General Medical Faculty to Associate Professor of Ophthalmology, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective July 1, 1990. Mr. Richard D. Pearson from Associate Professor of Internal Medicine and Associate Professor of Pathology to Professor of Internal Medicine (without term) and Professor of Pathology, for three years, effective July 1, 1990. Ms. C. Fay Raines from Assistant Professor of Nursing to Associate Professor of Nursing, effective July 1, 1990. Dr. Stephen H. Rosenoff from Clinical Associate Professor of Internal Medicine, Roanoke Program to Clinical Professor of Internal Medicine, Roanoke Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1989. Ms. Judith K. Sands from Assistant Professor of Nursing to Associate Professor of Nursing, effective September 1, 1990. Dr. Bruce D. Schirmer from Assistant Professor of Surgery to Associate Professor of Surgery, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1990. Dr. Charles J. Schleupner from Associate Professor of Internal Medicine, Salem Program to Professor of Internal Medicine, Salem Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1990. Dr. Arthur R. Slaughter from Assistant Professor of Family Medicine, Roanoke Program to Associate Professor of Family Medicine, Roanoke Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1990. Dr. William D. Spotnitz from Assistant Professor of Surgery to Associate Professor of Surgery, effective July 1, 1990. Dr. Frank F. Tellian from Assistant Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Salem Program to Associate Professor of Behavioral Medicine and Psychiatry, Salem Program, for three years, effective July 1, 1990. Dr. Siva Thiagarajah from Associate Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology, General Medical Faculty and Associate Professor of Radiology, General Medical Faculty to Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology, General Medical Faculty and Professor of Radiology, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1990. Mr. James C. Torner from Associate Professor of Neurosurgery and Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine to Associate Professor of Neurosurgery, General Medical Faculty and Associate Professor of Internal Medicine, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1990. Dr. Mary L. Vance from Assistant Professor of Internal Medicine to Associate Professor of Internal Medicine, effective July 1, 1990. Dr. Scott R. Vandenberg from Assistant Professor of Pathology to Associate Professor of Pathology, General Medical Faculty, for three years, effective July 1, 1990.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">LEAVES OF ABSENCE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following faculty members be and they are hereby granted leave of absence: Mr. Alex J. Baertschi, Associate Professor of Physiology, for the period January 1, 1990 through December 31, 1990, with partial pay, to do research. Mr. Lee B. Crigler, Assistant Professor, General Faculty, for the period November 1, 1989 through October 31, 1991, without pay, to pursue doctoral degree. Mr. Jay W. Fox, Associate Professor of Microbiology, for the period February 1, 1990 through January 31, 1991, with partial pay, to accept fellowship at the Max Planck Institut Fur Biochemie. Mr. Michael Garstang, Professor of Environmental Sciences, for the period February 16, 1990 through May 31, 1990, without pay, to accept a fellowship at the University of Cantebury. Mr. John Graham, Associate Professor of Rhetoric, for the period September 1, 1990 through May 31, 1991, without pay, to do research. Dr. Jack M. Gwaltney, Jr., Professor of Internal Medicine, for the period July 1, 1990 through December 31, 1990, with pay, to do research. Mr. Thomas T. Hammond, Professor of History, for the period September 1, 1990 through May 31, 1991, with partial pay, to continue to qualify for the early retirement plan as approved by the Board of Visitors. Ms. Leslie D. Hurt, Assistant Professor, General Faculty, for the period November 1, 1989 through October 31, 1991, without pay, to pursue doctoral degree. Mr. John A. James, Professor of Economics, for the period January 16, 1990 through May 31, 1990, with partial pay, to accept a Guggenheim Fellowship. Ms. Sally A. Moody, Associate Professor of Anatomy and Cell Biology and Associate Professor of Neuroscience, for the period January 1, 1990 through June 30, 1990, with pay, for personal reasons. Mr. James W. Moore, Professor of Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering, for the period January 16, 1990 through January 15, 1991, with partial pay, to continue to qualify for the early retirement plan as approved by the Board of Visitors. Mr. G. Carleton Ray, Research Professor of Environmental Sciences, for the period December 1, 1989 through March 31, 1990, with partial pay, because program funds are not in hand.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHANGE IN THE EFFECTIVE DATE OF THE LEAVE OF ABSENCE OF MR. SERGIO CONETTI The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the leave of absence of Mr. Sergio Conetti, Professor of Physics, for the period September 1, 1989 through January 15, 1990, without pay, to do research, as approved by the Board on October 6, 1989, be and it is hereby changed to read as follows: Mr. Sergio Conetti, Professor of Physics, for the period September 1, 1989 through December 31, 1989, without pay, to do research.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHANGES OF TITLE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following changes of title be and they are hereby made: Ms. Mary P. Abouzeid from Lecturer in Education, General Faculty to Assistant Professor of Education, General Faculty, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1989. Mr. Gary R. Allen from Visiting Associate Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs to Visiting Associate Professor of Economics, for one semester, effective January 16, 1990. Ms. Sara B. Blair from Acting Assistant Professor of English to Assistant Professor of English, for four academic years, effective September 1, 1989. Ms. Cheryl L. Eschbach from Acting Assistant Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs to Assistant Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs, for four years, effective January 16, 1990. Ms. Roseanne M. Ford from Acting Assistant Professor of Chemical Engineering to Assistant Professor of Chemical Engineering, for the period January 1, 1990 through May 31, 1992. Ms. Charlene E. Gill from Lecturer in Education, General Faculty to Assistant Professor of Education, General Faculty, for one academic year, effective September 1, 1989. Dr. Mark D. Griffith from Assistant Professor of Orthopaedics and Rehabilitation Medicine, Roanoke Program to Assistant Professor of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation, Roanoke Program, effective July 1, 1990. Ms. Rebecca Rawson from Lecturer, General Faculty to Lecturer, General Medical Faculty, for one year, effective March 1, 1990. Dr. Jerzy Sarosiek from Visiting Research Associate Professor of Internal Medicine to Research Associate Professor of Internal Medicine, for the period January 1, 1990 through June 30, 1990.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RETIREMENTS The following retirements were announced: Mr. Neill H. Alford, Jr., Percy Brown, Jr., Professor of Law, effective May 31, 1990. Mr. Alford has been a member of the faculty since October 23, 1947. Dr. M. Shannon Allen, Jr., Professor of Pathology, effective December 31, 1989. Dr. Allen has been a member of the faculty since May 1, 1958. Mr. Ernst O. Attinger, Harry Douglas Forsyth Professor of Engineering and Applied Science, effective May 31, 1990. Mr. Attinger has been a member of the faculty since July 1, 1967. Mr. Richard M. Brandt, Curry Memorial Professor of Education, effective May 31, 1990. Mr. Brandt has been a member of the faculty since September 1, 1965. Mr. Bernard W. Busse, Professor of Education, effective May 31, 1990. Mr. Busse has been a member of the faculty since September 15, 1954. Mr. James A. Cox, Professor of Architectural History, effective May 31, 1990. Mr. Cox has been a member of the faculty since September 1, 1967. Mr. James E. Deese, Hugh Scott Hamilton Professor of Psychology, effective May 31, 1990. Mr. Deese has been a member of the faculty since September 1, 1972. Mr. Robert L. Ellison, Associate Professor of Environmental Sciences, effective May 31, 1990. Mr. Ellison has been a member of the faculty since September 15, 1959. Mr. William H. Harbaugh, Langbourne M. Williams Professor of American History, effective May 31, 1990. Mr. Harbaugh has been a member of the faculty since September 1, 1966. Dr. Norman J. Knorr, University Professor of Psychiatry and Neuroscience, effective March 31, 1990. Dr. Knorr has been a member of the faculty since August 15, 1970. Mr. Irwin R. Konigsberg, Commonwealth Professor of Biology, effective May 31, 1990. Mr. Konigsberg has been a member of the faculty since August 1, 1966. Ms. Violette N. Lang, Lecturer in French, effective May 31, 1990. Ms. Lang has been a member of the faculty since September 1, 1967. Ms. Eleanor G. May, Professor of Business Administration, effective May 31, 1990. Ms. May has been a member of the faculty since September 1, 1970. Mr. Fred C. McCormick, Professor of Civil Engineering, effective January 15, 1990. Mr. McCormick has been a member of the faculty since February 1, 1955. Dr. William H. Muller, Jr., S. Hurt Watts Professor of Surgery and University Professor of Health Policy, effective June 30, 1990. Dr. Muller has been a member of the faculty since October 25, 1954. Dr. William M. O'Brien, Professor of Internal Medicine, effective January 31, 1990. Dr. O'Brien has been a member of the faculty since May 15, 1967. Mr. Vladimir D. Reisky, Associate Professor of Government and Foreign Affairs, effective May 31, 1990. Mr. Reisky has been a member of the faculty since September 1, 1964. Dr. James C. Respess, Professor of Internal Medicine, effective June 30, 1990. Dr. Respess has been a member of the faculty since July 1, 1955. Mr. Nathan A. Scott, William R. Kenan, Jr., Professor of Religious Studies, effective May 31, 1990. Mr. Scott has been a member of the faculty since July 1, 1976. Mr. Clifford M. Siegel, Professor of Electrical Engineering, effective January 15, 1990. Mr. Siegel has been a member of the faculty since September 15, 1951. Dr. Oscar A. Thorup, Jr., Professor of Internal Medicine, effective December 31, 1989. Dr. Thorup has been a member of the faculty since December 1, 1974. Mr. Thomas G. Williamson, Professor of Nuclear Engineering, effective July 1, 1990. Mr. Williamson has been a member of the faculty since July 1, 1960.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RESIGNATIONS The following resignations were announced: Ms. Susan G. Bader, Assistant Professor, General Medical Faculty, effective March 30, 1990, to accept another position. Ms. Ellin K. Deese, Associate Professor, General Faculty, effective June 30, 1990, to accept another position. Ms. Anjini Kochar, Acting Assistant Professor of Economics, effective February 9, 1990, to accept another position. Mr. David Little, Professor of Religious Studies, effective May 31, 1990, to accept another position. Mr. Thomas L. McKeon, Associate Professor, General Faculty, Continuing Education, effective January 31, 1990, to accept another position. Mr. Kwong Tai Ng, Assistant Professor of Electrical Engineering, effective December 31, 1989, to accept another position. Dr. Tae Sung Park, Associate Professor of Neurosurgery, effective December 31, 1989, to accept another position. Mr. Anthony J. Persechini, Research Assistant Professor of Biology, effective March 1, 1990, to accept another position. Ms. Dorothy R. Ross, Professor of History, effective May 31, 1990, to accept another position. Mr. Willis J. Spaulding, Associate Professor, General Faculty, effective June 30, 1990, to enter private practice. Mr. Daniel J. Walsh, Assistant Professor of Education, effective January 15, 1990, to accept another position. Mr. Edward J. White, Associate Professor of Electrical Engineering, effective December 31, 1989, to accept another position.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPOINTMENTS The following appointments were announced: Mr. Furman W. Barton as Chairman, Department of Civil Engineering, for five years, effective January 1, 1990. Mr. Robert C. Chapel as Chairman, Department of Drama, for three years, effective September 1, 1990. Mr. Joseph Cooper as Member of the Center for Advanced Studies, for two years, effective July 1, 1990. Mr. W. James Copeland, Jr., as Director of Athletic Programs, for five years, effective September 1, 1987. Mr. James D. Hunter as Member of the Center for Advanced Studies, for two years, effective July 1, 1990. Mr. Robert E. Johnson as Member, Center for Advanced Studies, for two years, effective July 1, 1990. Mr. Walter P. Jost, III as Chairman, Department of Rhetoric and Communication Studies, for three years, effective September 1, 1990. Mr. Paul W. Kingston as Acting Chairman, Department of Sociology, for the period January 1, 1990 through August 25, 1990. Mr. J. David Kovacs as Chairman, Department of Classics, for three years, effective July 1, 1990. Mr. John Marshall as Acting Chairman, Department of Philosophy, for one semester, effective January 16, 1990. Mr. Joseph C. Miller as Dean, College of Arts and Sciences, for five years, effective July 1, 1990. Mr. John G. Papovich as Assistant Dean, College of Arts and Sciences, for three years, effective July 1, 1990. Mr. Kent Sinclair, Jr., as Associate Dean, School of Law, for the period February 1, 1990, through June 30, 1992. Mr. J. David Summers as Chairman, Department of Art, for three years, effective July 1, 1990. Mr. Kenneth W. Thompson as Director of the White Burkett Miller Center of Public Affairs, for five years, effective July 1, 1988.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RE-APPOINTMENTS The following re-appointments were announced: Ms. Pamela K. Bouchard as Assistant Dean for Administration, School of Nursing, for one year, effective July 1, 1990. Mr. Julian W. Connolly as Chairman, Department of Slavic Languages, for the period September 1, 1990 through June 30, 1993. Mr. William A. Elwood as Associate Dean, Graduate School of Arts and Sciences, for one year, effective July 1, 1990. Mr. Robert J. Huskey as Associate Dean, Graduate School of Arts and Sciences, for one year, effective July 1, 1990. Mr. James S. Kennan as Assistant Vice President for Health Sciences Development and Community Relations, for one year, effective January 1, 1990. Ms. Patricia M. Lampkin as Associate Dean of Students, for three years, effective July 1, 1990. Mr. Murray Milner, Jr. as Chairman, Department of Sociology, for three years, effective September 1, 1990. Ms. Judy G. Ozbolt as Associate Dean for Research, School of Nursing, for one year, effective July 1, 1990. Ms. Cynthia F. Raines as Associate Dean for Academic Programs. School of Nursing, for one year, effective July 1, 1990. Ms. Jean Sorrells-Jones as Associate Dean for In-Hospital Services, for one year, effective July 1, 1990. Mr. Chelsea C. White as Chairman, Department of Systems Engineering, for the period January 1, 1990 through May 31, 1990.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DELETION OF THE RESIGNATION OF DR. JAMES W. CRAIG AS ANNOUNCED TO THE BOARD ON OCTOBER 6, 1989 The President announced that the resignation of Dr. James W. Craig, Professor of Internal Medicine, effective June 30, 1989, to qualify for the early retirement plan as approved by the Board of Visitors, be and it is hereby deleted. Dr. James Craig resigned from his administrative position as Associate Dean but not from his faculty position as Professor of Internal Medicine.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CORRECTION IN THE EFFECTIVE DATE OF THE RESIGNATION OF MR. EKKEHARD SINN The President announced that the resignation of Mr. Ekkehard Sinn, Associate Professor of Chemistry, effective January 15, 1989, to accept another position, announced to the Board on January 26, 1990, be and it is hereby corrected to read as follows: Mr. Ekkehard Sinn, Associate Professor of Chemistry, effective January 15, 1990, to accept another position.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DEATH OF DR. LUCIEN J. RUBINSTEIN Dr. Lucien J. Rubinstein, Professor of Pathology, died January 22, 1990. Dr. Rubinstein had been a member of the faculty since July 1, 1981.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ELECTION OF PROFESSORS EMERITI The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following persons be and they are hereby elected Professors Emeriti: Mr. Neill H. Alford, Jr., Percy Brown, Jr., Professor of Law. Dr. M. Shannon Allen, Jr., Professor of Pathology. Mr. Ernst O. Attinger, Harry Douglas Forsyth Professor of Engineering and Applied Science. Mr. Richard M. Brandt, Curry Memorial Professor of Education. Mr. Bernard W. Busse, Professor of Education. Mr. James A. Cox, Professor of Architectural History. Mr. Hugh M. Davidson, Commonwealth Professor of French Literature. Mr. James E. Deese, Hugh Scott Hamilton Professor of Psychology. Mr. William H. Harbaugh, Langbourne M. Williams Professor of American History. Dr. Norman J. Knorr, University Professor of Psychiatry and Neuroscience. Mr. Irwin R. Konigsberg, Commonwealth Professor of Biology. Ms. Eleanor G. May, Professor of Busines Administration. Mr. Fred C. McCormick, Professor of Civil Engineering. Dr. William H. Muller, Jr., S. Hurt Watts Professor of Surgery. Dr. William M. O'Brien, Professor of Internal Medicine. Dr. James C. Respess, Professor of Internal Medicine. Mr. Jaquelin T. Robertson, Commonwealth Professor of Architecture. Mr. Nathan A. Scott, William R. Kenan, Jr., Professor of Religious Studies. Dr. Oscar A. Thorup, Jr., Professor of Internal Medicine. Mr. Thomas G. Williamson, Professor of Nuclear Engineering.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ESTABLISHMENT OF THE ELSON PROFESSORSHIP IN ARCHITECTURE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that there is hereby established in the School of Architecture a Chair to be known as the Elson Professorship in Architecture, this Chair to become effective at such date as its funding is complete. The Board is grateful to Mr. Edward E. Elson who made the establishment of this Chair possible.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ESTABLISHMENT OF THE LUCIEN CARR, III, PROFESSORSHIP IN ENGINEERING AND APPLIED SCIENCE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that there is hereby established in the School of Engineering and Applied Science a Chair to be known as the Lucien Carr, III, Professorship in Engineering and Applied Science. The Board is grateful to the late Mrs. Harriet C. Weed who made the establishment of this Chair possible.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ESTABLISHMENT OF THE RICHARD F. EDLICH PROFESSORSHIP IN BIOMEDICAL RESEARCH The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that there is hereby established in the School of Medicine a Chair to be known as the Richard F. Edlich Professorship in Biomedical Research, this Chair to become effective at such date as its funding is complete. The Board is grateful to the United States Surgical Corporation and Leonard D. Kurtz, M.D., who made the establishment of this Chair possible.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ESTABLISHMENT OF THE THOMAS M. LINVILLE PROFESSORSHIP IN ENGINEERING AND APPLIED SCIENCE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that there is hereby established in the School of Engineering and Applied Science a Chair to be known as the Thomas M. Linville Professorship in Engineering and Applied Science, this Chair to become effective at such date as its funding is complete. The Board is grateful to Mr. Thomas M. Linville who made the establishment of this Chair possible.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ESTABLISHMENT OF THE PERRE BOWEN PROFESSORSHIP IN LAW The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that there is hereby established in the School of Law a Chair to be known as the Perre Bowen Professorship in Law. The Board is grateful to the late Mr. Perre Bowen who made the establishment of this Chair possible.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ESTABLISHMENT OF THE CLASS OF 1963 RESEARCH PROFESSORSHIP IN LAW The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that there is hereby established in the School of Law a Chair to be known as the Class of 1963 Research Professorship in Law. The Board is grateful to members of the School of Law Class of 1963, who made the establishment of this Chair possible.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ESTABLISHMENT OF THE CLASS OF 1948 PROFESSORSHIP IN SCHOLARLY RESEARCH IN LAW The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that there is hereby established in the School of Law a Chair to be known as the Class of 1948 Professorship in Scholarly Research in Law. The Board is grateful to members of the School of Law Class of 1948, who made the establishment of this Chair possible.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">REPORT ON CONSTRUCTION The President reported that construction projects valued at some $114 million are underway for the University Division. Roughly 25% of these funds are from State General Funds. Projects in the Hospital Division are valued at $230 million, 10% of which are from State General Funds. The Clinch Valley College Division construction projects are valued at $5.5 million - mostly all from State General Funds.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">GIFTS, GRANTS AND CONTRACTS The President reported that gifts to the College of Arts and Sciences have already exceeded four million dollars from private sources. He said that this is an exceptional achievement.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">REPORT ON LEGISLATIVE MATTERS President O'Neil reported that Higher Education (not exclusively this University) will undertake a number of studies. These studies include the study of Higher Education in Northern Virginia, increased flexibility in the State's two teaching hospitals, some interim measures for the financing of capital projects, the reduction of health care costs and some related issues. He said also, some increased attention to environmental concerns was requested. No action was sought on this report.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF THE FIRM OF BARNES VANZE &amp; ASSOCIATES FOR THE PERFORMANCE OF ARCHITECTURAL DESIGN FOR THE ADDITION AND RENOVATION OF THE UNIVERSITY PRESS BEMISS HOUSE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the firm of Barnes Vanze &amp; Associates of Washington, D. C., be approved for the performance of architectural design for the addition and renovation of the University Press, Bemiss House.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF NOMINATIONS OF MR. EDWARD E. ELSON, MRS. PATRICIA M. KLUGE, MR. CHARLES T. GILLET, MR. PETER HACKETT, AND MR. JOSEPH C. MILLER TO THE COLLEGE COUNCIL OF REGENT'S COLLEGE, LONDON The following resolution was adopted: WHEREAS, the agreement between Regent's College and The Rector and Visitors recognizes the University of Virginia's right to protect its academic reputation and to share in the direction of academic programs at Regent's College; and WHEREAS, the agreement between Regent's College and The Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia states that the University of Virginia will nominate five members to serve on the Council (Executive Board) and the Court of Governors of Regent's College; RESOLVED that Mr. Edward E. Elson, Mrs. Patricia M. Kluge, Mr. Charles T. Gillet, Mr. Peter Hackett, and Mr. Joseph C. Miller be and they are hereby nominated to serve as University representatives on the College Council and the Court of Governors of Regent's College until June 30, 1991.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF PROPOSED INCREASE IN TUITION AND REQUIRED FEES AND OTHER CHARGES FOR THE ACADEMIC DIVISION The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the tuition and required fees and other charges applicable to the Academic Division be and they are hereby approved as shown below, effective July 1, 1990: REGULAR SESSION: Virginian Non-Virginian Actual 1989-90 Amt. of Inc. Percent of Inc. Proposed 1990-91 Actual 1989-90 Amt. of Inc. Percent of Inc. Proposed 1990-91 Tuition and Required Fees Undergraduate and Graduate Schools Full Time $2,680 $258 9.6% $2,938 $7,060 $1,048 14.8% $8,108 Graduate Law $2,680 $384 14.3% $3,064 $7,060 $1,174 16.6% $8,234 Medical Technology $1,360 $128 9.4% $1,488 $1,360 $128 9.4% $1,488 Professional Schools Graduate Bus. - MBA $4,640 $368 7.9% $5,008 $10,120 $1,498 14.8% $11,618 Law - JD $4,060 $354 8.7% $4,414 $8,920 $1,134 12.7% $10,054 Medicine - MD $6,440 $488 7.6% $6,928 $13,320 $1,408 10.6% $14,728 Activity Fees General-All Students $28 -- -- $28 $28 -- -- $28 Architecture $20 -- -- $20 $20 -- -- $20 Commerce $10 -- -- $10 $10 -- -- $10 Darden $32 $23 71.9% $55 $32 $23 71.9% $55 Education $4 -- -- $4 $4 -- -- $4 Engineering $10 -- -- $10 $10 -- -- $10 Law School $28 -- -- $28 $28 -- -- $28 Medicine $70 -- -- $70 $70 -- -- $70 Nursing $10 -- -- $10 $10 -- -- $10 Residential College Programming Fee $100 -- -- $100 $100 -- -- $100 APPROVAL OF PROPOSED INCREASE IN TUITION AND REQUIRED FEES AND OTHER CHARGES FOR THE ACADEMIC DIVISION (cont.) CONTINUING EDUCATION: Current 1989-90 Amount of Increase Percent Increase Proposed 1990-91 Undergraduate (Non-Degree Programs) Per Semester hour Virginian $88 $5 5.7% $93 Non-Virginian $104 $14 13.5% $118 Graduate (Non-Degree Programs) Per Semester Hour Virginian $88 $10 11.4% $98 Non-Virginian $104 $19 18.3% $123 Special Students Registration through and admitted by the Division of Continuing Education in On-Grounds Courses Per semester hour Virginian $120 $10 8.3% $130 Non-Virginian $336 $54 16.1% $390 Masters Degree Programs Per semester hour Virginian $98 $25 25.5% $123 Non-Virginian $114 $34 29.8% $148 Graduate Televised Engineering Per Semester Hour Virginian $132 -- -- $132 Non-Virginian $298 -- -- $298 Admission Fee in Certificate and Special Programs $10 -- -- $10 Late Registration Fee $10 -- -- $10 Change of Course Fee $10 -- -- $10 Transcript Fee $2 -- -- $2 Late Exam Fee $5 -- -- $5 Other Miscellaneous Fees as established to recover expenses such as laboratory, materials, etc., on a basis of estimated cost. OTHER: Other contracted course and cooperative program tuition and required fee rates approved on a basis consistent with University contracting policies and procedures by the Vice President for Business and Finance.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF PROPOSED INCREASE IN TUITION AND REQUIRED FEES AND OTHER CHARGES FOR CLINCH VALLEY COLLEGE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the tuition and required fees and other charges applicable to Clinch Valley College be and they are hereby approved as shown below, effective July 1, 1990: Virginian Non-Virginian Actual 1989-90 Amt. of Inc. Percent of Inc. Proposed 1990-91 Actual 1989-90 Amt. of Inc. Percent of Inc. Proposed 1990-91 Tuition and Required Fees Full-time Students (12 semester hours or more per semester) Session Rate $1,870 $186 9.9% $2,056 * * Tuition $1,564 + Fees $492 = $2,056 $3,338 $378 11.3% $3,716 ** ** Tuition $3,224 + Fees $492 = $3,716 Students taking more than 18 credit hours per semester must pay for the additional hours at the part-time tuition rates listed below. Part-time Students (less than 12 semester hrs per semester) Rate per semester hour $60 $4 6.7% $64 $120 $12 10.0% $132 Off-Campus Instruction Credit Courses - Rate per semester hour $60 $4 6.7% $64 $92 $4 4.3% $96 Non-Credit Courses - Rate per CEU $20 $2 10.0% $22 $40 $6 15.0% $46 Dormitory Rent Dorms $1,320 $80 6.1% $1,400 $1,320 $80 6.1% $1,400 Apt. House $1,500 $90 6.0% $1,590 $1,500 $90 6.0% $1,590 Meal Plan 19 meals per week $1,420 $80 5.6% $1,500 $1,420 $80 5.6% $1,500 Other Fees Application Fee $15 $0 0.0% $15 $15 $0 0.0% $15 Applied Music Fee $120 $0 0.0% $120 $120 $0 0.0% $120 Student Teaching Fee -- -- -- $100 -- -- -- $100 The Applied Music Fee is applicable to Applied Music Courses 104, 105, 108, 109, 204, 205, 304, 305, 404, and 405 and is in addition to all other tuition and required fees. A registration fee for part-time students will be $5 per semester hour. The graduation fee will be $40 per year.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF PROPOSED ALLOCATION OF REQUIRED FEES FOR 1990-1991 The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the fee component of the tuition and required fees be and it is hereby established, effective July 1, 1990, in the amount of $568; RESOLVED FURTHER that the fee component be allocated for the 1990-91 Session as follows: Actual 1989-90 Amount of Inc/(Decr) Percent Inc/(Decr) Proposed 1990-91 Pledged for Facilities - University Hall $ 15.00 -- -- $ 15.00 University Transit 52.00 $4.00 7.7% 56.00 Auxiliary Services Fee (including debt service) 98.00 60.00 61.2% 158.00 Fringe Benefits 63.00 (63.00) -- -- Athletics 88.00 10.00 11.4% 98.00 Student Health 163.00 13.00 8.0% 176.00 University Union 45.00 4.00 8.9% 49.00 University Union Programs 16.00 -- -- 16.00 TOTAL $ 540.00 $28.00 5.2% $ 568.00</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF PROPOSED CONTRACT RATES FOR DINING SERVICES FOR 1990-1991 The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the student contract rates for dining services be and they are hereby approved as shown below, effective beginning with the Session 1990-1991: Approval of Proposed Contract Rates for Dining Services for 1990-1991 - continued Actual 1989-90 Amount of Increase Percent Increase Proposed 1990-91 Dining Service Contract 7 Day (19 meals) $1,518 $ 132 8.7% $1,650 6 Meals per week* * Meal Plan to be Eliminated FY 90-91 664 -- -- -- 9 Meals per week -- -- -- 1,400 12 Meals per week* 1,306 -- -- -- 15 Meals per week 1,428 172 12.0% 1,600 50 Meals per semester -- -- -- 600 100 Meals per semester -- -- -- 900 Residential College 7 Day (19 meals) $1,668 $ 162 9.7% $1,830 6 Meals per week* 814 -- -- -- 9 Meals per week -- -- -- 1,490 12 Meals per week* 1,456 -- -- -- 15 Meals per week 1,578 202 12.8% 1,780 Athletics 12 Meals per week* $1,392 -- -- -- 15 Meals per week -- -- -- $1,700 19 Meals per week $1,604 $ 146 9.1% 1,750 French House 4 Meal Dinners $ 578 62 10.7% 640</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF PROPOSED INCREASE IN FACULTY AND STAFF HOUSING RATES FOR THE ACADEMIC DIVISION FOR 1990-1991 The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the faculty and staff housing rates be and they are hereby approved as indicated, effective July 1, 1990: Utilities Furnished by UVA FACILITY WS (Water, Sewer) E (Elect.) O (Fuel Oil) G (Gas) HP (Heat Plant) C (TV Cable) Rents 1989-90 per Month Amount of Increase Percent of Increase Proposed Rents 1990-91 per Month Utilities Paid by Occupant Piedmont Estates 1 Bedroom Apt. (7) WS,E,O,C $320 $26 8.12% $346 2 Bedroom Apt. (16) WS,E,O,C $380 $30 7.89% $410 3 Bedroom Houses (16) WS,C $400 $32 8.00% $432 E,O Townhouses (10) 3BR WS,C $400 $32 8.00% $432 E Farmhouse (121 Mimosa) Apt. 1,1 Bedroom WS,E,O,C $310 $24 7.74% $334 Apt. 2,3 Bedroom WS,E,O,C $345 $29 8.40% $374 Apt. 3,1 Bedroom WS,E,O,C $310 $24 7.74% $334 Apt. 4,2 Bedroom WS,E,O,C $320 $26 8.12% $346 Monroe Lane 1 Bedroom (15) WS,G,C $280 $24 8.57% $304 E Efficiency (1) WS,G,C $240 $20 8.33% $260 E 404 Monroe Lane (2BR) WS,G,C $330 $26 7.87% $356 E 412 A Monroe Lane (2BR) WS,G,C $355 $29 8.17% $384 E 412 B Monroe Lane (Eff) WS,G,C $240 $20 8.33% $260 E Snowden Apt. 1 (1BR) WS,G,C $285 $25 8.77% $310 E Apt. 2 (1BR) WS,G,C $285 $25 8.77% $310 E Apt. 6 (Eff.) WS,G,C $240 $20 8.33% $260 E Apt. 101 (3BR) WS,G,C $420 $34 8.09% $454 E Apt. 103 (2BR) WS,G,C $355 $29 8.17% $384 E Apt. 201 (1BR) WS,G,C $285 $25 8.77% $310 E Apt. 202 (1BR) WS,G,C $285 $25 8.77% $310 E Apt. 203 (2BR) WS,G,C $355 $29 8.17% $384 E Sundry Vyssotsky Cottage (3BR) WS,C $345 $29 8.40% $374 E,O Upper Alden (3BR) WS,O,C $380 $32 8.42% $412 E Lower Alden (2BR) WS,O,C $335 $27 8.05% $362 E South Cottage (3BR) WS,C $180 $16 8.88% $196 E,O Carrs Hill (2BR) WS,E,HP,C $340 $30 8.82% $370 McGuffey Cottage (Eff) WS,E,HP,C $240 $20 8.33% $260 APPROVAL OF PROPOSED INCREASE IN FACULTY AND STAFF HOUSING RATES FOR THE ACADEMIC DIVISION FOR 1990-91 (cont.) Utilities Furnished by UVA FACILITY WS (Water,Sewer) E (Elect.) O (Fuel Oil) G (Gas) HP (Heat Plant) C (TV Cable) Rents 1989-90 per Month Amount of Increase Percent of Increase Proposed Rents 1990-91 per Month Utilities Paid by Occupant * * Will be vacant during FY 1990-91 2400 Stadium Rd (4BR) $450 -- -- -- Upper Mews (1BR) WS,E,HP,C $280 $24 8.57% $304 Lower Mews (1BR) WS,E,HP,C $335 $29 8.65% $364 Milton Airport (1BR) $165 $15 9.09% $180 WS,E Monroe Hill Range (2BR) WS,HP,C $400 $32 8.00% $432 E Monroe Hill Apt. (2)+ + Rent to Student Housing WS,HP,E,C $340 $30 8.82% $370 Birdwood Properties Cottage (1BR) WS,C $260 $20 7.69% $280 E Garage Apt. (2BR) WS,E,O.C $390 $32 8.20% $422 Cash House (3BR) WS,E,O.C $410 $34 8.29% $444 Birdwood House (4BR) WS,C $450 $36 8.00% $486 E,O,G Faulkner Property Holly House (2BR) WS,E,O,C $330 $26 7.87% $356 Holly House Lower (1RM) WS,E,O,C $160 $20 12.50% $180 Hedge House (2BR) WS,C $300 $24 8.00% $324 E,O Orchard House (5SRMS) WS,E,O,C $160 $20 12.50% $180 Carriage House (4BR) WS,C $350 $30 8.57% $380 E,O 118 Oakhurst-Upper (2BR) WS,G,C $345 $29 8.40% $374 E 118 Oakhurst-Lower (2BR) WS,G,C $390 $32 8.20% $422 E 409 Valley Road (2BR) C $330 $28 8.48% $358 WS,E,O 411 Valley Road (2BR) C $330 $28 8.48% $358 WS,E,O 503 Valley Road (1BR) C $270 $22 8.15% $292 WS,E,O Faculty Apartments Apt. 11 (2BR) WS,E,G,C $360 $30 8.33% $390 Apt. 12 (2BR) WS,E,G,C $360 $30 8.33% $390 Apt. 14 (2BR) WS,E,G,C $360 $30 8.33% $390 Apt. 15 (2BR) WS,E,G,C $360 $30 8.33% $390 Apt. 21 (Eff) WS,E,G,C $270 $22 8.15% $292 Apt. 22 (1BR) WS,E,G,C $275 $23 8.36% $298 Apt. 23 (Eff) WS,R,G,C $260 $20 7.69% $280 Apt. 24 (1BR) WS,E,G,C $275 $23 8.36% $298 Apt. 25 (1BR) WS,E,G,C $280 $22 7.85% $302 Apt. 26 (1BR) WS,E,G,C $280 $22 7.85% $302 APPROVAL OF PROPOSED INCREASE IN FACULTY AND STAFF HOUSING RATES FOR THE ACADEMIC DIVISION FOR 1990-91 (cont.) Utilities Furnished by UVA FACILITY WS (Water,Sewer) E (Elect.) O (Fuel Oil) G (Gas) HP (Heat Plant) C (TV Cable) Rents 1989-90 per Month Amount of Increase Percent of Increase Proposed Rents 1990-91 per Month Utilities Paid by Occupant Apt. 27 (1BR) WS,E,G,C $280 $22 7.85% $302 Apt. 28 (1BR) WS,E,G,C $280 $22 7.85% $302 Apt. 31 (1BR) WS,E,G,C $280 $22 7.85% $302 Apt. 32 (1BR) WS,E,G,C $280 $22 7.85% $302 Apt. 33 (2BR) WS,E,G,C $310 $26 8.38% $336 Apt. 34 (2BR) WS,E,G,C $310 $26 8.38% $336 Apt. 35 (2BR) WS,E,G,C $310 $26 8.38% $336 Apt. 36 (2BR) WS,E,G,C $310 $26 8.38% $336 E. &amp; G. Property Montebello (3BR) O $410 $20 4.87% $430 WS,E,G Big Morea (4BR) WS,E,O,C $305 $15 4.91% $320 Little Morea (1BR) WS,E,O,C $275 $13 4.72% $288 Sunnyside (4BR) O,C $525 $25 4.76% $550 WS,E Hotel D (2BR) WS,E,H $260 $12 4.61% $272 Monroe Hill House WS,E,HP $525 $25 4.76% $550 Pavilions Pavilion I WS,HP,E $505 $25 4.95% $530 *Pavilion II WS,HP $360 -- -- -- E Pavilion III WS,HP,E $505 $25 4.95% $530 Pavilion IV WS,HP $360 $18 5.00% $378 E Pavilion V WS,HP $360 $18 5.00% $378 E *Pavilion V Annex -- -- -- -- Pavilion VI WS,HP,E -- -- -- $530 Pavilion VIII Lower WS,HP,E $120 $36 30.00% $156 Pavilion VIII Upper WS,HP,E $240 $84 35.00% $324 Pavilion IX WS,HP $360 $18 5.00% $378 E Pavilion X WS,HP $360 $18 5.00% $378 E Blue Ridge Properties + + Facility has been removed from residential use. Bldg 913A (2/3 BR Apt) WS,E,HP $495 -- -- -- APPROVAL OF PROPOSED INCREASE IN FACULTY AND STAFF HOUSING RATES FOR THE ACADEMIC DIVISION FOR 1990-91 (cont.) Utilities Furnished by UVA FACILITY WS (Water,Sewer) E (Elect.) O (Fuel Oil) G (Gas) HP (Heat Plant) C (TV Cable) Rents 1989-90 per Month Amount of Increase Percent of Increase Proposed Rents 1990-91 per Month Utilities Paid by Occupant Blandy Farm ** ** Agreement of service in lieu of rent has been approved. Curator's House WS $285 -- -- -- E,O Farmhouse WS $270 $10 3.70% $280 E,O Greenhouse WS $50 $5 10.00% $55 E</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF PROPOSED INCREASE IN RESIDENTIAL HOUSING RATES FOR CLINCH VALLEY COLLEGE FOR 1990-1991 The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the Residential Housing Rates applicable to Clinch Valley College be and they are hereby approved as shown below, effective September 1, 1990: Proposed Rents 1990-91 Per Month Utilities Furnished By Clinch Valley College Rents 1989-90 Per Month Facility WS (Water, Sewer) G (Gas) Amount of Increase Percent of Increase Houses (6) WS $336 $18 5.4% $354 2 Bedroom Apt. (2) WSG $336 $18 5.4% $354 1 Bedroom Apt. (2) WSG $306 $18 5.9% $324</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF PROPOSED INCREASE IN THE FACULTY SALARY SCALE FOR THE ACADEMIC DIVISION FOR 1990-1991 The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following compensation plans applicable to the teaching and research staff in the Academic Division be and they are hereby approved, effective July 1, 1990: 1989-90 Normal Entrance Rate (1) (1) Amounts are stated on a session basis unless otherwise indicated. 1990-91 Proposed Normal Entrance Rate (1) Normal Increment Amt Interval General Faculty (4) (4) The rank of Lecturer is used for administrative faculty positions as well as instructional personnel whose assignment or status does not fit into the regular structure faculty rank. Salary levels will vary in accordance with level of responsibility and experience. Professor $42,800 $44,500 (2) (2) 0-15%; amounts in excess of 15% are approved as special salary actions. 1 year Associate Professor 35,200 36,600 (2) 1 year Assistant Professor 28,600 29,800 (2) 1 year Instructor 20,200 21,000 (2) 1 year Pre-Clinical Faculty (3) (3) Amounts in this category are stated on an annual (12-month) basis. (4) Department Head 56,900 59,200 (2) 1 year Professor 49,800 51,800 (2) 1 year Associate Professor 41,000 42,600 (2) 1 year Assistant Professor 33,000 34,300 (2) 1 year Instructor 25,800 26,800 (2) 1 year Junior Staff (3) Research Assistant 16,500 16,500 (2) 1 year Research Associate 17,000 17,000 (2) 1 year Sponsored Programs (3) Research Scientist 26,700 27,800 (2) 1 year Senior Scientist 33,500 34,800 (2) 1 year Principal Scientist 51,400 53,400 (2) 1 year</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF PROPOSED INCREASE IN THE FACULTY SALARY SCALE FOR CLINCH VALLEY COLLEGE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following compensation plan applicable to the teaching and research staff of Clinch Valley College be and it is hereby approved, effective July 1, 1990: 1989-90 Normal Entrance Rate (1) (1) Amounts are stated on a session basis. 1990-91 Proposed Normal Entrance Rate (1) Normal Increment Amt Interval Rank Professor $32,000 $33,000 (2) (2) 0-15%; amounts in excess of 15% are approved as special salary actions. 1 year Associate Professor $27,500 $28,500 (2) 1 year Assistant Professor $23,500 $24,500 (2) 1 year Instructor $20,000 $21,000 (2) 1 year</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF PROPOSED INCREASE IN CLINICAL AND PATHOLOGY FACULTY SALARY CEILINGS FOR THE SCHOOL OF MEDICINE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that subject to the approval of the Governor, the full-time Clinical and Pathology Faculty Salary Ceilings shall be as follows, effective July 1, 1990: Current Scale 1989-90 Proposed Scale 1990-91 Rank State Maximum Ceilings State Maximum Ceilings Professor and Department Head $81,300 $198,400 $84,900 $205,900 Professor and Division Head 77,100 186,600 80,500 195,300 Professor 74,100 179,400 77,400 187,700 Associate Professor and Division Head 67,000 162,300 70,000 169,700 Associate Professor 64,400 155,900 67,300 163,100 Assistant Professor 57,000 138,000 59,500 144,400 Instructor 44,700 108,300 46,700 113,200</field>
      <field name="fulltext">REPORT OF THE MEDICAL CENTER ACCOUNTS COMMITTEE The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the Medical Center Accounts Committee be and it is hereby authorized to write off as bad debts and free service accounts included in the University of Virginia Medical Accounts Committee Reports for the meeting of February 19, 1990 which includes the write-offs for the months of December 1989 and January 1990, totaling $10,697,562.15 and consisting of the following: Bad Debt $ 1,822,507.36 Indigent Care 8,875,054.79 --------------- $10,697,562.15 RESOLVED FURTHER that the above action shall not be a compromise, settlement or discharge of debts represented by such accounts.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF AMENDMENT TO THE COMPENSATION PLAN FOR RADIOLOGIC TECHNOLOGISTS IN THE RADIATION THERAPY AND DIAGNOSTIC DIVISIONS OF THE DEPARTMENT OF RADIOLOGY The following resolution was adopted: WHEREAS, the Vice President for Health Sciences and the Vice President for Business and Finance are authorized to amend the compensation for individual Health Care Professional classes subject to approval by the Finance Committee of the Board of Visitors; RESOLVED that the accompanying amendment (Attachment A) for the radiologic technologists in the Radiation Therapy and Diagnostic Divisions of the Department of Radiology be and it is hereby approved.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF COMPENSATION PLAN FOR HEALTH CARE PROFESSIONALS FOR 1990-1991 The following resolution was adopted: WHEREAS, the Appropriation Act approved by the 1989 General Assembly authorized the Board of Visitors to establish competitive compensation programs for Health Care Professionals employed in the UVA Medical Center; and WHEREAS, the Finance Committee of the Board of Visitors approved the initial Classification and Compensation Plan at its meeting on May 9, 1989; and WHEREAS, Medical Center and Department of Personnel Administration management conducted a Compensation Survey for Health Care Professionals in Hospitals in the Northeast, Southeast and Midwest; and WHEREAS, the survey results illustrate that compensation for UVA Health Care Professionals is below the compensation provided for similar positions at the hospitals surveyed; NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED that the accompanying Health Care Professionals Classification and Compensation Plan (See Attachment B), be and it is hereby approved to become effective July 1, 1990.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">STATEMENT OF MR. GILBERT J. SULLIVAN, DIRECTOR OF ALUMNI ACTIVITIES OF THE ALUMNI ASSOCIATION Mr. Gilbert Sullivan said that the University of Virginia Alumni Association is 150 years old and that its activities have continuing efforts to raise funds for University purposes. He said a major present responsibility of the Association is the operation of the University of Virginia Fund, which raises about $12 million annually. Related activities are the phonathons, investment services and similar organizations. Alumni records of 110,000 living alumni are maintained in a computerized system. He said the maintenance of the Jefferson Scholars Program and The Alumni News are also important activities. He assured the Board that the Alumni Association stands ready to work with the Board of Visitors in every way including fundraising. He predicted that private gifts from alumni will total $50 million this year.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">STATEMENT OF ATTORNEY GENERAL MARY SUE TERRY The Honorable Mary Sue Terry said she was delighted to be with us. She noted that the University is served by two attorneys, Mr. James Mingle and Mr. Larry White, and they both can look to the Attorney General's office in Richmond for a range of services. She pointed out that having a teaching hospital as a part of our organization presents special legal challenges. She said she has been meeting with education attorneys, and that a level of expertise in these matters is developing. She urged the Board to advise her of ways that the Office of the Attorney General can help the University or the Board. She concluded by saying that she was aware of the impact that the financial shortfall is having on the institutions in the Commonwealth. The Rector thanked Attorney General Terry for being with us.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPROVAL OF AUTHORIZATION TO LEASE LAND FOR OIL AND GAS AT CLINCH VALLEY COLLEGE The following resolution was adopted: WHEREAS, Clinch Valley College requests the approval of the Rector and Visitors to lease 13 tracts encompassing approximately 264.32 acres of land on its campus for oil and gas exploration and extraction and all products which may be derived therefrom; and WHEREAS, the lessee will be selected, and the royalty rates to the College will be determined, through a competitive solicitation in accordance with the applicable rules and regulations of the Commonwealth of Virginia; and WHEREAS, all operations will comply with applicable State and Federal subsurface mineral exploration and extraction regulations; RESOLVED that Clinch Valley College is authorized to lease its land for oil and gas exploration and extraction under the foregoing terms and conditions; RESOLVED FURTHER that the appropriate officers of the University be and they hereby are authorized to execute an approved oil and gas lease on said land.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CLINCH VALLEY COLLEGE ELECTIONS The following resolution was adopted: RESOLVED that the following persons be and they are hereby elected to the faculty: Ms. Dania M. Bilal as Lecturer, General Faculty, Clinch Valley College, for the period January 15, 1990, through June 30, 1991. Mr. Lucius F. Ellsworth as Professor of History, Clinch Valley College, effective April 1, 1990.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">APPOINTMENTS The following appointments were announced: Ms. Dania M. Bilal as Associate Director of Library Services, Clinch Valley College, for the period January 15, 1990 through June 30, 1991. Mr. Lucius F. Ellsworth as Vice Chancellor and Dean, Clinch Valley College, for three years, effective April 1, 1990. On motion, the meeting adjourned at 3:30 p.m. Respectfully submitted, Raymond C. Bice, Jr. Secretary RCB:jb</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ADDENDUM TO THE OFFICIAL MINUTES OF THE MEETING OF THE BOARD OF VISITORS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA Meeting Date: March 29, 1990 CERTIFICATION OF EXECUTIVE MEETING WHEREAS, the Board of Visitors has convened an executive meeting on this date pursuant to an affirmative recorded vote and in accordance with the provisions of The Virginia Freedom of Information Act; and WHEREAS, Section 2.1-344.1 of the Code of Virginia requires a certification by this Board of Visitors that such executive meeting was conducted in conformity with Virginia law; NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED that the Board of Visitors hereby certifies that, to the best of each member's knowledge, (i) only public business matters lawfully exempted from open meeting requirements by Virginia law were discussed in the executive meeting to which this certification resolution applies, and (ii) only such public business matters as were identified in the motion convening the executive meeting were heard, discussed or considered by the Board of Visitors. VOTE AYES: 16 NAYS: 0 [For each nay vote, the substance of the departure from the requirements of the Act should be described] ABSENT DURING VOTE: 0 ABSENT DURING MEETING: 0 Raymond C. Bice, Jr. Secretary, Board of Visitors, University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="fulltext">At a meeting of the Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia held on March 29, 1990 - 9:05 a.m., a roll call vote was taken immediately following an executive session. Members voting "yes" certify that to the best of the Member's knowledge (1) only public business matters lawfully exempted were discussed in closed session; and (2) only public business matters identified in the public motion by which the executive or closed meeting were discussed. In accordance with the law, any member of the public body who believes that there was a departure from the foregoing shall so state prior to the vote indicating "the substance of the departure". Any such statements are recorded below under "comments". NAME VOTE (yes or no) COMMENTS W. L. Lyons Brown, Jr. yes Robert G. Butcher, Jr. yes N. Thomas Connally yes Hovey S. Dabney yes Edward E. Elson yes Waller H. Horsley yes J. Thomas Hulvey yes Evans B. Jessee yes Mrs. Patricia M. Kluge yes Arnold H. Leon yes Leigh B. Middleditch, Jr. yes Mrs. Elizabeth D. Morie yes Freddie W. Nicholas, Sr. yes S. Buford Scott yes Jesse B. Wilson, III yes Thomas E. Worrell, Jr. yes</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ADDENDUM TO THE OFFICIAL MINUTES OF THE MEETING OF THE BOARD OF VISITORS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA Meeting Date: March 30, 1990 CERTIFICATION OF EXECUTIVE MEETING WHEREAS, the Board of Visitors has convened an executive meeting on this date pursuant to an affirmative recorded vote and in accordance with the provisions of The Virginia Freedom of Information Act; and WHEREAS, Section 2.1-344.1 of the Code of Virginia requires a certification by this Board of Visitors that such executive meeting was conducted in conformity with Virginia law; NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED that the Board of Visitors hereby certifies that, to the best of each member's knowledge, (i) only public business matters lawfully exempted from open meeting requirements by Virginia law were discussed in the executive meeting to which this certification resolution applies, and (ii) only such public business matters as were identified in the motion convening the executive meeting were heard, discussed or considered by the Board of Visitors. VOTE AYES: 16 NAYS: 0 [For each nay vote, the substance of the departure from the requirements of the Act should be described] ABSENT DURING VOTE: 0 ABSENT DURING MEETING: 0 Raymond C. Bice, Jr. Secretary, Board of Visitors, University of Virginia</field>
      <field name="fulltext">At a meeting of the Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia held on March 30, 1990 - 2:15 p.m., a roll call vote was taken immediately following an executive session. Members voting "yes" certify that to the best of the Member's knowledge (1) only public business matters lawfully exempted were discussed in closed session; and (2) only public business matters identified in the public motion by which the executive or closed meeting were discussed. In accordance with the law, any member of the public body who believes that there was a departure from the foregoing shall so state prior to the vote indicating "the substance of the departure". Any such statements are recorded below under "comments". NAME VOTE (yes or no) COMMENTS W. L. Lyons Brown, Jr. yes Robert G. Butcher, Jr. yes N. Thomas Connally yes Hovey S. Dabney yes Edward E. Elson yes Waller H. Horsley yes J. Thomas Hulvey yes Evans B. Jessee yes Mrs. Patricia M. Kluge yes Arnold H. Leon yes Leigh B. Middleditch, Jr. yes Mrs. Elizabeth D. Morie yes Freddie W. Nicholas, Sr. yes S. Buford Scott yes Jesse B. Wilson, III yes Thomas E. Worrell, Jr. yes</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ATTACHMENT A = Amendment to the Compensation Plan for Radiologic Technologists in the Radiation Therapy and and Diagnostic Divisions of the Department of Radiology UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA Department of Personnel Administration Carruthers Hall 1001 North Emmet Street P.O. Box 9007 Charlottesville. Va. 22906-9007 TO: Don E. Detmer, M.D. Leonard W. Sandridge, Jr. FROM: Michael T. Halseth Ronald A. Bouchard DATE: January 31, 1990 The Vice President for Health Sciences and the Vice President for Business and Finance are authorized to amend the compensation for individual Health Care Professional classes subject to approval by the Finance Committee of the Board of Visitors, with increases to the personnel budget of the hospital of no more than $200,000. The following is a proposal outlining the actions necessary to alleviate major staffing shortages in the Radiation Therapy and Diagnostic Divisions of the Department of Radiology. Conventional recruiting and retention practices have not alleviated the problem, thus some non-conventional interventions must be considered or these divisions will be unable to render appropriate and timely patient care. ANNUALIZED COST: $71,000. See attached for more details. Recommended by: Michael T. Halseth Interim Executive Director, Medical Center Ronald A. Bouchard Assistant Vice President, Personnel Administration Approved by: Don E. Detmer, M.D. Vice President for Health Sciences Leonard W. Sandridge, Jr. Vice President for Business and Finance An Affirmative Action/Equal Opportunity Employer</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ISSUE: RECRUITMENT OF RADIOLOGY THERAPY TECHNOLOGISTS Recent turnover of Radiation Therapy Technologists has left the Division understaffed by 33%. Three of nine staff technologist positions are currently vacant. Filling these vacancies poses a dilemma in that a severe nationwide shortage exists, precluding effective recruitment of experienced Radiation Therapy Technologists. Repeated recruiting efforts have not been successful. The more promising pool of Radiation Therapy Technologists exists within Radiology schools, one of which is in session at the University of Virginia. As graduation approaches, these UVa-trained Radiation Therapy Technologists will be approached by various medical centers, who may be in a position to offer higher starting salaries or recruiting bonuses. PROPOSED SOLUTION: Most recruiting bonuses are paid at or after employment commences. We are recommending that we secure a commitment from our students before other offers are presented, by offering our four students a recruiting incentive of $2,000 each, payable immediately, in exchange for a written commitment that each will work for UVa for one year, commencing no later than September 1, 1990. Further, as it is anticipated that shortages may exist in other areas of Radiology, a lesser recruiting bonus of $1,000 should be offered to other students, enrolled in our school, for a similar one year commitment. We believe that by providing students the recruiting incentive immediately, we will accelerate the conventional recruiting period and beat our competition. Plans are underway to redesign the stipend-scholarship employment provisions and requirements for future students who are enrolled in our medical center based schools. ISSUE: RETENTION OF EXISTING RADIATION THERAPY TECHNOLOGISTS Labor market survey data from our Fall 1989 survey indicate that for Radiation Therapy Technologists, UVa's ranges trail the market by 9% at the minimum and by 13% at the maximum, with average salaries down by over 6%. PROPOSED SOLUTION: To retain the present staff, it is recommended that they be given an increase of 6.0% effective February 1, 1990 ISSUE: STAFFING EVENING AND NIGHT SHIFTS IN THE DIAGNOSTIC DIVISION A major issue of dissatisfaction in the Diagnostic Division including CT Scan and MRI, is that of the technologists having to rotate shifts. Year to date, 8 vacancies have occurred, reportedly due largely to the dissatisfaction of rotating shifts. PROPOSED SOLUTION: To resolve the issue and prevent future turnover, it is recommended that the practice of rotating shifts be abolished, and that permanent shift assignments be made. As an incentive for Diagnostic Technologists, including CT Scan and MRI, to work evening and night shifts, it is recommended that an extra $1.00 per hour shift differential be added to existing shift differential rates. A $1.00 add-on was successful previously in Nursing when the need arose to encourage off-shift work. IMPLEMENTATION COSTS (1) RECRUITMENT INCENTIVES OR BONUSES FOR CURRENT RADIATION THERAPY TECHNOLOGIST STUDENTS (4) students x $2,000 incentive = $8,000. (2) 6.% INCREASE APPLIED TO: OLD RATES PROPOSED RATES Class Min Max Min Max Rad.Therapy Tech 22,370 30,557 23,712 32,390 Rad.Therapy Tech Sr. 24,458 33,407 25,925 35,411 Rad.Dosimetrist 24,458 33,407 25,925 35,411 Rad.Ther.Asst.Chief 26,745 36,517 28,350 38,708 Rad.Therapy Chief 29,230 39,935 30,984 42,331 Annualized Cost = $25,027.00 (Includes salary plus fringe benefits) (3) INCREASE TO SHIFT DIFFERENTIAL Shift differential increase of $1.00 per hour for the Diagnostic Division. SHIFT OLD RATES NEW RATES week day evening 1.25 2.25 week day night 1.50 2.50 weekend day .75 1.75 weekend evening 1.75 2.75 weekend night 2.25 3.25 Annualized cost = $38,000</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ATTACHMENT B HEALTH CARE PROFESSIONAL CLASSIFICATION/COMPENSATION STRUCTURE July 1, 1990 CLASS TITLE GRADE RANGE MINIMUM MAXIMUM MARKET DIFFERENTIAL Anesthetist 17 42994 65645 3.0% Anesthetist Asst Head 18 47000 71762 3.0% Anesthetist Head 18 47000 71762 3.0% Audiologist 10 23044 35184 3.0% Audiologist Supervisor 11 25191 38463 3.0% Bone Marrow Trans Tech 9 21079 32185 3.0% Bone Marrow Trans Tech Sr 11 25191 38463 3.0% Cardiac Cath Tech 8 19283 29441 3.0% Cardiac Cath Tech Sr 9 21079 32185 3.0% Cast Tech 8 19283 29441 3.0% Cert Nurse Practitioner 13 30105 45965 1.0% Cert Nurse Practitioner Sr 14 32910 50248 1.0% Clinical Perfusionist 0 0 85000 0.0% Clinical Perfusionist 0 0 80000 0.0% Clinical Social Work Supv 11 25191 38463 3.0% Clinical Social Worker 8 19283 29441 3.0% Clinical Social Worker Sr 10 23044 35184 3.0% CV Monitor Tech 8 19283 29441 3.0% CV Monitor Tech Sr 9 21079 32185 3.0% CV Monitor Tech Supv 11 25191 38463 3.0% Dental Hygienist 9 21079 32185 3.0% EEG Tech 6 16135 24636 3.0% EEG Tech Supv 8 19283 29441 3.0% EKG Supv 6 16135 24636 3.0% EKG Tech 4 13502 20615 3.0% Emer Med Tech Spec 7 17639 26932 3.0% Emer Med Tech Sr 8 19283 29441 3.0% Epidemiology Tech Adv 11 25191 38463 3.0% Epidemiology Tech Sr 9 21079 32185 3.0% Laboratory Specialist 8 19283 29441 3.0% Laboratory Specialist Adv 11 25191 38463 3.0% Laboratory Specialist Mgr 13 30105 45965 3.0% Laboratory Specialist Sr 9 21079 32185 3.0% Med Tech 9 21079 32185 3.0% Med Tech Lab Admn 15 35977 54930 3.0% Med Tech Mgr 13 30105 45965 3.0% Med Tech Sr 11 25191 38463 3.0% Med Tech Supv 12 27538 42047 3.0% Nutrition Program Dir 13 30105 45965 3.0% Nutritionist Specialist 10 23044 35184 3.0% Nutritionist Specialist Sr 12 27538 42047 3.0% Occupational Ther Asst 6 16135 24636 3.0% Occupational Therapist 11 25191 38463 5.0% Occupational Therapist Sr 12 27538 42047 5.0% Occupational Therapy Dir 15 35977 54930 3.0% Occupational Therapy Supv 13 30105 45965 5.0% Operating Room Tech 5 14760 22536 3.0% Organ Transplant Coordinator 9 21079 32185 3.0% Pain Mgmt Med Tech 8 19283 29441 3.0% Pharmacist 14 32910 50248 3.0% HEALTH CARE PROFESSIONAL CLASSIFICATION/COMPENSATION STRUCTURE July 1, 1990 CLASS TITLE GRADE RANGE MINIMUM MAXIMUM MARKET DIFFERENTIAL Pharmacist Supv 16 39329 60049 3.0% Pharmacy Assistant Director 17 42994 65645 3.0% Pharmacy Senior 15 35977 54930 3.0% Physical Therapist 11 25191 38463 6.0% Physical Therapist Asst 6 16135 24636 3.0% Physical Therapist Sr 12 27538 42047 6.0% Physical Therapy Asst Dir 14 32910 50248 3.0% Physical Therapy Director 15 35977 54930 3.0% Physical Therapy Supv 13 30105 45965 6.0% Physician's Assistant 12 27538 42047 3.0% Practical Nurse 5 14760 22536 3.0% Practical Nurse Sr 6 16135 24636 3.0% Psychologist 8 19283 29441 3.0% Psychologist Sr 10 23044 35184 3.0% Pulmonary Lab Tech 8 19283 29441 3.0% Pulmonary Lab Tech Sr 9 21079 32185 3.0% Pulmonary Lab Tech Supv 11 25191 38463 3.0% Rad Dosimetrist-RT 11 25191 38463 9.1% Rad Educ Asst Dir 12 27538 42047 3.0% Rad Engineering Spec 12 27538 42047 3.0% Rad Tech Asst Chief-CT 12 27538 42047 3.0% Rad Tech Asst Chief-Diag 12 27538 42047 3.0% Rad Tech Asst Chief-MRI 12 27538 42047 3.0% Rad Tech Asst Chief-NM 12 27538 42047 3.0% Rad Tech Asst Chief-RT 12 27538 42047 3.0% Rad Tech Asst Chief-SP 12 27538 42047 3.0% Rad Tech Asst Chief-US 12 27538 42047 3.0% Rad Tech Chief-CT 13 30105 45965 3.0% Rad Tech Chief-Diag 13 30105 45965 3.0% Rad Tech Chief-NM 13 30105 45965 3.0% Rad Tech Chief-RT 13 30105 45965 3.0% Rad Tech Chief-SP 13 30105 45965 3.0% Rad Tech Sr-CT 10 23044 35184 3.0% Rad Tech Sr-Diag 10 23044 35184 3.0% Rad Tech Sr-MRI 10 23044 35184 3.0% Rad Tech Sr-NM 11 25191 38463 3.0% Rad Tech Sr-RT 11 25191 38463 9.1% Rad Tech Sr-SP 11 25191 38463 3.0% Rad Tech Sr-US 11 25191 38463 3.0% Rad Tech Staff-CT 9 21079 32185 3.0% Rad Tech Staff-Diag 9 21079 32185 3.0% Rad Tech Staff-MRI 9 21079 32185 3.0% Rad Tech Staff-NM 10 23044 35184 3.0% Rad Tech Staff-RT 10 23044 35184 9.1% Rad Tech Staff-SP 10 23044 35184 3.0% Rad Tech Staff-US 10 23044 35184 3.0% Rad Tech Sup-Nuclear 12 27538 42047 3.0% Radiology Education Dir 13 30105 45965 3.0% Radiology Maintenance Supv 12 27538 42047 3.0% Radiology Manager 14 32910 50248 3.0% HEALTH CARE PROFESSIONAL CLASSIFICATION/COMPENSATION STRUCTURE July 1, 1990 CLASS TITLE GRADE RANGE MINIMUM MAXIMUM MARKET DIFFERENTIAL Radiology Physics Spec Advanc 13 30105 45965 3.0% Radiology Physics Spec Sr 10 23044 35184 3.0% Radiology School Director 12 27538 42047 3.0% Recreational Therapist 7 17639 26932 3.0% Recreational Therapist Sr 9 21079 32185 3.0% Reg Nurse Clin A 11 25191 38463 6.0% Reg Nurse Clin A (InPat) 11 25191 38463 8.5% Reg Nurse Clin A (OutPat) 11 25191 38463 1.0% Reg Nurse Clin B 12 27538 42047 6.0% Reg Nurse Clin B (InPat) 12 27538 42047 8.5% Reg Nurse Clin B (OutPat) 12 27538 42047 1.0% Reg Nurse Coord (InPat) 13 30105 45965 8.5% Reg Nurse Coord (OutPat) 13 30105 45965 1.0% Reg Nurse Mgr (InPat) 15 35977 54930 8.5% Reg Nurse Mgr (OutPat) 15 35977 54930 1.0% Registered Nurse 10 23044 35184 6.0% Registered Nurse Coord 13 30105 45965 6.0% Registered Nurse (InPat) 10 23044 35184 8.5% Registered Nurse (OutPat) 10 23044 35184 1.0% Renal Dialysis Tech 8 19283 29441 3.0% Renal Dialysis Tech Sr 9 21079 32185 3.0% Renal Dialysis Tech Supv 11 25191 38463 3.0% Respiratory Therapist 9 21079 32185 3.0% Respiratory Therapist Sr 10 23044 35184 3.0% Respiratory Therapy Asst Dir 12 27538 42047 3.0% Respiratory Therapy Supv 11 25191 38463 3.0% Respiratory Therapy Tech 6 16135 24636 3.0% Speech Pathologist 10 23044 35184 3.0% Speech Pathologist Supv 11 25191 33463 3.0% UVA Pool Reg Nurse 0 0.0% Venipuncture Manager 9 21079 32185 3.0% Venipuncture Tech 5 14760 22536 3.0% Venipuncture Tech Supv 8 19283 29441 3.0% Personnel Administration 3/14/90</field>
   </doc>
</add>