<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Motteux, Peter Anthony, 1660-1718</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Motteux, Peter Anthony, 1660-1718</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">motteux peter anthony 1660 1718</field>
      <field name="author_text">Motteux, Peter Anthony, 1660-1718</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">18th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1700's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V2.0108.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240355</field>
      <field name="date_text">1707</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:459851</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Thomyris, Queen of Scythia ; An Opera</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Thomyris, Queen of Scythia ; An Opera</field>
      <field name="title_facet">thomyris queen of scythia</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">thomyris queen of scythia</field>
      <field name="title_text">Thomyris, Queen of Scythia ; An Opera</field>
      <field name="year_display">1707</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1707</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1707</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459851&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459851&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Motteux, Peter Anthony, 1660-1718&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;motteux peter anthony 1660 1718&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Thomyris, Queen of Scythia ; An Opera&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;thomyris, queen of scythia&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1707&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1707&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Motteux, Peter Anthony&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1660&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1718&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Thomyris, Queen of Scythia&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;An Opera&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for Jacob Tonson [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1707&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872773-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv20108&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 18th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;18th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Thomyris, Queen of Scythia&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;An Opera&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 121 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Thomyris, Queen of Scythia.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Opera.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1707.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 1 Apr 1707.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THOMYRIS, QUEEN of SCYTHIA. AN OPERA,</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PREFACE. Tho' all the Airs of this Opera are by the famous Scarlatti and Buononcini, except a few by other great Masters, neither the Words, the Thoughts, nor the Design owe any thing to Italy, except the Advantage of the Musick; to which, with more Pleasure yet than Pain, I have endeavour'd to make 'em subservient: I hope those who would not have Sense sacrific'd to Sound, nor the Mind displeas'd while the Ears are entertain'd, will consider the Difficulties in working so many Airs of different Kinds into one Subject, and in putting Words wholly different from the Italian, to Songs so full of pathetick Notes and nice Graces, in a Language perhaps too manly for such Composures, if not manag'd with the utmost Art. As here the Choice of the Songs was not my Province, I may the better do Justice to the Gentleman who provided that Part of the Entertainment. Tho' Musick is only his Diversion, the best Masters allow him to be so good a Judge, that I have no Reason to doubt but his Collection will be generally approv'd; tho' 'tis impossible that, in such a Variety, every Thing should please every particular Fancy. As for the Recitative, Mr. Pepusch is known to be so great a Composer, that there is no doubt but he has also done his Part in that, and in adding such Ritornels, and other Musick, as were necessary to make the whole a Compleat Opera.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PROLOGUE. Long had a restless Monarch's boundless Sway Made half the Globe or tremble, or obey; Doom'd, like his Subjects, all Mankind his Slaves; By Choice destroying, as bless'd ANNA saves; And, turning all his Neighbours into Foes, Grudg'd Men Heav'n's darling Gifts of Freedom and Repose. T'oppose his Force was more than Man could dare; Heav'n had reserv'd that Glory for the Fair. With Virtues crown'd, adorn'd with ev'ry Grace, A Queen then rul'd a Warlike Northern Race; Who, bless'd and free, contented with their own, For Glory fought, and the World's Good alone. Down, by her Arms, Grand Cyrus soon was hurl'd, And, by a Woman, Heav'n reveng'd the World. So since to ANNA, in a happy Hour, Jove gave his Scales of Justice, and of Pow'r, Inspir'd by Her, what Wonders still afford Well-manag'd Treasures, and her Warrior's Sword! From willing Mines, with more than Human Care, Spirits are dealt thro' ev'ry Nerve of War. Her Genius quells the World's ambitious Foe: 'Tis Valour strikes, and Prudence guides the Blow. Yet, when this Day we show a Scythian Queen, Think not we dare attempt a Modern Scene. As Britain's Beauties all the World's excel, Great ANNA's Reign disdains a Parallel.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Persons Represented. Thomyris, Queen of Scythia, Signiora Margarita, who sings a Treble. Orontes, her Son and General, Mr. Hughs, or Signior Valentino, A Contra-tenor. Cleora, a Persian Princess, Niece to Cyrus, and design'd by him to marry Tigranes, Mrs. Tofts, A Treble. Tigranes, King of Armenia, Cyrus's Allie, Mr. Lawrence, A Tenor. Baldo, waits on Orontes, Mr. Leveridge, A Base. Media, waits on Cleora, Mrs. Lindsey, A Treble.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The SCENE is in that Part of Scythia, inhabited by the Massagetes.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Time of Action about Three Days.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. SCENE I. SCENE A Tent in a Camp, Trees on both Sides. Cleora is discover'd in a melancholic Posture, Media by her; Guards at a Distance. Cleo. From Scythian Bonds, to Persia's Court, Oh! how shall I return? Must I, alas! be Fortune's Sport, And only live to mourn? AIR. Freedom, thou greatest Blessing, Why have I lost thy Joys? Pining, no Rest possessing, Grief all my Hours employs. Thy Loss now to my Eyes A Flood of Tears will cost: Oh! why do we not prize Our Treasure 'till 'tis lost! Freedom, &amp;c. Med. Cease, Princess! Calm your Thoughts to Peace! Nor, grieving thus, your Woes increase. Pray Note, That throughout the Opera whatever is mark'd thus “with double Comma's in the Margent is left out, to shorten the Performance. “Women, fram'd for soft Alarms, “May of Eastern Kings complain, “Who luxurious, ev'n in Arms, “Clog Armies with a Female Train. “The Lumber of the War we prove; “And grace no Camp, but that of Love. Yet, tho' surpriz'd by Scythian Foes, The Niece of Cyrus feels unusual Woes, That Monarch, fortunate and great, Will soon reverse our Fate; And stubborn Scythia shall obey His Arbitrary Sway. AIR. Ever merry, Gay and airy, Be adjourning Care and Mourning! Sorrow never comes too late; We're impairing By Despairing. We're improving, Care removing. Then be happy, spite of Fate! Ever merry, &amp;c. Cleo. Thy gay Humour, to my Grief Brings no Cure, tho' some Relief. Yet, in Innocence secure, Bravely I'll the worst endure; Like thee, strive my Heart to chear; And lull asleep my Care. AIR. What should alarm me? No Foe can harm me. Let Virtue arm me; Fears will be vain. Yet, Freedom wanting, My Breast they're haunting; My Heart is panting, I live in Pain. What should, &amp;c. SCENE II. The Scene changes, and discovers Thomyris seated in State, Courtiers, Guards, and other Attendants. Thom. rising. With Heav'n's and your Assent, Queen of the Northern World I reign; Bless'd in your Ease, with Mind intent Your Freedom to maintain. My Soul no greater Empire craves: 'Tis nobler thus my Pow'r to hold, And lead by Love the Free and Bold, Than drive a World of Slaves. AIR. Rouse, ye Brave, for Fame and Glory, And oppose invading Spight! Drive the slavish Foe before ye! Turn to Terror all their Raging! You must conquer when engaging, 'Tis for Liberty you fight. Rouse, ye, &amp;c. Enter Orontes, and kneels to Thomyris. Oron. Hail! mighty Empress! O mia Regina! Note, The Part of Orontes being Sung by Signior Valentino, at the Desire of most of the Nobility who subscrib'd for the first Performances of this Opera, you have here the same in Italian, as it is translated out of English, and adjusted to the same Musick. Tho. Rise, my Son. Oron. Return'd with Spoils your Arms have won, Permit me at your Feet to bless Kind Heav'n, and you, for our Success. And may this first Advantage prove A happy Omen from above! [He rises. Vincitor qual io ritorno, Deh! Lasciate à vostri piedi Ch'io ringrazi, in si bel giorno, Voi, el'Ciel di tal vittoria, Primo grado a nuova gloria! Tho. So soon victorious! Oron. The numerous Foe, to pass the Flood, At distant Fords divided stood. A Part, spread o'er the Scythian Field, Was charg'd, and forc'd to yield: And here the Conquer'd wait, From you to know their Fate. Tento spesso l'Inimico Di passar l'opposto fiume; Ma il Valor dell' armi vostre L'assali, l'oppresse, é vinse: E il rubel conobbe in vano, Ch'il suo fato è in vostra mano. Tho. I'll see 'em now, and bless The Pow'rs who grant Success! The Trumpets, Kettle-Drums, Hoboys, &amp;c. begin a Warlike Movement. Enter several Scythian Soldiers, with Ensigns, Standards and other Trophies, and leading several Persian Prisoners, and Cleora last, attended by Media. Tho. Soldiers, stay, and, e're you go, Leave with me that Female Foe! [The Soldiers having left Cleora, march and Exeunt. Cleora unveils. Cleo. Feast, Thomyris, feast your Eyes With a weak, tho' Royal Prize! Oron. Guard me Heav'n! what Charms I view, Charms, that Conqu'rors may subdue! [Aside. Quai bellezze, o Dei, veggio, Ond'e vinto il vincitore! Cleo. Shou'd the Foe no Favour find, To the Virgin yet be kind! You'll perhaps but lend to Day What Cleora may repay. AIR. Gently, gently, treat my Sorrow, The Compassion that I borrow. I to Morrow may return. Soon to Mourning Joy is turning. I was happy in the Morning, In the Ev'ning here I mourn. Gently, &amp;c. Tho. Mov'd with Pity, not with Fear, Princess, we the Yielding spare. Let an ambitious restless Foe, Be proud of universal Woe. Whoe'er true Greatness understood Knows, to be great is to be good,— Honour'd, safe, and serv'd like me, In Scythia then remain. The Court your only Prison be, Your Word your only Chain. AIR. No more let Sorrow pain you! Our Love alone shall chain you; And ev'ry Joy restore. New Pleasures shall detain you: Liberty can give no more. No more, &amp;c. [Exit Thom. and Attendants. Oron. By my Royal Mother chear'd, What, bright Princess, can be fear'd? Firm in Protection, and in Love, To save and bless is all her Aim. Gracious, like the Pow'rs above, And, like 'em, Still the Same. Principessa piu vezzosa Delle Stelle, che temete? S'affidata ne'l amore Di mia Madre gia voi siete, Como Spirito immortale, Sempre dessa, é Sempre equale. AIR. “Tell me, why still lament you? “What Sorrow can torment you? “Your Eyes command their Fate. “Charmer, 'tis you alarm us: “Your very Tears disarm us: “You shine in ev'ry State. “Cleo. Thankful for your kind Relief, “Yet untun'd for Joy by Grief, “Let me, gen'rous Prince, compose “A Breast still mov'd, tho' eas'd of stormy Woes! “Oron. I must leave you—Yet I'll view,— “Oh! I must tear my self from you. “We lose with Ease, by Beauty's Charms, “What with Toil we got by Arms; “The Fair, subdu'd, a sweeter Conquest gains, “And the Proud Victor wears the Captive's Chains. AIR. Bright Wonder of Nature, Divine in each Feature, You conquer all Hearts: Admiring, we're dying: 'Tis only by flying We're safe from your Darts. Bright, &amp;c. [Exit Orontes. Delitie degl' occhi, Contento del l'alma, Deh! Lascia il rigor. Non vedi ch'io moro Suave ristoro D'amante mio Cor? Delitie, &amp;c. Da Capo. Cleo. He's gone—'tis well—not all my Pride Cou'd my Disorder hide. Ye Pow'rs, Oh! whether shall I move? From War's Alarms, I turn to those of Love. AIR. Med. Never let your Heart despair, While the Gods with Charms have crown'd you. Tho' designing Foes surround you, Spight and Envy cannot wound you. Innocence shall guard the Fair. Never let, &amp;c. Cleo. I chide my panting Heart in vain I feel a soft, a strange Emotion reign; And dread, yet love the Pleasure, and the Pain. AIR. I know not what alarms me, And warms me, Gently growing, Now all my Breast is glowing: My Heart is firing. I know not what to name The secret pleasing Flame; But sure, if Love's the same, Sweet is expiring. I know, &amp;c. [Exit Cleora. AIR, that may be sung instead of the foregoing. Love would invade me: My Eyes have betray'd me. Pride would arm me: But my Heart says, 'tis vain. When the Foe but invades me, to charm me, Danger ne'er can alarm me with Pain. “Med. Armenia's Prince, Tigranes, now in vain “May strive Cleora's Heart to gain. “What on him Cyrus would bestow, “Is doubly conquer'd by his Foe. Enter Baldo. Bald. Fair Damsel, if it is a Fault T'intrude upon a Virgin's Thought, Let, from the Prince, this precious Stone, From me, this precious Heart atone. Med. Fair-speaking Sir, 'tis well addrest. I, for the Ring, excuse the rest. Bald. To gain by yours, your Lady's Favour, Is a young Lover's first Endeavour. And, when the Pair of Turtles coo, Baldo the trusty Squire, and you, In Course know what we have to do. Med. I'll serve the Prince; and, as for you, I guess you have not much to do. AIR. Bald. My Delight, my Dear, my Princess! With Desire I lose my Senses. I before you feel with Fury My Blood hurry Thro' ev'ry Vein: Like a Dart I feel a Smart, And something tickle at my Heart. Dying thus who can complain? I had vow'd to play the Rover, Fool with Love, or give it over: But who can, tho' grave and wise, 'Scape those Dimples, Lips and Eyes! Then, to bless you, I'll address you, Press you, kiss you, and caress you; 'Till like me, you cry, 'Tis vain, Oh! my Dear, to frown and feign: Dying thus, who can complain! Med. Hold! how dare you be so urging? Would you ravish here a Virgin? Think you for your Ring I'll bear it? There it is—But I'll never wear it. [She makes an Offer to give him back the Ring, and at his Approach puts it up again. AIR. Away, you Rover! For shame give over! You play the Lover, So like an Ass. You press, and thunder, To bring us under; Then all you plunder, And leave the Place. Tho' you're for storming, And think you're charming, Your faint performing We read in your Face. Away, &amp;c. Bald. I'll be constant, never fear! Tho' that's strangely out of Fashion. If you doubt me, come, my Dear, Take an Earnest of my Passion! AIR. Med. Prithee leave me! presume not to court me! Bald. Pray relieve me, or do not transport me! Med. You so tire me, that I must fly. Bald. You so fire me, that I must try. Med. You're so teizing. Bald. You're so pleasing. Med. So presuming. Bald. So consuming. Med. So affrighting, that I must fly. Bald. So delighting, that I must try. Med. Tho' Bees may the Sweets be sharing, Which they're repairing, Empty Drones deserve To starve. Bald. Like the Bees those Sweets be sharing, Still repairing. Empty Drones Alone should starve. [She retires and goes off, Baldo following her all the while. SCENE III. A Prison. Tigranes is discover'd in Chains, with a Letter which he has been writing. He rises. AIR. Tigr. Joy and Empire are no more. Hope and Freedom are no more. Fate of Comfort does bereave me: Love alone will never leave me, And despairing I adore. Joy and Empire are no more, &amp;c. Die, Tigranes, then unknown, To thy self a Stranger grown! Shall Cleora know from me Still I live, and she not free?— But oh! Love once more bids me try To free the Fair, and die. Enter Keeper. Thou Keeper of this Seat of Woe, With this (a Soldier to relieve) To the Persian Princess go, [Gives him a Letter. And share the Gift I may receive! [Exit Keeper. Cruel Pow'rs, to you 'tis known How (her Freedom to retrieve) I fought, and lost my own. But, 'till I both regain, Can I her Love obtain! “Unhappy Princes sue in vain. AIR. In vain is complaining: The Way of obtaining Is bravely to dare! Fate ease me! Release me! My Passion so rages, Success it engages, Or noble Despair. In vain is complaining: The Way of obtaining Is bravely to dare. [Exit Tigranes. SCENE IV. A Palace. Enter Thomyris. AIR. Tho. Cares, on a Crown attending, How pressing is your Weight! Crouds to the Great are bending; But Cares command the Great: Cares, on a Crown attending, How pressing is your Weight! Enter Orontes. Oron. How pleas'd were I, cou'd I but share, Tho' not your Empire, yet your Care? Qual piacer, se dividesti Pene meco si moleste! Tho. I thank your Love—But oh! my Son, When you, the Hopes of Scythia, run Into the Dangers others shun, The Nation fears; I grieve unseen; And, in the Mother, lose the Queen. “Then wisely temper and controul “That noble Ardour of your Soul. “Oron. When you, Great Queen, in Souls inspire “Your more than Amazonian Fire, “Shall I not dare? and with Applause? “For such a Queen, and such a Cause? “Tho. Two Hundred Thousand Persians still “Our Plains with War and Horror fill. Our Troops are few; but those to join The King of Pontus does incline. The Pledge of Union is to be His beauteous Daughter, blest with thee. For this the People sue, this now the State demands; The Mother counsels; but the Queen commands. “Oron. Tho' the Subject must comply, “Great Queen, oh! grant a short Reprieve; “Yet averse to such a Tye, “To the Son some Moments give, “To strive not to deny. “Tho. Think—But know, superior Fate “Dooms the Great “To be Victims to the State. Exit Thom. “Oron. Victims indeed— You Pow'rs above! Oh! must I sacrifice my Love! Enter Cleora. Oron. But see! she comes—Oh! how she charms! How struggling Reason she disarms! Forgive, forgive, you Rules of State! I yield to Her, and Fate. Her very Silence is persuading. There is no Choice, when she's invading. Ahi! convien tradir l'amore. Ma s'en viene. O come è bella! Contro amor non val ragione. Deh! voi massime di stato, Perdonate! io cedo al fato. Cleo. Oh! my Blushes will reve al The Flame I wou'd conceal. Oron. Lovely Princess, oh! forgive me! Turn not from me, do not leave me, With a pitying Look reprieve me! Press'd from you my Heart to tear, I grow daring by Despair. Deh! Mia bella, ah! perdonate! Non fugite, e consolate Con un guardo l'amor mio! Il veder di speme un raggio Mi da forza, e piu coraggio. “With one Look my Flame approve, “And I swear Eternal Love. “Cleo. Ah! Prince. “Oron. Speak, my Goddess! speak my Fate: “I dread nothing, but your Hate. “Cleo. Cease a Passion to pursue, “That too soon may both undo. “By warring Pow'rs to other Loves design'd, “Will they bear to see us join'd? “Ah! no, the lost Cleora leave, “Who only dares to grieve. Cleo. Ah Prince, I must not hear—you must not stay. I shall gaze my Heart away. [Aside. AIR. Oron. A lover near despairing, Bright Charmer must be daring. His Flame he cannot smother, Nor can he love another: He must alone implore you, Alone adore you. A Lover, &amp;c. Amante disperato, Al fato oppone il core. Osi cimenti, e pera Quel alma, che non spera I frutti dell' amore! Amante, &amp;c. Da Capo. “Oron. Do but suffer me to Love, “And leave the rest to Fate: “I'm blest enough, if you approve, “But wretched if you hate. “Cleo. Partial Trial: forc'd Denial! [Aside. “Pride dissembles; Reason trembles. Be firm, my Mind! Maintain a Sov'reigns Part! Let the Head controul the Heart! AIR. Let us fly, let us fly our Undoing! Love allures us; but Reason denies. Those are caught, who the Chace are pursuing: But she's safe, and may conquer, who flies. Let us fly, let us fly our Undoing: Love allures us, but Reason denies. [Exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. SCENE I. SCENE A Palace. Enter Thomyris, Orontes, and a Captain of the Guards. Tho. By Time most Vict'ries lose their Fame, But yours the common Fate disclaim. The conscious Foes, with Grief, confess How great their Loss, and your Success. They miss their brave Allie, Tigranes. Oron. Among the Slain For him they've sought in vain. Fin or tra j morti l'han cercato in vano. Tho. Perhaps a Pris'ner, here unknown, He may himself disown. Oron. Let Search be made. [To the Captain, who bows and goes out. Ite a cercarlo. Tho. Since thus, my Son, ev'n Sov'raigns are Subject to the Chance of War, Your Nuptials must, without Delays, Secure our Empire, and our Race. To such an Hymen must I press you? Must I sue so long, to bless you? “Oron. Oh! Mis-call not disobeying, “Gracious Queen, a short delaying! “War commands an instant Duty. “Let your Soldier strive to prove “Worthy Honour, worthy Love, “And, by Glory, rise to Beauty. “Tho. Oh! Grieve me not with more Delays! “By all the Heroes of our Race, “By the dear, the moving Name “Of thy great Father, by his Fame, “By a Nation's Love, and Fears, “By thy widow'd Mother's Tears; “Mother's Tears, that yet disgrace “A Royal Face! “Oh! no more, no more delay me! “Kill at once, or now obey me. AIR. Ne'er torment me; But content me. Love repay me! Ne'er delay me! Love and Duty no Wav'ring allow, Why so dearly do I love you? Could I fear I ne'er should move you, Ne'er move you 'till now? Ne'er, &amp;c. Oron. Ah! too too much my Soul you move. Ye cruel Pow'rs!—Oh Tyrant Love! [Aside. Oh Queen! Oh Mother! I for Pity sue: I plead against my stubborn Heart for you; I'm rack'd, I'm torn in the Debate: I struggle with Aversion strong as Fate. I dread Complying, I dread Denying, More than Dying. Ahi, potenze all' Alma mia Troppo fiere! Ahi! crudo Amore! Deh! Pietà, Regina, e Madre! Quell' Oggetto, ch'io combatto Sol per voi, dentro il mio seno, E'piu forte del mio fato. Temo Ubbidire, E negar, piu che morire. AIR. I grieve to see your Sorrow; Yet would not grieve to die. But sure I'll die to Morrow, If I to Day comply. I grieve to see your Sorrow; Yet would not grieve to die. [Orontes leads out Thomyris. Oh! Dio! Qual pena sento! Non posso no ubbedir. Ah! che s' io ti contento, E certo il mio morir. Oh! Dio! &amp;c. Da capo. [Exeunt. “The SCENE changes to a Garden. “Cleora is discover'd by a Fountain. “AIR. “Lonely Pleasures ne'er relieve me, “Lonely Pleasures only grieve me. “Streams are flowing, “Flow'rs are growing, “Birds are courting, “Zephirs blowing; “All is sporting. “But how can I share “Those quiet Joys, “While Love, with Care, “In Absence here, “My Soul employs? “Bring my Charmer near me! “Oh! then you'll chear me. Enter Media, with a Letter, which she delivers to Cleora. “Med. A Fellow Captive, in Distress, “This by his Keeper sends you. “Not suffer'd nearer you to press, “At Distance he attends you. “Cleo. What do I read!—Ye Pow'rs, 'tis too severe! “Armenia's King, unknown, in Fetters here! “The Man I cannot love, nor hate, “Striving to save me, shares my Fate. “Unhappy Prince! too late, alas! you move: “Fortune has intercepted Love. “The Heart is gone, for which you sue. “Yet some Ease I'll strive to bring; “And show how I revere in you “The Choice of Cyprus, and the King. “Sure I some Pity may discover “To the Friend, tho' not the Lover. [Exit Cleora. Enter Baldo. He stops Media who is following Cleora. Bald. My Charmer! Med. My Tormenter. Bald. Stay. Med. I dare not. Bald. You may venture. Tell me, Queen of my Desire, When will Love reward the Fire Of the Prince, and of the Squire? Med. For the Prince, all may go well: But for you—I cannot tell. Bald. Don't you love me? Med. No, not I. Bald. How? not love me! That's uncommon! What's the Reason? Med. I'm a Woman. Bald. Give a better. Med. Why, thou Creature, Must a Woman give you many, And you Lover's ne'er have any? Bald. Prithee tell me! Med. In good Nature, now I will— Know, I value Reputation; And by thy Looks, and by my Skill I foresee What a Monster thou'rt to be. Thy Wife, spight of Inclination, Must be kind—to all the Nation. AIR. No more for Wedlock importune: In Pity I'll tell you your Fortune. Know, how will prove your Spouse. She'll rant, She'll stray, She'll paint, She'll play, She'll tope, Elope, She'll fall to all, and arm your Brows. She can't prevent it: Then rest contented. She can't prevent it, if she's your Spouse. She can't prevent it, she'll arm your Brows. “If then you rave, and curse, “She'll plague you worse “With a Clack never failing; “Railing, wailing, ever ailing, “Pouting, glouting, “Oh! how she'll swinge your Purse! “Wife will stumble, “Husband grumble, “Still 'twill be worse, and worse. She can't prevent it, she'll arm your Brows. Bald. I will prevent it, if you're my Spouse Tho' now Husbands never mind it, Nothing, when you're mine, will pain me. I'll so ply you, Child, you'll find it Work enough to entertain me. AIR. Do you think so warm a Lover For a Jest will e'er give over? No, no; I your Secret can discover. You to try me Seem to fly me. For, what Beauty can deny me? Do but view me, I've such Charms, if e're you knew me, Tho' I shunn'd you, you'd pursue me. Do you think so warm a Lover For a Jest will e'er give over? Med. Prithee, Fellow, why so pressing, Yet so negligent of Dressing? So strangely needing Air, and Breeding, You disgrace one with Caressing. AIR. What Lover ever Can hope for Favour, But must endeavour To charm the Fair? He makes Advances By Sighs, and Glances; He sings, and dances, And mends his Air. Then now to ease me, Pray cease to teize me, First learn to please me, And then—despair. What Lover ever can hope for Favour, But must endeavour to charm the Fair? &amp;c. Bald. A better way I'll please my Dear. Sighs and Glances, Foppish Fancies, Soft and tender Might offend her: Honest Roughness gains the Fair. AIR. Who can see, tho' of late 'tis so common, A Fop, aping the Airs of a Woman; Four long Hours waste in dressing, Not one in Possessing? While his Time in dull Ogling he passes, And bows to new Faces, [He bows in an affected manner. And makes Grimaces, How wretched his Case is! While he dances— [Baldo dances. [The Musick striking up in the middle of the Song. Another embraces Who can see, &amp;c. Come, come let us be Possessing. Med. No, no, no Dressing, no Possessing. [Media runs off, and Baldo follows her. SCENE II. A Prison “Tigr. Without Freedom, Life's a Pain. “Without Love, we live in vain. “Love and Freedom disagree: “How can Hope then comfort me, “Without Love's Sweets, and Liberty? “Hope's but a Flatterer, that deludes, to please: “Life's but a Pain, and Death our only Ease. A Light is discover'd. What Splendor dares invade a Cave Familiar with the Night! Those Beams, that Heav'n as Blessings gave, Now wound my Eyes, grown Strangers to the Light. Enter Cleora with Attendants, who keep at a Distance. Tigr. Ye Pow'rs! What Goddess, lower than the Grave Thus condescends to charm, and save, So ravishingly bright! Cleo. Tigranes! Oh! [Weeps discovering him. Tigr. 'Tis Cleora! oh! 'tis she. Cleo. Oh! killing Sight! Tigr. Oh Joy! oh Pain! Confusion, yet Delight! Cleo. Heav'ns! without Pity can you see Majesty in Misery! Tigr. Cruel Fortune! Fate unkind! I in Chains, and she confin'd! Cleo. Brave Tigranes, oh! forbear! For my sake those Chains you wear: Will you teach me to despair? I, tho' a Captive, like the Free, May taste the Sweets of Liberty. But I share, 'till I relieve you, The Pains that grieve you. Tigr. Oh! at once you fill with Joy, “Proud of Ruin, Free in Chains, “My Soul revels, Pleasure reigns. “When I ventur'd all to free you, “Fortune to the Foe betray'd me. “But now, when so kind I see you, “Pitying Heav'n has o'er-pay'd me. AIR. Strike me, Fate! now no Danger alarms me, Tho' tis dreadful to fall when so high. Spare her only who pities, and charms me; My fond Soul hence with Pleasure shall fly. Strike me, Fate! now no Danger alarms me, Tho' 'tis dreadful to fall when so high. Cleo. apart. Turn ingrate, rebellious Heart, Whom a Foe alone can move! Oh! I cannot tear the Dart. Gratitude my Tears impart; But Pity will not turn to Love. “Tigr. Again you Weep! Oh! now you pain me, “Am I worth the Tears I cost? “Ah! no, you weep your Freedom lost. “Why like a Slave, ye Pow'rs, d'ye chain me, “I'm a King, no more detain me. “Why sleeps your Thunder? “Wake, and strike my Bonds asunder. AIR. Cleo. Oh! in Pity cease to grieve me! Do but live, Fate will relieve me. Joy and Pleasure may return. Tigr. Oh! in Pity cease to grieve me! Do but smile, Fate will relieve me. Joy and Pleasure will return. Cleo., Tigr. “I alone may be lamenting. Cleo. “Your Despair is too tormenting. Tigr. “Oh! your Sorrow's too tormenting. “Both. Grief redoubles, when you mourn. “Oh in Pity, &amp;c. Enter Orontes and Attendants. Oron. apart. Death to my Hopes! what do I hear and see! My Soul's untun'd with envy'd Harmony. Just were my Doubts. Oh! how my Soul is mov'd; Sure 'tis Tigranes, or a Rival lov'd. Deh che vedo, ed ahi! che Sento? Giusti dubbi del mio Core! Non m'inganno, egli è Tigrane, O un rivale del mio amore. Cleo. The Prince of Scythia! oh! my Shame! [Aside. Tigr. Fatal Turn! Oron. Happy he, who here to mourn May Cleora's Presence claim! Lieto lui, chi pianger puote Di Cleora innanzi agli occhi! Cleo. Rather wretched those who grieve, When we have only Tears to give. Doubly wretched in Despair, When you envy 'em a Tear. Oron. Oh! you my Fears can ne'er remove. The Springs of Pity flow like Love. No; d'amor dalla sorgente Di Pieta deriva il pianto. Tigr. Tho' Love and Pity now were joining, Why should you be repining? Oron. What vanquish'd Foe dares talk so high? Qual Vinto mai osò parlar si franco? Tigr. A Soul unconquer'd dares all Foes defie. Oron. Ah! 'tis Tigranes sure—'tis he. Ben m'auveggo, egli è Tigrane. Tigr. 'Tis I; still Royal, spight of Fate— In Rage I lose my Shame. Undaunted, and in Ruin great, The Lion is the same. Oron. Then know—But, Guards, from Chains First set him free— Know, I'll not yield my beauteous Prize to thee. Sappi dunque—Ma sciogliete, Guardie, pria le sue catene— La mia bella a te non cedo. Tigr. Not yield her! Fate, oh once be kind: Set me but free, the Fair shall be resign'd. Do you, my Goddess, but conspire With Cyrus, and my Fire, From Chains I dare to Heav'n aspire. Oron. Ah! Princess! Ah! Principessa! Cleo. I dare not think of Love or Hate: 'Tis Cyrus over-rules my Fate. AIR. Oron. Say, must I then despair? Will you, my cruel Fair, No more regard me? Oh! grant me Love again! Or let me ne'er complain: With Death reward me. Dimmi, pietà ed amor, Bella, non ha il tuo Cor Per chi t'adora? Risolviti d'amar: O se deggio penar, Lascia chio moro. Cleo. OH! Leave me to despair! From Hope, and all that's dear, My Fate debarr'd me. Oron. Say, must I then despair? &amp;c. Dimmi, pietà ed amor, &amp;c. Cleo. Oh! Leave me to despair, &amp;c. [Cleora retires, Orontes following her, both singing all the while. Exeunt. Tigr. She's gone! she's gone! the conqu'ring Foe pursues her. She's yielding—Oh! I lose her. AIR. Ye Horrors of this hollow Grave, Redouble! Fill me, 'till I rave! Rise, ye Furies! Awake, and rage! With my Sense you a War must wage. Despair! Despair! Why must I languish here? Let me die; not complain! Oh! Reason, leave me. Life with thee is but a Pain, And will but grieve me. SCENE IV. A Palace. Enter Cleora, follow'd by Orontes. Oron. Stay, cruel Beauty! Soon, call'd by Duty, To kinder War I'll go. Since you leave me, And no Pity show, Death will not grieve me. Resta, o cruda! il mio dovere Alla guerra già me chiama. Se mia Vita a Voi non preme, Sol la morte è la mia Speme. Cleo. First by War, and you undone, Greater Dangers yet I shun. Cruel Prince, while you pursue me, Love, and you, may more undo me. AIR. Oh! I must fly! Cease to try To charm me! In vain my Heart you move. No Hope appears; Cruel Fears Alarm me. I dare not love: I dare not love. What could you claim, Should your Flame E'er warm me? Duty and Fate allow no Return. Hopeless, alas! would you see me burn? Oh! I must fly, &amp;c. Enter Thomyris. Oron. The Queen! La Regina! Exit Cleora. Thom. aside. My Son, and that lovely Foe! Sure their Looks betray'd Surprize! In my Breast some Doubts arise, Which yet I dread the gazing Croud should know. A Sov'raign's Thought must still be lying Deep, to 'scape the Vulgar's prying. Oron. Freed from Chains, as soon as known, Great Queen, Tigranes is remaining. “Tho' distress'd, “Not depress'd, ‘In sullen State by Choice alone, “Favour from a Foe disdaining. E'Tigrane in vostro mano. Non si tosto lo connobbi Che lo resi in Libertade. Tho. Your Valour vanquish'd him before; By gen'rous Care subdue him more, His Wants preventing. “To you the Royal Foe I leave, “Sure Favours to receive, “Tho' not consenting. AIR. A while tho' Conquest charms me, Compassion soon disarms me, And melts my tender Heart. Let Pity do her Part. The greatest Joy We have Is when we kindly save Those whom we may destroy. A while, &amp;c. [Exeunt. Enter Baldo, fantastically dress'd. Bald. What Plague is like Dressing! To work I'm well set. In all her odd Whims, I must nick a Cocquet. This Maggot of Coupling Now makes me a Fopling; All larded with Gold, stuff'd with Ribbons and Lace, Still fiddling, to mend a damn'd finical Dress. Oh! what a Fatigue, to set off a good Face. AIR. Slaves to the Fashion, What Slav'ry can be worse? Slaves to Love's Passion, You need no other Curse. The Modes like Women vary; Love plagues us 'till we marry; Then we're eas'd of both in course. Slaves to the Fashion, What Slav'ry can be worse. Enter Media. Bald. Oh! yonder comes Media! my Charms I must try. Med. Bless me! what Monster do I spy! Bald. My Goddess, 'tis I. Look, languish, and die! Look and die! Med. Away, Fool, away! Young Foplings divert us, when handsom and gay: But an old Fop is dull every way. Bald. Try me well e're this you say. Med. No worse Plague could e're befall thee. Bald. What would I not do, to maul thee! AIR. Med. Shou'd e'er the Fair disdain you, Leave her, and learn to range! In vain complain you; The more she'll hate and chain you. Hate her again, and change! Shou'd e'er the Fair disdain you, Leave her, and learn to range! Bald. Pray what nice Lover Proves a Rover, 'Till the Whim of Love is over? I would leave you, you so fret me; But Point of Honour will not let me. Then any other Task command me, And if I don't perform, disband me. Med. You'll not do it. Bald. I will. Med. I fear it. Bald. On this trusty Sword I swear it. [Draws his Sword Med. Kill your self then!—No denying. Bald. I deny!—See,—I'm complying. Hold—I might spoil this Face by dying. “Med. Go! A Coward ne'er can charm me, “Valour only can disarm me. Bald. Well, since you will my Valour try, I'll to the Bed of Honour fly, And return in yours to die. AIR. What wou'd I not do to gain you? I'll turn Hero, to obtain you. Still by cunning Ways you fire me Still by Arts you raise, while another wou'd tire me. Love a hungry still is fawning. But when full fed falls a yawning. Let my Dear still tantalize me! She invites, while she denies me. Love, like War, has Toils and Tortures. But all's forgot, When we're got Into good Quarters. [She runs from him, he follows her. Enter Tigranes in a Princely Dress, Orontes with him. Tigr. To your Favour much I owe: I find Friendship in a Foe. But how soon my Blessings end! I find a Rival in the Friend. Tho' I by you Cleora see, The greatest Pleasure once to me, When this I by a Rival gain, The greatest Pleasure turns to Pain. Oron. Repine not at the Joys I share, Tho' hopeless of possessing! To see the Fair, Is still a Blessing. Pago son di tal piacere, Sol veder la è mia fortuna, Se non spero de godere. AIR. The Chains of Love I wear, I burn, and I despair. Yet bless my Charmer. Too great wou'd be my Joy, The Pleasure wou'd destroy, Cou'd my Flame warm her. The Chains, &amp;c. La Stella a te crudel, E pur meco infedel, Sott' altro aspetto; E il raggio suo fatal Ma del suo crudo stral Ha per oggetto. La Stella, &amp;c. Da Capo Tigr. Oh! lead me back to Dungeons and to Chains, Or let me loose, to end my Pains. My Heart can no Rival bear; Jealous, ev'n of your Despair. Enter Cleora. Oron. Since uneasie still you prove, Impatient of my hopeless Love; I all Advantages disclaim, Unworthy of my Love, and Fame— 'Tis at an Army's Head alone A Prize so noble shou'd be won— Your Freedom to Cleora owe, Now, as she pleases, stay, or go! Exit Orontes. S'il mio amor ti reca pena, Non vuò alcun diritto indegno Del mio amor, e di mia gloria. Alla testa d'ell' Armata Vuò acquistar premio si bello: S'ora libero tu sei, A Cleora tu lo dei: S'a lei piace, resta, o vanne! AIR. Cleo. Ye Pow'rs! Oh! let me know, What Reason ought to sway? Shall I say, stay, or go? Shall I say, go, or stay? There's something in my Heart, That tells me we shou'd part: But yet, when this I move, 'Tis thought a Wrong to Love. He'll say I disdain: He'll rage, and complain. I dare not say, stay, nor go; go, nor stay. Ye Powr's, oh! let me know, What Reason ought to sway! Tigr. Oh! no more your Thoughts disguise. I read my Sentence in your Eyes. Yet so well I Love, I'll ease you, Nay die to please you. AIR. Tho' in vain I strive to gain you, I may die, no more to pain you. Farewel then, thou Beauty's Treasure! Ripe for falling, Honour calling, Hopes of Death are all my Pleasure. Tho' in vain I strive to gain you, I may die, no more to pain you. [Exit Tigranes. Re-enter Orontes. Oron. Lovely Mourner, still why grieve you? I, alas! too soon must leave you. Happy yet, if with a Tear You, my Love— Ah! che piangi, o Bella? Io vado Ma felice, s'al mio amore S'accompagna il tuo dolore.— Cleo. The Queen is near— “Suffer me to hide, by Flight, “My Disorder from her Sight. [Exit Cleora. Enter Thomyris. Tho. aside. What did I hear? Fatal Beauty, Youth's Decoy, Blasts a Parent's Hope, and Joy. But I'll seem not yet to know— To him. Come, my Son, no more bestow Your Hours on a conquer'd Foe. “Danger's ready to pursue you, “Let not Persian Pow'r subdue you! “Foes unvanquish'd are appearing; “Wary Chiefs, with Numbers daring. “Haste, again the Slaves defeat! “Be still your self, still truly great! “Haste, free the World, and do the Work of Fate. “Cyrus the Grand, by you declining, “His Glory to your Arms resigning, “Still shall raise your high Renown. “Immortal Laurels shall the Hero crown, “Who strikes the Blow I guide, “And throws Ambition down. AIR. Again be victorious! Be glorious! Bright Honour is calling; Ambition is falling. Eternally be glorious! Again, &amp;c. [Exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. SCENE I. SCENE A Garden. Enter Cleora. Cleo. Love in Absence finds no Ease; Crouds, diverting, but displease: This dark, this melancholick Grove Suits my Sadness, and my Love. Ye feather'd Songsters, round me flying, Courting, Sporting, Care defying; Oh! did you but feel my Anguish, Soon you'd change your Notes, and languish. AIR. Pretty Warblers, cease to hover. Pretty Warblers, help a Lover. From your Joys a Moment borrow: Tune your Musick to my Sorrow. Join, and answer, when I mourn. Grief alone is too tormenting; There's a Pleasure in lamenting, My Complaint when you return. Pretty Warblers, &amp;c. Enter Thomyris. “Tho. aside. While chosen Bands, by young Orontes led, “Press the retreating Foe, ‘Who, from our growing Army, dread “A fatal Blow; “I come as great a Danger to remove; “And save him from the Harms of Love.— “She's here; I'll strive to know “If she loves him.— “To Cleora.] Will you still your Fate bemoan? “Still indulge your Grief alone? Tho. Lov'd and cherish'd every where, What should pain you, grieving Fair? Sure you mourn an absent Lover. Cleo. aside. Oh! my Looks my Flame discover. Tho. Ev'n your Blushes I will spare: I'll be kind beyond desiring. Since now before my Son I hear Persia's Army is retiring, For your Return you may prepare. Tho' Justice might restrain you, Clemency will not detain you. Cleo. aside. Cruel Kindness! Tho. apart. Her Looks her Love betray. To her.] Are you not pleas'd? Cleo. Oh! with Favours now you pain me. How shall I my Debt repay! So much you bless, It griev'd me less To be confin'd, than now to go away. “Ev'n your Foes, admiring, share “The Blessings of your gentle Sway: “Thrice happy those, who ever here “Your lov'd Commands obey! “AIR. “Tho' boasted Freedom, priz'd above Measure, “Once seem'd a Treasure; “Now in Confinement Time I'm employing, “More Ease enjoying. “So Birds imprison'd sing, and ne'er complain. “Pleas'd with their Leisure, “Time turns to Pleasure, “What was a Pain. “Tho' boasted, &amp;c. “Tho. How slavish must those Spirits be, “Who lose the very Sense of Liberty! “Blest Freedom, lost are those who lose thee, “Doubly lost those who refuse thee. AIR. In vain, in vain is Delay— Near falling, Duty calling, 'Tis Time to go away. No more your self betray! When Reason Frees from Prison, No free-born Soul would stay. In vain is Delay. Cleo. Thus obliging, you undo. What is Freedom, losing you? AIR. Tho. When Duty's requiring, How sweet is obeying, How fatal delaying? Cleo. Your Virtues admiring, How sweet is delaying, Our Moments repaying? Tho. In vain do you press me! Oh why do you press me? Cleo. Oh why do you press me? Detain me to bless me. How sweet, &amp;c. [Exeunt Thom. and Cleo. Enter Media, follow'd by Baldo in a warlike Habit. AIR. Bald. Halt! when Love and Honour calls you. Tho' some other might maul you, No harm now can befal you, Your Anger takes me down. Take my Heart, my Love to crown. Let me garrison the Town; Then, then, let me hang or drown. Med. Follow your Prince! Go join his Army! Dare to be kill'd, and then, then, then, you'll charm me. Bald. I stay'd behind, from him to bear A Message to his Princely Fair. Med. You have your Answer: What more d'ye want, Sir? Bald. Some kind Token of your Favour; And then your Soldier's made for ever. AIR. Med. Can you leave ranging?—No Ne'er think of changing?—No. And constant grow.—No. Reform and marry—No. In Love ne'er vary.—No. You'd soon grow weary, And from me go. You'd wish to leave me. I'd wish to leave you. You would deceive me. I would deceive you. Your Fate you know. Can you leave ranging, and constant grow? &amp;c. Bald. in Imitation of Media, I'd ne'er grow weary.—No. Nor from you go.—No. Med. Will nothing fright you out of Love? Then know, I'll ne'er your Flame approve. What e'er of Constant Love is said; Of the dull Whim we're all afraid. Our Flame we must smother, When tir'd of each other. AIR. Wou'd you charm us? Wou'd you warm us? Learn to rove, and hide your Passion. Ev'ry Fair by Turns be courting, Never serious, ever sporting; Whining Love is out of Fashion. Wou'd you, &amp;c. [Exit. Bald. Who knows where to have her! In vain I endeavour. Oh! I cou'd rail; I cou'd rave; I cou'd curse; I cou'd wed her for Spight—I cou'd—never do worse. No; wisely I'll go, And turn my Fury on the Foe. Tho' wild, like Fortune, now I find her, My brave Exploits may make her kinder. AIR. Farewel Love, and every Pleasure! Honour calls, and we must part. War from you now claims my Leisure. I'll go raise my Fame, and Treasure: Storm, and Plunder; Fight, and Thunder: Then at last I'll bring you under. Gold and Conquest gain the Heart. Farewel Love, and ev'ry Pleasure! Honour calls, and we must part. [Exeunt. SCENE II. A Royal Tent. Orontes sleeping, and chain'd. Guards about him. After a short piece of Instrumental Musick, proper for a Sleep. Enter Tigranes. Tigr. “He sleeps! still Happy, spight of Fate. “Of Quiet he partakes; “Kind Dreams upon his Slumbers wait. “I envy him this easie State. “The Jealous ever wakes.— Wake, Orontes! wake, arise! [Orontes awakes; and, looking about, starts up in a great Surprise. Oro. Ha! sure I dream—What Objects strike my Eyes! To Arms—My Sword—Ha! Chain'd— Tigranes here!— My Fellow Soldiers!— Ah! ch'io sogno—che remiro— Strano oggetto! all'armi, all'armi. La mia Spada—Ahi! son legato— Qui Tigrane!—Miei Soldati!— Tigr. Surpriz'd, like you, Death, or your Chains they share. Retreating Cyrus, press'd by you, His Camp did to the Foe resign, With Dainties stor'd, and treach'rous Wine, Your Scythians to subdue. Lethargic Drugs, mix'd with the gen'rous Juice, Soon did to Sleep your wearied Troops reduce: “With Ease a Grave they found in every Bed; “Buried in Wine and Sleep, already like the Dead. Oro. Oh! Fraud alone of Vict'ry cou'd deprive 'em. Kill me! Why shou'd I survive 'em? Coll'arte sol tu vincergli potevi Se l'opra uvoi compir, me pure uccidi! Tigr. Brave Orontes, you must live. Oro. No; I hate the Life you give. No; se tu me la doni, odio la vita. Tigr. Live. Oro. No; let me die. No lascia, chio mora. Tigr. Live, from Revenge Cleora to retrieve. Oro. Oh! her Name forces a Reprieve. Ah! questo nome sol mi chiama in vita. Tigr. Promise to resign the Fair, And now I'll set you free. Oro. Death, or Slav'ry, let me bear; But claim her not of me! Ch'io la ceda? mai non fia. Morte, e catene soffriro ben pria. “Fate enough to you is kind; “You're free, approv'd, and I confin'd. “Tigr. Who knows what Fate designs! “I dread too sudden Joys. “When the glitt'ring Lightning shines, “Soon the Thunderbolt destroys. AIR. Unhappy Lovers are ne'er contented: Lamenting, tormented, I pine, I burn. My fair disdains me; Honour restrains me; Jealousie pains me; In vain I mourn. Unhappy, &amp;c. “Oro. The same my Passions, worse my Woes: “My Fair, and Fate, my Joys oppose. “Let Valor then the double Cause decide; “Honour's first, then Love's be try'd. “By Orosmades by the Sun I swear, “To her own Choice, I'll leave the Fair. “First release me, as I freed you, “Then let me fall, if she's decreed you. Tigr. “Be wise, comply! “Resolve, no more to love her, or to die. Oron. Without her, Life no Joys can give. No more to love her! 'tis no more to live. Senza lei, piacer non sento. Se non l'amo, piu non vivo. Oron. No more to love her! Ah, no! I'll ne'er give over. E're I comply, I'll die. I prize no Joy above her. Love chains my fond Heart. In vain from her you tear me: We ne'er can part. She's here, she's ever near me. No more, &amp;c. Ch'io piu non l'ami! Ah! no: morro ben pria. Vorrebbe i cor, No nol potra mai. Ella e crudel; Ma che piu bella assai: Ell' e infedel; Lo so; ma cio non fia. [Da Capo. Tigr. Honour has conquer'd: Gen'rous Foe, Take Liberty, the Debt I owe. [The Guards set Orontes free. Oro. I thank Tigranes: Tho' now Life's a Pain. Like Friends we'll part, like Foes to meet again. Benche il viver sia tormento, O Tigrane, io ti ringrazia. Amici or Siam, ci rividrem nemici. Tigr. I no Hopes can discover. Oron. I despair, yet I love her. Both. Like War's are Love's Alarms: Tho' Fatal are the Charms, Who can give over? In van sospiro, e bramo. Non posso piu sperar; E pur io amo. Exeunt severally. SCENE III. A Palace. Enter Media, Baldo. Med. The grieving Princess to revive, Is there no Hope, he's yet alive? Bald. Oh! Let the losing World complain. Scythias's Brave Prince, our other Hope is slain. Tho' great Numbers 'scap'd by Flight, He, with the rest, fell in the Night. While with our Queen the Nation mourns, Grief to revengeful Fury turns. Our Troops, of whom the Van alone Forc'd Persia's Camp, then were by Fraud o'erthrown, Now more wary grown, Retreat, but to give the Foe A nobler Overthrow. Med. The Princess comes—Away—you might enrage The grief I wou'd asswage. [Exit. Bald. Enter Cleora. AIR. Cleo. VVhy must Sorrow for ever attend me, Never end me! How long must I crave For Death, and the Grave! Hopes are lost—What I mourn Can ne'er return. Life's all Anguish: We but Languish, And our Loss deplore, When Love is no more. Med. Why shou'd you crave For Death and the Grave? Old Maids in Despair All Hopes may give over. But the Young, and the Fair, Chuse Life, and a Lover. AIR. VVhen One's gone, n'er keep a Pother. Get another! get another! Youth and Beauty should be gay. Cheer up, and again be shining, Never whining, Nor repining: Among Lovers that's the Way. Cleora goes out, and Media follows her, singing to her. [Exeunt. Enter Thomyris. Tho. Weep no more! or weep unseen, Hopeless Mother; mournful Queen! Tho' deepest in a Royal Brest, Woe must be born, yet not exprest. Oh! thou, my only Hope, my Son, While I retire to weep alone, Nobler mourning Scythia owing, Shall with her Tears see Persian Blood o'erflowing. AIR, Humble Shepherds, Grief may pain you: But no Forms in Woe restrain you. Your Complaint the Pain asswages. Fate with greater Anguish tries me; Yet the common Cure denies me. Grief oppos'd, more fiercely rages. Enter Media, who throws her self hastily at the Queen's Feet. Med. Help! Gracious Queen! Grant Innocence Relief. Tho. Who dares intrude on Royal Grief? Med. Oh! Pardon! In this dreadful Hour, Be Great in Mercy, as in Pow'r! Unless you save, Cleora dies, Devoted by the Crowd, an impious Sacrifice. Tho. Oh! She less wretched yet than I! But Justice bids me intervene: The weak from Lawless Rage to free, And still exert the Queen. Like the Thunder, Guilt alarming, Royal Frowns the World can awe. “Heav'n with Pow'r our Hands is arming “To maintain, and give the Law. [Exeunt. SCENE IV. A Temple. Enter Cleora as a Victim, Priests, and People. Cleo. Hear ye Scythians, e'er I fall! Heav'n, hear a Royal Victim's Call. Ye Pow'rs, my welcome Death forgive! To meet my Love, my Soul is flying. Since for him I could not live, With Joy for him I'm dying. Enter Thomyris, Guards, Media, and other Attendants. Tho. Forbear!—Hold your Impious Hand! Resign the Royal Maid! 'Tis I command.— Guards! To my Tent attend her.— When I Protect, who dares offend her? Cleo. Why must I thank you for the Life I hate? Great Queen, how wretched is my Fate! [Ex. Cleora, Media, and some Guards. Tho. Then what is mine! Was ever known So griev'd a Mother, or so dear a Son! He's lost; not vanquish'd, but betray'd. My Hope, my Joy, my Son, my Darling's dead! Scythians, here our Loss bewailing, See my Tears, Hear my Pray'rs! Join, join with me till they're prevailing. Tho. kneels.] YE Pow'rs! I for Vengeance call! Let the Grand Oppressor fall. Punish our invading Foes, Revenge our Wrongs, and give the World Repose. A Shout.] Hark! This joyful Scythian Shout Declares the Persian Rout. 'Tis done, Avenging Pow'rs! 'Tis done. And ev'ry Persian Mother mourns a Son. AIR. Sally, sally, before you they're falling. Revenge now is calling: Annoy 'em, Destroy 'em; Thro' Fire, And Water, Perdition, And Slaughter. Your Vengeance pursuing, With Terror renewing Despair, pale Horror, and Ruin. [Ex. Thom. and the People shout and Ex. SCENE V. The Field. Enter Tigranes in disorder, his Sword in his Hand, as from Fight. Tigr. All is lost: A hopeless Flight Succeeds the desperate Fight. Cyrus, glutted now with Blood, Swells with his own the Purple Flood. Barr'd a Retreat, in vain the Persians fly; In vain they Scythian Mercy try: I both disdain; and wou'd but bravely die. AIR. Vain Ambition, you ever fall: Tho' still you try To soar so high, You ever fall; All losing, while you aim at all. Pow'rs, who with great Souls inflame us, Why does Reason ne'er reclaim us Till our Fate is past recall? Vain Ambition, still you fall, &amp;c. Enter a Party of Scythian Soldiers, whom Tigranes engages till he is wounded; and Orontes enters. Oro. Hold! Scythians!—Let a nobler Fate— Sciti, fermate il pie. Piu nobil Fato— Tigr. Victorious Prince, you come too late— Yet enough you Fatal prove, And doubly kill me, in Cleora's Love. Oro. Oh! Live! Tho' for her to contend— Vivi per contrastarmi il suo possesso. Tigr. Too near my End, That Comfort Fate denies. Oro. Yet strive to live—Help! bear hence The wounded Prince, And save a Life a Prize. The Soldiers lead off Tigranes. Voi soccorrete il Principe ferito, E una vita, ch'io stimo a lai serbate. Ex. Tigranes and Soldiers. Enter Baldo. Bald. Hail! Prince, who the Day retriev'd, Who came, and sav'd, when lost believ'd! To your Valor Vict'ry's owing. See our Tears with Joy now flowing: Soon your Sight the Queen will cheer, And the Princess— Oro. Oh! She's here. Oh! lei sen viene. Enter Cleora. AIR. Cleo. I revive now you're returning, All my Mourning Is lost in Joy. Oh! I ne'er can bear the Pleasure. Sorrow pain'd above all Measure; Joyful Transports now destroy. Re-enter Tigranes supported. “Cleo. Oh! Like a fatal Dart, “Surprize, and Pity wound my Heart. “Tigranes!—who this Sight can bear! “Tig. Oh! you o'er-pay me with a Tear. “You give Pleasure in Despair. “I must leave you. “I'll not grieve you. “To Superior Merit due, “While Life and you I lose, let others for you live. “When a pitying Tear you give, “'Tis more to die for you. Cleo. Unhappy Prince! Exit. Tigranes supported. Enter Thomyris. Oro. The Queen! [Kneels. La Regina. Tho. My Son! Oh! rise! thou Guardian of my Throne! Oro. No! Let me rooted here remain, Till I from you new Life obtain. Can I without Cleora live? Life without Love no Joy can give. No, lasciate, chio non posso Viver mai senza Cleora. Chi sa viver senza amare Non sa viver, ma penare. Tho. Rise! be happy; I comply. Oro. Oh! now you drown my Soul with Joy. O qual gioia il cor m'inonda! AIR. Tho. Pleasure calls: Fond Hearts recover! Fears are over. Let the Lover At last enjoy. May the Passion sweetly pain you, Kindly chain you, And never cloy. Oron. Soul of Pleasure, now to you I for Life again must sue. The Queen permits Possessing; But Heav'n, and you, must grant the Blessing. Or dimando a voi la vita, Mio Tesor! Doppo Tomiri Tocca al Cielo, e tocca a voi D'accordarla a i miei desiri. “Cleo. Oh! ask no more what Fate's denying. “Let me rather share the Ruin “All my Persian Friends pursuing, “Than blush at my complying. “Oron. Oh! Reprieve me. “Cleo. Leave me! Leave me! “Med. When of Friends War has bereft me, “Will you lose the last that's left you! “Cleo. Hope's denied me. “Oron. Then I must no longer sue. “Adieu! Adieu, to Life, and you. [Going. “Cleo. Oh! Mortal Anguish! Oh! my Fears! “Stay! 'tis more than Death to lose you. Give me Time to dry my Tears. I wou'd, but Love cannot refuse you. Oron. Oh, Joy! Oh, Blessing! Past expressing. Dolce gioia! indicibil piacere! AIR, Cleo. Lost in Pleasure, Love beguiling, Oh! you disarm me. Oron. Oh, my Treasure! Kindly Smiling, Oh! how you charm me. Oh! mia vita! Oh! mia speme! Oh! mio Tesoro! “Tho. Bless the Pow'rs that grant the Blessing! “Med. Let the wond'ring World applaud! “Oron. Share our Joys, all Hearts possessing; “All. Lov'd at Home, and fear'd Abroad. CHORUS. Love and Vertue the Conquest obtain. Peace shall last; Freedom by Union shall gain: All Danger is past. Victorious, And Glorious, Astrea's Reign The Blessings shall maintain. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>