<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Cross, J. C., (James Cartwright)</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Cross, J. C., (James Cartwright)</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">cross j c james cartwright</field>
      <field name="author_text">Cross, J. C., (James Cartwright)</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1800's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V3.0632.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1809</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460961</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The False Friend ; or, Assassin of the Rocks ; A New Melo Dramatic Ballet of Action</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The False Friend ; or, Assassin of the Rocks ; A New Melo Dramatic Ballet of Action</field>
      <field name="title_facet">false friend or assassin of the rocks</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">false friend or assassin of the rocks</field>
      <field name="title_text">The False Friend ; or, Assassin of the Rocks ; A New Melo Dramatic Ballet of Action</field>
      <field name="year_display">1809</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1809</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1809</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460961&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460961&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Cross, J. C., (James Cartwright)&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;cross j c james cartwright&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The False Friend ; or, Assassin of the Rocks ; A New Melo Dramatic Ballet of Action&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;false friend or, assassin of the rocks&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1809&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1809&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Cross, J. C., (James Cartwright)&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The False Friend ; or, Assassin of the Rocks&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A New Melo Dramatic Ballet of Action&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for the Author, by T. Burton ; and published by Lackington, Allen, and Co. ... sold by T. Barker [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1809&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3873295-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv30632&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The False Friend ; or, Assassin of the Rocks&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A New Melo Dramatic Ballet of Action&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 66 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries, introductory and editorial matter omitted&lt;lb/&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;lb/&gt;Epigraph and dedication included with The Round Tower; or, The Chieftains of Ireland&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: The false friend.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Melodrama.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1809.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 25 Aug 1806.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE FALSE FRIEND; OR, ASSASSIN OF THE ROCKS.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">A New Melo Dramatic Ballet of Action, performed for the first time, September 7, 1806. The incidental Dances by Mr. BOLOGNA, Jun. The Music by Messrs. RUSSEL and CORRI, Jun. The Machinery by Mr. CABANALL, Jun. and the Scenery by Mr. MARCHBANKS.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHARACTERS. Horatio (in love with Julia) Mr. Bradbury. Mandeville (equally enamoured of her) Mr. Bologna, Jun. Howard (Father to Julia) Mr. Bologna, Sen. Zaluch (a friendly Jew) Mr. Slader Fitzhugh (an old Steward) Mr. James Captain of Outlaws Mr. Roberts His Lieutenant Mr. Makeen Will Surge (Horatio's Boatswain) Mr. Miller Orphan Boy Master Wallack Alice Mrs. Roffey Widow Wantley Mrs. St. John Cottage Girl Miss Jellet Rose Mrs. Spencer and Julia Mrs. Wybrow</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE I. Distant Sea View after a Tempest, with a Ship nearly a Wreck on the Ocean—Corn Fields, and a Cottage in the fore Ground. The Widow Wantley, Alice, and Children are discovered on the stage, grouped similarly to the Characters in Bigg's painting of the Shipwrecked Boy. CHORUS. The storm has subsided, gaunt terror departs, (Tho' batter'd) the Vessel has weather'd the gale; The dawning of hope gives new life to our hearts, Proceed, little Sailor boy, finish thy tale! BOY SPEAKS. Before I proceed let me heave one sad sigh, For alas! my recital is sad; In the grave's narrow confines my parents both lie, I, alas! am a poor Orphan Lad! But a Parent I met, in a Mariner bold, Who from his brave Captain procured me employ; But I dread they, alas! now are both dead and cold, And have left me to mourn them, a poor Orphan Boy. In the dead of the night a tremendous wave O'er board wash'd our Captain, my Friend stood anigh, And plung'd, him to snatch from a watery grave, But, alas! mourns their fate, a forlorn Orphan Boy. SOLO—ALICE. A Chief so lov'd, a Tar so bold, Can be—what makes me feel so silly! Can be but him our Isle adores, And my True-love, my bonny Willy! The Boy presents a memorandum, which he had drawn from his bosom, recording the first day he was taken under Surge's protection. DUET—SURGE AND ALICE. Alice. Ah! me! 'twill break my heart in twain! Surge. (without) Yeo ho!—I'm sure my reckoning tallies! Alice. Bless me! his voice! Surge. (without) —Yeo ho! Alice. —Again! Surge. Yeo ho! on board the pretty Alice! Surge enters, supporting Horatio, as just escaped from shipwreck—the boy, affectionately, falls at his Captain's feet—all group in thanks to heaven! CHORUS. High Heaven to thee our eyes are rais'd! The storm we've weather'd! danger's o'er! Omnipotence aloft be prais'd, Gladly we've reached the wish'd for shore! RECITATIVE—WILL SURGE. Well, Alice—Jack—Sal—Peg—how much you grown are, Dame, broach a cag of brandy for his honour; Cold comfort 'tis we've swallowed, and no prog, Damme! salt water makes but sorry grog! Alice takes up billet wood. That's right, girl! trim the fire—(without exception) No friends, e'er wish'd so, for a warm reception! Dame. Walk in your honour. Children. —Dear sir, pray walk in! Alice. Lord! I declare they're both wet to the skin! Surge. Why, aye, that's true, we're but in scurvy plight, But I dares say your dock here's dry and tight; The tide runs in, and in, my hearts, we go! (Bless your dear sparkling day-lights) ri tol, de rol, de rol, de rol, de ri do. Exeunt into the Cottage. Enter from the bottom of the stage Fitzhugh, an old steward, attended by Rapine. RECITATIVE—FITZHUGH. Well said, old Rapine—don't you think me right! I've master's orders here, in black and white! And if her pride and haughtiness endures, I'll turn the wheedling Vixen out of doors! Her Daughter I've lov'd long, and now am bent, That they shall starve, if they refuse consent! Odds bobs! all plagues and torments I'll divine, But I will call that little gipsey mine! (Alice comes from the house as looking for more billet wood.) Look there she is!—which way now shall I get on? Shall I like faint-heart sigh? or bully threaten? Zounds! I'll try both (throws himself at her feet) I love you to distraction! But, if refused—I'll—I'll have satisfaction: If to my sufferings you unfeeling prove, I swear I'll ruin you, and yours—my love! Alice. Ruin! I never could abide you, no, not never, And now, I'm sure, I hates you worse than ever! Fitz. Hate me! Alice. —Yes hate ye—can there be a doubt? (He attempts to seize her.) Paws off, old gentleman! or I'll cry out! (Surge appears at the door.) Surge. Holloa! avast! which way sets the wind now? Is that the way you take a girl in tow? (Throws him from her.) Insult a woman! look up if you can— And try for once, if you dare face a man! (Fitzhugh and Rap. approach with their sticks raised.) Sheer off you swabs, some other course pray steer: Why what the devil wind could blow them here! Fitzhugh, tremblingly, drops the following scroll: “Mandeville orders Fitzhugh, if the Widow Wantley's Rent is not immediately paid, to destrain her Goods.” Surge. Distress a Widow! Fitz. —Worse perform'd than plann'd! (aside.) Surge. My Captain's Friend, too, sanction this command! I ca'nt help thinking, (tho' I mustn't speak,) 'Twere well if that Friend's anchor were apeak! Yeo ho! you sharks! you dog-fish, be so kind To try a bit if you can't haul your wind? There (throwing down his purse) take your shot! Alice. —Dear! how my heart does beat! Pray, William, make him give you a receipt? (William motions Fitzhugh, who takes out his ink horn, &amp;c. and writes one.) Fitz. There, take it, Ralph— Rapine. —I'm duberous— Fitz. —You fool! (He gives it him trembling.) Surge. Luff, or I'll give you a receipt in full! Fitz. Here's a strange turn! Girls breathe but to deceive! I never will forgive this, while I live! Exeunt Fitz. and Rap. Surge. So you're aground, girl! zounds! that must not be, But did you ne'er forget me while at Sea? DUET—SURGE AND ALICE. She. 1. When Spring's light breezes sportive played! Or Winter's tempests whistled shrilly, In Summer's heat, or Autumn's shade, My every thought was fixed on Willy! Dearer than life, my love to me, Tho' he was far, far out at Sea! He. 2. When in fierce battle, cannons roar'd, Or storms assail'd with utmost malice; At helm, or round the social board, My every thought was pretty Alice! Dearer than life, my love to me, Tho' I was far, far out at Sea! He. 3. The sparkling bowl when landsmen fill, To toast their Pols, their Bets, and Sallies, She. The brim I kiss to sprightly Will, He. The glass I drain to pretty Alice. Both. Dearer than life, my love to me, Tho' he was, &amp;c. Tho' I was, &amp;c. Exeunt. Three huzzas are heard without, and Jury Masts erected in the Ship—the Sailor Boy, who had gone towards the Wreck for intelligence, enters, with hat, &amp;c. appertaining to Horatio, followed by a part of his crew; on tapping at the door, Horatio comes from the Cottage, and receives, highly gratified, their congratulations, Surge, returning with Alice, exultingly exclaims, Surge. True hearts of oak! on shore, boys, or on board, A brave commander ever is adored! Horatio dispatches a letter, he had penned in the Cottage, by the Boy, to Julia, then gives necessary orders to his Crew, &amp;c. RECITATIVE. Surge. Alice, do ye' see that packet? Alice. —Yes, I do! Surge. Master's as much in love as I—or you! Alice. Indeed! Surge. —Aye, with a first rate—generous as fair! Alice. The lady Julia, I do declare! Surge. They'll soon be spliced— Alice. —Spliced! Surge. —Married, as sure as fate! Alics. Heigho! I wish as how, that I was a first rate! Surge. Why as for that—as far as I discarn— (Horatio crosses and orders Surge to follow him, he tucks Alice under his arm.) I'm 'quipp'd your honour, and sha'n't lag astarn. Exeunt. A number of Cottage Girls, &amp;c. enter with refreshment, which they gladly offer the Seamen, and they chearfully accept. RECITATIVE—DAME. Dear, I'm so happy! chearful glides that toil Which glads the hearts of those who guard our Isle. A DANCE OF SAILORS AND COUNTRY LASSES. And Exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE II. Entrance to a handsome Park, appertaining to Howard's Mansion—a seat encircling a tree, on which Julia's name is engraved. Enter Mandeville, musing and intimating that he doats on Julia to madness—appears impatient for some one's arrival—Fitzhugh, his Steward, enters, of whom he eagerly enquires what success? RECITATIVE—FITZHUGH. (shaking his head.) Ah, sir! on artifice we always cann't relye! Plots, even shipwrecks wo'n't serve you, nor I! No, tho' false lights our wish did near attain— She righted, and our villainies prov'd vain! Your Friend (Rival I mean) and mine (I fear) Will reach us sooner than we wish them here! Mandeville can scarce contain his rage at this disappointment, but, perceiving Julia approaching, commands Fitzhugh to retire, who goes off muttering to himself. Fitz. Dog-fish! old shark! how Surge did storm and lour! But zounds! I'll trounce him if e'er in my power. Exit. Mandeville, watching the motions of Julia, conceals himself behind the tree—Julia enters (followed by the Boy) perusing Horatio's letter, which she kisses with rapture—Boy retires—Mandeville comes forward racked by jealousy and vexation, he cautiously approaches her—she starts—he bows and delicately takes her hand, which she withdrawing, presents the letter, intimating his Friend for whom it is designed is momentarily expected—shouts without announce his arrival, which as highly delight her, as they confound and abash him—but, perceiving Horatio approach, he summons up all his courage and hypocrisy, meets him with every appearance of the warmest friendship, and congratulates both on their approaching happiness—her Father enters, embraces Horatio, who with Julia kneels for his blessing, which he affectionately bestows; and Mandeville, endeavouring to conceal his jealous perturbation, hypocritically appears to participate in their happiness, by joining their hands, at the same time strongly marking (aside) the determined hatred he bears him. SURGE enters hastily with ALICE. Surge. Well pull'd, my girl, well pulled—four knots an hour, Is (to Julia) bless your sweet ladyship—your sarvent sir! Surlily salutes Mandeville—Horatio informs Julia, &amp;c. he had preserved his life—Julia offers him her purse—he refuses. RECITATIVE. Surge. No, madam, no! Surge would himself disdain, If he proved true, but for the love of gain! I lost a cutlash in the squall—that's gone— And if his Honour would but—zounds! he has flown! Exit Horatio, rapidly, into the House, followed by Julia. How Mandeville eyes me!(his Steward enters and whispers) what (old Shark) you're come! The Fury Fire-ship, and the Sulphur Bomb! But I say, Alice—who knows?—you soon may be Prefar'd to be Head-maid to our sweet Lady; To strut the quarter deck, here sport parades— Alice. La! Married Women ca'n't be Ladies Maids! Horatio and Julia joyfully return, Julia bearing a handsome Cutlas, which she presents Surge, and with which he seems much pleased, draws it, on the blade appears inscribed, “the Reward of Fidelity,” —he kisses it—Julia, &amp;c. are retiring. RECITATIVE—SURGE. Heaven's bless you, madam! blessings on you both! But stop, and please you hear a Seaman's oath! SOLEMN OATH. By England's glory and my King I swear In Peace or War my Captain's Guard to prove! His safety shall be to my Heart as dear As is my Country, Liberty, and Love! And if this oath I break, may vengeance shed It's curses dire on Will's devoted head! The various characters, concerned, during this, express appropriate feelings;—an enlivening march is heard without, and all exeunt, Surge excepted. RECITATIVE—SURGE. This is a gift!—I somehow feels quite gay, And yet I ca'n't help dashing off the spray! (Wiping his eyes.) Avast! no drops must stain this blade! no! no! But the red drops of an inveterate Foe! Well, I do'n't know how 'tis—some how or other I ne'er lost one friend, but I found another! SEA SONG—SURGE. [1.] To boast what one's born too, is nonsense and pother, 'Tis Providence sure takes in tow great or small; As to luck as I never knew Father or Mother, It was good luck, I think, I was e'er born at all! As to how when first launch'd, (for I had no relation!) I picked up my crumbs, deuce a bit can tell I! But this I've since learn'd, that whatever one's station, If a ball's born to hit you, 'twill never pass bye! So d'ye see I sings cheerly howe'er the winds blow, Pull away, and be jolly boys, yeo, hay, ye ho! 2. I've ta'en cruises many, in squalls and fair weather! Been loving on shore boys, and dauntless at sea; Made my mind up to take rough and smooth both together, Set sail fair or foul, for 'twas all one to me! I'm proud but of this, 'tis whoe'er tells my story, Ca'n't call to his duty, one truer than I; And conquer, or fall, in the moment of glory, If a ball's born to hit one, 'twill never pass bye. So d'ye see, &amp;c. RE-ENTER ALICE. Alice. La! it's all settled! William! Surge. —What d'ye say? Alice. The wedding's to take place this very day! The Parson's come— Surge. —Our chaplain, girl, or who? Alice. Pray ca'n't one Parson marry more than two? Surge. Aye girl, a dozen, give him but his swing— Alice. I dreamt last night about a wedding ring! And such a crowd of folks to chapel flocking! Surge. And zounds! I dreamt how well they threw the stocking! Mayhap now we mought realize the scene, And of yon cabin become king and queen! DUET—SURGE AND ALICE. Surge. On board man of war, I fought like a tar, And nobly am paid for my labour; But bless'd now on shore, With the girl I adore, I jig it to pipe and to tabor! When rolling at Sea, 'Twas all one to me, How rigg'd, or what birth in my swipes I was nabbing! But at home full of cash, I'll roll quite the dash, And swig to the sweet little queen of my cabbin! Yeo ho! hey down derry! Her eyes sparkle merry! I'm king, she the queen of our neat little cabbin! Alice. So dearly I love, Should you leave me, and prove Falsehearted, 'twould wound beyond bearing! Surge. Me leave! if I do— I'll be da— Alice. —No, no, no— Believe you, I can without swearing! Surge. But avast, Matey? sha'n't We some company want, On long Winter nights? I'm palaver no dab in! Alice. I guess what you mean, When we're crown'd king and queen, You'd wish a young prince should be rear'd in our cabbin. Both. Yeo ho! hey down derry! With eyes sparkling merry, A young heart of Oak for our neat little cabbin.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE III. An Oratory appertaining to the Baron's private Chapel. Procession to the altar, Girls strewing flowers, &amp;c. EPITHALAMIUM. What is love? a tender tie, That binds two hearts in sympathy: What are wedlock's mystic rites? A pledge which closer still unites. And happy must that union prove, Where Hymen's rites are crown'd by Love! May o'er your days Love long preside! Hail happy Bridegroom! happy Bride! After the Epithalamium, Julia decorates Horatio with a rich emblematical sash—the ceremony is on the point of taking place, all the characters having properly arranged themselves, when Mandeville, driven to madness, attempts, unperceived, to assassinate Horatio—a trumpet is heard without, he starts, and, conceiving himself observed, conceals the dagger in his bosom—Surge enters— RECITATIVE—SURGE. Bad news, brave Captain, the insatiate Foe, One more approach our Island to attack; Your prowess must atchieve their overthrow, And with our gallant Townsmen drive them back! Mandeville is rejoiced at this intelligence, but assumes an appearance of the most fervent affection to the nearly new married pair—drum beats to arms, and a messenger enters, demanding, in stronger terms, the personal attendance of Horatio—Mandeville urges him to depart, swearing that he will protect his affianced Bride and Parent during his absence—the alarm bell is sounded—“Our Leader, our Leader!” resounds from all quarters—warmed up to the extacy of military enthusiam, Horatio fondly embraces Julia, then draws his sword— RECITATIVE—SURGE. Alice, farewell! dry up your tears, my beauty, You all expect—and we will do our duty! Lord love ye! conquest ca'n't lag long astern, We'll die, or crown'd with Victory return! Exeunt, Horatio leading the way. The remaining characters group, Julia, &amp;c. offering up prayers to Heaven for their success—the scene closes—Alice comes forward. RECITATIVE—ALICE. Here now's a change!—all going on so right! Old nick for sartin sure, owes us a spite; The hours I've waited, and the miles I've walk'd, So near a wedding too! and to be baulk'd! Perhaps to Church he ne'er again may hand me, After I took such pains to make him understand me. SONG. [1.] With downcast eyes to speak his mind, When simple Cymon trembling ventures; For Love, tho' he is reckon'd blind, Oft through the eye the bosom enters. Blushing deep red with fervent glow, Or if his orbits raised are, blinking; Pray ca'n't you tell, says he, heigho! Pray ca'n't you tell of what I'm thinking? No! no! no! no! says Bell, no! no! how can I tell of what you are thinking. 2. But simple Cymon bolder grown, For Love, if smiled on, grows more pressing; Compell'd the lass at length to own His thoughts were worthy the expressing. He a ring display'd, with fervent glow, Her hand then kiss'd and slily winking: Pray cant you tell, says he, heigho! Pray ca'n't you tell of what I'm thinking? Yes! yes! yes! yes! says she, yes! yes! I now can tell of what you're thinking. Exit.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE IV. Romantic View by moonlight, with an opening through which Robbers descend; in addition to this a most extensive chasm, through which not only the Sea is visible, (on which the moon-beams play brilliantly) but a practicable Fort at a distance— a ruined Abbey attached to first Wing. Enter Captain and Lieutenant of Banditti followed by their Band. RECITATIVE—LIEUTENANT. Captain, the Moon sends forth so clear a light, I fancy for our trade, no luck to night! It's devilish hard! an idle life I hate! But come, a Dram—and leave the rest to fate! GLEE—ROBBERS. For arts little caring, In arms 'tis we shine; Advent'rous preparing, The loaded carbine: Disdaining the world and it's laws. How jovial life passes, While nothing's to pay; Then boys poize your glasses, And fire, fire away! A dram to the good of our cause, Fire away! fire away! Drink and exeunt on the prowl. After which a boat is rowed on, in which, as a passenger, is Zaluch. GLEE ON THE WATER, ZALUCH AND WATERMEN. Here in distant times The solemn Convent bell Bade responsive chymes To holy rapture swell: While fervently the cloister'd Nun, Chaunted her vesper orison! But now the distant roll, of the hollow, hollow drum, Mingled with the merry little fifer's play; To quarters calls each wandering Soldier home, Listen, listen, listen to the distant lay! Hark! hark! it does invite, To go to bed home, go to bed home, go to bed home, Good night, good night! As they separate, the moon is hid by a cloud, and a short summer storm takes place—the Banditti on the watch single out Zaluch as their prey; he appears much agitated, though not perceiving them. RECITATIVE. Zaluch. Vell, who'd have tought of dis now?—all so bright! And pless me! all at once so black as night! Dat's but a cut-throat road! it chills my blood! What's that, a gibbet? 'tis a hanging wood! I vas so eager for to get afloat!— What brought me here?—eh? bless ma heart! de boat. Where vas de Boatmen?—holloa! all, quite gone! I shall be robb'd! and lose what's not my own! My Conscience! tho' the venture was well meant, I'd not ensure myself for cent per cent! 'Twas a good motive, tho' a bad essay, To meet my Friend upon his wedding day! A Friend indeed! mine by de dearest tye, A Friend who snatch'd me from captivity! From a French Prison—'twould have been my grave, But British Tars, are as humane as brave! Vell, bless me! I must venture!—hang such woods! I vish I could insure myself and goods! (Going cautiously through the entrance into the Forest— starts.) What's dat? my heart jumps in my mouth wid fright! I'd give a premium, now dat all vas right! I ca'n't tink how it is my heart so fails! (As he pursues his journey alarmed, Banditti steal on after him.) Lieut. to Capt. Be firm, determined, dead men tell no tales! They seize and bear Zaluch off struggling, and crying “help! murder! &amp;c.” Enter HORATIO AND SURGE. RECITATIVE—SURGE. (listening.) Avast!—your honour!—hark! capsise my mess— But that's a signal—some one's in distress. (A pistol is fired without—Horatio draws his sword, and rushes off.) Off like a shot—master's among 'em smack, You too (drawing his cutlas) look eager, tight one for attack! And so here goes—if Pirates—why belike Will Surge is not the boy will make them strike! Exit. Re-enter Horatio and Surge engaged with Banditti, whom at length they conquer, and rescue Zaluch —Surge having taken a pistol from one of them points it at his head; Horatio disarms the other. RECITATIVE—LIEUTENANT. Don't—pray don't fire—because, d'ye see, you'll find, I'm like a lamb, so naturally kind! And if once more I could my freedom gain, You'd find me grateful as I am humane! Watching his opportunity, he snatches the pistol from Surge and fires, it passes his head, blowing his hat off—Horatio flying to his assistance, both Robbers escape—Zaluch falls at the feet of Horatio. RECITATIVE—SURGE. Damme! well missed!—what undersail! avast! Give me but one more grab, and zounds I'll hold you fast. Exit. RECITATIVE—ZALUCH. My Benefactor!—bless me!—can it be!— Rescued again by him from jeopardy! Pardon dese tears—my gratitude runs wild— I'm such a chicken—I cry like a shild! Horatio affectionately raises him.) My wish was at your wedding to appear, And bless ma heart! I meet my good friend here! (Draws out a Jewel Case.) Tank Heaven you're safe! dis vas my poor heart's pride! A grateful present to your lovely bride! (He opens Jewel Case and displays it.) Dis her sweet Image to your eye-sight bring! Dis yours discloses, by dis secret spring! Dere, take, and keep it for poor Zaluch's sake, If I was robb'd of it my heart would break! Enter SURGE out of breath. Surge. Zounds! they've out-sailed me! damn the sharking crew! Ah! my old Israelite, what is it you? Zaluch. Anoder friend! vell, vell! I'm too your debtor— Accept my tanks—my purse— Surge. —'Sha'n't—I knows better! The battle o'er, like light'ning Surge would fly, To save from found'ring e'en an enemy! Then may the swab be capsised, end for end, Who in misfortune wouldn't help a friend! GLEE. The hour's approach, our bells now chyme, The turn of tide proclaims the time; The Fortress Clock strikes three. One! two! three!—now briskly row, Pull away! pull away! yeo heave ho! While we our brief instructions follow! To the signal-whistle, and a hollow! They enter the boat, and at the end of the Glee are rowed off. ZALUCH. Good bye! good bye! may Heaven your efforts bless! And War or Peace crown Britons with success! Exit.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE V. Julia's Apartment—the Portrait of Horatio in the centre of the Scene—table, chairs, book, &amp;c. Enter Julia, followed by Rose, regretting the melancholy reverse of her fate, in so unexpected a separation from her destined Husband—Rose, in vain, endeavours to console her—she throws herself mournfully into a chair, and, ordering her attendant to retire, takes up a book.—Mandeville enters, unperceived, and cautiously approaches her—she starts on perceiving him, he affects to pay homage to Horatio's portrait, and condoles with her on his absence —at length throws himself at her feet, declares his passion, and, stamping with his foot, a Priest and four armed men appear!—he seizes her—she screams—he orders Priest, &amp;c. to retire, and drawing his dagger, displays the following scroll: “Be secret, or dread the Event.” Julia's Father rushes on—but the secret threats of Mandeville, who assumes before him his wonted friendly attachment, prevents her informing him of his treachery—a trumpet is sounded without, and a messenger enters with the following intelligence: “Horatio is victorious, and, accompanied by his faithful Surge, will return this Night.” Mandeville reads the first sentence with disgust, but seems pleased with the conclusion, and accompanies Julia and her Father off, pretending the most heartfelt satisfaction openly; but, aside, threatening Julia with vengeance if she betrays him.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE VI. Mandeville's apartment, decorated with splendid paintings, the centre consisting of the assassination of Julius Cæsar—a Banditti's cavern—a blood stained Murderer, &amp;c.—an appropriate sopha in the Scene. Enter Mandeville, gloomily meditating, seems to curse his fate and unexecuting arm, which failed him in compleating his Rival's murder at the altar—his eyes appear, at length, rivetted on the painting of the murderer, which becomes transparent—horror struck he throws away his dagger—the assassination of Julius Cæsar strikes his fancy—he hastily snatches it up again, and, throwing himself into the attitude of the Brutus of the picture, determines on revenge —the view of the Banditti confirms him, and he determines, by the aid of similar characters, to compleat the murder of his friend, and hastily rings a bell—Fitzhugh, alarmed, enters, to whom he intimates his determination, and dispatches him to procure aid; then throws himself on the sopha in great agitation—visionary objects arise before him, and, rushing forward, he wildly grasps at an air drawn dagger and pistol which appear within his clutch, and are in reality tendered him by Strongbow and his associate, who are introduced by Fitzhugh —bell tolls—his terror encreases—he bribes the Outlaws, and, terror struck, accompanies them, with Fitzhugh on their murderous project. Exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE VII. Rocky and mountainous View opening to an expanse of Ocean—an entrance to a Cavern on one side of the stage, and a ruined Cottage on the other —the Moon clouded. Enter Mandeville, Fitzhugh, and Robbers, the former appears, occasionally, to feel compunction; but, informed by Strongbow that Horatio and his Companion approach, summons up resolution. RECITATIVE—FITZHUGH. I'll watch around, and, safely screen'd from harm, Will give you early notice of alarm! Exit. Mandeville, &amp;c. conceal themselves; and Horatio and Surge joyfully enter, the latter as having just received a purse of dollars as a present from his Captain. RECITATIVE—SURGE. Thanks, ten fold thanks, your honour; this shall prove A wedding gift to the dear girl I love! We've bang'd the Mounseers, damme, as we ought, And this Cape cleared, will soon regain our Port! Your honour's Bride, and Al'ce, I dares maintain! Think Minutes Hours 'till we salute again! Horatio kisses the Miniature of his Bride, given him by Zaluch—Mandeville and Assassins steal from their places of concealment with swords drawn, and assail their unprepared victims—a desperate fight ensues, in which Horatio is wounded, and his Scarf torn from him half crimsoned with blood—Surge drives off the Banditti, and, during a hard struggle between Horatio and Mandeville, the Moon suddenly bursting forth, discovers to Horatio his False Friend as his assailant—the agitation of both is excessive—Mandeville shudders, but perceiving the Miniature of Julia pendant from the neck of his rival, seizes it, tells him 'tis for the love of her he has undertaken his murder, and, tearing it from his bosom, more desperately attacks him; almost fainting with loss of blood, Horatio is disarmed, and Strongbow and Fitzhugh returning, no means of his escape appears left—he is driven up the precipice pursued by his cruel and malignant rival, who, deaf to his last appeal, dashes him from the promontory into the Ocean; and the voice of Surge being heard without, the assassins hurry, alarmed, to their hiding places—Surge enters with his cutlas very bloody, and his face and hands sprinkled with gore. RECITATIVE—SURGE. Thank Heaven! of one of them I've made a wreck! But where's my Captain—Friend—Commander—speak? (Hallooing loud, and pacing across the Stage in agony.) They've borne him off—your honour—we'll ne'er part! Yeo! ho! a hoy! (whistles.) Answer your honour?—or you'll break my heart! Exit distractedly. Re-enter Mandeville with the Assassins. RECITATIVE—FITZHUGH. Make haste—disguise yourselves—anear this spot he'll roam! 'Gainst him we'll strive to bring the murder home. Or we may suffer—give to knavery souls! (Alarm bell heard.) For us, or him, yon solemn Death Bell tolls! Exeunt much agitated. Enter, after a Pause, ZALUCH. RECITATIVE—ZALUCH. Vat ails me! I ca'n't tink!—so sad I'm grown, As if, for all de vorld, dat Stocks vere down! Vell, be it so! for all dat I can say— Lame Ducks vill vaddle out on settling day! (Sees blood on the Stage.) Bless my heart! blood! dat's vorse dan de whole tote! I near vas robb'd, and now dey'll cut my troat! My conscience! more and more! dear! dear a me! Some One dey've kill'd, and trown into de Sea! (Follows the track of blood 'till he is gradually obscured by the rocks, &amp;c.) Re-enter, wildly, SURGE. RECITATIVE. Surge. In vain I chase him!—no where to be found! They've borne him off!—conjecture e'en's aground! Mandeville, Fitzhugh, and Strongbow enter, the former in long cloaks, the latter compleatly disguised, appear listening, attended by Officers and Soldiers with torches, but, who, approaching slowly, and on the listen, conceal them in their caps—during this Surge perceives and takes up his Captain's bloody scarf. RECITATIVE. Fitz. Mark! mark! his words! his guilty looks explore. Surge. Oh! how shall I e'er face ma'am Julia more! I! that to guard him, for her sake did swear! She'll look upon me as his murderer! This scarf she gave him!—the thought splits my brain! I never can see home or her again! Oh Alice! never more shall I taste ease! Fitz. Yonder's your Prisoner! the vile monster seize. CHORUS. His trembling limbs, his pallid cheek, His glaring eye-balls guilty lower! The ruffian Murderer bespeak! With hands still reeking, red with gore! They force him off.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE VIII. Julia's Apartment. Enter Mandeville hastily, with looks of terror, wildly casting his eyes round in search of Julia; but not perceiving her, draws the miniature he had torne from Horatio, cautiously, from his bosom' which he contemplates with exultation—she suddenly enters—and he hastily replaces it in his bosom—she starts at perceiving him, and attempts to retire, which he prevents—Alice enters weeping— RECITATIVE—ALICE. Ma'am, have you heard? (dear! I'm in such a taking!) William—his honour—(my poor heart is breaking!) Both have been murder'd!—sad's the tale they tell! (Noise of the clank of chains without.) William in chains! can it be possible? Rushes off. Julia, trembling, attempts to follow her, but is prevented by Mandeville, who endeavours to sooth the agitation of her mind—she treats his efforts with disdain—he suddenly and resolutely seizes her hand, and drops the following scroll: “Horatio is murdered, but Mandeville will avenge his Death.” She starts from him, disengages herself from his grasp, and wildly quits the scene—he following.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE IX. AND LAST. Court of Justice. Howard seated as Judge—Secretary at a table writing—Officers, Guards, &amp;c. in attendance— Surge discovered in fetters—Mandeville, Fitzhugh, and Strongbow, in evidence, bear the purse, sword, and bloody scarf—Mandeville appears as his accuser —Spectators, &amp;c. properly arranged. RECITATIVE—FITZHUGH. That blood-stained sword, scarf, purse, strongly concur, To prove yon savage wretch the Murderer! Who, to conceal the crimes he now outbraves, His Victim buried in the boundless waves. We traced the blood— Enter Julia distracted, attended by Rose—she looks sorrowfully on the blood-stained parapharnalia that surrounds her, and shakes her head mournfully at Surge, who appears heart-broken; but suddenly starts up indignant, at Mandeville pointing him out as the Murderer of Horatio!—she shudders—kisses the scarf, and faints in the arms of her attendant. RECITATIVE. Surge. 'Till worn a wreck, I'm guiltless I'll repeat— (Tho' I despise the sentence you are passing!) I've sarv'd some Years on board a British Fleet! But ne'er yet learn'd the trade of an Assassin! Murder my Chief, 'tis likely that I should, For whom I'd spill the last drop of my blood! Fitz. 'Gainst evidence this is but idle prate! Man. 'Tis but mere trifling, Sirs—pronounce his fate. (Howard, &amp;c. seem consulting, and apparently as if inclined to pronounce Surge guilty.—Zaluch enters slowly, but with looks of astonishment.) Zaluch. Bless me!—your sarvant, Sirs! I'm giddy sure! (Puts his hand to his Head.) Fitz. Their looks bespeak him lost, and us secure? During this, Mandeville places his hand in his bosom, as if on the miniature; but suddenly with drawing it to congratulate Fitzhugh on the prospect of Surge's conviction, with his hand drags forth the miniature, which drops on the floor—Zaluch, eagerly, snatches it up—a pause— ZALUCH. Bless me! from whom dis fall upon de floor! De Workmanship, I'll swear, I've seen before! Where vas you buy dis, may I be so bold? Mandeville, alarmed, secretly endeavours to bribe him with a purse. Zaluch. Your pardon—Zaluch does not worship gold! What your'e astonish'd, bless my heart dat's true! You thought me villain—cause I vas a Jew! Vell, vell—Mandeville lays his hand on his sword) aye, threaten, actions should accord, If gold wo'n't do, 'tis fit you use de sword! But to de point—and dat you must explain! Dis Picture, vhen and vhere vas you obtain? (During this, Fitzhugh and Mandeville exchange intelligent glances, Mandeville refers him to Fitzhugh.) Fitz. Long since, in London, solemnly I swear! “That precious bawble, singular as rare,” Was, by his orders made—proof we can bring— Zaluch. Vell, vell, if so—just touch de secret spring. (Mandeville receives the picture, and endeavours, in vain, to find it.) Zaluch. Vat! your hand trembles! (takes it) you've not larn'd de trade! Known but to me, and him for whom 'twas made! (Touches the spring, it opens, and discovers the miniature of Horatio.) What, does the object your poor sight offend? 'Tis but the Image of your murder'd Friend! Murder'd by you! who, eager for such food! Would glut your fury in more guiltless blood! (The Characters here groupe—the rage of Mandeville subsiding in terror, but still by action he demands judgment on Surge.) Surge. Who is it now that does his fate outbrave? Zaluch. You axed for “Judgment,” judgment you shall have? And tho' scarce mov'd, conviction you've withstood, Behold a witness that will freeze your blood! Horatio pale, and with his arm in a sling, enters, leaning on the Sailor Boy—Mandeville's terror is increased —Julia looks wildly on Horatio, and they affectionately embrace—each character, according to his situation and concomitant feelings, making one in an impressive groupe—a pause—Mandeville, with his sword, attempts to dispatch Horatio, whose life is preserved by Surge, and his sword wrested from him—Mandeville, seeing no way of escaping disgrace, draws suddenly a dagger, and, striking himself to the heart, falls lifeless into the arms of Fitzhugh and Strongbow, who are guarded off, bearing his remains. RECITATIVE. Surge. Can I believe my eyes! can it be true— His honour living!—is it, is it you? (Horatio embraces him, he falls at his feet! then starts up joyfully—Alice rushes on and embraces him.) Surge. Ah, Alice!— Alice. —William!—I can hardly speak! Dear! dear! I thought my poor, poor heart would break! The Characters congratulate each other on the happy termination of their miseries, Julia bending in gratitude to Zaluch. RECITATIVE. Zaluch. Heavens bless you Lady!—may your sufferings cease, And all to come be happiness and peace. And should these scenes again appear in view— Surge. Cheer a poor guiltless Tar— Zaluch. —And friendly Jew. FINALE. In the Journey of Life, ah! how varied the Scene, The prospect now dark, and now bright; Disappointment's dark cloud will too oft intervene, And eclipse the fair face of delight. But to grief bid adieu, to all anguish and care, Peace and pleasure let reign in each breast; To Love now has yielded the Monster Despair, And Beauty and Virtue are bless'd.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">This was originally the Finale to Julia of Louvain, but that Piece generally concluding with the recovery of the Heroine, it has been, by far, more frequently made use of in it's present situation. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>