<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Burges, James Bland, Sir, 1752-1824</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Burges, James Bland, Sir, 1752-1824</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">burges james bland sir 1752 1824</field>
      <field name="author_text">Burges, James Bland, Sir, 1752-1824</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1810's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V2.0637.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240355</field>
      <field name="date_text">1817</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460275</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Storm ; A Comedy</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Storm ; A Comedy</field>
      <field name="title_facet">storm</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">storm</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Storm ; A Comedy</field>
      <field name="year_display">1817</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1817</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1817</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460275&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460275&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Burges, James Bland, Sir, 1752-1824&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;burges james bland sir 1752 1824&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Storm ; A Comedy&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;storm&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1817&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1817&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Burges, James Bland, Sir&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1752&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1824&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Storm&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Comedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for Edward Kerby [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1817&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872591-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv20637&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Storm&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Comedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 167 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Only verse drama included&lt;lb/&gt;Play reproduced elsewhere in English Verse Drama omitted&lt;lb/&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;lb/&gt;Preface included with The Knight of Rhodes&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: The storm.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Comedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1817.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Unknown.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE STORM. A COMEDY.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Sunt mea, quæ vovi, sunt tibi vota rata. BOURN: POEM:</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DRAMATIS PERSONÆ. Men. Montalban. Ferdinand. Don Lopez de Gongora. Roderigo, Steward at De Silva Castle. Guzman, Surgeon at ditto. Gomez, Don Lopez's Servant. Sancho, Peasant. Pedro, Peasant. Women. Donna Victoria. Donna Clara, her Niece. Margaretta, Housekeeper at De Silva Castle. Teresa, a Peasant. Scene.—Andalusia.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. SCENE I. The Sea-shore. A violent Storm, with a Vessel at a distance. Enter Sancho and Teresa. SANCHO. Faster, good dame, let's try to gain some shelter; There's no resisting this tremendous storm. Enter Pedro. Pedro! What brings thee here in this foul weather? PEDRO. I sought some straggling goats, that from my herd Had wander'd to the cliffs; but now, by th' mass! They may return, or stay there as they list. TERESA. Saint Bridget save us! How the light'ning flashes! See there again! Marry, 'tis time to go. Enter Ferdinand and Roderigo. FERDINAND. This way, my Roderigo! See, where stand The peasants of our hamlet, wonder-stricken, All gazing on the elemental strife Which harrows up the ocean. RODERIGO. Aye, aye, give 'em But something new to stare at, they will leave Their tasks unfinish'd to turn out and wonder. Why stand ye gaping here, ye idle knaves! Your daily labours incomplete, your ploughs Left in the half-till'd fields— FERDINAND. Nay, chide them not; Think not less nobly of their gen'rous feelings Than of our own. RODERIGO. Aye, so you always say— TERESA. The poor man's blessing light upon you for it, And the poor woman's too! You're always kind, And treat the mean dependents on your bounty With courtesy, as if they were your equals. FERDINAND. And are ye not so? From a peasant's breast An infant prince may draw his nutriment, And servile hands may swathe his puny limbs, And smooth his couch. The proud magnifico, Who battens on the good things of the world, Looks to the lab'ring hind who tills his acres For the foundation of his wealth and state, While he, his task perform'd, from him in turn Receives the guerdon which maintains himself. Thus are our wants and aids reciprocal, And thus far are we equal. RODERIGO. You had best Not put such fancies in their heads. I know 'em— They're apt enough to spurn authority, And do not want your teaching. In my mind, Some mod'rate censure on their sauciness, Were more to th' purpose. FERDINAND. Talk not thus, I pray, To one like me, who am myself dependent. But we lose time. See, where amid the waves Yon vessel struggles with the tempest's fury. Now borne aloft, now whelm'd beneath the main, Her sails all shiver'd, tow'rds the shore she drives. PEDRO. Nay, if she drive much farther she must strike. While thus the tempest rages, she will find A rough reception on our iron coast. SANCHO. Saint Anthony defend us! There's a plunge! Her masts are all gone by the board!—She strikes! FERDINAND. Now, if you've hearts or feelings, follow me Quick to the strand. RODERIGO. You will not be so rash— FERDINAND. What! When our fellow-creatures are in peril To think of our own danger!—Come, my friends! Shew what ye are. Should the high-mounting surf Cast any on the beach, we may preserve them! [Exeunt. SCENE II. An Apartment in De Silva Castle. Enter Donna Victoria. VICTORIA. With what dread majesty the tempest rages, As if the skies were rending, and the earth Were hurl'd from its firm base! It is most dreadful! Yet I can bear it unappall'd, can see The forked lightning strike yon promontory Which overhangs the ocean, nor shrink back T' escape th' impending peril. Can affliction Thus render us insensible? Alas! Too surely such our feeble nature is, The sport of accident, the toy of fortune, Which takes its tone and colour from events, And makes us, poor chamelions, vary with them. Enter Clara. CLARA. Oh my dear madam! Are no news arriv'd Of our rash Ferdinand? VICTORIA. Is he gone forth? CLARA. An hour ago, as from the western oriel I gaz'd on the vext sea, I saw him go. VICTORIA. You should have urg'd him to return CLARA. I call'd to him, And begg'd him not to go, but all in vain. He us'd to mind me; but he's grown self-will'd. When he comes dripping home and chill'd with cold, He'll think perhaps that I'll take care of him— VICTORIA. Peace, foolish girl! When Ferdinand returns, He'll find you fond as ever. You forget He now no longer is the trifling boy, Who shar'd your pastimes, and with eagerness Partook of all your infantine amusements. Full sixteen summers are elaps'd, since first I brought him hither. You was then a babe, And he a prattling child, blooming and fair, Who toy'd with you, and taught you first to speak, At once your play-fellow and best instructor. But now, the consciousness of manhood stirs him To new pursuits more worthy of his years: His enterprizing spirit pants for action— CLARA. Why should he wish for change? I could, methinks, Live here for ever, so he liv'd here too. You will not let him leave us, madam, will you? I know how tenderly you love him. VICTORIA. Yes! From the first moment he became the child Of my adoption, I have never ceas'd To love him as mine own; and well his duty Hath all my watchful tenderness repaid. Poor Ferdinand! thou hast indeed a claim On my best feelings! CLARA. I have oft remark'd That you will gaze upon him, 'till your eyes O'erflow with tears, and from your heaving breast A sigh will burst, as if of stifled sorrow; And when I ask'd what caus'd you thus to grieve, You made me no reply, but gave a look So sad— VICTORIA. Ah my lov'd niece! Could I disclose The secret cause of woe, which, spite of all My self-command, sometimes o'erpow'rs me, I should but wring thy feeling heart. CLARA. Oh no! Could I but share your grief, I might relieve it. But why should Ferdinand thus cause you pain? He never troubles me, unless when thus He disregards himself. Do tell me, madam, What has he ever done to move you so? VICTORIA. Alas, my Clara! there's a secret cause, Which cannot be disclos'd, but which, whene'er I look upon him, brings to my remembrance Such mournful images, as time itself Cannot remove or cure. CLARA. Dear lady, weep not. I'm sure, could our good Ferdinand but know How for his sake you grieve, he'd chide himself For causing you disquiet. Never breast Contain'd a heart more gentle or more brave. Enter Roderigo. Oh Roderigo! where is Ferdinand? RODERIGO. I left him in Teresa's cottage yonder, Down by the beach. He bad me hasten hither, To tell my lady he was safe. CLARA. How's that? To tell he's safe? Has he been then in peril? RODERIGO. If, when the sea was raging mountains high, To plunge head-foremost in the madd'ning surf To save a drowning wretch, be perilous, Then hath he been in peril. VICTORIA. Prithee tell me, What cause impell'd him to an enterprize So hazardous and daring? RODERIGO. Truly, lady, There was a cause, which, to a mind that priz'd His neighbour's safety higher than his own, Was strong enough in conscience. For myself, Though I can find in heart to serve a friend, My notion is— CLARA. Pshaw! What is that to us? RODERIGO. Nay, give me leave, I pray. My notion is, That charity begins at home. VICTORIA. Nay, nay, Tell us at once thy story. RODERIGO. When the storm With tenfold fury rag'd, he drew me forth, To see, forsooth, whether some luckless bark Driv'n on the coast might not require our aid: As if a poor old man, like me, could brave The tempest which our castle's turrets shook. Well—he persuaded me—I could not help it. CLARA. Don't be so tedious! What of Ferdinand? RODERIGO. When to the first o'er-hanging cliff we came, We saw a vessel driving on the coast. In shorter time than I can tell the tale, Headlong she came on a projecting rock, And down she sank outright. VICTORIA. Alas for pity! Sank do you say? With all her crew aboard? CLARA. What became of them? RODERIGO. What became of one I witness'd, and can tell. As the ship founder'd, I saw him boldly leap into the sea, And buffet manfully the waves: but soon, Caught in the surf, he sank. CLARA. He perish'd too! RODERIGO. He would have perish'd, had not Ferdinand Rush'd forward to his succour. Swift as thought He dash'd into the roaring surf, and drew him Exhausted to the beach. But see—he comes. Enter Ferdinand. VICTORIA. Welcome, my gallant boy! CLARA. Oh Ferdinand! How could you, like a wild thing as you are, Alarm us so? Had the rude sea o'erwhelm'd you, You know it would have broke your Clara's heart. FERDINAND. My lovely friend, be satisfied. I'm safe, And, as you know what pow'rful motive led me To dare the waves, you surely cannot blame me. CLARA. In sooth I do not blame you; but remember, You must not be so rash again. RODERIGO. You may As well exhort him not to eat or sleep. I verily believe he has no feeling Of that first principle, self-preservation; And, what's worse still, he thinks all others should Be equally fool-hardy as himself. He wanted me, forsooth, I thank him for it, To try how I could gambol in the surf, And fish for dead men's corpses. FERDINAND. If I did, My pains were fruitless. You have liv'd so long, That you are grown enamour'd of existence, And, in proportion as your glass runs low, You prize more highly each remaining sand. VICTORIA. But tell us of the man you sav'd from death. Where left you him? FERDINAND. When on the beach I drew him, He had no signs of life; but we convey'd him To good Teresa's cottage, where her care In some degree restor'd his scatter'd senses. VICTORIA. Haste, Roderigo, summon Guzman hither, And Margaretta. [Exit Roderigo. Now it is our turn To perfect the good work which you began. Enter Margaretta. MARGARETTA. What are your ladyship's commands with me? VICTORIA. There is a vessel wreck'd upon our coast, From which, of all the crew, one hapless man By Ferdinand's exertion has been sav'd. You must provide wherewith to succour him, For he is destitute of all— Enter Guzman. GUZMAN. Here I am, Ever obedient to your la'ship's orders. What may your ladyship be pleas'd to want? I'll wager now some case has just occurr'd Which calls for my assistance. VICTORIA. You guess rightly. GUZMAN. Has your good ladyship been indispos'd? There is a flushing in your cheek—your pulse— With your good leave— [Attempts to feel her pulse. VICTORIA. No, Guzman, you are wrong. GUZMAN. That's wonderful!—Oh! then, 'tis the young lady. (He feels Clara's pulse. Hey! let me see—Why what's the matter here? On a full gallop!—One, two, three, four, five— CLARA. Let go my arm, I say; I'm well enough, And do not need your doct'ring. GUZMAN. Nay, young lady, I know what ails you better than yourself. If Guzman now must learn his trade of you, 'Twould be a pretty world. Not ill indeed! VICTORIA. You are again mistaken. GUZMAN. How? Oh ho! 'Tis the young gentleman then, after all! VICTORIA. His rashness might have thrown him past your help— GUZMAN. Aye, that same rashness is the common fault Of youth. How often have I said, “young man, “Take my advice; one's never in such danger, “As when one feels the strongest.” Galen says, And he says well— VICTORIA. Some other time we'll hear him. You're wrong again. Hs needs not your prescriptions. GUZMAN. He not ill neither? That is mighty strange! If you're all well, why do you summon me? VICTORIA. Be silent, and I'll tell you. The late storm Has wreck'd a vessel on our coast. Of all On board none 'scap'd— GUZMAN. That seems a desp'rate case, In which my skill can be of little service. VICTORIA. If you would talk a little less yourself, And give more heed to me— GUZMAN. I'm all attention. But surely your good ladyship can't think That, when a patient once is fairly drown'd— VICTORIA. Will you be silent, sir, and hear me out? GUZMAN. Close as a well cork'd phial. VICTORIA. Of the crew None 'scap'd, save one, whom Ferdinand preserv'd, And to Teresa's neighb'ring cot convey'd. Go there, and do your utmost to restore him. GUZMAN. Aye, that's another case. If he be living, The greater danger he is in the better. Let but a spark of life remain, we'll see If death or Guzman shall be conqueror! [Exit Guzman. VICTORIA. Now, Margaretta, we must try to find What may relieve this hapless stranger's wants. MARGARETTA. Of linen and apparel there's enough. Is there aught else you'd wish me to provide? VICTORIA. (To Ferdinand) —What seem'd the stranger's quality? FERDINAND. His garments Accorded ill with what his mien bespoke: For, though his cheeks were colourless, his eyes Half clos'd, and from his floating hair The briny flood yet dript, methought a ray Of innate nobleness beam'd forth, which shew'd He once had known a more propitious fortune; Like a rich jewel, which, though meanly lodg'd In a poor casket, still retains it's lustre. There was a something indescribable, Which shot across my breast as I look'd on him, Of mingled pity and respect. Indeed, His suff'rings to the former gave him claim, But why I yielded him respect I know not. Yet so it was. VICTORIA. We often see, that nature Stamps on the outward lineaments the mark Of the rare qualities which grace the heart. I too feel interested for the stranger, Whose mere appearance could impress you thus. Did he impart his name and his condition? FERDINAND. He did not; nor did I importune him With questions, ill adapted to the state In which the perils he had pass'd had left him. CLARA. Had I been there, I had been less discreet. There surely is some mystery about him. FERDINAND. So I should guess; for, whether it were owing To the confusion caus'd by his late danger, Or to some recollections which oppress'd His lab'ring heart, I know not, but his speech Appear'd to wander strangely. VICTORIA. Did you note What 'twas he said? FERDINAND. One passage seem'd so strange, I could not but remark it forcibly. When he recover'd sense enough to know That to my timely aid he ow'd his life, He rais'd his languid eyes, and for awhile Gaz'd on me, while his countenance betray'd A strange and quick succession of emotions: Then, cov'ring his pale face with both his hands, He deeply sigh'd, and with a feeble voice Exclaim'd—“Is it a phantom that I see, “Cloath'd in the living semblance of that being”— VICTORIA. The living semblance of that being, said he? Good heav'n! CLARA. What ails you, madam? You are ill. Send some one straightway to bring Guzman back. VICTORIA. No, no—remain—'twas nothing (to Margaretta)—Did you mark The stranger's words—“cloath'd in the living semblance” There is but— MARGARETTA. Hush! I pray you be compos'd. There may be nothing in it. VICTORIA (to Ferdinand). Pray go on. Said he aught else? FERDINAND. A sudden burst of tears Prevented farther speech. He made a sign, Imploring us to leave him. Though I wish'd To learn more circumstances of his story, I felt too strong a rev'rence for his grief Unduly on his privacy to trespass. VICTORIA. You acted well.—He may indeed have cause— Oh Margaretta! MARGARETTA. Why are you thus mov'd? VICTORIA. Those strange mysterious words— MARGARETTA. No more, I pray. Let me conduct you to your own apartment. VICTORIA. Do so.—(To Clara and Ferdinand) I would not have you be alarm'd— I'm sometimes thus—I shall recover soon. CLARA. Nay truly you're unwell; your colour changes. Let me assist you.—So—Go, Margaretta, See that the chamber be prepar'd.—Now, madam— [Exit Margaretta. Come, Ferdinand, and help me to support her. That's well—now, if you please. VICTORIA. Thanks, my kind love! [Exeunt. SCENE III. A High Road near De Silva Castle. Enter Don Lopez de Gongora and Gomez with a Cloakbag. LOPEZ. Plague on those sandy hills, those barren remnants Of primitive confusion, which reflect From their loose surface heat enough to melt A man of less consistence than myself! And double plagues light on the restive mule, On which this morn I mounted for my sins! I would have turn'd her from the narrow path, Which on the verge of a steep precipice She had chos'n out; but she, forsooth, preferring Her wit to mine, demurr'd. I rais'd my staff, And smote her o'er the ears; she rais'd her heels, And toss'd me some three yards before her head. The dogs may feast on her for what I care, And on me too, if e'er again I mount her. How far is't, varlet, to De Silva Castle? GOMEZ. 'Tis somewhat better, sir, than half a mile. It may be more or less for aught I know. I'll not be positive. LOPEZ. You will be positive, Nay most superlative, in formal dulness. Better than half a mile! GOMEZ. Aye, I'll be sworn 'Tis that at least. Why, it's a furlong hence— So said the muleteer—let's see—a furlong To Pedro's cottage—twice as much to Sancho's— LOPEZ. 'Tis a day's journey! I shall melt away, Like a wax image 'fore a witch's fire. Where is my cloak-bag, mongrel? I shall need A change of garments, when my journey's ended. GOMEZ. Here 'tis, an't please your worship. LOPEZ. Take it up— Why how unhandily you set about it! GOMEZ. 'Tis passing weighty, sir, for one like me. I can't— LOPEZ. What, mutiny?—Here—take it up. GOMEZ. I may as well attempt to move yon cliff As raise it up. I pray you lend a hand. LOPEZ. Marry, that I will straight. (Strikes Gomez. GOMEZ. Nay, an you strike me, Your fardel may lie here till doomsday, or You may e'en carry it yourself. I list not. LOPEZ. What's that thou say'st? GOMEZ. I won't. LOPEZ. Thoud'st best take heed. GOMEZ. Look you, Don Lopez, or Don Gongora, I know not if I give you your right titles, But this I know, I'll be your slave no longer. Here goes your liv'ry! Some two dozen valets Have worn't already, and it may fit others. Pay me my wages! I have serv'd ten weeks At th' rate of twenty crowns per annum— LOPEZ. Phew! Is the man mad? What ails thee, my good Gomez? Some gad-fly sure hath stung thee. Leave me, say'st thou? Thou know'st thy duty better, than to quit me Here in this desert, all alone and helpless. Tut! Thou'rt a simpleton. I did but joke. 'Tis a droll way I have. GOMEZ. Yes, mighty droll T'abuse and strike one. LOPEZ. 'Twas a joke, I tell thee. Here, take it up, I pray. I'll lend a hand. GOMEZ. If 'twere no more than joke— LOPEZ. It was no more. GOMEZ. Well, I'm an easy fool.—So—(puts on his cloaths) Raise it now. Give me my staff. LOPEZ. Now onward to the castle. (Aside) When we get there, I'll teach thee a new lesson. [Exeunt. END OF ACT I.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. SCENE I. Donna Victoria's Chamber. Donna Victoria and Margaretta discovered. VICTORIA. Leave me, my Mar'gret, I'm unfit for converse; Leave me to brood o'er the distressing thoughts Which rack my bosom. MARGARETTA. Dearest lady! do not Give way to useless grief. VICTORIA. Term it not so. You heard what this mysterious stranger said. Whose likeness could he find in the dear youth On whom he gaz'd, but mine? MARGARETTA. Nay, that is sure. From the first moment when I swaddled him, And bore him privately from Lagos Castle For fear his infant cries should reach your father, I noted his resemblance to yourself. He had your brow, the dimple on your cheek, And, when he rais'd his eyes and smil'd upon me, I could have sworn it was yourself in little. But how can this poor stranger— VICTORIA. Who but one, Upon whose mind the features of the mother Had an indelible impression made, Could in her offspring such resemblance find? Oh lost Montalban! from my constant heart Nor time nor absence can thine image blot! MARGARETTA. I grieve you thus should speak. Can you forget How ill Montalban has deserv'd your love? VICTORIA. Alas! too well I know it; yet, in spite Of all his falsehoods, still my heart is faithful: By day I think of him, and, when at night Sleep seals my eyes, I see him in my dreams, As he was then, when first my yielding heart Confess'd his pow'r, and own'd him as its lord. MARGARETTA. Nay, ma'am, that letter from his correspondent The great Peruvian merchant, which Don Lopez De Gongora, his factor here, once shew'd you, Containing the detail of his new nuptials, Is evidence enough of his deceit. If farther still were wanting, you have that, Which afterwards he wrote himself, denying To Lopez that you was his wife, and daring, Aye, daring you to th' proof of it. VICTORIA. Too well He knew I could bring none. Our only witness, The holy priest who join'd our hands, was dead, Ere to Peru his haughty father sent him To break those ties his pride disdain'd to sanction. Cruel Montalban! was it not enough To make me wretched? What had our child done, Thus to be made an outcast, thus to lose At once his name, inheritance and station? The very thought is madness! MARGARETTA. In good truth I hardly could believe it.—But those letters— There's no resisting them—and yet it may be— Are you quite certain, madam, of Don Lopez? VICTORIA. Why ask you that? MARGARETTA. I know not; but there's something In his appearance, and his manners too, May lead one to suspect he may have motives— VICTORIA. You know how much Montalban trusted him, And, since he left his native land, maintain'd Close correspondence with him. MARGARETTA. True, yet still Doubts will arise— VICTORIA. What int'rest can he have Thus to calumniate one, who, as he owns, Has ever prov'd himself his firmest friend? Let's think no more of him, but of some means To clear away the gloom which thus involves me. Perhaps this stranger— MARGARETTA. What do you hope from him? VICTORIA. Nothing—or ev'ry thing!—Could I but see him— What if we visit him? MARGARETTA. Nay, I beseech you— As yet, the myst'ry which attends your marriage Is known to Lopez and myself alone. Should you improvidently drop a hint Which may create suspicion—Be advis'd. VICTORIA. Your caution's just. Perhaps the trial might Prove more than I can bear. Do you, my friend, Go and converse with him. You know the whole Of my sad story. MARGARETTA. Marry, that I do. VICTORIA. Go then, and try to ascertain the truth. Whatever the result may be, 'twill sooth My heart to know it. MARGARETTA. Trust to me. I warrant I'll bring you full intelligence. VICTORIA. Come then. [Exeunt. SCENE II. Inside of Teresa's Cottage. Montalban discovered, reclining on a miserable Pallet, Guzman and Teresa standing by him. MONTALBAN. I thank you, sir, and you my worthy hostess! Methinks I'm much reviv'd, and would not tax Your services beyond what need requires. TERESA. You may feel better, but you yet are weak. While we can be of use to you, I'm sure Our time is heartily at your disposal. GUZMAN. Our time indeed! Pray answer for yourself, Good woman! Mine, I'd have you know, is precious. MONTALBAN. Then stay not here, I pray. A shipwreck'd man, Like me, can't recompense your services. GUZMAN. That's like enough.—Well, I may call again, Or I may not, as my occasion suits. Let's see—you've had a med'cine, to recruit Your wasted strength—you now require repose. Here's a narcotic, which will make you sleep Soundly, I'll answer for't.—Dame, see he take it. I'll send you by and by a fresh prescription, A nostrum of mine own— MONTALBAN. I shall not need it. GUZMAN. How's that? Not need it? Mighty fine indeed! Pray who's the better judge, sir, you or I? MONTALBAN. Nay, sir, I do not question your endowments. You may be very learned. GUZMAN. Wiser heads Than yours have found me so; and yet, forsooth, You take upon you to dispute with me! MONTALBAN. There's no offence, I hope. GUZMAN. Yes, but there is. When such a man as I demeans himself T'attend on one like you— MONTALBAN (rising). He should remember That breeding and humanity become him. GUZMAN. What's that you say, sir?—Here's a pretty bus'ness! One, whom from charity I condescend To visit and relieve, to dictate to me! One who has not a ryal in his pocket, The poor fee-simple of whose whole possessions Would fail to pay the prime cost o'th' drugs He has already swallow'd— MONTALBAN. Look you, sir, For that assistance you've afforded me I pay you with the only coin I have, My thanks; but for your most uncourteous railing, The sole return it merits is contempt. Take it, and go your way. GUZMAN. Mighty fine, truly! A pretty treatment this for Signor Guzman, A doctor graduate of Salamanca, And body surgeon to my lady here! But I am rightly serv'd—this 'tis to wait On vagrants— MONTALBAN. How! TERESA. You'd better go, good Guzman. GUZMAN. You are a fool!—Insult me at this rate! I'd have you know— MONTALBAN. I would not counsel you, For your own sake, to try my patience farther. I may be poor, sir, but I am a man. Once more, be gone! GUZMAN. Well, sir, since you're so gruff, You've my free leave to cure or kill yourself— 'Tis no concern of mine. So, sir, your servant. [Exit Guzman. TERESA. Ne'er heed him—thus he's always to the poor, Who must perforce submit and truckle to him, Or go without his med'cines when they're sick. They say he can bow low enough, and cringe, When he's in company with those above him; But, by the mass! he's proud enough with us. MONTALBAN. I've long been us'd to suff'ring, my good dame, And only wonder, that my mind has strength Enough remaining to resent his rudeness. I find I yet have much to learn, before My feelings can be properly subdued. TERESA. Aye, it's a sorry world for such as we. MONTALBAN. No, no, good dame, the world is not in fault, Nor the great pow'r that rules it. 'Tis a stage, Where all have parts; it matters not which falls To any of us, for our scene is brief, And, if we act it well, our recompense May be expected in a better place. TERESA. I think so sometimes, when I'm cold and hungry, And the reflection gladdens me.—Who's there? [A knocking at the door. Come in, I pray. [Montalban sits musing on the pallet. Enter Margaretta. Oh madam! MARGARETTA. Hist! Come here. (Aside) —I bring some things for the poor shipwreck'd stranger, And would converse with him; but, do you mark me, I wish him not to know me. TERESA. Aye, you are A charitable lady! MARGARETTA. Leave us, pray. [Exit Teresa. Save you, good sir—Nay, stir not, I beseech you; Your weakness needs repose. Here is a seat, On which I will sit by you.—(Sits)—I have heard Of your misfortune, and have brought some trifles, Which may perhaps supply your present wants. MONTALBAN. I will not wrong you, madam, by extolling Your gen'rous condescension to a stranger. You will have better praise than I can give you. MARGARETTA. Your suff'rings have been great, and you may need More succour than Teresa can afford you. MONTALBAN. My corp'ral suff'rings scarce require a thought. (Rising) —Some slight contusions, and a little weakness, Are all I can complain of. MARGARETTA. Pardon me; I should suspect there are some other evils, If I may guess from your appearance, which By many would be counted burthensome. MONTALBAN. What, poverty! the lack of rich attire? Call not those evils—they're of small account. Villains may boast their wealth, bear on their backs The spoils of provinces, and deck their tables With feasts that might supply an hospital, While honesty, in such a garb as mine, Houseless, expos'd to all the winds of heav'n, Would scorn their fellowship. MARGARETTA. You speak as if You had experience of the world's injustice. MONTALBAN. I've had experience of the world's reverses. From the bright summit of prosperity To be the wretch you now behold I fell: I once had riches, now am I a beggar; I boasted rank, and am a nameless outcast; I had a friend—he cheated and undid me— MARGARETTA. Those were indeed hard trials; yet consider, Riches and dignities are fleeting things, And falsehood in a friend, when known, grows harmless. MONTALBAN. I had sustain'd these patiently, if more And worse had not remain'd. Appriz'd at length Of the foul frauds of him I thought my friend, With my remaining pittance I embark'd For Barcelona. Scarce had I descried The shores of Spain, when from Algiers a pirate Bore me to harsh captivity. MARGARETTA. Take comfort; Your mis'ries now are o'er. MONTALBAN. I would they were. A man like me, long season'd to misfortunes, May bear with constancy all outward ills; But there are poisons, which assail the heart, And mock all antidote. Could you but know What passes here, you'd own I have strong cause For doubt and apprehension. MARGARETTA. May you not O'errate those apprehensions? MONTALBAN. No—Where'er I turn, my destiny seems almost hopeless. Oh madam! you're a woman, and can feel. Judge what must be my anguish, when I tell you I had a wife, dear to me as my soul— I pray forgive the weakness that unmans me. MARGARETTA. Alas for pity!—Is your wife living, sir? MONTALBAN. There, there you probe my mis'ry to the core. Oh! she was loveliness and truth itself; Her very soul seem'd mine; my bosom knew No other joy, no other hope but her; Yet was she torn from me!—As I hung o'er her, And press'd her to my agonizing breast, Scarce could her pale and quiv'ring lips pronounce Her last, last sad farewell!—Oh recollections Of happiness, for ever, ever lost, Why rush ye like a torrent on my soul! Why wring my heart with images of bliss, Vanish'd, and never—But I crave your pardon— Why should I trouble you with my distresses? MARGARETTA. They are so weighty, that my heart can feel An int'rest for them, as they were mine own. They tempt me to enquire—excuse me pray— What name you bear? MONTALBAN. I wish not to conceal it. Montalban is my name. MARGARETTA. Montalban! MONTALBAN. Yes— A name once great and dignified, but now Link'd to calamity. MARGARETTA. And what your wife's? MONTALBAN. That is a secret, which my honour guards More strictly than my life. I swore to keep it, 'Till more propitious fortune should allow me In the world's face to claim her.—But enough— I know not how it is—your kindness led me To call to my remembrance sad events Which, as my strength as yet is unconfirm'd, Have somewhat shaken me. With your good leave, I would go forth, and taste a freer air. MARGARETTA. Teresa! Enter Teresa. Here—take up this seat, and place it Before your door. A little change of scene And the fresh breezes may recruit your guest. Be of good courage, sir; things yet may mend. Nay, do not look so sad. If you deserve A better fortune, it may yet await you. [Exeunt. SCENE III. An Apartment in De Silva Castle. Enter Donna Victoria. VICTORIA. An hour and more are past, since Margaret Left me to visit this mysterious stranger; And still she comes not. Why thus palpitates My woe-worn heart? Is it because a ray Of hope breaks forth, to dissipate the gloom Which long each flatt'ring prospect has obscur'd? Howe'er delusive it may prove, I'll court It's cheering influence— Enter Donna Clara. CLARA. Who d'you think's arriv'd? I'm sure I should have just as soon expected The Grand Inquisitor himself— VICTORIA. As whom? CLARA. He liv'd at such a monstrous distance from us— He has such a name too—'tis Don something— VICTORIA. Prithee Speak out at once, nor keep me in suspense. CLARA. Stay—Don—Don—now I have it—'tis Don Lopez, Lopez de Gongora, from Barcelona. Ar'n't you surpriz'd? VICTORIA. There's nothing sure surprising, That one I've known so long should visit me. I thought at first it might have been another. CLARA. I wish it had been; for I ne'er saw one Whom I felt less dispos'd to like than him. I met him in the entrance, and before I could effect my escape, he rudely stopt me, And stunn'd me with a flood of fulsome nonsense About my brilliant eyes and my complection, Gloating and staring on me with a look So forward that I shudder'd. Still he held me, 'Till Ferdinand came up to my relief, And made him quit me.—As I live, he comes. Enter Don Lopez and Ferdinand. LOPEZ (to Ferdinand). You'll give me leave to tell you, young Signor, You have no right to meddle—(seeing Victoria) Ah my queen! Queen of De Silva! see your faithful servant From Barcelona comes to pay his court. VICTORIA. You're welcome, sir. LOPEZ. I'faith! I should be so, For I've sustain'd more perilous adventures Than any of your heroes in romance, O'er hill and dale, by water and by land— (Seeing Clara) Ah my sweet little rose-bud! have I caught you? CLARA. Pray, sir, keep off— VICTORIA. Nay, Clara, don't be shy— LOPEZ. There, do you hear? Come, we shall be good friends. So, now, your hand— CLARA. Protect me, Ferdinand! LOPEZ. Oh ho! Is that the case?—(to Ferdinand)—Stand aside, boy! A little more respect would best become you. FERDINAND. 'Twould more become you, sir, to leave her quiet, Nor thus forget the rev'rence of your age. LOPEZ. Why thus it ever is. These smooth-fac'd boys, Who think they're men because they're whipt no longer, Conclude that lusty manhood must be old. FERDINAND. If you dispute it, sir, I apprehend Your mirror or your feelings may convince you You bear about you symptoms strong of age. LOPEZ. I tell thee I am young, and stout to boot. Symptoms of age indeed! A puling child Like thee to tutor me! Od'slife, young sir, If thou once anger me— FERDINAND. Stop, sir, in time; I may be else provok'd. This lady's presence Prevents me from replying.—Come, my Clara, Let us retire— LOPEZ. Nay, an you quit me thus— [Exeunt Clara and Ferdinand. VICTORIA. Now, sir, perhaps, you will vouchsafe to tell me What urgent bus'ness makes you visit me. LOPEZ. What urgent business, say you? You shall know. I'faith, madonna! I am glad to see you With such a countenance, so fresh and blooming. By good St. Anthony, you look not older, Than when that runnagate, beshrew him for it! That wild Montalban play'd you such a trick. VICTORIA. That is a subject, sir, I would avoid. LOPEZ. Nay, 'twas a foul one. What could he discover In that far southern world to equal you? Yet, strange as 'tis, I find he still doats on her, And on her swarthy brood. VICTORIA. Have you then heard Aught new respecting him? LOPEZ. Aye, marry, have I; But nothing likely to afford you pleasure. VICTORIA. That may be, sir; but I should wish to hear it. LOPEZ. An you will know—A vessel from Peru, Which touch'd at Barcelona lately, brought me A letter from himself. Unless your heart Hath ceas'd to feel for him as it was wont, You'd best not ask its purport. VICTORIA. Speak it boldly: I am prepar'd for all. LOPEZ. Thus then it is. After detailing all his present comforts, He talk'd about his wife, sung forth her praises With all the ardour of a doating husband, And prattled of his children—he has six of 'em— As if I felt an int'rest in the brats. But this was a mere trifle to what follow'd. VICTORIA. What can be worse? LOPEZ. Nay, so I thought you'd say. But you will know it—Thus then he went on. I owe, says he, a duty to my children, And wish to bring them and my wife to Spain; But, while she lives who has a tie upon me— Meaning yourself no doubt—you know I cannot Adventure to produce them: tell me therefore, Adds he with earnestness, if fav'ring fortune Hath disencumber'd me from that dead weight. VICTORIA. That soon will be! I wanted only this To break my suff'ring heart. To be despis'd! Treated as a mere drawback on his pleasures! LOPEZ. From what he adds of his wife's wish to come, I should not marvel, if her strong intreaties O'ercame his scruples, and prevail'd on him To hasten home— VICTORIA (aside). It is, it must be so! That vessel bore them!—They are lost!—Oh heav'n! [She throws herself on a sofa, weeping. LOPEZ (aside). So, so, it works—the bait went glibly down. Go to—all favours me. Montalban's safe In the strong clutches of his Moorish master, And ne'er will come to claim from me his wealth, Or give the lie to my ingenious fictions. I sail before the wind. Now's the fit time To broach the purpose of my visit here. VICTORIA (starting up). Who waits? Enter Page. Send Roderigo hither. [Exit Page. LOPEZ. Nay, Now we are private you had better hear me. What I've to say is pleasanter than that On which we have convers'd. VICTORIA. Excuse me now I pray. Whatever be your cause of coming, Think yourself welcome— Enter Roderigo. Mark me, Roderigo, Wait on this gentleman, provide him all He may require or wish.—(To Lopez)—Use your good pleasure While here you sojourn, and take some repose After your journey. [Exit Victoria. LOPEZ. Take repose, quotha! I will take that, and some refreshment too. (To Roderigo) What station hold you in your lady's service? RODERIGO. That which may haply best your purpose suit. Her steward. LOPEZ. What! thou bear'st the household keys, Presidest o'er the butt'ry and the kitchen, Sole governor of all the ample butts Of gen'rous sherry and rich malvoisie? Give me thine hand. I reverence thy functions. RODERIGO. Would'st take a nap first, to refresh thyself, Or have a slight repast, to stay thy stomach 'Till dinner comes? LOPEZ. Let dogs sleep, an they will: I'm hungry, monstrous hungry. RODERIGO. They shall bring thee Some delicate conserves. LOPEZ. A steward thou! Think'st thou this bulk is nourish'd on conserves? I tell thee—What's thy name? RODERIGO. 'Tis Roderigo. LOPEZ. Then, master Roderigo, you mistake me. Such puny cates suit not my constitution. An thou would'st prove my friend indeed, conduct me To thine own regions, to the land of plenty, The fragrant kitchen, and the well stor'd cellar. RODERIGO. Take thine own pleasure. We have store enough. LOPEZ. I'm glad to hear on't.—Lead the way, brave steward! [Exeunt. END OF ACT II.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. SCENE I. An Apartment in De Silva Castle. Enter Donna Victoria and Margaretta. VICTORIA. No more! no more! It is, it is Montalban, Beyond all hope restor'd! Mysterious heav'n, How wond'rous, how inscrutable thy ways! That he alone should 'scape the tempest's fury, That his own child should save him from the deep! MARGARETTA. I joy to think your suff'rings now are past, And that your future bliss— VICTORIA. My bliss? Alas! A flatt'ring vision for a moment dazzled My slumb'ring senses—But 'tis past, and now I wake again, with keener pangs to abide The mis'ry that awaits me. MARGARETTA. Heav'n forbid! Have I not told you that your own Montalban— VICTORIA. Mine own Montalban, say'st thou? So, alas! I fondly once believ'd him—But he's false, And I'm most wretched!—Oh my Margaretta! I've had such fatal confirmation Of my worst fears, that not a hope remains To cheer my poor desponding heart. Don Lopez— MARGARETTA. What said he? VICTORIA. That Montalban had resolv'd, With her who claims the title rightly mine, To quit Peru, and hither to return. And is he not arriv'd? MARGARETTA. What proof is that? Wreck'd as he is— VICTORIA. Thence springs my strongest doubt. Preserv'd alone from the destructive waves, All evidences of his crime absorb'd In the same gulph that swallow'd up his wealth, May he not hope that with impunity In a new character he may impose On my credulity? MARGARETTA. It may be so. Beyond all doubt there was a mystery In what he said to me about his wife. Nay, now I recollect, he spoke of her As one for ever lost to him. What if You were yourself to see him? VICTORIA. Not for worlds! I cannot trust myself to such a trial. MARGARETTA. What other means remain to prove the truth? Justice to him and to yourself requires, You should not leave a matter undecided On which the happiness of both depends. See him—converse with him— VICTORIA. No more—a thought Has just occurr'd. Ask me no questions, Marg'ret, But do as I direct. Let the best chamber I' th' west wing of the castle be prepar'd— MARGARETTA. Why all this? VICTORIA. Ask me not.—Send Guzman hither— Make haste.—I am not mad, my Margaret, But desp'rate ills require a desp'rate cure. [Exit Margaretta. Now, if my project do but hold, I'll probe His inmost soul, and ascertain the truth. Enter Guzman. GUZMAN. Did your good ladyship enquire for me? 'Tis fortunate I just came back in time. VICTORIA. Where have you been? GUZMAN. Attentive to my duty; Still mindful of your ladyship's commands. He's doing very well. VICTORIA. Who? GUZMAN. Why the fellow, Who 'scap'd so narrowly a drowning bout. Another plunge had done his bus'ness for him. VICTORIA. You take strange liberties in your discourse. Know you of whom you speak, sir? GUZMAN. Know him, madam? Not I—I never saw his face before. Do you, ma'am? VICTORIA. He's a stranger, and in want— Sufficient titles, sir, for your respect. GUZMAN. I treated him respectfully enough; Though, to say truth, he gave himself more airs Than well became him. Would you think it, ma'am? When I just hinted at the obligations Conferr'd upon him— VICTORIA. How did you presume To take a freedom so unwarranted? If e'er again you venture to exceed My orders, sir— GUZMAN. I humbly crave your pardon, I didn't know, that is, I thought no harm In just insinuating— VICTORIA. You did ill. Know you not 'tis our duty to relieve Those in distress, but that we lose all merit, When in return we look for other tribute Than the warm feelings of a grateful heart? GUZMAN. To be sure, ma'am. VICTORIA. Remember it in future. GUZMAN. Yes, ma'am. VICTORIA. How did you leave the gentleman? GUZMAN (aside). The gentleman! VICTORIA. Why don't you answer, sir? GUZMAN. Why, I was telling your good ladyship. When he could swallow, I administer'd A cordial draught. It had a fine effect. Then, as I found he had some fev'rish symptoms, I threw in a narcotic. 'Twas a stout one. VICTORIA. I hope you have not rashly giv'n him Too strong a potion. GUZMAN. Not a grain too much. Trust that to Guzman.—Ma'am, I undertake, If your good ladyship were indispos'd, To make up such a med'cine, 'twould amaze you. Some thirty drops, ta'en in a glass of wine Just as you go to bed, then wrap yourself Up warmly— VICTORIA. Have you seen the stranger since? GUZMAN. This very moment left him—just return'd. Ev'ry thing right as I foretold—no fever— Pulse firm and regular—the patient dropt Into a sleep, from which he'll not awake For certain hours— VICTORIA. Ar't sure 'tis so profound? GUZMAN. Quite certain—you may beat a drum at's ear Without disturbing him. VICTORIA. 'Tis very well. You may retire; but see you go not forth; I shall have other business for you shortly. Send Roderigo hither. [Exit Guzman. This will render The project which I meditate more easy. Enter Roderigo. Hark, Roderigo!—I have form'd a plan, In which you must assist me. RODERIGO. Well, good lady. VICTORIA. Did you much notice the poor shipwreck'd stranger? D'you think there is much diff'rence 'twixt his size And that of Ferdinand? RODERIGO. Much diff'rence?—No. Their stature, as I guess, is nearly equal, And as for bigness, why 'tis much the same, There may be some small matter—but 'tis trifling. VICTORIA. Go then to Ferdinand's partment quickly, And unobserv'd bring hither the new habit I order'd for th' arrival of the viceroy. RODERIGO. What will Don Ferdinand, though, say to this? VICTORIA. That's my concern. Bring it away directly, And take it to the stranger. RODERIGO. To the stranger! VICTORIA. Aye, sir; but enter not, 'till from Teresa You learn he's bound in a deep settled sleep. Then cloath him in the garments you take with you, And to the castle's western wing convey him, (Still careful not to interrupt his slumbers) Where Margaretta will direct you farther. Do this discreetly, and my favour shall Reward your zeal. [Exit Victoria. RODERIGO. Oh ho! is't there you are? Discreetly, say you? 'Tis a goodly phrase, And suited to the circumstance. Well, well— Just as you please—'tis no concern of mine. Why, we sha'n't know De Silva Castle soon. I'faith! we're like to have a rare assemblage. There's one already hard at work below, Don Gongora—I left him in the cellar, Bestriding a full cask of Malmsey sack, Like a true drunkard. If this other's like him, All Spain cannot produce a third to match 'em. [Exit. SCENE II. Another Apartment in De Silva Castle. Enter Clara followed by Ferdinand. CLARA. I tell you, you're as tiresome as Don Lopez. You know I can't endure you when you're serious. FERDINAND. No, no; I've fairly caught you. You shall hear me. CLARA. Well, what have you to say with that grave look? FERDINAND. Though it may ill become me to exalt My hopes beyond their level, yet when thus I daily witness charms— CLARA. Pray stop a minute. If you begin heroics, I must take A decent state, and put on all the airs Of a vain heroine in an old romance. But I am ill at feigning; so leave off Romantic flights, and talk like other people. Why don't you speak? FERDINAND. Can nothing make you serious? CLARA. Why really, while you look so dismally, I cannot help—But come—I ask your pardon— I am quite serious. Now I hope I please you. Come—what have you to say?—I'm all impatience. Nay, now you're quite provoking. Wo'n't you speak? FERDINAND. In one word then—I love you! CLARA. Do you so? I'm glad to hear on't, for I love you too. FERDINAND. Transporting sound! Oh say it once again! CLARA. What need is there of that? You know I do. I've told you so a hundred times already. I could not love you more, were you my brother. FERDINAND. Only as if I were your brother, say you? CLARA. Why is not that enough? I never had one, And ne'er can wish for one while I have you. FERDINAND. Has your heart never whisper'd you, my Clara, There is a sentiment more warm and vivid Than what a sister for a brother feels? Mine has instructed me. CLARA. What is't you mean? I understand you not. From the first dawn Of reason, when we toy'd and play'd together, I'm sure I lov'd you better than myself. What more can I do now? FERDINAND. Ah! did you feel Like me, you would not ask. When absent from you, I think each hour a day, each day a year; I gaze with apathy on nature's charms, And all the beauties of reviving spring; The groves no more are vocal, the fresh breeze From the gay flow'ret brings to me no odours— CLARA. But when you're with me? FERDINAND. Then all nature smiles, My heart expands to transport, hours and days Fly swift as moments, spring assumes new lustre— CLARA. Ah Ferdinand! If this indeed be love, I've felt the same, or surely something like it. Without you all is sad: I sit and muse, But always on my Ferdinand; I sigh, And, when I ask my heart what caus'd its grief, It whispers me my Ferdinand is absent. When I am with you—But you'll think me foolish— FERDINAND. Sweet innocence! thus on thy hand I swear Eternal truth!—But hold—this may not be— What am I doing? How has passion led Rashly to nourish hopes beyond my reach, And aim at such perfection? CLARA. Say not so. In what respect am I superior to you? You've been, you know it well, my best instructor; From Marg'ret's lessons oft I've flown to you, And listen'd with delight when you discours'd Of truths, which, when she spoke them, had no charms, But which, prefer'd by you, like heav'nly music With magic influence stole upon my heart. No, no, my Ferdinand, you wrong yourself, And are unjust to me. FERDINAND. No, my lov'd Clara, I know and do full justice to your worth. Had I been plac'd by fortune in a station More corresponding with th' ambitious hope That warms my bosom, I might have aspir'd At excellence, which now—Forgive me, Clara— Pity me—think on what I owe to her Whose gen'rous bounty made me what I am. CLARA. Can you then doubt of her exalted goodness? Have you not always been her fondest care? FERDINAND. And shall I thus repay it? CLARA. Did she think Your happiness at stake— FERDINAND. Ah! lead me not Through flow'ry paths to a steep precipice, Lest my brain turn, and all my constancy Fade like a mist before the rising sun. Oh! you have rais'd a phantom, which might draw me Into a maze of errors—Look not thus, So tenderly— Enter Don Lopez. LOPEZ. Heyday! What's here to do? My little rose-bud smuggled into corners? Od's me! if that's the case I'll have my share. (Advances towards Clara. (To Ferdinand) What! you'd monopolize her, would you, boy? FERDINAND. I would protect her against such as thou. LOPEZ. 'Gainst such as me? Why, thou most puny milksop! Ten urchins like thyself would not suffice To make a man like me.—Stand off, I say— CLARA. Faugh! how he smells of wine! LOPEZ. I warrant me— That Roderigo is an honest fellow, And gave me of the best. In mellow sack I drank thy health. The liquor was divine; It cheer'd my heart, and through my veins transfus'd Rich lusty blood— [He attempts to seize Clara. FERDINAND. You come no nearer, sir— (To Clara) You'd better leave us— CLARA. Promise then you will not Let him provoke you— FERDINAND. Fear not, but retire. (Exit Clara. LOPEZ. Nay, an you 'scape me thus—What gone?—Od'slife! Boy, give me way— FERDINAND. You pass no farther, sir. LOPEZ. Oh ho! sir champion! must you be chastiz'd? (Draws his sword. I'll teach you better manners—(Pushing)—There—and there— FERDINAND. If you will force me to it— (They fight—Ferdinand disarms Lopez. LOPEZ. Where's my sword? Give it me back again. Enter Donna Victoria. VICTORIA. What means all this? Swords drawn?—Say, Ferdinand, whence rose this brawl? FERDINAND. To rescue Clara from his ribbald manners— I need not tell you more. You see his state. LOPEZ. Heed him not, good madonna. Send him off. I've something of importance to impart. VICTORIA. You'd better take some other time. LOPEZ. Why so? The present time's the best. I am not drunk— A little rais'd or so.—Send him away. VICTORIA (to Ferdinand). Let some of my domestics wait without, And leave us. FERDINAND. I obey you. [Exit Ferdinand. LOPEZ. That is well. 'Tis a most malapert and forward boy, Spoilt by indulgence. VICTORIA. Sir, you know him not. LOPEZ. No? Then I'll tell thee wherefore I am come. Let me sit down, madonna, for my head Seems somehow as it were—Now mark you me— (He sits on the sofa. I'm passing rich, you know. In lands and houses, Good mortgages, and fat securities, I'm master of ten thousand crowns a year. All this, perhaps you'll think, might satisfy A reasonable man; yet, so it is, I am not satisfied. VICTORIA. That's surely strange. LOPEZ. Not strange at all; for, when I see my wealth Daily increasing, when in my strong box My dollars are prolific, and my ducats And weighty moidores generate their like, I oftentimes bethink me that myself Should follow their example. Hey, madonna! Were it not pity that the Gongoras Should in my person be extinct? So, mark you, I have been looking out for a fit bride. VICTORIA. I wish you good success, sir. LOPEZ. One, whose youth And comeliness bespeak fertility, Who'd bring me little Gongoras in plenty, To cheer and cherish me when I grow old. And whom—I know you will be pleas'd to hear on't— Whom do you think I've honour'd with my choice?— Nay, an you cannot guess—'Tis your niece Clara. VICTORIA. Surely you cannot seriously propose— LOPEZ. Softly, madonna! She is fair and young, I'm very rich, and young enough in conscience. VICTORIA (rising). Let's hear no more on't— LOPEZ (rising with difficulty). No? Why not, I pray? Ten thousand crowns a year! I'll prove it to you. VICTORIA. There's no occasion. LOPEZ. Marry but there is. Who waits there, ho! Enter Page. Go to my chamber, sirrah! You'll find a cedar casket. Bring it hither. (Exit Page. Doubt my veracity? I'll prove to you What my pretensions are to woo your niece— I'll shew you such a catalogue of wealth— Plague on this potent sack! It 'gins to mount And whiz within my brain— (He staggers to the sofa, and throws himself on it. Why stays the knave? Enter Page. Aye—that's the casket—give it me—begone! [Exit Page. Which is the key?—Confound this awkward lock!— I've open'd it at last—now let me see— [He turns over the papers. Enter Margaretta. MARGARETTA (to Victoria). All is prepar'd— LOPEZ. That's not it—no, nor this— Let's see the next—Umph! umph! what ails mine eyes? The letters dance before 'em, up and down, This way and that—I'm surely very drunk! [He drops asleep, and lets the box and papers fall. MARGARETTA. Look, madam, if he be not fall'n asleep, And half his papers on the ground.—What's this? [She picks them up. “My cash account”—and this—“State of the monies “Sent over by Montalban from Peru.” If I were you, I'd look them over, madam. VICTORIA. Just now my mind is too much occupied; Meantime replace them safely in the casket, And lodge it in my chamber. Send some hither To bear away this drunken profligate. [Exeunt severally. Enter Roderigo and Servants. RODERIGO. How's this? Asleep, my hero of the cellar? Knock'd up already? Thou'rt a special fellow! SERVANT (shaking him). He has't, i'faith! RODERIGO. Aye, he has got his dose; That cask of malmsey did his bus'ness for him. But come, my lads, we must not leave him here. SERVANT. He is so fat and heavy, we can't stir him. RODERIGO. Then take him couch and all. No matter where You trundle him. 'Tis all the same to him. [Exeunt with Lopez. END OF ACT III.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT IV. SCENE I. A magnificent Saloon. Montalban discovered, superbly drest, lying on a couch, Guzman, Margaretta, and Attendants, standing by him. MARGARETTA. So, all is ready now.—How long d'you think 'Twill be ere he awaken? GUZMAN. 'Twill be soon. Conformably with all the rules laid down By the most learned writers on narcotics, When the complexion freshens, as his does, The patient soon revives.—Nay see, he moves. MARGARETTA. Each to his post! It is my lady's will That none be present when he first regains His recollection.—Now let music sound. [Exeunt Margaretta, Guzman, and Attendants. Soft music from above the stage. MONTALBAN. Heigh-ho! What time o'th'day is't, good Teresa?— What heav'nly sounds were those?—(He starts up.)—Ha! What means this? Where am I?—Surely 'tis enchantment all! These rich habiliments—my humble cot Chang'd to a sumptuous palace—Can this be Reality?—No, no! 'Tis witchcraft all, Or else some fev'rish dream, which taints my fancy With vain and unsubstantial images. It must be so. I'll lay me down again, And sleep myself once more into my senses. [He lies down. Voice from above sings. Life is short, and so are pleasures; Use them wisely as they flow: Take thy share of fortune's treasures, But ask not more than thou may'st know. MONTALBAN (starting up). This is prodigious! Who thus answers me As 'twere from th'clouds?—Was this delusion too? I do begin to think I am awake, And all I see and hear realities. [A voice from above sings. Happy stranger, now prepare To behold our sov'reign fair. Turn thee, stranger, turn and see Where she comes to welcome thee. Enter Victoria, richly dressed and veiled. MONTALBAN. Who's that? The goddess of these fairy regions? How graceful and how dignified her air! She bows to me. I'll venture to address her.— Forgive me, lady, if I dare to pay That homage which thine excellence demands. VICTORIA. I ask no homage, sir: to a mere woman, A weak one too, that term is misapplied. MONTALBAN. What less is due to one, who has the art Of working miracles? Have I my senses, Or are they by some incantation charm'd, To make me credit things, surpassing all That poets ere devis'd, or madmen dream'd? VICTORIA. There's no enchantment, sir, in what you see. When you shall know me better, you'll confess I am not one likely to deal in spells. MONTALBAN. Then it is true that I indeed was wreck'd, Laid in an humble cottage— VICTORIA. 'Tis most true. MONTALBAN. How then was I brought here? VICTORIA. By my command. MONTALBAN. And why? VICTORIA. I fear, were I to state my motive, You might conceive, as yet you know me not, I had outstept my sex's rigid rules, And hastily condemn me. MONTALBAN. Fear not that. I owe you far too much, lightly to censure. VICTORIA. 'Tis in your pow'r to owe me yet much more, If you object not to my terms. MONTALBAN. What are they? VICTORIA. I ask not wealth, for I've already more Than I desire or want; more ample pow'r Than that I now possess would not avail me: Were I to wish for rank more dignified, I should resemble one, who on the brow Of a tall mountain stands, and looks in vain For objects more exalted than himself. MONTALBAN. What more can you desire? VICTORIA. What avail these, And all the blessings rank and wealth can bring, If there be no responsive heart to share them? MONTALBAN. Have you then fail'd to meet with such a heart? VICTORIA. Alas! the fated hour was not yet come, When to its destin'd victor mine should stoop, And own itself subdued. MONTALBAN. Are you then form'd Of substance so insensible? VICTORIA. Ah no! I'm but too feeble. Were I to disclose My secret thoughts—Grant me your fair construction— Think you, were I to offer to a man, Reduc'd by fortune to distress and ruin, My wealth, my wide possessions and myself, I might not hope to meet a fair return? MONTALBAN. What man would hesitate to meet such proffer, And dedicate each moment of his life To prove his gratitude? VICTORIA. If so you think, Tell me, sir, ought he to compel the woman, To whose affection he is so indebted, To make the first advances, to forego The delicacy of her sex and station, And make avowal of those feelings, which Her fond confusion but too plainly speaks? Say, sir, would you be so insensible? MONTALBAN. I, madam? VICTORIA. Yes, sir, you. MONTALBAN. Madam, I know not. How my opinion—If the gentleman Should feel a similar affection, I should suppose— VICTORIA. Nay, sir, I pray you answer My question plainly. Make the case your own. What would you do? MONTALBAN. I really cannot say— Were there no pow'rful motive to prevent him, A gallant gentleman would doubtless spare A woman's blushes— VICTORIA. If you think so, sir, Why does your conduct—I implore your pardon— Your pity—I'm not us'd to sue— MONTALBAN. Good heav'n! What mean you, madam? VICTORIA. If you will compel me T'avow my weakness—know—'tis you who've won me! Nay, start not, sir, but hear me out I pray. I need not tell you how, when first I saw you, My stubborn heart receiv'd a fond impression. How strong it was, my conduct now may prove. If, hearing my confession, you can meet it With mutual love, myself, my all, are yours. MONTALBAN. Your frankness, lady, justifies my own. I know the value of the gift you offer, But I am wanting in a fit return. VICTORIA. All the return I ask for is your heart. MONTALBAN. Mine, were it free, were little worth your having; But, such as 'tis, 'twas long ago bestow'd On one, who gave me in return her own. VICTORIA. And if she did, what right has she to expect Thus to monopolize affection? No! Such fancies are romantic. Ev'ry day Bears witness to new vows of constancy, Which on the morrow vanish into air. Man's constancy! 'Tis grown into a proverb. MONTALBAN. I pray you, lady, pardon me; I wish Not to repeat what may appear discourteous. VICTORIA. If I've a rival then, tell me who is The happy fair who has engross'd your heart? MONTALBAN. That is a secret, deeply buried here. I cannot name her. VICTORIA. That's suspicious, sir. I doubt your constancy is fix'd on one, Who does but little honour to your choice. MONTALBAN. Such doubts are no impeachment of her worth. I do her justice. VICTORIA. Be she what she may, The vows you speak of now no more are binding. She's absent, lost to you— MONTALBAN. Aye, lost indeed! VICTORIA. Then are you free, then may you form new ties, And all my flatt'ring hopes may be fulfill'd. Think what a sacrifice I make—reflect— MONTALBAN. Lady, 'twould better suit you to reflect. You ask a heart—a heart which is not mine. Were I a villain, I might proffer it; But truth and honour dictate my refusal. VICTORIA (aside). What noble constancy! Were I but certain I were its object—I must leave him now, Ere my impetuous feelings master me, And prove it by a second trial.—(To Montalban)—Sir, If I have gone beyond the privilege Which custom grants my sex, I crave forgiveness. Reflect on what I've said. Such proffers may Deserve your serious thought. Meantime, I pray, Consider these apartments as your own, And those belonging to them as your servants. There is an ample garden 'neath the ramparts, Where you may take the air. When next we meet, I trust my suit will prove more welcome to you. [Exit Victoria. MONTALBAN. Th' unrav'ling of this myst'ry is yet stranger Than its commencement. Did I hear her rightly? An offer of herself? She seems most lovely— Of all her wealth? And she has princely riches— Rank, honours, dignities? They're tempting baits, All purchasable by the simple gift Of my poor heart and hand. A word will do it— But then that word for ever brands me villain. No, poverty! I will not thus exchange thee; Thou'rt honest, and I'll hug thee to my heart, 'Till I can give thee up without a blush. But hold—did not my tempter name a garden? It may afford me means t' escape—Who'rt thou? Enter Roderigo. RODERIGO. I'm one—(aside)—Beshrew me! but he bears it bravely; He looks as if that garb were nat'ral to him— (To Montalban) I'm one to whom the lady of this castle Hath giv'n commission to attend on you. MONTALBAN. 'Tis more than I require. But hark thee, friend, What is thy bounteous lady's name? RODERIGO. Her name? Did she not tell thee? MONTALBAN. No. RODERIGO. Not tell it?—(aside)—Humph! I smell the matter now.—(To Montalban).—As for her name, I'm but a servant, sir, and may not choose To go beyond mine orders. I'm grown grey, As you may see, good sir, in servitude, And, in the course of a laborious life, I have made one discov'ry. MONTALBAN. What is that? RODERIGO. That, when my lady for peculiar reasons Keeps a thing secret, I've no right to blab. MONTALBAN. But why, when thus she brings me to her house, And prodigally show'rs down bounties on me, Should she conceal herself? RODERIGO. Nay, that I know not. She uses her own pleasure. But time passes, And, what is worse, while we are thus discoursing, Your dinner cools. MONTALBAN. I have no appetite. RODERIGO. That's strange—I should have thought the keen sea air And your cold bath would rather have increas'd it. There's a repast within might tempt a hermit. MONTALBAN. It tempts not me. I rather would prefer To walk abroad, and view the various beauties Which lie around this sumptuous edifice. Your lady, sir, made mention of a garden. Pray which way lies it? RODERIGO. There, beneath the ramparts. The readiest way to it is through the hall, Where your repast awaits you. I'll conduct you. MONTALBAN. Be it so then. I'll follow you. RODERIGO. That's well. Take an old foolish man's advice for once, And, when good fortune courts you, do not scruple To enjoy her favours.—This way, please you, sir. [Exeunt. SCENE II. Another Apartment in De Silva Castle. Enter Ferdinand. FERDINAND. Thank heav'n! a short reflection has convinc'd me How nearly to the verge of shame and ruin My too presumptuous hopes had tempted me. The vain illusion which obscur'd my judgment Is vanish'd, and I once more am myself. But I am weak—I blush to think how weak, How little able to oppose the tide Of mast'ring passion. I must place a bar Betwixt the dear temptation and myself. Farewell, my Clara! I will fly those charms, Whose potency my heart cannot resist. Farewell for ever! Honour calls me from thee; My sword shall be my fortune; I will use it Against my country's foes, and either reap A harvest of renown, or nobly die! Enter Guzman. GUZMAN. Heyday! who talks of dying when I'm here? What, Signor Ferdinand! Bless me, good sir, What is the matter? Why you look as pale— FERDINAND. Away! no trifling now. I'm not dispos'd To relish your buffoonery. GUZMAN. How's that? Leave you alone? I'll tell you what, young sir, I know not what you're pleas'd to think of me, But this I know—there is not in Madrid A pharmacopolist or surgeon, sir, To whom I'd vail my bonnet. I have learnt— FERDINAND. It may be so; but there is one thing more It might behove you still to learn. GUZMAN. What's that? FERDINAND. Discretion, sir, to know on whom and when You may unbidden thus intrude yourself. I choose to be alone.—What! more intruders! Enter Don Lopez. LOPEZ (yawning). Yaw! How my head's confus'd! That sack was naught, Most villainously naught! I know not how I was o'ertaken thus.—Whom have we here? What, my young fighting sir?—I do remember We had a tilting bout, but we're friends now. Where is my lady, and my pretty Clara, My bride that is to be? FERDINAND. Clara your bride? LOPEZ. Why not? There's nought so wonderful, methinks, That a young sanguine fellow, like myself, Should like a pretty girl. I warrant me, We shall become a mighty happy couple. Do you know, I'm monstrously in love with her? FERDINAND. Monstrous indeed! Lambs may consort with wolves, And doves associate with the felon hawk, Ere she unite with thee! LOPEZ. Phew! here's a noise! I'll tell you what, young man—when I'm resolv'd, 'Tis not your pleasure, nor your big looks neither Shall fright me from my purpose. Here, sir, here— (Striking his pocket. I carry arguments you can't confute— Crowns, sir, pistoles, and good doubloons to boot, Of wond'rous efficacy to remove Obstructions— GUZMAN. Not so good as my elixir! Talk of obstructions! Pshaw! Why now, sir, (to Lopez) you Shall judge of it yourself. I'm glad I thought on't; 'Twill suit you to a hair.—(To Ferdinand) There, do you see him? What a swoln belly, and two legs like millposts! No subject can be more unpromising; And yet, sir, I will lay you ten to one, In half a dozen doses I'll bring down That tun of his, in half a dozen more Make him as lank and limber as a greyhound— LOPEZ. Why, thou half-witted puppy! Who art thou That dares thus prate of me? Elixir truly!— Physic my lady's lap-dog, an thou wil'st, He may be sweeter for't.—Look on me, mongrel! Survey this portly body. 'Tis well lin'd With solid and substantial food. These legs, too, Are firm and muscular, proportion'd columns Well fitted to support such superstructure. Why, I am made for immortality; My very blood's a distillation From gen'rous sack and fragrant malvoisie. Away, thou quack! thou mingler of base drugs! Thou lank anatomy! Enter Margaretta. MARGARETTA. What's here to do? I wonder, sir, you take upon you thus— LOPEZ. Nay, good madonna, I am not to blame. This scurvy med'cine-monger took upon him— GUZMAN. Aye, aye, deny it; but I'll say't again— LOPEZ. Let me come at him! I will teach you manners! GUZMAN. Aye, you may bluster— LOPEZ. An I catch thee, sirrah! GUZMAN (dodging about, pursued by Lopez). Pray stand between us—If I had thee once Fairly in hand, I'd work thee into shape— I'd ply thee with elixirs, lotions, potions— Pray keep him off—Cathartics— LOPEZ. By Saint Anthony! I'll maul thee—I've no breath to follow him— GUZMAN. Thou'rt one disease from head to foot—a mountain Of bodily infirmity—a mass— LOPEZ. Let me get at him— MARGARETTA. (She pushes Guzman out.) Nay you shall retire. And you, Don Lopez, too— LOPEZ. A paltry knave! An I lay hold of him— MARGARETTA. Prithee be calm, And get yourself accoutred as befits you. My lady and her niece would think it strange To see you thus. LOPEZ. Why truly, as thou say'st, My raiment is rather in deshabille. I'll to my chamber and refresh it.—Gomez! To physic me indeed!—What, Gomez, ho! [Exit Lopez. FERDINAND. Tell me, good Marg'ret, what did the wretch mean By talking about Clara as his bride? An old debauch'd voluptuary like him To form such expectation! MARGARETTA. He has broach'd it However to my lady. FERDINAND. Well, what said she? MARGARETTA. Nay, look not so alarm'd. One might suppose You had more int'rest in the question than You care to avow. FERDINAND. An int'rest? Aye, the strongest, In what relates so mainly to her welfare. You cannot think it strange. MARGARETTA. Oh no! quite natural. I warrant me, she'd feel the same for you, Were any antiquated dame to court you. Ah Ferdinand! if you would keep a secret, Learn to command your looks, and teach your eyes A little stricter discipline. FERDINAND. Indeed You go too far—Nay, prithee, jeer me not. If a presumptuous hope e'er glanc'd across me— MARGARETTA. You welcom'd it.—You see I've made remarks. Well, things may turn out other than you look for. FERDINAND. What mean you? MARGARETTA. What I'm not at leisure now To tell you more of. I expect my lady, Who has some orders for me. But I've giv'n you Food for reflection. FERDINAND. If I might presume To entertain such hopes— MARGARETTA. Nay, if you will not Believe me when I bid you entertain them— FERDINAND. I know you for my friend, and will believe you. MARGARETTA. That's well.—But go—I hear my lady coming— Go—say no more. [Exit Ferdinand. Enter Victoria. VICTORIA. Is ev'ry thing prepar'd As I directed? Roderigo tells me Montalban is about to walk abroad, And, from his manner and some words he utter'd, Conjectures 'tis his purpose to escape. We have no time to lose. Set Roderigo And Guzman on the watch; let them take heed He do not scale the wall. As for the gates, They are securely fastened. MARGARETTA. Had you done As I advis'd you, and reveal'd yourself When you was with him, you had 'scap'd this trouble. VICTORIA. While there remains a doubt of his affection, He ne'er shall know me. 'Tis his heart I aim at; If that prove true, my pains are well bestow'd. MARGARETTA. What more can you devise to ascertain it? VICTORIA. Love has a thousand ways to work his ends. Here is an engine which he bids me use— [Giving her a portrait case. Take it—Upon the spreading orange tree, Which overhangs the fountain, place it so He may not fail to see it. Make good haste. [Exit Margaretta. Now comes th'eventful crisis of my fate. Aid me, kind heav'n, and arm my lab'ring heart With fortitude the trial to sustain On which my bliss or mis'ry must depend! [Exit. END OF ACT IV.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT V. SCENE I. Night. A Garden, illuminated with Lamps interspersed among the Trees. On one Side, a Fountain overhung by an Orange Tree, on the other, a Wall and Gate. Enter Roderigo, Guzman, and Margaretta. MARGARETTA. I tell you both, such are my lady's orders. As she suspects the stranger may attempt This way to escape, she wills you here to watch, And, if he try to pass, to bar his way. RODERIGO. Truly there seems no need of these precautions. A fellow brought from rags and misery, Cloath'd like a lord, and treated like a prince, Will never run away from such good quarters. MARGARETTA. Be that as't may, my lady's orders are That you keep guard. So see you do it well. GUZMAN. But, Mrs Marg'ret, surely our good lady Has not reflected on the consequences Which may ensue, if thus we stand expos'd To the cold dews and noxious exhalations, Which at this time of the year, are so injurious To tender constitutions, such as mine. (Coughs) I do protest I've caught a cold already. RODERIGO. If that be all, the mischief is not great. GUZMAN. Not great? How can you say so, Roderigo? I've known such instances of bad effects Arising from a cold, it would amaze you. I'll tell you a remarkable occurrence. I had a patient once— RODERIGO. A patient, say'st thou? Now tell me honestly. Did'st talk to him? GUZMAN. Aye marry did I. RODERIGO. And he still was patient? GUZMAN. Pa—patient—Oh! that's very good indeed! Well, you're a wag. MARGARETTA. You know my lady's pleasure, And will be watchful. [Exit Margaretta. GUZMAN. Would I had bethought me, As a preservative against these dews, To bring with me a bottle— RODERIGO. Would thou had'st, Full of rich malmsey— GUZMAN. What d'you talk of malmsey? I mean my cordial water. You have heard Of Signor Guzman's cordial water, which Is universally confess'd to be The only sov'reign remedy 'gainst catarrhs, Obstructions and defluxions? 'Tis distill'd From certain simples— RODERIGO. So I should suppose, If you're the manufacturer. GUZMAN. Hey? How? The manufacturer? Oh ho! that's good. You had me there, I own. RODERIGO. Nay, worse than that— I have you here. GUZMAN. Good, very good again! There's no escaping you. RODERIGO. That's my complaint. Would I could remedy it!—But silence—look— Who's that approaching? GUZMAN. Where? RODERIGO. Among the trees— GUZMAN. 'Tis he whom we must watch. RODERIGO. Then to your post. (They stand aside. Enter Montalban. MONTALBAN. I lose myself amid this labyrinth. Here seems an op'ning—Ha! a gate and wall? Should but the gate be open—Let me try— No, strongly fasten'd—But what have we here? (Perceives the picture-case hanging on the tree. It seems as if inviting me to look At it's contents. (Opens it) Good heav'n! What is't I see? Have I my senses?—Can it—Yes!—'Tis she! 'Tis my Victoria's self! just as she was, When to my arms she came a virgin bride, Array'd in native loveliness! This is a prize Beyond my fondest hope.—How came it here?— No matter how it came—It now is mine; I'll lodge it next my heart, and keep it as A talisman to guide me to herself. Now for the wall—Let me but scale it once— (As he is mounting the wall, he is seized by Roderigo and Guzman. RODERIGO. Who passes there? MONTALBAN. Confusion!—Who are you Who thus presume— RODERIGO. We have authority. My lady gave us orders. That's enough. GUZMAN. Aye, 'tis her own prescription. MONTALBAN. Give me way! What right has she or you to keep me here? RODERIGO. You'd better ask that question of herself, For lo! this way she comes. Enter Victoria, veiled. VICTORIA. So, sir, 'tis well; I find you are an honourable man, Who may be trusted out on your parole. (To Roderigo and Guzman) —You've done your duty, and may now retire. [Exeunt Roderigo and Guzman. Is't thus you treat me, sir? Was't not enough To meet with proud disdain my proffer'd love, That thus with scorn augmented you attempt To punish me for over-confidence? Where can you go, ungrateful as you are, Where love like mine, unfetter'd, unrestrain'd, Courts your acceptance, and at once presents, In lieu of poverty, neglect and ruin, All you can hope of beauty, wealth and pow'r? MONTALBAN. True, madam; poverty, neglect and ruin Have long been my companions: but were fate To double ev'ry sorrow I've sustain'd, And leave me yet more destitute of hope, I'd still possess one treasure—conscious honour. VICTORIA. Keep it inviolate; but do me justice. Whate'er opinion, sir, my recent conduct May have induc'd you to conceive of me, I am not one of those, whom madd'ning passion Can tempt beyond the rigid line of virtue: But fortune has enabled me to choose The path best suited to my inclination; And, though the world fastidiously may deem The course I take unsuited to my sex, I scorn a law which man, not heav'n, ordain'd— MONTALBAN. No more, I pray. How can you thus forget The noblest attribute of female worth, That native delicacy, which adorns And dignifies your sex, thus to descend To gain a heart devoted to another? Had it but for a moment swerv'd from her, This treasure, which kind providence has sent me, Had kept me faithful to her. (Shewing the portrait.) Look upon it— As in a mirror trace the virtues there, The candour, gentleness, and innocence, Which won my heart, and follow her example. VICTORIA. When this was drawn, she was in youth's first bloom, Years had not trac'd their wrinkles on her brow, Nor care had faded those resplendent tints. Were you to meet her now— MONTALBAN. She'd still be lovely, Still more by ev'ry tie endear'd to me! Age would but purify her spotless soul, And ev'ry vestige of corroding care Would prove a fond memorial of affection. VICTORIA. Have wealth and splendour then no charms t'allure you? Has poverty no terrors? MONTALBAN. Not with her! Were our poor dwelling some half ruin'd cot, Whose mould'ring walls could scarce withstand the force Of the sharp-piercing wind and beating rain, Our food the scanty sustenance we drew From the cold ling'ring hand of charity, With her 'twere princely luxury to share it. VICTORIA. You speak as if a woman's constancy Were proof 'gainst absence. Do you think that one So fair, so young, as this resemblance shews her, Has not been tempted? And, if tempted, think you She has been able to maintain her faith? MONTALBAN. If innate purity and worth can warrant A woman's faith, I am assur'd of her's. That doubt, thank heav'n! never disturb'd my peace. But, had she been forgetful of her vows, Inconstant, false, lost to herself and me, Though I had wept her fall, the dear remembrance Of what she was had still preserv'd me her's. VICTORIA. No more, no more! My doubts are at an end! Henceforth we'll live to joy!—Gen'rous Montalban!— Enter Gomez, pursued by Don Lopez. GOMEZ. Help, help, good christians!—Will you murder me? LOPEZ. Give me my box, thou scapegrace! give it me! GOMEZ. I know nought of your box—'tis in your chamber. LOPEZ. What! rob me in my sleep?—Surrender it, Or by Saint Anthony— VICTORIA. What mean you, sir? Have you your senses? LOPEZ. Heyday! Who art thou, Thus dizen'd out with a convenient veil? No matter, so thou'lt help me to lay hold of That pilf'ring varlet—Let him not get by thee— VICTORIA. What has he done? LOPEZ. He has robb'd me of a casket Worth a king's ransom. GOMEZ. As I hope for mercy I touch'd it not. He was stark drunk e'en now, And is'nt sober yet. LOPEZ. I'll hamper thee— Thou sha'n't escape me.—(To Victoria)—Hark thee—thou art nimble— Run to the castle, send some quickly hither To apprehend the rogue. Meantime I'll watch him. Nay, prithee, do not linger—I'll reward thee. VICTORIA (aside). This turn is fortunate.—(To Lopez) Well, sir, I'll go. Stay here, and keep him safely. I'll send some Who'll do your bus'ness. LOPEZ. That is kind. But hasten. [Exit Victoria. MONTALBAN (aside). Can I believe mine eyes? 'Tis he himself! LOPEZ (seizing Gomez). Oh! have I caught thee, varlet? Now confess. I'll put thee to the question. (Draws his sword. GOMEZ (kneeling). Pray thy mercy! Put up thy sword—I cannot bear to look on't— As I'm an honest man I took it not. LOPEZ. Honest, forsooth! Aye, 'tis a pretty proof Of honesty, to take another's goods. Wer't thou not trusted with it? Tell me, caitiff, What can a breach of trust deserve, but hanging? MONTALBAN (advancing). Aye, what indeed? Look on me. LOPEZ (dropping his sword). How! Montalban! MONTALBAN. What makes thee tremble so? Hath conscious guilt Robb'd thee of utt'rance? Speak to me, confess Where is mine injur'd wife, where hast thou lodg'd The treasures, which I credulously trusted To thy perfidious care? LOPEZ (aside). So, so! he knows not Whose house this is! MONTALBAN. Wilt thou not answer me? I'll make thee find thy speech. LOPEZ. I'm so amaz'd To meet thee on a sudden, when I thought— How cam'st thou here? MONTALBAN. This morning I was wreck'd On the adjoining shore. I was alone Preserv'd— LOPEZ. Did'st thou save nothing? MONTALBAN. Not a doit. But cease this questioning, and answer plainly To what I ask. LOPEZ (aside). Let's see—Shipwreck'd, dost say? Lost ev'ry thing?—'Tis well—I know my cue. (To Montalban) —Aye, aye, I'll answer thee.—Why such assurance Surpasses all conception! Thou, Montalban? My dearest friend, my worthiest benefactor? Thou'rt an impostor! MONTALBAN. Dar'st thou face me down— LOPEZ. Aye, marry, thou shalt find I dare. Go to! Did I not know Montalban? GOMEZ. So did I; And, if I trust my eyesight, there he stands. LOPEZ. Away, thou base companion! GOMEZ. No, I won't— A figo for thee! I'll believe my senses. (To Montalban) —Doth not your worship call to mind one Gomez, Who once at Lagos was your faithful servant? MONTALBAN. Full well do I remember thee. GOMEZ. I said so! Well, what have you to say, Don Gongora? I'm valiant, now I've got a friend to back me. LOPEZ. An I lay hold of thee— Enter Ferdinand. FERDINAND. What's here to do? Is this a brothel or a carrier's inn, That thus ye clamour?—Who are ye? Don Lopez! LOPEZ. I'm glad you're come. I have been robb'd, sir, robb'd, And might have been assassinated too, Had you not succour'd me. FERDINAND. Been robb'd of what? LOPEZ. A casket, sir, more precious than my life. There stand the culprits. GOMEZ. Pray, your honour, hear me. 'Tis a false charge. I'm his own servant, sir. FERDINAND. That makes the matter worse, if it be true. LOPEZ. Aye, so it does, young gentleman.—A word— Examine them apart. While they're together You'll ne'er get at the truth. Begin with him, My varlet there. Trust t'other rogue to me, I'll give a good account of him, I warrant. Enter Roderigo and Guzman. RODERIGO. Is there one here who calls himself Montalban? MONTALBAN. That is my name. RODERIGO. Then am I order'd, sir, To put this precious casket in your hands. LOPEZ. 'Tis mine! I'll have it! RODERIGO (to Lopez). Keep your distance, sir. (To Montalban) Take it, and keep it, sir; 'tis fairly yours. It holds a statement of your dealings with him. MONTALBAN. This is indeed most wonderful. LOPEZ. 'Tis false! Merely a base contrivance to defraud me. (To Ferdinand) Don't let 'em, worthy sir, impose on you. This fellow, sir, is a confederate. RODERIGO. I'll shew you what I am. I've something more To say to you. You are my pris'ner, sir. You have offended 'gainst our Spanish laws. That casket holds a proof of breach of trust, For which you'll answer in another place. LOPEZ. Hush, hush, I pray thee. Do not speak so loud. Thou art an honest fellow, Roderigo; I know thou'st sense enough to understand me. I'll give thee fifty ducats to release me. RODERIGO. What's that you say? LOPEZ. I'll make 'em up an hundred— Two hundred—wo'n't that do?—Three—four—five hundred— RODERIGO. Would'st make 'em up five millions, I'd not take 'em. Dost think to bribe me? GOMEZ. So! the tide is turn'd. Who's the rogue now? Who's turn is't to be hang'd? GUZMAN. There seems indeed to be a strange revulsion. 'Tis a most sudden crisis, which denotes A speedy termination of your case. There is but one prescription now remaining— A quantum sufficit of hemp. Probatum est. LOPEZ. (To Roderigo) Help me to kneel, I pray thee.—(To Montalban)—I confess I have offended. Be not too severe— Consider I'm a poor old man, bow'd down With much infirmity. I will restore All I possess of thine with interest— 'Tis all thou can'st require. What can it profit To hang a miserable wretch like me? MONTALBAN. Thy meanness now exceeds thy former guilt. Let that of which thou wrong'd'st me be restor'd, And live disgrac'd. There are some other matters, Of infinite importance to my peace— LOPEZ. I'll tell thee ev'ry thing. MONTALBAN. Look thou dost so. But they're too delicate to be discuss'd Unless in private. Hence! I'll see thee soon. I pray you, gentlemen, let him be guarded 'Till he perform his promise. LOPEZ (to Roderigo). Help me up! I'm now, it seems, to learn a new vocation, That of refunding. 'Tis a bitter pill, Hard of digestion. Humph!—Well, after all, I have enough remaining to console me! [Exeunt Lopez, Roderigo, Guzman, and Gomez. FERDINAND. See that you keep him safely.—What a compound Of insolence and meanness!—(To Montalban)—But for you, sir, If, when I knew not of your quality, I paid you less respect than was your due, I hope to have your pardon. MONTALBAN. Nay, good sir, You acted like a noble gentleman. But hold—I surely cannot be mistaken— Are you not?—Yes—you are my brave preserver, Whose gen'rous kindness sav'd me from the waves. FERDINAND. Sav'd you, sir? Are you then the shipwreck'd man, Whom heav'n permitted me to save? In truth, I knew you not again. MONTALBAN. I marvel not; I am so chang'd, I hardly know myself. But the strong likeness, which you bear to one Whose dear remembrance rests upon my heart, Insures my recollection. May I ask Who were the parents bless'd by such a son? FERDINAND. I'm a poor orphan, one who never knew A parent's tenderness. On the wide world, Without a friend to cherish or support me, I had been cast, had not the noble lady, Who owns this castle, pitied and sustain'd me. She, like my guardian angel, rescued me From want and mis'ry; her indulgent care Rear'd me to manhood, taught me to become Such as I am— MONTALBAN. Such goodness might atone For frailties greater far than those she owns. Enter Victoria veiled, and Clara. (To Victoria) Lady, we spoke of you and of your virtues. This worthy youth, whose feeling heart o'erflows With gratitude, hath told me what he owes you. Heav'n, that delights in works of charity, Will show'r its amplest blessings on your head. VICTORIA. Next to th' approval of my heart, your praise Is grateful to my feelings. Nay, believe me. Whate'er of my past conduct you may deem, The moment's come, when, all disguise thrown off, In my true character I shew myself. If, to repay the mis'ries I've sustain'd, Heav'n yet has blessings in reserve for me, 'Tis by thy hand alone it can bestow them. I've tried thee, I have prov'd thee, my Montalban! Thou'rt true to love and thy Victoria, And thus (unveiling) I hold thee to my heart! MONTALBAN. Thou art, Thou art mine own Victoria! Yes, I hold thee To my fond heart which beats alone for thee! My lov'd, my long lost wife! thus once again To view thee—Heav'nly pow'rs! it is too much For my enfeebled senses to sustain! Oh my best love, give me a moment, least My throbbing breast burst with excess of joy Too exquisite for man! VICTORIA. Oh! let these arms Support thee, let thy too long widow'd wife Hail the return of peace and happiness! And yet I dread—Dearest Montalban! can you— Can you forgive me for the stratagem I plann'd to try your truth? MONTALBAN. I can't forgive, Where there's no cause for blame. Joy, gratitude And endless love now occupy my soul, Scarce leaving me remembrance of the past. VICTORIA. Come, Ferdinand, and you, my dearest Clara, Behold my long lamented lord restor'd To happiness. MONTALBAN. They seem as if kind nature Had form'd them for each other. VICTORIA. True—Nay, Clara, You need not blush. You know you have confess'd— CLARA. Dear madam, surely you don't mean to tell him— VICTORIA. Are you asham'd, my love, to own the truth? CLARA. Asham'd, ma'am? No—but I feel so confus'd— It is so awkward all at once, you know— VICTORIA. Take courage, dearest—I have seen your love, From your first infancy have trac'd its course, And in the prospect of your future bliss Found the sole consolation of my cares. FERDINAND. Do you then sanction my presumptuous hopes? VICTORIA. I do most fully. FERDINAND. Oh for words to speak The feelings of my soul!—And you, my Clara, Will you confirm my transports? CLARA. Can you doubt If Clara's heart be your's?—There is my pledge— (Gives her hand. FERDINAND. For ever be it sacred!—(To Victoria) My best friend! My gen'rous patroness! VICTORIA. Postpone your thanks. One sacred duty yet must be fulfill'd Ere she can be your bride: for know, young man, I have a solemn vow, witness'd in heav'n, That she in holy church shall ne'er be your's, Until your union shall be ratified By him, whose judgment should decide your fate. FERDINAND. Who is this unknown arbiter? VICTORIA. Your father! FERDINAND. My father!—Who—where is he? VICTORIA (pointing to Montalban). There, behold him! FERDINAND (kneeling). My father! MONTALBAN. Thou? Art thou indeed my son? Come to thy father's arms, and take his blessing! Was I for this preserv'd? Mysterious heav'n! 'Twas thine all-working providence that led him To snatch his father from a wat'ry grave, And crown him with excess of happiness! FERDINAND. Extatic thought! To save a parent's life, To hear him call me his deliverer, To have his blessing—(to Victoria) Oh my more than mother, Speak to me—sooth the transports of my soul Rack'd with excess of joy! (Kneels to her.) VICTORIA. Rise, my best lov'd, My gallant Ferdinand! and turn to him, Whose sanction must confirm your cherish'd hope Of happiness.—(To Montalban) I have impos'd upon you A pleasing duty— MONTALBAN. Gladly I fulfil it. Thus let me join the hands of those, whose hearts Love has united. Now let pleasure reign, Be ev'ry face around us grac'd with smiles To crown the transports of this happy day! [Exeunt Omnes. THE END.</field>
   </doc>
</add>