<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Studley, John, 1545-1590</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Studley, John, 1545-1590</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">studley john 1545 1590</field>
      <field name="author_text">Studley, John, 1545-1590</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">16th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V1.0954.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1581</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:459584</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Seventh Tragedye of L. Annaevs Seneca, Entituled Medea</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- Early modern and Elizabethan, 1500-1600</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- Early modern and Elizabethan, 1500-1600</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Seventh Tragedye of L. Annaevs Seneca, Entituled Medea</field>
      <field name="title_facet">seventh tragedye of l annaevs seneca entituled medea</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">seventh tragedye of l annaevs seneca entituled medea</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Seventh Tragedye of L. Annaevs Seneca, Entituled Medea</field>
      <field name="year_display">1581</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1581</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1581</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459584&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459584&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Studley, John, 1545?-1590?&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;studley john 1545 1590 &lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Seventh Tragedye of L. Annaevs Seneca, Entituled Medea&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;seventh tragedye of l annaevs seneca, entituled medea&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1581&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1581&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Studley, John&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1545&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1590&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Seventh Tragedye of L. Annaevs Seneca, Entituled Medea&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Imprinted ... by Thomas Marshe&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1581&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872065-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv10954&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- Early modern and Elizabethan, 1500-1600&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;Early modern and Elizabethan, 1500-1600&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Seventh Tragedye of L. Annaevs Seneca, Entituled Medea&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 137 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Only verse drama included&lt;lb/&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;lb/&gt;Epigraph and dedication included with Hercules Furens&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Medea.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1566.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 1566.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE SEVENTH TRAGEDYE OF L. ANNAEVS SENECA, Entituled MEDEA: Translated out of Latin into Englishe, by IOHN STVDLEY.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Argument. To the Tragedy, by the Translator. Care fore did grype Medeas heart to see Her Iason, whom shee tendred as her lyfe, And rescued had from plunge of perills free, Renouncing her, to take another wyfe. Loue spent in vayne breedes hate &amp; malice rife Enkindling coales, whose heate and greedy flame (Saue streames of bloud,) nought els can quench the same. Medea mad in troubled mynde doth muse, On vengeaunce fell, to quit her grieuous wrong. Rough plagues at length entendeth shee to vse: Yll venemous thinges shee charmes, with charming song Seekes out a Bane made of their poyson strong, In Trayterous gifts a Robe, and chayne of Golde, Nycely shee doth the hidden poyson folde. Sent are the Gyfts to Creuse and her Syre, They taking them that brought their dole to passe, Vnware are burnt by meanes of charmed fyre, Due vengeaunce yet for Iason greater was, Lyfe first on chylde by Mothers hande (alas) Expired hath, which though it him aggryse, Yet his other chylde shee slayes before his eyes.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Speakers names. MEDEA. CHORVS. NVTRIX. CREON. IASON. NVNTIVS.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE FIRST ACTE. Medea, O Gods whose grace doth guide their ghostes that ioy in wedlocke pure, O Iuno thou Lucina hight, on whom the chary cure Alotted is of those, that grone in paynfull chyldbed bandes, O Pallas by whose heauenly arte, Sir Typhis cunning handes Haue learnde to bridle with his helme his newly framed boate, Where with the force of fighting fluds hee breaking rides a floate. O God whose forked Mace doth stormes in rigour rough appeas, And cause the ruffling surges couch amid the rampinge Seas: O Titan who vpon the swift and werling Hemisphær Deuides the chearefull day and night by egall turnes t'appere, O threefolde shapen Hecate that sendest forth thy light, Unto thy silent Sacrifice that offered is by night, By whom my Iason sware to mee O heauenly powers all, And yee on whom Medea may with safer conscience call, O Dungeon darke, most dreadfull den of euerlasting night, O dampned Ghosts: O kingdome set against the Gods aright: O Lord of sad and lowring lakes, O Lady dyre of Hell, (Whom though that Pluto stale by force yet did his troth excell The ficke fayth of Iasons loue, that hee to mee doth beare, With cursed throate I coniure you, O grisly Ghostes appeare. Come out, come out, yee hellish hegges, reuenge this deed so dyre, Bring in your scratting pawes a burning brand of deadly fyre, Rise vp yee hiddeous diuelish Feendes, as dreadfull as yee weare, When vnto me in wedlocke state yee did sometime appeare. Worke yee, worke yee, the dolefull death of this new wedded Wyfe. And martir yee this Father in lawe: depryue of breath and lyfe King Creons ruthfull family: in plunge of passing payne Torment yee mee, that on my spouse doe wishe this woe to raygne: Preserue my Iasons life, but yet let him be bayled out A myching, roging, r?nagate, in forren townes about. To passe from dore to dore, with care to begge his needy bread, Not knowing in what harbring place to couch his curssed head: A banisht wretch, disdaynde of all, and still in feare of lyfe, Then let him wish ten thousand times for me agayne his Wyfe: This famous gest whom euery man will entertayne and haue, Let him be driu? at straungers gates the table cr?mes to craue. And that my bytter bannings may with mischiefe most abounde, God graunt in gulph of like distresse his chyldren may be drounde, To synke in sorrowes stormes, that doe their mother ouerflowe: Now, now, I haue, I haue the full reueng of all my woe, I haue dispatcht: my pyteous playnt and wordes in vayne I lose: What shall not I with vyolence get vp agaynst my foes? And wring out of theyr wrested hands the wedding torch so bryght? Shall I not force the firmament to lose his shrinking lyght? What doth my Graundsirs Phœbus face this heauy hap beholde? And standyng gasyng at this geare yet westwarde is he rolde, On glystring chariot hoysted hyghe, and keepes his beaten Race, Amid the christall colourde skye, why turnes hee not his Face, Retyring fast into the East backe vp the day to twyne? O Father Phœbe to me, to me, thy Chariot reynes resigne, That I aduaunced vp, about the marble skyes may ryde, Biqueath thy brydle vnto mee, and giue me grace to guide Thy yoked prauncing teame, with yerking lasshe of burning whip, That with thy feruent fyry beames on purple poole doe skip. Let Corynth countrey burnt to dust by force of flame and fyre Gyue place, that both the tumbled sees may ioyne: whom to retyre It doth compell, and dassheth of from banke on eyther syde, Least meete in one their chanels might, whose streames hee doth deuide. No way to worke theyr deadly woe I haue but this at hande, That to the wedding I should beare a ruthfull brydall brande, Anoying Creons carelesse Court: when finished I haue Such solemne seruice, as that ryght of sacrafice doth craue, Then at the Aulters of the Gods my chyldren shalbe slayne, With crimsen colourde bloud of Babes their Aulters will I stayne. Through Lyuers, Lungs, the Lights &amp; Heart, through euery gut, &amp; gal, For vengeaunce breake away perforce, and spare no bloude at all: If any lusty lyfe as yet within thy soule doe rest, If ought of auncient corage still doe dwell within my brest, Exile all foolysh Female feare, and pity from thy mynde, And as th'untamed Tygers vse to rage and raue vnkynde, That haunt the croking combrous Caues, and clumpred frosen cliues, And craggy Rockes of Caucasus, whose bitter colde depryues The soyle of all Inhabitours, permit to lodge and rest, Such saluage brutish tyranny within thy brasen brest. What euer hurly burly wrought doth Phasis vnderstand, What mighty monstrous bloudy feate I wrought by Sea or Land: The like in Corynth shalbe seene in most outragious guise, Most hyddious, hatefull, horrible, to heare, or see wyth eyes, Most diuelish, desperate, dreadfull deede, yet neuer knowne before, Whose rage shall force heauen, earth, and hell to quake and tremble sore. My burning breast that rowles in wrath, and doth in rancour boyle, Sore thrysteth after bloud, and wounds with slaughter, death, &amp; spoyle, By renting racked lyms from lyms to driue them downe to graue: Tush, these be but as Fleabytings, that mentioned I haue: As weyghty things as these I did in greener girlishe age, Now sorrowes smart doth rub the gall and frets with sharper rage. But sith my wombe hath yeelded fruict, it doth mee well behoue, The strength and parlous puissaunce of weightier illes to proue. Be ready wrath, with all thy might that fury kindle may, Thy foes to their destruction bee ready to assay: Of thy deuorsement let the Pryce to match, and counterpayse The proude &amp; precious pryncely pomp of these new wedding dayes. How wilt thou from thy spouse depart? as him thou followed hast In bloud to bath thy bloudy handes and traytrous lyues to wast. Breake of in time these long delayes, abanden now agayne, This lewd alliaunce, got by guilt, with greater guilt refrayne. Chorus altered by the Translatour. Who hath not wist that windy words be vayne, And that in talke of trust is not the grounde, Heere in a mirrour may hee see it playne, Medea so by proofe the same hath founde, Who being blind by blinded Uenus Boy, Her bleared Eyes could not beholde her blisse: Nor spy the present poyson of her Ioy, While in the grasse the Serpent lurked is, The shaft that flew from Cupids golden bowe, With feathers so hath dimd her daseld Eyes, That cannot see to shun the way of woe: The ranckling head in dented heart that lyes, So dulles the same, that can not vnderstand The cause that brought false Iason out of Greece, To come vnto her fathers fertile Land, Is not her loue, but loue of golden Fleece. Yet was his speache so pleasaunt and so milde, His tongue so filde, his promises so fayre, Sweete was the fowlers Song that hath beguilde The seely byrd, brought to the limed snare, Faith, in his Face, trust shined in his Eyes, The blushing brow playne meaning seemde to showe, In double hearte blacke treason hydden lies, Dissembling thoughts that weaue the webbe of woe. The honyed Lyppes, the tongue in suger dept Doe sweete the poyson rancke within the breast, In subtle shew of paynted sheath is kept, The rusty knife of treason deemed least: Lyfe seemes the bayte to sight that lyeth brim, Death is the hooke that vnderlies the same, The Candell blase delights with burning trim, The Fly, till shee bee burned in the flame. Who in such showes least deemed any ills. The hungry fyshe feares not the bayte to Brooke, Till vp the lyne doe pluck him by the gylls, And fast in throate hee feeles the deadly hooke. Woe Iason, woe to thee most wretched man, Or rather wretch Medea woe to thee, Woe to the one that thus dissemble can, Woe to the other that trayned so might bee. Thoughtst thou Medea his eyes to bee the glasse, Wherein thou might the Face of thoughts beholde? That in his breast with wordes so couered was, As cancred brasse with glosse of yealow golde? Did thou suppose that nature (more then kinde) Had placde his heart his lying lyppes betweene, His lookes to be the mirrour of his minde? Fayth in fayre Face hath sildome yet ben seene. Who listneth to the flatering Maremaides note, Must needes commit his tyred eyes to sleepe, Yeelding to her the taking of his boate, That meanes vnware to drowne him in the deepe, What booteth thee Medea to betray The golden Fleece, to fawning Iasons hande, From Dragons teeth him safely to conuay, And fyry Bulles the warders of the lande? Why for his sake from father hast thou fled, And thrust thy selfe out from thy natiue soyle? Thy brothers bloud what ayled thee to shed, With Iason thus to trauell and to toyle? Beholde the meede of this thy good desarte, The recompence that hee to thee doth gyue. For pleasure, payne, for ioy, most eger smarte, With clogging cares in banishment to liue. Thou, and thy Babes, are like to begge and starue. In Nation straunge, (O myserable lyfe) Whyle Iason from his promyses doe swarue, And takes delight in his new wedded Wyfe, O Ground vngrate, that when the husband man Hath tilled it, to recompence his toyle No Corne, but Weedes, and Thystles render can, To stinge his handes, that Fruict seekes of his Soyle. Such venome growes of pleasaunt coloured flower: Loe, Prynces loe, what deadly poyson sup Of Bane, erst sweete, now turned into sower, Medea dranke out of a goulden Cup,</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE SECOND ACTE. Medea. Nutrix, Aye mee, (alas) I am vndone, For at the Brydall cheare, The warble note of wedding songs resounded in mine eare. Yet for all this scant I my selfe, yet scant beleue I can, That Iason would play such a prancke, as most vnth?ckfull man, Both of my Countrey, and my Syre, and kingdome me to spoyle, And yet forsake mee wretch forlorne, to stray in forrein soyle. O hath he such a stony heart, that doth no more esteeme, The great good turnes, and benefits that I imployde on him? Who knowes, that I haue lewdly vsed enchauntments for his sake, The rigour rough, and stormy rage, of swelling Seas to slake. The grunting firy foming Bulles, whose smoking guts were sluft, With smoltring fumes, that fr? theyr Iawes, &amp; nosthrils out they puft. I stopt their gnash?g mo?ching mouths, I qu?cht their burning breath, And vapors hot of stewing paunch, that els had wrought his death, Or feedes hee thus his fansy fond, to thinke my skill of charme Abated is, and that I haue no power to doe him harme? Bestract of wits, with wauering minde perplext on euery part, I tossed, and turmoyled am, wyth wayward crasy hart. Now this, now that, and neyther now, but now another way, By diuers meanes I toyle, that so my wrong reueng I may. I would the wretch a brother had: but what? he hath a Wyfe. Goe cut her throate, with gastly wounds bereue her of her lyfe. On her ile worke my deadly spight: her, her alone I craue, To quit such bitter sowsing stormes, as I sustayned haue. If any graund notorious guilt in all Pelasga Land Be put in practise, yet vnknowne vnto thy harming hand, Thereof to get experience the time doth now begin: Thy former feates doe byd thee take good hope, to thryue herein: Let all thy guilts with thronging thick assemble thee to ayde, The golden Fleece (the chiefe Nouell) of Colchis Ile betrayde. My tender Brother eke, that with my Syer did mee pursue, Whom with his secret partes cut of, I wicked Uirgin slewe, Whose shreaded and dismembred corps, with sword in gobbits hewd, (A wofull Coarse toth' Fathers heart) on Pontus ground I strewd. How hory headded Pelias his wythred age to shyft To greener yeares, for longer lyfe: his daughters by my dryft His members all and mangled flesh with licour scalding hot Ysodden, and perboyled haue, in seething brasen pot. How oft in haynous bloud haue these my cruell handes bene dyed? And neuer any guilt as yet by wrath inflamde I tryed. But now the parlous poysning wound of Cupids percing dart, Doth boyle and rage within my breast, it ranckles at my hart. But how could Iason it redresse, whom fortunes froward wyll Hath yeelde vnto anothers hande, at lust to saue or spill? O rage of rufty cancred minde, this sclaundrous talke amende, If Fortunes grace will graunt it thus, let him vnto his ende Lyue still my Iason as he was: but if not Iason myne, Yet caytife suffer Iason liue, though Iason none of thyne: Who being mindefull still of vs some fauour let him showe, For these good turnes that our good will could earst on him bestowe: King Creon is in all the fault, and onely worthy blame, Who puffed vp with Scepter proude, vnable for to frame His fickle minde to modesty, made breach twixt vs agayne, Whom Hymens bands, and link of loue had made but one of twayne, By whom eke from her tender brats the mother (wretch) is drawne, Hee breakes the vowe, that gaged is with such a precious pawne. Seeke after such a villaynes bloud, in daunting pangs of smart, Let him alone bee surely dowst, such is his due desart, A dungell hept of Cinders burnt his Pallayce make I shall, That Malea where in winding strights, the lingring ships doe crall, Shall gase on smolthring turrets tops turmoylde in crackling flame. NV. For godsake (Madame) I you pray your tongue to silence frame. Eke hyde your priuy languishing and greefe in secret vayne: Who with a modest minde abides the Spurs of pricking payne, And suffereth sorrowes paciently, may it repay agayne. Who beares a priuy grudge in breast, and keepes his malyce close, When least suspection is thereof, may most annoy his Foes. He leeseth oportunity who vengeaunce doth requyre, That shewes by open sparkes the flame the heate of kindled fyre. ME. Small is the grype of griefe that can to reasons lore obay, And sneking downe with stealing steps can slyly slip away. But they that throughly sowsed are with showers of greater payne, Can not digest such corsyes sharpe, but cast it vp agayne: Fayne would I giue them trouncing girds. NV. Good daughter deare asswage Th'unbrydled sway, and boyling heate of this thy gyddy rage: Scant maist thou purchase quietnesse, although thou hold thy tongue. ME. The valiaunt heart dame Fortune yet durst neuer harme wt wr?g, But dreading dastards downe she driues. NV. If any corage dure, And harbred be in noble breast, now put the same in vre. ME. The show of sturdy valiant heart, at any time doth shyne. NV. No hope doth in aduersity thy way to scape assygne. ME. Hee that hath none affiaunce left, nor any hope at all, Yet let him not mystrust the luck of ought that may befall. NV. Thy Countrey cleane hath cast thee of, to let thee sinke or swim, As for thy husband Iason bee, there is no trust in him: Of all the wealth, and worldly mucke wherewith thou didst abounde: No porcion remaynes at all, whereby some helpe is founde. ME. Medea yet is left, (to much) and here thou mayst espy The Seas to succour vs in flyght, and landes aloofe that ly: Yea yron tooles, with burning brands we haue to worke them woe, And Gods that with the thunder dint shall ouerquell our foe: NV. Who weares ye gold?crested crowne him dred with awe yee should. ME. My Father was a King, yet I betrayed his Fleece of gould. NV. Can not the deadly vyolence of weapons make thee feare? ME. No, though such grisly Lads they were, as whilom did appeare. That bred of gargell Dragons teeth in holow gaping grounde, When mutually in bloudy fight eche other did confounde. N. Th? wilt thou cast thy self to death. M. Would God yt I were dead. NV. Fly, fly to saue thy life. ME. Woe worth the time that once I fled. N. What O Medea. M. Why shall I fly? N. A mother deere art thou, Fly therefore for thy childrens sake. ME. Yee see by whom, and how, A wretched Mother I am made. NV. Thy lyfe by flight to saue Dost thou mistrust? ME. Nay, fly I will, but vengeaunce first ile haue. NV. Then some shall thee at heeles pursue, to wrecke the same agayne. ME. Perhap ile make his c?ming short. NV. Be still, and now refrayne O despret dame thy thundring threates, and slake your raging ire. Apply, and frame thy froward will as time and tides requyre. ME. Full well may fortunes welting wheele to begging bring my state, As for my worthy corage, that shee, neuer shall abate. Who bowncing at the Gates, doth cause the creaking dores to Iar? It is the wretch (Creon his selfe,) whom princely power far Hath lift aloft, with lordly looke, puft vp with pouncing pryde, That hee may Corinth countrey, with the sway of Scepter guide. Creon. Medea. Nedea that vngracious Imp, king Ætas wicked chylde; Yet hath not fr? our careful realme her lingring foote exilde. Som naughty drift she goes about, her knacks of old we kno Her iugling arts, her harming h?ds are known wel long ago. From wh? will shee withhold her harme? whom will this cruell beast Permit to liue, from perrill free, in quietnesse and rest? Cleane to cut of this parlous plague it was our purpose bent, But Iason by entreting hard, did cause vs to relent. At his request we graunted haue, her life she shall enioy, Let her acquit our countrey free from feare of all annoy: Yea saufely let her pack her hence, in eger giddy fit, With lumpish lowring looke shee comes in talke with me to knit: Sirs keepe her of and set her hence, least vs she touch perhap, And driue her backe from c?ming nigh commaunde her keepe her clap. And let her learne at length, how that her selfe submit she may, The puissaunt payse and maiesty of Princes to obay. Run, hie thee quickly, trudge apace, haue hence out of my sight This horrible, most odious quean, this monstrous wicked wight. ME. My soueraygne liege, what greater crime haue I or lesse offence Commit against thy maiesty, to be exiled hence? CR. Alas, the guiltlesse woman doth demaunde a reason why: ME. If thou be Iudge indifferent, ordaynde my cause to try, Consider then my doubtfull case, and wey the ground of it: If thou be king, c?maund a Iudge for such a matter fit. CR. The princes powre thou shalt obey, b'it eyther right or wrong. M. The prosperous pryde of wronging crownes cannot endeuer long. CR. Auaunt, &amp; yell out thy complaynts at Colchis, get thee hence. ME. Full gladly will I get mee home, if he that brought me thence, Uouchsafe to beare me back agayne. CR. Alas, to late aryse Entreating wordes, when as decree is taken otherwise. ME. He that not hearing eyther part, pronounceth his decree, Unrighteous man accoumpted is, though ryght his sentence bee. CR. Whyle Pelias trusted to thy talke, from lyfe to death hee fell. Go to, begyn, we gyue you leaue your goodly tale to tell. ME. That type of Regall maiesty, that erst by Fortunes hand, Aduaunced to I dyd attayne, hath taught mee vnderstand, How hard a thing it is of wrath the rygour to asswage, When burning heate of boyling breast in flames begins to rage. Eke for th'adua?cement of their power more to display in sight Theyr kingly corage bolstred out with maiesty of might. They deeme it doth import asway, and hath a greater grace, Whome stately scepter causde to climbe aloft to prouder place. To perseuer with fansye fonde, in that to reasons spyght, Whose greedy choyce attaynted fyrst his minde with vayne delight. For though in piteous plyght I lye, throwne downe to great decay. With heauy hap, and ruthfull chaunce, to myserable stay, Thus hunted out from place to place, forsoke and left alone, A wyddow while my husband liue, with cause to wayle and mone, Perplext in maze of misery, wyth cloying cares so ryfe, Yet whylom I in golden trone haue led in happy lyfe. By high and noble parentage my bryght renowne doth shyne. From Phœbus eake my Graundsire great deryued is my ligne. Whear syluer streamed Phasis flood his wasshing waues doth shed, Or with contrary croking wayes his bathing channell spred, What euer wandring coast stretcht out is left aloofe behynde, From whence the roaming Scithyan Sea his channell forth doth fynde, Where as Mæotis fenny plashe with pure fresh water sprynges, Doth season sweete the briny Sea, that tyde in thyther brynges. Eke all the coastes enuyroned and kept within the bankes Of Thermodon, where warlike troupes, &amp; armed wyddowes ranckes, With paynted bucklers on their armes holde all the land in feare, With rigour rough of threatning sword, with force of denting speare. So farre to all these wandring coastes and countreyes round about, My Fathers ample regiment at large is stretched out. I being thus of noble Race, and in an happy plight, With glorious glosse of pryncely pomp in honour shining bright, Then pearelesse Peares my Spousall bed did seeke and sue to haue, But those to be theyr louing Feeres, now other Ladyes craue: Rashe, ticle, peuish, vndiscreete, and wauering Fortunes wheele, Hath cast me out, the crusshing cares of banishment to feele. In Scepter proude and hauty Crowne fix thine affyaunce fast. Sith vpsidowne with welkin wheele, whole mounts of wealth is cast. This Prynces doe possesse, that should theyr royalty display, Whose fame shall neuer razed be, with storme of lowring day, To succour those whom misery in pit of paynes doth souse, To shield and harber suppliaunts in roofe of loyall house. This onely brought I from my Realme, the precious golden Fleece, That Iewell chiefe, and eke the flower of Chyualry in Greece, The sturdy prop, the Rampier strong the bulwarke of your wealth, And Hercules the boystrous Imp of Ioue Ikept in health. It was by meanes of my good will that Orpheus did escape, Whose harmony the liuelesse Rocks with such delight did rape, That forced euen the clottred lumpes with hobling prickt to praunce, And eke the iocond nodding woods with footing fine to daunce. And that those heauenly twins Castor, and Pollux did not dy, My dew desart is doubled twise, sith them preserued I. Of Boreas blustring out with puffed Cheekes, his blasting Breath, His wynged Sons I kept aliue both Calais, and Zeath. And Linceus, that with pearcing beames, and sharper sight of Eye, Could Nauies on the farther banke of Sicill shore espy. And all the Mynians that did come the golden Fleece to win. As for the Prince of Princes all, I will not bring him in. With silence Iason will I passe, for whom though him I saue, Yet is not Greece in debt to mee, no recompence I craue. To no man him I doe impute, the rest I brought agayne For your auayle, that you thereby some profit might attayne. But onely on my Iason deare, him for my owne loues sake I kept in store, that hee of mee his wedded Wyfe should make. None other fault (God wot) yee haue to charge mee with but this, That Argo Ship by meanes of mee returned saufely is. If I a shamefast mayde had not with Cupids bayte bene caught, If more my Fathers health to haue then Iasons I had sought, Pelasga land had bene vndone, and falne to great decay, The lusty valiaunt Capitaynes, had cleane bene cast away: And ioly Iason fyrst of all this now thy sonne in lawe, The Buls had rent his swalowed lims in fiery chomping iawe. Let Fortune fight agaynst my case as list her eluish will, Yet neuer shall it grieue my heart, repent my deede I nill, That I should for so many kings their reling honour saue, The guerden due that I for this my crime commit must haue, It lyeth Creon in thy hande, if thus it lyketh thee, Condemne my guilty ghost lo death, but render fyrst to mee, My fault that forced me offend, then Creon graunt I this, Receauing Iason (cause of cryme) I guilty did amisse. Thou knowst that I was such an one when couring low I lay, Before thy feete in humble wise and did entreating pray, Thy gracious goodnes mee to graunt some succour at thy hande. For me a wreatch and wreatched Babes I aske within this lande Some cotage base, in outcast hole, some couching corner vile, If from the towne thou driue vs out to wander in exile, Then some by place aloofe within this realme let vs obtayne. CR. How I am none that tyrant like with churlish Scepter raygne, Nor proudly or disdaynfully, with hawty corage hie, With va?ting foote doe stamp them downe that vndertroden lye, And daunted are in carefull bale, thys playnly doth disclose, In that to mee of late I such a sonne in lawe haue chose, Who was a wandring pilgrim poore, with sore afflictions fraight, Dismayde with terrour of his foe, that lay for him in wayght. Because Acastus hauing got the crowne of Thessail lande, Requyreth in thy guilty bloude to bath his wreackfull hande. He doth bewayle that good olde man his feeble father slayne, Whom waight of yeres with bowing back to stoupe alow constrayne The godly mynded systers, all yblinde with misty vale And cloking colour of thy craft durst ventrusly assayle. That mount of myschiefe marueylous, to mangle heaw, and cut Theyr Fathers dere vnioynted limmes in boyling Caldron put. But for thy open guiltinesse if thou can purge the same, Strayght Iason can discharge him selfe from blot of guilty blame. His gentle handes were neuer staynde with goare of any bloude. Aloofe from your conspyracie refrayning farre hee stoode. His harmelesse handes put not in vre with goary tooles to mell. But thou that setst on fyre fyrst these mighty mischiefes fell, Whom shamelesse womans wily braine and manly stomack slout Doe set a Gog, for to attempt to bring all us about. And no regarde at all thou hast, how sounding trumpe of fame With ringing blast of good or ill doe blowe abrode thy name: Get out and clense my fyled realme, away together beare Thyne hearbes vnmilde of sorcery, my Lyeges ryd fro feare. Transporte thee to some other lande, whereas thou may at ease With odious noyse of diuelish charme, the troubled Gods disease. ME. If needes thou wylt haue me auoyde, my shyp to mee restore, Or els my mate with whom I fyrst aryued on this shore: Why dost thou bid that by my selfe I onely should be gone? I came not heather at fyrst wythout my company alone. If this do thee aggryefe, that brunt of warres thou shalt sustayne, Commaund vs both the cause thereof to shun thy realme agayne: Sith both are guilty of one art, why dost thou part vs twayne? For Iasons sake not for myne owne, poore Pelias was slayne. Annex vnto my traytrous flight the conquerde booty braue, My hoary headded naturall sler, whom I forsaken haue, With brothers bloudy flesh that mangled was with caruing knife, Or ought of Iasons forged lies he gabbes vnto his wyfe. These dreary deedes are none of myne, so oft as I offend, Not for myne owne c?modity, to come thereby inthende. CR. Time is expierd, by which thou ought to haue bene gone away, Wyth keeping such a chat, why dost thou make so long delay? ME. Yet of thy bounty ere I goe, this one boone will I craue. Although the mother banished, so sore offended haue, Let not the vengeaunce of my fault through wrathfull deadly hate, Myne innocent and guiltlesse Babes torment in wreached state. CR. Away: with louing friendly grype thy children I embrace, And as a father naturall take pity on theyr case. ME. Euen for the prosperous good encreace of fertill spousall bed, Of Glauce bright thy Daughter deare, whom Iason late hath wed. And by the hope of fruictfull seede, whose flowre in time shall bloome. By th'onour of thy glystring crowne, ythralde to fortunes doome, Whych shee so full of chop and chaunge, with ticle turning wheele Whirls vp and downe, in staggring state makes to and fro to reele. I thee beseech, sith to exile I am departing now O Creon but a little pawse for mercy mee alow, Whyle of my mourning brats with kysse, my last farewell I take. Whyle gaspe of fayling breath perhap my shyuering lyms forsake. CR. With craft entending some deceipt thou crauest this delay. ME. What falshode for so little time be cause of terrour may? CR. No tot of time is short ynough displeasure to preuent. ME. Can not one iot to weeping Eyes, and trylling teares be lent? CR. Although agaynst thy ernest suite vnlucky dread do stryue, One day to settle thee away, content I am to gyue. ME. This is to much, and of the same somwhat abrydge yee may. CR. Make speede apace if from our land thou get thee not away, Ere Phœbus horse with golden gleede theyr streaming beames doe shed, Of dawning lampe, thou art condemde to leese thy wretched hed. The holy day, and brydall both doe call me hence away: And wils mee at the sacred aare of Hymeneus to pray. Chorus. Lauish of life and dreadlesse was the wyght, Attempting fyrst in slender tottring Barge Wyth sliuing Ore the slyced waue to smyte, And durst commit the dainty tender charge Of hazered life to inconstant course of wynde, That turnes with chaunge of chaunces euermore, To vew the land forsooke aloofe behynde, And shoouing forthe the Ship fro safer shore, And glauncing through the fomy Channell deepe On sunder cut with slender Stemme the waue, Twixt hope of lyfe, and dread of death to sweepe, In narrow gut him selfe to spill or saue: Experience yet of Planets no man had, They needed not the wandring course to knowe Of Starres, (wherewith the paynted sky is clad,) Not Pleiads, (which returne of sayling show) Nor Hyads (that with showrs the Seas doe beate) No nor the sterne Amaltheas horned head (Who gaue the lyppes of sucking Ioue the Teate) Were wont to put the blundering ships in dread. They feared not the northerne Isy wayne, Whych lazy olde bootes wieldes behinde, And twynes about, no name yet could they fayne For Boreas rough, nor smother western wynde. Yet Typhys bould on open seas durst show His hoysted sayles, and for the wyndes decree New lawes: as now full gale aloofe to blow, Now tackle turnde to take syde wynde alee, Now vp to farle the crossayle on the mast, There safe to hang, the topsayle now to spred, Now missel sayle, and drabler out to cast, VVhen dagling hanges his shottring tackle red VVhyle stearsman stur, and busye neuer blin, VVith pyth to pull all sayles eke to display, VVith tooth and nayle all foree of winde to wyn, To sheare the seas, and quick to scud awaye. The golden worlde our fathers haue possest, VVhere banysht fraude durst neuer come in place, All were content to liue at home in rest VVith horye head, gray beard, and furrowed face. VVhych tract of time within his countrey brought. Riche hauing lytle, for more they did not toyle, No vente for wares, nor Traficque far they sought, No wealth that sprange beyond theyr natiue soyle, The Thessail shyp together now hath set, The Thessail ship together now hath set, The Worlde that well with Seas disseuered lay, It biddes the flouds with Oares to be bet, And streames vnknowen with shipwrack vs to fray That wicked Keele was lost by ruthfull wrack Ytossed through such perylles passing great, Where Cyanes Rocks gan rore as thunder crack, Whose bouncing boult the shaken soyle doth beat. The sowsing Surges dasshed euery starre, The pesterd seas the cloudes aloft berayde, This scuffling did bould TYPHIS minde detarre, Hys helme did slip from trembling hande dismayde. Then ORPHEVS with his drowping Harp was mum Dead in her dumpes the flaunting ARGOS glee, All husht in rest with silence wexed dum, What hardy heart astound heere would not bee? To see at once eche yawning mouth to gape, Of Syllas gulph compact in wallowing paunch, Of dogges, who doth not loth her mongrell shape, Her visage, breast, and hyddeous vgly haunch: Whom erketh not the scoulde with barking still? To here the Mermaydes dyre who doth not quayle, That lure the Eares with pleasaunt singing shrill Of such as on Ausonius Sea doe sayle: When ORPHEVS on his twanckling Harpe did play, That earst the Muse Calliop gaue to him Almost those Nymphes that wonted was to stay The shyps, he causd fast following him to swim. How deerely was that wicked iourney bought? MEDEA accurst, and eke the golden Fleece, That greater harme then storme of seas hath wrought Rewarded well that voyage first of Greece. Now seas controulde doe suffer passage free, The Argo proude erected by the hand Of PALLAS first, doth not complayne that shee, Conueyde hath back, the kynges vnto theyr land Eche whirry boate now scuddes aboute the deepe, All stynts and warres are taken cleane away, The Cities frame new walles themselues to keepe, The open worlde lettes nought rest where it lay: The Hoyes of Ind Arexis lukewarme leake, The Perseans stout in Rhene and Albis streame Doth bath their Barkes, time shall in fine out breake When Ocean waue shall open euery Realme. The wandring World at will shall open lye. And TYPHIS vvill some nevve founde Land suruay Some trauelers shall the Countreys farre escrye, Beyonde small Thule, knovven furthest at this day.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE THIRD ACTE. Nutrix. Medea. Why trotst thou fisking in and out so rash from place to place? Stand styll, and of thyne eger wrath suppresse the ruthfull race, The rigour rough of ramping rage from burning breast out cast, As Bacchus bedlem priestes that of his spryte haue felt the blast, Run franticke, hoyting vp and downe with scitish wayward wits, Not knowing any place of rest, so prickt with frowarde fits, On cloudy top of Pindus Mounte all hyd with Snow so chyll: Or els vpon the lofty riddge of braunched Nisa hyll: Thus starting still with frounced mynde she walters to and froe, The signes pronouncing proofe of pangues her frensy Face doth show With glowing cheekes, and bloud red Face with short &amp; gasping breath, Shee fetcheth deepe ascending sighes from sobbing heart beneath, Now blyth she smiles, ech t?bled thought in pondring braine she beats, Now standes she in a mammering, now myschiefe sore she threats. With chafing fume she burnes in wrath, and nowe she doth c?playne, With blubbering teares a fresh byliue shee weepes &amp; wayles agayne. Where will this lumpish loade of cares with headlong sway allight? On whom entendeth shee to worke the threates of her despight? Where will this huge tempestious surge slake downe it selfe agayne? Enkindled fury new in breast begins to boyle a mayne. Shee secretly entendes no mischiefe small nor meane of sise To passe her selfe in wickednes her busy braynes deuise. The token olde of pinching ire full well ere this know I: Some haynous, huge, outragious great, and dredfull storme is nye: Her firy, scowling, steaming Eyes, her hanging Groyne I see, Her powting, puffed, frowning Face, that signes of freating bee. O myghty Ioue beguile my feare. ME. O wretch if thou desire, What measure ought to payse thy wrath then learne by Cupids fire, To hate as sore as thou didst loue, shall I not them anoy That doe vnite in spousall bed, theyr wanton lust t'enioy? Shall Phœbus fiery footed horse goe lodge in western waue The drowping day, that late I did with humble crowching craue, And with such ernest busie suite so hardly graunted was? Shall it depart ere I can bring my deuylish dryst to passe? Whyle houering heauen doth counterpaysed hang with egall space, Amid the marble Hemispheares, whyle rounde with stinted race, The gorgeous Sky aboue the Earth doth spinning roll about, Whyles that the number of the sandes, lyes hid vnserched out, While dawning day doth keepe his course with Phœbus blase so bright, While twinkling starres in golden traynes doe garde the sl?bry nyght, While Isle vnder propping poale with whyrling swyng so swift, The shyning Beares vnbathde about the frosen Sky doe lift, While flushing floudes the frothy streames to rustling Seas doe send, To gird them gript with plonging pangues my rage shall neuer end. With greater heate it shall reboyle, lyke as the brutishe beast, Whose tyranny most horrible, exceedeth all the rest, What greedy gaping whyrle poole wide what parlous gulph vnmilde, What Sylla coucht in roring Rockes, or what Charybdes wylde, (That Sicill, and Ionium Sea by frothy waues doth sup) What Ætna bolking stifling flames, and dusky vapours vp, (Whose heauy payse wt stewing heate doth smoldring crush beneath Encelades, that fiery flakes from choked throte doth breath) Can with such dreadfull menaces in sweeting fury fry? No ryuer swift no troubled surge of stormy Sea so hye, Nor sturdy seas (whom ruffling winds with raging force to rore) Nor puissaunt flash of fyre, whose might by boystrous blast is more, May byde my angers violence: my fury shall it foyle: His court Ile ouer hourle, and lay it leauell with the soyle. My Iasons heart did quake for feare of Creon cruell king. And least the king of Thessaly would warre vpon him bring. But loyall loue that hardens hearts makes no man be afright. But beete, that he conuict hath yeelde himselfe to Creons might. Yet once hee might haue visited, and come to me his wyfe, To talke, and take his last farewell, if daunger of his life In doing this (hard harted wretch most cruell) he should feare, He being Creons sonne in law, for him it lefull were, To haue proroged somwhat yet my heauy banishment, To take my leaue of chyldren twayne one onely day is lent: Yet doe I not complayne, as though the time to short I thought, As proofe shall playne pronounce, to day, to day, it shall bee wrought, The memory whereof no tract of time shall wype away. With malice bent agaynst the Gods my wrath shall them assay: And rifling euery thing, both good, and bad, I will turmoyle. NV. Madame thy minde that troubled is, and tost with such abroyle Of swarming ills, thy vexed breast now set at rest agayne, The peuish fond affections all of troubled mynde refrayne. ME. Then onely can I be at rest, when euery thing I see Throwne headlong topsie turuey downe to ruthfull ende with mee. With mee let all things cleane decay: thy selfe if thou doe spill, Thou maist driue to destruction what els with thee thou will: NV. If in this folly stiffe thou stand, beholde what after clappes Are to bee fearde, none dare contriue for Prynces trayning trappes. Iason. Medea. O lucklesse lot of frowarde Fates, O cruell Fortunes hap, Both wh? she list to smite, or spare, in woe she doth vs wrap A like, the salue yt God hath geuen so oft, to cure our griefe, More noyeth then the sore it selfe, and sendeth lesse reliefe: If for her good deserts to me, amendment I should make. I hazard should my ventrous lyfe to leese it for her sake. If I will shun my dismall day, and will not for her dy, Then want the loue of loyalty, O wretched man must I. No dastards dread my stomacke stout can cause to droupe &amp; shrynke, But meere remorse appaulleth me, when on my babes I thynke. For why? when carefull parents are once reft of lyfe and breath, Sone after them their wretched seede are drawne to dolefull death. O Sacred righteousnesse (if thou enioye thy worthy place In perfect blisse of happy heauen) I call vpon thy grace, And thee for witnesse here alledge, how for my childrens part With pity prick: I haue commit these things agaynst my hart. And so I thinke Medea her selfe the Mother rather had, (Though frantickly as now she fares with rage of heart so mad And doth abhor with paynfull yoke of combrous cares to toyle) Her spousall bed, then that her seede should take the plunging foyle. I did determine in my minde, to goe her to entreate With gentle wordes, &amp; pray her cease, in feruent wrath to freate. And loe, on me when once she caste the beames of glauncing Eye, Full blythe she leapes, she iumpes for ioy, in fits she ginnes to fry. Deepe deadly blackish hate she seemes in outwarde brow to beare, And wholly in her frowning face doth glutting griefe appeare. ME. I packing, packing, Iason am: this still to chop, and chaunge The fleeting soyle of my abode, to mee it is not straunge. The cause of my departure yet (to me is straung) and new. I wonted was in followinge thee all places to eschew: I will depart, and get me hence, to whom for helping hande Entendest thou to sende vs forth, whom hence to fly the land Thou dost compell with thine alies? shall I repayre agayne To Phasis flood, to Colchis Isle, or to my fathers raygne? Or goary sweeting fieldes, that with my brothers blood do reeke? What harbring lands aloofe dost thou commaund vs out to seeke? What seas appoint yee me to passe? shall I my iourney dryue, Uppon the parlous hatefull iawes of Pontus to arriue, By which I did saufe conduct home kings valiaunt armies great, Where rearing rocks with thundring noise the flapping waues do beate Or on the narrow wrackfull shore, of Simplegades twayne? Or els to small Hiolcos towne can I retourne agayne? Or toyle, the gladsome pleasaunt lands of Tempe to attayne? All places that I opened haue vnto thy passage free, I shut them vp agaynst my selfe, now whether sendste thou mee? A banisht wretch to banishment thou wouldest haue encline, Yet to the place of her exyle, thou canst not her assygne, Yet for all that without delay I must depart and go: And why? forsoth the king his sonne in law commaundeth so. Well: nothing will I stand against, with grypes of passing payne Let me be scourgde, of my desarts such is the gotten gayne. Let Creon in his pryncely ruffe lay to his heauy handes, To whyp an whore in torments sharp, with iron giues, and bandes Let her be chaynd, in hydeous hole of night for aye her locke: Let her be cloyed with pestring payse of restlesse rowling rocke. Yet lesse than I deserued haue, in all this shall I finde: O thou vncurteous Gentleman, consider in thy mynde The flamy puffes, and firy gaspes of gastly gaping bull, And Ætas catell rych with Fleece of gorgeous golden wooll, That went to graze amid so great and mighty feares in fielde, Of vncontrouled Natton, whose soyle doth armies yeelde. Reuoke to minde the deadly dartes of sodayne starting foe, When gastly warriour (Tellus broode) to ground agayne did goe, Through slaughter red of mutuall launce, to this yet further passe, The lurched Fleece of Phrixes Ramme, that all thine errand was. And vgsome Argos slumberlesse, whom fast I causde to keepe His wery watching winking eyes with vnaquaynted sleepe. My brother eke, whose fatall twist of feeble lyfe I shred, And guilt that wrought so many guiltes when as with thee I fled. The daughters whom I set on worke entrapt in wily trayne, To slay theyr sire, that shall not ryse to quickned lyfe agayne. And how to trauell other realmes, I set myne owne at nought. By that good hope which of thy seede conceaued is in thought, Eake by thy stable Mansion place, and mighty monsters, that Downe beaten for thy health, I causde before thy feete to squat, And by these drudging hands of myne vnspared for thy sake, For dread of daungers ouer past that caused thee to quake, By heauens aboue, and seas belowe, that witnesse bearers bee, To knitting of out maryage vp, thy mercy vayle to mee. Of all the heapes of treasure great so farre of being set, Which Ætas sauage Scythians dyd trauell for to get, From Ind, where Phœbus scorching blase doth dye the people blacke. Of all this golde which in our bowers wee coulde not well compacke. But tricke and trym wee garnished our groues with golde so gay, I vanisht wretch of all this stuffe gat nought with mee away, Except my brothers slaughtred flesh, yet I employed the same On thee: the cares of countreyes health, my honesty and shame. My Father, and my brother both hath yeelded place to thee, This is the dowry that thou had my wedded spouse to bee. To her whom thou dost abrogate restore her goods agayne. IA. When Creon in malicious moode had thought thee to haue slayne, Entreated with my teares, exyle and life he gaue to thee. ME. I tooke it for a punishment, but surely as I see This banishment is now become a friendly good rewarde. IA. While thou hast time to goe, be gone, for most seueare, and harde The kings displeasure euer is. M. Thus wouldst thou dodge mee out? Thy hated trull cast of thou dost, that please Creuse thou mought. IA. Dost thou Medea vpbrayde mee with the breach vnkynde of loue? ME. And slaughter vyle, with trechery, whereto thou didst mee moue. IA. When all is done what canst thou say my guiltines to slayne? ME. Euen whatsoeuer I haue done. IA. Yet more this doth remayne: That thy vngracious wickednes of harme should mee accuse. ME. Thine, thine, they are, they are all thine what euer I did vse, Who that of lewdnesse reapes the fruict, is grafter of the same. Let euery one with infamy thy wretched Spouse defame, Yet doe thou onely take her part, her onely doe thou call A iust and vndefiled wight, without offence at all. If any man shall for thy sake polute his hand with ill, To thee let him an innocent yet be accompted still, IA. The life is lothsome that doth worke his shame who hath it chose. ME. The life whose choyse doth worke thy shame thou ought againe to lose. IA. Let reason rule thy eger mynde so vext with crabbed ire, And for thy tender childrens ease to bee at rest requyre. ME. I doe defy it, wholy I detest it, I forsweare, That bretheren bred vnto my barnes Creusas wombe shall beare. IA. It will be trim, when as a Queene of maiesty and myght Hath issue, kinne vnto the seede of thee a banisht wight. ME. So cursed day shall neuer on my wretched children shine, To mingle base borne basterdes with the bloud of noble Lygne. Shall Phœbus stocke (that beares the lamp of heauen in starry throne) Be macht with drudging Sisiphus that roules in hell the stone? IA. What meanest thou wretch, both thee &amp; mee in banishment to yoke? I pray then hence. ME. When humbly I my mynde to Creon broke, Hee gaue an eare vnto my suite. IA. What lyeth in my myght To doe for thee? ME. If no good turne, then doe thy worst dispyght. IA. On this side with his swerd in hand king Creon doth mee scarre: On other part with armed hoast Acast doth mee detarre. ME. Medea eke to coape with these, that more apaull vs may: Go to, to skyrmishe let vs fall, let Iason be the pray: IA. I yeelde whom sore aduersities haue tyerd with heauy sway. Learne thou to dred thy luclesse lot that ofte doth thee assay. ME. I euermore haue rulde the swinge of fortunes wauering will. IA. Achastus is at hand, and nygh is Creon thee to spyll: ME. Take thou thy heeles to scape them both, I doe not thee aduise, That thou agaynst thy father in lawe in traytrous armes should ryse. Nor in Achast thy cosens bloud thy wounding handes to gore, The vowes vnto Medea made, doe trouble thee so sore. Whyle yet thou hast not spilt there bloud, yet fly with mee away. IA. When armies twayne their banners of defiance shall display, And marching forth in fielde to fyght seeke battayle at my hande, Who then for vs encounter shall their puissaunce to withstand? ME. If Creon and Achastus king encampe together shall Admit that these in one with them should ioyne their powers all My Countreymen of Colchis Ile, and Ætas lusty kyng, Suppose the Scythians ioyne with Greekes, to ground I will th? bring, Cleane put to foile. IA. The puissaunt power of hawty mace I feare. ME. Take heede, least more thou do affect the same, then for to cleare, Thy selfe of Creons seruile yoke. IA. Least some suspicion grow, Of this our tatling long here let vs make an ende and goe. ME. Now Ioue hurle out thy flames &amp; force thy thundring bolts to fly, With fiery drakes bright brandishing disparst in burning sky: Strayne forth thy dreadfull threatning arme, dispose in due aray The tossing dint of lightning flashe, that wrecke our quarrell may. With rumbling cracke of renting cloud cause all the world to quake, And leuell not thy houering hand to stryke with firy flake Uppon my pasht and crushed corpes, or Iasons Carcasse slayne: For whether of vs thou smight to death his due rewarde shall gayne, Thy thumps of thwacking boltes on vs amisse they cannot light. IA. Fy, let thy mynde on matters runne that seeme a modest wight. And vse to haue more cheerefull talke, if any thing thou craue, Within my fathers house to ease thy flyght, thou shalt it haue. ME. Thou knowst my minde both can, &amp; eke is wont, to doe no lesse, Then to contemne the brittell wealth that Prynces doe possesse. This, this shalbe the onely boone that at thy hande I craue, As mates with me in banishment, my children let mee haue, That resting on theyr sighing breastes my carefull mourning hed, I may my chrystall teary streames into theyr bosomes shed. But as for thee, new gotten sonnes of wife new wed doe stay. IA. I graunt that vnto thy request I wishe I might obey: But nature mee with pity pryckes, that needes I must deny. For though both Creon and Achast, in torments force mee lye, I could not yeelde vnto theyr willes: on this my lyfe doth rest: In times of teares, this is the ioy of dull afflicted brest For better farre I can abyde the wante of vitall breath, And succour of my lymmes, or loose, the light of worlde by death. ME. What loue vnto his seely Babes is deeply graft in him? This worketh well I haue him tript, loe now there lyeth brim. An open place whereby receaue a venny soone hee may. Let mee or I departe, vnto my seely children say. These lessons of my last adewe, and graunt to mee the space, With tender grype of colling last theyr louing limmes t'embrace: This wilbe comforte to my heart: yet at the latter woorde I aske no more but onely that you shoulde mee this afoorde. If eger anguish cause my tongue to cast out woords vnkinde, Let all thing fly, let nothing be engraued in your minde But let remembraunce otherwhyle of mee to touch your thought, Let other thinges be wypte away that byle of wrath hath wrought. IA. I haue forgotten euery whit God graunt thou may of shake, These surging qualmes of frounced minde &amp; milder mayste it make: For quietnesse doth worke theyr ease that dented are with woe: ME. What is he slily slypt and gon? falles out the matter so? O Iason dost thou sneake away, not hauing minde of mee, Nor of those former great good turnes that I haue done for thee? With thee now am I cleane forgot: but I will bryng about That from thy carefull sighing minde shall not bee banisht out: Apply to bring this to effect, call home thy wits agayne, And all thy wyly fetches farre, eache artificiall trayne. This is the perfect fruict that may to thee of mischiefe spryng, To presuppose that mischiefe is not graft in any thing. Scant haue I oportunity for my pretensed guile, Because wee are mistrusted sore: but try I will the whyle To set vpon them in such sort, as none can deeme my sleyght: March forth, now venture on, fall to, both what lyeth in thy myght, And also what doth passe thy power. O faythfull nourse and mate Of all my heauy heart breaking, and dyuers cursed fate. Come help our simple meane deuice. Remayning yet I haue A robe of Pall the present that our heauenly Graundsire gaue, Chiefe monument of Cholchis Ile, which Phœbus did bestow On Ætas for a pledge, that him his father he might know. A precious fulgent gorget eake, that brauely glytters bryght, And with a seemely shyning seame of golden thryds is dight, Through wrought betwene the row of pirles doe stand in borders ro?d, Wherewith my golden crispen Locks is wonted to be cro?d. My lytle children they shall beare these presents to the Bryde, That first with slibber slabbar sosse of chauntments shalbe tryde. Request the ayde of Hecate in redinesse prepare The lamentable sacrifice, vpon the bloudy Aare. Enforce the fiers catching holde vpon the rafters hye With crackling noyse of flamy sparkes rebound in azur sky. Chorus. No fiers force, nor r?bling rage of boistrus blustring winde, No dart shot whirling in the skies, such terrour to ye minde Can driue, as when ye ireful wife doth boile in burning hate Depriued of her spousall bed, and comfort of her mate, Nor where the stormy southerne winde with dankish dabby face, Of hoary winter sendeth out the gusshing showres apace. Where veighment Isters waumbling streame comes waltring downe amayne, Forbidding both the banks to meete, &amp; cannot oft contayne Him selfe within his channels scoupe, but further breakes his way, Nor Rodanus whose russhing streame doth launch into the sea, Or when amid the floured spring with hotter burning sunne, The winters snowes disolude with heate downe to the ryuers runne: The clottred top of Haemus hill to water thin doth turne, Such desperate gogin flame is wrath that inwardly doth burne, And modest rule regardeth not, nor brydeis can abyde, Nor dreading death, doth wish on dinte of naked blade to slyde. O Gods be gracious vnto vs, for pardon we do craue, That him who tamde the scuffling waues, vouchsafe yee would to saue. But Neptune yet the Lord of Seas with frowning face will lower, That ouer his second Scepter men to tryumph haue the power. The boy that rashly durst attempt that great vnweldy charge Of Phœbus euerlasting Carte, and rouing out at large, Not bearing in his recklesse breast his fathers warnings wyse, Was burned with the flames which hee did scatter in the Skyes. None knew the costly glimsing glades, where straggling Phaëton rode, Passe not the path, where people safe in former tyme haue trode. O fondling, wilfull, wanton boy, doe not dissolue the frame Of heauen, sith Ioue with sacred hand hath halowed the same. Who rowde with valiaunt Oares tough, that were for Argo made, Hath powled naked Pelion mounte of thycke compacted shade. Who entred hath the fleeting rockes and serched out the toyle And tyring trauels of the seas, and hath on saluage soyle Knit fast his stretched Cable rope, and going forth to land. To cloyne away the forren golde with greedy snatching hand. Unto the seas (because that hee transgrest theyr lawes deuine) By this vnlucky ende of his, he payes his forfeyte fine. The troubled seas of theyr vnrest for vengeaunce howle and weepe. Syr Typhis who did conquer fyrst the daunger of the deepe, Hath yeelded vp the cunning rule of his vnweldy sterne, To such a guide, as for that vse hath neede as yet to learne. Who giuing vp his Ghost aloofe from of his natiue lande, In forreyn more lyes buryed vile with durty soddes in sande. He sits among the flittring soules that straungers to him weare. And Aulis Isle that in her minde her masters losse doth beare, Held in the Ships, to stand and wayle in croking narrow nooke: That Orpheus Calliops sonne who stayde the running Brooke, Whyle he recordes on heauenly Harpe with twanckling finger fine, The wynde layde downe his pipling blastes: his harmony diuine Procurde the woods to styr them selues, and trees in traynes along Came forth with byrds that held their layes and listned to his song. With lims on sunder rent in fielde of Thrace he lyeth dead. Up to the top of Heber floude, eke haled was his head. Gone downe he is to Stygian dampes, which scene hee had before, And Tartar boyling pits, from whence returne hee shall no more. Alcydes banging bat did bringe the Northern laddes to grounde. To Achelo of sundry shapes he gaue his mortall wounde. Yet after he could purchase peace both vnto sea and land, And after Ditis dungeon blacke rent open by his hand, He lyuing spred himselfe along on burning Oetas hill: His members in his proper flame the wretch did thrust to spill: His bloud he brewd with Nestors bloud, and lost his lothsome lyfe By traytrous gyft that poysoned shyrt receaued of his wyfe. With tuske of bristled groyning Bore Anceus lyms were torne. O Meleagar (wicked wight) to graue by thee were borne Thy mothers brethren twayne, and shee, for it with ruthfull hand, Hath wrought thy dolefull desteny, to burne thy fatall brand. The rash attempting Argonantes deserued all the death That Hylas whom Alcides lost bereft of fading breath. That springall which in sowsing waues of waters drowned was: Goe now yee lusty bloudes, the Seas: with doubtfull lot to passe. Though Idmon had the calking skyll of destenies before, The serpent made him leaue his lyfe in tombe of Liby shore. And Mopsus that to other men could well theyr fates escry, Yet onely did deceyue him selfe vncertayne where to dy, And he that could the secret hap of things to come vnfoulde, Yet dyde not in his countrey Thebes. Dame Thetis husband oulde Did wander like an outlawde man. Our Palimedes syre Did headlong whelm him selfe in seas. Who at the Greekes retyre From Troy, to rushe on rockes did them alure with wily light, Stout Aiax Oleus did sustayne the dint of thunder bright, And cruell storme of surging seas, to quite the haynous guilt, That by his countrey was commit, in seas he lyeth spilt. Alceste to redeeme her husbands Phereus lyfe from death, The godly Wyfe vpon her spouse bestowed her panting breath. Proude Pelias that wretch him selfe who bad them first assay The golden Fleece that booty braue by ship to fetch away, Perboylde in glowing cauldron hoate with feruent heate hee fryes, And fleeting peece meale vp and downe in water thin he lyes. Inough, inough, reuenged are O Gods the wronges of seas, Be good to Iason, doing that hee did, his Game to please.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE FOVRTH ACTE. Nutrix. My shiuering minde amazed is, agast, and sore dismayde: My chillish lims with quaking colde do tremble all afrayde. Such plagues &amp; venge?ce is at hand, in what exceding wise Do sharp assaults of greedy griefe still more &amp; more arise, And of it selfe in smothering breast enkindlesse greater heate? Oft haue I seene how ramping rage hath forced her to freate. With franticke fits, mad, bedlem wise, against the Gods to rayle, And eke bewitched ghosts of heauen in plunging plagues to trayle: But now Medea beates her busie brayne to bring to passe A myschiefe greater, greater farre, then euer any was. Erewhile when hence she tript away astonished so sore, And of her poyson closset close shee entred had the dore: Shee powreth out her Iewels all, abrode to light shee brings That which she dreading lothed long, most irksome vgly things: She mumbling coniures vp by names of ills the rable rout, In hugger mugger cowched long, kept close, vnserched out: All pestlent plagues she calles vpon, what euer Libie lande, In frothy boyling stream doth worke, or muddy belching sande: What tearing torments Taurus breedes, with snowes vnthawed still Where winter flawes, and hory knit hard the craggy hill, She layes her crossing hands vpon each monstrous coniurde thing, And ouer it her magicke verse with charming doth she sing: A mowsie, rowsie, rusty route with cancred Scales Iclad From musty, fusty, dusty dens where lurked long they had, Doe craull: a wallowing serpent huge, his c?brous Corps out drags, In fiery foming blaring mouth his forked tongue hee wags. He stares about with sparkling eyes, if some he might espy, Whom snapping at with stinging spit he might constrayne to dy: But hearing once the magycke verse he husht as all a gast, His body boalne big, wrapt in lumps on twining knots hee cast. And wambling to and fro his tayle in linkes he rowles it round. Not sharp enough (quoth she) the plagues &amp; tooles that hollow gro?d Engenders for my purpose are, to heauen vp will I call, To reach me stronger poyson down, to frame my feate with all. Now is it at the very poynt, Medea thou assay, To bring about some farther fetch, then common Witches may. Let downe, let downe, that sprawling Snake that doth his body spred, As doth a running brooke abroade his myghty channell shed. Whose swelling knobs of wondrous sise &amp; boystrous bobbing bumpes Doth thumpe the great &amp; lesser beare that feele his heauy lumpes. The bygger beare with golden gleede the greekish fleete doth guyde: But by the lesse the Sidon ships their passage haue espide. He that with pinch of griping fist doth bruse the adders twayne, His strening hard &amp; clasping hande, let him vnknit agayne. And crushe their squeased venome out, come further thou our charme O slymy serpent Python, whom Dame Iuno sent to harme Diana, and Apollo both, (those heauenly spyrites twayne) With whom Latona traueling did grone with pynching payne. O Hydra whom in Lerna poole Alcides gaue the foyle, And all the noysome vermen vyle that Hercules did spoyle. Which when on sunder they were cut with slysing deadly knyfe, Can knit agayne their sodred partes, and so recouer lyfe. Help wakefull Dragon Argos, whom first magicke wordes of myne Made Morpheus locke thy sleepy liddes, and shut thy slugring eyne. Then hauing brought aboue the ground of Serpents all the rout, Of filthy weedes the ranckest bane shee pyckes, and gathers out, That spryng on knotty Eryx hill where passage none is founde, Among the ragged Rockes, or what on Caucasus his grounde Doth grow that still is clad in Coate of hoary moary frost. That euermore vnmelt abydes, whose spattred fylde is soste With gubbs of bloud, yt spowteth from Prometheus gaping maw, Whose guts with twitching talent out the gastly gripe doth draw. Or any other venemous herbe amonge the Medes that growes, That with their sheafe of arowes sharp in field do scare their foes. Or what the light held Parthian to serue her turne can sende, Or els the rych Arabians, that dyp theyr arrowes ende In poyson strong: the iuyce of all Medea out doth wrynge, That vnderneath the frosen poale in Svveuia land doth sprynge. Whose noble state Hircinus woode doth high enhaunce and reare, Or what the pleasaunte soyle doth yeelde in pryme of smiling veare, When nature byddes the byrd begin her shrowding nest to builde, Or when the churlyshe Boreas blast sharpe winter hath exilde, The trym aray of braunche and bough to cloth the naked tree, And euery thinge with bitter coulde of Snowe congealed bee. In any pestilent flower on stalke of any hearbe doth growe, Or noysome ioyce doth lye in rotten wrythen rootes alowe, Hath any force in breading bane, those takes shee in her hande. Some plaugy hearbes did Athos yeelde that mount of Thessayle lande. And other Pindus roches hye and some vppon the top Of Pingeus, but tender twigges the cruell Sythe did lop: These Tigris ryuer norisht vp, that choakes his whyrlpoale deepe With stronger streame. Danubius those in fostring waue did keepe. Those did Hidaspus mynister, who by the parching zone With lukewarme siluer channell runnes, so rych with precious stone. And Bethis sonne, who gaue the name vnto his countrey great, And with his shallowe soarde agaynst the Spanyshe seas doth beat This hearbe aboade the edge of knyfe in dawning of the day Ere Phœbus Face gan peepe, bedect with glittring goulden spray His slender stalke was snepped of in deepe of silent nyght, His corne was cropt, whyle she wt charme her poysned nayles did dight. Shee chops the deadly hearbes, &amp; wrings the squesed clottered bloud Of Serpentes out: and filthy byrdes of irkesome miry mud: She tempers with the fame and eake: she brayes the heart of Owle Foreshewing death with glaring Eyes, and moaping Uysage foule, Of shryke Owle hoarce alyue she takes the durty stinking guts, All these the framer of this feate in dyuers percels puts. This hath in it deuouring force of greedy spoyling flame, The frosen ysie dulling coulde engenders by the same. Shee chauntes on those the magicke verse, that workes no lesser harme, With bustling frantickely shee stampes, and ceaseth not to charme. MEDEA. O flittring Flockes of grisly ghostes that sit in silent seat O ougsome Bugges, O Gobblins grym of Hell I you intreat: O lowryng Chaos dungeon blynde, and dreadfull darkned pit, Where Ditis muffled vp in Clowdes of blackest shades doth sit, O wretched wofull wawling soules your ayde I doe implore, That linked lye with gingling Chaynes on wayling Limbo shore, O mossy Den where death doth couche his gastly carrayne Face: Relesse your pangues, O spryghts, and to this wedding hye apace. Cause yee the snaggy wheele to pawse that rentes the Carkas bound, Permit Ixions racked Lymmes to rest vpon the ground: Let hungry bytten Tantalus wyth gawnt and pyned panche Soupe vp Pirenes gulped streame his swelling thyrst to staunche. Let burning Creon byde the brunt and gyrdes of greater payne, Let payse of slyppery slyding stone type ouer backe agayne His moylyng Father Sisyphus, amonges the craggy Rockes. Yee daughters dyre of Danaus whom perced Pychers moyckes So oft with labour lost in vayne this day doth long for you That in your lyfe with bloudy blade at once your husband slewe. And thou whose aares I honored haue, O torch and lampe of night, Approche O Lady myne with most deformed vysage dight: O three folde shap? Dame that knitst more threatning browes then one, According to the countrey guise with dagling locks vndone And naked foote, the secrete groue about I halowed haue, From dusky dry vnmoysty cloudes the showers of rayne I craue. Through me the chinked gaping ground the soked seas hath drunk. And mayner streame of th'ocian floud beneath the earth is sunk, That swelteth out through hollow gulph with stronger gushing rage. Then were his suddy wambling waues whose power it doth asswage The heauens with wrong disturbed course and out of order quight, The darkned sonne, &amp; glimmering stars at once hath shewed theyr light, And dr?ched Charles his stragling wayne hath ducie in dasshing waue, The framed course of roaming time racte out of frame I haue. So my enchauntments haue it wrought, that when the flaming sunne In sommer bakes the parched soyle then hath the twigges begunne, With sprowting blossom fresh to blome, and hasty winter corne Hath out of haruest seene the fruite to barnes on suddein borne. Into a shallowe foorde his shure distreame hath Phasis wast, And Isters channell being in so many braunches cast, Abated hath his wrackfull waues, on euery silent shore He lyeth calme: The tumbled flouds with thundring noyse did rore, When couched close the windes were not mouing pippling soft, With working waue the prauncing seas haue swolne &amp; leapt aloft, Whereas the wood in alder time with thicke and braunched bowe Did spread his shade on gladsome soyle no shade remayneth now. I rolling vp the magicke verse at noone time Phœbus stay. Amyd the darkned Sky, when fled was light of drowsy day. Eke at my charme the watry flockes of Heyæds went to glade. Time is it Phœba to respect the seruice to thee made: To thee with cruell bloudy hands these garlands greene were twynde Which with his folding circles nyne the serpent rough did bynde. Haue here Tiphoias fleshe, that doth in Ætnas Fornace grone, That shoke with battery violent king Ioues assaulted trone. This is the Centaures poysoned bloud which Nessus villayne vyle Who made a rape of Dianire entending her to fyle, Bequethed her when newly wounde he gasping lay for breath, While Hercles shaft stack in his Ribs, whose la?ce did worke his death: Beholde the Funerall cinders heere which vp the poyson dryed Of Hercules who in his fyre on Oeta mountayne dyed: Loe heere the fatall brand, which late the fatall sisters three Conspyred at Meleagers byrth, such should his destny bee, To saue alyue his brethyng corpes, while that might whole remayne, Which saufe his mother Althe kept, till he his vncles twayne, (That from Atlanta would haue had the head of conquered Bore,) Had reft of lyfe whose spightfull death Althea tooke so sore, That both she showed her feruentnesse in systers godly loue, When to reuenge her brothers death meere nature did her moue, But yet as mother most vnkynde, of nature most vnmylde, To hasten the vntymely graue of her beloued chylde, Whyle Meleagers fatall brande she wasted in the flame, Whose swelting guts and bowels moult consumed as the same, These plumes the Harpyes rauening fowles for hast did leaue behinde, In hidden hole whose cloase accesse no mortall wight can fynd. When fast from Zethes chasing them with speedy flight they fled. Put vnto these the fethers which the Symphal byrde did shed, Whom duskyng Phœbus dymned lyght syr Hercules did slynge, And galled with the shafte, that he in Hydraes hyde did flynge. You Aares haue yeelde a clattring noyse I knowe, I knowe of olde, How vnto mee my Oracles are wonted to bee toulde, That when ye trembling flowre doth shake then hath my Goddes great, Uouchsafe to graunt mee my request as I did her intreate, I see Dianas waggon swife, not that whereon shee glydes, When all the night in darkned Sky with Face full ope shee rydes: With countnaunce bright and blandishing but when with heauy cheare, With dusky shimmering wanny globe, her lampe doth pale appeare. Or when shee trots about the heauens wyth horseheade rayned strayte, When Thessayle Witches with the threats of charming her doe bayte. So with thy dumpish dulled blase, thy cloudy faynting lyght, Sende out, amid the lowring sky, the heart of people smyght Wyth agonies of suddeyne dread, in straung and fearefull wyse, Compell the pretious brasen pannes with iarring noyse to ryse Through Corinth countrey euery where, to shielde thee fr? thie harme, Least headlong drawne thou be from heauen to earth by force of charme. An holy solempne sacryfice to worship thee wee make, Imbrewed with a bloudy turphe the kindled Torche doth take Thy sacred burning night fyre at the dampishe mory graue. Sore charged with thy troubled ghost my head I shaken haue, And ducking downe my Necke alowe wt shryking lowde haue shright, And groueling flat on floore in traunce haue lyen in dead mans plight. My ruffled Lockes about myne eares downe dagling haue ben bownde Tuckt vp about my temples twayne with gladsome garland crownde: A drery braunche is offred thee from filthy Stigis flood. As is the guise of Bacchus priestes the Coribanthes wood, With naked breast and dugges layde out Ile pricke with sacred blade Myne arme, that for the bubling bloude an issue may bee made, With trilling streames my purple bloude let drop on Th'aulter stones. My tender Childrens crusshed fleshe, and broken broosed bones Lerne how to brooke with hardned heart: in practise put the trade To florishe fearce, and keepe a coyle, with naked glittring blade: I sprinkled holy water haue, the launce once being made, If tyred thou complaynest that my cryes thee ouerlade, Giue pardon to my ernest suite, O Perseus sister deare, Still Iason is the onely cause that vrgeth mee to reare With squeking voyce thy noysome beames, that sting like shot of bo So season thou those sawced robes to worke Creusas woe, Where with when shee shall pranke her selfe the poyson by and by To rot her inward mary out, within her bones may fry, The secret fyer bleares their eyes with glosse of yeallow golde, The which Prometheus gaue to mee that fyer fylcher bolde. On whom for robbery that he did in heauens aboue commit, With massy payse great Caucasus th'unweldy hill doth sit, Whert vnder with vnwasted wombe he lyes, and payes his payne, To feede the cr?ming foule with gubs of guts that growes agayne. He taught mee with a prety sleyght of conning, how to hyde The strength of fyer close kept in, that may not be espyde, This lyuely tinder Mulciber hath forged for my sake, That tempred is with brymstone quick at fyrst touch and take. Eke of my Cosen Phaëton a wyldefyer flake I haue His flames the monstrous staghard rough Chimera to mee gaue, In head and breast a Lyon grim, and from the Rump behynde He sweepes the flower with lagging Tayle of Serpent fearce by kynde In Rybbes, and Loynes along his paunche yshaped lyke a Goate. These Fumes that out the Bull perbrakte from fyry spewinge throat I gotten haue and brayde it with Medusas bitter gall Commaunding it in secret sorte to duske and couer all: Breath on these venoms Hecate with deadly myght inspyre, Preserue the touching poulder of my secret couert fyre, O graunt that these my cloked craftes so may bewitch theyr Eyes, That lykelyhoode of treason none they may heerein surmyse: So worke that they in handling it may feele no kynde of heate: Her stewing breast, her seathing vaynes, let feruent fyer freate And force her rosted pyning lymmes, to drop and melt away, Let smoke her rotten broyling bones: enflame this bryde to day To cast a lyght with greater gleede on fryseled blasing heare Then is the shyning flame that doth the wedding torches beare. My suite is harde, thryse Hecate a dreadfull barking gaue From dolefull cloude a sacred flash of flamy sparkes shee draue. Eche poysons pryde fulfilled is: call forth my chyldren deare, By whom vnto the cursed Bryde these presentes you may beare: Goe forth, goe forth my lytle Babes, your mothers cursed fruite, Goe, goe, employ your paynes with brybe and earnest humble suits To purchase grace, and eke to earne you fauour in her sight. That both a mother is to you, and rules with Ladies might. Goe on, apply your charge apace, and hye you home agayne, That with embracing you I may my last farewell attayne. Chorus. What sharpe assaultes of cruell CVPIDS flame Wyth gyddie heade thus tosseth to and froe, This bedlem Wyght, and diuelysh despret dame What rouing rage her pricks to worke this woe? Rough rancours vile congeales her frosen face, Her hawty breast bumbasted is vvyth pryde, Shee shakes her heade, shee stalkes vvyth stately pace. Shee threates our king more then doth her betyde. Who would her deeme to bee a banisht wyght, Whose skarlet Cheekes doe glowe with rosy red? In faynting Face, with pale and wanny whyght The sanguyne hewe exyled thence is fled Her chaunging lookes no colour longe can holde, Her shifting feete still trauasse to and froe. Euen as the fearce and rauening Tyger olde That doth vnware his sucking whelpes forgoe, Doth rampe, and rage, most eger ferce and wood, Among the shrubs and busshes that doe growe On Ganges stronde that golden sanded flood, Whose siluer streame through India doth flowe. Euen so MEDEA sometime vvantes her wits To rule the rage of her vnbrydeled ire, Nowe UENVS Sonne, wyth busie froward fits, Nowe Wrath, and Loue enkyndle both the fire. What shall shee doe? when will this heynous wyght With forwarde foote bee packing hence away, From Greece? to ease our Realme of terrour quight, And prynces twayne whom she so sore doth fray: Nowe Phœbus lodge thy Charyot in the West, Let neyther Raynes, nor Brydle stay thy Race, Let groueling light with Dulceat nyght opprest In cloking Cloudes wrapt vp his muffled Face, Let Hesperus the loadesman of the nyght, In Western floode drench deepe the day so bryght.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE FIFTH ACTE. Nuntius. Chorus. Nutrix. Medea. Iason. All things are topsy turuy turnde, and wasted cleane to nought. To passing great calamity our Kingdome State is brought. The Syre, and Daughter burnt to dust in blendred Cynders lye. C. What trayne hath them entrapt? N?. Such as are made for Kinges to dye, False traitrous gifts. C. What priuy guile could wrapped be in those? N?. And I doe meruayle at this thing and skant I can suppose That such a mischiefe might be wrought by any such deuice Ch. Report how this destruction and ruine should aryse N?. The fyzzing flame most egerly doth scoure with sweeping sway Eache corner of the Prynces court, as though it should obay, Commaunded therevnto so flat on flowre the Pallace falles: Wee are in dread least further it will take the townishe walles. Ch. Cast quenching water on it then to slake the greedy flame. N?. And this that seemeth very straunge doe happen in the same, The water feedes the fier fast, the more that wee doe toyle It to suppresse, with hotter rage the heate begins to boyle: Those thinges that wee haue gotten for our help it doth enioy. Nut. Medea thou that doest so sore king Pelops lande anoy, Twine hence in hast thy forwarde foote, at all assayes depart To any other kinde of coaste. Me. Can I finde in my hart To shun this lande? if hence I had first falne away by flight, I would haue traueled backe agayne, to gase at such a sight. To stande and see this wedding new, why stayst thou doting mynde? Apply, apply, thy sore attempt, that good successe doth finde. What great exployt is this, that thou of vengeaunce dost enioy? Still art thou blynded witlesse wench with vale of Venus boy? Is this suffisaunce for the griefe? is roote of rancour ded, If Iason leade a single lyfe in solitary bed? Some netling, thorny, stinging plagues vnpractised deuise: Prepare thy selfe in redines and fall to on this wyse: Let all bee fishe that commes to Net, haue no respect of ryghte, From mynde on mischiefe fixed fast let shame be banisht quyte: The vengeaunce they receaued at my lytle chyldrens hand, Is nothing worth: in earnest ire ententiue must thou stand. When heate of wrath begins to coole, cheere vp thy selfe agayne: Rayse vp those touches olde that wonted were in thee to raygne, That buried deepe in breast doe lye: and as for all the same That yet is wrought: Of godlinesse let it vsurpe the name: Doe this, and I shall teach them learne, what tryfling cast it was, And common practisde flimflam trick that erst I brought to passe. By this my raging malady a preamble hath made, To shew what howgier heapes of harmes shall shortly them inuade What durst my rude vnskilfull hand assay that was of wayght? What could the mallice of a Gyrle inuent her foes to bayte? Still conuersaunt with wicked feates Medea am I made. My blunt and dulled braynes hath so ben beate about this trade. O so I ioy, I ioy, that I smote of my brothers head, And slasht his members of: eake that from parents had I fled: And fliched haue the priuy fleece, loe Mars that sacred was. It glads my heart that I to bring olde Pelias death to passe: Haue set his daughters all on worke: O griefe picke out a way Not any guilt thou shalt with vnacquainted hand assay Against whom wrath entendest thou to bend thyne Irefull might? Or with what weapon dost thou meane thy trayterous foes to smight? I know not what my wrathfull minde consulted hath within, And to bewray it to himselfe, I dare not yet begin. O rash and vnaduised foole, I make to hasty speede: O that my Foe had gotten of his Harlots body Seede: But what so euer thou by him enioyest, suppose the same To bee Creusas Babes, of them let her enioy the name. This vengeaunce, this doth like mee well good reason is there, why, The last attempt of ils, thou must with stomacke stout apply. Alas yee litle seely fooles that erst my children were, The plaguing price of Fathers fault submit your selues to beare. O, horrour huge with sodayne stroke my heart doth ouercom: With ycie dulling colde congealde my Members all benum. My shiuering lims appauled sore for gastly feare doe quake, And banisht rage of malice hoate begins it selfe to slake: The hatefull heart of wife agaynst her Spouse hath yeelded place, And pitious mothers mercy milde restoreth natures face. O shall I shed their guiltlesse bloude? shall I the frame vnfoulde Of that, which louing natures hande hath wrought in me her moulde? O doting fury chaunge thy minde, conceiue a better thought, Let not this haynous sauage deede by meanes of mee be wrought. What cryme haue they (poore fooles) c?mit, for which they should abye? Upon theyr Father Iason right all blot of blame should lye. Medea yet theyr Mother I am worser farre then hee. Tush let them frankly goe to wracke no kith nor kin to mee They are: dispatch them out of hand: holde, holde, my babes they be God wot, most harmelesse lambes they are, no crime nor fault haue they Alas they bee mere innocents, I doe not this denay: So was my brother whom I slew: O false reuolting mynde, Why dost thou staggring to and fro such chaunge of fancies fynde? Why is my Face be sprent with teares, what makes mee falter so, That wrath &amp; loue with striuing thoughts doe leade mee to and fro? Such fighting fancies bickringe stormes my swaruing minde detarre, As when betwene the wrestling windes is raysed wrangling warre, Eche where the tumbling wallowing waues, are hoyst and reared hye Amid the iustling swolues of seas, that hot in fury frye: Eu? so my hart with strugling thoughts now sinks, now swells amaine, Wrath sometyme chaseth vertue out, and vertue wrath agayne. O yeelde thee, yeelde, a grising griefe, to vertue yeelde thy place: Thou onely comforte of our stocke in this afflicted case, Come heather, come deere loued Impe, with colling mee imbrace, Whyle that by me your mother deere sweete Boyes yee are enioyed, So long God graunt your Father may you kepe from harme vncloyed. Exile and flight approach on mee, and they shall by and by Be pulde perforce out of myne armes, with vapourde weeping Eye, Sore languishing with mourning heart, yet let them goe to graue Before their fathers Face, as they before their mothers haue: Now rancorus griefe, with firy fits begins to boyle agayne, The quenched coales of deadly hate do fressher force attayne. The rusty rancour harbred long within my cancred brest Starts vp, and stirres my hand anew in mischiefe to bee prest. O that the rablement of brats which swarmde aboute the syde Of Niobe that scornefull Dame, who perisht by her pryde Had taken lyfe out of his lymmes, O that the fates of heauen A fruictfull mother had me made of chyldren seuen and seuen. My barreyne wombe for my reuenge hath yeelded litle store: Yet for my sire and brother, twayne I haue, there needes no more: Whom seeke this rufflyng rowt of Feendes with gargell Uisage dight? Where will they deale theyr stripes, or wh? with whips of fier smight? Or whom with cruell scorching brande and Stygian faggot fell, With mischief great to cloy, entendes this army black of hell? A chopping Adder gan to hisse with wrethings wrapped rounde, As soone as did the lasshing whyp flerte out with yerking sounde. Whom bumping with thy rapping post Megæra wilt thou crush? Whose ghost doth heere mishapt from hell with scatered members rush? My slaughtred brothers ghost it is that vengeaunce coms to craue: According to his dyre request due vengeaunce shall hee haue. But flap thou fearce the fierbrandes full dasshed in myne Eyes, Dig, rent, scrape, burne, and squeas them out, loe ope my breast it lyes, To fighting furies bobbing strokes, O brother, brother bid These royles, that preasse to worrey mee, them selues away to rid. Downe to the silent soules alowe not taking any care: Let mee be left heare by my selfe alone, and doe not spare, To bast, and capperclaw these armes that drewe the bloudy blade: To quench the furies of thy sprite, that thus doe mee inuade, With this right hand the sacrifice on thaulter shalbe made. What meanes this sudden trampling noyse? a band of men in Armes Come bustling towarde vs, that mee will cloy with deadly harmes. To ende this slaughter set vpon I will my selfe conuay Up to the garrets of our house, come Nurce with me away, Bestow thy body hence with mee from daunger of our foes. Now thus my mynde on mischiefe set thou must thy selfe dispose, Let not the flickering fame and prayse in darkenesse bee exilde Of stomack stout, that you did vse in murthering of thy childe. Proclaime in peoples eares the prayse of cruell bloudy hand. IA. If any faythfull man here bee, whom ruine of his land. And slaughter of his Prynce doe cause in pensiue heart to bleede, Step forth that yee may take the wretch that wrought this deadly deede. Heere, heere, yee ioly champions lay loade with weapons heere, Haue now, hoyst vp this house, from low Foundacion vp it reare. ME. Now, now my Scepter guilt I haue recouered once agayne: My Fathers wronges reuenged are, and eke my brother slayne: The gouldens cattels Fleece returnde is to my natiue land, Possession of my realme I haue reclaymed to my hand: Come home is my virginity, that whilom went astray. O Gods as good as I coulde wisshe, O ioyfull wedding day, Goe shrowde thy selfe in darknesse dim, dispacht I haue this feate: Yet vengeaunce is not done inough, to coole our thristy heate. O soule why dost thou make delay? Why dost thou doubting stande? Goe foreward with it yet thou mayst, whyle doing is thy hande: The wrath that might should mynister doth qualefy his flame: The pryckes of sorrow twitch my heart attaynt with blusshing shame: Through rygour of thy heynous gore, O wretch, what hast thou done? Though I repent a caityfe vile I am, to slea my sonne: Alas I haue committed it, importunate delight, Still egged on my frowarde mynde that did against it fight: And loe the vayne coniect of this delight increaseth still, This onely is the thing, that wants vnto my wicked will, That Iasons eyes shoulde see this sight as yet I doe suppose, Nothing it is that I haue done, my trauell all I lose, That I employde in dyry deedes, vnlesse hee see the same. IA. Loe heere shee looketh out, and leanes vpon the houses frame, That pitchlong hanges with falling sway: heere heape your fiers fast, Whereby the flames that shee her selfe enkindled, may her wast. ME. Goe Iason, goe the obit rights the windinge sheete and graue Make ready for thy sonne, as last behoueth him to haue, Thy spouse and eke thy father in lawe that are entomde by mee Receiued haue the dutyes that to deade mens ghostes agree. This childe hath felt the deadly stroke and launce of fatall knife, And this with wailesome murther like shall lose her tender life. IA. By all the sacred ghostes of heauen, and by thy oft exile, And spousall bed, which breach of loue in mee did not defile, Now spare, and saue the life of him my childe and also thyne: What euer cryme committed is, I graunt it to be myne: Make mee a bloudy sacrifice to dew deserued death, Take from my sinfull guilty head the vse of vitall breath. ME. Nay sith thou wilt not haue it so as greeues thy pynched minde, Heere way to wreck my vengeaunce fell, my burning blade shall finde. Auaunt, now hence thou pesaunt prowd employ thy busy payne, To reape the fruites of virgins bed, and cast them of agayne When mothers they are made. IA. Let one for dew reuenge suffice. ME. If greedy thyrst of hungry handes that stil for vengeaunce cries, Myght quenched bee with bloude of one, then aske I none at all, And yet to staunche my hungry griefe the number is to small, If onely twayne I slea, if pleadge of loue lye secrete made, My bowels Ile vnbreast, and search my wombe with poking Blade. IA. Now finish out thy deadly deede, that enterprised is, No more entreataunce will I vse, yet onely graunt mee this, Delay awhyle his dolefull death, that I may take my flyght. Least that myne eyes wt bleeding hearte should vew that heauy sight. ME. Yet linger eger anguishe yet to slea this chylde of thyne. Ronne not to rashe with hasty speede, this dolefull day is myne: The time that wee obtayned haue of Creon, wee enioy. IA. O vile malitious mynded wretch my lothsome life destroy. ME. In crauing this thou speakst, that I should shew thee some releefe, Well goodinough, all this is done: O ruthfull giddy greefe, This is the onely sacrifice that I can thee prouide, Unthankfull Iason hether cast thy coyesh lookes asyde. Loe heare dost thou beholde thy wyfe? thus euer wonted I, When murther I had made, to scape, my way doth open lye That I may spring into the skyes: the flying serpents twayne Submitted haue theyr scaly Neckes to yoake of ratling wayne, Thou Father haue thy sonnes agayne, I in the wandring Skye In nymble wheeled Waggon swyfte, will ryde aduaunced hye. IA. Goe through the ample spaces wyde, infect the poysoned Ayre, Beare witnesse, grace of God is none in place of thy repayre. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>