<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Pocock, I., (Isaac), 1782-1835</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Pocock, I., (Isaac), 1782-1835</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">pocock i isaac 1782 1835</field>
      <field name="author_text">Pocock, I., (Isaac), 1782-1835</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1820's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V3.0741.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1823</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:461051</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Nigel ; or, The Crown Jewels ; A Play, in Five Acts</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Nigel ; or, The Crown Jewels ; A Play, in Five Acts</field>
      <field name="title_facet">nigel or the crown jewels</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">nigel or the crown jewels</field>
      <field name="title_text">Nigel ; or, The Crown Jewels ; A Play, in Five Acts</field>
      <field name="year_display">1823</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1823</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1823</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:461051&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:461051&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Pocock, I., (Isaac), 1782-1835&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;pocock i isaac 1782 1835&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Nigel ; or, The Crown Jewels ; A Play, in Five Acts&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;nigel or, the crown jewels&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1823&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1823&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Pocock, I., (Isaac)&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1782&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1835&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Nigel ; or, The Crown Jewels&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Play, in Five Acts&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;R. Wilks, Printer, [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1823&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3873388-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv30741&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Nigel ; or, The Crown Jewels&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Play, in Five Acts&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 225 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Nigel.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Melodrama.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1823.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 28 Jan 1823.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">NIGEL; OR, THE CROWN JEWELS, A Play, IN FIVE ACTS,</field>
      <field name="fulltext">INDUCTION. Enter a Lady, followed by an Author, in a cloak and black silk mask. Author. (Bowing and pointing to the side of the Stage, opposite to that on which they have entered.) This way will bring you to your box. Lady. Perhaps You're a Performer? Aut. No, ma'am—mind the traps— 'Tis as an Author I have sought my fashion. Lady. I doat on authors—genius is my passion. But why then mask'd? Aut. That I may not be known. Lady. What could you write and be so loath to own? Nothing equivocal, I hope. Aut. In me You see—or, but for this disguise, would see— And unknown champion in the muse's field, But more consider'd still, as more conceal'd, A guest in courts, in camps, in halls, in hovels— In short—the Author—of the Scottish Novels. Lady. Delightful! I've been three whole seasons dying For your acquaintance—Nay now, don't be flying— You'll come to me to-morrow evening—mind, Without your mask,—as soon as you have dined. A little early party— Aut. Pray excuse me. Lady. O, no excuses—now you sha'n't refuse me. Pledge me your word, or, in this public place, I vow I'll have that vizor from your face. Aut. I throw me on your honor then: you'll not Betray me now—my name is ?????? ?????. Lady. Dear, I'm so sorry. Aut. Wherefore? Lady. That's the name On ev'ry body's tongue—I meant to claim A secret to myself.—And did you write The Play then, we are come to see to night? Aut. I'm not its Author: though I fairly own 'Twas through my means it came before the town. It's one of those old plays, revis'd and clipt, Of which I've sev'ral yet, in manuscript, And from whose scenes you may have sometimes read A blank verse motto at my chapter's head. But, as the same event of James's day Founds my new Novel, and this ancient Play, The actors interweave such scenes of mine As come germanely to the play's design. Lady. Then, this is not, as former plays have been, The Novel shifted into act and scene? Aut. No: for this Novel, you will find, had not, Like some before it, a theatric plot. Be not displeas'd then, pray you, nor surpriz'd, If, for a Novel closely dramatiz'd, You find a plain, old-fashion'd Play before ye, With the old freedom, varying from the story, And following only one great rule and measure, The aim to give a gentle audience pleasure. Lady. I wish no scenes but your's had been embrac'd; Then I might praise, and not commit my taste; But to applaud an unestablish'd Poet— I may get wrong, perhaps before I know it. Now Lady Light-blue, who's a first-rate wit, Said the last Comedy was quite a hit: Miss Sourby, who's a critic and blue stocking, Said never any thing was half so shocking: Which was I to believe?—I do protest, I never in my life was more distrest! Aut. To-night, at least, applaud: and never fear But that your smile will carry judgments here; E'en the cross critics may be half controul'd— Lady. Let but the critics know your Play is old. And they'll uphold you, be it but to force Those horrid, forward moderns off the course. Aut. Spare the poor moderns; I am of their crew. Lady. Yes, sir; but all the world agree, that you Unlike the moderns of our tiresome race, Will come, in time, to have an ancient's place. Nay, more; I apprehend, that if the Play, Old as you call it, should succeed to day, The house must thank, in far the first degree, That modern muse, (long modern may she be,) Who takes her name from first-born Waverley!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DRAMATIS PERSONÆ. King James the First Mr. Bartley Duke of Buckingham Mr. Hunt Lord Dalgarno, an English nobleman Mr. C. Kemble Lord Nigel, a Scottish nobleman Mr. Abbott Sir Geoffrey Growther, an Officer of the Tower Guard Mr. Chapman Master Heriot, Goldsmith to the King Mr. Egerton Skourlie, a Scrivener, an exceeding knave Mr. Farren Trapbois, a miserly Usurer, in his dotage Mr. Blanchard Jenkin Vincent, commonly called Jin Vin, apprentice to Heriot Mr. Horrebow Strappet, a City Barber Mr. Fawcett Captain Peppercole, a cowardly Bully Mr. Farley Hildebrod, Bailiff of Whitefriar's sanctuary Mr. Taylor Skelter, a broken down Lawyer of Whitefriars Mr. Norris George, a serving man of Heriot Mr. Mears Dalgarno's Page Master Longhurst Nigel's Page Master C. Parsloe Skourlie's Clerk Mr. Ley Martha, Daughter of Trapbois Miss Lacy Margaret, Niece of Heriot Miss Foote Bridget, Wife of Strappet Mrs. Chatterley. Lords, Pages, Attendants, Huntsmen, Guards, Servants, Porters, Inhabitants of Whitefriars, and Crowd.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Scenes—In London, Westminster, and Greenwich.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Time—From the Afternoon of one day to the Afternoon of the next.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. SCENE I. An Apartment splendidly furnished, after the fashion of King James's time, representing a Saloon in Dalgarno's House. Enter Skourlie, and Page yawning. Skour. What, boy, asleep? Page. My Lord Dalgarno leaves me No rest, sir. I was up all night, i'th'city, With music, under master Heriot's windows, Piping at his niece, Marg'ret. Skour. Hum! I'll wait His lordship's leisure. [Exit Page. What, Dalgarno's glance Burns upon Marg'ret still? Why, I'm a gull At fifty years of age, thus to affect A chitty spinster—yet, does she inflame My thoughts, almost to slight my kinder mistress, The wealth I've woo'd and won, through good and ill. Dalgarno's schemes have paid me passably, But luck has made him rash, and frow'rd to deal with, And it were wise to cut the knot that binds us, Before I find a noose at t'other end. Enter Dalgarno, with letters; he calls to the Page. Dalg. Some wax! Dear woman loves a correspondent: To thrive with her a man must write his perj'ry, And be a rogue on record. Honest Skourlie! My ferret! mine edge-tool! my man of law! Skour. Your servant still. Re-enter Page, with sealing wax and taper, which he places on the table, and exit. Dalg. My lord of Buckingham Wants money. [sealing the letters.] Skour. Will you lend it? Dalg. Why, my purse Is much extenuated. Luck has run Against me with the dice. Then, my adventure In last year's pirate-cruiser, proved a loss: And inland, not a traveller of mark Has, for these three months, plumped into the toil Of our night-rangers: yet these gentry still Eat at my charge. Well, desp'rate fortunes look For desp'rate ventures. Skour. I'd have no such crew Of broken gentlemen; they live too high, And game too deep, to make the masque and pistol Keep them respectably, and yield a profit. Then if good luck does blow a windfall, comes Some rogue or other, for a hushing bribe, 'Till I am almost drain'd to begg'ry. Dalg. Thou! Thou'rt made of gold! thy very self an ingot, As hard, as dull, as ductile, and as dingy. Tush! never fear! wert thou tried, cast, condemned, I could obtain thy pardon through the duke. So, in a word, his Grace must have this money, And thou must lend it. Skour. I, my Lord! Dalg. No doubt; You shall have my security. Skour. My Lord,— Dalg. Good, round security. Have you forgot The loan I made to Nigel in your name, Taking a mortgage of his patrimony Worth ten times what I lent? To-morrow ends The term of payment; you foreclose: and I Possess the land. Is that security? Skour. He yet may pay the mortgage. Dalg. I have lull'd His diligence: fool'd him, with daily hopes Of getting from the king some certain monies He sues for at th'Exchequer; while the duke, My right good friend, keeps back his poor petitions From the king's sight and knowledge. Peppercole (without.) Pep. Tell not me, I have th'access. Dalg. 'Tis Captain Peppercole. As thou'rt my business, so is he my pleasure, Fetches and carries like a dog: can bark As loud, and take the lash as patiently: And for a go-between, there's nothing serves Like your coarse fellow, whom no husband frets at, Nor jealous brother doubts. Enter Peppercole: he is dressed in a thickset velvet jerkin, having a patch over one eye, and part of one cheek: buff gloves, with huge tops, almost to the elbows; and a large black-hilted back sword and dagger, in a very wide buff belt; he looks back angrily on his entrance, as chiding the servants who have delayed him. Pep. Distinguish, 'twixt Vile dun, and graced Soldado! Dalg. (to Peppercole) Here's employ For thy exub'rant humour: see this letter To Margaret Heriot's hands. Pep. She still avoids All chance of interview. Dalg. As wild as birds In a wet autumn! Pep. From her wench I gather That my young madam's notion doth incline To your companion—pish! the Scottish lordling, Whose lodging is so deep a secret— Dalg. Nigel? Pep. 'Tis he. Dalg. Why then my path lies clear! To-morrow, At six o'clock, we have him! Mind, no grace, (To Skourlie) Not half an hour. If he pay not his mortgage, Ev'n as the clock strikes, I enforce my forfeit, And become master of his fate. Re-enter Page. Page. My lord, Your lordship's barber. Pep. Strappet! prince of praters! Dalg. Bully, beware of treas'nous words against The barber! He's your master paramount! He clips the proudest; makes the bravest bleed; Comes, as the Gaul of old strode up the senate, And plucks the grey patrician by the chin: Nor death, nor mighty love, more universal: For every throat he has his weapon bared, And 'twixt his thumb and finger flits the breath Of all men's nostrils: Scandalum of him Must be a præmunire at the least. Admit him. [Exit Page. (To Skourlie) So, you'll see to Nigel. Skour. (significantly) Nigel, Or whomso else your Marg'ret may affect, No means of mine shall be untried to crush. Re-enter Page, ushering in Strappet, with a barber's basin under his arm, in one hand a dressing case, and in the other a note. Strap. Noon, my lord, past; please be adorn'd to-day? Dalg. (Sitting down). What have you there? Strap. (Delivering the note). Note, from Lord Nigel. [Dalgarno reading the note, while Strappet trims him with scissars and curling irons.] Dalg. Call At three—must wait at home until that hour For Master Heriot— Strap. Aye, my dame was saying The good man meant to call—pretty niece Marg'et To fetch him thence, upon her new white poney, Just for an airing—promised my good woman To let us see the nag—A perfect pattern, I'm told, that hobby. Dalg. Marg'ret call at Nigel's! Now could one trace what nook he makes his lodging, Hidden so charily from boon companions, And yet so visited by bonny wenches, One might give chase to this young mistress. Friend, Know'st thou his lodging? Strap. Oh, undoubtedly: It is my pride to be his body shaver. Chin some what long: Takes me twelve seconds more His chin, than any nobleman's whereof I have the handling—Always grieve to find Friend's faces long. Dalg. And where then is this lodging? Strap. Afraid I grazed—black patch will set all right: The DUKE had one, but two day past, since which Four yards three quarters of this black, believe me, Have been cut up in patches for the courtiers. (Puts on a Patch.) Dalg. And Nigel's lodging, fellow? Strap. Soft, my Lord, You will get touched again. Dalg. And so shall you, Unless— Strap. In truth, he little likes to have His lodging known,—purse, possibly, but low,— So, in your lordship's ear—I'm sure your lordship Will not betray my information—then, Between ourselves, he lodges—in my house. Dalg. What, somewhere by Paul's wharf? Strap. My noble lord, Why not? looks airy out—ships all alive— The courtiers to and fro upon the river, Betwixt Whitehall and Greenwich, as the Court Shifts:—Always see the courtiers with the tide, Saving your lordship's presence. Dalg. Well, and which Of all the crooked alleys, that compose That wilderness of tenements, may be thine? Strap. Long pole, next the old Boar: no doubt; you know The old Boar new revived—superb for spare-ribs— Landlord at door, fat man, red doublet: worth A thousand pound, they tell me,—pretty penny, Those griskins:—better singeing of pig's faces, Than beautifying courtiers'!—you'll excuse My little joke, my lord. Dalg. You're the kind husband Of pretty Bridget, then, whom we have heard of? Strap. Heard of, my lord?—How so, my lord? Dalg. O, nothing. [Strappet pauses aghast. Get on, sir—only when a lodger wins The friendship of a buxom landlady— Strap. Surely Lord Nigel says not that? Dalg. Mere friendship— Get on. Strap. You're almost finish'd— Dalg. Faith, well nigh: Two minutes more would finish me outright. Order the horses. [Calling to the side scene. Strap. For my wife, (turning back a loose hair) one touch To bring that straggler in. (puts up his instruments.) Pep. (to Dalgarno, coming forward and shaking his head at Strappet,) Had I not reason? Dalg. (to Pep.) For once. Pep. (Advancing upon Strappet.) Why, then, the curse of tongues be on thee; Rust eat thy razors up—disuse resolve The bristles of thy brushes— Strap. (to Dalgarno.) Just a word— Pep. (walking Strappet backward to the side scene.) The edge forsake thy polished steel— Strap. Like fortune Wait on thy vulgar brass! Pep. (pushing him off.) Moths gorge thy napkins, And splitting tooth-aches waste thy case of combs! [Exit Strappet. Dalg. At last, she takes the air, this pouting Marg'ret! My boots, boy: come, now, if I do but find Her pretty face where this old babbler points me, [Page brings boots, which Dalgarno puts on. It shall go hard, but I will part my damsel From her dull uncle. You, smooth-faced iniquity, to Skourlie) And copper bully, (to Peppercole) westward-hoe: wait for me At the Park-gate, by Charing.—Our fair citizens, When they go ambling, much affect the Park— And look you've there some sturdy swagg'rer, strong I' the arm, and not too weak i'th'conscience, with My page and horses— [Going and looking behind to Peppercole, who is following him.] And, dost hear, a pillion To suit a dainty dame. Exit, followed by Peppercole and Page. Skour. (alone) Yes, I'll be there, To balk that prank, I ween. And if I do, Why not step in at once, with honest offers, And foil my rakish lord? True, my first youth Is gone; but I have better metal, wealth, To make the charge withal; and woman's heart Is seldom mailed in such high temper'd stuff, As to be gold proof. Courage; we will try her! [Exit. SCENE II. The King's closet in Whitehall Palace, hung with pictures: the appointments and furniture costly, but disordered. On a table a high-crowned grey hat, encircled by a carkanet of large rubies. King James and Heriot are discovered. The King's doublet is of quilted green velvet, giving a protuberant appearance to his figure; with a sad coloured night-gown, from the pocket of which peeps a hunting horn; on his head is a blue-velvet night-cap with a heron plume in front. Heriot is habited richly, though gravely, in a cloak of black velvet, and hose of the same, slashed with purple silk; a doublet or purple cloth with numerous buttons of silver fillagree; a flat cap in his hand, a triple gold chain round his neck, and a silver writing case in his belt. They come forward. James. Alack, I doubt, friend Heriot, the whole wisdom Of Scotland left it, when we took our travels Southward. Her. The wise, an't please your majesty, Follow the wisest, ev'n as stags their leader. James. Aye, but the fools come too. No further back Than yester-noon, an Edinburgh beggar, Each dud upon whose back was taking leave Of its next neighbour, splash'd before our horse, And thrust a smear'd petition in our hand About our mother's debts, and sic-like trash. Whereat, our beast uprear'd, and, had we not Such seat as few, or kings, or subjects, have, We'd laid our gracious length upon the causeway. Oh, there is not a loon among 'em kens How a petition should be brought before The face of majesty! Her. Then, would I knew it, Were't but to teach my unbred countrymen. James. Now, troth, but ye're a civilized fellow, Geordie, And I'll bestow the lesson on you. First, Ye must approach the regal presence, thus, Shad'wing your forehead with your hand. (Heriot does so.) That's well, That's in a comely manner. Kneel, sir, next, As ye would kiss our garment's hem, or shoe-latch. (Heriot does so.) Now, (very well enacted,) we prevent This motion, signing you to rise; but you, Having a boon to beg, obey not yet, But, gliding thus your hand into your pouch, Bring forth your scroll, and place it rev'rently In our stretch'd hand. Her. (Putting a roll of paper into James's hands.) So, by your grace's goodness— James. (startled) What! have we taught the manual exercise To you, that you should thus present your piece At our own sacred body! Her. My presumption, Which yet I trust your princely clemency Will deign to pardon, is not for myself. James. (Raising him.) The worse: I wish it were: I would be glad To do thee kindness, Geordie: thou hast served Our need more times than once, mine honest goldsmith. (Opening the scroll). But how? a dun? Why aye, 'tis true enough, We owed some siller to Lord Nigel's father; But we are not absconding! What hath prick'd Nigel to dun us for't? Her. Alas! his want, sir, And not his will. Unless, ere night to-morrow, He raise six thousand pieces, all his lands, Mortgaged for that amount, but ten times worth So poor a sum, will pass for ever from him Into the lender's grasp. James. It must not be! Our old friend's son, a peer, thrust from his heritage By a base money'd carle! A gracious youth too; Bows well; hath parts and lore: Cannot you raise The siller, George? Her. Had not mistaken shame Withheld Lord Nigel from disclosing to me The strait he labours in, until this morning, I might have help'd him; but the sum I gather'd Yesterday, for your grace's privy purse, Has drain'd, not simply all my gold, but ev'n My ready means of borrowing. James. Now ye think Our purse is full. Ye're wrong: on a king's word All's gone, paid out, to th'last: It were as hopeful To ask the breeks of a wild Highlandman. Your credit strain'd too? Her. Aye, sir. James. Here, old Levite, (Taking the rubies from his hat) Raise him the gold on these. You've got them pledged For larger sums ere now: we will redeem them From the next subsidy. Oons, no more kneeling! Your plaguy genuflexions have already Cost us six thousand—if you should kneel down A second time, we're bankrupt. Her. In the name, then, Of my Lord Nigel— James. Name of nonsense, man, Get thee away, and do it. (Calling for his Pages at the side scene.) To the gate there, Knaves! keep a London goldsmith waiting, while Boys truss their points! he'll stir you!—So— Pages hurry across the stage, showing out Heriot, who bows and exit. Aye, jingler— Aye, canny gold and silver! that's the kind Makes way with those that keep the doors of kings! [Exit. SCENE III. Nigel's lodging. In the back scene, a wide window, like that of a cabin, shewing the river and ships. An old fashioned staircase descending into the room, down the steps of which, enter Nigel habited in a lavender coloured dress, with plaid scarf. A boy is bringing in a table with a cloth, cold meat, &amp;c. Nigel. Nothing from Lord Dalgarno? this suspense Is worse than tedious. Did you give John Strappet My note for him? (Sits down at the table.) Boy. My lord, I did. Nigel. Well then, I shall not want you yet. [Exit Boy. Enter Bridget dressed in a tight, well laced boddice, a short red petticoat, with a slight edging of silver lace, and brightly blacked shoes, with buckles. She brings in a hand-box. My gracious hostess, What cumbers you? Bridg. The dress I've been to fetch For you, my lord; what you're to wear to-morrow I'th'masque the Duke of Buckingham's to give. Nigel. Oh, thank ye. Bridg. I should like to see it; (puts the box down and unties the cord round it.) Sha'n't I Just spread it out? 'twould do these trifles good (A knock is heard at the street door.) If they were air'd. Nigel. (rising to receive Heriot.) No matter for the present. Enter Heriot, whom Nigel takes by the hand. Heriot. (After taking off his cap, and respectfully acknowledging the salutation of Nigel.) I fancy, dame, my lord can spare you, now. Bridg. (Retiring with spleen, from the band-box.) Spare! that's a mighty fav'rite word i'th'city! [Exit. Nigel. No help, I fear, good friend, with that hard loan My lands are pledged for. Her. But I hear the lender Is your sworn friend. Nigel. Skourlie, the scriv'ner sworn My friend! 'twas he, that lent it. Her. You're deceiv'd: He's but the nominal and formal party: The lender,—start not,—is my Lord Dalgarno. Nigel. Impossible: 'tis he that undertakes T'enforce my claim upon the king, for payment Of debts which would redeem the land. Her. And therefore Your claim is not enforced. He hungers too After those forfeitures of your late kinsman I'th'north, whereof you have besought the king To make release to you. Nigel. A nobleman, So frank and gay,—so base! I'll not believe it. Her. I've certain cause to know,—for I have channels Of knowledge at the Court,—that Lord Dalgarno Already has possessed the Duke of Buckingham, To your disparagement. Nigel. I'll give him thanks for 't. Her. We of the city seldom speak on hearsay; But I much doubt him in yet blacker dealings. Justice of late hath slung her sword so loose, That felony scarce slurs a ruffling gallant: One coronet, or two, have fused their gold Into the pirates' fierce copartnery: Nay, and ev'n inland, some, not low-born, ride At night, with knife, lanthorn, and cloak, wherever A fat pouch tempts the hazard. Nigel. Faith, the pardon To Overbury's titled murderers, Th'impunity wherewith, in Paul's church aisle, Ruffians by trade ply, through broad day, for custom, These are examples to relax opinion, And lend brute force a warrant. Her. Hence, our courtiers Laugh at such things for frolics. Pardon me, If I beseech you that you be more wary, Henceforth, of your allies. This time, I trust, Your false friend's policy is foil'd; for see What the king's justice sends. (Produces the rubies from a casket.) Nigel. How! the crown jewels! Her. To raise upon them what may pay the debt He owed your father, and redeem your lands. Nigel. My noble master! aye, and let me say My gen'rous friend! Go with me to the close Of this kind work, and help me to some agent Who shall procure the loan. Her. Command my service. 'Twill lead you to foul quarters: to Whitefriars, The den of thieves, and of the usurer, Trapbois; But the king's drafts have drain'd my better channels: The time is short; and, at whatever price, The full six thousand must be had to-morrow. Nigel. (Inclining his head to Heriot, and then calling at the side scene.) My cap and cloak! No page there? (To Heriot.) Oh, I left The cloak above. Nigel goes up the staircase. Her. I will but send away My niece, who waits for me upon her palfrey, Yonder. Nigel. (As he ascends the staircase.) I'm loath to part your company. Her. To-morrow will serve me: she shall go on As she was promised, to the Park: our men Will see her safe. Nigel disappears at the head of the stairs, and Heriot is going off at the side scene: enter Bridget meeting him. Bridg. What did your lordship call for? Her. Where is his boy? Bridg. I know not: loit'ring somewhere. Her. That's pity! 'Twere more seemly that his servant Wait on his call, than that his hostess come So often to his chamber. [Exit. Bridg. Well, I'm sure! Who should have thought of that? Keep your advice For your own folk, old tinsmith! I've a husband To lecture me, as wise, and very near As old, as you are; and that's quite enough For one young woman. (Her eye glances on the box.) Were not this the time To get my little peep? (Walks round the box: then takes out a domino, and a hat with a feather.) How very pretty! I've a month's mind to try how I should suit This kind of rattletrap. (Puts on the hat: the plumes flap in her face.) Feathers enough! But, as for this, (putting on the domino,) I can't make out the sleeve. Oh! now its right! During the latter part of this soliloquy, Nigel has descended the staircase, with his cap and cloak; and, coming on tiptoe down the stage, has been trying to get a side view of Bridget's face, which, however, fronting the audience, has throughout been averted from him. Nigel. What lovely visitor Does me this honour? Bridg. (Not perceiving him, and still occupied in arranging the dress) If there was a glass, That one might know what's the effect of it! Nigel. (Coming close behind, and recognizing her) Very becoming, dame, upon my word. Bridg. (Screaming, and starting back, so as to fall into his open arms.) Mercy upon me, how you made me jump! Dear heart! I thought your lordship had been out. During this alarm of Bridget, Strappet has entered, ushering in Heriot. Strap. Did you think I was out, too? Bridg. (Laughing.) You're out, now! Her. My lord, I fear we come inopportunely. Nigel. Appearances are awkward; but you'll find All simple. Bridg. Very. Strap. No, not all: you'll not Find me so simple. Nigel. I was wrong, I own, In peeping at a lady's toilet; but She look'd so well (to Strappet)—nay, now, I beg your pardon— Good host, you won't be angry with poor Bridget For looking well,—she can't help that, you know. [Exit Nigel, taking Heriot by the arm. Strap. Just in the nick, I fancy. Bridg. Now you think You have been near to have an honour done you, Which was not dreamt of. Strap. Not so sure of that, It jumps with what I've heard; for let me tell you, Mistress, your name is rife with rakish lords, That talk of pretty faces. Bridg. And what then? Worse faces have been spoken of, I trow, Than mine; nor will I hide it, good man, simply Because you're old and jealous.—I say, John, Who was it told you of my pretty face? Strap. Such as could little judge, be sure of that. Come, graceless madam, find some other haunt Than this apartment. Bridg. Well, don't madam me! I've done no harm. Strap. That's as may be: it looks Cursedly like it. Bridg. What, you dont believe me? Let my lord witness whether— Strap. A fine witness! I fancy, when a husband is abroad, The key's the only witness he should trust. [Holding up the key. Out of this room, I say! Bridg. Well, an't I coming? Here's comfort for a woman! (Pointing to Strappet) O you brute, What have you ever done that could deserve A wife like me? Strap. Ah, what, indeed? Bridg. But, sirrah! There will be ways to pay you off; and if I dont, and soon, saving my own good credit, Say there's no spirit in woman. [He approaches her, she screams. Gah! dont lay Your ord'n'ry paws on me! [Exit. Strap. Bubble and squeak! Here's a brave tack forsooth! Spirit! Why, gemini, To hear her squall, you'd think 'twas she had caught Me in the arms of frailty. Spirit, indeed! Good husband, if you'd scape unscratch'd, you'd better Ev'n stray yourself, than find a fair wife straying: The more her fault, more your offence to spy it: No matter, though you saw with your own eyes, She's wrong'd and you're a brute; whiz comes the storm,— Rain, light'ning, thunder, bounce, blaze, pelt, slap, rattle— And that is what the soft sex call,—a spirit! [Exit. END OF ACT I.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. SCENE I. St. James's Park. Enter Dalgarno shading his eyes with his hand. Dalg. Hither she comes! Enter Buckingham. Buck. (Coming behind Dalgarno) My lord! Dalg. (Not turning his head towards him.) I'm busy, friend. Buck. Friend, yet not friendly! Dalg. (Turning round.) Duke of Buckingham! I pray your grace forgive me. Buck. Coming in When others quit the ride? Dalg. There is a reason. Buck. A fair one? Dalg. Very. Buck. Well, I'll spoil no sport. Dalg. She's drawing to the snare! The thousand pieces Shall wait upon your grace to-morrow. Buck. (Going.) Ever My excellent friend! [Exit Buckingham. At another entrance Skourlie comes on. Dalg. Now, is the captain ready? Skour. With his assistant bully. But I hope You meditate no force? Dalg. Force! Oh, no more Than woman thinks becoming. Now! dost quail, Dost quake, poltroon, and doubt? Why do I pay thee! For what base use retain thee? Skour. Good, my lord, For fraud, not force,—to shuffle, forge, or do Any safe villainy. Dalg. I shall so use thee. Stop—she dismounts! (looking out) Now whilst her blue coat holds Margaret crosses at the back of the stage, attended by Jin. Vin. who wears thick close curls, and a flat 'prentice's cap, set obliquely on the head. The nags, my foot-page, as in boyish sport, Will cut the reins, and turn the steeds a-drift. In the confusion of pursuit, our captain Will place her on my roan, which is in waiting Near, with a pillion. As for you, Sir Softly Watch here, and on pretence to keep the peace, Make such cross movements as may best impede Her men, and give us time to clear our prize. (Dalgarno puts on his mask, and retires to the back of the stage with Skourlie.) Re-enter Margaret and Jin. Vin. Jin. Your voice, sweet mistress Marg'et, soft as 'tis, More stirs my heart, than will St. Dunstan's clock, When the last hour of my indenture strikes. Marg. This to your masters' niece! I pray young man Know your place better: There now, Mister Jenkin, While you prate thus, some other idle 'prentice Has cut my palfrey's reins! Fine doings, sir, To meet my uncle's ears! There,—there, the horses Both racing off! (looking out). Jin. (Springing forward.) But your one word can give me A greyhound's speed, to shoot a-head, and turn them! [Exit. Marg. [alone]. Who should have thought of such presumption? He, A flat cap 'prentice! There! he'll never catch [Whimpering.] Those runaways—O, I am vex'd to weeping. Enter Peppercole. Pep. My fellow, mistress has a horse at hand, Will carry double,—at your service, mistress. Marg. Your pardon, sir;—my haste is not so urgent. Pep. You have no cause to fear. My steed has stood The loud artill'ry,—borne me, madam, full Against a grove of spears.—What, fellow! Ho! Enter a Bully. Marg. [To Pep.] Sir, I request your absence. Pep. I am more Your friend, than to obey you. Take the maiden Up on your pillion. Marg. Help! Why, Jenkin! George! Re-enter Jin. Vin. with George. Jin. Curs, cow'rds, let go! (Jin. Vin, with his Stick, attacks the assistant Bully, while George, with his, engages Peppercole, who immediately runs away. George then comes to the assistance of Jin. Vin, upon which Dalgarno steps forward). Dalg. Cow'rds, say you? two to one. And call that one a coward! (Dalgarno collars George, takes his stick from him, and drives him off; while Jin. Vin. and the assistant bully go out fighting, so as to leave Dalgarno alone with Margaret.) Now fair mistress, Let me conduct you. Marg. Sir, I pray you, quit Your most discourteous hold. You should be one Of better breeding. Dalg. Nay, you must forgive This little violence: 'tis to preserve you That I seem thus ungentle. (She struggles.) By my soul,— Enter Nigel. Nigel. What! talks Dalgarno of his soul? And that In forcing a weak girl? Marg. (To Nigel, as if imploring his interference.) My lord! (Dalgarno, holding Margaret's hand, and addressing Nigel, who is trying to disengage her.) Dalg. Let go! This lady's in my hands; and were she not, The king's park is no place for quarrelling,— Except to those who wish to do it safely. Put up, and seek some place where 'tis less penal To draw, than in the precincts of the court. Nigel. The better—I shall rid them of a traitor. Dalg. Stand off, I say. Nigel. If it were at the foot O'th'throne— Dalg. You do mistake your man. Nigel. Oh, no; Spite of your mask, I know you for Dalgarno, And know Dalgarno for—a villain. (Strikes him with his loose glove.) Now Is your sword ready? Dalg. Self-defence is now, My warrant. (They fight.) Marg. Not for me, Lord Nigel! (Margaret throws herself on a bank. Dalgarno, pressing upon Nigel, forces him to give ground, and follows him, fighting, off the stage. Skourlie comes forward as they are going off.) Skour. Sirs, In the king's name keep peace! Lord Nigel! tilting About a woman, in the very precincts Of the king's court! (Looking at Margaret.) What eyes! what lips! what ancles! She has possess'd me wholly. Pretty mistress, I'll see you safely lodged. Marg. More insult! (She rises.) Re-enter Jin. Vin. Jin. Whither Lead you that lady? Skour. Only to her friends. Jin. I am her friend; her humble friend and servant. Marg. He is, indeed, sir. Skour. O, I'm satisfied. I seek no brawl—'tis not my trade to fight— Only, next time I do a lady service, I'll have, at least, her thanks. Marg. Sir, pardon me: I knew not your kind purpose; but I'm thankful, Trust me, and so will be my uncle Heriot: He'll gladly see, and thank you. Jin. (Consequentially) Sir, you're thank'd! Skour. (To Margaret) Then, by your leave, I'll wait on you and him. (Aside.) Here's a brave introduction! To the lady I could not have a better—And the uncle,— Oh, trust my gold for courting uncles! Jin. (To Margaret) Courage, Mistress! Re-enter Nigel. Nigel. A moment's breath! Marg. You are pursued! Nigel. Not by Dalgarno: him I had disarmed: But the noise waked the yeomen of the guard, And, being forced to fly, I have, by doubling, Outrun the scent. Marg. Ah, me! Skour. Why know you not 'Tis a Star-chamber matter to be found With a drawn weapon here? Much more to strike! (Nigel is going.) Nay, if you'll fly, fly to the sanctuary, Get to Whitefriars; halt at the Temple-gate, I'll come anon, and find you out a refuge. Nigel. Good friend, much thanks. (To Margaret) May I have leave to touch This hand? (Raises Margaret's hand to his lips.) Jin. Hand off! the guard is after you— A pretty time for kissing, faith! Nigel. I'm gone! Marg. Fly, fly, my lord, and may her blessing speed you, Whom you have saved. [Exit Nigel. Jin. (To Margaret) There, you are mighty grateful! For half those thanks, I would have done it thrice. [Exeunt Margaret and Jin. Vin. Skour. (Alone) So, for Whitefriars! It is the common sink Of our gross London: and th'off-scourings run Readily to it. Yes, I'll see your lordship Housed in the Sanctu'ry: who hides, they say, Knows best to find: and though the vulgar bailiff Arrests not there, no priv'lege bars the visit You shall be honour'd with from the Star-chamber. Let me but have your scent for those staunch blood hounds, And if you 'scape to-morrow, to redeem Your mortgage from Dalgarno, or to cross My chace of Marg'ret, then is Andrew Skourlie A scriv'ner bred, and yet but half a knave! [Exit. SCENE II. The Tap-Room of the Bull Dog Tavern, in Whitefriars. A table with men drinking ale, in various eccentric and ruffian-like dresses. At the top, Hildebrod, monstrously fat, with a red nose, and but one eye; dressed in a plum-coloured jerkin, much worn and stained, and unbuttoned at the paunch. On his left, Peppercole, and on his right, Shelter, with rusty gown, band torn, and wig awry. Next to Peppercole, Trapbois, in a thread bare hood of kersey, drawn over his head and buttoned about his neck. Hildebrod, with the chorus, singing as the curtain rises. Hildebrod and chorus. Old Sir Simon the king, Old Sir Simon the king, With his malmsey nose, And his ale dropp'd hose, And sing, hey, ding-a-dong, ding! During the ditty, enter Skourlie, introducing Nigel, who averts his face as much as possible from the stare of the company. Skourlie makes a sign to Nigel not to advance until the close of the song, which Hildebrod carries to a conclusion, scrutinizing Nigel narrowly with his single eye. Hild. (After the song.) So ho! a foreigner! (To Pep. and Shelter) Sword and gown, make way. The form at bottom there,—'twill hold you both. (To Skourlie) What cully bring you? (He confers aside with Skourlie.) Peppercole goes sulkily to a form at the bottom of the table, and sits down on it, with his back to the audience. Pep. Shall the militant Make way for smock-faced Tyro? Shelter. (Following him.) Dost thou grumble, When learned coif is thus unseemly shoved Out of his bench? Hild. Silence, rebellious peers! Take off your hat, sir. (To Nigel.) You're in the Duke's presence, The Duke, sir, of Alsatia; which high title Graces unworthy me. Pep. Now, by my whiskers, 'Tis Nigel! (Peppercole, with a significant look, steals out.) Hild. Whoso seeks th'immunities Of our Whitefriars (hight, in loftier phrase Alsatia) must propound to us his name, Degree, and cause of seeking sanctuary. Skour. Or, so your statute wills, pay double garnish. Shelter. That is the law. Skour. Which this good gentleman Will do in Rhenish. All. Noble gentleman! Most gen'rous gallant! Hild. Bring our ducal archives! (To the Drawer.) Tapster! the Rhenish. (To Trapbois.) For a lodging, Trap, Thine may accommodate our novice. Trap. Aye, For a consideration. The Tapster brings in the Rhenish, which is drunk greedily. Hild. Come, that stave then, Alsatia's installation chaunt. Strike up. Hildebrod beckons to Nigel, and they converse apart during the following GLEE. From the touch of the tip, From the blight of the warrant, From the watchmen who skip On the Harman-beck's errand; From the bailiff's cramp speech, Which makes a man thrall, I charm thee from each, And I charm thee from all. Chorus. For, by spiggot and barrel, By bilbo and buff, Thou art sworn to the quarrel Of the blades of the huff. For Whitefriars and its claims To be champion or martyr, To fight for its dames, Like a knight of the garter,— To live by thy shifts, And to swear by thine honor, Are the freedom and gifts, Of which I am the donor. Chorus. To be cheated, and cheat, To be cuff'd and to cuff: So thy freedom's complete As a blade of the huff. By the conclusion of the chaunt, the rundlet of rhenish has been emptied, and all the Alsatians, except Trapbois, march off in file, repeating the last four lines of the chorus, and huzzaing to Nigel as they pass him. Nigel goes off with Trapbois and Skourlie at the opposite door. SCENE III. An opening among wretched lanes in Whitefriars—On a board over the door of a large dilapidated house, are the words “Trapbois, Money Lente.” Enter Nigel followed by Trapbois and Skourlie, who are in earnest conversation. Skour. (to Trapbois.) But are you sure? Trap. I tell you, I've the jewels Pledged in my hands on purpose. (To Nigel) There's our house, sir,— (to Skourlie.) So you will be ready with your mortgage deeds, To be paid off. (Knocks at his own door.) You've notice, mind. [The door being opened, Nigel and Trapbois go into the house. Skour. (alone.) Some devil Has cross'd me here. Nigel redeem! and that With the king's jewels! having him once lodged Here, in Whitefriars, I thought the prey secure. Enter Dalgarno, followed by Peppercole and officers, who take their stand at the back of the stage. Dalg. Where have you sheltered Nigel? There's a warrant For this day's brawl i'th'Park. Skour. My lord, no process Runs here, but from the star-chamber. Dalg. I ask Where is he? Skour. In his lodging: in the cobweb Of the old spider, Trapbois. Bare apartments To house a fav'rite. Dalg. Fav'rite! Skour. Yes: it seems His credit has, of late, most wond'rously Shot up at court. Dalg. His credit? Why, by six To-morrow afternoon, his all i'th'world Will be the mem'ry of some land he had— Scant credit for a fav'rite! Skour. Yet he means To pay our mortgage off, and that with funds Provided by the king. Dalg. What, by the king Of Eldorado? Long will Nigel gape, If 'tis th'exchequer of king James he looks to. Skour. King James has other means—certain crown jewels— Dalg. And what of them? Skour. Which he has lent to Nigel, At Heriot's intercession, to obtain Advances on. But now I had the fact From Trapbois, who is set to find the money. Dalg. Curse on their Scotch intrigue! fav'rite indeed! Is there no help? Could nothing be devised Out of this morning's brawl, to fret the king Against him? Skour. That were likely. Dalg. To expose A naked rapier is, with gentle Jamie, A more unseemly fault than to fly from it. Skour. Have a star-chamber warrant then, and seize him. Dalg. That shall be done. But, for the jewels, Skourlie, Shew me the way to stop the ill they lead to— His land's redemption. Skour. There's but one; to borrow Those baubles, without which he cannot muster The gold for this repurchase—but to borrow The jewels, of old Trapbois, just till six To-morrow afternoon, no longer. Then, Nigel may raise Peru, it comes too late. Dalg. Borrow? How borrow? Death, there is no hazard I would not run to have them in my hold One day! Well how thou gap'st now with thy “borrow!” Thou dost not think he walks abroad o'nights With such a handful, for a sturdy knave To knock him down, and rake him? Skour. Nay, not so; But if—your ear—(Observing the officers, he whispers to Dalgarno.) Pep. (To the officers.) These manners for a lord! Broil me like any rasher, if I palate Such incivility: why, rabbit me, I am a soldier, sirs. Dalg. (Turning round.) Who talks so loud? Pep. (Sneaking a few paces backward.) My lord, I did but say I was a soldier. Dalg. No doubt, you did but say so. (To Skourlie.) While he sleeps? The exploit looks likely. Skour. And as safe as lying: You'll not ev'n break the old man's rest. The leads Over my office run behind his house; And from that stage up to his chamber window, (Whose grating has these several days hung loose, Through fear, I guess, of charge for its repair,) The height's not far. Besides, you will not keep The trinkets beyond six to-morrow evening. Dalg. You'll act as guide? Skour. My nerves, my lord, are weak; The valiant captain now— Dalg. The valiant captain Is quite as rank a coward as thyself. Skour. True, but he knows the chamber; has been suitor Unto the daughter: not, indeed, encouraged, But oft times there. Dalg. We'll take him, lacking better. This is a frolic to repay some hazard. Skour. And yet there's none. (To Peppercole.) Captain! (To Dalgarno.) I'll find you cloaks, Masks, and such implements else as you shall need, And wait upon you speedily. At midnight You'll do't in safety. [Exeunt Skourlie, Peppercole, and Officers. Dalg. I have known no prank Compass'd, since first I made this fellowship With my star-wandering boys, my night companions— Nay, none that high-born minion of the moon Or taking rogue e'er did, in merrier times, When mad prince Hal cried “Stand,” to Gadshill trav'lers, Or Robin Huntingdon took toll in Sherwood From portly priests, more fraught with golden issues Than this night's enterprize! The jewels gain'd, I bar my Scot of his pawn'd heritage, Drive him a beggar from this girl's idolatry, And crush the only influence that could claim The windfall of these northern forfeitures. O, that 'twere dead o'night, and the deed done! For darkness is the dawn of brave men's fortunes, The menstruum of the real alchymy! [Exit. SCENE IV. A Room in Heriot's house. Margaret is discovered sitting at a table, leaning her chin on the palm of her hand. Bridget bending over the back of her chair with a silver tankard. Bridg. What not a drop of this nice posset, rosebud? Well, if you wont, I must. [sipping] Marg. O, Bridget! Bridget! Bridg. Well what's amiss? Let's see your palm and try If I'm enough a gypsey, so to find What foot you halt upon. Marg. [Giving her hand scornfully.] As if I halted On any foot at all. Bridg. [Examining her hand.] Brave lines; wealth, pleasure, An equipage to shake Whitehall—Oho! You smile? Aye, sure, why should not smart Jin. Vin. Ride, great Lord Mayor, in a gilt coach to court? Marg. (withdrawing her hand) Jin. Vin. a clown! Then you forget who drew His sword for me? Bridg. Lord Nigel? Why, she's mad! You love a lord, and him a Scot? of course Prouder than Lucifer, though poor as Job. You, for a lord, child! Marg. How the woman stares With her wide eyes! I would not be so silly, Had I face like that, to make it plainer! Bridg. Silly I may be; but, for plain, young mistress, Perhaps, if faces came to be compared— Marg. O, we are angry, are we! Now, I'll tell you— Bridg. Tell your own looking-glass, since its so much In favour with you. I'll not stay to hear— Enter George. Bridget, who was leaving the room, turns back to listen. George. Mistress, one Master Skourlie. Marg. O, no doubt, With news of my preserver! [Exit George. Enter Skourlie. Pray, come in, sir: You were about to speak. He's safe, I trust; That is, I mean— Skour. Lord Nigel? In Alsatia, Quite safe, just now. What he may be to-morrow Before the star-chamber— Marg. The star-chamber! Skour. Oh, no affair of life and death: the penance Is but to lose the hand, to have the hand Lopp'd by the common headsman, nothing more. I see you shudder: and, in faith, a wrist Hideously sear'd by the law's minister, Might make a gallant loathsome, in the eye Of dames less delicate. Marg. I pray you, chuse Some subject less abhorrent. Skour. Your fair self: That were ripe matter for a commentary Of the best grace—Your smile, perhaps, has power Where you suspect not: Marg. (aside) Dare I hope it? Oh, He'd not have chosen such a confident! (To Skourlie) Explain yourself, I pray. Skour. We're not alone. Marg. (To Bridget) You said, dame, you were going? Bridg. O, an't please you! What now? (to herself) [Exit Bridget into an anti-chamber, at the back of the Stage. Skour. Perhaps that smile has pow'r to rescue Ev'n him who rescued you. Marg. Speak, speak! Skour. There needs But gold to scatter freely, and I'll vouch For his escape, though twenty officers Bark'd at his heels. A thousand pounds would waft him Safe over sea. Marg. Alas! but I've no thousand. Skour. I have: and mine fair mistress, would be yours— Sweet mistress, if— Marg. This is not for my hearing. Skour. Yes, by my soul, it is! To that first thousand Add thousands more, and thousands yet to those, I'm unexhausted still—nay, lend your ear— Whatever gold can buy, that woman covets, As what will gold not buy, I can bestow, And will, on thee. I've liv'd a life of gains, Lent at large usance—batter'd on th'estates Of prodigal great men—there's not a manor Of their inheritance, but I've my mortgage Under the surface, waiting like an earthquake, Its time to swallow all! But my broad gold, All my huge heaps, lie dark as in the mine, Till the meridian of those sunny eyes Shine on the ore, and bring it forth to light. Marg. You wrong yourself and me, Sir. Skour. Wrong you? no. For you, I'll wrong all else—do any thing—safe, To please, to tempt, to buy, to bribe your love. You shall have pageantry—a cloud of servants, To fly before your thoughts—a glare of lights, That shall make noon a shadow—carriages— Banquets—such couches, as the cygnet's down Where a harsh type of. There are jewels, too, My eastern treas'ry—Spoils of gorgeous queens, From their far glitt'ring regions—thou shalt have them— Pearls, like a galaxy, thick sown about thee, And starry diamonds, whose bright constellation Would make a firmament! Marg. I'll hear no more. Without! (calling towards the anti-chamber.) Skour. So cold, so scornful! it may cost thee Some burning tears, if thus I quit thee, mistress! Marg. On any terms avoid me! Skour. Be it so— I take thee at thy word. The rock that seem'd To spring a fountain here, (striking his breast) is closed again, And I'm once more myself. Re-enter Bridget. Marg. (To her) You're well returned.— A scriv'ner! Skour. But whose riches are nobility! I read your childish heart—read for whose sake The goldsmith's niece disdains the untitled scriv'ner. Let her, and let the lord she doats on, pay for't; One vice, at least, of noble pedigree The low born scriv'ner feeds—the lust of vengeance! [Exit. Bridg. Here's a brave suitor! I had served you right If I had left you longer to his love. Marg. Pardon that peevishness—I've been so flutter'd—(Taking Bridget's hand) Come, you'll forgive me now, my bonny wife,— And, Bridget, wear this for me. (Giving her a ring.) Bridg. (Affecting reluctance.) Oh, it's wasted On such a dowdy, plain-faced thing as I. Marg. Bridget—have you a mind to see the king? Bridg. (Half sullenly.) I like a frolic. Marg. You shall go with me. Bridg. Go where? Marg. To Greenwich Park. His Majesty Hunts there to-morrow early:—my good uncle Is gone to Epping, and will scarce be back Till tow'rd the afternoon; so I shall use His absence, ev'n to be a naughty girl, And wear— Bridg. What, pray you? Marg. Stay a moment here, And you shall see. [Exit into the anti-chamber. Bridg. (Eyeing the ring on her finger.) Really, th'effect is not Amiss, at all. Only I doubt if John Will let me wear it. Re-enter Margaret. Marg. Do you know this habit? Bridg. Another fancy dress! I've had enough Of them.—O, the Scots page's gear you wore Before King James, at Christmas, in the mumming.— He ask'd your name, I mind, and the joke was To keep it from him:—and your uncle Heriot Look'd grave, and took you home. Marg. But not till James Promised, that, for a song which took his fancy, He'd grant that page a boon. Bridg. And do you mean To claim it now? O, I suppose, a pardon For the young lord. Marg. You'll go? Bridg. Aye, that I will, Though my old John scold, after, for a week: I'll give his jealousy a twinge! Marg. By day break We must be there; so, lodge you here to-night. Bridg. I will: for should I sleep at home, I'm thinking John might not let me go. But, if the king Refuse!— Marg. Then I would break my heart! Bridg. And Nigel Would lose his hand. Why not dispatch a boat To take him from Whitefri'rs, to-night, on board Some foreign ship? Then, if you win his pardon, Out springs he from his covert, like a swallow After the winter:—if you fail, he takes Wing for a milder climate. Marg. Any thing Rather than risk the horrid penalty That villain harp'd on. Bridg. Well, Jin. Vin. will do it. Marg. Mo more of him. Bridg. Nay, not a jacket of 'em Knows the Thames better: and, to get a rival Pack'd off— Marg. A rival! Bridg. He'll work double tides. Marg. Well, as you list. Bridg. Then here's to love and luck— [Sips from the tankard. That my pet lamb may soon become my lady, And the tall tankard wet his brim with candle! [Exit. Marg. (alone.) If James refuse me? O, no unkind doubt Shall glance its shadow on my springing hope, That like a sunflow'r, turns her to the light, And blossoms there. Set fairly, then, soft gales, Upon love's path to-morrow! clear the film From the blue eye of Heav'n, and in all bosoms Breathe light and gentle spirits: that kind nature May move in my appeal, and high-wrought greatness Relax to favour, and sweet clemency! [Exit. END OF ACT II.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. SCENE I. A decayed apartment in the house of Trapbois, partly hung with tapestry. A huge oak-carved four-post bed, with cumbrous tapestry hangings. A cracked mirror in a massy brass-work frame. Chairs of various sorts and sizes, covered, some with leather, some with damask, and some with other materials. A slab against the back wall, with a box on it. In front, two chairs and a table. Enter Trapbois shewing in Nigel. Trapb. This is your bed-chamber. Nigel. Sir, it shall serve. Trap. And—ugh! I beg your pardon,—but it's usual,— Ugh—when we take in unknown lodgers, for 'em To pay before. Nigel. I should not be unknown, Seeing I placed, this morning, in your hands, No less a pledge than the crown-jewels, to raise Six thousand pounds on. Trapb. True, you are the gallant That came with Master Heriot—ugh! Yes, yes, I had almost forgot. Nigel. Has the boy brought The box I sent for? (Seeing it on the slab) Good,—I shall scarce stay Beyond three days, or four: but this will answer (Unlocking the box and giving him a piece of gold.) For four night's lodging, host. Trapb. You may stay more— The week, I hope, at least. Nigel. Another then, And leave me. (Gives another piece.) [Exit Trapbois examining the money. Nigel. (Taking his pistols from his belt, lays them on the slab, then, looking at the grate, calls after Trapbois.) But they've lit no fire.—Some fire there! No drudge to answer?—Ho! good host! some fire! Trapb. (without.) Ugh—ugh!—What now? who's there?—What, fire! why, Martha! Daughter of mine! Martha. (without.) Peace, father, all is safe! (Enter Martha and Trapbois following. She is dressed in a stiff ruff and farthingale; with a black hood on her head, concealing her hair.) Martha. What were you lacking, sir? Nigel. Nothing to tax Your courtesy far; a little fire, no more. Martha. Faggot and coal are yonder in your reach. Trapb. The gentleman shall not be put to fill The grate; I'll do't—for a consideration. He'd waste the fuel sorely! Martha. To be plain, My father's old; and, for myself, I care not How few I see or speak with: so, for service, You'll fare but scantly. Nigel. Could I hire no servant While I stay with you? Martha. In all places, stranger, And most in this, where ev'ry knave, that ties Your points, would pick your purse, the wise man's ever His own best servant. While you sojourn here, (And, if you've wit, you'll scarce outstay necessity,) Wait, therefore, on yourself; and let him not Advance you money; for his faculties, Ag'd as you see them in all else, would there Be more than match for youth. Trapb. I'll be his servant, And brush his cloak or shoes; do all his errands, Ugh, soon and safe—for a consideration. Martha. Give you good night: it ill beseems a daughter To hear a father thus, with his own tongue, Undo his own respect: his aged wit Grows mean, and draws his manners after it. 'Tis but the dread, lest robbers guess we've gold, Makes him affect this sordidness. Trapb. No more Of that, housewife; no more on't, or I'll beat thee, Housewife; ugh! beat thee with my staff, for fetching And carrying lies, to get our throats cut, housewife! Martha. (Drawing him away.) Father, to bed; the night grows late; to bed. Trapb. Sir, I'm a poor man, very poor, and willing To do you any turn in honesty,— For a consideration. [Exit, with Martha, who gently forces him off. Nigel. There they go, Well fitted each to each, like bitter med'cine Waiting upon disease.—How now? You never Can hold this life, Lord Nigel. Poor you are In all but your rich blood; which blood, so rich, Being indulged, doth make men to be poor; And your poor lord, like to a stately ship, Wanting the wind, that should make flush her sails, Lies logged, for lesser craft to mock in passing. You, sirrah, rapier out.—sure you and I With yonder pellets, (pointing to his pistols) and the Palatine flag, Could earn, upon some score of German skulls, A livelier livelihood, than waits us here. [Making a pass or two in the air. Enter Martha. Well, mistress, what's your errand? Martha. Of that rent Which your improvidence has paid my father In more than due advance, I have brought back This piece— Enter Trapbois. Trapb. Art mad? yield up my gold! Nigel. I gave it Freely. Martha. While yet he could, he kept the house; I keep it now, and suffer no extortion. There! (she lays it on the slab near the box.) Trapb. Take thy poor old father's life? Martha. I see You've arms. D'ye know their use? Nigel. I should so; I am a soldier. Martha. You will find enough Of fighting here, if you are fond of that. 'Tis well an't seek not you, and when least ready. Nigel. Have you such dang'rous neighbours? Martha. Mark that door: A castle-gate is not more arm'd. The windows We keep cross-barr'd o'th'outside; and within, Look at these shutters; at the bolts and chains Which guard them. Trapb. Shew him not the trick to lock, Or loose them—Ugh! on no consideration. Martha. Yet when a bolt's to be repair'd, 'tis left A fortnight ere he pluck up heart to pay A smith for mending it. The Old Man stands with his back to the audience, looking up the stage, towards the slab. He hears me not. Strange, that the love of gath'ring gold, should thus Swallow the love of all that gold can buy, Of life itself. Take care, sir, of your weapons, And let not yonder loadstone lie exposed, (Pointing to the gold in the half open box on the slab.) Lest it attract some steel nearer your throat Than may be healthy. [Exit Martha. Nigel. A harsh monitress! But the gnarl'd tree may bear a wholesome fruit. I'll profit by her caution. (Turning round, he sees Trapbois approaching the slab.) Master landlord, So near my arms? pray leave them. In strange lodgings They're safe companions, and, just now, conceive you, I want no other. Trapb. Why, I could be useful In your affairs—for a consideration. Nigel. Enough: I thank you. (Motions him to withdraw.) Trapbois still lingers. Friend, I say, I thank you. (Peremptorily.) Trapb. No cost for thanks! draw bolts. [Exit Trapbois. The heavy bolts are heard. Nigel. The sound is drear. (Looking at his arms.) If she spoke true, you're needful furniture. How chill the river-fog strikes on my spirits! A book, forsooth. Now. (opening it.) Heav'n's revenge for murder! Yes, these are awful narratives. (Turns over the leaves.) Blood, still Repaid with blood. Where man has broken in To the mysterious tabernacle of life, Dumb animals have brought the secret forth, And birds o'th'air convey'd the matter. Aye, The very grave has yawn'd, and sent its tenants Back to revenge—What ghastly thing is that? (During this soliloquy, Trapbois has crept into the room from a door behind the tapestry, and, when perceived by Nigel, is in the act of extending his arm towards the slab.) You at those arms again? What's your fell purpose, That thus a second time, at this late hour, You creep upon my privacy, and crawl To make your impotent clutch? (Nigel, meanwhile, has snatched his sword from the table; he unsheaths it, and points it at the breast of Trapbois. Trapb. I'm not afraid, You are. Nigel. I ask what brings thee near these pistols? Dost come to clear the way for stouter ruffians? Answer me, spectre! Trapb. What is mine, is mine; I care not for your blade. Enter Martha from a door behind the Tapestry with a light. Martha. A young man's sword Against the poor remains of four score winters! (Dashing aside the sword) I'll have it for my spindle. Nigel. Stand you back; I mean no harm to him; but I will know Why thus again, almost at mid of night, He prowls about my weapons. Trapb. While I live, I'll not resign my own. Martha. (Taking up the gold piece from the slab.) Why, look you there! All the bright store of steel, and burnish'd brass That flashes when the morning sun shines in Upon the armoury of London Tower, Are nothing in his eye, against the plack Of dingy gold, a careless gallant leaves Loose on his board. Nigel. Oh, your unsought rebate, Upon the lodging. Trapb. It is mine, I say; 'Twas giv'n to me for a consideration: I'll die before I quit it. Nigel. I entreat you, Let him enjoy his gold, and me my quiet. Martha. Well, be it so; note me your debtor for it. Trapb. (Darting upon the coin in Martha's hand.) Enough, enough, to bed; housewife, begone To bed; we're wasting oil. (Takes the lamp, and exit through the tapestry door.) Martha. Sir, I will see him Fast in his chamber; and for your forbearance To his infirmity, you have my thanks, With all good wishes. [Exit through the tapestry. Nigel. It is barely twelve, And yet there creeps a drowsiness upon me I cannot wrestle with. 'Twere hardly wise To doff one's sword, or habit; so, I'll seek A soldier's rest, and lull'd with harmony Of houseless dogs, and heavy swinging signs, That creak and flap in the low-moaning gust, Dream of the means to quit my sanctuary. (Throws himself in his clothes on the bed. SCENE II. The bed-chamber of Trapbois: very bare, hung, in parts, with ragged tapestry. A window on the left. Beneath it, a seat: a bed on the right: a table under which is a chest chained to the floor. From a door behind the tapestry, enter Trapbois, in an old damask night-gown. Trapb. Old as they think me,—ugh,—I can cross bite them. Let's see all safe before we sleep. These jewels, (Opening a casket which he takes from his pocket.) I would not lend six thousand pounds upon 'em, For all the Master Heriots in the town: But there be fools, who will; so I shall make The broker's penny on 'em—Ugh! they're things I never liked the charge of. I was wrong To let that Heriot have my undertaking (Unlocks the chest under the table with one hand, holding the casket in the other.) For the safe render of them; were I robb'd now, I must be answerable. Lie with me. (Relocks the chest, takes the jewels out of the casket, which he puts empty on the table, and folds them into a leathern case, which he thrusts into the pocket of his night-gown: Then putting out the lamp, he gets into bed.) We'll not be parted for to-night. So, so, I have the trick on't. (When all is still, Dalgarno without, from below, climbs to the window and enters, followed by Peppercole. They both wear masks and cloaks. Peppercole carries also a dark lanthorn.) Dalg. Speedily, but softly. Pep. An' this be called a frolic, then I know not What makes a burglary. Doth the true manhood, Like the salt water, wait upon the moon? Methinks, my valour then is most at full, When vulgar day is down—(he gropes towards the chest.) Beard of my father! What noise? Dalg. The echo of a bragging tongue; A swagger at the second hand.—Hast found it? Thou didst affect to be familiar here. Pep. The chest is chained. Dalg. Thou hast thy picklock: that Will serve the turn. Pep. What will it not, when I Command its service? Dalg. Work it then, and prate not. Pep. (picking the lock.) Hark! Dalg. Hush! Thou doest nothing, but with noise; Thou can'st not go a bat-fowling o'nights, But bear'st a cracker in thy lanthorn. (The moon rising, shines in over the window-seat. Trapbois stirs in bed.) Pep. There! Trapb. Who's that? Dalg. I shall know to silence him. Trapb. (stumbling out of bed.) Ugh!—thieves again! Dalg. (Forcing Trapbois back to the bed.) Dare but so much as breathe Above a whisper, and you breathe your last! Pep. Such a vile pickster! Dalg. Quick, knave, or this muzzle—(Pointing his pistol towards Peppercole.) Shall teach thy nostrils a more intimate smell Of dry salt-petre, than they ever whiff'd Of moist Virginia. Trap. I can hold no longer: Better my life be reft at once— (They struggle: the old man tears Dalgarno's scarf.) Dalg. Again! Thou strugglest toughly for thy years; but this (Noosing the torn scarf over the mouth of Trapbois.) At least will muffle thee. Trapb. (Grasping the leathern case, the top of which peeps from his night gown pocket.) What, wilt thou gag me? Dalg. And bind those bony hands. What's that they hug With such a deadly gripe? Pep. (bringing up the dark lanthorn.) The very jewels, The ruby gems we seek! How red they glimmer! Dalg. I'd have them, were they redder than his blood. Trapb. Help! murder! murder! Dalg. (tearing the jewels from the leathern case.) Nay, if thou peal out That shrill alarm, our own security Will need a shorter course. Martha rushes in, from a door opposite to the tapestry. Martha. No, on my soul, Murderer! for in a father's cause, the nerves Ev'n of weak woman catch a giant's strength, And dash th'assassin off! (She arrests the right hand of Dalgarno, which is raised over Trapbois, and falls on her knees in the effort; while Dalgarno's left hand becomes entangled in, and strains, the scarf, which having been noosed over the old man's mouth, is now, by his own resistance, slipped and tightened round his throat. Trapb. (Faintly.) They've done it, housewife. (The leathern case drops from his hand, he gasps and dies.) Dalg. 'Tis false, old churl—not I, but thine own struggles Have strain'd the noose thy feeble breath is choked with. Down, woman, down! A noise is heard behind the tapestry, as of some one trying to force his way. Martha stoops her head, and snatches a pistol from Dalgarno's belt. Martha. Down—but to rise in vengeance! Dalgarno with his left hand which he has withdrawn from the scarf, seizes Martha; and having parried, with his right hand, the pistol she points at him, endeavours to force it from her. Dalg. Then thus we close the strife. (He wrests the pistol from her) Nigel, bursting through the tapestry door, discharges his pistol at Dalgarno. Nigel. And thus make up Th'account of blood! Pep. (retreating through the open door at which Martha entered.) Which balance, I'll not wait The striking of. [Exit. Dalgarno presents at Nigel his pistol, which, missing fire, he throws away, and draws his sword. Dalg. I am but grazed, not maimed. They fight: Dalgarno is driven back to the window seat. Through the window opposite, lights are seen. Martha. Hark! voices! help! Good people, murder! help! Nigel. Yield, ruffian, thy resistance is in vain Against approaching numbers! Hildebrod, and others (without) Up stairs! Martha. Ha! They hear and come! Now, felon, we shall have thee! [Exit Martha. Dalg. (leaping upon the window seat) If I give ground, it is to numbers, not To thee. (Throws himself from the window with the jewels in his left hand, fighting with his right to the last.) Nigel. I'd rather fight a few more passes, Than keep this lonely guard of death and darkness. What, does the old man stir? Sure something rustled Like his harsh gown. Shame on my fev'rish fancy! The light! Re-enter Martha followed by Hildebrod Jin. Vin. habited as a Waterman, and Alsatians, bearing lights. Jin. One, now as I approached the house, Burst from the door. Nigel. The other fought his way To yonder casement. Hild. (approaching the body.) Here's no wound. Nigel. This scarf, This was the deadly means. Martha. (who has thrown herself on her knees before the body) No breath! no motion! Hild. (To Nigel) Both masqued, you say? Martha. (Starting up) Diligence, bailiff—Justice— And full revenge! Hild. To-morrow: my police Are scarce in trim to take the field to-night. Martha. What would you give the murd'rers time, t'escape? Hild. Silence! Martha. A daughter silent, while her father Lies murder'd at her feet! Man, it were best You trifle not with me! Hild. With a she-bear As soon. You will have justice, never fear, Mistress, for you can pay her. What is that? (To Nigel, who has taken up the empty casket, left on the table by Trapbois) A jewel-casket? Nigel. (throwing it again on the table) One I know too well! Its rich contents filch'd out,—and, with them gone The lands and hopes of Nigel! Hild. Why your burglar Must live by's trade, like others—Well, be watchful; And I will hold my inquest here to-morrow, At two i'the afternoon, when (To Nigel and Martha) you'll attend As witnesses. (Aside to Nigel) I leave you with the heiress; Hum! you conceive me? [Exit winking his one eye at Nigel, and followed by all, except Nigel, Martha, and Jin. Vin. Nigel. Pestilent ribaldry, Unquenchable as the Greek fire, will flash Amid the very damps of death itself! Now lad, (To Jin. Vin.) your bus'ness? Jin. I am sent by friends, That wish you from Whitefriar's. I've a boat yonder. (Nigel and Jin. Vin. confer aside. Martha. I knew 'twould come to this! My poor, poor father! For the accursed gold they've murder'd him! Nigel. (To himself.) The king's to hunt at dawn, in Greenwich park. Why not at once present myself before him, And trust his goodness? Jin. Well, resolve at once. Nigel. Wait for me, then, here, by the river stairs. Jin. Then, quickly. [Exit. Nigel. I am very loath to leave A lonely woman in the house of death; But I must quit this roof. Martha. I will go with you. Nigel. You! Martha. Yes. I will persuade my poor old father To quit this murd'rous den. My father! Oh! I have no father now. Nigel. Would I could help you. Martha. (As if suddenly taking her resolution.) Then give me but a passage in your boat, Unto Paul's wharf. I've kinsfolk there, with whom I would fain take my shelter, 'till this inquest. Nigel. The boat shall land you there. [Going. Martha. (Approaching the body.) Only a moment. It is not fit that nature's rude convulsion Should meet the eye so fearfully. (Composes and covers the body.) There, rest, My father, rest. With no irrev'rent hand (Loosens the scarf from his neck) I loose this web, this fatal instrument; But in the sacred hope, that by its clue Thy murd'rers may be traced. So, fare thee well, With this one look, the last. If thou did'st love Nought else of human kind, yet me, at least, Thou loved'st. So to die! and by such hands! Nigel. I would not break upon your griefs, but, time— Martha. My moan is made! my sorrow (all, at least, That man shall ever note in me) is past: My future thought shall be of justice only. (Strikes her foot against the leathern case.) What's here? the case where he was wont to keep His close and secret papers. Ah! I doubt me Lest its contents be little fit to meet The curious and most vulgar eyes of those, Who must sit here to-morrow. It is heavy. Nigel. I'll bear it: would I bore a heart as light! Martha. (Giving him the case.) If wealth might lighten thee, thou shouldst not lack Alleviation; for this case contains The key to all he had: bills, bonds, long harvest Of fourscore years, the bootless portion now Of his lone daughter. Come, thou lagging day, Bring back thy light, that I may set about The work of my revenge; for, if the murderers Fly to the earth's extreme, I will pursue, Till I have hunted down, this track of blood! [Exeunt. END OF ACT III.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT. IV SCENE I. Greenwich Park, at sunrise. Enter Peppercole. Pep. Body of me! If I had smelt a murder At the job's end, I'd stay'd at home. Yet who Should know us, masqued? Ev'n swell it publicly, And sport the inn'cent here, in the king's hunt,— That looks the safest. [He disappears among the trees. Enter Jin. Vin. preceding Nigel. Jin. This is Greenwich Park. (As he is going, Nigel offers him money.) No money. Nigel. Nay, let us part friends. Jin. We part Just as we met. Nigel. Your mind may change; and, should it, You'll find me in these av'nues, 'till the chase Shall draw the king this way. [Exit. Jin. (Alone.) That Marg'ret's whim Should take to that stark Scot! He little thinks She sent me for him. Well, t'have got a rival Away on any terms, was good for me: And, faith, for him,—if, as I doubt, this murder Should breed him trouble. [Exit. Horns are heard;—a stag-hunt at a distance. Enter Margaret, in a page's dress, laid down with silver-lace—a plaid sash, and black velvet cap and plume—followed by Bridget. Bridg. Hark! the hounds! Marg. My heart Fails. Should my uncle Heriot come home sooner Than we expected, oh, what shall I do? Bridg. Why, what shall I do, when my jealous spouse Finds I have been gadding? John, say I,— Bridget, says he—say I, are you not glad To see your dear come back again? Says he, To see myself a wittoll—No, say I; To see yourself a fool: patting, therewith, His russet cheek;—whereat, my master breaks Into a surly grin; I get my arm In his; then he, you know, in common manners, Can do no less than chuck me by the chin, Or, if I'd give him leave, salute my cheek; And then— Marg. What then? Bridg. Why then,—I think, betwixt Old husband, and young wife, it is enough; Is it not? Marg. How should I know? Bless us, Bridget, He's here! step back. [Margaret and Bridget retire among the Trees. Re-enter Nigel. Nigel. Thy race is run, brave stag. Who's that alone, breaking the quarry? Is it— It is—King James himself! Enter James, dressed in his quilted green velvet dress, and grey hat. James. First hart o'th'season! (looking at his hands, which are bloody) Fine hands this slaughter hath bedeck'd us with! (Starting at the sight of Nigel.) And who are you, man? by my soul, no other Than that pugnacious Nigel! Bonny work! Stop us! when we're on foot—alone too— Nigel. Pardon, If for one moment— James. (with trepidation.) We shall hear you best On horseback. Stand aside;—De'il's in my people! (Looking round for his attendants. Nigel. Sir, by your crown, which my forefathers fought for— James. (much alarmed, and trying to pass Nigel.) We're a free king, I hope; not in the power Of any subject! What can keep my folk? Here, Steenie, hillo! ho! Enter Buckingham, followed by Sir Geoffry, Peppercole, Hunters, and Crowd. Buck. What do I see? James. Treason, for aught I ken! or, as it seems, For aught you care. Buck. Treason! and, lo! indeed, There's blood upon the king! dear dad and gossip, You are not wounded? James. Why, I trust, I'm not; But search him; I am sure that fire-arms peep'd Under his garb. Nigel. (producing and giving up his pistols.) I bear them openly. James. There! said we not? We ken the smell of powder! Pepper. and Crowd. Oh! parricide! Off with th'assassin! Buck. Ever In deeds of blood! Nigel. 'Tis to the king I'd speak. James. Hence to the Tow'r with him, and with his weapons, Things odious in our sight. (Sir Geoffrey gives orders to an Officer, who, with Guards, takes Nigel into custody. Exit Nigel, guarded. We shall do justice, Since he appeals to Cæsar. Marg. (Stepping forward.) Now or never! My gracious liege— James. What, more Conspir'ators! speak! Marg. I cannot, Sir; let this speak for me. [Puts her hand into her doublet for her petition. James. Hold him! He likewise hath a pistol! Sir Geof. Only loaded With one great paper ball; a prayer of pardon For his confed'rate, Nigel. James. Young Misprision, Hold up your head! we ken you not; yet, sure, We've seen your face before. Marg. At Christmas, sir, When many of the City made a pageant Before your Grace—you did commend my voice, And say, that if thereafter I should need A boon of worth, I was to come again Before your presence, with this holiday-suit, And sing the song that pleased you. James. Why we mind Something of that same page. If you are he, E'en let us hear your music. Marg. Sir, Ill try, If fear will give my inexpertness leave. Song. Margaret. Beneath the earth, in her lonely caves, And across the unshelter'd moor, Above the rocks where the tempest raves, And along the wide water'd shore, And by tangled forest, and craggy hill, The haunts where the tygers prey, Through pain and peril, undaunted still, Love will find out the way! You may think him timid, so fast he flies, And speaks with a tone so mild; You may deem that darkness has veil'd his eyes, Or believe him a simple child: But if she, whose beauty is love's delight, Be conceal'd from the beam of day, Set a thousand guards on that lady bright,— Love will find out the way! Without a guide, and without a clue, Through the realms of unmeasur'd space, Where the Dove herself, that returns so true, Would be lost in her airy race; Though the night wind sweep, or the chill rain fall, Or the sun dart his fiercest ray; Oh! love, unconquer'd, will speed through all, Love will find out the way! James. Well sung! and therefore we will have this linnet Wired in a cage. Marg. My liege! James. In the same bars The other beasts his wings in—Just i'th'Tow'r, Whence love, we think, will scarce find out the way. Steenie, come hither! (aside to Buckingham) On my kingdom, man, This boy's a girl! Some pretty Citizen, Who loves this Lord: is't not? Now, her best boon And his best punishment, were to engraft Her lowly stock with his, and make him marry— Hey? Buck. Such, sir, is our English laws' humanity, It warrants not, for any man's offence, The punishment your Grace proposes. James. Whisht, A jest;—this afternoon, before your pageant, We'll sift this girl, for so she is—and Nigel, Thoroughly face to face. (to Sir Geoffrey) 'Till evening, lodge Yon sprig i'th'Tow'r. Marg. Is this your Grace's boon? James. Great issues oft have hung on threads as fine— So with her—with him—to the Tow'r: (going, looks back) now, Steenie, Kens not your King the smell of powder, think ye? [Exit, followed by Buckingham, Peppercole, Hunters, and Crowd; Margaret and Bridget go off on the other side, with Sir Geoffrey and Guards. SCENE II. Opening in Whitefriars before the house of Trapbois. (Same as 3d scene of 2d Act.) Enter, from the house of Trapbois, Hildebrod, Dalgarno, Skourlie, and Jin Vin, followed by Alsatians. Skour. (to Hild.) Aye, Cor'oner, the removal of that Scarf, The very engine of the murder, looks Strangely for Nigel. Hild. Is it not yet stranger, At such a time that Martha should be missing? Skour. (To Jin Vin) Nigel took Martha with him? Jin. Near Paul's Wharf, I landed them together. Presently, He came, alone, back to my boat; and Martha Appeared no more. Skour. Did they take aught of value? Jin. A huge black leathern-case. Skour. The very wrapper Wherein old Trapbois kept his goldsmith's notes, And other things of price! The usurer murder'd— His daughter missing—and Lord Nigel present From first to last—(to Dalg.) My lord, you've been his friend— Dalg. And am so still, though he has much aggriev'd me. Ask not my thought: I'm here but with the purpose To serve him in his absence,—not to stir Charges against him. Skour. (to Hild.) Well, the duty's yours. Hild. Then, since I hear he's carried to the Tower, I deem it fitting to adjourn the inquest Till his examination: mean while, too, Martha may be forthcoming. Dal. (aside) Not if I Can find her out, and spirit her from the kingdom. Hild. Cry a reward to any who shall give Intelligence of her. Skour. Cry, a reward! Who'll pay it? Hild. If none else, a good paymaster, Not often fig'ring in your books, belike,— Conscience! [Exit Hildebrod, followed by all but Dalgarno, and Skourlie. Dalg. Who says that Fortune's blind? a lie, A sland'rous lie! she sees and picks her gallants For parts and spirit—men that press her briskly, When in the cue to yield. Say I'm not fortunate. Say I'm not wise! Skour. Who doubts you're both? Will Nigel? Dalg. Why, no, I think the pit is fairly dug For that brief fav'rite. Such a stoat as he A half-clothed, unbred Scot, creep in betwixt Me, and my views—get the king's jewels lent him To slip my mortgage off—out-favour me In all things, ev'n to a fair wench's fancy— I'll blight his favour! Stour. Not, I doubt, with Marg'ret. Dalg. Yes, Sir, with Marg'ret. Let a woman see That you will have her, and you shall: that's law All the world over, no, my man of parchment! Skour. You would not marry her! Dalg. Why not, my rival Being bespoken for another noose? Skour. You banter. Dalg. Never more in earnest. Wherefore Ply your mock parsons of Whitefriars here, Your smugglers in the Hymeneal traffic, If not to pave a way for ticklish beauty Into our arms? The marriages they make Wear just as well as true ones—for a week, Perhaps a fortnight,—and your lawful loves Hold not much longer. Skour. Death! you would not slur So rare a creature with a fraud so foul! Dalg. Well, what dost gape at? by my faith if 'twere not Too monstrous ev'n to hang a laugh upon, I could almost conceive thou hadst thyself Cast a sheep's eye at this green sprout, thou look'st So maukishly! Skour. And if I had, my Lord, Where were the monstrous, or the laughable? May be I am not a Court-galliard; but All women like not in one fantasy, And I'm a man, I hope? Dalg. Certes, I hope so: But woe to her who proves thee! Ha, ha, ha! What use now could a woman turn thee to, In all the circle of her wants and whims? Skour. Very jocose—exceeding merry: (losing his forced grin) Hum! Dalg. To fancy thee grimacing at a woman! Croaking in madrigal—perking thy chin— Coaxing thy hat's immeasurable flap— Nibbling thy thumbs—twirling thine inky fingers Athwart the rat tails of that oily hair— Smoothing thy band—then settling those straight skirts Whose nether whalebone, like a term, out-standing, Protects th'entail:—such gallantries to please A woman! Skour. (who during the foregoing speech has committed these awkwardnesses in the order followed by Dalgarno) Where i'th'name of patience, is one To put one's hands? (thrusting them into his pockets.) Dalg. You lawyers mostly use To put them in the pockets of your neighbours. Skour. A mirthful tone!—You'll take a graver, soon. Skirts, band, and beaver, fingers, hair, and chin! I have no legs to please a woman neither, Hey, my keen critic? By this light, I fancy A woman might go further and fare worse! [Exit. SCENE III. An Apartment in the Tower. Nigel, guarded by a Sentry, who paces behind the doorway, in the back Scene. Nigel. A sad reverse of yesterday's fair hopes! The Jewels that should have made my fortune whole, Forced from my use by murd'rers, and myself Lodg'd in the Tow'r, the tomb of living men! (Sir Geoffry unlocks the door, leading in Margaret.) Sir Geof. A fellow captive!—Tis a slip scarce worth The turning of a key on. Nigel. I desire No company. Sir Geof. 'Tis the Lieutenant's order: We have no spare apartments, and he wills not So fair a lad be thrust with baser persons. [Exit. [Margaret stands trembling, and with downcast eyes, on the spot where Sir Geoffry has left her.] Nigel. He has a gracious mien!—What, pretty lad, Cheer up! your hand is cold, and trembles! She silently suffers herself to be led forward: then suddenly wrings her hands, and spreading them before her face, begins to sob aloud. Nigel smooths down her hair with his hand; she shrinks. Nigel. Nay, Weeping! O fie! you must not, like a girl, Give way to tears. Marg. Sir, you are very good— And I very unhappy! Nigel. Some wild frolick, Some naughty trick?—yet why i'th'Tow'r? Marg. Indeed, I'm innocent; that is, I have done wrong, But not— Nigel. (taking the end of her plaid sash.) This looks as we were countrymen: Whence do you come, my boy, and what's your name? Marg. My name to you? Oh, never! Nigel. You suspect me? Marg. No, no, I doubt you not; could tell you all, That is, not quite, my lord, but almost all. Nigel. (negligently.) Well, I but wish'd to serve you. (impatiently.) If all were right, you'd speak to me more frankly. Marg. Why, then, I am resolved to tell you nothing. Nigel. Why, then, you'll keep your secret; but, observe, I have found out one passage of your mystery, Marg. What means your lordship? Nigel. That my pretty comrade Wears not her sex's habit. Marg. It enfolds One who will not disgrace it! Nigel. From a man Those words might mean a challenge—Nay, fear nothing; Spite of that garb, I feel you cannot merit A wanton treatment. Marg. From your nobleness I hoped no less. Enter an Officer. Officer. A citizen, to speak With the Lord Nigel. Nigel. (to Margaret) Let not feverish thoughts Distract you now—your pulse is high, and rest Seems needful. (Points to a large chair in a recess.) Marg. (Hurrying towards it and dropping one of her Gloves) O yes, quickly, ere a stranger Comes in—the step approaches. Nigel. (Covering her face with her cloak and sash) You'll sleep now. Enter Strappet, to whom Nigel offers his hand. [Exit Officer. Landlord? Strap. O, no more courtesies, my Lord; Have had enough for life! where have you pack'd My runaway? Nigel. Your runaway! Strap. You know! My minx—my plague—my wife—at least that was, 'Till she became your Lordship's light-o'love! Nigel. I never touch'd her cheek, or hand, except— Strap. Have you forgot the masquerading dress? Nigel. Except in honourable courtesy. Strap. Aye, that's the very word; She always praised Your Lordship's honourable courtesy. You've cozen'd me, between you, with your courtesy O were your limbs but free, young as you are, This bit of oak should make you an example For courteous Lords! Nigel. Base groom, will nothing less Content you, than to have your numskull crack'd Against this wall? Strap. Oh bully on! You know Th'Alsatian rant! A woman has been here, (Picking up the glove which Margaret has dropped,) No long time since, that's plain; this never fitted Man's hand. Nigel. You have my answer. Strap. Will you say, Here's not, e'en now, a hidden petticoat somewhere? Nigel. There's not, I vow—no petticoat at all. Strap. (Approaching the recess where Margaret is sleeping.) I will be sure—What's in this chair, for instance? Nigel. (Intercepting his approach.) What's that to thee? Strap. (Getting nearer to Margaret.) I'll tell you, when I've seen The sleeper's face. Nigel. (Swinging him by his arm from the chair down the stage.) No, pardon me, good friend, Not so familiar neither. Strap. So familiar, Quotha! What, it's ill manners for a man To peep at's own wife napping! Nigel. But that napper Is not your wife. Strap. (Recovering from Nigel's shake.) Your manner's rather stagg'ring: Nigel. (To Heriot, who at that moment appears at the door.) Now this is kind. At such a time, a friend Enter Heriot. Is doubly welcome! Heriot. That's as conscience makes it. My lord, my lord, how can you raise your eyes, And look an honest tradesman in the face, Seducer as you are? Nigel. Are you mad too, About the barber's wife? Heriot. I've heard of that; But, you well know 'tis not of her I speak. Nigel. What, have I had the fortune to detach Some other lady, likewise, from her lord? Strap. Here is a precious devil among the women Heriot. Nor lord, nor lady; but a giddy girl From a too careless guardian. Why, 'tis monstrous T'affect this ign'rance that I come to claim My poor niece, Marg'ret. Nigel. What has witch'd the women? No charming creature in all London town But takes some freak, that I may bear the blame. Heriot. Well play'd, indeed! Nigel. I never saw her, sir, Save once at your own board, some three months past, And yester-eve, a moment in the park; Nay, all my memory of her face, is but That it was passing fair. Heriot. I'm not so answered. Strap. No, no, young courtesy, we're not so answer'd. Nigel. Then, by mine honour, and nobility, I have no knowledge of these gentlewomen, Where they have been, or are, or mean to be, Save that they are not here. [Bridget appears by the door at the back of the stage, struggling with the sentry, and comes in. Bridg. My sweet young friend, Must not be left alone. Marg. (waking with a start, and springing forward.) What's that? who call'd? [The two women thus occupy the back of the stage, right and left; Heriot and Strappet amazed, stand at equal distances in the front; so that these four form a square, in the centre of which is Nigel. Strap. Now! Marg. Bridget! Brid. Margaret! Her. Dissembler! Nigel. Devil! Strap. Two at a time, too! Have your Scotch no conscience? Marg. (attempts to cover her face, first with her cloak, then with her hands: these Heriot unceremoniously removes, giving her a slight shake.) Heriot. How comes this, minion? goodly gear, i'faith! You'd shew your little foot and ancle, would you? Nay, nay, your modesty's too late. Bridg. Well, John! Strap. Wife! Mrs. Strappet! do you face it out then? Bridg. Marry come up! does he suspect my virtue? Nigel. And mine too, Bridget. Her. Truly, with some reason. Bridg. Had I been that way bent, no nobleman I'm sure, would have been likelier than your lordship; But I would let him know— Her. Pray, do, good woman, For we are much i'th'dark. Bridg. Why then, this fuss Is all about a girl, a round faced girl, That's what my wise, bald, John is jealous of. Strap (Looking at Nigel) Girl, quotha! by my troth, a bouncing lass! (To Sir Geoffry) Look out, good master officer: 'twere better, Turn your wild beasts out, in Tower Hill, than let (Pulling Bridget with him) This smooth Lord loose on honest people's wives. Bridg. (Significantly at Nigel with a nod towards Margaret) You understand, I say no more, a girl! [Exeunt Strappet and Bridget. Nigel. I understand, a girl? why, yes! I see My pretty fellow-prisoner is a girl, And pretty girls, I know, are pretty things; But there my understanding ends. Heriot. Will neither Explain? Marg. You much mistake me, and not less This nobleman. Nigel. When all else league against me, The more I'm bound to one who does me justice. (Re-enter Sir Geoffry, with guards. Now, good lieutenant? Sir Geof. I am sent to place Your Lordship under stricter custody. Nigel. Upon what charge? Sir Geof. I grieve to say, of murder, Committed in Whitefriars, upon the body Of the old usurer, Trapbois. Nigel. And they dare Impute the crime to me, who chased the felons? Sir Geof. Then you were there? Nigel. Yes, and shall call his daughter To witness for me. Sir Geof. She has not been found; Which makes no trivial circumstance against you. Nigel. Clouds thicken round me, but I'll clear them still. Let but your smile, like a bright star, shine through, To light my spirit. (to Margaret.) Marg. Could I smile— Heriot. Enough! I'll to the King anon, and get you moved Out of this custody.—For you my Lord, Th'event must speak. Nigel. Meanwhile, then, my past life Shall be my surety: for, in lib'ral judgments, Good name is still the wearer's amulet Against crude calumny; and with a sweet And saving fragrance, like the balms o'th'East, Wards the rank breath of malice. Sir, I follow. [Margaret retires again into the recess:— Nigel goes out, preceded by Sir Geoffry, and followed by Guards and Heriot. END OF ACT THE FOURTH.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT V. SCENE I. Skourlie's office; shelves round the walls, with deed-boxes and papers. A time-piece over the chimney. Skourlie discovered alone. Skour. The sun slopes westward: (looking at the time piece)—half past five: no more? Well, one half hour: if, in that time, there pour not Gold from the sky, to pay off Nigel's mortgage, All his broad acres, arable, mead, and forest, As Dunstan's bell tolls six, pass to Dalgarno. The loss of those crown jewels, the sole means To raise this mortgage money, must have left Nigel without a hope; and yet, till six Has struck, I'm ill at ease.—Time's old,—and charity Bids us assist th'infirm: so, come, we'll speed him Some steps upon his journey. Puts the hand of the time-piece to “Six.” A knock is heard at the outer door. Bless my soul, What's that? (recovering) a client; nothing more!—'Tis strange How my hand trembles. That Whitefriars bus'ness Has some how—Death! what matters it to me? I did not pull the knot, nor hold the lantern, And yet I scarce have nerve to crook my fingers. Ah!—I must let no stranger find me thus: Folks might suspect that— Opens a closet. Where's the cordial? [Exit into closet. Knocking. Enter Clerk. Clerk. Coming! A pretty clatter—gently—gently—coming! Enter Heriot and Strappet followed by two porters, who bring a hand-barrow, laden with bags of money: these they unload from the barrow, under Strappet's direction, and place in rows upon a bench, or dresser. Your pleasure? Strap. But a word, friend, with your master. Clerk. He'll strait return. [Exit. Strap. (To Porters as they are unloading.) Chink it along, brave boys. Her. So that, at last, the matter being sifted, The fault is with the women more than Nigel. Strap. Well, I have made him what amends I could, For my suspicion, in these jolly bags. (The porters, having completed their unloading, go out; Strappet pays them.) Little you thought that any of my kindred Could pay a mortage for six thousand pounds Down on the nail, my master! Does one good Only to hear it ring. (Turns up the stage with Heriot.) Re-enter Skourlie, not perceiving them, with a flaggon and glass. Skour. Aye, that has strung My nerves a little. Come, another pull—(Drinks.) Now, I could face the devil! Her. (coming forward and startling him.) If you're braced To look on Satan, you may be less loath To see his kinsman, Mammon. Skour. (much agitated.) Sir, I know not— Guess not, sir, what you mean. Her. But that we've brought you The money, to discharge a certain mortgage Upon Lord Nigel's lands, which, whether your's Or your employer's, being in your name, We call on you t'acquit. Skour. Sir, I incline To think the time's expired. 'Tis now, you see, Past six. Her. Yes, by your clock. Skour. A trusty time-piece, From your own warehouse, Master Heriot. Her. 'Twas A trusty time-piece, when I sold it you: But it should seem that even a clock may come By keeping evil company, to lose Its character. Skour. You should best know the hour. Strap. (pointing to the bags.) All told and weigh'd. Skour. (calling at the side scene.) Just run for Lord Dalgarno; Nay, to make sure, I'll step myself and fetch him. (Snatches up his hat, and runs towards the door. Her. (to Strappet.) If thou'rt a man, keep fast the door. He seeks But to put off the time. Strap. (placing his back against the door.) We make the tender: There's the gold, take or leave it. Skour. Gentlemen, You think, perhaps, this makes Lord Nigel whole; But you're deceived: he's charged with murder, sirs. Her. Thanks for your pleasant news; but we may save That forfeit too, if you delay us not. Strap. Therefore, no shuffling, friend, lest your long ears Be trimm'd a trifle shorter. Skour. O, you threaten? Her. No threat: a little kind advice, that's all. Good man o'th'law, we know you: guess, perhaps, Near what peculiar corner of Whitefriars You were last night: therefore, the title-deeds! Skour. I must submit: I trust, I have been civil. I've done; here's your receipt; and there, the deeds You claim. Strappet takes up the bundle of title-deeds, to which Skourlie points. A knock is heard at the street-door. Dalgarno! O, too late! too late: That way, an't please you, gentlemen: 'twere ill (Pointing to the door in the side scene.) If you should meet. Her. Why, look you, then, to spare A bustle in your house, I'll go your way; But, pray conceive me, sir; I do not shun Th'encounter: I am old enough to know The law is mightier than your Lord Dalgarno, Or any lord in England. [Exeunt Heriot and Strappet. Skour. (Bowing after them.) I'm beholden— Your grateful slave: now, an eternal curse Light on you both! Enter Dalgarno. My lord, your servant ever! Dalg. 'Tis on the stroke of six. Now, Nigel! 'Sdeath, What ails thee, trembler? Skour. Me, my lord! I'm glad— I'm sorry— Dalg. Glad and sorry! hot and cold! It is the time, thou peddling, petty larceny— A church clock (supposed to be St. Dunstan's) strikes six. The hour of wealth and vengeance! Hark! it strikes: One, two, three, four, five, six! Well bang'd, brave hammers, The knell of Nigel! Every iron peal Has swung a manor! Come, the deeds: I long To greet my title. Skour. I—my lord—the deeds— I have them not. Dalg. You have them not! take care, Varlet! why point you to that pile of money? Skour. It is your own—it is— Dalg. Not the redemption money Of Nigel's mortgage? dare not say it is, Or I'll divorce thy petti-fogging soul From its base shell o'th'instant— Skour. (remonstrating in an agony of terror) I must call For help—'twas the law's act—what could I do? Dalg. Do! dost thou ask? What! were thy tricks, thy lies, Quirks, quibbles, shuffles, oaths, all spent? all gone? Or hold you those too good to be laid out For my behoof? But mark me well—thou know'st I've that, will hang thee. Skour. All that art and law Can manage, I will try. Dalg. Do, or be sure Thy lease of life and lies shalt not have long To run! the task is easy—recollect The hour was past before the tender made— And see that there be punctual witnesses To prove that fact. Skour. (recovering) I'll prove that Nigel's friends Used threats, aye, force:—I'd not been so ungrateful To let your lordship's interests suffer, else. Dalg. That strain does better.—Whence i'th'name of evil Comes this accursed dross? Skour. 'Twas Heriot brought it. Dalg. Plague blight him! But there's yet a way, Here, take The jewels. [Gives him the jewels. Skour. To what use? they're known too well To be disposed of. Dalg. Therefore, honestly Restore them to King James. Skour. And whence shall I Be taken to have got them? Dalg. You will say That Nigel sold them to you: sold them, mind, To you, this morning, in the town of Greenwich; That, seeing them among your wares, and knowing They were the king's, I bade you take them straight, As my most humble off'ring, to his highness, Making myself your debtor for the price. That fiction serves two ends: commends my zeal, And fixes Nigel with the stolen jewels Scarce two hours from the robb'ry. Skour. That may serve. Dalg. It shall! Skour. The time grows short though; 'tis the hour The king assigned to hear Lord Nigel's plea. Dalg. Well, to Whitehall then.—Heriot, hey? coax'd doubtless By fair niece, Margaret. Dainty Machiavel! When she shall hear the close compacted facts Of last night's murder—all the witnesses Cent'ring on Nigel, and th'auxiliar charge Of the crown-jewels rivetting his doom, O, then, how fast her pretty eyes will flash, And drown themselves in passionate grievous tears— While I, on his attainder, build a bridge May bring me, by the royal grant, once more Into these fair and forfeit lands of his, Which this vile step let go. (Going.) Skour. Most skilful!—but My Lord! Dalg. Well, Sirrah? Skour. You forgot to name The price I am to have for giving up These jewels to the king, Dalg. Make the work clear, (Taking two of the bags and tossing them to Skourlie. And take your wages. (Exit Dalgarno. Skour. (Alone, looking after him.) Aye, my lord, I will— And then dissolve our firm. So now, to seek The accomplice Peppercole; and, if I know Aught of the way a bargain should be driven, The large disclosures I can make, shall purchase Justice on you, a pardon to myself, And, haply, your coy Margaret for my wife. [Exit. SCENE II. The southern exterior of Whitehall Palace, forms the scene on the left of the spectators. At the back, right and left, is the Thames, with the Surry hills. The nearer part of the stage represents the garden of the palace, reaching to to the River. King James, Buckingham, Nigel, Sir Geoffry, Jin. Vin. Margaret, in her proper dress, Bridget, Lords, and attendants, officers, and crowd. James. And this is she! were we not right, my lord, (to Buckingham) When we opined that this most comely boy Was in good truth a girl? Perhaps ye thought That our's was not a hawk's eye for such gear; But old as ye may deem us, yet we know As much of sic-like toys, as may beseem A decent gravity. Sir Geoff. With shame she owns, And craves forgiveness of her vain disguise. Marg. (Archly) Then vainest, when against that royal wit Which none may hope to baffle. James. Deftly spoken: Heriot has taught the wench betimes to flatter. But here is darker matter to be dealt with; Robb'ry alledged, and murder—(To Nigel) Now, my lord, You've heard the charge. Are you prepared to bring The woman forward? or through other means Wipe off the strange suspicions cast on you, Both by her father's death, and by her absence? Nigel. My liege, I know not of her. When we landed, I bore her comp'ny through the dangerous alleys That wind about Paul's wharf; and having seen her Into the open street, there left her,—going She said, to some of her own kin, with whom She could have shelter. Since that time the woman Has not been seen by me. Hild. I fear, by none. Nigel. She said she should attend her father's inquest. Hild. But never came. James. You've read the depositions Of our Whitefriars Cor'ner, and the boatman. Nigel. I have, and do allow them. Buck. Fortune send Your Majesty may find those jewels safe Wherewith you trusted him—(aside) which, had I known it, You should have scarcely done. James. Doubtless you've raised The money on them, and redeem'd your lands As we gave warrant. Enter Dalgarno, Skourlie, and Peppercole. Nigel. So, my Liege, I should, Save for this old man's murder; but the jewels Having been lodged with him to find a lender.— James. Are gone! I see! Stol'n in this burglary! Nigel. I do beseech your Majesty— James. (To Nigel) Young Lord, You've tax'd our patience far! Our jewels gone, The lustre of our crown: we would have lost A colony rather! Dalg. He that slew the us'rer No doubt bore off the jewels; but, that Nigel, My valued friend here, needy as he was, Should have committed— Nigel. Only the respect (looking towards Dalgarno) I owe your majesty, reins in the rage Of my o'ergoaded spirit, when I see Each act and passage of my life thus foully Wrung to my ruin! How this plot was hatch'd, I cannot fathom; but by whom 'twas spawn'd, That I can guess at, and may punish yet. James. Were there a plot, think you our scent so dull, We should not have unearth'd it? We have guess'd At things as deep, I ween. Minion, resolve us, Where are the jewels? Silent! Dalg. (To Skourlie.) Now's the time! Skour. If it might please your majesty, forgive My innocent part herein, I have some knowledge Touching this matter. James. By my soul, thou hast Our favour: speak! Skour. I am, so please your grace, A scrivener by my trade, and versed in gold And precious stones, no less than in the drift Of honest usance. Comes to me this morning That noble gentleman (pointing to Nigel) with jewels, which He said had been his father's; offering them Below their value, to discharge some debts Which play had drawn upon him. Nigel. Villain! dar'st thou— James. Who interrupts our business? You shall have Your timely season. Skour. I entreat protection While I rehearse the truth: you know you said so, This very day, at Greenwich. Well, unknowing From what high source they came, I bought the jewels, And should have shipp'd them— Dalg. (Interrupting Skourlie and addressing the king.) Sir, they're yours. James. (To Skourlie.) Nay, speak— Skour. But that my Lord Dalgarno bought them of me, To lay before your grace's feet. Skourlie delivers the jewels to Dalgarno, who, kneeling, presents them to the king. James. True friend! Avis rarissima, in courts, they say— Of other princes,—Welcome, welcome, sparklers! Ye bright and bonny boys, thrice welcome back! Nigel. Most gracious prince, this fellow's every word Contains a perjury.—For his employer, [Glancing towards Dalgarno. Whose end in this suborning, is as plain As the dev'l's mark can make it, all I ask Is but to have my sland'rer stand before me Within the strait, and stinted liberty Of a fair ten-foot ring, my sword my own, And five short minutes to decide our strife, And if within that time and space, this hand Pluck not the mystr'y forth— James. Have you no words Fitter for royal ears, than such as breathe Of lawless bloodshed? Dalg. I am silenced, sir, Else, I could clamour in as high a strain, And dare, and haply too, perform, as much As this loud sir. James. (to Nigel) Would you speak ought, my lord In your defence, touching the usurer's death, Or disappearance of his daughter? Nigel. Nothing. James. (to Hildebrod.) Then bailiff, make your warrant of committal Upon the charge of murder. [Hildebrod writes: James counts the jewels. Skour. (aside to Margaret.) Margaret! Marg. Wretch! Skour. I have kept my word thus far, and brought him Close to the precipice: The power I had To sink, I have to save him. Marg. Use this power, And I will worship thee! Skour. You know the terms;— Be mine, and Nigel lives. Marg. Horrible choice! Skour. You still refuse? then let the warrant go, And Nigel perish. Marg. Oh, no more, no more! Save him, at any price. Skour. The price I fix'd? Marg. (faintly.) Ev'n so. Skour. (to James.) A pardon, sir, has been proclaim'd For any accessary, who shall bring Conviction home, on those that did the murder; Has that the sanction of your royal word? James. Aye, willingly. Skour. Come hither, Captain. Pep. Fear not; I will stand to it. Skour. (To James) Sir, I'm one, who long Have trod in slipp'ry courses, gath'ring wealth, Which fear forbade me to enjoy; but henceforth, I mean to live more safely, and defy The knaves that might betray me. Here is one. (Taking Margaret by the hand.) Who will sustain my good resolves: and straight, For a reward she gives, I will impeach— Dalg. (aside to Skourlie, with much fierceness.) Take care Skour. I shall! The real murd'rers— Her. (without) Room! Make room there! Enter Heriot and Strappet, making way for Martha. James. What unsightly fair is this? Nigel. Kind heav'n, the old man's daughter! Martha. (arriving on the spot) Do I come In time? Dalg. Some new imposture, royal sir. Dost thou affect to be the usurer's daughter? Martha. Dost thou affect to have forgotten me? My memory, thou shalt find, is not so frail. Hild. Why, this is she, indeed. James. But wherefore cam'st not Unto our inquest on thy father? How Hast pass'd this day? Martha. As it was meet to pass The first day of that life which Nigel saved, In Nigel's service: in collecting means To free (which with my kinsman's help's accomplish'd) (Pointing to Strappet) My benefactor's lands, pledged for a tithe Of their true value. But the price to clear them Could not be found 'twixt morning's dawn and six This afternoon, ev'n by “the us'rer's daughter,” Without some diligence,—and (seeing, too, Whose politics th'attempt must clash withal, My lord will apprehend)—(looking at Dalg.) some secrecy. For such cause only did I shroud myself From observation, and avoid that inquest, (Sighing.) Where yet my heart was present. Nigel. There will come A time for thanks. James. 'Tis well you're living, woman; But, the old man,—can you say aught that touches Your father's murd'rer? Martha. (Pointing to Dalgarno.) I impeach him, there. Dalg. She raves. This fearful issue has diseased Her brain. Martha. My liege, if there be not a wound On his left arm, like that Lord Nigel's fire Dealt to th'assassin from whose grasp he saved me, Then is my brain diseased, and I have wrong'd A guiltless nobleman. James. (To Dalg.) My lord! how say you To this? Nay, strip your sleeve. Dalg. Some groom has told her Of a late fall in hunting, where my wrist Was grazed. Martha. (To Hildebrod.) Speak, bailiff, do you know this scarf? Hild. The same, I fancy, which the murd'rer left About your father's throat. Martha. Thou say'st it. Dalg. Haply Left by the ill starr'd Nigel, in his haste To quit the chamber. Martha. Left by Nigel? pray you, How came Dalgarno's scarf to Nigel's hands? James. Dalgarno's scarf! Martha. My liege, I say the scarf Of Lord Dalgarno: and a web, indeed, Of no mean value; for, if I mistake not, It was the gift of majesty. James. Indeed! Dalg. Where is the light'ning's bolt, that should strike dumb This most audacious slander? Martha. May it please Your grace inspect the piece; the letters shew “Given to Dalgarno by the king.” James. (Putting the torn pieces together) It is— By our right royal word, it is the truth! Marg. (Breaking from Skourlie) Stand off, detested man! the King has said it, Nigel is innocent, and I am free! Jin. Then, at his choice, Jin. Vin. may hang or drown. Bridg. (Taking Strappet's arm:—archly to Jin. Vin.) What, fly to death, because you're saved from marriage? Skour. (savagely) Am I forestall'd, then, in discovery? and robb'd Of this my prize? Pep. (much frightened, to the King) Your grace will not recall The pardon? James. We shall judge how far 'tis earn'd. Skour. I will tell all—spare but my life and money, There's not a friend I have but I will give Into the hand o'th'law. O, mercy, mercy! [Exeunt Skourlie and Peppercole, guarded. Dalg. My Lord of Buckingham! Buck. Nay, not through me. James. (turning up the stage) What can they hope, but that just punishment Follow the guilty? Dalg. Punishment and justice! Who'll give the word? Your grace—(To Buckingham.) there may be secrets Best left untold; nay, if, as men presume, You have your master's ear, you may most humbly Whisper the question, how his royal justice Has follow'd Overbury's murd'rers? Aye, Bid the sage prince beware: for I may raise (turning to James.) A flame which, being kindled, will burn on, Ev'n though the hearts' blood of his inmost minions Should spout to quench it! [Exit. Buck. Follow, and arrest him! James. 'Twas well we took the hearing of your cause. No mystery baffles us. Nigel. I know not where I owe most gratitude: or to your grace, Or to this gen'rous woman (looking at Martha)—or to her (taking Margaret's hand.) Whom nothing, less than all my life, can show How much I love! James. Why, then, take all thy life To show it: and for you, young mistress, (to Margaret)—mind When you put on the wife, leave off the breeches. Now for your masque: I doubt though if 'twill yield us A plot more pregnant than your fortunes, Nigel; Themselves, perhaps, no unmeet argument To ground a play hereafter. May it find All favour and applause: provided always Our royal part therein be bodied forth With fitting rev'rence.—Come, the masque! the masque! THE END.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">EPILOGUE, Written by a Friend, Spoken by Mrs. Chatterley. Here I am once again—Pray be seated—don't fidget! I've something important—pray listen to Bridget. I walk'd from Paul's Wharf, all along by Fleet-ditch, To Whitehall—where I met with King James—he's a witch! He sees future destinies mark'd on the globes; “Sit ye down, child,” he cried. Then he twitch'd up his robes. “I'll tell you your fortune.” Odd thoughts seem'd to strike him. “You've got an old husband.” “Yes!” “How do you like him? “Um.”—“Speak.”—“Pretty middling; confess if I must, “He's not like old Port, Sir, the better for rust: “Time mellows our wine: that improves ev'ry hour, “But husbands, kept too long, are apt to turn sour.” “Odd's fish! you're a wag, girl, take paper and pen.” Then he stalk'd up and down: twitch'd his robes up again, And thus, deeply vers'd in the planets' decree, Foretold London's fate in the year twenty-three. “Young Ensigns in whiskers, and Dandies in stays, “Will niddety nod it in cabriolets; “O'er pavements ill mended, will kick up a clatter— “If their necks alone were in danger, no matter. “A frost will make noses on new year's day tingle; “A new Marriage Act will keep bachelors single, “While Homer's Achilles, without boots or gaiters, “Will stand in Hyde-park to astonish the skaiters. “Great folks will be gadding to Paris and Rome,— “They'd better by half spend their money at home. “Covent-garden will keep up her scenic renown, “And one Sleeping Beauty will wake half the town. “But,” (here he look'd grave) “in that year twenty-three, “She'll make a stage play of my Jewels and Me, “(As Shakspeare serv'd Bessy, our great predecessor, “Brought on in a crib, like a pig on a dresser.) “'Tis ludere sacris”—(and here he look'd graver) “And yet—if you ask it—they'll treat me with favour.” “Ah! sire,” I replied, “your may fail in your plan. “You don't know the Pit!—But I'll do what I can.” (To the Audience.) Then, sirs, by your hands, prove I've utter'd no fiction, And verify bonnie King James's pediction.</field>
   </doc>
</add>