<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Meriton, Thomas</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Meriton, Thomas</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">meriton thomas</field>
      <field name="author_text">Meriton, Thomas</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">17th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V1.0716.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240355</field>
      <field name="date_text">1658</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:459410</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Love and War ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 17th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 17th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Love and War ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="title_facet">love and war</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">love and war</field>
      <field name="title_text">Love and War ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="year_display">1658</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1658</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1658</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459410&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459410&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Meriton, Thomas&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;meriton thomas&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Love and War ; A Tragedy&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;love and war&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1658&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1658&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Meriton, Thomas&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Love and War&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for Charles Webb&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1658&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3871944-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv10716&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 17th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;17th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Love and War&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 266 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Love and war.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1658.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 1658.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">LOVE and WAR, A TRAGEDY.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Bellum gloriosum, pace turpi optabilius est. Demosthen. ex Orat.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Drammatis Personæ. Aberden, King of Bruzantia. Hollarro, the young Prince, his Son. Bellerrio, A Duke his Nephew. Murgorus, a Courtier. Nercius, a Courtier. Yernomy, Lord, subject to King Aberden. Fafrisius, Lord, subject to King Aberden. Buzarain, Lord, subject to King Aberden. Nevermo, Lord, subject to King Aberden. Quermero, a humorous fellow. Perpurgerus, his Companion. Celerinus], King of Numenia. Burgargo, a Generall. Orestes, a Lord. Sisterus, a Lord. Derisius, a Captain. Gervoron, a Captain. Burnomoy, a valiant Souldier. Adrenimia, Queen to Aberden. Lerenica, a Lady of honour. Histerica, her woman. Bardes to sing the Chorus, Souldiers. Attendants. Aglaia, Grace. Thalia, Grace. Euphrosyne, Grace.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Scene. Bruzantia.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">To the truly Noble, Ingenious, Judicious Gent, And my most esteemed Brother, Mr. George Meriton.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Prologue. If once is shewn the glimering Star, whereby Pluto is daunted, and great Jove knowes why: When by its circulation, driven course, At last by passage, lights upon by force Some watrish cloud, which by its structure foul, Is obscur'd from mens mortall eyes, they houl To see the radiall beams so quickly gone, As if all vanish, reliques thereof none: Just in resemblance, so shall I produce My future breathing, till some me conduce, To see your sparkling, splendent, orient eyes, Shining like Luna, Sol, Stars in the skies, Viewing my Pigmie, if perchance there be Pleasant looks in the Royall company Of your bright Train, more Angel-like then she, Apelles drew by art, yet could not be So well as nature wrought her; that same look Would purchase more, then I can with my Book, For it would raise Ambition, and bereave My fancy of its reason, to perceive Nothing but a Chimæra, and thereby Term my selfe new again if possibly; But if in opposition, it appear Just to the contrary, no looking chear, Nor smiling carriage, but then takes their place, Frowns, discommending, and absurd disgrace, Then I much like a Prisoner at the Bar, Shall be dejected, flying hence and far Do purpose to remain, as long as sense I have to weep for this my insolence. If story produce no laughter, nor the Wit Laugh at my folly in so doing it.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Act 1. Scen. 1. Aberden, Yernomy, Fafrisius, Buzaraine, Nevermo, Drum, Trumpet, a Florish, Souldiers. Aber. Receiv'd with gladness still my Lords you are, Gladly receiv'd, I say; we'l suffer all Our hands to be now numb'd with sense, let fall Our deadly swords; nothing in opposition Stands, we hear, but the whole Universe Endures in a paralectick posture; vast Worlds did Julius Cesar conquer, yet ne're Was able to withdraw our minds, but forc't To fly our summons; we'l range the steepy Bancks, those which with rudenesse hide Titan his raies, seek some terra incognita. Where men are absent, beasts may fulfil Our Warlike, yet not willful, incentions; Let us find it out, that by the prospect We'l gain the Victory, and surround the foe, Drench their hot hearts, as we all else, you know. Yer. None dare appear: but Numenia land Is said to have a will, bent to withstand Your Majesties (dread Soveraign) Army, for To know the right of Kingdoms, we abhor. Faf. The same, great Aberden, I will confirm, that They did help with unknown, potent strength, The last great Camp we rais'd; shewing to them Benigne favours, so they took them for their friends, No foe; which caus'd detard in winning the Rich Trophies, that you overcame at length. Aber. What? sure it cannot be; but if perchance That they do act a matter so disliking Me and mine, they shall not further trouble Their dull braines to make a search in pursuit After it; but I will so imploy their Grasping hands, to set all labour by, but what Concerns the martiall Banner, and bring it Home to them; War, which treads dame Nature's Courses, trampling under feet, her set Delivered forms, shall disclose, inclose to This Realm, strange unheard Iles. Numenia, With the rest of former Victories, shall Know my tribute; and I'l quickly see Wherein they my great force do disobay, Find them as farre as stars doth light the way. Buz. Then let us make a rule, and raise a Camp, Fall on them undiscreatly, and berdane Their Forces of a time, in which they Premeditating, may find Ammunition To dissolve our Troops, and to disgorge The obdure faculty of their sense, Defraud them in the time, and send them all To the native Earth, the Mother which they call, And fitly may be term'd so, and boyling Blood into the air, by the meteorious form Of it, a strange essence make, a full Similitude betwixt, we foresee they Purpose for to lead on; but let us go. Aber. Pray know for what, and why you do so, Nev. The thing is known, Aberden; yea, it is, Great Soveraign. Aber, See that the thing be fit, And bear, within its selfe, the full prologue Whereby it purposes to maintain its selfe, For too rash Counsell often breeds within A subject height, which may be call'd a sin, And that in prodigality, then done Beside its shifts, it can no other shun, But come to ruine. Yer. I, it is so, but this is not so bent, Because, great King, we have Your Counsel in't. Aber. But for I know, rash counsel doth maintain. Faf. Fear not that thought, for it will prove most vaine, Aber. If it be so, yet danger may be with Buz. It cannot be, it is a thing of mirth. Aber. Your censure so the subject for to be. Nev. Yea, that we do, that to eternity. Yer. So, shall we move with freenesse, till we come To that same object, which we in delay, Do stand most fearfull of, hoyst sails To it, search the triangular shapes Within its Region, where all the Pole doth count Full fifty Degrees it doth with height surmount, Yet comes not near the torrid Zone, whereby Our skins are scorched, and our flesh doth fry; We'l know the nature of Numenia's Land, In what longitude, or latitude doth stand. Aber. We'l know my Son his resolution to This great design, this overtaking of (I hope it will not be so as I call or prove In it) our strange unseeming enterprise, In following that my subjects do devise. Exeunt. Scen. 2. Hollarro alone. Hol. Stentorian voyces doth surround my ear, Echoing within the concave of the terrestiall Ball, all dolefull sighs doth pierce my tender Sense, of hearing; from those our spoyls Formerly obtained, and deeply groaning. Bidding farewell to Neighbours and their friends, With clamorous noyses of loath departing, And still Bizantia stands, who feeds the blood Of free born souls, who wisheth nothing but Th'element they move on; Oh spirits Generous, who nothing else desire to be Sepulchers for their falling lumps; What, is it thought a vapour impure, Of restless waters, can withdraw the fight Of quick-sight fury, or the bellowing waves, Stopt danger courses so, which gravell not Below, but fly above, the sense perceiving, And shall we thus decrepit rest at length Which will accompanied be with flegmatick And cholerous humours, for to be drawn Out by artificiall manner, skill, and art, As verity doth us shew, whose Turrets In a Tapers manner gives light to all Our Hospitality, and yet we are almost Stupid, lull'd with idleness, nothing but Slumbring dreams doth take abode and seize Upon our faculties: rowse, rowse, your leaden sense, Display your Arms, cleanse rusty swords amain, Look out your Helmets, Coats, bring home againe Your lost deceiving follies, search them out, And let not rust and canker turne their edge from Shedding blood; let not the hymns of musick Dull your ears, let Drums and Trumpets sound Still your intentions, untill there be found No vile lascivious fact with wanton ones, Which brings dull hearts, and lingeringness in bones, Hollarro's part doth differ far from it: They'l know as much, if they then defraud not Their much infeebled hands, for th'star where I, And under which my native time did come, Did impregnate here in stout acts to be As valour, rage, choller, blood, temper, free. Adrenimia with Attendants. Adre. Hollarro Prince, my son and onely joy, The matter still stands in a doubtfull way, To whom it bends, your judgement Prince, I pray, Decides the cause, Aberdens fickle will Runs hazzard, yet on tiptoes, whether the heads Be mine or no. Holl. Great Queen, you know, I nere led my mind in opposition To the same decree; let not deboysterous Humours so vail your discretion for Aberden the King, cannot deny, I'l undertake with temperance so far, Without a self-disaster, to bring on The purpose to a head, if you'l detard Procrastinate the thing which you have heard, But to the same effect the cause to me's Unknown. Adr. Why, it is this, if pardon lead The will of him, the subjects heads, who captives Are, by legions of his forces might, 'Tis the elixar of my diligence, May be a sacrifice to me, I in my hand May have command of them, disposing with At pleasures will, none challenge dare the same, It is no crime, since reason doth not blame. If it doth violate the Land, the Laws, It's soon amended where is known the cause, Let nothing interpose the same, but try, And gain my favour, least it come dearly. Holl. And were it not sufficient to have all their Bodies for your servitude, but in a fine Bereaving of their troubled lives, and to Send them to some unknown coast, where all New found discovered creatures and their souls Doth sleep, while you injoy onely vain Pattern of a hairy scalp; sure reason Should discover more then it, to please a Fancy so with noysom shapes. Adr. Hold you there, The King, though private carried in't, Devines as much, nay more; for surely it By the discerning Jove was long foretold, So waver not in will more this or that, But bring the same. Holl. Great Queen, your counsell is A severe guide. I'l go if earth and sky Were twist together by a prodigie, And all the foes with branded Lances met, Making such airy sounds with swords, helmet, That to the clouds doth raise a clamour, so By wounded souls which is deep fetcht most low, And all the sky with comets range their course, I would not fail, no not by all their gorse, But bring a sure certificate. Exeunt. Scen. 3. Belerrio, Murgorus, Nercius. Bel. My Uncles Palace is Apelles shop Of living pictures, which are set in No forms else but Ladies models. The Palace is the Judges, Ladies Diamonds; So it's a store, each Madam is an Angel. Murg. I, counterfeit Bel. Unheard of sound, who can dispose it so, They that do enlighten dull natures eyes Ner. Why, can it be so term'd? Cupid is blind, And it should follow his strange fashions. Bel. Yet opposition rise, though fortune deem The splendour of its rayes, therefore to seem In much lesse; oh that it could be said She turned was to moory shape, that strike It may not forth her worth so bright, For in her breast carries concealed fire, Which makes her fumes still by the flame aspire; All else were rightly coloured, but if she Give elimation, they turn' quickly be To Aurora's blushes, none dare take its place What decent is, unlesse she first imbrace Their rosey colour, but dejected are, Her crimson lips doth so excell them far. Mur. Do then explain her, sure she may be known, No fire there is, but by its smoak is shown. Bel. Her splendent parts doth so transcend clearness, That by its supernatures work, it dazels all Bright shining shadows; she is transparent, No muddy form is placed in her, but she Is the elixar of Virginity. Ner. Divulge her then, she sure cannot be leare, You count her so beyond the crystall clear. Bel. No quick-sight apprehension can discern The mould from whence she is took, nor delicacy By all her pencil art demonstrate her; Diana still grows shapelesse by comparison, Yea all the Goddesses are immur'd by her, None dare appear, nor in place come nigh her. Mur. Oh sure she is invisible to be Nam'd in our presence, that know her may we. Bel. In her you may discern Loves onely face, All Nymphs their parts, and that with comely grace, A front dependent, eye much like a sloe, Her lip a cherry, in her chin a bow; Her breast like alablaster crimson rose, Her waste like slender Pine disovered shews, Her hair the tresses, on her neck like milk, Display their pastimes like a twisted silk Or threds of gold. Mur. Still fomie passage lights in thy design, Name her, that this discourse may be at fine. Bel. What, stupid still, possest with ignorance, Not know her by these tokens I advance? I'l spare no passage now to spend my breath, To name the quintessence of all the earth, Lerenica she disposeth of My fickle will, and fancy at one both. Ner. What she? how backward runs the course? The time hath been when opportunities Hath sought occasion in their properties, By casting favours by her mush-red eye, Deluding objects to sobriety. To get the will of him, who intended The Zenith of love where under it did Rest, should be prolonged further, casting Aside those indisposed sight and tricks, As vain, and whom doth none regard. Bel. The Styx, her mists doth paraphrase your words, VVherein grim Cerberus doth bathe himselfe; Let the same vapour rise, and by its stench, Infuse an opiate virtue, there to dull My vitall spirits, to cut the hair Of danger's purpose, and whereby I shall Receive a quiet death, for a vexed life. Ner. Fear not, A gilded bait shall intrap this Barbell, VVe'l find her stratagems, devise a way The filly blind boy knows not, the which shall Imploy affairs deserving worth a name Of Chronolgoy, a cheat, or somewhat May worke effect with this same peevish brat. Bel. Let hope go with that design to the end, Methinks my top-sayls move with celerity, I gain acuteness and agility; VVho ever did take arrogance in strength, Or sound brave Nectars notes with Bacchus juyce, More freely then do I, must be more then Mother Nature doth put forth, sweep away, Inclose within thy arms; oh Cynthia, Thy master Titan's Candle, let not him Praunce on his journey to the top of th'hill; But curb his fiery trigon, suffer not No more his fight till we have done our plot. Mur. Though friendship promise more then strangenesse doth, Deride not one, but do receive then both, I'l bring whole fountaines of new-found desires, VVhich shall suck up the hony of your fires, And flames of love: we go. Exeunt. Scen. 4. Celerinus, Bugargo, Orestes, Sisterus, Dirisius, Gervoron, Burnamoy. Cel. Since time, tradition, forces against will And all the Countries invitations, Me to withstand Aberdens ardency, Of choller, which at length consumes all what It meets with, whose vast supportment would Not subsist, but be demolishe, and top Submissive to its feet, know if let rest, Sloath would enter course, yet Fame not be Ejected, your valour still would reigne, And, Bugargo, if you maintain our right; Supporting all our cause, and not detarding Shame, but Derisius, Gervoron, both Take part with him, you shall have recompence, I stand oblig'd all due to common sense. Burg. Courage strikes my resolute contentment High (Celerinus) immense vast Trophies, A Diadem, be purged from my thoughts; If all the prises then were equall poysed, And shar'd the lot, deciding judgement would, As me possest, term trouble: for a Peasant Without delay transported to a Prince, VVere a too great Hyperboly, I'le undertake. Cele. All grateful motions attend then your soul, You are the head, we members wait there on; And what composure may be thought upon By loving deeds, all experientiall skill May be put forth, or sacrifice thy will. Stand firm to it, inform us then no more, Affection lead, thou shalt have gold or ore, I wave my selfe, though speciall charge commands, Either gain Kingdom, or else lose your Lands; VVhat spoyls can blind, or mask our piercing glance? VVhat keen struck sword, black armour or the lance, VVhose sight corrupts the Element, which pure Contain'd in its selfe the cold moist air, Put forth betwixt my eye, all my desire To know the day it's that thou dost require. Deris. VVhat, is it thought that King Aberden will Hoyst sayles to us, dreads he, nor land, nor soyl, Which lends a death, a murror, and a broyl To their inhabitants, they'l nere wait, Pitching a leagure to o'recome the wall They are bent against, which shares with Nile, The Alpes would fair imprint a backward call, If once their eyes cast upwards be. Bugargo, doe command my legion, when Fear smites thy arm, fire Beacons, and let Drums sound loud. Ger. Let Bizantia's Monarch pursue the way, He has at length begun; for Morpheus Doth bear more frequent rule with leaden Mace, Then Mars with valour carried in his face. Heres no determed theam, by whose oppose May vent hot sparks of manhood from our Loyns; for as quick sight with well wrought temper, Gives a gloss to affect the matter; so Oft experience by assiduate practice, Makes that which is uncord then most prompt. Though love is strong, yet Cupid by might Combines with Mars a steely shirt though hard, Yet oftentimes is safer then a linnen frock; My blood doth buble, when is brought before Idle disposed fashions, martiall blades; Seeking, lost nothing, all armour proof, yet Uselesse are, which would possesse with a Fear, they stand in danger of each other; Nor can the fame be nought but great, They raise a Camp postreeme with us, when as The East and West doth seem a distance, not A foot in length, being fadomed by their might, Since then so large our enemies be found, Our glory still grows greater by their sound, What answer you? Orest. 'Tis right, renowned friend In prime to carefull be of our Soveraign In maintaining right, next to this City And thy Country good, if truth thou binds in That same Gordian knot. Sist. Then bold Fac'd Champions, leviated from the blood Of well tryed Princes, you may discern the Blast, if by prevention not made sure, Cause ruine o're this Land, if flint and steel Being met, expell their fiery beams; Well may your generous souls inflaming With valour, betwixt rough danger and Mild sloth, let fly over steepy hill, until you Are conducted to th'contrary by grim death. Bur. Since cause is equall, victory cannot be Debard from us, and no wayes misery Take here abode. Cele. Lets then beguile the time no more by talk, But see your guard and front be sure, Call o're in summons, display your Colours, Flags, Banners, Pendents, Streamers, see your men Be right for th'cause, great Generall Bugardo. When that is done, I'l cause my sacred Priests To move the gods, and all their hymnes set forth For your welfare, all what can thought be worth. Exeunt. Scen. 5. Quermero, Perpurgerus. Perp. Why so, since time delivers otherwise to be. Stretch forth thy arm, it's nought but exercise Brings on the same. Quer. Oh hold then pray you there; I'l stretch my hand, if fortune will give leave. But shall not be to kill, but to maintain Life by its help. Per. How strange to common sense! Draw out thy sword I'l shew thy postures; What if a man should challenge field with thee? Quer. Then I should dye. Per. Before the blow did come? Quer. I quickly sure, the sight's as good as blows With me; but since your Treaty is to draw, [He stands in a foolish posture.] I stand hear guardian of my selfe. Per. See, see, If't were possible, he would invite Heraclitus To laugh: I dare swear Plato might read A piece of Philosophy in his posture; Stand up man with a full breast, surely Mr. Quermero, your breech and feet are [Quer. nods his head. At difference— Per. Hold up your hand, and stiddy; how like you It—What, no answer, but by conjecture Postures; he shakes his head, 'tis well, hold up I say—hold in I say this breech, oh [Quer. makes a face. Pretty face; but if you'l make no answer, It is my means shall force you; [Per. beats him, and he runs away and layes down his Sword. What none—what none—what none. Quer. Gently good cousin, my bum is addle, Have care you break no Eggs; for if you do, The sent perfumes the room beside all Myrrh or Spiknard. Per. Why answer you not? Quer. Let pitty force compassion. 'tis My weak stomack and foolish condition, The nakedness of sword lends such terrour To my heart, reflects amazement to my Eyes, that while supported by my hand, no Word can utter the cause I it dismist. Per. Oh senseless pagan, take't up again; [He takes his sword. What, affraid, here take it, try thy valour, Shake thy weapon, now I'l draw mine. Quer. Then I'l Put up. Per. Hold, stay thy hand, and let us two inclose. [They clatter their swords Quer. I wish Aberden had no greater foes. Per. Hey bravely done, this is all, well man'd. Quer. Hey-day, methinks I am a second George for England, have at you then. Per. Stand further off. Quer. Stand further off. Per. Have care— Q. Stand further off. Per. You'l run in danger, hazzard the little life You have put up, put up. Q. Stand further off. (He cuts him.) Per. What now, draw blood, brave Champion, My joyes still grow the greater, wind whistle Forth thy fame, like sturdy Oak thou stand; All other are but shrubs, my blood cryes blood Again, stand Guardian still. Quer. Stand further off. (He hollowes.) Per. Your dexterous art works opposition to My term'd design, none can then curb your will, But what must spring from Bizantia. Quer. What, kicks thou? stand further off. Per. The pumel of my sword is lost, thou art like A Crocodile, pursuing flyes, flyes pursuing Your hardy courage, rises more and more, I hope to see the Land all in a gore; My spleen now riseth, works in the concave, A desperate motion, nothing shall thee save. Quer. I fear neither friend nor foe, stand further off. Per. I purpose now to put in motion some, Beyond capacity, strange unheard act; So then thou goes. (He trips his heels up) Quer. Oh, oh; What, my back broken by a fall, [Murther, murther. But stir not till he is gone, make much, Foster what I have got perchance the fact Is such, that quickly will not go. Per, Lie still, When sense bereaves thee of thy will, conjeal'd By a known accident, inforc'd by that Works invisible, a coard yet staies His friend, favouring by course what licence Give it's aid, I fetch attendants to wait On thee. Exit Perpur. Quer. Attend thy selfe, see that thou dost; Is he gone? Sword, where art thou? Hay, hay, [He rises by degrees. What, as lively as thy Master is, oh How the flesh corrupts thy edge; stay, is Perpurgerus gone? I'l lye close still, may Be he stands perdue, but gone or no, I'l Up, and see my wound; hay boyes, none, none, none. [He leaps. [He finds a hole in his Stocking. Oh stay here; what's this? oh deadly thrust, Fetch a Chyrurgion, I cannot go But must because am forc't; Oh, oh, oh, oh. [He halts from off the Stage: Exit. Scen. 6. Hollarro. Hol. A Conquest lost for want of obedience; That superstitious terrour, which with Force concatenates the wills of naturall Bears, and hangs its Flag, a sign of true Discretion, as making votes, sole Recreation in nought but prayer, And offering sacrifice, still stands in Behoving power, imploring the aid of Sublime Gods or Deities, a decree, Not challeng'd by a right, thou let us laud Them according to their deserts, we shall receive Pledges of felicity, and cancell out Our black transgressions; thus should it, none In exchange betwixt, them and us, for what Ascends when we descend, three-fold descends Again when we ascend; this same it will, By graduation, form a ladder passing From the celestiall quier to the terrestiall ball: And now nere want pleaded more her Cause than at this present; my care shall Be to see it fulfill'd, yet my Mother Queen Stayes out her time, my duty shall wait Leasure of her coming. Adrenimia, sola. Adr. Well, Prince Hollarro, I see you are not perverse You wait my leasure, I'l recompence, My ears hang at your tongue by a symphaticall Attention, striving with priority, who to Super-excede; the tenor by your voyce will give The Victory, what answere King Aberden? Hol. Most mighty Queen, my intreates did play Their course as Fortune thought it fit, Bent with a resolution not to return with Fruitlesse answers, until thought possest My tender judgement, they had gained Anger from King Aberden; yet like a Valorous Champion stood his ground, not Flying at the first, but reply over the Same again; but when the fury ended, mildnesse Did deliver, he would conceal. Adr. What, not the head, the least request could be; Why, when the swift long-winged faulcon playes Her game, her recompence shall be the head; What so e're her prey be, he would conceal, O If King would favour me, with majesty Of his great presence I'uld know the reason why. Hol. Great Princess, I'l see. Exit. Hol. Adr. So go thy way. Aberden, Hollarro, Yernomoy, Fafrisius, Buzaraine, and Nevermo. Aber. Adrenimia, you sent for me, I know the cause, Griefe still doth poyse the libra of my will, By a just weight, the beam is leavel, but to Whom give down (it's yet reserving power) Is unknown, you plead for it, ten thousand Pleads against; you are my Queen, all Other are my subjects; you save my name, The other save my life: to whom should it Give down? pray Lords aid you me in't; She pleads for head of those that captive be, The request is small, though much denyed by me; Are you content? then I shall notwithstand; Do you deny? then I will leave the Land. Hol. Your Majesty Astrea yet much courts, She with her grasped hand, and severe looks, With scale and sword makes in your mind her Sphere, yet will it enter into the hearts Of your subjects, and deem t'the clemency of a King, Grant it the Queen, great Soveraign. Yer. The Prince answers for all. Abe. Are you so all agreed? Yer., Faf., Buz., Ne. We are all, brave King. Hol. The game is up. Aber. My Queen, the onely will of him, who ever was Thy sole refuge, doth grant with fervency, The subjects heads that taken are by us; They are thy ransome, take you them when you please; My Ships have gain'd upon the angry Seas, Dancing levalto, my courage not refuse, To do the same, thy pleasure wills to chuse; Therefore, brave Princess, this thy self-design Shall be a virtue, not in least a crime; So take it freely, take it as a bliss, [He kisseth the Queen. Before my subjects, confirm it with a kisse. Omnes, Continuance long we wish. Adre. My King, my Monarch, what can I term thee lesse, In granting thy poor Queen a happy bliss? I thank thy high and mighty power for it, Thy subjects too, I'le frame a thing what's fit, Or best becoming all the tedious sense, Of your blest wills for this your kind presence. Exeunt. Scen. 7. Chorus , 1. Song 1. Shout aloud, Let a cloud Distill rain To the plain, 1. While with mirth We on earth, Mercy, Peace, Each imbrace: Let him want mercy, peace, and voyce, That cannot play when we rejoyce. 2. It combines And inclines Man and beast To a feast. 2. And Jove sounds To their rounds, Making sport To their sort. Let him want mercy, peace, and voyce, That cannot play when we rejoyce. 3, Mars put down To a room Lower then Worst of men. 3. Forc't to be There is he With relief Pining griefe. Let him want mercy, peace, and voyce, That cannot play when we rejoyce. 4. It's a time Bowls of wine, Follow game The self fame, 4. Go about Till they rout Fancies of Those that quaff; Let him want mercy, peace, and voyce, That cannot play when we rejoyce. 5. Within this All's a bliss, Not a sin Is within, 5. But all joy Nought distroy The least mite Of our right; Let him want mercy, peace, and voyce, That cannot play when we rejoyce. 6. Ceres with Her green sheaf In the morn Brings in Corn, 6. As the sky All doth die, Lands and streams With light beams; Let him want mercy, peace, and voyce, That cannot play when we rejoyce. [Chorus.] Song 2. 1. The time is all well-nigh spent, Fury begins to rage, All to War they are fully bent, Nothing else will asswage. 2. Now Joves pastimes must give way, Both man and beast must Fear, Mars must both rule and bear the sway, It whistles in my ear. 3. Those that mount even for to passe, Their time in Taverain, Must look to keep a Fort at last, Regard their Soveraign. 4. Ceres dismist is with that She hath with labour hew'n, Turning her with fame in her lap, Drums sound another tune, Exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Act 2. Scen. 1. Lerenica, Histerica. Ler. Display my tresses, see decent places Become their shapes, withdraw the stragling Hairs, reduce them to a set form. Hist. 'Tis done. Behold, delicious, sweet face't Hymens day, And what your will is with acceptance pleas'd To be, my purpose was to have took labour, In conveying you to some chaste Nunnery, Where all refreshment of a doleful day Should be low sighs; but your mind is turn'd You in its place receive a Palace bright, Where Diadems come to a grasping hand, Such riot by a fury is imploy'd, That reason would conclude (if sense guide not) That walls and houses were all eeven ground, And by it fumes sent by an airy help, Draweth a curtain betwixt friends and foe, And no other musick practised, But clamours from both wide and shril-sound throats, As't were a ransome to a Victory, The cause whereof Bellerrio counts you fair. Lere. Had you by favour obtained the good will Of Duke Bellerrio, and no outraging Carriage by a mysterious form, metamorphos'd The design, but expedition wrought with Nature so, that in the passage of affection, You by discretion wrought to the object, Combined with a smile, following by track, Or by tradition, to the wonted place, All the Nuptial Rights that are wished for, To present to the view a happy morn, As Bridegrooms morrows, Sack-posset, and beside, A thing not to be named. Hist. Oh! My blood is young. Lere. It would have favour'd time, so as an hour Rest, when waken all the joyes being past, And what did boyl by a lascivious lust, Would cooled be by a dull appetite, You may protest when tall Bellerrio, Did by his own known Counsell hide Within my soul a treasure not corrupt. In those consenting silent times he moved, Was but a gliding beam to Sol his selfe, Which by its fullnesse brings on this malady; But now renouncing those bad infections, Receives by means some vitall Spirits in, To bid defiance to those false allurements. Hist. It were too hard, you speak not like a Syren, For beauty, shape, with modesty, if tyrants all with- stand, are invitations to Venus Courts, The efficacy therein by which they bear, If were abrap'd, the Academy of Love were gone; Nay if by nature possibly I could Be turn'd a Man, if Icie temper seiz'd Upon my limbs, and put to prospect as One wanting soul, the like reward, also Hopeful enterprize, would then regenerate, As I have hear-said, calor naturalis in my veins; Nay if Midas his wish, with Jasons golden fleece, Put to redeem your same beautious piece, Yet all would prove too vain; for you are such, And have like virtues, both in least and much; I cannot so my selfe so full express, As if a man I were I do confesse, For then I should inlarge at every word, And here for three, three hundred then afford. Lere. Believe me, Histerica at this time doth pierce My understanding a thought of great belief, That he prefers you to a place so high, To be the prologue to his enterprise; But by his carriage he should be what wise, (And if he be) he should have took more care, Than to send such Orations as these. Learning is not a bait fit for Womens stomacks; Rather by intreaties, must perswade, and Fostered Muse, than any Tullian phrase, or Homers lines, you are too high in your design, And withall too tedious, away, away, Be sure your words are not in office, like Compelling swords, but turn their calling to Rebounding echoes; they are air, and so They vanish, and doth not enter my soul; And if by lot he chuses you again, Tell him from me he is not wise. Hist. Too hard Nature to work upon, and by temper, Was not first decreed to be a woman; For women are soft, you carry an opposition: For men to love, you stand against the cause, But 'tis no matter; now Bellerrio comes, [Enter Beller. He'l speak himself. Scen. 2. To them Bellerrio. Bel. My onely thoughts, thou art my Diamond that I dayly wear, and when my eye is cast Upon its splendor, its turn'd a mint of gold; When crystal beauty ushers in her train, And Ruby colour fetcht from the Indian mine, Doth act their quarrels in a lovely face, Whose cheeks are Roses, brow a comely mace, So Paris joy'd, when he fetch't Helen home; So Ulysses joy'd, to see his sweet hearts loom; So Hippomenes joy'd, when he the Apples got; So Æneas joy'd, when saved, it was his lot, So, and beyond all that, rejoyced he, (Except your selfe) obtain'd by a decree, the fairest of your sex; Nay, these are nought, in thought but vain deceits, Mine is the substance, these are onely baits, Not in the least, derived from a name; Mine's pure and perfect, their's is void of shame. Nought can by artificiall art be brought unto, More decent then pure Lerenica's hieu. 'Tis you, 'tis you, your sex I honour still, You above rest, in you my onely will Hath free beatitude, content and life. All things what else, that is then void of strife, I will endure for to maintain the cause Of your brave sex, and Champion in the Laws, That concerns you and yours, who perfect is, Sole happinesse, a thing beyond all blisse, Let me imbrace your will. Lere. Illustrious Duke, it were an injury Inforc'd by me, and I should by liberall Freedom violate the means of your true amity, Not concluding with a favourite, the Purpose was my own decree, you did Display their flames so in their ardency Of generous contemplations, that In circumference of its boundlesse hope, No room was left for me to expresse My selfe in equall ballance poysed your worth, But with a back-recalling sound of love, Made a retreat not worthy of the same, And with cherishing thoughts that pleasure Might be fill'd, and no disliking taste rise From its stench, you for to term me Most unworthy of such bright enterprises. Bel. Alass your answer is indisposed now, Do but resolve me how it would become A Peasant to deny a Prince, a martial man; Women fine smiling shews, surely I should Condemn my self as guilty, one stupifi'd by art, If that I should think so; come come, Your words doth not diminish, but give aid To my dull hopes of a brave Victory. Hist. Madam if leave may have so much freedom, hear This time, to help the case, give me a word, A Dialogue is good, when there's three persons; The Duke speaks fair, not sending his words As if they dealt more cruell by sighs and Sieges, more tempestuous than storming Neptune's blast; Or as if he intended Batteries against your beauties favour. But with a comely grace, understood of Sweetnesse, and smiling passage; withall, a Brave decorum, it would pierce an Adamant, Make restless motions, calme, serene and clear, And in stern looks where fury hath before Took potent place, 'twould quickly extinguish all. Lere. No want here is of foul conspiracy, A problem sure, and that invisible too Contain'd therein, no new found art can be By stars or reason, or interpreter, So quick-sighted in the way of these strange Politick notes; to lay it open, or Divulge the same, it must be silence with Perseverance thereof, who is the spouse Of long-sought mysterie, reveal this same; How can it be that you should both joyn in The same broad channel of deliverance? As if slit-looks should reason so the case, To be nunciate betwixt their tongues, Histerica keep silent in these hours, Bellerrio I'me not worthy to be yours. Bel. What still perswaded so, you transform it, And where you think conspiracy to be, It is not so, but the Oracles means, Delivered to our ears, the cause is right, Come bring no criticall point, no posture of Confusion to my maladies, be more mild, You deserve all, I single you from th'rest, Because an Angell, and a Virgin blest. Exeunt. Scen. 3. Celerinus, Orestes, Sisterus, Burnomoy. Cele. It is decreed, the businesse pursues the cause. Orest. My Leige, the post of quick known news Did come, not knowing your Majesties Privy Chamber, to my hands, he being Accompanied with many conditions Of King Aberdens will, and the fuel That now maintains the quarrell betwixt us And him, sent to your Highnesse presence, Did leave then to your best times consideration: Celer. Are they now present? Orest. They are, my Liege. Cele. Read them, I'le attend. Orest. Aberdens Conditions of this waging War, sent from Bruzantia to Celerinus, King of Numenia. Since all the Regions Under Northern Pole, Stretch forth their Distance as far as they can, Doth do obedience, (not One doth condole) Unto the Country and Bruzantia's man. Send yearly tribute, And their dayly vowes Unto their Gods to Prosper our successe. That by the clamour of Their open mouthes, We have a musick that Beyond all blesse. It is the purpose and The onely care Of great Aberden to Have you do so; And that hereafter You do not dispaire To do the like, and to His presence owe. If you refuse, his ships Are all rig'd for The Ocean waves, and by A prosperous gale; To sally out and come Unto your shoar, Before you think his Ships be put to sale; Therefore consider, take A serious time, Regard your cause, to Whom it should then bend, Do not then naver, follow Streight a line. To have Aberden either Foe or Friend: Sist. Put it up, its read, inclose the lines, A bold design to such a powerfull name. Cele. His usurping grace strives too too high, Who swels with blood of lost innocent ones, Which will by vacuation prove a gall, He cannot carry manhood for a praise Of Warlike courage as the free-born souls For country, good, and health, without more time, My mind is fixt, no other fancy takes My genius, but send a daring challenge To his will. Bur. It is right, dread Soveraign, My never tyr'd yet hand shall bring with it Vermillian hue, when 'se're return, and I, As long as strength doth give its aid, Withstand their bold attempt. Orest. My mind by looks did so much answer him, They were so fixt by fury in my brow. I slight his threatning lines with spitting fume, We can set envy up as well as he, Upon a banner tost, and make him know 'Twas rash without a Councell chose, Thus answers him, Orestes. Sist. The Chaos was my Mother, so to Chaos Will return, e're I be thought base in a Pedigree, my mind stands to their will. Celer. So, Hector by way ne'r gain'd such fame, as we, By this dread undertaking; but before We force a Camp, I shall ingagement bring Upon your souls, that you a solemn vow, By this my signature of all Numenia, To stand your colours, as long as flesh or Bone, and blood by circulation, keeps dame Nature in, and fight for him, (my selfe the Meaning is) as breath hath interal passage, And then postreme, to kill who's e're you take; See that you do confirm. Omnes. Long live Celerinus King. [They bow and kiss the Signature on his hand. Celer. Well said, brave noble souls, But before we for leagure do provide, We'l know our Generals will and Captains too, So Burnomoy bring them then into presence, [Exit Burn. And things right managed with a discreet will, Brings good well hap, and very seldom ill; For if the case be plain, and take no heed, Oft ruin comes by that same bad misdeed. Scen. 4. To them, Burnomoy, Burgargo, Derisius, Gervoron. Burn. Your command, great Prince, is here fulfill'd. Burg. Your businesse, stout Leige. Celer. It runs by Cypreans fields, Bruzantia's plain, By a spectatious sight, and information, A Paradise to shew whose in, beyond, The Tagus fragments go, by Poets fam'd to be Paved with a Pearl, her grace surrendring to The Queen of beauties pride Chloris with her Decency, strikes admiration to th'insatiate Soyls, to see themselves by Autum's clusters So prest down, and cooling Rivers which with Melodious tunes sing by the woody banks, While they with as well pleasing noyce, Whistle like Orpheus reed, Titan in Æstivious times, when torrid heat hath power, Dismisseth night, and gives day the full hour, Of number twenty four; then Burgargo, This Region (which I named) by scituation, Transcends the metropolis of every Nation, I stand defiance with a barbarous call, I purpose to choose you my Generall. Burg. When sense doth rave beyond its bounds, why then There is no reason that we should be men; Let sense and reason scorn my onely state, When I deny to govern this by fate, Which hath been separated from the rest, By Jove his hand, and he to be the guest That it should entertain; this Ile that which Gives livelihood, and makes the inhabitants rich, My hope is fixt upon, and firmly too, That sacred Gods will aid and fortune shew, Because we stand in our defence, not lust To have a War; but this our cause is just, We stand for right, not what is got by pelfe For lives, for wives, who are our second selfe; 'Tis pitty that this Nation should go down, And save your Majesty, none ought to wear the Crown, Except your selfe, who wisely with your hand, With voyce gives leave, with that their force with-stand, Let them display their colours, black visage, so unseemly sight, with plaited hair you know, Much like a Horses main, which gives a light, They are savage creatures, speciall in the night, When skyes become their favour; let them come, I'le be your Generall till day of doome. Cel. Your answer's good, they are both rash and rude In judgment, doing actions, and before Their nature be by valour curbed so, They'l ne're rest silent, but stratagems Inventing still, though with grief and amazing Flashes bring a float of destruction With whole waves of sorrow to their pedigree, My breast doth breathe not with a fair clear passage, Because corruption grows from nomination of Such hellish heathens; the Numenia's Land They strive to make their prey, and spoil of it; 'Tis not the fear of their great potent arme, 'Tis not Aberden with his hellish charm, 'Tis not their Chariots with their Iron wheels, 'Tis not their Ships with their well pitched keels, 'Tis not the fiercenesse of their nature foul, 'Tis not the savagenesse of their grim soul, 'Tis not the words of their well threatned voyce, 'Tis not the stroaks with which they make their noyse, 'Tis not the armour that they dayly wear, 'Tis not the colours wrought with silver clear, 'Tis not the conditions that they all sent, 'Tis not the words that they pleased to put in't, 'Tis niether this, nor that, shall work so fast, But I will fight their fury to the last. Deris. Your answer's like your selfe, noble, and that Most generous; I like a branch, you are The root, if you perish I must not stand. Gervo. Let fame want Trumpets for to blaze her self, Let my poor soul want blood to raise her selfe, When I deny to be as firm as you. Cele. Then my Lord Orestes, see a Legate Be prepared to send to King Aberden. You know the drift of th'cause, we will maintain The War he promiseth to our Land, and Burgargo with these two Captains, which are Derisius and Gervoran, and that valiant Souldier Burnomoy, draw down your forces To the port-Towns, cast trenches, ditches, that If they gain the Land, they know not where to Lead a squadern up, but stand amazed at their rash stricking shore. Omnes. Heavens blesse Numenia's King. Cel. After you return, (as undoubtedly victorious) Trophies shall be prepared of pure Gold, Elixars essence, what doth Nature hold, Be presents to your reward. Exeunt. Scen. 5. Adrenimia, Hollarro, with Attendants. Adre. My soul runs wandring from its way, Not knows its guide, till fortune by favours Whip, lash the occasion forward, that they May joyn their Forces by Sea or Land, My hands want blood, that (by its natural heat) Receive a quickning sense, my fury playes Upon the strings of the Præcordium, Which causeth a palsie in my hand, that Hold I cannot till some blood I have, I could with ease disgest the wrong that's done, If I should cause one of Aberdens friends To use my Altar, his head upon my spear, In the air to be an attom of delight, It is a thing disgorge with me most sure, I feel a weakning cause rise in my bones Which can be deemed nought else, but want of blood, Prethee Hollarro what, must still vacation, A rust corrupt your souls and weapon too, Resolve my quere, sure you are not bent To raise perplexity to a Queen her will, Blood, blood, still I will call. Holl. Great Adrenimia, the conditions which your King Was pleased to make a War, expected answers Are, when Post brings news, the tydings which you Wait leasure on, unto my Fathers Court, No sooner arrival shall take its abode, But with a fiery look and watry eyes, Bring to your Highnesse those same prodigies Which lurk betwixt affection and defraud, Your pleasure wills to crave that harsh design, Like Ebian wood, whose colour cannot be Changed to a whitish hue, no more can your Intreaty turn its black melanchollious Humour to a white waterish flegmatick Cause; my spirits raise ambition in my Veins, that such who works against natures will, Receives no free permission there to lay Its store for that same matter which you crave; But if a War go on with immarchlesse forces, My father's such a man (your Husband, Aberden) Stands to a word, though mentioned long before, To let those captive subjects, which by lot Caught in the gins of our free-born like souls Of Amazons, ne'r yeeld field to any, Either foe or friend, to lesse or many. Adr. What, is it so? what, is it so? still Hollarro stand against That same cannary bird, what's e're it be, Sings such a note with pains repining forth, Such unagreeing discord, and unhandsome Quavers, shall quickly have a Pip upon His tongue, a slit or gash about his neck, Make him sing sweeter changes then those same; Hollarro take care, look not to untwist Those arms of great Aberden and his Queen. He granted me, you stand in opposition; Talk more with silent counsell, then to th'face Of a Queens power, condemn it a disgrace That she takes pleasure in, it's blood that I Crave of my King, untill the day I dye, If none can have from forraign Countries then, Constrain'd I must take then our innocent men, Your part shall not scape free, if you do not Go to the Wars, the next will be your lot, Therefore blow up those fires that almost dye In your stout Souldier, that perpetually They may bring home great spoils unto the Queen, As captives, bracelets, all what my youth hath seen: See, see, you do, do so, dispatch the cause, Or else in this Land I will bring new Lawes. Hol. Your will's a Law, great Madam, to my force, I shall not be him that withstands your losse; The frigid Zone ne'r new the Icie way, Or tract her course more plainer then doth I, In your bright Horizon, the sphere of hope Wherein my restlesse will doth make her Orb. While Titan drives four prauncing Horses, That needs neither whip nor bridle; so move I To please the tender affection of your Princely grace; take not in least in heart My bad attempt, which flyes by the swift wings of ignorance, guided by staffe of folly, Ranging within the bowers of restlesse will, Seeking the corners of vain bad designs, Still let them fly for refuge to your grace, Let them there take their most reserving place. Adre. You are most hollow-hearted, while you see No good there is in gaining, what your will Hath minde to work its force, you then detard Most fatigated in that, what your purpose was, Desist your talk, I leave your presence. Holl. I, Stand submissive as becomes your Son, And wait your royal Person. Exeunt. Scen. 6. Aberden, Yernomoy, Fafrisius, Buzaraine, Nevermo. Aber. The Legate is dismist from them, 'tis well Their answer riseth so high against our will, Which hath bid stern Mars stand off, and the Brute Of troy-novant his race, hath stood with his Shoulders pending to the ground, by its Massy and assured waight, blest in the Perifery of a swallowing main, burst Great Numenia's wall, make skies to eccho As you do at Rome, when Pope stand elevated, Quell you their voyce by your secret harmony, That will make Hercules for to wonder, And Leo rejoyce to hear such single notes, And Tygers repeat it as a loving Song; That when the Inhabitants hear, struck with the Amazement of a terrours will, terming it Thunder; let Auster, Boreas, and the other two, Of Cardinall points, your fame blow aloud, In represention of (wrongs new redrest) Not to be vail'd by curtain of a foe, Or frightment, but fully resolved to be Revenged of th'quarrell, and his Majesty. Yer. Our glorious purpose, like the sparkling star, Gives light in dark, when leaden Saturn stands Nigh on his side, whose pale-fac'd tanyed state Makes splendor rise of th'star above the rest, When all the mists and watrish vapours of The middle Region cannot withstand him; But like a Diamond among pebble stones, Cast bighter blaze above the rest, then them; So we proceed, excell the others hope. Faf. Liberty stands bound, when with the crafty Whistle, or second sound of their advanced Pinnions, dives to the burroughs of a Childish fear, we will afford upon their Terrestiall plains, such unheard language, That shall not by graduation, but at first Seize on their clownish brains, and endue Our native Land unto posterity, With victorious praise. Buza. Right, Fafrisius, The cælestiall Quiers runs counter for to Gain us trophies by their help; for the Globe Which was the Antipodes Land, is now ours By fortunes onely guiding, by womens Innocent looks, strives with her force and will To have all good for us, and nothing ill. Nev. Your speeches are fully poys'd, no venture done, No good is had, we'l strike an oblick cross Unto their Land, if't be for no cause else, But for our Countries good, as for our King; That all the Penates with divine sound, Blesse all the Cities, Towns, and Castles of our Land, With most tranquillous times, Linraides Spreads Fields with Flora's Vesprey, and that Sol May have perpetuall motion in the Ram, Though hot and chollerick, yet a handsome Spring, which shall bestow on this the Title Of a fruitfull soyl. Abe. Your souls are generous To the last— Yer. And doth hope for to endure. Aber. As long as blood doth warm the heart. Faf. We will not flinch our ground. Aber. Your valour's stout, Much like a Trojan blade. Buz. Or Irish Moor, Who never stept from him that gain'd Ground. Aber. Then you will fight? Nev. VVe will my Leige. Aber. Then let valour range her course, go see what Ships are rig'd, and Gallies fit for sayl, That in two hours space or lesse, we may Bestride the Sea, with the whole Navy of Our Army, ten thousand Ships well prepared, To bear within concaves of their vast Great bellies, both men and Ammunition, Shot, under the conduct of Hollarro Prince, Twelve thousand horse, and forty thousand foot, Bearing the colours of a golden Ball Set in a large black field, with chevern of Three Mullits ore; next him, you Yernomoy, Bring up a wing of thirty thousand foot, Furnish'd with pike and sword, musket and bandalere And all displayed, with Griffins rampant on Their shield; so you Fafrisius follow next With nine thousand horse, well saddled, bearing A Rose upon their Armes, beset in Arg. Buzaraine, with your Captains and the rest, As Nevermo, stand you a distance from the rest, VVith nine thousand both of foot and horse, To aid these Lords, if that need require. VVhat subject you take, bring home unto my Queen, These are all your precepts. Omnes. Heavens bless Aberden King, and prosper his success. Exeunt. Scen. 7. Chorus , Song 1. 1. Acteon was not wise, Diana him espies, And caused him to be by Dogs tore. Because he did her see Naked with modesty, And grac'd him with two horns before. 2. Hellen she was most fair, Paris thought none compare Unto her well shap'd soul and face; She did at length destroy That famous City Troy, And caus'd both famine and disgrace, 3. Demonica that Queen, VVho for lucre and gain Betraid Ephesus with a wile Unto Brennus that man, VVhich afterwards became His sole distruction and exile. 4. And Atalanta, she Did chaste Peleus see, Would not give way unto her will, She falsely did accuse, And basely did abuse Him, to Acasius of ill. [Chorus.] Song 2. You see by these four examples, how women they do fail, In any matter that mantles, the good in ill prevail: They seek with sweet sugard words, And all things that pleasure affords, for to destroy their onely joy, be they tar Knights or Lords: Then fie upon this world, that such a thing should be. Then let us leave those silly brats, that do perdition bring, And discourse of more serious that's belonging Aberden: He draws his stout Captains on, And his potent Army long, against his foe, which he doth know to be of the same throng: Then fie upon this world, that such a thing should be.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Act 3. Scen. 1. Celerinus, Burgargo, Orestes, Sisterus, Derisius, Gervoron, Burnomoy, Souldiers, Ensign, Drums, Flagge. Cel. Their first arrival on Numenia's Land, They purchased it by a Legion of Their sacrificed lives. Aberdens men Were new beginners in those stratagems, Their Armour was no friend, but plai'd a foe, To their well nigh and half sweltred bodies: Our trenches work by wisdom, not by force, While we like Trojans stood and maz'd their folly. Come brave souls, lets meet them in the front. Bur. Let them strike anchor in our barren forts, While there no controversie riseth on ground, For their determed wills to make a choyce, Whether Sea or Land afford their execution; Though Æolus confirm with Neptunes Blustering noyse on the azure gliding Seas, Which hoysteth to th'memory a panick fear; Yet those shall stand in no similitude To our own Land-contrivings: chear then up, Your Numenia bloods, we'l put them to't Great King Celerinus, will you please to lead, Lets ralley them before they gather head. [They march and goe out. Aberden, Hollarro, Yernomoy, Fafrisius, Buzarain, Nevermo, Quermero, Perpurgerus, Ensigns, Drums, a march, Souldiers. Aber. March, march, let swift and sure set feet strike off Sloath her entreaties, the metamorphious forms Of their strange Land, shall lend to none of our Determi'd thoughts such a prodigious sense, As make a quick flown fury rise, as Choller in the veins created by burnt Adust blood, but with a milder grace, Send comfort to our hope with new supplies. The soaring Eagle ne'r prided more To play with air, or stand upon her wing, In the defiance of the lesser birds, Then I do in my potent Souldiers strength. Let them strike lance with dexterous art, My care shall ever be imployed to gain The field, her triumphs, by Bruzantia's hands; Lets detard time no longer. Hol. My Leige, your will, Though putrid bodies by corrupted stench, Breeds impure Atoms, infects pure air; Yet those most innocent souls must not go To the Elizium of eternall rest, Without reveuge do follow. [They march and goe out. A great shouting and hollowing, and the Battel within, Aberden, et cœt. Aber. What, still multiplies surround their courses? They rise like Ants from muddy mole hills, Surely want ne'r shew'd her face within the bounds Of this new prodigall Ile: men like the Putrifaction of a loathsome forme, breed Like the Atoms, the Sun his rayes, and Ne'r diminish, though voyce with bloody notes Send thousands to their far-sought homes, They lye with arms spread open to receive Their unnatural mothers, like Vipers to their dams; Yet Terrour strikes no sense to their benummed wills, But a carriage of presumptuous Law, Of free dom, licence, of their free born right, They like a Fury more than modest Grace, Spend wind and limbs a sacrifice to us: We fear nor courage, nor their valour; no, Their sights are not the weapons of our lust VVe have to fight; come, come, march on. Holl. We will, For ne'r shall that strange sound take place VVithin receptacles of a hearing, That Bruzantia's men lost ground; come march VVith me, my Lords. Yer. VVe follow your command. Exeunt. Celeriuns, &amp;.c. Cele. The service was hot, yet fear not you, Though ground doth thirst with her insatiate Will, to drink up more conjeal'd coagulated blood Of our lost soules and Souldiers, receiving A surfeit by its strange and faulty virtue, We have enough to stand a field, and face. Burg. Lets draw the scattered forces to a head, Bring ranks in order, and each his Ensign place, Not lose the day with folly in our hand. Burn. My stomack n'er did faint with killing till This day, my arm bids not desist, though Reason would plead for it, my sword cryes Vengeance still, each blow it gave brings rosey Blood its hue, from those strange hags, Bruzantia's Men, sending their woefull cryes to the skies, To frame a thunder. Cele. Valour runs with thy great will, from hence Lead thou the blew male-frocks to the field, Thy manhood shews thy grace, thy fame this day Won first its root, the next the branches they Thou wilt obtain, on which the Trophies hang Of those lost men, of which they made a mang; Let us see them once more, come follow me. Exeunt. Scen. 2. Quermero enters with two Swords, and all in Armour. Que. They force me to't; well surely, I shall be Prepar'd for the cause, this sword shall curb These will, and this maintain its right, A Cæsar, nay a Cæsar ne'r was So valiant as my two swords are, one cuts The flesh, the other hews the bone, my helmet Shews a force to kill a Guy, or Hercules, My Armour binds my body to the same; I wish a fortune would give more advice To him that falls in hand, then run his life; Suppose this Pillar were great Bevis stout, And I a Hector, as I am, stand to [He cuts the Pillar. Oppose the feind, my first progress it should Strike him under th'ear, the next take him here: Oh, oh, have at the man, have at thee; Nay this is nought, when Drums and Trumpets sound A fame unto my valour, I should be More like a Generall then a common man. I am sure as fancy pleaseth, now I could Put ten to flight, if all were Trojans stout, I should redresse my selfe with Tygars strength, And make them fear my swords. Burgargo enters, and Quermero throwes away his swords, and runs into a corner. Bur. The pillage of the soyl is left for him, Who bears the victory of these two land broyls, At present doth an opportunity shew forth, The way to steer thy course; forbear, I'le not As long as heat infuse my livelihood, To cast a backward look to those before Lie gasping on the ground, I will exchange My broken sword for two, which are like clifts For them to gaze at; and keep them under The thraledom of a fear; but I'le pursue The chase to find my prey. [Exit Burgar, and Querm. runs and gets up the broken swords Quer. What, art thou gone? 'tis well Thou scapedst so, he knew I was here, Or if he had not, I would have made him fear To take my swords, and leave a stump for me; Oh I wish he were now present, for now My chollar riseth, I would shew him such A twisting combate, as know a friend from foe. I am a Lion now, he's but a Lamb, I'le tear him, tear him, tear him; what, a Broken piece, he left unto my lot: Come, come, again, and let me flesh my Appetite, and kill thee for a name. Perpurgerus with a bloody sword. Quer. Come, come, Perpurgerus. Per. What, stand you still? rouse leaden spirits from Thy earthly soul. Que. This broken sword hath caused the absence of The bravest Hector: this sword and hand caus'd it; I made him run, I, run. Per. Some childish boy. Que. He was a Man, whose shoulders were like Mountains; a foot, a Pasty peel would Equall with its birth, his eyes strike dead the Heartiest man that goes, all armour furnished, Yet forc't to run. Per. How did he bear the blows? Qu. How did I bear the blows? like Vulcans anvill; For as he struck, my rebounding sense Answered him again; he stood like Nicodemus, or a fool, while I stood Breaking my sword upon his nose, He snuft, and said nought, else, but run. Per. You are stout. Quer. I ne'r knew my heart until this day, Now I perceive the rigor of its will. Hollarro enters with his sword drawn and bloody. Hol. The stygian lakes recoyl, Hero and Leander Maketh cold, their loves are froken to an Ice, Proserpina doth rule with fiery look, Pan now doth make a sword, a shepheards crook; Diana chaste, begins to fly for fear, Cynthia doth mask her face till the next year; Endymion waken is by these loud cryes, Nymphs they do court their Garlands miseries; Ceres doth lavish forth her full ripe ears, Venus complains her selfe with watrish fears; Juno is lumpish, and her love is gone, Pallas turn'd foolish, and she wit hath none; Mars rules full out with his most severe look, Themis stands potent with her justice book, Nemesis is troubled from the funded deep, Morpheus is waken from his creeping sleep; Apollo stands smiling at their folly so, Jove bids me fight, and know my friend from foe. Per. More aid shall come, I'l fetch them out my self. Exit Per. Qu. Great Prince, my valour riffe beyond its bounds, All for your Fathers right. Holl. Now let Burgargo come, my weapon's fixt To play its part, pierce tender bowel with Its three form'd point, and make his blood Still wait upon his shooes. Scen. 3. Burgargo following the flight. Bur. Stand stil your ground, the day breaks from the Skies, for to discern the foe, my hands are over loaded by the spoyls of this days labour, While some lie gasping, others crying loud, Here leggs, there arms, all bodies mortified, My spirit thirsts to see the Prince Hollarro, And to change Gloves with him, try valour at The point of naked nimble swords. Oh Goddesse blind, thou fortune hath inforc'd, To shew my progress of my lingering dayes In this brave soul, so stand prepare to fight. Hol. Your worthy carriage shews as much, nay more After the encounter of our steelly blades, Let after victory either rise or fall; And let Astrea poyse the truest cause By this the combate of our martial will, So General come on; stand, see your selfe. Bur. Your valour's to be prais'd he that dare Twist his hand with me, must have a grace More then such young years can put forth; I praise thy courage, but not thy discretion, Because thou runs upon thy death. [They fight, and he wounds Hollarro. Hol. Desist your purpose, so, till I close my wound, The blood speaks on my cause, a fury leads My temper now, stand still and pause, and then I will renew the second blow. Bur. Vain purpose of your will, to strive with him Who alwayes return'd with victory in his hands, You cherish folly in a strange conceit, strive with a weaker hand for to oppose A decreed sense which is much stronger; Yet shall it not be utter'd with a voyce I kill'd thee unawares, but take thy time. Holl. Rest upon your blade, ground its point, The time runs in swift motion to one Of our ends, the Elizium field doth open Large her panting soul, for to disgorge The vicious humour of our Fabricke, Within that space, the which we shall possesse, Rewards stand ushering in our power, To have the Crown allotted by those Saints; Come lend your force again, I now prepare For to receive my death by your unnaturall Hand. Bur. Fortune support then both our hands, Valour with-drawes unskilful helps, And shews a fair prospect to a foul design. [They fight, and he gives Burgargo a deadly wound. Burg. Hold, hold, I dye, take you the day, And Crown your self with Trophies of my blood, Your riper years sprung in a blossome stout, Shall be Encomium to Bruzantia; My spirit it doth vanish, as my blood Flowes from the veins, sending by legate cause All praise to your most severe stoutest arm. [sighs. Oh, my breath is prov'd an airy substance now, I wish it were confin'd a longer space To run its course, that I my King may shew, The man gave me this wound, him to exalt Above the rest by Title, degree and honour. [sighs. Oh, now the fading hour-glass consumes its sand, Each corn a drop of blood, and the three fates Come with their hungry appetite to cut My fatall end, and blood doth bubble by The hottest combate that us two did fight: [sighs. Oh, I must I must, the bones begin to be Afraid of flesh, the sinews stand at difference, All my body cold, save onely heart, doth Leap by its extremity of pains, and Hot with sorrow; [staggers. I come, I come, make room Amongst you, ghosts, see there be place for Me, [Falls down, and dies. I dye. Hol. Thou dyes then like a man, whose breath did bear The whole Numenia's Land in a subjection, The onely pillar of thy Countries good, Death hath surpris'd the conquest of thy soul, And this thy trickling blood that's here display'd, Doth shew thy progeny to take its flight From Brutus, or other greater Monarch, My spirit's sorry for such a thrice noble friend. Derisius enters. Holl. Return, return, thou runs upon thy death. Deris. Draw in that sulphurous breath: I live! and Here my Generall he lies slain; no, no, [Fight, Deris. falls and dyes. Hol. Die slave, as thou hast been ordained. [Exit Hol. Quer. turns the bodies over and over, to see whether they be dead or no. Quer. Robin dead, dead? Jack, dead, dead? are you Or no?—faith if you be not I'le make you, [He drawes his Sword. I'le panch you, Rogues, and make you know What I am,—what not [Deris. shakes his legge, and Quer. runs away, but after draws nigh again. Dead still, but stir you, hang You, hang you I'le have one of you sure Enough; come away, come away come—come— He trayles Deris. off the Stage, by his head. Scen. 4. Yernomoy. Yer. Fight, fight, the day's our own, Squeeze forth thy spleen with a censorious frown, And turn my serious blows into a wrack of gall, Deliver'd to my sight, ten thousand men Were slain, and like an Abyssus did the earth, Inclose all in a lump, converting so Their oakey chaists into a putrid form, And these my Robes, a badge receives from those, Of honour, pomp, and glory to the day. I follow them my selfe, so the compunction Of their boyling blood did then rebate My former stormes into most pleasant calms. Stand, stand, thou slave. [Burnomoy enters. Bur. I fear no Rebell, such an one as thee, [They fight, he kills Yerno. Consume thy selfe to ashes, and there lie: My Generall Burgargo, what, thou kill'd; What mortall motion propagated it? This cannot be withstood, but hymns must sound, And Elegies complain thy dolefull fall; The Firmament crack with a thunder, and The stars want light at this thy funerall; A marble shall inclose thy sacred soul, But cause its nature weeps, and may be term'd for thee. Exit Bur. and carries out Burg. Aberden, Hollarro, Fafrisius, Buzarain, Nevermo, Orestes, Sisterus, taken captives and bound, Perpurgerus, Quermero, Souldiers, Flag, Ensigns, Drums, a retreat. Aber. We contemn liberty, and honour with the same, By a most sottish will, and by idlenesse, Their ranks dispers'd, doth inflame fear with it; The blew pavillions in which comfort liv'd, Are routed by the heavens stormy blasts; His Forts demolished, and his Army broke Into a hundred squadrons, not able To do a damage to our potent strength, His Subjects hear our captives and his chiefs Of all the Souldiers slain, shot, powder, by Them vanished, all Bulworks they consum'd. The best politick way that must come here, Is to destroy both branch and root of them; And that Hollarro be the Captain of This new Dominion, so shall dame Peace Still flourish with her train. Holl. Your purpose is confirm'd by me, and that United to your onely selfe. My wound Doth fester, and begins to rave beyond A fury of its hot inclining, visiting me, Thus with torn tossed discord. Faf. The Heavens shews a face to prosper our Successe, the Sea is calm with gliding streams; The wind doth shut a favour with its blasts, And th'skie looks clear with serene splendent hieu, All by invasion strive to do us good, Then suffer all our Navy to the coast, And spring Bruzantia's Land, carry the Captives to the Queen of love, Adrinemia. Buza. A conspiration works with harmlesse will. The air displayes her friendship to the cause, The Element of water joyns her force, To suffer all a shipwrack, if not now We take this opportunity the Turrets Of our hope consume with fear, after invasion Of an obstinate and a perverse sense; So let us go to that our native soyl, The Captains stand and tremble at that word. Nev. Nature her Empire will at last give way, The limits are unclos'd in which she moves, A fainted courage can never withdraw Such a design, if knowledge be against: So most great Sovereign of your sacred will, Draw down the Forces to the River side, Because the day is vanish'd, and their force: Aber. Then, stout Hollarro, draw your whole Army down, Clear all the Camps, and set the bondmen free, Fear lest the Pleyades with its constellation Drop stormy weather, and a season foul; For now the Equinoctiall line doth poyze The day and night both into equall parts And no dysasterous foyl doth work such fate, As make a wisdom rise aginst our hate. Hol. Father, you King of great Bruzantia, Conquer'd Celerinus of Numenia. I needs must visit you with good for ill, If such a thing were forc't against my will. The noyse of fame, and nimble swift-flown hope Gives freedom pardon for to use her scope; You need not bid, but command him that stands Submissive in the way of your commands. I will conduct the Army, hoyst the sayls To where you please, in him it never fails. Aber. Confirm thy resolution. Quer. Hunger, hunger, preythee Perpurgerus Give me some victualls, my teeth begin to gnash. Per. Here, take all. [He gives him some scraps. Quer. Oh reward thee, its ready cut to my hand. (Exeunt. Scen. 5. Celerinus, Gervoron, Burnomoy. Cel. Burgargo's gone, and all my Lords taken Captives; when Titan, obscur'd within his Orb, The verdant fields receives a Gown of dew, But when my Generall lies in Elizium, Then floods of sorrow spends their store, And do prolong it by a cunduit art, And stew the whole soyl in salt, brackish tears. The wind doth shew its force as by a fury, So doth the ebbing Sea abound with gall; One strikes alarum with a thundring voyce In the air; the other like a Lion, Roars forth her spleen under the Globe, All to the celebration of the soul Of great Burgargo, my onely Generall, Without a transformation of a sudden change. They'l rage their bounds too far beyond their power, And if no calm strike overthwart their Lawes, Such a strange tossed tempest brings a ruine To the terrestiall Ball, and so with their Raging motion strike a fire, as Cyclops Throws his Thunder-bolts, bring a consumption To the substance of't all for Burgargo. Ger. The two-wing Pegasus doth stand ready To shew the fame about the world; her motion Is swift, but he is swift as she, Cutting the air, and parting grosser forms To view the lacrimy of such a friend, Soaring the Climates, prauncing by the stars, Viewing the lower, middle, higher of The three Regions, before he comes to th'Moon; So passing all till he comes to that light Of Jupiter and Falcifer at one sight; All for the praise of him who striv'd with hope To gain the Land from damage, losse and foyl: The holy Saints doth clamour with a sound, Welcome Burgargo to our possest ground, Take the Trophies of Martius Campus field, Who ne're did turn to Enemies or yield, Sit with a Coronet of a golden twist Upon thy head, to be the Prince of all th'rest, All make submissive forms, a solemn bow; All stand affraid, and make to him a vow, To be their King, for they did ne're injoy Such an Heroick soul as that same boy; Yet more's our loss, and pitty for the same, Parting both with his body, and his name, Because, of his blood no posterity follows. Burg. The valorous of all souls return with joy, The Cassiopeia and Ursa major crave, A fame of that same honour to the grave; They run by Tropicks of the frigid Zones, Leaving the carkass as the firmer bones; All stars lament by constellation, His down-thrown fame by a rebellion; They tear their Robes, casting about their sloufs, Nothing is left but print of their foul hoofs; The pale reflects of Cynthia's crystall front, Springing in the vaulty heaven there a font, To glide with restless streams a hilding bless Of gravities, and parts, from the work and mess Of best proportioned honour, pulling to The gifts of praise to whom they all do owe; They all presage unto a dreamy Throne Of their best wisdome, what he doth intomb, As honour, valour, and sobriety, Meekness and patience, with celerity, They found an Empire of all thoughts in him; They found the sweet of joyes fill'd to the brim, Within the structure of that sacred soul, In shew no shadow, but in selfe the moul Of onely valour, brave man-hood, with the same On which they'l fix an everlasting name. Cel. You have no envy in a rationall way, Lets make a happy Buriall to the deep, It greets the cause, prolong no future speed, Since he dyed valorous, let a valorous Grave receive his soul: Bur. Confirm the same with A Page of consort to the Muses, and Make a following pomp, expresse his worth. Exeunt. Scen. 6. Adrinemia, Murgorus, and Nercius. Adr. Resolve no resolution, for the cause Thou understands prevents no remedy In my sole knowledge, thou gives there no aid, To a prevention of a future danger; Wisdome cryes help, to call a resolution In th'hand of Labell, of a reall deed, With a commission of an issue true, Of shreud and pensive to a quick return. Charybdis or great Sylla threaten death To their swift navy, or the mount Ætna Hath burnt their top sayls, or cast down their masts, Turning their rudder to another coast, While time affords an ornament to deck My sensuall mind with shapes of horror, fear, And love, doth now dismember the defence I had, whereby I conduct my prov'd skill, They captives are, no captives they receiv'd, For else my King would have blaz'd his troops home He promis'd the company whom he took, No company here is sent, Murgorus, Tell the cause, the Court is black for want of Sparkling Lords, to give a lustre to its Marble walls. Mur. Most high Princess, Things by the counsell of vain sorrow's will, Doth sojourn with the cause, the whirlwinds Apt to make a tempest rise, bellowing the Waves till their whole mountains soar aloft, And by the craggy clifts whose obscure edge Strikes with a desperate blow to swift winde ships, May cause detard, and make sloath to ascend Her private and her with-drawing chamber, Of your censuring soul, and cause the twinckling of an eye, A minute more or lesse, to shew in length A number of long years, but suffer not Such Rivalls to exhale such innatural Fumes, bring a megrim to the vitall Spirits, and perplexity to the Brain. Nerc. The informer of the day-light struck a knell, The twelve a clock, against his sounding bell; When then by course the ships did promise fight, They arrive our coast before the next night; But now by fortune bond to favour gold, That hour is gone, and they still in the flood, And Sol like nimble passenger surrounds The hills again, discending to the downs, And yet no Herald doth blaze forth no fame, None strikes Love's onsets, or her words proclaim, It must be some strange tempest that drives back Their ships from shore, when they all things did lack: Adr. Why it's a ransome, for a Kings disdain, For his own Queen, not to her send a line, If storms did bind the ships within the harbours; Yet quick flown message might come to my ear, But ne're since the voyage took its game Upon the restlesse Seas; I heard by Post They stay their living, or confin'd their dead. Mur. I feel a pain, like Cerberus fasting jawes, And Tantalus his gaping with desire To gain the Apples, are not to compare To these the torments that doth drench my soul, All bring an ocean of a foul dispair, Because they stay beyond the bounds of time, And cause a lingring motion to answer For their detard. Exeunt. Scen. 7. Celerinus, Gervoron, Burnomoy: the Funerall of Burgargo passeth over the Stage, with his Scutcheon, Armour, Heralds, with Flags, Torches, and Mourners. Cel. Let earth kiss th'corps with sorrow, and rest you! Could potent strength, or magnanimous deeds, Bidding defiance to envy, spite and force; Solemn confirm'd to Jove in haughty sky, Or vertues Off-spring or the Nymphs of th'maine, Save this same mortallman from being slain; Then fortune had conquer'd death, and thy soul Still liv'd with us: but we may curse the fates With more hatred vows, and not lament thy Rape so to dispair, because Mars honour'd so Thy Royall valour, dying like a Champion: The scraggy fleshless bone; man, durst not bring, Or put to sight, a sheet to wind thee in, Had not first glory, a rich Garland hold, To crown thy merits, fram'd of brandish gold, The Country laments thy fall, and thy King too, My subjects to thy Herse doth make a bow, Giving the praise and honour of the day, Lauding thy name, and crowning thee with bay; But now the Cypress must take place for it. Elegies Song. Hector was famous for War, Achilles did excel him far; Scipio was valiant stout, Hanibal put him to rout; Ulysses knew to handle Lance, Ajax did above advance; Turnus fought well at a field, Æneas him forc't to yield; Priamus had kingly power, Agamemnon him brought lower; Hercules did valiant acts, Alexander did great facts; Paris was a valiant soul, Burgargo doth these controul; Hector was no man to him, Achilles knew nothing in; Then fall in pieces thou earth, Weep thy selfe into a dearth; Scipio he was not stout, Hannibal knew nothing to't; Then let us all mourn atune, To this soul that is here slewn; Ulysses held not a sword, Ajax he knew not a word; Then lament this down-throw fall, That is hapn'd to us all; Turnus may be termed foul, Æneas knew not his soul; Then break forth into a maine, Shower tears as if 'twere rain; Priamus had no hand in war, Agamemnon knew no jar; Then send rumour to the skie, And make thick clouds with our cry: Hercules was child in shew, Alexander ne're like knew; Then we'l mourn our selves to death 'Cause he is bereav'd of breath; Paris he was not a man, Burgargo did all with stand; Then we'l make both hills and dales Know the losse of all us males. Cel. The faculty of penetrating grief, Surrounds the brave Idea of all joy; The sable dressings of her mournfull dayes. Draws a curtain betwixt our eye and mirth, The body of Burgargo must be interr'd, And valiant deeds dies with that soul; For Julius Cæsar when he conquer'd Troy, Ne're knew such deeds as he doth here imploy, All are not worth a nomination to His rare atchievements. Bur. Let all their barbarous words bring hail with them Inviting Æolus, to make a tempest roar; Yet those we would whistle by as a jear, For all that, Burgargo's gone. Cel. Thy soul doth crush all pomp in infamy, Let not rage spend the courage of your hearts, You are, my Lords, my onely Lords I have, The Scythian Wolves ne'r war'd amongst the flocks, As your two valours did amongst your foes. My other Lords are took for sacrifice, To that hellish Queen Adrinemia; Yet we will grapple for the reason of't, When Lawes are settl'd, and the havock quell'd, Prolong your journey to the silent grave, For triumph of the Corps and Funerall; And let all Poets use their brains and pens In praise of him and pomp of buriall. Bur. My Leige, your will's fulfill'd. Exeunt. Scen. 8. Bellerro, Lerinica, Histerica. Bel. Are you not yet perswaded to combine? Ler. No, nor never. Bell. How Vulters in a cogitatious shape, Know my inflamed heart, masqing dismall Prodigies, let eccho answer contrary, Sound a retreat, cherish the trope of hope, Strike dum that sense, that is protractor Of those airy notions that again-sayes all, Answer once more, let passion move the favour, Dispatch the case, and mercy take a place, Shall birth rebound, I will and can: speak, speak. Ler. No no, great Duke, I cannot. Bell. That sound strikes dumb my soul, The Lilly, Rose, stands in battalia form, Acting their decent hieus 'gainst your frowardness, The Dazie carries lance to shew the savagenesse; Vesper and Hesper doth by aspect shew Their influence to fling still against you; Mounts and Dales make shirmish against other, Because you suffer such a Rose to smoother, Confounding nature, and deceiving earth, Killing both matter, and both air and breath. Ler. None of these strange Toads may make such need, And frame a darling of a vain dispair, I will not wrong both nature and the soyl With foggy mists of vicious quality As not to marry, but that vapoured slime Shall turn the voluptuous humour to A siccid substance, and not rowling forth That radical moisture to be soon exhald; I'le marry, but not yet. Bell. The winding comets, by confession brings An antidote, to acute feavours sharp; But you my Comet, and my blazing star, Turns me a Pagan, and speaks death thereto. The cask wherein the camp of graces lay, Is turn'd a den of groaning mischief loud; I cannot live, if th'loadstone of your will Change a virtue stupid to the Iron. Cupid may bend his shaft, his arrows loose, But ne'r hit so fair a mark as this, Venture a whole quiver to the Sea and Land, But rebound venom to such lips as thine; Marry, marry, for the present time Excells both past and future though divine. Hist. Sir, she is the master-piece of all Arts, A whirly-gigg of glittering stones, The Sun is clouded, and the stars want light, When she by her airy motion enters. See, speak again, she's like a purple die, Neither loose colour, nor her face thereby. Bell. The flowry shade devoutly kneeling to Brave Titans rays, with a compendium Of servitude, that by obedience, Both Woods and Fens receive a party shade, And Groves stand shivering with the drops of cold, Because offensive to his glorious head; But I stand like a Willow, more then Oak, Unto the shrine of your beatitude, Expecting licence when I may presume To violate the wind with a salute Of your bright palm, not daring crave a beam Of favour from your looks. Ler. The question of a danger, waits a doom, Meeting with death or life at Senate house; Therefore I'le enter with a reskue none, I hate no look from a Hermaphrodite, A man in shew, but woman in the speech, Therefore desist; no favour from my hands, No, none. Bell. The inraged foe, both pride and avarice, Aims at the Capitoll of poverty; And Phrygian plains, who, bound with Chariotteers, Is form'd a channell uselesse, out of date. Voluntary hearts oft ransackt bodies Of a lively-hood, and royall freedom Grant such a small request. Ler. The night derides the day, sure otherwise Such instances should not offer to rise, But more or lesse, none from me. Hist. Alas poor man. Bell. Oh object of dispair! But most sweet Madam, please to let me wait, The shadow comforts me when't wants the bait. Ler. The fester'd thoughts of your vain restless wil, Mocks but your habite, and with fancy fill. Bell. The servile tribute that I owe to you, Bindeth my glory for to waite you know. Ler. The Apple mollifies the heart that sees Its lusture, but not my soul if't please. Bell. Tis, 'tis your goddess-like soul that sweeps away The gloomy night, and brings with it bright day; Come then we'l go. Hist. I'le wait your purpos'd will. Exeunt. Scen. 9. Chorus Song 1. 1. Weep forth Phrygian Swans, Phrygian Swans weep forth To see so far (but cruel) A creature on the earth. Who is beyond all nature, Or pencill art can make; Weep forth, weep forth, So fair, but obstinate. 2. Heavens send a smile Prospering the successe, To gain so fair a substance Within her selfe a blesse; VVho is belov'd of all souls, Yet makes their bodies quake; Weep forth, weep forth, So fair, but obstinate, 3. She's a morning star, Lighting mens hearts; But when they see that object, She wounds them with loves darts; Yet they are so intangled, That they'l die for her sake: Weep forth, weep forth, So fair, but obstinate. [Chorus.] Song 2. 1. Let quick-foot nimble Doe Surround the valleys all, And make a pleasant consort, As they each other call, For peace doth bind them to it; Aberden got the day, Both Bucks and Does may play their fills, There's none will again-say. 2. He rides in great triumph, With subjects waiting on, And with his most cursed Queen, Without Rebellion. Celerinus forc'd to turn His Majesty to yield And glad that he escaped so To give Aberden field. 3. Their valours play their part, Æneas and Turnus great, Did neither of them manage Their Army so comple at: But when the foul smoaky clouds, That they with Gun-shot made, Was vanisht, and was turn'd serene, Aberden he best plaid:</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Act 4. Scen. 1. Aberden, Hollarro, Fafrisius, Buzarain, Nevermo, Orestes, Sisterus. Aber. Welcome once more unto Bruzantia's Land, My Lords, we lost not one but Yernomoy, Without discredit of the sword, or pelts, The flashes of their thunder-roaring Canons, Bred but a night not overcame the fight. They fainted as their sword aimd at our heads; Saying dame nature forgot the Deities; Fortune was turn'd a fool, they car'd not for't, When their rag'd Army was torn by discord, No Empire took their will, time chid their folly, Because they did dismember counsell skill; Experience hang a Flag to shew the woe That would pursue the evicted Army. Amazed all stood at distance, intending To give a shout and fly; but grief mounting Upon the soaring wings of utter'd speech; Did stop and cease both anger and the cry, Conspiring then again to win the Ile, Which was turn'd frustrate to the purpose, and We took the Lord, the which my Queen shall have In grateful sense. Holl. Your Princely grace, and sacred Majesty, May dazle the lustre of a glorious fire Foundation of mildnesse strives against the stream, If it seek a revenge within the gates, Or flowry bank of your resigned will; Mercy the sister of a peacefull time, Sav'd millions from the sparks and darts of death, Which by the worthy motions of your will Was carried on, or otherwise sharp and Keen swords had made no standard there, But sent pale death as Captain of the Fort. Faf. The Darts strove in the air, even then to chuse Whether to fall or fly; their feeblenesse Did so surprise their force; yet valiant you, My sacred Leige, stuck to the glittering Arms, Holding both sword and shaft to work a sign Of manhood, courage, degree and title; And passing fenced foords, to captivate These Lords we have, they trembl' within The Ring of fear, knowing no side Where passage makes escape; the Swan did Sing not half so many notes, as hollowing cryes And bloody screeks did make a harmony; Well, 'tis fortune, not the fates did work this Bold attempt. Aber. You speak still like your selves, which Lords And Princes are: what say you captives? Orest. Our soul and bodies are desolate of peace, Yet let your Queen and men be filld with wrath, We'l choose no spoiled gain, but truth to Celerinus. Sist. Yea, King, its so; though we be captives now, Time changes, and in them our manner doo; Though furies tear my body, yet my soul Shall stand for Celerinus, King of all Numenia; and your Queen's wrath are Pearls To us, because we dye not guilty. Aber. My lov's no worse to you, since truth rebounds With hope, you shall have hence my favour. Orest. No favour we crave. Sist. We desire no favour. Ner. The ancient freedom that we did possesse, Strikes a perpetuall fame unto your name, A full ripe plumed bird should be the guide And messenger to over-fly the world, And mount up to the skies, to let them know, Your excellency. Faf. 'Tis, 'tis most true. Aber. The day grows on, my Queen expects me now, The harmless will of her known genius, Flames in a lake of longing sighs for me, Proceed and be the buckets to quench it; But since the day consumes, I'le send for her, My Lord Nevermo, conduct the Queen to presence. Nev. My Liege, I go. Exit Nevermo. Aber. Come Captives, here must be your doom, She'l have your lives if you were twenty more, But yet my favour goes with you. Orest. I thank your Majesty. Sist. Great King, all glory wait on you; But I am conduc'd by willingnesse to dye. Orest. So I am, since I am an exile. Aber. You are, stay, here's the Queen. Scen. 2. Adrenimia, Nevermo, Attendants. Adr. Aberden, welcome to your Kingdom, and your Queen; Loe, I see Celerinus subjects bound, And for my use, which gives a resolution To my sense, if your own Queen by tractive Operation, work effect, to dismisse From contemplation of your soul, all Opportunities that doth bring dispair, You shall find no stratagem that to be Irrevocable, and the objects of Foul melancholly, shall not afford the Idols of vain puffing fears. For those are they that doth commit, and doth Drop unto eternity great contrarieties Unto your majesty, and place of Prince, The service of a sadfull humour, Works undiscreetly, and changing certain things, It's alwayes proved; the Chaos testifies You a great Warriour, both in Waves and Land, Whose pectorall force (expected) did prevail: No losse of War or Arms, if nature stood To oppose the slaughter of so many lost; But I'le sacrifice my wishes to your selfe, Gladly received my King. Aber. Your patient favour receives a great applause; And I your King expect no future joy; My Queen, your receivance is most gratefull, And bids adieu all sadnesse, but not contemplation, Which shews a firm judge of a prime design; Safety pleads leasure, and shew fair shape To commonalty, not a vain flasse-glass, Of best contriving virtues, To effect the Gardian (not a bad excuse) Of their firm liberty, the Gems of all The Indians strikes no lustre to your Fame; you are not fair, but virtue follows it: My Queen, the Captives stand at your command. Adr. My Leige, your favour. Holl. Duty doth force obedience to my knees, [Kneels. Great Queen, your sacred will if 't please to grant A blessing to Hollarro, a wounded subject To serve the Queen; your will? Adr. Rise, valiant Prince, my bless go to thy years, To find Aberdens blood in thy young youth. Holl. You may term void of sense unto my state, But hope survives the spirits, 'cause I bring A pardon firm and just, 'tis my duty. Aber. Hollarro, rise, your duty binds no further; But what I know. Holl. Your will, great Queen. Faf. It were a sacriledge, and that rashly Committed against your Princess goodnesse, Not to offer my selfe a Souldier to your will. Buz. Mine follows by a triple form, great Queen, Your subject salutes you with a happy Bliss. Nev. I stand a safeguard to your goodnesse. Adr. Faithfully done, here wants brave Yernomoy. Aber. Forgive the fact that's done, not rob'd your will, He's slain, to pay devotion to your looks; Rude was his fancy, but senselesse was his guide, Allowing no recovery to his kindled fame: He dy'd a Hector, a Prince; nay more, he slew Millions of Forces to ransom then his death; He left the world by Burnomoy's stout arm, But Burgargo, Hollarro, sleep did charm, For to describe true valour in fancy fair, In reall substance to deserve the chair: The Goddess of all hope favour'd his deeds, The Goddess of all might helpt him in needs; The Goddess of all right stood true to him, The Goddess of all happ did valour bring: The Gods and Goddesses struck union to His well fast blade, his stiffe fram'd bow of Yew. So brave Hollarro shall be onely name Through all Numenia, there to carry fame. Adr. Hollarro still thy atchievements soar above The mean capacity of a Queens recompence: These are the captives, I like them well, their Heads are large to be a pinnacle of fame; They're mine, great King. Aber. They are for recompence Of your deserts. Adr. You render pure substance of a divine will, By outward shew, no excuse they expect, But dye a sacrifice, for to restore The jewel of my fainting liberty: The Hatchet's well prepar'd to execute The case, the block perceives its finish'd, not In gaud, but martiall way, to make the Harmony, My attendants expecting the prosperous Sight of that same day, by forming new Altitudes, erecting large Houses for the Same: I'le make no great dispute, but finish it. Holl. Great Queen, the subjects I avouch by true Affect and powerfull law, descend of noble Blood. Adr. Well, they are no worse, but better for my use. Cap. Ah las, we must then dye. Adr. I, I; see who attends us there. Scen. 4. Quermero. Quer. I am here, I am here. Aberd. Well, what art thou? Que. A Gentleman of quality, as good as your self. Aber. Why, I am a King. Quer. Well, so am I, sause-box. Aber. My Lords, conduct the knave to prison, and Prepare a lash to execute its office. Quer. Oh las, you will; I'le try your force: [They carry Quer. out, and he struggles mightily with them. How, how—how—let go your hold. Aber. The slaves and bondmen, which have wrought a Councell, to digg the works of War, as the Pioneers do raggifie the walls: And they who use to toyl in labyrinth, And founders of their folly, are prisoners To your pick-axe; Hospitalls doth crave my Aid, and Eunuchs make a market for My home return; so force pleading my will, I leave you with my Serpents and my foes, As emblems to my valour and my state, Use discretion as time doth interview, And appoint a season to your sport; For I must dismiss your rank. Ex. Aberd. Adr. My King, a happy repose unto your soul; Who attends there? Bellerrio, Lerenica, Histerica, and attendants. Adr. The passage of a drowsie pomp withdrew A door of breathing betwixt the ark of store, Of hidden vowes, shewing the pride of fortune In a chance, ravishing the beauty of a Monsters hide, and stuck a stage of desire, To harbour the fancy of a dreadfull sign, To spill the blood of captives; Lerenica, You'l screek and vanish with the dame of fear; But I'le repulse that guide that titles it, So bring the captives to the slaugher-house. I'le shift such Robes fit for such enterprise. Exit Adre. Holl. Madam, I'le improve my reverend service, To see the same fulfill'd. Ler. The soveraign balm for fear, must be a heart Void of a sensuall cause; but I'le attend To see the genius of all mortall souls, Wear the sad Cypress of a gloomy day. Bell. Lerenica, your servant, will wait your time. Orest. Spare us, and let us speak before we dye. Holl. Give them time to breathe their last farewell. Orest. The stroke's a Basilick, the fight doth kill, Confirms a death by venom of its raze; Perfidious creature, more degenerate Fate. Steeping his aspects in foul Lethe's streams: So Adrenimia by her cursed hand. But fury bids defiance to those guiles, My time doth shew by prospect now full old, Tossing my senses by grim horror's waves; So noble Prince confirm to future time, And to posterity I dye a Man, A prop of th'Country, the Numenia: So by a swifter motion life surviews The dregs of mortalls to the prime of things: My appetite is fresht by gizard of a cause, To view the spirits of transcendent Kings, Great Jove, who weighs the ponder of this ball, Make creatures Angels in Numenia's Land, To stand the stratagems of forrain foes; Brazen their souls to yield to no deceits; (Oh, death makes my senses fly) And dare Aberden rule great Celerinus? Suffer the primum mobile to rest, Which rules the sphere according to their Orbs, Consume the highest Region, and drive down The splendent lights, but at length I must die; Desist thy talk, thy Candle waxeth dim, And onely such is left to see death grim. Sist. The smoaky mists bids light adieu, with her Obscure cloak; then suffer a dolefull sound To eccho my spirits with an Ebian cry: These chaines sayes, Mirth depart. So decent are These new found novelties unto my soul! So hymns of Elegies please a parting close, Rack I must suffer for my King and Land. Well, 'tis my duty, my breath's bound thereto, Onely a faculty's left to close a hymn, to Spend all its bounds to eternize your fame, Inform, some Goddess, where I shall begin To make a prayer according to the time: Brave valiant soul, Burgargo, I'le relate, Because thy death, my pain doth propagate, Thy sacred shrine directed, journey sweet In leaving us, bids mine go to and sleep; The griefs doth punish, consume the fountain Of my weak vitall spirits, and the main, A frustrous case bids anger play her part, And aim at nothing but my wounded heart; My life is trouble, but my death gives ease, So Jaylemen, Keepers, take us when you please. Attend. We are ready in our office. Holl. Procure them to the Queen her grace, I'le stay a season, but I'l follow straight. [Exeunt omnnes præter, Hollarro, Bellerrio, and Lerenica, and Histerica; and while Beller, and Lerenica discourse, Hollarro walketh on one side of the Stage viewing Lerenica. Scen. 4. Bellerrio, Lerenica, Histerica, Hollarro. Bell. Madam, It is a vain trifle of a small dispair, I bring to presence, and not tediousness, The businesse concerns much your safe-guard, Grant it, and then I will relate. Ler. 'Twere colours of a melanchollious sight, For to convert the gesture to the sense; And meaning of the close, your generous thoughts Must speak to Ladies, not covert with a smile. Bell. The night spends forth her dews, beguils her hours With strange adventures of a darksome truth, So I diluted in the practice of, In courting Ladies to their own content, Shall crave a place of watchman to your selfe, In the foul progress of a dangerous time. Ler. Contempt, despise, and onely disdain grows In my own breast against a cowards soul, If that report doth bring a news unto My audience, not valour flowes from veins Of your Microcosm; I should deride The case unto your face, so plead not that, I'le shift for one, take you no care for me. Bell. Oh obstinate! Holl. Heavens bless the wisdom of my genius now. [Aside. What State or Generall drew that velvet screene Of painting troubles 'twixt my eye and heart? Lerenica, what's that name Lerenica? Sure 'tis no Taper of a fiery blaze: She pierceth the rights, and joyneth union. Could my stiffe arm withstand Numenia, And not the glances of a womans eye? The Realm produceth no such knots of fear: I see her basis, and her vertex too, Surround the Camp of her delicious soul, Yet stand a loof, not undertake the cause, Because discreetest deeds bid me forbear. The various forms that heart and spirit moves, Were cause enough to make one lunatick: She enters souls, not cares for mortall shews, And makes my tongue tremble 'cause I report it; Well, 'tis thy garb and gesture wins the soul Of Prince Hollarro to a nuptiall song; My breath must have no passage, if dis-joyn'd From the bright rayes of such a mool-sun's light; Bellerrio shall know, 'twas Hollarro laid The same design (I love Lerenica) I long to see the wells and springs of fire Still kindled more; so I'le go to my sire, And make his Majestie acquainted with't. Exit Hollarro. Hist. A heap of vermine dispatch a famine To a common-wealth, and ill-disposed manners, So you dispair unto a Ladies will. Bell. Hold your tongue, you are troubled with Histerical fits, Time which reacheth forwards by its means, Falls under question of a sole denyall: Muse no more, but let discretion answer Unto the cause; the bud is sprung, and fruit Must have its time to come unto maturity; But too long kept, grows putrid in it selfe: Trenches and shelves are horrid stratagems, Unto the ships tost on the ruder waves, But time dilate them to their confusion, Making no Caves but solid earth of them. Mark then that Gentleman, which is rough before, But bald behind, and there no hold to get. Lere. The revenue of a Maidens life, Is the whole Wardrope of all mirth and joy; But when combin'd unto a fouler Mass, Provision of all strife and vain discord, Venturing the plundering of such nature gifts, Were sacriledge beyond the end of hope; Therefore desist a truder to bereive The same which never nature doth restore, Mine's kept for better spirits than your selfe. Bell. Those words are like a Parthian, flying kills, And raise a mutiny of furies in my brain; Forbear that contemplating case, Homer Had ne're blasted fair Helen's fame so far, But knew the disposition of that shrine, Would equalize her attributed parts: Prefer no more those sparing words, but quench The concealed fire of affection; Shall I imbrace, grant, help my mind? Lere. Great Duke, you take a spangled action of No man, to court the meeting of two Opposites, secresie requires advantage of a sight, But you erre grosse, losing honour by it, Because you force, rather then perswade. Bel. Madam, 'tis my desire must bring excuse, Because it's parts are invisible to the eye, Then a short return shall not impoverish My honour: I must, because in love. Lere. Vouchsafe no further to prolong your talk, For it is tedious, and the time requires Our absence now; Histerica, make a Fire in my Bed-chamber. Hist. 'Tis done, Madam. Bell. Since yet dejected, still I'le beg the place, To be your servant for an hours space. Exeunt. Scen. 5. Aberden, Hollarro. Aber. Dismiss that faculty. Holl. Forbear, I cannot My Leige. Aber. Oh strange, that pale Eos should feed the Tweed, Shouting such murdering cryes unto th'Altar, (Steeping its sound in poyson of a rage) Of all victorious souls, your own fame Strives at a higher glory, then one fair, It is a painted hieu that Ladies use, To put fine art before true plain Nature, Though you feel a pain, 'tis onely love, A foggy wrath ascends, when bright Sol mounts Swift Pyrosus; play no more upon faire, Let worth surmount the Towers of its foul mask, That influence cannot strike such unheard blows, As make your soul fly to dispair for help. Holl. Oh Lerenica, Lerenica, thou, thou. [beats his breast. Aber. Of future joy the Monarchs of the world Will sprinkle the notes of such a vain design; Phæbus will make the heavenly Diamonds Strike rays to shew the folly of your will; She is not worth a glimmering spark of stone, Much lesse your Princely Bed; Hollarro, chuse One that is deserving, and my will shall Not be against. Holl. The Tartarian Prince is gone to forrain soyls With other strange Hecatombs of all men; The Captain of my soul must follow them, If your Princely grace deny my full request; Could I sound sweeter then the Delian Dames, When the tall Cedars by my force did fall, Having more fame then the Ephesian Towers: At that same instant, by the stately steps Of manhood, valour; and not this requests 'Tis true, she's fair, her virtues second it, Which is the pinnacle of ambition I aim at, For means are dregs of th'earth, her person shews Her parts, Princes must have their liking; Not combind to objects of honour. Aber. The Audacious pines do not stand without fear, Nor doth your valour without trying it, Therefore that blind and senselesse Boy must take His bow, leave you his Arrows to supply his place, The madding waves of love, strives against stream Of reason, bringing contempt and disgrace To noble spirits, their smiles are smoothly Carried to delude the Olive-branch of hope; Therefore take one that is of noble blood, And follow discretion as your will doth guide Your disposition. Holl. The sayls of hope is turn'd to leaden plumbs, Because you plead still for a worthier one, Though it might be said, 'tis my fortune so, To mix with flashes of both fear and hope: Yet when my restelsse Navy comes to shore, That same coaste must give my sentence then, So as I sayl by rudder of sweet love; I hope the Magistrate of your affection Will give a glad mittimus to my soul; For if contrariety plead at the bar, Having its tryall to win over-throw. That deadly sentence must close up my breath, And make me fear neither Heaven, Sea, nor wind, Therefore deny and kill; Oh, oh— [Sighs. Aber. Strange to a common sense: reason then with Your selfe, she is a woman nought but flesh And bone, and a meer gall of bitternesse; You know your Mother well, her savagenesse, To brew her hands in teppid blood of foes, And you thus stand in a disposition Contrary to her heart; I wounder at That unnaturall sympathy, but e're You dispair, make choyce and venture there, Where sense doth guide your fancy, but for All, she is too low your birth. Enter Quermero in chains, naked from the shoulders upwards, and Jalors after him. Quer. Oh my back, oh my belly, oh my sides. Jayl. 1. Oh your breech, sirra, come away. Quer. Oh prethee spare me, give me time to breathe. That I may have wind to cry withall, oh, oh, oh. Jayl. 2. Ha, ha, ha, what, do you feel it then, You must not be so bold. Qu. What, as to cry; I will cry, if the King were here. Jayl. 3. But you shall not cry long. Quer. Oh bless thee, bless thee, shall I not cry long? Nay then I'l bid the gentle whip, come, come. Exe. Quer. &amp; Jayl. Holl. The civill pleasures that a dewy shower Doth gratifie the earth withall, cannot Be express'd; so your reply trebles my joy. Aber. Float no more with Deities of fear, But take the Empire of all hope and force; Grief leads no more vain anger as a sign Of wrath, and ill-disposed manners; haste To the Rock of mirth, make splinters fly To be attendants on your Majesty. Thou hast been valiant, no report shall go, Thou art dismayed by a woman foe; Pursue your course, as you have then begun. Holl. I will my Leige, long live your Majesty. Exeunt. Scen. 6. Adrenimia, Fafrisius, Buzarain, each of them bearing a mans head, and Nevermo following with a Hatchet. Adre. The siege of Thebes, and Ulysses Acts, Ne'r betraid fancy with so sweet a fight; The Heads doth gape, but cherisheth no amber breath; Oh las it is a pitty that no sooner had Hold them up, let's see the glory of the same, The night will betray my mirth, before my eyes Be satisfied, the Banquet and Musick That I took therein, brought recreation To my vitall sense, besides no equalls, Or raptures promis'd by a future joy, Could bring reward to what I here have seen; The Artillery of all hope was waggon'd up, Betwixt their heads and shoulders, that's their necks, My soul cannot by publick, or secrecy, Be sufficient Actor to King Aberden, In duty, or in praise, for this same fact. Unbolt the Prison Gates, set them open, And let the numerous slaves be glad to see Such great Triumphs, and their selves set full free, And mysteries explain'd, by Gods of Temples all, Because such prosperous jubilee fell out, I recruit my selfe to see those signs. Faf. The progeny of humanity challenge title in't, Because you shew like the Bithinians, The copulating troops doth entertain, Of fame and valour, your most bright Queens health, The heads doth shew your praise, and doth prepare A sacrifice unto your sacred shrine, With amorous gesture of a lowly look, Not like Amazons, but a Persians smile, The naturall rights within a Jewels hieu, Doth shew the perfect vertues of its selfe; So all your sex may with a comely brow, Seeing your deservements by wisdoms deeds, Turn thanks as bodies of a further fame. Buz. Discover Engins to subdue the hill Of all renowning praise, that when obtain'd, May be a ransome to your Empress; The ancient Romans had ne'r reflection Of so great happinesse, by any Pope, As we obtain by your Soveraignty, To keep all Lawes and customes in their forms, Not suffering them to be wrong violated, Making decent pavillions of sobriety, To be the Magistrates and Rocks of right, The streets rebound (as Alexander came) With redoubling voyces of your worth and fame, Adr. When Sols bright rayes shines through the curtain Of an Eastern fogge, then Animals rejoyce; So do I by your conjuring words, As if I had obtain'd the Phœnix nest, Which is a fountain of all sweet incense. Records and Chronicles to posterity, Let them challenge memory of the same, The brook wherein the Nymphs correct their garbs, Let shew the splendor of this brave design, As orient matter of a minerall, Strikes beauties pride through the dark of night, The deed's Syren, cause it wins the hearts Of all my subjects, unto Elizium. Ner. I am executor bearing the Axe That brought content and pleasure to a Queen; The Mayors and Senates of Bruzantia, Stood Officers to th'act and instruments Thereto; we live like Elephants, disturb'd By none, bearing the Castle of liberty On our shouldiers, and Wars thrown down, Living by Counsell of tranquillious time, While our foes heads do obeysance to th'Queen, Making a dance in a triangle, Avoiding the tortures of a moments fear, I'le bear the Axe of hope. Adr. Lets muse no more, seeing the deeds of worth, The streets themselves its praise will warble forth. Faf. The tempters of all justice, lastly throwes At greatest strength, when others potent shews. Buz. Love's guard bids yield; when honesty doth play Her questions and occasions for the day. Nev. Joyn art to arms, as honour bids us do, And make their heads and bodies lowly bow. Adr. And for this prize, let go the prisons then, Draw up Purcullises and set free men. Nev. 'Tis done, great Queen, as your generous soul, Is pleas'd to have, for it doth all controle, Faf. Then Quermero must go among the rest, Which of all others he will think him blest. Adr. See all do go, my joy doth countervail All former faults, be they e're or or frail. Buz. Clap hands for joy, because the Queen such things Doth propagate, and delightfull tydings. Omnes, Long live the Queen in health. Adr. Wheel off the plain, and purchase more fame Then Ixion does by turning wheel in flame, Fetch captives more, till th'Land it selfe doth yield No martiall soul to bear, or sword or shield Bring all Numenia's brood unto my hand; I know your strength none of them can withstand, So I you leave to see the tombs of those That dead do lie, and prisoners to unloose. Exeunt. Scen. 7. Hollarro. Lerenica. Holl. Love speaks as bold, as any Druids preach; Because its darts strike at the hope of fates, The champion of all eyes checks bashful thoughts, Fearing to enter the bar'd Gates of love, The standards of a lofty foundation, Gives freedom to the lesser pinnacles; So I by examples, get benefit To make a fair progress in affections, And as an interposition of th'Moon Betwixt our eyes and Sun, causeth eclipse; So fainting doubts with-draws a screen mantle Betwixt dispair and hope: But, fair Madam, If you I yield to be a Princess, I am The man will make you. Lere. Most noble Prince, The place is too honorable for my birth, And your bright grace flowes by dame virtues spring Of valour; you might command, not wooe a Humble soul, the Zodiack wherein your Lamp of goodnesse keeps its motion round, Like Cynthia's silver streams, is too radiant For on me to gaze; your honour deserves A Princess rightly born, for manners, tongue, Not a poor Peasant from a broken Ile; A Dido should make answer for my part, I am inferiour. Holl. The spirits of a double breast leads Van In love's Empire, no gulph doth back them to't. So unknown beauty of a judged look, Oft force affection to keep triumph there. Your beauty shews beyond a Prince his favour, Discretion guids the manners of your soul: You plead too poor, then moves the honour that, You shall sit crown'd with canopy of fame, To be a Prince his spouse: I venture soul More free then Scipio, Marius, or Sylla did, To maintain the troop of your crystall beams, My lance shal drop at your foot which monsters tame, And be a servant at your wills command, Yield and have the same. Lere. Great Prince, your will Hath vigour to with-draw the proudest soul; You'l knock at Pluto's Gate sore Pegasus, Yet feare no death by incense of their breath; Your brave Heroick mind dare face great Brute, Make Giants toyes, and not know where their's scope; And when you dance upon uneven waves, The Eolian blades, stand trembling with your fear, And Tritons sound your fame, to please the sense; Why, it is strange that you doth these repose, And not a womans shews of mean descent; I wish my blood were higher for to joyn In equall manner with your Princes right: But read some Poet, and you'l then agree I am too low. Holl. Oh, Poets are men compos'd of species four, [Enter Beller, and walks about on one side. They'l praise both virtue and vice all in an hour: 'Twas not Medeas words, but Ovids quill, That Hippolytus most chaste of will; For if that acute Ovid likewise would, Medea had been as chaste as e're he could; And 'twas brave Virgil made Æneas fame, Soar above action of brave Turnus name; But if that famous Virgil pleas'd to be, Turnus had been as great, nay more then he; So 'twas not Helens looks, but Homers mind, That made Paris his soul to her combind: For he as well could own her nature so, That where she's fair, she should be black as crow; Dispute no more of Poets, but give leave My hands for to imbrace, else you deceive Me of my life. Lere. Your words imbrew the altar of my will, And you may force where you have us'd your skill, The Phœbus of your mind hath grace full bright, My irksome caves, and my more irksome night, The influence that's shewn by its bright rays. Turns days to nights, and nights into clear days: Therefore my duty is, to not oppose Your Princely grace, but make choyce where it shews, But still I am too low. Holl. Most nobly receiv'd, We'l make a happy Nuptiall to the day, And th'King and Queen shall grace bright Hymens play. Lere. I am submissive. Holl. Come my joyfull Bride. It is not long till I lye by thy side. [Exeunt Hollar. &amp; Lere. Bell. Thou blazen Taper that surmountst my skill, Taken my Mistress mace of all my joy, Shall not live happy by the victor got, I'le work thy ruine by some budding plot; I'le go to Celerinus, make my plea, And joyn him once by love to cross the Sea. That he may cross my foe, Hollarro stout, Put King Aberden and the Queen to rout; And thee Hollarro, which by that design, He vanquish'd one, at last thou wilt be mine: Fair Lerenica, but cruell to shew Thy love to me, and to Hollarro owe The right and title of it; but that fact Shall ruin'd be, before he once doth act. I'le be a Traytor once to King and Land, And Prince and Queen, because my love withstand, Fetch him over the restless seas, the stars Will prosper my success, because the Wars Began first in our Land. Why tarry I To lose the day? both King Queen, Prince, shall fly. Scen. 8. Chorus. Song 1. 1. Let sweet face'd Hymens nuptiall songs Fill all, both hearts and years, With grace to quell the mournful day That brings in jealous fears. 2. And no compendium of state Drop envy to the hour, That Bride and Bridegroom spend their time, As in a pleasant bower. 3. Strange factious doing in the Land, Brings not a slavery Unto the Magistrates of it, By foul conspiracy. 4. Isis flowry banks shews not fair To that joyfull couple, Nor Mulmutius half so stout When his Sons did grapple. 5. Then let the leader of all hope Hollow triumphant fame, And let bright Sol beraze the day Of such a nuptiall train. [Chorus.] Song 2. 1. Still am I forc'd to fly, And be a traytor to my King, Because her obstinacy Doth force a horrid combating, Lerenica Doth bear the sway Of all this troubled distract, Causeth ruine And undoing, oh most unseeming act. 2. Celerinus shall inclose, And know vermillion from white, With his Bruzantia's foes, And frame a field, them for to fight, Make a battle Which will rattle. Sending thousands by the fact Unto their home, And their dark tombe, oh most unseeming act, Wayliday, wayliday, wayliday, wayliday.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Act 5. Scen. 1. Aberden, Adrenimia. Aber. The north and south both Poles do not contain The very thoughts of this our great Lands joyes, A Conqueror by popular grace; I raign with reverent voyce among my flock, Revenge will not spring up by angers dew, Or shew its muddy face by foul conspiracy; Fortune is prosperous, spurning gods of Love To dress our Land with crown of Trophies, Gold, Repulsing Legions of Furies that spend Their breathing hours nought but to wrack and ruin: All Lands implore my aid, drooping their head, Till hope doth blow the fire of better days, Sharp empty titles they make fame of them, While we with hostile voyce crack Thunder-bolts; And 'twas Hollarro's valour stated it, Which is a captive to fond Cupids bolt, Planting female Cannons charg'd with love, Whose shot is fear, and powder jealousy, Turning this Land to the Antipodes. Lerenica hath a stronger arm then he, And by her sweet-fac'd plots, which Tyrants turn, Hath the pledges of his Princely brow; But at the length he loves her so entire, That he hath promis'd union to her shrine, And marry her. Adr. 'Tis pride, not fortune sure, that nature leads, His years are too young to hide such vowes; That glorious rays will vanish with the Sun, Striking a seeming passage of dispair, And waken the papavered sense of his brain, Which by an opiate virtue is made dull, And will revive desire of extasie; But if that balm, that soveraign balm of love, Hath so impregnated by a silent look, The bed of all his joy, and heart of fire, Them to unjoyn, shall not be my desire; Let Myriads of prayers, and countries love sound all Large Hymns of mirth unto their nuptiall; And let all acute Poets seek their store, To give the Bride a gift beyond all o're; Let mirth and triumph then so joyn together, That there's no difference 'twixt fair or foul weather. Aber. The trembling silence of your dreadful vote, Hath turn'd his title to another sense, The extream load which virtuous valour bear By loves punnyard, is an abyss of pain; But your reply gives a supporter to That heavy heart, which is by th'load opprest, Out of the stage where honour plays her Scenes. I know he'l call reward unto your name; His duty binds such sonly grace to me, That Reason says he will not forget thee. Adr. The Syrian flames quench the damp of spirits, So honour'd terms brings conclusion to good will; I know the dainty Souldiers of such troops, Fear not the fight of ashes of mens Tombs, The constellation of his nature good, Doth bring a recompence beyond that form: There is no royall looks, or face of fame, Be more in gratitude then his own selfe, I wish the presence of his Princely plumes, Would over-fly the Court into this place, That peace might shew my pitty to consent, To the bright day triumph of his Bride, I give my free consent. Aber. His presence is Expected, heavens starry light doth shew By their true rays, the substance not far off; For time doth sacrifice unto the dame Of patience, the flower of its first prime, Because our mind stayes leasure of his will, Untill it please be present in our sight, The dismall looks of th'progress that he goes, Debars the splendency of his bright beam, Or otherwise he would have seen the Queen (Your selfe) my joy, with his blessed spouse; But stay, he comes with her. Hollarro, Lerenica. Adr. Is this her? Aber. Yes, this is she; welcome Hollarro. Adr. The civill war of all the world, bends knee Unto your judgement and excellency, And so I hope this Lady gives the Bayes Unto your Crown, I wish long happy days. Hol. Great Queen, the weaknesse of my youth did bend My fancy to a sensual carelesse end, Because no knowledge seem'd to admit its trust Unto your sacred wisdom which is just; But let a fickle fancy with weak mind, Crave pardon for my folly there inclin'd. Ler. And I, most Princely Queen, which Mother be To my poor soul, I thank on bended knee, Because you grant the same. Adr. Rise hopefull childe, Then King Aberden give the day its fill Of merriment unto a Princess will. Aber. I will, blest Queen, Hollarro take the Bride, And to the Church be thou a swift sure guide. Where all the Gods of th'Land stand in a form Of servitude, as they were all forlorn; But haste to th'Bishop that combines the knot, I'le stay at Palace for a future plot. Exeunt. Scen. 2. Bellerrio, Celerinus. Cel. 'Tis strange news you bring. Bell. But 'tis far truer. Cel. How can a hazzard of such war, imploy Any intention of undertaking? We pay a tribute to them of pure gold, And sacrifice our lives for recompence, And th'highest force of all my potent souls, Is a common Souldier; Burgargo gone! And 'tis a small Nation of its strength, to stand In revenge of th'looks of Bruzantia, I will not for a world be their combatant. Bell. Oh how can you upon Hæmus of fear, Rest so securely with subjection; Let Zephyrus gales move quicker in the ear, Inform the sense how Tyranny doth rule: I'le undertake with damage of my life, To bring your Army in by port Braveron, Amongst Bruzantia's Lords, and King and Queen, Before you tread a furlong on that ground: [kneels. Let hopes survive the spirits of a King, I beg it on my knees; you may perswade Your selfe, that I am here no Harpalus, But a true Athenian to your Majesty; Shall my request return with joy? Cele. A Monarch's will is not designed of, Without the counsell of his subjects votes; Therefore no sayls of joy must carry on Your wandring Pinnace, till the sight of them: The Olive branch doth cluster with her fruit, In the plain soyl of our inhabitance: Therefore to reflex on a gloomy shade Of fear and anger were discretion. Bell. Pitty such angry days that invent it, As not to admit of a private end, No forrain aid can help them, for their Land Is grown infectious by the fatnesse of't; Therefore surround their Camp, your victory Is sure enough, which fertility will make Your Land as prosperous as the Aegean Ile, Which is nam'd Delos, where then there was born Apollo and Diana, God and Goddess; Then let not peace, like an innocent lambe, Rule in the Theam, but a rampant Lion, Rousing from den of fury and ruine, Shall I you ingage great, King? Celer. Not my selfe, Unlesse my subjects by degrees would grow In love with Diamonds and a Pearl her grace; The massie waight of gold shall ne'r draw By North Pole virtue my mind to that Land, But here's my Lords, Lets hear their votes. Gervoron, Burnomoy. Cel. The man of generous brood Bruzantia, Affords utno the province Numenia, Is here imploring by a wooing cheeke, As th'Moon doth th'Earth in the Antipodes, That we may ceize a Lares, or Silvaines great, On their fatigated limbs in plenty: Yea, he will undertake to lead from coast, Our squadrons to the Court Bruzantia. Bur. No happier skie doth shew a light by blaze, Of planetary influence or rays, Then those same lines, if vigour be with them; I'le follow th'motion to carp twig from th'stem. Ger. The same I'le follow, and as a darling, Cherish; attired in such scarlet Robes; Will you maintain the deed? Bell. I will, Captain, Blaze your Troops unto the river side, Let no delay strike in with tarriance; For now their Land is Garden of the West, Fill'd to the bounds with aromatick fruit, An Ocean lake of dainties there's in hid; Therefore the time runs by dame fortunes will; Put off no longer, but hoyse sales to it. Cele. No more, no more, my Lord; can Pigmies stand Against Bellonia's threats? lets slide the main, And all our Gallies lanch into the Ocean, And make those azo ar parallels upon Its gliding surface, give a happy voyage. Bur. Nereus, and all the gods do pardon not Our wrong that's done, be pleas'd to view the bounds Of thousands well joyn'd ships ready for sayl, Ten thousand men at my command, all proof, Burning with desire of War, dappled Nags For to supply those Alexander souls. Ger. No more let frozen thoughts take place within Our naturall forms, as to be love-sick with An idle disposition: I know bright Sol Will favour us, by being in Cancer, a Waterish sign, proceed as preparation Doth give leave. Bell. Oh blest Numenia's souls, Make no dispute, time doth grow further on. Cele. Gervoron lead up the blew mayle frocks, And you Burnomoy be my Generall, Aberden shall see what force guides our hand, Once more commend our selves unto the seas, Make no delay. Bur. None great King, they are ready, All utensells for the voyage so we go. [Bell. with hope, with hope. Exeunt Scen. 3. Aberden, Adrenimia, Hollarro, Lerenica, Fafrisius, Buzarain, Nevermo. Aber. Now all Bruzantia's rights connfirms the day And Lacedemonan customes of the boy Hyacinthus bids meriment to th'same: Let shepheards write this nuptiall wedding day In red Capitall Letters for a Holiday, Joy to Hollarro, and the Bride his spouse. Adr. Hymens sits crown'd with Garlands of all joy, To welcome train of marriage, Ladies beds, Sprinkled in form of solace, and of mirth, And the Pyrene mounts drop offerings to Such sacred meetings as this day affords, Long live you both in health and happily. Holl. Great King, the duty of a weak desire Comes short in limits of a recompence; Let humble will, with intention, her aid, Strike thanks so worthy as you do deserve, Most virtuous Queen, the law doth guide my sense, If that I taste once of ingratitude, (A stranger plant then ever Glaucus eate) To turn my selfe into a main of fear, And counted their a God not for to live, But by a fained will, so thanks to you For gracing Nuptialls of my wedlock hour. Lere. The mind that treads in natures paths, must say With the guest of most free deliverance, All thanks to King and Queen. Aber. Then Prince Hollarro, now the knot is done, It shall not be said by Bruzantians, I like Amyens, caus'd your banishment; But all their tribute's quitted by this day, And thou shalt be the King of fruitfull place, And issue of my hope of all the Land; Acknowledge Prince of the Cecilian soules; And like great Butes, have a Champion race; How like you it, my Lords? Faf. You are a sire of all firm judgement, Brutus divides not the least Atome from't, Where the way your credit takes its course, Is argument enough for me to yield. Buz. The succour of the Gods descends from Jove, So all our lives and Pedigree of us. Hath conduits of all plenty, good and great, From the protection of your mighty hand; Therefore if I deny, no pardon's there, But grim unjustice must devide the spoyl, Give me the worst, and shame thereunto boot; So let both Nature, Nation, and all friends, Give vote as free, as my soul doth unclose, Or wish to have the fame Hollarro King. Nev. Great King, your will is good, I like the same. Hoping he'l prove a Lapithenian soul, A second Phlegias; your motion's good, And lik'd of all, here is the Bardes presents The Groom and Bride a song. Enter three Brades, and sings to the Musick. 1. Great Sol was dim By a pearly dew, But now doth fling Off that muddy hieu, By the sweet motions of such smiles, The Bride and Bridegroom time beguiles; Then let both heaven, earth, and sea, Four Elements, whats e're they be, Give happy joy, and mirth for ay, To those brave guests of this same day, For ever, for ever, let all sing Hymns to the Queen, and her brave King. 2. A joyfull day, But more joyfull night, Lead on the way To that same delight; And when its past a happy morn, To th'Groom that is by his Bride born, And so we wish to after rest To th'Bride, that is by Bridegroom prest: So let all joy wait leisure on, To pleasure them in splendent morn; For ever, for ever, &amp;c. Aber. The Diadem Hollarro is stayed, Of all Bruzantia on your noble head: Numenia's Land is struck with fear and quakes, Under the blow of such a martiall soul. After the drowsie pomp of nuptiall terms, You shall begin your Raign. Holl. The massy weight of such a grave design Would act its part far better with your selfe, But since a freedom breathes such spicie notes Of father's love, my duty must give way. For Celius, the father of immortall Gods, Ne're did indue his Sons with greater joy: Cacus he was not in least politick, To lose his Trophies by a Hercules: Strength shall not subdue wit, if it hath play, I'le rule the Land, and I will you obay. Aber. Thou shalt, brave Prince: the Temple's clad with joy, To receive your sacred presence, and also Honours most stately camp doth obeysance To your heroick shrine: be thou the King. Omnes. Heavens bless his Majesty. Lere. My breast's an altar to the sacrifice Of loves due rights, unto my loyal King. Holl. Thou art a Queen, and my onely spouse, Both King and Queen, Lord blesse your Majesties. Scen. 4. A great noyse within of landing! and afterwards, they cry, (Kill all, kill all, &amp;c.) and by and by, enters Celerinus, Bellerrio, Gervoron, Burnomoy, Souldiers, Ensigns, and Drums, Flourish. Aber. What is the news within? Heavens bless me! What is't? Adr. I wish all things were right, then see, My Lords. Nev. A foul invasion, we are betraid, Celerinus comes. Cele. I, and die you shall; [Fight. Fall on brave souls, let's ruine root and branch, Like the Hybernian blades, sound a loud, Lead up the fronts; strike, strike. Faf. Oh Traytor, traytor. Bell. Die, die, thou slave. Celer. Wound not the Queen: let her pains rest, to be A future punishment. Aber. Oh I die, I die, thou vain destroyer Of mens lives. [Here all Aberdens side, with himself, is kill'd, save onely Adrenimia, who is chain'd, and carried out; and Hollarro, who defends himselfe, and escapes, and takes Lerenica with him. Cel. Conduct the Queen to prison, The day's our own, with the Supreams of th'Land. Bur. We will, great Leige, let's follow out the chaise. Exeunt, march. Quermero with a dish full of furmity. Quer. Oh me, stay, what's here to do? what, a sleep? or tumbling; Pox take't, you'l break your brains with it, and I My belly with plum pottage; rise for shame: What, is here the slave that imprison'd me; A bard, a burd, or a turd, tell; what, art thou Dead, alive, or drunk; rise, and stand, [Takes the Kings Cloak, and puts it on wrong side outwards. Thou haste a velvet Cloak I'le see how it fits me, Hey, it becomes my Princely person right. I look like some grave Minister or Divine, A black blew velvet, and scarlet gippo; See, my foot stands like some reverend Bishop, And my back-side like a Prince behind; These pottage, pottage, trouble, when I King; But stay, they'l do me courtesie at time, I'le put them up; hold up velvet Jacket; [Puts the Pottage in his pocket. Oh these are warm still from the heart to th'breast; But for all my jesting, what do you mean To go to dinner or no? I'le promise Here's good furmity for the same, Come go? What, you are mad sure: but if you be, I'le right your senses straight to its same form: [He kicks them. Oh how their guts cry Pease and Bacon hot: [Nevermo pisseth. I'l break the Pitcher and let the juyce out, As hot as my pottage; stay, where are they? Ho, in my pocket, in my pocket, Scen. 5. Enter Burnomoy. Bur. What art thou? and for whom? Quer. A turn-coat, and for my selfe. Bur. Dye then thou slave. [Falls as if he were dead, &amp; while he lies, eats up his pottage. Que. I with all my heart. Bur. Once righteous cause, shews face against its foe, And Northern scourge brings yoak of Scipio's fear; My hands imbrew'd in warlike Champions, All save Hollarro the Bruzantian soul; A Brennus, or Nenius of fame [Quer. I sleep sound for all that: swallow's Custard and pelts of vill a's. Whose shallowed concaves, compels in valour All mushrums of fear (save onely he) Trampled by beast of forrest, and of plains, I shall be Lord or King by the conquest. [Enter Hollar. Holl. Nay, that thou shalt not, stand then like a man, [Fights. Bur. falls &amp; dyes, An equall bond is now shar'd by my blade: The Cyprian Queen like chaste Diana, Of all my hope, waits leisure of a time; I'le not stay from her, but requite my self. Exit Hollar. Que. Oh, oh, I have got the wind chollick by Lying on my belly, the pease and Broath Doth run such Barly-breaks within my maw, That if the back-door hold not, I shall leak; Hold Punniard and Sword. I dare not stir, Fear lest I send my broath then parboyl'd out: Ill ventur'd, my breeches is clean; up, up, [He riseth. I go as if I had a Frenchman in my Boots; But now I'm forc'd to turn, I shall be kill'd, Or else fouly bestride. [lies down again. Celerinus, Gervoron, Bellerro, Souldiers, Drum, Ensign. Cel. The wrath of Nero is not yet appeas'd, We are like Nevervian souls, stout to a spoyle, Though Law and Nature be our enemies, Yet we will raine the Hyperborean pole, And make our Land like shepherd Hyræus hoste, A place for to receive none but the Gods: But after Gradivus hath then clattered thus, Let's make a buriall to the Elizium field, So Souldier take up the bodies of the dead, Carry them as Trayors to their long sought home. [Quer. Then they'l let me alone, for I am not dead. Ger. See you perform your office, the King commands. Soul. We will, great King, and noble Generall. Ger. Lo here is slain brave Burnomoy, the blade Who deserves pomp, as much as Burgargo had. Cel. That time and this is not now poys'd alike, The War conveys a change of Sea and Land, Therefore he must be buried 'mong the rest, So then confirm your place. [Exeunt omnes præter Souldiers, Sould. 1. Come, lets make a hole, and put them all in. Quer. Oh, what must I do then? faith I'le dye with them, For I shall be kill'd if I stir. Sould. 2. Let's take the plunder of the field first; Oh here's a good suit, I'le have this, none else. Sould. 3. What, here's one fellow warm, I believe he Is alive still; [He kicks Quer. to see whether he be alive or no and Quer. answerth nothing, but makes a face. But if he be quick, he shall be put in the grave first. [Exeunt, and carrie out the dead bodies. Scen. 5. Hollarro, Lerenica Holl. The time runs round by hidden motion, I was a King, but now more desperate; And you my Queen, but fortune frown'd thereon. I wish that Halia could have then opprest, Her Father Nereus with a glad design, To drown their ships in Cynthia's merciless realm, Before they footed this Bruzantia: Fair Lerenica, I must fly for fear, To adore the sorrows of an exiles place; I'le leave my Princely Robes, and dress my bones According to the custome of a Pilgrims form; And beat the banks which Neptunes waves have tost To hunt my death, because I loathe the same; And at my last farewell, I'le use no art, Let sighs, tears, kisses, bid loath to depart. Lere. Those drops of blood doth stain my maiden face, Because my sole Artemon must fly hence, Sure Jove will strive to make the Ganymedes, For the Hesperidon Dragon cannot stand The force of such a Hercules: let hope, Where's e're you tread your Princely guard, then guide Your hood-winck actions in unknown places. I willing am to stay, to make a prayer, When you depart you'l kill my life, that thing. The Swan's near death, when she begins to sing. Holl. Oh Damsel of my breath, let not such debt Lie on the fabrick of Hollarro, Though I have Diomedes fame, I'm loath To prove Domitianus to thy soul; Heaven and Earth will not forgive the fact, No sacrifice nor kneeling pay the act; The starry bowers would send a loathsome smell To strangle death in the prime of my days; Besides the edge of furious war would bring A State to begge reliefe for thy great woe; What, I be Demopheon to Phillis? To cause untimely death? far from Hollarro, Aid requires no help; I'le carry you Along with me, to make the Indian foes Grow stiffe with fear, because they see the Sun Eclips'd by your bright brow; then go with me. Ler. Display your self no more in inward love, My heart and tongue cannot express my mind; I'le dwell within the Land, Bruzantia's walls, As long as breath sees still the inner rooms; Go noble Prince, as power doth give thee aid, For thy own sake, I'le live and die a maid. Holl. Sweet Lerenica loath, but I must go, My soul bids fly, my heart cryes out the same, Then fair Lerenica, please to take th'air, Of other Princes from Numenia: So I must go, my tongue fails, nought but this I can express; fair, give me adieu kiss, Constant Lerenica, constant Lerenica. [Exit Holl. Ler. Go noble Prince, stay, take another kiss; What, art thou gone? woe, woe, Lerenica, Cannot my warbling voyce crave Niobe, To be with her turn'd into a dull stone, That those stretching motions may then faint At my more flinty nature, then my breast Can expell from it, as such stormy blowes, Or with Iphianassa and Lysippe, Chang'd to strange furies, that no woe may pierce, My vitall spirits; pish, now I feel A stronger temper then those Goddesses, No Dælalus his Labyrinth can hide, My woe from running its due ordered course; Then let me frame a twist as Iphis did, For to make sorrow have abortive birth, Or turn'd to man, to have a stronger heart In the defiance of my wandring woe: But stay, I wrong poor natures time, For to detard the blow that rids my pains, So pangs strikes larums to my parting close; Then do appear thou ender of my life, [Drawes her knife. Bring licence from Elizian souls to me; Come, come, thou quick Physitian, welcome now, Thy medicines to my poor panting soul, No tears shall hinder virtue of thy will, Nor Ivory breast turn point of steely form; So then I come Hollarro, dear Hollarro, [stabs. To which place thou'l follow me, woe, woe, woe. Now I will frame and ocean for my soul Of pure blood, to hoyst a Gallie in. And its same say I shall aim at no port else, But the Hollarro, Hollarro of my joy, So spend you drops and make a quick convoy, Drench all my soul to make that great deluge; But if your wandring channels run to him, Inform his ear my heart was th'messenger, And for his own dear soul I bleed my last, I wrong my soul to stay the time so long: [stabs again. Now then you happy Nymphs, make passage free, Let no foul ghost turn back my bloody hand, Though grim Prometheus vulture's tear my breast, Yet still my journey tempers all those paines. Then Jove that loves Diana's Nymph that's fair, Ruling the whole universe in form, Send down a smiling look, take pitty of Her, who doth welter in her own hot blood, As in the great red Sea, whose water boyls, The time begins to challenge priviledge: Oh, oh, I fail; oh, oh, I fail, and come, Now, now, methinks, whole Kingdoms come to me: Oh sweet sweet Musick, and a melody, Hollarro, so I go, Hollarro— [Falls and dyes, and lies on the Stage. Scen. 6. Celerinus, Gervoron, &amp; Bellerrio. Cel. Mars, Armocares, is still our friend, The mounting Eagle soars upon the wind, And makes pale Moon a Diadem to her Crown, And so all language smiles with hollowing cryes, To shew our force like the Athenian, Great Agatho, strange man of might, but weak Unto our souls, who are Hyperions Son, They stood like Pigmies, while we Albions And Bergions stood to oppose the wrath; Their Towns are ours, we'l make a happy skie, Present a prosperous morn unto our souls; And when crystall Aurora gives the foy! To Cynthia's wandring Chariot, then I'le give, And all divide the Land according to the place Of every Souldier, the whole Kingdom shall Be in fragments. Ger. Great King, the appointment of your sun-bright Judgement, gives peace and plenty to our minds, Whole Regions of a violentiall form is turn'd To peace, her wishes in a splendent case; And as the aggregate of future losse, Is over-vail'd by joy of present time; Even, so your sacred will stops envies teeth, To give this Kingdome in a recompence. Cel. Though Maulinus, they were noble in their deeds, To use the chain of liberty with friends, The Phœnix of that age, which rob'd the time With his best deeds, are trifles to my vote; I hope my time will not prove like Cavinus, But live to see my men in silver forests, Urania's I vre shall not content the mind, Nor Aruns Lute so well as gift will do, To morrow morning it shall be confirm'd. Bell. Your royall Majesty hath shap'd my lot; If Achilles were here, and Pargamus, Their fame could be no greater then ours won; Neptune and Nereus conspir'd with all one vote, And Titans rays for to redeem your Land, And, noble Leige, you have fulfil'd your part. Ger. The storm is over of great rage and War, Rhenus her waves ne'r flowed with Nilus tides, To make a fertile soyl, may be compar'd To this your most King-like decree of fame. Cel. Here I Ulysses, they Alcanders stand, While the Troys blades strike dead those Sarpedons, The Agonius god is at command: I'le do what pleaseth fancy of my care, Though Alexanders fame runs much in world, Yet bounty takes the place of all his acts, Alecto, and the other two, cannot Withdraw the purpose that I have decreed; So we'l begon, to morrow is the day. [Exeunt Cel. Ger., manet Bellerrio. Bell. Where's now Lerenica? sure, speed will drive Her feet, to make a ranscat for her bold Attempt, I shall be King or Prince, the King Fore-tells, by service I did perform; The brazen Gates of Hell dare not withstand The bilbow blades of my great thundering arm: [Finds Lerenica. But stay, what's this? the spoils of some strange story, 'Tis not Lerenica sure, her face is black, A contrary climate to her element; I'le clense thy face to see with sorrows eyes, Sure't cannot be fair Lerenica; Let's see thy chin, thy finger and thy ring; Oh las, it is the signature I gave To her dear soul. oh curst Bellerrio, I have done wrong for to defame my King, And lose my Dame, a mock-star of the Sun; Oh slavery of Heirs, to fight and die By that great War I overcame by blows; Let one Urn conclude both of our ashes, A servile man unto my sorrow: no, This arm shall send a weapon to my heart, No policy shall work by quick design, To turn the mind that hangs on that same string; She's dead, she's dead, and stab'd her selfe for griefe, By home-bred strife, and a full stretcht arm; What, shall I live to see those dayes of woe, With this my body, and want the life of th'soul? No, sure I may with Carthaginians, Be buried quick as Philenius were, Make Celerinus prove to me a Cyrene Oh that would be a joyfull day to see, Such a mutation in my barbarous plot; Or like Orpheus wife Euridice, Be stung with the Aristæan Adder, And so cause end to this my gloomy light: But these afford no aid unto my dying soul, Then let me be with Babylonian dame, To Dirces fish converted, in moment, That all Pallanian dames may hiss my woe, To see my foul and unreserving thought; Let flocking furies strangle breath within Such a presumptious soul, to venture it; I caus'd her death, then death must recompence That virgins act; I must, I must then dye, The battle's ended, but in arms with me, Such objects fright my inner vitalls sense, [Draws his sword. So thou must be my friend when all forsake; A happy key to open death the Gate. Cut, cut, the veins, that hath wrought such a foe, To fair Lerenica in her resting sleep: Then here I come with a most sweet content, [stabs With Cancus bird, to pine away with mirth, oh—oh— The pangs begin to work, I leave this place To be surnam'd (Bellerrio's comfort With Lerenica)— [Falls and dies, so they are both convey'd off the Stage. Scen. 7. Hollarro in a distressed condition. Holl. This dismal life gives tongue unto my mind, What Arcadian mountain, or Pholot wood, Receive my soul, and charge it as a prey, A Panetolium forrest would befit My sense with decent alarums of fear; Rouse then authority of hellish cryes, Be thou a foe when substance wants its force, Bring in a full carreer of desperate shouts, And tax the muster-role of all my sense, Though the Athenian Cynegirus Holded the ship, while hands and stumps did last: So I in fathers Kingdom equall'd him, In that Halcyion's nest of all my joy, No choller mov'd me to't, but duty did imprint To lend that of aid of my full strongest arm, By whose great blowes the air it did inflame; I forced all those Symbarians by a rule, To make the earth a pillow for their souls. That which was matter and spirit, is now turn'd To matter onely in a putrid form: The Spirit's gone like an airy breath, And a sweet musick onely by its sound. When I have done all, this, must now return Into a hopelesse humour of my life, Losing my Kingdom, cast as reprobate: No sure, I shall ne'r undergo't with hope, To boyl in lake of famine and dispair, Vengeance cryes loud unto my fearful soul, But impotency warns me to desist, A desolate forrest yields no comfort to A Princely humour, lest be by combate Of savage creatures in their form and shape, But let a hope survive my vital sense, Often good fortune haps to a forrain Prince: But stay, methinks I wander without brains, Where's Lerenica my onely Queen and joy; Oh that's the deed, no hope can recompence; Now, now, these thoughts bequeath my life to death, Let Orcus streams that flow from Stygian lake, Make her full course in channel of my throat; Or like Ocnomatus, an Elian King, Treacherously slain, not knowing friends from foe Or else like Daphne, turn to tri-form, Wearing a Laurell Crown of Prince's power; But all these dayes are gone, a quicker charm Shall do the deed, come thou my steely man: [He drawes his sword, and sets it to his breast, but cannot make it enter. Oh strange, oh strange; what, is my soul an Adamant? The point is turn'd, sure gods hath against said, I'le try once more, perchance it was my fear; [He tries again, and his sword breaks. Heavens bless me, what's the matter? what, is My sword confounded, and my breast yet firm? Well, I'le go range for a fury to kill Me, or else die with dispair. Exit Hollarro. Celerinus, Gervoron, Souldiers. Cel. After the Queen is punish'd by courage, Of lash, of fury, with a martiall hand, The storms grown calm of all our forrain foes, All poetick Centaures leave the game, Not one assayl on credit of our fame; Then Gervoron be you the Lord of The woody Province of Bruzantia; As for Bellerrio he hath sung a doleful close Of ecchoing quavers to Elizium: And all my Souldlers have a fitting bound, According to the valour they have won. Ger. Most noble Liege, Time doth surrender office to your Crown, Giving the Theater of all Kingly power, Making all Rebels venture for safeguard, Suffering no bulwork of discretion; Therefore grave judgement is in balance now, And your great Majesty hath poys'd the same, By prosperous spoyls; all ponderous rage is gone Fled with the viper to the cave of fear: All foggy shaddows turn a crystall rays, To make the misty humour ascend up; Tears wip'd from us, a joyfull day now comes, No stars are now, but turn'd to glittering suns. Cel. Let Tagus spangled shore void up all Gems, And Nilus gliding streams recruit all stems, The quintessence of all four Elements, And all the earth as they each one frequent, Joyn all in one to make Elixar true, Yet all are vain to what is born to you, The mass of all the round terrestiall globe, Is unto that you have, but a poor node; You in abyss of joy is plung'd full out, And in a Wardrobe which none can recrout; Go blessed souls, take spoils or fields, what you Do most approve of, or best in your shew. Sould. Noble Heroick Liege, all grace wait on Your Kingly honour, and royall person. Exit Sould. Ger. Honour of honours, and the field of fame, Give Victors, Trophies, to your divine name; Let them all sound, to make the rocky stones Know whose's their subject, who helps their great moans, And let the wheel of valour still at hand, Stand present at the sign of your command. Cel. The rector of all the spred dapled skies, Who holds the Poles, and all that on them lies, Bids gloomy Luna take possession free, Of golden Titan and his splendency. So we'l depart, Aberden must give way To Celerinus, who still rules the day. Exeunt. Scen. 8. Chorus , Song 1. 1. Let sable mourning fling away Her dusty Robes, here comes the day, Which makes bright Ceres smile to see Such Bacchalian tranquillity, All Gods and Goddesses both far and ne're, Must sing and praise this day with grateful cheer 2. The Stygian lakes must cease to be, And Cerberus greedy of his fee, Peace doth make Bellonia frown, Mars yields up, and gives Peace the Crown; Then let us all clap hands for joy of this, That nought can recompence below a blisse. [Chorus.] Song 2. See how the flocks possesse the ground, While men do wait thereon, And all things in a blessed form, And joyfull union; All Cities quiet, singing hymns, While children plaies thereby, Skies send to them a happy morn, All by milde jubily; Therefore since peace doth make these things, Let us spend all our dayes To frame such peace while peace doth last In all our wandring wayes: How bravely Nymphs and Satyrs play, And skip in valleys low; And how great Jove doth like the same In such a pleasant shew; Then sound, clap hands, and make a noyse, Till skies they do rebound, To see such friendship and such love, 'Twixt their Land and this ground. Exeunt. The Graces, with the Ring of Amity. Agl. Aberden caus'd Celerinus to fly. Tha. Celerinus made Aberden know why. Eup. Neither of those Kings knew which first should die. At. Here's Aberdens ashes laid in tomb, And Souldiers lye so thick, there is no room For future damage, the clear stars wax dim, A Serpent now is vice-roy of all sin, His subject made their answer and design, Still viewing Countries, till with him made fine; The wide mouth of all swallowing angers throat, Gapes like Eagle or Lion from his vote, No Empire bounded, but this Nymph will see The bounds and freedom of its liberty; She's born of crooked nature, 'cause her will Is oft imploy'd to manage what is ill; But let grim Anger wait, as long as days, Or years, or months, or Sol hath any rays, She still shall be debarred from us three, Who live in ring (naked) of amity. Tha. The hellish Queen, great Adrenimia's paid To her deserts, in prison chain'd, and laid For future trouble of a dreadful day; Greedy her hands were to spill blood alway; But now expect revenge from that same King, Where she imploy'd such a Lethalian thing. Eup. The Prince Hollarro still must wander time, In smiling Dales and Woods then full of crime; The hoysting sayls of all his hope must be, After foul cross to have community, Until the spangled skies doth give such rays, I wish bright Sol may turn all nights to dayes; But if my wish be too severe in sight, I wish all native Princes had their right. Exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">? credula vitam Spes fovet ? Tibul. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>