<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">More, Hannah, 1745-1833</field>
      <field name="author_facet">More, Hannah, 1745-1833</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">more hannah 1745 1833</field>
      <field name="author_text">More, Hannah, 1745-1833</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">18th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1780's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V2.0560.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1782</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460219</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Belshazzah ; a Sacred Drama</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Belshazzah ; a Sacred Drama</field>
      <field name="title_facet">belshazzah</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">belshazzah</field>
      <field name="title_text">Belshazzah ; a Sacred Drama</field>
      <field name="year_display">1782</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1782</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1782</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460219&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460219&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;More, Hannah, 1745-1833&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;more hannah 1745 1833&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Belshazzah ; a Sacred Drama&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;belshazzah&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1782&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1782&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;More, Hannah&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1745&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1833&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Belshazzah&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;a Sacred Drama&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for T. Cadell [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1782&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872538-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv20560&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 18th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;18th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Belshazzah&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;a Sacred Drama&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 76 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Only verse drama included&lt;lb/&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Belshazzar.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Drama.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1782.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Unknown.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">BELSHAZZAR: A SACRED DRAMA.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">How art thou fallen from Heaven, O Lucifer, Son of the Morning! How art thou cut down to the ground, who didst weaken the nations! Isaiah.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PERSONS of the DRAMA. BELSHAZZAR, King of Babylon. NITOCRIS, the Queen-mother. Courtiers, Astrologers, Parasites. DANIEL, the Jewish Prophet. Captive Jews, &amp;c. &amp;c.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE, Babylon. Time, Night.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">This subject of this Drama is taken from the Fifth Chapter of the Prophet Daniel.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PART I. SCENE, Near the Palace of Babylon. DANIEL, and captive JEWS. DANIEL. Parent of life and light! sole source of good! Whose tender mercies thro' the tide of time, In long successive order, have sustain'd, And sav'd the sons of Israel! Thou, whose pow'r, Deliver'd righteous Noah from the flood, The whelming flood, the grave of human kind! Oh Thou! whose guardian care, and out-stretch'd hand, Rescued young Isaac from the lifted arm, Rais'd, at thy bidding, to devote a son, An only son, doom'd by his sire to die. (Oh, saving Faith, by such obedience prov'd! Oh blest obedience, hallow'd thus by faith!) Thou, who in mercy sav'dst the chosen race, In the wild desert, and did'st there sustain them, By wonder-working love, tho' they rebell'd, And murmur'd at the miracles that sav'd them! Oh, hear thy servant Daniel! hear, and help! Thou! whose almighty pow'r did after raise Successive leaders to defend our race; Who sentest valiant Joshua to the field, Thy people's champion, to the conq'ring field, Where the revolving planet of the night, Suspended in her radiant round was stay'd, And the bright sun, arrested in his course, Stupendously stood still! Chorus of JEWS. I. What ailed thee, that thou stood'st still, O sun, nor did thy flaming orb decline? And thou, O moon, in Ajalon's dark vale, Why didst thou long beyond thy period shine? II. Was it at Joshua's dread command, The leader of the Israelitish band? Yes—at a mortal bidding both stood still; 'Twas Joshua's word, but 'twas Jehovah's will. III. What all-controuling hand had force To stop eternal Nature's constant course? The wand'ring moon to one fix'd spot confine, But He, whose fiat bade the planets shine? DANIEL. Oh Thou! who, when thy discontented host, Tir'd of Jehovah's rule, desir'd a king, In anger gav'st them Saul, and then again Didst wrest the regal sceptre from his hand To give it David—David, best belov'd! Illustrious David! Poet, prophet, king! Thou, who didst suffer Solomon his son, To build a glorious temple to thy name, Oh hear thy servants, and forgive them too, If, by severe necessity compell'd, We worship here—we have no temple now; Altar or sanctuary, none is left. Chorus of JEWS. O Judah! let thy captive sons deplore Thy far-fam'd temple is no more! Fall'n is thy sacred fane, thy glory gone, Fall'n is thy temple, Solomon. Ne'er did Barbaric kings behold, With all their shining gems, their burnish'd gold, A fane so perfect, bright and fair; For God himself was wont t' inhabit there: Between the Cherubim his glory stood, While the high-priest alone the dazzling splendor view'd. How fondly did the Tyrian artist strive His name to latest time shou'd live! Such wealth the stranger wonder'd to behold: Gold were the tablets, and the vases gold. Of cedar such an ample store, Exhausted Lebanon cou'd yield no more. Bending before the Ruler of the sky, Well might the royal founder cry, Fill'd with an holy dread, a rev'rend fear, Will God in very deed inhabit here? The heav'n of heav'ns beneath his feet, Is, for the bright inhabitant unmeet: Archangels prostrate wait his high commands, And will he deign to dwell in temples made with hands? DANIEL. Yes, thou art ever present, Pow'r supreme! Not circumscrib'd by time, nor fix'd to space, Confin'd to altars, nor to temples bound. In wealth, in want, in freedom or in chains, In dungeons or on thrones, the faithful find thee! Ev'n in the burning cauldron thou wast near To Shadrach and the holy brotherhood: The unhurt martyrs bless'd thee in the flames; They sought, and found thee; call'd, and thou wast there. First JEW. How chang'd our state! Judah! thy glory's fall'n. Thy joys for hard captivity exchang'd; And thy sad sons breathe the polluted air Of Babylon, where deities obscene Insult the living God; and to his servants, The priests of wretched idols, made with hands, Shew contumelious scorn. DANIEL. 'Tis Heav'n's high will. Second JEW. If I forget thee, O Jerusalem! If I not fondly cherish thy lov'd image, Ev'n in the giddy hour of thoughtless mirth; If I not rather view thy prostrate walls Than haughty Babylon's imperial tow'rs. Then may my tongue refuse to frame the strains Of sweetest harmony, my rude right-hand Forget, with sounds symphonious, to accord The harp of Jesse's son, to Sion's songs. First JEW. Oft, on Euphrates' ever verdant banks, Where drooping willows form a mournful shade; With all the pride which prosp'rous fortunes give, And all th' unfeeling mirth of happy men, Th' insulting Babylonians ask a song; Such songs as erst in better days were sung By Korah's sons, or heav'n-taught Asaph set To loftiest measures; then our bursting hearts Feel all their woes afresh; the galling chain Of bondage crushes then the free-born soul With wringing anguish; from the trembling lip Th' unfinish'd cadence falls, and the big tear, While it relieves, betrays the woe-fraught soul. For who can view Euphrates' pleasant stream, Its drooping willows, and its verdant banks, And not, to wounded memory recal The piny groves of fertile Palæstine, The vales of Solyma, and Jordan's stream? DANIEL. Firm faith and deep submission to high Heav'n, Will teach us to endure, without a murmur, What seems so hard. Think what the holy host Of patriarchs, saints, and prophets, have sustain'd In the blest cause of Truth! And shall not we, O men of Judah! dare what these have dar'd, And boldly pass thro' the refining fire Of fierce affliction? Yes, be witness, Heav'n! Old as I am, I will not shrink at death, Come in what shape it may, if God so will, By peril to confirm and prove my faith. Oh! I wou'd dare yon' den of hungry lions, Rather than pause to fill the task assign'd, By wisdom infinite. Nor think I boast, Not in myself, but in thy strength I trust, Spirit of God! First JEW. Prophet! thy words support, And raise our sinking souls. DANIEL. Behold yon' palace, Where proud Belshazzar keeps his wanton court! I knew it once beneath another lord, His grandsire Nebuchadnezzar., who subdued Jehoiachin, And hither brought sad Judah's captive tribes; Together with the rich and sacred relics Of our fam'd temple; all the holy treasure, The golden vases, and the sacred cups, Which grac'd, in happier times, the sanctuary. Second JEW. May he, to whose blest use they were devoted, Preserve them from pollution, and once more, In his own gracious time, restore the temple! DANIEL. I, with some favour'd youths of Jewish race, Was lodg'd in his own palace, and instructed In all the various learning of the east: But he, on whose great name our fathers call'd, Preserv'd us from the perils of a court; And warn'd us to avoid the tempting cates Pernicious lux'ry offer'd to our taste. Fell luxury! more perilous to youth Than storms or quicksands, poverty or chains. Second JEW. He who can guard 'gainst the low baits of sense, Will find Temptation's arrows hurtless strike Against the brazen shield of Temperance. For 'tis th' inferior appetites enthrall The man, and quench th' immortal light within him; The senses take the soul an easy prey, And sink th' imprison'd spirit into brute. DANIEL. Twice Daniel, Chap. ii. and iv., by the Spirit of God, did I expound The visions of the king; his soul was touch'd, And twice did he repent, and prostrate fall Before the God of Daniel: yet again, Pow'r, flatt'ry, and prosperity, undid him. When from the lofty ramparts of his palace, He view'd the splendors of the royal city, That magazine of wealth, which proud Euphrates, Wafts from each distant corner of the earth; When he beheld the adamantine towers, The brazen gates, the bulwarks of his strength, The pendent gardens, art's stupendous work, The wonder of the world!—The proud Chaldean, Mad with the insolence of boundless wealth, And pow'r supreme, conceiv'd himself a God. “This mighty Babylon is mine,” he cried, “My wondrous pow'r, my godlike arm atchiev'd it. I scorn submission, own no deity Above my own.”—While the blasphemer spoke, The wrath of Heav'n inflicted instant vengeance; Stripp'd him of that bright reason he abus'd, And drove him from the cheerful haunts of men, A naked, wretched, helpless, senseless thing; Companion of the brutes, his equals now. First JEW. Nor does his impious grandson, proud Belshazzar, Fall short of his offences; nay, he wants The valiant spirit, and the active soul, Of his progenitor: for Pleasure's slave, Though bound in flow'ry fetters, silky-soft, Is more subdued, than is the casual victim Of furious rage, and violent ambition. Ambition is a fierce, but short-liv'd fire; But Pleasure with a constant flame consumes. War slays her thousands; but destructive Pleasure, More fell, more fatal, her ten thousands slays: The young, luxurious king she fondly wooes In every shape of am'rous blandishment; With adulation smooth ensnares his soul, With love betrays him, and with wine inflames. She strews her magic poppies o'er his couch, And with delicious opiates charms him down, In fatal slumbers bound. Though Babylon Is now invested by the warlike troops Of the young Cyrus, Persia's valiant prince, Who, in conjunction with the Median king, Darius, fam'd for conquest, now prepares To storm the city: not th' impending horrors Which ever wait a siege, have power to wake To thought, or sense, th' intoxicated king. DANIEL. Ev'n in this night of universal dread, A mighty army threat'ning at the gates; This very night, as if in scorn of danger, The dissolute Belshazzar holds a feast Magnificently impious, meant to honour Belus, the fav'rite Babylonish idol. Lewd parasites compose his wanton court, Whose impious flatt'ries soothe his monstrous crimes; They justify his vices, and extol His boastful phrase, as if he were some god. Whate'er he says, they say; what he commands, Implicitly they do; they echo back His blasphemies, with shouts of loud acclaim; And when he wounds the tortur'd ear of Virtue, They cry, All hail! Belshazzar live for ever! To-night a thousand nobles fill his hall, Princes, and all the dames who grace the court; All but the virtuous queen, sage Nitocris; Ah! how unlike the impious king her son! She never mingles in the midnight fray, Nor crowns the guilty banquet with her presence. The royal fair is rich in every virtue Which can adorn the queen, or grace the woman. But for the wisdom of her prudent counsels This wretched empire had been long undone. Not fam'd Semiramis, Assyria's pride, Cou'd boast a brighter mind, or firmer soul, Beneath the gentle reign of 2 Kings, Chap. xxv. Merodach, Her royal lord, our nation tasted peace. Our captive monarch, sad Jehoiachin, Grown grey in a close prison's horrid gloom, He freed from bondage, brought the hoary king To taste once more the long-forgotten sweets Of precious liberty, and cheerful light; Pour'd in his wounds the lenient balm of kindness, And bless'd his settting hour of life with peace. [Sound of trumpets is heard at a distance. First JEW. That sound proclaims the banquet is begun. Second JEW. Hark! the licentious uproar grows more loud. The vaulted roof resounds with shouts of mirth, And the firm palace shakes! Retire, my friends; This madness is not meet for sober ears. If any of our race were found so near, 'Twou'd but expose us to the rude attack Of ribaldry obscene, and impious jests, From these mad sons of Belial, now inflam'd To deeds of riot from the wanton feast. DANIEL. Here part we then! but when again to meet, Who knows save Heav'n? Yet, O, my friends! I feel An impulse more than human stir my breast. Rapt in prophetic See the Prophecies of Isaiah, chap. xlvii. and others. vision, I behold Things hid as yet from mortal sight. I see The dart of vengeance tremble in the air, E're long to pierce the impious king. Ev'n now The fierce, destroying angel stalks abroad, And brandishes aloft the two-edg'd sword Of retribution keen; he soon will strike, And Babylon shall weep as Sion wept. Pass but a little while, and you shall see This queen of cities prostrate on the earth. This haughty mistress of the kneeling world, How shall she sit dishonour'd in the dust, In tarnish'd pomp and solitary woe! How shall she shroud her glories in the dark, And in opprobrious silence hide her head! Lament, O virgin daughter of Chaldea! For thou shalt fall, imperial queen! shalt fall! No more Sidonian robes shall grace thy limbs. To purple garments, sackcloth shall succeed; And sordid dust and ashes shall supply The od'rous nard and cassia. Thou, who said'st, I am, and there is none beside me: thou, Ev'n thou, imperial Babylon! shalt fall: Thy glory quite eclips'd! The pleasant sound Of viol and of harp, shall charm no more; Nor song of Syrian damsels shall be heard, Responsive to the lute's luxurious note. But the hoarse bittern's cry, the raven's croak, The bat's fell scream, the lonely owl's dull plaint, And every hideous bird with ominous shriek, Shall scare affrighted Silence from thy walls. While Desolation, snatching from the hand Of Time the scythe of ruin, sits aloft, In dreadful majesty and horrid pomp; Glancing with sullen pride thy crumbling tow'rs, Thy broken battlements, and columns fall'n; Then, pointing to the mischiefs she has made, The fiend exclaims, This once was Babylon!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PART II. SCENE, The Court of Belshazzar. The King seated on a magnificent throne. Princes, Nobles, and Attendants. Ladies of the Court. Music—A superb Banquet. First COURTIER. Rises, and kneels. Hail, mighty king! Second COURTIER. Belshazzar, live for ever! Third COURTIER. Sun of the world, and light of kings, all hail! Fourth COURTIER. With lowest reverence, such as best becomes The humblest creatures of imperial power, Behold a thousand nobles bend before thee! Princes far fam'd, and dames of high descent: Yet all this pride of wealth, this boast of beauty, Shrinks into nought before thine awful eye, And lives, or dies, as the king frowns, or smiles! BELSHAZZAR. This is such homage as becomes your love, And suits the mighty monarch of mankind. Fifth COURTIER. The bending world shou'd prostrate thus before thee, And pay, not only praise, but adoration! BELSHAZZAR. Rises, and comes forward. Let dull philosophy preach self-denial; Let envious poverty, and snarling age, Proudly declaim against the joys they know not. Let the deluded Jews, who fondly hope Some fancied heav'n hereafter, mortify, And lose the actual blessings of this world, To purchase others which may never come. Our Gods may promise less, but give us more. Ill cou'd my ardent spirit be content With meagre abstinence, and hungry hope. Let those misjudging Israelites, who want The nimble spirits, and the active soul, Call their blunt feelings virtue: let them drudge, In regular progression, thro' the round Of formal duty, and of daily toil, And, when they want the genius to be blest, Believe their harsh austerity is goodness. If there be Gods they meant we shou'd be happy, Why give us else these appetites to be so? And why, the means to crown them with indulgence? To burst the feeble bonds which hold the vulgar, Is noble daring. First COURTIER. And is therefore worthy The high imperial spirit of Belshazzar. Second COURTIER. Behold a banquet which the gods might share. BELSHAZZAR. To-night, my friends! your monarch shall be blest With ev'ry various joy; to-night is ours; Nor shall the envious gods who view our bliss, And sicken as they view, to-night disturb us. Bring all the richest spices of the East, The od'rous cassia, and the dropping myrrh; The liquid amber, and the fragrant gums; Rob Gilead of its balms, Belshazzar bids, And leave the Arabian groves without an odour. Bring freshest flow'rs, exhaust the blooming spring, Twine the green myrtle with the short-liv'd rose, And ever, as the blushing garland fades, We'll learn to snatch the fugitive delight, And grasp the flying joy ere it escape us. Come—fill the smiling goblet for the king; Belshazzar will not let a moment pass Unmark'd by some enjoyment! The full bowl Let every guest partake! [Courtiers kneel, and drink. First COURTIER. Here's to the king! Light of the world, and glory of the earth, Whose word is fate! BELSHAZZAR. Yes, we are likest gods, When we have pow'r, and use it. What is wealth, But the blest means to gratify desire? I will not have a wish, a hope, a thought, That shall not know fruition. What is empire? The privilege to punish and enjoy; To feel our pow'r in making others fear it; To taste of pleasure's cup till we grow giddy, And think ourselves immortal. This is empire! My ancestors scarce tasted of its joys: Shut from the sprightly world, and all its charms, In cumbrous majesty, in sullen state, And dull unsocial dignity they liv'd; Far from the sight of an admiring world, That world, whose gaze makes half the charms of greatness; They nothing knew of empire but the name, Or saw it in the looks of trembling slaves; And all they felt of royalty was care. But I will see, and know it of myself; Youth, wealth, and greatness court me to be blest, And Pow'r and Pleasure draw with equal force And sweet attraction: both I will embrace With fond delight; but this is Pleasure's day; Ambition will have time to reign hereafter; It is the proper appetite of age. The lust of pow'r shall lord it uncontroul'd, When all the gen'rous feelings grow obtuse, And stern dominion holds, with rigid hand, His iron rein, and sits and sways alone. But youth is pleasure's hour! First COURTIER. Perish the slave, Who, with officious counsel, wou'd oppose The king's desire, whose slightest wish is law! BELSHAZZAR. Now strike the loud-ton'd lyre, and softer lute; Let me have music, with the nobler aid Of poesy! Where are those cunning men, Who boast, by chosen sounds, and measur'd sweetness, To set the busy spirits in a flame, And cool them at their will? who know the art To call the hidden pow'rs of numbers forth, And make that pliant instrument, the mind, Yield to the pow'rful sympathy of sound, Obedient to the master's artful hand? Such magic is in song! Then give me song; Yet not at first such soul-dissolving strains, As melt the soften'd sense; but such bold measures, As may inflame my spirit to despise The ambitious Persian, that presumptuous boy, Who rashly dares ev'n now invest our city, And menaces th' invincible Belshazzar. A grand Concert of Music, after which an Ode. In vain shall Persian Cyrus dare With great Belshazzar wage unequal war: In vain Darius shall combine, Darius, leader of the Median line; While fair Euphrates' stream our walls protects, And great Belshazzar's self our fate directs. War and famine threat in vain, While this demi-god shall reign! Let Persia's prostrate king confess his pow'r, And Media's monarch dread his vengeful hour. On Dura's Daniel, chap. iii. ample plain behold Immortal Belus See a very fine description of the Temple of this Idol. —The tow'ring fane Of Bel, Chaldean Jove, surpassing far That Doric Temple, which the Elean chiefs Rais'd to their thunderer from the spoils of war; Or that Ionic, where th' Ephesian bow'd To Dian, queen of heaven. Eight towers arise, Each above each, immeasurable height, A monument at once of Eastern pride, And slavish superstition, &amp;c. &amp;c. Judah Restor'd, Book I., whom the nations own; Sublime he stands in burnish'd gold, And richest offerings his bright altars crown. To-night his deity we here adore, And due libations speak his mighty pow'r. Yet Belus' self not more we own, Than great Belshazzar on Chaldea's throne. Great Belshazzar, like a god, Rules the nations with a nod! To great Belshazzar be the goblet crown'd! Belshazzar's name the echoing roofs rebound! BELSHAZZAR. Enough! the kindling rapture fires my train, And my heart dances to the flatt'ring sounds. I feel myself a god! Why not a god? What were the deities our fathers worshipp'd? What was great Nimrod, our imperial founder? What, greater Belus, to whose pow'r divine, We raise to-night the banquet and the song; But youthful heroes, mortal, like myself, Who by their daring earn'd divinity? They were but men: nay, some were less than men, Tho' now rever'd as Gods. What was Anubis, Whom Egypt's sapient sons adore? A dog! And shall not I, young, valiant, and a king, Dare more? do more? be greater than the rest? I will indulge the thought.—Fill me more wine, To cherish and exalt the young idea! [He drinks. Ne'er did Olympian Jupiter himself Quaff such immortal draughts. First COURTIER. What cou'd that Canaan, That heaven in hope, that nothing in possession, That air-built bliss of the deluded Jews, That promis'd land of milk, and flowing honey; What cou'd that fancied Paradise bestow To match these generous juices? BELSHAZZAR. Hold—enough! Thou hast rous'd a thought; by Heav'n I will enjoy it; A glorious thought! which will exalt to rapture The pleasures of the banquet, and bestow A yet untasted relish of delight. First COURTIER. What means the king? BELSHAZZAR. The Jews! saidst thou the Jews? First COURTIER. I spoke of that undone, that outcast people, The tributary creatures of thy pow'r, The captives of thy will, whose very breath Hangs on the sov'reign pleasure of the king. BELSHAZZAR. When that abandon'd race was hither brought, Were not the choicest treasures of their temple, (Devoted to their God, and held most precious) Among the spoils which grac'd The name of Nebuchadnezzar not being reducible to verse, I have adopted that of Nebassar, on the authority of the ingenious and learned Author of Judah Restor'd. Nebassar's triumph, And lodg'd in Babylon? First COURTIER. O king! they were. Second COURTIER. The Jews, with superstitious awe, behold These sacred symbols of their ancient faith: Nor has captivity abated ought The rev'rend love they bear these holy reliques. Tho' we deride their law, and scorn their persons, Yet never have we yet to human use Devoted these rich vessels, set apart To sacred purposes. BELSHAZZAR. I joy to hear it! Go—fetch them hither. They shall grace our banquet. Does no one stir? Belshazzar disobey'd? And yet you live! Whence comes this strange reluctance? This new-born rev'rence for the helpless Jews? This fear to injure those who can't revenge it? Send to the sacred treasury in haste, Let all be hither brought;—who answers, dies. [They go out. The mantling wine a higher joy will yield, Pour'd from the precious flaggons which adorn'd Their far-fam'd temple, now in ashes laid. Oh! 'twill exalt the pleasure into transport, To gall those whining, praying Israelites! I laugh to think what wild dismay will seize them, When they shall learn the use that has been made Of all their holy trumpery! [The vessels are brought in. Second COURTIER, It comes! A goodly shew! how bright with gold and gems! Far fitter for a youthful monarch's board, Than the cold shrine of an unheeding god. BELSHAZZAR. Fill me that massy goblet to the brim. Now, Abraham! let thy wretched race expect The fable of their faith to be fulfill'd; Their second temple, and their promis'd king! Now will they see he's impotent to save, For had he pow'r to help, he wou'd have hinder'd This profanation. [As the king is going to drink, thunder is heard; he starts from the throne, spies a hand, which writes on the wall these words; Mene, Mene, Tekel Upharsin. He lets fall the goblet, and stands in an attitude of speechless horror. All start, and are terrified.] First COURTIER, after a long pause. Oh, transcendent horror! Second COURTIER. What may this mean? The king is greatly mov'd! Third COURTIER. Nor is it strange—who unappall'd can view it? Those sacred cups! I doubt we've gone too far. First COURTIER. Observe the fear-struck king! his starting eyes Roll horribly. Thrice he essay'd to speak, And thrice his tongue refus'd. BELSHAZZAR, in a low trembling voice. Ye mystic words! Thou semblance of an hand! illusive forms! Ye dire fantastic images, what are ye? Dread shadows, speak! Explain your horrible meaning! Ye will not answer me.—Yes, yes, I feel I am a mortal now—My failing limbs Refuse to bear me up. I am no god! Gods do not tremble thus.—Support me, hold me, These loosen'd joints, these knees which smite each other, Betray I'm but a man—a weak one too! First COURTIER. In truth 'tis passing strange, and full of horror! BELSHAZZAR. Send for the learn'd magicians, every sage Who deals in wizard spells and magic charms. [Some go out. First COURTIER. How fares my lord the king? BELSHAZZAR. Am I a king? What pow'r have I? Ye lying slaves, I am not. Oh, soul-distracting sight! but is it real? Perhaps 'tis fancy all, or the wild dream Of mad distemperature, the fumes of wine! I'll look upon't no more!—So—now I'm well! I am a king again, and know not fear. And yet my eyes will seek that fatal spot, And fondly dwell upon the sight that blasts them! Again, 'tis there! it is not fancy's work. I see it still! 'tis written on the wall. I see the writing, but the viewless writer, Who, what is he? Oh, horror! horror! horror! It cannot be the God of these poor Jews, For what is he, that he can thus afflict? Second COURTIER. Let not my lord the king be thus dismay'd. Third COURTIER. Let not a phantom, an illusive shade, Disturb the peace of him who rules the world. BELSHAZZAR. No more, ye wretched sycophants! no more! The sweetest note which flatt'ry now can strike, Harsh and discordant grates upon my soul. Talk not of power to one so full of fear, So weak, so impotent! Look on that wall; If thou wou'dst sooth my soul, explain the writing, And thou shalt be my oracle, my God! Tell me from whence it came, and what it means, And I'll believe I am again a king! Friends! princes! ease my troubled breast, and say, What do the mystic characters portend? First COURTIER. 'Tis not in us, O king! to ease thy spirit; We are not skill'd in those mysterious arts Which wait the midnight studies of the sage; But of the deep diviners thou shalt learn, The wise astrologers, the sage magicians, Who, of events unborn, take secret note, And hold deep commerce with the unseen world. Enter ASTROLOGERS, MAGICIANS, &amp;c. &amp;c. BELSHAZZAR. Approach, ye sages, 'tis the king commands! [They kneel. ASTROLOGERS. Hail, mighty king of Babylon! BELSHAZZAR. Nay, rise: I do not need your homage, but your help; The world may worship, you must counsel me. He who declares the secret of the king, No common honours shall await his skill; Our empire shall be tax'd for his reward, And he himself shall name the gift he wishes. A splendid scarlet robe shall grace his limbs, His neck a princely chain of gold adorn, Meet honours for such wisdom: He shall rule The third in rank throughout our Babylon. Second ASTROLOGER. Such recompence becomes Belshazzar's bounty. Let the king speak the secret of his soul, Which heard, his humble creatures shall unfold. BELSHAZZAR , points to the wall. Be't so—Look there—behold those characters! Nay, do not start, for I will know their meaning! Ha! answer; speak, or instant death awaits you! What, dumb! all dumb! where is your boasted skill? [They confer together. Keep them asunder—No confed'racy— No secret plots to make your tales agree. Speak, slaves, and dare to let me know the worst! First ASTROLOGER. [They kneel. O, let the king forgive his faithful servants! Second ASTROLOGER. O mitigate our threaten'd doom of death, If we declare, with mingled grief and shame, We cannot tell the secret of the king, Nor what these mystic characters portend! BELSHAZZAR. Off with their heads! Ye shall not live an hour! Curse on your shallow arts, your lying science! 'Tis thus you practise on the credulous world, Who think you wise, because themselves are weak! But, miscreants, ye shall die! the pow'r to punish Is all that I have left me of a king. First COURTIER. Great Sir! suspend their punishment awhile, Behold sage Nitocris, thy royal mother! BELSHAZZAR. My mother here! Enter QUEEN. QUEEN. O my misguided son! Well mayst thou wonder to behold me here, For I have ever shunn'd this scene of riot, Where wild intemperance and dishonour'd mirth Hold festival impure. Yet, O Belshazzar! I cou'd not hear the wonders which befel, And leave thee to the workings of despair: For, spite of all the anguish of my soul At thy offences, I'm thy mother still! Against the solemn prupose I had form'd Never to mix in this unhallow'd crowd, The wond'rous story of the mystic writing, Of strange and awful import, brings me here; If haply I may shew some likely means To fathom this dark mystery. BELSHAZZAR. Speak, O queen! My list'ning soul shall hang upon thy words, And prompt obedience follow them! QUEEN. Then hear me. Among the captive tribes which hither came To grace Nebassar's triumph, there was brought A youth nam'd Daniel, favour'd by high Heav'n With pow'r to look into the secret page Of dim futurity's mysterious volume. The spirit of the holy Gods is in him; No vision so obscure, no fate so dark, No sentence so perplex'd, but he can solve it: Can trace each crooked labyrinth of thought, Each winding maze of doubt, and make it clear, And palpable to sense. He twice explain'd The monarch's mystic dreams. The holy seer Saw, with prophetic spirit, what befel The king long after. For his wond'rous skill He was rewarded, honour'd, and caress'd, And with the rulers of Chaldea rank'd; Tho' now, alas! thrown by; his services Forgotten or neglected; such the meed Which virtue finds in courts. BELSHAZZAR. Dispatch with speed A message, to command the holy man To meet us on the instant. NITOCRIS. I already Have sent to ask his presence at the palace; And, lo! he comes. Enter DANIEL. BELSHAZZAR. Welcome, thrice venerable sage! approach. Art thou that Daniel, whom my great forefather Brought hither with the captive tribes of Judah? DANIEL. I am that Daniel. BELSHAZZAR. Pardon, holy Prophet; Nor let a just resentment of thy wrongs, And long neglected merit, shut thy heart Against a king's request, a suppliant king! DANIEL. The God I worship teaches to forgive. BELSHAZZAR. Then let thy words bring comfort to my soul. I've heard the spirit of the Gods is in thee; That thou cans't look into the fates of men With prescience more than human! DANIEL. Hold, O king! Wisdom is from above, 'tis God's own gift. I of myself am nothing; but from him The little knowledge I possess, I hold; To him be all the glory! BELSHAZZAR. Then, O Daniel! If thou indeed dost boast that wond'rous gift, That faculty divine, look there, and tell me! O say, what mean those mystic characters! Remove this load of terror from my soul, And honours, such as kings can give, await thee: Thou shalt be great beyond thy soul's ambition, And rich above thy wildest dream of wealth: Clad in the scarlet robe our nobles wear, And grac'd with princely ensigns, thou shalt stand Near our own throne, and third within our empire. DANIEL. O mighty king! thy gifts with thee remain, And let thy high rewards on others fall. The princely ensign, nor the scarlet robe, Nor yet to be the third within thy realm, Can touch the soul of Daniel. Honour, fame, All that the world calls great, thy crown itself, Cou'd never satisfy the vast ambition Of an immortal spirit, which aspires To an eternal crown, a crown of glory! First COURTIER. [Aside. Our priests teach no such notions. DANIEL. Yet, O king! Tho' all unmov'd by grandeur or by gift, I will unfold the high decrees of Heav'n, And strait declare the mystery. BELSHAZZAR. Speak, O Prophet! DANIEL. Prepare to hear what kings have seldom heard, Prepare to hear what these have never told thee, Prepare to hear the Truth. The mighty God, Who rules the sceptres and the hearts of kings, Gave thy renown'd Nebuchadnezzar. forefather here to reign, With such extent of empire, weight of pow'r, And greatness of dominion, the wide earth Trembled beneath the terror of his name, And kingdoms stood or fell as he decreed. Oh! dangerous pinnacle of pow'r supreme! Who can stand safe upon its treach'rous top, Behold the gazing prostrate world below, Whom depth and distance into pigmies shrink, And not grow giddy? Babylon's great king Forgot he was a man, a helpless man, Subject to pain, and sin, and death, like others! But who shall fight against Omnipotence? Or who hath harden'd his obdurate heart Against the Majesty of Heav'n, and prosper'd? The God he had insulted was aveng'd; From empire, from the joys of social life, He drove him forth; extinguish'd reason's lamp, Quench'd that bright spark of deity within; Compell'd him, with the forest brutes, to roam For scanty pasture; and the mountain dews Fell, cold and wet, on his defenceless head: Till he confess'd—Let men, let monarchs hear!— Till he confess'd, Pride was not made for man! NITOCRIS. O, awful instance of divine displeasure! BELSHAZZAR. Proceed! My soul is wrapt in fix'd attention! DANIEL. O king! thy grandsire not in vain had sinn'd, If, from his error, thou had'st learnt the truth. The story of his fall thou oft hast heard, But has it taught thee wisdom? Thou, like him, Hast been elate with pow'r, and mad with pride. Like him, thou hast defy'd the Living God. Nay, to bold thoughts hast added deeds more bold. Thou hast out-wrought the pattern he bequeth'd thee, And quite outgone example; hast prophan'd, With impious hand, the vessels of the Temple: Those vessels, sanctified to holiest use, Thou hast polluted with unhallow'd lips, And made the instruments of foul debauch. Thou hast ador'd the gods of wood and stone, Vile, senseless deities, the work of hands; But He, the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, In whom exists thy life, thy soul, thy breath, On whom thy being hangs, thou hast deny'd. First COURTIER. [Aside to the others. With what an holy boldness he reproves him! Second COURTIER. Such is the fearless confidence of virtue! And such the righteous courage those maintain Who plead the cause of truth! The smallest word He utters, had been death to half the court. BELSHAZZAR. Now let the mystic writing be explain'd, Thrice venerable sage! DANIEL. O mighty king! Hear then its awful import: God has number'd Thy days of royalty, and soon will end them. The All-wise has weigh'd thee in the even balance Of his own holy law, and finds thee wanting: And last, Thy kingdom shall be wrested from thee; And know, the Mede and Persian shall possess it. BELSHAZZAR. [He starts up. Prophet, when shall this be? DANIEL. In God's own time: Here my commission ends; I may not utter More than thou hast heard; but O! remember, king! Thy days are number'd; hear, repent, and live! BELSHAZZAR. Say, Prophet, what can penitence avail? If Heav'n's decrees immutably are fix'd, Can pray'rs avert our fate? DANIEL. They change our hearts, And thus dispose Omnipotence to mercy. 'Tis man that alters, God is still the same. Conditional are all Heav'n's covenants: And when th' uplifted thunder is with-held, 'Tis pray'r that deprecates th' impending bolt. Good 2 Chron. Chap. xxxii. Also, Isaiah, Chap. xxxviii. Hezekiah's days were number'd too; But penitence and tears were mighty pleas: At Mercy's throne they never plead in vain. [He is going. BELSHAZZAR. Stay, Prophet, and receive thy promis'd gift: The scarlet robe, and princely chain, are thine; And let my heralds publish through the land, That Daniel stands, in dignity and pow'r, The third in Babylon. These just rewards Thou well may'st claim, though sad thy prophecy! QUEEN. Be not deceiv'd, my son! nor let thy soul Snatch an uncertain moment's treach'rous rest, On the dread brink of that tremendous gulf Which yawns beneath thee. DANIEL. O unhappy king! Know what must happen once, may happen soon. Remember, that 'tis terrible to meet Great evils unprepar'd! and, O Belshazzar! In the wild moment of dismay and death, Remember thou wast warn'd! and, O! remember, Warnings despis'd are condemnations then! [Exeunt Daniel and Queen. BELSHAZZAR. 'Tis well—my soul shakes off its load of care: 'Tis only the obscure is terrible. Imagination frames events unknown, In wild fantastic shapes of hideous ruin; And what it fears, creates!—I know the worst; And awful is that worst as fear could feign: But distant are the ills I have to dread! What is remote may be uncertain too! Ha! Princes! hope breaks in!—This may not be! First COURTIER. Perhaps this Daniel is in league with Persia, And brib'd by Cyrus to report these horrors, To weaken and impede the mighty plans Of thy imperial mind! BELSHAZZAR. 'Tis very like. Second COURTIER. Return we to the banquet. BELSHAZZAR. Dare we venture? Third COURTIER. Let not this dreaming Seer disturb the king. Against the pow'r of Cyrus, and the Mede, Is Babylon secure. Her brazen gates Mock all attempts to force them. Proud Euphrates, A watry bulwark, guards our ample city From all assailants. And within the walls Of this stupendous capital are lodg'd Such vast provisions, such exhaustless stores, As a twice ten years siege could never waste! BELSHAZZAR. [Embraces him. My better genius! To the banquet then! [As they are going to resume their places at the banquet, a dreadful uproar is heard, tumultuous cries, and warlike sounds. All stand terrified. Enter soldiers, with their swords drawn, and wounded. SOLDIER. Oh, helpless Babylon! Oh, wretched king! Chaldea is no more, the Mede has conquer'd! The victor Cyrus, like a mighty torrent, Comes rushing on, and marks his way with ruin! BELSHAZZAR. Impossible! Villain and slave thou ly'st! Euphrates and the brazen gates secure us. While those remain Belshazzar laughs at danger. SOLDIER. Euphrates is diverted from its course, The brazen gates are burst, the city's taken, Thyself a pris'ner, and thy empire lost. BELSHAZZAR. Oh, Prophet! I remember thee too soon! [He runs out. They follow, in the utmost confusion. Enter several JEWS, MEDES, and BABYLONIANS. First JEW. He comes, he comes! the long predicted prince, Cyrus! the destin'd instrument of Heav'n, To free our captive nation, and restore Jehovah's Temple! Carnage marks his way, And conquest sits upon his plume-crown'd helm! First JEW. What noise is that? Second JEW. Hark! 'tis Belshazzar's voice! BELSHAZZAR. [Without. O Soldier! spare my life, and aid my flight; Such treasures shall reward the gentle deed, As Persia never saw! I'll be thy slave; I'll yield my crown to Cyrus, I'll adore His Gods and thine—I'll kneel and kiss thy feet, And worship thee—It is not much I ask— I'll live in bondage, beggary, and pain, So thou but let me live! SOLDIER. Die, tyrant die! BELSHAZZAR. O Daniel! Daniel! Daniel! Enter SOLDIER. SOLDIER. Belshazzar's dead! The wretched king breath'd out his furious soul In that tremendous groan. First JEW. Belshazzar's dead! Then, Judah! art thou free! The tyrant's fall'n! Jerusalem, Jerusalem is free!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PART III. Enter DANIEL and JEWS. DANIEL. Bel boweth down Isaiah, xlvi., and haughty Nebo stoops! The idols fall; the God and worshipper Together fall! together they bow down! Each other, or themselves, they cannot save. O, Babylon! where is thy refuge now? Thy wisdom and thy knowledge, meant to save, Pervert thee; and thy blessing is thy bane! Where are thy brutish deities, Chaldea? Where are thy gods of gold?—Oh, Lord of life! Thou very God! so fall thy foes before thee! First JEW. So fell beneath the terrors of thy name The idol Chemosh, Moab's empty trust; So Ammonitish Moloch sunk before thee: So fell Philistine Dagon; so shall fall, To time's remotest period, all thy foes! DANIEL. Not for myself, O Judah! but for thee, I shed these tears of joy. For I no more Must view the cedars which adorn the brow Of Syrian Lebanon; no more shall see Thy pleasant stream, O Jordan! nor the flocks Which whiten all the mountains of Judea. Nor Carmel's heights, nor Sharon's flow'ry vales. I must remain in Babylon! So Heav'n, To whose awards I bow me, has decreed. I ne'er shall see thee, Salem! I am old; And few and toilsome are my days to come. But we shall meet in those celestial climes, Compar'd with which created glories sink: Where sinners shall have pow'r to harm no more, And martyr'd virtue rests her weary head. Tho' ere my day of promis'd grace shall come, I shall be try'd by perils strange and new; Nor shall I taste of death, so have I learn'd, 'Till I have seen the captive tribes restor'd. First JEW. And shall we view, once more, thy hallow'd tow'rs, Imperial Salem? DANIEL. Yes, my youthful friends! You shall behold the second Ezra, chap. i. temple rise, With grateful ecstacy; but we, your sires, Now bent with hoary age; we, whose charm'd eyes Beheld the matchless glories of the first, Shou'd weep, rememb'ring what we once had seen, That model of perfection! Second JEW. Never more Shall such another structure grace the earth! DANIEL. Well have you borne affliction, men of Judah! Well have sustain'd your portion of distress; And, unrepining, drank the bitter dregs Of adverse fortune! Happier days await you. O guard against the perils of success! Prosperity dissolves the yielding soul, And the bright Sun of shining fortune melts The firmest virtue down. Beware, my friends, Be greatly cautious of prosperity! Defend your sliding hearts; and, trembling, think How those who buffeted affliction's waves With vig'rous virtue, sunk in Pleasure's calm, He Solomon., who of special grace had been allow'd To rear the hallow'd fane to Israel's God, By wealth corrupted, and by ease debauch'd, Forsook the God to whom he rais'd the fane, And, sunk in sensual floth, consum'd his days, In vile idolatrous rites!—Nor think, my sons, That virtue in sequester'd solitude Is always found. Within the inmost soul The hidden tempter lurks; nor less betrays, In the still, seeming safety of retreat, Than where the treach'rous world delusive smiles, Who thinks himself secure is half undone; For sin, unwatch'd, may reach the sanctuary: No place preserves us from it. Righteous Lot Stemm'd the strong current of corruption's tide, Ev'n in polluted Sodom; safe he liv'd, While circumspective Virtue's watchful eye Was anxiously awake: but in the shade, Far from the threat'ning perils which alarm With visible temptation, secret sin Ensnar'd him; in security he fell. Second JEW. Thy prudent counsels in our hearts shall live, As if a pen of adamant had grav'd them. First JEW. The dawn approaches; let us part, my friends, Secure of peace, since tyranny is fall'n! DANIEL. So perish all thine enemies, O Lord! So, mighty God! shall perish all, who seek Corrupted pleasures in the turbid waves Of life's polluted stream; and madly quit The living fountain of perennial grace!</field>
   </doc>
</add>