<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Boucicault, Dion, 1820-1890</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Boucicault, Dion, 1820-1890</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">boucicault dion 1820 1890</field>
      <field name="author_text">Boucicault, Dion, 1820-1890</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1940's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V3.0586.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1940</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460917</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Louis XI</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Louis XI</field>
      <field name="title_facet">louis xi</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">louis xi</field>
      <field name="title_text">Louis XI</field>
      <field name="year_display">1940</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1940</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1940</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460917&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460917&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Boucicault, Dion, 1820-1890&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;boucicault dion 1820 1890&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Louis XI&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;louis xi&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1940&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1940&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Boucicault, Dion&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1820&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1890&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Louis XI&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Princeton, New Jersey&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Princeton University Press&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1940&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3873259-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv30586&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 20th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;20th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Louis XI&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 165 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries, introductory and editorial matter omitted&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Louis XI.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1855.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 13 Jan 1855.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">LOUIS XI</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CAST OF CHARACTERS Louis XI, King of France Duke de Nemours The Dauphin Tristan L'Ermite, Grand Provost and Executioner Philip de Commine, the Historian Jacques Coitier, the King's Physician Oliver, the Barber Minister François de Paule Cardinal d'Alby Monseigneur de Lude Cranford, Officer of the Scottish Guard Marcel Peasant Richard Peasant Didier Peasant Count de Dreux Montjoie, Herald of France Toison d'Or, Herald of Burgundy Marie, Daughter of Philip de Commine Marthe, A Peasant French and Burgundian Lords, Guards, Priests, Pages, Courtiers, Citizens, Peasants, Etc.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. Exterior of the castle, Plessis-les-Tours. Tristan enters with the prevotal guard. Richard enters from hut. Trist. Thy name? Rich. Richard, the swineherd. Trist. Thy dwelling? Rich. There. Trist. The King forbids all egress at this hour. Rich. Death is beneath my roof. I seek a priest To thrive a fleeting soul. Trist. Back to thy kennel! Or else thy carrion swings on yonder oak To mark the wakeful justice of the King. Rich. My son— Trist. Obey! Rich. —is dying. Trist. Darest thou prate to Tristan? Rich. Tristan! Heaven preserve the King! [Exit. Enter Cranford with Scottish Guard] Officer. Halt! Who goes there? Trist. The Grand Provost. Officer. The countersign! Trist. Faithful! Officer. France! [Exeunt. Enter Philip de Commine] Com. The day shows faint and sickly in the east. Welcome, my only hour of calm repose, Robb'd from the body's rest to rest the mind. Hark, 'tis the watch-cry of the Scottish soldier Hired to defend yon Tours, and guard the life Of Louis, King of France. Château de Plessis— Tomb of a living King! Thy watch and ward, Thy lofty ramparts and thy deepest fosse Will never scare th'assassin who now seeks The life of Louis. Yet a few poor days He may dispute with death, and then—[Enter Coitier and Richard] Coit. Fear not; He sleeps. The danger now is past; he yet May live. [Exit Richard] Com. Coitier! Coit. Commine! Com. Dare you thus Neglect your duty to the King? Coit. The King—the King— Always the King! Com. His life from day to day hangs on your skill. Coit. My skill were well bestowed elsewhere. Com. Somewhat has angered you. Coit. Smother wanton crime. This swineherd's son Was wounded nigh to death last night. Forsooth He dared to linger near the castle walls Gaping in wonder at the gloomy pile. A Scottish archer from the battlement Transfixed him with an arrow. Com. Louis of this is innocent. Coit. The King who tolerates a crime commits it. Com. Thou art the only man who dares thus chafe him— But haste thee in—already he has waked And calls for Coitier. Coit. Let him call and bawl, And when he's tired he'll wait, 'tis well he should, Patience is a medicine he must gulp, 'Twill soothe his choler. Thus I can repay The sufferings he heaps on me. He hates me, Taunts me with lack of skill, and mocks my art— That's when he's well—but when from fever'd sleep By some avenging spectre he is chased, To me he cries for help. Coitier must wake; To Coitier is exposed his ulcered soul, Creeping with terrors and alive with crime. 'Tis then my turn to taunt, to jeer and mock! We change our parts; the tyrant I become, And he, the abject slave. Com. Thou art too hard Upon a dying man. Coit. 'Tis true he dies. But like a snake with all the venom quick And ready in his tooth, to the last pulse There's a murder in him. Com. Why, then, toil With all thy art to keep such crime alive? Coit. My mission is to heal, and not to judge. Com. Does not his abject fear of death move you To pity? Coit. Dost thou ask me For pity for the murderer of Nemours? Com. Nemours was guilty— Coit. 'Tis false! His only guilt Was his offensive goodness. Louis could bear No virtue save in a priest. Beneath his roof I passed my youth where I was born a serf. Nemours first lifted my intelligence, And bade me think. Sustained by him with hope I struggled on, and by his help became The wonder of the time. Nemours built up My fortune—yet when his own ebb'd fast, When he and his three children lay immured In the Bastille, Louis denied my prayer. Nemours, my master, benefactor, friend, Fell by the tyrant's axe. One child alone Was saved; aided by thee he was conveyed And hid away. Com. Coitier— Coit. I say by thee. Com. In Heaven's name speak lower! Coit. Then why say Nemours was guilty? Com. Be more just to me. I loved Nemours; and when he fell, did I Mourn idly? No! I sounded anxiously The King's intent, and found his thirst for blood Unslaked. The children of Nemours still lived; I roused them from their grief and bade them fly. The eldest only would be warned in time, And sought the shelter I had found For him with Charles of Burgundy. Coit. A welcome guest. If Charles the Bold should need an instrument Of cold, determined steel, there is the weapon, Steeped in the hideous poison of revenge, And hungry for the heart of Louis. Com. Such Was the Duke's design, but foiled ere ripe. My daughter Marie, then a child, was lodged Beneath the roof where I had placed Nemours; She was the sole companion of his exile. They grew to love; their union is agreed When Heaven shall bring back brighter days to France. Coit. You mean, when he is gone. Com. Who? Coit. He! Com. Beware! I hear footsteps. Coit. 'Tis Marie. Com. My child! No more, she might betray us. Coit. How! Dost fear her? Com. Not so—but hush, she comes. Coit. By Heaven, he has suspicions Of his own child. [Enter Marie] Marie. Ah! my father—good morning, sir. How fares the King? Coit. He is in his hour Of excellence—his only gentle mood. He sleeps. But whence that glow upon your cheek? Marie. The King last night bade me and Bertha rise Before the dawn and ride across the wood To watch the coming of the holy man, François de Paule, and quick to bring the news When from the distant spires the pealing chimes Rang out a joyful welcome—and each town, Village, castle and hut poured forth its life To greet the hermit. Coit. You have seen him, then, This anchorite, this miracle performer? Who by his intercession is to heal The ills of mind and body, and restore The King to youth and health? Marie. Dare you to doubt His power? Have you not heard his wond'rous deeds? Coit. Oh, yes, I have heard. Marie. Yet what simplicity! No sacerdotal pomp—no purple robe To command the homage of the eye; no crook Of gold he wields; no jewelled mitre gleams Upon his head; but neatly clad, not rudely; Modest, not vainly humble. A simple staff supports his aged limbs, And as he sheds his blessings on the crowd, His silvered brow is luminous with love And seems to radiate benevolence. Com. Yesternoon the Dauphin left Plessis To seek this hermit. Marie. They met François de Paule beyond Amboise; The Dauphin straight dismounted, and his train Walked by his side. The nobles laid apart Their weapons, and, bareheaded, prayed his blessing. Then high the people waved their fresh-hewn boughs And chanted hymns of praise. The peasant girls Strewed all the path with forest flowers; and thus To Plessis comes François de Paule. Com. Thou shalt awake the King with this good news. Marie. A word, my father. Com. Go, Coitier, do thou Announce these happy tidings to the King. Coit. Good news from Coitier? He will ne'er believe it. [Exit] Com. He is gone. Now tell me, Child, what happy secret O'erflows your eyes and flutters on your cheek. Marie. Can you not guess? Com. News from Peronne! Marie. The village Of Plessis is thronged with knights who bear The badge of Burgundy. Com. It is the envoy of the Duke. He comes Full-mouth'd with war. Louis has given aid And succor to the revolted Swiss. Even now A deputation from the Cantons here within Craves audience. On the Burgundian border, too, Brancas and Chabannes have by surprise Seized on the frontier citadels. For this Charles will demand most ample satisfaction. Didst learn this envoy's name? Marie. The Count de Rethel. Com. Rethel! I know there was an ancient house Long since extinct who bore that name, Rethel. Amongst the nobles of Peronne heard you Of such a one? Marie. Rethel? No! Com. Strange! Marie. I hoped This envoy might be bearer of some news From him. Com. Nemours? Marie. Nemours! Who knows; ere now He may have quite forgot Marie. Com. Nemours forget! Marie. In childhood it was I who sought Nemours, A cold, abstracted, silent youth, who fled The commerce of the court, its plays, its jousts; But did I speak Of Louis, his hand would grip his dagger hard; He gazed upon me, yet he knew me not. I chased away the drops of agony That beaded o'er his brow, but he felt not The tears I left there. Com. Hush! Another year Will give another king to France. Nemours may then return. Marie. Oh, were the gentle Dauphin on the throne He would not let me sue in vain. Nemours Would be recalled. Com. Marie, I have observed The Dauphin courts thy company. Marie. He does, Poor youth. Com. That youth one day will be a king. Marie. Must I for that avoid him when he comes To seek me; implores my aid to read The chronicles of France? Com. Enough! Enough! He is too old to learn from lips like thine, And thou too young to teach a guileless task! He loves thee. Marie. Father! Com. Avoid his company! Hark, they approach. Come, let's in. [Exit. Enter Peasants, François de Paule, Dauphin, Duke de Nemours, Nobles, Toison d'Or] Fran. Forbear, sweet Prince, and leave me here awhile To rest from weary state. Dauphin. Father, permit That I precede thee to the King, who craves Thy blessing. He will come forth, and to the dust Abase himself before thy saintly presence. My lords, attend me! [Exit] Female. Father, pity my child; he's sick to death, And 'tis my only one. Marc. Reason has fled My mother's brain; restore it ere she die That she may bless me. Rich. Enter my hut; Look on my dying son, and he will live. Fran. Arise, my children, from your knees. 'Tis thus Heaven only should be sought. Why look on me? I am a man most feeble and infirm, Bow'd down with age. Judge then, had I the powers You claim of me, should I be thus? Rich. Had I been noble, He had healed my son. Marc. But what are we?—Are we Deserving of a miracle? Nem. We are alone, my son— Alone with Heaven— For Heaven is with thee, my father. Fran. As with all Who put their trust therein. Nem. Beseech its mercy For one whose hours are numbered. Fran. Not for thine— No, thou art young; thy cup of life is full. Nem. Ay, full of blood, held by my father's spectre To my lips, and as I quaff, 'tis filled and filled From my murdered brother's gaping wounds. Fran. What would'st thou do? Nem. What is thy mission here? Fran. To comfort and console. What thine? Nem. To bear the vials of Heaven's wrath. Hard on the priest Cometh the headsman. Fran. These words are wild, my son. What ill design do they import? Reflect— Pause! Nem. Bless me, my father. Fran. Willingly, my son. Thou hast my blessing. But what shall it avail thee if thy heart Meditates evil? If thy thoughts are pure, Mercy will better plead for thee above Than my poor words. Yet I do bless thee. Fare thee well! May Heaven be thy guide. [Exit]</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. The Throne Room in the castle. Marie discovered. Enter the Dauphin. Dauphin. Marie! Marie. Your highness! [Rises] Pardon; I saw you not. Dauphin. And now you see me, does the sight repel And drive you from me? Marie. Ah, your highness, My service is commanded by the King. Dauphin. Stay! Marie. 'Tis late. Indeed I must— Dauphin. Remain, Marie, I pray you. I—command. Marie. Your highness, I obey. Dauphin. No, no, forgive me, Marie, You have my leave to go—yet do not go. Do as thou wilt—ay, leave me. Marie. In disgrace? Dauphin. There is a saying, “Happy as a king.” There might be one, “As wretched as a prince.” Marie. You wretched! Dauphin. Ay. My father hates me. Marie. Hush! Dauphin. Far from his thought or care, my childhood passed Within the gloomy walls of Amboise. There I grew as the wild flowers grew—unheeded, My only lesson was to fear the King, And tremble at his name. Marie. All his love and care Lie in his kingdom. Dauphin. Oh, that my kingdom were Some little, unregarded isle, and thou My only subject. Marie. 'Tis time I should begone. Dauphin. Stay! Goes the King forth today? Marie. He does. Dauphin. To hunt? Well, I will ride beside thee. Marie. No. Dauphin. What then? Marie. A pilgrimage. Dauphin. A pilgrimage? What for? Marie. My lord— Dauphin. I mean, to whom? Whither? Marie. The King Today will seek the village shrine hard by, The Chapel of St. Martin in the Woods, and there Will pass the vesper hour in prayer. Dauphin. I wish Thou wert a saint, then I would be devout. My father wears his saints about his cap, But I would wear thee in my heart. Marie. I must Begone. Dauphin. Stay yet—come hither—see what I have here. Marie. A book! Dauphin. And full of pictures. Look! Knights, combats, and great feats of arms! Marie. I tremble did the King suspect. How came You by it? Dauphin. I stole it from my uncle, Orleans. Come, let us read it. Marie. No! Dauphin. Why not? Marie. I fear. You know the King forbids that you shall read From any book but that which he himself Has writ for your instruction. Dauphin. Yes, I know, But his book is so stupid. Marie. Hush! A king Is never stupid. What is your book about? Dauphin. That you shall teach me. Come, sit here, and so Now if I mistake, correct me. [Reads] “The Chronicles of France, written in the year Of Grace—” There come figures. I will Skip the figures. Marie. For certain reasons. Dauphin. “Wherein there is recited all the feats of Arms of those most noble knights, Dunois, Lahire, And—and— Lahire, and—and—Du—du—Du—guess—” Marie. Dugueschin! Dauphin. Oh, what a hard word. Marie. Ay, but a great name. Dauphin. “And how the Realm of France, Being oppressed, was saved by The great prowess of a shepherd girl named Joan of Arc.” Marie. The Maid of Orleans! Dauphin. I know of her, And of another whom the late King loved, Agnes Sorrel. I have often thought That thou, Marie, shouldst resemble her. Marie. The mistress of a king. Dauphin. She might have been His Queen. Marie. I am too lowly born for that; Too nobly, to be the toy of any man. Dauphin. Then, when I am King I can, alas, in nothing shew my love For thee. Yet, take this ring. Marie. My lord— Dauphin. Take it, And come the day I may a service grant, Claim it by token of this ring; and here I pledge my knightly faith and royal word, What title, lands, or grace soe'er. Marie. Even should I pray you to recall An exile, and to grant him pardon? Dauphin. Him! Whom? Marie. One who pines, afar from home and kin. Dauphin. Ha! You love him. Marie. Ay. Dauphin. You love him. Marie! Give me back the ring. Marie. 'Tis here, my lord. Dauphin. No, retain it, it is thine. I did but jest. You love this exile—it is well. You hold His pardon, come what may. The Dauphin's word Shall by the King be faithfully redeemed. [Exit] Marie. The pardon of Nemours. [Enter Commine] Com. How now, Marie, That name upon your lips. Marie. You bade me check The Dauphin's suit. Com. What have you done? Marie. I have confessed my love and cast myself Upon a prince's generosity. Com. Imprudent girl! The rashness of your heart Will prove your lover's ruin. Marie. Father, list. Go sit beside the King, and deal out law To cure those ills that ail the commonweal, For thou'rt a very crafty councillor. But if thou wouldst preserve that high repute, Leave love alone! Or should the question start, Seek counsel of a fool and shut your eyes. Com. Away, and take thy folly with thee. Go! [Exit Marie] The Count of Rethel scarce arrived, demands An instant audience. I am bid to sound This proud Burgundian ere the council meet. He must be bought—but how? That rests with me What coin to offer—titles, gold, or laurels. [Enter Officer] Officer. The Count de Rethel. [Enter Nemours] Com. Nemours! Thou here, Nemours? Nem. Here then he lives; here in this naked tomb. Com. Hast thou forecast thy peril? Knowest Thou the very echoes here are spies; the stones Are traitors? Nem. Fitting palace for a king! As I approached the walls, I saw the track Of Tristan's gory footsteps. The very river Blushed for its human burthen; each tree bent, Shame bowed, with its unnatural quiet. The air Is clogged with death. Com. And yet you came. Nem. Confiding in your faith, your love. The secret of my name is known to you, Marie, And Coitier. Which of ye will betray me? Com. None, none! Nem. Think you the King will recognize in me The child, who only once stood in his presence, When I and my two brothers were thrust forth Beneath the scaffold where our father fell? Com. Why seek him now whose hand Has crushed thy race? The Duke did ill to send thee here, Nemours; Another would have served his end as well. Nem. Louis had bribed another; but in me, Charles in his wrongs, in hate, in person—all Is represented. Like me, alone survivor Of his house—like me too, by a murder left An orphan without home or kin. Com. Nemours, who knows thy wrongs so well as I. But is there no soft word that can disarm Thy wrath? Marie— Nem. Marie! Com. Listen, my son, France is thy home, thy country; for her sake Forget thy wrongs. Louis and Charles are foes, But thou canst make them friends, and thus at once Canst salve the country's wounds, and heal thine own. Thy titles, lands and home will be restored; The King will pardon and forget. Nem. Forget! He will forget! What do I hear? Forget That night of crime—the victim of the block— Three children made to kneel beneath the scaffold, Clothed all in white as if beneath a shrine, Assisting at a joyous ceremony. Sudden, The sound of footsteps came, and then a voice. 'Twas his, my father's; he was murmuring A prayer he taught me. Then he spoke my name, And those of my two brothers. “My poor children! Heaven shield my helpless children.” Then he prayed Again; and then, silence—no more. No more! Stretching my arms towards him in the gloom, As I would kiss him for his prayer, I felt What seemed to be his tears, that drop by drop Fell on my face. His tears! No, no! Those eyes Could shed no more. They were no tears that fell. Com. Nemours! Nem. 'Twas blood! 'Twas blood! My father's blood! Forget! He may, that king who watched the deed, And saw the stream, which still flows here, let out My father's life. He may forget; I never! Com. Nemours, be calm; they come. Nem. Oh, fear me not. In presence of my foe thou'lt see Who best can play the master. [Exit] Com. Perdition seize the Duke. Why hath he sent This frenzied youth to raise the foul fiend here? How finely has my mission been achieved! When Louis asks me what report I bring, What shall I say? [Enter an Officer] Officer. His majesty the King! [Enter Louis, Oliver, Coitier, Tristan, Count de Dreux, Courtiers and Citizens] Louis. Look to't, Sir Count, look to't. Let me but hear A murmur from people, and my hand Is on ye. My doubts confirmed, I send you straight To Heaven for mercy. Therefore make you up Betimes, the budget of your soul, d'ye hear? As for your body, that I'll see to. Count. Sire, might I— Louis. Ay, ay! My people you'll depress, Exacting more from them than I, their King. My people and myself are one; the least of them Is part of me; touch 'em, and you raise your hand Against my royal person. This you have done. Count. Dread sire— Louis. You have! I beg you beg from these, My friends, good honest citizens of Tours, Five hundred crowns for me—raised two thousand; Robbing them and me—me most especially. Why, look on me; upon this king you count at nought. Am I dead? Ha! Or quick? Look, man, look up! I'm not so near the grave as some may think. You're paler, Count, than I. Why, by my faith, You die first now. Have you an heir? Count. [To Coitier] Save me—interpose—in mercy! Coit. Ho, sire, come! Enough of this. You must not yield to anger; 'Tis hurtful. Louis. True! But I am well today; I may indulge. The sight of that good Saint François de Paule has quite refreshed my life. Coit. Dismiss me then, and trust to him. But still This useless rage and vengeful eye, methinks, As little do become the Christian sire As the invalid. Louis. Coitier! Coit. Oh, do not waste Big words on me. You're wrong. Louis. Coitier! Coit. Yes, wrong, and I am right. See now, why look The mischief's done; your Face is changed already. Louis. Eh, what! Is't changed, indeed? Coit. Ay, is't. Louis. Well, then, I'll be more calm. Coit. Oh, not on my account, go on. Suffer And die. 'Tis your affair. Louis. There, there, now, Coitier. Coit. You're the King. Louis. Come, come. Coit. Why, do then as you list, But afterwards, don't come to me complaining. Louis. There, good Coitier, there, forgive me. So, Look now, Sir Count, hark ye! What you have ta'en From these good folk restore within three days, For that's the price I put upon your head. Which, if it suit you, well. If not, I'll take it; But without anger—to which I am forbade As being hurtful. Count. Sire, I submit. Louis. You hear? How say ye, am I my people's champion? Ha! Oliver, thou'lt see these fifteen hundred crowns Repaid. 'Twas he denounced yon traitor from the start. You'll freely give my faithful Oliver Five hundred crowns—that is, if he accept. Oliver. Sire! Louis. He refuses. Oliver. No; I say your word is law. Louis. A thousand crowns remain. But there's My faithful Coitier. Coit. No! I'll none of it. Louis. He will. Press him. So, that's settled. Now let's on to State affairs. Speak, Oliver. Oliver. My liege, the deputation of the Swiss await. Louis. Let 'em begone! Oliver. Unheard? Com. Your majesty Has recognized their rights, their liberties. Louis. Their liberties! I hate the word, freedom. What next Will they demand, these chamois hunters? Ha! What is their country worth? Com. The Duke of Burgundy Can tell. They make good head against his grace. Louis. Let them begone. The Count de Rethel else Would charge us with their entertainment. No! You bear me witness, all, I bid them go Unheard. [Aside to Oliver] Treat with them. Oliver. How? Louis. You know—you know! Give the least they'll take, and promise all They ask. Oliver. Enough! Louis. [Aloud] Shall I take part with them Against my cousin, Burgundy? Foster rebellion? No! Let them have hospitality, no more, And their good speed. [To Oliver] Ply 'em with wine, d'ye hear? The Swiss drink hard; You'll catch them in their cups. Oliver. Ne'er fear me, sire. Louis. How now, my good Commine! Say, have you seen that envoy, ha? Com. Ay, sire. Louis. Well—well—eh? Com. I find him incorruptible. Louis. Bah! Com. My liege— Louis. I tell you, no. Com. He's honest. Louis. Then you confess That you have bid too little. I must see to't. Go—bring him here. We will receive him now. Com. If I may venture to advise your majesty, Avoid this audience. Louis. Tut, man, go do my bidding. [Exit Commine. Enter Marie] Come hither, truant, let me sun myself Beneath thy smiles. How fares our saintly guest? Marie. I scarce have left him, sire. Louis. The odor of his sanctity still clings to thee. Tell me, what miracle has he performed already? Marie. Not one, sire. Louis. No! He garners up his power To let the fullness of it fall on me. But hark! the Dauphin greets the envoy of the Duke. They come. Leave us, sweet gossip, leave us. Marie. My liege, I would entreat your leave to stay. Louis. Know you this Count de Rethel? Marie. No. Louis. Indeed! You must Have seen him at the court of Burgundy? Look where he comes. Marie. Ah! Louis. Ha! How now? Marie. 'Tis he. I leave you, sire. [Aside] It is Nemours! Louis. What's this? She's troubled. Ha! I'll fathom this. Begone! [Exit Marie. King ascends the throne] Mont. The envoy of The most high and mighty Prince Charles, Duke of Burgundy and Flanders, Heralded by Toison d'Or, humbly entreats your majesty To grant him audience. Louis. Admit the Count. Tristan, be on your guard. Close round me, gentlemen. [Enter the Dauphin and Commine. Flourish] Louis. Largesse to Toison d'Or. How now, Sir Count, Our presence troubles you; you tremble and look pale. Nem. If so, it is with anger, sire. The wrongs That bear me here are ocean wide, and though I fain would curb them, still you see they burst And foam upon my face. Louis. Out with them, then. Let us hear them. Nem. Right speedily you shall. Know then, that my most puissant lord, Duke Charles Of Burgundy, first peer of France and sovereign prince— Louis. Enough, I know the states and vassals of my crown. Pass to the facts. Nem. To you, then, King of France, His brother and ally, he sends me in his name To charge thee with foul breach of faith and treaty. Louis. Ha! Nem. You have consorted with his foes, the Swiss, Sending them secret aid; and even now You entertain their chiefs within these walls. Louis. I have not seen 'em; bear me witness, all. They are dismissed unheard. Now, sir, what more? Nem. This much! Lords of Brancas and Chabannes Have crossed our frontiers, and by treachery Surprised and seized upon our citadels. Louis. If this be so, these lords must bear the blame; 'Twas done against my will. Nem. Give me a proof. Louis. Agreed! Nem. Ay, sire, but prompt, and on the spot. Louis. Well—well? Nem. Their punishment! Louis. Sir Count, you ask too much. Would this be fair? Should I condemn these lords Unheard? Nem. Oh, sire, your ever-ready axe Ere now has fall'n for less than this On nobler heads than theirs. Louis. Ay? Whose head? Nem. Heaven knows, And when your hour of judgment comes, He who condemns will shew it ye. Louis. Your head is in my power. Nem. Why, take it, then, but first Attend, for you shall hear my message out. Louis. Ha! Charles the Bold is represented well. He never merited that name till now! How say ye, gentlemen? Pursue, Sir Count, pursue. Nem. Hear me then, Louis of Valois, and you, Most noble knights and lords of high estate. Duke Charles, whose wrongs this paper doth set forth, Demands and will have justice; or by me declares The Lion Banner of great Burgundy, unloosed For every duchy, barony and fief He holds in vassalage from thee; he now Casts off his fealty—Avenger of the past! He doth invoke in aid that ghostly train Of murdered peers whose blood anoints his cause. Their champion, Charles the Bold of Burgundy, As knight thine equal, and as prince thy foe, In single combat will this quarrel try With thee or thine. In proof, there lies his gage. Lift it who dare. Dauphin. That do I For Valois and for France. All. I—I—sire! Louis. Ha! Well done, brave sirs, and he my son, the first Amongst them all—so young—so brave. 'Tis well He is a child of France. Dauphin. My father— Louis. So—so—enough! Here, Toison d'Or, take back This glove. [To Nemours] And thou, to whom in mercy I restore it, thank my clemency Which doth exceed thy madness. But I esteem thy boldness as fidelity. We will confer in council on this matter, And, as Heaven guide us, we'll do right and justice. Today, after our pious pilgrimage, And in the presence of our saintly guest, François de Paule, This treaty shall be canonized. Till then I must resign my heart to prayer, And in my own misdeeds ease thought off thine. [Exit Nemours with escort] Louis. Commine! Tristan! Com. You would not be advised. Louis. I like these angry folk, one sees them all At once. This treaty must be signed. Com. How, sire! Louis. That seems a grave mistake, eh, gossip, eh? Com. Most grave, sire. Louis. When with pen and ink you make An error, have I not seen you scratch it out? Com. Ay, sire. Louis. Ay, with a knife—go to, then, gossip— If I make a blot, I'll use the knife, But not till then. Marked you the Dauphin? Com. Ay, I did, my liege. Louis. His royal blood o'erflowed. Com. What princely valor! Louis. Ay, he might prove dangerous If he rebelled. Com. Oh, sire! Louis. Ay, ay, I know. I know How much a royal son can do against a king. I was A dauphin once. Tell me—ha! This Count de Rethel knows Marie? Com. My daughter, sire? Louis. Reply! Com. I know not, sire. When she resided at the Court of Charles, Amongst the noble youths who sought her, she— Louis. Distinguished him. Speak man! Com. Sire, I did hear, To Marie's beauty— Louis. Ay, ay, ay! Com. He was not insensible. Louis. He loves. You know it, and you said That he was incorruptible. Go, go, my good Commine, Go! I'll know the truth from her. [Exit Commine] Tristan! Trist. Ay. Louis. Come hither. Trist. I am here. Louis. Nearer. Trist. So. Louis. Nearer. Trist. Speak low; I'll listen with my eyes. Louis. Well, gossip, ha! You heard this haughty vassal? Trist. Ay. Louis. I pardoned him. Trist. You said so—umph! Louis. And I did right. Trist. The King can do no wrong. Louis. I sign this treaty, yet if Heaven decree Some dire reverse to Charles—perhaps defeat— Trist. And Heaven send it soon, that same decree. Louis. That's an unchristian wish—a wicked wish. Trist. It is an honest one. Louis. Still, if mishap Befall the Duke, were it so well, d'ye think This treaty should arrive in Burgundy? Trist. The Count is in your power. Louis. How! Violate His sacred office? No, let us respect The laws of nations. Trist. Oh! Louis. I can allow Nothing to happen—here. Trist. How then regain The treaty if you let him go? Louis. Can't I Provide him with a trusty escort? Trist. Ay, you must. To do him honor, protect him to the frontier. Louis. Ay, gossip, as you say, To do him honor. Trist. Who will command the troop? Louis. I thought of thee, eh? Trist. Oh—of me! And how Shall I compose it? Louis. As thou wilt. Trist. I see. Fellows I can trust. Louis. Ay! So! Trist. And numerous. Louis. Double his band—to do him honor. Trist. Good! It shall be done. Louis. And then, d'ye hear, who knows When in some lonely wood— Ha! What's that? The Angelus? [Bell rings] Trist. Ay, sire. Louis. Who knows, when in some lonely wood, A cause of quarrel may arise? Trist. It shall. Louis. Your people, by his guards insulted. Trist. Ay. I'll see it done. Louis. You will defend yourselves. Trist. We will. Louis. And so, you may regain the treaty. Trist. Ay, but then, the Count— Louis. The Count? How dull you are. Trist. Heh! Must I— Louis. Ah! you smile, old friend. You understand me, then. Trist. I comprehend.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. An open spot in the wood near the castle, Plessis-les-Tours. A village fête. Music. Marcel, Didier, Richard and Villagers, Male and Female. Dancing groups about the stage. Marthe. [C.] Who knows how the King fares today? Marcel. [L.] No worse—no better. Marthe. A King, it seems, is very long a-dying. Marcel. The place is such a good one. Marthe. Who can tell why Master Tristan bade us here? The chapel is Prepared; the altar decked with flowers, and we have orders To assemble here to sing and dance. Didier. And be most joyful. Marcel. Ay, on pain of death. Rich. Beware! I hear a footstep. Didier. 'Tis Master Oliver. Marcel. The Barber Minister. Quick, to your places! Strike music! [They dance and sing. Enter Oliver] Oliver. Good—this is well! Sing—dance—be happy! Marcel. You see, my lord, we can't be happier. When once the Grand Provost said, “Be joyful,” we know there's No excuse. Oliver. Well done. Proceed! Perhaps the King May venture out amongst ye. Didier. The King! Rich. Here? Marthe. Amongst us? Oliver. Why not? Why do ye recoil? Marcel. 'Tis the—the—joy—I feel when I hear his name. I feel a—a—respect for him that makes my blood run cold. Oliver. When he comes, you will speak to him, but freely, gaily— Marcel. I speak—a—gaily? Noble sir, I am of a sad temper, But here is Richard who sings an excellent song, let him speak. Rich. No, you, Didier. Didier. Me? Marthe. I'll do it. What am I to say? Oliver. Open your hearts, and tell him all you think. Marthe. I have it! I will let him know we hate his Scottish guard. All. Ay! Ay! Didier. And how our crops are ravaged by his game. All. Ay! Ay! Oliver. How now? What insolence is this? Marthe. Pardon, sir, you bade us tell him all we think. Marcel. That's true! Tell us, sir, what is our opinion? Oliver. You love your king. Marthe. We'll think so. Oliver. Like a father. Marcel. I never thought of that till now. Oliver. Tell him so—speak frankly—raise his spirits with Your rude and rustic merriment. Laugh loud, and if he jest— Marcel. Eh? Oliver. Reply in sort, and keep his humor up. Hush! Here he comes. All. Where? Marcel. What? That old, decrepit man? Oliver. Decrepit! Fool, do you prize your head? He is in excellent good health. Marcel. Yes, sir, I see now. So he is. Oliver. Sing, dolt! Marcel. [Sings rather trembling a line of the previous melody] Oliver. Louder! Quick, be gay! Sing, all of ye, and dance. It is the King! [They do so. Louis enters, leaning on Tristan, and followed by Scottish archers who remain at back. Goes to back and sits. Oliver creeps over to him. The peasants gaze in terror] Louis. The sun is fierce today; the air is heavy; it weighs upon Me, and yet the air of France used to be pure. Methinks the Climate must have changed since I was young. Oliver. It has been so remarked, sire. Louis. Ah Oliver. Oliver. Look, sire. These peasantry were happily Engaged here as you came; join in their gaiety. Speak to them. They do not Recognize you. Louis. I will. I'll play the King incognito. Oliver. This noble lord would speak with you, come near. Louis. Aha! Come hither, rosy face. Marthe. Please you, sir. Louis. Bounty of nature! You deserve a prize for Health. How came you by it? Marthe. How? Hi—hi—hi! Louis. Ah! How? Marthe. It comes by stealth, I know not how, no more Than why the grape grows. Perhaps it comes from heaven By night, fattening the heart with happy dreams. Louis. But you have sorrows? Marcel. Why—ay. Life has its changing weathers, sir. All is Not sunshine. But sorrows come like rain; they freshen up A man. Sorrow's a good providence. Marthe. And a light heart flows over it. The hardest lot Can always find some wretch to covet it. Marcel. There's cousin Mallard owes five quarters' rent. That comforts me who only owe a half. Louis. [To Oliver] These wretches find a cause of happiness In everything. But when disease arrives, and strikes ye down? Marcel. Ah, when our sheep have got the rot. Louis. Nay, your own mortal sickness. When you behold Your substance lavished upon doctors? Marcel. We're no such fools. Doctors, forsooth! When I am sick, I draw a horn of wine, And laugh at 'em. Who pays a doctor robs his son And heir. When a man's due, death lays his hand On him, and never asks a doctor's leave. Louis. You speak of death as if you feared it not. Marcel. I do believe death is not near so bad As folks would make it. 'Tis a bad life that makes Death so dreadful. When I behold a train Of weeping mourners, and think that he they follow is Preceded by a black account of crime, ill-gotten wealth, Murders— Louis. Oh! Marcel. Then death alone has terrors. The bearers of the dead Seem fiends. Louis. Perdition! Marcel. Then fear I death. Yet why, I know not, for I never wronged my neighbors, nor shed fellow creature's blood. Louis. Begone! Marcel. What have I said? Oliver. Idiot! Louis. Death—hell—eternal torture! Heaven pity, help me! Hence! No, come answer me. Who bid thee, wretch, To speak these words to me? Marcel. Nobody. Nobody. Louis. Thou'rt paid to do it. Speak! Marcel. No, as I live. Marthe. Not he, sir, there's no harm in him. I'll warrant him— He's but a fool. Marcel. A downright, well known fool, sir. Ask all the neighbors. Louis. I did but jest. He's your husband, then? Marthe. I would not ask a better. Louis. Then you shall earn his pardon. Marthe. That will I. How? Louis. He says he has no sorrow. I will provide him one. He, he! Hark! With such a buxom air, those ruby lips And sparkling eyes, you must have lovers in the village On the sly. Name them! Marthe. Lovers, sir? Not I! Louis. Take care; his pardon hangs on it. Marcel. Name them all, Marthe; as you love me, out with Their names—I'm deaf! Marthe. Well, if I had a choice— Louis. Ay, ay? Marthe. Amongst the men I've seen, I'd choose— Louis. Who? Who? Marthe. You! Louis. Me! He, he! Marthe. Be quiet. Louis. Would you fear an old hunks like me? Marthe. Not so old neither; you've a sly look. Louis. [Aside to Marthe] Good, good! Marthe. A sturdy form. Louis. He, he! Marthe. A fool would be the maid would trust you. Louis. You think so? Marthe. I only wish our good old king had such an air, And bore his years as well. Louis. What, what? Marthe. Then for his precious life we'd have no fear, For you will live to see a hundred years. Louis. A hundred years! You love your king? Marthe. Love him? Ay, do we all. France has but one voice, And you have heard it. Oliver. There, sir, you can't accuse them of flattery. Louis. A hundred years, that I shall live to see. [Kisses her] The King thus thanks you for your prophecy. Marthe. The King! All. Long live the King! Louis. Good souls, good souls! For France and myself I thank ye. Ah, I shall see a hundred years. For every year of that good Wish, here is a crown. Take these jewels; take 'em all. Go sing, dance, drink, pledge me good health—long life. Drink To my hundred years! Marcel. I shall tell everyone the money I have received. Marthe. Yes, and I shall tell how I have received Two kisses from the King. All. Long live the King! [Shout and exit U. E. L. H.] Louis. 'Tis sweet to be thus loved. Oliver. And when the avowal comes from hearts that know Not how to feign. Louis. A hundred years! Did you mark, Oliver? Oliver. These common people predict with wondrous truth. Louis. You jest, gossip. Oliver. Not I. Louis. Her words agree with my nativity. My horoscope portends I shall outlive my foes. Oh, life, life! Let me but live To see these sores of France, these sovereign vassals Levelled to the herd. Their lands, their crowns, Their very pride I would escheat to swell The royal power, till there should be in France But one estate—the people. Ay, all people— Except me! Oliver. Blessed hour! Louis. Let me secure my cousin, Charles the Bold of Burgundy, And in a good stout coffin see him cribbed, and then, my Well beloved subjects, ye great dukes of Burgundy shall never Chaffer with the knight of France for right or privilege. But hush, he lives. Tell me, this Count of Rethel, has he Seen Marie? Oliver. Not yet, sire. Louis. So. Bid him come hither. [Shouts “Long live the Dauphin!”] What shouts are these? Oliver. It is the Dauphin, sire. The people greet the Prince. Louis. Their love is too profuse; it worries me. He is not yet Their king. He comes—begone! [Exit Oliver into the chapel. Enter the Dauphin] How now, what mean these transports? Dauphin. Sire, the people crowded on my path, invoking blessings on me. I was moved to tears. Louis. Tomorrow you return to Amboise. Dauphin. So soon? Louis. So, you would taste of popularity, The people's breath! 'Tis a foul poison, Prince. To win their voices, throw but a crown or two, and while they Fight for 'em, they'll cry ye deaf. You deemed their shouts Were hearty? Eh! 'Twas I who bade 'em do't. They had Been paid for't. Dauphin. How! 'Twas ordered? Louis. Ay; by me. Dauphin. Oh, sire! Louis. Now let this be a lesson, so—begone and meditate upon it. Dauphin. What have I done? Louis. Thou? Nothing! What dared? What could you do? Dauphin. Alas, not even please you, sire. And yet— Louis. What? Dauphin. I dare not. Sire—my liege—my father— If you could grant me your love. Louis. How! What it seems that I do not love you, heh? Dauphin. Oh, pardon, sire. Louis. I hate you? So! So! I am a savage, an inhuman father. This Has been prompted; 'tis not of your thought. Who told you This? Ha, 'twas your uncle, Orleans. Come, Charles, my son, Tell me in confidence, who was it? Dauphin. My uncle once did say that France sooner or later must Own me for its master. Louis. [Aside] Ah, the traitor! And said he not that old and sick I must ere long—I—Ha! 'tis false! And then he said the Crown was well-nigh in your grasp. Dauphin. Oh, sire. Louis. 'Tis false again! Does its weight make me bow? I tell ye, Boy, another diadem, and yet a third heaped on this wrinkled Front, would lighter sit than that same silken cap upon thy Baby brow. Dauphin. My father, live—live long; it is my only prayer—my hope Beneath your sway, may France grow great, and if my days Could serve to lengthen yours, I'd pray that Heaven may take Me in my youth, and add my life to thine. Louis. My son, my son, this is weak. Begone! [Dauphin exits] That's a good son who still perhaps deceives his father. [Enter Marie from chapel] Ah, 'tis she. Come here, child. What brave attire! Thou Never hast thy beauty thus enshrined for me. Marie. You bade us to a ceremony where I thought— Louis. To meet some cavalier. Marie. I do not understand you, sire. Louis. Your cheek does. Well, let's speak of something else. You Shall be secret, yet if there be a thing I love, 'tis to make Young lovers happy. Marie. You are a great king, sire. Louis. Ay, I know some newly married folk that say as much. I hoped I could have lent my aid to thee, but since you love not— Marie. I, sire? Louis. Let us speak of something else. Marie. But—what then did you think? Louis. Come, sit you here. I thought that at the Court of Charles Some brave and handsome cavalier—what more natural—had Touched your heart. I saw him, as I thought, at your feet— A noble youth—let's see, should he be noble? Marie. Oh, yes, sire, noble and most unhappy. Louis. True! A count! And then I dreamt this swain, so lost in love Was he, that in the guise of envoy came to see this fair. Marie. Oh, Heaven! Louis. Nay, had arrived today, and even had my royal word obtained To sign— Marie. A treaty! Louis. And a marriage bond. Marie. And you—you, sire? Louis. Methought that I consented—but 'tis false. 'Tis all dreams. Marie. You know then, sire? Louis. Let's speak of something else. Marie. 'Tis true! Oh, pardon— Louis. Ah, you have secrets from me. I will be revenged. Marie. Pardon—I ask it on my knees. Who had betrayed him? Louis. Who? Commine. Marie. My father! He has told you all, and you forgive? Louis. I do. Marie. Nemours— Louis. [Aside] Ah, 'tis Nemours! Marie. Ah, give me leave, my liege, to fly to him and join my Hopes to his; To bless your royal name, and mingle prayers for your prosperity. Louis. Not for his life. Hark, he believes himself unknown. Ha, ha! Thy father and myself have planned a plot, see? I'm a traitor For I let it out. Well, we have planned the moment and the Place to lift the mask from this impostor's brow. Marie. Oh, sire! Louis. You know I love my jest. Come, then, and swear to me by all Thy hopes of heaven and love, never this matter to divulge. Marie. I promise, sire. Louis. Upon that silence rests thy lover's life, which I have sworn To spare. Redeem thine oath, and I'll remember mine. [Aside] Nemours! And in my grasp! A word, a look and he is dead. But what may then ensue? I'll think on't. Tristan! [Tristan enters] Adieu, dear child, adieu! [Exit] Marie. Must I not speak? Oh, treason to my love. Must I then have A joy which he has not? No, it will overflow, as now it does At these rebellious eyes. Yet he will come. A word I sent Him by my page will guide him hither. Ah, a footstep! To its tread my heart keeps time. 'Tis he! [Enter Nemours] Nemours! Once more we meet, and, as I oft foretold we should, Beneath our native sky. Nem. Look on me; let me not see beyond thine eyes, nor roam beyond Thy heart. Speak to me, and let me hear thy voice. Marie. I have one theme, and that is all my language. Hope, Nemours; I speak and bid thee hope. Thy fortune still is in the royal Hand that plucked it from thee. By another word, the voice That banished thee may bid thee back. Nem. I see a meaning in your eyes, Marie, that overtakes thy tongue. Marie. I dare not tell thee more. Already I have said too much. Hush! See! [Procession advances from the chapel] The chapel doors unclose; they come! Farewell! [She separates from him. Enter the Burgundians. Nemours joins them. As Marie advances towards the chapel, Louis, François, Oliver, Tristan, the Cardinal, d'Alby, Craven, Commine, Priests and Courtiers appear on the steps. Louis holds the treaty in his hands] Louis. There ends unholy strife. Bear witness, Heaven, I do approve And sign the bond of peace. The Count de Rethel hath his Mission done with haughty menace, which I had avenged did I Not hold my people's happiness above my pride. Nem. He who can read the human heart doth know how much of it Is on thy tongue. Not for myself I speak, but in The name of him I serve. Duke Charles now holds His wrongs atoned, and justice done. Louis. To Charles of Burgundy, my dear ally, before these holy symbols And in sight of Heaven, I swear most solemnly this bond To keep most unviol—[Enter Dauphin hastily followed by Dunvis and de Lude] Dauphin. Hold! Oh, hold, my father! Louis. How now? Dauphin. News, news, my liege, of moment. Pardon! There has arrived a Despatch from Burgundy—a messenger who brings the tiding. Charles, thy foe— Louis. My foe! Charles, my brother—my ally! Dauphin. Has been defeated. Louis. How? How say ye? Speak! Dauphin. I say defeated—utterly undone—and lost! Nem. Charles— Louis. Art sure of this? Dauphin. The lords of Loucy, Dunvis, and de Lude assure it true. One of his captains did betray his cause. Louis. Ah, the coward! Nem. This is a false report, which soon a glowing triumph will belie. Charles the Bold— Dauphin. He's dead. Louis. Dead? Dead? The proofs! Dauphin. They are here. [Hands Louis despatches] Nem. Duke Charles defeated—dead. 'Tis false, and Count de Rethel With my life maintains— Louis. 'Tis true—Duke of Nemours. Dauphin and All. Nemours! Nem. Betrayed! Louis. Ay! True it is—impossible. See you now, Heaven's vengeance Has overtaken him, as sure as mine shall now find thee. Secure him! Nem. [Drawing sword] Death—treachery! A rescue! Burgundy! Louis. [Retreating] Upon them, France! Fran. Hold, in Heaven's name, whose temple you profane. Nem. Put up your weapons, gentlemen, and yield. This is my cause Alone. Alone I'll fall. If Charles still lives, the terror Of his name will better aid me than your bravery. If he be dead, alone I'll follow him. [Casts sword at King's feet] To meet thee, I had need like thee to feign. For my design, I'll render an account above. Cast thou unto my father's Murderers another prey, but there is one delight you cannot Have—I have no son, no brother, no not even a friend whom Thou canst force to kneel beneath my scaffold to receive the Blood that thou wilt shed. Louis. Tristan! Tonight, his judgment, and at daylight, the rest. Fran. Have pity, sire; thou art a king. Louis. Ay, as a King, my father, I might pardon, but I am The Church's head; he hath insulted her, and to approach Those sacred relics there with sacrilegious—Oh, I will Avenge! Go, prepare his soul. Fran. And thine, my son. Dost give no thought to that? [Exit with his train] Louis. Montjoie, St. Denis—ha! Demois, gather six hundred spears— Ride for Peronne, to Arras, Baudrecourt with all the force You can. Let Artois ere one month be France. Down upon Flanders, you. Burgundy is ours! I give it ye as spoil. Seize what and where you can, and rend the soil amongst ye. Counties and fiefs—for all who win shall wear 'em. But hold! Hold ye awhile! The noble duke has met a hero's fate. He Was my foe, but all my wrongs are hid and buried in his tomb. He was my cousin. The court will wear full mourning for a Week.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT IV. The King's bedchamber. Enter Coitier followed by Nemours. Coit. Come in, my son, thou art in safety here. Nem. Good Coitier. Coit. Look on me, Nemours, and let me trace The features that I love upon thy face. Methinks thy father smiles upon me now. Nem. The likeness ends not there—the same dire fate Awaits his son. Coit. By Heaven, it shall not be. I'll guard thy life; Ay, with my own. Fear not this toothless wolf. Nem. Yet I am caged—these bars—this gloomy cell. It is a prison still. Coit. 'Tis the King's bedchamber. Nem. This? Coit. This. Behold yon relics! See how they are worn by his Impassioned kisses—A poignard—he dares not touch, Yet fain would always have beside him. There His bed, where he would hide in vain his terrors. Nem. Why have you brought me here? Coit. The King desires to speak to you. Nem. Alone? Coit. He dares not. No, he'll come surrounded by his Myrmidons. Nem. What would he with me? Coit. Thou art beloved by all the chiefs and citizens Of Burgundy; the idol of the soldiers; thy Friends command in all the citadels. I told The King that on thy bidding, Artois would submit And Flanders yield a bloodless victory. Nem. Thou said'st so, Coitier? Coit. The remedy's extreme, I own it, but thy peril— Nem. How! Betray—despoil my benefactor, Charles? For whom? the headsman of my race? No! Never! It Were a murder of my father's memory, a burial Of his wrongs alive. Coit. Nemours, thou art resolved? Nem. To die, if't must be so. Coit. Behold this dungeon! 'Tis the sole retreat Where I am master. When I bound myself The tyrant's slave, not all his wealth could buy My ministry, had he not yielded me my liberty And right of free egress. See! See! This key opens The postern gate. Take it. It was my freedom, Now 'tis thine. Nem. But then—his vengeance! Coit. Tut—he suffers. Nem. His rage when my escape is known! Coit. He suffers. Fear not, I know him well. Away! Stay! Take this dagger—descend the spiral stair, A vaulted passage leads to the moat— Then a few steps—a door that key provides For—then the open fields, the wide free heaven And liberty, Nemours. Nem. Give me the dagger. Coit. There! Now, go! Begone! I hear a step! It is The King. Away! I fly to meet him. Speed! Speed, while I retard his coming. [Exit] Nem. My liberty! No, Coitier, no! Thou hast bestowed a Treasure still more priceless. Revenge! [Conceals himself. Enter Louis, Commine, Marie, Tristan and Coitier] Coit. Believe me, sire, the air will do you good. Louis. No, no, 'tis cold; see how I quake. [Aside] Where is Nemours? Coit. You are in pain, sire. Louis. Ay, in every limb it leaves me no repose; the Very air is like a serpent's tooth. Oh, endless, Endless death! Nemours—what said he? Coit. There, sire, warm your starved limbs. Louis. Ah, ah, a fire! Marie. Sit here. May it revive you, sire. Louis. Why cannot thy young and glowing heart give Heat and life to mine? Come, smile. Com. [Aside to Marie] Courage, Marie; obey. Marie. Alas, I am unable. [Weeps] Louis. Tears! You sadden me. Go, or cease weeping. I can repair The past—cure everything. Marie. And will you, sire? Louis. Ay, and I will. [To Coitier] Nemours— Coit. Be bidden, sire, for once to bed. Louis. Not yet. [To Tristan] Where is Nemours? Go bring him here. Trist. You know he is no longer in my keeping. Louis. He is in thine. [To Coitier] Trist. He was my due—judged and condemned. I love to finish All that I begin. Marie. Ah, father! Com. Hush! Louis. True, true! Thou, Coitier, hast him. Why is he not here? Coit. Because he would not come. Louis. He would not? Coit. No, he would have braved you. Louis. Ay! Coit. You would have killed him. Louis. Well? Coit. That crime, at least, I saved you. He is gone. Louis. Gone! Coit. Ay, escaped! Louis. Aided by thee! Coit. Your victim is beyond your rage. Pursuit were folly. Louis. Wretch, thou darest say so, villain! [To Tristan] And Thou, thy boasted vigilance and power he has evaded. Oh, ye are traitors, all. Whither has he fled? Speak, Dog! Away, away! Alive or dead, I'll have him. Marie. Oh, mercy, sire. Mercy for me, by whom he Was betrayed. Oh, at your latest breath may Heaven Deny your prayer for mercy if you now are deaf to mine. Louis. [To Commine] Take her away. Marie. Give me to death; spare, spare Nemours. Louis. Away with her! For you, traitor, death. Tristan— Tomorrow—death. Coit. Why say tomorrow? Strike at once—today. Louis. Away with him! Coit. Farewell, we soon shall meet. I'll give you just ten days to live. Louis. Ah, villain, be it so; then I will die, I will; but still I'll—I'll—[To his suite] Go! Begone! [To Coitier] Stay you. [Exeunt all but Coitier] Think not thou wilt escape thy fate. No—No—for thou Shalt die in torment. Ay, thou shalt. Coit. So you have said already, sire. Now do it. Louis. Ay, I will. Ha! you think I prize your skill. Ha! Ha! I laugh at it, your art! What has it done for me? Go, cheat the herd with quackery. I'll do without ye, and I'll live by my own will alone. I feel I can. Coit. Excellent! Will try? Louis. Ay, thou traitor, ay! François de Paule can with a single Word repair my life; his breath can give me youth. Coit. He'd best make haste, then. Louis. Ay, he can. Coit. Of course—no doubt of it. Louis. Oh, Coitier, ungrateful Coitier, have I deserved this of thee? Coit. Why, look ye, sire, ungrateful I had been, had I not saved My benefactor's child. Louis. Your benefactor! Coit. Ay! I owed his father all. Louis. What then, have I been scant? I give, and count not what I Give. What gave this benefactor, then, to be so much preferred? Coit. His love! What right have you to gratitude? Thank Heaven, I owe you none. We give and take, and owe each other nought. Come, sire let's be honest. You give from fear; I take from Interest. I give my life, consume it, to prolong Your days. I sell, you purchase. 'Tis a bargain. You kings imagine all is bought with gold; you Pay a courtier, and you buy a slave, but not a friend. Oh, sire, there's but one price for him—that's love. Louis. Then Coitier, I will love thee tenderly. Nay, I do love thee. Coit. Ay, for thyself. Louis. No, as I live. I am in dreadful pain. See now, I do believe This holy man may, if he will, restore me. Yet behold, I do Forgive thee this that thou hast done. Ay, freely. [Enter Oliver] Oliver. Sire, François de Paule attends you. [Enter François] Louis. See, my father, he has braved his king, yet I have pardoned him. Go, Coitier, go rest thee awhile within. Dear friend, Adieu. [Exit Coitier] Ah, traitor, come the day when I've no need of thee. We Are alone. Fran. What seek you with me? Louis. Let me unveil my heart. Fran. Arise, my son. Louis. Let me abase myself, my forehead in the dust, and kiss the Print thy saintly feet have made. Fran. Reserve thy kneeling for Him to whom alone we owe that homage. Rise! Louis. So great the blessing I would ask, I know not how to stoop too low for it. Fran. What can I do? Louis. All. I know your wondrous power. Endowed by Heaven with gifts miraculous. Fran. My son? Louis. Since at the peasant's prayer you pour the dews Upon the parching earth, pour young red blood Into my veins; refresh this arid heart. Command this broken frame to knit its thews And rise again invigorate with youth. Stretch out your arms, and lift me up to health. Touch these pale, livid features with your hand, And smooth this wrinkled brow. Fran. Blaspheme no more. What am I? Louis. Ten years! Oh, say ten years, my father; grant me that, And I will load thee with my gratitude. Hear me. I have precious saintly relics Beyond all price. They shall be thine, and more If I obtain these twenty years I spoke of. I have power at Rome, and thou shalt find A place 'mongst the saints. Amongst what, say I, Above all. I'll lay a tax Upon my faithful subjects; dedicate A temple to thee. But for such expense A score of years is surely not enough. No, let me live on—life—life—ah, grant me that. Prolong my life! Fran. Can I cry halt to time? Change at my will the laws of nature? King, That life thou seekest, thou must have indeed, But not on earth. Louis. I'm weary of that prate. Won't do thine office? Exercise thy power, Or I have means to make you. I am King! Ah, no; pray pardon me; I know not what I say. Fran. Thy mortal malady Is but remorse. Repent. Louis. I will. Then shall I heal and live? Fran. It may be so. Louis. Then I repent, and will confess. Fran. Sinner, who call'st me to this holy office, Speak, speak, what hast thou done? Louis. The King, my father, died; his ailment, it was said, Was terror of the Dauphin. Fran. A son abridge the old age of his father? Louis. That Dauphin was myself. Fran. You! Louis. The crown was tottering, and France was lost. State reasons supersede the ties of nature. I had no choice. Fran. Thou wicked son, confess thy crimes, but Seek not to excuse. Proceed! Louis. I had a brother. Fran. Well? Louis. He also died. Fran. How? Louis. By poison! Fran. By thy command? Louis. It was so suspected. Some did suspect so. Would they who said it had fallen in my clutch! Fran. 'Tis not so, then? Louis. I said not that. Fran. Oh, Heaven! 'Tis true! Louis. But he deserved his fate. Fran. Unutterable horror! Dost thou find Excuses fast as crimes? Down to the dust! Thou art no more a king. Down, on thy knees, Thou fratricide! Louis. Pardon— Fran. Pour out thy leprous soul. Repent, and cleanse thy heart. Louis. I do—I do! See—on my knees—I do. I've yet a crime untold. Fran. What! More? Louis. Nemours. He did conspire; His guilt was proved, but still his death was crime. I forced his sons to witness it, while from the scaffold His life-blood fell on them. Fran. Most barbarous! Louis. I confess. Yes, I have judged With rigor. Fran. Judged! Louis. No—no! They are crimes—foul crimes! The silent wave has been my executioner; The earth, my jailer. Here beneath these walls My captives groan, forgotten and unknown. Fran. This crime can be atoned, thank Heaven for that. Come! Louis. Where? Fran. To release these prisoners. Louis. Stay—stay—you ask too much. The Church has pardons which a king can buy. Fran. Not so; they must be merited. Louis. Then they are mine by right of misery. Oh, could you look into my soul, my father, My body's anguish is but half my pain; The present is a terror, but the past— Oh Heaven, I dare not turn and look on that! My days are wretched, yet they bring relief, And come to scare away my nights of terror. The gloom takes forms to mock and gibe at me; The silence whispers names I loathe and dread; And when I sleep, a demon sits and broods Upon my heart. I thrust him off, and then A naked blade held in a viewless hand Pierces my throat. I try to rise; my couch Swims in a sea of blood, whose gory waves Rise up to drown me. Such my daily life! And quitting it, I thirst for more. To drain This poison'd cup is all my fear. To eke it out, my only hope. Fran. One act of mercy will restore thy peace. Free these, thy captives. Louis. Tomorrow—I will think it out. Fran. Death may come ere then—tonight—this instant. Louis. Death! From whence? No, I am too well defended. Fran. Adieu, then. Merciless thyself, how canst thou hope for mercy? Louis. Ah, you condemn me. Fran. No, 'tis not my office. But, oh, my son, wouldst thou release thyself? Undo these prisoners' chains, and free thy soul. Their curses drown thy prayers! Make them be still, And thou'lt be heard in Heaven. Farewell! Farewell! [Exit] Louis. Father! He leaves me! Stay! I do consent! I—No! That were but weakness! He is gone! Oh, who will aid me now? [Enter Nemours] Sweet saint, I pray thee plead for me. Thou knowest My heart is pitiless. A king must use the power he holds From Heaven, or wrong his trust. In punishing The guilty I would Prove my right to thy protection. In return I'll build thee Churches; load thy shrines with gifts. But let me gratify My just revenge for thine especial honor, And mine too. Nem. Silence! Louis. Silence! Nem. Not a breath! Louis. Not one. Nem. Thou art well defended. Louis. Oh, Nemours! Nem. Who dares to risk his life is master, then, of thine. Louis. What would ye? Nem. Justice! Louis. Oh, be merciful. Nem. I am not thy judge. Louis. Who, then? Nem. My father! Louis. No! Thou—thou! Nem. My father! Louis. Thou, Nemours! Nem. My father! Louis. He would kill me. Nem. Thou hast said it. Louis. Hear! Oh, hear me first! Nem. As thou didst hear my father's dying prayer. Louis. Nemours! Nem. 'Tis here! Look on it now; he bore it on his breast, When by thy fell command he suffered. 'Twas sent By him to thee to melt thy heart to pity. Thine answer wouldst thou see? 'Tis there—his blood! Come, read! Read! Louis. Mercy! Nem. Read, I say! Louis. I cannot. Nem. Beneath the fatal weapon he could write. Read, as he wrote. Louis. No, no! I cannot! That horrid steel distracts me—blinds my sense. I cannot! Nem. Listen, then. Louis. Oh, spare me! Pity me, Nemours! Nem. [Reads] “My most merciful and gracious sovereign, With all my humble heart I plead to your offended majesty For pity and for pardon—” Louis. I will restore thy title—thine estates, Make expiation, full and humble. I do repent. See, see, my tears? Put me but to the proof. Nem. Listen. [Reads] “I will atone my sins and serve you So well and faithfully that my repentance Shall o'ertop my crimes. Oh, let my tears Assuage your anger.” Louis. My son, think of my child! Nemours, Leave him not fatherless. Nem. [Reads] “Yet not for me, but for my children's Sake! Oh, for Heaven's charity, my liege, con- Demn them not in me. For my transgression Will they in dishonor live to beg their bread. Oh, sire, have pity for my unoffending children.” Louis. I will deliver to thee Tristan; He it was who did the deed. Deal with him As thou wilt. Nem. [Reads] “May Heaven preserve your majesty, and Imbue your heart with mercy for your Childhood's loved companion.” See! Murdered! See! Read! Read thyself! Louis. I cannot. Nem. There! Louis. [Reads] “Your childhood's loved companion, Jacques Of Armagnac.” You weep, Nemours; let fall those tears on me. Wash out my sins. Nem. Oh, thou shalt pay them dearly. Louis. Nemours! Nemours! Nem. What tortures can avenge me? where to find A forfeit equal to his crimes? Louis. He'll kill me! Nem. Ah, there is but one. Louis. My death! Nem. No, fiend, thy life! I know thy anguish; I have heard thy woe. Die on! Die slowly! Mass up crimes each hour. Linger till death with lagging steps arrive To seize thee still more guilty. Live in torment! Heaven in its justice listens to thy prayer, And grants thee life to double my revenge. Louis. Help, Tristan! Help! the villain murders me! Tristan! that dagger! Hew him down, I say. [Tristan and guards rush on] Tristan—the traitor's there—the door—pursue— O'ertake the assassin—there!—search!—look!—the curtains Behind the bed—that's where he hides! How, wretches, Can ye not find him? He'll slay me in the midst! Surround me!—close! No, traitors!—back away! I fear ye all!—Ah, there's a shadow—there! See, Tristan! Help, he's here again! He strikes! His dagger's red with blood! Help! Tristan! Kill! [Falls in convulsions]</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT V. Throne Room in the Castle. The stage is filled with courtiers. Lude. Is't true, my lord? They say that Coitier Was an accomplice. Lord. Ay! Lude. Messire Tristan, Can this be so? Nemours and Coitier? Lord. Ay! They are judged—to death; and when the King revives, To sign their sentence, justice will be done. Lord. The Parliament convoked, the peers assembled— This looks like death. [Enter Commine] Com. A page, ho! Quick! This to the Duke of Orleans—away! This to the Lord of Beaujeu! Lude. The Duke and Beaujeu! Then the King is in extremis. Com. There is no hope. Trist. See how they flock about the coming reign. Lude. Be comforted, sweet Prince. Com. Think of Nemours. Let your first act be one of mercy, sire. Dauphin. Have I the power? Com. Speak but one word to Tristan. Dauphin. Be it so. Com. Tristan, you have heard. Nemours— Trist. His highness needs but look to be obeyed. Lude. See, here is the Cardinal. [Enter Cardinal d'Alby] Dauphin. The King, my lord, the King? Card. Fast fleeting, Prince, inanimate. Yet still, my lord, be comforted in this That by his gifts and great beneficence, The Church assures his life to come. Let us All hope to make as Christian-like an end. Dauphin. Then there is no longer hope? Card. Accept the throne; it is your burthen, sire, Which we will help to bear. Dauphin. And he will die Without a word—a look. Com. My lord, 'tis hard. Lude. He is unnatural! He ever treated you With cruelty. Dauphin. Silence! He was my father. That which he did seemed fit to him, and must Seem so to me. [Enter Oliver] Oliver. My lords, our prayers are heard. The King revives. Dauphin. He lives! Card. Providence be praised. Oliver. There is no fear, his senses have returned. There is great hope. He has desired this couch To be prepared. Prince, he would be alone; All must retire but Commine and Tristan. Dauphin. But this affects not me; I am his son. Oliver. Alas, my lord; trust to my offices, And he shall ask for you anon. Dauphin. Accept my gratitude. Com. And mine. Lude. A king Thus undecided if to die or not, Compromises everybody now. Who knows which way to turn? to whom to bow? Oliver. We are alone. Com. Well? Trist. Will he live? Oliver. Of course, to them I said so, but 'tis doubtful Still. Com. Speaks he of Nemours? Oliver. No, he forgets. Com. Come death—ere he remember. Oliver. His brain is gone. Just now, why, nought would serve him but he must Preside at council. On his haggard brow I needs must place the crown, though with the weight His wizened chin sunk upon his breast; And o'er his ague-stricken form, he wears The royal mantle. Then he will walk, forsooth, But scarce has made one pace, when, breathless, helpless, He sinks back, crying that he never felt so well. Faith, He never felt so well! See, he comes. Trist. Has such a phantom life? [Enter Louis and an Officer] Louis. What men are those? Oliver. Commine. Tristan. Louis. Think you I cannot see 'em? One would suppose my eyes were failing me. Good day, sirs. Leave me, fellows; let go your hold. Can I not stir without ye? Oliver. There, repose; rest you awhile, sire. Louis. I am not weary. Oliver. No. Louis. I am strong and capable. Oliver. Most capable. Louis. Since you will have it so, Why stands he there, And gazes on me so? Does he find me changed? Trist. I, sire? I never saw you look so hale. Louis. That's well. This room is spacious; there is air in't; I can breathe. [Dozes] Oliver. He sleeps. Com. Remember, gentlemen, He bade us once when his last moment came To warn him. Trist. Ay. Oliver. He might desire to make Some last bequest to us. Trist. In that case, we'll Let him be told. Louis. Tristan, art thou there? Trist. Ay, sire. Louis. Watch—guard me—guard! Trist. Fear nought. Com. He sleeps again. Oliver. Who will assume this office? Trist. It must be done by one who can convey The matter tenderly. [To Oliver] You are the man. Com. The very man, indeed. Oliver. I would accept, but faith, I love him so I could not keep my feelings in command. Nay, it must be firmly done, and you, I think, would do it best of all. Trist. He's right. Com. I am willing; but why thus prolong His woe? 'Twere better and more merciful To speak outright and break the truth At once, as you would do. [To Tristan] Oliver. Why, so it would. Trist. Eh, gentlemen, Let us confess the thing is delicate. Louis. Why do ye whisper there? Oliver. We bless the day for your recovery. Louis. Why is not Coitier here? Where does he lay? Go fetch him! Trist. Sire, you know— Louis. I know—I know he never is where I Would have him be. Trist. But, sire, you bade— Louis. Away! I bade you bring him here. No words! Obey! [Exit Tristan] I feel in cue for Hearty exercise. Go bid my grand equerry have the train In readiness. Oliver. How, sire? Louis. I'll hunt the wolf Today. Announce it loudly to my court. Oliver. But, sire— Louis. Begone! Oliver. Were it not well to pause Till Coitier— Louis. Again? Oliver. He is himself again. [Exit] Louis. Remove this idle pomp, Commine. My crown— Why have they thrust it on me? Place it there. Nearer! Nearer still; beneath my eyes; under my hand! [Enter Coitier and Tristan] Coit. From my lips he shall learn what you so fear To tell. Louis. Ah, Coitier, art thou there? Whence came ye? Coit. Whence! This is too much! Louis. Why, speak! Coit. Look on my wrist, still blushing with the rust Your manacles have left there. Whence come I! Job's patience! from the dungeon. Louis. A dungeon! Thou? Who gave the order? Coit. Who? You! Louis. I! Coit. 'Fore Heaven, He will deny it now. You in my presence Gave it. Louis. Where? For what? Coit. Accuse me of a deed So vile! Why, man, had I the stomach for it What hindered me? A drug—a remedy o'erdone— One drop too much, and I had done with ye. But, introduce a midnight murderer While ye were sleeping— Louis. Hold! Hold! That vision In the night—behind those curtains, said ye? Com. Coitier, what have you done? He had forgotten. Louis. No, no, I do remember now. Thanks, thanks! 'Twas he—Nemours! Nemours! A dagger raised Against my life. [To Tristan] Speak! He's dead? Trist. I waited, sire. Louis. How, traitor, he is not dead? Trist. The Dauphin, sire, forbade the execution. Louis. Ah, ah! My son! Doth he presume To reign so soon? 'Tis doubtful he may reign at all. Coit. Oh, sire, think not on such designs. Have done with vengeance; look to your own affairs. Your hour is come. Louis. Eh? How, say you? Coit. The truth! Look well, I say, to what you do. For by the light of Heaven, this day will be Your last. Louis. If so, it shall be also his. Tristan, come here. Let it be now, at once; and hark, No juggling with me, or your head shall answer it. Begone! Com. Tristan! Trist. My life or his, you hear. I have no choice. [Exit] Louis. My blood grows chill, Deserts my limbs and gathers round my heart. Nay, this weakness is but a spasm; 'twill pass, 'Twill pass, so wipe my brow. It is the sweat Of agony, and not the dews of death. Ah, mercy!—now it comes. Ay—go—the Dauphin— Quick! Com. I fly, sire. Louis. No, come back! If thus he saw me, he'd believe 'twas past And over with me. Oh, look not so, sirs, This is mere pain, not death. It cannot be. Save me, Coitier! Oh, give me air—air! Oh, all my treasure for one breath! Take, take, But save me. Quick! 'Tis not death; 'tis not—[Falls] Coit. Ah, but it is. Away, apprize the Dauphin. Tell him he is King of France. [Exit Commine] I am free at last. These shrunken lips and sightless glazed eyes Bear impress of the livid seal of death. He's gone— And Nemours, Nemours is saved— The heart beats still! He may survive the spasm, And live awhile—that is, if I revive him. Wherefore? To eke his anguish out one hour? Just time enough to act another crime— The murder of Nemours! No, 'tis enough. Nature, Do as thou wilt. I yield him up to thee. [Enter the Dauphin, Commine and Courtiers] Dauphin. My father, I am here; I come. How now, his face is changed, Coitier. What means This silence? Is it too late? He is no more. Leave me; I would be alone. Com. My liege— Dauphin. Away! I do command ye. [All retire] Oh, my father; Oh, my sovereign, let thy spirit hear me And listen to thy son. Believe my heart, Unknown, forbidden, and outcast by thee. This poor cold hand of thine which now I take To warm with tears. 'Tis not thy tenderness But death that gives me leave to kiss it thus. [Places his hand on the crown] This fatal bauble stood between our hearts, Symbol of earthly power. [Marie rushes in, followed almost immediately by the Court] Marie. My liege! Dauphin. Marie! Marie. He is condemned, sire. Tristan is engaged Upon his fatal work. Stay—stay it, sire. I claim your royal word; see, here is your pledge. I ask the pardon of Nemours; his life. His life or mine! They lead him out to death. Dauphin. The King redeems the Dauphin's word. Nemours—[During this the King revives; the Dauphin quickly withdraws his hand from the crown] Louis. No, keep it; it is thine. My hour is come. Marie. Nemours—one word for him— Fran. You hear— Marie. My liege, my liege, as thou dost hope for pardon, Extend it now. [Bell] The bell! 'Tis for his death! Oh, Heaven! See! Nemours, Nemours! Dauphin. One word, my father; speak and give him life. Fran. Sire, while thou yet hast time. Louis. If I forgive, Shall I, too, in my turn find mercy? Fran. Would'st thou Contract with Heaven, and die accursed As thou hast lived? Louis. No—no— I pardon. Save him! Save him! Marie. Hold! Ah—My life for his. [Rushes out] Louis. Father! Speak—save—absolve! Is there no hope? Oh, mercy! Mercy! The mortal foe! See! See you not? It comes! I feel his icy grip. Pray! Pray for me! I do entreat ye all—pray! I command—[Dies. Montjoie breaks his staff] Mont. The King is dead. The King is dead! Long live the King! CURTAIN</field>
   </doc>
</add>