<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Todhunter, John, 1839-1916</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Todhunter, John, 1839-1916</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">todhunter john 1839 1916</field>
      <field name="author_text">Todhunter, John, 1839-1916</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1920's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V3.0661.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1924</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460989</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Goethe's Faust : First Part</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Goethe's Faust : First Part</field>
      <field name="title_facet">goethes faust first part</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">goethes faust first part</field>
      <field name="title_text">Goethe's Faust : First Part</field>
      <field name="year_display">1924</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1924</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1924</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460989&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460989&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Todhunter, John, 1839-1916&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;todhunter john 1839 1916&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Goethe's Faust : First Part&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;goethes faust first part&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1924&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1924&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Todhunter, John&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1839&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1916&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Goethe's Faust : First Part&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Oxford&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Basil Blackwell&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1924&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3873327-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv30661&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 20th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;20th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Goethe's Faust : First Part&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 366 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Goethe's Faust.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1924.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Unknown.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">GOETHE'S FAUST FIRST PART</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS. This translation of Faust is the last important work my husband completed. It was ready for publication in 1914, but the war rendered the moment inopportune. He would wish to acknowledge his obligations to his friends, the late Professor Dowden (who considered this the best translation made hitherto), for his interest and encouragement, to the late T. W. Rolleston for some valuable suggestions, and to Mr. J. Lœwe (formerly of Woodstock Road, Bedford Park), to whose ever-ready help and sympathy he was much indebted. John Todhunter's aim was a translation preserving the original metres, “without which,” Professor Dowden writes, “the characteristic effects cannot be reproduced.” And he adds, “It will be a real loss to English readers if your version is not published.” D. L. T., Orchardcroft, Bedford Park, W.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DEDICATION. Again, ye wavering shapes do ye draw near, That showed yourselves once to my saddened eye, Shall I now seek to hold you prisoners here? Feel I my heart yield to that phantasy? Ye throng around! 'Tis well, in power appear, As when in gloom and cloud ye rose round me: My breast feels itself throb, grown young again, Urged by the magic breath, breathed by your train. Ye bring with you visions of happy days, And many a well-belovèd Shade appears; Like folk-tales told in half-forgotten lays, Come first-love, and the friendships of dead years; The pain grows new, the plaint echoes always Of Life's perplexing labyrinth in mine ears, And names the good, who, of Joy's felicity Cheated by Fate, have vanished before me. They hear no more the songs that follow here, The kindred souls to whom the first I sang; Scattered is now the friendly band, so dear, Dumb, alas! those first echoes that round me rang. My song sounds for the unknown crowd, and fear Even when they applaud, shoots through my heart a pang; And those who once rejoiced to hear my lay, If still they live, are scattered far away. Unwonted yearning seizes me, I long For that calm, solemn Kingdom of the Shades; In tones uncertain soars my faltering song, Like an Æolian harp's it swells and fades; A shudder grips me, tears on tears will throng, Weak tenderness now my stern soul invades; What I possess, like things far off I see, And scenes long-vanished alone seem real to me.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PRELUDE IN THE THEATRE. Manager, Dramatic Poet, Clown. Manager. Ye twain, who here so oft by me In trouble and need did stoutly stand, Say what, in this our German Land, From our new venture ye hope to see? I have wished so much to please the crowd we seat, Since it lives, and lets us live, after all. The posts and planks are fixed—here is our hall, And everyone anticipates a treat. They sit there now with raised brows, patiently, And some amazing thing they long to see. The Public I can humour; but protest I ne'er came here with such a puzzled head; True, they are not accustomed to the best; But what a frightful lot of things they've read! How shall we manage that all be fresh and new And full of meaning, and yet please them too? In sooth I long to see the crowd with pain Throng in full stream into our booth to-day, And with renewed and strenuous effort gain The narrow door of grace, and push their way By clear day, ere the clock strike four, Push, fighting to the Cashier's wicket Like starving folk for bread to the baker's door, And well-nigh break their necks to get a ticket. The Poet alone can work this miracle, On diverse minds; my friend, work now that spell. Poet. Oh! speak not to me of that motley crowd, At the first glance my spirit takes to flight! Hide from mine eyes its billows surging loud, That, 'gainst my will, tug me with whirlpool's might. No, bear me to some calm nook of the sky Where alone for the Poet pure joy can bloom, With love and friendship, our hearts' blessed power, By God's own hand created, nourished each hour. Ah! what sprang once deep in the breast like seed, What the lips coyly murmured, now may be A failure, that may haply yet succeed, One tyrannous moment swallows ruthlessly. Oft when through years it penetrates, indeed, In perfect form appearing, it struggles free. Bright pinchbeck is but for the moment born Pure metal fades not in the future's morn. Clown. Nothing about the future let me hear! Suppose about the future I should prate Who would make sport this present year? They want it, and must have it, I tell ye. The presence of a jolly fellow I think's worth something at any rate. He who with others well can play his part, The people's humours cannot sour; He wants but a good crowd to show his art, And stir them up to own his power. Then quit you well, and a good sample show, Let phantasy be heard with all her choirs, Reason, sense, passion, sentiment also; But mark me! eke the mirth your Clown inspires. Manager. Let enough happen, then, howe'er it be! They come to gaze, like best the things they see. If many scenes before their eyes go by, So that in wondering concourse gape they can, Soon you've gained over the majority, You are a well-belovèd man. The mass but through the mass you can subdue, Each for himself picks something out at last; Who brings much, brings to many something too, Each leaves the house well-pleased with his repast. You give a piece, give it to them in pieces! Such a ragoût your fame increases; Easily 'tis produced, thought out as easily. What boots it you brought forth a whole? You see The Public soon picks your great work to pieces. Poet. You do not feel how bad such handiwork must be! How ill it suits an artist pure and true; This pretty coxcombs' bunglery Seems quite a principle with you. Manager. Such a reproach leaves me unscathed; I say A man who works in the right way Must use tools for the work best fit. Think, you have sappy wood to split, See then distinctly for whom you write! If your fine work should bore them quite, Each from your feast comes surfeited away, And, worst of all for your fine flight, Some have been reading journals half the day. They come with absent minds, as to a masque they'd go, Each step winged with mere curiosity; The ladies come, themselves and their fine clothes to show, And play for us without a fee. What do you dream of on your poet's height? What makes a full house take things pleasantly? Look at your patrons well to-night! Half of them cold, half rude, you see. One hopes for a game of cards after the play, A wild night on a wench's breast one chooses. Why, ye poor fools, plague night and day, For such an end, the gentle Muses? I tell you, give but more, and ever, ever more, And then your shafts the mark will never miss. Seek to intrigue your audience. I wis To please them is a problem sore. What moves you now, delight, or agony? Poet. Hence with thee, seek another slave to-night! The Poet must, forsooth, the noblest right, Man's right, ungrudging Nature gave—content, For thy sake, wickedly squander away! How is it all hearts he moves can sway? Wherewith rules he each element? Is it not the harmony that, gushing from his breast, Draws back into his heart the echoing world's unrest? When Nature spins the unending thread of Fate And on the distaff evenly doth wind, While the discordant throng of things create Chant, all at odds, their grewsome lay, Who gives new rhymes to dull monotony, Animates all to move in concord sweet? Who calls each voice to join in sacred glee, When in the bliss of noble chords they meet? Who makes the storm to passion rage and swell? Evening's red gleam in reverent senses glow? Who sows all fair Spring flowers, plants bud and bell On quiet paths where lovers go? Who twines the modest leaves on myrtle-rods Into a wreath of honour for Worth unknown? Who fends Olympus, reconciles the gods? Man's power, in the Poet revealed alone. Clown. Use, then, your finest strokes of art, And ply well your poetic trade, As on a love-adventure you would start! One comes by chance, feels, stays, your game is played, Soon he's entangled, heart and feet, His pleasure grows, your victory's complete, He is enraptured, then comes pain, perchance, And, ere he can suspect, the thing becomes romance. Let us give now just such a play! Grip fast the fullest life of man, I say! Everyonyone lives, each knows life little at best, And, where you seize it, all you interest. In varied pictures, dim in sooth, Much error, and a spark of truth, You brew best the refreshing cup, That quickens all the world, and builds it up. Then your play draws Youth, with its budding powers, To wait some revelation eagerly, Each gentle spirit from your tragedy Sucks melancholy food, as bees from flowers. Then is one here, one there, moved by your art, Each sees but what he bears in his own heart. Then they are soon ready to laugh or weep, Enjoy illusion, take fine flights seriously; Who is full-fledged may hold your efforts cheap, Those yet in growth will ever grateful be. Poet. Then give me back those happy times, When I myself was growing still, When a deep spring of rippling rhymes Gushed in a never-failing rill. Then cloud concealed the world from me, Each bud promised a miracle I plucked a thousand flowers in glee, That richly filled each vale and dell. Nothing I had, yet wealth in sooth, Loving delusion, yet impelled tow'rd truth. Give me those tameless impulses, That happiness, so full of pain, The power of hate, love's might—give these, Ah! give me back my youth again! Clown. Youth, my good friend, at all events you need, When foes around you throng to battle, Or when about your neck, indeed, The loveliest maidens hang and prattle, When far the prize of the swift race There from the hard-won goal is blinking, When, after dancing at a whirlwind's pace, You spend the night feasting and drinking. But now to strike familiar strings, With courage, charm, to show your skill, To wander on your spirit's wings Tow'rd what self-chosen goal you will, This duty, old Dons, is yours to-day, For which we honour you no less. Age does not make us childish, as they say, Yet finds us still true children, I confess. Manager. With bandying words be now content, Let me see deeds as well at last! Time spent in bartering compliment In useful business might have passed. What boots this talk of moods to me? Unmarked by sluggards they drift away. You deem yourself a Poet, pray Command for us your poesy. You know well what we want, I think, We wish to taste some potent drink; Then brew it for us without delay! To-morrow ne'er you'll do what is not done to-day. No day should idly past you trip: Let Resolution's hand robust The Possible's forelock boldly grip, His grasp will never let it slip, He'll work away—because he must. Upon our German stage, you see, Each strives to do what do he may, Then do not spare to use to-day Fine landscapes and machinery! Use heaven's lights freely, great and small, Stars you must squander lavishly; With water, fire, and rocky wall, With beasts and birds you must make free. And so, within our narrow house-of planks, You'll stride through all Creation's endless ranks, And ramble swiftly, yet discreet as well, From Heaven, through the World, to Hell.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PROLOGUE IN HEAVEN. The Lord, the Heavenly Hosts. Afterwards Mephistopheles. The Three Archangels come forward. Raphael. Among his Brother spheres, the Seven The Sun vies, chanting the ancient song, And on his course prescribed, through Heaven With thundertread he speeds along. His vision gives the Angels power, Though fathom him no Angel may The mighty works, mysteries this hour, Are glorious as on Time's first day. Gabriel. And swift, and swift past estimating, The splendour of the Earth whirls round The light of Paradise alternating With darkness dreadful and profound. In wideflung waves upswells the ocean And o'er the rocks his head uprears, And rock and sea are hurried onward In the swift endless race of spheres. Michael. And storms come roaring and contending From sea to land, from land to sea And raging weave a chain unending Round Earth of deepest energy. There flames a fiery devastation Before the thunderbolts' fierce way Thy Heralds, Lord, in adoration Watch the soft footsteps of Thy day. The Three. The vision gives the Angels power Yet fathom thee no Angel may, And all Thy mighty works this hour Are glorious as on Time's first day. Mephistopheles. Since Thou, O Lord, to us once more drawest near, And askest how all things with us are going, And Thou wert once well-pleased to see me here, My face among Thy courtiers I am showing. Pardon me, I cannot make fine speeches, after Such strains, and if at me Thy whole Court should scoff, My pathos well might give Thee food for laughter, But that the habit Thou hast long left off. Of suns and worlds I cannot speak, naught knowing, See but how men plagues for themselves are sowing. The little god of the world still keeps his mould of clay, And is as whimsical as on Creation's Day. A little better he might have thriven, Hadst Thou to him a glimpse of heaven's light ne'er given Reason he calls that ray divine, And by its aid lives worse than any swine. If such a trope Your Grace deem not improper. He seems to me like a long-legg'd grasshopper, That flits about with flying springs, Then in the grass the same old ditty sings: And would 'twere but in grass to lie he skurries! In every heap of dung his nose he buries. The Lord. Hast thou naught further for mine ear? Comest thou still accusing here? Does nothing ever on earth seem right to thee? Mephistopheles. No, Lord! I find things there as ever, bad as could be I pity men long days moaning their miseries, Even I am loath to plague poor devils like these. The Lord. Knowest thou Faust? Mephistopheles. The Doctor? The Lord. My servant. Mephistopheles. He? Truly! He serves you in the strangest fashion. Not earthly are his meat and drink; some passion In the fool's blood fermenting, drives him far, Half conscious of his folly, without rest From heaven he still demands each loveliest star, Each highest pleasure earth can give would test, And all things near, and all things far Appease not the deep trouble of his breast. The Lord. Though now he serve me in perplexity, Soon will I lead him to the light of morning, The Gardener, when green buds burst on the tree, Sees flower and fruit the late year adorning. Mephistopheles. What will you bet? You lose your Protégé. If your permission you give to me To lead him gently on my own way. The Lord. As long as on the earth he lives, So long to thee be that allowed, Man still must stray while still he strives. Mephistopheles. I thank you; but the dead in shroud I never cared to haggle over, Of plump, fresh cheeks indeed I'm a most ardent lover, I'm not at home to corpses in my house, My game is like the cat's with a live mouse. The Lord. Well, from thy claws I will not snatch him, Draw thou that spirit from its deep source away, And lead him, if thou canst but catch him Down thy own path with thee to stray, And stand ashamed when thou must recognise: A good man in his dark hour of temptation Knows the right way, though other paths he tries. Mephistopheles. True! but these moods have short duration, Without a fear my wager's chance I take, If I succeed and win my stake, Permit me then to triumph with full breast Dust shall he eat, and eat with zest, Just like my Aunt the celebrated Snake. The Lord. Here mayst thou freely appear in thy old station; I have never hated spirits of thy kind. Of all the spirits of negation, The cynic knave weighs least upon my mind. Man's energy soon sleeps 'twixt good and evil, And soon he loves in perfect sloth to lie, Wherefore I give him a companion sly, Who goads and drives, and plays the part of Devil. But ye, pure Sons of God, delight you Where living Beauty's richest fields invite you! Powers yet half born, that ever work and live, Bind you in Love's sweet bonds like happy lovers, While ye through enduring thoughts permanence give To what in glimmering, fading vision hovers. Heaven closes. The Archangels separate. Mephistopheles (alone). From time to time I like the Old Lord to see To break with Him shun all occasion, 'Tis fine so great a Personage as He Should with the Devil himself hold conversation.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE I. In a high-vaulted Gothic chamber Faust sits restlessly at his desk. Faust. I have now, alas! Philosophy, Law's mystery, and Medicine too, And, woe is me! Theology, Studied devoutly through and through, And here I am, poor baffled fool! Wise as before I went to school; Magister, Doctor, I'm styled forsooth, Lead by the nose our studious youth, Some ten years over the same old ground, Up, down, here, there, about and around— And see no knowledge can come of our learning! That sears my heart with a quenchless burning, Yet I am shrewder than all these fribblers, Doctors, Magisters, Parsons and scribblers; Doubts and scruples plague me but little, For Hell and the Devil I reck not a tittle— But then for my pains all joy is bereft me, I dream not the knowledge of right is left me, Dream not some doctrine I may find, To better or to convert mankind. Nor have I gold or land or birth, Honour, nor lordship of the earth; No dog such a life would longer live! Wherefore to magic myself I give, That I, through Spirit's voice and might, May learn many riddles to read aright, No longer, sweating for bitter woe, May prate of things that I do not know, That I the inmost forces find Which firmly the world together bind, All germs, all energies watch, explore, And deal in empty words no more. Would thou didst gaze, full moon, again, For the last time, upon my pain, Whom I, so many a midnight drear, O'erwatched, this desk before me here: Then, over many a script and book, Thou, my sad friend, didst on me look! Ah! could I but in thy soft light Wander upon the mountain's height, O'er mountain caverns with spirits hover, The meads in thy faint gleams float over, From all the fogs of learning free, Bathed in thy dews, be healed by thee! Ah! pens this dungeon still my soul? Accurséd, musty, walled-in hole! Where even the light of heaven, so dear, Sad, through stained windows enters here. Cramped by these books in monstrous heap, Which bookworms gnaw, which dust defiles, Where to the ceiling, vaulted deep, Reams of smoked paper are stacked in piles; With limbecs, boxes ranged around, With instruments that serve me not, Heirlooms, encumbering the ground— That is thy world! what a world, God wot! And dost thou question why thy heart Quakes in thee cramped with inward strife, Why some vague sense-eluding smart Checks all the movements of thy life? Instead of living Nature now, Man's home ordained in God's own plan, Smothered in smoke and dust art thou, With fleshless bones of beast and man. Flee! up! away! To the wide land! And this old Book of Mystery, From Nostradamus's own hand, Is it not guide enow for thee? Then shalt thou know the stars' fixed course, If Nature still direct thy way, Raised by thy soul's exalted force, Converse with spirits as spirits may. In vain by arid thought read clear, The sacred symbols enlighten thee: Answer me now, if ye can hear, Ye spirits hovering over me! (He opens the Book, and catches sight of the symbol of the macrocosm.) Ha! what a rapture streams at the first view Through all my senses now, even as I gaze That holy joy of life my youth once knew I feel new-glowing through nerves and veinlets' maze. Was it a God indeed who penned that sign, The storm that raged within me stilling, This hope-sick heart with rapture filling, And by some strange impulse divine The omnipresent powers of Nature now revealing? Am I a god? All grows so clear! In the pure scripture of the scroll Nature's fine energies lie open to my soul. At last I understand what spake the Seer: “The World of Spirit is closed not to thee, Thy sense is shut, thy heart is dead! Up, scholar! bathe ever unwearied, Thy breast of clay in dawnlight red!” (He contemplates the symbol.) How all things one great pattern weave, Each in the other doth work and live! How heavenly powers ascending and descending, Pass their gold ewers through lines unending! With blessing-breathing wings From heaven pierce earth, while from all things The harmony of all with all outrings! What vision! but alas! a vision alone How shall I grasp thee, Nature, Infinite One! Where are thy breasts? Life-springs that all sustain, Whereon hang heaven, earth, stars that burn, For which man's withering heart must yearn— Ye flow, ye nourish, and pine I now in vain? (He turns reluctantly to another page of the Book, and looks at the Symbol of the Earth-Spirit.) How differently upon me works this sign! Thou Spirit of Earth, to me art nigher, Even now I feel my powers mount higher, Even now I glow, as with new wine. Courage to face the world within me glows, Courage to bear all earthly joys and woes, To fight the tempest when it blows, Blench not when down the crashing vessel goes. Clouds gather over me— The moon conceals her light, The lamp grows dimmer! Mists rise!—red rays flash quivering Around my head—there breathes A horror from the vault above And seizes me! I feel Thou hoverest round me, Spirit, called by my prayer. Reveal thyself! Ha! how it seems my heart to tear! With new, strange feeling All my senses are raging and reeling. I feel my whole heart given away to thee! Thou must! thou must! though my life pay the fee. (He seizes the Book, and mysteriously pronounces the spell of the Earth-Spirit. A reddish flame flickers around, and the Spirit appears in the flame.) Spirit. Who calls me? Faust (turning away.) Dreadful apparition! Spirit. With potent summons thou drewest me here, After long tugging at my sphere, And now? Faust. I cannot bear thy vision! Spirit. Thou prayedst, panting, to look upon me, My face thou wouldst gaze on, my voice thou wouldst hear, Thy strong prayer drew me from my sphere, I am here—what horror so piteously Now grips thee, Overman? where is thy soul's glad cry? That breast which framed a world within it secretly, And bore, and fostered it, with exultation Swelled, as 'twould match us daemons in our station? Where art thou, Faust, whose voice to me could thrill, Who thrust thyself on me with potent will? Canst thou be he, who, when my breath thou feelest, Scared to life's deeps, tremblest and reelest, Writhing away, frightened worm! Faust. Yield to thee, shall I, flame-shape, in fear? Faust am I, Faust. I am thy peer! Spirit. In life's wild billows, in action's storm, Surge I like a wave, Weave unrestingly Birth and the grave, An infinite sea, A web still growing, A life still glowing, At the whizzing loom of Time I ply, And the living garment of God weave I. Faust. Thou who through all the wide world wendest! Much-toiling spirit, how near I feel to thee! Spirit. Thou art like the spirit thou comprehendest, Not me! (Vanishes.) Faust (collapsing.) Not thee? Whom then? I, image of the Godhead And not even like thee! (Someone knocks.) Faust. O Death!—I know it—this is my Famulus— He comes to ruin my fairest joy! Oh! that this hour of fullest insight, The dry-brained sneak should so destroy! (Enter Wagner in dressing-gown and night-cap, a lamp in his hand. Faust turns to him in angry disgust.) Wagner. Pardon me, I heard your declamation; You read, I doubt not, some Greek Tragedy? I fain would profit by this recitation, This art would now much profit me. I have often heard it said a preacher Might well accept an actor as his teacher. Faust. Yes, when the preacher, as at times we see, Is a comedian, with a part to play. Wagner. Alas! when, banished to one's library, One sees the world but some rare holiday, But from afar, as through a telescope, To guide it by persuasion can he hope? Faust. You strive in vain, if you are void of feeling, If from your soul all does not swell, To the old, strong fount of joy appealing, Your hearers' hearts you must compel. Sit there for ever, from each full table Steal scraps to cook your own ragôut Blow up the flame, so miserable, From the cold ash-heaps piled by you! Win childrens', pedants' admiration, If to your taste you find it so; But heart to heart you ne'er will weld with passion, If yours pour forth no kindling glow. Wagner. Delivery makes the orator's success, I feel it, though far backward I confess. Faust. Let him seek honest victory! With cap and bells play no fool's part! Reason, good-feeling easily Express themselves with little art; When some grave thing you burn to say, Must you go hunting words all day? Yes, all your speeches brilliant of their kind, With scraps of human relics curled and bristling, Are unrefreshing as the foggy wind, That in the Autumn through dry leaves goes whistling. Wagner. Ah God! Yes, art is long, And short our time for living. How often, o'er my critic labour striving Fears to my head and heart will throng. How hard it is to acquire the means whereby One clambers to the ancient source, And ere half-way up one has toiled, perforce For all his pains, must a poor devil die. Faust. Dry parchment, is it then the sacred spring Wherefrom a draught stills thirst for evermoe? Refreshment naught to thee can bring, If from thy soul all does not flow. Wagner. Pardon me! It is my greatest pleasure To breathe each age's spirit, in a measure To see how, ere we lived, a man deemed wise has thought, How far, splendidly far, our labours we have brought. Faust. Oh yes! far as the stars are high! My friend, those times of yore so long gone by, For us are but a book with seven seals; And what the Spirit of the Age you call Is but the old scribe's own spirit after all, The mirror that his age reveals. There oft, heart-sick, you search the gloom, At the first glance you well might run away! You find a dust-bin, or a lumber-room, At best a solemn farce old courtiers play With fine pragmatic maxims, well-befitting The mouths of puppets through stiff poses flitting. Wagner. Ah! but the world! the heart and spirit of man! 'Bout these we all should gain some information. Faust. Yes, called so by the pedant clan! Who dares to give the child its proper designation? The few who have some scraps of truth discerned, But were such fools, their full hearts not concealing, They flung to the mob their views, showed it their deepest feeling, Men, age by age, have crucified and burned. Pardon me, friend, 'tis now deep in the night We must break off our conversation. Wagner. Gladly I would have watched till dawned the light, To hold with you so learn'd a disputation. Tomorrow, though, at dawn of Easter Day, Permit me a few more questions, pray. With zeal I have pursued my studies here, and so In truth know much; but all things I would know. [Exit] Faust (alone.) How soon all hope decays, save in the mind Of one who clings to stuff dry as the sand Will dig for treasure with a covetous hand, Glad if a coil of earthworms he may find. Dared such a mortal voice sound in this place, Where spirits in full throng surrounded me? Yet ah! this once my thanks to thee, Most miserable of all the human race. Thou then didst rescue me from dull despair, Which soon had hurled my senses to perdition. Ah! what a dwarf I felt beside Him there, So giant-like that mighty apparition! I, image of the Godhead, who fain would be, Half thought myself the glass of truth eternal, Joyed in the glimpse of heaven's clear light supernal, And stript off earth's mortality; I, more than Cherub, whose power, with uncurbed sway, I felt already through Nature's veins far-streaming; And, to enjoy the life of gods now scheming, Measured myself with Him; penance of dreaming! One thunder-word hath swept me far away. I dare no more to count myself thy peer, I had the power to draw thee from thy sphere, No power had I to force thee here to stay. In that blest moment of exaltation; I felt myself so small, so great; Thou drov'st me in horror and consternation, Back to mankind's uncertain state. Who teaches me? What must I shun? That impulse must I now obey? Ah! like our sorrows, even the deeds that we have done Cripple us, walking on Life's way. The noblest aims, our spirits' fine aspirations, With more and more base metal are defiled; When the world's wealth we gain with toil and patience Things better lying dreams are styled. Our noblest feelings, Life's own gift, grow numb, In the world's crazy turmoil overcome. Though once Imagination, in bold flight, Soared to the Eternal, full of hopes that flattered, But little room she needs, when each delight Sinks, one, by one, in Time's great Maelstrom shattered. Care makes her nest soon in the heart's deep core, And secret pangs breeds evermore, Restless she rocks herself, killing all peace and joy; And donning still new masks breeds new annoy, As house and home, as wife and child may she come creeping, Fire, water, venomed blade; each shape You tremble at, though all you scape, And what you never lost must mourn for, vainly weeping. I am no mate for gods! that feeling thrills too deep; I am like the worm, framed through the dust to creep, That, as for food it fain must grub and root, Is crushed and buried by some passer's foot. Is it not dust that in this high-built wall With hundred shelves, narrows my sphere, These thousand trifles, useless lumber all, In this moth-world cramping me here? Shall I find here what most I need? Read in the thousand volumes on my shelves How one man, here and there, was happy indeed, And everywhere mankind have plagued themselves? Why dost thou grin so, hollow skull, at me? As though, like mine, seeking the light of day, Thy brain grew crazy, when dull twilight fell on thee, And, craving truth, miserably went astray! Ye instruments, surely ye mock at me, With wheel and cog, with bow and cylinder. Before the door I stood, deemed each a key; But your key-bits are bent, the bolt ye cannot stir. In day's clear light, a mystery still, Nature lets no man of her veil bereave her, And what to thine own soul she deigns not to reveal, Ne'er shalt thou force from her, by help of screw or lever. Old household furniture I never used There still stand'st thou, because my sire did use thee, Thou ancient scroll, thou wilt be with smoke suffused As long as on this desk the dim lamp's reek suffuse thee. Far better had I but my little spent and sped, Than burdened by that little sweat here 'neath its oppression, What from thy sires thou hast inherited Earn, and so make thy own possession. What is not used becomes a load of lead, Each moment can but use tools of its own creation. But wherefore do I still fix on that spot my sight? Is yon small phial there a magnet for mine eye? Why all at once this clear serenity, As when in some dark wood the moon bathes us in light? I greet thee well, phial of phials, and hence I take thee down with care and reverence! In thee I honour man's mother-wit and art, Thou essence of all suave and drowsy juices, Extract of subtlest powers Death gently uses, Grant now thy master grace to play his part! Looking on thee, I feel my pain appeasèd, I grasp thee, and my strife of soul is easèd. Gently my spirit's flood now ebbs away, The mirroring tide shimmers about my feet, I am lured to strange new shores by a new day. A fiery chariot hovers on light pinions Tow'rd me! I feel ready to steer On my new path, through ether's vast dominions, To new activity in some purer sphere. This higher life, this rapture so divine! Thou, worm but now, meritest thou this grace? Yes, from the kind sun of this earth of thine, With resolution turn thy face! Dare but to burst that gloomy portal, Which everyone would willingly slink by! 'Tis time to prove by deeds that a mere mortal Pales not on godlike heights, but keeps his dignity, Before yon gloomy cave can tremble not, Where fancy damns each soul to its own pain, Can strive even tow'rd its throat, whence, hot Around its narrow mouth, all hell flames up amain; Serenely dare to take that step naytheless Wer't even a perilous plunge into mere nothingness. Now come thou down, thou pure crystalline cup, Out of thine ancient case, where, long stored up, I have not thought of thee this many a year! At my forefathers' feasts oft didst thou shine, Enlivening the grave guests with wine, As each to his next neighbour passed thee on, To the rich art of pictures, many a one, Each toper must pay tribute, in rhyme explaining Their merit, at one draught his bumper draining. Thou mindest me of many a night of Youth; I will not pass thee now to any neighbour, Nor o'er thine artistry to shew my wit now labour; Here is a juice that soon makes drunk, in sooth. With its brown tide in flood, it fills thy bowl, This I prepared, choose at Life's goal, My last draught be it now with all my soul A festal greeting pledged to Morn's glad youth! (He raises the cup to his lips.) Peal of bells and Choral Song. Choir of Angels. Christ is arisen! Joy to each mortal O'er whom at Life's portal Creeps his corruptible Heirloom destructible, Burst is his prison. Faust. What deep-toned boom, what sound so sweet and clear Plucks from my lips the glass, with gentle power? Do ye, deep bells, announce unto me here The Easter festival's first sacred hour? Ye choirs, chant ye even now the comfortable song That once through the grave's night rang from the Angel's tongue, Pledge of new covenant, promised long? Choir of Women. With spices holy Embalmed Him we have, True friends yet lowly, We laid Him in the grave; In pure white linen Did we Him wind, Alas! The Christ here No more we find. Choir of Angels. Christ is arisen! Blest be the loving, Who sorrows enduring, Health-giving, soul-curing, Went glad to their proving By torment and prison. Faust. Ye heavenly sounds, why do ye seek, With mild constraint, me in the dust? Go wandering, singing still, where men are weak, I hear your message well, but have not faith to trust; Miracle is Faith's best beloved child. To those high spheres I have no will to strive, From whence it sounds, that message mild; And yet from childhood's days accustomed to that sound, Even now it calls me back, and bids me live. Ah! once Heaven's love fell on me like a kiss Upon my brow, in solemn Sabbath stillness, When rang so bodefully the pealing bell-tone's fullness, And then a prayer to me was fervent bliss; Mysterious longing, sweet ecstasies, Drove me through wood and mead alone to thee; While thousand tears burned in mine eyes I felt a world arise in me. Youth's merry games that strain heralded blithely pealing, Spring's festival of careless glee; Memory now holds me back, with the old childlike feeling, From the last step's grim agony. Oh! ring ye out, each sweet and heavenly strain, My tears gush forth. Thou hast me, Earth, again! Choir of Disciples. Living and glorified, From the grave's prison, He who lay buried here Now is arisen; Lo! in Transfigurement Tastes He Creation's bliss; Ah! o'er Earth's bosom bent, Grieve we in loneliness. We, His own sheep here, Pine, left by Him we miss; Ah! must we weep here, Master, Thy bliss? Choir of Angels. Christ is arisen Out of corruption's womb! Break the bonds of your prison Rejoice o'er the tomb! Praise ye Him deedfully, Show your love's loyalty Feast ye fraternally, Preaching o'er land and sea, Promising bliss to ye, Still is your Master near, Dwells with you here!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE II. Before the Gate. People of all ranks press out. Group of Artisans. Why do you go that way? Others. We're for “The Foresters” to-day. First Group. And we would sooner stroll off to the mill. An Artisan. Go to the Water court, that's my advice. Second Artisan. No pleasant path before you lies. Second Group. What then dost thou? Third Artisan. Where t'others go, I will. Fourth. Come up to Burgsdorf, then, there you will find good cheer, The prettiest damsels, and the best of beer, The sport the finest anywhere. Fifth. Cock o'the walk thou fain wouldst be, Itches thy hide for drubbing three? I loathe the place, just catch me going there. Servant-Girl. Nay, nay, I'm off, back to the town I'll go. Second Girl. We'll find him standing by yon poplar-tree. First Girl. Great happiness for me, if so; To watch him sidle up to thee, Dance with thee on the grass-plot there. What for thy pleasures do I care! Second Girl. To-day he's not alone, he said That he would come along with Curlyhead. First Student. Lord! how yon sturdy queans are striding! Come, Brother, come! Push on, and walk beside them. The strongest beer, tobacco hot and biting, A housemaid in full dress are cates I most delight in. First Citizen's Daughter. There, look at those two fine young fellows! It is a scandal really; In the best company they would be welcome, After those maids they run, you see! Second Student. Don't go so fast, two more come on behind, And both most daintily drest, I vow! Our neighbour's daughter's one, I find, I'm a bit sweet upon her now. They pace demurely, friend by friend, But will accept our escort in the end. First Student. No, Brother, no! Quick, lest we lose our prey! I can't be fashed my freakish tongue to fetter. The hand that wields the broom on Saturday, On Sunday will caress you all the better. First Burgess. No, I don't care for him, this new-made Burgomaster! Now he's got there his pride grows daily faster. What's he done for the town then, pray? Each day growing worse, none to gainsay him, Must we not all more humbly obey him, And taxes, more then ever, pay? Beggar Sings. Kind gentlemen, and lovely ladies, So finely drest, cheeks like the rose, Graciously deign to look upon me And see, and succour all my woes! Let me not grind my hurdy-gurdy In vain! Who give thrice blest are they, This day, when all are merry-making, Be if for me my harvest day! Second Burgess. Sundays and holidays, there's naught I more delight in, Than talk of war, and the fierce battle-cry, When, far away in Turkey there, I hear how folk with folk are fighting. One at the window stands, his glass will drain, Sees on the stream below the painted boats go by, Then glad at even comes home again, Blessed be peace, and peaceful times, say I. Third Burgess. Ay, neighbour, ay! I too let hap what may, Each foreign fool crack t'other's noddle, All topsy-turvey turn some day, While, as of old, at home things toddle. Old Woman (to Citizen's Daughter.) Hey! we're so smart! Young blood its tale will tell! You've smitten all the men, I assure you. Don't be so proud! All's going well! And what you wish I know how to procure you. First Citizen's Daughter. Come, Agatha! I fear it is not right With such a witch to chaffer openly; And yet 'tis true that on St. Andrew's Night My future Lover she showed to me. Second Citizen's Daughter. She showed me mine in the crystal sphere A gallant soldier, mid his comrades bold; I look around and seek him everywhere, But ne'er he'll meet me as she foretold. Soldiers. Castles with lofty Ramparts that rise, Maidens with haughty Scorn in their eyes, These let me win! Bold is the venture Noble the prize! Hark! the loud trumpets, With summoning breath, As unto pleasure, Call us to death. Driven by a whirlwind Life's a stern splendour, Maidens and castles To us must surrender. Bold is the venture, Noble the pay, Off go the soldiers, Marching away! Enter Faust and Wagner. Faust. Released from ice are stream and river, At the glance of Spring's life-kindling eye; The vale grows green with hope's ecstacy; Old Winter grown weak, on limbs that shiver, Back to the craggy hills must hie. From thence he sends, as he turns to flight, His feeble showers of icy grains; In streaks they light o'er the greening plains; But the sun brooks never a trace of white. All things are stirring, living and striving, All with gay colours would he enliven. Though yet no flowers bloom o'er the lea, This gay-clad crowd in their place takes he. Turn round, and now, from this hillock high, Look back, and fix on the town thine eye. Out of the gloomy, vaulted gate A motley multitude throngs elate. Gladly each suns him on the sward, They hallow the Rising of the Lord; For they themselves have truly risen, From musty rooms, homes most miserable, From handicrafts, trades, as from bonds and prison; From the oppression of roof and gable, From the irksome crush of the narrow way, From churches dim in their sacred night, All with one impulse are seeking light. See, just see! how the crowd swift-advancing Through garden and field are scattering gay. How, o'er the river's broad surface dancing, Crowds of pleasure-boats glide to-day! Almost to sinking overladen, The last skiff pushes from the shore, Bright-hued raiment of youth and maiden Gleams from far hill-paths they wander o'er. I hear the noise of the village fair, The poor folks' real heaven is there. Both great and small shout lustily; Here am I man, and dare to be. Wagner. Doctor, to walk with you is recreation, An honour that much profits me Yet when alone I shun such dissipation; To all that's rude I'm a sworn enemy. Fiddling and shrieking, skittle-pitching, Are noises I have hated long; They howl as though some fiend had set them itching, And call it pleasure, call it song. Peasants under the Linden. Dance and Song. The shepherd deckt him for the dance, Jacket, wreath, ribbon, at a glance The finest fancy showing. The ring was thronged, and lass and lad Under the linden danced like mad. Hurrah! hurrah! hurrah! Hip, hip, hurrah! Blithe went the fiddle-bowing. Quick to the ring he hastened there, His elbow nudged a maiden fair, As past her he was going. The sprightly damsel turned and said: “You seem both stupid and ill-bred!” Hurrah! hurrah! hurrah! Hip, hip, hurrah! “Fine manners you are showing.” Yet soon into the ring they went, Danced right, danced left, her anger spent, While petticoats were flowing. And they grew red, and they grew warm, And rested, panting, arm in arm, Hurrah! hurrah! hurrah! Hip, hip, hurrah! With hip to elbow going. Don't take such liberties with me! How many a trusting maid we see Betrayed, her love bestowing. But soon he wheedled her away From the far linden sounded gay: Hurrah! hurrah! hurrah! Hip, hip, hurrah! Shrill cries and fiddle-bowing. Old Peasant. Herr Doctor, this is kind of you To mix with us you don't disdain, So learned a man, as now you do, While all throng round, to greet you fain. Take then this mug of fine old ware, That with cool drink for you we fill; I bring it now, and wish aloud, Not only that your drouth it still; Each drop it holds of sound old beer Add to your life another year! Faust. This cool, refreshing draught I drain, Thank you, and pledge you all again! (They crowd round him in a circle.) Old Peasant. In sooth, Herr Doctor, you've done well, That you this happy day appear For you, in evil days gone by, Did what you could to help us here, Where many a one stands living now, Whom your good Father, snatched at last From burning fever's rage, I trow; He checked the plague's venemous blast. And you yourself, young as you were, Went into every pesthouse too, Full many a corpse forth did they bear, Yet out unscathed, thank God, came you, Many a hard trial you bore that year; The Helper above helped the helper here. All. Health to the true and well-tried man, Long may he help, as help he can. Faust. To Him above in reverence bend, Who help inspires and help doth send. (He passes on with Wagner.) Wagner. O thou great man, what feelings must be thine, So honoured by these folk who round thee crowd! Oh! happy he with gifts endowed Whence he may draw profit so fine! The Father shows thee to his boy, Each questions, hustles, hastes to gaze, The fiddle stops, the dancer stays, Thou goest, in ranks they stand and stare, Up fly their caps into the air; Little it lacks but they should bend the knee, As came the Venerabile. Faust. A few steps more upward to yonder stone! Let's rest awhile, after our wandering, there. Here often I have sat in thought alone, Torturing myself with fasting and with prayer, In hope still rich, in faith still fast, With tears and sighs my hands oft wringing, I thought that foul plague's end at last To force from God, to Him still clinging. The crowd's applause sounds to me like scorn well won. Oh! could'st thou in my inmost heart but read How little Father and Son Were worth such honour then indeed! My Father was an honest charlatan, O'er Nature's mystic circle would he brood with passion, In all good faith, but in his own strange fashion, His freakish thoughts to reveries ran. He with his Brethren, Adepts able, In smoky Kitchen with locked door, Following receipts innumerable Would loathesome broths together pour. There the Red Lion rose, bold with desire In tepid bath to wed the Lily fair. Then both of them in flaming open fire Were from one marriage-bed to another tortured there— And then appeared a gay-clad Bride, The Young Queen in the crystal glass, Here was our Mithridate, the patients died, And none asked: “Who got well?” Alas! Thus did we rage with hellish boluses Through all these vales, these mountains—these, Worse than the plague, in that fond craze. To thousands I myself the poisonous drug have given; They perished, I must go on living, That the rash murderer men may praise. Wagner. Why grieve with vain remorseful sighing? Does not a man of good renown Enough, the art his father handed down With skill and knowledge punctually plying? If thou, as youth, didst honour thine own sire, Gladly his lore didst thou receive; If thou, as man, for science didst more achieve, Thy son may even reach a goal still higher. Faust. O happy he who still can hope From this deep sea of error at last to rise! What no man knows, each wants, will for it grope, And what he knows can use nowise. But let us not this hour's divinest grace O'ercloud with thoughts born of such sadness! See, as the sun departs with glowing face, Each cottage, bowered in green, blushes for gladness. Weary he sinks, done is his daily round, Yet on he hastes, to call forth life again. Oh! that no wings can lift me from the ground, After him, near, and nearer still to strain! To see in the eternal evenglow Beneath my feet the calm world glowing, Enkindled every height, at rest each vale below, The Silberbach in golden streamlets flowing. Naught now can stay me in my godlike flight, Not the wild mountain with its clefts deep-yawning; And soon with sun-warmed bays the sea is dawning Clearly upon my astonished sight. Though the God seems at last away to sink, New impulse wakes in me new might, I hasten on, his quenchless light to drink, The day before me, after me the night, The heavens above me still, below the billowing sea. A splendid dream, even as it fades away. Ah! for the Spirit's wings it seems but play Mere bodily wings to outrival easily. Yet in each mortal 'tis inborn, His feelings urge him upward, onward still, When o'er us, lost in the blue space of morn, His quivering song the lark doth trill, When o'er the rough crag's bristling pines, The eagle soars on outstretched wing, O'er plain and sea in ordered lines The cranes press home swift voyaging. Wagner. I have had my hours of freakish reverie, But such strange impulse never troubled me. One soon gets tired of seeing field and grove, A bird's wings I ne'er envied, nor desire. How differently the Spirit's joys inspire, From book to book, from page to page to rove! This lends to Winter nights a joy so sweet, A blissful life warms you from head to feet, And ah! when some superb old parchment you unroll, All heaven comes down, your pleasure is complete. Faust. With one strong impulse thou art now possest, To know another school not thy heart! Two souls, alas! are dwelling in my breast, And one would from the other fly apart; One to the world in love's fierce ecstasy With grasping tentacles would ever cling, The other from the gloom on powerful wing To the ancestral fields would flee. Oh! are there spirits in the air That hovering between earth and heaven have sway, Let them stoop from the golden ether there, Bear me to new, more varied life away! Yes, were but a magician's mantle mine, To waft me to strange lands, I trow, I would not barter it for costliest garments now, Not a King's mantle, be it ne'er so fine. Wagner. Oh! call not down the ill-famed multitude, Who, round their misty circles ever going, A thousand plagues for men and perils shrewd, From every quarter still are sowing. From the North comes the stinging “Spirits' Tooth,” Upon you with its arrow-pointed tongues; From the East come they, bringing deadly drouth, And love to feed upon your lungs. When from the South they send the desert-wind, Blast after blast falls glowing on your crown. The West-wind brings the swarm, fresh airs blow kind, Thee and thy field and meadow soon to drown. They hear us gladly still on mischief bent, Obey us gladly, to deceive us trying, They feign that straight from heaven they are sent, Whispering like angels when they are lying. But let us go! The world's already grey, The air grows cool, mist clouds the way. At eve the joys of home we prize— Why stand you so, amazement in your eyes? What, in the twilight can enthrall you so? Faust. See yon black dog tracking through corn and stubble go? Wagner. I saw him long ago, he did not interest me. Faust. Look at him well! What think you the beast to be? Wagner. Merely a poodle, that in his own fashion After his master's trail is worrying. Faust. Observe but how, in those wide circles going, Near and more near to us he's hurrying. And, if I err not, showers of sparks leap glowing Around his path continually. Wagner. Naught but the same black poodle do I see; Some optical delusion it must be. Faust. It seems as he a magic web were weaving About our feet, our future lives to bind. Wagner. I see him timidly, doubtfully round us springing, Two strangers, not his master, here to find. Faust. The circle narrows, now he is near! Wagner. You see, a dog, no ghostly thing is here. He growls, fights shy, then on his belly lies, And wags his tail in doggish wise. Faust. Come along with us then! Come here! Wagner. A comic poodle-dog, 'tis clear. Stand still, he sits, and begs for you; Call him, and he'll come jumping on you too; Lose anything, and he'll soon find that thing, Into the water for your stick he'll spring. Faust. Yes, thou art right; no trace I find remaining Of spirits, good or bad, 'tis all mere training. Wagner. A well-trained dog will gain the faster The affection of so wise a master. Yes, he will well deserve that master's grace Best scholar among students of his race. (They enter the City gate.)</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE III. Faust's Study. Faust, entering with the Poodle. Faust. I have forsaken field and meadow, Enshrouded now in deepest night, With boding of mysterious horror My better soul wakes, craving light. The wilder passions now are sleeping, The rage for fierce activity, The love of Man within me wakens, The love of God awakes in me. Be quiet Poodle! Stop running to and fro! At the threshold why sniffest thou? Behind the stove lie down there—go! My softest cushion I give thee now. As thou out there on the craggy way With running and leaping didst do thy best To cheer us, I pledge thee my word, and say I welcome thee, be but a quiet guest. Ah! when within our narrow cell The friendly lamp burns clear agen Clear in the breast grows all as well In hearts that know themselves, and then Reason once more begins to speak, And Hope once more begins to bloom After Life's brooks yearning we seek, After Life's source—ah! through the gloom. Growl not so Poodle! with the heavenly tones Embracing my whole spirit in ecstasy. Vilely thy brutish howls agree. We are used to this that men ever despise What they don't understand. That the Good, the Beautiful 'neath their eyes Puzzles their dulness, sets them growling; Will my own dog take like them to howling? But ah! with the best will I feel too well Peace in my breast will never more upswell. But wherefore should the stream so soon run dry, And leave me again in thirst to lie? Oft I've experienced the privation, Yet may supply this want in a measure Things higher than earthly we learn to treasure, We long still for some Revelation, Which purer nowhere shines with light Heaven-sent, Than here in the New Testament. I am forced for new examination The ground-text to unclasp once more, With reverent mind, for new examination The Holy Original again to explore, Make in my own dear German a new translation. (He opens the Book, and prepares to write.) 'Tis writ: “In the beginning was the Word,” I stick fast here! Who now can help afford? I cannot for the Word claim power so great, This I must otherwise translate If by the Spirit I am rightly taught, 'Tis writ: “In the beginning was the Thought.” But o'er this first line ponder still Lest over-haste misguide thy quill. Is it the Thought creates, works hour by hour? It should stand: “In the Beginning was the Power.” Yet, as I write it down, unsatisfied, Some warning comes, “In this do not abide.” The Spirit helps! counsel comes now at need, Boldly I write: “In the Beginning was the Deed.” If with thee I must share my dwelling, Poodle stop howling and yelling, Stop barking there! Such a troublesome comrade I ne'er Could tolerate as near neighbour, I trow. One of us now Quits the cell I vow! Guest-right it grieves me to give thee no more, Thy path is free through the open door. But now what must I see! Spawned Nature a thing like thee? Is this a phantom, or see I aright? How swells my poodle in length, breadth, height! He rises with mighty force, No form of a dog shows he! What goblin have I brought home with me! He takes the form of a river-horse, With fiery eyes, and teeth in dreadful row. Ha! now thy race I know! For such as thy half-hellish brood The key of Solomon is good. Spirits in the Passage. Prisoned within is one of us, Stay without, follow him none of us! Like a fox in a trap, Quakes an old Lynx of Hell, mayhap. But beware! Hover near and hover again, Up and down, Till he break the Wizard's chain. If the Seer ye can outwit, In the lurch let him not sit, Plagued by spells that sting and burn, We owe him many a good turn. Faust. To baffle this beast with my lore I need the spell of the Four: Salamander fly glowing, Sylph vanish, in air, Nymph in streamlets fast flowing, Gnome swink in thy lair! Who knows not aright Each element's might All their powers and special dowers, No Master he Of the Spirits' can be. In flames fly glowing, Salamander! Rush in one channel flowing Nymph of the streams! Shine in the meteor's gleams Sylph so light! Tend the house to-night, Incubus, Incubus! Come forth and end this game 'twixt us! None of the Four Has the beast in his core He lies quite quiet and grins at me; I have not twinged him yet I see. For thy probation Hear a stronger conjuration! Mate of my cell Play'st thou truant from Hell? Behold this sign To whose power divine Bow the Hosts of darkness there! He swells up now with bristling hair. Reprobate Spirit, Can'st read, endure it? The Uncreated Ineffable Word Effused through all Heaven, Our sin-pierced Lord. Spell-bound behind the stove he lies, Swelling an elephant in size. Soon the whole room his girth will fill, Then in a cloud away 'twill fleet. Tower not to the very roof Lie down there at thy Master's feet. I threatened not in vain, behold the proof! I'll singe thee now with holy fire Wait not, foul Sprite, The three-times glowing light, Wait not foul Sprite, My Art's most potent assay! Mephistopheles. (As the mist disappears, stepping out from behind the stove in the dress of a Travelling Scholar.) Why all this fuss? Command, and I obey! Faust. This was the poodle's kernel, eh? A travelling scholar, I laugh the climax to see. Mephistopheles. To the learn'd Doctor my respects I pay! Well, you have soundly sweated me. Faust. What is thy name? Mephistopheles. Paltry the question seems For one who treats the Word with such disdain, And, far aloof from all that seems, Still strives to catch Substance in vain. Faust. With you, sirs, one may as usual claim To read your nature in your name, Hence yours one may quite clearly know, When you are called Fly-God, Corrupter, Liar also. Good! but who art thou, then? Mephistopheles. A part of that great Power, Which would work evil still, yet brings forth good each hour. Faust. What hidden meaning in this paradox lies? Mephistopheles. I am the Spirit that still denies! And there I am right for all that space brings forth, Save through destruction is nothing worth. Far better there were no creation, What ye call ruin, sin, devastation, In short all things that ye call evil, Are my own element as Devil! Faust. Thou call'st thyself a part, yet standest whole by me? Mephistopheles. The modest truth I tell to thee. Though Man, that foolish little world, so droll, Is prone to think himself a whole, Part of a part am I, who at the first was all, Part of the Darkness of whom Light was born, Proud Light, that now would work his Mother's Fall, Sieging her ancient throne in space each morn; Yet ne'er succeeds, howe'er his craft he plies, For Light to matter ever clings, From matter streams he, matter beautifies, Matter arrests his thought-swift wings; And soon I hope will come the day When Light in matter's wreck will fade away. Faust. Ha! now I know thy worthy employ! In great things nought can'st thou destroy, So triest thy hand upon things small. Mephistopheles. Yet little way in sooth I make at all. O'er what is Nothing's enemy, That Something, this botched world we see, So far as I have tried as yet, But small advantage I can get, With storms, waves, earthquakes, lightning's brand There, when all's done, at peace lie sea and land! And even from that damned stuff, the beastly-human brood, Nothing I've gained, long as I've worried. How many thousands have I buried Yet ever circulates anew the fresh young blood. So it goes on, one might go mad beholding: In earth and water, as in air A thousand germs one sees unfolding In warmth and cold, in moist and dry! Had I not in the flame reserved a lair, Nought for my private shelter had I. Faust. So strivest thou still to resist Benign creation's motive force, Shak'st at it thy cold Devil's fist And find'st thy spite foiled in due course. Seek, then, some new task to discover, Whimsical Son of Chaos now. Mephistopheles. Well, we must really think it over, At our next meeting, I and thou. But now may I make bold to leave you? Faust. Why thou should'st ask I don't quite see I have but now made thy acquaintance; Pray visit me when thou art free. Here is the door, and here the window, Or by the chimney enter, pray! Mephistopheles. Let me confess, there's a slight hindrance here, I simply cannot walk away, The Druid's Foot upon your threshold. Faust. The Pentagram plagues thee, I fear. Ha! Son of Hell, I prithee tell me If that's a bar, how camest thou in here? How could I such a spirit delude? Mephistopheles. Look at it well! Your drawing is not good. One angle pointing, to the exit now, You left half-open, as you see. Faust. That was a stroke of luck for me! And then my prisoner wast thou Thus no doubt was thy guile confounded! Mephistopheles. The Poodle saw nothing, as headlong in he bounded. But now the thing is t'other way about, The Devil's in the house, and can't get out. Faust. Then why not through the window flee? Mephistopheles. It is the law for Devils and ghost, you see: That where they first creep in they must again creep out. The one way we are free, the other slaves fast-bound. Faust. Hell even has laws? Thou art in pound! That suits me well, can I then make a pact With that swart crew that shall be binding still? Mephistopheles. All that we promise, you shall enjoy at will, We are not stingy, nothing we retract. Terms are not settled easily though, We'll speak of that some early day. And now most earnestly I pray That you will this time let me go. Faust. Yet still a moment more remain, With some good story beguile my leisure! Mephistopheles. Nay, let me go! I'll soon come back again; Then you may question at your pleasure. Faust. I did not set a trap for thee, Into the snare didst thou rush amain. But catch the Devil, and set him free, You'll not so soon ensnare the slippery rogue again. Mephistopheles. Well, if you please, I'm ready here to stay Awhile to keep you company But on condition we wile away The time with my fine magic pleasantly. Faust. I'll see it gladly. Play freely thy part But give me pleasure with thine art! Mephistopheles. Thou shalt, my friend, in this brief hour Learn more of thy own sense's power Than ever in a year before. What now my delicate spirits sing thee, The splendid visions that they bring thee, Are not mere magic but something more. Odours upon thee they will pour, Upon thy palate flavours lavish With joys of sense all senses ravish. We need no dull rehearsal here Begin, ye spirits, hovering near! Spirits. Vanish, ye gloomy Vaults where ye frown! In the ravishing hue Of Heaven's tenderest blue Ether look down! If but the gloomy Clouds would roll by, Stars would be twinkling, Now in the sky Suns mildly gleaming Softly would shine Children of Heaven Spirits divine With undulant motion We see you glide by, Loving and longing, Seek you in the sky, While your bright raiment's Fluttering strands Float o'er the bowers, Float o'er broad lands, Float o'er the bowers Where in revery deep Lovers their troth plight Swear ever to keep. Bower after bower! Vine-branches grow fat, Heavy grape-clusters Fall in the vat, From the wine-press's crushing The clear wine comes foaming, In streamlets fast-gushing Through clear channels roaming, Like jewels down-rushing, Leaving the mountains Lying behind them, Broadening to lakelets, Round hillocks they wind them, Now pleasantly greening, And birds of the air Sip from each streamlet A joy without care. Flying then sunward, Flying away Tow'rd yonder clear islands Far over the bay, That seem to be heaving On billows that sway; Heark to yon chorus, Who, striding along, With voices sonorous Rejoice in their song! In the green meadows The dancers we see Scattered in parties Over the lea. Some in hill-climbing Their pleasure will take, Others are swimming Over the lake And lover by lover The dancers still hover, All glad to be living, All gazing afar, While grace falls from heaven From every star. Mephistopheles. He sleeps! 'Tis well! My elves, airy and young! And soundly too. Well have ye sung, And for this concert I am in your debt Well, thou art not the man the Devil to bind, as yet! Play round him still, with sweet dreams lull his mind, Sink him in seas of phantasy uncouth! But now, to break the threshold-spell, I find The thing I need is a rat's tooth. I need no lengthy conjuration, Soon will come rustling here one of that sharp-eared nation. Lord of rats, and eke of mice, Flies, and frogs and bugs, and lice! Hasten hither without fear, And gnaw for me this threshold here, As though oil on it were dropt— Why here already thou hast hoppt! Now quick to work! The point that bars my way Just tips that angle, nip it, pray! Now one bite more, the thing is done! Till our next merry meeting, Faust, sleep on! Faust (awaking.) Can I then be once more deluded? Vanished is now the throng of Spirits, I see, That with a false dream of the Devil deceived me, And of a poodle that ran away from me.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE IV. Faust's Study. Faust, Mephistopheles. Faust. Who knocks? Come in! What new plague must I dread? Mephistopheles. 'Tis I! Faust. Come in! Mephistopheles. Thrice must the word be said. Faust. Come in, then! Mephistopheles. So you humour me. We soon shall come to terms, I trust! To drive the dumps away from thee, I am here, a gallant squire, with gust Wear this red gold-laced jerkin smart, In stiff silk mantle play my part, With a cock's feather in my cap, And long, sharp rapier at my side; And now I counsel thee to swap Thy gown for garb like mine, that wide, Untrammeled, thou mayst wander free, Experience all that life can be. Faust. In any garments I should feel the pain Of Earth's crampt life too bitterly Too old to take my fling, I see, Too young fond wishes to restrain. What can the world promise me now? Renounce must thou! renounce must thou! That is the everlasting song Ringing in every mortal ear, Which sings to us our whole life long, And every hour more hoarse and drear. Each morn I wake in horror and despair, In bitter tears would burst out weeping, To see each day that on its course will fare, And grant no wish, not one, within me sleeping, Each hope of joy, even, from me wrest, With captious wrangling still destroying, Thwart the dreams of my labouring breast With thousand, paltry tasks annoying. And I must even, when o'er me sinks the night, In anguish stretched upon my bed, Even there find no rest for my head, And from wild dreams awake in fright. The God who in my bosom dwells Can rouse my inmost energies; He who o'er all my active powers is throned Can move the outer world nowise; And so, for me, with Being's burden opprest, Death I desire, hate Life, and so would rest. Mephistopheles. Yet Death, it seems is never a really welcome guest. Faust. Oh! blest is he, in victory's glory Whose temples Death with bloody laurels binds, Whom when the swift rushing dance is over, Clasped in a maiden's arms he finds! Oh! were I, by the highest Spirit's power, Entranced, struck dead, far hence were sunk. Mephistopheles. Yet someone, at a certain hour, That night a brown juice left undrunk. Faust. It is thy sport, it seems, to play the spy. Mephistopheles. Omniscient am I not, though much, 'tis true know I. Faust. When, from the terrible turmoil, A sweet, remembered sound attracted me, Ghosts of my old childish emotions Breathed cheating echoes of bygone glee; And so I curse all that the soul With cheating jugglery would bind, And in this miserable hole With flattering self-delusion blind, Curséd be first high aspirations, With which the Spirit herself arrays! Curst the vain mockeries of appearance, Thronging each gate of sense always! Curst all that comes in dreams deceiving, Those old delusions, Name, and Fame! Curst all that flatters as possession, As wife, child, servant, plough land-claim! Accurst be Mammon, when with treasures He goads us to foolhardy deeds, When he entices to vain pleasures, Serves with soft cushions our lazy needs! Curse on the grape's bright juice balsamic! Curse on Love's noblest graces first, Curséd be Hope! Be Faith accursèd, And, above all, be Patience curst! Invisible Choir of Spirits. Woe! Woe! Thou hast destroyed it The beautiful world, With powerful fist; To destruction 'tis hurled! Ruined by a Demigod's despair We must bear The fragments into nothingness Weeping there O'er the beauty, lost, foredone. Mightier Than the Sons of Earth, Lovelier Build it again, Within thy breast build it once more! New paths of life to explore Begin! Go hence With clearer sense, While new songs then Above it soar! Mephistopheles. These spirits fine Are elves of mine. Hear how they to action's joys Counsel thee in cunning wise! To the world wide, From thy loneliness Where thy blood stagnates, dull grows each sense They would lure thee hence. [Mephistopheles] Hear now, to deal with thy vain sorrow, Which like a vulture feeds upon thy heart, The worst of company would rouse the feeling That among men a man thou art. But 'tis not in my mind With vulgar folk to class thee, Not one of the great I may be; But take me as partner now, Through life thy footsteps to guide, I'll serve thee well-satisfied, On the spot I agree Thy comrade to be, Suit myself to thee willingly now, I'll be thy servant, thy slave, I vow! Faust. And how shall I requite thy service? Mephistopheles. Take as long credit as you list. Faust. Nay, nay! the Devil is an egoist, And for God's sake will do but little To help another when he comes here. Name thy conditions to a tittle, Such slaves are dangerous in one's house, I fear. Mephistopheles. Here I will bind myself to be thy servant, Come at thy call, and rest not, nor delay; When, in the world up there we meet, My service here thou shalt repay. Faust. Little to me up there it matters, And torest thou this world to tatters, From them another may arise. Out of this Earth my joy's clear founts outstart, And this bright Sun shines on my grief of heart; Can I but soon from them depart, Let hap what will in any guise. No more of this I wish to hear, Whether the dead love, hate, desire, Or whether in each far-off sphere There is a lower, and a higher. Mephistopheles. In this sense, then, venture you surely may, Bind yourself, and, this very day, Gladly my sorcery thou shalt see. What no man ever saw I'll give to thee. Faust. What, then, poor Devil talk'st of giving? Was any man's free spirit after things highest striving, Ever been trapt by Spirits like thee? Yet food unsatisfying thou hast, And ruddy gold that changes fast To quicksilver, and runs out of your hand, A game to cheat the winner planned, A wench, who, clinging to your breast, Ogling your neighbour, plights her troth away Honour the demigod's joyous quest, That, like a meteor fades in day. Show me the fruit that, 'ere 'tis plucked, will rot, The trees that every day grow green again! Mephistopheles. Such a strange order frights me not, Such treasures for you I can obtain. But, my good friend, the time is come, I see, When something good we may enjoy at leisure. Faust. If e'er on slothful bed I loll with pleasure, In that base hour all's up with me! Can'st thou with flattery so deceive me, That satisfy myself I may, Canst thou with all Earth's joys befraud me, Be that for me my life's last day! Take you my wager? Mephistopheles. Done! Faust. And done with thee! If to the moment I shall say: “Tarry, so beautiful thou art!” Bind me in fetters then ye may, And back to earth go brain and heart! Then for me may the death-bell toll, Then from thy service thou art free, The clock may stop, hands mark life's goal, And Time shall be no more for me! Mephistopheles. Ponder it well! this we shall not forget. Faust. I grant thy right to have thy hire. Not wantonly did I incur this debt, To thee or others, I don't inquire. Mephistopheles. I'll go to-day to the new Doctor's feast, And serve thee there with all goodwill. But one thing, live thou or die, at least, Give me but two strokes of thy quill. Faust. Pedant, thou cravest a written bond, I see, Hast thou ne'er known a man, known what his word can be? Is not my spoken word enough as gage Valid through all the days assigned me? Does not the world through all its arteries rage, And shall a promise for ever bind me? Yet this delusion makes our hearts its nest; Who shall get free, when its webs enwind me? Happy the man, true honour in his breast Who rues no loss incurred thereby! But a mere parchment, signed and sealed, at best, Is but a ghost, whereof all men fight shy. The word's already dead in the goose-feather, The world is ruled by wax and leather. What wilt thou Evil Spirit from me? Bronze, marble, parchment, paper, shall it be? Style, chisel, quill, to write with shall I use? Thy choice is free, pray take thy pick! Mephistopheles. Why these hot floods of rhetoric Exaggerated and profuse? A single leaflet is just as good So you but sign it with a little drop of blood. Faust. If this will fully satisfy thee, The trifle I will not deny thee. Mephistopheles. Blood is a quite peculiar juice. Faust (signing the bond.) Then have no fear that I this bond will break. My utmost power I'll strive to use, To keep the promises I make. I have swelled too high in vanity, Among thy peers only I take my place. That mighty Spirit flung scorn on me. Nature before me veils her face. The thread of thought is rent in twain, Long have loathed all our Science vain. In the depths of sensuality Let my glowing passions be stilled for ever, Behind the magic veil, rent never Each miracle promptly prepare for me! In the rushing of Time let us plunge straightway, In the world of action our part let's play! So then may sorrow and joy, Success and heart's annoy, Change with each other as they can, Restless endeavour tests the man. Mephistopheles. Measure nor limit bounds you nowise, Range where you will, and take your fling, Catch every moment on the wing Have every thing that most your prize, And fear not while to me you cling. Faust. Nay, hear me, mere delight is not the question, To Life's wild drunkenness myself I consecrate, To fond hates, quickening griefs, joys that are pain. My breast, from learning's dull oppression healing, To no man's woe shall e'er be closed again. And what to all mankind is dealt by Fate I, in my inmost self will joy in feeling, With my own Spirit grasp all things, high or low Store in my bosom all their weal and woe, So my own self through their selves shall extend, Till, even as they, I am shattered at life's end. Mephistopheles. Oh! trust me, who for many a thousand year, This hard and bitter cud have chewed, None, from the cradle to the bier, Could e'er digest this yeasty food. This Whole, if you'll believe my story, Was only fashioned for a God! He finds Himself throned in Eternal Glory, In utter darkness, us He hath pent from Light, While ye are fashioned for day and night. Faust. I'll work my will! Mephistopheles. Well, that may be! One thing I fear, though will be strong, That Time is short, and Art is long, I think, you'll now be schooled by me. Take some Poet as partner and share your views, Let the gentleman, roving, think in your stead, Each noble quality you choose Heap them upon your honoured head: The Lion's courage, The Stag's swift flight, The Italian's blood of fire The North's enduring might. Let him for you the secret find, Nobility with craft to bind, And with warm impulses of youth Make you a love-making plan, forsooth. If such a Lord himself might know, “Lord Microcosm” I'd style him, though. Faust. What am I, then, if 'tis not in my power The crown of manhood even to gain, Tow'rd which all senses strive in vain? Mephistopheles. Thou art in the end—just what thou art. Put then upon thy head a wig with million locks, Prop thy feet on a pair of yard-high socks, Thou still remainest—just what thou art. Faust. I feel it, vainly have I at every treasure Of man's keen spirit snatched as it went by, And now at last, when I sit down at leisure, No new power springs within me as they fly. I am not by a hairsbreadth higher, Nor to the Infinite am I nigher. Mephistopheles. My good Sir, you but see the matter As everyone the matter sees; We must be cleverer in our scheming, Before the joy of living flees. Hast thou not hands, feet, head—deuce take it? And other organs too are thine! But all things while I can enjoy them, Are they therefore less truly mine? If I, forsooth, can buy six stallions, Are not mine then their strength and speed? As though on four and twenty feet careering I drive along and am a man indeed. Up then! let all this thinking be, Come straight into the world with me! I tell thee a fellow lost in thoughts profound Is like a beast on a rough heath astray, And which some Evil Spirit drives always round and round, While pastures green lie all about his way. Faust. Where then shall we begin? Mephistopheles. Forth now, out of this tomb. What kind of torture-chamber is this room? What life is thine, o'er parchments poring, Thyself thy pupils ever boring? Leave that to Master Bug, thy neighbour! Why wilt thou plague thyself in threshing straw? What's best in the knowledge gained by thy labour, Thou durst not share with boys quite raw. I hear one at the door already. Faust. I really can't see him to-day. Mephistopheles. So long the poor young chap has waited, He shan't go unconsoled away. Come, give me your cap and gown; and flit! This masquerade's a treat for me. (He puts on Faust's cap and gown.) Now leave it to my mother-wit! But fifteen minutes will suffice me quite Meanwhile get ready for our pleasant flight. [Exit Faust] Mephistopheles (in Faust's long gown.) Contemn only reason and learning's dower, Of all mankind supremest power, Be thou in magical delusion Confirmed still by the Spirit of Lies, So thou art mine without conditions— Fate has endowed him with a spirit that flies Ever upon its path, restless, straight forward, And in its ever-hastening flight Springs over all the joys of Earth. I'll drag him through wild life with me Through dullest scenes of vulgar mirth, Flounder, grow numb, stick fast shall he; For his insatiate appetite Meat and drink 'fore his greedy lips shall hover; For refreshment then he will pray in vain; And even had he not himself to the Devil made over, Still he must perish utterly! (A Student enters.) Student. I came here some few days ago, With deep respect I wait on you, To speak with you, a man to know, Whose name all mention with reverence due. Mephistopheles. Your courtesy much pleases me! A man like other men you see. Have you looked round, seeking your way? Student. For your kind interest let me pray! I come here in a quite earnest mood, With little money and fresh young blood; My Mother would hardly let me go: Mephistopheles. Here is the very place for you. Student. I wish I were out of it, 'tis true: Within each portico, each hall, No pleasure I can feel at all. Pent in such cells I've never been, Without a tree with nothing green. The Lecture Room, with narrow benches Dulls sight, mars hearing and thinking quenches. Mephistopheles. Custom alone cures that, my boy. The baby takes its mother's breast, When given it first, with little joy, But soon it feeds with hungry zest. So at the Breasts of Wisdom, you Will find each day your thirst renew. Student. Around her neck will I most gladly cling But tell me how to approach her—that's the thing. Mephistopheles. Ere you go further enlighten me, What do you choose for your Faculty? Student. Thoroughly learned I wish to be All things on Earth I fain would know, All things in Heaven would comprehend Science and Nature investigate. Mephistopheles. There you're on the right track, my friend; But time and strength you must not dissipate. Student. I am with you there in body and soul But frankly I should like some pleasure A little freedom when at leisure In the warm summer holidays to stroll. Mephistopheles. Use well your time, it runs so fast away, Order will teach you to save time each day. And, my dear friend, my advice is this, Your College Logic pray do not miss. Then will your intellect be well braced, In Spanish boots tightly enlaced, That you discreetly, as one ought May creep along the Path of Thought. And don't go roving here and there, Will-o-the-wisping every where. Then they will teach you many a day What at one blow achieve you may As easily as eat and drink, One! Two! Three! useful don't you think? 'Tis true that the great web of thought Like a weaver's masterpiece should be wrought, Where a thousand threads at one stroke unwind, The shuttle over and under plying, The unseen threads up, downward flying, Each stroke a thousand threads will bind. Here the Philosopher, you see, Steps in and tells you “so it must be”: The first was so, the second so, Therefore the third and fourth are so. And, were the first and second not there, The third and fourth would be nowhere.” This everywhere the Scholars extol, Yet grow not weavers after all. Who wishes things living to know and to portray, Seeks first their spirit to drive away Then, in his hand as he holds each part, Naught lacks but the spirit's combining art. Self-styled Encheiresin Naturae, chemistry Makes a mock of herself and naught of it knows she. Student. I can't quite understand you here. Mephistopheles. The next time all will grow more clear, When all things you can reduce to terms, And classify your learning's germs. Student. So stupified by all this I feel, As if in my head whirled a water-wheel. Mephistopheles. Next, before all things, you must perforce Get through your Metaphysical course. See you profoundly comprehend What puzzles all human brains, my friend; For what goes through them, and what goes not, A splendid and useful word we've got. But, above this, all first half-year, Come regularly each course to hear! Five hours they'll give you every day, Be there at the first clock-stroke, pray! Be well prepared before you go, Each paragraph you well should know, That you may see, while there you sit, Your Don says nought save what in the book is writ; Take pains your text be neatly engrossed, As 'twere dictated by the Holy Ghost! Student. You need not say that twice to me! I feel how useful that must be; For what one has in black and white One can take home, contented quite. Mephistopheles. And now, pray choose your Faculty. Student. For Law I must confess no prepossession. Mephistopheles. I blame not your dislike to that profession. I know how things are done in law, you see. Statutes and rights all men inherit, Like an eternal dire disease; They drag from generation to generation, And still they change by slow degrees. Reason grows folly, kindness a curse's mask. Woe to you, your forefathers' heir! The rights born with us are no man's care, Of these, alas! none deigns to ask. Student. My loathing is by you increased. Happy is he you teach at least! Perhaps Theology would be more in my way? Mephistopheles. I do not wish to lead your steps astray. As to that science I can scarce advise; It is so difficult to shun false paths, you see. Here so much deeply hidden poison lies, That from the medicine scarce discerned can be. Here also it were best if you but One will hear, And by the Master's Word shall swear. In fine then—by the Word, hold fast! Then go through the sure door at last, Into the Temple of certainty. Student. But some clear concept in the Word must be. Mephistopheles. True, but one need not ply self-torture too severe; When one's conception is not clear A word turns up at the right time, you see, With words one can fence finely ever, With words can fashion a system clever In words one can firmly believe, No jot from a word you can slyly thieve. Student. Pardon my interrupting with more questions But I must trouble you once more. Concerning Medicine and its lore I beg some valuable suggestions. Three short years soon away will glide, And God! The field is quite too wide. Had one some finger post, I own, I might begin to find my way. Mephistopheles (aside). I'm getting tired of this dry tone, And now again the Devil must play. (aloud) The Spirit of Medicine you soon may seize; The great world and the small profoundly know, And at the end let all things go, As God may please. In vain you rove through all the sciences, Everyone only learns just what he can But he who can the moment seize, He is the real man. You seem well-built, as young men go, Not without boldness, I surmise, Dare then to trust yourself. If so Others will trust in you likewise. 'Fore all learn how to manage women, Their everlasting moans and sighs, Their thousand various diseases Are curable at one point, where they arise; And when you treat them half-modestly You have them well in hand, you'll see. First make your title good to be familiar, That your skill may surpass that of your peers; You are welcome then to feel your way to many a trifle, For which another man might strive for years. Learn then their languid pulses well to squeeze, Then, with sly, ardent eyes, fast as you please, Grip them around the slender waist, To see how tightly they are laced. Student. Well, that looks better! The how and why one sees. Mephistopheles. Grey, my dear friend, are all fine theories, While ever Life's golden tree is green. Student. It seems, I vow, that dreaming I have been. Might I but come to trouble you once more! To hear on what you found your wisdom's lore? Mephistopheles. I'll do for you whate'er I may. Student. I scarce can tear myself away. I must present my Album, ere I go, And beg from you a line or so? Mephistopheles. With pleasure! (He writes and returns the book.) Student (reads.) “Eritis sicut Deus, scientes bonum et malum.” [He respectfully takes his leave] Mephistopheles. Follow the ancient tale, and my good cousin the Snake then, Spite of the likeness to God thy heart with horror shall quake then! (Re-enter Faust. Faust. Well, where now shall we go? Mephistopheles. Where'er it pleases thee. The little World and then the Great we'll see. With how much profit, how much pleasure, We'll sponge upon the whole World's treasure. Faust. But with this long beard that I wear I lack the worldling's easy air. Small joy this rash attempt will bring me I know not how into the World to fling me. With others so small I feel myself, I shall get laid upon the shelf. Mephistopheles. My good friend, all gives way to those who strive. When thou canst trust thyself, then thou hast learnt to live. Faust. How shall we from the house get clear? Where hast thou coachman, coach and pair? Mephistopheles. We just unfold this mantle here, Which soon will waft us through the air. But take with thee in our bold flight No heavy luggage, something light. A little hydrogen, that I'll prepare before, And nimbly from the Earth we'll soar. If we are light, aloft we'll quickly fly, And joy in thy new life I wish thee heartily!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE V. Auerbach's Cellar in Leipzig. Drinking-bout of Jolly Fellows. Frosch. Will no one drink? A laugh who raises? I'll teach you to sit making faces! To-day you're like wet straw, I see, Once ye could blaze quite brilliantly. Brander. It rests on thee; thy wit brings forth, confess, No sottish jest, no spicy hoggishness. Frosch (emptying a glass of wine on Brander's head.) There thou hast both. Brander. Thou double swine! Frosch. That one must be, 'twas your wish, not mine. Siebel. Who quarrels here, show him the door! With a full breast sing a round, swipe and roar! Up! Holla! ho! Altmayer. Woe's me, I'm done for. Here! Some cotton-wool! The brute has burst my ear. Siebel. When round the roof the echoes go, You soon begin the Bass's power to know. Frosch. Right! Out with him who takes a jest so ill! Ah! trall-lal-lal, lal-la! Altmayer. Ah! trall-lal-lal, lal lal lalla! Frosch. Your throats are well-tuned still. (sings) The dear old Holy Roman State, Now holds it now together? Brander. A scurvy song! Fie! a political song! A sorry song! Each morn thank God up there, The Roman Kingdom does not need your care! I hold it now at least a gain for me, Nor Emperor, nor Chancellor I be. But even if we must have an overlord, We'll choose a Pope with one accord. Ye know what kind of quality May turn the scale, the man raise high. Frosch (sings.) Nightingale, soar far and free, A thousand times greet my Love for me! Siebel. No greeting to thy Love! No more of that I'll hear! Frosch. I greet and kiss my dove! No bar from thee I fear! (sings) At still midnight lift the latch, Draw the bolt, thy Love doth watch Bolt the door! Morn peeps once more. Siebel. Ay, praise and celebrate her, sing it o'er and o'er! At my own time I'll burst with laughter. She led me on, with thee the same old game she's after. Now may some Kobold have her for his mate! At the cross-roads jest with his pretty sweeting, An old buck-goat, come from the Blocksberg late, May bleat her, galloping by a good-night greeting! A lusty lad of flesh and blood Is for the hussey much too good. From me no greeting shall she get. Save that I'll break her windows yet. Brander (thumping the table.) Give o'er! give o'er! be ruled by me! Gentlemen, confess that Life I know: Two love-sick fools sit here, I see, Precedence now by rank must go. Attention, a song in the newest style! And chant ye the chorus loud the while! (he sings) Her way to a cellar a rat once found And lived on fat and butter, And soon her little paunch grew round As that of Doctor Luther. The cook laid poison in her way Her world grew narrower every day, As though she had love in her body. Chorus (shouting joyously.) As though she had love in her body. Brander. She roved around, she roved away In pools her thirst assuaging, She gnawed, scratched round the house all day, Nought stayed the venom's raging; She leaped in anguish, leaped again, Soon the poor beast had enough of pain, As though she had love in her body. Chorus. As though she had love in her body. Brander. She came for torture to the clear day, And crept about the kitchen, Fell on the hearth, and writhing lay, Panting for breath, and twitching. Then laughed her poisoner, “week, week, week!” Ha! there she pipes out her last squeak, As though she had love in her body. Chorus. As though she had love in her body. Siebel. What these dull fellows call enjoyment! Poison for a rat to strew, Is, I am sure, a fine employment! Brander. Do rats find favour, then, with you? Altmayer. This bald-head with his fat pot-belly! His bad luck makes him mild and tame, In the swoln rat's ill fate, I tell ye, Seeing his own image his pity claim. (Enter Faust and Mephistopheles.) Mephistopheles. Before all else I must usher thee Here into jovial company, To show thee how lightly life can pass away, With folk who make each day a holiday. With little wit, much jollity, To dance the same old round they never fail, Like a young cat after its tail. And when from headache they are free Long as the host presents no bill, Without a care, they are jolly still. Brander. From travel they have just come here, In their outlandish manners that is clear; They've not been here an hour, I see. Frosch, There truly thou art right! Hurrah! Leipzig for me! Paris in little, she educates her youth. Siebel. What strange folk are they, think you in sooth? Frosch. Let me go sample them! O'er a full glass I'll draw, as easily as a child's tooth, The maggots from their noses, or I'm an ass. They come of a good House, it would appear,— They look proud, and not well-contented here. Brander. Mere charlatans, I bet a pottle! Altmayer. Perhaps? Frosch. Just watch, I'll wipe that fellow's eye! Mephistopheles (to Faust). Folk never guess the Devil is nigh Until he grips them by the throttle. Faust. We greet you, gentlemen! Siebel. Thanks, we in turn salute. (Aside, looking at Mephistopheles.) Why halts the fellow upon one foot? Mephistopheles. May I beg that to your table you invite us? Instead of the good liquor we cannot count on here, Your company would much delight us. Altmayer. You are a connaisseur, 'tis clear. Frosch. You have lately come from Rippach, tell me pray, Have you just spent a night in supping with Jack Ketch? Mephistopheles. To-day we passed him, your town to fetch; The last time we enjoyed his conversation, About his cousins he has much to say, Sent many greetings to each blood-relation. (He bows to Frosch. Altmayer. He had you there! He twigs! Siebel. A knowing chap is he! Frosch. Just wait, I'll best him presently! Mephistopheles. We heard, I think, or am I wrong? Trained voices in full chorus singing? How splendidly a jovial song Must set the ceiling's echoes ringing! Frosch. You are a virtuoso at any rate? Mephistopheles. Ah no! my power is small, my love of art is great. Altmayre. Give us a song! Mephistopheles. A budget, if you incline. Siebel. Then give us, pray, some brand-new strain! Mephistopheles. We have but just come back from Spain, That glorious land of melody and wine. (sings) There was a King of old time, Who had a monstrous flea— Frosch. Hear that! a flea! Have you well caught the jest? A flea is truly a charming guest. Mephistopheles. There was a King of old time, Who had a monstrous flea, He loved it not a little, As it his son might be. He called for his own tailor, The tailor quickly came: “Come measure the Squire for a jacket, And breeches of the same!” Brander. Be sure to tell that tailor, in a twinkling To measure him quite perfectly, And, lest his head the forfeit be, To fit those breeches without wrinkling! Mephistopheles. And now in silk and satin Was he completely drest, With ribbons on his jacket, An order on his breast. A Minister they made him, And a huge star wore he, At Court all his relations Held posts of dignity. On courtiers and their ladies Like plague they quickly fell, The Queen and Maids in Waiting Were stung and bitten well. They dared not crack the vermin, And scratch the itch away; We grip him, and we nip him, When one makes us his prey. Chorus (with enthusiasm.) We grip him, and we nip him, When one makes us his prey. Frosch. Bravo! bravo! That was fine, Siebel. Be that the fate of every flea! Brander. Point your finger, and squashed is he! Altmayer. Hurrah for freedom! Hurrah for wine! Mephistopheles. To honour Liberty a glass I'd gladly drain. If but these wines of yours were better worth the pain. Siebel. That we don't want to hear again! Mephistopheles. Our Host, I fear would take it crustily, Or I would give each worthy guest From our own cellar, of the best. Siebel. Out with it, I'll take the blame on me. Frosch. Give us but one good glass, our praises shall be ample. But don't be stingy with your sample. If I'm your taster for the job, With a good mouthful drench my gob. Altmater (aside.) They come, I fancy, from Rhine's green shore. Mephistopheles. Get me a gimblet now! Brander. What will you do with it? You can't have got your casks outside the door? Altmayer. Behind there stands the Host's tool-basket, with his kit. Mephistopheles (takes out a gimblet: to Frosch.) What would you sample? Take your pick! Frosch. How do you mean? Have you all kinds at will? Mephistopheles. Each freely choose, and damn the bill! Altmayer (to Frosch.) Aha! already you begin your lips to lick. Frosch. Good then, if I may choose, Rhine wine whate'er the brand, The very best of gifts come from the Fatherland. Mephistopheles (while he bores a hole in the edge of the table where Frosch sits.) Give me a piece of wax, and soon I'll make some corks. Altmayer. Ah! that's the way the Juggler works. Mephistopheles (to Brander). And you? Brander. Champagne's the wine for me, Sparkling and foaming let it be! (Mephistopheles bores, while one of the others makes stoppers and plugs the holes.) Brander. At foreign wares one can't always cavil, Good things oft lie far from our view. Your true-bred German hates all Frenchmen like the Devil; But drinks their wines, and likes them too. Siebel (as Mephistopheles approaches his place.) Sour stuff, I must confess, I shun always. A glass of pure sweet wine then, pray! Mephistopheles. Here soon for you shall flow Tokay. Altmayer. Nay, gentlemen, look in my face! I see that you are making us your jest. Mephistopheles. Hey! hey! To mock each noble guest Would be too perilous a trick. Say then what would you have, be quick! With what wines can I serve you now? Altmayer. With each in turn, and soon, 'twere best! (After all the holes have been bored and stopt.) Mephistopheles (with strange gestures.) Grapes the vine bears, and no thorns, And the buck-goat bears his horns! The wine is juicy, the vine-branch wood, This wooden table gives wine as good. A piercing glance through Nature's veil, Only believe, here's a miracle! Now draw the plugs, quaff at your ease! All (as they draw the plugs the wine desired by each flows into his glass.) Fair spring that flows with wines like these! Mephistopheles. Only beware that ye spill nothing, please! (They drink, and drink again.) All (sing.) Jolly as cannibals are we Or as five hundred sows, O! Mephistopheles. The louts are at their ease, see how they enjoy their spree! Faust. Let us go now, I'm past all patience! Mephistopheles. But, just observe, their bestiality Grows ripe for splendid revelations. Siebel (drinking carelessly the wine flows over the floor, and turns to flame.) Help! Fire! Help here! Hell's flame's unpent! Mephistopheles (rebuking the flame.) Be quiet, friendly Element! (to the Company) This time 'twas but a drop of purgatorial fire. Siebel. What's this? Wait! You shall smart for this, mad Squire! You know us not, that's evident. Frosch. Let him with his vile tricks again provoke us! Altmayre. I think 'twere best we now run him out quietly. Siebel. What sir? You dare such jests with me, Play on us here your hocus-pocus? Mephistopheles. Shut up, old wine-cask! Siebel. You broomstick, you! You dare again to treat us rudely? Brander. Just wait! We'll dust your jacket shrewdly! Altmayer (draws a plug out of the table. Fire springs out on him.) I'm burning! burning! Siebel. Sorcery! Stab him! Some outlaw he must be! (They draw their knives and attack Mephistopheles.) Mephistopheles (with solemn gestures.) Vision false, and spell Change sense and place as well! Here, yet there be! (They stand in amazement, and gaze at each other.) Altmayer. Where am I? What a lovely land! Frosch. Vineyards! Or see I aright? Siebel. And grapes close to my hand! Brander. Here, neath green bowers, whose branches twine, See what fine grapes! See what a vine! (He seizes Siebel by the nose. All seize each other in the same way, and draw their knives.) Mephistopheles (as above.) Error loose their eyes from band! Mark how the Devil his humour shows! (Vanishes with Faust. The Comrades release each other and separate.) Siebel. What's up! Altmayer. Eh? Frosch. What! Was that thy nose? Brander (to Siebel). And thine I've got still in my hand! Altmayer. I felt a shock that seemed my limbs to tear! I'm swooning! Quick, bring me a chair! Frosch. But what has happened, pray explain. Siebel. Where is the chap? Track him once more, He shan't escape alive again! Altmayer. I saw him myself ride through the cellar door— Upon a cask. I saw it plain— Heavy as lead my feet are growing (turning to the table.) Think! If the wine-stream still were flowing? Siebel. All was delusion, falsehood, sham. Frosch. Yet I drank wine, half sure I am. Brander. But, for those grapes? Was all but spell? Altmayer. Tell me, should one believe no miracle?</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE VI. Witch's Kitchen. (On a low hearth a huge caldron is set over the fire. In the steam that rises from it many strange shapes appear. A female Monkey sits by the caldron, skims it, and sees that it does not boil over. The Male Monkey with a young one sits near, and warms himself. The walls and ceiling are bedecked with strange Witch's furniture.) Enter Faust and Mephistopheles. Faust. Oh! how I loathe mad magic rites like these! And dost thou promise my life's disease By this vile dotage cured shall be? Do I need counsel now from an old wife? And shall this filthy cookery Take thirty years from body and life? Woe's me, if naught better thy skill can find, All hope is vanished now for me. Has Nature? Has a Spirit of subtle mind No balsam found, not one? How can this be? Mephistopheles. Once more thou speakest sooth, my Friend! There is a natural means to make thee young again; But in another book the text is penned, 'Tis a strange chapter, conned with pain. Faust. I wish to know it. Mephistopheles. Good! a means gold cannot wield, Magic nor medicine obtain: Go then at once out to the field, Begin to chop and delve amain, Keep thyself and thy thoughts within The narrowest circle with labour shrewd Nourish thyself with simple food. Live with thy beasts as beast, think it not robbery, The field thou reapest should be dunged by thee; This, trust me, the best way appears To keep thee young at eighty years. Faust. I am not used to this, such work I could not stand, Took I a spade into my hand. This narrow life is quite unfit for me. Mephistopheles. Then must the witch work the spell for thee. Faust. Why just this Hag then do we need? Can'st thou thyself this drink not brew? Mephistopheles. A pretty pastime that indeed! A thousand bridges I'd build, while seethed the stew. It needs not science and art alone, But patience while the work is done. A quiet spirit must work for years, long hours; Time only gives the ferment its full powers. And all things that pertain thereto Are wondrous mysteries, you may take it The Devil himself devised the brew; But even the Devil could never make it. (Looking at the Monkeys.) Watch these fair creatures at their trade! That is the man! and that the maid! (To the Monkeys.) It seems the Dame's not in the house? Monkeys. To carouse, Out of the house Up the chimney she's flown! Mephistopheles. How long stays she feasting with toothless jaws? Monkeys. As long as we are warming our paws. Mephistopheles. How findest thou this pretty pair? Faust. Things so disgusting I ne'er saw anywhere! Mephistopheles. Nay, conversation such as this, Is just what I were loath to miss! (To the Monkeys.) But tell me then, accursed puppet Why stir ye round this bubbling brew? Monkeys. We cook thin beggars' broth—they sup it. Mephistopheles. A roaring trade then ye must do. Male Monkey. The dice let's pitch, And make me rich, Let me win from thee! My luck has been bad, If money I had Half-crazed I should be. Mephistopheles. How happy even this dolt would think himself If in a lottery he could win pelf! (The young Monkeys have meanwhile been playing with a large ball, and roll it out.) Male Monkey. The world is this ball, 'Twill rise and fall, And still it will roll; It rings like glass: Which, soon breaks, alas! 'Tis hollow inside. Here shines the sphere, Yet brighter here. I'm a living soul! My darling son, Let it alone! Thou must die! From clay 'twas blown, Into shards will fly. Mephistopheles. What use is that sieve? Male Monkey (taking it down.) If thou shouldst thieve, I should soon spy thy game. (He runs over to the Female Monkey and makes her look through it.) Look through the sieve! See'st anyone thieve, Whom thou dar'st not name? Mephistopheles (coming to the fire.) What's in this pot? Male Monkey. The poor fool knows not! He knows not the pot, He knows not the kettle! Mephistopheles. Uncivil brute! Male Monkey. Take that mop there, And sit on the settle! (He makes Mephistopheles sit down.) Faust (who meanwhile has stood before a mirror and drawn close to it, and then moved back from it.) What do I see? What heavenly shape Shows itself in this magic glass! O Love, lend me but thy swiftest wings to escape, And bring me where her footsteps pass! Ah! when from this one spot I move, too bold, Dare to her now to go too nigh, I can but see her as though clouds dimmed mine eye! Of womanhood the fairest mould! Is't possible, is woman so fair? Must I, in this perfect form reclining there, The very essence of all the heavens behold? Can aught like this exist on earth? Mephistopheles. Naturally, when a God troubled Himself six days, Cried bravo! at last in His own praise, Some clever work must come to birth. Gaze now, till thou art satisfied; I know where we can pick up such a treasure, Happy is he whom Fortune gives a bride, A bridegroom can take home with pleasure! (Faust still remains gazing into the mirror, while Mephistopheles stretching himself on the settle, playing with the mop, and begins to speak.) Here I sit like a king upon his throne, The sceptre here I hold, lack but the crown alone. (The Monkeys, who have been moving about one another with strange gestures, now bring Mephistopheles a crown, with a great cry.) Oh! be so good With sweat and with blood This crown to glue! (They move awkwardly around with the crown, which they break into two pieces, with which they skip about.) Monkeys. Now all's up, let it be! We speak and we see, We hear and rhyme too! Faust (before the mirror.) Alas! what craze comes over me? Mephistopheles (watching the Monkeys.) And my own brain almost begins to twirl! Monkeys. When happy are we, When all things agree Thoughts come in a whirl! Faust (in the same place.) My breast begins to burn within me! Let us but quickly get away! Mephistopheles (still on the settle.) Well, now at least one must acknowledge That real poets exist to-day. (The caldron, which the Monkeys have left untended, begins to boil over; a great flame arises, which rushes up the chimney. The Witch comes down through the flames, with an appalling shriek.) Witch. Ow! ow! ow! ow! Ye damnèd beasts! accursèd sow! Neglect the caldron, singe your Dame! Accursèd beasts! (Seeing Faust and Mephistopheles.) What is this here? Who are you here? What want ye there? Who slinks in so? The fire's fierce woe Through your carcase glow! (She dips the ladle in the pot, and flings fire towards Faust, Mephistopheles, and the Monkeys. The Monkeys whine.) Mephistopheles. (who holds the mop in his hands, turns and strikes with it among the glasses and pots.) In two! in two! There lies the brew! There lies the glass, Mere sport it was, Thou carrion, I Beat time to thy melody. (While the Witch, full of fury and terror steps back.) Knowest thou me? Old Carcase! Thou scarecrow, thou! Knowest thou not thy Lord and Master? What hinders me from smashing now Thee and thy Monkeys here, like shapes in plaster? Hast thou for my red jacket no more respect? Have I concealed my face, fair Dame? Canst thou my smart cock's feather not recollect? Perphaps I must even tell my name? Witch. My Lord, this rude greeting pardon me! But your colt's foot I cannot see, And where are your pair of ravens, pray? Mephistopheles. This time thou may'st get off scot-free; For truly 'tis a long time now since we Have seen each other, I must say. Culture too, which the world licks up so fast, Has reached the Devil himself at last; The Northern Phantom now none sees in twilight pale; Where spiest thou horns, and claws, and tail? As to my foot indeed, which part with ne'er I can, 'Mong the gay crowd 'twould damage me; Therefore I've worn, like many a smart young man, False calves for years, as you may see. Witch (dancing.) I'm reft of sense and reason sheer, Do I then see Squire Satan here? Mephistopheles. Woman, that name I can't permit! Witch. Why? How are you annoyed by it? Mephistopheles. 'Tis writ in fable-books, long stale folk-lore; Yet men are better for it not a whit. Freed from the Wicked One, they are wicked as before. Call me then “Baron,” pray, the title's just as good; Like other cavaliers, I am a Cavalier. Thou art not doubtful of my noble blood; The arms I bear will prove it, see them here! (He makes an indecent gesture. Witch (laughing immoderately.) Ha! ha! That's just your style, I swear, You are the same old rogue you always were. Mephistopheles (to Faust.) My friend, learn well this method, which is The only proper way to deal with witches. Witch. Now, sirs, what can I do for you? Mephistopheles. Give us a good glass of thy famous juice, But give us, please, your oldest brew, Each year doubles its powers for use. Witch. Gladly! a flask in on my shelf, I sometimes take a nip myself. 'Tis now free from the slightest stink; Gladly I'll give you a small glass. But, if this man quite unprepared should drink, You know well he would die before an hour should pass. Mephistopheles. He's a good friend, with whom it will agree; Give him a bumper of thy bree! (Witch with strange gestures draws a circle and places curious things within it; while the glasses begin to ring, and the caldron to sound, and make music. Finally she brings a huge book and places the monkeys in the circle, so as to serve her as a reading-desk, while they hold torches. She then beckons Faust to come to her.) Faust (to Mephistopheles.) Nay, tell me what all this may be? This silly stuff, mad posturing I see This foul repulsive conjuring, I know it well, and hate the thing. Mephistopheles. Fudge! Tricks to laughter that provoke us Don't play the harsh, and strait-laced man! Like Doctors, she must play her hocus-pocus, That well the juice may serve you, as it can. (He forces Faust to enter the circle.) Witch (beginning to recite from the Book with exaggerated emphasis.) This thou must ken! From One make Ten, Take Two off then, Quick make it Three, Rich thou shalt be. The Four out score! From Five and Six, So the Witch speaks, Make Seven and Eight, Sealed is thy fate: And Nine is One, And Ten is None. That is the Witch's One-times-One! Faust. The Crone, I think, speaks as in fever. Mephistopheles. That kind of rant goes on for ever. I know it well, so rings the Book all through; I have lost much time with it, skimming its pages, Flat contradiction, it is true, Is mystery alike to fools as 'tis to sages. My friend the art's old, yet new, you see, The method of every age, in sooth, With Three and One, and One and Three, Error to spread instead of truth. Men prate and teach sans doubt or fear; Who cares to meddle with a fool? Men commonly believe, when but fine words they hear, Some food for thought they think must lurk there, as a rule. Witch (stepping out of the circle.) The lofty power Of Wisdom's dower, From all the world concealed, Is given to him Whose wits are dim, Without his care revealed. Faust. Why drones she to us this nonsense drear? My wretched skull 'twill soon be breaking In one great chorus I think I hear A hundred thousand mad-folk speaking. Mephistopheles. Enough, enough, O Sibyl without peer! Give us thy drink and fetch it here, Fill to the brim the cup, and quickly now; With my good friend the draught will well agree, A man of many grades is he, Who has swallowed much ere this, I trow. Witch (with many ceremonies presents the drink in a cup.) Down with it quick! No heel taps now! Thy heart 'twill gladden by and by. Thou art with the Devil thou and thou, And wilt thou at a flamelet shy? (The Witch breaks the circle and steps out.) Mephistopheles. No rest for thee! We must take flight. Witch. May that small mouthful well agree! Mephistopheles (to the Witch.) If now I can do a good turn for thee Thou may'st remind me on Walpurga's night. Witch. Here is a song that, when you sing it, I know You are on the track of some strange transmutation. Mephistopheles (to Faust.) Quick! come—I'll bear thee by translation; Thou must be bathed in perspiration, So that within, without the power may flow. A noble idleness I'll teach thee now to treasure, And thou shalt feel anon, with deep ecstatic pleasure, How Cupid works while springing to and fro. Faust. Let me a moment look into the glass! That woman's form was, ah! too fair! Mephistopheles. No! no! That paragon of women shall pass Full in thy sight alive, I swear! (aside) By this drink in thy veins made human, Thou'lt see a Helena in every woman.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE VII. A Street. Faust. Margaret passing by. Faust. My fair young lady, may I dare Offer my arm to escort you somewhere? Margaret. I'm not a Lady, nor fair I be, And can go home without company. (She escapes him, and goes away. Faust. By Heaven this child is fair! I ween Naught like her I have ever seen. Modest and virtuous, and well-bred, Yet with a saucy look she fled. Her sweet red lips, cheeks flushed in pet, While the world lasts I shall ne'er forget. The way that she cast down her eyes Is printed in my heart likewise; And then how cross with me she grew, That fills me now with rapture too! (Enter Mephistopheles.) Faust. Hear! thou must get me this girl, I say! Mephistopheles. Well, which? Faust. She has just gone by me here. Mephistopheles. That one? she's just come from her Priest away, Who has absolved her clean and clear; Beside her hassock I crept near, She's a young thing, quite innocent, That for nothing to confession went, Over such chits I have no power. Faust. She's past fourteen, if she's an hour. Mephistopheles. Thou speakest like some Jack-kiss-me-quick, Who every flower for himself would pick, Thinks there's no honour, nor no grace He cannot pluck in any case, Yet thus one can't always succeed. Faust. Worshipful Master, is't so indeed? Peace with thy points of Law so clever! If in my arms this fresh young maid Rest not to-night, and by thine aid, At midnight we shall part for ever. Mephistopheles. Think what may hap in various ways, I need at least some fourteen days To find my opportunity. Faust. The Devil would be of little use So young a creature to seduce, Had I but seven good hours to try. Mephistopheles. You speak much like a Frenchman now; Pray don't go worrying for your toy: What boots one soon-snatched hour of joy? The pleasure's not so great, I trow, As when you first come flitting round, Till with arts of all kinds the way you've found The puppet deftly to knead and mould, As in Italian Tales 'tis told. Faust. I have appetite without such zest. Mephistopheles. Now without scoff, and without jest, I tell you, with this pretty maid, Don't go too fast; once for all 'tis said. By storm to take her's not your game here, With cunning we must slyly tame her. Faust. Bring aught from my Angel's treasures to me, Bear me to where my Love doth rest! Fetch me the kerchief from her breast, A garter, from my Heart's-darling's knee! Mephistopheles. That you may see how in your pain I'll serve you well, promptly and fain, We'll not a moment more delay, I'll bring you to her room this very day. Faust. And shall I see her? have her? Mephistopheles. No! To a near neighbour's she will have gone, Meanwhile you can stay, quite alone, With every hope of future pleasure, Drink in the air she breathes at leisure. Faust. Can we go now? Mephistopheles. Too early yet. Faust. Some splendid present for her go get! [Exit] Mephistopheles. Presents already? Bravo! Well for success he's playing! I know of many a pretty spot Where buried treasures may be got. I must look round, his hest obeying. [Exit]</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE VIII. Evening. A Clean Little Room. Margaret. Something I'd give, could I but say Who was that gentleman to-day! A gallant man he seemed to be, And come of a noble family, That from his brow I could have told— And else he would not have been so bold. [Exit] (Enter Faust and Mephistopheles.) Mephistopheles. Come in, tread softly, but come on! Faust (after remaining silent for awhile.) I beg thee, leave me here alone! Mephistopheles (peering about.) Not every girl's neat as this one. [Exit] Faust (looking round.) Welcome to thee, sweet evenshine! That hoverest through this holy place. Seize on my heart, love's pain, sweet and divine! That livest on hope's fresh dew, pining for grace. How breathes around the sense of quiet, Of order, sweet content as well! This poverty seems wealth's abundance What bliss within this narrow cell! (He sinks into the leathern chair by the bed.) Receive me here, thou who the old folk, long gone, In joy and sorrow with open arms didst hold! How oft, ah me! around their Father's throne, A little flock of children hung of old! Perhaps, even, grateful for the Christmas gift, My Darling here, with her plump cheek so fair, Her Grandsire's withered hand to kiss would lift. I feel, O Maiden! thy spirit rare Breathe on me content and order; with deft hand Motherlike, here it teaches thee to lay The cloth, so clean and smooth upon the table each day, Beneath thy feet to scatter the crisp sand. O thou divine, dear hand! Through thee This cot becomes Heaven's Kingdom for me. And here! (He draws back the curtains of the bed.) Why seizes me this rapturous fear? Here hours and hours I fain would wait. Nature, thou didst in gentle dreams create The home-born Angel who nestles here; Here in sweet sleep, her tender breast Filled with warm life, the child has lain, And here her form divine, at rest Fashioned itself without a stain! And thou! What then has brought thee here? How stir within me passions long sere? What wouldst thou here with heart grown heavy and sore? Ah! wretched Faust! I know thee now no more. Does magic mist breathe round this chair Urge me to rush to bliss to-night, Feel myself melt in dreams of Love's delight! Are we the sport of every breath of air? Yet, were she suddenly through the door to pass, How wouldst thou for thy fault find vengeance meet! I, the great clown, so small, alas! Would lie there melting at her feet. Mephistopheles (entering.) Quick! Here she comes, I see, below. Faust. Off! off! I will come here no more! Mephistopheles. Here's a small casket, heavy though, I have brought it from a secret store Hide it somewhere, this press will do 'Twill drive her crazy now, I swear; I have put some trinkets in it for you, Another ninny to ensnare. Well, maid is maid, and game is game. Faust. I know not, shall I? Mephistopheles. You ask? For shame! Mean you, perhaps, to bag this treasure? Then to Your Lustihood I say: Trouble not further this fine day, Nor me, to wait upon your pleasure. I scratch my poll, and rub my hands— (He puts the casket into the press and shuts the door.) Now quick! away! I find you this young thing sweet as May, Tame to your will, and heart's demands, Peeping you come, As though you entered a lecture-room, And, standing grey and lifelike 'fore you there, Physics and Metaphysics were. Away! [Exeunt] Margaret (entering with a lamp.) It is so sultry and close in here (opens the window.) Yet the street was cool, as fell the gloam, I feel I know not how—so queer— I wish my Mother would come home. Through every limb I shudder so, I'm a silly, timid girl, I know. (She begins to sing as she undresses.) There was a King in Thule, Faithful unto the grave, To whom his Mistress, dying, A golden beaker gave. Nothing he held more precious, At feasts, in solemn wise He drained it, and in drinking The tears o'erflowed his eyes. And when Death's hand drew nigh him He grudged his Heir not one Of all his realm's fair cities, He grudged that cup alone. He sat at royal banquet, Round him his chivalry, In the great Hall of his Fathers, In his Castle by the sea. There stood the brave old toper Drank up his life's last glow, And flung the sacred beaker Into the tide below. He watched it falling, filling And sinking in the sea, His eyes grew dim to swooning, No drop evermore drank he. (She opens the press, to put her clothes away and finds the jewel-casket.) How comes this casket here thrust in? I am certain that I locked the press! But it is wonderful! And what may be within? Brought here as someone's pledge, I guess, My Mother lent on it, no doubt. Here by this ribbon hangs a key, I think I'll open it, and find out. What's this? O God in Heaven! Look there, Such things as in my life I've never seen! A set of jewels a Noble Dame might wear, On highest holidays, I ween. How would this chain look upon me? But who can own these splendid things? (She puts on the jewels, and steps before the glass.) If mine were only these ear-rings! One looks so different when they're on. What use are beauty and fresh young blood? That is all very well and good But counts not much with anyone; They praise you, but half in pity. Round gold men throng, For gold they long, Ah! we poor folk in the City!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE IX. A Public Walk. Faust pacing up and down in thought. Mephistopheles entering, comes up to him. Mephistopheles. By the pangs of despised love, by the quenchless fires of Hell I would I knew anything worse, to curse by that as well! Faust. What ails thee? Grips thee some strange qualm? Such a mad face I never saw till now! Mephistopheles. I'd give myself straight to the Devil, I vow, But that a devil myself I am. Faust. Has aught gone wrong within thy brain? Does it become thee to rage in this mad vein? Mephistopheles. The jewels I got for Gretchen, only think, A priest has cribbed, ere one could wink!— The Mother managed to get a peep, A secret horror 'gan o'er her creep; The woman has truly the finest scent, From snuffling, over her prayer-book bent, Sniffed round each thing, and sniffed again, To see if 'twere holy or profane, And o'er the jewels the scent grew clear, No trace of blessing found she here. “My child!” she cried, “all ill-gotten good Ensnares the soul, consumes the blood. To the Mother of God let's consecrate it, With heaven's manna our souls be elated!” Your Gretchen made a wry face thereat; To look a gift horse in the mouth were that, And surely! no godless man were he Who brought her so fine a thing, thought she. The Mother sent, the Parson came; And soon he cut into the game, Looked at the jewels with grave delight. Says he: “There's good sense in the saw: Who conquers keeps, by victor's law. The Church hath a stomach of mickle might, Whole countries hath She oft-times eaten Yet never suffers from repletion; My sisters dear, the Church can best Ill-gotten goods in peace digest.” Faust. That is a custom-sanctioned game, A Jew or King would do the same. Mephistopheles. Brooch, ring and chain he pouches there, As though but mere mushrooms they were, He thanked them neither less nor more Than if off a basket of nuts he bore, Promised reward in Heaven some day— And truly edified were they. Faust. And Gretchen? Mephistopheles. Now sits restlessly, Nor what she would, or should, knows she, Thinks of those jewels, day and night But more of the bringer of such delight. Faust. My darling's trouble is pain to me. Go, get her new ones immediately! The first were but paltry gifts, I say. Mephistopheles. Oh yes! To your Lordship 'tis all child's play. Faust. Do, direct all to serve my will! Hang thou about her neighbour still! Be not a Devil of pap, but bring New jewels, worth my offering. Mephistopheles. Yes, Gracious Master, with heart-felt glee. [Exit Faust] A fool in love would puff, sans care, Sun, moon, and all the stars that be, Just for his Mistress' pastime, into the air. [Exit]</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE X. At the House of a Neighbour. Martha (alone.) God pardon my dear husband now, He has not used me well, I trow! Into the world straight he has gone, And leaves me on my straw-bed alone. And yet I never was a shrew, And God knows that I loved him true. (She weeps.) Mayhap he's dead!—Oh! pain to wait! Would I'd his death-certificate! Enter Margaret. Dame Martha! Martha. Gretchen, what's wrong with thee? Margaret. My knees are ready to give way! Another casket I found to-day, In my own press—of ebony, And in it splendid things there are, Richer than those first sent by far. Martha. This you must never tell your mother; She'd go and confess it, like the other. Margaret. Ah see them only! only see! Martha (putting the jewels on Margaret.) O happy creature that thou must be! Margaret. Ne'er alas! could I dare be seen In street or church with them on, I ween. Martha. Come over often to me, then, Put on your jewels in secret here, Walk 'fore the looking-glass an hour, now and again. How we'll enjoy ourselves, my dear! Then comes your chance, some holiday, When, one by one, to folk your gems you can display. A chain at first, then in your ear a pearl, Your mother shall not see, we'll hoodwink her, my girl. Margaret. But who could bring these two caskets to me? This haps not when all's right you see! (A knock at the door.) If 'twere my Mother! God pardon sin! Martha (peeping through the curtain.) Tis a strange gentleman—Come in! Mephistopheles (entering.) If to intrude I make so free, I beg the ladies to pardon me. (He steps back respectfully before Margaret.) I wish to inquire for Dame Martha Schwertdlein. Martha. What would you ask sir? That name is mine. Mephistopheles (aside to Martha.) I have made your acquaintance, now leave you free; This lady has called on you, I see Pardon the liberty I have ta'en, This afternoon I will call again. Martha (aloud.) Of all things in the world, child, hear, This gentleman thinks thou'rt a lady, my dear! Margaret. Indeed but a poor young maid I be, Ah God! the gentleman flatters me: This finery is not my own. Mephistopheles. Ah! but 'tis not the jewels alone She has a presence, a look, an air! I am glad to stay, if stay I dare. Martha. What brings you then?—I am anxious to— Mephistopheles. Would I had happier news for you! I crave your pardon for what I tell: Your husband is dead, and greets you well. Martha. Is dead? true heart, forlorn am I! My husband's dead! Ah! I shall die! Margaret. Ah! dearest dame, do not despair! Mephistopheles. Hear the sad story that I bear! Margaret. Ne'er would I love all my life's day, If for such a loss I should pine away. Mephistopheles. Joy must bring grief, grief joy likewise. Martha. Tell me of his life's close, and death. Mephistopheles. In Padua in his grave he lies, St. Antony's great church beneath, In a well-consecrated ground His cold last bed of rest he has found. Martha. Have you naught else he bade you bring? Mephistopheles. Yes, but one heavy and hard request, That you for his repose three hundred masses let sing! My pockets are empty for the rest. Martha. What! not a trinket, not a coin to show? What every journeyman hoards in his satchel, where His keepsakes lie, preserved with care, Would beg or starve, ere sell them yonder! Mephistopheles. Madam, my heart feels for your woe; But all his money in sooth he did not rashly squander, Ruing moreover, his faults full sore, Ay, and complained of his bad luck much more. Margaret. Alas! that so unhappy men should be! Full many a requiem now for his poor soul I'll say. Mephistopheles. You soon should make a right good match some day: You are a girl worth loving, I see. Margaret. Ah no! That cannot be as yet. Mephistopheles. If not, meanwhile a gallant you may get. The greatest of heaven's best gifts it were, To clasp in one's arms a thing so dear. Margaret. Here it is not the custom, sir. Mephistopheles. Custom, or not, such things occur. Martha. But tell me more! Mephistopheles. I stood beside his dank death-bed. 'Twas better than muck half-putrified, Half rotten straw; yet he a Christian died, But found he had many a thing still on the score, he said. “How,” cried he, “must self-hatred in me waken Thus to have left my trade, my wife forsaken! The memory kills me, as here I lie. Would she but pardon me while yet I am living!” Martha (weeping.) Good man! long since his faults I have forgotten. Mephistopheles. “But, God knows, she was more to blame than I.” Martha. There he lied! What! to lie at the grave's brink! Mephistopheles. He wandered when at grips with death, I think, If in these matters I'm not half-dense. “I had no time to gape idly about!” he said, “First children came, then I must win them bread, And bread too in the widest sense, And never once was left to eat my bit in peace.” Martha. My love, my faith, forgotten, if you please! My drudgery long nights and days! Mephistopheles. Nay, in his heart he thought of it always. He said: “I shipped from Malta, in poor plight, And prayed for wife and children fervently. And then Heaven favoured us; at sea We took a Turkish galley in fair fight, That had for cargo the great Sultan's treasure. Then had our bravery its reward, And I received my rightful share, full measure, Of the prize-money she had aboard.” Martha. Eh! what? Where is it? Has he, maybe, buried it? Mephistopheles. Who now knows whither the four winds have hurried it? A pretty girl got hold of him, as he Wandered the streets of Naples without a friend, Promised to love him ever faithfully. He wore her favours to his blessed end. Martha. The rogue! the robber of children and of wife! Their misery, their lack of bread Could not amend his scandalous life! Mephistopheles. Ay, see what came of that! He's dead! Were I myself now in your place, I'd mourn for him a decent year, And seek meanwhile a sweetheart with God's grace. Martha. Ah God! whate'er my first appear, I scarce could find on earth such a wild gander, A softer-hearted fool there scarce could be. He loved too much over the world to wander, And foreign women, and wine loved he, And that curst dicing more, I ween. Mephistopheles. Well, well, you might have still rubbed on, If he perchance, as much had seen, From his own point, of yours. Upon This one condition, I swear 'tis true, I gladly would change rings with you! Martha. The gentleman is pleased to jest! Mephistopheles (aside.) Gad, I must bolt from her, and quick! To his own word she'd make the Devil stick! (To Margaret.) How goes the heart in your soft breast? Margaret. What mean you, sir, by that? Mephistopheles (aside.) Thou good and innocent Maid! Ladies, farewell! Margaret. Farewell! Martha. Quick! tell me! I need your aid. Some evidence I wish to have Where, how, and when my Dear died, and where lies in his grave? I like to have all in order, fain would read His death-lines in “The Weekly News,” indeed. Mephistopheles. Good Madam, yes, two witnesses must swear A deposition—thus the truth is clear. A smart young fellow is with me now, I'll take him before the Judge, I vow! I'll bring him here. Martha. Oh, do so, pray! Mephistopheles. And this young Lady here will stay? A fine young man, much travelled too, Young Lady, I bring his respects to you. Margaret. 'Fore the gentleman I must blush for shame. Mephistopheles. Before no King of the World who came. Martha. Behind the house, in my garden, then, This evening we'll expect the gentlemen.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE XI. A Street. Faust and Mephistopheles. Faust. How goes it? Speed we well? Is the coast clear? Mephistopheles. Bravo! Do I find you all on fire? Gretchen will soon grant your desire. At Neighbour Martha's house this evening you shall see her. There's a rare woman, who knows her trade, As Gipsy-coupler of man and maid! Faust. 'Tis well! Mephistopheles. But one demand she made to-day. Faust. One service by another we should repay. Mephistopheles. We must bring valid proof, and testify That her dead husband's bones in Padua lie, In consecrated ground at rest. Faust. How clever! And now post-haste to Padua we must go! Mephistopheles. Sancta Simplicitas! That were a bootless quest; Swear to it, though much you do not know. Faust. If you've naught better, to shreds the plan must go. Mephistopheles. O saintly man! Hang back, 'twere best! Is it the first time in your life that you Have borne false witness, if that be sin? Have you not of God, the World, and all that moves therein Given definitions, with mighty power too, With impudent brow, unfaltering breath? Yet sound the depths of your own being Of things like this, confess you can't help seeing You knew as much as of Herr Schwerdtlein's death! Faust. Thou art, remain'st a Sophist and a liar. Mephistopheles. Yes, if a little deeper you don't inquire. For wilt thou not to-morrow, in honour's name, Befool poor Gretchen, without shame, Forsworn in the old canting soul's-love game? Faust. From my heart, truly. Mephistopheles. Well and good! Then will come faith and love eternal, One impulse, resistless, unique, supernal— Will this too gush with your heart's blood? Faust. Sneer not! It will!—When in my mind, For the unrest troubling my breast, I seek for names, and none can find, Then through the world, with senses keen, I rove, Snatch at some word, all words above, This glowing fire wherein I flame Eternal, infinite I name Is this a devilish lying game? Mephistopheles. Yet I am right! Faust. Hear! mark but this— Pray spare me further exercise of lung— He who will have his way, and only has a tongue, Get's his hearts lust. Come, I've had prate enough, changed parry and thrust; For thou art right, I yield because I must.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE XII. Martha's Garden. Margaret on Faust's arm, Martha with Mephistopheles walking up and down. Margaret. I feel it well. You make excuse for me, Stoop to me, make me blush for shame. A traveller is used, you see, Kindly to pardon talk so tame: I know too well your wise, experienced mind In my poor prattle no interest can find. Faust. A glance from thee, a word interests me more Than all this wide world's sagest lore. (He kisses her hand.) Margaret. Don't incommode yourself! How can you kiss my hand? It is so coarse, so grimy too! What have I not about the house to do! Mother's so strict in all she has planned. (They pass on.) Martha. You, Sir, are always travelling, are you not? Mephistopheles. Ah! business, duties, drive us ever away! With how much pain one leaves each pleasant spot And here, once more, we cannot stay. Martha. In one's brisk years 'tis blithely done, Free, round and round the world to sweep; But the bad time must come anon, When the old bachelor alone to his grave must creep, That ne'er did good to anyone. Mephistopheles. Shuddering I see it far away. Martha. Then, my dear sir, be advised in time, I say. (They pass on.) Margaret. Yes, out of sight out of mind! I see That you are used to courtly ways, With heaps of friends you spend your days, They are more sensible than I be. Faust. Ah, dearest! trust me, what common sense men call, Is oft short-sighted vanity. Margaret. How so? Faust. Ah! that the simple, innocent never know Themselves, their sacred value for us all! Modesty, lowliness, gifts highest, these two, That Nature's hand distributes lovingly,— Margaret. Do you think then one little minute of me, I shall have time enough to think of you. Faust. Then thou art much alone? Margaret. Yes, our housekeeping's but small, I own, Yet must be looked to, small or great. We keep no maid; must cook, clean, knit, you see, And sew and bustle, early and late And then my Mother in everything will be So accurate! Not that she really needs to stint herself at all; We might make a better show than others, you understand, My Father left a tidyish bit of land, A house and garden beyond the city wall. But now I have some fairly quiet days; My brother is a soldier tall My little sister's dead, I had my dearest cares by the child's little bed; Yet undertook all trouble so willingly always, The child was ah! so dear. Faust. An angel, if like thee. Margaret. I brought it up, and dearly it loved me. 'Twas born some time after my Father died; We gave my Mother up beside, In such deep misery she lay, And she recovered slowly, picked up, just day by day. She could not think, in her sad plight Herself of nursing the poor wee mite, And so I reared it all alone On milk and water, so it grew my own. Upon my arm, and on my lap, It coo'd, throve, sprawled, grew by good hap. Faust. Then surely thou hast felt the purest bliss? Margaret. And many an hour of weary toil, I wis. The wee-thing's cradle stood at night Beside my bed; and if it moved or cried, I woke outright. Then I must feed it, cuddle it by my side Then, if it was not quiet, from bed must rise, And dance it round the room to still its cries; And when day dawned must at the wash-tub stand; Then tend the hearth, to market then away And the same round run every day, One's courage, Sir, fails one sometimes, at best, Yet my food tasted sweet, 'twas sweet to rest. (They pass on.) [Exeunt] Enter Martha and Mephistopheles. Martha. Poor women get the worst of it, these days: 'Twere hard to change a bachelor's habits, 'tis true. Mephistopheles. 'Tis only given to women such as you To train me now in better ways. Martha. Say frankly, Sir, have you yet nothing found? Has your heart never anywhere been bound? Mephistopheles. The proverb says: “One's hearth, household, And a good wife outvalue pearls and gold.” Martha. I mean, Sir, have you fancied someone, never? Mephistopheles. I have been received with courteous kindness ever. Martha. I would ask has your heart ne'er throbbed with real passion? Mephistopheles. One cannot dare to jest with women in idle fashion. Martha. Ah! you don't understand! Mephistopheles. That pains my heart to find! Martha. Yet I perceive—that you are very kind. (They pass on.) Faust. Thou knewest me little Angel, didst recognise, When I came through the garden, instantly? Margaret. Did you not see? I then cast down mine eyes. Faust. And thou didst pardon me the liberty I took, my impudence, that day, As from the church thou camest away? Margaret. I was amazed, that ne'er had hapt to me: No one could say bad things about me never. Ah! thought I, in my behaviour now whatever Bold or improper could he see? He thought he might come straightway to me, Like any common wench pursue me. But, I confess, I really did not know What in your favour began to speak, 'tis true; But with myself I was really angry, though, That I could not be angrier with you. Faust. Sweet darling. Margaret. Wait awhile! (She plucks a daisy, and picks off the petals one by one.) Faust. What's that for? A bouquet? Margaret. No, it is just a game. Faust. What? Margaret. You'd laugh at me. Go away! (She plucks and murmurs.) Faust. What murmurest thou? Margaret (half-aloud.) He loves me—loves me not. Faust. Thy sweet face light from Heaven has caught! Margaret (still picking off the petals.) Loves me—Not—Loves me—Not— (Picking off the last petal with innocent joy.) He loves me! Faust. Yes, my child! Let this flower's sweet word Be for thee God's decree. He loves thee! (He seizes both her hands.) Knowest thou what that means? He loves thee! Margaret. My joy o'erflows! Faust. Oh! tremble not! Let this fond glance, Let this hand-clasping say to thee, What words can ne'er express: To give thyself wholly away, a bliss To feel, that must eternal be! Eternal!—Its end would be indeed despair. Ne'er let it end! No, never end! (Margaret presses his hands, and runs away. He stands for a moment in thought then follows her.) Martha (entering with Mephistopheles.) The night draws on. Mephistopheles. Yes, off we must race. Martha. I'd ask you longer here to stay; But 'tis too scandalous a place. None seems to have either work or play, Nothing to do in any shape, Save at their neighbour's goings-on to gape, Whate'er you do gossips must have their say. And our sweet pair? Mephistopheles. Just now down yonder path have flown. The wanton Summer-birds! Martha. He's sweet on her, you'll own. Mephistopheles. She too on him. That is the world's old way!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE XIII. A Summer House. Margaret springs in, hides behind the door, lays her finger on her lips, and peeps through the chink. Margaret. He comes! Faust (coming.) Ah rogue! thou temptest me! I've caught thee! (Kisses her.) Margaret. (embracing him, and returning his kiss.) Dearest man, from my heart do I love thee! (Mephistopheles knocking.) Faust (stamping.) Who's there? Mephistopheles. A friend! Faust. A beast! Mephistopheles. 'Tis time you parted, come! Martha. Yes, sir, 'tis getting late Faust. May I not see thee home? Margaret. My Mother would be so—farewell! Faust. Must I go then? Farewell! Martha. Adieu! Margaret. Soon may we meet again! [Exit Faust and Mephistopheles] Margaret. Dear God! what is there a man like he Can't think about all things easily! I stand ashamed before him there, Just to say “Yes” to all I dare. I'm but a child, with ignorant mind, Can't think what in me he can find. [Exit]</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE XIV. Forest and Cavern. Faust (alone.) O sublime Spirit, thou hast given me, given me all For which I prayed. Thou hast, and not in vain, Turned unto me thy countenance in fire; Given me majestic Nature for my realm, With power to feel, to enjoy. Not merely now A cold astounding visit dost thou grant, Thou dost permit me into thy deep breast To gaze, as into the bosom of a friend. Thou bringest the pageant of all living things Before mine eyes, and teachest me to know My brethren in the quiet groves, air, water. And when the raging storm snarls in the woods, And strips the branches from the giant pines, Neighbours, that, bruised and shattered as they fall, Send a dull, hollow thunder through the hills, Thou leadest me to a lonely cave, and there Showest me myself, and in my own inmost breast Deep and mysterious wonders are revealed. And when before mine eyes mounts the clear moon, Softening the skies above, around me hover From walls of rock, and from the dewy grass, Silvery shapes out of the ancient world, Assuaging contemplation's sterner joys. Oh! that for men no perfect thing can be, As I feel now. Thou gavest with this delight, Which near and nearer brings me to the Gods, That strange Companion, whom even now no more I can do without, when, with cold impudence, He lowers me in mine own eyes, with a word's breath Annihilates the gifts thou gavest me, He kindles in my breast a tameless fire For that beautiful Shape, with busy craft; I stagger from desire to possession, And satiated, pine for new desire. Mephistopheles (entering.) Have you had enough of this life for the nonce? How long ere it will pall on you? 'Tis well enough to sample it for once, Then off again to something new! Faust. I would that thou hadst more to do, Than thus to spoil a genial day. Mephistopheles. Well, well! I won't disturb you—Pooh! Such things in earnest you should not say. A crabbed, gruff mad fellow like you I soon could part with, if I chose. All day forsooth, my hands full, I must groan! What pleases him, what one must let alone, One cannot e'er guess from His Lordship's nose. Faust. That is indeed just the right tone, The fellow must have thanks for boring me. Mephistopheles. What then, thou wretched son of clay, Without my aid would thy life be? Have I not cured thee, many a day, From all the whim-whams of fantasy? Were I not by, from this earth-ball Thou wouldst have walked off once for all. Why hast thou in cave and rocky cleft Sat like an owl of sense bereft? Why suck'st thou from damp moss, and dripping stone, Like a dull toad, thy food alone? A pretty, sweet amusement too! I see the Doctor still lurks in you. Faust. What a new power of life, didst thou but guess, Comes from the commerce with the wilderness, Hadst thou a notion even of this, Thou art devil enough indeed to grudge me such a bliss. Mephistopheles. A super-earthly pleasure too! To lie by night on mountains in the dew, Embracing Heaven and Earth rapturously Letting ourself swell to divinity Crawl through Earth's marrow, with boding divination, Feel in our breast the six Days of Creation, In pride and power enjoy, I know not what, Then, in love's bliss, o'erflow all things, in thought, Clean vanished is Earth's puny Son, And then the noblest intuition—(with a gesture) I daren't say how—'twill to birth be brought. Faust. Fie on thee! Mephistopheles. You are hard to please to-day; You are quite right, 'tis proper “fie!” to say Before chaste ears we must not mention this, Which yet chaste hearts cannot endure to miss. In short I grudge you not the gratification Of lying to yourself upon occasion; But long you can't hold out, 'tis plain. Thou art once more driven from thy way, And, if thou tarriest swept astray, In madness, or in horror and pain. Enough of this! Thy Love sits there apart, And all for her grows drear, confined Ne'er absent from her thoughts thou art, Love of thee masters heart and mind. Thy love's first rage gushed overflowing, As when, with melted snow a brook o'erfloods the plain; And thou didst pour it into her heart, And now thy brook's grown shallow again. Methinks, instead of sitting throned above The woods, my Lord might be so good, Now to reward for all her love This poor young thing of flesh and blood. The time for her seems miserably long; She stands at the window, sees the clouds go by O'er the old town-wall, as they fly. “Were I a bird!” so goes her song All day, and then half the night long. Sometimes she is lively, mostly sad, Her tears wept out in pain, Then, as it seems, tranquil again, Loving still, sad or glad. Faust. Snake! Snake! Mephistopheles (aside.) Caught thee! I've won my stake. Faust. Accursed Tempter! Get thee hence! Dare not to name that woman so fair! Bring not the longing for her sweet body ever Again before my half-distracted sense! Mephistopheles. What happens, then? She thinks that thou art flown, And thou art half-way gone, I own. Faust. I am near her still, though were I far away, I never could forget her, never leave her, When her lips touch the Body of the Lord, My envious heart is filled with jealous fever. Mephistopheles. Well, well, my friend I have often envied you Those twins that browse on roses, it is true. Faust. Away, thou pander! Mephistopheles. Good! You insult me, and I must laugh. The God who fashioned man and maid Sanctioned from the first day their noblest trade Even made things easy on their behalf. Off, then! Here's a fine burst of woe! To your Love's chamber you must go, Not to death, anyhow! Faust. What is the heavenly joy, clasped in her arms? Let me warm myself on her bosom's charms! Feel not I ever the risk for her? Am I not myself a fugitive without home, Inhuman, without aim or rest, Who, like a cataract roaring through rocks have come Raging to the abyss with eager quest And, she, apart with dull and childlike mind, In a small cot set in an Alpine field, Plying her household tasks assigned, Within her little world confined. And I, the accurst of God, unsatisfied that I Had seized the rocks, and crushed them, Shattering them utterly! And she, her peace now must I undermine! Thou, Hell, this victim to thee I must resign! Help, Devil, make brief my torment's hours that crawl! That which must happen, let it happen straight! May her ill fate on me ruining fall, And she with me be crushed by Fate! Mephistopheles. All seethes again, all glows again, Go then, thou fool, her heart to cheer, When such a noodle seeks escape in vain, The end before him soon grows clear. Long live the man who still is bold! Thou wast possessed once with half-devilish daring. Nothing more loathsome on this earth I hold, Than a poor devil who sits despairing.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE XV. Gretchen's Room. Gretchen alone at the Spinning-wheel. Gretchen. My rest is fled, My heart is sore, And peace I find never And nevermore. Where I have him not Is the grave plot, The world is all Turned for me to gall. And my poor head Is all astray My poor thoughts fly, Each its own way. My rest is fled, My heart is sore, And peace I find never, And nevermore. I watch from the window For him alone, To seek him only Abroad have gone. His noble presence His bearing high, The smile of his lips, The power of his eye. The magic flow Of those words of his, The clasp of his hand, And ah! his kiss! My rest is fled, My heart is sore, And peace I find never, And nevermore. My breast yearns for him In his long flight, Ah! might I clasp him, And hold him tight! And kiss him, kiss, None to say me nay, Till on his kisses, I passed away.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE XVI. Martha's Garden. Margaret and Faust. Margaret. Promise me, Heinrich! Faust. What I can. Margaret. Tell me now as to religion, how is't with thee? Thou art at heart so good a man, Yet, as I think, thou treat'st it carelessly. Faust. Leave that, my child! Thou feel'st to thee I am good; And for my Love would part with flesh and blood, Would no one of his faith or church bereave. Margaret. That is not right, in it one must believe! Faust. Must one? Margaret. Ah! if I had some hold on thee! Thou honourest not the Holy Sacraments, I see. Faust. I honour them. Margaret. Yet longest for none. 'Tis long since thou to Mass, or to Confession hast gone. Dost thou believe in God? Faust. My Love, who dares to say: I believe in Him? Ask priests or sages what think they, Their answer seems but mockery grim Of him who questions them. Margaret. Believ'st thou not? Faust. My sweet-faced Love, mistake not so my thought! Who dares to name His name? proclaim: I believe in Him? Who that can feel What all things reveal Dare say: I believe not? The All-embracer, The All-sustainer, Clasps and sustains He not Thee, me, Himself? Arches not Heaven there above us? Lies not earth, founded fast beneath? And mount not, kindly peeping, Still the eternal stars on high? Do we but gaze, eyes into eyes, And throng not all things Into thy head and heart, And weave in eternal mystery The invisible visible in thee? Fill with it then thy heart, great as it is; And when in feeling thou art filled with perfect bliss, Call it then what thou wilt, Happiness! heart! love! God! I have no names in sooth For this! Feeling is all; Names are sound, smoke, not flame, Clouding the heaven's glow. Margaret. That is all beautiful and good, I know, The priest indeed says much the same, Only in a rather different way. Faust. So everywhere they say All hearts under the heavenly day And each in his own tongue, Then why not I in mine? Margaret. When so one hears, it sounds so fine, But something wrong lurks there at last, No Christianity thou hast. Faust. Dear child! Margaret. It long has troubled me, To see thee in such company. Faust. How so? Margaret. The man thou hast for mate, From my soul's inmost deeps I frankly hate; Nothing in all my life E'er stabbed my heart so, as with a knife, Like that man's loathsome face, God wot! Faust. Dearest poppet, fear him not! Margaret. His presence curdles all my blood, To all men else I wish but good; But much as I long thy face to see, Before him strange horror comes over me, I hold him to be a scoundrel too! God pardon me, if wrong to him I do! Faust. Such cynic knaves there must always be. Margaret. I would not live with such rogues as he! When through the door he slinks in here, He looks about him with a sneer, Half-furiously; One sees that nothing e'er moved him to sympathy; 'Tis written, his frowning brows above, That not a soul he could ever love. I am so happy in thy arm, So free, so given to thee, so warm, And his vile presence cramps my inmost heart, I vow! Faust. Thou evil-boding angel, thou! Margaret. This cows me with fear so sore, That, when he even may pass our way, I feel as though I loved thee then no more, And when he comes here I can never pray, That eats into the heart of me; And, Heinrich, it must be so with thee. Faust. Thou hast a strange antipathy. Margaret. Now I must go. Faust. Ah! ne'er can I One little hour repose upon thy breast, Bosom to bosom, soul to soul be prest? Margaret. Ah! if alone I did but sleep! I would unlock the door to-night for thee; But Mother's slumber is not deep, And, if she chanced on thee and me, Upon the spot I should fall dead! Faust. My Angel, there is naught to dread. Here is a flask! Three drops, but three Mixed with her drink, she will not wake, But sleep a natural sleep, and pleasantly. Margaret. What would I not do for thy sake? I hope in no wise it will harm her! Faust. Should I advise it, then, sweet charmer? Margaret. Dearest, when thee I look upon, I know not what subdues me to thy will; So much for thee already I have done, But little more to do is left me still. [Exit] (Enter Mephistopheles.) Mephistopheles. The monkey! Is it gone? Faust. Spying, as I surmised. Mephistopheles. Well how things go I have understood, Herr Doctor here was catechised; I hope that it will do you good. In their own interest girls are well-advised, To find one sleek and pious in the old way. They think, if here he bends he'll follow our lead some day. Faust. Thou monster, thou can'st ne'er have known How these true souls, who love, believe Full of their living faith, Which can alone Sanctify their frail hearts, divinely grieve That they must deem the man they love lost at his death. Mephistopheles. Thou sense-transcending, sensual squire, A maiden leads thee by the nose. Faust. Thou abortion, born of filth and fire! Mephistopheles. In physiognomy a master's art she shows. And always in my presence she feels, she knows not how, My mask reveals to her my hidden thought; She scents an evil genius in me now, The Devil himself mayhap she's caught. And now, to-night—? Faust. What's that to thee? Mephistopheles. There's pleasure in it even for me!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE XVII. At the Well. Gretchen and Lieschen with pitchers. Lieschen. Hast thou heard naught of Barbara? Gretchen. No word, I come not much in people's way. Lieschen. 'Tis sure. Sibylla told me to-day! She's played the fool at last, ha! ha! All through her haughty ways! Gretchen. How so? Lieschen. It stinks! She feeds two when she eats and drinks. Gretchen. Ah! Lieschen. Serves her right too, such gaits a-ganging. How long about the fellow she's been hanging! Trapesing the lanes about, To dances he took her out! Everywhere first she must flaunt, so fine, He treated her always to pastry and wine; She fancied her beauty was something divine, She was so mean she had no shame To take his presents when they came, Kissing and cuddling there alone, And then her maiden flowers were gone! Gretchen. Ah! the poor thing! Lieschen. What! Thou still pitiest her? When from our spinning we could not stir, At night our Mothers kept us from the street, She stayed there with her wooer sweet; On the door-bench, and in alleys dim, The hours seemed short for her and him. Now she must hang her head and rue That in sinner's shift she must penance do. Gretchen. He'll surely take her for his wife. Lieschen. He'd be a fool! A smart young chap Has fun enough elsewhere, mayhap; Besides, he's off. Gretchen. That is not fair! Lieschen. Even if she hooks him, we'll plague her sore. The lads her wedding-wreath will tear, And strew chopt straw before the door. [Exit] Gretchen (going home.) What shrewish things I could boldly say, Once, when a poor maid went astray, How, o'er the sins of others, I Ne'er found words enough from my tongue to fly! How black it seemed, could it blacker be, Yet black enough never it was for me. I crossed myself, and proud I grew, And now in sin I stand naked too! Yet—all that drove me on to this, God, was so good! ah! such sweet bliss!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE XVIII. Rampart. In a shrine in the wall a devotional picture of the Mater Dolorosa, a flower-vase before it. Gretchen. (putting fresh flowers into the vase.) Ah! bend thy face To me in grace, Thou rich in sorrows in my need! With sword-pierced heart, Thousandfold smart, Thy dying Son thou seest bleed. To the Father bending, Sighs thou art sending To Heaven for His and thine own need. Who feeleth How stealeth My pain through every bone? What fears in my poor heart are thronging, How it trembles, how 'tis longing, Thou dost know, but Thou alone! Wherever I may go, What woe, what woe, what woe My breast breeds dolorously! I am, ah! scarce alone, I weep, weep, weep, and moan, Till the heart breaks in me. The flower-pots before my window I watered with tears, ah me! As in the early morning I plucked these flowers for Thee. The Sun within my chamber Shone early, as he rose, I sat in all my sorrow, Upon my bed of woes. Help! Save from shame and death, my meed! Ah! bend Thy face To me in grace, Thou rich in sorrows, in my need!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE XIX. Night. A Street. Before Gretchen's door. Valentine (a soldier, Gretchen's brother.) When at a drinking-bout I have sat, Where many bragged of this and that, And fellows loudly praised to me Some flower of maiden modesty, In a full bumper pledged their Toast Propt on their elbows made their boast; I sat secure my heart at rest, Heard all their swagger, as round they pressed, And stroked my beard, as with a smile I lifted the full glass in my hand, And said: “Each after his own style! But is there one in all the land With my dear Gretel can compare, Hold to my Sister a candle who dare? “Hear! hear! cling! clang!” so it went round Some cried: He's right, and right is he, The jewel of all her sex is she! There sat each toaster in silent stound. And now—I could pluck out my hair, Try to run up the steep wall there! Each scoundrel now, with taunt and sneer, Will heap vile insults on me here! Like some base debtor must I sit, Each chance word give me a sweating fit! But, though I made mincemeat of them all, None of them liars could I call. But who comes here, stealing from view? If I mistake not, there are two. Is't he, I'll soon grip him by the skin, Alive from this place he shall not win! Enter Faust and Mephistopheles. Faust. How from the window of the sacristy Light from the ne'er-quenched lamp there upward shimmers, And weak and weaker on all sides glimmers, Till swallowed in the darkness quite. So in my breast gathers the night. Mephistopheles. Like a lean cat I seem to be, That up the fireman's ladder creeps, Slinks round the wall, 'ere on he leaps. Meanwhile I feel, quite virtuously, A spark of thievish joy, and rammish lust in me. So haunts me, through each limb and vein, Magnificent Walpurga's-night! But two nights hence 'twill come again, One knows why one wakes there by weird moonlight. Faust. Does not the treasure now rise into sight For I see something glimmering bright? Mephistopheles. You soon can experience true joy of soul, Lifting the offertory bowl. Just lately, when I squinted in it, There were splendid lion-dollars within it. Faust. But not a jewel, not a ring, Wherewith my dear Mistress to adorn? Mephistopheles. I saw in it some such pretty thing, As a necklace of pearls no wench would scorn. Faust. Then all is right! It works me woe, When without a present to her I go. Mephistopheles. Well, it should give you no annoy, Gratis another treat to enjoy. Now, while the starry heaven glows You'll hear a real work of art. I'll sing her a moral song I chose, Surelier to befool her heart. (He sings to the zither.) Why stand before Thy lover's door, Kätchen once more, Ere dawn in day is fading? Win past the gin, He'll let thee in, As maiden in And out no more a maiden. Ah! then take heed, When done the deed, Good night, ill speed, Poor jades when wedlock lingers! Love your good name, Play no sly game, And keep Love tame, Till rings are on your fingers. Valentine (coming forward.) Whom lur'st thou here? By the Element! Accurst ratcatcher, ware my whinger! To the Devil first with the instrument! Then to the Devil with the singer! Mephistopheles. The zither's smashed, to pot may go the shreds! Valentine. Now comes the game of splitting heads! Mephistopheles. Herr Doctor, don't give ground! and quick! Here to me, follow my lead, don't tarry! Out with your whisk now, that's the trick! Do you but thrust and I will parry. Valentine. Then parry this! Mephistopheles. And wherefore not? Valentine. This too Mephistopheles. Of course! Valentine. I think the Devil fights here! But what is this? Already my hand grows lame. Mephistopheles (to Faust.) Thrust home! Valentine (falls.) Wo's me! Mephistopheles. Now is the lubber tame! But now off! We must vanish ere they wake For soon the cry of “Murder!” they will raise. With the police I get on well always, But for sheer murder terms could never make. Martha (at the window.) Come out! come out! Gretchen (at the window.) Here! Bring a light. Martha (as above.) They wrangle, rage, they shout and fight. The Crowd. Already one lies dead! Martha (coming out.) The murderers, have they already flown? Gretchen. Who lies here? The Crowd. 'Tis thy Mother's son. Gretchen. Almighty! what misery! Valentine. I'm dying! That's soon said, I trow, And sooner yet 'tis done. Women, why stand ye, and shriek and moan? Come hither, and hear me now! (All crowd round him.) My Gretchen, see! Still young art thou, And art not yet discreet enow, Thou art in evil plight. I tell thee in confidence, no more: Than this: thou art once for all a whore; Then ply thy trade aright. Gretchen. My brother! God! Why this to me? Valentine. Leave our Lord God out of the spree. What's done, alas! is done, and so How go it can, e'en let it go. With one in secret didst thou begin, And soon with others thou wilt sin, And when a dozen feres thou hast, Then the whole town may have thee at last. When Shame is first conceived and born, Secretly comes she to the world's light, One draws the curtains of the night O'er head and ears in scorn; Ay, one would gladly strangle her there. But still she grows, claims greater sway, And then goes naked even by day, And yet grows not more fair to sight. The uglier grows her loathsome face, The more by daylight she courts disgrace. I see it, soon surely the time will come When townsfolk, with pure wives at home, As from an infectious corpse will flee From thee, thou brazen strumpet, thee! The heart in thy body will breed despair, When folk shall stare thee in the face! No gold chain henceforth shalt thou wear, Nor in church at the altar take thy place! That fine lace-collar upon thee there, No more light-hearted to dances fare! In some dark, miserable hole With beggars and cripples hide, cheek by jole: And even if God should pardon thee, Be on this earth accurst by me! Martha. Your soul needs mercy, and God's dear grace, Will you burden it now with slander base? Valentine. Could I grip thy dry carcase of skin and bone, Thou scandalous, bawdy, trafficking crone, For all my sins of every kind Full pardon I might hope to find. Gretchen. My Brother! What hellish pain for me! Valentine. I say, let all this weeping be! When thou forsworest honour for lust, Thou gavest my heart its deadliest thrust. I go, through the sleep of death in the grave, To God, a soldier true and brave. (Dies.)</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE XX. Cathedral. Mass is being celebrated by organ and choir. Gretchen is among the crowd, an Evil Spirit behind her. Evil Spirit. How different, Gretchen, with thee, When, full of innocence still, Here to the altar come, From the much-thumbed little prayer-book Thy prayers thou lispedst, Half in childish play, Half with God in thy heart! Gretchen! What of thy head? And, in thy heart there, What most foul misdeed? Prayest thou for thy Mother's soul, through thee, After its long, long pain sinking through sleep to death? Upon thy threshold whose blood is that?— And—there, beneath the heart Stirs not some quickening life, Torturing itself and thee With its ill-boding presence now? Gretchen. Woe! woe! Were I from these thoughts but free, That o'er me come, and slowly pass away, In spite of me! Choir. Dies Irae, dies illa Solvet saeclum in favilla. (Organ tones.) Evil Spirit. Wrath seizes thee, The last trumpet sounds! The graves are heaving! And from thy heart From ashen rest For fiery torment Now again is shapen, Arise! Gretchen. Would I were hence! It seems as though the organ's tone Were stifling my breathing, The holy hymn Loosening my heart-strings. Choir. Judex ergo cum sedebit, Quidquid latet adparebit, Nil inultum remanebit. Gretchen. I smother here! The walls' huge pillars Close round me now! The massy ceiling Weighs on me—Air! Evil Spirit. Hide thyself! Sin and shame Remain not hidden. Air? Light? Woe to thee! Choir. Quid sum miser tunc dicturus, Quem Patronem rogaturus, Cum vix justus sit securus? Evil Spirit. The Saints in glory Their faces turn from thee. The pure their hands refuse thee Shuddering in horror! Woe! Choir. Quid sum miser tunc dicturus? Gretchen. Neighbour Your smelling-bottle— (She falls in a fainting-fit.)</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE XXI. Walpurga's Night. Hartz Mountains. Region of Schirke and Elend. Faust and Mephistopheles. Mephistopheles. Are you not longing for a broomstick, eh! I wish I had a stout buck-goat for steed. By this rough path our goal is far away. Faust. So long as still untired my limbs can play, This knotty stick will serve my need. What boots it to cut short the road?— Through all these labyrinthine valleys creeping, Then o'er these rocks climbing and leaping. Whence evermore the bubbling spring has flowed, On such a path this relish serves as goad! Spring stirs already in the birk, And even the pines can feel her now, Must she not eke be in our limbs at work? Mephistopheles. No trace of this I feel, I trow! 'Tis winter still within my carcase; Snow, frost, upon my path I wish to see. How sadly now the moon's red crescent mounts yonder, And shines so feebly, that gainst rock and tree, At every step you stumble on your way. But let me hail a wisp-light, pray! I see one there that now burns lustily. Ho there, my friend! May I beg thee to come hither? Be good enough to light us now up thither, Why shouldst thou thus uselessly flare? Will-o'-the-Wisp. With all respect, I hope I may be able To curb my nature so unstable; By zig-zags, though, we usually fare. Mephistopheles. Ho! ho! ye would ape men, who do the same. Go straight for once, in the Devil's name! Or thy poor flickering life I'll soon blow out. Will-o'-the-Wisp. You are our Clan's great Chief, I have no doubt I'll do my best to suit your paces. Think, though, the mountain's magic-mad to-night, And, if a Will-o'-the-Wisp must now guide you aright, You must go round a bit in places. Faust, Mephistopheles, Will-o'-the-Wisp, (in alternate Song.) Now the sphere of dreams and magic We, it seems, are entering, Lead us well, and on thine honour Forward on our journey bring, To the wide, waste desert spaces! See! trees after trees run races Swiftly past us they are trooping, And the cliffs' proud heads are stooping, Long rock-noses past us going; How they're snoring, how they're blowing! Through the stones, through grass and heather, Brook and rill rush down together. Hear I murmuring? hear I singing? Voices sweet love-plaints intoning, Heavenly days of old bemoaning? What we hope, what loves may find us! While Echo, like a Saga, droning Of days of yore, sets echoes ringing. Oo-hoo! shoo-shoo! nearer they hover, Crying, screech-owl, jay, and plover: Are they all awake behind us? Hides each bush a salamander With fat paunch, and limbs so slender! Like huge serpents, roots of trees Writhe from rocks and from the sands, Stretching grimly freakish bands, Us to frighten, us to seize: From thick trunks, as you go by, Stretch the suckers of Polypi, To'wrd the Traveller, and the mice Thousand-coloured, in hosts likewise, Dart through the moss and through the heather: And the glow-worms flit together, In crowded ranks, a swarming throng All in confusion they lead along. Are we tarrying, tell me pray, Or pressing forward on our way? All seems to whirl round me to-day, Rocks and trees are making faces Will-o'-the-Wisps crowd in all places Puft with pride more thick come they. Mephistopheles. Grip my skirt with grip not weak, Here we are on the midmost peak Where one astounded may behold How in the mountain glows Mammon's gold. Faust. How strangely glimmers through the valley A sad gleam, like the morning-glow, And even in the deep abysses Of the steep crags it creeps below. There mists rise, there float exhalations, Through gauze-like vapour steals the glow, Then creeps, a tender thread of radiance, Then like a gushing spring 'twill flow. Here it winds onward, far extending, With hundred veinlets, through the vale, Here, pent within a gorge's ending, The sundered streamlets glimmer pale. There glitter nearer sparks of light, Like golden sand strown over all. But see! o'er all the mountain height, Enkindles now the rocky wall. Mephistopheles. Does not Lord Mammon for this feast Light up his palace gloriously? This thou hast seen, what luck for thee! Already I scent many an eager guest. Faust. How wind-gusts rage now through the air! Their buffets deal my neck many a rude shock! Mephistopheles. Thou must grip tight the old ribs of the rock, Or 'twill soon hurl thee to thy grave down there. The night's growing thicker with cloud! Hear how the woods are moaning loud! Owls there in terror are flitting, Hear how the columns are splitting In the ever-green palaces now: Sighing and breaking each bough. The stems too mightily moaning, As roots yawn, creaking, and groaning! In dreadful and confusèd fall Over each other the trees crash all, And through the ruin-choked gap's abyss Wild wind-gusts howl and hiss. Voices on the heights dost hear, Distant now, and now more near? Yes, the whole mountain-side along, Streams a maddening magic song. Witches in Chorus. The Witches to the Brocken hie, The stubble is yellow, and green the rye. There in huge crowds they congregate, Up there Herr Urian sits in state, O'er stick and stone go the sweating crew, The Witches stink, and the goat stinks too. A Voice. Alone Old Baubo is coming now, She rides upon a farrowed sow. Choir. So honour those to whom honour's due! Dame Baubo first, well-escorted too! A good strong sow, and the Mother thereon, Then follow the Witches everyone. Voice. Which way came'st thou here? Voice. Over Ilsenstein! I peeped in the owl's nest, her pair of eyne Glared wickedly! Voice. Oh! to Hell with thee! Voice. Why ridest thou so furiously? Voice. Completely she's flayed me, See! one wound she's made me! Witches in Chorus. The way is broad, the way is long, How find ye this for a furious throng? The pitchfork prods and scratches the broom, The child is choked, and burst the womb. Witch-Master. Half-choir. We creep like the snail that carries her house, The women in the foremost places, For, when they're bound for the Devil's house, The women lead by a thousand paces. Other Half-Choir. We are not certain that is so, The woman a thousand steps may go; But, let her make what speed she can, Up in one spring will come the man. Voices (above.) Come with us, come from the Felsensee! Voices (below.) Gladly with you on the heights we'd stray. We wash; but no end to our toil we see! Our labour is barren eternally. Both Choirs. The wind is hushed, and sinks the star, The moon would hide her sad face afar. And whizzing scatters the magic choir Thousands of glittering sparks of fire. Voices (from below.) Stay! stay! Voices (from above.) Who calls from the clefts of the rocky way? Voices (from below.) Take me with you! Take me with you! I'm climbing now three hundred years, And yet the peaks I can ne'er attain. I would I were with my kind again. Both Choirs. The broomstick bears one, the walking-stick, The pitch-fork, the buck-goat—take your pick! Who proves not to-night that mount he can, He is forever a lost man. Half-Witch (below.) I have tript after, many a day; Why are the others far on their way? At home I have no peace at all And here my progress is but small. Choir of Witches. The salve makes all the Witches bold, If for a sail a rag you hold, A trough for boat is a good stand-by, Who flies not to-night will never fly. Both Choirs. And when the peak we soar around, Swoop deftly down and skim the ground, Cover the heath, both far and nigh, With your vast swarm of witchery! (They alight.) Mephistopheles. What crowding and chattering, what whirling and pushing! What whispering, and prattling, and tugging, and rushing! Gleams, sparks, stinks, flames are now unpent, A genuine witch-element! Cling to me! lest we apart be rent. Where art thou? Faust (some way off.) Here! Mephistopheles. So soon torn from me quite? I must claim lordship here to-night. Room there, Squire Voland comes. Room, my sweet rabble, room! Here, Doctor, grip me tight! Now in one spring we come Out of the crowd, from the crush we're free; It is too mad even for the likes of me. Close by there something shines with quite peculiar glare, It lures me to yonder bush, I see. Come, come! We'll slip behind it there. Faust. Spirit of Contradiction! On then! Thy lead I wait. I think, though, thou hast been too clever quite; Here to the Brocken we come upon Walpurga's Night, And yet prefer ourselves to isolate. Mephistopheles. See but those many-coloured flames! A merry Club are at their games, 'Mong few one's not alone, you see. Faust. Yet up there I would rather be! I see fires glow, smoke whirl even now. There streams the crowd to the Evil one, Where many a riddle must be solved anon. Mephistopheles. And many a riddle knit fast, I trow. Do thou let the great world run riot Here we will house ourselves in quiet. 'Tis handed down without a break, That in the great world one a little world may make. I see young witches there, stark-naked all, And old ones drest with sly coquetry, For my sake treat them courteously! The sport is great, the trouble small. I hear the instruments some stock-piece playing, Discord accurst! One must endure their braying, Come with me! come! It can't be cured, you see. I will step on, and bring thee in with me, I'll win thy gratitude again. What sayest thou, friend? This is no paltry Space. There, look all round, the bounds evade thy gaze. A hundred fires in rows burn o'er the plain; They dance, they chat, they cook, they drink, they court; Now tell me where one could find better sport? Faust. Wilt thou, in ushering us into this revel, Present thyself as conjurer or devil? Mephistopheles. Though well-accustomed oft to come incognito, On these, our gala-days, our Orders we may show. A garter does not distinguish me, My colts-foot here at home is honoured loyally. See'st thou yonder snail? She's creeping here, no doubt With groping eyes, searching each spot, She has already half tracked me out, I can't deny myself, if here I'm caught! But come! We'll go from fire to fire, I am the pander, thou of dames the squire. (To some who sit over a dying fire.) Old gentlemen, why sit ye at the end? Had ye good places in the middle your nous I should commend, 'Mid revelling youths ye should have come, One has enough of loneliness at home. General. Who can trust Nations to remember How much for them one has done in by-gone days? For with the people as with women, The Young ramp in the first always. Minister. They have strayed too far from the right way, I praise the good old times; when truly We all ourselves were honoured duly, That was the Golden Age, I say. Parvenu. We were no fools then, I'll be bound, And often touched things rather shady, But now all things are turning round, Just when to bag our plunder we were ready. Author. Who anywhere now for serious writing cares, Reads books of solid information? Never before were seen such impudent airs Among the dear young rising generation. Mephistopheles (who seems suddenly very old.) I feel these folk ripe for the Judgment Day As for the last time up the Witches' Mount I wheeze, While turbid runs my cask of clay, The World itself is on the lees. Huxter-Witch. Kind gentlemen, don't pass me by! Don't lose your chance, as on you fare! Look with attention at my ware, Many a fine bargain here have I. Yet in my shop there's naught for sale That Earth can match, search high or low, Which has not worked notorious bale To men, and to the World also. No dagger's here wherefrom blood hath not dript, No cup whence one of sound and vigorous frame Hot, wasting poison ne'er hath sipt. No jewel that ne'er some fair, love-worthy Dame Seduced, no sword that ne'er some solemn bond hath severed, Or through a foeman's back a fatal thrust delivered. Mephistopheles. Dear Aunt! you are behind the times, one sees, What's done has hapt, what's hapt is done! Change stock, and deal in novelties, We hunt for novelties alone. Faust. Of losing my own Self, beware! This I call something like a fair! Mephistopheles. The whole huge whirlpool strains above You are shoved along, even when you think you shove. Faust. See! who is that? Mephistopheles. Look at her curiously! 'Tis Lilith. Faust. Who? Mephistopheles. Adam's first wife is she. Be on thy guard before her splendid hair, On that one jewel she prides herself alone! When with it she allures a youth, all's done, Not soon she lets him further fare. Faust. There sits a pair, an old witch, and a young, They have already well skipped and sprung. Mephistopheles. There is no rest for them to-day. They're starting a new dance! Come, let's cut in, I say. Faust (dancing with the young witch.) Once a fair dream came over me; And there I saw an apple-tree, Two splendid apples there did hang, They tempted me, and up I sprang. Fair One. You longed for those twin apples fair, As come from Paradise they were, I am moved with joy because I know Such apples in my garden grow. Mephistopheles (with the Old Witch). Once a wild dream came over me, I saw it in a cloven tree, It had a— So—it was, it pleased me well. Old Witch. With cordial greeting I salute The Knight who wears the cloven foot! Keeps he a—ready to ply, If he—does not shy. Procto Phantasmist. Accursed folk! how dare ye venture here? Did we not long since plainly prove A Spirit on real feet could never move? Now ye even dance as we men do, 'tis clear! The Fair One (dancing.) Why comes to our ball that fellow there? Faust (dancing.) Pooh! He comes prying everywhere. While others dance he criticises, Each step must go as he advises, Or it must count as though 'twere never danced. But most it vexes him when forward we've advanced. If you would in a circle turn as he Turns round and round in his old mill, That, he would say, at least showed skill; If you took off your hat to him especially. Procto Phantasmist. What! you're there still? Such things were never heard, I say. Vanish then! This we have quite explained away. This Devil's pack asks not for any rule, A spook haunts Tegel still, though we've learnt sense at school. Have I not been sweeping out these fancies long enough? The filth's there still; I never heard such stuff! Fair One. Shut up! You bore us with your dull orations! Procto Phantasmist. To your face I tell you ye phantoms there, The despotism of spirits I will not bear; I cannot drill mine into patience. (The Dance goes on.) I've no success to-day, I know it; I'll go a-travelling far away, And still I hope before my dying day, To get the better of the Devil and Poet. Mephistopheles. In some foul puddle he will soon be sitting, That's how he finds his ease is best ensured And when horse-leeches well his bum have bitten Of spirits and bel-esprit he will be cured. (To Faust, who has come away from the dance.) Why hast thou left that pretty maiden lonely, Who, dancing, charmed thee as she sang? Faust. Faugh! In the middle of her song there sprang A red mouse out of her mouth, 'twas plain! Mephistopheles. That was all right! Don't be so strict, I say! Enough that mouse was red not gray. Who minds such things, playing the shepherd swain? Faust. Then I saw— Mephistopheles. What? Faust. Mephisto, seest thou there, Standing alone, far off, a child, pale and so fair? She drags herself slowly from the spot, With fettered feet she seems to stumble there. I must confess, it seems to me That like my good Gretchen is she. Mephistopheles. Let the thing be! Sights like these profit none. It is a magic shape, lifeless, an image alone. To meet this phantom is not good; Her stony stare can curdle a man's blood, Straighway he almost petrifies; Thou hast heard tell of Medusa's eyes. Faust. Those are the eyes of one dead, verily, That loving hand ne'er closed; and this Is the dear breast my Gretchen gave to me, This the sweet body I embraced with bliss. Mephistopheles. That is her sorcery, thou soon-caught simpleton! Like his own Love she appears to every one. Faust. Ah! what a rapture! what agony! From that fixed stare I cannot flee. How strange it is that slender neck so fair Is decorated with one blood-red line, No broader than a knife-cut fine. Mephistopheles. 'Tis true, I too can see it there. Under her arm her head eke she can carry, Since Perseus cut it off. Why tarry? You long for some delusion still! Come, let's go up this little hill! Here 'tis as merry as in the Prater; And, if I'm not gone magic-blind, I really see a Burg-Theatre. What's running now? Utility-Man. All's ready now behind. A new piece, 'tis of seven the last; It is our custom here to stage the lot. A Dilettante wrote it, and the cast Are Dilettanti. Hiss them not! Pardon me, Sirs, if I fade from view, To dilettantise up the curtain! Mephistopheles. If on the Blocksberg I meet with you, I shall be pleased; that's your true sphere I'm certain.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">WALPURGA'S NIGHT'S DREAM OR OBERON AND TITANIA'S GOLDEN WEDDING. Intermezzo. Stage Manager. Here we take a rest once more, Valiant Sons of Mieding, Dewy vale and mountain hoar Are all the scene we are needing. Herald. That the wedding golden be, Must fifty years pass over! This Golden one best pleases me Strife done 'twixt love and lover. Oberon. Trip to me, spirits, o'er the green, Behold, this hour united, Fairy King and Fairy Queen Once more in love troth-plighted. Puck. Here comes Puck, and skips about And foots it in the measure, Hundreds follow him about, With him to take their pleasure. Ariel. Ariel awakes the song, Pure tones in heavenly cadence: Many a minx it lures along, And many pretty maidens. Oberon. Spouses who would well agree, Learn from us this wonder, If a pair would lovers be, Keep them but asunder. Titania. Nags the wife and sulks the man, Part them dexterously, Her to the Mediterranean, And him to the North Sea. Orchestra Tutti (fortissimo.) Long-nosed gnat, and snouted fly, With kin of all conditions. Frog in leaves, grigs through grass that hie, These are our blithe musicians. Solo. Here the bagpipe's coming, see! Swoln like a huge soap-bubble, Hear its cackle blown blatantly Through its snub-nose with trouble. Spirit (coming into existence.) Toad's paunch on spider's feet made crawl With tiny wings of fairies, Can make no kind of beast at all, Yet a small poem there is. Young Couple. One short step, spring high with me, Through dews and odourous vapour; You can trip it well, I see, Yet in the air can't caper. Inquisitive Traveller. Is this a masquer's mockery play? Can I believe my eyes here? The fair god Oberon to-day I see with glad surprise here! Orthodox. No claws, no tail, wonders ne'er cease, There's no mistake about it, He's, like the ancient gods of Greece, A devil, who can doubt it? Artist (from the North.) What I can catch as yet may be But sketchy; yet I'm daring For my grand tour in Italy Even now to be preparing. Purist. Ill fortune brings me here, alas! What lust inflames this crowd here A host of witches before me pass And two wear only powder. Young Witch. Powder and stiff hooped petticoat Suit grey old frumps' chaste rigour, So I sit naked on my goat, And show my plump firm figure. Matrons. We are all too well-bred by far To bandy words with you, miss; Yet, young and buxom as you are, Hope you'll soon rot, 'tis true, miss. Conductor. Long-nosed gnat, and snouted fly, Don't crowd around the naked, Frog in leaves, grigs through grass that hie, Keep time with me, deuce take it! Weathercock (at one side.) Wish better company who can! Brides, brides, with charming features, And smart young fellows, man for man, The hopefullest of creatures. Weathercock (at the other side.) If earth soon gape not, wide and deep, This rabble here to swallow, I will myself, with sudden leap, Spring into Hell's red hollow. Xenia. Like small insects we are here, With wee sharp shears; but truly The worth of our Papa, so dear, Satan would honour duly. Hennings. See them throng in serried host, Sly with each other playing! But at the end they blandly boast: We have kind hearts they're saying. Musagetes. Among this motley witches' crew, I roam with genuine pleasure, I'm apter in their games, 'tis true, Than in the Muses' measure. Ci-Devant Genius of the Age. With the right people some chance one has, Come, grip my skirt securely, The Blocksberg, like our German Parnass, Has a broad summit surely. Inquisitive Traveller. Pray who is that stiff gentleman, With haughty steps there walking? He sniffs wherever sniff he can, “Jesuits he must be stalking.” Crane. I fish clear waters happily, In muddy pools I revel; Just as the pious man we see Rub shoulders with the Devil. World-Child. Yes, trust me, for the saintly Seer, All's but a vehicle; They build upon the Blocksberg here Their Bethels hard by Hell. Dancer. Does a new choir speed here anon? I hear a distant drumming. Don't be disturbed! In unison Bitterns in the reeds are brumming. Dancing Master. How everyone his feet outflings, And as he can gets through it! The awkward hops, the cripple springs, None cares how others view it. Fiddler. They hate each other, the stupid rout, Would join in deadly battle; The pipes make peace, lead them about, As Orpheus' lyre all cattle. Dogmatist. To decry error is not for me, Doubt, criticise or cavil; Something the Devil must surely be; Or how were there a Devil? Idealist. In my own senses phantasy Is this time too imperious; If I be all things, verily To-day I'm quite delirious. Realist. Existence plagues me, heart and mind, Still by vexations haunted; And, for the first time now I find My feet not firmly planted. Supernaturalist. With how much pleasure here mid this crew I enjoy myself demurely; Convinced there are good spirits too, Since there are Devils surely. Sceptic. Hoping to find the treasure, they Follow their wisplight's revel; I stand on the right spot midway, Doubt all, so doubt the Devil. Conductor. Frog in leaves, grigs through grass that hie, Accursed Dilettanti! Long-nosed gnat, and snouted fly Ye are fine players, I grant ye! Nimble-Ones. “Sans Souci,” our merry crew They call, for ne'er we grumble; More on our feet we cannot do, So head o'er heels we tumble. Slow-Coaches. We have spunged for many a morsel sweet But now, may God preserve us! We tramp the road on naked feet, Our shoes danced off in service. Will-o'-the-Wisps. Bred in the marshes, dank and drear, We come to show our talents; Now in bright ranks we muster here, Most splendid of court-gallants. Shooting-Star. From heaven, with starry, fiery light, I shot; my wreck's complete now, Prone in the grass I end my flight; Who sets me on my feet now? Hulking Fellows. Place there! place! Tramp out a ring On the green sward; for spirits Come; but stout limbs with them bring, Wherewith to show their merits. Puck. Don't hulk about in this rough play, Like elephant-calves a-frolic, Or Puck may prove himself to-day The stoutest in the rollick. Ariel. If loving Nature to spirits still Gives wings, as myth supposes, Fly on my track, if ye have skill Up to the Hill of Roses! Orchestra (pianissimo.) Gauzelike mist, and clouds that speed Shine in dawn's light elysian. Breeze in leaves, and wind in reed, And vanished is the vision.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE XXII. Melancholy Day. Open Plain. Faust and Mephistopheles. Faust. In misery! despairing! Long wandering in distress over the country and now imprisoned! Shut up in a dungeon as a malefactor, and doomed to horrible tortures, that sweet unhappy creature! It has come to this! To this!—Treacherous, contemptible Spirit! This, then, thou hast concealed from me!—Stand there —stand! Roll thy devilish eyes in thy head in sullen rage! Stand and defy me with thy insufferable presence! In prison! In unallieveable misery! Given over to evil spirits, and to men without feeling, her Judges. And meanwhile thou hast rocked me to rest in abominable dissipations, concealed from me her ever increasing misery, and left her to perish without help. Mephistopheles. She is not the first. Faust. Dog! Execrable monster!—Transform him thou infinite Spirit! Transform this reptile again into his mongrel shape, in which it pleased him to trot before me by night, to loll at the feet of the harmless traveller, and to hang on his shoulders when he stumbled. Change him again into his favourite shape, that he may crawl on his belly in the sand before me, that I may trample him under foot, the reprobate—“Not the first!—” Misery! Misery! The soul of man cannot conceive that more than one creature should sink into the depths of such wretchedness, that the first had not sufficiently atoned for the guilt of all others, writhing in her deadly agony, before the eternal Forgiver of sins! The misery of this one girl rages through my marrow and my life. Thou grinnest ruthlessly over the fate of thousands more! Mephistopheles. Now we are again at the boundary of our wits, where the senses of you men, overstrained, snap short. Why dost thou become our partner, if thou canst not carry it through? Wouldst thou fly, when thou art not secure from giddiness? Did we thrust ourselves on thee, or thou on us? Faust. Gnash not thy ravenous fangs at me! It makes me sick. Great and magnificent Spirit, who didst deign to appear to me, thou who knowest my heart and my soul, why hast thou fettered me to this shameful companion, who battens upon mischief, and rejoices in destruction? Mephistopheles. Hast thou done? Faust. Rescue her! or woe to thee! The most horrible curse Be upon thee for thousands of years! Mephistopheles. I cannot loosen the bonds of the Avenger, nor draw his bolts— Rescue her!—Who was it that drove her to destruction? I or thou? (Faust stares wildly around.) Dost thou grope for a thunderbolt? 'Tis well they were not given to you miserable mortals! To crush the innocent standing in his path, that's the tyrant's way of getting out of a difficulty. Faust. Bring me to her! She shall be free! Mephistopheles. And the danger to which thou exposest thyself? Remember that the guilt of blood shed by thy hand still lies upon the town. Over the spot where a man was slain avenging spirits lurk for the returning murderer. Faust. That again from thee? The murder and death of a world be upon thee monster! Bring me there, I say, and set her free! Mephistopheles. I'll bring thee there. Now hear what I can do! Have I all power in heaven and earth? I'll cloud the senses of the Warder; get possession of the keys for thee, and bring her out by the hand of a mortal. I will watch. The magic steeds are saddled, I will bear thee away. That I can do. Faust. Up, and away!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE XXIII. Night. Open Plain. Faust and Mephistopheles riding furiously on black horses. Faust. Why hover they there round the gallows-tree? Mephistopheles. I know not what they are cooking and brewing. Faust. Hovering up, hovering down, they are bending and bowing. Mephistopheles. 'Tis a Witches' Guild. Faust. They are sacring and strewing. Mephistopheles. Go by! go by!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE XXIV. A Dungeon. Faust (with a bunch of keys and a lamp, at a small iron door.) Unwonted horror holds me in thrall, The anguish of all mankind now clutches me. Here dwells she, here behind this sweating wall, And her one crime, deluded innocency. Going to her, thou loiterest here! To see her again fills thee with fear! On! while thou tremblest, Death lurks for his fee. (He grasps the lock. Singing heard within.) My Mother, the whore, She has murdered me, My Father, the rogue, He has eaten me! My wee Sister, my own, Bore every bone To a cold house of clay; And then a pretty wood-bird I'm grown; Fly away! fly away! Faust (unlocking the door.) She bodes not that her lover is listening near, The clanking chain, the rustling straw can hear. (He enters.) Margaret. They come! oh bitter death! Woe's me! Faust (speaking low.) Peace! peace! I come to free thee here. Margaret (crouching before him.) Art thou a man, feel for mine agony! Faust. Thy shrieks will wake the Guards from sleep, I fear. (He grasps the fetters to unlock them.) Margaret (kneeling.) Thou Hangman, who this power and right Over me could give? Thou tak'st me now, 'tis but midnight, Have pity on me, and let me live! Were't not time enough when Matins are rung? I am so young, I am still so young! (She stands up.) And now must die! Fair was I too, my ruin came thereby. My Love was near, now he is far away: Torn lies my wreath, its flowers scattered for aye. Lay not thy grip with such force on me! Spare me! What have I done to thee? Let me not pray in vain for grace, In all my life I have never seen thy face! Faust. Can I endure this harrowing sight! Margaret. I am in thy power, forsaken quite. Let me but nurse my child again. I hugged it to my heart all night; They stole it, to make me sick with pain, And now they say I murdered it outright! And never again, shall I be glad, I know. They sing bad songs about me! 'Tis cruel of folks, in sooth! A sad old story ended so, Who points its truth? Faust (falling on his knees.) Here at thy feet I kneel, thy friend, Thy fettered misery to end. Margaret (throwing herself into his arms.) Oh! let us kneel, cry to the Saints in prayer! See! under that stair, Under the threshold's tiling Hell now is boiling! The Evil-One, With dreadful grimace, Makes horrible noise! Faust (loudly.) Gretchen! Gretchen! Margaret (listening intently.) That was my Lover's voice! (She springs up. The chains fall off.) I heard him calling! Ah! where is he? I am free! No one shall hinder me To his neck will I fly, On his breast will I lie! He called “Gretchen”! He stood at the door Through the howling of Hell, through its clatter and roar, Through the fury of Devils, who mocked my moan, I knew it, that sweet, that dear loving tone. Faust. 'Tis I! Margaret. 'Tis thou! Oh say it once again! (Embracing him.) 'Tis he! 'Tis he! Where has flown all pain? Where is the torture of chain and cell? 'Tis thou! Come to save me, all's well! I am saved!— Again the dear street I can see, Where for the first time I saw thee, The pleasant garden too, Where I and Martha awaited you. Faust (trying to get her away.) Come with me! Come! Margaret. Oh stay! Gladly I'll stay, here where thou stayest. (Caressing him.) Faust. Hasten! If thou delayest, I tell thee we shall rue it sore. Margaret. What! thou canst kiss no more? My Love so lately fled from me, Forgets how to kiss, I see. Why on thy breast do I now feel such strange fear? Once, at a word from thee, a glance from thee, Closing around me all heaven drew near, And thou didst kiss me, as thou wouldst smother me. Kiss me, Or I'll kiss thee! (She embraces him.) Alas! but thy lips are cold, Are dumb. Thy heart so loving Where is it roving? Who brought me to this? (She turns away from him.) Faust. Come, follow me dearest, courage now! I'll clasp thee with thousandfold passion, I vow; Come, follow me only, I beg thee but this! Margaret (turning to him.) Is it then thou? Is it thou for sure. Oh bliss! Faust. 'Tis I! Come with me! Margaret. Thou hast loosed my chain, Wouldst take me on thy lap again How comes it thou dost not shrink from me?— Knowest thou then, my friend whom thou wouldst free? Faust. Come! come! Deep night is growing pale. Margaret. I murdered my Mother, 'tis an old tale, I drowned my child—Ah me! Was it not given to me and thee? Thee too—'Tis thou! I scarce trust this. Give me thy hand! No dream it is! Thy own dear hand—Ah me, but it is wet! Wash it away! I think there's yet Blood thereon! Ah God! What hast thou done? Put thy sword away, I beg of thee! Faust. Let what is past be past indeed I say! Thou slayest me. Margaret. Nay, thou must live, not die! I'll describe how the graves must lie: These be thy care. When morn shines fair: Give to my Mother the best plot, There my Brother beside her lay, Me farther off; but not Too far away. And my little one here upon my right breast. No one else shall lie by me!— Once by thy side to nestle to thee, That was the dearest, the sweetest bliss, But never again taste this I may; It seems I must force on thee my kiss, As though thou pushest me away; Yet thou look'st good and kind, and art, I know. Faust. Feel'st thou 'tis I, come let us go! Margaret. Out there? Faust. Into the free air. Margaret. Is the grave out there? If Death lurks there, then come! Hence to the eternal bed of rest, No step further for me— Thou goest forth? Heinrich, could I go with thee? Faust. Thou canst! Will but to go! The door stands open. Margaret. I dare not go; for me there's no more hoping. What boots to fly? They are lurking there for me. It is so wretched to beg one's bread, With evil conscience, sins on one's head, It is so wretched in foreign lands to roam And they would catch me, though far from home. Faust. I'll stay with thee. Margaret. Quick! quick! from that wave Save thy poor child, ah save! Off! keep to that way, Up by the brook Over the bridge, Through the woodland grey, Left, where the plank stands, O'er the pool Quick! catch it fool! It strives to rise, It struggles still! Save it! save it! Faust. Summon wits and will! A single step, and thou art free! Margaret. Were we but past those hills there—see! There sits my Mother upon a stone, It chills my scalp with dread! There sits my Mother on a stone, And shakes at me her head; She becks not, she nods not, her head is heavy and sore; She slept so long that she woke no more. She slept that we might have our bliss. Those times were happy, I wis. Faust. Naught boot my entreaties, naught all I say, I'll risk it, carry thee away. Margaret. Loose me! No force will I suffer now! Grip me not, so murderously! Once I did everything for love of thee. Faust. The day dawns! Dearest! dearest! Margaret. Day! Yes, it grows light! the Last Day hastes for me, My wedding-day it should be! Tell no one that with Gretchen thou hast been, Alas! my crants Are torn in twain! We shall see each other again; But not in the dance. The crowd is gathering, no word is spoken. Through square and lane They are thronging amain. The bell tolls, and the staff is broken. How they seize me and bind me! To the blood-stool I am snatched away. Now sweeps o'er all the necks behind me The sword brandished for mine to-day. Dumb lies the world as the grave! Faust. Oh had I ne'er been born! Mephistopheles (looking in.) Up! or you're lost! Day's dawning. This useless trembling, tarrying and prating! My horses are shivering and waiting. Margaret. What rises where earth is yawning? He! He! Send him away! In this holy place what seeks he for prey? He wants me! Faust. Thou shalt live! Margaret. Judgment of God to thee myself do I give! Mephistopheles (to Faust.) Come! come! I'll leave you both in the lurch I vow! Margaret. Thine am I, Father! Save me now! Ye Angels, ye Heavenly Host! Camp round me now, or I am lost! Heinrich, I shudder at thee. Mephistopheles. She is condemned! Voices from Above. Saved! Mephistopheles. Here to me! (Vanishes with Faust.) Margaret 's voice from within dying away. Heinrich! Heinrich! FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>