<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Shore, Louisa, 1824-1895</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Shore, Louisa, 1824-1895</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">shore louisa 1824 1895</field>
      <field name="author_text">Shore, Louisa, 1824-1895</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1870's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V3.0642.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1870</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460971</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Lost Son ; A Drama</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Lost Son ; A Drama</field>
      <field name="title_facet">lost son</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">lost son</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Lost Son ; A Drama</field>
      <field name="year_display">1870</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1870</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1870</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460971&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460971&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Shore, Louisa, 1824-1895&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;shore louisa 1824 1895&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Lost Son ; A Drama&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;lost son&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1870&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1870&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Shore, Louisa&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1824&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1895&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Lost Son&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Drama&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Smith, Elder And Co.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1870&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3873320-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv30642&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Lost Son&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Drama&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 227 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Only verse drama included&lt;lb/&gt;The following play has been taken from this source:&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: The lost son.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Melodrama.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1870.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 18 Jan 1831.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE LOST SON, A DRAMA.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PERSONS. Sir Hugh Lyle, of Lylford Hall. Bernard, his eldest son. Ulric, his young child. Olive, his young child. Annabella, his adopted daughter. Adrian, Earl de Warenne, a friend of Sir Hugh Lyle. Doria, brother of Annabella. Humphrey, servant and retainer of Sir Hugh Lyle. Cuthbert, servant and retainer of Sir Hugh Lyle. Gilbert, servant and retainer of Sir Hugh Lyle. Lettice, servant and retainer of Sir Hugh Lyle. Oswald, servant and retainer of Sir Hugh Lyle.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. Scene I. —The Library, Lylford Hall. Sir Hugh Lyle. Enter De Warenne. Sir Hugh. Well met, De Warenne. De War. Better elsewhere, surely, Than in this hermit-cell. Sir Hugh. It suits me. De War. Nay, Why not put by those papers for an hour, And join your children on the green plot yonder? You should be less alone. Sir Hugh. I am less so, When busied thus, than listening to their talk. I like they should be happy, but care not To join them. De War. Yet you are wrong. Sir Hugh. We 'll let that be. I have had much to think of, and to do, Of late, in ordering my affairs so far As fate has left them in my power—so far As pen and parchment may, trusting to you Hereafter to interpret to my boy What pen and parchment cannot. De War. Why this now? You have years and years before you. Sir Hugh. Have I? Fewer, Perhaps, than you may think; and there is something Still left to say. De War. Why, what is this, this fancy? Nay, what 's your age? What 's fifty years, my friend, Or a half-dozen over? 'T is a jest. You straight and strong, too, as the tallest pine In yonder sturdy grove! So much of life Is left you still, so much of comfort, too, Would you but think so! Sir Hugh. It may be I have Too weakly let one sad blot overspread These ten years all the colouring of life. Indeed, you know how it has been with me As well as I myself. De War. For God's sake, Hugh, Speak not of that! Sir Hugh. 'T is the first time, and shall be, So help me, God, the last! But such a life In death as mine has been, is now, I think, Fast wearing to its close, and I must look To you—I know you 'll not refuse me this— To be the guardian of my boy and girl Through all the years of tutelage, and stand In my place to them for more years than those— To be their friend—and that is saying all. They could not have a better. Though you seem Beside me, fresh still in your vigorous prime, Yet in the school of life you are more trained, Tried on a wider field, abroad, at home, Accomplished and approved. And yet your life— You know it, let me say so—is a house Whose noblest chambers are untenanted. I would you had a wife. De War. A wife! What, I? Sir Hugh. And since I know you will not now go forth As knightly youth does, far away to seek her, And since you stand above the need to add Either lands, wealth, or splendour, or a name, To that all-perfect ladyhood I wish To see your home crowned and made happy by— Nor ever were a worshipper of these— Have you ne'er thought how near you might be found E'en such a lady worthy of your suit? I say not she is lightly to be won; But hearts unswayed by butterfly caprice, And honest as the very sun in heaven, Own their true mates in time. You guess not yet? She is my daughter now; but when I die, What home has Annabella then? De War. My God! With whom but me? Sir Hugh. With you? Why, stay! Is this so? You love her, then, already? That is well. Win her then, Adrian; win her, for in her You win a noble wife, a noble home, Nor, search the country in its length and breadth, Would you find statelier beauty than hers, now In her maturity of womanhood; At least, to my accustomed eyes it seems so. De War. To mine no less. Sir Hugh. I am very glad you love her. De War. Love her! I said not that . . . though to my thought No woman equals her . . . but I ne'er dreamed So to aspire . . . and I must think this over . . . She is good, she is beautiful, may become homeless— And would she deign so far . . . but she is proud, Too proud I think to love. But I 'll not hear you Talk thus of death, as though at the next corner You saw him waiting. Sir Hugh. And he shall be welcome. A heavy care your words have something lightened; And for the comments of the worldly-proud, If those you heed, at least we have our proofs That her unknown lost family and name Can be no mean ones. De War. Oh, that would be nothing, If I should give this thing a serious thought She is herself alone amongst all women. But you are weary, Hugh—your voice is faint, And you grow paler. Let me leave you now. Sir Hugh. See me again ere you depart. De War. I will. [Exit. Scene II. —The Garden. Olive gardening; Cuthbert clipping a Holly Tree. [Olive sings.] Sir Ralph sits in the old watch-tower, and looks out on the night, And if the sky and sea are dark, he sets aloft a light; But trust not to that false, false spark, ye mariners at sea! 'Tis burning for no good to you, or there it would not be. Long has Sir Ralph been dust, but to this very hour His wicked ghost comes stealthily to the old ruined tower; And in dark night, he sets a light, and dreams of times gone by, When he won many a golden booty by that flaming lie. Oh, Cuthbert, I have tired so of your peacocks, And all the rest of them; do cut us out Some newer kind of monster. Cuth. That 's your way. There 's nought can please you long; what 's good is no worse For being old. Peacock, lion, or bear, You 'll get nought else from me. Ol. Clip me a dodo, And all my life I 'll thank you. Cuth. Make my garden A scandal with unchristian things like that! You 'll have no dodo here whilst my head aches— No, no, not in my garden. Ol. Oh dear dear! I 've dreamed about the dodo all my life.— Then why not let this choose its own green shape, Have its own lovely way, with bough and berry, As other trees do? Cuth. Lord forgive your folly! What, grow like the wild hollies in the wold? Then what 's the use of gardens? Ol. Do you think The bowers of Paradise were clipped like these? [Sings. 'T were long if I should count for you the precious things of yore, The mighty merchandises lost on that cruel shore; And luckless men and women, whose fate the sea-birds know, As, wailing for the shipwrecked, round and round and round they go. Those treasures are all scattered, the drowned ones make no sign; But the old curse is handed down, along his luckless line. And ever when you see that light, some evil shall befall To mariners at sea, and the Lyles of Lylford Hall. Cuth. Still singing, singing! Such a ceaseless worry; As if there were not nightingales and finches, And daws too, more than enough! By day and night The noise goes through me. Ol. Are those pretty things Grumbled at me? Cuth. 'T was not so much amiss When that boy, Bernard, hooted to the owls, Until they hooted to him back again. There was sense in that. Now I am sick of it all, And 't is a wicked wicked world. Still climbing Here, there, and everywhere—finding out all The secretest caves and nooks—knew everything Of his own head—you can't say how he learnt it— Mostly he kept his odd thoughts to himself,— And to end so! Ol. Now you have done your scolding, What are you talking of? Cuth. Oh, what, you heard me? What fool has taught you just that song, young mistress? It mostly is forgotten in these parts. Ol. Who taught me? Oh, the blackbird in the elm, That 's the sweet fool whose songs inspire my own. I like the sad ones best, you know. Cuth. Ay, ay! You have no heart, you young ones. All alike,— Not one to mend another. Why, a child Might have known better than to sing that song Before me, and your father within there. Ol. My father? Oh, he never heeds my singing, And you are always talking mysteries, And always they mean nothing. Why on earth Should I not sing that song now? Cuth. [Putting down his barrow.] Mistress Olive, Do you not know what came when last that light Was seen in the old ruin? But you young ones, You never think. Ol. How would you have me know, When no one ever tells me anything? But now, now you must tell me all about it. When was that light seen? Did you see it? Cuth. Ay. Ol. What happened then? Cuth. You know as well as I. Ol. What? Oh, you mean the great storm and the shipwreck Down yonder? Well, you know better than I, I was not born then. But you saw the light? Cuth. Ay, ay, as plain as ever star in heaven, And said to myself, “A ship will go to pieces On those accursed rocks before the morn.” Ol. You must have dreamed it. Cuth. If you choose to think so, It matters not to me,—oh, not a jot! Ol. Why have you never told me this? You have never Talked of that night. Cuth. Do you think I took such pleasure To see a ship-load of poor Christian souls Go down in sight of land, that I should love To chatter on 't? Ol. And did you see all that? Oh, Cuthbert! see her caught in the white breakers— Poor unknown ship? Oh me! And nothing left To tell her name or history! Pitiless sea! But then the prize, the great prize that it gave us, Worth all the plunder of the Spanish Main! Cuth. Better the sea had kept that. Ol. Cuthbert, Cuthbert! You are very wicked now. For shame! Do you know Of whom you are speaking? What, the sea keep her, The cold dark sea keep such a creature! What! Do not you know she is an angel sent In that strange way to keep misfortune from us? Cuth. And rarely well, forsooth, she did her business! Let angels stay in heaven. Ol. What 's that you're muttering? My Lord de Warenne says,—for once I asked him,— No need to know from whence she came, for never Was lady that could match her; and for beauty, Were she beheld at court, all eyes would so Worship her, 't would be her court, not the queen's. No, I'll not talk to you. Cuth. I'm a poor man, Yet not so ignorant but what I know That 's almost treason. Talk of beauty! Trash! Would she had gone to court then, and stayed there, Since that 's her place. She brought much sorrow here. Ol. No, you mean happiness. Sorrow! She bring it? You put me past all patience! How and when? How could a baby such as that bring sorrow? I know she came a little baby creature. Could syllable her own name, nothing more. How could you say that? Cuth. Nonsense! I say that? Ol. Oh yes, you did. If you would hide your thoughts, You must not think aloud. Put down your barrow Once more, and tell me straightway everything I want to know. What was that terrible something Befell ten years ago that none will speak of! I do remember something . . . . Cuth. Hush, I say! Ol. I know poor Leolyn was found one day Down on the white sands yonder . . . dead . . . Cuth. Come, come! Enough of that. Ol. But I will know. How died he? And then my mother . . . she died then, I think, And I was brought to her bedside to kiss her. I went unwilling, cruel little wretch! Being much engaged in teaching of his letters, To Druid there—oh, I remember well! Cuth. Poor lady! Ah, you 'll never be like her, However long you live—no, never be So good, nor yet so beautiful. Ol. I know it. No need to tell me that. But Bernard . . . tell me, Did he die then? Cuth. Die? Ay, be sure he did. Who ever said aught else? Ol. Why no one ever Says anything to me. Then did he die After my mother? Cuth. What is that to you? Ol. I cannot make you out. How you do look!— I guess it now. He is not dead at all!— I am sure that he is somewhere far away: I am sure he is not dead, though you will say so! Cuth. What makes you think that? Ol. Where is he? Oh where? I fancy I remember he was grave And gentle—like none else I 've ever seen— And sometimes even now I dream of him. Had he not blue eyes? How can you refuse To tell me where he is? Cuth. No matter—dead. Come, mistress, I have no more time to lose Over your idle chatter—not a word Of sense in all of it. And look you, there 's My Lord de Warenne coming. [Exit. Ol. Druid, hush! Enter De Warenne. Old dog, old dog! Will you ne'er know your friends?— He does not see me, he stops short—he's lost In one of his dark moods. Well, to my flowers then! De War. [musing] Oh, Annabella! magnet of my soul! Who, noble as thou art in innocence, Hast power to draw me down from heaven to hell— Who draw'st me still, as thou hast drawn for years, To this sad house where I have vowed so oft Never, never again to set my feet— Whom evermore to seek, ever to shun, Seemed my accursed destiny till death— Can duty bid me now to win and wear The terrible prize, the awful happiness, The hope of which is bitter as despair? What do I hope for? Shouldst thou smile me “yes,” Should I not shudder, wondering why I sought it— Regret almost this torture of suspense— The long waste of intolerable days? If “no,” the sudden chill of sick despair, When all light fades, and everything seems nothing— But I shall win—some devil tells me so. What, Olive, you? Ol. Good even, my good lord. Were you there with my father? De War. I have just left him. You are a busy gardener. Ol. All the winter I plan how I will play the tyrant here Amongst my summer subjects. De War. Do your flowers Know you for one of them, and talk to you In language of their own? Where 's Annabella? Ol. Stay; you can hear her. She hast just begun To dream her soul out o'er the organ yonder. Listen! You know those slow sounds are her thoughts. Oh, if I had her gift! De War. Wish yourself first A second St. Cecilia. [To himself] Gracious heavens! How does her soul from where she sits unseen Send its mysterious message out to mine! Each angel-voiced and crowded harmony Seems meant for me—each change of tone and theme Each rise and fall, my heart starts up to answer As to its own anticipated thought. Oh! if our spirits thus in air can meet, What law, what power, shall separate our lives? If she will love me, 'tis the voice of God. [Going] Olive, your father lives too much alone. Try you and win him to enjoy your talk, And know the blessing that his children are. Ol. I have tried, my lord, and try,—but if I speak He does not hear me, or I seem a shock Of discord on the slow tune of his thoughts. He smiles not when we laugh, nor asks a question Save on grave matters. De War. Ah, 't is pity, truly! Ol. Was he thus always? Never, since you knew him, Has he had any pleasure in his life? De War. No . . . he was ever silent . . . he was . . . no, Not quite as now. Ol. Oh sit, my lord, beseech you! I want to ask you something. I begin To think of many things. Surely my father Has lived thus chiefly since my mother's death, . . . And all the strange things which befell just then That none will speak of! De War. Oh, and why should you? Ol. Ah, there it is! Why, e'en old Cuthbert scolds me If I but breathe a word—pray stay a moment! I do so long to know. Wherefore says Cuthbert My Annabella brought misfortune here? De War. She brought? . . . Ol. I have thought . . . did they . . . my brothers . . . love her?— What have I said? Have I said what I should not? Speak to me! De War. You have said no wrong, my Olive, But in your ignorance you make wild guesses. She was a child. Ol. What, and am I a child? For she had just the age that I have now. De War. And have you lovers, then, my pretty friend? Ol. I want no lovers; and you say that only To make me angry, and to stop my talking? De War. No, no, I did not. Pardon me, indeed I cannot stay. Ol. Oh yes, you must, my lord! For there she comes, with streaming folds of blue, The colour, see, of purplest hyacinth, Sweeping the steps. De War. What said you? Did you speak? Enter Annabella. An. My Lord de Warenne, I am glad you are come. I think Sir Hugh has longed for you. De War. Not more Than I to be here. Ol. Hark, the nightingales! An. Yes; they are wakening up on all sides from The afternoon's long trance. De War. They are rapturous maniacs. How sweet the evening! Will you walk awhile? An. Surely. What say you, Olive? Ol. Make a third, Shall I? No, I will weed this bed of lilies. Druid shall go with you. And here comes Ulric! Oh, how that violent boy will waste my time! I know he comes to drag me down the glen To his beloved cove. Enter Ulric. Ul. Come, Olive, quick! A shoal of porpoises is bounding now Across the bay. You can see them through the limes there. Come down with me and watch them from the beach. Ol. Oh, must I? Well!—But there 's my lord. Ul. Your pardon, My Lord de Warenne, and good even. Come! [Exeunt Ulric and Olive. An. Will you walk now, or will you rather choose To linger here? De War. I think we are well thus. You reigned just now a very queen of music, Over a world of sounds most magical. I followed where you led through the sweet maze, With heart and brain submissive to your will. It seemed as if you thought with my own soul, Yet I seemed moving in a mystery. What was your thought? An. Oh, I thought not, I dreamed. De War. Your dream, what was it? Reverently I ask. An. Such vague unconscious movements of the mind Are scarcely worth recalling. De War. Your proud spirit, Does it reject the sympathy of one Whose heart beats with your slightest inspiration Unconsciously in rhythm? An. [after a pause.] It was a trance Wherein I scarcely seemed to hear the sounds That floated into space and lost themselves, Or know their meaning, till when all had ceased, The air seemed sighing with an invocation To some unbodied soul astray in æther, Some desolate wandering waif for ages lost, Nor claimed by any world, to come to this And find a home. De War. Would I had been that soul Through all the ages of its misery, To be so called by you. You scorn my folly— So says that curling lip. An. Indeed, my lord, Though I had lost myself in lofty nonsense Just now, I looked not for such flights from you. De War. Yet tell me do you often lose yourself In dreams so strange, such far-fetched poet-fancies? And is that why you care for no one? An. Oh, You do not think I care not, though you are pleased To say so. De War. You just let yourself be loved, And that is all. An. Not so, for I am grateful To all that love me—and they are not many— Nor care to add one to the number. De War. Oh, Cold noble angel! Shall not smiles, not tears, Shine ever on our passionate worship through The haughty seriousness of those large eyes? How vain to speak! How make you understand,— How make you care to understand, I love you? An. I am sorry for it . . . if 't is so indeed . . . I had long ceased to fancy this could be. De War. I am a fool to tell it—a mad fool! Yet who can choke the suffering heart for ever? No answer? Only that proud cold surprise? An. No; for I cannot love, and will not marry. De War. You cannot love, you will not marry me— That 's what you mean. An. Oh, love 's not of my world. De War. Why not? In heaven's name, why not? An. Must I tell you? But scarce should you have needed me to tell it. Ten years ago, that mystery of horror . . . That which I see you shrink to hear me speak of, As I to speak . . . have made such fancies hateful, If e'er I could have had them. Nay, my lord, You are wrong to go in anger. De War. Angry! My God! Angry with you? But can you wonder, then, That when my heart 's refused for some sad phantom Of girlish years gone by, the agony Is more than it can bear? I will not plague you With my vain passion more. An. It is not that— I have no love, no dream. Over the past A blinding pain has settled like a mist. . . . I need not speak of that . . . only, to give My life to this ill-fated family has seemed The one thing possible to my lonely heart. Not if my unknown and unguessed-of parents All smiling from the world of visions came, And stretched their arms to court me to a palace, Could I for these desert my second father. Yet stronger call could never come to me; All other dreams seem poor beside a dream So beautiful as that. De War. So deeply true— So pitilessly cold! But if—but if— Himself, Sir Hugh, owned for his keenest wish That we should be united?—I speak truth, He does desire this thing. He feels his life Waning. An. It is so. I have seen it too, His life is waning—and I am not kind To grieve for him who grieves not. De War. Oh, believe me, To bring him back his hopes and happiness . . . To bring back all that miserable past . . . I would . . . but no, I cannot talk of that. Enough, I feel it may be as he thinks— I cannot bear to think it, but at least This let me say—he longs for this last comfort, Though—silent, sad, and patient as he is— He would not urge it on you. Can you give it? Can you with me join to prepare a home, A future, for the bright young pair you love— For all our sakes? Oh, dare to be my wife, And found new happiness for him, for all! An. He shall not, no, he shall not send me from him. De War. I would not take you from him—only pray you To own a second home along with this— So might your life pass 'twixt two happy changes. And oh, if true love can absolve the soul From all the sins its past has stained it with, However deeply they may need forgiveness, Then may I humbly dare to think mine own Is worthy to be mated e'en with yours, And worship you for ever. Annabella! If I believed not this, I would lay down This heart beneath your feet, and, while you crushed it, Smile silent o'er the expiating torment, Love's penitent martyr. An. Wherefore this, my lord? Why this to me, who know your high deserts, And ever honoured you? De War. Honoured me! Love me! If we two loved, we could defy the world! Alas, that I can never strike from you That spark of passionate romance which lights Suddenly the dark doubtful pathway up, And sets the future all ablaze with stars! But give me then my answer. An. Let me think A moment, if a loveless heart can bear The lifelong burden of another's love, If such a life as I might lead beside you, Would, if most passionless, at least be noble— If one incapable of happiness Could make another happy. Let me think, And do not speak to me. De War. I will not breathe. [Leaning against a tree] Now, whilst she turns away her beautiful cheek, Weighing my doom like a severe, just queen— Now, can I pause to think what I am doing. No, no—too late! One moment's flash of hope Has dazzled all those ghastly doubts away That stood between us—and she shall be mine. An. My lord! De War. Speak, speak! I wait! An. You have my promise. De War. I have no words . . . not one . . . to thank and bless you . . . Never, never, never shall you repent— And, whatsoever you may find in me, Believe this, and this always, that I love you, You only, with my heart and soul, for ever! An. And have you thought if you can be content With such unjoyous and cold constancy? De War. It was too rash to hope you so would love me That whatsoe'er I be,—however short Of that all pure ideal I once soared to, However sometime traitor to world-laws— You still could prize the best, the love in me, And pardon all the worst—too rash! Oh, dare I E'er put it to the test? But I am raving— It is my part to strive and win this from you, And I will win it. An. I have told you all You ever can win. Having yielded that, Now let me beg one quiet hour to think. De War. What, leave you ere I quite believe this vision That I have had a glimpse of? An. Yes, pray leave me, And come again to-morrow. De War. Then how know I But all will melt in air? An. My word is given. De War. And not repented of? An. I am not so light. Good-night, my lord. De War. Good-night, if so it must be. [Exit Annabella. Oh, am I mad—or am I happy—which? If she had loved me, as some women can, Then in mine own eyes I had been absolved— But now I seem like one that lures away To dangerous seas, an ignorant comrade bent But on some pleasure-voyage of an hour. Oh for a heart to love me as I love, To love my true self, not interpret me, As the mistaken world interprets us, Crudely by the mere accidents of fate! Oh, Annabella, couldst thou but prove such! [Exit. Scene III. —The Sea-cove below the Grounds of the Manor Hall. Ulric and Olive seated on the Rocks. Ol. I can't think why you are so rude to him. I felt my cheeks on fire to see you so Turn your back on him! And my lord the while So gracious and so gentle. Ul. What of that? I do not like him. Ol. Not like Lord de Warenne! That 's a discovery! What has he done? Ul. Done? Nothing. It has grown upon me—somehow. Well, there 's one thing that I have noted, too, Which has escaped your eyes—where were they then? Have you ne'er thought that he loves Annabella? Ol. Ulric!—well, yes, of course he loves her—who Amongst us does not? Love her! As a lover, Do you mean that? Ul. Just that. A hundred times I 've seen him follow her with eyes intense As Gilbert's kestrels when they watch and watch— Not knowing or not heeding that I saw him. He thinks me but a foolish boy, you know, But I have guessed his secret. Ol. Can it be? I do believe you are right. This evening—oh, How lost, how strange he was, until she came! He scarcely seemed to understand or hear me, Broke off abruptly, asking where she was? And when she came, he looked— Ul. Oh, I could kill him! Ol. And this is why you hate him? Ul. Hate him! Who Said that I hate him? But what right has he To think of Annabella? Ol. She 'll not take him. She is too proud to marry, be you sure. Ul. What, not for a coronet? Ol. A coronet? She 's a king's daughter, if we did but know. Oh, Ulric, I believe she came to us Just as some rare bird lights upon our isle, A moment flashing all its wondrous plumes Amongst our woodlands—then away, away, Across strange oceans and to unknown shores, Never more to return to this. How oft I dream this, and I wander up and down Through forlorn lovely landscapes of enchantment, And look for her in vain. Ul. If she flew from us I'd follow her to the uttermost parts of earth, Like one of Arthur's errant knights of old, And never cease till I had won my quest. Ol. Yes, yes, he loves her. That was why he looked So white and awful, when I said one thing— Ul. What, Olive, what? Ol. I am ashamed to tell it. Ul. But tell me. Ol. Well, I spoke about our brothers. Ul. Of them? you spoke of them? Ol. Why should I not? I asked if haply . . . they could both have loved her? Ul. How strange you thought of that! What did he say? Ol. Oh, scarcely anything. It was his look— I felt that I had said a strange thing, Ulric! There is some mystery. I am sure now Old Cuthbert thinks that Bernard is alive. Ul. (after a pause). I think so too. Ol. And never told me, Ulric? Where is he then? Why did he go? What had it To do with Leolyn's death? Ul. Don't talk of it, Olive, I hate to think about it. Ol. You, too! You will not tell me. Ul. Well, I 'll tell you this, The time will come when I must ask my father, Have I, or have I not, a brother living? I wait, because I know that not once, since He lost them, has he uttered either name; And so I shrink from breaking in with questions. Ol. Do tell me more of this. When have we two Had secrets from each other? Ul. No, I cannot. I could not tell such things to any girl. Ol. For shame, girls are not always frightened fools! What do you mean by “such things?” Ul. Things I never Have told as yet to any one on earth, Things that no mortal creature knows but me . . . And that I try to put away from me, Half-hoping I have only fancied them. 'T is only since I 've ceased to he a child I half perceive their meaning . . . it comes out Like an invisible ink revealed by fire . . . And still the more I hate to think of it . . . Ask me no more. Look there! Ol. Why, who can that be? Ul. He looks like some seafaring man, but 't is not One of our fishermen; he has climbed the rocks Yonder at low tide. Ol. How he leans and gazes Like one entranced up the rough pathway: what Seeks he, I wonder? Does he know our house Stands at the head of that steep glen above him? One might guess by the cawing of the rooks That some old manor hall was hidden there Behind the tall pine grove. Ul. I must go see What he is like. Ol. But here comes our own Ella. Enter Annabella. And where 's my Lord de Warenne? An. He is gone. Ol. And did you come, then, here to look for us? An. Let me confess I had forgotten quite, You had fluttered down before me. Truth to tell, I have come here, hardly knowing how I came. Ul. [whispering to Olive]. She is thinking about him, be sure of that. [Walks away. Ol. You scarcely ever come, and when you do, You only count the waves. An. They fascinate me. Ol. This spot is such a gem! So fittingly The blue waves fill up the white curve of sand, And the red walls of rock on either side, With the green glen and golden gorse between, Make such a brightness, too, that in the dark Even to think of it dazzles my two eyes. Ul. [returning]. He seems a sailor, and he looks so strange, Somehow I scarcely like to speak to him, Or rouse him from his thoughts by coming near. I 'll find out all about him from the fishers. [Exit. Ol. Dear Annabella, you 'll not marry him? You will not leave us all for Lord de Warenne? An. But I shall be the same to you as ever. Ol. Then you do mean it? You do really mean it? Ella, then will you really marry him? An. One day. Ol. Oh, Ella! An. But why speak as if You hated the old friend you doated on so No further back—and that 's but yesterday— Than when you were the naughtiest of children? Ol. But when I think you are betrothed to him It seems so different. Do you—do you love him? An. You ask me that just in the awe-struck voice You used to urge me on with when I paused In telling fairy tales; and, truth to speak, The question suits those silly stories best. Ol. I do not think that I can ever bear it. Why should there be a change? We were so happy. If I should tell you what I think of it, You would laugh at me again. No chivalry— Nothing romantic—nothing wonderful— Of course I never shall wed any one, But if I did—of course I do not mean to— It should be some one from afar, some stranger Suddenly lighted at our gates, half knight, Half angel, dropped amongst us from the skies. But as for you . . . Just tell me one thing, Ella. Will you be angry with me? An. What new question? I fear, no wiser than the last. Ol. I wish You had loved some one else. If, now—if, now, Suddenly Bernard should return amongst us . . . An. Do not go on with that. Ol. May I not, Ella? Will you not tell me if he still is living? An. I know not. No one knows. Ol. What do you think? An. That he is dead. What can this be to you? To you he can be but a faintest painting On childhood's blotted, confused memory; No more than one you have read of in a book. But I had grown to feel them both my brothers, And therefore every time I speak their names, 'T is like a blood-drop wrung out of my heart. [Starting up. Oh, no! I cannot, will not, bear this spot! Ol. Forgive me, Ella! Let us come away. An. [kissing her]. Poor baby! But I was not angry with you. [Exeunt Annabella and Olive. Scene IV. —The Library. Sir Hugh seated; Annabella kneeling before him on a Footstool. An. You do—you do approve, then? Sir Hugh. Truly so. An. You are glad? Sir Hugh. I am glad. 'T will be to me One pleasant thought 'twined like a golden thread In the grey fabric of my life. An. Oh, then, I am glad too—I have done well—I have not Lived quite in vain. Sir Hugh. The friend so true to me, Will in due time to you—and you will love him— Be as the strong sheet-anchor of your soul; Whilst she, whose erring trust has worn in sunder, Shall find herself one day with sad surprise, Drifting away upon a cheerless sea, To mourn such freedom, and to love no more. That 's an old truth, I know. An. Yes, but old truths Flash sometimes back on us with startling newness. You are so tired—may I stay and read to you? Yes, let me read Chaucer, or Fairy-queen, Or the dear tale of Arthur and his knights? Sir Hugh. Not now, my child, not now—I have much to do, And for hours yet to come—good night. An. Good night, then . . . . I am dearly glad that I have pleased you so. [Exit.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. Scene I. —A Woodland spot in front of Gilbert's Cottage. Enter Bernard and Gilbert from different sides. Gil. You fellow there, what seek you? vagabonds And ruffians are not harboured on this manor! Come, what 's your business here? Bern. Only to rest A little moment, on this bench, my friend. Gil. [coming nearer.] Indeed, sir, you look pale. You have walked far, Perhaps, already, though the sun 's not high. Bern. I have wandered all the night. Gil. “Sir,” did I say? Well, no great harm in that, whoe'er you be— But though your speech is like the gentlefolks, You might be, as I guess, some shipless sailor . . . . Bern. I have been a sailor. Gil. And what are you now? Bern. A wanderer. Gil. That is to be nothing, man, Or worse than nothing. Bern. So I am. Gil. For shame! Such a strong likely fellow talk like that! Work, work, my friend, and make your own hands keep you. Bern. I am willing, show me how to earn a meal first, Ere I go further. Gil. Oh, for that, no matter, A crust to break your fast with, I'll not grudge you— And may be I can spare you a few minutes, To hear your story. Bern. Thanks. We 'll let that be A moment. [A pause.] Will you tell me . . . who is your master? Gil. You will have seen the Manor Hall, I think— The dark, red, ivied house amongst the elms? You would have passed it—that is Sir Hugh Lyle's, My master's—many a hundred years, they say, Lyles have lived there. Bern. Is he . . . an old man is he? Gil. Old? Not so old. It is not age, but somehow, He 's broken,—yes, he 's broken. Bern. [after a pause.] I should like To stay awhile in these parts, if I could . . . I would fain go no further . . . say I sought Service with—this Sir Hugh? Gil. Ah, now 't is out! That 's what you 're aiming at! Why, here and there, True, I might find you odds and ends of work, But we don't harbour vagrant strangers—no! Come now, your story, friend! where do you come from? Bern. No matter that, if I care not to tell. Gil. You take things easy, on my word, sir vagrant! Bern. You can but try me. Gil. You have a name at least? What do you call yourself? Bern. Well—Leonard Grey. Gil. Come, that is something—you have at least been christened. You 'll have to vouchsafe more, though, my good friend, If you are to stay here. What can you do? Can you train hawks—ride or break in a horse— Mend fences, or tend cattle? Bern. All these things I have done in my time. Gil. You are a strange fellow! I know not why I send you not straightway After your business, which it seems is nothing. I think I am the greatest of all fools; But I do trust you—I can't help myself. I'll speak to our young master. He 'll be here, Be sure, ere long. Bern. I thank you. Did you say Sir Hugh . . . was failing somewhat? Gil. Ay, that is he. Bern. Sickness? You say he is not old. Gil. Say rather He has had troubles. Bern. [after a pause.] What may those have been? Has he had losses? Land, I mean? or money? Gil. Ah, 't is a strange tale. Well, in that old house Some ugly things have happened. Bern. In your time? Gil. No, not in mine. I have been here but five years; I was bred further north, on the estates Of my late lady's father—she you know 's dead— And this I speak of was, ay, ten years back. They keep it close, that people at the Hall, But 't is a village tale, as you may guess, Though they all say that our young master, Ulric, And my young lady, to this day know nothing. You see 't was in their childhood. Bern. Will you tell me What is this village talk? Gil. Well—why tell you? But 't is no secret. Bern. Let me hear it then? Gil. Truly I do believe it all arose From that unlucky shipwreck, and that child! Bern. Tell me of that? Gil. 'T was on those very rocks Below the rough glen yonder. You can't see them, Though you just hear the murmur of the waves— But 't is a cursed spot for such mischances— Though this was long years back. Bern. Go on. Gil. I've heard it Often—the strangest tale! Who would have thought All that would come of it! 'T was a tall ship, Of foreign build they fancied, as the gleams Of lightning showed it them by fits and starts, That pitch-dark night—and crash! they saw it too Split like an eggshell on yon ugly pavement, Whilst crowds stood watching—all the old sad story— Sir Hugh amongst them, and my Lord de Warenne —A youth then from his travels just returned— And all did what they could—and that was nothing. Bern. But some . . . were saved? Gil. Oh yes! That makes the strangeness. By miracle—I know not rightly how— A little two-years' babe—it might be less, It might be more—was rescued from the sea. Sir Hugh and his kind lady took the orphan And reared it as their own, to their own sorrow. You know 't is said whoever saves a soul From drowning, saves it to his own undoing. Bern. Was it so now? Gil. As you shall see. And doubly Ill-omened was that rescue, for 't is said By those who know, 't was the ghost-light up yonder In the old ruined watch-tower, wrecked that ship. 'T was there that wicked old Sir Ralph was wont, In days gone by—so say the people here— To set false signals for poor mariners, All for the greed of booty—so thenceforth That light in the old tower shows itself Each time a ship is doomed to touch those rocks. Whoever sees it knows a wreck is near— And each time, for three hundred years they say Some evil has befallen this family, Although themsleves scoff ever at the story— No Lyle has seen that light, or ever will. Nay, are you listening? With your head in your hands That fashion, one would say you were asleep. Bern. I was not sleeping. Pray go on. Gil. Your voice Sounds sleepy though; yet one would think my tale Might keep the dead awake. Now but hear this: That self-same pretty child they saved that night, When she grew up a slim and fair young maid, She, we may say so, robbed the good Sir Hugh Of his two first-born, and his wife as well. You 'll wonder how that could be? Sad to tell For love of her one brother killed the other. Heaven save us! Why, what now? Where start you to? Bern. [returning.] Pardon me. I have lived a life so wild And wandering, I have learnt, I think, rough ways. But I heard all . . . How, tell me, was this known? Was there no doubt? . . . Did any see the deed? Gil. No, 't was suspicion only. Bern. Who could dare Suspect a thing so monstrous? Gil. I can't tell you All the sure proofs they had, but proofs there were. And this I know, young Leolyn's corpse was found One evening in the cove stabbed to the heart. The mother died next day, the brother fled, And has not since been heard of. Bern. [after a pause.] Do they still Believe he did it? . . . Nothing more discovered? Gil. Oh, nothing that I know of—not a soul But feels assured he did it, now as then. Lad as he was, nor given, they say, to wrangling, And unlike other striplings of his age. But Sir Ralph's blood ran still and deep within him. The eldest, Leolyn—a haughty youth, I 've heard he was, but thought at court a Phœnix— Was only one-and-twenty, as I think, And mad in love, they say, with that young creature, When first he came home from his foreign travels. I tell you all believe 't was as I say, Though it had been hard matter, so 't is thought, To have scraped up proofs enough for judge and jury. Now you know why Sir Hugh lives broken-hearted. Bern. My God! Gil. Such things do not chance every day. Well may you wonder that one mad young fool Should bring such misery down on each and all For a love fancy. Had I been their father I would have sent that girl, for all her beauty, Out of my sight, away to the world's end. Bern. But she still lives with them? Gil. Ay, that does she, And just as handsome as in days gone by. They treat her like a queen, ay all of them, And like a queen I'll own she bears herself, Proud, mischievous foreigner! Oh pity, pity!— Ha! In good time! You hear those horse-hoofs yonder, Amongst the trees? 'T is the young master out Already with his sister; they both love Their morning gallop o'er the bluebells. Hold! Here he is coming to us. [Enter Ulric, riding.] Ul. I will follow! Do not wait, Olive! Gil. I 'll just say one word About yourself. Don't draw back, let him see you. Ul. [approaching.] Here, Gilbert—ha! whom have you here? what is he? What does he want? Gil. Sir, I've just promised him— Ul. What eyes, by heaven! And how he looks at me! Is he unhappy? Why, his eyes flash blue! But what about him? Gil. Sir, 'tis an odd fancy, You 'll say, for me to take—and so it is— I never saw the man until this morn. I only know that he has been a sailor. Ul. The very man! I saw him on the rocks Last evening, wandering like a shipwrecked ghost. I said he was a sailor! Gil. And, he 'll tell you, Many things else—but will not tell his story; And yet is fain to take some service with us: Says he can train hawks, horses, and what not. You see he 's a fine noble-looking fellow, For all that rough, wild mane—I'll wager, sir, No ruffian, nor mere rustic,—speak to him! Calls himself Leonard Grey. Ul. Good-morrow, friend— Gilbert here tells me—say, have you no home, No friends? Bern. None. Ul. Stay—don't walk away. You wish then To stay and serve here? Bern. If I be permitted. Ul. Won't you say where you come from? Bern. That 's small matter, If I but do my duty; yet I pledge My word to you, I come of honest parents, And early left my home to seek my fortunes. I have failed, but through no fault. Gil. [to Ulric.] Now, look you, sir, He might so glibly have just forged a tale, To satisfy us. Silence looks more honest, Sir, to my thinking. Ul. Oh, he does look honest! Now you know, Gilbert, you have often groaned For a young pair of hands to help you— Gil. Sir, I dare swear there is none will call me idle. I do my duty—but by little and little All burdens fall on me. I 'm falconer, Forester, and all things else in one. And now I 'm getting old, too. I will own This fellow takes my fancy mightily. I am a fool—and yet the more I look The more I see he is no mere ne'er-do-well, That will work hard at all things, save his business. Ul. Oh we will keep him. Stay, you can train horses, Leonard, you tell us? Bern. I have tamed, ere now, The wildest colts of the savannah. Ul. Gilbert! Oh, think not I will spare him to your hawks, If this be so. Leonard shall be my groom, If he can master Sorcerer. There, Gilbert! I 've found a test for him. Gil. You 've found a way, sir, To break his neck, I think. Right well you know There 's ne'er a man now in your father's stables That can so much as mount him. Ul. 'T is a shame! A horse the wonder of the country-side, The beautifulest of devils! I declare, I 'd do it, if they 'd let me—will you try him— Will you try Sorcerer? Bern. Whene'er you will. Ul. He has a devil, mark me!—is, I think, Satan himself. Bern. I'll try to exorcise him. Ul. I 'll show you him when I come home again.— Gilbert, keep Leonard here till I return. [Exit. Gil. A lucky morning this, for you, I think— Well may you look at them! Oh pity, pity, The other two are wanting. But Sir Hugh, To my mind, sins to fret so evermore For those he has lost. He might take pride and pleasure, A little, in that noble boy and girl. Enter Lettice. Why, here 's more company. Let. What, a friend with you? He has walked away—but 't is no secret neither, I come to tell you. Gil. Come to bring me news So early? Let. News, indeed! I used to think Nothing could ever happen in our house Again, in my time. Gil. Well, what is it now? Let. First—we are all bidden to a festival That 's holden in the hall to-night—no less Than—wonder now—a dance! For us, for you, For all the retinue of the old place yonder, That list to come. Gil. Well now, if you had said Sir Hugh had bid fell all the timber round, You had amazed me less. Let. Truth, I assure you. Gil. 'T is just one of your jests. This very night, too! How will the maidens have their finery ready? Let. Come up to-night, and see. You have not guessed The meaning of this merrymaking. Gil. Out with it! How should I guess? Let. 'T is a betrothal—there! Gil. What! that child? Why, she rode past us just now! Let. Not she! Forsooth, it is our foreign beauty,— 'T is she that weds— Gil. Whom, in the name of wonder? Let. Whom but my Lord de Warenne? There 's news for you! Gil. She marry! That proud princess! She at last! Let. Sir Hugh, it seems, for once, is almost glad; And so he bids rejoice this abrupt fashion. He won't have any of his own degree— None but his own folk from his own lands. You Come in good time, and you shall dance with me. If not so young as all those giddy girls, You 'll own I 'm more experienced in my steps. Gil. No, no! you go too fast for me. What say you To him there for a partner? I will tell you About him shortly. Let. Well, bring whom you will. I must be back again in haste to the hall. [Exit. Gil. Well, now we've done with gossip, see my falcons: They are worth the trouble, I can tell you that. [Exeunt. Scene II. —The Manor Hall. A Gallery overlooking the Court. Enter Annabella and Olive. Ol. Come to this window—see that strange new groom, Ulric has found—dropt somewhere from the clouds— Mount Sorcerer. Ulric says he has promised To bring the rebel to his senses. An. Has he? My heart is on the side of the poor rebel. Ol. They are all waiting there, the grooms and horse-boys— And now comes Ulric. Oh, you must look now! The furious, beautiful, black creature, all A-quiver with the hell-fire raging in him! An. Poor savage! brave in vain against his fate, The tyrant's master-mind. Ol. There! there! that sailor— That must be Leonard—with the wild brown hair, That smothers half his face! How quiet he is! He knows—I trust he knows—what he is doing. [Covering her face.] Oh, I can't look! it 's frightful! He will be killed! [Cries of “Well done!” heard from below. An. Safe in the saddle! Ol. Oh, thank heaven! thank heaven! That storm of whirling hoofs hid all from me! 'T is magic! Conquered almost by a look, Was he not? An. We shall see. Ol. There 's Ulric mounted, And Oswald. Off goes Leonard through the archway! An. Like Satan and some mortal that has just Outwitted him in a bargain for his soul. Ol. But what will happen next? Will he return With limbs unbroken? Ulric says that horse Plays strangest antics, curls into a ball, And then uncurls in diabolic fashion. Shall we go? What are you thinking of? An. [speaking half to herself.] How can I tell? A chance look, a chance tone, something or nothing, Touched on some sensitive nerve within my brain, And straight a long-closed door seemed to fly open, A light streamed in, and there was all the past! And, oh, how past! For, ten times spring has brought The sunsets flaming through young chestnut-leaves, And scent of sweetbrier, and of grass new-mown, And Babel-clamours of the birds again— But not the girlish spirit back with them, More evanescent and ethereal still . . . Enter De Warenne from the further end. Ol. [meeting him.] You have found us out. De War. They told me you were here. Accept my greetings. Ol. If your eyes seek her, She is in that window there. She has seen a spirit— Go, ask her all about it. [Exit. De War. Annabella! An. Oh—who is that? De War. Do I so startle you? You surely looked to see me? An. Surely—yes . . . After our last night's parting. De War. Is that all? My coming does not please you? An. Do not think so. My word and faith are given to you. De War. And yet I find you in your thoughts so far away, You start to see me. An. I will tell you then— Since in some sort I owe my thoughts to you— And mine lay deep down and were sad ones too— What I was pondering . . . De War. Tell me, in God's name! An. Some perplexed questionings on human crime . . . De War. Of human crime, great heavens! An. I wondered, as I oft have wondered, if a crime, . . . a great Irrevocable crime . . . may not be sometimes The one exceptional action of a life . . . Linked neither with the past nor with the future By any evil bias of the soul . . . A thing to put aside . . . De War. Surely it may— At least I think so. Yes, I think that men Have groaned under a hopeless burden, had Their whole lives poisoned to them, either by Secret remorse, or published ignominy, Through some unhappy deed . . . that not themselves But, as you say, some accident of fate . . . Take . . . take the crime whose name affrights us all . . . Perhaps we are the veriest slaves of names . . . Perhaps the immortal spirit which one blow,— Too swift, it may be, even to be felt,— Released from flesh, may smile at that word . . . murder . . . Smile that its wakening to new life and light Should here be called misfortune, and the deed Which wakened it, a crime. An. I wish I knew If your thought springs from the same source as mine— If—but I see it pains you—and me too.— Have you yet seen this wondrous Leonard Grey? [They pass out of the gallery. Scene III. —The Court-yard. Bernard and Ulric just dismounted from their Horses. Ul. Oh, Leonard, what a man you are! That demon Against his will you 've turned into an angel! And now black Sorcerer, you have found your master For ever more! Oh, how have we all lived Without you? There is Oswald—he can ride, We all know that—but he 's a child to you— Oswald, you know it. Osw. That 's as may be, Sir. [Aside] 'T is not my fault—I 've made no league with Satan. Ul. When he began his devilry again, Just as we got upon the turf, you know— You 'd say he had a hundred hoofs, not four— Then I did think it was all over with you. He meant it—he meant murder, nothing else— In truth I knew not half his wickedness, No, nor yet half his worth. Oh, you must teach me The cunning secrets you have brought away From your wild west with you. How old were you When you left home? You must have had adventures And wondrous—by the score—by land and sea? And fought the Spaniards oft? Bern. Yes, I have been Where human lives were tossed about in the air As children toss their balls. Ul. But I shall never Get half my questions asked. Why, why not tell me Who you are—where you come from? Bern. 'T is small matter. The past is past—why should we talk of it? Ul. And shall you never see your home again, Nor parents? Bern. Well—I cannot talk of that. Ul. Well, Leonard, then at least you 'll stay here always? Bern. That may be doubtful. Ul. I shall speak to-night About you to my father. Bern. But if Fate Held me as in a leash, to pluck me back, When my time comes? Ul. Oh, but where would you go, If you left us? Bern. Where would I go? Oh, God! I need not think of that yet—no, not yet. The very dead may leave their graves at night! Ul. Leonard! But you talk thus, to startle me From asking you more questions. See you come Up to the Hall to-night—I must be gone. To-morrow you shall tell me everything. [Exit. Scene IV. —The Hall. Servants, Retainers, etc., entering and filling it by degrees. Enter Humphrey. Humph. Well, friends, this truly is a pleasant sight; I trust you feel Sir Hugh's great condescension. And you, young lads and lasses, you in chief, Met for the first time under such a roof, Must show your humble gratitude to him By your discreet deportment, mostly then When he and his vouchsafe to come amongst us, And when, perhaps—I just may hint so much— My lord himself and Mistress Annabella, And our young master and young lady, too, Will of their goodness dance one dance with us. No giddy noise and laughter then, I pray,— Enjoy yourselves with seemly merriment, As fits the time and place and such a presence. Let. Good man! He understands how fittingly A humbling admonition prefaces And adds to the enjoyments of young folks! The bashful ones seem much encouraged. Enter Cuthbert. Here Comes one too late for the lesson. Well done, Cuthbert! You are the death's-head ready at hand to check us Whene'er we grow too noisy. Well, what think you? Does not the dull old hall show to advantage, Though you did stint us so in bough and blossom? But we have done our best. Cuth. Advantage! What! You have done your best, I warrant, with this rubbish, The sweepings of my barrow. Ten years back 'T was different—ay, the old hall was as gay, With the fine colours of the gentlefolk, And with the ladies' talk and laughter, bless you, As Mistress Olive's gilded aviary there. Had he that 's dead and gone been here this day— Why do you talk to me? I am an old fool! I have no business here,—but something drew me, I can't tell what—to see that poor lad's sweetheart Take a new love with all this talk and noise. A proud young fellow, too, he looked the master, He looked the master of us all—but you— None of you think of that now. Let. Why what use To think of it? Don't call up our old ghosts, To-night, old man. Cuth. Oh, I 'm content, I tell you, Content enough, so others be content. I don't set so much store by yon fine damsel This lord 's to marry—let him please himself. Only she has much to answer for, I say, For all her shy looks, and her proud pretences, As though she saw not well enough, forsooth, With those two great brown haughty eyes of hers The fools who came to bow and coax and flatter— And such a veriest May-wand as she was! Lord, what a rose she carried on her cheeks, though— And such a thing as that to work such mischief! Let. Come, come, old man, truce to your mutterings. The youngsters will be catching up your words— And I shall fancy if you talk on so, Some horrid ghost is crouched behind the hangings! Enter Bernard and Gilbert. Humph. Who is that stranger Gilbert brings with him? Do any of you know him? Osw. That 's the man They talk so much of—Leonard Grey, that rode Black Sorcerer to-day, and had such luck. Another day, perhaps, he may fare worse, But now they all think him the sorcerer. Humph. Is that the man? Osw. Ay, that 's the favoured mortal That has bewitched our Master Ulric so. Let. He 's fain to go back to his mad black horse, I think. He looks, amongst us cheerful Christians, The very saddest of the sad—or, rather, Like one who has just forgotten his own name. I 'll presently go tell him what it is. Why, Cuthbert there can't take his eyes from him— He has spied out a Jesuit. Humph. Good even, Gilbert. [To Bernard.] Young man, I bid you very welcome here, And trust you feel how fortunate you are, To be admitted at a time like this. You will soon see our master's family, Who graciously have promised so to honour The honest folk here met. You see that door,— The great carved oaken door and canopy At the far end,—'t is there you 'll see them enter And take seats on the dais. Look round, pray you. It is a noble hall—a sight, no doubt, That 's new to you, who have seen many things, It may be, less worth seeing. Bern. That is most true. [Humphrey moves away. How often have I been here in my dreams! Humph. [turning back.] Then must your dreams, young man, be very strange ones. To show you things you never saw awake. Nay, friend, don't tell me that. Bern. I mean . . . of course . . . I only mean that in my hardest straits I have dreamed of beautiful and happy homes, As famished men dream of the banquet board. 'T is a fine hall. Humph. See all the portraits hung 'Twixt those deep oak-framed windows—ay, and note The carved black oaken tables ranged beneath them; They are thought a miracle of workmanship, Those feathers, flowers, and foliage. You may count here Whole generations of the Lyles gone by, But none of those now living—our late lady, She, too, is elsewhere—in the library: But that 's no matter now. Gil. [aside to Bernard.] One day I'll show you Two other portraits I'll not name that hang Out of the way in . . . Humph. You should look up too. Strangers that come do ever much admire The carved and gilded groining of the roof. Well, to my other duties: now, young man, I trust that you will well enjoy yourself Under our roof to-night. Gil. You are in luck, For that grave gentleman thinks well of you. He talks to you this condescending fashion, Because he knows you are from over seas; And he is so proud to show this hall of ours To travelled strangers—and you look so wise And thoughtful, you don't seem like one of us. Ay, you have dropped here, too, at no bad moment— On any other day but this, I know, You would have thought a corpse was in the house, You scarcely hear a whisper within doors. Bern. All this bewilders me . . . let me stand back . . . I do not care to dance . . . nor yet to talk . . . Gil. Well, as you please. 'T is time the gentlefolk Should show their faces now. The young ones all, You see, are growing eager for the dance— 'T is time, I say, these empty chairs were filled: Nay, one step nearer—there! Enter Sir Hugh, De Warenne, Annabella, Ulric, and Olive. Where are you? Oh, No need to shrink back, they 'll not notice you! A noble-looking gentleman, you see, Is good Sir Hugh; but 't is just as I said, Feebler and paler than his age. Bern. Oh, God! Gil. What now? Why, on my soul, 't is you Are pale—ay, trembling, too, from head to foot— Your very lips white! What is this has seized you? Sit on this bench, then. Bern. You will think it strange. These lights . . . the heat . . . Gil. Nay, go into the air And get this faintness over. Stay, drink this. You 'll be well straightway. You strange being, you, To be so strong and weak both! Are you often Seized thus? Bern. Oh, no—but I have lived so long In the free air . . . Thanks, I am well again. [Music strikes up, Cuthbert approaches Bernard and Gilbert. Let. Come, Cuthbert, shall I find a partner for you? 'T is only twenty years since last you danced. Cuth. Ay, when I danced with you. Let. That must have been When you danced me a baby in your arms. [To Bernard.] I dare not, after what you have heard just now, Propose myself to be your partner, but Will cheerfully lead you to some younger fair one. Gil. Oh, he 'll not dance he tells me. Let. Is he crazed, This friend of yours? He might, at least, have thanked me, Instead of staring at the great folks yonder. Are you sure he knows where he is? Gil. Excuse him, He has lived in the rough places of the earth, And is not used to such fine company. Let. He seems bewildered, like a prowling owl Straying abroad by daylight. Gil. Wake up, friend! You are bid to dance, but I have answered for you, Your own thoughts please you best. Bern. Oh, yes . . . with thanks . . . I know I scarcely have a right to burden Your gala-night with such a useless presence . . . I will relieve you soon. Gil. No, no; cheer up! Bern. I ought to, looking on such joyous faces. De War. [Taking Annabella's hand.] You know 't is ruled we two should lead the dance, And Ulric there will follow with his sister. An. Oh, as you will, my lord. [To Sir Hugh.] We 'll come back to you, And go away together, shall we not? Sir Hugh. I shall be patient whilst you dance, my child. You must not think of me. Ul. Come, Olive, come! One dance, and then 't is over. How I hate it! [The dance begins. Why there is Leonard, looking on so gravely From under those dark meeting brows of his! I wonder what he 's thinking of? Ol. Of strange Adventures, doubt not, in the golden dream-lands, Away in Spain's enchanted Indies.—Oh! Do but admire grave Humphrey there with Phœbe, With what a stately grace he takes her hand. You don't treat me with half such ceremony. Gil. Now, tell me, is not that a sight worth seeing? That pretty creature, dancing with her brother? If they inherit troubles with their name, At least the Lyles inherit beauty too. But then the other one—the beauty—why You look at her and wonder—she just looks To my mind, like some queen from over seas, In all her foreign bravery—you would never Take her for English bred, although she came So young here that she knows not where she came from. You saw that golden rosary? They say She always wears that—it was found upon her When she was cast on shore. By that you see She comes of Papist kin. Bern. She . . . which was she? Gil. The tall one, dressed in white, broidered with gold— She that was dancing with my lord, you know— Where strayed your eyes when she was on the dais? Bern. I could see nothing there in all that glare— I only saw my—'t was Sir Hugh I looked at. Gil. There, there she comes! Bern. 'T is some resembling sister . . . Oh no, herself . . . her very self . . . but changed!— My God! I cannot bear this! Gil. What is that You are saying? Are you awake then? Cuth. [approaching.] Master Gilbert, You are wanted by those fellows there. [Gilbert leaves them. How know you She is changed? Bern. What say you?—Old man, you are dreaming . . . I did not speak. Cuth. Do you wish to kill your father? Bern. What do you mean? Cuth. For shame! No more of that! You can't deceive me, sir. Away with you! Bern. Cuthbert . . . how did you know me? All the rest, You see, have quite forgotten me . . . I thought I was too changed. Cuth. And so you are—you are. You were a lad then—now you are a strong man. Oh, but I knew you at a glance—I knew you! And there 's none here remembers as I do— Your father's elder brother—your own namesake, As you are now, you are just his portrait—ay, Came to the scaffold just about your age. But his crime, I have always said, his crime Was not so damnable. They called it treason— But Cain did worse. Bern. Cuthbert, you were my friend once. Cuth. Ay, so I was—best talk no more of that. You must be gone. Your father, by God's mercy, Sits thinking in himself, and sees just nothing— Don't look at him—by the lord, sir, are you mad? What, Druid, too,—blind Druid—has found you out! Do you think they 'll not see that? Don't they all know He 'll lick no stranger's hand? Why to this day He growls at my lord, there—Plague on the brute! Whining already! Come out, no one 's looking. [Exeunt Bernard and Cuthbert. De War. [passing with Annabella.] Then, Annabella, is this happiness? Or are we but two players on a stage, And playing our parts ill? Fool that I was! Whilst thus so kindly cold you move beside me, Methinks that we are only baffled phantoms Reacting on the pale Elysian fields, In a mechanical and silent game, The old intensity of joy and pain, The strain and passion of a warmer world. Your very beauty, even whilst I speak, Seems waning from its own imperial tints, To make the sad comparison more just. Or what else, tell me, means this pale eclipse, This moonlight copy of yourself,—no colour Save the brown shading of your eyes and hair? You are tired—we 'll rest. An. Oh, let us come away. De War. Yes, Sir Hugh rises, we will follow him. An. And as for happiness . . . what matters it . . . If neither you nor I should ever find it? How can the heart that feels . . . ever be happy? De War. I 'll lead you to the summer-parlour, then Start on my homeward ride ere set of moon. An. You will go so soon? De War. Why should I stay? The moon Above me, will not be more lone than I. Ay, here and now. An. But you will come to-morrow? You said that you were going, did you not? I am so strangely tired. . . . Yes, to-morrow? De War. I know not. Yes, perchance, if you desire it. Ul. Come, Olive, let us go. We have done our duty. [Exeunt Sir Hugh, De Warenne, Annabella, Ulric, and Olive. Scene V. —The Garden. Bernard, Cuthbert, and Druid. Bern. One friend that 's true to me . . . poor dog! dear dog! Cuth. You can't stay here; no, not a moment longer! It was a shame to come. What, did you think That you could show yourself? Bern. You mean, of course, I shall be hanged if I am found here? Cuth. Oh, I don't say that, sir; no, I don't say that,— Things may be known that can't be proved by law; And I don't say there 's one here would betray you; But you would have such shame as kills some men, And you would kill your father. He is sick. I have seen it ofttimes when I 've stopped my work To watch him as he paced along. Young master, I cannot talk with you! I can't, I can't! Away with you; say nothing to old Gilbert. He 'd talk and hinder you. Bern. I shall not go Till I have seen my mother's grave. Where is it? Cuth. What, have you heart and front enough for that? Oh, were I you, I 'd pray the earth to open And swallow me, before I would stand there. Poor lady! As she lies there in the dark, Could she but know who 's talking of her, why Her heart would break again beneath the sod. Bern. My mother! Cuth. Ay, it killed her. Bern. Where is her grave? Cuth. She lies in the churchyard—she loved the flowers And birds so, she would say she ne'er could rest In the cold vault, and so Sir Hugh bade lay her Under the elm, that we call the ghost's tree; And Mistress Annabella and your sister They have set primroses and violets And snowdrops, and such common things as those, Above her. Bern. You will never see me more; So I might tell you, but that it would be useless . . . No, best forget me quite. [Exit. Cuth. And I must watch him— Ay, and that dog too, for the poor blind brute Would let all out. I 'm a worse brute than he; But there 's no help for it, none. Tough as I am, I do think this will kill me . . . I ne'er looked for it . . . O Lord, that I might lie, my day's work done, Under the daisies too! By this time sure He has reached the churchyard wicket: I must follow. [Exit. Scene VI. —The Court-yard. Enter De Warenne and Ulric. Ul. They are at their foolery, every man of them, Groom, horse-boy, serving-man, and all—and all, Perchance, despite old Humphrey, less than sober; But I will saddle you your bay myself, If you are pressed to go. De War. Yes, yes, to-night I do not care to stay. I 'll go with you. Ul. I did hear some one saying he had seen Leonard with Cuthbert talking in the garden. He is not within, I know, but 't were waste time, Methinks, to seek him now. De War. Oh 't is no matter, We 'll go now to the stables. Enter Cuthbert. Ul. Here 's one straggler. What, Cuthbert, have you broken from the revels So early, you, the very life of the dance? Cuth. My lord, my lord! A word apart with you! De War. I am pressed. Cuth. Ay, so am I too. [Whispering.] There 's none else 'T is fit to speak to: not that poor lad there— Too young by half. De War. Come then, tell me this trouble; Some freak of yonder revellers? That concerns Old Humphrey's office. Cuth. No, no, no, my lord! No grief like that; 't is noways what you think. Ul. Well, then, whilst Cuthbert whispers this great matter, I will go saddle you your Moslem. De War. Thanks! [Exit Ulric. Now, my good friend? Cuth. Well, well! No use nor time, To beat about the bush. I 'll tell it plainly. That man, my lord—that self-same Leonard Grey, Who rode black Sorcerer—that very man Young Master Ulric sets such store by— De War. Is Some thief that has broke prison, Jesuit spy, Or disguised Spaniard? Cuth. I must out with it! That man, my lord, is—Bernard Lyle himself! Oh, I knew well that I should startle you! But rouse yourself, in heaven's name! Look to it! Though I do see your face is white,—ay, whiter Than this white moonlight makes it,—there 's no time, My lord, for wondering; something must be done, And quickly. De War. Some impostor— Cuth. No, no, no! Don't tell me that! I not know my own lad! Trust me and Druid! De War. Oh, some dexterous knave, Trusting to a chance likeness, and the changes Ten years may print on any stripling's face, Covets the lands of Lylford. Cuth. And the gallows Along with them? De War. Man, you are mad to say so! Who dares speak such a word? No law could touch him, Whatever you or I may guess or think; For we may feel a deed in the air around us, May see it written there, yet never prove it! Cuth. That 's as may be. But Bernard Lyle it is, And here he must not stay. My lord, you 'll tell him! De War. Not I? I will not see him. Cuth. What, my lord! And will you have your lady that 's to be— De War. What? Cuth. Be the first to give him welcome hither? De War. In the devil's name, what mean you? Cuth. This, my lord— I saw her white dress flitting down the path To the churchyard—and there she will find him; And 't is not fitting—no. I think, my lord, She knew him in the hall. I saw her dart One look at him,—'t was whilst she danced with you,— And turn as white as you are now. De War. By God! You are right—I see it! Madman that I have been! What devil sealed my eyes? [Exit. Cuth. And she they thought Did love the other, talking with his murderer! And my lord jealous! Ay, it needed that To wake him from his stupor. I scarce thought To see him so struck down. But I did well: He is a noble gentleman, and loves My master. Curse it! Oh, my poor, poor lad! I 'll go and watch that boy from coming near them. [Exit. Scene VII. —The Churchyard. Bernard rising from his Mother's Grave. Bern. Thank God! The rending throes are over now. I can think where I am, and what I am, Without a second frenzy. I am calm, And I can calmly think of you, my mother. Oh, mother, mother, mother! you believed, You—only you—in your unhappy son! You did not turn him from your kind heart's door— You did not ban him from his house and home, When my own father—oh, my God! my God!— My father—my own father—with white face, He looked the curse I almost heard him speak. And so, a guiltless Cain, accurst I am, By man's injustice, by the devil's hate, And God's disdain of such a wretch as I! And mother, in a life of misery, Your darling voice, your own ineffable smile, Have soothed my dreams and agonized my wakings, Till I have longed to die—and yet lived on, Through the fierce energies of strenuous youth's Instinct, recoiling from death's nothingness— That I might drain the cup to the very dregs. Now let me try and lay up for myself One thought, one memory—just one water-drop For those strange fires of misery I go back to, Unpitied and unknown as first I came. Where shall I find it? Let me try to think— For I have seen all that I came to see, The grave of the one being that believed me— My father, broken-hearted, yet to me But a blind distant deity of stone— Those little ones, my brother once and sister, Grown up to live without a thought of me— And my one love . . . Oh Annabella, love! My barbarous, barbarous love! bound to another! No, never mine! You never, never knew, And now would loathe to think I could have loved you— And yet I live, and yet I am not mad! Enter Annabella unseen. An. Bernard! Bern. What! Who is there? Has the Ghost's Tree Summoned its phantom hither? An. Is it . . . Bernard? It is so dark there . . . Bern. It is he. An. Oh Bernard! . . . I saw you in the hall . . . I knew you . . . Bernard! Bern. Why do you come here? Are you not one of those Who call me Cain? An. Bernard! Bernard! For years I wondered . . . and this eve a light flashed on me— Say what you will, I shall believe your word. Bern. Then God, it seems, is merciful at last, And I will speak. That I should have to say it! I did not kill my brother—God alone, God knows, not I, who did. There! That is enough! I may go now. An. Oh Bernard! Oh, lost brother! You see I try . . . You see I cannot speak . . . Come home, dear, and forgive us! Bern. Annabel, You know not what you say—I have no home— I must not, cannot stay—and you must never Speak of me. It is better so . . . my father Will bear his burden yet a little while, . . . Then die . . . and know my innocence. An. You kill me! Come now, now, now! Bern. I would I might die now! I must not stay. Enter De Warenne. De War. I pray your pardon, madam, For breaking on this private conference, And further, in my right as your betrothed, Bidding you leave this spot. You, sir, how dare you To hold this lady here in talk? Bern. 'T is hers To choose whom she will talk with. An. Adrian! Adrian! 'T is Bernard, our lost Bernard! Do you not know him? De War. What madness is all this? An. And he is guiltless! I am ashamed to say so before him— Guiltless as you are. Bern. Calm yourself, my lord. Enough for me she knows my innocence; I ask not for your verdict. For the rest, I shall go hence—my father shall remain Unvexed by me for ever. De War. Sir, you will lose For your own sake no moment. I will add, So you will rid us of your presence now, You have nought to fear from me. I will assume You are that you call yourself—but that 's not proved. Were you but the wild sailor that I think you, 'T were your best wisdom still to— An. Stop, my lord. Or I shall hate you! De War. Come away then—come, We will talk this over calmly. Enter Ulric. Ul. So I have found you! Cuthbert misled me. My lord, Moslem 's saddled— What is all this? What has happened? Won't you speak? Why look you on each other? Bern. All this means, My boy, that I must leave you, and for ever. An. No, Bernard, no! De War. Hush! Ul. Bernard . . . is that Bernard? An. Yes, Ulric, 't is your brother. Bern. Ay, my boy, 'T is useless to deny it now. Ul. My brother! . . . Leonard my brother! . . . Does my father know? Bern. You must not tell him—do not say a word. An. I will . . . Oh, I will tell him—carefully, And gently. Let me tell him. De War. Silence! For shame! This must not be borne longer. Go, sir, go! Enter Lettice hastily. Let. Thank heaven I have found you! Mistress Olive Is frightened past her wits: Sir Hugh is ill In the library—a faintness like to death— She fancies he will die, though he has come Gaspingly back to life . . . asks for you all, You too, my lord . . . pray you come instantly!— He has tasked his strength too far—but it may pass. An. Bernard, you dare not go now! Bern. Father! father! Ul. Oh, come with me—I 'll take you to the steps Of the oriel window—you shall wait there—come! [Exeunt omnes. Scene VIII. —The Library. Sir Hugh leaning back in an Arm-chair. De Warenne, Annabella, Ulric, and Olive around him. Sir Hugh. It is past now—I shall not die this time. Yet 't will come suddenly whene'er it comes . . . The hand of death still lingers on the latch Waiting to enter . . . nor unwillingly I listen for him . . . for I like to think That he will lead me to a world where haply This life's sad problems may be solved for me, And the great question of the Universe, “Why do I suffer so?” at last be answered. I should not speak so much about myself . . . But you will bear with me, for 't is the thought Of one . . . not here . . . whom I have tried in vain To pardon . . . God forgive me . . . that makes me long For light to understand how I may pardon And love him once again . . . An. [to De Warenne.] I must speak now. De War. And hurry him to death? He cannot bear it. Sir Hugh. I have heard you—do not fear, my child, to speak Whate'er is in your mind. An. Dear friend and father . . . Your son is innocent . . . indeed he is! We know it now . . . Sir Hugh. You think so! Can you prove it? De War. Stop there! For God's sake stop there—ere too late! Ul. Then now I will speak out: she says true, father! And I will tell you who the murderer was . . . When I get breath . . . De War. Fool! for your father's sake, No more of this! Sir Hugh. Let him speak, Adrian. Ul. Yes . . . I would have told before . . . it has so plagued me . . . Only I hardly understood the thing . . . the thing . . . That has so haunted me from a child . . . but now I know the murderer was—my Lord de Warenne. Look at him now. An. and Ol. [together.] Ulric, for shame! for shame! De War. Sir Hugh, you 'll let your boy utter such words Of your old friend? Ul. I saw you on that eve— For I remember it like yesterday— Hastening down to the cove, and . . . Sir Hugh. Turn, De Warenne, And look me in the face. Did you do this?—[a long pause.] Yes, you did murder him. De War. 'T was in fair fight. Sir Hugh. Where are your witnesses? De War. My word. Sir Hugh. A villain's.— I see all now, as dying men see truth. You coveted the girl your friend's son loved, And with your strength matured, and practised arm, In a mock combat slew the boy that loved her— You broke the heart of one who was to you All angel kindness through her lovely life— You let Cain's curse fall on the innocent— And, having groaned ten years beneath your secret,— As if ten years and their remorse could wash The original blackness of your deed away, You now would take possession of the prize. But the mask falls at a breath—go, Adrian, go! Not I, nor mine, will touch you—but your crime, And my boy's innocence will not be hid Beneath a bushel. Go you and repent, If penitence to you may be vouchsafed. Your country is no country now for you; Fly from the sight and hearing of good men, And thank just heaven she does not share your fate. An. [drawing off a ring.] Ulric. go give him this . . . and take back mine. De War. [approaching Annabella.] You, bitter angel, ere the gates of Hell Have quite closed on me, show me Paradise Just opening on another. Devils are kinder. [Exit. Sir Hugh. I see you look, each upon each, my children, With a pale horror that 's too great for words . . . You have passed a terrible moment. An. Oh, of you, Of you, it is, we think before all things. [Kneeling before him] Alas! you have lost your friend, but you have found Your dear, dear son again. Sir Hugh. Not in this life. He will not stand before my dying bed Whom I have wronged, as surely never yet Father wronged son. An. He shall, he shall! You have borne Such misery, can you now bear joy? We know Where Bernard is . . . he has reached English ground . . . Sir Hugh. Send for him, and at once. An. He is here. [Ulric rushes out by the window, calling, “Bernard! Bernard!” and re-enters with him. Bern. [throwing himself at the feet of Sir Hugh.] Oh, father! father! Sir Hugh. My son! [a pause.] My son! forgive me . . . had I years To live, as I have only days . . . yet never Should I forgive myself. My martyred boy! Bern. Oh father! Sir Hugh. Vainly do I ask myself, Vainly . . . what reparation I can make. Time is not left me, were it possible . . . But these dear three will make it. Bern. 'T is enough I see you once again . . . all is wiped out. Sir Hugh. I am almost spent . . . just now I scarce have breath To say but this . . . you must not think it strange If I should bid you leave that unmasked felon . . . That hapless wretch . . . who has confessed his crime, . . . Your father's friend . . . to God's great vengeance only. It cannot fail him. Bern. Will you think your son Unworthy of his name, if I confess, At such a moment, not a thought of vengeance Touches my soul? I only think of you. Sir Hugh. I am content, dear boy. Changed as you are, You see I use the old name. Come then, help me To my own chamber . . . for my strength is spent. I shall be better soon . . . and I shall rest With happier thoughts than heretofore. Then leave me, And come back to these children. Bern. But how leave you, Father, to-night? For you are ill indeed. Sir Hugh. Not so—I am better. Give me your arm now. [Exeunt Sir Hugh and Bernard. Ol. Oh, Annabella! An. You must love him, dear. Ol. Yes, I will love him . . . but . . . Ul. Neither of you Know yet half what he is. Ol. 'Tis all so dreadful! Re-enter Bernard. Bern. He would not let me stay. An. We should not weep so . . . It seems but a sad welcome . . . but it is not. Bern. I should blush . . . only you will bear with me . . . You see I cannot help it—let us sit, Beseech you, on these steps, that I may breathe The old-world perfume of this honeysuckle, Which seems to blot out ten years' exile. [Olive gathers, and gives him a spray. Olive, Are you my sister, or some delicate work Of rainbow-tinted wax, we dare not touch, Too beauteous to be real, like all I see Round me on English ground? Ol. Am I much changed? Bern. No, you are just the same . . . the very tyrant Who ruled me with a little rod of iron— As you should rule me still. Ol. [sobbing] Oh I can't help it. Everything seems . . . everything seems so strange. An. Bernard, ah see, this is too much for her! The hour is late—you'll go to rest my child, I will come soon. Ol. Bernard . . . good night. You will not Think I don't love you? Bern. Good night . . . my own sister. [Exit Olive. When all last night I wandered round the house, Little I dreamed of this. When last I left it, It flared up in my fancy far behind me, As men escaping o'er a dark waste sea Look back to see the ship that was their home Transfigured to a pyramid of fire. I have seen that, too. An. Ah me, how shall we ever Bear to hear half your tale? And how shall we Bear not to hear it? Bern. Do not ask it now— Not now—this moment is too blest, too perfect, To stain with all the ten years' lurid past, All the wild wanderings, strange companionships, Enmities, friendships—and, by land and sea, Warfare and danger—horrors blent with beauty— Things more than I can tell. An. No—talk not of them. Bern. Yet I could tell you too of unimaginably Beautiful things, that blessed me in my sorrow; Oh God, I have suffered much, but never yet Has my heart failed to beat in adoration Of the great spirit of Beauty in all forms. What things I would, if I could, paint for you! What prodigies of nature's tropic fancy, What glooms of forest, pillared Eblis-halls, Alight with fire-flies, all one dance of stars,— Where, glaring through a serpent-twist of flowers, Broods like a damned deserted tyrant, some Forgotten idol of an unknown race— Ul. Oh Bernard! An. You take us out of this earth. Bern. Or desolate paradises, where it seemed Neither man walked, nor God—lovelily weird, With blue lake and blue sky—savannah-seas, One blushing outbreak of extravagant bloom, Incredible colours that surprised a shout Of wonder in the utter solitude,— Foolishly happy in their useless beauty; Mountains all smothered in soft plumes of green, Splendours of foliage woven close as moss, And such a glory inexpressible As I could fancy in the unvisited stars. Folly! Why talk of this? Not Eden's self Were worth to me one dewy hedgerow bank Of England, blue-starred with the speedwell's eyes— Not all those strange bird-miracles, whose shocks Of colour burst on us like fire from heaven, Could charm me as, on some wet reed-fringed mead, One flying flash of the small kingfisher, The little brilliant phantom of the brook. And I have seen this!—seen this once again! An. Say, you are happy now? Bern. There is no name For what I feel this moment. Past and future, I will forget them both just now. Your faces Are all my world—my treasure: they are mine, Though I should never see them any more. I have not come in vain. An. With such a tone Of hopelessness you speak e'en now, it wrings me To think of all you have borne. Bern. Oh, listen! listen! Those fairy bells up-ringing through the dark! The first lark waking. An. It will soon be dawn; The garden is grey with twilight. Oh, my Olive! I promised her to come. And Bernard, yes, You 'll sleep once more beneath your father's roof, And in your own old room! Ul. I 'll go seek Humphrey— He has the key, I know. Bern. And the laburnum Still flings its showers across the casement? Ul. Oh, As thick as ever. Humphrey's stirring still, I 'll wager, after such late merrymaking; He will be at his reckonings in the spence, Or busying about something just as useless: I must just whisper to him all about it: You know . . . they will all know to-morrow. Wait A moment for me. Bern. Annabel, my sister . . . It was worth while to come back for this moment To feel again what joy was! An. You must be An angel, dear, so to forgive and love us. I should be, oh, so humble in your sight . . . Only, somehow, I never did believe it . . . Never . . . although I thought I did. 'T was like Some bitter dogma of a narrow creed, Which heart and reason writhe from, yet from habit Avowed in words . . . and then your father . . . just Because he doated on you two so proudly . . . Poor Leolyn! . . . But Bernard, our whole lives Henceforth shall be yours only! Bern. Annabel, Your words so bless me, whilst they wring me—once To have seen my father's face again on earth Is such a treasure laid up for my life; Only, let no one name that man to me, Lest I should break out in some frantic word Or act . . . An. Oh, calm yourself! How you are trembling Forget all that. Bern. With your dear hand in mine I can be calm. And I will try to hope I, too, have brought some blessing. May I not Trust, should I e'en now leave my father— An. Leave him? Bern. E'en so, would not his life be happier? An. Bernard, You are hiding something from me! Why will you Hint at I know not what, as if your home E'en now were not your home? Bern. And if—and if— An. Then now I guess it, now I see it all— You have a love, a wife! Bern. You make me laugh. An. But you deny it not! Bern. A love! A wife! If you but knew the home, the love I come from! An. What—who is it? Bern. What, who is it? you ask? You who have been my love, my agony, Through my long banishment, you ask me that? An. Bernard! Bern. Since that day—more than ten years past— When I came home to find you from a child Transfigured to a spirit-mystery Moving amongst the old familiar things, Radiant and shy as from another world, My life too was transfigured—but the change, Was still, like music, or the sense of Spring, A beautiful pain—and I had scarcely dared Own to myself that mingling with my dream Was a wild fantasy of hopeless hope, Till that sharp agony when first I thought You loved poor Leolyn. An. Ah no! ah never! I let him yield me homage, being then— Though it seemed natural to be crowned a queen— So young I knew not that such things could be Serious realities. Alas for that! For oft in the dead night the dear sad ghost Reproaches me. Bern. But then, he, in his pride, Seemed like the eagle gazing on the sun— Those secret serpent eyes that watched us both I guessed not . . . but I dare not speak of that . . . So with a silent gnawing of the heart, I held aloof . . . and then . . . then . . . you know, how I fled and followed long the roving star Of many a reckless flag by land and sea. Oh, how in loneliest wildernesses, lost From sight or sound of man, or hope of life, Your voice has thrilled through the still, awful air, In silver syllables like little bells, Articulately as now; how, on the bed Of fever, raving in the deadly fires, I have seen you pass before me, o'er and o'er, In some mysterious wedding pageantry, To some unknown church-altar; or you seemed Weeping to sit upon some wild sea-shore Weeping, but not for me—and everywhither, Cruelly sweet, unutterably dear, You followed me like an angel of despair! I have seen faces beautiful to terror, Creatures of flame whose startling witcheries Seemed revelations from some magic star— Yet what were these, but hollow dreams of things Beside my one reality of love?— All this means nothing. All I ask of Heaven, Would be, that only I might die for you, To watch you ever as your guardian spirit, And make you happy though you knew me not— But e'en that will not be. An. Oh, . . . I do think, My heart has found its other half at last, And now without it, it would bleed to death! Bern. Wretch that I am! I never meant to tell you . . . I meant to have forgone such utter rapture . . . E'en had I dreamed it was for me to win . . . Oh, would, for your sake, love, you meant it not! No—no—not that—you must not think me mad . . . To-morrow all my heart I 'll tell you. An. Bernard! I cannot guess your meaning . . . You have caught The trick of hopelessness . . . but I persist In joy ineffable to have you back . . . Whether you love me, or you love me not . . . And my heart's vow that you shall yet be happy. Re-enter Ulric. Ul. All 's ready for you—Humphrey is in amaze— I have told him you will speak to him to-morrow— But for that matter, 't is to-morrow now. Bern. So shall we lose less of this precious time Whose minutes should be hoarded up like gold. [Exeunt omnes. Scene IX. —A Chamber upstairs. Olive sleeping; Annabella standing at a Window. An. I 'll think of that no more: I 'll cast away The horror, the bewilderment, the shame— Shame for another, worse than for ourselves— And triumph in his happiness and mine! Oh, how the inventive genius of my heart Shall wake, each day, eager to exercise Its happy art, in multiplied devices Of consolation and of tenderness, And find the day too short for half of them! Such bliss is only possible on earth, Nor heaven itself were such a heaven as that! So let the lightning of that luminous smile, Which for one moment over his sad face Flashed such a glory, then went out again In tremblings of emotion, be my star Of happy omen till we meet once more.— Oh, my poor child! She is sobbing in her sleep! That is not sleep, but pain. [Goes up to Olive. Ol. [waking]. Why, Ella! is it So very late? Have I slept so long? An. Nay, dear, 'T is early yet; one by one all the birds Have waked, but they are scarcely yet in chorus. But you were sleeping in such troubled fashion, I am glad you have wakened from it. Ol. Oh, I know What I was dreaming of. But am I, tell me, Wicked . . . would Bernard think me wicked, Ella, For pitying—him? I cannot, cannot help it! So changed, so shamed, so fallen as he went . . . And we all turning from him! Ella—Ella! I shall remember it to my dying day. But how you shudder! Do you hate me! An. Ah! To pity wretchedness for you is easier Than to realise crime. And pity is The keenest pain I think the heart can feel. . . . For martyrs and for heroes it may swell With what transcends all pity . . . but— Ol. To see That which we honoured brought to infamy! An. Oh, think of Bernard, rather! Ol. But, perhaps, There may be, if we only knew . . . let me Say only this, and then I 'll say no more. . . . There may be—oh, I do not mean excuse— But something not so fiendlike as it seems. If I can 't think so, I must go half-mad! I did so honour, so believe in him! An. Alas! so did we all.—Now sleep again. There 's yet an hour or two of rest for you. I 'll watch beside you, for I could not sleep.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. Scene I. —The Courtyard. Enter Lettice and Cuthbert. Let. [weeping]. Oh, my poor master! Just when we all thought He was to be so happy! That poor fellow— Come home in time only to see him once, And then to find him dead in his bed my morn! Oh, my poor master! Cuth. Why, I might as well Be a log of wood, I think, for I can't feel it— I can't feel anything. I only think How wickedly I treated that poor lad. 'T were almost better I should hang myself, Than live to fret about it all day long. And, for my master, I 'll be bound he knew What worthless trash life is, and was content To part in peace when he had seen his boy. How I could make a devil of myself, To torture him like that, I can 't guess now. Did not I always know how kind he was, And tender to dumb things? and then to fancy That he could— Let. Oh, you were no worse than others! Old man, forget it. But, now, tell me this— Who did it, then? Cuth. Don't think that I shall tell you. I 'll tell you nothing that is not my business— I leave that to my betters. If there be, though, A devil on the earth! It would fare ill With that man if I met him,—I might chance To brain him with my spade—ay, just as like As I might kill a worm. Let. Well, we have got A master we may all be proud of—Humphrey Already speaks as if he were a god.— Oh, poor Sir Hugh!—There's Humphrey calling me. [Exit Scene II. —The Terrace in front of the House. Enter Bernard and Olive. Ol. I was ashamed to weep so, yesterday . . . And now I seem almost too tired for tears, And feel as if I could not weep again! Oh me, he looked so peaceful, I am sure He thought of you and blessed you ere he died. Bern. My father, my dear father! Ol. You will take His place, and comfort us. Bern. How thankfully would I Were I permitted happiness so great . . . Were it but possible . . . How sad and sweet The holy summer perfume of the morn! How should a world so beautiful as this Be wasted on such devils as men are! Ol. Bernard! Bern. The innocent wild creatures—birds, And beasts, and happy insect tribes . . . they are not Unworthy to possess it . . . and some few Of humankind are too pure to be left Amongst the rest . . . Oh that the good might die, And see no more of all the misery here! Ol. We seem all in a dream . . . and Lylford too Is like some new strange place . . . Enter Annabella. Bern. [meeting her.] Dear, he died happy. An. Half of my sweet dream gone—the happy things I meant to say to him, unsaid for ever! The friend of all my life—my dear, dear father! Bern. Perhaps we are wrong to mourn him . . . had he lived, Some other sorrow might have come . . . An. Ah, Bernard . . . He had borne the worst. Bern. It was not in his nature To feel keen happiness . . . not even ere His outward troubles came. An. I 'll strive to think 'T is well for him . . . Oh, what should we now be, Henceforward, without you? Bern. How hard you make My duty! An. Do not turn away from me— But let me comfort you. Bern. Come apart with me, I have that to say which needs my heart's whole strength— Would in some magic word I could sum up All that the past has left unsaid, and all The future ought to say. But easier were it Here at your feet to die than put in words The passion of my soul past and to come! Alas, I cannot even in my own Concentrate all the pain. An. And do you grudge That I should share it with you? Bern. Dear, forgive me! An. What can I have to forgive? Bern. 'T is now begins The insupportable anguish of my task. An. Bernard! Bern. Oh look not so . . . for it is more Than I can bear. An. But you bewilder me! Bern. What would you say . . . were I to tell you this, That I am bound, irrevocably bound, To leave . . . you, love, and home and happiness . . . And . . . there, 't is said! An. Leave me!—At such a moment? At this first anguish of our sudden loss? Now, whilst our dear one, in that darkened room, Waits burial?—For a day you mean? How long? Bern. I dare not tell you . . . no, nor think. To live Away from you one moment is heartache— But a whole life! An. Bernard!—Oh me, my folly! I did believe you meant it—for one instant! But do not frighten me again. Bern. Alas! It is the simple truth . . . and I must leave you. You must believe it, dear. An. But to go whither? I cannot understand. Bern. But I am sworn Not to reveal where and to whom I go. An. Why, Bernard, you are laughing at me now! This is a tale, a dream! Bern. Ah no, no dream! I am no more my own . . . I have won leave, Wrenched as by miracle, from . . . but that's no matter . . . To snatch one glimpse of all I love on earth, And then . . . for ever leave it. An. Why, why will you Harp on these dreadful fancies? Bern. I have had That glimpse . . . I bless my God for it . . . and but For you, dear, and your wounded love . . . alas! Why did I tell you mine? . . . I should go hence, Resigned to misery. An. Great God! What mean you? What is this cruel, horrible mystery? Is it . . . but no! I will not say that now— I know you love no other— Bern. Love another! My Annabel! my only love! my wife! An. Then, O beloved, cease to say such things! Or tell me what they mean? What shall I do? You speak and look as if all this were earnest, Yet will not tell me why you torture me, Lest I should show you that some fantasy Born of past sufferings has unhinged your soul, And led you to believe some madness—made you So utterly enamoured of despair, Your conscience so to misery bigoted, You see no sacredness but in pain . . . just think A moment calmly . . . I am calm, you see, Because I know you have made some strange mistake, I could explain would you but tell me—speak! And do not turn away so hopelessly; For I can bear no more. Bern. And do you think I would say this if there were left to me One possible loophole of escape? An. And I Standing here in the bright daylight hear you Talk of such horror as a possible thing? Are we both mad? The joy of yesterday All a delusion? Bern. It were better far That we should die; we have known the best and worst, Who love—such love as never yet was loved . . . For you do love— An. To the last beat of my heart! Bern. But I must live. For to die now, and so Escape my fate, in me were baseness past All baseness. God, duty, and honour call me Inexorably from you . . . Annabel, Believe me by the anguish that I should, But cannot, stifle—by all sacred things, Believe and pity— An. Pity! Is there a name For what I feel? To live on here in meanless Safety and luxury . . . and you . . . and you . . . Banished—I know not why, I know not where— There is a curse then! Oh, I thought we had known The worst, and that, our two sad mornings over, Some good was yet in store for you and me . . . But if, indeed, I understand you now, If you are bound to some dark nameless woe, Something so dire and strange you dare not tell me, Whilst I go pining, wondering, to my grave . . . Doubling my grief by night's inventive dreams— If you must so destroy yourself and me . . . Is there a God? And wherefore were we born? Bern. How can I say that I may not . . . come back? An. You do not cheat me—you will come no more. Oh Bernard! Bernard! Bernard! [Olive runs up to her. Ol. What is it? What is it, Bernard? Ella, Ella, tell me! Is it something new? Bern. Come in,—I have much to say,— I would spare you this if I could . . . Let us go in . . . And help me to be calm. An. Calm, oh my God! [Exeunt omnes, Scene III. —The Hall. Humphrey and the rest of the Household assembled. Let. Sure such a day as this was never known here Since Lyles have owned this place! Another And poor Sir Hugh Above there lies asleep, and cannot speak A word to help his children. Anoth. And they all weeping Around him, the poor broken-hearted things, And praying him to stay! Anoth. I think the curse Of old Sir Ralph has come on him in madness. Humph. Hush! hush! They are coming, I'll do what I can. Trust me, I'll speak to him. We must hope the best. Enter Bernard, Annabella, Olive, and Ulric. Humph. [coming forward.] Sir, I beseech you pardon us our boldness. But we have waited here in hope to move you By our united prayers not to forsake Your heritage, your home, and faithful household, Whose chief desire is henceforth so to serve you As they have served your father. Oh, sir, see How all you love are weeping round you, whom We truly would all die for, as I think, But 't were more natural you should live for them. Oh, sir, sir, be persuaded! Bern. My good Humphrey, I was not born under a happy star, And such a life as that is not for me. There 's none of you here but would do as I With such a call as mine, for I must go . . . And now no more . . . I would fulfil my part As may become a man . . . hinder me not, For it is hard— Ol. [throwing her arms round his neck.] No, Bernard, Bernard, stay! Our hearts are breaking . . . Who can be to you What we are? Bern. None. Ul. I shall so hate this house, These lands, all you would have me take in your place! Bernard, I'll own it now—just for a moment, I did, I did grieve they were not to be mine, Wretch that I was! And now I hate it all! Only stay with us! An. Bernard, at your feet, With agony that language cannot utter, For the last time your own, own love implores you Not to forsake us! Bern. Annabella, spare me! Ul. O look, the tears are streaming down his cheeks, And yet he will not yield! Bern. Why will you make me Seem to myself a monster, while I struggle For strength to seek . . . no garden of delight . . . No bed of roses . . . only my own despair? What should I seek else? In the universe, What lure but misery could bribe me from you? I have questioned, in my strange and stormy life, Well nigh of everything in heaven or earth, Have challenged all conventions' dogmas—doubted All creeds of man's devisings,—but find here A law of my heart, an instinct of my conscience, Transcending every doubt, all questioning. I go, dear love, because I have a debt Which to disown were to deny all duty, Because I have a trust which, to betray, Were to be Judas, . . . what can I say more? I go . . . because to stay would be to suffer The deep damnation of my own self-scorn . . . And make the heaven of your love my hell! Well I will tell you—I must tell no more, Nor must you image things beyond the truth. I have a friend to whom I owe whatever Man can owe man . . . who waits for my return In misery, and will miserably die If I return not . . . die for me, whose life He has saved ere now, taking his own in his hand . . . Who still would die for me without complaint . . . Yet I must save him . . . ask me now no further, My heart has almost burst to say so much, And cannot utter more. An. Bernard, I ask This only . . . is there any help or hope? Does all the world hold out a single chance Of your return? Bern. I dare not say I see Or hope, or help. I see in all the world Only a doom unalterable, and love Unalterable as doom. An [after a pause.] Yes, I have played A barbarous part . . . so torturing the tortured, So breaking the true heart that will not bend! Forgive me . . . and go from me with the blessing Of love intense . . . eternal . . . and complete! Tell me but how to lay up comfort for you, That something may be left me in my life. Bern. Oh, all I ask is but one sacred word Of farewell, ere I go . . . One moment leave me, Dear ones I pray . . . wait for me in the porch, The little moment left.—I will not mock you, By bidding you forget me, for if years Of chance and change could not deaden my heart, Life's mournful peace will scarcely stifle yours; Nor dare I now to bid you pardon me For rashly telling you my love— An. To know it Is my one treasure— Bern. Yet it pierces me As with a fiery fang to leave behind Such anguish— An. Ah no, that 's my treasure too. To suffer so in my love's suffering, To be so wholly one with him, that neither Distance nor silence, time nor death, can cleave The single passion of two hearts in twain, Nor dim by but a shade my utter trust— For though in blind bewilderment you leave me, One light shines in the darkness like a star, And that 's your stainless truth—oh, my own love, Repent not that for this you trusted me With your heart's secret, since by that you crowned My worthless life with glory, and have blessed, With the strange blessing of a pain sublime, A lonely heart for ever. Bern. I will think Of all this, o'er and o'er again . . . and try To rise so near your height of angelhood, As to subdue weak self-reproach for what I dare no longer call a wrong— An. Whenever Your martyrdom . . . whate'er it be . . . shall seem To pass endurance . . . Oh think I am there To bless and pity! So, for evermore, My spirit shall be with you— Bern. If I speak not The unspeakable, you will understand . . . . and now . . . The fatal moment . . . we must part. An. And nothing Yet said! Bern. Nothing—yet everything— An. How . . . by what token shall our two souls meet? Bern. Each moment's consciousness. An. At every sunset Listen, my Bernard . . . listen for the organ. I will play all my soul into the strains You love, and send them through the space to you . . . Daily till death . . . and when I die, be sure I 'll come to you . . . as you . . . you 'll promise me, If you die first, your spirit shall come hither. Bern. I promise. An. Then we two shall meet again. Bern. Farewell!—'T is over. [Rushes out. An. He is gone for ever!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT IV. Scene I. —The Hall. Enter Ulric and Olive. Ol. We seem forsaken of all things on earth. If only she would wake to life again, And be as one of us! Oh! I do hope, Now the unearthly horror of the winds Through those three miserable, endless days, Is over, and the sea moans itself still, She will no more sit gazing from the window, And seeing nothing as she gazes. If I speak to her, she rests her large eyes on me Wildly and answers not, and if I kiss her She does not heed . . . yet it was worse than all When, like a frenzied angel, she would roll Those awful organ peals into the rain And thunder— Enter Annabella. An. Did you see him? He is here! He is come back! Ul. Come back! Where, where? How know you? An. In the yew-walk . . . I saw him . . . he is there! [Exit. Ol. It is her fancy, Ulric! He would never Have hidden from us!—how could he be there? Ul. We 'll follow her and see. Ol. Ah me; she looked So wildly happy—her two eyes like stars! Ul. Olive, they say that light has shone each night, Since Bernard left us. Ol. I should have laughed at that Once . . . but we are so miserable now, It gives me a heart-chill. Ul. Oh, 't is all folly. Come to the yew-walk. Ol. Let me first go to her. [Exeunt. Scene II. —The-Yew-Walk. Enter Annabella. Bernard approaches from the other end. An. Is Heaven so merciful? Bernard! Bern. I come My promise to redeem. An. Oh, love, what promise? Why do you shrink from me? Why do you look So strangely . . . so unlike yourself? Oh, Bernard! You will stay now—you will stay now? Bern. I must not. From the deep sea I have come back to you, Because I love you, but I cannot stay. All 's over now, and all at peace with me. An. What means that? . . . all is over? Bern. Annabel, He who now speaks to you on earth is nothing. You see a phantom, but I love you still. And he I died for will be here to-day— Tell him what now I am. Farewell. [Vanishes. An. Why—Bernard! Where are you? Enter Olive. Ol. Ella! How you look! What was it? Who has been here? Was it you Cried out just now? An. Where is he? Ol. Who, dear Ella? We have seen no one. An. Now I know he is dead. I have seen him, talked with him—and he is dead. Ol. Oh, if you love me, do not talk so! An. Olive, My child, I love you, and will live for you. But he is gone for ever. Enter Ulric hastily. Ul. There is come A foreign stranger here . . . he looks so wild, And gaunt and awful! First I thought him crazed, Until I saw that misery and hardship Had made him look so strange—he asked my name, In his slow, stiff-toned English—gazed all round him— Spoke of you, Annabella.—Here he is! Enter Doria. An. [advancing to meet him.] I knew that you would come. Dor. What, does your heart Own nature's ties already? Or how else Do you know who I am? For, who you are, I knew not till I reached these shores to-day. An. I know not who you are—I only know He told me you would come. Dor. He? Where is he? An. In the deep sea. Dor. [looking round.] What does this mean? An. He has perished To keep his faith to you. I know no more— But this I know—he will not come again. Dor. You cannot know it. Let me look at you, For I do see a horror in your eyes. My friend has been here—tell me where he is. An. Twice has he been here—once, a living man, To be, methought, the joy of all our hearts, But left his happy home to die for you. And once again he has come— Dor. Quickly! Speak on. An. It was his ghost. Dor. By this strange shivering, Methinks some awful thing is near me. What Was it you saw? An. I met him walking here, Pale from the battling storm, and calm and sad As from the eternal parting with this life. I saw him plainly as I see you now, And with his own voice, plain as I hear yours, He told his death and told me you would come; Then even as I looked, where he had stood Was empty space. He is dead as certainly As if he lay, where he will never lie, In yonder churchyard. Ol. Ulric . . . the ghost light! Ul. Do not speak of that, Olive . . . 't is too terrible. Dor. Where am I? . . . I can only understand A voice from the other world has come to tell me I am too late! [lifting up his hands] And I have lived for this! My friend! my friend! The noblest, and the best That ever lived in this black world of fiends, Has died for me! Why should I live at all? Not you, not even you, can comfort me— Though you are my own sister. An. If you loved him, You are my brother. Dor. If I loved him!—Oh, If all that 's strong and tender in a man— The strength that toils and bears, nor wavers through Racking solicitudes and ghastly perils, Through chains and torments, and a weight of woe— Tenderness such as brushes the least fly From the pale sleep of pain, and yields the drop Of priceless water to another's thirst, When heaven seems in the cup—Almighty God! If I forget to love him for these things, For these, and more an hundredfold than these— Devils remember me, and devils only! An. Speak on . . . you have tones like his. Dor. I speak the tongue He taught me . . . painfully, as a precious thing . . . But cannot repeat him, nor copy the least Touch that was part of him and of none other— E'en to the grave and unexpected jest, Born of quaint fancy and the sensitive heart . . . And have I come a stranger to his land, Only to meet a message from the dead, Mysterious as his life was and his death? Yet bless the merciful storm that saved him from The living death he went to! Faithful heart! When the time comes I will tell what you were. And the strange story of our misery . . . How shall I tell it? Can such things be told? An. Tell all. Dor. I see you—oh, I see you now, Rushing out to me, radiant as of old, From one of nature's secret haunts of beauty, With eyes that seem to have discovered heaven— And if a heaven there be, you have found it now! And, as I 've seen you, too, so oft, asleep And dreaming, deep in the bright dews of dawn, Your arms thrown back above your head, your brows Knit nobly in a frown, not stern, but sad— E'en thus I know you look, where now you lie! An. Ah me! a magic mirror are your words. Dor. You call me back to earth—to his own England. Why have I come here? How I have escaped From demons and from uttermost despair— Through toils that might have won a world—held firm On danger's dizzy brink, by the vain hope To reach and save him—is not now worth telling: So let that pass. I look on you, and see A monument of broken-hearted love As beautiful as the sad cypress-tree— You, whom I last saw in your rainbow days Of infant smiles and tears—and yet I see, And know again my sister. Proofs I have, As sun-clear as that rosary you wear, Which links, by an invisible chain of prayers, Us two to generations of the past; But I will ask you first whether your heart Denies me, or has memories that own Its birth-place where the green and golden groves, Which are to these, as sunshine is to shade, Paint a gay border on the tideless blue? If it believes not you are Annabella, My sister, and I Doria—and we two Named with one name, still great in Genoa? Ask of your heart, then speak. An. It is too broken To doubt, and nothing now seems wonderful. That he has loved you is worth more to me Than the attestings of an emperor's seal Stamped on historic parchment. Be my brother, And be the brother of this pair as well. They are all that 's left me. Dor. They are mine. An. Oh, brother, Your words seem distant, and the world swims round me. [Faints. Dor. Follow me, children, whilst I bear her in. There will be time hereafter for us four To weave our two sad stories into one.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT V. Scene—The Hall of De Warenne's Castle. De Warenne alone. De War. This place, that has so echoed to my groans, Why do I linger in it? Why delay To fly from it for ever? Can one turn Of fate, 'twixt sunset and sunrise, or wildest Longings, bring her and me together ever, Ever again? Or could I face her now? Oh, she can see no deeper than the rest, And knows not that, with such a love as mine, Whate'er the past has been, or men may say, She would be happy, spite of all. She knows not. In her eyes I am but— Enter Aylmer and Arden, friends of De Warenne. Ayl. You will excuse us For breaking in thus on your worshipful presence— De War. By heavens! Your business with me? Ayl. Nay, de Warenne, Your pardon for so rudely disregarding Your sentence of exclusion, and assuming Old friendship's privilege. De War. Pray pardon me; I have been so tasked . . . so fretted . . . that I scarce Know what I say. You are very welcome. Ard. Now, Must I confess, then, we are hither spurred By a keen curiosity— De War. I know, To curiosity there 's nothing sacred; But you may ask more than I'll choose to answer. Ayl. Your tone 's a strange one. This nigh passes jest. My lord, we 'll take our leave. De War. Again your pardon. Pray stay—and ask your pleasure. Ard. Well—this rumour From Lylford—is it true? De War. What may you mean? What rumour? Ayl. You ask? Why that the lost son Has suddenly come home—no murderer, It seems, but innocent as you or I. Come, is this true? De War. How should I know? Ard. But you Are fresh from Lylford! You must have heard something— You of all men. De War. 'T is days since I was there,— And I know nothing. Ayl. You choose not to tell us— But something there has been. And it does touch us— Since we would know if we may give our hands To this returned young outcast. Enter Doria. De War. 'T is too much! What means this new intrusion? Is my house No longer mine? Who are you? Dor. You, it seems, Are Earl de Warenne? De War. Ay, sir, and I bid you Recross this threshold straightway, ere I summon My servants to chastise you. Dor. Wait. I am Doria of Genoa—and, in the name Of Bernard Lyle, who for your crime has suffered Banishment, shame, captivity, and griefs Uncounted, and now sleeps in the fathomless sea,— In his name I am come to challenge you, As murderer, liar, and hypocrite, to draw Your sword and fight. [A pause. Ayl. and Ard. If you 're a man, De Warenne, Tell him he lies! Dor. The odds that you delight in, Shall still be yours. You murdered your friend's son, Without a witness—your own comrades here, And countrymen, shall be your witnesses This day—that 's three to one. Ten years ago You fought with an untried, unwary boy; In me you meet a man whose strength is broken By toil, starvation, torture, and despair, Such as were his who lost his home through you. So draw your sword, and fear not. De War. You are mad— Chains and the lash best fit your malady. Begone, I say. Dor. Sirs, I appeal to you. Is not guilt written in that face before you? Do honest men shrink from a madman's eyes? But I 'm not mad, though much that I have borne In rags, in fetters, 'neath a sun whose flames Were as the flames of Hell, might well, I think, Have turned my brain—but I had one true friend Who shared all with me, stood by me, and when At last his dear home welcomed him, forsook it, The martyr of his faith to me, and died— Whose life this villain blasted, and who now Sleeps where no tear can fall upon his grave— And that was Bernard Lyle. Do I not honour This traitor here beyond his due deserts, In bidding him draw sword and fight with me? Ayl. Speak in heaven's name, De Warenne! De War. I'll not fight, No, not with you—for something, God knows how, In that accursed face of yours, recalls The woman I love best—and for her sake I do not choose to kill you. Dor. Dare again To speak of her! [Strikes him in the face. De War. [starting up.] My sword! where is my sword? I have it not—you, Aylmer, give me yours! Wretch, I 'll not balk you now! Ard. What, are you mad? This shall not be! De War. [shaking him off.] It shall! [They fight, De Warenne falls. Tell her . . . tell Hugh . . . Ayl. What . . . will be never known . . . for, heaven! he's dead! Dor. My task is done. I have avenged my friend.</field>
   </doc>
</add>