<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Hill, Aaron, 1685-1750</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Hill, Aaron, 1685-1750</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">hill aaron 1685 1750</field>
      <field name="author_text">Hill, Aaron, 1685-1750</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">18th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1750's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V2.0269.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1750</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:459985</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Merope ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Merope ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="title_facet">merope</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">merope</field>
      <field name="title_text">Merope ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="year_display">1750</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1750</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1750</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459985&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459985&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Hill, Aaron, 1685-1750&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;hill aaron 1685 1750&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Merope ; A Tragedy&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;merope&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1750&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1750&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Hill, Aaron&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1685&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1750&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Merope&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for A. Millar [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1750&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872317-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv20269&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 18th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;18th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Merope&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 174 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Merope.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1749.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 15 Apr 1749.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">MEROPE: A TRAGEDY.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">EPILOGUE. Spoken by Mr. PRITCHARD. I'm glad with all my Heart, I've scap'd my Wedding— Glad! cry the Maids?—Heaven keep such Joy from spreading! Marriage, (poor Things!) don't move their Heart so coldly. 'Tis a dark Leap, they own—but, Love jumps boldly.— Fair fall th' Advent'rers! I'm no Husband-hater.— Only, be warn'd by Me, and wed no Traitor. Pain-hunting Murm'rer! born, to growl, and grumble! No King can please him,—and no Wife can humble! Sick to the Soul, be Heaven his kind Physician! Earth's ablest Drugs are lost, upon Ambition. All Warwick-lane falls short:—and, to my Knowledge, No Cure is hop'd for, in our Female College. Shun plotting Heads, dear Ladies!—All miscarries. When One, who hums and haws at Midnight, MARRIES. Better, plain, downright Dunce—No Dream, pursuing: One, that means bluntly—and knows, what he's doing! Not Him, whose factious Mind, outsoaring Pleasure, Is still most busy,—when his Wife's at Leisure. Better, a Sportsman, sound of Wind, and hearty.— Better, Sir Sot,—than Spouse dry drunk, with Party! A hunting Husband hallows—and you HEAR him.— A drunken Deary stag—gers—and you STEER him.— Each—conscious of his Wife, takes Care, to make her, One Way or other—an indulg'd Partaker. But, your sage, saturnine, ambitious Lover, Keeps no one Secret, Woman wou'd discover. Stranger at home, he strolls abroad, for Blessing: And holds whate'er he HAS not worth possessing. Freedom, and Mirth, and Health, and Joy,—despises! And scorns All Rest—he, so pro-found-ly WISE is! At length, thank Heaven! he DIES: kind Vapours strike him: And leaves behind,—ten thousand Madmen, like him.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Persons Represented. Poliphontes, General of Mycene. Mr. Havard. Merope, Widow of the late King. Mrs. Pritchard. Eumenes, her Son. Mr. Garrick. Euricles, a Lord, of Merope's Party. Mr. Usher. Narbas, Foster Father to Eumenes. Mr. Berry. Erox, Favourtie of Poliphontes. Mr. Bridges. Ismene, Daughter of Narbas. Mrs. Green. Chief Priest, and other Priests. Mr. Beard, &amp;c. Ladies, Officers, Guards, &amp;c.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. Scene I. An Apartment in the Palace. MEROPE, mournful, on a Couch. ISMENE, leaning melancholy, below; and Attendants. ISMENE. See! where the lone majestic Mourner weeps; Lost, even to Musick's Power!—try: strain each Note, In Melody's wide Compass.—Happily, Some Change, through sad, to lively, may have Force, To strike recov'ring Sense, and wake Regard. —First, in low Sympathy of Sorrow's Softness, Sooth her dejected Soul—then, start at once To Swells of Joy—and storm Attention's Ear. [Musick with Trumpets.] After the Musick Merope rises, and comes forward. MEROPE. Let me, when, next, thy too officious Love, Faithful Ismene, trys th' harmonious Charm, Let me, have Musick, solemn, all, and slow, Sad-suited to my Thoughts—Mix not for me, Who have no Power to taste, such spritely Notes, As they who are more Happy, find more Sweet? ISMENE. Why, when the Gods grow gentle, are You sad? You felt their Anger, sharply.—Now they smile, Embrace their proffer'd Bounty—All the Lords Of glad Mycene, in full Senate met, Take Measures to proclaim you reigning Queen: You, whom Distress but brightens!—to whose Charms, Made aweful by your Grief, Woes add new Majesty! MEROPE. What, no News yet, of Narbas? or my Son? ISMENE. May it be soon!—No Prince, of Birth like His, Where-e're conceal'd, can 'scape such Search, unknown. MEROPE. Will ye, at length, ye Powers, reward my Tears? Will ye, at last, restore Eumenes, to me? —If he yet lives—this only remnant Heir Of his wrong'd Mother's Miseries!—oh, save him. From his dear Breast, strike wide the Murd'rer's Dagger. Is he not Your's? a Branch, from Great Alcides? What, tho'—(forget it, and be hush'd, O Faith!) What, tho' to Traitors prosp'rous Swords, you gave His Father's fated Life—ah, yet! desert not This Image of his Form, that fills my Soul. ISMENE. Dear, tho' he doubtless was, and justly mourn'd, Shou'd you exclude all Sense of Bliss, beside? MEROPE. I am a Mother:—with a Mother's Fears. ISMENE. But, can a Mother's Fears efface the Stamp Of Hero's Soul, that marks a Race like yours? —Sweet, tho' his infant Smiles, they dwell, too fix'd, Too deep, on your touch'd Memory!—Long Years Are past, since first you lost him. MEROPE. Lost him?—never.— In twice seven dreadful Years, no Moment's Light Broke on my Eyes, but brought His Image with it. Why tell'st thou me of Time?—Days, Months, and Years, Have grown; but with 'em grew, my Pain, to lose him. —Weigh that last fatal Hint, thy Father sent me. Hope, soon, said he, to see the Prince Eumenes All, you wou'd wish:—fear All, from Poliphontes. ISMENE. Wisely, you fear him.—but 'twere wiser, still, So fearing, to prevent him.—Hear the States: Quit, at their Prayer, this Regent's Name—be crown'd: And rise, indeed the Queen they meant to make you. MEROPE. Is not the Crown my Son's? ISMENE. A Son, so lov'd— Shou'd he return, wou'd thank— MEROPE. Perish the Heart, That, meanly proud, and poorly fill'd for Self, Swells, from Another's Losses! ISMENE. Public Interest— MEROPE. Curse on all Int'rest, that includes not Honesty! —But, here, ev'n Int'rest brings no Plea to tempt me. What can a childless Mother hope, from Empire? What has Distress to do, with Pomp's vain Luster? —I see the very Light of Heav'n, with Pain. Never shall Splendor chear these blasted Eyes, That saw my bleeding Lord, my murder'd Children; Saw my Friends fall: Saw Men and Gods forsake me. —O, Guilt! O, Perfidy!—oh! Death's dire Day! Present, for ever, to my frighted Soul. ISMENE. Oft have I wept,—to hear that Day's sad Tale. MEROPE. I hear it now!—Even yet their Cries rise round me! Save, save, the King—save the poor gasping Princes: Save the distracted Queen!—I scream—I fly— On every Side I turn meet battling Crowds: Swords, glitt'ring Spears, loud Shouts, and mingled Groanings. Meet, last—a Sight—beyond all Sense of Horror! Meet—an expiring Husband's out-stretch'd Eye, Strain'd, with a death-mix'd Tenderness on mine— And struggling from his Blood, to reach and clasp me. ISMENE. Patience, O Madam, and forget these Horrors. MEROPE. —There two expiring infant Suff'rers fell, The Eldest, of our Loves!—duteous, in Death! Cross the King's Breast, they threw their little Bodies, And lent their Hand's weak Aid—to save their Father. —Only Eumenes—'scap'd th' Assassin's Fury. Some interposing God vouchsaf'd to veil him: And He, who screen'd him, then, may, once, restore him. —Narbas, thy wise, thy faithful Father, bore him Far from my Sight—to some dark safe Retreat: Some Desart,—barren of Distress, and Man! SCENE II. MEROPE. ISMENE. EURICLES. ISMENE. Madam!—Lord Euricles— MEROPE. Welcome—what Hope? EURICLES. Vain was our Search—From Peneus' Bank, it spread, O'er vast Olympus: far and wide, through Greece, Enquiry, lab'ring, lost its fruitless Prayer. Description cou'd not wake the least Idea. None knew, none ever heard of, Narbas' Name! MEROPE. Alas! he breaths no more—my Son is dead. ISMENE. So, Fear makes real every fansied Woe. —You've heard, that, on Report of this new Peace, My Father guides him, secret, to your Hopes. EURICLES. Just was his Caution! Narbas, wisely loyal, Veils his Return, and cautiously conveys him. Narbas knows All his Dangers—I, mean while, Watch, with a guardful Eye these Murd'rers Motions: And, with determin'd Hand, prepare to save him. MEROPE. On Faith so try'd as Thine, even Woe leans, easy. EURICLES. Doubt but my Power's Defect: My Will finds none. —But I have News more threat'ning. Th' assembled Senate vote, in warm Debate, A Consort in your Crown.— MEROPE. Presumptuous Care! You shou'd have call'd it Insult. EURICLES. Words were vain. Truth, unsustain'd by Power, but fights, to fall. The partial People roar for Poliphontes: And Right, and Law, and Pity, sink before him. MEROPE. Can Fortune, then, reduce the Great to Pity! Can Kings, in their own Realms, contract to Slaves? EURICLES. Something must be resolv'd, to check their Speed. MEROPE. Yes—I will face these Lords, of Kings, and Law: Comets of Empire! these portent'ous Stars, That sparkle by the Fire they steal from Majesty! I will go dart Truth's Light'ning in their Eyes, And thunder in their Ears the Rights of Thrones. I will revive lost Sense of Trust and Duty: I will assert their Sov'reign's near Return. (going.) EURICLES. Oh, Heav'n! be wary—That way, Ruin lies. Their Tyrant Leader starts, already fir'd, By that Alarm: and dreams, of what he dreads. MEROPE. What can he, more—so much already one? EURICLES. Jealous of Danger, Men make Haste in Guilt: Work, to be safe, and hold no Means too wicked. Mycene, but by Faction, freed from Faction, Claim'd like a Conquest, he computes His own. No Tye so sacred binds endanger'd Valour, Where hot Ambition spurs it—Every Rampart Gives Way, before him. Law, corrupted, guards him. Wealth dresses, Poverty attends, Pride leads: And Priesthood presses Gods who hate—to serve him. MEROPE. I see th' Abyss, before me—Let it be. If I plunge in, and crush this Poliphontes, 'Tis but, to fall for Vengeance. EURICLES. Soft!—he comes. Exeunt Euricles and Ismene. MEROPE. Wear for a Moment, Heart! the Veil thou hat'st. SCENE III. MEROPE. POLIPHONTES. POLIPHONTES. Ever in Tears, my Queen!—lend a long Truce To Sighs; and cast aside your needless Sorrow. Shake, from those injur'd Eyes, each Cloud that dims 'em: And to the Voice of Love, vouchsafe your Ear. —You frown— MEROPE. I do, indeed: and gaze, with Horror! POLIPHONTES. Gaze on.—I am no stranger to myself: Nor to a Woman's Passions.—I grew grey Beneath a Weight, of Winters spent in Arms. —I know, Time's Furrows are no Paths to Love. I know it, All—But, Wisdom knows it not. —Weigh not my Offer in Disdain's light Balance. You are the Daughter, Mother, Wife, of Kings: But the State wants a Master.—What avails Vain Title, till some Sword, like mine, supports it. MEROPE. Bold Subject, of a King who call'd me Wife! Dar'st thou defame the Mem'ry of thy Lord, With such audacious Hope?—Aspire to me! Me, to supplant my Child! my Heart's whole Care: Stain his dishonour'd Throne, with Guilt and Thee! Me, can'st thou dream so base, to wed Thy Lowness: And crown with Empire's Wreath a Soldier's Brow? POLIPHONTES. Soldier? immortal Gods!—Who more deserves To govern, States, than He who, best, can save? He who was, first, call'd King, e're That, was Soldier. Great, because brave; and scepter'd by his Sword. I am above Descent; and prize no Blood. Scarce is my own left mine; 'tis lost, for Glory: Spilt in my Country's Cause: in Yours, fair Scorner! Take Safety—'tis my Gift. Fill half my Throne; My Party calls All mine: Love shares it yours. MEROPE. Party? Thou fell Provoker, of Reproach! Party should tremble, where a Monarch rules? POLIPHONTES. There will be Parties; and there must be Kings: And he, who best can curb, was form'd to reign. —I, who reveng'd your Lord, by Right succeed him. MEROPE. Succeed him, Traitor?—Has he not a Son? Gods were his Great Forefathers,—thence, his Claim. POLIPHONTES. Far other Value, bears Mycene's Crown. Right, to rule Men, is now no longer held By dull Descent, like Land's low Heritage: 'Tis the pluck'd Fruit of Toil—'tis the paid Price Of Blood, lost nobly: And 'tis, thence, my Due. MEROPE. What hast thou done, thou Wretch! to dare such Hope? POLIPHONTES. Bethink you, of that Day, when these proud Walls Blush'd with the Blood you boast, from Traitor's Swords. Review your helpless Husband—see your Sons, Expiring, round you.—Wipe those gushing Eyes— And view me, what I was: Not, then, too low To share your ruffled Passions—Yes: 'Twas I, From your freed Palace chas'd th' o'erwhelming Foe: Sav'd your Herculean Sceptre, and its Queen. —I, I, repell'd,—the Woes you could but weep. See there, my Right, my Rank, my Claim to Love. MEROPE. Hear, hear him, Heaven! and give me back my Son. POLIPHONTES. Yes: Let him come, this Son!—He shall be taught Lessons of Glory: Taught my Arts to reign. —Joy to the Blood of Hercules!—I, too, Revere: Let others dread it. My Ambition Climbs, beyond Progeny—To spring from Gods, Is less, than mine—who, like a God, command. MEROPE. If thou wouldst emulate a God, be just: Man can be brave, too boldly.—Hercules Sav'd many a King—But, did he steal their Diadems? —Woud'st thou resemble Hercules?—Protect Unfriended Innocence. Assert thy Prince. Restore th' unhappy Wand'rer to my Arms; Cease to afflict; and give him, to my Fondness. —Thus, cou'd thy Influence move, so try'd, so courted, Who knows—for, Gratitude has Power, like Love— Who knows—how far I might forget my Glory— And—if Peace dwells with thee—Expect it not— I will not bid you hope—that I can stoop So low.—Bend, I am sure, I cannot. [Exit Merope. SCENE IV. POLIPHONTES, EROX. EROX. Ent'ring, I heard her too presumptuous Scorn, And wonder'd, at your Patience! Waits a King, For a weak Woman's Wish, to fix his Throne? Greatly and bravely have you clear'd your Way To the Hill's Foot: Yet, when it courts your climbing, Fall back, to sigh; and seek her Hand, to lead you! POLIPHONTES. Near, as thou think'st I stand, my warier Eye Marks, 'twixt the Throne and me, a Precipice, Where Faith or I fall headlong.—Does not Merope Know, her Eumenes near?—Shou'd he return, Th' inconstant People wou'd with Shouts receive him, And smooth his way to Empire, o'er my Bosom. —Thou know'st, from Proofs, most timely intercepted, This new Boy King returns, and hopes Mycene. EROX. Trust your high Fortune, and disdain to Doubt. Foresight and Fierceness are the brave Man's Gods, And his own Hand supports him. POLIPHONTES. My late Order? EROX. 'Twas, with a silent Firmness, well obey'd. —From Elis to Mycene, every Road Is watch'd, by sleepless Warders.—If they come, Narbas and He, their Gods must march before 'em: Or not Alcides' Blood could scape the shedding. Your Soldier's Zeal is warm. POLIPHONTES. But is it blind? EROX. It is.—None knows his Name, whose Life he waits. All they have yet been told is, a sad Tale, Of an old wily Traitor, leading with him, On murd'rous Purpose, an Assassin Youth, Urg'd by exacted Oaths, to seek your Death. POLIPHONTES. But, what this Rumour, of Misanthus kill'd, Before Alcides' Temple?—Is that true? EROX. Too sure, he fell.—I chose his trusty Arm, Join'd with his martial Brother's, as most fit, To guard that likeliest Station; where, should Narbas Dare, with his Exile, touch Mycene's Border, First, they wou'd rest, to beg That Godhead's Care, From whom their Race presumes its proud Descent. POLIPHONTES. 'Twas Forecast, worthy of a Zeal, like Thine. Nor cou'd thy Care have chosen an abler Hand, Or one more try'd in Blood, than That Misanthus. —'Twas He, thou know'st, that, faithful to my Cause, On that black Night, attending, near Cresphontes, Taught the King's Sword, amid the Dusk of Slaughter, To pierce its Master's Breast.—An Act, so daring, Deserv'd the Sword, tho' three rich Gems adorn'd it, He had it: And he wore it, for his Pains. EROX. Yet, at Alcides' Temple, drew it rashly, And lost it, with his Life. POLIPHONTES. How scap'd his Brother? EROX. Scar'd, out of Mem'ry's Use, All he cou'd tell me Was, that the God inspir'd some dreadful Form! Some more than mortal Monster;—And He fled, POLIPHONTES. Vile Safety!—left his Brother unreveng'd: And shun'd a Soldier's Death.—We must be watchful. Some in-felt Bodings bid me call this Stranger Eumenes: Or his Friend. EROX. That Fear was mine: Till, on Reflexion that he came, alone, It look'd unlikely.—Chance it, as it may, Whene're he this way comes, he comes, to die. POLIPHONTES. True.—Yet, I cou'd have wish'd to spare this Crime, But, one first chosen, the Rest grow necessary: So falls the Son.—The Mother must not follow. Her, I have Need of. Marriage mends my Reign. Her rightful Title consecrates Ambition: And Usurpation whitens into Law. —The People love her: I, possessing her, Hold her Friends too, in Dowry.—Erox!—thou, Whose Fate grows close to mine, assist my Scheme. Skill'd how to spread Craft's Nets, allure the People. Train 'em, by ev'ry Art: poize ev'ry Temper, Avarice will sell his Soul: Buy That, and mould it. Weakness will be deluded; there, grow eloquent. Is there a tott'ring Faith? Grapple it fast By Flatt'ry: And profusely deal my Favours. Threaten the Guilty. Entertain the Gay. Frighten the Rich. Find Wishes, for the Wanton: And Reverence, for the Godly,—Let none 'scape thee. Dive into Hearts: Sound every Nature's Biass— And bribe Men by their Passions.—But, These Arts, Already Thine, why waste I Time to teach thee! Vainly, the Sword successful scales a Throne; Since, Fortune changing, Strength's lost Hope is flown. But Art, call'd in, attracts reluctant Will: And, what were lost by Power, is gain'd by Skill. End of the First Act.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. SCENE I. The Palace. MEROPE. EURICLES. ISMENE. MEROPE. Is the World dumb, on my Eumene's Fate? ISMENE. Calamity, too soon, had found a Tongue. MEROPE. Has nothing, from the Borders, yet been heard? EURICLES. Nothing, that claims your notice. MEROPE. Who is He, This Prisoner, I am told, but now, brought guarded? EURICLES. A rash young Stranger, caught with guilty Hand, Red, from the recent Marks of some new Murder. MEROPE. A Murder! an unknown!—Whom, has he kill'd? How? and where, was it?—I am fill'd with Horror. ISMENE. Oh! Sense too lively, of maternal Love! All Things alarm your Tenderness. You hear Chance speak: and take her Voice, for That of Nature. MEROPE. What is his Name? whence came he?—Why unknown? EURICLES. He seems, and is, if Truth may trust Appearance, A Youth of that soft Stamp, which Fortune leaves To Nature's gentlest Care; some Nymph's Adonis Whose Eye, might sooner be suppos'd to kill Th' unpity'd Maid, than his gay Sword the Man. MEROPE. Whom (tell me) has he kill'd?—answer.—I'll see him. EURICLES. What strange Emotion, This.— MEROPE. No Matter.—bring him. If I discover Guilt, 'tis mine to punish: If wrong'd, I owe him Mercy. EURICLES. —Should he have Merit, 'Tis plac'd so low, by Fortune.— MEROPE. Fortune's Faults, Where Merit suffers, call on Kings, to mend 'em. EURICLES. What can a Wretch like This deserve, from Power? MEROPE. O, Euricles! look inward: ask thy Heart. Be, for a Moment, but, This Wretch, Thyself— And, then, acquit the Power, that scorn'd to note thee. —Besides, who knows? he may—be still, prompt Fear. Perhaps, my troubled Mind starts Hints too lightly. Hearts that have Everything to fear, slight Nothing. —Let him be brought.—I will, myself, examine him. EURICLES. Your Will must be obey'd. MEROPE. Go, my Ismene! Bid those who guard the Pris'ner bring him hither. Exit Ismene. [Euricles, offering to go.] MEROPE. Stay, Euricles. Stay: and partake more Terrors—Cou'd you think it? Press'd by new Sorrows, I forget my past, And have not yet inform'd you—Poliphontes Has dar'd demand my Hand: dar'd—talk of Marriage. EURICLES. Oh! Queen! I know his Offer Insult: know, It stains Your Name. Yet, blushing, add,—Your forc'd Consent, Grown infamously necessary,—stands, The sole, safe Bar, 'twixt All your Race, and Ruin. MEROPE. 'Tis Horror, but to think, so vile a Dream! EURICLES. So thinks the Army.—So, the Senate thinks. So, think th' exacting Gods:—and, so— MEROPE. The Gods!— Why were They nam'd?—Cou'd they forgive such Fall? From their own Offspring, to a Son of Clay! EURICLES. The King, your Son— MEROPE. Ah! Name not Him.—How, Euricles! How wou'd He thank, my Choice of such a Father? EURICLES. Princes grow wise by Sorrows. He will see That hated Choice the Root of all his Safety. MEROPE. What, what, have you been telling me? EURICLES. Hard Truths: Due, from firm Loyalty, to weak Distress. MEROPE. Can Euricles then plead, for Poliphontes! EURICLES. I know him guilty:—but, I know him rash: Know him resistless: know him childless, too; And know, you love Eumenes. MEROPE. Loving Him, How can I chuse but hate, the Hand that wrongs him? Princes shou'd be above these Self-securings: And born, to live for Truth—or die for Glory. Sits and weeps regardless of Eumene's Entrance. SCENE II. MEROPE. EURICLES. ISMENE. Guards, with EUMENES, in Chains. EUMENES. —(To Ismene.) Is That the Queen, so fam'd for Miseries? ISMENE. It is. EUMENES. How sweetly aweful!—how adorn'd, by Sorrows! ISMENE. Why dost thou pause? the Queen admits thee nearer. EUMENES. No wonder, so much Sweetness, so distress'd, Mov'd, even so greatly distant,—as to me: And drew me, from my Desart!—Give me Leave To stand, a while.—and gaze unmark'd—and note her. —O, ye protecting Gods! whate're becomes Of an abandon'd, nameless Thing, like me, Bless this Supreme Unfortunate! ISMENE. Madam!—the Prisoner waits. MEROPE. —Turning, to observe him. A Murderer, This!— Come forward, Stranger. —A Mien like this, a Murd'rer's!—Can it be, That Looks, so form'd for Truth, so mark'd for Innocence, Cover a cruel Heart?—Come nearer, Youth! Thou art unhappy; bid That Fate protect thee: And speak, as to an Ear that loves the Wretched. Answer me now.—Whose was the Blood thou shed'st? EUMENES. Oh, Queen!—Yet—for a Moment—spare my Tongue. MEROPE. Murder, and Modesty!—Whence, all this Shame? EUMENES. Respect, Confusion,—something, here—un-nam'd, And never felt, till now,—have bound my Tongue. But—oh! do Justice, to your Power to shake me; And, let not Hesitation—pass—for Guilt. MEROPE. Go on—Who was he, whom, I'm told, thou ha'st kill'd? EUMENES. One, who with Wrongs, and Insult, urg'd my Rashness. Young Blood takes Fire too aptly. MEROPE. Young!—was he young? Ice, at my conscious Heart, were warm—compar'd With what he chills my Soul with!—Did'st thou know him? EUMENES. I did not. All Mycene's Earth, and Air, Her Cities, and her Sons, are new, to me. MEROPE. What, was he arm'd, this young Assaulter? came he With Malice? or for Robbery? Be of Comfort. If he attack'd thee, thy Defence was necessary. And sad Necessity makes All things just. EUMENES. Heaven is my Witness, I provok'd him not. 'Tis not in Valour's Wish, to offer Insult: And sure! it is no Crime, to check it, offer'd. MEROPE. On, then—relate the Chance, that led thee hither. EUMENES. Entring your Borders, I beheld a Temple, Sacred to Hercules; the God, my Soul Low, as my Lot was cast, aspires to Honour. —What shou'd I do? bare Vot'ry as I was! I had no Off'rings: brought no Victims, with me. Poor, and oppress'd by Fortune, what I cou'd I gave—I knelt, and pour'd a Heart before him, Warm, as a hundred Hecatombs! pure, humble, Pious, and firm.—Th'Unhappy can no more. I ask'd not, for myself, his undue Blessing. I pray'd Protection, to his own high Race: For, I had heard, Great Queen! your Wrongs requir'd it. The Present God, methought, receiv'd my Prayer. His Altar trembled; and his Temple rung! Keen, undulating. Glories beam'd, about me: I know not how I bore it!—but, my Heart, Full of the Force infus'd, at once grew Vaster. My swelling Courage, far above myself, Sustain'd me:—and I glow'd, with All the God. MEROPE. (Rising in Emotion.) Go on. Methinks, the God thou nam'st speaks in theee! And Ev'ry Hearer glows, as warm'd as Thou! EUMENES. I bow'd, and left the Temple—Following, came Two Men, of haughty Stride, with angry Lowre: Roughly, accosting, they reproach'd my Prayer. How did I dare, they ask'd, solicite Heaven, To aid Sedition's Purposes? No God Shou'd save a Wretch like me, prescrib'd by Power. —I heard, astonish'd; and prepar'd to speak: When, with impatient Fierceness, Each rais'd Arm, With Rage conjoin'd, came on. MEROPE. Interrupting. Both!—Came they, Both, To wound thee!— EUMENES. Both, with Madman's Frenzy, Struck at my Breast, ignobly. MEROPE. Thou has eas'd me. Go on.—These Men had Souls, that match'd their Fate. EUMENES. Un-arm'd, and inoffensive, so surpriz'd, The God I had address'd repaid my Prayer. —Warding the weakest Stroke, with swordless Hand, Swiftly I clos'd, and seiz'd the wrested Steel From Him whose stronger Arm more nearly press'd me. Seiz'd it with Lightning's Swiftness: for, Oppression Rowses Distress, to Vengeance.—On Himself, I turn'd his pointed Weapon: sav'd my Breast, And plung'd it in His own.—He fell.—The Other Started, and curs'd: but, like a Coward, fled, False to his dying Fellow.—Mighty Queen, This is the sad short Truth. May the kind Power I bow'd to, touch your Ear; and move your Pity! MEROPE. She were a Tygress, that cou'd hear this Tale, And pause, upon thy Pardon—Still, go on: How wer't thou seiz'd? hide Nothing: and hope All. EUMENES. Shock'd by uncertain Dread for what was done, I gaz'd astonish'd round: and mark'd, beneath, Where, at a Furlong's Distance, the Salt Wave Broke on the Shore. Sudden I snatch'd the Corps, And, hast'ning to the Beach, gave it to the Sea. That done, I sigh'd, and fled: Your Guards, great Queen, For what escapes such Eyes, as Heaven's, and Yours! Unseen by me, mark'd all; follow'd, and took me. MEROPE. —To Euricles. Did he resist, when seiz'd? EUMENES. I cou'd not, Madam. The Name of Merope disarm'd my Will. They told me they were yours. I bow'd, and yielded. Gave 'em my new-gain'd Sword: and took their Chains. EURICLES. This Youth, by Him he kill'd, was judg'd Another. MEROPE. Oh! I have noted All: and Heaven was just. —Retire, to farther Distance, gentle Youth.— I'll tell thee, Euricles! Methought, at every Word this Wanderer spoke, Pity—or Something, tenderer than Pity, Clung to my aking Heartstrings! nay, 'twas stranger! For, I will tell thee All.—Cresphontes' Features, Heav'ns, what Ideas Hopes and Fears can raise! My dear dead manly Lord's resembled Features; I saw, and trac'd, (I blush, to think what Folly!) Trac'd,—in this Cottage Hero's honest Face. ISMENE. Compassion is a kind and generous Painter. —Yet, Truth Herself must grow as blind, as Fortune, Ere she cou'd look on That unhappy Youth; And find him less, than worth her kindest Pity. EURICLES. Ismene speaks my Thoughts. He's innocent. The Gods have stamp'd their Mark of Candor on him: And no Impostor's Art inhabits there. MEROPE. (To Eumenes.) Again, approach me.—In what Part of Greece Did it please Heaven to give thee Birth, good Youth? EUMENES. (Advancing.) In Elis, generous Queen. MEROPE. In Elis.—Tell me. I hop'd, it had been nearer.—Hast thou, ever, In thy low Converse, heard the Swains, thy Neighbours, Mention the Name of Narbas?—or Eumenes?— —The Last, thou must have heard of. EUMENES. Never, Madam. MEROPE. Never?—That's strange! what then was thy Condition? What thy Employment? and thy Father's Name? EUMENES. My Father was a Shepherd: learn'd, and wise; Prince of the Sylvan Shades, and Past'ral Vale, He led th'attracted Hearts of list'ning Swains, And pleas'd 'em into Subjects—in himself Too humble, for Distinction—had not Virtue Compell'd him into Notice.— He liv'd un-envied: for, excelling All, He veil'd superior Eminence, by Modesty: No claim'd Exemption eas'd his Life from Care: Peacefully poor! and reverently belov'd! His fleecy Harvests fed him:—and, his Name Was Policletes, Madam. MEROPE. What thy Own? EUMENES. Low, like my past'ral Care—to Cottage Ears Adapted—and unform'd for your Regard. —Yet, Elis, oft, may deign to speak of—Dorilas. MEROPE. Oh! I have lost my Hope. Heaven mocks Relief: And every starting Spark is quench'd, in Darkness: So, then, your Parents held no Rank in Greece? EUMENES. Did Rank draw Claim from Goodness, they have Rights Wou'd leave all Place behind 'em, Inborn Virtue Can borrow no Enlargement, but lends all That keeps Contempt from Titles. MEROPE. Every Word He utters has a Charm!—But, Why, at home So bless'd, and, to such Parents, doubly dear, Didst thou, forgetful of the Care thou owd'st 'em, Quit their kind Cott, and leave 'em to their Tears? EUMENES. A vain Desire of Glory, first seduc'd me. Oft had I heard my Father mourn Mycene, Weep, for her Civil Wars, and suff'ring Queen. Oft, had He charm'd my young, aspiring, Soul, With Wonder, at your Firmness!—So, inflam'd, I learnt, by slow Degrees, to think my Youth Disgrac'd, by home-felt Virtues: Weigh'd the Call Of Glory, against Duty; and grew bold To hope, my humble Arm might add some Aid To prop your warring Standards.—See! great Queen, The only Motive of my erring Rashness. For, Heaven has taught me, tho' it loves your Cause, I merit my Distress: who left my Father, Wanting, perhaps, in Age's feeble Calls, Some Help, I might have lent him.—'Twas a Fault. But, 'twas my first: And I may live, to mend it. MEROPE. [aside. Methinks, I hear Eumenes—So, my Soul Informs me, had He known Descent, thus lowly, So, my Eumenes wou'd have thought, and spoke. —Such, is his Age, where'er conceal'd he mourns: Perhaps too, such his Fortune—driven, like This, From Realm to Realm, a Wand'rer, thus unknown! Friendless, and hopeless, and expos'd to Poverty! —I will have Pity, on his Youth's Distress: And cultivate his Fortune.—What bold Noise? [Shouts heard without. Whence can such Rudeness flow!—What is't, Ismene? ISMENE. [at a Window. All Ills are Poliphontes. The vile Rabble Shout their sure Vote, for Treason. Poliphontes Is King, proclaim'd—and Hope is now no more. EUMENES. Oh! for the Sword, once more, your Guards took from me! Now, now, I feel these Chains: Now, first, they bind me. MEROPE. Give him his Sword. Let him be free, as Air. Honest Proposer!—but, Thy Help's too weak, To prop a Throne, in Donger.— EUMENES. O, Queen!—forgive Presumption, in the Poor, When They dare pity Greatness. All have their Mis'ries—but, when Crowns grow wretched, 'Tis Arrogance, in mean ones, to complain. [Exit Eumenes. EURICLES. Too fatally, I prophesied.—Confess This hard Necessity: which, now, you find; And seem, at least, to sooth the Tyrant's Hope. MEROPE. I misconceiv'd the Gods. I durst not dream. They cou'd have bid Guilt thrive: and given up Virtue. EURICLES. They will not, Madam. MEROPE. So, my sad Heart, still, Struggles to hope: and, if they mark my Woe, They will forgive my Rashness. EURICLES. Come what must! I will assemble round you the few faithful, And, failing to protect, partake your Fall. [Exit Euricles. SCENE III. MEROPE. ISMENE. MEROPE. O, People! People! They, who trust your Faith, Bids the wild Winds blow constant. ISMENE. The People's Voice is call'd, the Voice of Gods. MEROPE. What villain Baseness wants some bold Pretence That drags in Heaven, to grace it? Thefts, Plots, Perjuries, Avarice, Revenge, the bloody Zeal, of Pride, And unforgiving Bitterness of Heart; All—have their Gods to friend! their Priests, to sanctifie. SCENE IV. MEROPE. ISMENE. EURICLES, with a Sword. EURICLES. Sorrow on Sorrows bear down Hope's last Prop. Now, be a Queen, indeed!—arm your great Heart, With Preparation, to its utmost Stretch: —For, if it stands this Shock, its Power's immortal. MEROPE. No—I am sinking, from all Sense of Pain: And shall grow safe, by Want of Strength to suffer. Speak—there is now but one sad Truth to dread: And my Soul waits it heard;—then, rests, for ever. EURICLES. It has pleas'd Heaven—this Sword! this fatal Sword! MEROPE. I understand thee; thou woud'st say, he's dead. EURICLES. Oh! 'tis too surely so: th' atrocious Crime At last, succeeded—and all Care is vain. MEROPE. Gods! Gods!—'tis done.—now all your Bolts have struck me. ISMENE. Guard her distracted Brain! EURICLES. Save her, kind Heaven! MEROPE. What have I done? Where have I been? EURICLES. Alas! where Grief, too oft, Has left, th' Unhappy—recollect. MEROPE. Oh! Euricles: I recollect, too much. Trust my sustaining Heart, it breaks not, yet. Comfort's brief Clouds, methought, came shadowing, o'er me. But I am found, again: a Wretch, so friendless, That Madness will not lend Relief: but shuns me. EURICLES. Perish, That young, that impious Hypocrite! That ill-admir'd Attracter of your Pity: Whom your Protection spar'd—for fancied Virtue! MEROPE. Who?—What?— ISMENE. Not Dorilas? EURICLES. Him, Him,—That Dorilas. MEROPE. Monster! beyond all Credit of Deceit! ISMENE: He!—'tis impossible. EURICLES. He was the Murderer. I bring too clear a Proof. Passing, but now, I found him waiting: freed him from his Chains; And, to re-arm him, for the Cause he chose: Call'd for his Sword—Which, as he stretch'd his Hand To take, I mark'd, and trembled at the View, These once-known Gems—too well remember'd, here! MEROPE —taking the Sword. Oh, All ye sleeping Gods! 'twas my Cresphontes 'Twas the King's Sword. Narbas, beyond all Doubting, Sav'd it, that dreadful Night, for my Eumenes. Oh! what a false vile Tale this Flatterer form'd, To cheat us into Pardon! Take the dumb dreadful Witness from my Sight. [giving Euricles the Sword. Yet, stay—return it me.— [resumes the Sword—and kneels. —I thank ye—Gods! Thank your inspiring Justice: and accept it. Live, but to thank you,—for this dire, due, Sacrifice; Which, from the childless Mother's widow'd Hand, Your Heav'n-directed Vengeance well demands. [she rises. Yes. I will sheathe it, on my Husband's Tomb, Deep, in the bleeding Murd'rer's panting Heart; Then, scorning Poliphontes, pierce my own; So, die, reveng'd, and safe,—absolving Heaven. —Go, Euricles.— EURICLES. Not so.—Yet bear his Sight: That, from his own dire Mouth, we may compel Discovery, of his Guilt's commission'd Cause: And, to the Bottom, search this fatal Tale. [Exit Euricles. ISMENE. Erox!—the Tyrant's Minister of Death. SCENE V. MEROPE. ISMENE. EROX. EROX. [aside. Now, aid me, wily Powers of winning Art! MEROPE. How now! What bold Intrusion plac'd thee here? EROX. Queen, of the Kingdom's Lord! his Heart's high Empress! Suffer a Voice unequal to the Task, To wrong th' intrusted Sense of his told Grief Who sends me to condole you.—Poliphontes, Had you but smooth'd that Brow's Majestic Bend, I meant to have said, the King,—this Moment, heard The Fate, most pitied, of the Prince, your Son Heard, and takes equal Part, in all your Wrongs. MEROPE. More, than his Part, he takes, in what is Mine. Else, had he never dar'd aspire, to seize His Master's Throne; nor Name my murder'd Son. EROX. Wishing, he waits but Leave. Respect is delicate, And wou'd not, un-admitted, now, approach. Fain wou'd he talk of Comfort, to your Sorrows, Who, weeping, wants the Power to curb his own. MEROPE. What wou'd your artful Sender come, to say? EROX. To beg, that to his Hand you wou'd commit This hateful Murd'rer's Punishment.—He glows For Vengeance in your Cause. Shou'd think his Claim Unworthy a Crown's Trust; less worthy yours, Cou'd he forget, that Justice props a Throne. MEROPE. No. Tell him no. My Hand revenges, here. Too short of Reach, Heaven knows! but, what it can It shall: and neither asks, nor bears, his Aid. EROX. The King too tenderly regards your Will, To cross it, ev'n in Anger—less, in Reason. —I humbly take my Leave. MEROPE. I grant it, gladly. [Exit Erox. Hunted on every Side, why waits Distress, Till still new Growths of Anguish, more, oppress? How poor a Thing is Life, drag'd on to Age, To stand, the pitied Mark, of Fortune's Rage! Death shuts out Mis'ry: and can, best, restrain The Bite of Insult, and the Goad of Pain. The End of the Second Act.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. SCENE I. The Tomb of Cresphontes. NARBAS alone. Hail venerable Scene! Hail sacred Shade! Hail sad-sought Manes of my long-lov'd Lord! My Eyes last Object on Mycenian Earth, Was thy dear Life and Empire lost in Blood; Now late returning, their first mourning Search, Finds in this cold still Tomb, the whole shrunk Reach Of thy contracted Reign! Yet here, ev'n here, Were thy Eumenes render'd back, even here Narbas had held some hope to sooth thy Ghost. How shall I meet his Mother's mournful Eye, Who bring new Weight, to Woes o'ercharg'd before. From every madd'ning Street, I hear loud Shouts, Those execrable Bawds, to flatter'd Power! Proclaim the Traitor Poliphontes, King. He! who, from Clime to Clime, track'd our sad Way! Held, like a hunted Deer, his Prince, in Chace; Hot in Pursuit, for Murder!—Each known Prospect, Each Point, each Outlet of this neighb'ring Palace, Brings to afflicted Mem'ry some new Stroke Of Sorrow, fresh to Pain—tho' fifteen Winters Have snow'd their whiteness on me, since they fell! Wou'd, I cou'd find the Face of some old Friend! But, what Court Friendship's Life lasts, fifteen Winters: —Soft. Whom has Heaven sent, here! If Innocence— Dwells yet on Earth, such Looks as these must house it. [Starts, as Ismene comes nearer. Bless the resembled Mother's copied Softness! 'Tis my Ismene: 'Tis my own dear Daughter. Time cannot hide her, from a Parent's Eye: Child as she was—and chang'd since last I saw her. SCENE II. Narbas, Ismene, follow'd by a Train of Virgins in white, who bring Baskets, and strew Flowers on the Tomb. ISMENE. Who is this bold Unknown? So sagely form'd! Yet indiscretely rude—at such an Hour, To break, abruptly, on the Queen's sad Purpose! NARBAS. Fairest, of Forms— ISMENE. Who are you? NARBAS. Chide me not, Sweet Picture of the Powers, who shed soft Pity! —I am a nameless, friendless, weak, old Man. Once, I was Servant, to the Queen you serve; O, grant the gracious Privilege, to see her. ISMENE. Rev'rend, and Wife! The first, I see you are: The last, my Heart conceives you—what a Time Have your misguided Wants unaptly chosen! Your Sight wou'd, now, offend her.—Deep Distress, From dire Solemnity of Purpose, brings her, —'Twere prudent to withdraw. NARBAS.- [in a low Voice, Come near—Ismene. ISMENE. Immortal Powers! Who can it be?—He knows me! Fain wou'd I dare mix Hope, with Fear and Wonder. [approaching him. NARBAS. Thou art my Child. Kind Heaven has sent thee, to me. —Be cautious—and observe. ISMENE. [Kneeling. Prophetic Heart! Oh, Sir—I cannot speak! NARBAS, [raising her. Hide thy Surprize, Ere yet some dang'rous Note detects our Meeting. —Soft as thy Eyes Ismene, be thy Voice. And answer to my Question—round this Tomb. Why thus assembled moves that virgin Train? ISMENE. Alas! the afflicted Queen, Distracted comes,—to offer on this Tomb, Her Life's last Sacrifice—a dreadful Victim! —The Murd'rer of her Son. NARBAS. Eumenes, dead?— ISMENE. Alas, Sir! cou'd you be a Stranger to it? NARBAS. Blast! of my Soul's best Hope.—Who dar'd this Villainy? ISMENE. A Youth, who found him in Alcides' Temple. One, from whose Air of manly Modesty None, surely cou'd have fear'd—behold! he comes. That fetter'd Criminal is He.—Oh, Sir! Where will you, now, be hid? NARBAS. In Death, Ismene: If I now hear and see—and am not dreaming! ISMENE. From the Queen's Eye, I dare no longer.— NARBAS [holding her. Stay. Queens, Kings, nor Gods, shall tear thee from my Arm, Till thou hast heard me fully. SCENE III. Solemn Procession to a Dead March. Merope. Euricles, with the Sword. Eumenes, in Chains. Guards. Priests, as to Sacrifice—The Queen goes up weeping, and kneels silent, at the Tomb. While the Rest range themselves, on each Side the Scene. NARBAS, to ISMENE. Some black-soul'd Fiend, some Fury ris'n from Hell, Has darken'd all Discernment!—Call'dst thou not That fetter'd Youth the Murd'rer of Eumenes? ISMENE. I call'd him so, too truly. NARBAS. He is Eumenes. What angry God misleads the Queen, to Madness? She dreams Eumenes kill'd—and kills Eumenes! ISMENE. Now are my Heart's late Tremblings well explain'd. Quick let me rush, and warn her erring Hand. NARBAS. Not, for a thousand Worlds—to save him, So, Were but to lose him, Surer—Poliphontes Has Ears and Eyes too near us.— I may anon find Means, when all are busied To hide myself, unmask'd, amid'st the Crowd. Sad and solemn Musick. Then a SONG, of Sacrifice: Mr. Beard, as Chief Priest. Hear, from the dark and silent Shade! Hear, ye pale Bands of Death! Gliding from Graves, where once your Bones were laid, Receive a Murd'rer's Breath. Chorus, of Priests and Virgins. Receive a Murd'rer's Breath. MEROPE, rising and coming forward. Where is this Victim—odious, to All Powers, But one,—the dreadful Nemesis? The Guards bring up Eumenes. EURICLES. Yet, er'e he dies, 'Twere fit, some Force of Torture should compel him To name his vile Accomplices. MEROPE. It shall. Say, Monster! what provok'd thee to this Guilt: And what Associates join'd thee. EUMENES. I appeal The Gods, who find it fit my Soul shou'd buy, At this dear Rate, the Moment's Hope you lent it; Those Gods can witness for me; They! who curse The perjur'd, and disclaim the Base one's Safety. My Lips detest Imposture: —Nor know I, by what Change, in Heav'ns high Will, I, who of late so bless'd, had touch'd your Pity, Fall, now, beneath your Anger! MEROPE, taking the Sword from Euricles. View this Sword. Know you the dreadful Object. EUMENES. Twas the Villain's, My just Hand punish'd with it. MEROPE. Seize him. Rend him. Swift to the destin'd Altar, drag the Traitor. He owns it! glories, in his bloody Crime: And my shock'd Soul akes, at him. The Guards seize him. EUMENES —struggling. Off—away— Spare your officious Grasp.—I will be heard; One last loud Word—in Spite of Arms and Insult. MEROPE —after a Signal to the Guards, who quit Eumenes. Thou then, who deal'st in Death, can'st find Death fearful. EUMENES. No, Madam! you mistake. Death shakes the Happy: But He who is a Wretch receives him gladly. —Yet, 'gainst imputed Guilt, the humblest, wrong'd, Rise, bold in Innocence. —Tell me, nor let your Pride deface your Pity, Whose, so high-rated Blood was This I shed? —If he was dear to You, curs'd be my Memory, Or I had rather lost my Own, than His. MEROPE. Where has this cruel Wretch been taught Deceit? Why was that Look, so like Cresphontes, His! Half fainting. EURICLES. Great Queen! sustain your Purpose. Think of Vengeance. The Laws of Nature,—and the Lives of Kings. EUMENES. Do Laws and Kings, then, call Injustice Vengeance? Shame on the Great! why long'd my Eyes for Courts? Courts, where the Pride of Guilt lays Claim to Honour. —Haughty of Heart, why have they Souls thus abject They threaten, praise, fright, flatter, and insult me! —Yet, oh! twas just.—I left my Father, rashly; Felt not the Pangs: weigh'd not the Tears I cost him. Fate drew me from my Forest's guiltless Quiet, Deaf to the Warnings of a Father's Wisdom: And a griev'd Mother's Bodings. MEROPE. Mother, said he! Barbarian! ha'st thou yet a Mother, left thee? I was a Mother too—till Thy fell Hand Depriv'd me of a Son—and all Life's Comforts. EUMENES. A Son!—your Son? MEROPE. Mine, Monster! Murd'rer! Mine. EUMENES. If Such was my Misfortune, Such my Curse, If Heaven has made it possible—that He, Who in a fatal Moment, err'd—and fell By my ill-destin'd Rashness, was Your Son, Earth holds not such another Wretch as I am! And Mercy's faintest Glimpse shou'd shun to reach me. Eumenes, here, offers to speak, and Merope interrupts him. Mercy! thou Hypocrite.—If thou dar'st pray, Raise thy dumb Hands: and ask, in vain, from Heaven, The Mercy, thou deniedst my dying Son. EUMENES. Yet hear— MEROPE. Stop his detested Mouth; Force the doom'd Victim to the Altar's Foot, Veil him from Light, no more to be beheld: Hide his quench'd Eyes, for ever. Two Priests approaching, with a Veil, he snatches it, and throws it from him. EUMENES. Off! ye vain Forms! Cover the Eyes of Cowards: Mine disdain ye. Mine can, with stedfast and advancing Scorn, Look in Death's Face, fullsighted.—When It comes 'Tis to be met, not hid.— Welcome, Eternal Day;—Bad World, farewel. Advances, between the Priests, to the Tomb—follow'd by the Queen, Euricles, Ismene, &amp;c. MEROPE. At the Tomb—with the Sword drawn, and Eumenes kneeling ready. Shade, of my murder'd Husband!—hear my call. Chorus, of Singer's Voices. Oh! hear. MEROPE. Soul of my bleeding Son! hear, thou— Chorus of Singer's Voices. Oh! hear. MEROPE. Un-expiated Souls!—if, in those Glooms, Where walk the sullen Ghosts of earth-wrong'd Kings, You hear Atonement's Voice, and wait Redress, Rise, from your dire Domains! Chorus, of Singer's Voices. Oh! rise. MEROPE. —Thou, last, Tremend'ous Power! pale Goddess! present, still, To direful Vengeance! nerve this lifted Arm, And thus assisting— Ismene preventing the Blow, Narbas breaks into Sight, and cries out loudly, Stay, stay that bloody Purpose. Death has already been too busy, here: And Heaven disclaims such Sacrifice. MEROPE, in a frighted and trembling Attitude, Who art thou? EURICLES. O, 'tis Narbas! Cautious conceal this chance, or Ruin finds him. ISMENE, —aside—to the Queen. Your Victim is your Son,—the Prince, Eumenes. Merope lets fall the Sword—astonish'd, and trembling. EUMENES —rising himself to look round. I heard a well-known Voice, now heard no longer. Open, sad Eyes! once more, from the Grave's Brink, And find what seem'd—oh! 'tis—It is—My Father! NARBAS, aside, to EUMENES. Hear: and be mute. Thy Fate, unwary Youth! Depends upon thy Silence. EUMENES. Whence, O ye Powers! Can all these Myst'ries rise! MEROPE. Oh!—'tis too much— And Life and I are lost. Faints: and is supported by Ismene. NARBAS. Assist the Queen. ISMENE. Stay your unhallow'd Rites: the Queen's in Danger. EURICLES. Quit, rev'rend Priests! your unpropitious Sacrifice. [Exeunt Priests. Follow me, Guards; I will secure your Victim. EUMENES. O, Father— NARBAS —to EUMENES. Shun me: and patient wait th' important Cause. EUMENES. O, bid me, ere I die, but hope your Pardon: And, if I leave you bless'd—'tis all my Prayer. NARBAS. No more.—The Gods, who love, reward thy Virtue! [The Soldiers, and Euricles, go off, with Eumenes. ISMENE. Kind Heaven restores the Queen. MEROPE. Where!—whither have ye brought me?— —Ismene?—what means This!—Why weep my Virgins? —Oh! I have kill'd him:—looking wildly round her—for I see him not: And I am doom'd to Pains, in Life immortal. NARBAS. Ease your sad Heart's too apprehensive Startings. Euricles has secur'd him: And nothing's known. MEROPE. Still that kind Vision haunts me.—Art thou Narbas? NARBAS. Let my Tears answer—in this Gush of Joy— I give you back my Trust, my King Eumenes. MEROPE, on her Knees. Oh, gracious Heaven! support a Woman's Weakness: And, what my Heart, yet panting, fails to utter, Take, from my Soul's touch'd Sense; and make my Prayer. You are too Great, for Thanks! too Good, for Duty! [Rises. EURICLES, re-entering hastily. Death! to th' insatiate Tyrant's Thirst of Insult! —This Royal Scandal, to the Name he steals, Has, with some fatal Purpose, seiz'd the King; And holds him, to examine. MEROPE. Follow me. Now shall he see, what Marks denote the Queen; What Diff'rence, 'twixt the Guilty, and the Wrong'd. NARBAS, going. Madam!—It must not be. EURICLES. Stay: Curb this Rashness. MEROPE. Is he not mine! Is he not yours?—your King? EURICLES. The moment you confess That dang'rous Truth, No God, but hated Hymen, saves Eumenes. MEROPE. There, thou hast let in Light, upon my Soul, —Rather than wed this Poliphontes.— NARBAS. Wed him? WED—Polyphontes! EURICLES. Him. NARBAS. The World's last Groan, Wrapt in surrounding Fires, had less amaz'd me! EURICLES. 'Tis with That View the People call him King. Since he reveng'd Cresphontes' Blood, they say, He, best— NARBAS. He!—Every Curse of Death surround him! He! He reveng'd!—The Villain's own damn'd Train Shed,—spilt it. I beheld 'em: Trac'd the Fiend Thro' all his dark Disguises—thro' Night's Eye Saw the pale Murd'rer stalk, amidst his Furies. His was the half-hid Torch,—the Postern Key, That open'd to the Rebel's Rage the Palace. —In the pierc'd infant Breasts of two doom'd Innocents, I saw him plunge his Poignard: Twice receiv'd it, Deep, in my own, encumber'd with my Charge: Struggling, to bear the third sav'd Prince to shelter; And, track'd by my lost Blood, with Pain escap'd him. MEROPE. When will my growing Horrors reach their End! Oh! my fix'd Hate was Instinct. Something, fatal, Dwelt on his dreadful Brow, and bad me shun him. Blind! headlong! ill-discerning! noise-driv'n People! EURICLES, looking out. Soft! the Tyrant comes! MEROPE. Can the Gods leave That possible?— Narbas, be hid, this Moment— [Exit Narbas. —Euricles! Fly thou—find to my mournful Son Access, Comfort his Fears—but keep the Secret from him. [Exit Euricles. SCENE IV. Merope, Ismene, Poliphontes in Nuptial Robes, Erox, and Train. POLIPHONTES. Health, to my Sovereign, late! Now—so the States Decree—my Wife!—my Sister! and my Soul! Dress'd is the Altar; and the Priests attend. —Nay, do not turn aside, and shun your Triumph. Look—and admire the Wonders of your Power! The God of Love, to-day, smoothes all my Wrinkles: And I am taught by Joy to smile back Youth. —One Care alone precedes impatient Love. They tell me, your too tender Heart recoil'd: And lost your purpos'd Vengeance.—Let it be. Beauty was meant to wound, a gentler Way. Mine, be the Stroke of Justice.—When I view This murd'rous Stripling, thro' the Grief he brought you, Pity disdains his Cause; and Fate demands him. MEROPE. I find myself, 'tis true, too weak, for Vengeance. Wou'd I had Power, more equal to my Wrongs! POLIPHONTES. Leave it to Me: 'Tis a King's Right.—I claim it. MEROPE. I shall consider of it. POLIPHONTES. Why? what doubt you? Slackens your Anger? that your Vengeance hesitates! Is your Son's Mem'ry now, less dear, than lately? MEROPE. Perish, the Will, that wrongs him! but, this Murd'rer, This Youth—they tell me you suspect Accomplices— Were it not prudent to suspend his Fate, 'Till he declares, who join'd him? POLIPHONTES. What expect you To clear, beyond your Son's known Fall? MEROPE. His Father's— That was a Cup of Gall.—Oh! conscious Guilt! How dumb, thy Voice, unlook'd-for, strikes the Bold! [Aside. POLIPHONTES (after a Pause.) Well—ev'n of That too, We ourself will ask him. MEROPE. You are too busy, Sir! in a Pursuit, That, least, admits your Quick'ning. POLIPHONTES. Strange Perplexity! That what most seeks your Ease shou'd most offend! But, spring it, whence it may, the Cause remov'd, There, ends the Doubt, and Pain.—This Wretch shall die. [Going. MEROPE. Barbarian! horrible, inhuman—Sir! Why have you sought to startle me?—I fear'd— You meant to snatch my Victim from—my Vengeance. POLIPHONTES. But—shall he really die? MEROPE. Die!—Who?—He—die? POLIPHONTES. This Murd'rer of your Son. MEROPE. I go, this Moment; And will, alone, examine him. POLIPHONTES. Stay, Madam. This new Embarrassment, of mingled Pains; This Tenderness in Rage; these Hopes, Fears, Startings, This Art, to colour some ill-hid Distress, That casts Confusion o'er your troubled Soul: Half Sentences, broke short; Looks, fill'd with Horror, Are Nature's thin Disguise, to cover Danger. —Something you will not tell alarms my Caution; And bids my summon'd Fear take Place of Love. —In ent'ring, here, I had a Glimpse, but now, Of an old Man, who seem'd to shun my Presence. Why is he fled?—Who was he? MEROPE. Scarce yet call'd A King—and see! already fill'd with Jealousies! POLIPHONTES. Be kind, and bear your Part, then.—Burthens, shar'd, Press light the eas'd Sustainers.—Come; your Hand. MEROPE. A Moment since, you talk'd but of Revenge: Now, 'tis again all Love—Away: Keep separate, Two Passions, Nature never yet saw join'd. POLIPHONTES. Let it be so, then. Death shall strait remove That Obstacle: And but one Wish remains. Follow, at Leisure, you: While I prepare. [Exit Poliphontes. MEROPE. Act for me, now, and save me, Great Alcides! To Power like thine, all Things are possible: And Grief, oppress'd on Earth, finds Friends in Heaven. Then when the woe-sunk Heart is tir'd with Care, And every human Prospect bids despair, Break but one Gleam of heav'nly Comfort, in; And a new Race of Triumphs, thence, begin. End of the Third Act.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT IV. SCENE I. The Castle of Poliphontes. Poliphontes. Erox. POLIPHONTES. She has her Views, I mine.—I shou'd have fear'd, Some Hint's officious Reach had touch'd her Ear; I shou'd have dreamt, her Eyes had catch'd some Glance, To guide Discovery, down the dark Abyss, Where my close Crime lies veil'd, in dumb Obscurity. —But, that I know, she is a WOMAN—Erox! And born to be capricious. EROX. Pride—not Distaste, Holds out her Heart, against you. POLIPHONTES. Let her keep it. My Hope is humbler, Erox. 'Tis her Hand I seek: Hearts are Girls' Gifts to School-boy Lovers. Now, let her Spleen start wild. When Time serves aptly, Means shall be found to curb it—Thou art come From sounding this fierce captive Son of Wonder. What have thy Thoughts concluded? EROX. 'Tis not He. No Race of Hercules need, there, alarm you. This but some rural Brave, of simple Nurture; Void of Ambition's Flame: Bold, blunt and honest: Fearless of Menace, tasteless of Reward, And wanting ev'n the Wish, to dare, for Power. He cannot be Eumenes. POLIPHONTES. Who, then, is he? EROX. He says he is a Shepherd's Son:—what, more, He will not be provok'd, nor brib'd, to tell. Firm without Fierceness; without Weakness, gentle: Open as Day-light; yet, as dumb, as Death! Spite of my Prejudice, he forc'd my Praise; And Hatred must admire him. POLIPHONTES. Praise him on. Be what, or whom, he may, 'tis fit he die. The People, who conclude his Punishment Inflicted, for Eumenes' fansied Murder, Will dream that Race extinct; and cleave to Me. So Danger comes less near: Nor shakes my Throne. —What hast thou learnt, of that conceal'd Presumer, Who, when the Arm of Merope was rais'd, Restrain'd it, with some Power that touch'd her Soul? EROX. The young Man call'd him Father. Chance, it seems, In that nice Moment, brought him to his View. He mov'd the Queen's Compassion, for his Son, Fled, like a Wanton, from the Good Man's Care, Who, in his Search, came sorrowing on, from Elis. POLIPHONTES. I cannot trust this Tale. Thou grow'st too credulous, Mysterious Caution hangs too thick a Veil O'er all their late Proceedings. That old Man, Left the Queen's Presence, starting, at my Entrance. Why was he hid, if a young Rustick's Father? Why shou'd my coming fright him? He has heard Since then, his Son's redoubled Danger dwells But in my Menace: Yet he comes not near me. I had, ere now, beheld him at my Feet, Had his Heart trembled with a Father's Terrors. EROX. See, Sir! he's free—and mark—the Queen, how near! POLIPHONTES. I note it, and determine. —Now! my Sister. SCENE II. Poliphontes, Erox, Merope, Ismene, Euricles, Eumenes, and Guards. MEROPE. You see, Sir! I dare know, and use, my Rights. How had your Will presum'd to seize my Victim? Am I but Queen of Shadows? that my Vengeance Must move, as you direct it? POLIPHONTES. Nobly urg'd! The Victim is your Right, requires your Hand: Mine had defac'd your Vengeance.—I assum'd Pretence to aid it, but to fire your Languor. Take Courage. I resign him. With his Blood Wash this reluctant Faintness from your Heart: And give it Warmth to meet me at the Altar. MEROPE. Horrid, and impious, Hope! POLIPHONTES. Looks Love so frightful? EUMENES to Poliphontes. Who taught thee to associate Love with Cruelty? What Right has Cupid to a Captive's Blood? —Yet, mispresume me not, that I court thy Pity— He has too poor a View from Life, to prize it, Whose Death can only serve, to shorten Pain. —But, I am told, Thou call'st thyself a King. Know, if thou art one, that the Poor have Rights: And Power, in all its Pride, is less than Justice. —I am a Stranger,—innocent,—and friendless,— And That Protection, which thou ow'st, to All, Is doubly due, to me:—For, I'm unhappy. POLIPHONTES. Protection is for Worth:—Guilt calls for Vengeance. EUMENES. And what does Wrong's licentious Insult call for? —In my own just Defence, I kill'd a Robber: Law call'd it Murder; and the Queen condemn'd me. Queens may mistake. Ev'n Gods, who LOVE, grow partial. I can forgive th'Injustice of a Mother: And cou'd have bless'd her Hand, beneath the Blow. Nature has Weaknesses, that err to Virtue? —But, What hast Thou to do with Mother's Vengeance? Law, that shocks Equity, is Reason's Murder. POLIPHONTES. So young! so wretched!—and so arrogant! Methinks, the Pride of an Alcides' Blood Cou'd scarce have swell'd a Soul to loftier Boldness! MEROPE. Pity presumptuous Heat. 'Tis Youth's Prerogative. POLIPHONTES. Mean while, how happy such unpolish'd Plainness! To move Defence, from Art so skill'd as Yours. Your Son, sure! lives. MEROPE. Lives! and shall live. I trust him to the Gods: They can—they did—they will protect him. POLIPHONTES. What cannot Woman's Pity! None, who marks The willing Pardon your soft Looks insure him, Can charge your Heart with Cruelty. MEROPE. My Looks, Perhaps, hint Meanings, Prudence shou'd decline To lend too loud a Tongue to.—but, there are, Whose Heart speaks Nothing: Yet tells All, by Actions. POLIPHONTES. Mark, if I speak not, now, my Heart's true Language. —Traitor! receive thy Doom [Drawing his Sword. MEROPE, (interposing.) Strike here, here, Murd'rer! Menace my Breast; not His. POLIPHONTES. Whose Heart speaks, now? EUMENES. Now, ye Immortals! not to die, were, not To triumph.—To be pitied, here! so pitied! By such a Queen as Merope!—'tis Glory That every Power beneath a God might envy! POLIPHONTES. If you wou'd have him live, confess, Who is he? MEROPE. He—is— EURICLES (to Ismene.) Oh! we are lost. ISMENE. All, all, is hopeless. POLIPHONTES. If he has Right in You, be swift to own him: Or, lose him by your Silence. [Offers to kill Eumenes. MEROPE. Stay—he is— POLIPHONTES. Who? What?—say, quickly. MEROPE. He is My Son, Eumenes. POLIPHONTES, (starting, and aside.) 'Tis as I fear'd; and all my Schemes are Air. [Stands pensively fix'd. EUMENES. Heav'ns!—Did I hear That, rightly? MEROPE, (embracing him.) Thou art my Son. Loud in the Face of Men and Ear of Gods, Cresphontes was thy Father: I attest it: I tell it, to the Winds: Proclaim it—boast it, Hear it, Thou Soul of Murder! I have found him: And, if I lose him, now, whole Heaven shall curse thee. EUMENES. I cannot comprehend it!—Yet, I kneel, To thank you—but for deigning to deceive me. Bless'd is his Fate, who dies, in such a Dream! MEROPE. One Way, thou art deceiv'd.—The Mother's Love Forgets the Monarch's Danger.—Poliphontes! POLIPHONTES, (starting.) Go on—I meditated—but—speak, Madam. MEROPE. Thou now hast wrung, from my affrighted Heart, The Secret, that oppress'd it. Thou behold'st Thy King, distress'd, before thee.—Sigh, if thou can'st, Sigh,—for the Son, Prince, Mother—Fame, and Nature. POLIPHONTES. How to resolve will ask some needful Pause. —Mean while, it shakes my Faith, to trust your Story. You hear, the young Man's Honesty disclaims This Greatness, you wou'd lend him. EUMENES. Modest Sense Of my unequal Worth compell'd some Doubting; But, now, 'tis Truth contestless. Royal Tears Flow not for pitied Falsehood; and they prove it. MEROPE. Tears touch not Hearts of Flint; and I will spare 'em. Bid your (kneels.) Pride hear me—for, your Pity cannot. See me an humble Suppliant, at your Feet, Now first confessing I can fear your Anger. This shou'd, beyond all Proof of Tears, convince you, That Merope's his Mother.—Still, you frown: I forget My own long Sorrows—all my Wrongs, and Insults: Smile to the future—and absolve the past. —Let him but breathe—to reign, were to be wretched; —Cruel! you answer nothing!—look less dreadful. Ease my distracted Soul—and speak some Comfort. EUMENES. O, Madam! quit that Posture.—My proud Heart Aspires to keep the Glory you have lent it. —If I, indeed, was born, to call you Mother, Why do I see and hear you, not a Queen? [Raises her. —Nor think my Soul too haughty:—No Distress Absolves Dejection: 'Tis the Brave's Prerogative, To feel, without complaining. Now!—Strike, Tyrant— Courage, restrain'd from Act, takes Pride to suffer. POLIPHONTES, (to Merope.) 'Tis well. I have, with just Attention, heard; And, in impartial Silence, weigh'd it, all. Your Sorrow claims some Right to call for mine: And his high Spirit charms me.—I take him [Takes Eumenes by the Hand. Into my heedful Care; remit his Sentence, And, if found Yours, adopt him as my Son. EUMENES. Yours, said you?—Yours! MEROPE. Be patient, good Eumenes. POLIPHONTES. You rule his Destiny. You know what Price I rate his Life at. Smile; and meet my Wishes. For, may the Gods, conjointly, curse my Reign, If he survives Refusal of my Prayer! —Bethink you. In an Hour, I shall expect you; Where, at the Altar, to th' attesting Powers, You may proclaim your Choice. That Moment makes him My Victim, or my Son. 'Till then, farewel. MEROPE. You cannot be so cruel.—Leave him, with me. To see him, might persuade me. POLIPHONTES. See him, there: See him, in Hymen's Temple. Erox, attend him. [Exeunt. EUMENES. Oh, Queen! oh, Mother! If I, already, dare assume a Right To call you, by that dear, that awful Name: Think, nothing, that may misbecome your Glory— Do, nothing, that may mix Contempt, with mine. —I leave you to the Care of Heav'n; and die. Lead me to the Tyrant. SCENE III. Merope, Euricles, Ismene. MEROPE. Fly, follow, Euricles; hold thy kind Eye Fix'd, to this Tyrant's Motions. Fain would I dream, He threatens, but to fright me. EURICLES. Willing Hope So flatters, to deceive you. Too, too sure, His Purpose! Ev'n by Nature, stern and bloody, How more, when Power and Safety prompt his Cruelty! [Exit Euricles. MEROPE. Find thy good Father, Haste, Ismene; call him. Tell him, Distress grows headstrong, and my Soul Sickens for want of Counsel. ISMENE. [Aside. What a Blindness Is Thirst of human Grandeur! Give me, Gods! A Cottage, and Concealment. Save the Queen; And, from the Curse of Courts, remotely place me. [Exit Ismene. MEROPE Alone. No, there is none; no Ruler of the Stars, Regardful of my Miseries.— Oh, my lov'd Son! my Eyes have lost thee, ever. I shall no more snatch Comfort, from thy Hopes, Or wonder at thy Sweetness.— Why have the Deities permitted this? Why have they sported with a Mortal's Mind, Unpitying it's Distraction? sent him to me From a far distant Land? Sent him, for what! To glut the Murd'rer's Sword, who kill'd his Father. —Yet, you are just, ye Gods!—Amazing Darkness Dwells o'er th' Eternal Will, and hides all Cause. I must not dare to tax Almighty Power, For what I suffer from it. Let it but pay me With that curs'd Tyrant's Punishment attain'd: Let me but see myself depriv'd of Him— See him expell'd, from Light, from Earth, from Name, Deep, as the chearless Voids below can plunge him! And I will (kneeling) kneel, a Wretch, and thank your Justice. SCENE IV. Merope, Ismene, Narbas. NARBAS. Oh! Queen! August in Woes! What Wrongs are yours! MEROPE rising. Yes, Narbas,—I have sacrific'd my Son— Have given him up, to Death—have, madly, own'd him: —What Mother, who beheld her Son, as I did, Doom'd and endanger'd, cou'd have, then, kept Silence! NARBAS. Gen'rous your Purpose! gloriously, you err'd: And fell, but from a Height, 'twas Fame, to reach. Dry up your Tears, and summon All your Soul: Time presses,—and a Moment, lost, is Fate. [Shouts heard. ISMENE looking out. Uproar, and Cries without, in rising Wildness, Heard from the City, reach the Palace Walls: Sure Sign of new Confusion! NARBAS. I saw the Tyrant meet th' expecting Priests; Attended, not in Hymeneal Robes, But Vestments, such as Sacrifice demands; And Pomp of bloody Rites, at dreadful Altars. To These, his Hand consign'd the Victim, led: And deaf'ning Shouts receiv'd him.—From the Train Of Priestly Horrors, this Way mov'd their Chiefs; Follow'd by loud, licentious, Bursts of Joy. Amid th' enormous Swell of whose coarse Roar, All, I distinctly heard was Poliphontes. MEROPE. —Where are my Guards? Arm'd, for my Vengeance, call 'em. [Enter three Priests. SCENE V. Merope, Narbas, Ismene, Priests. MEROPE. What! are ye here already?—Out of my Sight, Ye sanctify'd Deceits! You! whose bold Arts Rule Rulers! and compel even Kings, to Awe! Be gone, fly, vanish— Ye Mouths of Mercy! and ye Hands of Blood! CHIEF PRIEST. Sorrows, and Wrongs, claim Privilege to rail: And Heaven's affronted Vot'ries must forgive. MEROPE. Cool, in your Cruelty!—Religion's Veil Ill cloaks Rebellion's Licence. Death was your Errand. Why talk you of Forgiveness?—'tis not yours. CHIEF PRIEST. Not in Death's Cause we come; but Heaven's—and Love's. If Vows were plighted, 'twixt the King and You, No Power on Earth dissolves 'em. MEROPE. False, as Hell! He knows, I heard his hated Vows with Horror. —Slight Insolence!—To this ill-founded Charge, Silence, and Scorn, shall answer. [turning away. CHIEF PRIEST. Gracious Sovereign! Suspend your Anger: 'tis unjustly rais'd. —Enlighten, and command us.—Found too easy In one wrong'd Faith, we twice, perhaps, have err'd: Alike deceiv'd, in Both.—Unbend that Brow: And deign to teach our Doubt, what Name to give This Stranger? this young Captive to the King? MEROPE. Give him the Name you dare to misapply. Call him your King—my Son—my lost Eumenes. CHIEF PRIEST. Hear That, prophetic Soul! high Heaven!—I tremble, In Dread, this great Discovery comes too late. The shouting People crowd the waiting Altar: And, erring in their Zeal, mis-hail the Day. —What can be, shall be try'd, to cross his Doom. They shall be taught, with bold, adventrous Speed, To save their Sovereign's Right—and, hence, rash Queen, Learn due Repentance: and no more, let loose The Rage of Wrongs, against the Tongues of Gods. [Exeunt Priests. MEROPE. —This solemn Sharpness of deserv'd Reproach, Struck my too conscious Guilt, with infelt Awe! I have been warm too soon: and just, too late. What, tho' Religion's Guardians taint her Tide! Pure is the Fountain, tho' the Stream flows wide: Too oft, her erring Guides her Cause, betray: Yet, Rage grows impious, when it bars her Way. End of the Fourth Act.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT V. SCENE I. A Prison. EUMENES. NARBAS. EURICLES. EUMENES. Think, think upon your Danger: fly, lov'd Father! Fly from the Tyrant's Power, and leave me to my Fate. NARBAS. All Sense of my own Danger lost, in yours, I threw myself, regardless, at his Feet. Full of the fatal Subject, I began, Uncautious in my Transport. Starting Conscience Fled from the Face of Truth. He shun'd to hear, Broke short, reply'd 'twas well: gave me Permission; Nay, full of seeming Zeal, injoin'd my coming— Bad me go pay my last short Debt, of Counsel: And try to bend your Heart, to meet his Will. EURICLES. He added, that his Queen—he call'd her His! I blush to name her such: but so, he charg'd me. Since she, he said, in Pity but for you, Yields a reluctant Hand, to close with his, 'Tis Time, her Son, whose Life she holds so dear, Aids his own Int'rest, and confirms her Safety. —The Rest, he paus'd and thought: but held it in, Frown'd a disdainful Nod—and bad us leave him. EUMENES. Slowly awaking, from my Dream of Wonders, I seem re-born, to some new World, unknown; Where every thing, I meet with, shocks my Soul. —You talk of dying, whilst I, yet, half doubt, Whether, existing now, I really live! If I am, truly, the lost Wretch I seem, If in Mycene now inclos'd, I find Queen Merope, my Mother—King Cresphontes My Father, murder'd—his fear'd Murd'rer crown'd, With his stol'n Diadem: and, in it, daring Offer his widow'd Queen a Hand, stain'd, frightful, In her first Husband's Blood—All This, to me! Seems, while I drink in Heaven's fair Light, and view Yon Mansion of the Gods, who govern Man— Incredible! astonishing!—and horrid! EURICLES. 'Tis horrible, indeed! too dark for Thought! —But, Reason's Line wants Depth to sound Heaven's Will. NARBAS. Deign, my devoted Prince! my King!—my Son! Suffer me, still, to use that long-lov'd Name— Deign but—to live.—Time, Chance, and Fortune's Changes, May vindicate your Glory.—Since the Tyrant Tempts, to betray—reward him, with his own. Deceive Deceivers, and Deceit grows Virtue. EUMENES. This, in thy Forests, Elis! had I heard, Even there, I shou'd have blush'd to hear, from Narbas! But, as I am.—No more.— Kind was your Motives!—pitying my Distress, You, but, forgot my Duty. NARBAS. Happy Forests! Wou'd, Ye were Ours, once more! there, Peace dwelt with us: There, Safety slept, upon unguarded Hills, And every Tree's soft Shadow cover'd Anguish. EURICLES. Soft! behold!—the Tyrant comes! SCENE II. POLIPHONTES, To the Foregoing. POLIPHONTES. Retire: and wait, without. [Exeunt Euricles and Narbas. —And Thou, rash Youth! Whose unexperienc'd Years, and gen'rous Plainness, Fill me with all the Pity, due to Weakness! For the last Time I come, to bring thee Power. Leave to my Toil, to smooth thy future Paths; And root out Faction's Thorns, which trouble Empire. —When I am dead—as Age admits short Stay, Thou, and my Merope will reign, at Ease, And thank my painful Cares: and love my Memory. —Why art thou dumb?—Pause on—I read thee, rightly. Thou hast, I know, a kind of stubborn Pride, Call'd Courage—and mistak'st it, for a Virtue. —'Tis Virtue: when Presumption drives it not: But suffers Thought to guide it. EUMENES. Guiding Thought Has held me patient, long.—Now, answer me. Am I Mycene's Monarch? POLIPHONTES. For thy Birth, Be it, as Truth, or Trick, or Chance, conclude it, If, from some low, some nameless Stock, derived, Be humble, and advis'd—and rise to Greatness. If happier Offspring cast thee for a King, Make thyself worthy, of the Crown I mean thee. —'Tis but, to wait me to the Marriage Altar, Where Love, and Merope, and Peace, attend. There, to the Gods and me, (Mycene's Guardians) Swear Homage, and devote thy faithful Sword. That done, Sports, Joys, and Safety, crown thy Youth: And, in thy riper Years, expect the Diadem. —Determine.— EUMENES. 'Tis determin'd. POLIPHONTES. Tell me how? EUMENES. Why am I left unfree to chuse—yet, press'd To tell thee my Decision?—The compell'd To yield, disgrace Consent: and make Faith doubtful. —I am a Captive. He, who holds not Freedom, Has not his Will his own:—and chuses nothing. POLIPHONTES. Fierce, amid Misery! thou, at once, art brave, And insolent, and wretched!—but, beware, Nor trust, too far, my Pity of thy Poorness. I give thee, yet, some Moments, to resolve. I go, before thee: but, my Guards attend, To bring thee to the Altar. Come, determin'd To swear—and hope my Crown, and live, my Son: Or die, a Slave un-own'd, and lose thy Name. [Is going. EUMENES, (calling after him.) Thou goest then? POLIPHONTES, (stopping.) To expect thee. EUMENES. I will come. And with me, (tremble to be told it,) comes The God, that rais'd my Race to root out Tyrants. Soon shall the Throne thou stol'st no more be Thine: Horror and Penitence shall pale those Eyes, Whose daring Insolence now frown on Virtue. Menace and Insult, then, shall quit thy Voice, And groaning Anguish grind it.—What the Gods Restrain my Hand from reaching, happier Sons Of my immortal Sire shall rise, to execute: And hurl thee from a Power, that hurts Mankind. POLIPHONTES. Here, Narbas! Euricles!—You may return. I leave him to your Lessons. Too too deeply, He feels their past Impression. Teach him better: Or your exacted Heads shall answer to me, For every well-known Help I owe your Hatred. —Narbas! Thy Age, I think, might best be trusted. Experience lays his Dangers open to thee. Thou, as thou lov'st, advise him.—Whether born The Son of Merope, or Thine, no matter. I must adopt him mine,—or Death demands him. [Exit Poliphontes. SCENE III. EUMEMES, NARBAS, EURICLES. EUMENES. Where did this ill-instructed Tyrant learn To threaten, for Persuasion!—I suspect, He does not seem to doubt, but doubts indeed, I share no Blood of Hercules.—He's gone: And call'd me, to his Altar.—Let us follow. NARBAS. Stay.—Whither wou'd such fatal Rashness lead you? EURICLES. The Queen has Friends: howe'er too weak, too few: Who dare defend her Cause. Give us but Time To weigh, and to resolve, and these shall aid you. EUMENES. No.—In an Hour so black, so dire, as This, I task but my own Heart, and Heaven, to aid me. If I must fall, I will.—I go—to try What God forsakes the Friendless. [Going out, meets Merope. SCENE IV. MEROPE and ISMENE. MEROPE. Stay, my Son— Th' Usurper sends me to thee.—Rest, unheard, His Errand: but my own requires thy Ear. It has, perhaps, been told thee, that the Woman Conquers the Queen. —Let no light Credit of a Guilt so shameful Insult the Daughter, Mother, Wife,—ah, me! And Widow—of a King.—Yet, I must go: Must, at the Altar, lend my trembling Hand; And seem—oh, Heaven!— EUMENES. O, Madam!—so, to seem, Were so to be. Can solemn Vows, at Altars, Leave Room for Art's Evasions? See me, sooner, Tingeing the spotted Stone with gushing Blood: And my torn Breast th'unseeming Sacrifice. MEROPE. So look'd, so spoke—so, sometimes, frown'd, Cresphontes. Full of thy godlike Father, copy too, The Confidence, he lent me. He had scorn'd To doubt me, for a Moment, less than Merope. EUMENES. If I was guilty,—think— MEROPE. —No more.—Time presses;— Hear my resolving Will: and curb thy own. Th' Usurper of thy Throne no sooner joins My Hand's suppos'd Consent, than, at the Altar, He swears—in all the Pomp of priestly Witness, To free thee from thy Chains—and, from that Hour, Confirm Succession, thine.— EUMENES. Think, at what Price comes Empire, bought so dear! Rather than see you wed this— MEROPE. Rash, again?— Bound, by an Oath, so witness'd, by the Gods, And All Mycene's Priests—and All her Peers— He dares not break it: and Thou liv'st, to reign. —For me, who have, thenceforth, no Call for Life, I seek thy Father, in the Glooms, below. EUMENES. —No more. —It shall not be.—See! my repugnant Soul Shrinks from th' abhorr'd Conception. The felt God, The God, glows, in me: swells, against Controul: And every springy Nerve is active Fire! Come on, Friends! Father! Mother!—trust my Firmness. See, if I bear a Heart, that brooks this Wrong: That poorly pants, for a base Hour of Life— And let a Woman's Blood outdare a King's. [Going. MEROPE. Oh! stay: return.—Call: stop him. EURICLES. Sir! NARBAS. Prince! MEROPE. Son! EUMENES, (Returning. Look out: see yonder: view my Father's Tomb. Know you his Voice! Are you a Queen? Come listen— I hear him—Hark!—my King, my Father calls! MEROPE. Methinks the God He talk'd of, swells, indeed, his widening Soul, Lifts him above himself—above Mankind. EUMENES. Come—let me lead you to the Altar's Foot. There hear, there, see—there, dwells th'Eternal's Eye! MEROPE. Ah! what is thy Design! EUMENES. To die,—to live. Friends!—in this warm Embrace, divide my Soul. [To Narbas, who presses him tenderly. —Weep not, my Narbas. No Blush, for Deeds unworthy your Instructions, Shall stain Remembrance of the Care, I cost you. Stay thou, that this good Lord returning from me, May find thee, and impart a ripening Hope Whereon your Council may direct and save. On to the Work of Fate—it calls me hence— I hear it, and obey. [Ex. Eum. Mer. and Eur. NARBAS. Away—I wou'd not see thee share my Sorrow. ISMENE. Oh! 'twere too poor a Wish. Heaven knows, I seek No Share,—I long for Power, to bear it, All. NARBAS. Thou art too good, for Courts—where Ruin preys On Innocence; and nought but Guile is safe. —What are thy Thoughts, of this lost Prince's Virtues? ISMENE. I am unskill'd in Men: and, most, in Kings. But, sure! if ever Beauty dwelt in Form, Courage in Gentleness, or Truth in Grandeur, All those adorn'd Perfections meet, in Him. NARBAS. Yet, see! how Heaven, that gave him all these Claims, Forgets 'em, and resigns him.—Let That teach thee, When, soon, as soon they will, thy Splendors fall, Thou losest nothing, but a Right to Woes: ISMENE. Shou'd the Queen, Best, of her Sex! Leave this loud Stage of Pain,—and rest in Death, Oh! teach my willing Feet to find some Gloom, Dark, as my Prospects, deep inclos'd, for Safety; And silent, as the Brow of midnight Sleep! NARBAS. Yes, we will go, my sweet Ismene, go, Where Sorrow's sharpest Eye shall fail to find us. Where we may mix with Men, who ne'er deceiv'd, And Women, born to be, the Charms they look. —There is a Place, which my Eumenes lov'd, Till Youth's fond Hope of Glory dash'd his Peace; Where Nature, plainly noble, knows no Pomp; And Virtue moves no Envy: [Shouts. —Hark! That Cry Bodes Horror—'tis the Signal of some Fate. —Listen, again— [Shouts. ISMENE. Again I hear: and tremble. Who knows, but, now, the Queen's too direful Deed Has ended all her Mis'ries!— NARBAS. No more these Eyes shall find thee, fated King! Cresphontes, and his Race, are, All, no more. ISMENE, at a Window. Hence, from the Temple, to the Palace Gate, The scattring Crowd runs, wide, a thousand Ways: All busied, without View—All, driven, by Terror! SCENE IV. Narbas. Ismene. Euricles, bloody. NARBAS. Breathless and bleeding see! who comes!—O, Euricles! EURICLES. Scarce had I Strength, wedg'd in by crossing Crowds, To stem yon breathing Torrent.—Give me Rest. NARBAS. Eumenes?—does he live? EURICLES. He is—the Son confes'd—of Grecian Gods! NARBAS. What has he suffer'd? EURICLES. Nothing—but, has done— Beyond Example's Boast.—Oh! such a Deed! So terrible! so just!—so fill'd with Wonders! That half Alcides' Labours, scarce were more. NARBAS. And shall he be a King? EURICLES. He is NARBAS. And Merope? Great Mirror of Affliction!—lives She, too? How was it?—say.—My Joys will grow too strong? EURICLES. The Altar, strew'd with Flow'rs, was ready dress'd, The smoking Incense rose, in fragrant Curls, And Hymen's lambent Torches flam'd, serene, Silence, and Expectation's dreadful Stillness, Doubled the solemn Horror of the Scene! —There, Poliphontes stood: and, at his Side, Dumb as a destin'd Victim, stood the Queen. Our Prince's summon'd Hand had touch'd the Altar; His Eye sought Heaven—as if prepar'd to swear. The Tyrant smil'd:—when strait, the Priest look'd pale; The Lights extinguish'd—and the Temple's Roof, Shook by descending Thunder, seem'd to bow! The God! the God! the reverend Starter cry'd, Forbids these baneful Nuptials.—Yes: I HEAR him, The dreadful Prince reply'd: and, at that Word, Leapt, from the Altar, to the Tyrant's Breast— And plung'd the sacred Axe of Sacrifice, Snatch'd, like a Lightning's Flash! and reach'd his Life. —He fell—and o'er him while with pendant Eye Th' indignant Hero hung, with Arm new-rais'd, Base, from behind, pale Erox pierc'd his Side. —Red, in his mingled Blood, and rising Anger, He heard the Crowd's protective Cry—turn'd short, And buried in his Brow the rapid Steel. Then, to the Altar's Height sublimely sprung, Stood, Monarch, all-confess'd; and wav'd the Throng. Come, let me guide you to this Work of Heav'n. Haste, and partake it—fly— NARBAS. Oh! Happy Day— [Exeunt. SCENE the Temple of Hymen. Eumenes discover'd on the Altar with the Axe of Sacrifice in his Hand. Merope kneeling, Priests, Attendants and Guards. [Trumpets and Shouts heard. MEROPE. Now, now, ye Gods, my Pray'rs are heard. [A loud Clap of Thunder. EUMENES. Hark! Madam, Heav'n approves! th' attentive Gods Hear Hearts, and make Voice needless—Doubt not then They are the good Minds Guardians—my Deliverance Proves how they lov'd your Virtue: in your Safety I feel their Blessing perfect—may I live In Deeds, not Words, to thank the Good they gave. MEROPE. Deeds, Words, and Thoughts are theirs— Heav'n claims us all. EUMENES to the People. Hear me, my People, take your King, and with him, Heav'n's best Gift, your Liberty—Haughtier Monarchs Place Greatness in Oppression: Let my Throne Find Safety, but in saving— Pride is too apt to harden prosp'rous Pow'r, But he, whose Youth is chasten'd by Distress Makes Subjects Happy, and himself ador'd. Enter Narbas, Euricles and Ismene. All speaking, kneeling. Hail! and be ever bless'd, O King! O Queen! MEROPE. Rise—and lament no more, ye happy Friends Of Virtue, and of Heaven!—See! what the Gods Have done—to shame Suspicion, into Faith! Oh! never let the Innocent despair: The Hand, that made, can save: and best knows when. [To Eumenes. —Son of Alcides!—for, what Heart, but His, Nourish'd in Misery! by Wants obstructed! Ere sprung, like thine, at Youth's first Shoot, to Glory? Trod on a Tyrant, and redeem'd a People? EUMENES. 'Tis but the low, the last, the lightest Duty Of a King's Hand, to dare. 'Tis His, to save; To think, to hear, to labour, to discern, To form, to remedy,—to be—but one: Yet, act, and love, and fear, and feel,—for All. —Oh, Madam! I am yours, midst all these Claims. Be Those my Glory's, This my Duty's Care, To add my Royal Father's Love, to mine: And, with a doubled Rev'rence, seek your Comfort. —Narbas! what Power can Language lend my Love, To paint the Joy, Thy Sense of Pleasure gives me? Thou Source, and Soul, and Author, of my Virtues: Suspend we Thoughts, thus tender.—Let us, now, Summon Mycene's Chiefs, and calm her People. [To Merope. Come, Madam! He who reigns, but climbs to Care; Tho' Safe, his Throne, he finds no Softness, there. Dangers, and Doubts, and Toils, each Moment seize, Hang on his Business, and perplex his Ease. Bright but by Pomp of Woe, Kings shine in vain; Envy'd for Anguish, and adorn'd for Pain. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>