<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Wilson, John, 1720-1789</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Wilson, John, 1720-1789</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">wilson john 1720 1789</field>
      <field name="author_text">Wilson, John, 1720-1789</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">18th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1760's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V2.0754.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240355</field>
      <field name="date_text">1764</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460358</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Earl Douglas ; Or, Generosity Betray'd ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Earl Douglas ; Or, Generosity Betray'd ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="title_facet">earl douglas or generosity betrayd</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">earl douglas or generosity betrayd</field>
      <field name="title_text">Earl Douglas ; Or, Generosity Betray'd ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="year_display">1764</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1764</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1764</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460358&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460358&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Wilson, John, 1720-1789&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;wilson john 1720 1789&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Earl Douglas ; Or, Generosity Betray'd ; A Tragedy&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;earl douglas or, generosity betrayd&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1764&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1764&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Wilson, John&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1720&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1789&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Earl Douglas ; Or, Generosity Betray'd&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Glasgow&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed by R. Urie, for the Author [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1764&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872246-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv20754&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 18th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;18th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Earl Douglas ; Or, Generosity Betray'd&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 160 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Earl Douglas.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1764.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Unknown.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">EARL DOUGLAS; OR, GENEROSITY BETRAY'D. A TRAGEDY.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">To her Grace, MARGARET, Duchess of DOUGLAS. The following Tragedy is, with the most profound respect, humbly inscribed by, Her Grace's most humble Servant, The AUTHOR.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Persons of the Drama. MEN. James II. King of Scotland, about ten years of age. William, Earl of Douglas. Sir David Douglas, Brother to the Earl. Lord Malcolm Fleming, their cousin and tutor. Sir William Douglas, another cousin. Sir Alexander Livingston, Regent during the King's minority. Sir William Crichton, Lord High Chancellor. Crichton, Jun. son to the Chancellor. WOMEN. The Countess dowager of Douglas. Lady Beatrix Douglas, sister to the Earl. SCENE, EDINBURGH. Sometimes in Earl Douglas's Lodgings; sometimes in the Castle. TIME, from Sun-rising to Sun-setting.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. SCENE I. An antichamber in Earl Douglas' lodging. Enter Lord Fleming, newly returned from his Embassy to France, with Sir William Douglas. Sir William Douglas embracing, Welcome, my Lord, to our unhappy country,— Unhappy, since our upstart Rulers rais'd Fierce Discord from the depth of hateful hell, To bathe sharp Scottish swords in Scottish breasts. Each potent tyrant treads the humble down; Industry faints; on rapine, Rapine preys; And Treach'ry lurks in ambush to destroy. At breasts of fainting mothers, babes expire; The full-grown drop, requesting help in vain; For meagre Famine in his iron paw Grasps hard the heart, and slow wrings out the life, And all the ways and fields with carnage strays. Fleming. This town, late all alive with chearful crowds, Mourns her green streets. Sir William Douglas. There fun'rals funerals press, As birds in sable flocks seek ev'ning shades. The grave's enrich'd, and glutted with our spoils, Hell banquets on our woes, and quaffs our tears. Fleming. Our savage rulers on good subjects prey; And each, by turns, their sacred monarch seize; Whom, in a coffer cram'd, the Regent steals; Then to his rock by force the Chanc'lor bears, And, in their wrath, lead rapine, famine, death, And devastation, through a bleeding land. Sir William Douglas. Now, weak by mutual wounds, despis'd, abhor'd, They make a truce; and on lord Douglas fawn; Recal him to the honours, trusts, and powers, By birth his due. His journey scarce begun, Lord Chanc'lor meets him, leads him to his house; Where splendid feasts, and princely shews consume Three whole expensive days. To-day he meets The King, and Regent, in Edina's castle. Fleming. Their mutual wounds yet bleeding, they embrace; Some dire design's in view.—Their hate burns inward. They fear lord Douglas, upright as his sire, Who hated ev'ry knave, the highest most; Condemn'd their crimes, and dar'd their highest rage. For this in dungeon thrice his virtue suffer'd; But still dispell'd the storm, and brighter shone His country's darling, glory and defence. How rev'rent have I seen our peers arise! And bowing, his superior merit own. Sir William Douglas. It was his due; for a long line of heroes Had glorious labour'd in the fields of fame, And shone in council; down from valiant Sholto Not one degenerate: yet most gen'rous he. Fleming. The poor supported, humble virtue rais'd, Learning caress'd, and industry rewarded, Form'd a melodious concert in his praise; The tyrant's dread, and patron of mankind. With friendship's last dear accents to my care He left his sons; when his great manly spirit, In mortal conflict with a fiery fever, Felt strong commotion; on the verge of heav'n The friend serenely shone. He graspt my hand; “In thee a father to my sons survives; Half of my soul. O form their youth for glory. Them greatly teach to suffer, greatly dare, To live for Scotland and for Scotland die; And glory still in virtue more than rank.”— This said, he dy'd.—His trust I'll not deceive. Sir William Douglas. Your pious care has in his sons restor'd His ev'ry virtue. All his dauntless truth, His noble scorn of slav'ry, and of wealth, Except for gen'rous ends, adorn his heir. His last night's lib'ral deeds disclose his soul: To you, for ever, Wigton he returns; Great lord of Galloway his brother shines; His mother's portion, doubled, waits his sister; The pious countess' charity may flow, Wide as her will, embracing all the wretched. A divine splendor on his morn of life Bursts radiant: joy attends where-e'er he moves; On heav'n's blest confines he sublimely soars; Yet ever listens to the stifled sigh Of modest merit, sinking in distress; And arm'd with power, flies rapid to relieve. Fleming. His zeal burns ardent for his country's good. How sped your embassy? Will Ross and Crawford See Europe's richest source of wealth and power, Our gift from nature, drain'd by greedy strangers? Or raise their country empress of the main, Their King dread arbiter of Europe's fate, Shall freedom's throne be firmly fixt in Scotland? Sir William Douglas. Ross offers all his islands, ports, and harbours; These yield convenient stations, active hands, Well practis'd to the trade, and cheap to hire; Thousands now idle, turbulent, and desp'rate Through want, may, thus employed, abound in wealth, And bear our floating thunders o'er the main. The mighty peers burn to embrace their cousins, And hence will hold as theirs his friends and foes. Fleming. Then safely waits on Douglas' rising greatness Count of fair Longueville; great duke of Touraine, Besides ten thousand crowns of annual gold He counts as marshal of the Gallic powers. Sir William Douglas. These he devotes t'advance the Scottish fishing. Illustrious youth! Heav'n thus for ever pour His choicest blessings on his happy head. Fleming. Just is your joy; you share in Douglas' success, Blest with his friendship, and his sister's love. Sir William Douglas. They're all my pride; our love began with life, And death alone shall quench my growing ardor. Fleming. Your noble uncle took you from the nurse: His countess often set you on her knee Beside her daughter, kissing both by turns, And bade her daughter kiss her future husband. Sir William Douglas. But, ah! our vast disparity of fortune! She's form'd to grace a throne, and bless a kingdom. I cannot bear to think I'll marr her greatness. In sportive youth, I with her brethren oft Have plan'd our future friendship's destin'd course; How bold we would in senates raise, and stand Freedom's firm bulwark, and her en'mies dread: Or how, with me, my brethren they would call Companions of their arms, to marshal fields; How fierce we'd thunder forth, and blast the foe; Invulnerable by our mutual aid: Return with trophies crown'd; mine I will throw At her dear feet, o'erpaid if she approves. Would you believe young Crichton rivals me? Fleming. Such rivals you may scorn; the blood of Douglas Can only join with heroes of its kind: Who to the dance prefers the painful march; Deep midnight studies, to the late amour; And honours torn from foes, to ladies favours: Whose manly face becomes the crested helm; Whose limbs agile in massy armour move, And fearless, as the bold war-horse he rides, Dares thunder thro' the iron ranks of war. Sir William Douglas. Were she the prize, to be by battle gain'd, (A brighter prize than palms, or crowns, or thrones,) For her, how would I fight! in her, how blest! But, if our kingdom nodded to its fall, By wild ambition's rage, who could be tame? Or, should dire Tyranny his iron arm, To crush our land extend, who would not rise To break its force, or with his country fall? Fleming. I know the noble maid would scorn the man, Whose grov'ling spirit basely could resign Glory and manhood for soft female charms, And, for a fond caress, give up his country: But him would prize, who, when the brazen voice Of war roars loud, and Scotia calls, To arms, From her most fond embrace would bravely burst, Just snatch a hasty kiss, and say, Farewel; Rush to the field, and blaze before the van. Such, like her sires, you are; such she must love. Sir William Douglas. Haste we to glad the brothers with the news Of our success; for sure fraternal love Ne'er higher flam'd, nor in two worthier breasts. Fleming. Haste! let us free them from their en'mies snare; Their sire, now lost; they're all their country's hope. SCENE II. COUNTESS and Lady BEATRIX. Lady Beatrix. Can't Heav'n's fair light, with all its rays reveal'd, Dispel that gloom, which clouds your widow'd heart. Your children, with their lives, would buy your ease; You! who have nurs'd, with care, their tender age, And with demestic virtues bless'd their sire. Countess. So ev'ry wife and mother ought: but few, With love and duty, are so well repaid. One soul moves in you all.—A gen'rous soul! O much lov'd heirs of my dear husband's virtues! How just to grieve such sire! Such husband lost! This town the mem'ry of that loss renews.— Ah! mournful loss! never to be repair'd! Here oft he shone, of Scottish peers the chief:— Here now he shines no more. O my dear children! Lady Beatrix. Just was your grief, in absence of your sons. Pensive alone, in converse sad and absent; For them your fond maternal heart still trembled: But their return may yield your soul delight. Countess. Youth finds delight, in converse or retirement, And sings alone, or sparkles in the ball: The raging stream, the tempest or the foe, With terror strike not her gay chearful breast. Not so the anxious wife espous'd to care: The mother portion'd out in all her brood, Husband or child abroad, a thousand fears, All strange to youth, attack her tender breast. At drops of rain she shrinks; each breeze forebodes A hurricane; each cloud with thunder swells; She sees them struggling with the stream, or foe; And hears them shriek for help, or wounded groan: Their absent moments counts: her heart and eyes Are still abroad, but pain'd with every view: For busy fancy, to their moving shape, Moulds every tree, while disappointment waits, Keenly intent, to stab each infant hope. So fell my hopes of my lov'd Lord's return; Who ne'er return'd, since that sad solemn day He left his castle, with a numerous train Of gallant squires, brave knights, and noble lords. Oft! oft he said, Farewel! and oft he kiss'd The starting tear from either flowing eye.— These eyes still weep!—but see my Lord no more! Around me still his circling arms I feel; The mighty heavings of his manly breast; And glowing of his cheek, close pressing mine. Lady Beatrix. Then, round each brother thrown a valiant arm, My sons, he said, as you begin, proceed In virtue, goodness, and fraternal love: Be brave, be upright, gen'rous, and humane; Act like your sires, and seek your country's good Nor enter both where my false foes command: While one is free, the other is secure. Countess. Cautious, as virtuous, would my sons but mind The whole advice! Why lodg'd they both with Crichton? Three long slow heavy nights, three joyless days, Clogged with care, crawl'd off, ere they return'd. Lady Beatrix. At last they came and unsolicited: Your gen'rous Douglas Countess. Order'd his affairs, Like those that take farewel of life.—Sad omen! His sire, with solemn counsels, and farewels, Set out, and ne'er return'd. I flew t'attend him On love's swift wings,—and found but—Breathless clay! This bounty's lost on me.—I know no joy In gay attendance, feasts, or rich attire. My Lord's high rank requir'd a load of state: But now my glory's gone! my crown's fall'n off! These eyes for ever set, I shone to please. My sun is set: you, like three beauteous stars, Chear my sad night; else, gloomy as the grave. You now are all my ornaments and joy.— And, lo! my sons! to glad my mournful heart. SCENE III. Enter Earl DOUGLAS and Sir DAVID. Douglas. My friends shall joy, while I can gladness give: My fortune, heart, and life,—my soul is yours. Sir David. My brother's deeds proclaim his heart aloud.— But, ah! the deep-felt pain of generous minds, Opprest with favours not to be repaid. Heav'n send a time, to shew how much I hold My life's blood cheaper than my brother's love. Douglas. Few are his joys, who feels but for himself: 'Tis like a God to feel with human kind, And feast on happiness with all the blest. The generous flame of goodness bursts from heaven On the benev'lent heart, and beaming thence On all around, from every glad'ned face Again reflected, comes redoubled back. Countess. Thine arm, my daughter. My glad heart's o'ercharg'd, Thy lively eyes run o'er.—Let us retire. O worthy sons, how could I bear your loss! —O killing thought!—How oft that thought intrudes! O spare me, Heaven!—That loss I cannot bear! O hear my pray'rs! Long spare to me my children. [Exit Countess and L. B. SCENE IV. Earl DOUGLAS and Sir DAVID. Douglas. O brother! O my soul's far dearer half! Why are these eyes cast down? that lovely face A stranger to its wonted chearfulness? It grieves my soul to see thee seem but sad. A friend's the brother of our choice, but heav'n In thee has chosen me the kindest friend. Come to my ardent breast, and let us swear Indissoluble friendship; endless love. Sir David Douglas. By all that's fear'd, or hop'd, or lov'd, by man, Nothing shall e'er divide this breast from thine. Whatever fate bestows, with thee I'll share, In life, in death, inseparable still. Douglas. Spare oaths, for friendship's wrought thro' all thy soul, Alike we joy to bless the human kind. But, ah! how impotent is human power! Sir David. Each knave plants ills that thrive to many an age; Nor can the gen'rous Patriot root them up, And bid the blessings they expell'd re-bloom. Douglas. What I can do, I will; and never more Did our dear country claim the Patriot's care. Through all the day for her my heart is pain'd; By night in dreams I hear her genius mourn, And seek a Douglas to relieve her woes. My sires rise glorious in their mighty deeds, And, frowning on me, ask why Scotia's groans Disturb their rest, while I their honour's Heir? Ye venerable shades! I'll heir your worth. To me, my country shall not sigh in vain: 'Mong her assembled Peers, I'll be the first To seek her good; to reconcile her sons, Forgive my wrongs; and make the rest forgive. Sir David Douglas. The wrongs they've done, could foes as well forgive, All might be well; but villains ever fear, And dread the vengeance of the injur'd brave. Douglas. My honest soul all low suspicion scorns. Sir David. In happy time our guardian has return'd, When much we need his sage experienc'd counsel. Douglas. Well merits he our confidence and love; Our father's dearest friend; our second father; Who, skill'd in all the Greek and Roman wisdom, Joins to the sage the Patriot and the Hero. SCENE V. Enter CHANCELLOR and CRICHTON, Jun. Chancellor. Love makes me too familiarly intrude, And from your gen'rous friendship hope excuse. Douglas. Lord regent reconcil'd! my Prince's favour; A peaceful prospect of the highest honours; To you I owe: when friends exceed his love, May Douglas bend before his foes in war. Chancellor. Such sentiments will suit your glorious race. Crichton, Jun. Your virtue's fame, like sacred incense spread, Delighting earth, and grateful to the skies, First charm'd mine ear; your virtue, now my soul. My brave deliv'rer! When th'enraged bull, On each strong horn, presented instant death, Your thund'ring sword soon blasted all his strength. Douglas. Such aid from me the meanest had receiv'd.— SCENE VI. Enter FLEMING and Sir WILLIAM DOUGLAS. Douglas. Welcome, my Cousins, to my house and heart! Report your success, all you see are friends. Fleming. Trust not too soon; for some have long been foes! Chancellor. Let not distrust pepetuate Scotia's plagues, Now tott'ring on destruction's dreadful brink; Suppress resentment, and fly swift to save. Sir William Douglas When Scotia's state was govern'd by her peers, She rose from ruin to renown and power: Shut from her councils, peaceful they retir'd, And to their country sacrific'd revenge, While o'er their heads their base inferiors rose. Fleming. Our nobles suffer'd much, my share was large. My wife beheld her father's house destroyed; Their high descent, their royal blood profan'd: My life pursu'd, I bore the dungeon long. Lord Douglas knows the suff'rings of his sire. Chancellor. Yet gen'rous he forgives! O my good Lords! Remit the past; let penitence attone, And future friendship live, for former wrongs. Douglas. 'Tis godlike to forgive repenting foes. To be implacable ill suits frail man, Who daily errs, and daily pardon craves. Fleming, giving Letters. My honest bus'ness, friend or foe may know; These from the king of France, salute you Count Of Longueville, and Touraine's potent duke, With all the powers and rev'nues of your sires. All. God bless Touraine's great Duke. Earl Douglas to Sir David. Dear Longueville! Hence in both kingdoms we united shine; In Scotland, Douglas and his Galloway; In France, Touraine and his dear Longueville: And Wigton's generous care shall find reward. Chancellor aside. Hell blast their thriving greatness!—Hell I call T'assist my hate! Their virtue bribes the skies! Sir William Douglas. Behold this bond by Ross and Crawford seal'd. They hold your en'mies theirs: to-night expect them, With noble peers who dwell beyond the Forth. Chancellor aside. Enough t'alarm the Regent's rage and pride. My royal charge requires me, but my son [Aloud. Desires to stay. Adieu, most honour'd Lords. Exeunt cæteri. Manet Sir William Douglas. My uncle bred me as his son to greatness; His sons have ever as a brother lov'd me: How gen'rous are their hearts! How great their souls! This wond'rous maid! The glories of her mind Outshines even all her heav'nly beauty's brightness! She moves an angel! Heav'n beams from her eyes! And lo she comes, majestic in her charms! Enter Lady Beatrix. Your safe return and success give us joy. Sir William Douglas. Heav'n, and your gen'rous heart, reward your goodness, Thou miracle of truth, and gen'rous love! But what can I return to all your kindness? Lady Beatrix. A num'rous family of noble friends, Earth's richest treasure, shall requite my brothers: And me, your stedfast truth and virtuous love. Sir William Douglas. More gen'rous still! with such increase of fortune. Lady Beatrix. Truth scorns to alter, or by wealth, or want. Sir William Douglas. How exquisite thy joy's cœlestial virtue! Thou join'd our souls; nor shall they e'er divide. Fools in a thoughtless, gay, delirium rove, As passion whirls, they either lothe or love; And, if their bonds unbroken must remain, They fret, they rage, and struggle with their chain. Lady Beatrix. But happy they whom heav'nly virtue binds, Unfelt she ties consenting kindred minds: Truth, honour, reason, gentle love remain The shining links of her immortal chain: By these confin'd, the happy captives stay, And bask, and brighten in her heav'nly day. Sir William Douglas. Th'Eternal rais'd her adamantine throne Of solid rock, coeval with his own. Below the world's, its fixt foundation lies, And high as heav'n's, he bad the summit rise. Dissolve shall earth, and heav'n shall melt away, Ere virtue's bands dissolve, her power decay. Exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. SCENE I. A Hall in the Castle. Chancellor solus. Their success, whom I hate, burns up my vitals. All hell's within me.—Livingston and I, Each 'gainst the other, sought the father's aid; Who proud reply'd, “The sooner two such knaves Should be destroy'd, the better for the land, And honest men.”—That pride shall slay his sons. The letters Douglas wrote, I kept at Crichton; Mine, in his name, must have to madness fir'd The Regent: since this Douglas is too generous To ruin him; he must this Douglas ruin: Then fall himself with more to raise my son. Enter Livingston the Regent. My lord, that friendship to our hate succeeds, I count the greatest blessing life could yield. Chancellor aside. Our hate has only borrowed friendship's veil: Could I salute thee with a breath as fatal As that of Basilisk's, or my embrace Blast thee like light'ning's flash; they should be hearty. [They embrace and salute. Chancellor to the Regent weeping. My thoughts, too big for speech, choke up its passage. How could I quarrel with so great, so good, So wise a man! The support of the state!— Forgive me, Heav'n;—and good your grace forgive me. Livingston. Travelling, I from the wise of ev'ry clime; Reading, from annals of all ages; learn'd, That concord oft exalts the lowest states, And discord soon the highest lays in dust. While friends, we wealth enjoy'd and lordly power; Since foes, our wealth decays, our power is blasted: Rude Insolence authority now spurns; And Anarchy stalks hideous thro' the land. Unite we then t'enforce the slighted laws, Depress the proud, and make the bold obey. Chancellor. O grac'd with all persuasion's winning force! Thine eloquence at pleasure sways my soul. True are thy words! Our ruin all desire; Us Commons hate; and us the Lords despise. Livingston. Them I despise. I'll raise the royal power So high, that proudest peers shall humbly bend Before the lowest officer of court. Chancellor. Curse on his pride, he thinks he props the skies; [Aside. I know your grace's zeal, to raise our Prince To god-like sway; but arduous is the task: The peers are mighty, and disdain to serve; And on their head the Douglasses will shine. That clan is num'rous, daring, true, and steady; Their chief young, vig'rous, lib'ral, brave, and popular, Most royal-like in state, and high behaviour; Creating knights, and scatt'ring wealth and honours. Livingston. Audacious stripling! all his father's pride To his was mild humility.— Chancellor. Pray, hear me. This morning, his ambassador, Lord Fleming, Brought a seal'd treaty from the Gallic monarch For mutual aid: the like from Ross and Crawford, His uncle's son presents: to night these Lords With all the peers beyond the Forth will meet Touraine's great duke, Livingston. Touraine! Chancellor. And Longueville! Marshal of France, with all the powers and honours His sires enjoy'd, and all their boundless rev'nues. Livingston. 'Tis Fleming's daring work; the heads are mighty: Ross in the north reigns king, and o'er the isles; All Fife and Perthshire Crawford sways at will; The south and west attend Lord Douglas' call, Chancellor. The grandeur of that lofty house you know; His strong allies; the cheiftains of the name: His strengths, and wide domains; his daring leagues With kings abroad, and king-like Lords at home. His court I view'd; I mingled with his train, Which swells in thousands for his daily state. Squires, knights, and lords crouding from ev'ry wind, Conducted him to town. Here splendid rode The ever famous Keiths; there mighty Humes; The graceful Hepburns, and the noble Hays; The valiant Seton, and the worthy Ker; The bold Dunbar, with gen'rous Ramsay came; The potent Scot, and Graham of high descent. Livingston. Heav'ns! what a list of peers!—t'attend a traitor. Chancellor. Well, I shall pass the flower of Annandale, By Johnston led, and those that drink the Nith With Maxwell bold, Montgom'ry, Cunningham, And Boyd, with westland Lords: young Kennedy, The cousin of our King: The Somervile And Hamilton, with Clydesdale's gallant chiefs. The brave Carmichael bore the spear he broke Unhorsing Clarence on his crest display'd, When conqu'ring England first stood check'd in France. Livingston. Say, in a word, the whole of Scottish Peers Attend a rebel boy. Chancellor. Let me but mark The mightiest of the name; the sage Dalkeith, Great Angus, Abercorn, and princely Nithsdale.— Livingston. Hell! I can hear no more.—Douglas is King, And rebels all our Lords, who prop his pride. Chancellor. Had you but seen their grandeur, as they march'd On neighing steeds, which trode the earth with scorn, And mark'd what dignity their brows adorn'd! O'er all the rest, a daring lofty air The Douglasses distinguish'd!—Valiant name! Superior to them all the brothers shone; Their dress, their arms, and equipage the same. Two seraphs in the prime of heavenly youth They seem'd, conducting a fair band of heroes: And Fleming with them rode, as god rever'd. Livingston. Tortures! How shall we blast their odious glories? For theirs or ours must suddenly expire. Chancellor. Provoke not fate, but yield; the chiefs are gracious; They may forgive their own, their father's foes. Livingston. Distraction! Age, experience, legal power, Yield to unskilful youth, to wild ambition Give up the nation, and the King to ruin. Chancellor. To ruin;—no:—there's many a worthy Lord To aid their councils.—Well Lord Fleming's prudence Would suit my place, and noble Douglas' yours. Livingston. Accurs'd be Fleming,—Douglas,—all the traitors. I know Lord Fleming,—and I know Lord Chanc'lor. Chancellor. I know thee too.— Livingston. What know'st thou me to be? Chancellor. A worthy Lord; the Atlas of our state; Learn'd, good, and wise; my friend, my country's father. Livingston. Excuse my warmth; thou know'st what deadly hate 'Twixt me and Fleming burns: how strong its causes! Chancellor seeing the King entering. I know't, my Lord; and late Lord Douglas' spite, Whose bold ancestors claim'd their Sov'reign's crown. SCENE II. Enter King. Whence the foundation for so bold a claim? Livingston. From Huntingdon, the brother of our King, Three beauteous daughters sprang; and from the first, Baliol and Cumin; Douglas heirs their right: The Bruce, next male in blood, the second weds; From him your right descends, which God maintain, In spite of Douglas and of all your foes. Chancellor. If Douglas be a foe, he's near of kin. His father of your royal aunt was born, Whose sister shar'd your hapless uncle's bed. Livingston. His tragic death forbids to trust thy kin; Whom, in his father's life, his uncle starv'd, O had you seen him beg; but beg in vain, The coarsest crumbs with piercing famish'd cries; And seen him tear his flesh, and gnaw his bones; You would have own'd, crowns tempt to direst deeds: This mov'd his uncle to destroy your sire. In vain the haughty Cumins were reduc'd, The Baliols exil'd, mighty Albany, And Athol fell, all rich in royal blood, While Douglas reigns with all their power and pride; Their daring blood fierce raging in his veins, And thinks, like these, his sov'reign's crown his right. Chancellor. Douglas is bold and young, and such aspire; Rise, Douglas cannot, but his King must fall; And more than half the nation wait his nod. All wish him King; his fathers claim'd the crown; His leagues with foreign kings secure their aid; His allies here have harbours, ships, and men: The mainland Ross's-islanders infest, And Douglas' borderers the inland shires. Yet loyal Douglas meditates no war. In his domains he royal power defies; Such rights, he says, were granted to his sires. He's fam'd for virtue, and a patriot soul. My friendship trusts to fame, and fears not Douglas. Livingston. All demagogues virtue's fair liv'ry wear; A seemly dress to catch the staring croud; But only wear it till they gain their end; Then throw the cumb'rous rob abhor'd aside. Their guilt glares hideous through the thin disguise. Awake, O King! Douglas thy throne invades; And if, alone, Lord-Chanc'lor sees no danger, The more I tremble for my sov'reign's safety. King. The brav'ry of his sires, his early worth Such honours gain; I'll be like my dear cousin, And be admir'd and follow'd: He is virtuous; And good men's power secure their neighbour's safety. Livingston. True, said the poet, whom the world admires, Bad is that government where many rule. Rule he supreme, who holds from heav'n his right; And at his will the laws and people sway. Kings, while they can, must crush each rival's pow'r. All deeds are lawful which a king preserve. Chancellor. Alas! my Lord, I'm a plain simple man, Deny'd your eagle-eye, consummate skill, Learning profound, and vast state-weilding wisdom: I'm caught with seeming worth, and crampt with scruples, Yet prize no friend above my sov'reign King. You, with a glance, see through the thick disguise, And well you know to use entrusted power, [Giving a sealed paper. Our King, by this, requests you well to guard His safety and the states; and what you do For that, declares to be his special will. King. You urg'd my hand to this, and spoke of plots Against my life and crown: but harm not Douglas, I love him well: you love him too, Lord Chancellor? Chancellor. I do: He shall my utmost care employ. [Exit King. Here, while our King his fav'rite cousins feasts, By copious wine, and free familiar speech, We'll search their inmost souls: detain the chiefs Till all their train retires. Your grace is wise To know what then the public good demands. [Exeunt. SCENE III. A Hall in Douglas's Lodgings. Lady BEATRIX reading, enter CRICHTON, Jun. Crichton, [Aside Left here my father's spy: I'm real friend To these young Lords, and this bright maid's adorer. —O beauteous Wonder!—I could gaze for ever! [She rises to retire; he falls at her feet. O leave me not—Thou glory of thy sex! Picture of Heaven! and pattern of perfection! My soul thee worships; all her powers adore thee. Lady Beatrix. I scorn the fops who flatter, cring, and kneel, And impiously rob Heaven, to tickle folly: But prize the man whose words are big with sense; Whose manly deeds will merit admiration; Who speaks what ought to please; nor doubts I know it. [Exit. Crichton, Jun. Solus. O lovely and admir'd! Thy awful frowns, Like Heav'n's resistless fires, dart ev'ry glance, Through my dissolving frame; but killing charm. What dignity adorns thy graceful air! How fair thy form! thy virtue how divine! O Love! O torment! O despairing anguish! Enter Chancellor, in a profound Soliloquy. What splendor shines! what happiness dwells here! Love beams from breast to breast of high and low. What joy t'a friend were this! to me what torment! The dame, and guardian, with glad transport view Each virtue springing in—Mine en'mies brood, Whose ruin I pursue in friendship's dress— —Most base!—O had I never seem'd their friend! Then had I never known their lovely virtues, Nor Heav'n's blest voice in thunder shook my soul; Saying, These bear my image; touch not these,— In effigy then can I murder Heav'n! And butcher Virtue in her loveliest form? Shall I hug ruin for the sake of virtue? Douglas when known will rise his King's delight, His country's darling; I shall sink abhor'd;— My shame still black'ning, as his glories brighten.— —I cannot bear the prospect; perish he, With all that's virtuous. Perish I, myself, Ere thus the sun of Douglas triumph o'er me. Crichton, Jun. Starting from his Revery. Must Douglas fall! dreadful suspicions croud [Aside. On my distracted mind. Thick flew dispatches To Livingston; my sire, as Mediator, Lord Douglas's sent by me: from me receiv'd The answers: still Lord Regent read in wrath; And yet his answers ever pleas'd Lord Douglas. All is not fair—his trust has been abus'd. To gen'rous friendship treachery's repaid. Chancellor, observing his Son. Still charm the virtues of thy new-gain'd friends? Crichton, Junior. The more fair Virtue's seen, the more she charms: Safe, plain, and easy are her artless ways; With face erect, her eyes look streight before; For dauntless is her march, her steps are sure. Not so pale Fraud; now here she turns, now there, Still seeking darker shades, secure in none; Looks ever back, and wheeling often round, Runs headlong to the ruin she would shun. Chancellor aside. Plagues! my own son, with pencil smear'd in hell, My picture draws; but pours profuse on theirs Heav'n's glories blending in assemblage bright. Well, my philosopher, since thou hast learn'd To moralize so sagely, strive to mix The useful with the honest: study profit; And mix with all a wond'rous deal of caution. Men are not what they seem: we see the mask, But not the man, till vice disdain a veil. Crichton. My love, and friendship's bright cœlestial flame, Such dark suspicions banish from my breast. Chancellor. Whom dost thou love? Crichton. Lord Douglas's lovely sister; Her beauty and her virtue— Chancellor. Yes. Her portion May charm a King. Stand not aloof admiring: Be bold and forward. Women love the bold. Crichton. I'm fill'd with awe; such sanctity of manners, And dignity of soul, like angels guard her; My mind corrected in her presence stands, Her judgment waiting with a holy dread; And all her thoughts my soul doth purify, As for th'inspection of a heav'nly eye.0 Such virtue, with so dazling beauty crown'd, Is like divinity with thunder arm'd, To blast who dare approach with thoughts profane. [Exit. Chancellor Solus. Heav'n wills the worst to mend.—Should this succeed, My son will higher rise than fraud can heave him. I lov'd his mother well—then virtue charm'd me.— Him may it ever charm.—For him I'm wicked.— Oh! may he never know my inward tortures! Once more, O Heaven, after a long neglect, My soul looks upward.—Ah! with what dismay!— Yet bliss begins to dawn within my breast. Hence envy, base suspicion, hellish malice;— How blest the soul ne'er felt your dire dominion! But, Ah!—these letters—Yes—they'll all reveal,— How, in my wickedness, I am entangled! By means unjust when wicked mortals strive To undeserved power and wealth to rise; These very means their flattering hopes betray, And when they seek repentance guard their way. No peace, no rest their tortur'd breasts can find: Detection flames, and vengeance roars behind; Guilt with a thousand terrors drives them on: From crime to crime they rush, and are undone. [Exit.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. SCENE I. A Hall in Earl Douglas's Lodgings. Earl DOUGLAS, FLEMING, and the CHANCELLOR. Chancellor, giving Letters. These bear the friendship of your cousin King, These from Lord Regent, with our select friends, Beg you to meet and treat of high affairs, Which at their meeting must th'estates employ. Douglas to Fleming. With equal friendship I their love embrace. Read these, and say who can such kindness scorn. Fleming. The words are fair; such oft foul hate conceal; Dissembling suits a court, as courtiers say; But ev'ry honest mind such conduct scorns. Chancellor. Too true, good Lord: too oft the Courtier's words Are foreign to his heart; their jealous eyes Watch ev'ry step. Their friendship is, at best, A gentle torture to explore the soul: Oft a fair engine with destruction charg'd, To burst at once, and crush th'unwary wretch. Beware of trusting courtiers, good Lord Douglas. Douglas. I scorn the thought which fears to be explor'd: And what are cens'ring or applauding worlds, Whose voice can neither make me blest nor wretch'd. Chancellor. Your sentiments I praise; yet honest fame Is a fair ornament; dishonest, stains Even your high station. Fleming. What ill fame dares touch him! Chancellor. 'Tis said, your borderers, us'd to plund'ring foes, The inland spoil; whom you from justice shield; Too jealous of your rights: your rights and powers Came from your sov'reign's and your country's love; Claim loyal service, and subjection due; Not discontented wrath, and bold resistance. Shame springs from pride; ambition's big with woe: And, when from greatness great mischiefs arise, Their country's ruins crush the great disturbers. Douglas. Who hurts the innocent shall feel my vengeance. Chancellor. I'm rudely free; but friendship rudely pulls The friend from unseen ruin's dreadful brink; While selfish flatt'rers won't offend to save. Douglas. Well doth your salutary freedom please: The sickly eye lothes all-revealing light; But on the sound its glories grateful pours. Chancellor. Your faults need but be seen to be reform'd: My crimes, alas! are of more heinous kind, And may provoke your wrath.—But spare your country. Revere your glorious sires; nor let their blood, Which freely flow'd to save the land, be vain: For what avails deliv'rance from the foe, To fall by mutual wounds? The King, Lord Regent, Request your speedy presence: you can heal Our breaches. Your great power can force tranquillity. Fleming. Trust not his words, dear Douglas. Thus decoy'd, With thy great sire, I bore the dungeon's horrors. He, true like thee, would trust our courtiers words; But foul he found their deeds, when kindest these. Chancellor. O Scotland, Scotland! know thy woes no end? Accept these tears;—thy Crichton can no more:— Fleming, what will convince thee? See my tears; They flow not frequent, nor for trivial cause. Mark my plain truth;—almost too harsh for friendship: Will flatt'rers for men's welfare risk their favour? Or trusts thou oaths? That awful last appeal Of mortals to the justice of Omnipotence; Devise an oath confirm'd by each solemnity Religion knows: I'll pledge my deathless soul. Douglas to Fleming. My friend;—nay, dearer still, my country's friend. Behold his face with sacred tears bedew'd; With tears for Scotland:—canst thou these despise? Fleming. If this is false, no fairer truth can seem. I'll bring the priest, and meet you at the altar; And there call heav'n to bind our amity. [Exit. Douglas. Hate's banish'd hence to hell; triumphant peace From heav'n I'll bring, to bless my happy country: Her friends are mine; who bleeds for her my brother. Chancellor. What praise the stripling seeks! his views distract me. [Aside. My Lord, your virtue charms me. How I joy That stronger ties may yet cement our friendship. Douglas. I know none stronger than my plighted faith. Chancellor. Int'rest sways men.— Douglas. But me my honour guides; And, whom it guides not, from my soul I scorn. Chancellor. Haste, let me fly to fix so precious friendship; And, as we go, I'll open all my soul. [Exeunt. SCENE II. Enter Sir WIL. DOUGLAS, and Lady BEATRIX. Sir William Douglas. Why grieves my Joy? Lady Beatrix. What mountains bar our bless! Sir William Douglas. Rise they to heav'n, I'll o'er them force my way. Lady Beatrix. My ghostly father damns our love as incest. Sir William Douglas. Curse on his habit which protects the pedant. Dares he blaspheme our love? Pure as the seraphs, Burning in blest abodes with social transports. Priests feel not the desire of virtuous breasts To join their fates and blend their very souls. Their vile amours on virtue's ruins rise, Decoying girls to leave their careful friends To spouse with God.—The rest my tongue disdains. Shall such oppose our bless? Lady Beatrix. How easy can The man we love persuade!— Sir William Douglas. Nor priest, nor prince, Nor hell itself shall part us.— Lady Beatrix. Long the priest Convers'd with Crichton.— Sir Willilm Douglas. Spiteful cunning fox. By heav'n, this sword— Lady Beatrix. Be calm, my love is stedfast; My brothers true, his son's attempts are vain. Sir William Douglas. 'Twere safer for his son to interpose Between the roaring lion and his prey, Than to disturb my love. Thy gen'rous brother Just now swears amity with that old traitor. The Lords have sent t'invite him to their council. I'll wait, and bear him to their messengers; And save him from the snares of Crichton's friendship. Safety is with the Lords; with Crichton, death. [Exit. SCENE III. Enter CRICHTON, Jun. My father's gone to swear,—and—to deceive! [Aside. Yes.—Like the dire hyæna he usurps The voice and actions of humanity T'allure and to devour.—If I reveal it, He dies,—and justly;—most unjust from me, Returning death for life.—To one I must. At his life's peril, Douglas rescu'd mine. O father! friend! for either could I die: But if I save the one, I kill the other. O happy they, who see fair virtue's path! Tho' rocks rise high across, and furies guard it: But darkness broods on my benighted way! But O what joy to save that heav'nly Wonder From such impending griefs! Now love resolves me. [She observing him, offers to retire. Crichton advancing. O grant one pitying look to ease despair! Knew'st thou my heart, sure thou wouldst grant me hearing. Lady Beatrix. What signifies my pity, or my hearing; I never can, nor will be thine. Adieu. Crichton. Yet hear me.—Stay.—If thou regard'st the life Of Douglas.—If thine own most precious life.— [Seizing her gently. Lady Beatrix. O save my brother's life.—Let mine suffice. Crichton. Sure death attends. Lady Beatrix. Heav'n guard me. Re-enter Sir William Douglas, with his sword drawn. Brutal ravisher! Unhand her.—Draw,—speak not,—but guard thy heart. [They fight; Crichton is wounded. Lady Beatrix, interposing. Stain not my brother's hospitality. Crichton. O rival! had thy sword but pierc'd my heart. Sir William Douglas, in disdain. My rival thou, and in this lady's love! Crichton. One word,—Lord Douglas' life. Sir William Douglas. Tempt fate no further; But fly,—and tremble at the name of Douglas. [Exit Sir W. D. and L. B. Crichton solus. How dreadful is a Douglas in his wrath! Oh parricide, thou most gigantic crime! All other murders, tho' most deadly crimes, To thee are pigmies. I have nearly 'scap'd thee! But base ingratitude! Must Douglas die? Who sav'd my life at peril of his own. Unjust reward! I'll drop a written warning, To keep them from the castle: here they're safe, SCENE IV. CHANCELLOR entering. Just now I met the cousins; they are destin'd For one another's arms; and Douglas owns it.— My son! he bleeds!—It must be by this ruffian. —Fly hence, and tremble at the name of Douglas.— These words were his. And now I understand them. The Lords have sent to call their brother-peer; They know they have his mind. I'll watch his body. Here all my friendship give I to the winds; My hate return'd, burns fierce with double fury. How could I dream of friendship with the Douglases! But from their hearts I'll have thy blood repaid. Crichton. 'Twas all mistake. Chancellor. Thy youth and inexperience Mistake thy foes for friends. Crichton. Regard your oaths. Chancellor. Oaths! shackles forg'd by knaves for cred'lous fools: The wise man's engines to effect his purpose. Kingdoms and states eternal friendship swear, Touch holy gospels, and eat hallowed bread, Yet bathe in blood at ev'ry slight offence. Subjects to sov'reigns, sov'reigns swear to subjects, To guard the rights they mean to overthrow. No place of profit, or of power is got Without its oaths; forgot as soon as sworn. Crichton. Yet oaths, profan'd, demand heav'n's hottest vengeance! Chancellor. But they begin the war; this sanctifies Each hostile deed of ours, by force, or fraud; Absolves our oaths, and frees from ev'ry crime. What fool would warn the foe he kills for safety! Crichton. Hence lonely stalk, O man, thro' dreary wilds, Shun thy own kind: no savage can be feller. The fiercest beasts, the very lion roars An honest warning, when he spies his prey. But, ah! if aught in human shape approach; Grind, every savage, grind your teeth and fangs, And tear him: He's a treacherous destroyer. Chancellor. Be calm. I'll on their ruins build thy greatness. Crichton. Heav'n save me from the greatness built on guilt. But your's ye made me share; I bore the forg'ries Which may destroy my generous deliv'rer. O while you may, repent, return to virtue. Let me not lose my friend, nor hate my father. Douglas, his cousin, all are innocent:— 'Twas all mistake: the blame was wholly mine. Chancellor. Thou knowst how much I love thee; how my heart Is touch'd with ev'ry thing that touches thee. Blest in thy virtue, I must love thy friend. To Crichton thou must haste for writs of moment, Needful before the meeting of th'Estates. Crichton. This with my wish conspires, to save my friend. [Exit. Chancellor. Now shall my son be far from guilt and danger. Were men themselves but what they wish their children, Vice none could boast, save monsters, in her train. [Exit. SCENE V. COUNTESS and Lady BEATRIX. Countess Alas! what fears o'erwhelm my boding mind! As usual thou my morning slumbers watch'd, Saw them disturb'd, and I awakned sad. I dream'd I in the castle met our queen; And on my breast two new-blown roses flam'd; 'Twixt these a lily fair, which Crichton's son Attempt'd to seize, but from his touch it shrank. Old Crichton then with Livingston advanc'd; Each cropt a rose's head, and dash'd to earth; There ly, said they, the heads of Douglas' sons: To earth I glanc'd, beheld two bleeding heads, Knew them my children's, and aghast awoke. Lady Beatrix. Thither the Queen invites us. Countess. It is well. Since thither go my sons, I must attend. SCENE VI. Enter Earl DOUGLAS and Sir DAVID. Douglas. Freed from obscurity, with rapid wing, We'll, hand in hand, to glory's summit soar. Sir David, shewing the note dropt by Crichton. I hope no honour from our father's foes: This note says death awaits us in the castle. Douglas. Such arts are lost on me; my honour's pawn'd, Which I'll redeem with life; to me 'tis dearer:— Who fears, may stay; Douglas dares go alone. Sir David. Then I attend. 'Tis for thy dearer life I fear, and not my own. I'll clasp thee fast; And, sink thou to perdition's deepest gulph, I'll keep my hold, and never glance aside To catch at help, that will not save us both. SCENE VII. Enter Lord FLEMING. Fleming. Your servants went to bring you from the grass, The gen'rous coursers, which you rode to town; And found them dying both. Vile foxes tore Their breasts yet heaving. Countess. Ah! too like my dream. Douglas. Set in a brave man's eye his country's good, He spells not omens, nor interprets dreams: Let war roar dreadful, through her brazen throat, And fiery volleys belch of pond'rous deaths, Gaping immense with all her iron teeth, Fearless he flies upon her horrid front, And thinks his life well sold to save a land. Intreat no more: my honour shuts my ears. Countess. At my life's peril, first you saw the light, Nature's hard law on all my sex impos'd; But could the repetition of these pains, With what more fell e'er female-nature felt In all the deepest agonies of death, Save or restore your lives; I should not plead, Nor weep; but bleed, groan, agonize, and die, To save such worth.—And must I lose you both! [Enter Chancellor unperceived. Douglas. Leave not your mother.—O my brother, stay, Our Father's counsel mind. Thou hast not sworn. Sir David. Had our brave sire, in danger from the foe, Forbid thee to approach; thou hadst been deaf To such command; and all his danger shar'd. Were I in danger, thou wouldst interpose, And joy to intercept its fiercest rage. Bind oaths to foes? then sure to brothers more. When good arrives, thou bounteously bestows; When ills oppress, I'll bear a brother's share. In soul we brothers are; and shall remain, In life and death, inseparable still. Chancellor advancing. Fears Douglas friends, by wond'rous goodness gain'd; The more his friends the less we hop'd forgiveness. Or will we blast our own, our country's hopes? For who, but Douglas, can command a peace? Or who, like him, will pardon all offenders? O Douglas! thou out-shin'st thy bravest sires; Saving, without the horrors of a war; No troops thy triumphs share: thy goodness gains Thy en'mies hearts, subdues thine own resentment. Thy sires were heroes, thou appear'st divine; And shalt be more belov'd to endless ages. Yet danger if thou fear'st where I command, Arm'd let thy pow'rs attend: I fear not thee. Douglas. Most gen'rous friend, I go— Fleming. I can't forsake you. Chancellor aside. Attend this once; and you shall ne'er forsake him. Douglas, [Joining one arm in Fleming's and another in the Chancellor's.] Sage wisdom, and experience my supports, Now happily in firmest friendship join'd, I walk secure; two surer, wiser guides To honest fame, from men I could not chuse. Thy love hath ever all the parent shewn; [To Flem. And thine, though later sprung, is scarce inferior. Countess. Farewel; God guard you, since so well resolv'd; But my poor boding heart will burst. O Douglas! Douglas. Farewel. 'Tis his, who guides our fates on high, T'appoint us when, and how, and where we die; Our care shall be, 'tis all that mortals can, To live with honour, or to die like men; Still firm to truth; and warm with virtue's fires; Bold for our country; dauntless as our sires. [Exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT IV. SCENE I. The Governor's Hall in the Castle. The CHANCELLOR and LIVINGSTON. Chancellor. You heard but little of this city's transports: All ranks prest eager round, and choak'd their way; The rabble clapt their hands, and danc'd, and cry'd; (Their bonnets hurling at the face of Heav'n,) God bless our peers, our country's brave defenders. Livingston. Ev'n at this gate they rudely roar'd aloud, God bless the brave, the gen'rous, noble Douglases; Health to their friends; confusion to their foes. Where'er they shine, our splendors sink extinguish'd; But soon my great revenge shall quench their brightness. Chancellor. Between them see the King! link'd arm in arm, Smiling on each by turns, in earnest converse: Here step aside and listen to their talk. SCENE II. Enter the KING between the Douglases, an arm in each of theirs, Lord Fleming walking along. King. I'm told my subjects, a bold stubborn kind, Must hard be rein'd, and to the lash inur'd. Fear awes the bold, who scorn too gentle sway. Fleming. Should a kind parent march with grateful sons, Against a tyrant lashing trembling staves; Their number equal; which the trustiest band? Or is the stern oppressor, 'midst the groans Of wretches mad with woe; or blest, or safe, As the glad sire, amidst his joyful race. Vig'rous of limbs and mind; firm, active, bold, To kindness grateful, deep resenting wrongs, Thy gen'rous subjects, like th'informing mind, Unfelt their ardor guide; and drench'd in sweat, Shall industry each gainful art employ. Bright Genius, leading nobler arts, shall shine; And commerce crown'd with gold, pour riches round. Then all thy people, prosp'ring by thy care, Shall guard thy life, and glory in thy greatness. Nor are the means of greatness hard to find: Exhaustless shoals choak up your swarming seas; And huge your hills with precious metals swell; T'embrace large fleets vast ports spread wide their arms; And aged forests groan to plough the waves. Douglas. Seize then the means of greatness nature yields, And rise redoubted monarch of the main; The darling of the free and happy land; No party's head but parent of the whole. And, if the foe provokes, we'll dauntless rise, An host of brothers, brave with free-born souls, Far distant drive the rav'nous monster, War, Her thirsty jaws deep-bath'd in hostile blood; Return triumphant, while above our heads, Bright Victory, who makes the brave divine, Soaring to Heav'n shall clap her golden wings. Sir David. And while thou guard'st thy King, and quell'st his foes, My shield shall hide thee, and my sword defend. Douglas. Methinks I see the glorious marshal'd field, The waving colours, soldiers daring pride, And all the direful horrors of the war. I hear the fierce defiance; trumpets found; The neighing horses; and the mingled noise Of rage and pain; of triumph and dismay: It fires my soul; I feel the martial rage Flame in my breast; and burn through ev'ry vein. Fleming. The conqu'ror's savage joy, to see a field With mangled carnage heap'd, of friends and foes, Is low to his, who sees a kingdom blest; Conscious they owe their happiness to him. King. Your words, as new as pleasant to mine ear, Have charm'd my soul: like you were all my peers, How blest I were! But nobles hate their kings. Fleming. The nobles love their kings, and freely shed Their blood for all who will deserve their love. They rais'd brave Bruce above our greatest kings. King. So speaks the Queen; but since she lov'd another, Lord Chanc'lor says, she hates my father's children. Yet when, last night, I stole to her embrace, Her eyes dissolv'd in tears, her words in sighs. Her tender kisses, soft encircling arms, Pour'd all the mother on my melting soul. Her breast which heav'd, as if that moment bursting, So soft, so warm, so tenderly prest mine, It shar'd th'emotion; and our beating hearts Flutter'd to meet; and knock'd th'opposing ribs.— A thousand nameless things still bade me love her. Douglas. Deny not love to her who gave you birth, But follow nature, nature's God obey. Fleming. Warm is a mother's heart; most to the fruits Of dear love lost. At your great father's death, Her body cover'd his, receiv'd the wounds Aim'd at his royal heart. Could love do more? Heav'n high uncommon worth exacts from kings, Made gods or furies to the sons of men; And curs'd, or blest, as they destroy or save; This precious truth lodge deep within thy breast: A happy people makes a monarch blest; Who all to mercy's gentle pow'r inclin'd; His people's guardian, loves the human kind; Who for his subjects toils, and sheds his blood; Their voice his council, and his end their good: Who, while around his throne the mighty bend, Will gracious to the poors complaint attend. [Exeunt King, Douglases, and Fleming. SCENE III. LIVINGSTON and CRICHTON advance. Livingston. They come to triumph in their Sov'reign's love, To blast our credit, and commend our foes. Chancellor. How brave the spirit of the gallant Douglases! A gen'rous pair! How sage Lord Fleming's counsels! Livingston. The crisis of our fate approaches nigh; We must resolve; that they or we shall fall. Chancellor. My dulness to thy penetration yields. Livingston. But this so potent train— Chancellor. May be remov'd. Livingston. How? Chancellor. Let my dear son enjoy Lord Douglas' land. Livingston. He shall. Chancellor. This way, and listen to my purpose [Exeunt. SCENE IV. Enter DOUGLAS, and Sir DAVID. Sir David. Imprison'd here the best of fathers lay; And here, as friends, we with his en'mies feast, Who cannot love his sons. Your train attends, While yet you may retire, trust not your foes. Douglas. 'Tis from within men judge. The honest heart Scorns base suspicion. Who would trust his oaths, Who thinks all may be perjur'd? Sir David. Spare such words. The time draws near to prove my oaths sincere; I see and welcome it; for life's a torment, Since thou canst doubt my faith: if none were falser, Thou might'st be safe. For thee alone I tremble. SCENE V. Enter, on one side, the KING with FLEMING; on the other side, LIVINGSTON, CHANCELLOR, and Courtiers. Chancellor. Whene'er we meet at council or at banquet, We have agreed that none shall enter arm'd. [The Chancellor and Livingston, and their party, give the guards their swords.] Douglas, giving his sword. I'll bear no sword among unarmed men. Chancellor, looking at Douglass' sword. This pond'rous blade bears deep undoubted signs Of long hard service to your valiant sires. Douglas. Thrice twenty times with this the good Sir James Return'd triumphant from the glorious field. At Annand, Halidon, and Otterburn, And many a field in Britain and in France, It strew'd the plains with heaps of Scotia's foes. From sires so brave descended, now from me It loudly claims the like illustrious deeds: Who weilds this sword commands our faithful powers. [Exeunt. SCENE VI. Enter COUNTESS and Lady BEATRIX. Lady Beatrix. How fair and wide this goodly prospect spreads! See Forth majestic rolls his mighty flood 'Midst villas fair, and seats of princely peers: There pop'lous Fife pours thick her frequent towns; And Lothian here extends her fruitful fields: Royal Edina rears her lofty towers, Piercing the high-hung azure of the skies; Here low lies Leith bathing in briny waves; There ragged rocks swell up t'assault the heav'ns. Let sights so charming, chear your mournful mind. Countess. My mournful mind finds greater cause for grief: See how in ruins hangs the antient seat: These fields, once fruitful, ravag'd, waste, and bare, Mourn for our statesmen's desolating broils, Whose snare surrounds my sons! [Enter a Servant. Where are thy Lords! Servant. Just newly enter'd with the King to council; And next a splendid banquet for them waits. Lady Beatrix. I knew their virtue nothing had to fear.— Countess. Here dwells our gracious queen: here enter we. Enter the Chancellor, with the Earl's Sword drawn, attended with an Officer and a Servant. Chancellor. [The Earl's party strolling about. Your gracious Lord, who sees this crowded fort Denies convenience, bids you strait retire; And sent this well known ensign of his power; See its bright handle, and its deep-hack'd edge. By this good sword his valiant grand-sire slew, On one most dreadful day, three seeming kings; And had the true, but for the timely aid Of France-subduing Henry's matchless might: By this the English arms first met rebuke By his brave sire in France, when Clarence died. [They draw off. Whene'er they're gone, shut fast the gates; set guards; Bring me the keys; and have your ruffians arm'd: And, when you see a bull's raw head serv'd in, Rush in, and bind them hard.—See none relent;— Whoever fails,—shall answer with his life. [To the Servant. When, for last course I call, send in the head. [To the Officer. [Exit Officer and Servant. Like a sagacious spaniel round my prey, With fixed eye, and full intent, I move; Till on their heads the sudden ruin bursts. The bull, I baited for their sport, broke loose, And would have kill'd my son; but Douglas slew him: Then loud applauses tore my tortur'd ears; I saw him shining by my son's disgrace; And sick'ning loath'd the heav'nly light which shew'd it. He speaks so slightly, when I force out thanks, As shew he values low my rescu'd son: But since that debt I never can repay; His hated presence shall not long upbraid me. SCENE VII. The Scene drawn, discovers a Hall with a long Table: The King sitting at the head; on one side the Douglases and Lord Fleming; on the other, Livingston, as Regent; the Chancellor entering, takes his seat next him: the rest of the Council on both sides below. Livingston. Our country's state calls loud for swift redress, Long torn by civil hate; the laws despis'd. Our Kings, but Kings in name, in vain resent The wrongs they can't revenge; by statutes bound Of haughty Lords; which they must stamp for law: For justice flows from Kings, on them depends. Fleming. Far higher's her descent: God is her sire; His goodness her conceiv'd; his wisdom tutor'd. These fram'd the laws of order and of love; Which are not sprung of yesterday; nor shall To-morrow see them chang'd; they never die. By these heav'ns Monarch sways the boundless whole. His vengeance is but vig'rous goodness, arm'd Against Disorder's rage, to save his offspring; Nor falls his sword, even on the guilty head, Till all the power of gentleness has fail'd. Sir David Douglas. Be princes thus his images, thus reign, By stedfast laws, for public good devis'd; With filial duty serv'd; as sires rever'd. Fleming. Let boundless goodness claim unbounded power, And perfect wisdom to itself give law, Secure from change where they immortal reign: But flatt'rers kings seduce, their ear abuse; And patriot kings their thornes to tyrants leave. Hence stedfast laws must prince and people guard, Such as Bruce fram'd with his heroic peers. Douglas. These sons of freedom tore the hostile yoke From Scottish necks, and bad the land be free; And left the noble purchase to their children; Nor thought it dearly bought with lives and fortunes. Freedom's the guard of right, the nurse of truth; Parent of science, and all gen'rous deeds. This steel'd their breasts, and made them dauntless rise, Unconquer'd by defeats; and forc'd at last Vict'ry to crown a brav'ry so resolv'd. If such thou reign, thou such shall find thy peers. King. Thrice happy Bruce, in peers so true and brave! If mine be such, I'll worth, like him, reward. Livingston. His heirs have felt his lavish bounty sorely, Which rais'd so many rivals to their power. Do thou these gifts resume; and at thy will, King-like, command our fortunes and our lives. You first, my Lords, into his hands resign Estates, and honours, privileges, powers; From royal grace, with int'rest to return; For by that tenure, Scots henceforth shall hold Most sure, when none dare blame the royal will. Fleming. Liv'd our great sires for this? and bore with joy The painful march, and dangers of the field? For this were all their glorious wounds and deaths. Sure hadst thou shar'd like these the common war, And shone the first in danger and in fame, Thou couldst not see thy fellow-soldiers slaves. Douglas. And fell so many of my valiant sires In freedom's cause, that I should first of Scots Receive the yoke, and teach the peers to serve? Hear, Scotia's champions once, now guardian saints! Listen from heaven, and hear your offspring swear Like you, to die before he lives a slave; And stain your race, by deeds so nobly rais'd. Can any think we'll lives or fortunes hold, Like bubbles blown, or bursting by the breath Of each vile tool of arbitrary power? Perhaps a whore's, to whose imperial spleen, A martial land must, with its tyrant, bend; While her vile creatures trample down the brave. Fair Liberty! thy champion I am sworn; Their deadly foe, who seeks thy sons t'enslave. Livingston. Since grace thou scorn'st, vengeance sure awaits, Heavy to fall and crush thy stubborn pride, And end at once Aristocratic power. Douglas rising. Beware then, tyrant. Douglas is thy foe; Whose sword is sacred to his country's cause. King. My Lord!—My Cousins! both be pacified. Sit! calm your wrath!—Be friends!—Dear cousin Douglas, To me this once your anger sacrifice. Chancellor, apart to Livinston. Scare not your prey; the net's just closing round them. A moment's patience all your wishes crowns. King. Listen! be friends! and make your Sov'reign blest! Douglas. His King's desire to Douglas is a law. [Sits down. Chancellor. Will Scotia's dearest son provok'd to wrath Bathe her in blood? or in his furious rage, Her skillful pilot steer her on a rock? To-morrow's sun th'assembled peers beholds: There free delib'rare; here, in social love, Enjoy the banquet which prepar'd awaits. Fleming. Well spoke! and happy state, where ev'ry rank May meet, explain their griefs, and find redress; From faction free, above the tyrant's awe, And only subject to their country's law. SCENE VIII. The Chancellor rising, and advancing to the front of the Stage; the Scene drops on the rest. Enter an OFFICER. Officer. They all are gone; strong watchful guards are set; The gates are well secur'd; receive the keys. [Exit. Chancellor. Now nothing here can hinder my designs. Straight disappointment, terror, and surprize, My foes shall waken from their golden dreams Of royal favour, power, and public greatness. Fools may scorn knaves; but knav'ry prospers here; Here!—but Hereafter,—what awaits them there! O curst Hereafter!—think I must not,—dare not. My foes excell in virtue; I in cunning: And thus must triumph. So the prince of hell; (His plot 'gainst man succeeding but too well; And those heav'n's favour destin'd for his place, By his dark wiles seduc'd from heav'nly grace, No hope of heav'n in his fell breast alive,) Rejoic'd to see his hellish projects thrive. [Exit.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT V. SCENE I. A Table furnished with Deserts and Wine. The King at the head, on the Regent's right-hand: next the Regent, the Chancellor: on the King's right-hand, on the other side of the Table, opposite to the Chancellor, the Douglases; next them Fleming: and other Courtiers on both sides of the Table below them. Chancellor. Be hence, my Lords, familiar at the board Of your young King; his frequent welcome guests. King. I love you cousins as my soul. Your honours Shall shine, eclipsing all your sires enjoy'd, As the ascending sun out-shines the stars. Douglas. If our best blood can do our Sov'reign honour, We'll hold it cheap as sweat of lab'ring swains. Chancellor to the Servants. Bring the last course. Bear you these trifles off. Their powers are gone. Take these; and rule at will. [Giving the keys to Livingston Livingston. Now dost thou prove thyself a precious friend. Chancellor drinking. Honour and health to all the brave and good, Who for their King and country shed their blood. [All drink. [Enter servants with a bloody raw Bull's head, and set it on the table before the Douglases; follow soldiers with spears, who surround them.] Fleming. What means this insult? Livingston. Hast thou ne'er seen A stollen bull's head presented to the thief. [Earl Douglas sounds a golden whistle to alarm his train.] Livingston. Whistle at will, young Lord; thy followers hear not: They're gone; the gate's fast shut; behold the keys. Pinion the traitors. [To the soldiers. Fleming. Dogs! you are too base; To hold a bason to these noble hands; And add you such indignity to murder? Livingston. Bind that arch-traitor hard. Fleming. 'Tis me you hate; Spare these young Lords, and I with pleasure die. Douglas. Live thus disgrac'd! after my guardian's death. I'll share thy fate; or live for thy revenge. King. O let my cousins live.—Throw down the cords. Bind not the hands which should defend my throne. How can you gall with cords the noble hands, Which ye so lately shook in solemn friendship? These arms you strain so hard were twin'd in mine. Regard my tears.—O could they melt your hearts, Your hearts of flint,—ye tyger-hearted monsters! To spare my noble, my beloved cousins. Sir David Douglas. If guiltless blood you seek, let mine suffice; A single life. His high-born wife's, his children's, Hang on Lord Fleming's fate; and on my brother's His father's house, his country's happiness. I'll smile in agonies; I'll pray in death For blessings on your heads, if Douglas lives. Douglas. Forbear, my brother: Douglas fears not death. But, Ah! thy tender youth, thy gen'rous worth, Might make the fiends relent. If thee they harm, Heav'n's choicest plagues in flaming wrath shall pour More dreadful than their blackest guilt divines. Livingston. Dares thy bold pride to threaten,—even in bonds! Douglas. These bonds do threaten thee. Unrighteous deeds, The tyrant's cruelties, the villain's crimes, Th'oppressed's groans, and injur'd virtue's tears; The butcher'd liberties, expiring laws, And miseries of an enslaved land;— These threat:—and never did they threat in vain. Livingston. My threats not vain, in anguish thou shalt feel. Douglas. 'Gainst virtue all the rage of foes is vain. King. If ye regard my love, or fear my wrath, Rob not my youth of friends most dearly priz'd: Men who would make me wise, and great, and good; And happy in a happy people's love: Who from my land would drive the rav'nous war, And give their lives to make my reign renown'd. —Must they not live?—because I love ye slay them.— A monarch's love is fatal to his friends. I'll spend my future reign in vengeance for them.— O let them live.—Take ye my power and treasures. We'll fly from greatness and live blest in virtue; Happy in hearty love, and humble friendship. Tho' you relent not, sure the men without Will hear their prince, and save their noble friends. [Going. Chancellor detaining the King. Thy danger, not our hate, extorts a deed That wounds my very soul; while Douglas lives, Thy throne's unsure, thy royal life unsafe; Usurpers must destroy their Kings or die. Why wilt thou weep and break my tortur'd heart? But better 'tis thy tears, than blood, should flow; Though these thou mourn'st would see it flow with joy. King. 'Tis false as hell; thou dost bely my Cousins. [Exit weeping, the Chancellor following. Livingston. In scorn of us, and of your lawful King, Thou Douglas sent; and thou false Fleming past Ambassador, to treat with foreign kings. You leagu'd with Lords at home; whose barb'rous clans, To spoil the mainland, from their isles you rous'd; While your lewd bord'rers plunder th'inland shires. These you protect against your sov'reign's power, Whose functions you usurp, creating knights, Conferring honour and nobility. Your train and daily state your King's exceeds. By you seduc'd, his peers your courts attend, Plotting to seize his small remains of power. For these bold treasons, I condemn your heads To be divided from your treach'rous breasts. Thou David, shar'd their crimes; their judgments share. Fleming. These are not truths, or are not crimes; but part Is forg'd, and part our nat'ral right.— Livingston. Forbear. Your doom is fixt, and all defence is vain. Douglas. Tyrants can only give a glorious death, Secure the patriot's endless bliss and fame; And plunge themselves in guilt, disgrace, and horror. Livingston. Guards, keep them sure, to wait our future will. [Exit. Sir David. Late thro' Edina's spacious streets we march'd, 'Midst loud applause of all the friendly throng. To honour us, nobles with nobles vy'd; Nor could a brother's love exceed our King's. But now enclos'd with walls, 'midst cruel guards, Disgrac'd like felons, bound with galling cords; Our high descent from heroes and from kings; Our splendid honours, wealth, and mighty power, All fortunes trappings; all her favours past, But deck us out a gaudier sacrifice. Like thougthless birds decoy'd, like cattle butcher'd; Whose life or death no glorious deed adorns; Our en'mies scorn.—Not thus our fathers fell. Douglas. Yet neither treach'rous foe, nor adverse fate, Can tear the gen'rous purpose from our breasts; Which still in truth and brav'ry match our sires. Fleming. The brave and innocent can smile at death, By sword, or ax, fierce foe, or treach'rous friend. Should gaping earth devour, or thunder strike, Serene they meet the blow; and hear with joy Th'imperial voice; from toil to triumph call'd. Exert their force, collect their utmost strength, With dignity their glorious course to end. Douglas. The same the dungeon's gloom, or glorious field, If conscious virtue meets her own applause. Myriads of eyes immortal view the strife, And call the conqu'rors to immortal thrones. Sir David. This welcome time shall prove my heart sincere; And worthy of my brother's gen'rous love. Douglas. These words, O brother, deeply wound my heart, Who to thy faith preferr'd a fawning foe, And sorely griev'd a breast so kind and true. I scorn'd my sister's griefs, my mother's tears, My father's last commands, your prudent counsels. —O brother!—O my guardian!—Victims both Of love to cred'lous Douglas.—Ill repaid! O bitt'rer far than death! thus to destroy Whom best I lov'd. Fleming. My dear defenceless babes! Long may you prattle of your sire's return, Which ne'er shall glad your little slutt'ring hearts. O best of women! Thou the royal blood Of all thy father's house, saw shed. My death Thy loving heart will—O my wife! my children! Douglas. O brother! my dire folly, and thy love.— Sir David. Grieve not for me.—It was my ardent wish, Opprest with favours, to deserve thy love; And now I could:—I could die for thee, Wert thou but safe; then were I blest indeed. Douglas. Thou must not die; for Douglas at his death, Will condescend to humble supplications; Kneel, weep, intreat, and beg his foes to spare thee. Sir David. Think not I'll thee desert. Since thou must die, We'll fearless launch, and unknown worlds explore; Hand join'd in hand. With like and equal virtues Heav'n join'd our souls; and never will them sep'rate: With joy I die, since thou my faith approves. Douglas. What have I ruin'd? Wisdom how mature! [To Flem. What early virtue! what has Scotland lost! [To Sir. D. Severe distress! Firm in himself, the brave Can only be distrest in them he loves. Fleming. Virtue tastes sorrow here, and vice has joy, Neither sincere: the awful time hastes on To drink them pure, as well-weigh'd merit claims. Heav'n kind to virtue sooths the weakling's way. But who her highest honours hope to gain, Must struggle hard, must agonize, and groan. Perfection is by dreadful suff'rings won; But glorious and immortal her rewards. Douglas. For her high summit stretch we then our flight. Our minds, enlarg'd with ev'ry godlike aim, With ev'ry virtue can adorn our souls; We'll shine distinguish'd ev'n among immortals. Enter Livingston. Now, on cool thoughts, will you submit to hold Your lives and fortunes of our special grace? Fleming. We scorn such slav'ry to a rightful King; Far more to thee, deceitful tyrant. Livingston. Guards, Drag him to death.— [The Guards offer to drag him away. Fleming. Keep off your hands, ye slaves. Virtue meets death undaunted, and undragg'd; So tyrants dare not, by their guilt dismay'd. [Exit before the Guards. Livingston. In pity of your youth, too soon misled, I offer grace. Submit, be wise, and live. Douglas. The bull's dire head, and these disgraceful cords, Thy unjust sentence, and our guardian's fate, Have fixt thee hence eternally my foe: Nor hope thou peace till Fleming mediates for thee. Enter Chancellor. Treating forsooth! but they're too much provok'd; The courage of a Douglas grows with danger. Livingston aside to the Chancellor. I pity them, but they disdain to yield.— Chancellor. Had you two furious lions fast ensnar'd, And all their fierceness rous'd, would you release them? 'Tis dang'rous to retreat. The dead resent not. Livingston aside. Then shalt thou share the guilt. See judgment done. [To the Chancellor. Let those who scorn our mercy, feel our vengeance. [Exit Livingston. Chancellor. Delight you now in greatness or revenge? Your foe you may destroy and fill his place. Let but your sister wed my darling son, And Scotland you shall sway, and Scotland's King. Douglas. Hence, odious traitor! As the hiss of fiends, Thy words are hateful, and thy self as hell. Chancellor half aside. These words may cost thee dear; tho' scorning death, Yet their's thou lov'st may wring thy stubborn soul. Douglas. Alas! my brother. Sir David. Mind not me. Thy brother, Thy father's son, disdains by mean submission, To purchase life. [They both turn from the Chancellor with an air of the highest disdain and indignation.] SCENE II. Enter COUNTESS and Lady BEATRIX, from the Queen's Apartments. Countess. This Queen alone excell'd me once in greatness; And now in grief. How seldom are they sep'rate! Her foes have of her royal brood the charge; In faithful Fleming, mine have found a father. Lady Beatrix. Let us retire: we heard a hapless wretch This way pass guarded to his death. Such scenes Are shocking to be near. Countess We'll beg his life. Lady Beatrix. Your sons had done it, had his crimes allow'd: Yet some dear sister left may mourn his death; Some virgin's faithful heart in secret bleed. Countess. Perhaps his sire bedews his silver beard; Ah! some poor lonely widow may survive! Or tender infants helpless and forlorn! [A Soldier passes over the Stage. Lady Beatrix. Can'st thou inform us who was doom'd to death? Countess. Silent he goes, and pitying looks casts back.— This place looks dismal.—Crouds of armed men, —But none of ours are seen.—Alas, my sons! As a poor bird, who sees her tender young, Flutt'ring about the hawk's rapacious nest! Sill hovers near, and keeps them in her eye, Waiting, with panting heart, their tragic end: Too weak to help, she mourns with plaintive sound, And grieving, pines her feeble breast in vain: So mournful I attend my gen'rous sons, As much distrest, as impotent to save. Chancellor entering. By this, Lord Fleming lies without a head. Countess. Lord Fleming! O my sons! Lady Beatrix. Alas! my brothers Could never see their father's friend in bonds! [Enter the Brothers bound and guarded. Arm'd guards! O my dear brothers! Countess. O my sons! Sir David We liv'd like brothers, and like brothers die. Douglas. I only fear the stroke which thou must feel. Sir David. O may they kill me first, for I can die Easier than see so dear a brother bleed: But thy kind heart would feel as much for me. Countess. And must my sons then die? Must both my sons? Lord Douglas' noble house exist no more! Lady Beatrix breaking through the guard to them. Death shall not sep'rate us.—Alas, they're bound! Bound hard with galling cords! these noble hands, Sacred to gen'rous deeds, bound like a felon's! Countess. If heav'n breath'd sharp, my bosom hid these hands, Now gall'd with cutting cords.—O sight of anguish! Douglas. Then are you here!—both!—in our en'mies power! For death, but not for this, we were prepar'd! Countess kneeling with Lady Beatrix. See, how on earth, the wife of noble Douglas Kneels to his foes, for mercy to his sons. Lady Beatrix. His daughter kneeling, begs to die for them. Douglas. Guards, lead to death. 'Tis worse than death, so see My father's wife and daughter kneel to foes. Now Crichton triumphs o'er the house of Douglas. Chancellor. This haughty fair disposes of their fate.— If she consents to wed my son, they live. Lady Beatrix. O let them live!—To save their precious lives, I'll wed abhorrence, endless discontent: Let them but live, how much soe'er I'm wretch'd! Douglas Then life I lothe, and thee I must renounce As alien to our blood:—but sure our sister, So basely never will betray our honour. O save from this disgrace a line of heroes! Sir David. The brave may be betray'd, insulted, slain; But never conquer'd: while they scorn to yield, And basely purchase life by mean submissions. [Lady Beatrix looking at the Earl with earnest affection, seems about to speak.] Douglas. O do not bid me live to scorn, to hate thee! Despis'd, disgrac'd,—abhorr'd for thy debasement! Lady Beatrix. Then scorn me, hate me, stab me dead:—but live! Countess. O live, my sons, to bless my lonely widowhood! Your mother begs it, who could die for you. Douglas. Why urge me to disgrace?—Ah, mother!—Sister!— How can I yield? hither I forc'd Lord Fleming; And here he fell.—Shall I reward his murder With our alliance? with my sister's bed? When men recount the heroes of the name; The valiant Sholto, and the good Sir James; William, the hardy; William, flower of chivalry; Undaunted Tineman, my unyielding sire; The daring Douglas, slain at Otterburn, Whose name when dead, brought victory from the skies: In such a list, to be design'd, The soft, Faint-hearted William, whom soft female tears Melted to bow before his treach'rous foe, And prostitute his sister to his son: When brave men scorn; the very rabble hiss The dastard Douglas, who surviv'd his honour; The first of all his race who fear'd to die; Too late by death I'll seek to fly dishonour, Th'eternal stain of an unsullied race. Douglas. Spare fruitless words, let us with honour die; Not live with shame, dishonour'd by the world. Enter Livingston. The town pours forth her crouds, the nobles rise; The tumult hither rolls;—Hark—how they shout! My son led forth my followers.—Now in triumph,— The en'mies cry, A Douglas. Aid my son. Chancellor. My troops must guard the fortress. Livingston. Rescue mine. They'll aid. Chancellor. Too many mouths are bad for sieges. Lady Beatrix. Now all is well! I hear the march of Douglas. Countess. Now gracious heav'n preserves my virtuous sons. Douglas. Scotland shall flourish; see, her tyrants tremble! Enter a Messenger to Livingston. Thy party flies; thy son is seiz'd, and dies, If Douglas or his brother suffer harm. Livingston. They both shall live; I fly to save my son. [Exit. Messenger. The guards within hold parly with the nobles. Chancellor. They dare not:—yet can faith be hop'd in ruffians? [Aside. Hah! what a tumult! now they enter!—Lords, Forgive the past! Douglas. When our dear Cousin asks it. Countess. Can all our lives restore thy worthy guardian's? O live, to save thy father's house, and his. Chancellor. Save my dear son; he's guiltless of your wrongs. Douglas. I know't. My vengeance hurts no guiltless man: T'assembled peers shall judge in all between us. Chancellor to one attending. Bring them their swords. My hands will loose the cords. Your gen'rous goodness cheers me, noble Douglas. Enter a Second Messenger. The foe is worsted. Chancellor. Lucky news! be brief. Countess. Oh! heavy tidings! Lady Beatrix. O distracting event! Messenger. Lord Treasurer, with a band of chosen friends, His nephew reinforc'd; hard was the combat, Till your brave son return'd and charg'd the foe, And to the town drove back their fainting numbers. Chancellor. Off with their heads; and fix them on the wall, To terrify the peers: my son deserves A greatness built upon their mighty ruins. Why stand you staring? quick,—dispatch them,—slaves. [The Ladies clasp about the Brothers. Countess. My sons, I'll hold you, while my arms have strength. O help! O Heav'n!—Doth heav'n forsake the virtuous? Chancellor. Tear them asunder. Lady Beatrix. Drag us all along. We'll stick thro' life, and end our woes together. Douglas. Forbear t'unbend our souls, which should collect Their utmost strength, a trial so severe With dignity to bear, and end with glory. Sir David. I cannot bear your tenderness and sorrow. Countess. O that the bitterness were mine alone! But Ah! must I resign these lovely necks T'a mangling bloodly ax!—O horror, horror! Chancellor. Part their embracing arms.—Lead off the criminals. [The back Scene opening, discovers the Block, and the Executioner standing by it; at the sight whereof the Ladies fall.] Douglas and Sir David. O cruelty! O cords we feel you now! See how they lie; nor can our hands them raise. Chancellor. Pull down the traitors. Strike and make them headless. Douglas, saluting his brother Sir David. Embrace we cannot; receive this parting kiss. A moment's pain brings speedy endless joy: Our souls shall to eternity embrace, Where treach'rous murd'rers shall no more disturb us. [The back Scene shuts. Manet Chancellor. Enter a third Messenger. Chancellor. There's consternation in thy dastard looks. Messenger. The reinforced peers dispers'd their foes; Their leaders seiz'd. Your son still guards the entry. [A stroke of the Ax heard within. Chancellor. There dies young Douglas. Bid my son retire And shut the gates; while th'enraged peers Pour all their fury on the Regent's kindred. [Another blow of the Ax heard within. Chancellor. That ends another Douglas. [A deep groan heard within of the Countess dying. Mourn, proud ladies. Lady Beatrix speaking behind. Strike, butcher, strike; and mix my blood with theirs. Chancellor, aloud to the Executioner. Fly to the wall and shew their bleeding heads; And tell the peers, They come too late to save them. Enter Officer. How blest is virtue's end! How wretch'd the slaves Of tyrants, doom'd to execute their cruelties! Chancellor. Are my commands fulfill'd? Officer. Alas! too fully. Now headless lie, the loveliest, bravest pair That ever eyes beheld. The fainting mother, Rous'd by the blow which ended noble Douglas, Beheld his lovely brother's mournful end; And tow'rd her, reeking flow'd their mingled blood; At which she with a heavy groan expir'd. Wild with her grief, the beauteous sister ey'd Her mother's corps; and then the bleeding trunks, And heads of her dear brothers; last her eye Points on the bloody block; on which he flew.— “Sacred to honour'd deeds, on thee I'll die.— Strike, butcher, strike; and mix my blood with theirs;” She said; and stretch'd her stately snowy neck. When none would strike, she rose, and fixt her view Upon the mournful ruins: now she lifts Her eyes to heav'n, then wrings her snowy hands, Beats her soft breast; next stands as struck with thunder In silent majesty of mighty grief. Chancellor. Now let her scorn my son. Her pride is humbled. Enter the King. Durst thou confine me to mine own apartments, Till those I love were murder'd? I'll have vengeance. [Exit hastily. Chancellor. I love to keep your Majesty from danger. Enter Livingston. Ten thousand curses blast thee; for my son And brother, thy vile treach'ries have murder'd. When dropping gore, yet warm, the peers beheld The heads of Douglas' sons, they gave the word: I saw my first-born's blood flow reeking round. Chancellor aside. My keen revenge cuts with a double edge; First Douglas' house; then Livingston's comes down. Livingston. Behold the genuine letters Douglas wrote; These hadst thou sent— Chancellor. These! say whence hadst thou these? Livingston. Just as I reach'd the gate, thy son was ent'ring; And that same fatal moment on the wall Appear'd the murder'd heads. He wildly star'd. Behold by these, how thou hast been abus'd: These are the letters wrote by gen'rous Douglas. He said; and out upon his rival salli'd. To me, he cry'd, thy Cousins owe their death; I bore the odious forg'ries which destroy'd them. Then with his sword upon him rush'd; but turn'd Its point aside, and all his foe's receiv'd: Thanks for my cure, he said; life's a disease Surviving honour: mine expir'd with Douglas. But, Ah, my sire much time needs to repent! Gen'rous in height of wrath, the peers command To bear him hither, that, from insults free, He may in peace expire, and rest unharm'd. Chancellor. O heavy news! thus am I doubly damn'd, And wholly lose the price of my damnation! Marking the way with his dear blood he comes! Would my heart's blood restore him, it should flow! O can the world afford thee no relief? Crichton. No: none to me; who ignorant assisting The hateful treach'ry, which destroy'd my friends, Have courted death to hide me from dishonour.— Repent, and yet find pardon.—Mercy, Heav'n.— [Dies. Chancellor. He dies! and what a tender look he fixt On my accursed face! I have destroy'd him. He's nothing, who was all the world to me;— Yea, priz'd o'er heav'n, and all that it contains.— What I regarded now, cannot avail him. All pleasure here is gone with him; from virtue I sought no support: from insulted heav'n, No comfort hope; and hell hath none to give me; But mocks my folly, and derides my woes.— This was my choice, and now complaints are vain. Enter Lady Beatrix. Justice, though often slow, yet ever sure, Hath reach'd you, traitors! in your guarded fortress. Behold her just awards! Your kindred die For mine; a mean revenge. Your troops have op'd The gates, and see the nobles come for vengeance. Enter Sir William Douglas, his sword dyed in blood, with numbers of the Nobles attending, with their swords in their hands. Sir William Douglas. Ye murd'rers! draw your swords. Ye stare, and dare not. 'Twould stain my sword to do the hangman's office. [To the Chancellor. This sword reeks with thy blood:—thy dearest blood. Death he deserves not; but thy cruel treacheries Have pierc'd his breast thus far. You may look dismal. Bind them, till justice shall requite their crimes. Let mortals know, who move from bad to worse, Success in ill, is heav'n's severest curse: For, when the wicked highest swell in pride; Th'Almighty rising, on the adverse side, Extends his arm resistless; and the blow In thunder falls, crushing the blasted foe. But divine virtue, tho' on all sides prest, Is never wretched, howsoe'er distrest; Supported from on high, she keeps the field; And scorns to pleasure or to pain to yield; Slight hopes and fears that hang on feeble breath, Grows strong by suff'ring; and triumphs o'er death. Exeunt Omnes. THE END.</field>
   </doc>
</add>