<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">University Press</field>
      <field name="author_facet">University Press</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">university press</field>
      <field name="author_text">University Press</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1970's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V1.0801.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1974 for 1976</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:459484</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Wasp or Subject's Precedent</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Wasp or Subject's Precedent</field>
      <field name="title_facet">wasp or subjects precedent</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">wasp or subjects precedent</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Wasp or Subject's Precedent</field>
      <field name="year_display">1974 for 1976</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1974</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1974</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459484&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459484&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Wasp or Subject's Precedent&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;wasp or subjects precedent&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1974 for 1976&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1974&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Wasp or Subject's Precedent&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Oxford&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University Press&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1974 for 1976&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3873439-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv10801&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 20th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;20th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Wasp or Subject's Precedent&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 230 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Jacobean and Caroline verse drama.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries, introductory and editorial matter omitted&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Copyright (c) 1974 The Malone Society. This text should not be reproduced, except for fair dealing purposes, without the express permission of Chadwyck-Healey and the copyright holder&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: The wasp or subject's precedent.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: History.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1974.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 1636–1640 ?&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Square brackets represent sections of text which have been deleted or added at different stages in the evolution of the manuscript.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE WASP OR SUBJECT'S PRECEDENT</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Act I sc. i Enter Conon, Elidure, Deuon Archi«b » Conon: Good morrow Lords: wt. Clowdy clere yr. Browes our night of slavery is ore, the bright day of freedome begins to breake, &amp; throw gilt Beams vpon vs, the sonn rize danceing on the Britishe Cliffts &amp; smyles on our attempt. Elid: It does, it dos, and tho great Britaine (wt h thre quarters of the world) Be by warrs chance, made Romaine tributaries our Homage paid, we are not slaves to Rome, but owners of our Honors, &amp; our Titles wc h this yong Prorex, haughty Marianus wood Iustle vs out off Deuon nay does, the poore he makes slaves, &amp; like horses yoakes 'em vp in Teames to till our owne Land for the Romaines vse, Arch [Elid]: our wifes &amp; daughters they make prostitutes eat vp the rich, make bondslaves of the poore &amp; oppresse all Conon. nay we that Are the peeres &amp; barrones of the Land, are howrly fleicd, off Titles &amp; additionns Arch. wt an Affront was given last day to Barron Clarydon, by prowd Varletti his base Mynion a skipping Zanny, a mere virginall Iack a fellow bred, no better then a ffidler. Conon. yes he can dance, &amp; do his grownd trickes cleanlye has taught strange changes synce he came into Britaine Elyd. grownd trickes dee call em? me thinkes theyre too loftye he caperd Clare out of an honord offyce. Deu. let sincapace looke well vnto his ffooteinge an other trick like that will breake his neck else Con, meane tyme I feare has broake the Barrons hart he went home heavy. Arch: he had small reason for that. tho. his estates lighter by a 1000l per Ann?. but to the busines. wt are we all sound bosoomde? o?s all of a peice. showes a Paper Arch Then wt. our tongues have sworne &amp; our hands seald vpon our warlike swords lets se performd, &amp; pluck that sicophant out of his Armes, or him out of his chaire Elid: thats the maine Business that Convented vs Conon. A bout it then, this is [old Gilberts Castle] Mount Claridon, lets call him forth. Gilbert, the Countess scylence Enter Countess Clarydon. Count. my noble Lords Con: ffaire Countess wheres the Barron, Count busy wt hin sr. like a man prepareing for a long voyage— Arch oh tot h Holy Land. has beene about it Long, this germaine Crochetmonger makes old Gill mad, prethe go call hym hether wele staye his voyage for this once Count. wood Heaven yow were so fortunate, hees wondrous sick Arch. Sick nay I ferd asmuch may we make bold so see him. Count. Tis' my desire, but he talkes somwt Idlye Arch for want of slepe, I have done so my selfe, when I was a yong Reveller, vncurten come come lets se him— Count: Sir husband /— Bed discoverd. Gilb: in it Gilb: staye: I prethe, prthe death Looke not so grimly—I confess my life stands for feit to the, but the day of payment is not yet come, &amp; Ime a litle busye. Count. busy about wt? Gilb mary swete wife a mask— a prety Anty mask—wc h death and I must dance—Varletti? no, no, hes for state state measurs all, [theres ner a champeon to be disarmd int] Arch. that rascall troubles him. Count pray sr take comfort, some of yor best freinds are come to se yw. Gilb let e'm ha that they come for then, good chere titles aditions Honours offices I cann well spare &amp; they have need of em, as good I give em to my freinds Alive as ha my foes take em when I am dead. but who are those thow calst my freinds Varletti one of em? Cono no, no, [old] true Conon. Elidure Devon &amp; old Archibald Gilb my fellow peeres. Con? &amp; sharers in thy sorrowe, that come a purpose Gilb. peace, peace, purpose nothinge Varletties crochetts &amp; crosspoints will blowe yor purposes to aire, Bubles, mere nothings. Arch still that Iack troubles him. Conon) well then laye[ing] by the busynes we came for being so weake hees much Incapable of it &amp; in my minde twer far more necessarye he sett things in good order—. Gilb: made my will? that workes done Long Agoe Arch. And whome have yow Apointed executors &amp; over seers Gilb none, I Loue none so ill to Author there damnation no not Varletti, I'me so charitable I made myne owne hand my Executor &amp; myne ey my[n]e overseer Conon yow have don well int &amp; shalbe sure to have yor well per formd wt have yow giue the king Gilb the king more mercy &amp; less Iustice, but no tyranny Arch. wt to yor freind Varletti Gilb: Varletti: my offices, all my offices, &amp; a mule to carry em, for the Ass has more tiltles then he can well beare all ready. Con: wt to yor sonn. Gilb A Britaines hart and an Italeans Braine, wit to kepe his tongue in his mowth and his head on's shoulders wher is the springall— Count. Sent for to court Gilb. Is the foole begd allready—sent for to Court for wt? The boy wants wit to be a statesman, oh theres revells towards, hele make an Excellent Dancer Varletti has taught his (Marginal note) he sincks a pace allreadye, wt h tricks I like not pardon, pray pardon Ime all most lost, my Imagination swyms in troubled waters, were yow asking me somewt. about a will? Conon- It was our last request sr. Gilb: vnder my pillow, prethe, prethe wife shalt finde one ready seald. Intreat thes Lords to witness it, pervse it at yor Leasures, wt s there in perfect Memory I writ &amp; my Request is it may be ?formd. Conon yow have dealt nobly wt h yor wife &amp; Sonn devided yor Inheritance betwixt e'm— Elid &amp; wt h discretion too, for it cutts of Conon. think her dovr to lye yet least yor sonn may (Marginal note) gardian &amp; ward ship &amp; confyrms her both, Conon Twere not amiss [he] to set down over seers Gilb How over seers? why my Noble Lords tho sick, I wood not have you think me mad to hyer wolfes to overlooke my lambes so there fat cubbs might lapp vp the swet milk &amp; my leane slincks lack whey, Ile no such overseers no— Ile leave em full Bowles, if they wonot feed freindly wt hout an vmpier, fast &amp; wellcome Countess a word Count. wt h me sr would yow speake? Gilb onely wt h the &amp; privately the rest may at there plesurs go to rest Arch. swete peace be thy companion, for the Romaine wolfe that makes such havock of our British heards wele ether hunt him home into his denn, or worry him wt h mastives, —Ext. Gilb. vse yor skill mans blood cost dere, its dowble synn to kill wheres my man Howlet Enter Howlet How. I have bene talking a cold word wt h Melpomine, Matron of the Muses Lynnen ward rope, a bout the price of a winding sheete for yor Lordship; for as my Lady will bestow a toombe of yor body, Ile be at the cost of a cleane sheet for yr virtues, I wood not have e'm walk vp and downe, as I have sene slovenly ghosts in fowle lynnen; no Ile have as faire a poeticall windeing sheete as I can get for my mony— Gilb: thow meanst an Eitaph Howl. some such ffooleishe thing I intend sr Gilb ffooleish indeed, vaine &amp; superfluous if my good deeds &amp; memory be so poore they are not able to live of them selvs wt hout a Poets bought Benevolence let em e'en dy wt h me, too for trew desert will Live beyond a flattering Epitaph Howl: Tis but a dead comodity indeed now I thinke ont, Ile een loose myne Earnest, &amp; turn't vpon the poets hands agen, he may finde crafty marchants enow, that will have more need ont: but wherfore did yor Honour call me. Gilb Ile tell the [Howlet,] for the Honnest Service thow hast done me, the ffarme thow dwelst in. Howl. calld the Ivy bush the Howlets have livd int tyme out a Mynd Gilb: And shall Inioye it still for tho my sonnes by right as tis a part of his Inheritance I giue it the &amp; to thine heirs for ever Howl I thank yow sr, but pray If it be yor. sonns rights make not me accessarye to such a wronge, Gilb dost take it as a wronge Howl. yes to rob any man of his right, &amp; yow say thats yor sonnes, Gilb. Tis myne owne yet, and whilst I am alive, altho it be not (mentiond in my will) (Marginal note) in witnes of my wife I giue it the Howl. And when yow are dead she[le] shalbe my witnes that hele take it away agen, so she may be witnes of both sides and save the price of a subpena. Gilb put that vpon the tryall, this box of Iewells I leave vnto thy trust, if he deny the farme sell e'm, theyle raise a some sufficient to buy as rich a purchase, Howl. If I should purchase Newgate by the Bargaine Gilb: take em &amp; put 'em vpp. Howl. I do not vse to take boxes at any mans hands, &amp; yet pray madam be witnes that I do take this at my Lords, &amp; put it vp very thankfully too, Gilb wt h this condicion if my sonn kepe touch about the farme, thow givest it hym Howl who I give yor sonn a box so I may be soundly [buffetted indee«d»] boxt my selfe &amp; thats more then every man can saye. but the condicion of the obligation is vnderstood, read sealed &amp; subscribed [in the prsence &amp; witnes of my Lady], but the box of Iewells not to be delivered, till I the owle, be in full possession of my farme the Ivish bushe, &amp; all this in the presence &amp; witnes of my ladye, Gilb thow vnderstandst me right &amp; prethe Countess Count on thy soules perill, se it performd,—Cont. I shall sr. and now ffarwell my soule setts saile toth cape of blisse Instead of tears give me a parting kiss— Count Ay me my husband, helpe some Ladies helpe Howl: I shall need none of theirs, now yours nether, go into Closset &amp; comfort yor selfe, let me &amp; my fellows alone to take an order wt h the course Count. some weomen there to wind him— Ext. Howl. Leave all to me I tell yow, I that could turne him in his bed when he was alive, will make shift to winde him in A shete now he is dead; so so Ile make sownd work by yor Leave, now alls clere my lord my noble lord. Gilb now honnest How let all the vulturs gone. Howl. vultures? what meane yw by that sr. Gilb ffreinds, freinds &amp; Phisitians man, they flutter A bout a sick man like vulturs a bout a dyeing horse, Howl. wt. to peck the eyes out of his head sr. Gilb noe to pull the mony out of his purse, &amp; giue him hard words fort too as convulsion obstruction, pullulation, a litle more Phisick would ha made me hart sick«.» But to the present Busyness. The Reason why I assumd this Counter feit sicknes, wt h so much more of my Bosome, as serves for direction, I have allready given the ffurther suffyceings expect not, Is my disguise herse &amp; casket of gold ready. for the Conveyance of my funerall I trust the all other workeings Leave to the Event a plott vnknowne, no Artist can prevent Ext. Howl. A plot dee calt? tis a very darke one, &amp; devillish Intricate, I that had a hand in the casting of it, am all most lost In't: that he meanes to put his wives constancy &amp; sonnes Honesty to the tryall so far I see into this mill stone of knavery. And he that sees any further, must have clerer Eyes then a Howlet, But I must work close &amp; quick, bury a man alive &amp; [make] shirts &amp; make my weding shirts (Marginal note) of his windeing shete, &amp; thats but a theveishe tricke yowle saye, well doot I must &amp; yet am nether sexton nor grave maker nether Ext. [sc. ii] Enter Maryanus Varletti. Lords.— fflorishe Pro: Attend wt hout, our conference must be private) oh my Varletti Iewell of my soule I want apt language for expression thart myne soe much above my selfe, that like a covetous Landlord, I could thrust my life out of myne owne fee symple, &amp; become Tenant [to that of]/[at will to] thine, it is so pleasant &amp; comely Built Varl. A homely Cottage myne, &amp; as slutishlie kept in troth my Lord. onely I trym it vp somwt. the handsomer I confess, be cause it pleases yor highnes now &amp; then to Lodge yor pri?nc?ely affectionns &amp; kingly Love int. Pro. both lod ge &amp; live int my Varletti wood the surly Baronns Varl. Barrons! Bakon eaters? feare yow there mallice? are not yow a Romaine placd by great Cesar Prorex over Britaine &amp; shall yor hart wishe for a happines &amp; yow not reach it Pro. It should not my Varletti nor shall it Long if Archibald were come once Varl. who: the kersy Lord, the lynsy wollsy gentlem the yeomanly Barron, The bottome of Browne thred—the Pro. Title hym how thow wilt, that bells well cast &amp; tho plaine mettaile has a silver sound (Enter Archibald But no more words he comes. how now my Lord Archib Lord a Lead, call me old Tom: plaine home spon Archibald, thats title high Inough for my minde, &amp; sutable Inough to my manners, for my contry Bred me, myne owne shepe clothe me, &amp; myne owne beefe feeds me; I eat good Iannck &amp; drinke strong Barly brothe, homely yowle say but I finde it wholesome, Cesar has none [so good]. like it. yor ffrenche grape &amp; spanishe [wine]/[Berrye] comes not in my gutts, to wrangle &amp; beget advlterate quarrells in my Braine, to set whole states, &amp; kingdomes togither by the Ears, no Ile none of that ahem; I am sownd at hart too: And wt neede have I of yor Indean druggs &amp; Arabean spices &amp; gums to make a hotch potch on my mawe, &amp; beget a neast of neopolitane surffeits in my stomach, &amp; then spend more of a ffoolish phisitian to cast em vp, then I did of my knaveish Cooke to cram 'em downe. besides a blade or two of Saffron &amp; a sponefull of british Honye is Phisick worth twenty of em, Varl. yave showne sufficient reason ffor yor dyet but why so plaine Arch mary my Lord because I wonnot were oakes of my Back (as too many doe,) &amp; let my parkes go naked. Besides I cannot roast my Beefe in Harvest, nor warme my workmen &amp; Tenants at ?pmass, wt h a few silken shredds: no let my Woods growe &amp; make Leavy Tentes to howse my dere in, theile make a better showe there, then ether of my Back or in the mercers shop booke. poore widowes too, &amp; orphanes may have some comfort of the windfalls &amp; brushy vnder woods, for thats all there vailes. Pro. good president for Howskepers to write by but to our Business, How do the surly Barrons brooke the affront done to the Earle of clare Arch. how they Brooke it I know not, but that he has tane his death vpont I am too sure on, Pro The old man dead? Lillyes &amp; Roses spring about his grave, How do the comons take it Archib. as strong men do phisick all cropsick vpont, it stickes vpon the walls of there stomaches. &amp; wnnot disgest. tas poisend there allegance &amp; breakes out in pimples of conspiracy allready: wc h suffred to take head will grow to an Incurable rebellyon, Pror rebellion Arch. ranck rebellion. I am plaine homespon Tom, not a thred off fflatterye in me, theres but one Antidote to prevent it, &amp; that is to Banish Varletti. Pro. Banish Varletti Arch yes, restore there Antient priveledges &amp; customes, they have sworne to pluck the out of thy throane ellse, I am plaine Tom &amp; thow knowst I cannot desemble, Varl. thats somwt. strange tho. Being the devills Oracle Pro. Audatious traitors, yet I wrong 'em too they are trewly noble, I tell the Archibold (for I presume my secretts safe in the) wood but these Barrons Bend to me, [a] in favour of my dere freind Varletti here Varl of me? Tanti. I scorne the [pesaunts]/[bull befe eaters].—(.scornfully.) Pro. my fre thoughts have noble favours to bestow on em— Arch. I am glad I know't. hees a conng Angler tho, And Ile play a litle Longer wt h the baite, er I swallow the hooke by his Leave, If as yow say to make 'em yours be the point yow saile to: yow change yr compass, &amp; stere an other course, for tho (being chaste) they are feirce &amp; Indomitable as Lyons. fayre Language And Intreats will make em tractable as Lambes. Varl. your only way is to peticion em by treaty of pacification—tractable Pro. Intreat! shame take me then? Intreat my slaves. no if they scorne to knele vnto my Love Ile make em swym vnto my hate in blood Arch. why thats there Sum? bon?. they are like the Cimbrelins—never in there owne Element till they fight in blood, &amp; like them they paint there Bodyes full of artificeall wounds, to show the foe they delight &amp; take a pride in naturall ones, but se the names of the Arch-conspirators. Pro. Conon, Elidure, Devon, Tom Archibald. et tu Brute art thow amongst em too. Arch. who I: a prime man, I must seeme so at least, how should I steale away there secretts else, but the hart my Lord, the harts sownd &amp; so long Pro thow art so Iust «t»were synn but to suspect the Varl I like thy pollicy in this well, contynew it, seeme as arant a knave as the rankest traitor of em all. cavill at and «r.»quister govrmt (Interlined note) to draw them on— Arch. why so I saye, to draw them on, And hang yow vp, if I can mete a handsome opportunitye. Varl. that will show well, Arch. As I will handle it, but yor. honor. must pardon me if I be somwt saw cy wt h yow. Varl. wt h me thow canst not, call me (sicophant) pesantly vpstart Arch. ffoole, fidler Varl. Any—anything to drawe them on, &amp; doost here, when there splenes are swolne to [is «in»] the full height of bitternes. be sure to have a strong gard ready. Arch. to hale em to the block Varl. thow [apprehendst me]/[hitst my conceit of the head] most swetely—a trusty guard Arch. I shall, sr. &amp; be captaine of it too, looke toot old Tom, thast two menns workes to doe the traytors &amp; the trew mans.— Ext Varl: worke it off cleanly— thult get credit byte (Interlined note) I must Be banisht then Pro. yes, thus &amp; thus give me thy cloake take thow my Robe of state &amp; for thy hat were my Imperiall Crowne Send in the surly Lords, synce they repine fill [thow my]/[Cesars] chaire, [my]/[his] Conquests call all are thine Enter. Conon. Elidure, Deuon, Archibald. Varl. How prowd they looke Pro: Now over dareing Lords. wheres all yor reverence? Conon Heare in our Loyall harts not in our hatts [&amp; knees] like Romaine sicophants Pro not to yor king Deuon. yes weed vaile thus to Cesar for the, thow'rt but his Image at the most &amp; Britaines scorne to wor ship Images— Conon. How Cesars Image! thow art not so good thast given away thy title Lent out thy Crowne To a mock king [to] hele goe a feasting wt h. Pro to that mock king then I will make yow kneele Arch. Knele oh monstrous Idolatrye, do but marke me now my Lord) knele to a Calfe wt h a white face? a gilded Citterne head, he Lookes for all the world like a Babyes face painted of the Butt end af a Bandora; do I touch the trew string or no sir? Varl. thow doest it passing well, somwt too modestly— Arch: let me alone Ile mend that falt I warant yw Pro. suppose him baser, then yor splens can make him, hees noble tho, &amp; rarely quallifyed. Arch. oh admirably quallifyed, can tune a Citterne perhaps. a paire of virginalls. this will set the Iacke goeing or nothing Conon. And in the Honor of his new stolne office, the champio will breke Arch. did I not tell yow? Breake? breake wt. not a staff I hope Conon. a staff, a stick a warlike ffidle stick Pro. can my Varletti brooke thes scornes wt h sylence. Varl. yes sr. wt h sylence, a wise man canot give a foole a better answeare Arch. foole, thers a favour for yow Conon, Varl: &amp; yet, my lord to showe I am sencible, (tho careless) of there envye I will vouch safe a slite rebuke vpon em, Bean-chaweing Barrons home to yor contry farms— dispute the price of Beans &amp; buttermilk &amp; cast vp by yor flaile Arithmetick how many Barly sheves will cram a barne &amp; medle not wt h musick tis an Art too much above yor swineish Intellects Conon. swine Germaine Boore fatted wt h british mast compare wt h peeres go fum the tother Testerne out of a ffarmers windowe, sol fa me that now. Pro oreweeing Lords, How dare yow if trew subiects abvse our freind Conon. how darst thow if a kinge Abvse &amp; wrong those that wood be trew subiects, for a squeaking Hoboye a base Organ-pipe Deu. nay more how darst thow being Cesars prorex lend out his Honor s. Lease his royaltye, Elid. monopolize his Titles vnto pesants Conon. spruze Iack a dandyes, but be cownselled Loozen the raine of Iron oppression, Deu. vse the swith—gently &amp; forbeare the spurr Elid. shake off that viper Arch Throw that venemous toad to his native cradle the dunghill, &amp; wele lay our harts vnder our knees to do the service ?es If not Pro. aguard ?es A guard for whome Con? ha yow a mynd to se yr goodly Iewell dangle in the [eare of the] gallows [eare] Pro. yourselves base traitor s. know yw these names. Con? wt synon has Betraid vs? the names are ours. Pro. do yow not Blushe to owne e'm? Arch. not: nor to make good the oath belongs vnto e'm— Varl. well acted Archibald, &amp; thats to kill a kinge Conon no but pluck a pesant out of a kings Armes or him out of his chair?e? Pro. whats that but capitall treson, Arch. calt wt yow will, &amp; takt how yw please, cut of our heads yow maye &amp; if yow doe we care not, we yeild em ffor feit &amp; deserve to dy for haveing a traitor amongst. tyme will vnmask hym, Varl not in hast, if thow kepest thyne owne counsell [the old fellow]/[he] does it the best Pro. &amp; puts it off the cleanlyest. Bold conspirators resolute Catelines—theres no contending wt h em— Arch I told yr grace wt. metaile they were mad of Pro. Thow didst: &amp; this there resolution wakens our slumbering corage, Marianus Blushe &amp; be a shamd, to be out done in Honor yowle not Imbrace Varletti ?es Romaine never Pro. we scorne to aske it twice. And now to showe a Romaine Prorex one that have displaid Cesars spread Eagle over halfe the world disdaines a Crew of British muteeners yor fforfeit lifes we throw yow back againe to let yow know we scorne to wound a lyon an other man has chazd into the toile the game we kill, wele hunt our self— &amp; make the stowtest Hart in the English pale pay blody ters for ransome Arch He never spoake the Romaine tongue till now Pro. Home to yor factionns, let yor ratli?g droms, a maze the Aire wt h thonder, press yor Tenants and raise an Army all of Archibalds Varl. &amp; hes a tough old blade I warrant him Pro. worthy yor names &amp; Marianus Anger here stands the [price]/[dere] yow [throw]/[aime] at, [wyn]/[shoote] him faire, &amp; hees yor owne (Marginal note) Varl. But afore that yowle se me— hyde head horns &amp; all to choke y (Marginal note) wave Cesars dread full Eagle in the feild wt h my fate in her Tallents, teare it thence &amp; wt h it tread my titles into dust &amp; my wingd soule shall bere yor names to Heaven, &amp; file em mongst the worthyes. Pro. thow wordst it well Varl«e»ti Varl. Ile sword it better if it comes [once] to Action, onces Pro. The day of Bataile ?s Barons. vpon ffryday next Pro. Var. write it in British Blood Florish oes Bar in Romaine text Ext.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Actus secundus [sc. i] Sollempne Musick Recorders Enter 2: Heralts wt h gilt spurrs &amp; Gauntlet, a rich Herse wt h 5. pendantes, Armor. plumed Helmet &amp; sword vpon it, The countess &amp; yong Gerard as chefe mourners—then Archibald. Conon Devon, Elidure, Gentleme &amp; servants Howlet buzy Amongst e'm— Heralts Lead the rest in order after the Herce, [a] fflamyns lead it Gerard. Sic finis priami so much for the Mourners part, &amp; I think I have plaid it off handsomly too, for a halfe heire, &amp; why but halfe an heire, doth my father make a Cot Lamb on me, &amp; bycause my mother lawe brought me vp by hand, wt h a litle clarifyed whey may Buds [blancht Allmds] &amp; buttermilke, must she go halfes wt h me in the whole in heritance? No. His man Howlet gents. vsher to his Barbary mare, (Interlined note) Ta witta woes me out of a ffarme of 200 per A?n of the old Rents [too], but I have put in a Cave, at comon Lawe all ready. And a Civillean has promisd me wt h a trick of Tertullea, to set both there Rights beside the Cushion in that Court too: my mother pre tends a great zeale to turne vestall, &amp; that spark will I blow to a flame &amp; feed it wt h fuell of fare promise &amp; peace full composition &amp; ether foole or fright her out of my «in»heritac [if that] [faile Ile fyer her out of my Inheritance, by la?we?, Ile make her] [zeale fry fort else], Ile to [court A bout] it presentlye—worke vpon that &amp; to court presently Ext [sc. ii] Enter Prorex in his Gorget &amp;c. Varletti Pro we shall have stormes Varletti, kpe thy Tent some musick there, &amp; whilst we tread a march dance thow a measure. but wt pa?s that the plotforme of some Battaile, thow art still medling wt h danger, Varl Theres no [safety] bullwark like it: weare ner so safe as when in sight of danger. It ministers occasion to shon it this tho's a slite request I wood intreat yor highnes hand to ere the Batailes Ioind 'bout setling my estate, heres pen &amp; Ink sr. Pro: And hears my hand. thy shoulder—and yet staye first let me se if it be worth my signeing &amp; thy receveinge, to mary wt h my sister. slite one Indeed.—but hast thow ner a wife Varl. yes my good lord—but know— Pro. I may dispence wt h such slite Tryvialls, hast got her consent Varl. neither my Lord—but Pro. but thow knowst our will must be her law &amp; ther fore— Varl. now tis done Lor Pro. I thinke the penns not willing to the Mach twonot cast Inke, no matter my Varletti for beare till I have conquerd the Barrons &amp; then wc h will ad «mo»re vnto thine Honor Ile have e'm all vnder there hands subscribe both thy divorce &amp; mariage. Enter Capt Iordan Varl. yow much Honor me Pro. Ile do the Right Varletti—now thy news— Capt my Lord the Barons strangly penitent Humbly Intreat pro. pece do not flatter me Barranns intreat Capt. [humbly]/[submissive] vpon there knees, pror knees they have None, at Least like Elephants none that will Bend, no not to Iove him selfe, Capt. to yow they do tho Varl. if to one offs tis no matter wc h, I looke the liker a Tyrant of the Two, but go admit em youle be too mild give me yor crowne Agen, Enter all Barrons in shirts night caps &amp; Halters Pro. Olimpus sunck old Atlas on his knees Varl. a plot a plot, [tis one of]/[I smell old] Archibalds. Pro why how now Lords? what is yor warlik march turnd to a chamber maske, wt new web of tresonn isith lombe now. troe. Varl. [quick shutle monger, the conceit come I know thy workmanship] [&amp; dee here se that it Be a good one: or.—] Arch Do not mistake me Lords, old Tom Cannot Desemble, thinke it nether cowardize, nor desperate madnes, but resolvd Vallor &amp; well advizd Iugment, for haveing tryed &amp; found yor nature rather disposd to mercy then Tyrannye, to avoyd a generall ruyne I have by pollicy Brought in thes Rebells. Pro. a pr.ty change, both strange &amp; vnexpected Varl. How can it chose ist not Tom Archibalds: he has a quiver full of em, Conon. Humbly Intreateing that our trespass cause not our cuntryes [ruyne]/[bondage], nor the poore comon's Ruyne Deuon [And for our selves, so we admire thy Valour] [in thy fre pardon of our fformer treason,] out [make vs thy bondmens drudges slaves thy horse boyes drudges.] [Any thing Servile] Varl. [thow shalt be my page, rosyn my sticks &amp; string my fidles, a squirs place I can tell the] Pro. Rise trew harted Britaines men of yor corage Dare not Desemble rise Conon. most gratious conqueror, both our hands &amp; harts are at yor service Pro. &amp; my sword at yours &amp; for an ernest all taxationns save Cesars Tribut we take off, yor Lawes customes &amp; antient Charters we Restore ?es Britaine is Blest in such a conqueror Pro. but Rome more Honourd in such fe«o»daryes. as dare check vice, sat in Cesars throne Varl. They red a musick lecture vpon me Pro didt not show well twas one of Archibald Varl [trew] why so I say had it come from Any man but hym now to my suite my Lord Pro. &amp; well remembred it fitts the Tyme. Now reconciled Lords in signe all antient grevances are cancelld some pen &amp; Inke, altho we might comannd &amp; Be obayd: yet we request yor hands to new condicionns &amp; to Assertaine yw. theres no deceit, or fraudulent purpose in e'm theres our hand first Varl. Ile be yor deske my Lord. Conon. Nay now the vnicorne has dipt his horne in the Brook, the heard may drink frely &amp; never fere poisen. thers myne Deu: &amp; myne Elid &amp; myne Pro. Tom Archibald the last Archb. In place my Lord, but first in Love &amp; Dutye, give me the Penn. Varl. quickly old Tom tis for my private good Arch. Ist so sr. nay then—I am afraid tis for the publique [good]/[Hurte]. yow know me I am plaine Tom &amp; cannot Desemble, Varl. nay nay we know that, already come quickly thy hand, the desk will go nere to crack else— Pro. I I thy hand— Arch. my hand? I have a coople my Lord. but they are both blinde—pray out therefore give myne Ey Leave to see, &amp; tell em wt they subscribe, they may aswell out of blinde Ignorance, in stead of fredome, signe to the whole kingdomes slaverye Pro. do yow suspect our Love then? Arch. no my Leige nor to be plaine giue too much Credit toote, the rather cause it, concernes his privat good. Varl. why dost not thou Love Arch to abvse yow wt h all my hart, I am old Tom and canot Desemble Varl a very prety one Conon. How cann it chose it is old Archibalds Varl. but[nd] one of the worst that ever I hard come from him Arch &amp; since Has Lent me eyes I wood weare em in there Right plaes my head, &amp; not like the Lamie in my pocket. &amp; make myne ere my eye to follow other by the noise Pro. Are yow so coning? Varl. [a smoake dryed Mackerill, seeres &amp; derides yow to yor face] Conon. [Set downe] to thy hand old Tom the kings displeasd Arch. Let him be pleasd againe then, set my hand to Blancks &amp; Blinde charters. not I: tho yow Like spaniells fawne for a litle fredome, I scornt, Infants vnborne shall never cry out &amp; curse, old Toms hart for setting his hand to the Generall Ruyne, [torture me,] [teare me, rack me, roast me, boile me in scalding Lead bake] [me in Brimston Ixions whele, Sisiphus Stone, Prometheus] [vulture, Phalleris bull] Varl [&amp; Miloes ox stop thy throat] Pro. Are yow resolute: for his contempt we heare disrobe him of all atributes Honors &amp; titles of gentility &amp; charge yow vpon paine of our displeasure yow be not seene wt hin ten Miles of Court he that writes, sends our but confers wt h the shares in thy sentence se our will ? formde Arch. I thank yow gratious sr:. thes 60 winters Iu'e worne golden fetters, rowd and tugd An oare ithe state gally. now I am ffree I [a] humbly thank yr highnes &amp; wt h the scole boy Say gratias great sr. yave given me Leave to playe. Varl. so Phalleris Bull go chew the cud go—&amp; now may it please yor highnes: shew thes my Honorable freinds wt they subscribd— Pro. wt h all my hart, and yet twere far more honor to hav't confirmd in a full [parlament]/[Senate] first Varl. And so twere too, but I ha not the virtue of Abstinence in me. Pro. Read then my Lords, had old Tom Archibald knowne the contents he would ha ben the first Conon troth that he wood. but is yor highnes in Ernest Varl. do yow not see his hand toot, it cost me some Labour I confes &amp; much art to work him toot. but Exitus acta probat the end ???s all—how do yow like it Lords amb. [Deu] Exceeding well Varl troth Ime bownd vnto yow, pray my Lords read it Conon It is fully decreed &amp; absolutely concluded by the Prorex of Britaine &amp; Lord Barrons of the same, that signior Varletti shall forth wt h be—be— Varl. Maryed to the kings sister Honoria. nay out wt h it, there wilbe work for Bells &amp; Boonefyers I can tell yw. Conon. That there will in trothe, that Varletti be forthwt h banisht the court &amp; dureing the Prorex pleasure confynd Varl. Mery mistake in troth my Lords, but I canot blame yow pray let me read it Pro. on thy Life touch it not, go se it proclaimde Elid Ile put on Wings &amp; fly &amp; this make not work for bells &amp; boone fyres Blame me.— Ext Varl. stay art thow mad, sure yow mistooke the paper sr. Pro. I thinck I did too, but willingly mistooke it. why thow [base]/[high] mynded, but Low merited pesant hast thow a wife, noble &amp; virtuous I but one sister &amp; she trewly chast &amp; darst thow tympanied wt h a litle Honor once motion Mariage Varl. my most gratious Lord Pro. out fawneing parasite &amp; graceles varlet Empty Impertinent, one of fortunes fooles [[seest]/[canst] thow not [se]/[yet] how she has flattered the] [wt h gawds &amp; golden apples full of smoake] [vp to the very Zenith of her whele] [how she has fed &amp; dandled the wt h ffavours] [given the thy fill of Honor Title office] [&amp; all the various delicacyes on Earth] [&amp; now thow scornst the gods in thy Excesse] [she hurles the Headlong to the Antipodes.] thow knowst thy sentence, come not nere the court thy life we lend the. Varl. [Ile]/[scorne not] thank the fort but tis a Maxim. such as like me aspier to tread on starrs, wt h Phaeton ride in fier Ext Conon. patience great sr. twas one of Archibalds, but Exitus acta probat the end crowns all.— Ware that old lad, but here to laugh a litle Pro. he was to rashe, he wood not giue his blessings Enter. Gerald season to growe &amp; Ripen In, but pluck e'm in the grene Bud, whose that yong [Geraldine]. Claridon? wellcome to court, we are sorry for yor loss how does yor mother law the noble countess Ger. Like a good bowle ill turnd, she ronns quite from the Byass of her Sexe, and as the fooleishe girle that got a rizeing in the Kydneys wt h eating of Lamb stone forswore all mutton for a twelf month &amp; a daye, so she for the death of my father, have for sworne all mankinde for Terme of life, &amp; has maryed her self to Vesta's monastary Pro. A noble course &amp; a Religious Ger. do, but se how she has disposd of her transitoryes &amp; yowle swere it Pro. she has conferd her whole estate on yow. wt hout condicion, gift nor legacy to be Ducted Conon. a good mother law. Ger Is she not my Lord? wood yor son &amp; heire had [one]/[half a dozen] no worse, Pro: ffor her sake &amp; yor owne, &amp; his thats dead, wole giue yow Honor. Ger As much honor as yow please, but no office &amp; yow Love me, for I Being a wild yong heire, [&amp; none of the wisest, nether, «w»oold] be haveing more wealth than ether heale or wit to manage it wold be (Marginal note) Imagind I bought it, And some of the Court wits would ex officio beg me &amp; the fooles paradice myne office over myne eres. fut I remember my fathers case concerneing the Champeon &amp; Pro. we do not meane to trouble yow wt h any ther fere no office I be sech yr mt e (Marginal note) yor first Imployment shalbe to observe Varletti newly Banisht from the Court Ger. Varletti? is that Alamyre, [&amp;] solfade out of the Court gamoth I owe him a good turne for a Cort curtesy he did my father, Pro. pay him home now then, hees in suspect for treasonn, bait hookes to cach hym vrge his Bannishment point at revenge, &amp; if yow chance to scatter in draweing of em on, som thing like treason, yow have comission fort, but Be not too bolde, Ger I warne yow my Lord, I have had a monstrous mynd to speake treason of a litle one, I have whisperd &amp; whistled it to my shadow in private, &amp; now I have comi«s»ion to speke it Viva voce, a fore company yor highnes could not have done me an honr like it, never a noble Britaine her Loves me ?es we all love &amp; Honor yw. Ger. no the king I thank him has honord me Inough: onely if yow Love me do me one curtesy Conon. It must Be a strange one Ger. no no, a very com? one since the Romans came in, onely to beg my Lands &amp; liveings while I am in the state of a trew [man]/[subiect] Con? [yar no traitor yet]/[why do yow intend to be a trayter] Ger. I am Inioynd [&amp; do fully pur pose] to speake treason &amp; then som roman will begy«l» my Lands &amp; my life too, [&amp;] whether I [do] speake treason or no, if they do but say I did, theyle ha my life &amp; be but fer Love off my Lands, &amp; I wold once (cheat a bagarly Romane &amp; I had but the wit toot (Marginal note) Pro So we conceive yw get a pardon drawne so yor offence be onely verball &amp; growe not by act of treason we will signe it Ger. theres som signe of Love in that yet; the plowman may whistle the shepherd hoope &amp; the Huntsma Hollow there harts out, but if teache em not all to speake treason, hang me wt h my pardon about my neck, [when it] Ile go &amp; get it drawne prsently— Ext. Pro. Thow needst noe tutor, now my Honourd lords we have in our Iust sentence on Varletti &amp; tryall of old Archibalds Alleageance troubled yor expectac?ns, but Tyme shall make all clere, &amp; teach me so much Art hence forthe to throw our favours one Desert Conon yave Drawne the fforme of a rare prsident but for old Archibald Pro. no more of him to save the head we [may well wound]/[hazard but] a limb. [sc. iii] fflorish Enter Howlet in som od disguise [Howl. [my yong Lord playes the old devill a mongst vs: has stript] [my lady stak naked of her Inheritance, &amp; Hooted poore howlet] [out of his Ivy bush too, has warants against me bout the box] [of Iewells too, but Ile warrant my self of them, And to blinde] [Iustice that is too Blinde allready. I am flowne into a new] [fashion, tho but a scurvy one, I have sene some scarce soe] [handsome, they say mad grig sells knocking downe ale here] [abouts, Ile spend one halfe dozen to [spend]/[showe] my new sute &amp;] [recreate my selfe a litle. byr' leave ho. grig of grig hall wt hin] [Enter grig: [yor freind &amp; mr grig Brandwell is wt hin—a mile of a] [knave at any tyme. yor Busyness wt h me. [yor]/[yow seme a man of] education &amp;] [one that can accomidate—your Business)—] [Howl. [a poore cuntry Artist, a kind of hanger on a yor dangling] [proffession: now yor name Being so famous amongst vs] [in the countrye, has drawn me vp to the City onely to tender] [homage to thy Aplesquireship.] [grig. [Art thow a Brother of the cord? [but thy accomodations show it] most hardly wellcome,] [theres not a ropeman Nozemonger, wt hin the pale of America] [but grig will vouch safe to [take]/[accomidate] halfe a dozen of ale &amp;] [Tobacco on for the function sake, Indeed my Anuall tribute] [wt cuntry man, Accomodate me that now] [Howl [Cumberland by birth. Hempshire gave me education] [fflintshire Infucd my nature, &amp; break neck shire a trade] [Grig. [I am thy country man in that kinde once a moneth, I shold] [be sory else, [here] all this [I accomodate] to old turne over the ferman of the Iury a] [good substantiall fre holder &amp; yeoma of my wardrop, pledg him] [&amp; now where is thy residence—] [Howl. [my [lay] dwelling [is]/[was] at Mayd stone in Kent I am at this tyme a non resident] [grig. [And thats has bene a good thriveing seat, yave rich pippins brother] Howl [And so many poore Iohns &amp; cuntry Russettings theyre scarce] [worth the pareing. I assure yowsr. I have not had to my] [vailes, a whol?e? shirt or a conducible smock, I sell em to] [ragmen &amp; for my wollen wardrop I ha made that over by] [Lease parroll, to a marchant map maker in kent strete.] grig [By this can I both Credit &amp; pittie the, for I my self who am write] [most exquisit, for hang, drawe, &amp; picth vnder poale Againe,] [haveing my Lunary Tribute, from the triple tree nere padinton] [The maine traffick &amp; whole venter of Hazards bridge waping] [Croyden &amp; kingston wt h other By blows &amp; ?cro?ss capering] [Accomodations can hardly live like] [a man of any good Credit, yet now &amp; then I eat a swann py wt h a] [bold yeoman. &amp; accomodate a dishe of Tripes wt h a [greazy]/[fatt] seriant,] [Howl. [Hears A health to the swan py; I love the yeomo well; but] [for Trillebub the Seriant twas disputed last day who had] [the more charitable trade, the Sariant or the Hangma] [but the Iudgement went of our side, for twas decreed the] [Sariant brings men Into trouble, &amp; the Hangma putts em out] grig By the thomb ring of Iames my Deare Benefactor accomodate (Marginal note) [Truly the Iudge was iust in his censure,] enter. dampit Huntit, Kenwell. [but whome ha we here my very good freinds] [Dampit, Kenwell &amp; Huntit, by the thomb ring of Iames.] [&amp; penny pot companions wellcome here is a very Loveing brother] [of the nooze, come vp a purpose to [see me]/[afflict or visit me], pray Accomodat] Ken [very ob sequiously wellcome] Damp. [most auspitiously I grete yow] grig. [I thank yow gentleme, som A gran Iury of freshe canns who accomodats the table,] [&amp; now Being so hapely drawne to gither let all, vs all hang on the] [same string of fraternity—] Howl. [Like a rope of Onynes by the necks so I may have the cutting of yw downe «or» pilling of yow] grig. [&amp; acco?odate a litle of the Antiquity &amp; estimation of our severall] [callings, &amp; my Brother of Breakneack, shall wast spend &amp; consume his] [ripe ripe Iudgmt. wc h of vs 4. is the most necessary &amp; acco?date member] [forin a com? wealth] Damp. [but will not yor brother be a partiall man] Howl. [A martialls man no sr. I belong to the shreve, &amp; will hang] [my owne mr vpon the file of Execution—] grig [If the Law accomodate at Least he may or I ether] Damp. [first then for the reputa?on of Lombards. we derive our antiquity] [from the Iews, in memory of whome we canot indure] [to live like good christians, yet for formality sake we go like em] [&amp; are somtymes taken to be of them, too, by wc h meanes we] [rise to offices as church wardens &amp; collectors, when indeed] [we are mere out-side men, &amp; absolute neglectors of the poore] [[I meane,] &amp; so in tyme we growe to be Mr s. or rather marrers] [of our parish, Deputyes nay absolute despicers of our ward.] grig: [very good accomodation and a proper, moisten yor quaile pipe] Damp. [If the rich call vs to accownt, we have a trick to stop there] [mowt hes wt h a Hartichoake py at a dynner in the guest howse] [if the poore gromble, or complaine, whip away wt h em, we] [kepe blew coats in paye for the same purpose] Howl. [Yow lashe it out I se then, but indeed Mr Dampit I did not thinke] [yow had bene so charitable. but sure I am perswaded. that] [Honest men &amp; fooles are yor best Customers, for the proverb] [sayes a crafty knave needs no Broaker: now Mr. Decoye.] Kenw. [Thus as I am a cheat or a dicer I allwayes cary my Bale about] [thats my protection, as I am a shark my mistery as a stale my] [vocation—as a diver my quallity as a nip my calling as a vagra or wandring star] [my prambulation, as a stand my station, as a list my practize] [as a thefe my lawe, as a hy lawyer my proffit &amp; as a cut purse] [my Handy Craft for my liveing comes in at my fingers ends, now all] [thes trades well practisd &amp; put to gither are like] damp: [Wt. are they like [mr]/[brother] Kenwell] Kenw [mary they are very like to breake any mans neck at the gallous] [that vse em, I scapt it hardly my self [next]/[last] Sessionns] Howl. [Theres som hope on the next then, a my word a most Int«ri»cate] [proffession &amp; Ingenerous. now for the honor of deformers.] Hunt [know then we are wind Instruments yr country lawyer practises] [much vpon, our best concord is grownded vpon discords, vpon] [wc h roning descant, we beget voluntary devision, quarrells] [causes suits &amp; actions, our faith is wholy Included in the penall] [statutes &amp; our Relligion grownded vpon writts of Error, we sell or] [conscyences to purchase our places, &amp; if we chance to vndo, two or] [thre Lords of the soile, yw must not think it envy but want of good] [mannor s: one trick we borow too frô the knights oth poast] [to have our heareings when our ears are lost.] Howl. [I mary sr thes are lofty virtues indeed; a co?o capacity] [cannot reache e'm. now Brother grig for our function] grig. [I shall accomodat in Brefe, first we have the trew virtue] [off Hospitallitie, for we entertaine all that come to our office of wt. degre] [age, sex or condicion so ever, next we go beyond all precept] [counsell or roprhension, for if a thefe, grow so obstinate] [as the whole bench cannot perswade him to Leave his trade] [let me but talk wt h hym in to my office a litle, &amp; Ile so accomodate] [him wt h a trick that I have he shall nere have a mind toot while he Lives after, [we]] to shut vp all, we (Marginal note) [are Mr s. of the Black bagg, into wc h some of all religions] [&amp; proffessionns drop, we are the period of controversies,] [the vltm? vale of [contentions,] complements the finis catastrophe, And] [conclusion, of treasons rapes muders ffellonyes &amp; burglaryes] [&amp; to accomodat &amp; end all, we are the but end of the lawe] Howl. [And that but, hast thow Broacht &amp; drawne downe to the very] [Lees made our trade, the top &amp; top gallant of all trades [we can giue the proudest mate of em all the chek. chek him vnder the chin] (Interlined note) thow] [hast wonn the Hempen wreath from 'em all, &amp; ther tis.] grig [no I love to accomodat my freinds were it thy self good brother.] Kenw. [even share it Betwixt yow, &amp; now to matter of more consequenc] [there lives a lusty widow here at walltamstowe, faire rich] [&amp; Bounte full, now I knoweing my self a man well built] [outwardly by nature &amp; well to Borrow my Brothers grigs] [word, accomodated Inwardly by art, am resolvd to woe &amp;] [confident to win her, if mr Dampit will but furnish me.] grig. [Accomodate brother accomodat had bene the more proper word] Damp. [I will both fit, furnish accowtre &amp; accomodate the at all] [points, &amp; prices, &amp; for thy more grace wele all Ride along [wt h the,]/[to countnance the]] Ken: [if a poore gentlema may stand so gratious wt h yow] Damp. [freindship forbid else, Ile furnish yw all] [furnish—furnish a horse garnish a table but accomodate a man I saye a«v»ay«n»e] grig. [Accomodate me, like a sterne solyer, in a buff Ierkin [wt h]] [? tercins Bilbo &amp; a Bownceing-Bumbasket—my name alexander Han: dangerfield] [—captyne of the garis«on» in gvnpowder Ally &amp; bowtice for the rest] Damp. [ Da: that will make a bonny nose but (Marginal note) Ile fit yw all &amp; my selfe too: in my damask coat. my Bulloigne] [Breech. my chaine of gold, my thomping thomb ring, my] best [Brooch by st. Martin set in my steple Crownd Bever] Ken. [&amp; yor Brasill staff wt h the fooles head vpont, Limping a litle as] [if yow had a spice of the gowt] damp. [spice quoth yw. my great toes pepperd wt h that a pax ont] grig. [very fit accomodation. Indeed tis the flesh brand the devill setts vpon his] [howshold servants [servants] &amp; vserers espetially—wlld colts] Dampt. [[then] has markt me for his owne then, I were his seale at] [Armes of my great toe, [but come lets furnish for yr Iornye]] Howl. [Theres a scarfe to weare it in, &amp; so yow Ioyne hemp &amp; tow totigether] grig [very [fit] genuyne accomodation &amp; [a] proper, but for the reckoning who accomdates yt n] Damp. [[tis] twill prove but a Brabling matter in the end &amp; cause we being ffreinds wold be] [loth to ffall out [for a triffle,] Giue the stranger Leave to pay [it] all] [Twilbe a meanes to make him know vs better an other tyme] Howl. [wt h all my hart gentlem? &amp; thank yw to. &amp; if I mete yow at the widows. I may] [chance to accomodate yow in yor kindes for this. &amp; so I leave] [yow to yor good fortunes—adew good brother of the corde.] grig [farwell swete frater of the nooze thou showst thy generous educati] [farwell &amp; be hangd come gentl to horse]</field>
      <field name="fulltext">[Actus Tertius] [sc. i] Enter. Varletti: Kathrine Kath. Banisht from Court? Varl. yes Banisht from court, &amp; like a sentles hownd past servyce rebuked &amp; rated home to my kennell, by the Barons &amp; the king Kath. the king! thow shouldst, I durst &amp; wood ha told the['m] king he dealt not like him selfe, but tis a curse ffollowes a woman that like me will marry a man of a Mans makeinge, capable of no prferment more then cap and knee can scrape from a kings smiles, &amp; wt. are they? but dyeing vanities, blossomes that fade &amp; fall off ith bloome, wert thow a Man yet? Varl man, mad woma: wt am I else a beast? but no more thow dost but ad wings to the winde &amp; throw oyle into Eatna, for how ever I seme to force a slavish patience I could [chew my] in [the] a [noble]/[mere] Bitternes of vexation chew my gall and spit it in the ffaces of the proud Barronns. But that forgetfull Prorex Kath. Now I comend thy spirt &amp; will Ioyne strengthes in thy Revenge. thine ere yong Geraldine sonn to [the] Earle [of] clarydon— Varl. [Hates me for wearing of his fathers title, champeon] Kath. [that hate (wt h a trick I have) Ile turne to Love] Varl. [trust not to [that] tricks, hele out [trick]/[Iugle] vs both if it come to [that]/[tricks]] out [once, [he is as]/[for] I am [faithfully]/[credibly] Informd, he is by the king [to get]] Imploid vpon intelligence to get wt hin &amp; betray my Loyalty] Kath: [thers subiect for my Wit to worke on then,] out [I know hym to be desperate, Humerous strong] [in Tenants &amp; in [freinds] Allyes.] Varl. [&amp; wt can yor wit worke out of all that now.] Kath. [make him a freind &amp; beare go An equall share venturer.] [in yor maine faction] [I mary sir Hic Labor Hoc opus. this were a Labour worthy a she Hercules] Varl. [such a trick handsomly playd woold be a good help to a weak game Indeed] Kath. [feart not tis sure, now sr the news wt h yow.] Enter. serv. yong Geraldine Kath: the man I wisht admit him Ile to work streight Varl. &amp; wt must I stand Idle Kath. Onely salute &amp; complement, observe out. [be wise &amp; make the best vse of yr knowledg] [for warnd halfe Amd.] Varl. [but for the trick yw talkt on.] Kath. [the rest]/[Leave that] to me, yw shall se prety sport] A Lamb beguile a ffox Ile hunt close fort. Enter Gerald wt h a Pardon Ger Now Rome for a knave cu privelegio [for] &amp; vnder pardon being spoken I am a kinde of state Intelligencer, [«bu»t] Varl. my Lord of Clare, wt. er yr Busyness be yar nobly wellcome Ger: noe great Busyness sr. onely kynde visitacion to yor self &amp; to renue acquaintance wt h my prety play fellow yor wife Varl. they ha byn at game then, why tis kindly done, And to the best Intertainment, a dispicd Iaile can yeild (my howse at this tymes no better) yar frely wellcome Ger Soe much I hard, &amp; wonder at yor more then manly fortitude to beare it, that proud Baron Conon— Varl. is a noble gentlema &amp; worthely wears the Honor s I put off Ger. whither yow put em off, or the prorex pluckt em off [I] In dubio est is a dowt amongst Doctors [know not]: But I thought to have found yow in the full heat &amp; Harvest of action, writeing &amp; receveing letters. solliciteing ffreinds somoneing Tenants, &amp; busy as a Bee, in building vp the [body] frame of a new ffaction, if he has any spark of revenge in him this will kindle it or nothing, Is yor life in chase by Lyons &amp; Tigers? &amp; yow ronn a scaperloiteing wt h boyes after Beetles &amp; butter fflyes the very thought ont mads me, Varl. never moves me: Bid thy freind wellcome Kate I wisht for a chaire of ease &amp; now I hate— Ext Ger. a stoick a mere Tymonist I may make wast paper of my pardon, theres no such vanity as speaking off treason in Rerum natura Kath. pray sr a word Ger wt h me swete play fellow? Kath wt h yow sr. tho my husband like a hogg— Ger. A swine, a very Boarish Animall &amp; Lookes— Kath. no higher then the trough he eats his huskes in I have an ey—to wepe myne owne &amp; a hart to compassionate [hart] [to mourne] my freinds wrong Ger. How yor freinds—a my life in Love wt h me— Kath. yes yours. for how ere clowded. yow are in deathes black booke as depe as we Ger I in deathes Bookes for wt. I never bought nor sold wt h [that slipery m'chant]/[him], how the devill should I come in his Bookes then, &amp; for wt. Kath. for feare yow should revenge yor fathers murder. Ger. my fathers murder thers treason a cing the mints going already Ile help to stampe it, they wc h they (Marginal note) Kath yes they poisend him. Ger The Barrons? Kath. &amp; the prorex. Ger: did I [mary sr.]/[not say soe] why this is treason to my harts Desire, It honyes me A litle more &amp; I surffeit: I hard such a whisper Indeed Kath. that whisper now is growne to a full voice &amp; sayes the prorex poisend Clarydon,— Ger. And this be not as trew treason as ever Tobacho shop or Taverne yelds thers no spirit in Canary. Kath. &amp; cause my husband wood not yeild consent they Banisht [me]/[him] the court. she draws me into play spite of my teth (Marginal note) Ger. &amp; sent me a Batfowleing to catch him in the limbush of Kat. Intelligence, I could have told yow that [too]. afore too. his life they cannot touch tho. Ger. nor I nether he lyes at too sure guard, &amp; I comend him fort too. some of there coppie holds Ile touch to the quick tho. Kath. Las wt s one single valour gainst so many could yow but worke my husband to yr faction Ger. How work him toot, he wonnot, canot sha not deny me Kath. If my best Art can stand yow in stead he shall not Some pen &amp; Inke a charitable pittye [move] to se so swete a disposition wrongd moves me to this: you shalbe ruld by me Ger. by the? in any thing, why thart my patrone, my protection my Polletico my pardon is a meere parenthesis to her, (&amp; yet if Varletti should stand off: as all things considerd, he has no great reason to come on. I shalbe as able to powder the prorex as he was to poisen my father, Kath. so, I have done, perv'st, and as yow like the sence, sub scribe or cancellt. Varl now for the trick she talkt on— Ger. Reads. Noble Varletti, for my fathers most Inhumaine murder, I purpose a sharpe &amp; sodaine revenge, In wc h I request yw to Ioyne &amp; share fortunes, the Prorex dead, we two wilbe competitors in the crowne: Subscribe it: yes both wt h my penn &amp; sword. the pen.—yor s. Geraldine. Varl. I mary girle This trick cleanly tane vp may Be worth a crowne Indeed Ger Brave amazonian. this thy Noble encoragement, name of a crowne, and easy demonstrac?n to attaine it, makes me all fyer, &amp; active flame, wele kill him at table kneling at his Devotion Kath that were to charitabler. be ruld by me, to morow the king mainetains a sollem?ne hunt for the stag Royall, at wc h my husband &amp; yor self Disguisd, haveing singled him Ger. no more, theres thy fee, when I am king shalt ride in purple, be sargeant of the Coife &amp; crossclothe, but will thy husband Ioyne hands thinkst— Enter Varletti Varl. Both hands &amp; Harts, I overhard all, &amp; like it so well, as give me but that noat to evidence my Loyalty. when yow come to be king once, as that Honor I dare promise y«w» Ger. And Ile desyre no greater, takt wt h my hart Varl but it will cost some heads— Ger Never feare thine, for the Porex dead, &amp; by thy hand for tis my purpose to giue the the Honor of it, both court &amp; comons will hold it an Act in the being A Romaine worth Cronocle at Least if not Meritorious— Kath. &amp; not wt hout cause, for by it they shake off all slavery. Ger. redeme there fredomes, displant the Romaine Garison Varl. chose &amp; proclaime a king of there owne nation Kath And who so fit to succed Tarqu? as Brutus—yor self Ger. And I had but his berd, his gravetye, we want a beard a man of experience to countenance &amp; direct vs. Kath &amp; well remembred? wt. saye to my vncle Percy banishd by the Prorex into ffrance. Varl. [a man made for the purpose swete Kate write for him stregh] Ger [Percy. I should know him: wt was that Percye] Varl [brave mettled fellow, Humorous blody &amp; somwt. vainglorious] Ger. [thre admirable virtus in a co?der. Allex. had none better.] Varl. [hees Eminent in em all tho.] Ger. [write for him streight, &amp; when I am king once as let me se] [all this is vnder pardon yet, for till the stroke] [be given alls veniall no condicion broake] [&amp; tho I canot rule my tongue Ile governe my hands.] [let my Romaine spirit take the Honor of that] [write for [him] thine vncle streight; the prorex downe.] [we twole be rivalls in the British Crowne] Ext. Varl. [when I have done wt ht, but haveing reacht it once] [Ile stand alone tumble my Ladder downe] [if he slip from me, or but one step mistread] [I haves owne hand here to strike off his head.] Kath. [thank her that got it] Varl. my she Machevill excellent in all, best both at good and ill— ext [sc. ii] Enter Clarydon, throw of his cloke Apeare disguisd as the waspe. Gilb. ffarewell old Clare, &amp; welcome mr waspe, In this fantastick &amp; ridiculous habit Tyme gives me Leave to play [thy] the foole, &amp; [for] make a foole both of the Tyme &amp; my self too, &amp; fooleing in this Censorious [&amp; over Curyous] age, is a fashion that some [of yr witts will vouchsafe to walk in—yor Timonist or as] [we call e'm Tyme-ist is yr onely man—for he is allowd or] [at least takes allowance, to raile at Authority, gird at [the]] [governement &amp; vnder pretence of strikeing at pety Abuses] [[beg] in others, begets &amp; generates greater in himself—&amp; in] [this swarme do I buz and make a noise but sting none, noh—] [I differ from yor tyme-ist in that] [my Wife, a faire &amp; I hope a good one, thrust from her] [right by my vngratious [son] boye lives in disguice here at] [Waltamstowe, wt h whome to make tryall of her disposyti?] [I live [as] a servant, my h? man howlet I have sent in quest] [of my sonns behavior, &amp; here he comes—how now disguizd] Enter Howl. Howl. A litle transformd, my metamorphosd lord, a poore Tassell that dangles at the purse string of the fashion, but I have most contagious news to tell yw of yr sonn; Gilb. wt ist knave dooth he kepe a good howse &amp; governt Noblye. Howl. for howskepeing, he kepes the very same howse yw did, &amp; all land to y but has got such a palsy ins elboo wt h shakeing a dy—all is i«n» danger to be cast away at a cast, for good chere I think he kepes more, then ever yw could or wood do. Gilb some comfort in that yet how dos he kepe it How mary so close, that a poore man may sooner break his neck then his fast wt h him—hees very temperate tho, for to avoyd gluttony and drunkenes he kepes a leane kichin, &amp; a dry Butterye, has casheird all yr old servingme, &amp; kepes onely a Coach man, two footmen and a page. Gilb. [that all his traine] Houl. [Tis well the peacock has so much. considering the course he take] Gilb. [course wt. course] How. [why hees turnd scholler sr., goes to schole, &amp; studies the Art of] [memory (the wrong waye,) wc h is to fforget his father &amp; not] [remember his freinds, [w] he proffits wondrous well too for he knowes not him] [selfe all ready, has made my Lady a prentise turnd her tyme over] [to the vestalls [for]/[&amp;] me poore Howlet he has thrust out of my] [Ivy bushe, &amp; threatens to hang me for the box of Iewells you wot on, &amp; to] [shonn the offycers like other gentlm I flew into a new fashion,] Gilb: [well let him ronn his course Ile shortly course hym out on't.] [Ile se yw provided for, wt h one yow litle dreame on. go wet yor beak ithe butery ywle sing the clerer] Exit Howlet Enter. Countess. Luce Count. wt. thinkst thow of this country life my girle my constitution doeth like it far beyond the Honorable miserye that waits on greatnes—pride is here a stranger ffly blowne ambition has no being heare here snarleing Envy has no residence heres Earthes content, &amp; here I do not feare the slipery fall of noble wrechednes Gilb. she makes som vse of her retirement I comend her for that ye Count: The vigilant Cock is heare my wach &amp; clock &amp; my sonn Diall is the sonn it selfe, a quire of Harmeles [Birds swet] swet-tongd nitingales, (Harmonious [vntaught] Choristers of natures teachinge) do dayly chawnt me various madrigalls The plowman whistles and the milkmaid sings &amp; heres the life that [trew contentme]nt full sufficeings brings— Luce. In my Mynde tis better being here, then sit bloweing a cole wt h the vestalls, rather then I wood be shut vp from the company of man as they are, I would ventur of six husbands in seven weeks tho I ware sure to bury every mothers son of em— Gilb. Thow woldst ha bene a good wife fer a bucher, tho lovst flesh so well, Count ah wench the Love of my deare lord deceast has closd my hart gainst thought of second Mariage, Gilb shas not forgot me yet then, some comfort in that too— Count. And yet thow seest I am dayly cloyd wt h suitors &amp; for the Honourd port that I have kept I still affect a bounteous howskepeing &amp; canot chose but give e'm freindly welcome yet I could wish I ware well rid of em, Gilb Lass good Penelope, but Ile take away that trouble from the p?tly. Count But wheres that downe-right honnest man the waspe his harmeless buzzing highly does content me, vpon my word I like his open waye of playnes, tas no trick of flatery int. I am perswaded has had better breeding then he makes showe off, but here he comes himself now Mr. waspe where ha yw byn buzing this morneing Gilb Marry Mr s. I have byn buzzing &amp; huming to find out that wc h any man may finde wt hout seekeing Count. whats that Gilb. knavery Roguery cozenage villanie, I have sene the devill &amp; the flesh beat the worlds eyes out, &amp; now being blinde she takes vpon her like gill Iustice &amp; mistakes every thing, so that an honest man can nether speke nor doe any thing in safetye, but mr s. I haue a suit to yw. Count. I have too many suiters allready Gilb I must prefer one more tho, not to be yor husband but yor good-man, in the sence of service I meane, he has but a few good condicions &amp; ther for ant plese yw let him relate e'm him selfe, Come sr a— Enter Howl: re herse some of yr best parts Howl. Trewly Mr i s. when I was a stripling I cheated a lawyer of his lyeinge, &amp; in less then a yeare he was allmost beggerd for want of it, &amp; I was never the Richer [wt h it] fort nether, because I lack the skill wit to make trew vse it, so I in pity gave] it [him] the pore fellow Agen, &amp; he has thriven &amp; growne devilish] rich by it] Count A very Charitable part &amp; a conscyonable] Howl. [he belongs not to that court tho, he will not ly at so low] [a prize, then I met wt h a poore Taylor, &amp; robd him] stet [of his truth wc h I have kept ever synce, for the] [Taylour wonnot have it Againe, if I wood give him] [mony to boot, for hees now Mr of his parish and his cloak] [butterd quite thro wt h velvet] Gylbert [so then by this it Apears thow canst nether ly nor steale] [trulye] Howl. [trewly I can do nether] Count: [I like the the better, &amp; Intertaine the] Howl. [I doe Imbrace yor—Intertainement &amp; kiss the cheke of—] [my good fortune into the bargayne, &amp; will enter my name] [into the buttery Booke, very subito— [but whome ha we here h]unph—] [my neast of Nynnes come to accomodate the reckning? Ile] [provide em a cage to sing alle paid in presently.] [Exit Howlet] Enter 4. Count. [more suiters yet wellcome all gentleme.] Kenw. [Retire &amp; know yor places. I tooke yow as Aids not peremptory] [corivalls &amp; therfore fall off.] gr: [I am a soulyer, the word of courage is come on; &amp; ther fore] [ffall yw off into the Reare, Ile have the Honor of the van my selfe] [if yow will accept the affectionate service of an vnconquerd] [Martialist, Hanniball, Cesar Dangerfeild, gunpowder Ally] [my Millitary Garizon, I freely tender it, I am by title a] [Solyor.—Alexander hymsclfe no more, &amp; tho my function be] [bloody &amp; all for purple Execution—] Gilb. [talks like a Hangma—] Count: [conffesses him self a cuthroate.] gr. [yet it is knowne I never put any Man to the sword, wt hout a] [Iusticiary tryall, In all my designes I have byn victorious] [&amp; never came home empty of Spoile, all wc h, wt h my sword] [gauntlet, &amp; swete selfe. I humbly prostrate at yor service] Gilb [Thanks good Horatio (but take thy glove Againe, she ansers] [no challenges, I am her champeon: How dee like him widowe] Count [Somwt. to bloody if I shold mary yow sr. I must bynde yow to] [the peace, for I am a very coward: [the next]. How now] Hunt: [I am by quallity a lawyer, &amp; yet no lawyer but a cuntry] [sollicite r. &amp; have skill to vndo more clyents in one returne by] [my single knavery—then 20. cyty coun sellors. can soader] [a gen in a terme wt h all ther vnited Honestyes. I have but litle] [Land, &amp; that lyes comon too: &amp; yet wt h a trick of myne] [owne trampling I make it yeld me 4. Crops a yere constant] grig [thats nothing I have one tre beres me fruite 12. tymes] [a yeare, once a moneth at least. a kind of choke peare I] [confess. but] Gilb. [An orchard of such trees, wood set vp a yong costerdmonger.] [how doe yow like em now?] Knock Count. [so well I know not wc h is worst, &amp; wood wt hall my hart be] [[rid off em all;] How now who knockes there? som Habeas] [Corpus to remove em all I hope.] Damp. [Swete mistress of my Ascendant] Enter. servas serv: [Mr ffalbridge the cunstable of the Hundreth.] Damp [&amp; he were constable of ten thowsand Ile speake out my spech] [now I ha studyed it, most bowntefull &amp; riche] Count. [pray kepe yor riches I have no need of em,] Damp [my part Mr s. will yow not give me Leave to play my part] Count. [T wood be a far greater part of modesty in yow to for beare] [this fall-bridg is a shrowd fellow &amp; he be chafft. let yor] [spech alone till dynner tyme, twilbe the better gracd I assur yw] How. [By yor Leave widow—] enter Howlet. &amp; officers Damp. [Imortall Zenith off Beatitude, the next line ravishes her] How. [By virtue of the k: warant to Iustice Byndover, I am to] [make privy serch for 3. or 4. disguisd rascalls. now cause I will] [not be Impartiall in my office, I must serch the rich widow aswell as the poore] [My wit gives me warant for it &amp; my pollicy shall bere me out in it] grig. [good Mr wit &amp; pollicy I hope we are not those rascalls—] Houl. [wit &amp; pollicy for bid &amp; yet a knave lookes so like an honest man—] [an officer can scarce know wc h is wc h. but those I serch for are] [fled the city for meritorious rogueryes, the one is a hangma] [much of that Gentlemans picthe] grig [My pich? wt a snuffling grinkans this—Harke yow, mr ffalb. are not yr] [Eyes sisters] How. [My wp s wit conffesses it, but wt. means yr pollicy to aske] grig [Mary because, that the sisters—if one of em should Crye-out] [wc h were a shrowd Blemish in an eye, the tother could not come to her] [Labour, tho she wood take the paines to it, causa patet, the bridg is broken] [downe betwixt em.] Howl. [my wit vnderstands yow. gent. but my pollicy, canot giue yw so] [sownd an Answeare as I could wishe.] Gilb [I partly believe yw but forward mr ffalbridge] How. [This mad hangman, had a trick to be lukewarme in his office, &amp;] [burnt a thefe in the hand wt h a cold Iron; for wc h it is knowne he] [tooke bribes &amp; thervpon, he is privately fled the Citye,] Ken. [theres a test for yw mr. grig.] grig. [pox ons fingers that made it, this romes to hot, Ile go cole my self in the Irish aile] Damp. [mary a faire winde after yw. mr. Camelion. &amp; I could but come to speke] [my spech once, thy sparkling nose thy sparows eyes.] How. [The second was a Broaking Lombard, for conyveing wt h theves] [&amp; receiving stolne goods; wc h found ins howse hees likewise ffled,] Damp. [they were found since I came forth then—A pore rascall peacht] [me last Sessions I confess. Ile be gone for fere the stone choke me the next] Hunt. [stay diner speake yr spech &amp; take yr answer of the widow first] Howl. [The third was an Informer. who takeing a 100l. bribe of vintners] [&amp; vitlers, for dressing &amp; vending flesh vpon fasting dayes,] [had wit to take the mony &amp; pollicy to betray them to a brother of] [who sued the statut vpon e'm. recoverd &amp; sharde the divident] Hunt: [now I have eat the Roast, I am in danger to be beaten wt h the] [spitt: this kichins to hott for me I must take a cooler Roome,] Ken: [[Afore yw have an answere from the widow, se now am I] sols cu sol] Howl. [The last is a most dellicate sharkeing rascall, that has some 24.] [trades, a man of monstrous acquaintance, for he knows all the] [Tibs &amp; the Toms. the Natts &amp; the Molls—all the Hee &amp; she cozeners] [&amp; cut-purses, pick pockets &amp; chetes in the city I have hym vnder] [the clawe of my pollicy too, &amp; my wit assurs me I shall fynd] [him out] Ken: [But may not, yor wit &amp; yor pollicy be decivd in him think yw.] Howl. [no, no—deceivd no no no noh] Ken: [pax of yor noe'-s &amp; I curse not to late, I must een turne fidler] [too, &amp; sneake after my noise, if I can play the trew thefe &amp; steale] [my selfe honcstly out of there companies I care not.] Ext Count. [These are a pack of swet beagles, well worth hanging indeed,] [[now gent. to yr speche, lets ha yr Iudgmt. mr ffalb.] but my suiters where «.»] How. [why they &amp; the 4. rascalls I serch for are gone togither &amp; se] [all my wit &amp; pollicy is gone Along wt h e'm.] Count. [How my new Servant turnd constable, How comes this A bout] How. [why thes weare the very same men disguisd, that I pr tended] [my serch for, now to rid yow of a trouble, &amp; wipe of an old] [Recking that was be twixt vs. I put this clinch vpon em.] Count. [I thanke the, &amp; will well reward the fort:] Howl. [Ile go carry home my wit &amp; pollicy where I borrowd it, for] [for the constable that lent it me is as very coxcomb as I wt hout it] [Gilb.] [well go thy wayes, for a sodaine Ieast I ha seene a worse.] but now widow [thes vermyne being frighted awaye wt h this painted staff of pollicy] wt s. the reason yw Blow of yor substantiall suitors so sleightly. Count onely to drawe thee on, &amp;—I perceive it dryves the further off Hast Any stomach to mary? Ime most Horibly in Love wt h thee. Gilb. Troth not to desemble, tis more then I am wt h yow then Count. yor reason? am I not yong beutifull &amp; wealthy. Gilb. yes &amp; wc h is worth em all, somwt I?odest Count Imodest come yar too bitter: tho it be yor nature to buzze, &amp; make a sawcy noise wt h yor ffellows— (the more my fault to countnance it) yet if yw goe about to stinge my reputacion once— Gilb. Reputac?n marry buzz: reputaco?: thast none never hadst Any. knowst not what it is reputacion ha ha ha mary buzz. Count. dost laugh Imposture Gilb &amp; hartely in trothe; to see yow can Indure no Ieast madam, Count How madam? Gilb a word broak prison [gainst my knowledge]/[a fore I was a ware ont]. Count calt in agen in tyme then least yow Answer fort Gilb no synce tis out, let it go, if be calld in question fort Ile make it good. Count. that I am a lady wood thow couldst else— Gilb. that yow are a lady I can, nay more a Countess I will, &amp; more then that an Honob l e. countess the Erle of Claridonns Countess. Count. Am I betrayd Gilb. no nere mistrust it—for by the Love I ought yor husband, for whose sake I thus carfully observe yow, yor life[s] &amp; Honors as safe in my kepeing as in his owne being alive Count. nay tho a stranger I dare Credit the &amp; cann take no thing ill that comes from the.— Indeed thy services are so gentile fayre &amp; becomeing they comand acceptance &amp; som thing in me pleads [thy]/[a] suit for the would ha me call the husband &amp; halfe perswades me thow worthely deservst it. Gilb me husband? mary buz, I am meane &amp; poore yow see, Count it Is not wealth but virtue &amp; thy care of my wrongd Honor—And wart not I have vowd a single life, sure I should mary the. Gilb: lass good Penelope, that webbs woven long agoe, theres som kyndnes in her affections yet theyd faine take acquaine taince on me &amp; she would suffer vm. But if yow Love me as yow proffesse &amp; I partly Beleve, here a good Ieast madam, wt. say yw if to gull the world &amp; make our selvs merry we pr supposed a private Maryage, &amp; gave out our selvs to be man &amp; wife Indeed. Count: Livd &amp; so kept howse togither twold allow our thoughts much fredome of familiarity Gilb &amp; rid yow from a great many of vnruly suiters, besides we are not the first paire of Barbarie pidgeons, that have buzd &amp; billd togither in the day &amp; flowne to severall Locker holes at night Count. An excellent conceit, &amp; I a prove it will instantly go voise it [a]'mongst the tenants &amp; [my] howshold servants, take [giue thee purse keyes &amp;] government of all, [Controwle the Howhold,] alter my estate [buy sell make bargaines, build &amp; Ruynate.] renew old Leases but do not rack my Tenants. Gilb. I comend the for that yet, hold e'm still at theld rent Count. be liberall to the poore banquet the rich be bowntefull to all Gilb If Iturne mizer vn husband me Agen, Count. &amp; now &amp; then for more variety seeme to finde fault—&amp; ccoff me, chide a litle! thow art too myld to chide Gilb I can buz a make a Horible noise if I be angry once not else Count let me alone Ile anger the I warne the— G. &amp; Ile buz then fer? not the Count. &amp; then like children wele fall out &amp; wrangle for toies &amp; triffles &amp; ath sodaine playe our selvs good freinds &amp; fall in. [againe twill be my plesure] Gilb. By no meanes no falling in theres danger in th«is» I shall st«i»g «t»h? Count. to be comanded by the—I shall take great plesure Gilb: I comend the for that thy tother husband was a good comander &amp; if ere I do come to enter the breach thow shalt fynde me no bench whistler, when —I do sting I sting to the quicke Count. Show yor selfe generous &amp; take state vpon yow you may have cause to vse it Gilb Trew I may come to be vpper churchwarden. or high constabl«e» of the hundreth. [plant a sparagas] garden [for recreation] &amp; [too] [to proffit my self &amp; plesur my fre] &amp; then—a gowne [furrd] linde wt h a litle state will not be a mis [for entertainemt] Count. strange power of Love, I cann for beare no Longer grant fate I do not Ieast my self into an Earnest dotage, for by this amorous kiss— as chast &amp; harmeless as the dreams of babes I love the as derely as the Count thats dead &amp; can deny the nothing Gilb yes his bed. Count: I had forgotten that, come husband now grant [Iuno] Vesta Love make me not Breake my Vow. Ext Gilb. wert not a good Ieast &amp; yow should see me make my self a cuckold now, twere no very strange thing &amp; yet my modesty Blushes at the very conceit of it yet wher fore blushe, when a peice of grownd lyes com?. ech sexe may till it, aswell man as woman [Ex] [This is myne owne severall tho, &amp; I may make the] [bolder wt ht by all that yow know] Ext</field>
      <field name="fulltext">[Actus Quartus.] [sc. i] Arch now's plaine old Tom ins trew garb Indeed a statsman still, tho but a wooden one I have more fellows, this parkes my Comon wealth thes trees poore subiects, ore whome I domineere &amp; playe the prorex. Cherish Hopefull plants but vseles dew boughes, Varletties that grow prowd I cut off as offendors for the fyer. but Leaveing him &amp; them, cut downe some boughes to build thy Leavy pallace, men never care wt we have beene but looke at wt we are. Enter Varl: &amp; Gerard. vizarded. Varl. Ambushe he comes. His traine has all forsooke [hym], &amp; lost hym in the chase, Anarmd and single Enter Prorex Pro. An ambushe in my Way Wt would yow villaines Ger. be wt thow calst vs villaines &amp; ha thy blood. Pro. my Blood traytors? why am Britains king Arc. wt thonders that Varl. but wele vntitle yow &amp; Crowne a Man More worthy old Archibald Arch The king in danger? &amp; my Name questiond? Have amongst yow traitors—Beat Em off Pro: gramercy Wood man—a stout Downe-right fellowe thow camst in tyme, but Ile soone send the rescue wind yor Horne (Marginal note) Enter Conon. Deuon, Elidure—other Con? Tis the kings Horne, How fares yor mat i e we feard some danger Pro: then yor feares are trewe I was set vpon by traitors, but a stowt woodman, Carry him rescue, Ile not have him Loose one dropp of Blood, good hart has none to spare, that way they went— Ext. Deuon &amp; others: Enter vxor. filius. fili: oh good my lord, my father Lovd yow well, —ronns to Conon &amp; Kneles had (yow like him) byn thus disgracd &amp; throwne out vnto scandall, he would ha spoake for yow— Conon —for him I dare not tho. Pro. the busyness there Conon. the wife &amp; sonne of Archiballd fili: plaine Archiballd. he had a title once, eminent as thyne owne. Pro: peace Malapert yow lye. fil: Lye. Ile swere thow ner wert solyor wt ere thow art by that word. give a trew gent. the lye? so much I am tho but a litle one, my Loyal father— Pro: thy traitor father. tis aparant Conon, the villaines threatned to vntitle me &amp; crowne old Archib: ther king fil. my father king? oh that I were a man for there sakes— Ide ha the combat on him durst but think soe. Enter Deuon wt h Archib. bleeding Pro. A cradle champeon? now ha yow found the woodma. father Ile call hym, for he gave me life. Deu. this good old man we found vnder a noake bleeding &amp; fainte, Pro. go beare him to a surgions those wounds are myne, the blood he looses, myne wt. care &amp; cost yow wood bestow on me had I those [wounds] Hurts [yow w] confer on him—for they &amp; death hym selfe came Armd gainst me— Arch. bleede still, let me be ever wounded, allwayes bleeding to heare such musick. vxor. My husband ?es: Archiballd fili: my deare Lord &amp; father? wt saye now my leige? whose the Lyer now? whose the false traitor now, my Loyall fathers hand have savd yor life. Pro. shall I be still out Honourd by this Britaine Conon —should Iove dart thonder. I cann hold no Longer, has done the part my Leige of a bold— Pro traytor— oes traytor? Pro. yes traitor, bold and dangerous Conon. wt lookest at boye fili: to see whither the king has got two tongues or noe, for one of em, sayd even now he savd hym from traitors; how dars the tother be so Conon my leige our Lands, our Honor s, &amp; our lives sawcy then to call him trayter shalbe [all] come bownd, &amp; pawnd for his allegeance, fil: It shall not need, my Lord, take myne for all, twas ner yet knowne an Archiballd was false Pro. At yor Intreaties—how now the Hasty news.— Deuon Hasty Ile sweare, the horse that brought the messenger is falne downe dead, the man lives, but scarcely Breathes. Pro. It seemes then tis materiall, from whome, &amp; whence? mess. ffrom Rome I think, read quickly good my leige, A tyrde gentlema put that into my hand &amp; a halter about my Neck, &amp; chagd me spur for life &amp; so I have done, Ile take my death ont Pro. Read. looke to yor selfe, deathes busy in the chase &amp; Hunts yor life; beware of Archiballd &amp; the false Barronns.—yordespisd vassall Varletti Loyall tho somwhat late: this Being comparde wt h my past danger, proves them Authors of it tis a clere truth, how has opinion faild nay foold my Iudgment to protect false traytors &amp; throw of a trew subiect—Honnest Varletti, Con. mayt please yow take old Archiballd to favor. Pro. we had such a purpose. but now our mynde is changd, we shall not vse his service nor yor s Longe, let Geraldine be sent for to the court. trust not the Barrons— I long to heare his reason, send for Varletti too— Con. that letter troubles him— filius. wood he had Broake his neck that brought it Pro. take away that traitor vxor. yor grace was pleasd to call him other wise fili. He had [had as litle] vice as he has grace by this tyme &amp; that I think had byn litle Inogh if [he had not found hym otherwise] Pro Riffle his castle, cease his plate and Iewells &amp; turne his Lasy famely a begginge fil. How lasy famely: tis more Industrious then thy Romane slaughter howse, &amp; thy Augeons stable far better governd too. Pro. the yong cub bites to, but wele breake his fangs, go take that boy &amp; place him in the kitchin wt h the black guard fil. in the cole hole &amp; yow will, I can Bless my freinds &amp; curse myne Enemyes there, aswell &amp; wt h asmuch devotion, as thow saist thy prayers in Iupiters chappell. Pro. A waye wt h Hym—his wife place in the Lawndrye. vx. een where yow please Pro. go chaine him to a mill put out his eyes, or blind fold like a horse, there let him grinde, stint him vnto his taske &amp; if he loose one mynut let the whipp [make him gaine two fort] [filii. whip: whip thy doggs: whip thy pesants &amp; fawneing Parasites, my father] is a better gentleman &amp; nobler borne, then the prowdest Ro: of yw all] [Pro. yow know our plesure quick dispose of em,] [1. gard come madam to the Laundry.] [2 gard to the kitchin sr a. &amp; se we ha good Brewess to breakfast.] [fili: As boileing lead &amp; ratsbane can make yow. Let me se yw there] &amp; for my fathers sake, Ile giue yw a cast off myne office] a Ladle full of scalding brothe to liquor boots wt h. at any tyme.] [Pro. And now my Lords, mownt &amp; a way to court] heares a mandamus chides vs from our sport Ext [sc. ii] Enter. Gibert &amp; Countess. Gilb: Morow wife good morow. is Parrat sullen this morning, mary buzz. Count: Mary buzard yow meane, make strip &amp; wast of my woods? fell my Timber pluck downe my howses, rack my Tenants? Gilb: Tenants, small wines wife hege wines will never drinke well &amp; they be not soundly rackt. Count. the Devill will rack the in hell fort one day Gilb: I: when thow art foore man on's Iurye, what I have done Ile answeare afore my betters &amp; thyne too— Count that shalbe tryed &amp; Iustice Byndeover were come once. Gilb Bynde-ove«r» an Antient bencher, Indeed, he was a Iustice I thinke a fore he was a gentleman,— Enter Howlet &amp; dashe disguisd yor wop s. most kindly wellcome a howshold Iar betwixt my wife &amp; my self Howl. nay nay yor goodnes is knowne, Gilb I hope yor good worship will take— How. noe bribe no I am none of these these not I: bynd hym over for that Dashe, Ile teach yow to offer Iustice a Bribe an other tyme— G: &amp; not giue him one— Gilb: I confesse twas my Ignorance, &amp; shalbe glad to Lerne sr. Howl. Sr. what sr sir. I am no knight sr Knave, Gilb: I know that most worship full Howl. He knowes me for a worf l knave he sayes, Bind him over againe Dash Dash bind over every man that knows yow—so—I might ha work Inough. Gilb. a bottle of sack &amp; a new rowle for mr Bindover How. no let yor rowles alone, tho bread be a bynder: my man Dashe can binde fast Inough wt hout it, wher be yor Atturnyes amb: we have feed none sr. How. And if they come wt hout ffees hang e'm—no matter a company of Bawleing fellows, trouble both towne &amp; countrye, All lawe thers no Iustice to be hard a mongst 'em—yow know yor owne causes best. ee'n plead em yor selvs, &amp; save a dowble fee, toot pro et Con come, yow pro the plaintife &amp; yow con the defendant. Gilb: please yor wp p. tast a cup of sack first Howl. &amp; thank the too I comend the, yet thow feedst thy cause well. tis like to thrive &amp; batten the better, some hide bownd Clients [star??] starve a suit in lawe as they do a child at nurse for want of wt. it should have, &amp; then laye the Blame of the Honest lawyer—wet thy neb too Dashe, thy pen will cast Inke the clerer, now Pro— show cause pro, showe cause, Count thus then, he rackes my tenants, ruynes my howses, fells my okes. Howl. wt s. that Dashe: wt do she talke on, Dash. talkes of felling of oaks sr. Howl so I thought for myne eyes were gathering Carpenters chipps—a cup of sack to clere em Dashe—so he fells thine okes Count. &amp; wood sell em too, but afore this reverend Iustice my freind &amp; thine Howl. How hows that? does she make Iustice any mans freind bynd—her over for that Dashe over wt h her Dash. nay sr. she makes a Iack of both sides on yow: freind to plaintife &amp; defendant too. Howl. does she so, does she so, bind her over dowble for that. for by this wine as I am trew Iustice I am freind nether to pro nor con— Dash. yow may Beleve hym he takes a depe oth: shees downe sr. Count. but touch an oake, an Arme, a bough, a branch a bushe, nay so much as an akorne cup, &amp; thow darst, dost here, for thine ears &amp; thow darest Howl. shele make a good Atturny her self in tyme she mootes handsomly all ready; now pro, wt can yow say for yr self pro— Gilb: why harke yow, hark yow yow Mr i s. of the Mandamus office shall not I fell myne owne sell myne owne, touch myne owne Count thyne owne? thow oakes of thyne owne: where grow they in Knaves acre furlong? oakes of thine owne nor so much as a rotten elder to hang the best freind thow hast one. Howl. no elder no oake: a triyall consequent, drawne a Minore ad Maius: she plaies home to yw. prove the okes yor owne, yor cast ellse. Gilb. Her owne Argument concluds it: she confesses they are hers. Howl. Ergo none of yor s. gone agen pro, gone Agen, the old statute of millio. quillio. trillio. calld Meum non est tu? cuts yor plea off by the Hams. Gilb: I give it new leggs Againe thus then? man &amp; wife being one the consequent proves there goods chattles &amp; all other Implemt s. to be soe. but we are man &amp; wife Ergo— Howl. a plaine case in ploiden, the man carryes it. [Are] yow are content to stand to our Censure, minister the oathe Dashe, giue him the full oath—Dashe has paid fort aforehand Dash. yow shall swere by the contents of this to stand to my Mr s arbytramt. Gilb. I do— Dash- kiss the booke then, So sufficient &amp; nowe—. Howl: what dost thow meane to do knave Dash. why to take his oath mr. ist not my place do I sit here for nothing Howl. Tis well done on the Dashe, now mister hers. Dash. yow are content to take the same oath yr fore-man did Count I am. &amp; ther vpon I kiss the booke. Dash: tis sufficient Dash. wt do yw meane sr. Howl. mary to take her oath my selfe, I shall make affidavit wt h the safer conscyence—I think I had best leave binding over &amp; begin to take Depositions thers most swetnes int of the two, but to the order set it downe Dashe: An oake is a body now a body yw all knowe belongs to the topp: the top is the head, but the husband is the head Ergo he being the head may Ritu Mariti challenge the body Armes hands, Dash thighes leggs Calfes Anckles feete toes &amp; all— Howl. no, theres a Quere [for] in that, for the thighes &amp; legs, being deawe boughes, [that] &amp; bushes that grow vnder Covert Barron as we call it, she may vse occupy, &amp; in way of chamber fuell, ritu vxoris Imploye. Count a reasonable order &amp; conscionable, let hym take the bodye &amp; giue me fredome to make vse of the boughes &amp; the bushes. Gilb. no. I will not part wt h a bough nor a Bushe, so big as to fforme a Hare or burrowe a Cony in—give yw the boughes &amp; the Bushes, mary Buz. Count prethe Leave buzing my boughes &amp; my Bushes are all thine swete husband [intr] be freinds good mr Iustice intreat him— Howl. Intreat I comand him, be freinds or Ile bynd the over, (&amp; affirme &amp; that ipso facto may this wine never go thorough me else Gilb: well to [kepe] giue yor oath [in yr belly] clerer vent I am content but— Enter one One: is not one Iustice Byndover here Gilb. the man of worp. sits there one: Sr. a company of sea fareing men at yr shop wood spek wt h yow. Howl. Brazele m'chants a my life, oh How, how do I tym a way my tyme here &amp; hazard the Loss of a whole flete of Tobacco: where ly the buyeing weights Dashe In the Dowble Deale box in the lower counter— Gilb. I think this be Dowble Dealing Inough in?: Gilb [but why] do yw not sell &amp; buy all by one scale Sr. (How.) Iustice for bid else, but there maye be difference in weights secundu quall: &amp; yet all trew secundum quan: too: Count: I did not thinke yr wop. had To co?rt this Iar came Luckely about twill ope a sluce, to let much busyness out Ext; (Marginal note) byn [a Tobacco man Till now:] soe well skilld in Tobacco Howl. Quere for that, why may not a [Tobacco] Marchant be a Iustice aswell as a pynn-pedlar, a Lord-Lord Maistress have I done yow. so many Iobbs of Iorny work &amp; do yow not know my workmanship yet Count yes yes, a knave is easy to be knowne from— How. a Iustice if yor eyes were maches, or but a trew paire of spectacles— Gib: thow art the onely make peace—when alls Done; come wife thow seest wt. paines our servants take, to cover our Errors &amp; mainetaine our Creditts, come buss buss &amp; be freinds— Count. Buss mary Buz: Are yow not content to abvse me yor selfe but set yor Iack-anapes his to mock &amp; mowe at me too— Howl. trewly Mistress. I do nether mock at yw. nor purpose to mowe in yor medow, but—be freinds wt h my Honest mr. or on goes my gowne Agen, &amp; then I bynd yw over, [wt hout] hand and foot wt hout Baile or maine prize— Gilb: prethe swete wife— Count. I scorne the title, fell my oakes doe sell the Timber yow maye; Gilb- nay nay but wife— Count. pull downe my howses: Gilb- wt wife I saye, Cont. rack my poore Tenants— Gilb: prethe. Count. I scorne the Gib. here me Count. I defye the, tho thow wearst the sword of Iustice (as thow wodst doe my head) vnder thy girdle, here in the Countrye, Ile to the court &amp; there: Gilb. the court? mary buz. thow tot h cort Count: yes I to the court, the king will know me &amp; redress my wrong. I shall fynde iustice out, tho it be long—first sra my horse. Gilb. go se her well horst &amp; do yow man her; mak hast I do not yr erand afore you [sci. iii] Enter Prorex. Gerard. Varletti Barrons Pro. Thow hast given Me full sufficeings—&amp; thy letter thoughsomwt. late, exprest much Loialtie. for wc h we owe the, but to the busyness. now lords of Britaine (much against our will) tis Cesars plesure, that yor government should be reformd.— shows a paper Conon. I told yw we should here more of that letter— Dev. wt. Cesar or yor selfe please to comand shalbe obeyd. Pro: we thanke yow first tis his plesure that yow three by name being worne out, &amp; tyred in Court service Be easd, &amp; sent home to yor contry howses, o?s In yow, we do obey great Cesar Pro. tis yor dutyes. yor offices &amp; titles Leave behinde yw.— (giue vp there staues to our dispose, so now yow may Begone Conon and wepe to se, that wc h we cannot shonn— our shame, &amp; the whole Lands Ruyn— Ext—. Pro. goe, &amp; be trew proffitts, now Geraldine ffirst wt h this staff of office we Create the Britaines high Champeon, thy fathers office, next Erle of Conon, Mr of our horse captaine of both our guards, pen?t?ioners, &amp; switzers Ger. If ever we have occasion to stick &amp; scwer let em Looke to there weasands. Pro. Varletti, wt h this staff we make the Marshall, &amp; generall of our Romaine Garrison,— Varl. the Bene fice I gapd for Pro. wt h it high admirall of our Navy royall, Varl. the whole comand of the kingdome, nothing else, as good give vs the Crowne too, &amp; save vs a labour, for have it we wll your highnes honors are above my merit Pro: study to reach em then, thes two are statesmen, fit for my purpose, a loose prodigall &amp; a spruce Reveller, the old men ware to wise &amp; full of pollicy, call forthe Archiballd, gerard thine eare Ger. for a Hang man, say no more, Ile be for yow streight— Ext Pro. about it, &amp; be serious, se he enters. Enter, [Keper.] Conon Archibald Conon [Kep]: wilt please yow eat sir, yave done yor forenones taske &amp; may refresh yw r. selfe. Arch. and thanck yow too, I'ue a good stomach now— toile whetts the Appetite, is this my dineing chamber— &amp; these my Cates, I'ue had a larger table &amp; better furnisht wt h provision—but Heaven &amp; my king be thankd for thys [t]is more then I desyre, or can Deserve— Pro. hees more then man sure, or at least no Britaine they cannot speake this Language, Arch. this Bread (tho somwhat course &amp; hard) is wholesome &amp; sawsd wt h hunger, has as swote a tast as yor court vyands, battens a great deale better, now let me vewe my Cup-board of Court plate, this wooden dishe, In wc h vpon my knee I drinke a harty health to my kings wellfare Pro And I could all most pldge it in my teares. Arch This water, (tho but pudle) has refresht me, better then all yor wyne, &amp; spyritted liquor that stead of cooleing over heats the blood &amp; fills vs full of surffetts &amp; diseases. Varl. Hunger has made him a phisitian too— Enter filius wt h somthing— fil. wt. have we heare, a dishe of water and a crust of mowldy Iannick? Is this diet for my father? he allows better to his hownds, I could fling it in the cooke Ruffians face that provided it, come my noble father, heres somwt. better chere yet, a cold capon &amp; a bottle of old Malligo. Arch. ah las my child wt. hast thow done fili: got yow good victualls father, I know yow want not a stomach Arch Labour Indeed prepares one, but in doeing soe thow hast vndone thy selfe, broaken the kings comand fil wood I had broake his neck, that causd the king give that comand I meane— Val. the boy has a knaveish meaneinge at sombody Arch. ah las poore boy thow takkst [thow knowst not wt.]/[as thow hast done] In both, thow knowest not wt. fil. But I doe father, fall to yor meat &amp; Ile tell yow. I know the king said, any one that relevd yow was a traitor, I have relevd yow &amp; yet am none, there the king was in An Error by his Leave Pro: da' mercy Boy thow tellst me my faults mildlye Conon [Kep.] come sawse box leave prateing, take away yr scrapps &amp; get yow gone tis more then my comission but he is yr father, &amp; ile winke at yw for once, Pro. I am prowd I have a servant Dares be honest yet Arch. How get hym gone? thow art a villaine then, pardon me nature I must do the wronge he is a traitor, &amp; tho he be my sonne &amp; onely store of my posteritye atach &amp; hale the traiterouse boy to prisonn or Ile atach yow both. Varl. stark mad wt h loyaltye Kep. yow shall not need sr., Ile take order wt h hym, come sr a. fili why &amp; sr a. yow need not be thus officious, Ile go wt hout haleing, my father lent me life, &amp; synce tis his plesure to take it againe, Ius aut Nefas—I cannot bestow it better if I be a traitor to the king, I am sure trew subiet to Heaven &amp; my father, vse me how thow wilt wt. I have done I scorne once to denye I durst offend, and Dare as boldly dye —Ext. Arch. Be this thine Epitaph here lye two in one An Innocent traytor &amp; a knoweing sonne. Pro. And thow the root of admiration Arch: is the boy fast? Keper. as lock &amp; key cann make him— Arch: then Blind fold me, &amp; letts to work agen, Ile grinde, till my strong Ioints faint vnder me so the great Prorex will but take me vp, &amp; say well Labourd Loyall Archiballd. Pro this canot be Desembled, &amp; Ile torture his Loyalty no Longer, (Enter Gerald. disguisd Varl maintaine yor tryall, here comes Geraldine, Ger. By yor Leave officer, whers my fellow Archiballd Kep: yor fellow Hang man? Ger. &amp; I were a Hangdog I might be thine? yow know this ring? Kep. yes, tis the kings Signet Ger let that seale vp yor chapps. &amp; deliver me yor prisoner, Kep I must obay. Heaven bless the Archiballd I do not like that villaines Lookes— Ger. give me the Key and leave vs, &amp; now must I have a word &amp; a blow wt h yow sr. the king my master requests a favour from yow Arch. Request he may comand, wt. ist sr? Ger. yor calfes head &amp; purtnance, to make a Cullise for a blood-hownd that lyes sick of a consumption, Arch My head? pray take it, tis his owne, &amp; yet the faith full Service I have done him merritts nobler reward Ger the whole land knows that, but wt can yow expect from a tyrant? Arch. Tyrant whome meane yow? Ger. why the prorex? Arch. Villaine vnspeake that word, recant thine Herezye I shall apeach the for a traitor else. Ger. not when yow know me, se I am Geraldine animated by the Barrones to thrust my self into this disguise, to kill the prorex and work thy fredome Arch. geraldine! treason, capitall treason, give me a tongue of thunder to proclaime it Geraldine, Conon, Elidure, all traitors the kings in Danger, treason, murderous treason, Pro. I can forbeare no Longer. who ist Names treson? Arch tis I my Leige, yor vassall Archiballd yow are Betraid, this Villaine whome yow sent to doe a noble office, proves a trayter nay never pluck me, tis yong Geraldine— Pro. how Geraldine? Arch. nay Ile do yor Errand, profferd to give me fredome, on condicion I would abett &amp; second the bold treasonn of him, false Conon, Elidure &amp; Deuon, Ger to all wc h had not yor highnes enterd afore yor Cue he seemd willing Inough to consent to Pro. devill tempt no more, I shame to have done so much Arch. And cause I scorne to be Impartiall Se heare my leige, here is another Trayter tho yong most dangerous. Enter filius Pro. oh thow meanst thy sonn cause his offence was but Releveing the at thy intreaty we will pardon hym, Arch. At my Intreaty? Loyalty for bids I should intreat for traitors, yet nature I confess moves to that purpose ffil. Then Nature is a coward. Intreat for me? no Iff I merit Death giue me faire lawe, a tryall by my peeres Britaines—or Romaine Devills if they haue soules I dare stand a censure, if I merit death via? I scorne to weare a life a bout me thats not myne owne, &amp; yet I lov't the rather that it dares dy for Loveing of my father. Pr. Cesar has not a courage more vntamde his fathers spirit speakes in him to se them dy vallour wood dy wt h grefe, make nature bank root Leave her not worth one spark of resolution to stock a second generation wt h. we must not loose such Iewells. well synce nether Iutice can clere, nor Evidence convict the Imbrace &amp; love these Lords thy fellow peeres instead of Devon Elidure &amp; Conon &amp; kepe thy offices in court: if not— Arch. Keper come chaine me to my mill agen, for want of graine, Ile grind my bones to powder ere ile be yoakd wt h such fili: Capering Iack a dandyes: my ffellows of the black guard are sub stantiall yeomen to em, Ile to my old cole hole agen Ex«t» fil. farwell myll gard. Archrascalls all. Pro. wele not intreat yw. adue good good mr Archib.— Away wt h hym, nor think it Tyrany safety sayes, weare thy danger in thyne Eye. Arch. I am yor vassall, &amp; submit to all. this howre yor sport, the next my Buryall. Con? not if my life &amp; service cann prevent it Arch my cozen conon? Cono. yes old Archiballd this shape wt h gold I purchast of thy keper to acquaint the wt h a dangerous stratagem, In wc h, tho yet vnknowne, the king hym selfe &amp; the whole kingdome must intreat thine aide &amp; I by Intercepting of this Letter Luckely found per vse it, how dost like it Arch. Tis an vndertakeing worthy— a state smans sword. &amp; a conspiracye Miraculously reveald, the man I must present I am perfect in; a rough-Hewen humorous solyor Conon. rashe, bloody, &amp; vaine glorious, Blinde of an Eye, Arch. Ile play him to accont but for munition, men, horse &amp; Armor. Conon, there in show thine Art drawe thyne owne swords against e'm—&amp; yet Deuon, &amp; Elidure have got materialls fit for the buildinge, Arch: for the work man shipp Leave that to me, Heaven prosper my Intent &amp; call my life the subiects president—</field>
      <field name="fulltext">[Act: Quint:] [sc. i] Enter. Geraldine. Varletti gallant wt h staves. Kather Varl Morrow to my good Lord of Conon, [capt] champeon Roiall to the kinge, Mr off the Horse, &amp; captaine of both the guards pentioners &amp; switzers. Ger the like to my good Lord of Deuon chefe generall of the Romaine Garison, Lord high [admirall &amp;] Marshall &amp; admirall of the Navy royall. Kath. I mary sr theres deitie in these Titles Able to inchant &amp; make a man Imortall, Ger &amp; is not this better then lyeing like a boare in a stye crawncheing of raw Acornes. thy life &amp; diet in thy confinemt. was no better. Kath thine scarce so good thank a few huskes of Intelligence, that the counsellor, that betterd it Ger oh my Sariant of the Coife when I am king once, wc h wilbe wt hin these two dayes now, &amp; this percy were come once, for alls but buble &amp; shadow wt hout him— Kath. I wonder at his stay, I writ to him to full purpose Varl &amp; se the man. right noble vncle— Archiballd Enters Ger. Bold Percy wellcome— Deuon Elyd. Conon Kath. yor lingring frighted vs, &amp; all most killd the hart of the most Hopefull Expedition, Arch. Now &amp; I can but hit of his ratling humor. lingring? hoida, knaves &amp; fooles Boyes &amp; girles, tell me of lingeringe? &amp; I ware in ffrance againe, Ide se yow all flead, &amp; roasted alive, like soe many but now I am spich cocks, ere Ide take halfe this paines to releve Landed with why when, knaves garzone my horse. fil: [presently sr knaves &amp; boyes my capt: horse ther (Marginal note)] Kath. [yow must soothe vp his humor, hele begone againe else,] Ger [Nay good sr. staye, How ever they talke Idlye] [I know it a labour worthy Hercules,] [to ship &amp; land so many horse &amp; men,] [on such a sodaine.] Arch [why thow speakest somwt. like sence yet. Ile tell«e» the wt.] [geraldine I take it] Ger. [old Gilbert sonn sr] Arch. [now, I remember the: thow hadst a father, a stowt] [waryour he was, &amp; a boldone, he &amp; I have followed] [an execution, when our prowd coursers have Ietted] [in purple Buskins, &amp; trod the lofty Mattachins in blood] Ger [a good solyor he was] Arch. [nay there were a coople of vs, &amp; such a coople as] [tho I sait, but to the busyness.] Varl [A chaire &amp; a cushion, for myne vncle good sr the] [manner of yr Landing] Arch. [in a word thus. Hanniball went over the Alpes, a lofty] [attempt &amp; a high one, but his men made hym a paire] [of staires first, wc h tooke his clamberinge credit one story Lower] [by his Leave, Horatius swom Tibur in his Armor] Ger. [Has throwne hym self from the top of the Alpes into the] [Bottome of Tibur at one Leape.] Varl. [give hym Leave hele Iump Into th? Britaine the next.] Arch [da Mercy Sextus that beat him off land and made him] [take water for his life. his reputac?n and memory] [had both sunck else, ffabius cunctator came somwt. neere] [me, I conffesse but alas the day he fell short too, an] [vnmercifull deale short] Varl. [but how the manner gentle vncle tell vs—] Arch. [knaves &amp; fooles yar not worth it, suffice I did it, let] [boyes &amp; girles set there Idle witts a work to learne how] but now I am Landed wt h this my dareing associate in wt, forwardnes is yor proiect? Varl Ready for execution the Ro: garrisons are all ours. Ger: my freinds &amp; tenants Armd in readynes. Conon Deuon &amp; Elydure, muzled in there Kennells of confynement Conon They are loose Inough to pluck out yor throates tho—[but] filius), &amp; yow be not hees a fre«n»d in a corner to help yw. Elyd. [Deu.] but haveing all things in Readines Arch I Knaves &amp; fooles, why fall yow not to instant action then Varl. onely for lack off yow, we ha power but want direcc?n Ger Have the Lyon at advantage, but want Art to shackle him in the Toile, Varl ffredome at comand, but know not how to manage it Ger A Crowne in our ey but want Authority to set it on our heads. Kath. now wt h all theis wants can yow and yor grave associates furnishe em, Archib knaves &amp; fooles so I can too, but are yow willing to put that honl b e. offyce vpon my trust Ger. Make yow our Generall. put our selvs and solyor s. vnder comaund of yw and thes yor noble assistants Cono: &amp; we desire no more. fil: but to have yw like hounds in so many halters no more Elid: twilbe for yor s. and the whole kingdomes good then— Varl Voweing to doe nothing wt hout or contrary to yor dirccon Arc. Sweare that vpon my sword. why good a mercy—&amp; since yow have conferd that place of trust vpon me, yow shall se old Iack will discharge it, wt h that Corage &amp; fidelitye as yow &amp; all Britaine [&amp; the whole world] shall have Iust cause to comend me. but knaves &amp; boyes heads must off &amp; &amp; tall ones too. Varl Spare none, if they oppose yow hew em downe Ger. better no head say I then not a crowne. Arch why darst thow weare a crowne thinkst &amp; thow hadst it Ger how were one? yes and dy wt ht in my Armes.— fil: by mars his helmet so durst I &amp; I had but right toot not els Arch. knaves &amp; boyes that wele trye awaye I long for execution— Ext Con. Be britaine blest in the successe [sc. ii] Enter Prorex. Lords, Gilbert Pro Come on mr waspe yow have Been so busy wt h our Ladyes, Looze fore parts,, head tyres &amp; trymeings, yow have made em Angry— Gilb: Angry? marry Buzz why angry. they askt me wt. vanityes were most in fashion, &amp; I think I told em there owne is there any hurt in telling em there owne 1. Lod. some Citizens, marchants &amp; mony masters wold be glad to be told there owne, [n] 2. L. there can be no hurt in telling any man or woma ther owne Pro. noe hurt at all, but come thow hast byn a great traveler wt. country yelds best Honny. Gilb. Hony. theres some in all, &amp; very good in most, but first wt h yor owne, theres excellent Hony at roome, but the wall[s]— fflowers tis gatherd on, being waterd wt h the first founders. blood, it tasts so bitter of a weed calld splenewortt—&amp;. Pro. noe more yar Bitter buz on to next Gilb excellent Hony all Italy over; but tas a smack of Narcissus flower, Philautia or self love, &amp; that mars the sale of it 1. L. tis a shrowd Blemishe to the cuntry &amp; much takt off Pro. The complexion of the climbe nothing else. Gilb: Admirable Hony in Spaine, &amp; as yellow as gold, but being symples gatherd of an Herbe calld Indean Rue, &amp; [the topps] of [the «Iland»s] of—the mountaynès [Tyranye], takes [much of] the virtue from it. 2. L: that fault is much mended a late tho. Pro. ech contry has his discomoditie, wt. Hony in ffraunce, Gilb: plenty of Hony there, but I dare not be to busy wt h them, for feare the Bees sting me by the browes. Pro. Are they a wing theyle be soone downe agen, 1. L: Nullum violentu perpetu?, wt. Hony in Russia? Gilb. Admirable Hony there, but theres such civell war betwixt the Bees &amp; the bears a stranger cannot get a combe amongst em. Pro: ffrom them to holland wt Hony yeilds that? Gilb. Holland, or No land meane yw, if it be any tis but a skirt rent off [the] anothers coate [of spaine], there bees gather wt. Hony they haue, o the water, [&amp; that smells so ranck of sea wrack, blood wort &amp; piracye,] not one amongst a 1000 cares for tasting of it Pro. I cannot blame em, wt Hony in Britaine? Gilb oh yor British Hony caryes the name from em all, Hamp— sheire espetially. but the poore russet Bee that should gather it is so terribly afflicted by a swarme of pestilent out landishe flyes, new stolne over from Rome sure for we had none of em here till they came in wt h Cesar 1 L. In wt h Cesar? take hede wt yw buz waspe? in wt h Cesar? Pro. fflyes from Rome, wt are they Gilb nay I know em not, they never drunk a my cup, &amp; yet they are sawcy Inough. some of there names ly scatterd vp &amp; downe my memory &amp; I could hitt of em, oh Exaction oprssion monopoly, symonye, transportacion, extortion, Rack rent vsery Brokery Bribery knavery knavery, all manner of knaverye, not an honest British name amongst em [Pro. all thes Delinquents if we find em reall.] [Gilb. Reall mary Buz find em &amp; fine em. punish em &amp; pillory] em, Hamper em, Hang 'em, such outlandishe Lurchers, if] any such ther be at least for I speake by heare saye] steale both Hony &amp; Wax Credit &amp; proffit, from the poore] natiue Be Brand, burne, banish rid the Land of e'm.] Send em home (Like vagrants) to lick there owne mothers] milke, they have suckt too much British blood, by here say] I cannot condem them, the mores the pitty] [Pro. thow art honest, &amp; I dare proclaime the Loyall] thy zeale vnto the comon good confirmes it] &amp; now from thes to thine owne Busynes] thy wife has challengd the of much vnkindnes—] [Gilb. my wife challeng me, marry Buz. I am here in the list ready] to answere her, at her owne wepon, let her enter when she dare] Pro. now gentle woma, yor Husbands here in personn.— Enter Howlet &amp; Countess Count. my husband, I defy him, scorne hym renowne him disclayme hym, Am the worse when I looke vpon hym. Howl oh the fretts mr s. [the] Remembr the frets: many a good horse dye of em Count poore Beggerly fellow I tooke him in &amp; kept him of Allmes to be my foole &amp; make my freinds merrye Gilb ffoole? trickes in myne age? Beggerly foole, trickes Merry trix wife, I shall fly out, I shall buzz. I shall sting do wemen take husbands to make fooles off Count. [once more I scorne the, fly to the Devill, &amp; spare not, buz till thy] [neck breake I care not] How. [nor I nether but the fretts take heed on the ffretts good Mr s.] Count. [sting thy hart out I shalbe glad ont.] Gilb. [buz buz.] How [ware wasp Mr s. he bites his thombe, hes angry, downe [good]] [submit, humble yr selfe, or he exalts &amp; that presentlye] Count my husband poore fellow. Gilb yor husband prowd huswife, or as good a man as ever went on his Leggs at Least Count thow wert not worth to truss his points, make cleane his shoe«s» pardon my Leige, but plese ?vse this: yow may Conceive as a Pa? muche, Helpe to vncase me sra.— a Pa? Howl I have vncasd, &amp; vnlacd many a fat conye in my tyme but ha not felt a plumper kidny in my [tyme] dayes, yow do not shame yor pasture, yow thryve &amp; Batten well—but-vds me the countess. Pro. Rise noble countess we conveive thy wrongs— &amp; cannot but comend thy noble courage not to give way to Basenes, sr a. recant yor Herezy, or looke for punishement Gilb recant? mary Buz I scorne it, disclaime it, she knows I knewe her aswell before, Howl. as my father did my mother [behinde] Gilb. wt. I have said Ile maintaine, I have wed &amp; beded her Count. bedded me Howl. I am witnes toot Gilb I am as good a man as ere went of old Gills leggs Count. my husbads legs How. Ile be disposd, vpont Gilb &amp; crave no better Iudge then yor marestye How. nor other foreman of the Iury then Howlet Pro. old Claridon Alive. Count. my noble Lord &amp; husband Gilb yr husband, fy no, a begarly fellow yw kept of Allmes. to be yor foole &amp; make yr freinds mery, merry trix in yor age wife do yow remember that Count. pardon my Ignorance Gilb: intreat his Mat i e s. that note will give yor grace Ample sufficeinges of all occurrents past, &amp; for our owne parts now like a coopl? of Babes we have wrangled our Belly fulls, wele like a paire of Loveing Turtles, bill buz &amp; be freinds agen, sra begon Howl. my old Ivy bushe, I know my Lodging, let yor sonn whoot me out there now &amp; he Dare Pro. yor sonne I se has plaid the wag but tyme, will tame hym, we have put some Honors on him Noyes. wc h if well vssd may vsher more,—wt hdrawe, « e» some noise &amp; busyness in the court « e» it be, I charge yw Be not sene; till call for yow. « c»omaunds a lawe Ext. n the Court gates. «st»rong guard for the great Chamber, make good the presence « ch:» have an ey to the private staires there oes. Downe wt h the tyrant downe wt h the opressor Pro: The voice of Treason. are the surly Barrons. in armes agayne, Varleti geraldine— Enter. Var: Gerd Arch: Conon. Devon Elyd yor sights speke comfort whence that noice of treaso? o?s. ffrom-vs-from all.— fil: yes &amp; from me too— filius wt hin— downe wt h the tyrant downe wt h the oppressor. Arch Hark dost Here king? the whole land speaks no other Language Pro. Are yow turnd rebells? have our Honourd favours created traytors. o?s: No, but trew harted subiects Pro: why come yow then in Armes? Varl. to right my wrongs. Ger. revenge my fathers murder Arch. My vniust banishment? Pro Art thow there percy! cuthroat— Arch yes knaves &amp; fooles to make thy court a slaughter howse. Pro Traytors! wheres Conon, Devon Elidure Ger. Ha yow forgot yw sent em home to there cuntry farmes, to shale beanes &amp; lap butter milke, they were too wise yow must ha fooles a bout yow. Varl. Emptie revellers &amp; loose prodigalls, that have nether wit nor tyme to thinck of state Ger a few cast offices are Bawbles good Inough for such babes to playe wt hall, they looke not so hye as a crowne, Ile be so bold as Looke of this tho— Arch doe, looke out &amp; spare not, but for thy head lay not a disloyall—hand int, am not I yor generall. ha Con. De we his assistants Ioynd in comission saye Ger. How the old wolfes barke; we do confess it &amp; yow shall be obeyd Con. D. nay we wilbe obeyd— fil: I we must be obeyd Arch. must, must &amp; wilbe obayd. have yow not hunted the lyon, into the Toile, Posse et Nolle Nobile, the Honor lyes in the conquest not in the case, please yor Mt i e resigne yor Crowne, &amp; trust me wt h the kepeing of it. Pro. Synce ffate has servd her prowd Mandamus on Me &amp; yet my Romaine spirit can scarce obeyt [as good resigne by faire means as by force] this golden Ball, lent me to play wt hall the chase being lost I tosse into the Hazard, Let a ffreshe gamster taket, but traitors knowe yow rob not me But Cezar and hele throwe his thonder bolts amongst yow. Ger. Let em come, let em come, wele thonder em, Varl. &amp; bolt hym too quite out off Britaine, if these Iron Bars hold at Least. Arch. knaves &amp; fooles is not this Better, now then Violence Ger. It Argues yor Experience. &amp; Indeed we sent for yw to purpose the same Pro. now to wt. Iaile or dungeon? I deservt for plucking downe the trew Nobillity &amp; raiseing Boyes &amp; vpstarts. Arch. Art advizd of that king, theres no trusting «s» state buildings espetiallye, theyle giue in «p» old Iacks of a Better season tho, thow ha«s» Crowne, &amp; Ile warrant thy personn, wt h fa vsage too; Ile make some shoulders walk wt hou«??s» Ile onely make bold to trye a conclusion wt h thy Crowne, Ger. the old ffellow workes him handsomelye, Varl. did I not say so I chose em to the same purpose Arch. now Geraldine, hears the golden Curry combe, yor head Itch to be rubd wt h: &amp; cause old Iack wilbe as goods his worde, sit &amp; Soft Musike. Inioy it, A Banquet, Musick, &amp; royall attendaunts for yor new king there— A Table ffurnisht, Ladyes &amp;c Varl: I knew there would come a tyme for bells &amp; bonefyers, [now, whoe is the state scarcrow now? who playes the mock] [king now? Live Geraldine &amp; live long my fellow kinge] Ger [two words to a Bargaine sr. by yor Leave—king] [that word begetts a new Creation in me,] [makes me Imortall, speake it Againe] Varl. [I shall great fellow king.] fil: [oh that my berd were color de Roy] [of the hayre royall how wood I scramble to be a King] Ger: [It is a stile admitts no fellowship] [tis an Imperiall Casket casd wt h gold] [in wc h are many Curious Cabynets] [yet not one Empty—tis a heape of gold] [of severall stamps, &amp; Iet the least pece Currant] [&amp; yet this gold, this curious Cabynet] [will fit no case, but a kings royall bosome] [for theres its natureall Center, &amp; trew Myne] [where perle &amp; Dyamonds generate in Clusters.] Arch [that myne are yo w now mr off—(rich Indean)] Varl. [He &amp; I vncle, twas a covenant betwixt vs] Arch. [open yor caskett royall, toss &amp; tumble yr Iewells—take wt] [yow list yor selfe &amp; [tak throw] tosse the rest to yr freinds] Var. [wele make a muss wt h em amongst our ffavorites, who sitts] [on the Zenith of for tunes whele now? whose tumbled to the] [Antipodes now?] Pro. [thes scoffs afflict me more then my deposeing] Arc. [Men of yor owne creating, statsmen of yor owne choseinge] but come fall to, theres nectar &amp; Ambrosia, why do yow not bath it. a Bank of roses on one side &amp; a bed of violets of the tother, tomble em, toss em, ruffle em Riffle e'm &amp; make the blusheing Leaves fly about there ears in kisses, Pro. How the old Ruffian hartens on his cubbs. Varl. why trew, we sent for hym to the same purpose Ger. thart a brave Bold &amp; noble counsellor, Ladyes lay by yr blushes yow may have more cause to weare them anon, now lets fall to, heres Vyands for a— the table turns &amp; such things apeare devill: snakes toads &amp; newtes go cram em downe the traitors throats Arch. wt. for there Art, they are vyands fashiond into thes proportions by art, for the more state &amp; novelty. Val: And yow ha no stomach, let me come, &amp; they were lyve scorpions Ide ceaze em— ? nay then I cry yow mercy. &amp; death. thy stir &amp; ?all the dishes ar yor confectionary yelds, &amp; the livelyest, if they wonot ne stay yor stomach heare. «m»ary sr. thes plesurs are naturall, art has not poisend thes «y»et: come let me play the wanton on yor Brests whilst yow chase winged Cupids in myne Eyes, &amp; take em prisoners in these golden tramells. ?L?ad. noe sir we have stronger toyles to take yow in Lust full incestuous [tyrant] trayter. Ger. death a she Hangman 2.lady nay heres a coople of vs. Pro. Theres somt looks like worth in this old fellow. Ger. the old Ruffian fflowtes me Varl. why did yow not send for him to the same purpose. I se his ayme he kepes the crowne for me da mercy good uncke. Ger. Treason our Guard Conon. we are ready for yw sr. Deu. stirr &amp; yow dye Ger: my Intrailes burne reache me som wine Arch: wine for the king, &amp; se yow spict well, Ger. villaine wt putst intoot Elyd. nothing but a litle ratsbane Varl. A delicate cooler for a hot Lyver, are yow content I shalbe yr fellow king—yet Ger Am I a king? Pro. such a one as tis. Varl. but the Itching of my Brow sayes yow will not be so longe. Ger &amp; Dare yow vse me thus feed me wt h snakes associate me wt h strumpetts poisen my wine corrupt my officers (a sword hangs &amp; fury since all below conspire against me: Heaven sheild me, protect me, save me, guard me se, [se]— se a nakd sword hangs by a slender twine Iust ore my head-se-se-a fury Armd wt h sheeres to cut it, hold:—Omnipotence Enter Gilbert my ffathers ghost too, all my youth full synns ripen togither &amp; fall downe in clusters about myne ears we shall have a full Harvest. Arch. open yor casket royall now, thers variety of Antidotes apply some of them now. Ger. do not afflict me thow old devill do not Pro did yow not send for him to the same purpose? Ger. I am amazd, distracted, frantick all my vaines instead of blood are choakd wt h gellye ffeare nums my synews, I have nether strength corage nor any sum-tom of a man in or about me, yow gods of Britaine, free me. Pro. No cause thow scorndst the gods in thy Excesse theile hurle the headlong to the Antipodes. Varl. thow shalt not live to seet ronns at hym Conon. but he may sr. &amp; there yow ly now. (strike him vp— Deu. he is our charge &amp; we dare protect him Pro. I thank yow for my life, &amp; owe yow fort Arch. Better no head then no crowne, do yow remember that? yow wood Live &amp; dy wt ht in yor Armes thinke vpon that, yw are sworne to be rulde by me too in all, do not quite forget that. yw have [the crowne]/[it] for yor owne plesure &amp; yr head shall were it for myne, [ether] [or]/[of] yor sholders [«o»r of a hop poale chose yw wc h.] were no head chose wch Ger: [my]/[noe] head? pray take it, take it wt hall my [A] hart but first «take» hence my fears Arch. ffears: knaves &amp; fooles were yow he that «m» danger? for a crowne [&amp; now yow are «p]lyve &amp; dy wt h it in yor Arm? away lik a scorpion now yw hate. [agen,] yow are willing to resig Ger. yes on my knee, on my Bare knee &amp; th«e» Arch: yowle be no king then, not to have his c Ger. are my heles now this golden hoopes off my «h» Arch. A Britaine &amp; afraid to were a Crowne I am ashamd on the coze yow are a right Romaine Spirrit, &amp; will go to «B» the Devill for a crowne, will yow were it Varl. I knew twold come to this, were the Crowne? &amp; thank y«w» too &amp; now good nuncle take away thes Horrors. Arch. Take e'm away why tis Impossible, they are as inseperable attendants on a Crowne, as the shadow to the body. wc h tho sometimes darkened, yet never for sakes it. Varl. Ile be no king then Kath. Cowardly Pesant: have I spent my Braine? troubled my freinds, put my dere life &amp; Credit in hazard to advance the, &amp; but take the Crowne &amp; weare it like a man, or like a Beast fall by a woman. Conon. good at stabbing staye Impartiall Iudges must maintaine fayre playe yowle be noe kinge Arch. no king? make a foole of old Iack, shall Britaine have no king? Are yow content the prorex shall hav [the Crowne]/[it] Againe then. Varl. wt h all my hart, &amp; wishe hym no greater punishment for all my wrongs. Ger. Nor I for myne, &amp; my fathers murder Arch. knaves &amp; fooles wt. a puzle has thes boyes put me to, please yow great sr. receive yor Crowne Againe, I borrowd it onely to trye a Conclusion, (as I told yor highnes) &amp; now tis Done humbly on my knee, as I receivd it, I surrender it: Pro. Wood I had more such traitors Arch. Now please yr mat i e. fill yor chaire Agen, [knaves &amp; fooles] the boyes cannot fit it, some musick, please yor highnes tast a homely Banquet Soft Musi«k»e. Ger A poacht toad, or a live snake, twill make yow looke yong in yor grave Pro: wt h a good Appetite, for this Discourse Table turnes has Bred one in me, &amp; thes comfortable vyands. Ger generall let me be king Againe now. Varl. vnckle or me: me at any hand good vnckle— Arc. knaves &amp; fooles, yor old cates will crawle about ye agen then— Varl why waite they not on him then? Arch. They are onely seene to vsurpers such as yow are but like darke shadows they Crepe after him &amp; Dare not Looke a trew king in the face his Lookes are armd wt h such Divinitye they alter Nature, &amp; Drive essences out off all Being. strike treason on it knees —Con. De. Knele turne Arrogance into obedience Lad. Knele An Angell wo«v»e «the p» &amp; devills them selvs to Angells, he can vnlock yor Caskett royall; &amp; weare all these Iewells in there trew Lustres, that crowne the wedding Ring ffitts no mans Temples but a royall king. Con?. &amp; this is he, yow traitors &amp; vsurpers &amp; so we ceaze yow. Ger. we sent not for yow to that purpose tho, as I rember.</field>
   </doc>
</add>