<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">D'Avenant, William, Sir, 1606-1668</field>
      <field name="author_facet">D'Avenant, William, Sir, 1606-1668</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">davenant william sir 1606 1668</field>
      <field name="author_text">D'Avenant, William, Sir, 1606-1668</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">17th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V1.0313.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1673</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:459060</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Play-House to be Let</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 17th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 17th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Play-House to be Let</field>
      <field name="title_facet">play house to be let</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">play house to be let</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Play-House to be Let</field>
      <field name="year_display">1673</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1673</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1673</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459060&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459060&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;D'Avenant, William, Sir, 1606-1668&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;davenant william sir 1606 1668&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Play-House to be Let&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;play house to be let&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1673&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1673&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;D'Avenant, William, Sir&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1606&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1668&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Play-House to be Let&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed by T. N. for Henry Herringman [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1673&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3871713-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv10313&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 17th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;17th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Play-House to be Let&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 209 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted&lt;lb/&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;lb/&gt;Dedication included with The Play-House to be Let&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: The play-house to be let.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Comedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1673.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Aug 1663 ?&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Play-House to be Let.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">TO HIS Royal Highness.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PROLOGUE. Since you affect things new, what I'm to say, Shall be as great a Novel as our Play, Custom would have me speak a Prologue now, But that we may intire adherence show To Novelty (which in the Mode of Plays Like soveraign Nature over Custom sways) I mean my Prologue shall a Riddle be; And thus propound it to the Company. A teeming Muse big with imagination, Conceiv'd a Monster of so new a fashion That of the hasty birth, b'ing brought to Bed, We found it neither had a Tail or Head. The Limbs are such, as no proportion bear, No correspondence have, and yet cohere: Of several use, and several forms they be, Yet in the whole contexture they agree: They are disjoyn'd and yet united too, Which cannot but a Monster seem to you; Yet such a Monster 'tis, as you'l admit For Pleasure, and still pay for Nursing it. I see y'are puzl'd; but we so dispise Th'advantage we might make by a surprise, That to unridle this, you here may come And joyn your Heads together in one Room, Where, for your Money, you shall sit at ease, Two hours a day, till Christmas if you please.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The First ACT. The SCENE opens, and upon two Stools are discover'd the Tire-woman and Chair-woman, one shelling of Beans, and the other Sowing. Enter Player and House-Keeper. Play. What, shelling of Beans? 'tis a proper work For the Long Vacation. You may e'en dry 'em In the Sun, and lay 'em up in the Tiring-house For the Players: they may get Bacon to 'em When the Term comes. Hous. K. Nay you may work on too, 'tis Hospital ware, Course shirts for the poor Poets. [Knocking hard at Dore. Play. Are they mad? sure they take the Play-house for The Church-yard o're the way; and mean to wake Our dead Neighbours. What would you have? [Knocking agen. Tir. W. Pray knock civilly. I believe it is Some Country Poet with a stock of Plays. He brings his Ware to sell when the Fares's done. [Knocking agen. Play. Some University Muse is in hard labour, And she takes our Tire-woman for a Midwife. Open the Dore.— [Exit Hous. K. and enter again with Monsieur. Mons. Be you von, two, tree of de Teatre. Hous. K. We are standing properties of the Play-house, Which, in vacation, lye in pawn for the Rent, Mons. Dat is vel, bi de Bill de House is to let. Play. 'Tis to let, but you, Sir, knock'd so hard As if you meant to take it by assault. Mons. Sir, me besesh your pardon, and vill give De good mony vor de Rent dis Vacation. Hous. K. What would you do in't? we must like your Trade Before we let our Shop, lest we should ride With John Dory to Paris to seek Rent. Mons. Mi vil make Presentation of de Farce. Tir. W. Farces, what be those? New French Bobs for Ladies? Play. Pray peace; I understand the Gentleman. Your Farces are a kind of Mungril Plays. But, Sir, I believe all French Farces are Prohibited Commodities, and will Not pass current in England. Mons. Sir, pardon me; de Engelis be more Fantastick den de Fransh. De Farce Bi also very fantastick, and vil passe. Play. The Monsieur's in the right; for we have found Our Customers of late exceeding humorous. Mons. De vise Nation bi for tings heroique, And de fantastique, vor de Farce! Tire. W. I like not that these French pardonne-moys should make so bold with old England. Hous. K. Peace, Woman; Wee'l let the House, and get money. Play. But how will your French Farce be understood? For all our travell'd Customers are gone To take the Air with their own Wives, beyond Hide-Park a great way; a homely Country mode Of their Fore-fathers. Tir. W. With grief we speak it; They may be asham'd to leave their poor Mistresses And us behind 'em without Customers. Play. Pray save your tears for our next Tragedy. The Monsieur's all for merry Farces, but (As I said, Sir,) how shall we understand 'em? Mons. Me have a Troop of French Comœdien Dat speak a litle very good Engelis. Tir. W. Bless us! a Troop? Play. Woman, thou art no Linguist; they in France Call a Company of Players, a Troop. Tir. W. I thought he had ta'ne our long Tennis-Court For a Stable. Play. And you are shelling Beans for his Horses. [Knocking without again. Hous. K. Our Bill at the Door draws in more Customers. [Exit House-Keeper. Play. House-Keeper, look out! Monsieur, you may draw up your Troop of Farcers Within the Pales, they may chance to give us A short trial of their prowess in Poetry. Mons. Vel, Sir, you sal see trange ting. [Exit Monsieur. Play. Who is't that knock'd? [Enter House-Keeper. Hous. K. Nay there's a couple. Play. What are they? Hous. K. Men in their shirts doing Penance, For the most scandalous sin of Poverty; Two very hot Fencers without doublets: They would hire our Play-house. Play. For what use? Hous. K. For a School, where they'd teach the Art of Duel Which is a fit trade in the long Vacation; For nothing makes young Gentlemen so quarrelsom As want of money. Play. Tell 'em the Red Bull stands empty for Fencers. There are no Tenents in it but old Spiders: Go bid the men of wrath allay their heat With Prizes there. Hous. K. I told 'em of Paneras-Church, where their Scholars (When they have kill'd one another in Duel) Have a Church-yard to themselves for their dead. [Knocking again. Play. Bid 'em march off. [Exit House-Keeper. We'll let this Theatre and build another, where, At a cheaper rate, we may have Room for Scenes. Brainford's the place! Perhaps 'tis now somewhat to far i'th' Suburbs; But the mode is for Builders to work slight and fast; And they proceed so with new houses, That old-London will quickly overtake us. Enter House-Keeper, Musitian and Porter bearing Cases for Instruments. Hous. K. I've brought the man, who, without the Merchandize of two Cats, shall make us all rich Whitingtons. Play. Hey, what have we here? A load of Tombs for dead Fiddles? Mus. I find, Sir, by your Bills you'd let the Play-house. Play. We would find means to live, this dead Vacation. Mus. That is, you wou'd have a good round Rent for it. Play. Which you'll scarce pay by playing Sellingers-round. Mus. Your wit, Sir, will never grow up to madness: 'Tis only the fume of an empty stomach. You may recover in the Term, when you Get money to get meat. Play. Pretily well said; but however, Sir, You should have been sure of our Shop before You brought in your Ware. Mus. Rest you merry. There is another Play-house to let in Vere-street. Hous. K. This man of musick has more in his head Than meer Crotchets. I pray a word, Sir: I am the House-Keeper. Mus. You may sleep out your Office, Sir. Y'are not like to be wak'd with visitants. [Going out. Play. Sir, under your favour, let's not part thus. Please but to clear the mist which you brought with you. Mus. Well, Sir, be brief. Play. Why came you with such confidence to take The House, as made you bring your Furniture Before we treated for the Rent? Mus. Because I thought you had been more in love With your profit, than with your wit. Play. I, that's the point? whence should our profit rise? Mus. I meant to entertain the People with A Novelty; which I suppose is no Ill bait for those small Fishes, which I thought Mine own, and purpos'd you a share i'th' Net. Play. But what's the composition of your Bait? Mus. I wou'd have introduc'd Heroique story In Stilo Recitativo. Play. In Stilo Recitativo? 'tis well; I understand you, Sir. But do you think That natural? Mus. Because 'tis not in custom You therefore think, Sir, it is out of Nature? Play. It seems so, Sir, to me, unless you would Metamorphise men into Birds. Suppose I should not ask, but sing, you now a question, And you should instantly sing me an answer; Would you not think it strange? Mus. Well, Sir, as how? [Plays and Sings. Play. Take out your Watch, and tell me, Sir, the hour? Then you reply, My Watch, Sir, is at Pawn, but 'tis past Four. Mus. Your heart is good, Sir, but y'are an ill Mimick In Musick, and your voice does breed some doubt Of your Virginity. Play. You'd make me blush If there were strangers here; but if you please Cease your rebukes, and proceed to instruction. Mus. Recitative Musick is not compos'd Of matter so familiar, as may serve For every low occasion of discourse. In Tragedy, the language of the Stage Is rais'd above the common dialect; Our passions rising with the height of Verse; And Vocal Musick adds new wings to all The flights of Poetry. [Knocking within again. Hous. K. Look out again! there's a fresh Customer. [Exit Tire-Woman. Play. Be pleas'd, Sir, to retire awhile, and tune Your Instruments. You shall make trial of The length and depth of all the Ears we have. Mus. I'll chuse the Womens Tiring-Room for privacy. Play. You may; for they are gon, Sir, to rob Orchards, And get the Green-sickness in the Country. [Exit Musician and Porter at one Door, Enter Tire-Woman at the other.] Tir. W. There's such a crowd at door, as if we had A new Play of Gundamar. Play. See who they be. [Exit House-Keeper. Our Bill has been up but two days, and I perceive We shall have use again of our Wardrobe. Go Woman! drive away the Moths; For they are grown as big as Butterflies. [Exit Tire-Woman. Enter House-Keeper with a Dancing-Master. Hous. K. All the dry old Fools of Bartholomew Fair Are come to hire our house. The German Fool, Yan Boridge of Hamb'rough, and numberless Jack-Puddings; the new motion men of Norwich, Op'ra-Puppets; the old Gentlewoman That professes the Galliard on the Rope; Another rare Turke that flies without wings, Rich Juglers with imbroider'd Budgets; Hoop-men, And so many Tom-Tumblers that you'd think Lincolns-Inn-Field a Forest of wild Apes. Play. Your Tumblers may trot hence, your Jugglers too May e'en pass and repass away to Southwark; But, till the nation be more civiliz'd, Your Fool and Devil may be entertain'd; They'l get money; none now but very choice Spectators will vouchsafe to see a Play Without 'm. Pray, what is that Gentleman? Hous. K. Not a spectator, Sir; but one that would Fain hire our House to draw spectators hither. Play. What is your Mystery? Dan. Ma. Historical dancing. Play. How? high History upon Ropes? Danc. Ma. Fie no, Sir; I'm for down-right plain history Exprest in figures on the floor, a kind Of morals in dumb shows by Men and Beasts. Play. Without any Interpreter? Danc. Ma. Pardon me, Sir; the Audience now and then Must be inform'd by Chorus's in Rhime. Play. O, dumb-shows with speeches? Danc. Ma. Yes, Sir, the same: but very short. Play. I apprehend you, Sir, if these be not Novelties, I'll to Sea, and strait seek out A new World to find 'em. These will take rarely, Hous. K. Wee'l buy Shovels to keep our Money from rusting. Play. Well, my dear fantastick friends of London, Who love Novelty, and would scorn to look Even on the Moon, but that she changes often And becomes new; I hope we shall please you now. [Knock again. Hous. K. Another man of Mystery! [Exit Hous. K. Play. Sir, pass the back way over to the Grange; An Inn where you may bait your Men and Beasts; And wee'l be for you strait. [Exit Danc. Ma. Enter, at the other door, House-Keeper. Hous. K. Here is one Goodman John Leyden desires To speak with you; and he does promise great satisfaction By a word to the Wise. Play. Tell him, the Wise are not at leisure now To hear his Sov'raignship. What would he have? Hous. K. He would hire the Turband, Scepter, and Throne of our Solyman the Magnificent; and reign This long Vacation over all the dominions In Portugall-Row. Play. He was an Enemy To the exil'd Comicks: I will not hear him. Hous. K. Consider well! He'll draw spectators hither. Play. Yes, such as will give no more to see him here Than in the street to see a Blazing Star. Money is the main material of Rent: Your Kings of Munster pay in prophecies only. Hous. K. He has a Ream of Paper about him: They are Bills of Exchange or Prophecies. Play. Bills of Exchange sign'd long ago at Munster. Bid him be gone. Hous. K. He's not such an enemy to the Comicks, As one without is a Foe to him; One who desires admittance too. Play. What is he? Hous. K. A man of Meeter, a Poet. Play. Dismiss your Doling, and let in your Poet. We must be ever civil to the Muses: Hous. K. The Poet has a special Train behind him, Though they look lean and empty, Yet they seem very full of invention. Play. Let him enter, and send his Train to our House-Inn, the Grange. [Exit House-Keeper. Virgil himself, as ancient Poets say, Was once a Groom, and liv'd by Oats and Hay. Enter House-Keeper and Poet. Poet. The Bill upon your door shews that Your House was not of late much haunted. Hous. K. Not with Play-visitors, nor is it now With Spirits, for you see none are afraid To hyre it. Poet. I did not suspect, Sir, it could be haunted With Spirits, for you Players never hide money. Play. You Poets do; for 'tis but seldom, Sir, That any has been found about ye. Poet. D'you set up of your selves, and profess Wit Without help of your Authors? Take heed, Sirs! You'l get few Customers. Hous. K. Yes, we shall have the Poets. Poet. 'Tis because they pay nothing for their entrance. But, my friends, leave off the endeavour to Grow witty without occasion. I pray Be in earnest. Do you mean to get money? Play. That's the cause why we endeavour at wit. Poet. Wit will not do your work alone. You must have something of a newer stamp to make your Coyn current. Your old great Images of Love and Honour are esteem'd but by some Antiquaries now. You should set up with that Which is meer new. What think you Of Romances travest. Play. Explain you self. Poet. The Garments of our Fathers you must wear The wrong side outward, and in time it may Become a fashion. Hous. K. It will be strange, and then 'tis sure to take. Poet. You shall present the actions of the Heroes, (Which are the chiefest Theams of Tragedy) In Verse Burlesque. Play. Burlesque and Travesti? These are hard words, And may be French, but not Law-French. Take heed, Sir, what you say; you may be question'd for't. We would do nothing, Sir, but what is legal. Hous. K. If it be French, I pray translate it to us. Play. Good, Sir, no French translation till the Tearm; It is too precious for Vacation-ware. Most of the men of judgment are retir'd Into the Country, and the remainder that Are left behind, come here not to consider But to be merry at such obvious things As not constrain 'em to the pains of thinking. Poet. Would you avoid Translations out of French? Play. We had a trial here of so much force As humane wit could bring, but truly, Sir, The number of our Customers (for whom Our Shop is chiefly open in Vacation) Affect Commodities of lesser price. Poet. You meet my judgment in a direct line. Play. The French convey their arguments too much In Dialogue: their speeches are too long. Poet. Indeed, such single length in their debates Bears some resemblance with that famous Duel, Which, in the fields of Finsbury, was fought. Whilom at Rovers with long Bow and Arrows: It began at Day-break, and ended at Sun-setting; whilst they each did gather up The weapons which the other shot, and sent Them back again with like effect. Play. Such length of speeches seem not so unpleasing As the contracted walks of their designs. Poet. Which are as narrow as the Allies in Our Citty-Gardens. Play. I perceive you take the Air sometimes within the Walls of London. Poet. If I agree with you in finding your Disease, it is some sign that I may know Your remedy; which is the Travesti, I mean Burlesque, or, more t'explain my self, Would say, the Mock-heroique must be it Which draws the pleasant hither i'th Vacation, Men of no malice who will pay for laughter. Your busie Termers come to Theatres, As to their Lawyers-Chambers, not for mirth, But, prudently, to hear advice. Play. You'd take our House for Poetry-burlesque? Poet. I would, and introduce such folly as shall Make you wise; that is, shall make you rich. Play. Well, we'll be content, like other rich Fools, To be laught at. There is an old tradition That in the times of mighty Tamberlane, Of conjuring Faustus, and the Beauchamps bold, You Poets us'd to have the second day. This shall be ours, Sir, and to morrow yours. Poet. I'll take my venture, 'tis agreed! Play. You bring materials with you to set up? Poet. My Mock-Burlesquers are without. Play. Conduct 'em to the Wardrobe, Sir, where you May take your choice of Cloaths and properties: Only, give way, Sir, to your Predecessors: The proverb does appoint the first that come To be first serv'd. Here is a Monsieur with His Farce; A spiritual Musician too With his seraphick Colloquies exprest In stilo recitativo. Hous. K. And historical Dancers that disperse Morality by speeches in dumb-shows. Poet. Well I will take my turn, I must come last. But, to declare my self a linguist, Sir, I dare pronounce, Finis coronat opus. [Exit Poet. Enter Tire-woman at the other door. Tir. W. The crowd are hast'ning to our doors, as if— Play. It were to see an old acquaintance hang'd. What is the bus'ness? Tir. W. They would come in, and see strange things for nothing. Hous. K. They follow'd the Porter that Brought the load of Musick. Play. A man may bring a Pageant through the streets As privatly upon my Lord Mayor's day, As a burden of Viol-cases hither. Tir. W. The fat Gentleman desires he may come in; He that has but one hand. Play. He is our constant friend; A very kind and a hearty spectator; One who ne'r fails to clap at ev'ry Play. Hous. K. How can he clap with one hand? Play. 'Troth, the good man makes shift, by laying his Plump cheek thus—then with such true affection Does so belabour it.—He shall come in. Woman, bid him hasten to the back-door. Hous. K. We have some half hearted friends who clap softly As if they wore furr'd Mittens. Play. We must provide our Party 'gainst to morrow; Watch at the doors before the Play begins, And make low congies to the cruel Criticks As they come in; the Poets should do that; But they want breeding, which is the chief cause That all their Plays miscarry. Hous. K. There is least malice in the upper Gallery, For they continually begin the plaudit. Play. We'll hire a dozen Laundry-Maids and there Disperse 'em, Wenches that use to clap Linen; They have tough hands, and will be heard. Hous. K. They shall be heard, or els we'll make 'em bring Their Laundry-Battledores. Play. Go, Guardian of the house, bestir your self; Hous. K. And bid our new Projectors to make haste: If you will lend 'em clothes and properties, I'll fit some of our Scenes for their occasions. Play. Let them begin in order, and to work. This is their day of trial, whilst we sit Like two judicious Magistrates of wit. The Spanish Poet had six hours to do, What we dull English undertake in two. [Exeunt several ways.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Second ACT. Enter Gorgibus, Celie weeping, Servant. Celie. Ah tinke not myn Art vill consant to dat. Gorg. Doe you grom-bell littel impertinant. Vat vould your young fantasque braine govarne mi Raison paternell. Vich sold give de Law De Fader or de Chile. You sold be glad Of sush a Husband. You will say you be ignorant Of his humeur, bute you know he is rish, He has terty tousant Duckat, and derefore Is honest Gentill man. Celie. Helas! my Arte! Gorg. If de colore soud mi transport, I soud Make you sing helas in anoder facon. Dis is de fruit of de Romance, fling me In de fire, dos papiers dat vill your head Vit Colibets, ende rede de Stanzas of Pibrac. Ende de Tablets of de Consilier Matieu Viche vill teach you to follow mi direction. Am I not Gorgibus your Vader. Celie. Ah Vader vill you dat I forgete d'amitie Dat I vow to Lelie, I soud be blame If vit out your consant I dispose min person, Bute your self did give min fait to his oat. Gorg. Lelie is vell accomplis bute all ting Must submit to de good occasion of Richess; de rishe person vill come dis nite, If I see you regard him vit de helas I sall—vell I say no more— [Exit. Serv. Madam, I finde tis convaniant to have De Husband to ly vit one in de cold nite. De Ive Berry viche show finely on de Tree Ven seperate is good for no noting; peace be Vit min dead Martin. I did tinke it redicule To use de cerimony of ayring de sheet In de vinter, bute now I shake and quiver In de Dog days. Celie. Sall I comit de forfat of de vou In abandon Lelie vor dis uglea person? Serv. Your Lelie is but Asse to let his Voyage stop him so long, de length of his distance Make me sugest some shange. Celie. Ah do not sink me dead vit de presage. Serv. I know you love him mush tenterly. [Celia draws forth Lelie's Picture and gazing on it falls into a sound. Madam, from vence procede dis. Ah! ce falls Into a sonde! Fley quickely, Ho la Help some bodey. Enter Sganarelle. Sgan. Vat is de matter. Serv. Myn Matresse is dying. Sgan. Is dat all? I did tink all vas lost to hear Sush cry, but mi vill aprosh her. Madam, tell me If you be dead. Hey! see say noting. Can I believe her vit out her vorde. Serv. I vill veche some body to carry her a vay. Vill you old her uppe? [Exit Servant. Sgan. See is cold every vere. I vill feel if Her mout give de breat. Let a me feel a littel. [Lays his hand on her Breast. By my trot me know not, bute me doe finde Some signe of de life— Sganarelle's Wife looks out of the Window. Wife. Ah! vat I see, a Damoselle in de armes Of myn Usband? I will goe doone. He betray me, Ende I will surprise de villaine Husband. Sgan. Vee must depesh to sucor her; she vil Be to blame to let her self dy: to goe To toder vorlt is grand sottise van vee May tarry in dis. [Exit carrying her out. Enter Sganarelle's Wife. Wife. Ha! is he already slay vay vit his Dilicate Minion. Mi vonder not mushe At de strange coldness of his late affection. De ingrate doe reserve his caresse for oder. Ah how angry be I dat de Law does not Permet de Vife change Husband as de Smock: Dat voud be commode. But vat doe I finde— De Enamail is singuliar, de Graving Charming; me vill open it.— [Opens the Picture. Enter Sganarelle. Sgan. Dey tought her dead ande see is live again As de Harang in de Sea. Ha! min vife here! Wife. O even! a Picture of man, of fine personage? [Sganarelle looks over his wifes shoulder. Sgan. Vat does see consider vit so muche attention. Dis Picture speake no good ting to min honeur; I feel de littel horne on mi bro. Wife. De vorke is more vort den de Gold. It smells sueet. Sgan. Vat a plague! does see kisse it? Wife. Vou voud not be attacque by sush fine man? Ah vy has not min Usband sush bon mien. But min Usband has de vil'd palt-pate. Sgan. Ah Curr Beesh! [Snatches the Picture from her. Doe mi surprise you in your vantones, In meditation to injure your usband, Is not min morsell sufficiant to Stay your stomach, but must you taste de Haut gout of a Gallant. Wife. Dat is good jeast; you tink bi 'tis finees To evade min complaint. Sgan. Let oders be made Tom-foole, de case is Plane in min hand, a token of your Amours. Wife. Min anger has allready too mush occasion, Tink not to keep dat from me. Sgan. May I not as vell make mush of de Copie, As you of de Originall. Wife. Verefore you say dis, you keep de Mistris in your arms. Vell I can see your trick. Sgan. 'Tis is de fine boy, de minion of de Bed, de dainty Drolle vit vome.— Wife. Vit vome? proceed.— Sgan. Vit vome, I sall tell tee in time. Wife. Vat does de good man drunkard means by tis? Sgan. Goody slutt you understand me too vell. My name sall be no more Monsieur Sganarelle, But mi lore Cuckol; mi sall make your body lesse By vone arme, ande two ribe. Wife. You dare continew dis discours to put Me off, of de tought of your Mistris. Sgan. Ande you dare play me dis divellis trick. Wife. Vat divilis trick, speaka? Sgan. 'Tis not vort min labeur to complaine now, Bute you provide min brou vit a fine Feadar of a Buck. Wife. Vell, after you give me de most sensible injure Dat can invite a Voman to great vengance. You voud amuse me vit counterfeit anger To prevent d'effect of myn resentment. You make de offence, and begin de quarrell. Sgan. Rare impudence, you carry it cunningly To make me tink you vertuous voman. Wife. Goe to your Mistresses ande caresse dem; Bute returne min picture vit out more trick. [She snatches away the Picture and runs out. Sgan. You tink to scape me, bute I vill ave it once more. [Runs after. Enter Lelie. Lelie. Min Arte does abandon me too mush To feare. De Fader has promesse allwaies, And Celie has manifesse dat love Viche support min hope. Enter Sganarelle. Sgan. I ave got it from de baggage mi vife. [Starts at the sight of Lelie, and compares the Picture with his face. De Devil is not so like de Devil, as dat face is to dis. Dat is de Villain dat make me de trange Ting call'd de Cuckol. [Lelie spies the Picture in his hands. Lelie. Vat do I see? if dis bi min picture: Ah Celie vat soud I tink of ti love? [Aside. Sgan. Ah pauver Sganarelle, to vat destine Is dy reputation expose now? [Aside. Lelie. Dis token does alarme mi credence. [Aside. Is it departed from de faire hand, To viche I gave it one time. Sgan. I sall be discern'd between two fingers, In de Ballade vit horus on mi bro. [Aside. Lelie. Do min eies deceive min heart? [Aside. Sgan. Ah Villain hast dow de courage to make A Cuckol of Sganarelle in de fleur of his age. [Aside. Lelie. Min eies dos not sheate me; 'tis min owne picture. [Sganarelle turning his back to him. Sgan. De man is cunning. Lelie. Min surprise is exceeding. Sgan. Vat voud he ave. Lelie. I vill accoste him. [Aside. May I—Hey! of grace, a vord. [Aside. Sgan. Vat voud he say? Lelie. May I obtain de faveur to know now How dat picture came to your hande? Sgan. Pardon me; I vill advise a littel— Begar, tis mi man, or rader tis Mi Vives man. He compares the Picture and Lelies face together. Lelie. Put me out of paine and say from veme it came. Sgan. Dis picture viche does vex you, is your resemblance. It vas in de hand of your acquaintance. De sweet ardeur betweene mi Lady ande you, is known To me, bute, I sall desire you hereafter To maks no more sush kine of love to injure De Husband, and to abuse our marriage. Lelie. Vat do you meane her, from vome you had dis token? Sgan. See is min Vife, and I am her Husband. Lelie. Her Husband? Sgan. Yes, her Husband; and a very melancholique Husband, you know de occasion. Ande I sall acquaint her Parents vit it. [Exit. Lelie. Ah vat have I heard? I vas told her new Espouse Vas ugly as de Devil. After tousant protestation From de unfaitful mout couds don shange me For sush a vile object. Dis sensible affront Togeder vit de toyle of mine long voyage Does give me on de sodains a chocque of sush Violence dat min Arte begin to fayle. Enter Sganarelle's Wife. Wife. I vill seek min perfidious husband; did you not see An ugly knave passe dis vay?—Helas! Vat is it dat troubll dis fine Gentelman? You are ready to fall downe vit sickness. Lelie. Tis sickness dat take me on de sodaine. Wife. I be feare you vil fall in de sound: In compassion let me lead you to the Porch of min House, You may sit down a vile to recover. Lelie. Vor a moment I accept dis faveur. [Spies them at his Porch. Enter Sganarelle. Sgan. Ah! vat do I see? I dy! dere is no question Of de coppie of de picture, now I finds Min Vife vit de original. I not Dare enter in mine house, vor fear of mine collere And vor more fear dat his collere should be Greater then mine own.— Wife. Maks not sush haste avay. your sicknesse [Exit Wife. If you depart so soon vil take you agen. Lelie. No, no, I give you all tank imaginarie Vor dis obligeing faveur. I am recover'd. Sgan. Dit is cunning? dey disguise all vit civillitees; He perceive me; let see vat he vill say. Enter Celie, and Lelie gazes on her. Lelie. Min Art revive, dis object mi inspire. But I soud now min selve condamne vor min Injust transport; see can not be blame. If be de error of fortune dat vill No let me ave a Vife so delicate. [Exit. Sgan. sees not Celie, but looks after Lelie's going out. Sgan. Ven he casts Seep Eies toward min house, Den I soud tink he voud make me one Ramme. Celie. Lelie has appear just now to min Eie; Min cruel Fader has conceale from me His returne from his voyage. Sgan. Vat min Vife doe may be in civilitie Ande compliment to him; de compliment Be good sometime: but 'tis no good fason To make de Usband Cuckol. Vel sal I Lament vit out revange? Celie. Sir, de Gentilman dat vas before you Just now, vere did you know him? Sgan. Helas! 'tis not mi, Madam, dat know him, But it is he dat kno min Vife. Celie. Vat does give tro-bell to your Esprit? Sgan. Madam, I ave great disposition to cry. Sganarelle is rob of his honeur, bute Figa for honeur, I be rob of min reputation Vit de Nabeurs. Celie. Vit your permission tella me how? Sgan. Dat young Gentil-man (I speak it vit reverance To his qualitee) make bole vit min Vife. Celie. He dat now passe by? Sgan. De same, he make mushe of min vife in corner. Celie. Ah, mi did judge dat his secret returne From his voyage vit out min knowledge, Vas presage of loose trick. Sgan. Madam, you take min part vit mushe sharitee, You grieve vor poor Cuckol, bute oders Of de vicked vorlt made laugh at dem. Celie. O Even! Is it possibel dat he tinke To live after dis perfidie? Sgan. Madam, he is not dying: he is steale vay To eate de good pottage to make him abel To make me more Cuckol. Celie. Ah Traitre, vicked man vit dobill Art. Ende vit no Soule. Sgan. Mi not kno if he ave soule, bute mi Vife be acquainted vit his body. Celie. No torture is sufficien vor his grand crime. He deserve to ly on de Rack. Sgan. He doe ly allready at Rack an Manger. But dat doe him good ande me hurt. Celie. Helas de inconstancy! Sgan. Hey! Bute de sigh vit out revange be [Sighs aloud. To no more propose den de bray of de Asse. Celie. Ah, injure de Arte dat never vas infidel. Sgan. De man dat make Cuckol ave no justice. Celie. 'Tis too mushe, ende de Arte cannot tink On it vit out dying vit grief. Sgan. Be not too mush in colere, Madam, I pray, My grief give you too great impression. Celie. Tinke not I vill dy vit out mi revenge; I vill instantly about it. [Exit. Sgan. Trange ting dat her goodness promps her to be Revenge vor me! mi tink her anger does Augment min disgrace, ande teache mi vat to doe. Begar I vill be revange vit grand fury: [Steps two or three steps forwards &amp; returns back. Bute, Sganarelle, softely if you please! De Cuckol-maker may be muche valiant, Ande lay de Baston on de back as he doe lay de Horne on mi head. He may kille me. 'Tis better to ave de Horne den no life. If my vife has done injure, let her grieve: Vy soud I cry dat doe no rong? But agen I begin to be sensible and vil ave de vengeance, Ande soundely, vor I vill virst tell de vorlt Dat he ly vit min vife. [Exit. Enter Gorgibus, Celie, Servant. Celie. I am prepar'd to submit to your vill; Dispose, Fader, of min vous ande of me; Ordonne mi vedding ven you please. Gorg. In trot de joy of dis doe transport me. If I not feel de Gout, my leg voud caper Vor joy of your obediance: you make mi Young as de chile, and I vill goe make de Preparation to make you gette de chile. [Exit. Serv. Dis shange be ting of vonder. Celie. Ven you sall kno de motive dat constrain me To dis fason of doing you vill not vonder mush. Serv. Dat may vell be. Celie. Kno Lelie invad min Art vit perfidie, He is come from de voyage and vas vit— Serv. Look vere he come.— Enter Lelie. Lelie. Before dat vor perpetual time I sall depart From you, I sall reprosh you justly. Celie. Vat can you ave de confidance To speak vit me agen? Lelie. If I soud not reprosh you for your shoice, I ver vicked man, live! live contant Ende make mush of vort mor espouse. Celie. Vell Traitre, mi vill live, ande mi desire Soud be dat your Arte be troubell to see it. Enter Sganarelle in Armour. Sgan. Bigar mi be desp-rate, ende de-fy Man, Voman, and Chile dat make de Cuckol. Celie. Vat doe you turn your eies vit Same ende not anser mi. Lelie. Ah I ave see too mush. Celie. Do dis object suffice to confond ti. Lelie. But it oblig you to blush rader. Sgan. My colere care not noo one littel Pudding vor his valeur. Lelie. Vat man be you dat tro-bill me? ende make Mi angry! vit vom vod you vite? Sgan. Vit some body, bute mi be cunning As de Devil and vill no tell. Lelie. Vi be you armed in dis fason? Sgan. Perhaps 'tis my fason vor fear it soud rain: Vat contantmant it vod be to kill him? Sganarelle tak corage. Lelie. Vat you say? Sgan. Mi say notin bute about bussnes Vit min selfe. [He beats his stomach and face. Lelie. Dat is strang man! Sgan. If mi had tayle like de Lyon, mi voud Beat min body into courage. Celie. Dat object soud make you ane shame, From vich your eyes seem to be vonded. Lelie. Yes mi know bi dat object, dat you be Guilty of infidelite inexcusable. Sgan. Min Arte is littel as de Pin head. Celie. Ah, cease before mi Traitre dis Cruel insolence in your discour. Sgan. Begar see be more angry for mi, den I be vor mi selve. Be generous, Sganaril, Ands kille him a littel as soon as he Sall turne his back— [Lelie passing two or three steps without design, makes Sganarelle return, who did approach to kill him. Lelie. Celie, since min discour move your colere, I vill seem vell satisfait of your Arte, Ende praise de choice it has made. Celie. Yese, my choise is sush as noting can allter. Lelie. Yese, you doe vell in defending it. Sgan. See is stout voman ende does vel to defend Min cause: Sir, your amours bi not legall. But I'm vise, else strange slaughter voud proceed. Lelie. From vence dis plaint ende brutal anger? Sgan. Min vife is min in publique and yours in privat. Lelie. Sush sugestion be redicule. Celie. Ah Traitre! dou kno vell to disembel. Lelie. Vat be you also angry because mi Teache him discretion? Celie. Make your discour to him: he kno too mush. Sgan. In trot, Madam, you oblige mi vit your Trobel in mi defence [Enter Sganarelle's Wife, and speaks to Celie. Wife. Vell ave I found you now one oder time? Mi see vat doe passe; bute you soud doe vell Not to seduce de heart of min veak Usband. Celie. Vat is de occasion of dis tempeste? Wife. You ave as mush conscience as de Devil, Ven he be seeke vit eating vlesh on Fryday. Celie. Vat conscience, speaka boldly. Sgan. No body send for your Company Caroyne. Doe you kerelle vit her vor defending mi? Dont feare, dy Gallante sall be taken avay. Cel. Goe, be not feare mi ave sush intantion. Dit be vone extraordinarie dreame. Lelie. Vat extravagance be dis. [Turning towards Celie. Serv. Vat be de ende of dese Galantries. Servant steps between Lelie &amp; her Mistress. De more mi listen, de lesse mi understand. I see mi must be concerne. Lelie. Vel, vat you say? Serv. Make response in order and leta me speak. Vat is it dat you reprosh to my Maitress? Lelie. De Infidel has change me vor anoder. Ende upon de rumour of her being mary'd Mi vas transport vit grief not to be egall'd. Serv. Marry'd? to vome? Lelie. To dat vonderfull Gentilman. [Points to Sganarelle. Serv. Vat, to him? Lelie. Yese, en verite! Serv. Voo told you sush ting? Lelie. Himselve. Sgan. Begarr dis be true as de Sun shina, Dat I may be marryd to min Vife. Lelie. Mi did see you vit great tro-bell of Arte snash min picture. Sgan. Vell, ende here it be. Lelie. You tolda me de person from vome You did snash dis Token, vas bond to you Vit de knot of mariage. Sgan. Mi vas cunning to snash it; vor Vit out dat, mi now discover her vile amour. Wife. Vat story bi tis, mi found it by shance Under myn veet; ande presantly after Mi got Monsieur in his veaknesse into min house. Mi kno not vome de picture resemble. [Shewing it Lelie. Celie. I vas de cause of dis adventure Of de picture; vor mi let it fall ven mi Vas by your care convey to your house. Serv. Vit out me dere had bin strange misprision. Sgan. Sall vee take dis as currant money of France, Ende tinke de horne vas imaginaire. Wife. Min feare, is not depart so quickaly. Sgan. Bi mi trot let us tinke our selve onest puple. Accept vit out delay de berregaine propose. Wife. Take heed den of de Cudgel, if I learn new ting Of your designe in corner. [Celie having talkt aside with Lelie. Celie. O Evens! if it be so, vat ave I done? Vor tinking you vit out true fait, mi ave Take in revange de unhappy resolution Viche I did alvay reject. Mi ave promesse To min Vader—bute here he come. [Enter Gorgibus. Lelie. Mi vill speak yit him. Sir, you see me returne Vit min first ardeur of true love, ende nou Mi hope you vill accomplis your promesse Touchant mi mariage vit Celie. Gorg. Sir, I see you returne vit de same ardeur, Bute mi resolution ave found occasion— Sir, your hum-bill serviteur. Lelie. Vat, Sir, vill you shange min felicitie? Gorg. Yes, Sir, min daughter sall follow de Law. Celie. Helas! how sall min duty be expresse? Against de honeur of min love? Gorg. Be dis spoken like de daughter to min Commandements. Vell you vill den retreat from Your inclination to Monsieur Valere?— [Enter Villebrequin. Bute dere be his Vader, sure he is come To condus de businesse.—Vat bring you here? Monsieur Villebrequin? Ville. One important secret dat I be tell Dis morning viche does break min promess to you. Mi Son vome your Daughter did accept vor Espouse, has in private deceiv'd us all. Gorg. Vat be de intantion of dis? Ville. He has bin espoused four mont to Life Ende de Lady being of goot alliance, Mi vant de power to break de Contract Mi made to you.— Gorg. Vell let it broken, if so, vit out Your leave your son Valere be first ingage To anoder; mi cannot conceale from you, Dat my selve did make promesse to my Daughter, dat Monsieur Lelie soud marry her, Hoo is come riche in virtu from his voyage, Ende sall ave her. Ville. De choice please me vell. Lelie. Ende it vill crowne min life vit happinesse. Min Arte is leap out of min Breast for joy. Sgan. Did ever some body tink himself more Cuckol den I. Vell, a vise man may be Deceive sometime, derefore to de Husbands As a presant I sall dis council bring, Dat is, tho you see all, believe no ting. Gorg. Bi mi trot it sall be a new proverb, Ende vor de joy of dis conclusion Let us have a dance a la ronde. Ville. Mi vill make one. Gorg. Mi vill make two. Wife. Ande mi vill make vone, two, tree. Sgan. Mi cannot dance, but sall veche one Dat sall dance rare Sarabrand vit Castiniet. [Exit Sganarelle. They dance a la Ronde. After the Dance Sganarelle returns in a Buffoon habit, and dances a Jig, and so the Farce ends. The Song to the Dance a la Ronde. Mrs. Gosnel. 1. Ah, Love is a delicate ting, Ah, Love is a delicate ting, In Vinter it gives de new Spring. Chorus. It makes de dull Dush vor to dance Nimbell as Monsieur of France. Mrs. Gosnel. 2. Ande dough it often does make, Ande dough it often does make, De head of de Cuckol to ake; Chorus. Yet let him bute vinke at de Lover, Ande de paine vill quickly be over. Mrs. Gosnel. 3. De Husband must still vink a littel, De Husband must still vink a littel, Ande sometime be blinde as a Bee-tell: Chorus. Ande de Vife too some time must be, Ven he play trick as bline as he. The End of the second ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Third ACT. Enter House-Keeper, Player. Play. W'are now to take a farther voyage than From England into France, and think Our selves with Captain Drake in the West Indies. Hous. K. Now we shall be in Stilo Recitativo. I'm in a Trance, when I hear Vocal Musick; And in that Trance, inclin'd to prophecie That 'twill bring us inundations of shillings. Play. Thou understand'st Recitative Musick, As much as a Dray-horse does Greek. THE HISTORY OF Sr FRANCIS DRAKE. Exprest by Instrumental and Vocal Musick, and by Art of Perspective in Scenes, &amp;c. THE DISCRIPTION of the FRONTISPIECE. An Arch is discover'd, rais'd upon stone of Rustick work; upon the top of which is written, in an Antick Shield, PERU; and two Antick Shields are fix'd a little lower on the sides, the one bearing the Figure of the Sun, which was the Scutcheon of the Incas, who were Emperors of Peru: The other did bear the Spread-Eagle, in signification of the Austrian Family. The First ENTRY. The preparation of the opening of the Scene is by a prelude and Corante. Afterwards the Curtain rises by degrees to an ascending Ayr, and a Harbour is discern'd, (which was first discover'd by Sir Francis Drake, and called by him Port-pheasant) where two Ships are Moor'd, and Sea-Carpenters are erecting a Pinnace, whilst others are felling Trees to build a Fort. The narrowness to the entrance of the Harbour may be observ'd, with Rocks on either side; and out at Sea a ship towing a Prize. And likewise on the top of a high Tree, a Marriner making his Ken. This Prospect is made through a Wood, differing from those of European Climats, by representing of Coco-Trees, Pines, and Palmitos. And on the Boughs of other Trees are seen Munkies, Apes, and Parrots. The Introduction of the Entry is by a Martial Saraband. The Saraband being ended, Enter Drake Junior, and Boatswain. Drak. jun. Climb, Boatswain, climb! and from the height Of that steep Rock inform thy sight! From yonder Point our Master call. I'll here attend our Admiral. [Exit Boatswain. The Mist ascends, and south'rd it grows clear! Methinks at distance somewhat does appear, Which wakens us with hope. Boats. A Sail! a Sail! Drak. jun. 'Tis English built, or else my sight does fail. Boats. within. Oho! Oho! another Ship I spy, And, by their Course, both to this Harbour ply. Dak. jun. She lowrs her Main-sail, the wind does rise! Boats. within. She now bears in, and she does tow a Prize! Enter Drake Senior. Drak. sen. To Sea, to Sea! Man out the Boat! Drak. jun. It has not Tyde enough to float. Drak. sen. Stir, Mates! stir, stir! and bring more hands: Shove, shove! and roul her o're the Sands! Lanch forth, and make your Ken! Both by her Rigging and her Mould She brings our Country-men; And has a rich and heavy Hould. [Exeunt. Enter a Marriner. 1 Mar. Ho, Mate! ho, ho! what canst thou see From the top-Gallant of that Tree? Mar. within. The Ship does Anchor cast; And now her Boat does haste To reach the Shore. 1 Mar. What seest thou more? Mar. within. Enough, to make me hasten down: For if my eyes prove true, The bowels of Peru Shall be ript up and be our own. The Lion Rouse is landed here. 1 Mar. I'll run to meet him at the Peer. A Tun of yellow Gold, Conceal'd within our Hold, For half my share I scorn to take, When he is joyn'd with Dragon-Drake. [Exit. Two Marriners having met with another newly landed, dance to a Rustick Ayre. The Dance being ended, Enter Drake Senior, Captain Rouse, Drake Junior, and Page. Drak. sen. Welcome to Land my brother of the Sea! From childhood rockt by winds and waves like me. Who never canst a danger dread, Since still in dang'rous Tempests bred. Yet still art safe and calm within thy breast, As Lovers who in shady Coverts rest. Thy fame about the world does make her flight, And flies as swiftly as the wings of light. Rous. My fame does lay her Trumpet down, When yours does publish your renown. Drak. sen. What is your Prize? Rous. 'Tis fraught with Spies: A Carvel rigg'd at Sivell for this Coast, To fetch from hence Intelligence; But, meeting me, she has her voyage lost. Drak. sen. Brave friend, wilt thou now guided be By that bright Star which ushers me? Rous. What man is that, Lov'd Admiral, Who does not hasten at your call? He must be either deaf, or ever lame, Who follows not your loud and leading fame. Drak. sen. My course must now not be Upon the open Sea: Our Country's foes we must invade Through Woods, and seek them in the shade; And follow them where Phœbus never shines, Through depths as dark and winding as their Mines. Chorus of all. That which enlightens, and does lead The World, and all our Vict'ries breed, We in those Caverns shall behold, In seeing Man's bright Mistress, Gold. Drak. sen. Boat all our Guns! haste, haste aboard! Unlade! then let our Ships be Moor'd! To raise our Fort, some hew down Trees! Whilst others rig our Pinnaces. Their watchful Guards let ev'ry Sentry keep, That, after labour, all may safely sleep. Some o're remoter grounds Walk, and relieve their Rounds: Whilst some secure each Post On out-lets of the Coast. That, after wandring long to trace Wild Rivers, we may find this place For our imbarkment free, To wander more at Sea. Drak. jun. The jealous Spaniards long have understood The danger of this Harbour's neighbourhood. 'Tis therefore fit That thou shouldst leave behind, To govern it, A great experienc'd mind. Drak. sen. I know it is of high import. My second thoughts conclude, thou Rouse shalt stay, To finish and secure the Fort; Whilst we to Venta-Cruz enforce our way. Chorus of all. We must the Main forbear, And now a Coasting go, Then up with Rivers steer, To watch how far they flow. But if landing we pass Where Recoes through Foords are long wading. Then we in pitty, alass, Their Mules must ease of their lading. [Exeunt omnes. The Second ENTRY. A Symphony variously humour'd prepares the change of the Scene. The SCENE is chang'd. In which is discern'd a Rockie Country of the Symerons, who were a Moorish People, brought formerly to Peru by the Spaniards, as their Slaves, to dig in Mines; and having lately revolted from them, did live under the government of a King of their own Election. A Sea is discover'd, and Ships at distance, with Boats rowing to the shore, and Symerons upon the Rocks. The Prospect having continu'd a while, this Song is sung by a Steersman in the foreostm Boat, and the Chorus by Marriners rowing in it. Steersman. 1. Aloof! and aloof! and steady I steer! 'Tis a Boat to our wish, And she slides like a Fish, When chearily stem'd, and when you row clear. She now has her trim Away let her swim. Mackrels are swift in the shine of the Moon; And Herrings in Gales when they wind us, But, timeing our Oars, so smoothly we run, That we leave them in shoals behind us. Chorus. Then cry One and all! Amain, for Whitehall! The Diegos we'll board to rummidge their Hold; And drawing our Steel, they must draw out their Gold. Steersman. 2. Our Master and's Mate, with Bacon and Pease, In Cabins keep aboard; Each as warm as a Lord: No Queen, lying in, lies more at her ease. Whilst we lie in wait For Reals of Eight, And for some Gold Quoits, which fortune must send: But, alas, how their ears will tingle, When finding, though still like Hectors we spend, Yet still all our pockets shall jingle. Chorus. Then cry, One and all! Amain, &amp;c. Steersman. 3. But oh how the Purser shortly will wonder, When he sums in his Book All the wealth we have took, And finds that we'll give him none of the Plunder; He means to abate The Tyth for the State: Then for our Owners some part he'll discount: But his fingers are pitcht together; Where so much will stick, that little will mount, When he reckons the shares of either. Chorus. Then cry, One and all! Amain, &amp;c. Steersman. 4. At sight of our Gold, the Boatswain will bristle, But not finding his part, He will break his proud heart, And hang himself strait ith' chain of his Whistle. Abast and afore! Make way to the shore! Softly as Fishes which slip through the stream, That we may catch their Sentries napping. Poor little Diegos, they now little dream Of us the brave Warriors of Wapping. Chorus. Then cry, One and all! Amain, &amp;c. This Song being sung, Enter the King of the Symerons, Drake Senior, Pedro, and Page. King. Great Wand'rer of the Sea, Thy walks still pathless be. The Races thou dost run, Are known but to the Sun. And as the walk above, Where he does yearly move, We only guess, though him we know, By great effects below. So, though thy courses traceless are, As if conducted by a wandring Star, Yet by thy deeds all Climes acknowledge thee; And thou art known and felt as much as he. Drak. sen. So narrow is my merit wrought, That when such breadth you thus allow my fame, I stand corrected and am taught To hide my story, and to shew my shame. King. As tireless as thy body is thy mind: No adverse current can thy progress stop. Thy forward courage leaves all doubts behind. And when thy Anchor's lost, thou keep'st thy Hope. Welcom! and in my Land be free, And pow'rful as thou art at Sea. Drak. sen. Monarch of much! and still deserving more Than I have coasted on the Western shore! Slave to my Queen! to whom thy vertue shows, How low thou canst to vertue be; And, since declar'd a Foe to all her Foes, Thou mak'st them lower bow to thee. King. Instruct me how my Symerons and I May help thee to afflict the Enemy. Drak. sen. Afford me Guides to lead my bold Victorious Sea-men to their Gold: For nothing can afflict them more, Than to deprive them of that store With which from hence they furnisht are T'afflict the peaceful world with war. King. Here from my bosom Pedro take, And him thy chief Conductor make. Who once was an unhappy slave to them; But now is free by my deserv'd esteem. He is as watchful as the Eye Of Age still wak'd with jealousie; And like experienc'd Lovers wisely true Who after long suspicion find, They had no cause to be unkind, And then with second vows their loves renew. Drak. sen. He is, since so deservingly exprest, Remov'd but from thy bosom to my breast. King. All other ayds requir'd to thy design, Chuse and receive, for all my strengths are thine. [Exeunt. Enter Four Symerons, who dance a Morisco for joy of the arrival of Sir Francis Drake, and depart. Then this Song is sung by a Chorus of Marriners within. Chorus of Marriners within. Winds now may whistle, and waves may dance to 'em, Whilst Merchants cry out, such sport will undo 'em. And the Master aloud bids. Lee the Helm Lee! But we now shall fear nor the Rocks nor the Sand, Whilst calmly we follow our Plunder at Land, When others in storms seek Prizes at Sea. The Third ENTRY. The change of the Scene is prepar'd by a Symphony, consisting of a Martial Ayr, which having continu'd a while, the Scene changes, and repesents a Peruvian Town, pleasantly scituated, with Palmeto-Trees, Guavas, and Cypresses, growing about it, whilst English Land-Souldiers and Sea-men seem to be drawn up towards the West end; whilst the Peruvians are feasting their Guests, and Two of their Boys bearing Fruit towards the Strangers. This Object having continu'd a while, Enter Drake Senior, Drake Junior, Pedro, Page. Drak. sen. March! March! wheel to the right hand still, To shun loose footing on that Hill. From thy Meridian run, O thou inflaming Sun! The Ayr above us else to fire will turn, And all this Sand beneath like Cynders burn. Now give the word! Drak. jun. Stand! Within. 1. Stand. 2. Stand. 3. Stand. Drak. sen. All firm and sudden to command! Halt for our Reer a while, and then West from that Wood draw up our Men. Stand to your Arms till we send out Our trusty Symerons to scout. Pedro. Scouts I have chosen, who can trace All the Retreats, which in the chace The hunted seek all shades to which they run, When strength leaves them, and they the Hunters shun. Drak. sen. Are these Peruvians friends, or, by surprize, Must we secure them as our enemies? Pedro. Great Chief, they rev'rence thy renown, And thou mayst quarter in their Town. Yet so advance with care, In all the shapes of War; That when the Spaniards know How well they treat their Foe, The entertainment may appear, Not the effect of Love, but Fear. Drak. jun. Their dwelling seems so fresh and flourishing, As if it still the Nurs'ry were Of all the seeds that furnish out the Spring For ev'ry Clime, and all the year. Drak. sen. Here Nature to her Summer Court retires: Our Northern Region is the shade, Where she grows cold, and looks decay'd, And seems to sit by artificial fires. Drak. jun. Advance, Advance, And in the Rear, To make our number more appear, Let all our trusty Sym'rons spread Their Ranks, and be by Pedro led. Chorus of all. All order with such clemency preserve, That such as to our pow'r submit, May take delight to cherish it, And seem as free as those whom they shall serve. [Exeunt. Five Peruvians Enter, and dance to a Rustick Ayr, after which, this Song is sung by a Peruvian, and the Chorus to it by his Countrymen, whilst they dance again in a Round. Peru. 1. With Boughs and with Branches trim up our Bowrs, And strew them with Flowrs: To receive such a Guest As deserves for a Feast All that the Forest, or the Field, Or deeper Lakes and Rivers yield. Chorus. Still round, and round, and round, Let us compass the ground. What man is he who feels Any weight at his heels? Since our hearts are so light, that all weigh'd together, Agree to a grain, and they weigh not a feather. Peru. 2. The Lord of the Sea is welcome to Land, And here shall command All our Wealth, and our Arms; For his name more alarms The Spaniards, than Trumpets or Drums: Hark how they cry, Drake comes, Drake comes! Chorus. Still round, and round, and round, Let &amp;c. Peru. 3. Though to his Foes like those winds he is rough, That meet in a huff: Yet that storm quickly ends, When embrac'd by his friends: Then he is calm and gentle made, As Loves soft whispers in a shade. Chorus. Still round, and round, and round. Let &amp;c. The Fourth ENTRY. A Wild Ayr by way of Symphony, prepares the change of the Scene: which having continu'd a while, the Scene is chang'd; wherein is discern'd upon a Hill, a Wood, and in it a Tree, which was famous in those times for extraordinary compass and height; on the top of which, Pedro (formerly a Slave to the Spaniards, but now employ'd by the Moorish King to conduct Sir Francis Drake towards Panamah) had promis'd Sir Francis Drake to shew him both the North and the South Atlantick Seas. English Souldiers and Marriners are reposing themselves under it. At distance the Natives are discern'd in their hunting of Boars; and at nearer view, two Peruvians are killing a Stagg. This Object having remain'd a while, Enter Drake Senior, Drake Junior, Page. Drake senior. A boar so fierce and large No Hunter e're did charge. Advance thy Spear, And turn him there. Drak. jun. This last encounter he has bravely stood; But now has lost his courage with his blood. Drak. sen. He foams, and still his Tusks does whet, As if he still disdain'd retreat. Drak. jun. The wound you gave him makes him turn his head, To seek the darker shades, where he was bred. Page. Follow, follow! Drak. sen. Stay my Victorious Boy! When a couragious Beast does bleed, Then learn how far you should proceed To use advantage where you may destroy: To courage even of Beasts some pity's due; And where resistance fails, cease to pursue. Enter Pedro. Pedro. Our men have firmly stood and swiftly run: The Game was plenteous and the Chace is done. Drak. jun. Pedro in sev'ral forms has all That ev'ry where we merit call. Drak. sen. Wary in War as Chiefs grown old; And yet in suddain dangers bold. Civil and real too in Courts; Painful in bus'ness and in sports. Pedro. Behold that Tree which much superiour grows To all that in this Wood Have many Ages stood: Beneath whose shade your Warriours may repose. Drak. jun. There let us stay And turn our Prey Into a Feast Till in the West The Cypress curtain of the night is drawn. Then forward march as early as the dawn. Drak. sen. Is this that most renown'd of Western Trees On whose Main-top Thou gav'st me hope To view the North and South Atlantick Seas? Pedro. It is; therefore with speed Thither, my Chief, proceed: And, when you climbing have attain'd the height, Report will grow authentick by your sight. Drak. sen. When from those lofty branches I The south Atlantick spy My vows shall higher fly, Till they with highest Heav'n prevail, That, as I see it, I may on it sail. Drak. jun. No English Keel hath yet that Ocean plow'd. Pedro. If Prophesie from me may be allow'd, Renowned Drake, Heav'n does decree That happy enterprize to thee For thou of all the Britans art the first That boldly durst This Western World invade; And as thou now art made The first to whom that Ocean will be shown, So to thy Isle thou first shalt make it known. Chorus of all. This Prophesie will rise To higher Enterprise. The English Lion's walk shall reach as far As prosp'rous valour dares adventure War. As Winds can drive, or Waves can bear Those Ships which boldest Pilots stear. [Exeunt. This Song is sung by two Land Souldiers, and two Seamen. Seam. How comes it you Landmen, and we of the Sea, Though oft mixt together yet seldom agree? Landm. A Riddle, which we can find out no more Than you can why Seas contest with the shore. Seam. We give a shrewd guess how our quarrels have grown; For still when at Land we are joyntly design'd To the dainty delight of storming a Town, You run to the Plunder, and leave us behind. Landm. Alas, our dear Brothers! How can we forbear? But aboord when you have us, where wonderful Gold Is shovell'd like Ballast, y'are even with us there: We fight on the Decks, whilst you rummidge the Hold. Seam. But now we shall march where the Diegos (though loth To part with it civ'ly) may soon oblige both. Landm. They so much are scar'd from their wits with their dangers, That now they want wit to be civil to strangers. Chorus of all. Come let us joyn hands then, and nere part asunder, But, like the true Sons of trusty old Mothers, Make equally haste to a snap of the plunder, Then justly divide, and spend it like Brothers. This Song being ended, the two Land-Souldiers and two Sea-men dance a Jigg, to intimate their future amity. The Fifth ENTRY. This Entry is prepared by an Ayr and C?rante; and then the Scene is chang'd, in which is discover'd the rising of the Sun through a thick Wood, and Venta-Cruz at great distance on the South side. This being discern'd a while, Enter Drake Senior, Drake Junior, Page, Souldier. Drak. jun. Bold Rouse, doubting our safety by our stay; Thinking his patience longer than our way; And having well secur'd our Port, Our Trenches digg'd, and rais'd our Fort, Is here arriv'd, resolving still to be A sharer in your worser destiny. He was conducted by a Symeron; And bows for what his rasher Love has done. Drak. sen. I shall be very slow. When I must backward go With punishment to overtake The errours which my friend did make. Tell him I know his fault is past; And now I cannot but go fast, When I shall forward move To meet approaching Love. [Exit Souldier. The morn begins her glory in the East; And now the World prepares To entertain new cares; Though th'old suffic'd to hinder all our rest. Drake. jun. Benighted Seamen now their course reform Who, Coasting, were misguided by a storm. Now Merchants to imported stowage haste, Whilst Plowmen drive from Cottages their Teems. The Poor in Cities rise to toyl and faste; And Lovers grieve to leave their pleasant dreams. Drak. sen. Be careful not to let The Camps Revelie beat To make our Warriours rise and move: But as Heav'ns Traveller above Unheard begins, and silently his way Does still continue till he perfects day, So all this progress must be calmly made. The winds, which still unseen Have in their motion been, Oft pass without a whisper through the shade. Drak. jun. Each, dutious as your slave, Does to your Orders grow; And all, as in the Grave, are husht and private now. Drak. sen. E're we begin to march, send out The Symerons again to scout: Let not our Wings be loosely spread: The Van I'll at some distance lead. Those who the Baggage bear Let Pedro still relieve, and closse Secure their haltings in our Gross. You shall command the Rear. Enter Rouse. Rouse. Arm, Arm! make haste, and bring me to my Chief! Drak. sen. What great distress does hasten for relief! Rouse. I come not now thy pardon to receive, Because my rasher love without thy leave Durst venture for a share Of thy mishaps in War. Drak. sen. What wildness more Than I have seen before In Deserts openly expos'd Or Woods with ancient growth of shades inclos'd, Or Seas, when nought but light'ning has appear'd, And only Thunder and the Winds were heard, Does now thy wond'ring looks possess? Drak. jun. What more than yet thou canst express? Rous. Drake, thy belov'd renown is lost, Of which thy Nation us'd to boast: Since now where thou a sword dost wear, And many marks of pow'r dost bear, The worst of license does best Laws invade: For Beauty is an abject captive made; Ev'n whilst those flowry Ornaments are worn Which should the Bridal dignity adorn. If thus the crowd be suffer'd to deride The sacred Rites and Honours of a Bride, Let savage War devour all civil Peace, Love fly from Courts to Camps, and Sexes cease. Drak. sen. Thy mystick meaning thou dost less By words than by thy looks express. Drak. jun. That we may better know Thy thoughts, make haste to show The object of our wonder, and thy fear. Rous. Turn your unhappy eyes, and see it there. The Scene is suddenly changed into the former prospect of the rising of the Morning, and Venta Cruz; but about the Middle, it is vary'd with the discov'ry of a Beautiful Lady ty'd to a Tree, adorn'd with the Ornaments of a Bride, with her hair dishevel'd, and complaining, with her hands towards Heaven: About her are likewise discern'd the Symerons who took her prisoner. Drak. sen. What dismal beauty does amaze my sight, Which from black sorrow breaks like Morn from Night? And though it sweetest beauty be Does seem more terrible to me Than all the sudden and the various forms Which Death does wear in Battels and in storms. Rous. A party of your Symerons (whose eyes Pierce through that darkness which does night disguise Whom weary toyls might sleepy make, But that revenge keeps them awake) Did e're the early dawning rise, And close by Venta-Cruz surprise A Bride and Bridegroom at their Nuptial Feast, To whom the Sym'rons now Much more than fury show; For they have all those cruelties exprest That Spanish pride could e're provoke from them Or Moorish Malice can revenge esteem. Drak. sen. Arm! Arm! the honour of my Nation turns To shame, when an afflicted Beauty mourns. Though here these cruel Symerons exceed Our number, yet they are too few to bleed When Honour must revengeful be For this affront to Love and me. Drak. jun. Our Forces of the Land, Brave Chief, let me command. Drak. sen. March on! whilst with my Seamen I advance, Let none, before the Dice are cast, despair; Nor after they are thrown, dislike the chance; For Honour throws at all, and still plays fair. Rous. In beauties noble cause no Seamen doubt, If Poets may authentick be. For Sea-born Venus sake let them march out: She leads them both at Land and Sea. Drak. sen. Long yet e're night I shall in fight Their stormy courage prove: Each Seaman hath his Mermaid too; And by instinct must love, Though he were never taught to woo. Enter Pedro. Pedro. Stay! stay! successful Chief! my heart as low As the foundation where thou tread'st does bow: But 'tis not for my own offence; For if I should offend My King, in thee his friend, I would not with my self dispence. Thy mercy shall our pattern be, Behold th'afflicted Bride is free. The Scene is suddenly chang'd again, where the Lady is vanisht, and nothing appears but that Prospect which was in the beginning of the Entry. She is as free and as unblemisht too As if she had a Pris'ner been to you. Drak. sen. What are they who disguis'd in nights dark shade, Unlicens'd, from our Camp this sally made? Strait to the stroke of Justice bring me those! Pedro. They thought their duties was to take their foes. Be merciful, and censure the offence To be but their mistaken diligence. Drak. jun. Suspect not Pedro in this crime, who still Has shewn exact obedience to thy will. Pedro. And noble Chief, the cruelties which they Have often felt beneath the Spaniards sway (Who midst the triumphs of our Nuptial feasts Have forc'd our Brides, and slaughter'd all our guests) May some excuse even from your reason draw: Revenge does all the fetters break of Law. Drak. sen. The future guidance and the care Of their demeanour in this war, Is strictly, Pedro, left to thee: The gentle Sex must still be free. No length of study'd torments shall suffice To punish all unmanly cruelties. March on! they may e're night redeem By vertuous Valour my esteem. [Exeunt Drake senior, Drake junior, Rouse, and Page. Pedro. Ho! ho! the Pris'ners straight unbind, And let the Bride all homage find; The Father and the Bridegroom hither bring. E're yet our Van shall far advance, Know Diegos you must dance. Strike up, strike up, in honour of my King. Enter the Father of the Bride, and her Bridegroom; the Bridegroom dancing with Castanietos, to express the joy he receives for his liberty, whilst the Father moves to his measures, denoting the fright he had receiv'd from the Symerons, when he was surpriz'd at his nuptial Entertainment. The Sixth ENTRY. This Entry is prepar'd with a Martial Ayr, and presently the Scene is chang'd; wherein is discover'd the Prospect of a hilly Country, with the Town Panamah at a distance, and Recoes of Mules, in a long train, loaden with Wedges of Silver and Ingots of Gold, and travelling in several Roads down a Mountain. There likewise may be discern'd their Drivers and Guards. Enter Drake Senior, Drake Junior, Page. Drak. jun. The Reco is not yet within our Ken. Drak. sen. It will be strait. Draw up our men, And in low whispers give our orders out. Drak. jun. Where's Pedro now? Drak. sen. Upon the brow Of that high Hill, I sent him there to scout. Enter Rouse. Rous. Chief, we are all into a Body drawn, And now an hour is wasted since the dawn. Drak. sen. The time will yet suffice. We halted here To stay for our tir'd Baggage in the Reer. Rous. If ought from new resolves thou wilt command, Speak, Chief, we now in expectation stand. Drak. sen. If English courage could at all be rais'd, By being well perswaded, or much prais'd, Speech were of use: but Valour born, not bred Cannot by art (since being so, It does as far as Nature go) Be higher lifted, or be farther led. All I would speak, should tell you, I despise That treasure which I now would make your Prize: Unworthy 'tis to be your chiefest aim. For this attempt is not for Gold, but Fame; Which is not got when we the Reco git, But by subduing those who rescue it. Enter a Souldier. Sol. Pedro descends the Hill, and does desire That from this open plain you would retire, And wheel behind that Wood a little space. Drak. sen. Divide our Forces to secure the pass. [Exeunt. Enter Drake Junior, a Souldier, Rouse, and a Mariner, the Souldier and Mariner being brought to be plac'd as Sentries. Drak. jun. This must your station be; Stand stedfast as that Tree! Rous. Bravely alive upon this ground, Or greater else in death be found. [Exeunt Drak. jun. and Rouse. The Bells of the Mules are heard from within. Mar. Mules! Mules! I hear their walking chime, Ting, Ting!— They love sad Tunes, how dolefully they ring? Sol. This sound seems single, and from far does come. Would I were leading one rich Mule at home. Mar. Still one and all I cry. Sol. The rest are passing by. Hark! hark! this mournful toling does foretel Some Diegos death, it is his passing-Bell. Enter Pedro, leading a Symeron to be plac'd as a Sentry. Pedro. Here Sym'ron, you must bold and watchful be. Two Foes resist, but if opprest by three, Then strait fall back to that next Sentry there: Or if in Gross th'Enemy does appear, Both to the third retirement make, Till we th'Alarm, advancing, take. Mar. Friend Pedro, friend! Is't one and all? Pedro. Speak softly, Sentry, dost thou call? Mar. How many golden Recoes didst thou spy? Pedro. But two: in which I guess By distant view no less Than ninety loaden Mules are passing by. Sol. What number is their Guard who march before? Pedro. Five hundred Foot, their Horse may seem threescore. [Exit. Sol. Friend of the Sea, their number is not small. Mar. 'Twill serve our turn, they crying one and all! But brother of the Land, We now must understand That Basta is the Word. Sol. Would thou wer't safe aboard. Mar. Asleep under Deck, and danc'd on a Billow, With two silver Wedges, each for my Pillow. Enter Drake Senior, with his sword drawn. Drak. sen. That Volly was well fir'd, Our out-Guards are retir'd. Draw all our Sentries in! The Skirmish does begin. [Exit. Clashing of Arms is heard afar off. Enter Drake Junior. Drak. jun. More Pikes! more Pikes! to reinforce That Squadron, and repulse the Horse. Enter Rouse. Rous. The Foe does make his first bold count'nance good. Our charge was bravely made, and well withstood. Enter Pedro. Rous. Your Sym'rons, valiant Pedro, seem to reel. Pedro. Suspect your Rocks at Sea. They do but wheel. Haste! haste! brave Sym'rons, haste to gain that bank, And with your Arrows gall them in the flank. [Clashing of Arms within again. Exeunt. Enter Drake Senior, Page. Drak. sen. How warmly was this strife Maintain'd 'twixt Death and Life, Till Blood had quench'd the flame of Valours fire? Death seeming to advance in haste, Whilst Life, though weary, yet stood fast; For Life is still unwilling to retire. My Land-men bravely fought, And high renown have got, For twice my Sea-men they from death reliev'd. As oft my Sea-men have Preserv'd them from the grave, And did requite the rescue they receiv'd. Enter Drake Junior. Drak. jun. They fly! they fly! yet now they seem to face All those who them pursue, And would the Fight renew. [Enter Rouse &amp; Ped. Rous. They fly, they fly! Drak. sen. Away, make good the Chase. [Exeunt omnes. Chorus of all within. Follow, follow, follow! Enter Drake Senior, Drake Junior, Rouse, Pedro, Page. Pedro. The Mules are seis'd, and in our pow'r remain. Drak. sen. Draw out new Guards, and range them in the Plain. Those who hereafter on our Legend look, And value us by that which we have took, May over-reckon it, and us misprize. Our dang'rous course through storms and raging floods, And painful march through unfrequented Woods, Will make those wings by which our fame shall rise. Your glory, valiant English must be known, When men shall read how you did dare To sail so long, and march so far, To tempt a strength much greater than your own. Drak. jun. And now by making our Retreat, We shall new Wreaths and Statues get. The Grand Chorus, first sung by Drake sen. Chorus of all. Our Course let's to victorious England steer! Where, when our Sails shall on the Coast appear, Those who from Rocks and Steeples spy Our Streamers out, and Colours fly, Will cause the Bells to ring, Whilst chearfully they sing Our story, which shall their Example be, And make Succession cry, To Sea, to Sea. Exeunt omnes. The Grand Dance begins, consisting of two Land-souldiers, two Seamen, two Symerons, and a Peruvian; intimating by their several interchange of salutations, their mutual desires of amity.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Fourt ACT. Enter House-Keeper, Player. Play. Now, Friend, we must still suppose Our selves at Peru. Hous. K. What's he? a humane Bird. Play. A feather'd Preist, who must speak in the Dumb show, and describe the condition of America, Before the Spaniard surpriz'd it. The Cruelty of the SPANIARDS in PERU. The Argument of the whole design, consisting of six ENTRIES. The Design is first to represent the happy condition of the People of Peru anciently, when their inclinations were govern'd by Nature; and then it makes some discov'ry of their establishment under the Twelve Incas, and of the dissentions of the two Sons of the last Inca. Then proceeds to the discov'ry of that new Western World by the Spaniard, which happen'd to be during the dissention of the two Royal Brethren. It likewise proceeds to the Spaniards Conquest of that Incan Empire, and then discovers the cruelty of the Spaniards over the Indians, and over all Christians (excepting those of their own Nation) who landing in those parts, came unhappily into their power. And towards the conclusion, it infers the Voyages of the English thither, and the amity of the Natives towards them, under whose Ensigns (encourag'd by a Prophecy of their chief Priest) they hope to be made Victorious, and to be freed from the Yoke of the Spaniard. The First ENTRY. The Audience are entertain'd by Instrumental Musick and a Symphony (being a wild Ayr sutable to the Region) which having prepar'd the Scene, a Lantdchap of the West-Indies is discern'd; distinguisht from other Regions by the parcht and bare tops of distant Hills, by Sands shining on the shores of Rivers, and the Natives, in feather'd Habits and Bonnets, carrying in Indian Baskets, Ingots of Gold, and Wedges of Silver. Some of the Natives being likewise discern'd in their natural sports of Hunting and Fishing. This Prospect is made through a Wood, differing from those of European Climats, by representing of Coco-Trees, Pines, and Palmitos; and on the boughs of other Trees are seen Munkies, Apes, and Parrots; and at farther distance, Vallies of Sugar-Canes. The Symphony being ended: The chief Priest of Peru enters with his Attendant after him. The Priest is cloth'd in a garment of Feathers, longer than any of those that are worn by other Natives, with a Bonnet whose ornament of Plumes does likewise give him a distinction from the rest, and carries in his hand a guilded Verge. He likewise, because the Peruvians were worshippers of the Sun, carries the Figure of the Sun on his Bonnet and Breast. The First Speech, Spoken by the Priest of the Sun: Taking a short view of their condition, before the Royal Family of the Incas taught them to live together in multitudes, under Laws, and made them by Arms reduce many other Nations. Thus fresh did Nature in our world appear, When first her Roses did their leaves unfold: E're she did use Art's Colours, and e're fear Had made her pale, or she with cares lookt old. When various sports did Man's lov'd freedom show, And still the free were willing to obey; Youth did to Age, and Sons to Parents bow. Parents and Age first taught the Laws of sway. When yet we no just motive had to fear Our bolder Incas would by Arms be rais'd; When, temp'rately, they still contented were, As great examples, to be only prais'd. When none for being strong did seek reward, Nor any for the space of Empire strove: When Valour courted Peace and never car'd For any recompence, but publique love. We fetter'd none, nor were by any bound; None follow'd Gold through Lab'rinths of the Mine: And that which we on strands of Rivers found, Did only on our Priests in Temple shine. Then with his Verge, each Priest Could, like an Exorcist, The coldest of his students warm, And thus provoke them with a Charm. The First Song. In pursuance of the manner of their Life, before their Incas brought them to live in Cities, and to build Forts. 1. Whilst yet our world was new, When not discover'd by the old; E're begger'd slaves we grew, For having silver Hills, and strands of Gold. Chorus. We danc'd and we sung, And lookt ever young, And from restraints were free, As waves and winds at Sea. 2. When wildly we did live, E're crafty Cities made us tame: When each his whole would give To all, and none peculiar right did claim. Chorus. We danc'd and we sung, &amp;c. 3. When none did riches wish, And none were rich by bus'ness made; When all did Hunt or Fish, And sport was all our labour and our trade. Chorus. We danc'd and we sung, &amp;c. 4. When Forts were not devis'd, Nor Cittadels did Towns devour: When lowly sheds suffic'd, Because we fear'd the weather more than pow'r. Chorus. We danc'd and we sung, &amp;c. 5. When Garments were not worn, Nor shame did nakedness resent: Nor Poverty bred scorn: When none could want, and all were innocent. Chorus. We danc'd and we sung, &amp;c. The Second ENTRY. An Alman and Corante are play'd: after which a Trumpet-Ayr changes the Scene; where a Fleet is discern'd at distance, with a prospect of the Sea and Indian Coast; the Ships bearing in their Flags the Spread-Eagle, to denote the Austrian Family; and on the right side are seen some Natives of Peru, pointing with amazement to the Fleet, (as never having had the view of Ships before) and in a mourning condition take their leaves of their Wives and Children; because of an ancient prophecy amongst them, which did signifie, That a Bearded People (those of Peru having ever held it uncomely to wear Beards) should spring out of the Sea, and conquer them. The object having remained a while, the Priest of the Sun enters. The Second Speech, Describing briefly the pleasant lives of the Incas till this season of fulfilling that prophecy, when a Bearded People should come from the sea to destroy them; and two of the Incan Family ruine that Empire, which twelve of the Emperours had erected. In all the soft delights of sleep and ease, Secure from War, in peaceful Palaces, Our Incas liv'd: but now I see their doom: Guided by winds, the Bearded People come! And that dire Prophecy must be fulfill'd, When two shall ruine what our twelve did build. 'Tis long since first the Sun's chief Priest foretold, That cruel men, Idolaters of Gold, Should pass vast Seas to seek their Harbour here. Behold, in floating Castles they appear! Mine eyes are struck! Away, away With gentle Love's delicious sway! The Incas from their wives must fly! And ours may soon believe We mourn to see them grieve, But shall rejoyce to see them dy. For they by dying safety gain: And when they quit, In Death's cold fit, Love's pleasure they shall lose Life's pain. The Second Song, Intimating their sorrow for their future condition, (according to the Prophecy) under their new Masters the Spaniards. 1. No more, no more, Shall we drag to the shore Our Nets at the ebb of the Flood; Nor after we lay The toyls for our Prey, Shall we meet to compass the Wood. Nor with our Arrows e're delight, To get renown By taking down The soaring Eagle in his flight. 2. Make haste! make haste! You delights that are past! And do not to our thoughts appear: Lest vainly we boast Of joys we have lost, And grieve to reckon what we were. The Incas glory now is gone! Dark grows that light, Which chear'd our sight, Set is their deity, the Sun. Chorus. All creatures when they breed, May then with safety feed: All shall have times for liberty but we. We, who their Masters were, Must now such Masters fear, As will no season give us to be free. This Song being ended, a doleful Ayr is heard, which prepares the entrance of two Indians, in their feather'd habits of Peru! they enter severally from the opposite sides of the Wood, and gazing on the face of the Scene, fall into a Mimick Dance, in which they express the Argument of the Prospect, by their admiration at the sight of the Ships, (which was to those of Peru a new and wonderfull object) and their lamentation, at beholding their Countrymen in deep affliction, and taking their leaves of their Wives and Children. The Third ENTRY. A symphony, consisting of four tunes, prepares the change of the Scene; the prospect consisting of a plain Indian Country, by which are discern'd at distance two Peruvian Armies marching, and ready to give Battel, being led by the two Royal Brethren, Sons of the last Inca, Arm'd with Bows, Glaves, and Spears, and wearing Quivers on their backs. The object having continu'd a while, the Priest of the Sun enters. The Third Speech, Intimating the unhappy event of the love of the last Inca; for he (contrary to the custom of all his Royal Ancestors, who always marry'd their own Sisters) had chosen to his second Wife the beautiful Daughter of an inferiour Prince: his Priests and People having always believ'd no blood less distant than that of his Sisters, worthy to mingle with his own for propagation of the Emperial Race. This foreign Beauty so far prevail'd on his passion, that she made him in his age assign a a considerable part of his Dominion to a younger Son, his Ancestors never having, during eleven Generations, divided their Empire. This Youth, growing ambitious after his Fathers death, invaded his elder Brother at that unfortunate time when the Spaniards, pursuing their second discovery of the Peruvian Coast, landed, and made a prodigious use of the division of the two Brethren, by proving successful in giving their assistance to the unjust cause of the Younger. How fatal did our Inca's passion prove, Whilst long made subject to a foreign love? Poor Lovers, who from Empire's arts are free, By Nature may entirely guided be, They may retire to shady Cottages, And study there only themselves to please: For few consider what they mean or do; But Nations are concern'd when Monarchs woo. And though our Inca by no Law was ty'd To love but one, yet could he not divide His publick Empire as his private bed. In Thrones each is to whole Dominion bred. He blindly pris'd his younger son's desert, Dividing Empire as he did his heart. And since his death, this made the younger dare T'affront the elder's sov'rainty with war. Ambition's monstrous stomach does encrease By eating, and it fears to starve, unless It still may feed, and all it sees devour. Ambition is not tir'd with toyl, nor cloy'd with pow'r. The Third Song, Which pursues the Argument of the Speech, and farther illustrates the many miseries, which the Civil War between the two Royal Brethren produc'd. 1. Twelve Incas have successively Our spacious Empire sway'd; Whose power whilst we obey'd, We liv'd so happy and so free, As if we were not kept in aw By any Law, Which Martial Kings aloud proclaim. Soft conscience, Nature's whisp'ring Orator, Did teach us what to love or to abhor; And all our punishment was shame. 2. Our late great Inca fatally, Did by a second Wife Eclipse his shining life, Whilst reason did on love rely. Those Rays she often turn'd and check't, Which with direct Full beams should have adorn'd his known And first authoris'd Race: But Kings who move Within a lowly sphear of private love, Are too domestick for a Throne. Chorus. Now rigid War is come, and Peace is gone, Fear governs us, and jealousie the Throne. Ambition hath our Chiefs possest: All now are wak't, all are alarm'd: The weary know not where to rest, Nor dare the harmless be unarm'd. After this Song a Warlike Ayr is play'd, to which succeeds a Martial Dance, perform'd by four Peruvians, arm'd with Glaves, who enter severally from opposite sides of the Wood, and express by their motions and gestures the fury of that Civil War, which, by the ambition of the younger Brother, has engag'd their Country; and then depart in pursuit of each other. The Fourth ENTRY. A symphony, consisting of four tunes, prepares the change of the Scene; which represents a great Peruvian Army, put to flight by a small Body of Spaniards. This object is produc'd in pursuance of the main Argument; for the Spaniards having first bred an amazement in the Natives, by the noise and fire of their Guns, and having afterwards subverted the elder Inca by assisting the younger, did in a short time attain the Dominion over both by Conquest. The object of this Scene having remain'd a while, the Priest of the Sun enters. The Fourth Speech, Intimating the amazement of the Peruvians at the sight of the Spaniards in Arms; the consideration of the great distance of the Region from whence they came; of the ill effects of Armour worn by a People whom they never had offended, and of the security of innocence. What dark and distant Region bred For War that bearded Race, Whose ev'ry uncouth face We more than Death's cold vissage dread? They could not still be guided by the Sun. Nor had they ev'ry night The Moon t'inform their sight; How durst they seek those dangers which we shun? Sure they must more than mortal be, That did so little care For life, or else they are Surer of future life than we. But how they reasons laws in life fulfill We know not; yet we know, That scorn of life is low, Compar'd to the disdain of living ill. And we may judge that all they do In life's whole scene is bad, Since they with Arms are clad Defensive and Offensive too. In Nature it is fear that makes us arm; And fear by guilt is bred: The guiltless nothing dread, Defence not seeking, nor designing harm. [Exit. The Fourth Song, Pursuing the Argument of the amazement and fear of the Natives, occasion'd by the consideration of the long Voyage of the Spaniards to invade them. 1. Those foreign shapes so strange appear, That wonderful they seem; And strangeness breeds esteem; And wonder doth engender fear: And from our fear does adoration rise: Else why do we encline To think them Pow'rs divine, And that we are ordain'd their sacrifice? Chorus 1. When we our Arrows draw, It is with dreadful awe: 2. Moving towards them whom we are loth to meet, 3. As if we marcht to face our destiny: 4. Not trusting to our Arrows but our feet, As if our bus'ness were to fly, to fly! All in Chorus. 2. We thought them more than human kind. That durst adventure life Through the tempestuous strife Of Seas and ev'ry raging wind. Through Seas so wide, and for their depth so fear'd, That we by leaps as soon May reach th'ascended Moon, As guess through what vast dangers they have steer'd. Chorus. When we our Arrows draw, &amp;c. This Song being ended, a Saraband is play'd, whilst two Spaniards enter from the opposite sides of the Scene, exactly cloth'd and arm'd according to the custom of their Nation: and to express their triumph after the victory over the Natives, they solemnly uncloak and unarm themselves to the Tune, and afterwards dance with Castanietos. The Fifth ENTRY. A doleful Pavin is play'd to prepare the change of the Scene, which represents a dark Prison at great distance; and farther to the view are discern'd Racks, and other Engines of torment, with which the Spaniards are tormenting the Natives and English Mariners, which may be suppos'd to be lately landed there to discover the Coast. Two Spaniards are likewise discover'd, sitting in their Cloaks, and appearing more solemn in Ruffs, with Rapiers and Daggers by their sides; the one turning a Spit, whilst the other is basting an Indian Prince, which is rosted at an artificial fire. This object having remain'd a while, the Priest of the Sun enters. The Fifth Speech. The horrour of the Natives, bred by the object of the diversity of new torments devis'd by the Spaniards. These study arts of length'ning languishment, And strength'ning those for pains whom pain hath spent. They make the Cramp, by waters drill'd, to cease Men ready to expire, Baste them with drops of fire, And then, they lay them on the Rack for ease. What Race is this, who for our punishment Pretend that they in haste from Heav'n were sent, As just destroyers of Idolatry? Yet will they not permit We should our Idolls quit, Because the Christian Law makes Converts free. Or if, to please their Priests, some Chief permits A few of us to be their Proselytes; Yet all our freedom then is but deceit. They ease us from our Chains To makes us take more pains, Light'ning our legs to give our shoulders weight. And other Christian strangers landing here, Strait, to their jealous sight, as spies appear: And those, they so much worse than Heathens deem, That they must tortur'd dye. The world still waste must lye, Or else a Prison be to all but them. The Fifth Song. Pursuing the Argument of the Speech, by a farther detestation of that cruelty, which the ambition of the Spaniards made them exercise in Peru. 1. If Man from sov'reign reason does derive Or'e Beasts a high prerogative, Why does he so himself behave, That Beasts appear to be More rational than he! Who has deserv'd to be their slave. 2. How comes wild cruelty in humane breasts? Proud Man more cruel is than Beasts; When Beasts by hunger are enrag'd, They no long pains devise For dying enemies, But kill, and eat, and are asswag'd. 3. So much is Man refin'd in cruelty As not to make men quickly dye. He knows by death all pains are past. But as he hath the skill A thousand ways to kill, So hath he more to make pains last. Chorus. When Beasts each other chase and then devour, 'Tis Natures Law, necessity, Which makes them hunt for food, and not for pow'r: Men for Dominion, Art's chief vanity, Contrive to make men dy; Whose blood through wantonness they spill, Not having use of what they kill. This Song being ended, a mournful Ayr is play'd, preparing the entrance of three Peruvians, limping in silver fetters. They are driven into the Wood by an insulting Spaniards; with a Truncheon; then enter again loaden with Indian baskets full of golden Ingots, and silver Wedges, and lying down with the weight of their burthens, are raised by the blows of the Spaniard, and fall into a halting dance, till the Spaniard reviving their weariness with his Truncheon, drives them again into the Wood. The Sixth ENTRY. A symphony prepares the last change of the Scene, and an Army is discern'd at distance, consisting of English and Peruvians; the Van is led by the English, who are distinguisht by the Ensignes of England, and their Red-Coats. The Reer is brought up by the Peruvians, who are known by their feather'd Habits, Glaves, and Spears. There is likewise discern'd a Body of armed Spaniards, their backs turn'd, and their Reer scatter'd as if put to flight. These imaginary English Forces may seem improper, because the English had made no discovery of Peru, in the time of the Spaniards first invasion there; but yet in Poetical representations of this nature, it may pass as a Vision discern'd by the Priest of the Sun, before the matter was extant, in order to his Prophecy. This object having remain'd a while the Priest of the Sun enters. The Sixth Speech, Intimating their first adoration of the Spaniards when they landed, the behaviour of the Spaniards towards them, and a Prophecy that they shall be reliev'd by the English. We on our knees these Spaniards did receive As Gods, when first they taught us to believe. They came from Heaven, and us o're heights would lead, Higher than e're our sinful fathers fled. Experience now (by whose true eyes, though slow, We find at last, what oft too late we know) Has all their cous'ning miracles discern'd: 'Tis she that makes unletter'd mankind learn'd, She has unmask't these Spanish dark Divines: Perhaps they upward go, But hasten us below, Where we, through dismal depths, must dig in Mines. When first the valiant English landed here, Our reason then no more was rul'd by fear: They streight the Spaniards Riddle did unfold, Whose Heav'n in caverns lies of others Gold. Our griefs are past, and we shall cease to mourn, For those whom the insulting Spaniards scorn, And slaves esteem The English soon shall free; Whilst we the Spaniards see Digging for them. The Priest being gone, a wild Ayr is play'd, (differing from that in the First Entry) which prepares the comming in of a Spaniard out of the Wood, loaden with Ingots of Gold, and Wedges of Silver. He makes his footing to the tune of the Instruments; and after a while he discovers a weariness and inclination to sleep, to which purpose he lies down, with his basket for his pillow. Two Apes come in from opposite sides of the Wood, and dance to the Ayr. After a while, a great Baboon enters, and joyns with them in the dance. They wake the Spaniard, and end the Antique Measures with driving him into the Wood. The Sixth Song, Pursuing the Argument of that Prophecy, which foretells the subversion of the Spaniards by the English. We shall no longer fear The Spanish Eagle darkly hov'ring here; For though from farthest Climes he hither fled, And spatiously his wings has spread: Yet th'English Lyon now Does still victorious grow, And does delight To make his walks as far As th'other e're did dare To make his flight. Chorus. 1 High, 2 high, 3 and high 4 Our Arrows shall flie, And reach the winged for our prey. Our Nets we'll cast, and Sprindges lay: The Ayr, the River, and the Wood, Shall yield us sport and change of food. All in Chorus. After all our disasters The proud Spaniards our Masters, When we extoll our liberty by feasts, At Table shall serve, Or else they shall starve; Whilst th'English shall sit and rule as our guests. This Song being ended, an Ayr consisting of three Tunes, prepares the grand Dance, three Indians entring first, afterwards to them three English Souldiers, distinguisht by their Red-Coats, and to them a Spaniard, who mingling in the measures with the rest, does in his gestures express pride and sullenness towards the Indians, and pays a lowly homage to the English, who often salute him with their feet, which salutation he returns with a more lowly gravity; whilst the English and the Indians, as they encounter, salute and shake hands, in sign of their future amity.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Fifth ACT. Enter House-Keeper, and Player. Play. Now we must have one voyage more from Peru to Alexandria (which in good troth, Is but a step to swift imagination) And then we may sleep in our empty Inn Until next Term. Hous. K. We have no Scene of Alexandria. Play. A Canopy of State to shew the Majesty Of those who are presented will serve turn. Hous. K. Have w'ee quoth the blind Harper, When he wisht to be as little seen as he saw others. Draw ho! The Scene of the Canopy where Cæsar, Anthonius, Lepidus, Ptolomy, and Cleopatra appear, and their several trains on each side of them. Play. This Vision should have been enabled too By a short speech t'acquaint the doubtful Spectators With Cæsar, Antonius, and Lepidus, Ptolomy, Cleopatra, and their train. Hous. K. That w'are to make this a kin to the dumb show.— Enter the Gypsies, Men and Women. These are the Gypsies with which Cleopatra Entertain'd Cæsar, as blind Authors say. The Gypsies dance. The Dance being ended, the Gypsies depart, and the Scene changes into a Parrad or Court du Guard. Play. But where are now our Bullies the Burlesquers, That show the wrong side of the Hero's outward? Enter two Ev'nuchs. Oh, here comes two of Ptolemies Ev'nuchs. Enter Nimphidius, and another Ev'nuch. Ev'n. You of your news Nimphidius are so dainty! Nimp. If I had news, in troth I would acquaint ye. Ev'n. Then I have some, but oh, 'tis doleful matter! Nimp. Hab nab's the word! All castes are not Cinque quater. Ev'n. Rome now of Egypt quickly will beguil us, Tyber is come to play her pranks in Nilus. Nimp. If Tyber brings her plund'ring base Burgonions, Farewell on Nilus Banks our Leeks and Onions. Ev'n. A cruel wight; whose name is Mark Anthony, (So hard of heart that it is held all bony) Is here arriv'd for love of our black Gypsy, On Cleopatra he has cast a Sheeps-eye. And Cæsar too with many a stout Terpawling Landed with him and comes a Catterwawling. Nimp. How she will simper, at the sight of Cæsar? And oh, how trusty Tony means to tease her? Ev'n. Ah fickle fortune! who would e're have dreamt this, Rome's roaring Boys will swagger now at Memphis. Nimp. Behold they come who quickly can inform us. Ev'n. Nimphidius, mum, be silent as a Dormouse. Enter Cæsar, Mark-Anthony, Cleopatra, Ptolomy, Anthonio leading Cleopatra. Nimp. There Tony is, our Cleopatra leading; Her eyes look blew; pray Heav'n she be not breeding? Ev'n. There's Cæsar too, and Ptolomy behind him, Proud Princock-Cæsar hardly seems to mind him. [Exeunt Nimph, Ev'nuch. Anth. Which is your Brother dear? I prethee shew me? Cry mercy, Sir, are you the King Ptolomy? Ptol. I am as surely he (most mighty Tony) As she is my sweet Sister, and your hony. Anth. Great Cæsar come, shake fists with stripling Royal, Though Pompey was betray'd, this Imp was loyal. Cæsar. Know tender Springal (I'll not chide but frump ye) You play'd at Trap, when Traps were lay'd for Pompey. With finger in eye his Wife had not wept here If stead of Trapstick you then had us'd Scepter. Ptol. When Fortune frumpish is, who e're withstood her? Cæsar, this bus'ness makes too great a pudder: I would not slander Pompey now he dead is; Yet let me tell, what by my people said is, You'll say the pratling people falsly charge men; But all report that Pompey's Barge and Bargemen Had plunder'd Nilus banks till there was scarce one Turky or Pigg left for the tyth of Parson; Of which even Pompey muncht his share in Cabin, Where, from the shore, he becken'd many a drab in: Under the Rose I speak't, he was Dragon, When he brown Damsel got, with scarce a rag on; And came not here for rescue, but to rob us; Yet we at last bob'd him who meant to bob us. Cæsar. Youth, you are to young to sit in the Sadle, And crow in a Throne, go cry in a Cradle. Tutor should teach you to speak well of dead men, Go learn to rob Orchard, not to behead men. With blood of Roman, your Ev'nuch does grow fat; Such knaves wax cruel, having lost—you know what. He rules the roste, but some body go call him! I swear by Hector Haunch, I mean to mall him! Cleo. Is this your Cæsar? tell me dearest Bunting? I faiks I must have leave to speak of one thing. Can he that's Cock of Rome be so mistaken As thus to threaten poor Egyptian Capon? I scorn, though but a Female and no Roman, To meddle with an Ev'nuch who is no man. When first we saw you sailing to our Haven, We little thought to find your cock a Craven. Anth. Peace Lamb, and be like Lamb-kine meek, and humble, Cæsar like Wolf, will bite when he does grumble. Where place does not itch, I seldom do rub ye, Nay, you are strait blub'ring if I but snub ye. If Cæsar's blood be up, Blade will not spare ye, Egypt will then be in a fine quandarie. Cleo. I'll not be scar'd, though he look ne'r so hideous, He may go snick-up if he hates Nymphidious. Anth. His stomach bears not long the wrongs he swallows, But, if you'll not be counsell'd, take what follows. He'll strait be all for plunder and for forage. Cleo. Cæsar may spare his breath to cool his porridge; He'll be the worse, the more one him beseeches. Anth. Chuck, I have done, I see you'll wear the Breeches. Cæsar. What have I heard? shall it be said in Hist'ries, That Marcus Tony squabl'd with his Mistress. If Love be out of joynt, I'll be the Joyner, Say son of Scepter, speak thou Monarch-Minor! Shall Lovers fall to scratch like midnight Pusses. Let's turn their frowns and wrath to leers and busses. Ptol. Most puissant Plund'rer! know the short and long is, That all who know thee, find thy breath so strong is, As meerly with a word it quells the mighty, And stuns them past the cure of Aqua-vitæ. Cleo. Egypt's no fool for Rome to put her tricks on, And you shall find that I can be a Vixon. Must warbling Ev'nuch dye, who ne'r was sick long; And sing short Psalm in Rope, who taught me prick-song? Ptol. Shall he who can read, and love lessons taught her, Be now deny'd Book, and dye for Man-slaughter? Anth. Cæsar, things are not as th'World now supposes; The case seems plain as on your Face your Nose is. Great Pompey near shore, for Poultry was gaping, Did count without Host, and so was tane napping. Cleo. What Ev'nuch has done, he did for your sake then: As Pompey did brew, he made him to bake then. Cæsar. Let Memphion Mistress look but blithe and bonny, On Cæsar smile, as she does smerk on Tony Then Ev'nuch plump shall live, and grow still thicker, Like Hostess fat, who sits in chair of Wicker. Cleo. Cæsar, Gramercy, you now shew your breeding, Invite him sweet heart, I pray to our Wedding. I thought my self truly quite under hatches. But now call Maid to bring her Queen new patches. Bring Kirchief lac'd? I'll no more be a Mourner! And Cæsar, you shall find—a friend in corner. Anth. Great son of slaughter leers? he'd fain be at her, I'll dash his chops, if mouth begin to water. [Enter Cornelie. Cæsar. Sly scowling look (though men of Mars ne'r mind it) Hat black and broad, long Cypress down behind it, Gown short and loose, and her hair under Pinner, (As if locks on Cheek, were token of Sinner) Where Bodkin is stuck in fashion so odly As though out of zeal, Dame layd the French mode by. 'Mass now I think on't, 'tis Pompey's rich widow. Anth. Of mumping Minx, would we were fairly rid hoe! Cleo. Lord, how she looks? she could out us in Collops: Shall Tony, and I, fear ev'ry fat Trollops? Like hard hearted heart she over us hovers, As Kite watches Chickens, she watches Lovers. Corn. What have I caught ye! how all of ye stare on't, I'faith I'll to Rome, and their do your errant: By Senate y'are sent to follow your calling, They think you are now their Enemies mauling: Man, Woman, and Child, you chief should be killing, But 'stead of bombasting you are a billing With Queen who should be her Parishes pattern, Good Housewife in House not sauntring young slatern. Cleo. Bodikins! pray why a gog Mistress Pompey? As high as you are; a Joan may out-jump ye, Be an example before y'are a Tutress! You want a Tarquin to make you a Lucress. Corn. Marry come up, Goodman Ptolomey's daughter, Faith in your Wine, I perhaps, may put Water; For all your new Gown, y'are but a black Gypsey, Sure Tony and you have drunk till y'are tipsey. Nay take the whole Mess, y'have yet but a spoonful, I'll bate not an Ace, as Widow of Consul. For though you now perk it, as daughter of King, Birlady, I'll give you as good as you bring: I know your back's broad enough, I'll put you to't. Cleo. Well, Gossip, I know too the length of your foot. Cæsar. Hey for Cornelia! she's still for old Rome. Corn. Cæsar, yo'd cog now, but some wiser than some, Your crony and you in Egypt now flant it, Spending like Roysters, whilst honest ment want it. Leave off your hectring with Heirs whilst you fool 'um, And drinking Beer-glasses super naculum: Drowning of sorrow like negligent Debters, Sending to Provinces short begging Letters, Which being deny'd, then with Armies you goe And take what you'll pay back to morrow to mow. Cæsar. Your Tippet's up, but Bilbo Wights ne'r mind ye, Turn Buckle of Girdle, wear it behind ye. Anth. Let Gossips shake hands, and Cæsar appoint her Some Blade that has house to make her a Joynture. Widow, be friends, make no more such a hot coyl; We'll find out rich Husband to make the Pot boyl. Cleo. If the wound be sew'd up, I'll not unrip it, I'll keep my tongue in, if she'll pin down Typpet. Cæsar. Proud Pompey (whom now we never shall lack more) Came in at a Gate, sneakt out at a Back-dore. Great was the mortal, and long cock-a-hoop too, But down he did fall, whom all men did stoop too. Yet Fortune has done, but what does become her; In Winter w'are Hay, and Grass in the Summer. Corn. In troth it is true! we are of that sort all! Then farewell sweet Pompey since thou wert mortal. Cleo. Well said, Cornelia, I see you are heart whole, Hang up all care, which from Body would part Soul! Where are the Fidlers? what Tune shall we fix on? Faith, let's have the round of merry Mall Dixon. Cæsar. Call in the Fidlers but heark ye friend Tony, Whilst now I think on't, have you any money? For though in War I did bear all before me, Cash stays behind, and I'm fain to cry score me! Anth. Cæsar, my plunder (I speak it with sorrow) Is squander'd with Girles, and I'm forc't to borrow, Yet let 'em play us but princum and prancum, And we'll pay at last, or els we'll thank 'um. The Dance. Cæsar. Let's to the Ale-house go, where Tapsters know me, Fat Hostess there wil trust; lead King Ptolomey. Fidlers will thither come, and never grumble; In Play-house they are proud, in Ale-house humble. Gossips shall tatle there, while tongues will wag on, And to my Gypsies health I'll drink a Flaggon. [Exeunt. Hous. K. What is all done? Play. I, and we are undone, some body has let Our neighbours in—'slight the House is e'en full, Stop 'em! they're like to hear, if they will stay An Epilogue, since they have seen a Play. [Exeunt omnes.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">EPILOGUE. Since you at Land no more can hurry'd be, The shifted Scene should turn us now to Sea? Where our small Bark does strike, where we d'spy You're the Admiral, with your Main-Top high. Our Pilot-Poet should his Laurel vayl, (Which is his Flag) as low as we our Sayl. To shew you things yet newer, we did mean To represent a Mermaid in that Scene; Not proudly combing, with a Comb of Goul, Her long wet hair, till the vain wretch takes cold, (For so she's painted by each bungling Rogue) But in her hand an humble Epilogue; Which thee by signs (for Mermayds seldom speak) Should recommend to Criticks on the Deck: And by a court'sie, should a Plaudit beg;— Note, female fishes, never make a leg. But that's an observation by the by. And now, methinks, I hear some ask me why That observation's made? Our Author says 'Tis just like those which Criticks make at Plays. He said he wisht for our sakes, not his own, (Yet that's a charity but rarely known) Such Audiences as learning doe forbear; I mean, who never strive to shew it here. This Landtschap of the Sea (but by the way) That's an expression which might hurt our Play, If the severer Criticks were in Town; This Prospect of the Sea, cannot be shown: Therefore be pleas'd to think, that you are all Behind the Row, which men stile Portugal. The title at our dores was that which drew You hither by the charm of being new. You'l spoil the jest, unless the Play succeed; For then we may, e'en let our House indeed. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>