<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Sheil, Richard Lalor, 1791-1851</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Sheil, Richard Lalor, 1791-1851</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">sheil richard lalor 1791 1851</field>
      <field name="author_text">Sheil, Richard Lalor, 1791-1851</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1810's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V3.0015.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1814</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460475</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Adelaide : or The Emigrants ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Adelaide : or The Emigrants ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="title_facet">adelaide or the emigrants</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">adelaide or the emigrants</field>
      <field name="title_text">Adelaide : or The Emigrants ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="year_display">1814</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1814</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1814</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460475&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460475&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Sheil, Richard Lalor, 1791-1851&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;sheil richard lalor 1791 1851&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Adelaide : or The Emigrants ; A Tragedy&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;adelaide or the emigrants&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1814&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1814&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Sheil, Richard Lalor&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1791&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1851&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Adelaide : or The Emigrants&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Dublin&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for R. Coyne [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1814&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872818-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv30015&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Adelaide : or The Emigrants&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 149 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Adelaide.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1814.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 19 Feb 1814.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ADELAIDE; OR THE EMIGRANTS: A TRAGEDY, AS PERFORMED AT THE THEATRE-ROYAL, DUBLIN.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">TO MISS O'NEILL. Madam, I am indebted to your great talents for the success of this tragedy, and dedicate it to you as a feeble testimony of my gratitude. The part of Adelaide was written for you. In adapting it, I endeavoured to combine beauty, innocence, and feeling. I knew that your representation of such a character would not be the effort of art, but the spontaneous effusion of nature. The lines which the author of Zaire has addressed to Mademoiselle Gaussin, are applicable to yourself: Ce sont tes yeux, ces yeux si pleins de charmes, Ta voix touchante, et tes sons enchanteurs, Qui du critique ont fait tomber les armes. Ta seule vue adoucit les censeurs: L'illusion, cette reine des cœurs, Marche à ta suite, inspire les alarmes, Le sentiment, les regrets, les douleurs, Et le plaisir de repandre des larmes. I have the honor to be, Madam, Your most obedient and very Humble Servant, RICHARD SHEIL.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Many blemishes will be found in this tragedy. The author would have endeavoured to render it more deserving of publication, if the laborious studies of his profession had allowed him to devote to its original composition, and subsequent correction, the toil, which he is well aware that so adventurous an undertaking must require. He submits it to the public with a diffidence, which the success of its representation has not tended to remove; for he is sensible that whatever beauty it appeared to possess, was reflected from the young lady who performed the part of Adelaide. To the other performers the author is much obliged for their exertions. This tragedy is not printed exactly as it was represented, as many alterations and omissions were made when it was already in the press.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PROLOGUE. Written by J. H? H?, Esq. While Irish genius soars through every clime, And gains new laurels from the hand of time, Why should her sons to foreign nations roam, Nor trust the native patronage of home? Is it that Irish taste, and Irish sense Are words of idlesse all, and vain pretence? Or fears our country to enroll her name Amid the candidates for critic fame; And, uncontested, yields to British brows The laurel wreath that classic taste bestows? Forbid it heaven! in this enlightened age Such treason should disgrace our history's page. Long time indeed our stage has been supplied With stale productions, first in Britain tried, As if no play this chilling clime could try, Unless matured beneath a British sky. Our author scorns this hateful path to trace, Which only brands his country with disgrace. No emigrating spirit leads him forth, To seek in other lands the meed of worth: But, fired with patriot ardor, dares to claim From his own land the just award of fame. Ye belles of Erin, whose approving smile Lulls every fear, and gives a zest to toil, On you he rests the triumph of his cause, Sure of success, if sure of your applause. What tribute of applause to him so dear, As the soft sigh and sympathizing tear? Oh! could he hear the half-extinguished sigh, Or view one tear-drop fall from beauty's eye, How every pulse of feeling would unite To fill the measure of his just delight!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DRAMATIS PERSONÆ. The Count St. Evermont Albert, his Son Count Lunenberg Colbert Godfrey Madame St. Evermont Julia Adelaide</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. SCENE I. A Gothic Castle, in a Forest.—The Ruins of a Monastery are seen at a distance.—Evening. Enter Count Lunenberg and Colbert. Lunenberg. Colbert, we hail our travels' end, and reach The aged towers of Gothic Lunenberg. Colb. It is a place of loneliness: and here The noise and tumult of the distant world Are like the fall of some far cataract. Lunen. I am your debtor, that you left with me Vienna's range of high-piled palaces, And journey hither. Colb. This romantic scene Has recreative power: but you, my lord, When Hymen's solemn rite demands your stay At Austria's court, and e'en the emperor Commands the union of your noble house With her, whose fortunes and high ancestry Of fame and sway give golden promises, Why seek again these unfrequented domes? Lunen. I would be great. Ambition in my heart Has reared her throne, with all the retinue Of lofty thought and noble enterprize: Glory has bent her burning eye upon me, And woos me to her charms: but do not think so, No other joy can nestle in my soul. If the proud eagle soar against the sun, Is there no down upon the eagle's breast? Colb. I know thee, Lunenberg; thy heaven is fame, Thy thought is mounting fire, and shoots to heaven. In boy-hood's budding years you were my friend, And even then I hailed the impetuous hope, The daring mind, and fine extravagance Prophetic of the man: ere since that time I have beheld you in imperial council, Or in the fields of war pursue renown. What other passion? Lunen. One of mighty power. Colb. Then are you changed. You are no more the man. Lunen. I am not changed: the torrent is the same, But rolls along another precipice. It is not love, for I have heard that love Was a soft longing of the pensive soul, A suspiration of most gentle sighs, An eye now sadly bent upon the earth, Now movelessly contemplative of heaven; But if such things be love, thou well hast said It never could be mine: for know, my friend, That it is desperation. Adelaide! Betray thee, Adelaide! Colb. What fairy charm Hath wound the spell of woman's influence? Lunen. Fast by yon abbey, through whose broken arches The purple setting of the sun is seen Among the trees, whose whitened blossoms seem Spring's swelling bosom, heaved by evening's breath, A cottage rises; there, even there she dwells Unknown, and like a beauteous star that shines Deep in the blue infinity of heaven, Unseen its peaceful glory. Colb. Say, my lord, Whose beauty weighs against a prince's favor? Lunen. When winter's weight hung down the stooping woods, It was my chance to sojourn in this castle. The misty-day was fading, and the wind Heaved longer sighs among the waving trees. Sudden a knocking of the gates was heard, And one, who travelled through the forest gloom, Intreated refuge from the coming night. I went to see him: shrouded o'er with snows, Silent he stood, and when the torch's flare Fell on his face, all bleak and desolate, It had the grandeur of a wilderness. Upon his breast inanimate reclined Two female forms, whose arms were thrown around him, But with such feeble pressure that it seemed As death had left them in life's attitude. Beside him stood a man of hoary years, Sustaining with his aged feebleness Another shrinking woman. When I spake, He answered not, but looked upon his wife And on his child, and stretching forth his arm, With supplication's mournful smile to her Who lay supported by the old man's care, He lowly asked a refuge from the storm For emigrants. Colb. And who, at such an hour, Of those whom fortune hurled relentlessly, Stood at your gate? Lunen. The Count St. Evermont. Colb. Whose deeds are grown familiar in the page Of war-recording story! Human greatness, How art thou fallen! Lunen. His was a tale of woe. 'Twas on the fatal day that death's decree Fell on his only son, he fled from Paris. At night he reached his castle, and beheld The tumbling spires enveloped in a flame That kindled all the sky with conflagration. Frantic he rushed, and from the raging fire Preserved his wife and child; then far away With these companions of adversity And yet another daughter of misfortune, He journeyed forth from France's bleeding realm. I bade him seek in yonder green abode Forgetfulness of sorrow. If you had seen her, With what a look she gave me gratitude, And threw herself upon her father's bosom, And knelt in rapture down! Oh Adelaide! Colb. Misfortune is a shield of sanctity. Your plighted faith to Austria's noblest dame Forbids the thought of marriage. Much, my lord, It has been marvelled at Vienna's court That you delay, with study of pretext, An union gilded with imperial favor. This love is hopeless; and to cherish it, Were cradling infant ruin in your heart. Lunen. Colbert, I am a weak and trembling villain, That have not in me courage to do right, Nor am resolved in guilt. I am a man Who reel along from virtue into crime, And then back to virtue. If I break The compact which my sovereign has commanded, His frown will blast me in my bloom of honors; And if I yield my Adelaide, I lose All hope of that delicious happiness That only satisfies. Colb. Yet think, my lord, Should you refuse the noble lady's hand, Whose nuptials an imperial wish decrees, You fly the court for ever, and must seek That recompense in love, love ne'er can yield. Say, shall another lead our armies forth Which you have tutored in the art of conquest, And win the laurels planted by your hand? Lunen. Oh! thou hast roused me with a trumpet's sound, And wak'st my soul to arms. It shall not be. Colb. Spoke like my friend—but we are interrupted. Enter Albert St. Evermont. Albert. If, as your habit speaks, you are the lord Of yon high domes, that o'er the vast expanse Of waving woods exalt their Gothic pride, One who amid this leafy labyrinth Has lost his course, and whom fatigue weighs down, Entreats your guidance. Lunen. 'Ere the day depart, And yonder summits hide their golden heads In deep obscure, you cannot hope to reach This solitary forest's boundary; And many a lengthened travels' weariness Has lent a toil and effort to your step. Whate'er of soft repose and cheering fare These antique towers can yield, are yours to-night. Alb. This courtesy wears all that polished truth Desired in palaces. I take the boon, For I am faint with countless leagues of toil, And I have held a fellowship with care. Lunen. Forgive enquiry of the cause of sorrow; It bears no common aspect. Alb. Ah! my lord, 'Tis not on me alone adversity Has loosened ruin's weight, nor I alone Have cause to ask of heaven, why is it thus? For there is many a one whose tears are shed O'er those who claimed the tender name of parent, Of sister, and of wife. May I not call her By that endearing title, from whose arms A band of revolution's ruffian sons Swept me away to dungeon solitude, E'en in the hour she owned a mutual flame. In chains they bore me to the dread tribunal, Where death was throned in judgment: I had reached The engine of swift-executing murder, And almost bowed before it, when a cry Came on mine ear, and told the tyrant's fall. The tumult swelled: my guards abandoned me, I saw salvation opened to my step; I fled—why did I fly? Colb. Can you lament To have preserved what the imperious call Of nature bade you keep? Alb. My life! 'twere better I had descended to the peaceful dead, Than wandered o'er the surface of the earth, A forlorn emigrant! When I left the town Where murder held his revelry of blood, I hastened to my father's distant castle. A heap upon the blasted plain it lay, Blackened with conflagration. All was silent, And wild and desolate: and none was there To speak the fate of its inhabitants. 'Twas agony to think it; but at last I heard a rumour in the neighbouring town, That they had been preserved, and fled their country. That hope, that lingering hope, allures my steps: I seek the all that fortune yet may share. My, lord, you seem disturbed. Lunen. (aside) It cannot be. Excuse the wanderings of my wayward thought. Colbert, lead on. [Colbert and Albert exeunt. These fears are idle all. It cannot be: and if it were, by heaven I now have gone so far, that 'tis in vain To wish the deed recalled. Her brother? no! Death sends him not to fright me, from the grave: Or, let the tomb disgorge a thousand brothers, I'll dare them all; for I have ta'en a leap Off from a precipice. I plunge along, And heaven itself were impotent to save. [Exit. SCENE II. The outside of St. Evermont's Cottage.—Evening Scenery. Enter Madame St. Evermont and Julia. Mad. This has its cause, for I of late observe A sadness muses in her countenance, Moves in each measured step, and to her form Imparts its fixed and mournful attitude. Why is it thus with Adelaide? Julia. In truth, A melancholy, like the heavy air That hangs its sickness on a budding tree, Weighs down the rosy blossoms of her beauty. Full oft amid the abbey's loneliness, When evening's star ascended in the west, I have surprised her weeping 'mid the tombs: And when I chid the tears that trickled down, With such a woeful smile she strove to hide them, I too have wept. Then would we sit and think Of times gone by and Albert. Mad. Oh! my Julia! Julia. To lose him in the hour of holy love. Mad. Do not, who hast decreed that we should suffer, Do not forbid our tears, but leave us yet That miserable comfort of the wretched. But Julia, let those tears be secret ones: Not in the presence of St. Evermont Indulge those sorrows, which afflict him more Than all his own endurance: and howe'er There is an agony in seeming happy, Yet let us wear the semblance of content. Julia. It is an art which I must learn of thee, My gentle tutoress in resignation, And more than mother. What though destiny Between our luckless hearts hath interposed Its iron hand—and I was never Albert's— Yet have you ta'en me with parental fondness, And saved me. Mad. Julia, thou art precious to me: And had my Albert lived! You are my child; I love you as my Adelaide, and she Is dear, as to the pilgrim of the desert Are the remaining drops which he has saved From his subverted urn. Julia. Those fair blue eyes, Where shines a soul most pensive and most loving, Her soft variety of winning ways, And all the tender witchery of her smiles That charm each sterner grief, her studious care In all the offices of sweet affection, Would make the world enamoured. Mad. Her endearments Have all that soft and downy consolation That, like an Indian's breast-plate made of plumes, Repels the arrows of adversity. Have I not seen her, with a parent's pride, Smoothing the wrinkled sorrows of her father, And, with the whispers of her gentle voice, Where care awakened in its broken sleep, As music lulls a sick man to repose, Persuade it to oblivion of itself. Julia. He is in need of comfort. Mad. There are few Whom heaven hath visited with such disaster. For know the Count St. Evermont was once Among the great ones of this little world. Julia. Sorrow indeed has done its work upon him. Mad. Yet only leaves such clefts as does the fire That lights upon the summit of an Alp, And striking shakes not. Julia. And yet oftentimes I have observed him mutely gaze upon us, When we have sat together, round the hearth That cheered the coldness of a winter's eve, In woman's workmanship. Then would he start, And suddenly compress us to his bosom, While from those eyes that sent a look to God Tears shed their trickling heat upon my breast. Mad. See where he comes, and moves as if the soul Infused its nobleness o'er all his form. That letter, if his face doth speak aught, Is sure joy's harbinger. 'Tis very long Since joy hath been with us. [Enter St. Evermont with a letter.] St. Ever. Almighty one! Forgive, if e'er in tribulation's hour I rose a rebel 'gainst thy providence, Thou who mysteriously dost arbitrate In comfort, and in grief! my wife, my Julia, I almost think that I am not unhappy. Mad. (who has snatched the letter from him) My Adelaide! what, Holstein! Julia. Let me be A partner of your comforts: I have been The partner of your sorrows. Mad. Oh! my husband! My Julia! at the dead of slumbering night, I have knelt down and prayed that, in the hour We should be laid beneath the earth together, There should be one to lift her from the tomb, To take her in his arms and to console her. (to Julia) Count Holstein asks the hand of Adelaide. Julia. She will be blest; for Holstein is a man Whose soul was formed of heaven's own milder air. Mad. All, Julia, will be blest. Though we are fallen From off the pinnacles of human life, A quiet freshness spreads along the vale, A tranquil green down the declivity Where all the sweet felicities of home Have fixed their sheltered dwelling. St. Ever. Oh! my country! Mad. Hold not such muttered converse with yourself: Look not so very sadly: who forgets That he was happier once is happy still. Is she not ours? But where is Adelaide? St. Ever. I bade old Godfrey seek the ruined abbey Where she is wont at such an hour to stray. Julia. See where they come together. [Enter Godfrey and Adelaide.] Mad. Adelaide! St. Ever. Come to my bosom, Adelaide, my child! And art thou left me still? Adel. My gentle father! Amid the deep recesses of these woods Where not an echo of the talking world Hath told its pompous moral, I have learned The precept of that sweet philosophy Instinctive nature teaches,—to belove you. My mother! Mad. I have saved thee, Adelaide, E'en as perhaps the first of mothers bore A little flower from Eden's holy bowers, And loved it more than Eden, and thou art As pure and lovely as the first fresh rose That, in the dewy groves of Paradise, Grew in creation's morning. St. Ever. Read, my child. Julia. She trembles, ha! she faints. Adel. Support me, Julia. My life, but not my heart: oh! take my life, And do not frown upon me: oh! my father! St. Ever. Thou wilt not wed Count Holstein? Mad. Adelaide. St. Ever. I must endure this too. Fond cheating hope, Thou meteor in the evening of my life, That from the hot affections of this heart Exhaled a bright illusion. Mad. Do you love me? Adel. Were my heart made transparent, every thought And each particular wish made visible, You would behold a prayer, that, like the eye Of an arch-angel, supplicated heaven To pour its blessings o'er my parents' age. St. Ever. “Arise, and” leave me. Julia. (to Adelaide, as they go out together) Ah! my weeping friend, What sorrows yet can fortune have in store? [Exeunt Adelaide and Julia. St. Ever. Suspicion is the growth of meaner spirits; Yet does misfortune often cherish it, And then it lurks a rank and leafless weed Amid the ruins of a noble mind. He is the friend of my calamity. (To Godfrey) You came to me with fearful hesitation, 'Tis scarce a month, and when I bade you speak, You cried, beware Lunenberg. In wrath I flung you off. Godf. Beware of him, my lord. Mad. Old man, you wrong her. Godf. Madam, I am old. Mad. I am a mother. St. Ever. Speak, I charge thee, speak. Godf. Upon the very evening 'ere the day Count Lunenberg departed; o'er the hills That from your cottage slope in woods away, I chanced to wander: suddenly I heard The murmurs of a voice most tremulous, And pausing, looked through twilight's sinking veil, When straight I saw a man, who kneeling pressed A woman's hand: she wept and sobbed in grief, He rose and clasped her. Mad. It was not my child! Godf. It was your daughter Adelaide. St. Ever. 'Tis false. I now remember me thou hadst a child, And that she perished; thou dost envy me, Wouldst make me wretched as thou art thyself: Thou didst not see all this, or if thou didst Thou shouldst not have believed thine aged eyes: Or if thou didst, false dotard.—Look not on me, For, when I gaze upon thy countenance, I cannot but remember thou hast followed Misfortune's footsteps: time has changed thy hair, But time, nor fortune, could not change thy faith. Mad. Oh Adelaide! thou wert my only solace. St. Ever. There is a tomb, where sleep my ancestors: None e'er hath stood upon that sepulchre And said, Here rests a coward or a wanton. It is a vault of glory. Adelaide. [Enter Adelaide and Julia.] Adel. Is it my father's call? St. Ever. It is thy father: Who tells his daughter that he keenly feels What nature's providence has wisely willed A father's love; yet tells his daughter too That if a thawing breath of infamy Drop its corruption on thy name of snow, He would, all crimsoned with thy filial blood, Pluck the hot dagger from thy panting breast, And lift it, reeking o'er with life, to heaven. Adel. (to Julia) Protect me, Julia, save me in thine arms. Mad. And shall I ever curse my travail for thee? St. Ever. Have I not honor still? And who shall take What I still hold, in proud despite of fortune And all the malice of conspiring stars? Count Lunenberg, I'm not that thick fat root That draws its juices from the sepulchre, And feeds upon the dead. I will not live On my child's shame. 'Tis done. From hence, for ever! To-morrow's setting sun shall see me far From thine accursed towers. Preserve me, heaven, Save me from infamy. I do not think That thou hast done the utmost deed of shame, But, by the mighty power that made the world, One impure thought, one touch.... 'Twill make me mad. [Exit. Mad. This earth is all too full of misery. [Exit weeping. Adel. Am I permitted still to sob upon thee? Dost thou constrain me, Julia, to thy heart And weep upon me. Julia. Here, upon my bosom, On friendship's pillow lay your sorrows down: From infancy we shared each little joy, And we have conned affliction's book together. I claim your grief, for it is all mine own. Adel. Heaven has abandoned me. Julia. Say, what has happened. Adel. Oh! there is not an outcast of the world So lost, or so distracted. Julia, Julia, What will become of me! oh! Lunenberg! Julia. That name, I fear, came bursting from your heart, A load of misery. Speak, Adelaide. Adel. And was it not enough that he should leave me? That after one short month of exstacy, One little month, he tore him from my arms? You frown; but hear me, Julia, and if e'er Your Albert was beloved, you'll pity me. Julia. Yes, I will pity thee, but, Adelaide— Adel. Thine eyes proclaim a meaning which the lips Would fear to utter. Dost thou, canst thou think it? No! Though I love him with a fainting rapture, And cling around his memory with a clasp Of most enamoured fondness, witness heaven That if thy minister, with holy rite, Had not to love extended sanctity, I never had been his. Julia. What! married! then You still are innocent. Adel. If she can be so Who, in despite of that high ordinance That wills a parent's empire o'er his child, Gave promise that she never would reveal Her marriage to her father. Julia. Why demand it? Adel. He said, if e'er it reached the imperial ear, His sovereign's frown would blast him, and my father Would never brook a moment's secrecy. And then by all our loves he did entreat I ne'er would speak of it. Julia. And this you trusted? Adel. Is there not sweet perdition in his eyes? Is not that face refulgent with a soul Sublimely ardent, while his every word Is tempered with a wooing gentleness? And has not glory wreathed around his brow A garland from her ever-green? Whose arm Hurls swift destruction through the ranks of war With might like his? Whose smile hath such a beam? Whose lips such soft persuasive eloquence? And has he not received my father's sorrows, And dried my mother's tears? Who had not loved him? I loved, and, loving, never could suspect. Julia. I own him all that woman's virgin wishes In fancy's kindling vision can pourtray; Yet high ambition swells within his heart. Adel. Oh! he has sworn by every sacred power, By all heaven's host that glitter through the night, That Adelaide was dearer than his glory; That to one sigh, one smile of Adelaide, He would resign the empire of the world. If you had seen the flash of fervid soul Suffused o'er all that burning countenance, If you had felt the throbbing of his heart When, in the tumult of impetuous passion, He seized my hand and clasped it to his bosom, Then would you say he loved. Dost thou remember That day, when down a winter torrent's roll He plunged precipitous? He cleft the tide, And bore me back to life and to my father? Julia. Yet why demand this strange mysterious silence? Adel. O Julia! thou hast opened many a wound, And bid'st them bleed afresh. Thou hast recalled My wandering thought from scenes of happiness To present sorrows, and to future perils. Within my breast there is a messenger Of shame and misery: nay, let me tell thee That when amid the abbey's mouldering altars I swore the nuptial vow, ('twas in the hour Of calm and holy night, when vigilant heaven Opes its bright eyes to watch the sleeping world) A secret voice was whispering guilt and horror: And, Julia, when I threw me in his arms To hide my blushes, and to quell my fears, He trembled too: his eye was all on fire, And dreadful passions flared upon his face. How soon he left me too! Julia. Alas, my friend, Heaven has decreed calamity enough! Adel. He left me, Julia! one poor little month Was all of bliss that I have ever known. Yet was he still as ardent as before, And spoke and looked all exstacy. At length An order from the court commanded him Back to Vienna. Julia, I have pined E'er since that time in weeping solitude: My heart is wasted: and the rising morn And setting sun behold me still in tears. Julia. Fly to your mother, open all your bosom, Reveal this fatal marriage. Adel. 'Tis impossible. E'en as he parted, and my winding arms Detained him still within their long embrace, E'en in the pressure of the last sad kiss, E'en as I prayed another of his lips, He whispered, Adelaide, the stars alone And yonder orb be conscious of our loves. Julia. Your father cried that he would hence for ever; And 'twas the look and accent of resolve. Adel. What! o'er the world! the cold and heartless world, Thrown out! To have no hope, no smiling hope, To lean on in his age! to see the night Fast gathering o'er his head, and have no home: Then think on better times! I will kneel down, I will entreat him! What? It cannot be! Then heaven have mercy! Send some pitying angel To rescue my distraction! Oh my husband! Where art thou, Lunenberg? [Exeunt. END OF THE FIRST ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. SCENE I. The Ruins of a Monastery. Enter Lunenberg and Colbert. Lunen. This ruined holiness, those sepulchres Are loved by Adelaide; and here to-night Perchance I may behold her; e'en from hence I've seen her raise her fine face up to heaven: Sometimes a cloud that floated near the moon Enclosed her form within its shadowy veil, And when the lovely orb emerged again, Methought she seemed more beautiful and sad. Colb. But, Lunenberg, these towers of ages gone That cast their awful shadows o'er the soul, Were fitter place of congress for the elves And all the populace of poesy. Lunen. Our loves are melancholy. Marvel not That we should haunt a place so wild and wizard. The soul of Adelaide is sorrowful, And, like a moon-beam, rests upon a tomb. Colb. Oh! I have seen the day when Lunenberg Had spurned the sickly phrase of sentiment, And the fierce beauty of Bellona's frown Inflamed the soaring thought: then if perhaps His eye would glance upon the face of nature, He sought a bright similitude of fame. I've heard thee say, when we have strayed at eve Along the shores of fair Geneva's lake And watched the summit of a distant peak, Red with the glories of the parting day, That thus hereafter, while the rest of men Lay in oblivion's wide obscurity, Memory would throw her radiance on the great Who rise like mountains o'er the sphere of time. Lunen. Still am I what I was. The long array Of war, embattled in a field of flame, The shock of nations and the cannon's roar, The headlong rush of charging cavalry, The clangor of the trumpet, and the shout, Yet croud ambition's vision. Once indeed I knew no thrill of rapture save renown: And o'er my soul the other passions blew As winds o'er Lapland's ocean; but at length A furious passion burst the icy plain And rages here: I love. Colb. Why then love on: Renounce your glory. Lunen. Never. Colb. Yield your fame, And bear the scorn of courtiers as you pass, Or tear this cancer passion from your breast. Lunen. Stab through my heart, for you must seek it there. Colb. Yet are there other instruments of peace. Lunen. Then teach me where they are, and I will grasp them. Colb. Fly from this spot, and ere the dawn of day Return we to Vienna. Lunen. 'Ere I see, Or hear, or touch, that every ravished sense May tremble like a lyre when I depart, With soft vibrations of remembered joy! Colb. To-night, my lord, to-night, or ruin waits you. Lunen. Why then let ruin come. I'll hear no more. Begone, nor freeze me with thine oracles. Colb. Then stay; be passion's play thing; from thy brow Pluck the oppressive helmet's warrior weight, And be a woman's slave. [Exit. Lunen. Thou dost not know That in the rushing stream of destiny I have plunged headlong down, and 'tis in vain To fight against the torrent. Fate, roll on, And bear me to perdition! I'll not think, For reason cannot stay necessity, But calmly stands upon the precipice And lifts her torch above the black profound To point the gulf, but cannot check the passions That, like a band of furies, seize the soul And hurl it off. It is necessity That with a dreadful impulse leads me on. A flaming comet shone upon my birth And guides me to destruction.— 'Tis herself: Or 'tis an angel with as light a tread Has ta'en her form to woo an angel's love. [Enter Adelaide.] Thou throbbing of my heart, my bane, my blessing, My hope and my despair! my Adelaide! Adel. My husband! ha! (she swoons) Lunen. Why shrinks thy tenderness? Ope those bright eyes, and shine upon my soul. No, Adelaide, I would not have thee wake! Thus let me hold thee! Unsubstantial beings, Ætherial spirits! ye that round us bathe In yon pure deeps your incorporeal forms, Do you not envy man's material sense, And all the rapture of an earthly touch? Adel. It was the voice of Lunenberg, and came Like midnight music down a wooded lake. My fancy oft has played the fool with me, But ne'er with such a semblance of the truth. Lunen. I hold thee near my heart: I have thee here: I gaze upon thee, travel o'er thy charms, And feed each kindled sense with all thy beauties. O thou sweet trembler, would that poison dwelt Within the dewy roses of thy lip, That I might kiss the sweet contagion thence, And die.—My love! my life! Adel. My timorous soul Distrusts the dear delight. It is himself, It is my Lunenberg. This fainting heart, Can scarce sustain the oppressive load of bliss That weighs it down, and sickens in the pleasure. Lunen. I come to thee, as exiles to their country. Adel. And be my heart thy home. Thou ne'er again Shall wander from thy tender Adelaide, For I have wept to think how far away My Lunenberg hath strayed. Full oft at night Have I stood here, a lone contemplatist, And gazed on yon fair hermit of the sky, That seemed to rise more sadly o'er my sorrows And pity my abandonment. But oh! If it was pain to part, there's surely bliss In thus beholding thee. Lunen. And can the shout That fills the ear of conquest, can the pomp Of triumph, winding up the mount of fame, Touch with thy sweet sublimity of joy? Thrones of the world, I see you now beneath me. Oh! thou art all that wishing man can hope for: The glorious stars have not a joy beyond thee.— She weeps! My Adelaide, why are these tears? Why heaves that bosom that was made for pleasures? And swell those waves upon a sea of bliss? Adel. My father, oh! Lunen. Speak, Adelaide, thy father? Adel. If e'er you loved me— Lunen. Loved thee, Adelaide! The flame that mounts from Ætna, does not burn Through the black night so fiercely as the fire That rages through the darkness of my soul. If e'er I loved! Adel. Be calm: oh listen to me. Lunen. Then smile, and I will gaze upon thy smile, And feel contagious gentleness effuse A magic influence. A madman's eye Would lose the fury of its raging glance If once it rested upon Adelaide: And there is music in that warbled voice Will pour its sweetness o'er my troubled soul, As if an angel's harp was heard in hell Adel. Count Holstein— Lunen. What of him? Adel. Has sought my hand. Lunen. I'll leap upon him with a tiger's plunge. Adel. When I refused to wed, my father frowned, And bade me leave him. Scarce had I retired, When, with the terrors of a thunder's peal, He summoned me before him. With dismay I saw him lift his clenched hand to heaven, And an exalting wrath inspired his form. He cried that he would bear me hence for ever. Lunen. From hence for ever! Adel. Fly, disclose our marriage: Implore a blessing on our wedded loves. Lunen. He must not hear of it. Adel. You never loved me. (weeping) And you are come to triumph o'er my sorrows; To smile upon the ruin you have made; To part—what! part! what! never see thee more! To know, while thus you strain me to your bosom, That I must never feel its pulse again. But be it so: renounce me, Lunenberg, Renounce, abandon me. I'll weep indeed, And oh! there was a time when Adelaide Would not have wept in vain; but if my tears, And if the breaking of this wretched heart Can yield thee joy, I will not murmur at it. I'll lose thee for thyself: go, Lunenberg, Pursue ambition's meteor.— Yet grant me this, it is an humble prayer, Will you not sometimes think of Adelaide? There is a place among the whitening tombs Where first I heard thy words of tenderness And listened to perdition: when I'm dead, As speedily I shall be, let my grave Be very humble in that mournful spot. I pray thee sometimes visit it at eve: And when you look upon the fading rose That grows beside a pillar down the aisle, And watch it drooping in the twilight dews, Then think of one who bloomed a little while, E'en as that sickly rose, and bloomed to die. Lunen. (embracing her) Who now shall take thee hence? who now shall part us? Adel. Why did ye curse me with this bane of being? Lunen. Oh! thou wert made for love, for frantic love! Come, Adelaide. Adel. And whither would you lead me? (The voice of St. Evermont is heard in the Forest.) Where art thou, Adelaide? where is my child? Adel. O Lunenberg! it is my father's voice. I am not wont to tarry here so late, And now they seek me. Tell him, tell him all, And save me from this horrid secrecy. [Enter Godfrey] Godf. Do I behold my noble master's daughter? O heavens! and in the arms of Lunenberg. (Godfrey rushes up.) Lunen. Go stop a thunderbolt. Godf. She is their all. Adel. O Godfrey, take me with you. Godf. Hold, my lord! Old as I am, you shall not wrong the child Of Count St. Evermont; and in the name— Lunen. Aye, in the name of love's superior power I throw thee off. Godf. You make me bless the hour I lost my child. (he falls) Adel. What hast thou done? Lunen. Preserved thee.— Rise fiends from hell, rush angels down from heaven, Nor heaven nor hell shall rob thee from my heart. [Exit carrying Adelaide. Godf. I had a daughter once, and she was fair; And on that eve, in beauteous Languedoc, She did entreat that I would lead her forth To fix her dying eyes upon the west, When I beheld consumption's mocking bloom Flush in the rosy light, my heart was smote; And in the night (it was a dreary night) When I stood by the couch on which she lay And I beheld her dead, I wished to die; But now I thank thy will unsearchable That deigned to take my daughter to thyself, For she went white and innocent to heaven. [Exit. SCENE II. The Forest.—Rocks are seen in the back-ground. Enter Madame St. Evermont and Julia. Mad. Talk not to me of marriage—I'll not hear it. I know but this, that Lunenberg's returned And Adelaide is gone. Where is my child? Speak, tell me where thou art: oh! answer me. Julia. She said that in the very deep of night, Amid the abbey's ruined solitude, The holy rite was done. Mad. (who has not listened) Oh! do not speak, Lest you disturb the quiet of the air, And then—Hark! there—a step—it comes this way. 'Tis she. 'Twas nothing but the fitful breeze That rustled through the multitude of leaves. Julia. Perhaps— Mad. Perhaps! It is a blessed sound, And hope is fond of it. The sable slave Stands on the beach of western India's isles In evening's breathing hour, and says ‘perhaps.’ The captive in his darksome prison house Doth watch a ray of light upon the wall, And gives an utterance to the holy word. 'Tis heard within Potosi's silver tombs, Gasps in the fetid air of hospitals, And in the naked hut of poverty. Why is that comfort then denied to me? Why then not say ‘perhaps’? Speak it again: It is a drop of balm upon my heart. Julia. (pointing to the rocks) Look there: it is the Count St. Evermont. He rushes up the rocks: he has ascended: See where he stands upon the precipice. Mad. Let me not lose him too! [Enter St. Evermont, descending from the rocks.] St. Ever. I'll tell thee, woman, The horrid hope that, like a lightning's glare, Flashed on my soul, and winged me to that height. I stood upon the gulf's terrific verge, That I might see one drop of pendent blood Upon a bramble's leaf. 'Twere exstacy To find the bleeding bosom of my child Burst on the pointed ridges of a rock: Some scattered limb—to hear a dying groan! Mad. What! hope her dead! my child, my Adelaide! St. Ever. The child were lost—but honor had been mine— I would have followed her. Mad. Almighty power! St. Ever. Thou shalt not pray: the angels laugh at thee. I dwelled in palaces, and ruled in courts: Thou wert my wife. Oh! I was very happy. Hark thee, and wither! I beheld the blood Reek from my consecrated monarch's head, And then I prayed: I saw my house in flames: Thy frenzied shriek is yet within my brain: At morn I knelt me on the smoking pile, And still I prayed: I saw thee shrink away Beneath the pelting of the warring tempest, And still I prayed: at last I found a friend Who did receive my sorrows, soothed my grief, And robbed me of my child. I'll pray no more. [Enter Godfrey.] Mad. Speak, is she safe? I'll kneel, and at thy feet I'll pay thee with a mother's burning tears. Godf. I sought the abbey's aisles, for there I knew That she was wont to linger. Mad. And you found her? You found my child? Godf. Within a villain's arms. (Madame St. Evermont faints in Julia's arms.) Godf. I threw myself upon my aged knees, And strove to wake a pity in his heart: And when he spurned my supplicating hands, I roused a vigor in my trembling frame And rushed to save her from his impious clasp, When with a blow he threw me to the ground. The flakes of many winters have descended Upon this whitened head, and time has bent This feeble form, or I had never brooked To see the child of Count St. Evermont— St. Ever. Oh! wake me, wake me from this horrid dream, And drive these phantoms off. Godf. Have mercy on him! St. Ever. Ha! there it is again— He rifles all the treasures of her bosom. Hold! ruffian, hold! That kiss—I'll kneel to thee, I will entreat thy mercy, Lunenberg, Spare, spare the consolation of a father. Behold me kneel who never knelt before: Be not more cruel than my cruel fortune, And rob me not of what my fortune left. It is the central fibre of the heart That knits the parent and the child together. Thou wilt not? I will dare thee to the fight: Villain, come on. (St. Evermont in his frenzy imagines he is fighting Lunenberg.) He falls: do not forgive him. [Rushes out, followed by Godfrey. Julia. Where does he rush? where does his frenzy lead him? And here is yet another spectacle Of utter wretchedness. Returning life Dawns on her face, and she awakes to grief: Her eyes are oped in horrid vacancy. There yet is room for hope. Mad. Hope is a cheat: I'll none of it. Bring back my child to me: Then only bid me hope. Oh! do not press me, Thine arms are not so soft as Adelaide's, Nor canst thou fill me with thy cold embrace. What was my sin in my prosperity That she should leave me too? Do I deserve To be this childless desolated wretch? [Exeunt. END OF THE SECOND ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. SCENE I. A Chamber in Lunenberg's Castle.—Storm.—Night. Lunenberg. Here I will seek a refuge from myself. Am I not damned already, since to me Repentance is denied? Can I recall, By sighs as heavy as the tempest's moan, Deeds sinking down eternity's abyss? She sleeps: how sweetly innocent she looked! Her breathing was the perfume of the soul, As, trembling to the couch of loose desire, I led the unsuspecting purity. How could I bear the murmuring tenderness With which she whispered, ‘he will weep to-night?’ [Enter Adelaide.] Adel. Where is my husband? where is Lunenberg? Lunen. Better to see a vampire's ghastly shape, And feel it suck my blood. Adel. And art thou here? Have these lone chambers, whose profound recess Appears an habitation of the spectres That sweep along their dreary emptiness, Moving in measure with the falling winds, Has all this scene of antique desolation More charm than Adelaide? Why did you leave me? Lunen. I raised the lamp to look upon thy face: Thy slumber was as mild as is a babe's, And there was o'er thy lips a tender smile That seemed to say thy dreams were happy ones: I could not bear that smile. Adel. Why is it thus? In what have I offended? You fright me with the quivering of your lip. Oh! take me to thy heart! Thou dost not know When, as I woke and heard the roaring tempest That howled along the castle's tottering age, And shrunk for refuge in thy circling arms, What terrors filled the soul of Adelaide, To find thee gone. I started up, and listened, And in the voices of the sinking storm Methought I heard a cry most sorrowful: Methought I heard my father! Take me, Lunenberg, I need the solacing of thy affection. Lunen. Thou art a very beauteous wretchedness. Adel. Then hast thou ceased to love me, Lunenberg. Though 'twere my lot to dwell within a cave, Scooped in the bosom of a desert rock, That far from land among the rolling waves Uprose in solitude; where nought was heard Except the sleepy murmur of the sea; Yet if I still could think at evening's hour, When haply I should sit and watch the west, That thou didst still remember Adelaide— Lunen. Oh! thou wilt loathe me. Adel. Loathe thee! Lunen. Thou wilt curse me. Adel. Thus let me throw myself upon thy bosom. Lunen. Come, look thee here, and try if he who wrote A warning on his front who murdered first, Hath traced ‘a villain’ here. Thou tremblest! ha! 'Tis so—the characters are burning flames— I am a murderer too—for I have killed thee, And damned thee with myself—No, Adelaide, Thou still art innocent: not thine the crime: Pure as the spotless seraph that adores In burning contemplation. Adel. Save me, heaven! Lunen. Two silent fiends will bear me to a dungeon, And cast me down, and close the grate for ever: Nothing shall there be heard: no sound, no touch, No ray of light be there, save when a demon Will come with some blue lamp's infernal power, In semblance of thyself, to haunt my sight And look me in the eyes with tears like thine, Then vanish with a shriek. Yet thou perchance, If, haply wandering with thy sister saints, Thou should'st approach my place of punishment, Then wilt thou think with pity on the man Whose sin was loving thee. Adel. Why how is this? The sin? What sin? Thou couldst not play me false. With burning blushes thus I cast it from me, And turn to thee, my life, my lord, my husband, In all the confidence of boundless faith, And all the constancy of woman's love. Lunen. Thou wilt not leave me then? No change, no crime, Shall ever wring thee from my bleeding heart. Adel. Though want should wither all thy worldly substance, Though scorn should touch and blast thy name for ever, Though all men fled thee like a noisome plague, Yet never dove hung o'er her dying young With half the tenderness I'd cling to thee. Nay, I'd exult to share my husband's shame, And glory in the proud sweet consciousness That I was thine for ever. Lunen. Damned ambition, That hurled from heaven's light and God's bright presence Millions of spirits, splendid and immortal, To live a long eternity of pain, Intense and endless: thou whose sacrilege Rifled the realms of bliss, and with a curse Dried up the bounty of the teeming earth, Why stoop from desolation so sublime, From mighty havoc that assailed both worlds, And tempt so pitiful a knave as I am, To tear this modest wild-briar from its fence, To toy awhile; and then to trample on it? Adel. I've scarcely breath to ask what this may mean? Lunen. Oh! thou confiding goodness, I've betrayed thee: I am a villain, and the most perfidious Who e'er belied an unsuspecting faith, And stained the lilies of a virgin's love. Adel. What dreadful mystery is bursting on me? Am I dishonored? Answer me, my husband: My honor is thine own. Nay, now you mock me— The book, the altar, and the man of God— I saw them with these eyes: these ears have heard The holy form of prayer that made me yours, Made me for ever yours—your wedded wife. Lunen. Never was wife more true, or more beloved. Adel. Ten thousand blessings on thee for the word: Hope has come back to my affrighted heart. Lunen. Had I but loved thee less, I ne'er had wronged thee: Or had it been my destiny to know thee Before— Adel. Am I your wife? Lunen. 'Twas madness seized me: The fury of a guilty desperate passion. Before I saw, before I burned for thee, My faith was plighted, and my sovereign's will Commanded marriage. Call the lightning down! I lured thy unsuspecting innocence, And, with a semblance of religion's rites, Abused thy trust, and plunged thee into shame. But here, behold me kneeling at thy feet, Behold me here renounce the world for thee. Adel. An icy adder winds around my heart, And now it stings and stings, and yet I live. Not wedded to thee! Oh for some dark depth To hide me from all eyes, where odious light Could never see my shame! False! false! all false! And I am that vile thing I dare not name. Lunen. My fame, the pride of power, the legion's guidance, My emperor's smile, my all, I yield to thee: The pomp of courts, the soldier's acclamation, The host, the battle, and the victory. I'll lead thee to the altar, and proclaim Our consecrated nuptials. There a priest, With all the solemn rite and circumstance Religion asks, shall join our hallowed hands. Adel. They curse me! Lunen. Here shall be thy throne, thy empire. (Placing his hand upon his heart.) Adel. Not wedded to thee! then I'll wed despair. Come my new bridegroom to this heart: 'tis thine, For ever thine: thou wilt be faithful to me: Thou canst not flatter: thou wilt not deceive me: Come then: let's fly: but hold—no mockery now, We'll wed in earnest, and without a priest. Lunen. My wife, my Adelaide: I'll call thee wife, For so thou shalt be— Adel. Ha! unhand me! help! Pollution's in thy touch. Enter Albert St. Evermont. Alb. It came this way. It is the master of these lonely towers, And with him's one, whose sorrows at this hour Rose like a spirit's wailing on the blast. Her cheek is blanched, and every broken thought Intruding on that lovely dreariness, Appears a wild and haggard wanderer. Adel. They call me back: they bid me come to them. Lunen. Where wouldst thou rush? Adel. Thou shalt not stay me from them— I am their child! (Thunder) Aye, thou art angry, heaven! Why does the lightning flash, and not fall here Upon this guilty head? Strike here and blast me! [Exit. Alb. What may this mean? It seems a fitting place For deeds of foul mysterious villainy; And sure the storm, that shakes these tottering towers, And swings the forest with its groaning strength, Doth howl auspiciously. Count Lunenberg! Unconscious of the sound! 'tis something terrible, For in the hollow of his gleamy eyes The dreadful passions light their murky fires; And in my chamber from this very place I heard the voice of intermingled anguish— Lunen. He was unfortunate, he was my friend! (turning to Albert) Begone: avoid my sight: avoid a plague: My bosom heaves with guilt, and every breath Will shed a rotting leprosy upon thee. If in the social cup I had infused The chilling draught of death, or at the couch Of him who sought a shelter 'neath my roof Had crept at midnight to the act of blood, I were not half the villain that I am. Dost thou not fly me yet? Then hear it all, And thou wilt bid volcanos burst between us. I robbed the fondest parents of their child, The noblest mind of honor's treasured hoard, Abused a believing woman's confidence, Trod down the blooming of her innocence, The flower that grew upon the grave of hope! Alb. (aside) I had a sister. Lunen. Adelaide! Alb. Speak on! Lunen. Thou art the emigrant, and thou hast cause To load me with the choicest execration, For she was consecrate of misery And shared thy griefs. I would avoid thy face, For thou rememberest me that he was wrecked In France's stormy fate. Alb. Hear me, ye heavens! I saw my country frantic with the thirst Of her own blood: I have awaked at night, And, from a dungeon's subterranean depth, Have heard the tocsin with its fierce alarm Arouse the Furies from their dreams of blood. I've lost my name, my fortunes, and my country: I am without the sparrow's privilege, Without a home, a naked wanderer. But let not all be crowned with infamy. Speak, thou proud lord, my blood is pure as thine, Its fount as noble. Hast thou tarnished it? Hast thou received me in thy guilty towers That I might see thee gorge thy lechery Upon a sister's shame? Speak, who was this, That tossed her arms on high, and rent her hair, Then rushed into the centre of the night? Lunen. What? lie upon the cold and barren earth! That form, whose delicate and tender touch Would hardly leave impression on the bed Which love had strewed with roses; and that bosom Where lingering thought hath never yet reposed, And was not heated into exstacy. A torch there! hoa! a torch: set night in flames: Awake, and through the forest's blackening depth Wave your exploring fires. (rushes out) Alb. Hear, villain, hear! Thou shalt not 'scape me thus: if it be she— Let it not be my sister—make me poor: Poor, not dishonored; wretched, not disgraced. [Exit. SCENE II. The interior of St. Evermont's Cottage. Enter Madame St. Evermont and the Count. Madame. I cannot trust thee, Julia. Married! no: The proud relentless heart of that bad man Would never stoop to wed an emigrant. Thou dost but feed a hope that will not live. Thou sleepest: happy they who can forget That they have been—or are. Alas! my child.— St. Ever. I wish that I could weep as easily As thou dost weep. My sorrow will not melt: 'Tis here and here—the cold that chills my heart: The heat that fires my brain. Mad. My child! my child! St. Ever. Child, child! I pray you do not speak that word; It is a very arrow in my soul, That deeply rankles here; and when 'tis touched By memory's hand, oh then the barbed shaft Doth quiver with a pang most exquisite. Mad. There's not a name of melting melody, A soft harmonious concourse of sweet sounds, To speak the love with which I doated on her. Her saddest smile chased sternest grief away; And all her offices of filial care Were moss upon the rocks of misery. Do you remember? St. Ever. Aye, I well remember: And would I could forget, that infamy Has laid its rottenness upon my name: That she, my child—'Twill make me mad again. If the great power, that punishes hereafter, Did stretch his hand across the burning gulf, Grasping the writhing soul of that black villain, I'd cry ‘plunge, plunge!’ though I should follow for it. Hell would be heaven, if I beheld him damned. Mad. She was more dear than all: her artless talk, Her beauty, and her winning tenderness, Had made me feel a mother's deeper joy. To leave me, Adelaide, to break the tie That very feebly held me back to life! St. Ever. But I will throw, I'll blot thee from my heart! Mad. And is it then so easy to forget? The rest were ta'en away, but she was left me! Have I not often in the dead of night Started in frenzied horror from my dream, And rushed to catch her in my yearning arms, To be persuaded by my very senses She had not perished too. She yet was left me, And I was blest! St. Ever. To filch me of my child! Load with disgrace the stooping of my age, Make infamy my epitaph! Damnation! [Enter Adelaide, with her hair dishevelled.] Adel. My father! (she sinks at his feet) Mad. It is Adelaide! Ye heavens! And do I hold thee here? Art thou returned To fill the dreadful void within my heart? For, when thou didst abandon my misfortune, I spread my arms, and closed them round my breast, And found no daughter there. Adel. I come to die. But, ere I go to that eternal rest, Here let me kneel, and with a bursting bosom Implore one look of mercy. I am dying. Mad. And hast thou then restored her back to me, That I might see her perish in my arms, Watch the slow fading of this livid cheek, The eyelids close upon the beamless sight, Till every pulse and stir of life has ceased, Then clasp a cold and senseless heaviness? St. Ever. (wildly) Let me observe that woman's countenance: She's very like my daughter— And yet it is not she: for, look you here, The blush upon the cheek of Adelaide Was beautiful as summer's evening skies; But here's a face more pallid than the shroud Of one that's newly dead. Not Hesperus, Seen in the quiet of a ripless lake, Beamed with more radiant meekness than her eyes; And they were made of smiles. Nor this the hair, Whose ringlets the soft breathing of the south Scarce dared to kiss with too much wantonness. The warmth of youthful life was in my child! Mad. Alas! distraction lingers in his eye. Oh! look upon her, for she is our child. St. Ever. I'll know that straight; and take her in my arms, And feel if she's my daughter Adelaide. By heavens! it is! the throbbing of her heart! Now it beats quicker: now it heaves with life. Adel. It is my father's voice, and on his bosom! Let, let me go, unloose me from your clasp, That I may throw myself upon the earth, Lie prostrate in the dust, and, at your feet, In anguish weep my wasting sight away: For never, never more shall I be pressed Against the bosom where I used to slumber. This is the place for me: here will I lie, And wring my hands in grief. I'll gaze intent, Until I see you turn an eye of pity; Then will I raise me thus from off the ground, Make one last effort of exhausted life, And, clinging round about your parent knees, Unloose the filial hold at last, and die. St. Ever. Are you my child? Adel. I am that wretched one; But now I am not worthy of the name: For I am she than whom upon the earth There's not a thing more vile; the finger-mark Of bitter scorn; opprobrium's cruel jest; Who left a father's for a traitor's arms, Nor pitied your calamity. But oh! I am not half the guilty thing I seem. To trust a man, to believe a perjury, This is my crime; for, with religion's rite, Count Lunenberg deceived me. St. Ever. (addressing himself to heaven) Dost thou hear it? The morning dawns, and nature's glorious priest, The mighty sun, collecting from the earth The perfumed dew, makes sacrifice to God. But I have incense will ascend above, A fitter offering; 'tis a father's curse. Make him unfortunate, but leave him still A daughter beautiful and innocent: Give him a child in whom his heart may joy: Then find a friend to tear her from his heart, And steep her in pollution— Adel. He will curse me: Oh! save me from his curse. Mad. St. Evermont! Give not an utterance to the dreadful sound! St. Ever. Curse her! what father ever cursed his child? Adel. Lay me for ever in that bed of peace Where sleep, untroubled by a dream, shall close My eyelids in oblivious happiness. My weary spirit will be laid in rest; Nor will the withering of a father's prayer Blast the green sod upon my lowly grave. St. Ever. My tears begin to flow: at length I weep. Adel. And can you speak so very tenderly? Can you indeed forgive me? St. Ever. Adelaide! How, Adelaide, could'st thou abandon me? Adel. Alas! Count Lunenberg— St. Ever. Count Lunenberg! Thou smiling cold and marble-hearted villain, Whose soul came reeking from the pools of hell, A vapour from its blue sulphureous gulf! I weep, and yet he lives: he breathes the air, He grins, and mocks, and triumphs in my ruin: Where is my sword? I perish, or avenge. [Exit. Mad. St. Evermont, my husband! hear me! hear! He goes to die! Adel. To die! Mad. For you. Adel. O God! [Exeunt. END OF THE THIRD ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT IV. SCENE I. Cottage.—Enter St. Evermont and Godfrey. St. Evermont. The day has climbed the mountain's golden top, And to the dreary tempest of the night The rosy flush of opening morn succeeds. A black and heavy gloom still deepens here, In which no twilight reddens. Through the dusk The spectre of departed greatness stalks. Godf. Your sword, my lord. (gives the sword) St. Ever. My last, my only friend. And yet not so. I wrong thee much, old man. Thy youth attended my prosperity: And now thine age hath not deserted me. Godf. Alas! my noble lord! St. Ever. I charge thee, Godfrey, Call me no more thy lord: for who am I? Yes: I was once the Count St. Evermont! It was a name that, down through centuries, Came freighted with the weight of glorious deeds, Entailed on time hereafter. I have spent The precious hoard, and now disgrace remains. And yet my sword! my sword is left me still. Come forth, thou minister of great revenge, And let me feel that thou canst pierce his heart, And vindicate a father. Godf. I have seen it, When nations met in death's hot revelry, Where all the onset burst with fiercer rage, Flash swift destruction from your whirling arm, And fall with ruin's weight upon the crest Of high plumed war. I well remember me, (For I had followed) with this very sword You climbed the steep, and scaled the battlements; Then plucked the standard of our France's foe From off the tower that flamed with batteries. St. Ever. 'Tis gone: and as it had never been. 'Tis gone, and like the golden palaces, That, on the ridges of a gorgeous mount, The setting sun-beam in the purple west Builds with the vapours of a summer's eve, The pageantry of fame has passed away. Why is not memory buried in the tomb Where hope is laid at peace? Who cannot hope, Ought not to recollect. This little sword! 'Twas given me by my king, to be the mark That I had merited. It is as bright As from the scabbard when I drew it first; And on the polished surface of the steel There's not a tarnish of consuming rust. Godf. 'Twill yet be true: it is an ancient friend. St. Ever. And therefore, Godfrey, should it not be trusted. For friend is now another name for villain. Friend is indeed less grating to the ear: 'Tis like the crooked adder's speckled skin, And hides beneath the venomed perfidy. And yet, perhaps, this sword will not desert me. For, though the load of time is on my frame, (Misfortune has leagued itself with time) There will be that within a father's heart, To rise triumphant o'er its withering sway. Thou follower of calamity, come with me. Enter Madame St. Evermont, Adelaide, and Julia. Mad. You shall not go. Adel. I will entwine my wretchedness. The bony gripe of death shall never tear A father from my arms— Mad. I am your wife: With you I have been blest and miserable: And misery doth endear— Julia. Look upon me: Oh! hear the wailing sounds of supplication! Adel. I left you: infamy is on my head: My soul is black: I am not fit to live: But yet I am your daughter. Hear it, hear! You shall not shed your blood upon my soul: By the great parent of the universe, I will not, must not be a parricide. My father! oh! you shall not burst from hence; You shall not break the chain that nature links; For I will hold you with a furious strength. I feel the force of madness in my arm: Now who shall tear me hence? St. Ever. Hold! honor, honor! Julia. Honor! Shall honor case you o'er in iron? Shall that fantastic thing that's made of air, An empty sound, a word without a meaning, The fruit of fashion's ideot wantonness, Impel you on destruction? Mad. Hear me, hear me! See nature flings herself upon your way: She clasps her hands, and, weeping in entreaty, Arrests your course. If you have ever loved, (And sure you often swore it) in the name Of that blest day when first I called you mine, By all the happiness which we have known, And by the recollection of our joys, And by the mitigation of our sorrows, And by the memory of our murdered Albert— St. Ever. Thy tears, my Emmiline, unman my purpose. Mad. Tell me, St. Evermont, have you e'er thought That I have taken from adversity A single pang, and been of comfort to you? St. Ever. Ah! Emmiline! Mad. Then you will not desert us? Adel. Why do you weep? why do you fear it now? For, see how fast I hold him chained around, And oh! he gently lifts me to his bosom. I will not let him die for Adelaide. St. Ever. O thou! if on this sphere of misery Thy providence looks down from mercy's throne; If man be still thy care, and one whose head All ills of human life have hailed upon, May dare to pray: Creator of the world, When I am laid within that silent place, Where not one sigh can reach, and not one tear, Protect these wretched ones. Without a friend, Upon this earth all desolate and lost, They need the fostering of thy vigilance. Be thou the husband of the widow's grief; Be thou the orphan's father. O my wife, My Julia, and my child! do you not feel With what an agony I hold you here? It is my last embrace. Mad. Your last embrace! St. Ever. There is a prophet here— Adel. Then kill me first: I shall be judged before a father's blood Can dye my spectre red! When I appear, A thunder will be heard in frighted heaven, And from its cloud a trumpet will proclaim ‘Behold the parricide!’ St. Ever. No, Adelaide! If I should perish; and perhaps the dew, In twilight's hour, will fall upon my corpse, I'll go before thee, and I will implore That he should pardon. Mad. Think, there will be none To be the sentinel of misery: There will be none, with tender watchfulness, And all a parent's sweet solicitude, To guard our Adelaide. Do not abandon her: I then shall be no more, and in the tomb Lie down with thee to an eternal sleep. What will become of her? St. Ever. Spare, spare me this! Mad. The bitter blast of poverty will blow The garb of virtue from her shrinking form. St. Ever. Revenge, revenge! by hell's eternal flame! Away, unloose me! I will hear no more. Adel. My father! Mad. O my husband! Julia. Hear me, hear! St. Ever. Yet one last look; one glance of human weakness; And now for ever! Heaven have mercy on them! [Exit, followed by Godfrey. Julia. Where shall I lead you? Mad. Julia, to my grave. [Exeunt. [Manet Adelaide.] Adel. Gone to be slain: the fountain of my being! The deep of hell hath heard it, and the damned Hold festival below: the shout of joy Bursts from the center and assails my brain. Enter Albert. Alb. 'Tis she: and if that wild and woeful look Proclaims aright, grief maddens in her soul. My sister? no! Yet horror shakes my frame: Six years have passed away since last I saw Her morn of beauty, when a convent's walls Received her in their holiness. My sister? I dare not ask: I fear to be resolved Adel. Why do you look upon me? Has a voice Gone forth, and through the world proclaimed the deed? Is all mankind then risen up in arms To purge the earth of its contamination? What would'st thou then with me? If 'tis to see The child that slew her father; here, behold me. Alb. To know the worst is better than to doubt it. If it be she: if it be Adelaide! Adel. Call me not Adelaide: it is a name Too sweet, too tender, and too innocent. It was the name of her whose father raised His arms to heaven, to call down blessings on her. But he was never heard: for curses fell As thick as midnight dew upon the night-shade. Alb. Whate'er thou art, still will I pity thee. Adel. And can you pity me? You are a man, And I'll not trust your tears. You do but mock me. Alb. Be comforted. Adel. Be comforted! Alas! You mock me now indeed. Alb. I cannot bear it. I'll burst this veil of mystery at once. What art thou? Speak. Adel. My name is parricide. My father lived upon my very smiles: He used to say they were the cure of grief: And when he pressed me closely to his breast, He called me by each gentle little word That can endear. I ope'd the sepulchre To his old age: I'm covered with his blood. Alb. I'll work a horrid vengeance: I am Albert, Albert St. Evermont! Adel. (shrieks) Preserve me, save me! If from the regions of the dead thou comest, To bear me with thee: if thou art the shade Of Albert, sent a delegate of wrath, To lead me to the pestilential tomb, Oh! mercy, mercy! Alb. Think not I am dead. Would that I were, and had not lived to see My name polluted by thy loose desires, Thy damned incontinence. To hell's abyss I'll hurl thy lover first; then fling thee after, On beds of fire to dally in his arms. Adel. But thou wilt save my father? Do with me E'en as thou wilt. But fly: be swift as light, And overtake the fates. E'en now, perhaps— Wilt thou not save him? Wilt thou let his blood Be spilt upon my head? Away, away! Nor tarry here to kill me! I myself— Oh! for a bowl of cold and freezing death To quench this raging furnace. [Rushes out. Alb. Oh! distraction! Enter Julia. Julia. It was a burst of louder grief, and came To rouse the weeping stillness of my sorrows— What do I see? Is this a sweet illusion, The conjured image of my buried love? Or is it Albert? Art thou here indeed, That destiny may never part us more? Alb. Alas! that we should part in adverse chance, And meet in agony! These tears, my Julia, Are not of joy. Alas! why do I live? And yet 'tis sweet to see thee ere I die. It was a prayer was heard indeed above, But oh! how is it granted? Julia. Alas! my Albert! I never thought to look again upon thee. I wept unceasingly: full many a kerchief Grew heavy with the weight of fallen sorrow. Yet is there a forgetfulness of grief In thus beholding thee. Alb. I must not hear thee! A woman's softness melts within my heart, When great revenge should halloo in my ear, And give the tyger's fury to my purpose. Julia. You know then all. Alb. Aye, all! I know that shame Is piled in mountains. Say, where is my father? Julia. Thou wilt not, Albert! Alb. When she bade me fly, It seemed the wandering of a frenzied mind: But now thy face speaks horror. Heaven! my mother! These limbs refuse to bear me to her arms. Enter Madame St. Evermont. Mad. What voice, more lovely than a seraph's hymn, Arising in the sadness of the night, Came on my ear? 'Twas memory's melody. Oh! 'twas a voice I oft have heard before, And most familiar to a mother's ear. And there—it is his vision, sent on earth To mitigate the excess of desperation. And do I see thee? Dost thou weep upon me, Thou image of my Albert? Dost thou come To bless and solace my distracted heart? Alb. I do not marvel that you gaze upon me, E'en as the stranger of another world: But while I press thee to my bosom's heave, Let every sense inform thee that I live, And live to love thee. Mad. If it be a dream, Let me dream on for ever. Closer still Clasp me yet nearer; strain me to thy bosom, That I may feel that fond and sweet embrace, That would persuade me that my Albert lives. It is himself: my son: it is my Albert: My son: my triumph. Julia. Thou wilt pity her, Howe'er thou deal'st with me. Mad. My son, my joy, weep not: or, if thou dost, Shed tears of wild o'erflowing happiness. Dost thou not live? Art not come back to me? Yes! heaven is merciful, and sends thy love To lift me up from prostrate misery, And cure me of affliction. Tell me, Albert, What angel came in death's terrific hour, And saved thee for thy mother? Tell me all, Didst thou oft think of her who wept for thee, Who bore thee, suffered for thee, loves thee, Albert? Alb. Do you not feel convulsion in my heart? 'Twere better that I ne'er had seen you more, Than in the place of high impetuous joy, Which fancy promised, horror should await me. Mad. What means that sigh? Why dost thou turn away, And wilt not let me gaze upon thine eyes, And feed my soul with nature's exultation? Oh! I am happy! let all ills rain down: Let me be poor, unpitied, and despised: Let me go forth in shivering beggary, To ask a crumb of bread, and be refused: Let me behold the closing of the night, And strew my bed upon the drifted snow: Be heaven my roof, the world my habitation, I will be happy still, for I have found him. My son! my son! (kneeling down and praying) I thank ye, heavens! I thank ye. Alb. Where is my father? Mad. (shrieks) Ha! Alb. That blasted form, That dreadful cry, proclaim it to my soul. Oh! for the movement of a spirit's wing, Borne on a thought across the universe, To be salvation's minister. Julia. My Albert! One glance, one last kind look of parting love, To treasure in remembrance. Albert! Albert! [Exeunt Julia and Albert. Mad. Why am I made the very jest of heaven? It was enough to weep upon his grave, And see him dying in my midnight dream: But 'tis too much to raise him from the tomb, To give him to my arms, that death might rush And tear him back again? It is too much. But I will bid defiance to the stars, And laugh at destiny. My son, my daughter, My husband, all! a widowed childless thing! Fate, try to make me feel another pang, To rack me with another agony. Know, when you spoil a mother of her joys, And take her children, she may laugh at you. Welcome despair! come, fiend, possess me all, Give to mine eye thy stony vacancy, And blast my cheek with thoughtless desolation, That wheresoe'er thy spirit lead my walk, All may be horror. Let no mother dare To meet me then, for I will look upon her With such a fixed, a wild and hopeless eye, That she will catch contagion from the gaze, And kill the infant sleeping on her breast: To clasp it there, and hug the certainty That it is dead indeed, and ne'er will come To make her fierce, and desperate, and mad. [Rushes out. END OF THE FOURTH ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT V. SCENE I. The Ruined Abbey.—Storm. Enter Adelaide, with her hair dishevelled. Adelaide. Flame! winged angels of the rolling storm, Ye blessed lightnings, lead me to my father, Conduct my tottering steps—flash, burst the gloom, And light my desperation. I will save him, I'll throw myself between their gleaming swords, And murder, frighted with a daughter's shriek, Shall stay his bloody purpose. Oh! relent, Thou tyrant death, relent a little while, Stay thy cold potion from my sinking heart. Alas! it will not be. The potent draught Has chilled the lazy current of my blood: It freezes o'er the fountains of my life. But I will save him: one fierce fight with death, One burst of furious strength. E'en now perhaps The fatal point is turned against his breast. It will not be! the drooping of my soul Sinks down, and feebly languishes to earth. [She sinks down, then starts up. I swear by nature 'tis impossible: He must not fall: he cannot: parricide! There's no such thing: it is a crime so dread, The blow would shake the universe, and rock The throne of God himself. I'm sick at heart. (Enter Lunenberg.) Lun. A deep-drawn sigh came lengthening on my ear: Again: what form of haggard wretchedness Heaves from yon sepulchre a tottering frame? It cannot be: it is not Adelaide: Or if it be, strike here: be merciful. Adel. (rushing up to him.) And hast thou killed him? Is he dead, quite dead? Oh! thou hast murdered him, for here is blood, Hot steaming blood, it trickles from thy hands. Didst stain thy sword with life so sanctified? Didst look upon his face, and couldst thou do it? Hadst thou no mercy on his hoary head? Hadst thou a father? Was it not enough To leave the child no refuge but the tomb; But must it redden with a father's blood? But speak: but kill me: tell me how he lies: How stiff, how cold, how drenched upon the earth: The winds all howling round his mangled corpse: Congealed the gaping of each ruddy wound: And the white sightless balls, up-raised to heaven, E'en as they were, when in the pant of life, He lifted them, and cursed me as he died! Lun. Hell take me down; for whatsoe'er is hell Is heaven to this. Adel. Yet shew me where he lies. Perhaps he did not curse me: he was gentle And ever kind. Then, shew me where he lies: Perchance upon his ghastly countenance Forgiveness lingers in a livid smile. Lun. Grant, grant me that I never had for thee! Charge not thy father's murder on my head: Have pity. Adel. Then he lives: my father lives! I loved thee, Lunenberg: heaven knows I loved thee With all my sex's fondness, all its folly: My heart was full of thee. Thy darling thought Was in my bosom a perpetual sigh, And wet my pillow with delicious sorrows. To hear thee speak; to watch thy wandering eye; To feel thee breathe, to touch, to look upon thee, Was all the paradise of Adelaide. With thee I could have wandered through the world, Have thought it happiness to die with thee. I could have borne each way of sufferance, The pangs of scorn, of want, and poverty, And loved thee better still. Beside thy couch I could have sat a watchful sentinel, When sickness weighed upon thy throbbing brow, And wished its aching mine: and when you slept, I would have gazed enamoured on your face. Yet do not think that at your feet I lie, And raise my hands in fainting supplication To charge my injuries upon your head. But if you ever looked on Adelaide And half relented, while you see me thus, If you can pity me, oh! spare my father, Spare him! and though this wretched heart be broken, Though I deserved another fate of thee, I will forgive thee all: here I kneel down And clasp thy knees: and spare, oh! spare my father. Lun. Oh! do not look upon me, Adelaide, With such a meek and supplicating grief, But start and be a fury: call the bolt Red from the storm: arise and execrate! Thy fainting form, that feeble tremulous clasp, The tears that trickle from thy closing eye-lids, Those lips where utterance vainly strives to move, And dies upon the pallid quivering, Reproach more bitterly than imprecations. Adel. Oh! I will die in blessed peacefulness, Since thou hast pledged that soft benignant look. The hand of sacrilege should ne'er be raised Against my father's life: and Albert too, Thou wilt not harm a hair upon his head; For he alone, when I shall be no more, Is left to assuage their sorrows. In his care They will forget a most unhappy one. Lun. What here! upon a tomb! these tender limbs, As soft as down on wings of cherubim, Exposed to all the fury of the blast, The sport of the contending elements! [Draws his sword. Adel. What would you do? Lun. I would appease thy wrongs: Then wilt thou say, that he was never yet Who loved with half that madness of the heart Which taught me first to wrong, and then avenge thee. Adel. Thou most unkind, to think it. Could not all The fond devotion of thy Adelaide, (Still let me call her so) Could not my heart, That beat responsive to each throb of thine, Inform thee of my love? But look upon me, Look here upon this pale emaciate cheek, Where once the rose had strewed its brightest bloom, Look on the form which you were wont to praise, Look on me now, and tell me if I loved you? These tears are all my vengeance: live for me. Lun. Dost thou not hate me? Adel. Hate thee, Lunenberg! Lun. My wife! oh! let the fondest constancy, Let all the purity of wedded fires, Thou spotless innocence, thy wrongs repair. Yes! I will live, and know the softest bliss That pours its morning radiance on the soul. With thee I'll fly where sound shall never reach Of this vain world. The scorning eye of man Shall never pierce the verdant screen of woods Within whose bosomed solitude our years Will glide, a lapse of unperceived decay. In some lone island of the farthest sea, Where spring for ever dwells, and every grove Blossoms perpetually, will we seek A beautiful asylum, and our lives Shall wear as sweet an evergreen of love. Adel. Why this is fancy's cruel wantonness, That paints the visions of futurity Upon a winding sheet. Lun. Still is there hope Of pure and hallowed happiness. Adel. Alas! Yes, there indeed is hope of happiness, But not upon the surface of the earth, Amid the breathing regions of the air. Oh! Lunenberg, it tears my heart asunder: 'Tis here, and now 'tis there: let, let me die. Lun. What pang, what horror deepens in thy face? What strong convulsion shivers through thy frame? Thou shalt not die! Adel. Support me, Lunenberg, For I would pray. Oh! thou almighty one, Let these last pangs, with which my toiling spirit Goes forth to meet thy wrath, atone the deed That hurried me before thee. I was wretched, I could not live. O heaven! have mercy on me! And visit not my crime. Protect them: save them: Give back their country. Take me, Lunenberg, Within thine arms; and then this raging fire Will flame less fiercely in my tortured bosom! Lun. What hast thou done? An horrible suspicion..... Adel. I saw my father rushing into death.— Encompassed with distraction, wild with ruin: I seized a draught of death: who would have lived? It is a sea of fire within my breast. (Lunenberg starts back in speechless horror.—Enter Madame St. Evermont and Albert, bearing his father's sword.) Mad. I do adjure thee by the name of mother. Alb. I'll hunt him to the limits of the earth. Mad. What! here! before me! then I'm lost indeed. Lun. Who's he that with a loud and boisterous voice Disturbs despair? The death-bell tolls: come, listen to its peals, Nor break upon the solemn harmony. (Adelaide rushes up and seizes Albert; her mother arrests the arm of Lunenberg.) Mad. A mother sues! Alb. I'll rouse thee from thy trance, (strikes him) thou coward! Lun. Coward! (He draws his sword, then flings it from him.) Let the dawn of fame, Bright as the rising of the golden sun, Kindled with glory, let the page of war, Let this attest it. (He rushes upon the sword of Albert: Adelaide shrieks.) Mad. Albert! oh my son! I did not, after all my mother-pains, Embrace thine infancy with half the joy With which I hold thee now. Alb. Where is my father? That I may render back this bleeding blade, Misfortune's bright avenger. Lun. Thou hast freed me: And whatsoe'er thou art, I thank thee for it. How sweet a lethargy comes on my soul! The blood that rioted now ebbs apace, And passion's torrent stagnates. Adelaide! Where art thou, Adelaide? This gushing life Is all that I can give, in reparation Of all the wrongs I've done thee. We shall lie down together in the grave, And when the sound of heaven shall rouse the dead, We shall awake in one another's arms. Speak to me: let the voice of Adelaide Still breathe its sweetness on my deafening ear. My eyes cannot endure the glare of light; But I will cast a last long look of love, And gaze my soul away. Where is thy hand? I'll lay it near my heart. Oh! Adelaide! (dies.) Mad. Hide, hide me from that dreadful spectacle. Alb. Sure horror never swayed a form so fair! Her eyes stream moonlight. [Enter Julia.] Julia, never yet Was comfort wanted more, and never yet It came more sweet and lovely! Julia. Art thou safe? And am I blest indeed! Alb. If Albert's love Can bless his Julia. Julia. Oh! poor Adelaide! Enter St. Evermont, followed by Godfrey. St. Ever. Is't done? am I revenged? art thou my son? Alb. Receive the sword entrusted to my hand. St. Ever. I am again the Count St. Evermont! My son, the glory of my aged days, Thou unexpected succour of misfortune, Worthy of France and her nobility, Thou bright reflection of my warrior youth, My stay, my exultation, and my son. I gave thee life: thou hast restored my honor: And by so much as honor's more than life, I owe thee more! (he sees his daughter) My child! support me, Godfrey, I would weep. Mad. Look on me, Adelaide, I am your mother! Bend not your eyes on airy emptiness, But turn them here, as you were wont to do In happier hours. Look on me, Adelaide! Adel. Hush! hush! he sleeps: thy cries will break his slumbers. I too could rend the air with shrieks like thine, For there's a torch alighting in my brain: But I'll not do't, lest he should wake. Look here: He has ta'en my hand, and holds it to his bosom. Does he not love me? Look: how calm a sleep: Ha! here's a drop of blood: who has done this? I do not feel the beating of his heart. St. Ever. Remove her from the corpse. I did not think That there was sorrow left within the cup Of my afflictions. This last drop is bitter. [Albert attempts to remove her. Adel. You shall not take me from him. Help, there, help! He is my husband! Wake, my Lunenberg! They take me from you: wake! Oh now I have thee: Now am I wedded to thee: who shall part us? Who says we are not wedded? Let them say so! I care not: let us fly, and mock the world. Awake, and we will seek some far-off desert, As lonely and as burning as my brain. How the hot winds will blow: the whirling sands Will rise in fiery mountains on our heads, And bury us together! O my heart! [Dies. END OF THE FIFTH ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">EPILOGUE. BY H. W. ESQ. Spoken by Miss Walstein and Mr. Farren. Miss W. You can't be serious, Sir. What shall I do? Ladies and Gentlemen, I appeal to you: Will you permit me, if he persevere, To ask this stranger, what's his business here? Mr. F. I'm in for it. There's no retreating now: And first to make my very best stage bow; Next, aid me, impudence! and let me dash on, An enterprising amateur of fashion, Sent by the London managers express, Against this play to venture an address. Miss W. Well, Sir, when I have done, you may proceed. Mr. F. But, after you've prevailed, could I succeed? How vain the effort! What a risk to run, To win the ears Miss Walstein once had won! Miss W. So bold and so gallant, though just on shore! You've been, I guess, on Irish ground before. Mr. F. Or, if you please, another plan we'll try: I'll urge my strong objections, you'll reply. Miss W. Agreed: with this provision all the time, That while we reason, we must try to rhyme. Mr. F. And first, as precedent the rule affords, New plays should issue from the London boards. Miss W. By their decrees, forsooth, we must abide, And their decisions teach us to decide. Mr. F. Besides, it violates the London ton: No modern play can hope to have a run Without some troops of cavalry. Miss W. To draw O'er the fallen drama and the drama's law An idol engine through the scenic plains, And see it crush John Bull's devoted brains! Mr. F. But what's a modern play without a battle? Drums, trumpets, cannonade, incessant rattle, Horses and men together, dead and dying? Miss W. Children and pigs, and geese and colours flying! Mr. F. Spectacles all. Let those, who wish to rise As authors, write to nothing but the eyes. Miss W. Is this your taste? this, Covent-Garden fare? Sight, the sole faculty you worship there? Though small our scene, though so confined our sphere, 'Tis not the only sense we practise here. Mr. F. Nay, but the tempting intellectual treat Of witnessing a grand equestrian feat, Where every rider's rooted to his seat! Some damsel fighting on a snow-white steed! At every lounge a dozen Tartars bleed. Miss W. How woefully must Dublin critics blink, Till Astley's jockies teach them how to think! Mr. F. The play wants incident. Too cold to charm, It has not heat enough to keep us warm: No passage that inflames: no castle's blaze Burns bright and brighter on the dazzled gaze! Oh! give it, pray, a brilliant termination, And end it in a general conflagration. Miss W. The piece wants fire, you think? Mr. F. No doubt about it: No piece has ever yet gone off without it. Nothing but men and women in this play! Why men and women we see every day. Heavens! with what civilised exalted rage, Would England hoot it from a London stage! Miss W. A stage? A stable: a preposterous mew, Where wild beasts are exposed to public view; Where brutes, as human as their keepers, toil All day, in rigorous study, to beguile John Bull at night of his Athenian smile; Where sabres clash, dogs howl, and horses neigh, Young virgins shriek, men shout, and asses bray; Where elephants, in more enlightened rage, Shake their unwieldy fury o'er the stage. Beasts of all kinds the beastly chaos throng, And tortured puppies yelp the dismal song. Oh! what an age! where brutes of every stature Act plays ‘to hold the mirror up to nature;’ And what a theatre, where every ass Delights to see himself in such a glass! Mr. F. Siddons and Kemble, who adorn our time— Miss W. Are less attractive than a pantomime. She, of her art the first, has disappeared, Her matchless powers and judgment unimpaired. At distant intervals her brother seen, ‘Like angel visits, few, and far between.’ Now could I ask, and even to you refer, Which of these exhibitions you prefer? Whether the horses, elephants and bears, Grimaldi, and the rest of Pidcock's players, Hurry from side to side like frighted hares, Or Kemble's chaste magnificence of mien Touch with a living grace the polished scene, Or, like a nobler god of war, appear, And scare the Volscians with a Roman cheer, Rejoicing in the noon of glory's fierce career? Again I'd ask, again refer to you, Which scenic splendour would you rather view? Towers all on fire, and reeling ere thy fall, Flames fiercely preying on a pasteboard wall; The rosin-flash betray the dread design, Our stage-artillery blowing up a mine, While the vast building to its centre shook— Or Siddons blasting Stukely with a look? Oh; then the moral luxury to trace, Virtue's pure anger mantling o'er her face, Like eve's fine glow spread o'er a summer sky, And all the lightnings of her glorious eye. Mr. F. There's no disputing on a point of taste. Miss W. Then we'll adhere to that we think the best. Our bard too young, too timorous yet to rise, With trembling pinion tempts his native skies: Will you forgive, indulge the venial flame, That burns so early for an Irish name? Let this one truth be proved by this essay, An Irish audience haile an Irish Play. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>