<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Johnson, Charles, 1679-1748</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Johnson, Charles, 1679-1748</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">johnson charles 1679 1748</field>
      <field name="author_text">Johnson, Charles, 1679-1748</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">18th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1710's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V2.0280.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1713</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:459995</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Successful Pyrate ; A Play</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Successful Pyrate ; A Play</field>
      <field name="title_facet">successful pyrate</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">successful pyrate</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Successful Pyrate ; A Play</field>
      <field name="year_display">1713</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1713</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1713</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459995&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459995&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Johnson, Charles, 1679-1748&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;johnson charles 1679 1748&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Successful Pyrate ; A Play&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;successful pyrate&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1713&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1713&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Johnson, Charles&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1679&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1748&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Successful Pyrate&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Play&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for Bernard Lintott [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1713&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872335-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv20280&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 18th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;18th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Successful Pyrate&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Play&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 191 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: The successful pyrate.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragi-comedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1713.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 7 Nov 1712.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE Successful Pyrate. A PLAY.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Ne, quicunque Deus, quicunque adhibebitur Heros. Regali conspectus in auro, nuper &amp; Ostro, Migret in obscuras humili sermone tabernas, Aut, dum vitat humum, nubes &amp; inania Captet. Hor.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PROLOGUE. Spoken by Mr. Wilks. In ancient Days, when Poetry was young, She sung her Labours to the vulgar Throng, Artless and unattir'd from Door to Door The Goddess wander'd, innocent and poor. In Magick Verse her moving Fable dress'd, And the rude World, at once both taught and pleas'd. When that old Bard appear'd, whose Verse with Time Keeps Pace, but never will decay like him; Yet Homer, tho' immortal were his Lays, In that dark Age scarce got him Bread and Praise. At length the Stage of Athens rais'd her Head, With grateful Joy receiv'd the virtuous Maid, And call'd her Daughter Musick to her Aid. These beauteous Painting join'd, and the gay Scene Gave new Delight, the Pencil grac'd the Pen. Now they unite to please our Reason's Taste, And with immortal Food the ravish'd Fancy feast, By them dead Worth revives, old Heroes Rise, And with dissembled Grief, give real Joys. Without the Toil the distant World you see, And view all Nature in Epitome— This Stage has long with home-bred Fops been cloy'd, And ev'ry shining Coxcomb here enjoy'd: Our Author, therefore, willing to delight, Begs Leave—t'import a Fool or two to Night; While young remov'd to Africk's warmest Bed Transplanted Slips of the true English Breed. Then—When our Musick bids the Curtain rise, And shows the shadow'd Landskip to your Eyes, Let powerful Fancy your weak Faith beguile, Believe your selves in Madagascar's Isle. Behold the Men and Manners of the Place, We'll make your Passage easie cross the Seas: The Curtain—in three Hours, will drop again, And set you—safely down—in Drury-Lane.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Dramatis Personæ. MEN. Arviragus, King of the Island of St. Laurence, or Madagascar. Mr. Booth. Aranes, an Omrah in Zaida's Train. Mr. Wilks. Boreal, Admiral to Arviragus. Mr. Mills. De Sale, Lieutenant to Arviragus. Mr. Keen. Richardo, Captain of the Guards. Mr. Cory. Piracquo, De Sale's Creature. Mr. Husband. Sir Gaudy Tulip, Master of the Ceremonies. Mr. Pinkethman. Chicane, a broken Lawyer. Mr. Norris. Jollyboy, Treasurer to Arviragus. Mr. Leigh. Judge Bull. Mr. Bullock, Sen. Serjeant Dolt. Mr. Bullock, Jun. Counsellor Smooth. Mr. Pack. Herring, Member of Mobb. Porpoise, Member of Mobb. Shark, Member of Mobb. Codshead. Member of Mobb. WOMEN. Zaida, Aurengzebe's Grandaughter, contracted to, and in love with Aranes. Mrs. Porter. Semanthe, her chief Attendant. Mrs. Cox. Lydia, Piracquo's Wife. Mrs. Spiller. Lesbia, Tulip's Wife. Mrs. Sanders. Attendants, Guards, &amp;c. SCENE the City of St. Laurence in the Island of Madegascar.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. SCENE I. SCENE the Port of Laurentia, Ships in the Harbour, and a fine Country in Prospect. Enter Piracquo and Boreal. Bor. What, always preaching Sedition? Pir. But hear me, good Admiral. Bor. Such disquiet Spirits as you are the Bane of Government, the Wens of the Body Politick, and should be cut off, to preserve its Health and Beauty. Pir. I say this Arviragus, who rules our fruitful Island, has been a Pyrate—I hope 'tis not Treason to speak Truth. Bor. No, you know it is not; his Fault, his only Fault is Mercy: If it were Treason, you would pin your Tongue within the Portcullice of your Teeth, and not dare to mutter an Accent, but burst with your own Venom. Pir. You misconceive me; I love the Man, and therefore shou'd be glad to hear his Virtues. Bor. Don't I see all your Blood turn to Gall, and a squalid Paleness overspread your Face while I praise him; but you shall hear his Story, because I know 'tis the greatest Torture I can give you.— Pir. Come on, Sir; I'll oppose you with his Faults: Is he not extremely violent, and intemperate in his Desires? Bor. Granted: A Hero shou'd be so; that immoderate Desire of Power, that unquenchable Appetite of Rule, has been long dignify'd by the Slaves of Tyrants with the Name of Virtue; but he is no Tyrant, therefore 'tis Virtue in him to desire Power. Arviragus is a Briton, he was my Fellow-Subject—Now he is my Prince—His Country, his Friend and his Mistress, in his Youth, all us'd him with the utmost Ingratitude, for the most faithful Services. Pir. Nay, nay; what, always repeating the same Tale, humming the same dull Tune— Bor. You shall hear it, tho' you waste a Drachm a Word— He commanded a Fire-ship in the Dutch Wars, I was his Lieutenant: I saw the Boy, for then he was no more, intrepid in the midst of Fire—Yes, I saw him all in Flames grapple the tall stout Hollander—In vain her missive Lead and Iron Deaths hiss'd round us; the Showers of fatal Hail flew thick, and pierc'd our burning Canvas—Board and Board we lay, he was the first and last in Danger—We saw 'em both blow up, the dreadful Shock in a tumultuous Eddy whirl'd the Waves, and almost overset our Long-Boat. Pir. Well, he dares fight; we know he loves Danger, so does a Bull-Dog and a hatch'd Egg—Are not you a little vain, Old Gentleman, of the Feats of your Youth? Ha! Bor. I am, I glory in it; hadst thou been there, thy Soul wou'd have gone out, like a Taper in a damp Vault, with the Sweat of thy own Fears—Well, Sir, he return'd, and as the Reward of his Gallantry, he was broke, and made incapable of ever serving more— Pir. No, no, there you are out—that was for caning his superior Officer, who refused to fight him. Bor. Right! He call'd a Coward by his proper Name, and beat him to prove it—Well, to add to this grateful Return, he found his Friend had entirely deny'd his Trust, had cheated him of his Estate, and was marry'd to his Mistress—I've heard him call that Fellow Villain—but he forgives the Woman, for he is a perfect Master of Gallantry as well as Courage—I think his Friend's Name was Mavoli. Pir. He stings me to the Soul. O cursed Fortune, to throw me on this hated Shore, on this abhorr'd Island, where Arviragus is Lord. [Aside. Bor. Thus spighted at this World, he sought a new one, declared War upon Mankind, renounc'd the Rights he was born to as a Member of Society, and fixt himself here on his own proper Basis, which how well he has maintain'd, be this fair Island, of which he is sole Monarch, my Evidence— Pir. Nay, nay, tell thy Tale out, Man; you see I keep my Complexion; the Indian Expedition. Bor. There he was shipwreck'd, there he fell in Love, and marry'd the bright Zelmane, an Omrah's Daughter; by her he had a Son—I've heard him oft lament his leaving him, and threaten to make a Voyage on purpose to retrieve him, and settle him here his Successor; that is the utmost Scope his Desires now seem to aim at. Pir. Notwithstanding all you have said, he is still only an overgrown Thief— Bor. Ha, ha! Prithee Clod, whence sprung all your Demigods? What was the Divine Son of Ammon? What was Julius? What have their Purple Descendants been? I laugh to see a Scepter'd Robber at the Head of a Hundred Thousand, truss up a poor Caitiff as an Example to the rest of his Brother-Theives, for stealing two Eggs out of Form, while he is burning Cities, ravaging Countries, and depopulating Nations. Pir. Wou'd you have all demand a Right to all, as Savages in the simple State of Nature? Hah! Bor. Why, the worst you Hypocrites of Order can say— and I think 'tis to his immortal Honour—is, that he has leapt the Pale of Custom, and is a Royal Out-law; he has erected himself a Throne, ay, and in the Hearts of his People too; reduc'd Barbarians—Romulus was made a God for this; yes, and what I think more glorious yet, bound and cemented by civil Laws a Race of Vagabonds, the Out-casts of the Earth; and thou art one of 'em, but a malignant Knave, that wou'd breed Faction in Hell, rather than want Employment. Pir. Nay, now you lose all Temper. Bor. Are not you a Coward? Pir. Is a Coward then, brave Sir, a Whet-stone? Bor. Ay, for he sets an Edge on another, without being able to cut himself—I forgive you now, take Warning tho', and preach no more Faction to the Mob.— Pir. The Mob—very good, in my Opinion, there are no Degrees of Comparison here—Tell me now with Temper, is there one among us you ever spoke well of? Bor. Because you are all Sheep in Foxes Skins—I never rail at Rogues, but Fools—your half-fac'd Villains, who paint but one Side—Now to hear a thing like thee make Pretences to Knavery— Pir. You can't heat me, Admiral, I pity you, I know you rail by Complexion, as Jollyboy our Treasurer is always merry, you are always angry; yet neither can you help your Sourness, nor he his good Humour—'tis Constitution—Who's that comes this Way? Oh, Sir Gaudy Tulip, the Master of our Ceremonies— Bor. Yes, I like him, that Fellow is no Hypocrite, his Genius always lay to Trifles, and he has all his Life indulg'd it, therefore he is only study'd in Tea-Tables, Women, China, and Snuff-boxes; his Age indeed sometimes afflicts him, and he dreads the Glass he us'd to doat on. Pir. Oh, the Head of an old Beau is seldom long discompos'd; 'tis a sort of Ever-green, and, like your Box and Holly, flourishes in Winter. Bor. That Scull of his is indeed a lightsome Garret, a happy Void. Pir. How came he here? A Beau in an Island fill'd with Sailors and Pyrates? Bor. I'll tell you: Tulip had an Intreague in his Youth with a Covent-Garden Madona, whom he for twenty Years together mistook for a Dutchess, 'till, as it sometimes happens in these Cases, his Mistress and his Estate took their Leave of him together; when finding the Secret, and that his Credit in old England had given up the last Gasp, he wisely projected to transport himself, with a Cargo of Essence, Snuff and Powder, to the West Indies, and there marry for Subsistance; but the Ship was taken by Arviragus, and Tulip thus happily preferr'd, to the only thing on Earth he cou'd desire, or deserve— Enter Tulip. Tul. Lord Admiral, your most Obedient—Piracque yours— Pir. Health, and eternal Beauty, worthy Knight. Bor. Ah, supple thy Back, dear Sir Gaudy, it creaks like an old Door, that turns upon a rusty Hinge—Spare thy Complements, and thy Chine, thou worthy Son of Musk and Civet— Tul. Ha! Tart as a Barberry; ever smart upon your Friends, but 'tis the Token of your Esteem. Pir. You must bear with him, my soft Knight—he is a wholesome Sour. Tul. Ay, a sort of Sauce to Company, call'd a Sevil Orange, that's good. Pir. And you are the Veal to his Orange: Now Sir Gaudy. Tul. Ha, ha, good again! I'd give a thousand Dollars my Set of Foreteeth were arriv'd, that I might have the Privilege of laughing aloud at my own Jokes— Pir. I think you lost 'em in the Service of your Wit. Bor. A Dutch Boatswain knock'd 'em out for railing against his Whiskers. Tul. Ay, the Tarr was choleric, unbound my Gums, and I never made a biting Jest since—the Fellow tho', bating his Whiskers, was otherwise an honest Water-Rat. Bor. Why, can't a Man have moral Honesty, and wear Whiskers? Tul. That is doubtful; for why shou'd a Fellow who is not naturally barb'rous desire to look like the Saracen's Head? But I'll meddle no more in't, Admiral, 'till I have Laws made to support me. Bor. Thou shalt be aided by the Civil Power; we'll have all our Girls bred Sempstresses, and our Boys Barbers. Tul. I'll have a Statute made to encourage the Importation of Starch and Taylors, it shall be Fellony to wear foul Linnen, and High-Treason to smoak Tobacco; what is that nauseous Weed good for? Bor. Why, it digests our Thoughts, and our Dinners. Tul. Ha! then we may know when the Meat is a boiling by the Smoak in the Chimney—Look'ee I'll draw up a Remonstrance, and represent the State of this Island to our King Arviragus; for whatever you may imagine, your Country is inhabited only, not peopled; you cover your Nakedness, but you don't dress; you talk, but you can't converse; you devour, but you never taste; and you make Love, as you dine, without Ceremony; so that your Tables, your Cloaths, your Company, and your Mistresses are wholly Inelegant; in short, you only hate Nastiness, just enough to forbear eating one another. Bor. And you'll turn a Nation of Tarrs into Beaus; do you invent your own Fashions, or keep a Correspondence with the polish'd World? Tul. At present I am oblig'd to Europe, and I find by our latest Advices from England—They wear fring'd Gloves there. Enter Jollyboy. Joll. New, News, my Boys of Mettle, my Lads of Oak, and Canvas, there's a Sail brought in worth an Empire's Ransom— Women and Gold Boys, Plenty of both—the only two valuable Blessings of Life are arriv'd in Laurentia, and landing this Minute. Bor. Of what Country? Where taken? When thy Joy will permit thee, give us the Particulars. Joll. Of India, the Ship was found busking on the Seas, without a Mast or Rudder—There's such a Blaze of Jewels, Beauty, Gold— Tul. As have extinguish'd the Eyes of thy Understanding; be brief and plain. Joll. The Grand-daughter of the Great Mogul is taken, with her whole Dow'r and Train: She was, it seems, contracted to the King of Persia; this Ship was transporting her, but Fortune has convey'd it, and her, and all, to the Arms of her dear Favourite Arviragus; Arviragus resolves immediately to view the Prisoners, and make an equal Distribution of the Spoils; you are commanded to Range 'em all in order in the Palace. [To Tulip. Tul. I'll be there in a Moment; now will I hold six to four, the Princess likes me before any Man in the Island—How do I look to Day, Boreal? Bor. Why, when you grin thus, your tann'd Countenance looks like the Head of a roasted Rabbit. Tulip. He, he, ha! let me be bit by a big-belly'd Woman that long'd for it, if you are not very facetious; but Business calls, I have no Time to lose in Words—Gentlemen, your most Obedient, and most Faithful Humble Servant. [Exit. Joll. You are likewise commanded to attend in Council. [Exit. Bor. I'll follow you. Fortune, who governs with Caprice her darling Children, and dashes her best Gifts with Gall, is constant only to Arviragus; she heaps her Favours on him, loads him with her Blessings; for every Rising-Sun smiles with some new Addition to his Wealth and Glory. [Exit. SCENE Changes to the Inside of the Palace: Enter on one side two or three Omrah's and other Men Captives: And at the upper End of the Stage, Alvarez and Aranes: On the other side Morulla, Mariana, Lesbia, Lydia, Semanthe, and Zayda, all veil'd; and Tulip busily disposing them in Order. Tul. Sir, you'll infinitely oblige me, if you'll move one Step forward—so, there Madam—Diametrically opposite to that Gentleman; a little more to the Right, dear Sir, for we must form a Semicircle with an opening at each end, that the King may more conveniently make his Choice as he passes thro' it. [Ranging the Prisoners on each side. Aran. I have my Wish, Alvarez. Alv. What Wish, my Lord? Aran. These Chains. Alv. I understand you not. Aran. We ignorantly kneel, and pray for Curses; How often have I askt, with fervent Vows, That Heav'n wou'd make my Fortune equal Zaida's. Behold us in Captivity the same. [Pointing to Zaida. Behold that Royal Maid, whom Yester Sun Confest the Brightest Jewel of his East, Tho' there, with Beams condens'd, he labours Light, And ripens Drops of everlasting Day, A Daughter of Imperial Aurengzebe, The Captive of a Pyrate—oh Alvarez! Error and Fortune rule us. Alv. Worth in Distress, like a high rising Spire, Is nearer to the Gods, the less it looks To mortal Eyes— My Lord, the Valiant are in Battel try'd, Adversity is Virtue's glorious War, And when the Mind, still present to her self, Stands unasailable these Shocks of Chance, She darts Immortal to the Realms of Light, And triumphs over Fortune, and the Grave. Aran. 'Tis true, Alvarez, Heav'n has sav'd my Love, Fom Persia's Arms—yes this Captivity May prove a Blessing, if those blisful Powers Guard us; if suffering Virtue be their Care, Zaida is some Fair Angel's special Charge. Tulip. [who has been all this while ordering the Prisoners, bowing to the Princess, speaks to the Lady next her.] Most Beautiful, let me, in the most obliging manner, beseech you to retire one half Step; you obscure the Princess; dear Creature, let the Sun shine—Ladies, Ladies, for the love of Order, stand back, the King has his Choice, 'tis true; yet but one of you can fall to his share; There can be but one Queen, and she, who commands all Hearts and Eyes, has by Nature a Title to Empire; and he must be a Traytor to Love and common Sense, who does not acknowledge the most Illustrious Zayda—tho' I must sigh my Life away in vain— [Trumpets sound. But Hark! our Sovereign appears. Enter Arviragus, De Sale, four Gentleman, Trumpets sounded, &amp;c. Arv. De Sale, the Spoils are truly rich and noble; What is the common Sailor's Dividend? D. Sale. To each particular Head five thousand Dollars. Arv. Let 'em be paid without Delay or Fee: [To Jolly. Your Life shall answer for a Doit detain'd From any private Man— I'll have no Greasie Drones of Civil Power, Fat with the Spoils of Widows, and of Orphans, Spunge like, to suck the Blood of the poor Soldiers. D. Sale. Therefore they pay Obedience for Protection; Therefore they love and fear you. Arv. Have they not rang'd the Globe to serve my Cause; With me they made a Circle round this World, Disclaim'd Relation, Country, Friendship, Fame, They toil'd, they bled, they burnt, they froze, they starv'd, Each Element, and all Mankind their Foe, Familiar to their Eyes saw horrid Death, In every Climate, and in every Shape, When, in this Isle, our shatter'd Barks found Rest, With Universal Voice they call'd me King. And when th'Oppressor laughs, when Right and Wrong Intangled lye in Law; while Wealth is Judge, When Merit begs despis'd; while Justice sleeps, Or winks for Bribes, unpunish'd, may I fall, Like some o'erweening Tyrant, who believes Himself a Law, and Governs by his Lust. Aran. He talks this well, Alvarez, what's all this [To Alv. But Rapine and Injustice?—Are we then By right his Slaves,—Insolent, haughty Pyrate. Alv. We're now within his Power; 'tis therefore rash And reasonless, my Lord, thus to provoke him; See, he observes us. Arv. What's he, De Sale, who furls his youthful Brow, Impatient of his Fate—His manly Arms Embrace himself, his Eyes are fixt on Earth, Behold the flushing Blood bounds o'er his Face, And with a generous Pride disclaims his Chains, Unbroke to Servitude, the stubborn Boy Seems better to despise, than bear his Fortune; Know you his Name or Quality? [To de Sale. D. Sale. Aranes is his Name; his Followers say His Birth is Noble,—Mighty Aurengzeb Chose him the first Attendant of Bright Zaida. Arv. I have been taught, young Man, by various Fate [Coming forwards to Aranes. To use my Power with Mercy; here no Slaves In Barb'rous Triumph grace the Victor's Wheels. Unmanacle his Hands; be free; if here [They unchain him. You will reside, you shall have Means, and Honours, Justly proportion'd to your Worth and Virtue; And, if there be a Mirror in the World Worthy to hold Mens Eyes, 'tis our Laurentia; But if the Love of your own Native Soil Delights you more, you shall have Conduct Home. Aran. I thank you, Sir; you shew a worthy Mind; You've found the Means to make me more your Slave; You know that Gratitude, to a large Heart, Is a much stronger Bond, than Links of Iron. Arv. Unveil the Women. [Tulip unveils the Women. Aran. I tremble, my Alvarez, a cold Sweat Hangs on my Brow, an Ague shakes my Soul, Foreboding Fears, and jealous Pangs invade me; I cannot bear the Thought of losing Zaida; He has a Conqueror's Right, and she's his Slave. See, see already he has catch'd the Fire, His burning Eyes drink the fresh Beauties in, And greedily devour her Charms; Those Orbs of Light, the Windows of the Soul, Confess it all—Counsel me, aid me, Friend; Oh! I am Lost— Arv. De Sale, I never saw so fair a Creature; There's a bewitching Softness in her Eyes; She sinks into my Soul—I have her here; Why did you suffer all this Flood of Light To burst at once upon me! 'twas too much, I shou'd have fall'n obliquely.— Aran. Have I not all my Fears; yes, over Measure, [Aside to Alva. He says he's just; I'll throw me at his Feet, Tell him our mutual Love, that Zaida's mine, By Contract mine; that we've sworn no Time, Fortune, nor Wealth, nor Power, nor Force shall part us. Alv. Do, tell him you're his Rival, let him know That you must be secur'd ere he is Happy; Recall your Strength of Mind, this is unmanly. Arv. Uplift thy Eyes, fair Excellence, and Reign; [To Zaida. Accept what I can give, my Throne and Heart. Too mean the Sacrifice, but 'tis my All, Receive then what my zealous Duty pays; For were I Lord of all th'Ambient Sea Flows round, I shou'd not then presume to think I cou'd deserve; High Heav'n has sent you here, Imperial Maid, to found a Race of Kings, To be the Mother of a mighty Nation, For late Posterity shall see your Line Dispensing Laws, and dealing equal Justice To Nations round us! Zaid. Beauty too oft, like false Ambition, Sir, Mounts its unhappy Owners but to fall; Like shining Lights unguarded set on High, By every adverse Wind to be extinguish'd. Why do you talk of Reigning to your Slave, And mock a Wretch you hold in servile Bonds? Arv. By Heav'n, my Eyes, lost in that Beauteous Prospect, Beheld not these unworthy Marks of Slavery. What Savage durst inchain these Snowy Twins?— [He unlooses the Bonds. Let all her Followers be unbound this Moment, Be every Captive free; the Sun this Day, [They are unchain'd by Arviragus's Officers. Wherein the Royal Zaida chear'd our Isle, Shall see the wretched happy; let 'em date Their Liberty, as I my Life, from Zaida. Forget your Cares, forget your Father's House, And deign to Rule, and smile upon Laurentia. You shall have Time with Decency to mourn This Change of Life, till constant Services Have wean'd you from your Sorrows, we'll conduct you To an Apartment fitted to receive you, Your Ladies shall attend you; our whole Court Have our Commands to serve you; I cou'd say We must obey by Force; but Words wou'd wrong thee. For praising thee, is Painting of a Rose Refin'ing Fire—with a weak Taper's Light Decking the Eye of Heaven! [Ex. Arv. leading Zaida, and all Exe. except Aranes and Alvarez. Aran. Who wou'd not grasp at Empire, wade thro' Blood, Confound all Right and Wrong for such a Prize, Since by the Means he sanctifies the Vice? Happy Arviragus! thy Power, call'd Right, Now leads thee to Imperial Zaida's Arms. Is it not so, my Friend? Injurious Gods! Why was I form'd with such exalted Passions, And thrown into Plebeian Clay; the Mock Of fickle Fortune, and contending Winds? Alv. When the fermented feverish Blood boils high, The Patient restless turns from Side to Side, Tho' Motion blows the Flame;—Ev'n so your Mind Creates the Mischief, and encreases it; All may be well—He knows not yet your Right, And he affects to govern here with Justice; Therefore he dares not do an open Wrong; Perhaps he would not— Aran. Did she forbid his Hopes? Did she once steal A Look, to ask a mutual Sigh or Tear? Did he not press her Hand, call her his Queen? As such he led her hence—That jealous Throw, Like an envenom'd Dagger, strikes my Heart. Alv. You'd call another base, who utter'd this; You know her Truth, now visit her and prove it. Aran. O my Friend! I wrong her—yes, I basely wrong my Love, I know she is as chaste as Infant Dreams, And true as dying Martyrs to their Faith. I'll visit her—Suspicion is unworthy A gallant Mind, and yet it haunts and burns it; Pale Jealousie, that Child of Fear and Love, Does both our Passion and our Frailty prove: Our Brittle Forms, unable to sustain Unchanging Joy—we ebb and flow again; Alternately we Pain and Pleasure feel, Immortal Raptures only, with Immortals dwell. [Exeunt. The End of the First ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. SCENE I. SCENE the Hall of a Palace. Enter Boreal and Chicane. Chi. 'Tis contrary to Law: Draw Lots for Wives! Bor. How now, Lawyer? What, a worthless Fellow, and afraid to trust Fortune—Look round thee, and behold her Darlings. Chi. Ay, but things are not done in Form, not Legally, Admiral— There shou'd have issu'd out a Writ de Uxore Capiendâ, with a Precept to the Sheriff, and a Fi. Fa. annex'd, to have levy'd the Bodies of the several beautiful Women, &amp;c. and have brought 'em before us such a Day apud le Guild-Hall in le Pall' Royal'. Bor. Pox o'your Gibberish. Lawyers Tongues have made more Beggars than Luxury or Dice. Nature produces nothing that is immortal but a Chancery-Suit. How many noble Estates have I known ground to Death between the Milstones of the Law, while an old Dunce in a Coif pores thro' his false Eyes, to discover whether the good or bad Success of the poor Subject's Cause depends upon the doubtful Tittle of an i, or a deficient Top to an l. Chi. Ay, ay, I know with you now all our Pleadings are despis'd, and our Reports laugh'd at, and Cook, Dyer, Lennard, Croke, and the rest of the voluminous Historians of contentious Mortals, are Fellows of Form, without Fire—But to the Point, Sir; The Prince here ought first per Attorn' suum to declare; then we have time to plead; he replies, we rejoin; he surrejoins, we join Issue; then comes a Demurrer, then a Writ of Error, then 'tis argu'd, then an Appeal, then— Bor. Oh, don't make me giddy with thy Nonsense, dear Insipid— Chi. Look ye, in the Case of Marriage— Bor. Ay, in the Case of Marriage—a Man's Understanding is so often bubbled by his Eyes, that our wise Prince, to prevent the Evils of our own Choice, resolves Fortune shall determine the whole Matter—But see, they are here; and for all this, thou unrighteous Judge, thou must be content with the Wife thy Chance shall give thee. Chi. Quo Warranto, Sir—'tis contrary to Magna Charta. Enter Jollyboy, Piracquo, Tulip; and on the other side, several Women, Lydia and Lesbia; a Laurentian Boy, in the native Habit, with a Jar fill'd with Balls of Wax for Lots. Joll. Hah, my Golden Hearts, my merry Boys, Children of Joy and Pleasure, a gracious Prince, a bounteous Sovereign, he has chosen out the finest Women in the Island for you; and Heaven and you know 'tis but thinly peopled with Petticoats— yet further, he has order'd me to pay 2000 Gold Ducats a Head for every Wife drawn by Lot amongst you. Pir. Pox, who wou'd drink Poison for the Honour of kissing a Gold Cup? Tul He has taken the only Dish from the Table I cou'd fancy, and advises me to sit down, and feed very heartily for Life, upon whatever is casually set before me. Pir. 'Tis an Imposition upon the free Subject. Joll. What, Man? We must mend the Breed, we must provide for Posterity; wou'd you have him leave a whole Nation of Sons of Whores behind him? Tul. Look ye, I'll breed for ne'er a King in Christendom— he may marry me, that is, I may have a Wife de facto, but Zaida is the Sovereign Mistress of my Soul de jure—Gad, she is a fine Woman, Piracquo—He has cull'd the Top o'the Basket, and left us nothing but what is Worm eaten and Wind-fall'n— But let it go, I shall have an Intreague with her; I have already squeez'd her Hand, and fathom'd her Heart by her Eye— I shall mend his Breed, if he goes to that. Chi. You confound the whole Matter with your de facto and de jure, Sir Gaudy—We are to obey the King in all that is lawful; now 'tis lawful to marry, but things are not done in Form, and therefore may be superseded per curiam. Bor. I wou'd have no Lawyers marry here—Heav'n bless us! if a Pettifogger shou'd be join'd to a Scold—what wou'd be the Offspring? A Fury; Discord in Flesh and Blood— Such a Conjunction must produce either a Casuist or a Rebel, and be the Parent of Faction in future Times—Now Treason is the Child of Faction, which, like Sophistry, makes Knots in Truth, and cuts what it can't untie—Come, come, prepare for your several Lots; let the Boy go round. Tul. Adieu my Liberty, my Peace, indolent Joys, and sweet Repose—Ye happy Hours of Love and soft Desire—Adieu. Come, Boy, I am ready for Execution. Lyd. May Fortune give me to him again, Lesbia, if that is not my Husband. Lesb. And as I live there stands my very old Winter Tulip. Lyd. Have we ran 3000 Miles from each other to meet in this Centre? Lesb. I find I am born to break that Beau's Heart—It vexes me tho'; I thought we shou'd have been wholly unknown here. Lyd. The Sight of that Fellow has given me an incurable Spleen—Oh Lesbia, I am Husband-sick to Death. [The Men draw several Balls, in which are enclos'd the Names of their Wives—Piracquo draws Lydia, Tulip Lesbia, Jolliboy Morulla, Boreal Mariana, and Chicane an old Woman. Pir. Ay, here she is in neat Italick—Lydia, my very Identical, Numerical London Wife—Why, this is giving a new Bond for an old Debt. Tul. Hah, what have we here? Lesbia, as I hope to be happy —Fortune is an unmannerly Huswife—Is this weaving your True-Lover's Knot, to give one up to the Arms of an old Acquaintance, and make one Tenant for Life to a Goal? Pir. I never lov'd Chance; but Fortune unravels all the Plots I work up, and makes me, whether I please or no, drag her Chain—Now she has made me a Present of a Wife— So, Madam, [To Lydia] What malignant Star threw you upon Laurentia? Lyd. What evil Genius brought us two together? Pir. I abandon'd my native Soil to fly you. Lyd. I banish'd my self, that I might not breathe the same Air. Pir. You are the only Woman I wou'd have shunn'd. Lyd. You are the only Man I wou'd have avoided. Pir. Fortune shan't join us. Lyd. I'll die to break the Knot: Have we not sworn everlasting mutual Hatred? Pir. Cursed be he or she who first is perjur'd. Lyd. When I break it, may I be as common as a Bed in an Inn. Pir. When I don't observe it punctually, may I lie in the same Bed. Lyd. May I be as ugly as a Death's Head, may my Desires outlive my Charms, and may I sue to thee for Mercy. Pir. May I pity thee. Lyd. Your Hand on't. Pir. Agreed. Lyd. To disagree. Pir. Eternally. Lyd. For ever. Tul Very elegant truly; a happy Couple, a perfect Copy of conjugal Affection—really you have said abundance of civil things to one another, and now the Heat of your first Courtship seems to be a little over I wou'd treat with you, Piracquo, will you change? Pir. For a Fool's Laugh or a Strumpet's Smile, I'd give thee my Life to boot rather than keep this Bargain Tul. No Passion, my dear Piracquo—look ye, I believe it may be prov'd I have as many Obligations to that Lady as you owe there; I had the most delightful Dream with her for twenty Years together—sure never was Man so agreeably deceiv'd—Oh how I curs'd the Hour when first I wak'd, and found her Grace the Dutchess de Bellchose to be a plain Plebeian, vulgarly call'd or known by the Name of Cecily Ogle. Lesb. My Dear, we have already explain'd upon one another. Tul. My Love, I am easie, I know 'tis not in the Power of blind Fate to shuffle us together again—You have had my Estate. Lesb. You the Dutchess—You were in love with my Quality, not my Person. Tul. Therefore 'twas natural to drop the Passion with the Character. Lesb. We were both Actors, 'twou'd be ridiculous to wear the Habit when the Farce is done. Tul. Yet for a while, like old Bed-fellows, we turn'd our Affections the seamy Side outward, and were awkardly kind to one another, 'till we cou'd not endure our own Hypocrisie. Lesb. We liv'd together 'till Indifference had extinguish'd Jealousie, 'till Anger gave Place to Neglect, and Pity quitted to Contempt. Tul. This was the Process—first Love kick'd Reason out of Doors, where Reason like a cool Privy-Counsellor waited patiently 'till after Possession, and then summoning the Posse Com. of my Senses to his Aid resum'd his Seat. Madam, is it your Pleasure that we play booty with Fortune, put a Trick upon our Stars, and be happy in spite of one another? Lesb. Sir, I play all the Game—I have from my Youth upwards been the Workwoman of my own Happiness—You see this Gentleman and I are not like to hit it. Tul. A Bargain—one hearty Wish, my Dear, and so we part,—first may our Friendship still continue like a Vine round a dead Oak, tho' our Love is expir'd. Lesb. May that Lady give you as much real Joy, as I have Imaginary, may no rude Wind uncurl your Wig, no stormy Days nor Time it self plow up your Features. Tul. May you flourish like a Medlar, be delicious in decay. Lesb. May you like gen'rous Wine get Strength by Age. Tul. Piracquo, observe, this 'tis to be well-bred, this is parting politely—Gad I am mighty well off tho'—I was in a Sweat when I saw her come up—Ho! Admiral, what luck have you had in this Lottery? Bor. Why I have drawn a Prize, Tulip, the Sun sees not many such in all his Circuit—I have ask'd her several Questions, and either she has no Tongue, or she holds it—take it which way you will she is a very valuable Woman. Tul. Ha! Then she'll keep a Secret. Bor. Mighty well, if she can't speak. Tul. How do you like our Wives? we have barter'd, Piracquo and I have chang'd Hands, what think you of these Fillies? Bor. Tho' I am not much skill'd in Phisiognomy, I can read in both their Faces, separate Maintenance, Alimony, Divorce, Adultery, Doctors Commons, Curtain Lectures, and Cuckoldom —That Leer cou'd be learnt in no part of the habitable Globe but Covent-Garden. Chi. I have a Woman here too Gentlemen, if any Man wants a Wife and brings his Action of Trouver against me, I'll plead guilty, or he shall snap Judgement by Default—For toss me over the Bar, if I don't think she is the most execrable Creature I ever saw. Bor. Poor Chicane, she is indeed a plain Woman—What sort of Mate is thine, Jollyboy? Joll. Ha, ha, ha, faith she is pert and small like Lambeth Ale—tho' I am mighty well pleas'd in troth my merry Boys, she has given me two or three biting Repartees—If your Wife wants a Tip to her Tongue, we can spare it. Bor. No more, the King appears. Enter Arviragus, De Sale, and Attendants. Arv. The laughing God now plumes his purple Wings, He lights his Torch, and smiles on lawful Love, The Libertine may boast various Delight, The Slave of every Lust may talk of Freedom, He feels it not, his Joys are false and short, He wants within his home; true Happiness Is found alone in chaste unsully'd Sheets: We hold our self indebted to each Man Who gives the Common-wealth a Legal Heir, For Marriage is the Bond of Government, That Cement fixes us by Natural Ties, By joining our Affections to our Interest. Each Monarch Husband in his private Realm, While he with virtuous Order rules his House, Pursues the general Good—obedient Children Make faithful Subjects—therefore we ordain'd This Lottery of Love you all must win, And Fortune often chuses better for us Than we our selves. Tul. Ah sweet, how he gilds this bitter Pill? Pir. Now he has clapt on the Clog, he perswades us to play with it—This Fellow wou'd talk a Nation out of their Senses, and their Liberty too. Arv. My Fellow-soldiers, we resolve to follow Your good Example, and with holy Vows Inchace our Love; high Heav'n has deign'd to smile, And with a Star t'enrich our Diadem. Imperial Aurengezebe's Illustrious Race Shall govern your Posterity—Away, Each with his several Bride, and may this Day Be ever markt with White to latest Years. Pir. I am horribly vext, but there's no Remedy yet. [Exeunt all but Arvi. and De Sale. Arv. I sent by thee to ask bright Zaida's leave To visit her; say, did you see the Princess? De Sale. I found her all devoted to her Sorrows, The silken Lids, those Curtains of the Sight, Half vail'd, gave way for the warm Tears to flow, The precious drops hasten'd to kiss her Cheeks, And bathe her rising Bosom; where her Sighs, Sweeter than bloomy Nature, or the Breath Of wanton Zephyrs, did indulge her Grief: I spoke your Message, Sir; she rais'd her Head, Reclin'd upon her lilly Hand; her Hand, Softer and whiter than the Cycnets Down. She said, and then another Sigh broke way, She hop'd she might have leave to mourn; if not, She was your Captive, and she must obey. Arv. I think thou art her Lover by thy words, This warm Description fires my amorous Breast, I see her charming in her Sorrows dress. Oh my De Sale, this sudden change of Life Shakes her soft Frame, As every change of Air stains the pure Chrystal, I'll wait upon her, sooth her gentle Grief, And by most constant Service gain her Love. Whoever thus does for bright Beauty burn, Must with the fickle Fair one laugh and mourn; His Passions all must her Commands obey, For Love's a Lord of Arbitrary Sway. [Exeunt. Enter Aranes and Zaida. Aran. The joyous Light glads our extended Eye, And feeds with various Paintings the gay Sense; The Balmy Air breathes his redundant Odours Till the Brain akes with too luxuriant Pleasure, Sweet Musick tunes and lulls the wanton Spirits In most Extatick Raptures—Thou art all, The Light, the Breath, the Musick of my Soul, Thou Abstract of all Nature's Charm's in one. Zai. And yet ev'n now my Love, A pointed Sword hangs by a Hair above us. Arviragus, malevolently kind, Beholds they hapless Zaida with Desire. In awkward Pomp he woes me, and has sent By his Lieutenant to intreat a Visit; It is not fit he see us thus, that Sight May raise a fatal Storm, and wreck us both; Think whose we are, and where.— Aran. I idly talk, And only beat and flutter in my Cage, When I shou'd Act; redeem thee with my Sword, But Time must fashion it. I know it is not fit he see us thus, My Love, I will retire: oh Death to part! May those unbody'd Spirits who enjoy Uninterrupted Bliss, look down with Pity, When they behold a Soul like theirs distrest, And guard thee with Ætherial Wings from Danger. Zai. Gallant Youth, May all the Gods preserve thee, may each Maid Who truly loves in all succeeding Times, Be bless'd as I in thee—And may thy Name Shine a bright Instance to Posterity Of faithful Love. Enter Arviragus. Arv. Hold, hold, my Heart! there, there's the Cause of Sorrow, The Reason of those Tears; Let me controul my Temper, and be calm.— If your Sorrows, Madam, Admit the Wretche's Comfort, a Companion, I humbly beg my Share; when Beauty droops, The Sun shou'd mourn behind a sable Cloud, The Southern Winds drive down the Tears of Heav'n, The Flow'rs and Plants shake off their dewy Grief On the damp Earth, and sympathizing Nature Sigh with her fairest Work— Zai. Blame me not, if I'm covetous of what I only now can call my own; these Tears, They will admit no Fellowship, and ask For Solitude; Grudge not your Slave her Sighs. Arv. You have a Gracious Princess, Sir, she deigns To let you share her Melancholly Hours, And gives you what a Monarch begs in vain. Aran. As I have felt the Sunshine of her Fortune, My Gratitude, as well as Duty, Sir, For ever binds me to my Royal Mistress, And asks a Subject Tear for her Distress. Arv. No more of this; why do you meanly thus Disguise your Loves? Hypocrisie is base. I see those Tears are shed for your Aranes, And does not your Aranes weep for Zaida? Aran. Then you see Two Minds in one, a grateful Harmony Which you wou'd turn to Discord; but remember, 'Tis not in Seas, or Prisons, or lawless Power, To break this happy Union—Rigid Fate Will but a while divide us; after Death My separated Soul shall hover round her, Her Genius here, and Guide to Paradice. Arv. Fair Zaida is the Gift of Providence, As such I take her—no Tyrannick Wish Shall urge my Power to violate her Will. Aran. This, Sir, is generous, and truly great, 'Tis God-like to bestow unbounded Bliss, And we have no Ambition left but Love. Give us some Corner of your Earth to breathe in, Disturb not the clear Stream you cannot drink, Let us possess our Lives in Peace together. Zaid. Oh, Sir, renounce this Flame; my Lord and I Have mingled Souls like meeting Streams: Can you divide the Waters Drop by Drop, And reunite 'em to their former Currents? Can you command the glorious Light to stay, When the Sun leaves us?—Our two blended Hearts Are riveted by Fortune, Time and Fate. Arv. Fortune has made you mine, and changing Time May rzae that darling Image from your Soul, And place me there—Aranes is my Captive, The Creature of my Smile—whom my good Sword By just Invasion holds. Aran. Invader's but a Royal Term for Tyrant. Arv. That I am no Tyrant Let this declare, that you dare call me so Unpunish'd—Yet my Subjects general Voice Proclaims that Falsehood faithful in all Dangers— But know, fond Youth, I here am Absolute, The Founder of Laurentia's mighty Empire, And greater thus than if I claim'd my Right From a long Line of lazy Ancestors: Look round the World, search the Records of Empire, What were their Titles first? First, Power form'd Laws, When gracious Victors did descend to rule By equal Justice—The same Power gave Place, And fixt me here on fair Laurentia's Isle, I gave 'em Laws, and dropt the Conqueror's Sword To rule by Civil Right. Aran. Then wherefore do you break your own Commands, And thus invade another's Right, my Zaida? Arv. Know thou that all are Tyrants in their Love, There each wou'd Monarch be, and rule alone, There I dispence with Law; ev'n thou, my Slave, Claim'st a superior Right to love above thee; Still love, but do not to my Ear avow it, Stifle thy haughty Passion, and be safe, Tis Death to own it here. Aran. Not own my Love! (Now wert thou King of Hell, As thou art but his Deputy, and rul'st His Subiects here) thus wou'd I loudly claim her. She is by Faith, by Inclination mine, By all the Ties of sacred Love and Duty, Nor shall thy Power disjoin us, bloody Pyrate. Zaid. This Rage, Aranes, will destroy us both. Stifle your fatal Passion in its Birth, Or all is lost. Arv. Your idle Passion, like an angry Infant, Beats its own Parent; with your feeble Breath, You might the Ocean's Bosom blow to rage, And curl the Face of Neptune, but ne'er hope To stir my Mind. Zaid. Be calm—Inflame him not, you blow a Fire That will consume us both—Oh think betimes, If Power unbounded meets remorseless Rage— Aran. Yes, Zaida, all the Passion of my Soul Shall melt into my Eyes—relent in Dew, To beg a gracious Boon of my good Master. I am his Slave, his Creature. You gave me Liberty, you gave me Life! [To Arv. Oh! What is Life or Liberty to Love? Cou'd you command the Globe, and at my Feet Throw all Mankind my Slaves, I shou'd with Scorn Behold the Tributary World beneath, And only then look up to Heav'n and Zaida: Extended Empire, Freedom, Life and Love, Live all within the Circle of her Arms! What shall I say—thus bending to the Earth— [Kneels. I humbly ask more than my Life or Freedom; Oh give her yet—yet give her to my Arms, Restore my Zaida—Honour, Sir, and Virtue With me demand my Love. Arv. No more in idle Transports wreck your Spirits; But know, presumptuous Boy, no Power on Earth Shall ravish from my Heart this God-like Maid— Be gone, aspiring Fool— Claim not a Right to Heav'n, and call it Justice; Here she shall blaze like our warm Eastern Sun, The Royal Partner of my Bed and Throne. Aran. Imperial Thief, Despair and mighty Love Know no Command or Equal; guard thy Life— Zaid. Ruin, Distraction! whither will it lead you? Aran. I'll conquer, or I'll bravely die her Martyr. Lay by your borrow'd Robes of Royalty, And meet me with your good Sword Hand to Hand, Or by the Gods I'll speed the Rod of Justice, And dash this horrid Meteor into nothing, This Child of Earth and Vapour. Arv. A Guard there—Seize this hot-brain'd foolish Boy, Enter De Sale and Guards. Do him no Violence—Convey him hence. This I forgive—but never more appear Within my Palace Walls, on Pain of Death, Immediate Death—The next fair Cruise we have, Our Admiral shall set you safe on Shore, On the first Land he makes—Absence, fond Youth, May cool this boiling Fever in the Blood, Absence the Death or Cure of wounded Love. [Exeunt Guards with Aranes. Zaid. Oh, Sir, if ever you did Pity feel, If now you know the Pangs of jealous Love, If e'er your Heart glow'd with the honest Flame Of chaste Desires, and mutual Faith exchang'd; Wou'd you erect a Monument to last, Beyond all Æra's of succeeding Time, To break the Teeth of Envy and Detraction, Exert the Hero, and forgive your Rival, Be greatly virtuous, and command your Passion. Arv. Madam, I do forgive him, but his Rage With sudden Execution blows up all Who dare oppose him—Since he can't obey, I banish him—Here I will rule alone. Yet, Zaida, that is but a feeble Boast, For your Tyrannick Eyes are absolute. Zaid. I cannot feign a Falshood to my Love, To save us both; he must be mine for ever, There is no Cruelty but parting us. Arv. O talk not thus, sooth me with flatt'ring Hope, Or I shall lose my self in black Despair, And be a Tyrant to thee. Zaid. Embark us in a Vessel all unmann'd, Without a Pilot, me and my Aranes, Commit us to the raging Winds and Waves; The Winds and Waves, in pity to our Loves, Wou'd waft us to some hospitable Shore; Or we shou'd both be bless'd, and die together. Arv. Why do you stab me thus, too cruel Zaida! By Love, by Fate, by Fortune, thou art mine. I burnt beneath the fierce Æquator's Heat, Then steer'd to rougher Seas, where the wild North Rides furious on the mighty Ax of Heav'n; There twenty Years endur'd the warring Æther. Ambition urg'd new Toils—When Fortune smil'd, And crown'd me here, my Labour's fair Reward, Thee too she gave me, sprung from Regal Loins, To fix her Empire long—No, Madam, no, I owe this Justice to my self and you; Unerring Destiny has made you mine. Obey your Fate; 'tis Cowardice not Courage To struggle with the just Decrees of Heav'n. Oh plead not for him, and be fafe—Thy Words, Like subtle Lightning, blast my distant Wishes. Zaid. You say you value me; 'tis in your Power To give me Freedom, Life and Happiness, Yet you inexorable all deny. [Exit. Arv. O my De Sale, this Indian Maid undoes me, Laurentia's Sceptre strikes to Love's proud Boy; All the large Honours, Glory, Power, Fame, And countless Wealth, which I a private Man Snatch'd from the lazy Hand of Chance, to deck My Brows with ever-living Lawrels, fade, They fall—Oh Shame to Arms! A Woman's Martyr! She is Aranes Right—There Justice bleeds, And Reason flies the Field—my burning Blood Governs without a Rein. De Sale. She's yours by Conquest, make your lawful Claim By Heav'n and by your Sword. Arv. What has the Victor's Sword to do with Love? Th'impassive Mind can never be subdu'd By human Force—However, yet I'll strive. Women are changeable, and what to Day They hate to Death, to Morrow they approve. Time is the Nurse of Hope—Secure the Palace, That no Attempt succeed for her Escape; Then wait me in my Closet, your Advice May guard against this Rebel in my Heart. O thou gay Son of Venus, young Desire, Extinguish Thought, or quench this burning Fire; For when our Lusts against our Judgments rise, The purple Tide within to wild Disorder flies; The mighty Monarch's govern'd by the Croud, And sacred Reason's rul'd by the licentious Blood. [Exit. De Sale. I hate this Renegade, this Scepter'd Rogue: And why? Because he is but half himself. His Virtues share his Faults; ay, therefore 'tis, Therefore my Eyes abhor him—Oh pale Envy, Thou Vulture of the Liver, aid my Plot; I have debauch'd Piracquo to my Interest, And he some of his Favourite Knaves; the Mob Are stirr'd with diligent and monstrous Lies, Of Rapine and Injustice, Bugbear Laws Forming against their Liberties and Rights, While stupidly he dreams thus sunk in Love, He hears not of their Clamours. Well, I shall taste of Sovereign Rule and Beauty, For Zaida and his Throne shall both be mine. Why, but he loves and trusts me—Therefore 'tis I have the Means to ruin him—your trusted Friend Holds in his Palm your Life—Besides, this Beauty Employs him all; and therefore now I'll strike; In this Lethargick Love-Fit steal his Crown, And hurl the nodding Lumber from his Throne. [Exit. The End of the Second ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. SCENE I. SCENE A Court Hall. Enter De Sale, and Piracquo. Pir. Sedition is on Foot, my Boy; the Fruit is just ready to gather, there's a new Model of Government making up in every Shop. D. Sale. I am glad to hear it, Piracquo—'tis difficult indeed to breed Faction in a Country, where there is no Religion for a Pretence. Pir. And where Mony is a Drug; for here our Gold, like a fine Woman, has lost half its Value by being common. D. Sale. 'Tis a Master-piece of Policy to raise the Devil without a Bribe or a Masque, without Mony or Hypocrisie, nay without any Pretence of evil Government, against a Captain too I thought they doated on. Pir. They are us'd to a Storm, and are sick in a Calm; the Courage of the People, like a high mettal'd Horse, must be rid down by continual Exercise, or he throws his Rider; give 'em Action and you are safe. D. Sale. If I do mount the Head-strong Multitude, they shall level Mountains, and lave Seas, ere they want Employmett: But who of any Weight have you brought over to our Enterprize? Pir. Chicane, Jollyboy, and Tulip, three of his Ministerial Fools; for he has always chose Men of moderate Sense to serve him, because he wou'd have their Understandings, he says, all passive, and like the Limbs of the natural Body take their Directions implicity from him their Head. D. Sale. But he shall find we'll chuse another Head to his Body Politick; well, and were the Fools difficult to be prevail'd on? Pir. No, I gain'd on 'em by indulging their darling Passions. I affirm'd to Chicane, and prov'd by Sophistry, that Arviragus was an Usurper, and rul'd contrary to Law; he believ'd me, and cited Statutes made in old England to prove it. D. Sale. But how did you draw in Jollyboy and Tulip? Pir. Why Sir Gawdy was satisfy'd 'twas the last new Fashion, and Jollyboy is so perfectly good-humour'd he cou'd deny his Friend nothing; but Tulip has another Reason, he fetches such deep Sighs for the Princess, you wou'd think his Lungs grew in the Bottom of his Belly—He groans and sings (Love has no Power.) Indeed the common Rabble are generally disturb'd about this Declaration the Tyrant has publish'd, obliging 'em to take Wives by such a Day—Oh they roar out most musically against Arbitrary Power—But what think you, shou'd not Aranes be sounded, he is a Youth of Spirit, and hates, ay, and with Reason hates Arviragus. D. Sale. No, by no Means—a puling Lover in an Enterprize of Fire—I think I shall provide for him otherwise— Lovers and Madmen are govern'd by Fancy; a slippery Basis to support Action—Well, I have drawn a Scheme of our whole Design with special Directions for the Execution— We'll meet at eight at your House, let all concern'd have Notice— This Evening my Boy we'll strike for Liberty and Plunder. [Exit. Pir. When I reflect, I can't help wondring at my inveterate Pursuit of Arviragus—I can't forgive him, because I have wrong'd him; I hate him, because I know I deserve not to be lov'd by him—I loath my own Ingratitude, and yet like a harden'd Sinner trot on in the old Track, so difficult 'tis when Vice has Possession of us to regain our selves. But few, while young to vicious Habits bred In Age the thorny Paths of Virtue tread; If Strength and Reason can't the Torrent stem, Will weak old Age and Folly turn the Stream? The following Years crowd the preceding on, The rushing flux of Time rowls swiftly down, And ere we Leisure have to think, we drown. [Exit. Enter Zaida and Semanthe. Zai. Oh my Semanthe! How has my' Aranes's Passion, Th'intemperate Fire of Rage, robb'd me of all Our Lives are so entwin'd, in him I live, My Lords, my House, my Family, my Wealth, My Children; all—Indeed my burthen'd Heart Yet knows not to support the heavy Loss. Sem. Madam, your wounded Mind may yet be heal'd, But you with piercing Fears retard the Cure— De Sale, the King's Lieutenant, has profess'd A generous Regard for your Misfortunes, He begs as a Reward, the Honour only To serve your Highness; here his Trust is great, In him your Hopes yet live; he waits without To know your Pleasure: Zai. Semanthe, much I fear to be oblig'd; But drowning Wretches catch at Reeds; admit him. Enter De Sale. Thro' what strange Labyrinths, what entangling Mazes Will my hard Fortune lead me? D. Sale. So Venus look'd in the Idalian Grove, So mourn'd the Loss of her expiring Love, Ambrosial Dews from heav'nly Fountains shed With new born Flow'rs enrich'd her grassy Bed, Thus all the Graces, all their Beauties arm, Adorn her Grief, and make her Sorrows charm: Happy the Lover, who that Hour preferr'd His Vows, then every Lover's Vows were heard. Zai. These silken Terms, this gaudy Dress of Words Can bring no Aid; and yet when Fortune smil'd, My Mind was ever so in Love with Truth The Metaphor with me destroy'd the Musick: But oh, if your good Heart is touch'd with Pity, Behold an Object worth your Charity: A Princess thus sues in the Beggar's Phrase. D. Sale. You cover me with Shame—this to your Creature? Know Madam—I have form'd a Scheme to help you; Ere a few Hours expire, blind Fortune's Wheel Again shall lift you to your former Glory. In the mean time wou'd you not see your Lord? The King is in his Closet—Opportunity Stands fair—I know the value Lovers set On a stolen hour of mutual Conference. Zaid. My guardian Angel, Thanks—My bounding Heart Yet knows not how to pay her grateful Joy— Oh gallant, generous Man, my constant Vows Shall weary all the Gods for Blessings on you. De Sale. I'll post this happy Lover to your Arms; But let your Interview be short—or else It may prove dangerous, which Heav'n forefend, You'll find my Deeds as faithful as my Words. [Exit. Zaid. High Heav'n has rais'd this virtuous Man to help us, Inspir'd his generous Breast with godlike Pity; For like the Gods he graciously bestows, Without the hopes of a Return. Enter De Sale, Aranes, and Alvarez. Aran. I thank you, Sir, I know not how to wish you a Reward Beyond that Pleasure which Heroick Minds (When they perform a virtuous Act) receive. The Consciousness of a good Deed, exalts The Mind above the sordid Earth she wears: And she is more than half Immortal here. De Sale. Waste not your Time in empty Words on me, I am your Slave, my Lord, I know your Worth, And labour thus to give you Joys Immortal; For Death and Virtue claim 'em. [Aside.] [Exit. Zaid. Oh my lov'd Lord! Aran. My Heart bounds up to meet thee at my Lips, Oh take the little flutt'ring Wanderer in, Or let him grow thus to thy Snowy Bosom, And be th'Immortal Guard of Faithful Love. Zaid. I cannot tell thee how I love Aranes, Yet sure thou mak'st Captivity a Blessing; For when I see thy Face, I lose my Sorrows, Forget my Father, Country, what I was, And what I am; and all I give to thee. Aran. 'Tis not, ye Rulers of the World, in Power, In Wealth, nor all the glittering Train of Pride, To give the Mind true Happiness, 'tis Love, Tis mutual Love and Virtue. Zaid. De Sale, that truly great, that generous Man, Has vow'd to aid our Cause, we shall be free. Aran. We shall, and in some homely Villa live and love, Free from the Envy, from the Guilt of Greatness; We'll steal a private Life in Peace and Innocence, Our Air untainted, and our Table pure, When on the fragrant Earth, with wholsome Viands, We feed on Nature's Bounty—all around The feather'd Choristers, on pendent Branches, Shall grace our Artless Feast with Artless Musick— Our happy Fathers thus in blest Security, And rural Sweetness liv'd, ere Fraud and Art Invaded their chast Joys. Zaid. To hear thee speak charms my distracted Mind, And makes all calm within; but when I see thee, My greedy, longing Eyes wou'd gaze for ever Unsatisfy'd—Might I indulge their Joy, Swift Hours wou'd unregarded pass, whole Years, As in a gentle Slumber, steal away; The rapid Stream of Time wou'd, like one Moment, Flow back into Eternity again. Alvar. 'Tis happily remembred, Time flows fast, And Dangers here surround you, then be wise, Divide your selves, that you may meet again. Aran. Oh that we must, that we must part, my Love, Yet 'tis but for a Moment, our good Genius Works with De Sale to Insure our Happiness— Ministring Angels guard thee—Virtue stands Like a white Rock in Neptune's troubled Surge, And Winds and Waters impotently Rage. Enter Arviragus, De Sale, Ricardo, and Guards. De Sale. Behold, my Sovereign, your Rival there, Behold your Captive in your Mistress' Arms, She holds him in a Circle that the Gods Might envy. Zaid. Farewel—but Time will march a Leaden Pace, 'Till I behold my much-lov'd Lord again. Aran. 'Till then we live on Hope, that Flatterer Hope! But yet, remember, tho' he tires our Prayers, Tho' he fatigues our Wishes, he'll be lost, When next we meet, in never-ending Joys! [Exit. Arv. Hah! 'tis Despair, 'tis Death, my boiling Veins Will burst—So Madam—why d'ye start? I am a Statue King, and Owls may perch Upon my Marble Sceptre—Yes, you know it, Or I had crush'd this sawcy Slave to nothing; When first the haughty Worm presum'd to Love. Zaid. This Slave, in spite of Sceptres, here shall reign, The faithful Lord of me. De Sale. I must withdraw, she shou'd not see me here: The King shall act what wou'd make me appear For ever odious in her lovely Eyes; Thus doing all unknowing—Politicians Move like the secret Wheels of Fate unseen, By Second-Causes work. [Aside.] [Exit. Arv. Still wou'd I gaze, and still her Eyes behold me With Hatred and Contempt—Inhuman Fair! Yet be advis'd—the Rage of Kings is swift, And killing as the Thunder-Stone—You know That I can crush your Favourite, smooth Adonis. Zaid. This, Sir, is base; And now the painted Gloss of Virtue's off, I see a Bravo at the Head of Thousands, And a mock King bloated with ill-got Power. Arv. Disdainful Woman! My Heart already bleeds, unpity'd, mock'd, And shall it shed the Crimson Drops alone? Away fond Mercy—let the hopeless Cupid Be dash'd with Blood—pursue th'ungrateful Boy, And let the Traytor pay with Life his Crime Ye both Conspire—Hem him within my Guards, Then nail him with your Javelins to the Earth, Let this Ixion feel an angry Jove. [Ex. Richardo and Guards. Zaid. Hold, hold, you dreadful Ministers of Vengeance— Good Sir, recall your fatal Message quick, Now, now, remand 'em, ere the fatal Blow Is given—Oh Sir, Aranes' Life is mine, Then if you Love me, will you Murther me? Arv. Thy Words, fair Maid, like Honey-dews destroy What they shou'd save. Zaid. I see a tender Mercy in your Eye, Oh give it speedy Birth, and save your self And me from black Despair and Death— Why do you stop—Each Moment is Eternity— Away then let your generous Pity save him, Oh save him, Sir—reverse your bloody Doom, You will, you do, I see your Mind is mov'd. Arv. Thy Truth and Innocence against my self Have stirr'd me—but behold Richardo comes, I fear my Orders are pursu'd. Enter Richardo. Richardo, how were my Commands obey'd? Rich. We found Aranes in the Pallace Grove, He and his Friend Alvarez; when they saw us, Both drew, prepar'd to make a brave Defence, And Back to Back they firmly stood our Onset. Aranes' Eyes shot fire; the Stag at Bay Defies his Hunters so; his killing Sabre Uplifted, fell with mighty Slaughter round him, And dy'd with his Assailants Blood the Earth; At length, all breathless, and oppress'd with Numbers, A well-pois'd Javelin met his Manly Breast, The pointed Spear pierc'd deep; repeated Wounds Follow'd the deadly Blow—he stagger'd wide, His rowling Eyes struggled for Light in vain; Then with a sudden Turn upwards he sprung, So shot his Valiant Spirit to the Gods, And left the lifeless Lump of Clay behind In good Alvarez' Arms. Zaid. Enough; enough; oh mighty Sum of Woe! The Springs of Nature break, I am dismiss'd— Your Slave will now be free—Confusion! Night! [Swoons. Arv. Assist her, aid her; see she dies, Semanthe! What has my rash unthinking Passion done? But, like an Idiot, blown the Taper out That gave me Light and Heat—Indeed within, I find all dark and gloomy. Sem. A clammy Sweat bedews her Brow—her Breast Labours for Breath—she sighs, and Life returns. Zaid. Ha! are not these my Murtherers, Semanthe? Bleed, bleed, ye Veins, sluice every Artery, Give in your goary Evidence to Heav'n, Ask the Gods Justice—but they sleep, and careless Make their Vicegerents Tyrants—'tis a Fault; Hark, 'twas a Screech-owl's Hoot, the Bird of Night And croaking Raven sing Eternal Dirges, But I am hoarse, and cannot chant my Love, To his sweet Rest—Will you be good, and give me Some Flowers to strow his Grave—oh my poor Brain! Enter De Sale. Arv. This is a heavy sight—oh wise De Sale Now give thy Master Counsel, for his Heart Is grown too great a Burthen for his Breast. Zaid. I do not call thee Tyrant, Murtherer, Language has yet no Meaning bad Enough, No—but I'll tell a Tale of thee to Heav'n, Shall bar the Gates for ever to thy Soul; Not Penitence, not a whole Sea of Tears, Nor Mercy's self, shall wash thee white again. Sem. Your Wrongs must call down Vengeance from above, In the mean time asswage your Griefs with Patience. Zaid. Patience, the Slave of Fools, a Chain that's fixt, To senseless, lifeless, animated Nothings. Sem. Will your hard Fate admit no Comforter? Zaid. Is he not dead? has not the greedy Grave At once devour'd all Joy and Comfort with him? Confusion on all Comfort! I disclaim it. Comfort's a Parasite, a flattering Knave, Melts Resolution, and destroys Despair, The Soveraign Lord of my poor Heart and me: Look, the relentless Fiends with Wonder gaze On my vast Griefs, and dare not bid me hope. D. Sale. My Lord, your Presence here inflames her Hurt; Retire, till Time has worn it from her Memory: Women are violent in Grief and Joy. Like Infants, wail to Death for a fond Trifle, Which if not taken from 'em they despise, And throw neglected by. Arv. Oh cou'd I call some few fled Hours back! It may not be, I feel a Load of Guilt, And all within is Tumult— De Sale remain, and give thy best Assistance To that wrong'd Fair one—lost, unhappy Zaida! Zaid. What, does the King of Terrors pity me? Ye mighty Gods, where will you find New Scourges, When you inflict such Punishments, that Hell Feels some Remorse, and Fiends themselves drop Tears? But why do I complain of righteous Heav'n? And yet how like a Tyrant Justice looks, Without her Sister Mercy by her Side: See there he lies all pale and cold; 'tis Pity, Cover him, keep him warm, I'll bathe his Wounds, And hide him in my Bosom from their Fury: Alas, he's vanish'd—oh! D. Sale. Convey her to Repose, console her Loss, And meet her Tears with yours, 'twill ease her Heart. [Exeunt all but De Sale. So, thus the Wind sits fair for Love and Empire; Fools kneel to Fortune, let the Driv'lers wait Till Rivers are run dry; my Brain alone Fashions my Fate, and I am my own Fortune. I know that Zaida cannot weep for ever; Therefore when Time shall lenifie her Grief, She'll thank me for my Vengeance on the Tyrant, And gratefully discharge her Obligations With her fair self—then must I sooth her Sorrows, And soften her to Bliss with oily Words. So when the chaste Ephesian Matron's Grief Wou'd know no Comfort, nor admit Relief, Close to her Lord's cold Monument she lay, All drown'd in Tears wept the slow Hours away. But when the bold Centurion gently woo'd, The Dame's fair Breast with softer Wishes glow'd, She dry'd the mourning Fountains of her Eyes, Her rising Bosom heav'd with warmer Sighs, Soon she forgot her bury'd Husband's Charms, And took the living Soldier to her Arms. [Exit. Enter Herring, Shark, Porpoise, Codshead, and several Mob. Omn. Huzza! Liberty and Property, Property and Liberty, huzzah! Cod. Hear me Neighbour Shark, there are three Reasons why we all rise at once thus like a great Wind—first and secondly to preserve our selves unmarry'd, and thirdly and fourthly that we may live Batchelors. Her. Be happy, and be drunk, you Dogs; for we will have no Arbitrary Wives to controul our Commands. Cod. No, no, one and all we'll not be marry'd. Omn. One and all we'll not be marry'd. Her. We'll all live and dye Batchelors, and our Childrens Children shall have reason to pray for us; I'll have no Family but a full Cellar. Cod. We most of us came into the World without the help of the Person. Por. And we'll walk quietly out on't, without his pushing. Cod. If any one among us is so hardy to own himself lawfully begotten— Por. He's a Son of a Whore. Her. I'll be a Slave to nothing but Sack, I'll be marry'd to a Pipe of Canary, and drink my Wife dry.— Por. Thou shalt be fill'd brimfull of Wine, then tunn'd up, and kept for a rich Cordial when thou art old. Her. Matrimony is sour small Beer, I ha' made an Oath not to drink a drop on't—I'll be true to Sack, constant as the Turtle to his Mate—'tis dearer to me than my own Father's Wife and Children, and when I dye, I'll make some Provision. When I dye, let me have In a Hogshead my Grave, And fill it with racy Canary; Then ye Jollyboys come, Drink and roar round my Tomb, I'll make all the Good-fellows merry. Look ye, this is no Rebellion, but an Uproar, and I am Lord of Misrule; 'tis a sort of a great Riot, when the Youth of the Kingdom boil over in Frolick. Shark. But my Brother-Citizens, and Sailors, when we have mended the Breeches of the Commonwealth, and patcht up the State, who will you have for your King, or will you rule your selves? Por. We'll rule our selves, that is, we our soverign Lord the People will bear Authority over our Sovereign Lord the People. Cod. Learnedly Argoll'd, therefore I say we'll all be Kings. Her. You lye like a fresh-water Lubber—I'll be your King, and govern you all most dissolutely—Sack shall govern me, and I will govern you, and in order to that I will drink incessantly, to buoy up my Spirits, and make me fit for Action: Sack warms the Veins, And cheers the Brains; When I'm drunk, with the Beggar, I'm happy: Then I revel and sing, Am an absolute King; Tis the Joy of my Life to be Nappy. Cod. Well then, let us march soberly to the Palace. Por. And there most humbly remonstrate to our King Arviragus,— Shark. That unless he will please to let us do what we think proper— Cod. And live like sober Gentlemen in Common, without any Enclosures— Por. Then we in all Humility beg leave,— Cod. To burn his Palace about his Ears— Por. Rifle his Treasury.— Cod. And kick him down for an Usurper. Omn. Ay, ay, let's to the Palace, burn, fire, murther,— [Going off. Her. Hold, hold, you most outrageous Rebells; I'll make a Speech first—I am always Eloquent in my Liquor—Gentlemen all, Fellow-Citizens, Fellow-Soldiers, Fellow-Sailors, Fellow-Drunkards, and Fellow-Rebells, if there be Virtue in Sack, as sure there is much, then are we Virtuous, for we are full of Sack—Is there a Man among us that will refuse a Bumper, let him dye in fresh Water, or become a Toast for small Beer; and be most scandalously supt up by some penitential Sinner, who cools after drinking—as for my poor part, I will with your Assistance deform the Common-wealth; for tap me, Gentlemen, if 'tis not a very great Enormity to see your sober Rascals walking steadily about at Eleven at Noon, those sober Rascalls will destroy the Common-wealth. He's a Traytor that thinks, He's a true Man that drinks, Then fill it about, honest Fellow: See, it swells o'er the Glass, And smiles in my Face, Like my Mistress, 'tis pleasant and mellow: I'll drink and sing, with any Man in the Kingdom—How now, what's here? Lawful Authority! then Legs look to't, if they trip you up, they'll find you guilty of Treason. Enter Boreal, Richardo, and Guards. Bor. Topsy turvy faith, the Government upon its Head, and reeling drunk too—Hark ye, ye dirty Rags of Faction, ye Knave-Tools—Get you all home to sleep immediately, digest your Wine and your Grievances, or I'll send such a Show'r of leaden Arguments among you as shall quiet you, if not convince you. Her. Hold, hold Admiral; you're always hot and heavy, like a Tailor's Goose—Suppose we all design to be hang'd to prevent our being marry'd, then you are bit. Cod. Look ye, I have two Wives already in Old England, and I gad I lov'd 'em at first, as if Heav'n and Earth wou'd come together, but I care no more for 'em now, than an Apple's like an Oyster; so that if I marry again no body will pity, me they'll say I was an old Offender, and wou'd take no Warning. Rich. The King commands you instantly depart, Each to your several House, and cease your Riot, His gentle Mercy calls it yet no more; If you obey he grants a general Pardon, If not, his Sword shall justifie his Right, And take severe Revenge on every Traytor. Por. A most gracious Prince truly. Cod. A very gracious Prince, and I forgive him with all my Heart. Her. I begin to relent too—we'll obey him, and drink his Health in a Bumper—my dear, de—ar Admiral, tell him I am very sorry I have offended him, and that I humbly hope in his great Mercy he won't marry me—and so we bid you heartily farewel. [Exeunt. Bor. You must have Wives, my Friends, to keep you at home, and preserve your little Heads from being perplext with Politicks —Look, if the guilty Fools are not all stole away already— Richardo, we must search carefully for the Secret Wind that rais'd these Waters—I have long suspected his first Favourite De Sale, but my Suspicion must, like a Setting Dog, lye close till my Net's over him, then let the Game rise, all is safe—Ha! Yonder goes Tulip, I have observ'd of late that poor Creature has in vain endeavour'd to hide Business in his Face—If they have trusted him with the Secret, they have done him an Injury— he was never design'd by Nature for a Plotter—I'll look into him and see—the Breast of a Fool is transparent like Glass; His fearful Face his guilty Bosom tells, And what he Covers (like clear Streams) Reveals. [Exeunt. The End of the Third Act.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT IV. SCENE I. SCENE Continues. Enter Tulip and Boreal. Bore. Come, unlock, unlock; how awkwardly the Fool looks with a Knave's Coat on—What Wickedness have you been meditating? Why is your solemn Brow loaded with Care? Tul. Who, I careful? Gad, you are the most mistaken Creature— If Courtly gentle Damon dies, [Sings. Let his Monument say, Both the Year and the Day, When he fell by a Shot from fair Zaida's Eyes. Heigh-ho—in troth Admiral, I am most desperately in Love, and it whirls about my Head, and makes such work in my Brains; I took you just now for Piracquo, and was about to tell you that— Bore. What? Tul. Nay, nothing at all, only—If Courtly gentle Damon dies—Oh, I had such a horrible Dream last Night of a Gallows, and Execution, and Officers of Justice—but that they say signifies Preferment, Admiral, Ha! come, come, let us be Merry, very Merry: Let us banish all Care and all Sorrow, 'Twill be here soon enough Boy to Morrow. Oh dear—well Sir, I am your most Obedient, and most Humble Servant. Bore. Hold, hold, we must not part thus—Well, what Discourse had you and Piracquo? Tul. Who I? as I hope to be Happy in the Arms of the most Illustrious, I have not seen him this Age—Gad, I don't like him so well, I believe he's a Traytor. Bore. What Reason have you for that? Tul. Lord, Lord, I tell you I am entirely Ignorant of the whole Matter—Did not the Princess look most triumphantly in her Tears to Day, like the Sun in Eclipse, or the Moon in a Cloud, or like fifty Things besides—My Spirits are in a hurry, I am hipp'd consumedly—Well Sir, your most— Bore. Nay, nay, you shall not stir one Foot from this Spot —Come, come, deliver your whole Cargo—I know Piracquo, like Old Satan, would never converse with a Fool, but to Seduce him. Tul. Ay, ay, I perceive you know something of it—Pox take his Conversation, I have not slept a wink since he pour'd his damn'd Plot into my Ears, and fill'd me full of Treason—Ad it has fermented and work'd within me like new Wine in a crazy Cask—if it had not broke out at the Bunghole, it wou'd have burst the Hoops—I am a Traytor d'ye see, and that is all— 'tis out, thank Heav'n, and I hope you won't Hang me, Admiral. Bore. No, provided you Hang all the rest; don't prove tender-mouth'd, swear home, and make a full Discovery. Tul. Imprimis then, there's my Wife and Piracquo—they continually buzz'd in my Head such Stories against my Lawful Prince, they wou'd never give me a Moment's Rest 'till I consented. Bore. Envious Fiends! Tul. What cou'd I do? the Devil was at one Ear, and the Woman at the other, who cou'd help falling? Bore. How many are there, and who? Name 'em. Tul. Why there are o'my Acquaintance, De Sale, Chicane, Piracquo, Jollyboy, and my Wife Lydia, don't forget her; cou'd not one, Admiral, upon this grand Occasion of Impeaching, throw in a Friend or two one has an old Grudge at, or so? Bore. You'll have Business enough within the Compass of Truth—Where do they meet? Tul. At Eight this Evening at Piracquo's House. Bore. Have you heard none of their Instructions? Tul. Yes, I remember at our last Conference (tho' then my Fear had almost extinguish'd my Understanding) the Castle was be seiz'd at Ten this Evening, when the Guards were to be reliev'd— Arviragus Assassinated, the whole Island plunder'd, and all who offer'd any Resistance, or were found in Arms, murther'd— And further this Deponent saith not. Bore. Keep your Appointment, that they may entertain no Suspicion of the least Discovery—precious Villains! they shall feed Crows—discharge thy Brows of their Burthen, smooth thy Forehead, Care breeds Wrinkles; thou shalt not turn Pendulum this bout—attend thy Hellish Committee; I'll wait on you with an Equipage shall set all right again. [Exit. Tul. So, now have I, like a deep Politician, secur'd my self both Ways—if the Plot succeeds I shall be one of the Glorious Restorers of the Liberties of the People—be an eminent Patriot— and if it miscarries I shall have a Statue erected for my Fidelity to my Prince. [Exit. SCENE Piracquo's House. Enter De Sale, Piracquo, Jollyboy, Chicane. De Sale. Where's Tulip? has the Clock struck? Pirac. 'Tis not yet Eight. De Sale. Between the mighty Thought and Execution Of some great Deed—Time hangs his leaden Wings, And drives the lazy Hours but slowly on, For heavy Expectation clogs the Wheels. Pirac. Here comes our Friend and Brother. Enter Tulip. Sir Gaudy, Welcome. Tul. Gentlemen your Creature to the Centre—You see I follow you Punctually—Yes Faith, Punctually— as to Day did Yesterday—true as your Shadows—in troth, I am wonderfully alert my Friends—Come, come, let us to Action—yet methinks, the cutting Throats is but a slovenly sort of an Employment for a Gentleman. Jolly. No, no, not at all my Jolly-Heart, my Boy of Pleasure, we are all five to be Rulers, to have an equal share in the Government—What is that hard Word you call it, Piracquo? Pir. A Pentarche—The Model is all new, a Foundation upon which no Government on Earth was ever built before— I know 'twill prove auspicious. De Sale. I know ye all, 'tis therefore vain and idle To hope to move your Minds with trifling Words, Who jumpt at once, like the great Wheels of Time, Into one Movement for Immortal Liberty. Tul. In good serious my Heart begins to sink again, I cannot keep it up—I wish Boreal would make haste with his Myrmidons, I shall be hurry'd away here into some cursed Affair or other. [Aside. De Sale. Hear only how you are dispos'd, and then Let Action follow Resolution's Laws. You, Piracquo, must head those Guards we have brought over to us, and seize the Palace—I will, in the mean time, with this Ponyard secure Arviragus; you, Jollyboy, must open the Doors of your Treasury, and fling Rewards among the hot-brain'd Populace—while you, Tulip, at the Head of our Banditti, and the discontented Sea-men, seize all who make Resistance, and put 'em to immediate Death. Tul. Sir! De Sale. What, do you tremble? Does your Courage quail under the glorious Cause?—I wou'd not think it. Tul. Tremble! No, Sir, not at all—I put 'em to Death! Damn'd Rogue! he makes my Back ake consumedly. De Sale. Have you not sworn to take your equal Share In this great Enterprize for Power and Fame, And do you shrink now Action calls you forth? I gave you this great part only to try you. The Fire has prov'd you; base and squalid Fear Sits shaking in your Front—My Fellow-Patriots, This Miscreant will betray us, if he has not; It is not fit he live—we must prevent him, [They draw, and enclose him. And sacrifice him to the publick Good. Tul. For Heav'ns Sake—What, will you carbonado me alive?—Nay, nay, as you are Gentlemen—Well, I will cut Throats or do any thing—Oh spare my Life, I do confess that I have— Enter Boreal, Guards and Soldiers, who seize 'em all. Bor. Gentlemen, at ten this Evening you were to be in Possession of the Palace, You shall keep your Words, I will conduct you thither. Villain De Sale, thou wert thy Master's Sin, And therefore justly might have prov'd his Ruin. Viper, to sting the Bosom that had warm'd thee, And rais'd thee from the Earth to Wealth and Honours, His second in the Throne; be dumb, black Fiend, It best becomes thee—sullen, gloomy Traytor. Chic. Why, we are all nonsuited—I'll have a Noli prosequi; what, wou'd you take Possession vi &amp; armis—Gentlemen, don't be discomfited, I'll bring you off; bearing of Arms in this Case is not High Treason; look into Stat. 25. Edw. III. there 'tis plain, Sir. Joll. Cods so, my Jolly Boys, all undone, Faith—blown up at once, like your great Dealers—Well, well, I am satisfy'd, my brisk Boys, I shall fare as the good Company does. Ha, ha,—We shall be chain'd like your City-Posts—We shall be compleatly dress'd, have Stockings of Iron—Cuffs of the same— Tul. And Neckcloths of Hemp—Gad, you came in the nick, Admiral, or I had been minc'd by these bloody-minded Ruffians—What now, Gentlemen, what, you are merry— Don't you know me, prithee be quiet, Friend. Sold. 'Sdeath, Sir, if you stir a Limb, I shall send a Brace of Plumbs thro' your Jaws shall spoil your singing. Tul. Good lack, you are mighty touchy—Dear Sir, oblige me so far to drop your Bull-dog a little—it makes my Stomach sick—Why, Boreal, Admiral; pox, can't you hear nor see? Why, I tell you, I am an Evidence—I peach. Chic. Sir, you can be no Legal Evidence in this Case; 'tis contra formam Statut'. Tul. Prithee, Paper-worm, tie up thy Tarrier, that is, hold thy Tongue, there's a Decree against thee—What's all this for a Blind, Hah! Admiral? Bor. No, Faith, we have Evidence enough without you, and five, you know, Sir Gaudy, make the best Company in the World. Tul. Did not you promise me?—Who the Devil shall turn true Traytor to serve you for the future—Admiral, Admiral, by all that is dear to me on Earth, my Complexion and my Cloaths, I'll swear you into the Plot, if you don't do the fair thing. Bor. Come, Soldiers, bring 'em along. [Exit. Tul. Hyrcanian Tyger! Go, relentless as the Rocks and Winds—but Winds are still, and Rocks are calm again— Ah Tulip, Tulip, must this Breath, that shou'd have gone out in a Sigh, expiring at the Feet of my Princess, be rudely stopt by vile Plebeian Hemp—Must these Eyes cease to gaze, this Shape to charm, these Legs to lead a Minuet— Sold. Come along, Sir, I can't wait to hear you complement your self. Tul. You are a dirty Clown, refuse a Main in Affliction a Soliloquy— Well, I will die like a Gentlemen—tho' positively I cannot endure to think on't. [Exeunt. SCENE A Grove. Enter Zaida and Semanthe. Sem. Madam, you must not thus indulge your Grief, Duty and Love forbid it, while you thus Tread o'er the Grave of your dear murder'd Love; I fear you cannot bear too sharp Reflection, It will again distract the wounded Sense. Zaid. No, no, my Blood rides on its chrystal Streams Unmov'd, my Eyes are dry, my Senses sound, And yet, believe me, Memory remains; This is the glorious Light, and this the Air; Yonder the foamy Waters of the Sea Break on the chalky Cliffs—there stands the Palace, And this, ev'n this, is that ill-fated Spot, Where poor Aranes fell—ev'n here he lay Weltring in Blood—You see I talk it cooly, Distinguish, think—What a Companion's Thought In Misery like mine? Sem. Inexorable Death hears not your Sighs, Nor will regard your Tears. Zaid. I ask not a Return, I know he's gone For ever, and for ever will I mourn. When the poor Turtle's ravish'd from her Mate, The little Widow pines her Life away— I prithee, Maid, lend me a social Tear; My burning Heart drinks the warm Spirits up, And, Miser-like, denies my Eyes a Drop. Sem. Wou'd but our Tears bribe the remorseless Grave To give him back— Zaid. 'Tis false, he is not dead, Yonder he rides upon a Purple Cloud, Cloath'd in soft Light—see, see, he steals the Thunder From nodding Jove—and now he strikes the Tyrant. Thus, thus he falls to Earth—Ye rising Sweets, Ye springing Flow'rs, cool Glades, and talking Rills, Soft Musick, sinking down, seraphick Peace Lull my dear Love to Rest. Aranes enters at the upper End. Sem. See yonder thro' the Trees your Lord Aranes, Look there he comes—Oh Horror and Amazement! Zaid. Have I then rais'd him from the peaceful Grave?— 'Tis he, 'tis my Aranes, or my Eyes Wou'd cheat me with the pleasing dear Illusion. O save me, good Semanthe, or I sink. My trembling Knees deny their friendly Aid; Hide me, 'tis all a flatt'ring faithless Dream. Aran. Thus let me fly to save her, thus thro' Death, And all the darksome Terrors of the Grave, I break to guard my Love—Oh! 'tis too much, And her o'er-burden'd Mind sinks with the Weight. Awake, my Love—thy lost Aranes folds thee; And Life and Joy, like the first Dawn of Light, Chears our reviving Love. Zaid. Yes, 'tis his Voice—or still the ravish'd Fancy Holds hard the lov'd Idea—Here I see him, His pleasing Image joys the dying Sense— Or is it but an Antepaste of Heav'n! 'Tis no deluding Vision—'tis my Lord, Aranes is return'd—Say, quickly say, How wert thou rescu'd from the Jaws of Death? What Miracle preserv'd thee? Yet my Eyes, Yet they demand thee all—I cannot hear. O my exulting Heart, how shall this vast Extravagance of boundless Joy be born? Aran. O Zaida, be assur'd, excelling Maid, Thy Virtue is the Care of Providence. Zaid. How has good Heav'n preserv'd thee? Say, Aranes, The tuneful Orbs, Celestial Harmony, Wou'd be rude Discord to the pleasing Tale. Aran. When last we parted, on this very Spot The Guards attackt us; the declining Day, Like a weak Taper, shot imperfect Light. We stood prepar'd to sell our Lives like Men. Firmly we fought, and dealt Destruction round us; When a sharp Javelin's Point struck to the Heart My valiant Friend—Pious Alvarez fell, Into my Arms he fell. The Ministers of Vengeance straight retir'd, And thought they had perform'd their bloody Orders, Mistaking him for me—The glimmering Twilight, Which feebly glar'd upon us thro' the Trees, Improv'd their Error. Zaid. And restor'd to me My Life, Aranes; yet a grateful Tear Is due to brave Alvarez. Aran. It is, my Love, nor must excessive Joy, As the glad Years revolve, on this great Day, (Tho' it gave Zaida to my Arms) deny A Tributary Tear to good Alvarez. Zaid. Eternal Peace attend him—But since then How didst thou waste the miserable Hours With thy poor murder'd Friend? Aran. All the remaining melancholy Night I spent in pious Rites on my Alvarez, And bury'd in the Sands the bleeding Body. Zaid. Yet art thou undiscover'd, art thou safe? For I can feel no Fears but for thy Safety. Aran. I am, and owe it to the generous Mind Of gallant Boreal; he, with noble Pity, Saw my distrest Condition, call'd me Friend, With hospitable Arms restor'd a Wretch Abandon'd to Despair, and fed my Hopes: By him I learnt the cruel King repents, And that De Sale prov'd to us both a Villain, And urg'd his Master's Rage—but he is fallen By his own Arts. Zaid. My Vows are answer'd, ev'n the vast Extent Of all my dearest Wishes is compleat; And the good Gods, to make the Blessing greater, Can only make it thus—unchangeable. Aran. My dancing Spirits feel thy tuneful Words, And nimbly course thro' their small winding Channels; As when brisk Musick warms the sluggish Blood— There is but one thing now looks inauspicious: During the bloody Conflict of last Night, A Soldier tore that Bracelet from my Arm, Which with uncommon Care I always wore. Thou know'st, my Zaida, 'twas my Mother's Gift, My dying Mother bound it o'er my Arm; Receive, said she, thy valiant Father's Pledge, He whom thy Eyes ne'er saw bequeath'd thee this, Good Fortune will be constant while you keep, But when you lose it, changeable and bad. I am not superstitious, yet methinks 'Tis ominous, and somewhat touches me. Zaid. No, no, our sullen Days are fled like Clouds, We have exhausted all our evil Fate, Drank up the bitter Draught, and now methinks I see the shining Hours advance—fond Love Triumphant draws 'em up—his rosy Cheek Smiles, like the genial God of Light, on all; He leads his Favourites from the noisie Crowd, To rest for ever on his purple Wings. Aran. 'Tis wronging thee to think of Sorrow now, Joy without Art smiles in each beauteous Feature, Like that primæval Innocence and Truth, When the gay World was young, and free from Fraud. Thus in those happy guiltless Days of old, Ere mercenary Love was bought and sold, As his chaste Heart inspir'd, each happy Swain Chose some bright Maid upon the flow'ry Plain; No Sums were by hard Fathers ask'd or paid, Or meanly barter'd for the lovely Maid; Like ours their mutual Hearts were join'd by Heav'n, And Love for Love, the Gods great Dowry, giv'n. [Exeunt. The End of the Fourth ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT V. SCENE I. SCENE A Court of Justice. Enter Mr. Justice Bull preceded by a Tipstaff, two Council, Mr. Serjeant Dolt for the King, and Mr. Smooth for the Prisoners. The Prisoners chain'd on one side of the Stage. Tips. Make room there, make Room for the Court. Judge. Well, what have you to say Mr. Serjeant against the Prisoners at the Bar, for if no Body appears against 'em, look ye, we must either acquit 'em, or condemn 'em. Chic. Sir, I dispute the Jurisdiction of the Court, I'll have a Habeas Corpus, and a Certiorari to remove the Body, and the Cause, Sir. Judge. We shall hang you Sir, we shall make you feel the Jurisdiction of the Court, and after that, if you don't acknowledge it, I am mistaken. Go on Mr. Serjeant. Serj. May it please your Lordship, and you Gentlemen of the Jury, the Prisoners at the Bar stand indicted, for that they the said Prisoners Predict die, Predict Mensis, &amp;c. Scandalose &amp; Malitiose Conspiraverunt &amp; Consultaverunt Unanimiter (Anglice one and all) Murthrare &amp; overthroware Constitutionem Nostram, (Anglice our Constitution) contra formam Statut, &amp;c. My Lord, we have very full Proof that the Prisoners at the Bar did all meet; that upon that Meeting they did consult, there is the Conspiracy, and the Consultation: Now they wanted nothing but an Opportunity to put these their bloody Designs in Act—And my Lord, if there is no Overt-Act, yet I do say that their Intentions were declarative of an Overt-Act. Smooth. If your Lordship pleases to favour me with one Word, on the other Side; I am Council in this Case for the Prisoners, (I hope what I shall say in Defence of my Clients won't be taken otherwise than as my Brief instructs me for their Defence, if innocent.) Judge. No, no, Sir, you have free Liberty to say any thing for your Clients, provided you say nothing that shall displease the Court, or in Defence of the Prisoners at the Bar. Smooth. I humbly thank your Lordship— Serj. But my Lord, with entire Submission to your Lordship's Judgment— Smooth. Mr. Serjeant, I did not break in upon you. Serj. Pray Sir, give me Leave— Smooth. With your Favour, Sir—my Lord, in this Case— Serj. Pray Sir, I am Council for the King— These Conspirators, my Lord—the Indictment 'specially sets forth likewise, Quod compassavere &amp; imaginati fuere Destructionem Domini Regis (Anglice, the Destruction of the King). Smooth. Tell the Cook I wou'd have the Venison well soak'd, and d'ye hear a Pudding in the Belly of the Hare; you'll remember the six Dozen of the Red Burgundy, the same we drank Yesterday. [To a Servant behind him. My Lord, what Mr. Serjeant offers, tho' it bears the Face of an Argument; yet with Submission I pray Leave to object in half a Word— [To the Court. Judge. Sir 'tis past twelve a Clock—I will hear no Objections. Smooth. I have done my Lord—But here is no Proof of any thing but a naked Meeting and bearing Arms. Now the Statute says, Mes soit adjuge Felony ou Trespasse selonque le Ley de Terre auntientment use. And so 'twas resolv'd in Parliament the fifth of Henry IV. the Earl of Northumberland's Case. Serj. The Earl of Northumberland's Case is very well known —But here let me tell you—Voluntas Reputabitur pro Facto, as in the Case of Goose and Pennyfeather. Judge. Ay, ay, Sir, we will take the Will for the Deed— Is it not the surest Way to prevent Mischief—Look'ee, wou'd it not be Madness to suffer audacious Rebels to run on 'till there were some Proof of their Villany? Smooth. But with Submission, my Lord, it appears in the Case of King Elfred, before the Conquest, and in Beverly's since— Judge. Fie, fie, Mr. Smooth, why will you carry things so far? Smooth. I don't insist on these Cases; but my Lord, this is a very heavy Charge that is brought against my Clients, the Prisoners at the Bar; their Estates, their Lives, their Families at Stake—But Mr. Serjeant Dolt has stated the Objection as thus, my Lord—Either there has been an Overt-Act, or there has been no Overt-Act; if there has been no Overt-Act, what Overt-Act has there been? Chic. That's right, let 'em stick to their Apertum Factum— prove that. Judge. Why, if they are guilty of Treason, they are guilty of Treason, Mr. Smooth, whether they have committed any Overt-Act or no; for a Person may be guilty of an Act look'ee without doing, or thinking of it—Provided always there be a Legal Proof. Smooth. I submit to your Lordship's great Judgment, but— Judge. Look'ee, Mr. Smooth, I am resolv'd before-hand to hang 'em all; so if you have any thing further to say in their Defence, Heav'n forbid I shou'd hinder you from doing your Duty for your Client—Fiat Justitia Currat Lex. Tul. Sir, Sir, you know my Case—Here is a small Parcel of dumb Orators, let 'em prevail with you to throw in one Word more for your most Obedient— [Coming forward to Mr. Smooth. Smooth. It shall be done—Hem— Tul. I shou'd have been an Evidence, Sir, for I discover'd the whole Matter, but I receiv'd the most ungentleman-like Usage. Smooth. Enough, enough, I'll take care of you. I beg Leave only to trouble the Court one half Quarter of a Minute, in behalf of Sir Gaudy Tulip, one of the Prisoners at the Bar—My Lord, my Client is now in the seventy fifth Year of his Age. Tul. What is that to the Purpose? What has he to do with one's Age? Smooth. And he has, for above threescore Years last past, been happily distinguish'd by all the politer World for a Gentleman of very elegant Dress, and Address—(Anglice a Beau) in that Character he has run through all the necessary Courses, he has been duped by his Mistresses Friends and Companions; he has been a constant Bubble to his Vanity, and when his Glass wou'd give him Credit no longer, he has been flatter'd by his own Footmen— Now, my Lord, I must appeal to your Lordship, and the Court, and if Mr. Serjeant can shew in all his Books one Precedent of a Gentleman in his Character, that ever was, or suspected to be, or before my unfortunate Client accus'd of being a Plotter—why, I'll give up the whole Cause, tho' my Client's Life depends upon't—For, my Lord, 'tis contrary to the very Nature of the Creature, a Conspirator is always fierce, bloody, secret, active, and intrepid; a Beau is gentle, tender, open, indolent, and meek—the one is affable and free, the other close and thoughtful—In short, my Lord, 'tis opposite to the common Reason of Things—the general Consent of Mankind, and the Law of Nature. Yet further, my Lord, let the Gentlemen impannel'd on the Jury look stedfastly in his Face, and if they can with Conscience, let 'em declare whether they think it possible he shou'd be guilty of what is here laid to his Charge— therefore I humbly hope Judgment may not pass as to his Particular. Tul. Besides, my Lord, I was to be an Evidence, I was to peach. Judge. Ay, ay, 'tis true; Codso, I had like to have made a Mistake; 'tis true, he is the King's Evidence— Tul. I am infinitely oblig'd to your Lordship— What a cursed Mistake wou'd here have been; 'tis ten to one it came into his Bullet Head before I was hang'd. [Aside. Judge. Well, but Sir Gaudy, you swear then point blank, and generally to every Particular Article in the Indictment, against the Prisoners at the Barr? Tulip. Yes, my Lord, to every Particular, if there were twenty &amp; cætera's more in it. Chic. I fling in my Writt of Appeal, I'll not be try'd by your dumpling Headed Judges, nor your Pack'd Jury neither. Judge. How now! how now! what, do you affront the Court? take him away, take him away there. Chic. Remember, remember 'tis contrary to Magna Charta, and the Liberty of the Subject. Judge. So, we've done, return 'em to Goal, and expect a Warrant for Execution. De Sale. Ye empty Tools of Arbitrary Power, Why do you use these silly Forms of Justice— Oh Piracquo.— We ventur'd hard, but Fortune has undone us. Pirac. Ay, Fortune, and that Dough-bak'd Thing, Sir Gaudy. Tul. You are merry Gentlemen, I wish you a good Journey, you'll excuse me I hope, that I can't possibly wait on you. Tipst. Make way there, make way for my Lord Judge. Judge. Come Brother, come, really I am afraid our Dinner will be spoyl'd. [To Serjeant Dolt.] [Exeunt. SCENE changes to a Grove. Arviragus discover'd alone. Arv. Yet ere this busie Form's resolv'd to Air, Yet—let me think—but when I inwards turn The piercing Probe,—and backwards trace the Scene Of Blood and Rapine—my distracted Mind Wou'd, like the Viper, hide her Monstrous Brood From Heav'n and Earth: And yet repentant Tears Might cleanse and wash these crimson Stains away; They might; but Oh! my stony Heart, Obdurate Merits not Mercy's gentle Touch; but once The Stony Rock, struck by the Prophet's Wand, Pour'd forth a limpid Stream. No more—No more— Reflection wounds me worse than Death; Despair Is a most ugly Friend—Aranes, oh! Ay there he stands, fast by the Throne of Grace, A bleeding dreadful Evidence against me.— Enter Boreal. Who's there? Ha! Boreal, Welcome; you and I Have fought together, when the shatter'd Rigging Lay smoaking on the Bloody Deck; our Masts Shot by the Board, and Death in various Forms Lookt ghastly to appale our constant Hearts, Yet then I knew no Fear;—How comes it, Soldier, That now I feel an inmate Foe who shakes me? I tell thee that I tremble at my self. Bor. My Lord, what you call Fear is only Spleen, Perhaps the Fumes of indigested Food. Arv. Aye! We know 'tis Constitution all; the Blood Stands cold, a sluggish Puddle, in our Age, And breeds these Ague Damps, like Marshy Air. No more, I am satisfy'd—Well, to your Business— Bor. I came to ask your Warrant, Royal Sir, For Execution of those Criminals Our Law has judg'd worthy the Pains of Death. Arv. Ha, ha, what Right? what Royalty's in me? Death! who must Die? what, must my Fellow-Creatures, Because they bravely wou'd no longer bear A single Person's overweening Pride, And Power usurp'd: What, must they die for this? Oh! Boreal, I am sick of my own Folly, The gaudy Bubble breaks, this Toy Ambition Is idler than a Feverish Dream, or Infant's Wish. Bor. You rightly hold your Power, and justly use it. Arv. What hast thou learnt, Old Friend, to flatter too? Nay, then this Air's Infectious. Bor. No, let those gilded Flyes buz in the Sunshine, Who cannot live without it; my good Sword Will feed me, Sir—I need not sell my Words. Arv. Well—but I have a Friend wou'd commune with me Alone, he says, a clamorous Bosom Friend; Leave me, good Boreal.— Bor. But one Word more, and I obey my Lord; These Jewels, worthy to be worn by Kings, [Gives him a Bracelet of Jewels. And deck a Diadem; I found this Morning In the Possession of a private Soldier, And seiz'd 'em for my Royal Master's Use. His Noble Spirit's touch'd with deep Remorse, Now, now's the Crisis; Aid him, candid Virtue, Fair Daughter of the Gods, and give him Strength; [Aside. Oh what Revulsions must his burning Blood Feel, ere this Physick heals—How d'ye, Sir? Arv. As one who Labours up the Stream, is thrown By stronger Waves yet further from the Shore; Why do you heap on this superfluous Guilt, I had enough before to sink a Nation— Zelmane dropt this Sacred Pledge from Heav'n, A living Witness of my perjur'd Love. Where had the Soldier this? it shakes my Soul. Bor. He tore it from Aranes' bleeding Arm. Arv. Aranes whom I murder'd! That Aranes! Bor. From that unhappy Youth, whose I'll-tim'd Love Made him a Sacrifice to your Command. Arv. Thou ly'st, old Dotard—This is false as Hell. Oh Heav'n, and Earth! what, wou'd you load my Soul With filial Murder—Yet 'tis just, ye Powers, From my Youth upwards, double dy'd in Blood, At length I've finish'd the whole Tragick Scene, And turn'd the Reeking Point on my own Off-spring; Whip me ye Fiends, plunge me in Seas of Sulphur: Let your Eternal Fancies work New Torments, And add 'em to the Pains of Hell—But here; Oh here I feel 'em all—Hah, Boreal there Look, there's a Sight— [Aranes and Zaida coming forwards in the Grove, guarded by Officers. Why do's the Air take that Tremendous Form Now they advance—Oh bury me, ye Rocks! Hide me, ye Mountains—'Tis not in Feeble Nature To stand this dreadful Shock. Bor. Recover your Amazement, Sir, he lives, Aranes lives, by me preserv'd, and here Dismiss the Terrors of your troubled Mind, And be your self again. Aran. Shipwreck'd, and cast by Fortune on your Shores, Again, I ask, in the high Name of Heav'n, Your Hospitable Care—It well becomes Your Trust, to guard the Innocent and Stranger, If your reviving Reason feels her Error, Retrieve the past, and present, by the future: Arise the Patron, and the Guard of Virtue, Bright Seeds of Honour seem inclos'd and lock'd Within the Cast of Custom, and a rough And lawless Habitude of Ill, like Jems, They shoot a Lustre thro' the Gloom of Night. Arv. Joy, Wonder, Fear, Amazement, all at once, Burst on my Soul, and tear my trembling Frame. Oh 'tis the Voice of Heav'n—Illustrious Youth, Eternal Mercy's ward: How didst thou 'scape A Barb'rous Tyrant's Rage? but a New Scene Breaks on my Ravish'd Tongue, and bids me ask What Miracle first brought you to Laurentia? Aran. You've heard from Indian Shores, the Raging Seas Drove your Unhappy Captives to this Port. Arv. From India, right; Were you of Noble Blood? Aran. An Omrah's House, the Valiant Ariaspes Gave Being to my Mother. Arv. Oh Boreal, Boreal! [Turning in Transport to Boreal. You talk'd of Ariaspes, Sir, and India. Your Mother too was call'd— Aran. Zelmane. Arv. My Hopes, my Joys are just; let me Embrace thee. Propitious Heav'n! Aran. Say wherefore, Sir, is all this Curious Search? What means my Sympathetick Heart, That joyns his Joy, and seems to aid his Transports. [Aside. Arv. Your Father was not Born in India too? Aran. My Father was a Briton, as your self, Averio call'd; Brave, but Unfortunate; Restless, like the Great Orb of Light: He roll'd Around the Globe, and in the Western Ocean, Like him he set; the Ocean was his Grave, For his o'er-travell'd Ship founder'd at Sea, And weary'd ere his Mighty Spirit flagg'd. Arv. Bear it ye Winds upon your Balmy Wings, Sound the loud Mouth of Fame; let her big Trump, Around the Concave Vault, the Arch of Heav'n, In never-dying Ecchoes still repeat My never dying Joy! Welcome my Son: [Embracing him. The Gods immediate Gift—Oh Bounteous Heav'n! Thus let me Kneel o'burthen'd with my Joy, And pay the worthless Tribute of my Vows, My grateful humble Thanks for endless Mercies. Zaid. New Scenes of Wonder fill the Ravish'd Sense, Aranes, Heav'n is still the Guard of Virtue. Aran. Still have I felt a Reverential Awe, Which when I call'd you Tyrant, check'd my Tongue. Yet Fame reported that your shatter'd Bark Perish'd at Sea; and that you shar'd her Fate. [Arv. takes another Bracelet, that he wears, from his Arm. Arv. She perish'd on the Seas, but with our Boat We reach'd another Vessel I commanded, And steer'd successfully to this Fair Isle. But here, Oh here's an Everliving Proof, This Bracelet is the Counterpart of this, These we exchang'd, when I, and chaste Zelmane, Your Beauteous Mother, were by Fate divided; Behold the plated Side, in double Hearts, Wrought by the Graver's Skill, these Words appear, Averio, and Zelmane; 'till I chang'd The Name my Father gave me, for Arviragus, I was call'd Averio. Aran. There is no room for doubt, each wondrous Word Recalls my Mother's Story to my Mind: And while I view you thus with eager Eyes, I trace that Image which Zelmane wrought, Which yet survives within my Memory, Yet there is one Debt due to Virtue still, Let this fair Favourite share the Blessing with me, Shake off that fatal Passion, give me, Sir, Without a Rival now to Zaida's Arms. Arv. I had resolv'd before to quench this Flame, Tho' in Eternal Night; bright Zaida live, Live then Unrival'd, live Aranes' Queen; Behold Aranes, see, her rising Joys Suffuse around her Face a blushing Light, Such as the Morning Sun gives opening Roses, Now I behold her with the purer Flame Of Love Paternal—with such chast Affection As Angels feel, or Souls of ancient Friends, The grosser Particles of Earth dismist. Zaid. And such Rewards as Filial Piety, As Angels feel, or Souls of ancient Friends Receive from the just Gods, be yours for ever. Arv. But say, did you unwounded then escape The barb'rous Orders of my jealous Love? Bor. O, Sir, you open now a Wound that bleeds Afresh; his pious Friend Alvarez dy'd The Martyr of your Rage—dy'd for Aranes. Arv. Hold, hold, I no where turn my Thoughts, but Guilt Glares horribly on all my Actions past. Melt, melt, ye frozen Veins, relent, and move With penitential Waters heav'nly Mercy; My Hours to come, like Roses in th'Alembick, Shall waste themselves in Tears, and weep to Death. Here I resign all Power and earthly Rule: The gaudy Tinsel of ill-taught Ambition, First tempted me to leap at once the Pale Of all Laws Human and Divine, to reign, But here I lay it down—Take it, Aranes; Thou may'st without a Crime enjoy my Throne, That was not the foul Purchase of my Guilt, Altho' the Means that fixt me here were bad. The Nation with one Voice proclaim'd me King, And made their Gift successive—May you both For ever reign with Peace in Madagascar. Aran. O, Sir! what Gratitude, what Duty now Must filial Piety for ever pay? Arv. I merit not your Thanks, weary of Rule, Before the Miracles of this blest Day Ripen'd to view, I had resolv'd to quit Imperial Sway, and die a private Man, As I was born—And well I hop'd in Britain, Such strong Desires mov'd me to taste again The Sweets of native Air—I thought with Gold, Gold, (the World's Mistress) to attone my Crimes, And buy off with the Prize the Penalty. Bor. With what Contempt the Brittish Heroine view'd That vast Temptation, Wealth; but in Britannia Strict Justice sways alone. Arv. Ay, there the Goddess Themis rules in Person, She holds the equal Ballance of the Globe, And trembling Guilt dares not approach her Throne; The jarring World in Expectation stands, And humbly waits her sacred just Commands. Europa bleeding knelt, and beg'd a Peace, She spoke, and straight the fatal Thunders cease; The Mighty felt in Camps her glorious Sword, And what they fear'd in War, in Peace ador'd. So when rough Winds in adverse Discord jar, All Nature feels her Elemental War— The Woods, the Fields, the Herds, the swelling Waves, Share in the Civil Strife, their angry Master's Slaves; 'Till some blest Angel wings from Heav'n his Way, And with a Word recals the peaceful Day. Restores to the wreck'd Orbs their equal Reign, And gives the shaken Earth Saturnian Days again. [Exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">EPILOGUE. Spoke by Mr. NORRIS. Gentlemen of the Jury—You have heard What has from all our Witnesses appear'd. Now give me Leave the Evidence to summ, And leave poor Bays from you to hear his Doom. The Poet stands indicted, for that he Combin'd with a grand Theif, one Avery, Illegally seducing Half a Crown From ev'ry Lover of a Play in Town; That he has neither brought you Plot nor Wit, Nor ought that is diverting—That you're bit. Now, Sirs, the Statute of the first of Phœbus Says Wit shou'd not be cramm'd—in omnibus rebus. So in the fourth of Horace, Let your Bully, Says that Wit-Lawyer, rage and beat his Cully; Old Soldiers brag, Slaves lie, and Clowns be dull, And each Man in his Character a Fool. The Ancients wou'd have look'd with Scorn and Pity Upon a Wretch unseasonably witty. Well, if you find him then excus'd from Wit, Inquire if all be pertinently writ. That Serjeant Aristotle says is good, And in his fourth Reports 'tis so allow'd. And so th'aforesaid Horace more than once, Scribendi rectè sapere est &amp; principium &amp; fons. Now, Gentlemen, he says in his Defence, He travell'd far, was at a large Expence, And for your Sterling Mony gave you Sterling Sense. That you must try, you are the Standard here, 'Tis current thro' the World, if it your Touchstone bear. This is the Sum; Culprit must stand or fall, Then as your Consciences direct—judge all. I have advis'd him, if you find it bad is, To bring a Certiorari to the Ladies. If to that brilliant Court he moves his Cause, And they approve, can you deny Applause? Ladies, be kind, maintain your Empire still, And prove your Eyes can Save, as well as Kill. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>