<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Munday, Anthony, 1553-1633</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Munday, Anthony, 1553-1633</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">munday anthony 1553 1633</field>
      <field name="author_text">Munday, Anthony, 1553-1633</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">17th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V1.0638.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1618</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:459344</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Sidero-Thriambos. Or Steele and Iron Triumphing</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 17th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 17th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Sidero-Thriambos. Or Steele and Iron Triumphing</field>
      <field name="title_facet">sidero thriambos or steele and iron triumphing</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">sidero thriambos or steele and iron triumphing</field>
      <field name="title_text">Sidero-Thriambos. Or Steele and Iron Triumphing</field>
      <field name="year_display">1618</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1618</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1618</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459344&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459344&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Munday, Anthony, 1553-1633&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;munday anthony 1553 1633&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Sidero-Thriambos. Or Steele and Iron Triumphing&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;sidero thriambos or steele and iron triumphing&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1618&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1618&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Munday, Anthony&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1553&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1633&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Sidero-Thriambos. Or Steele and Iron Triumphing&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed by Nicholas Okes [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1618&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3871906-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv10638&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 17th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;17th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Sidero-Thriambos. Or Steele and Iron Triumphing&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 28 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Sidero-Thriambos.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Entertainment.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1618.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 29 Oct 1618.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Sidero-Thriambos. Or Steele and Iron Triumphing.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">To the Maister, Wardens, and whole Assistant body of the Ironmongers Worshipfull Society.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">This famous and most Honorable Citie of London, hauing (for many hundred yeares) had the Royall preheminence, to make choyce of her chiefe Magistrate, by the title of Lord Maior, and two Sheireffes, as his worthy Assistants in Office for the yeares authority, vnder the highest and supreme power enioying the same by free voice &amp; sufferages of publick election, in the Guild-Hall of London. Now in this instant yeare 1618. Sir Sebastian Haruey, Knight, and Aldermam of this Noble City, and free of the Right Worshipfull Company of Ironmongers, being chosen into that great and gracefull dignity; his affectionate &amp; kinde Brethren (according to ancient and precedent custome, obserued to many more Lord Maiors of the same Society) did thus tender their willing and hearty seruice to him, vpon the day of his inauguration, when (passing by Barge with the other Aldermen his Brethren) hee went to take his Oath at Westminster, on Thursday the 29. of October.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The first deuise, presenting it selfe for his Honors seruice, is an imaginary Island, tearmed Lemnos, very ingeniously and artificially fitted, surable to the dayes solemnity. And, because fauourable conceit, must needs supply the defect of impossible performance, especially in so slender a compasse: let the Isle it selfe be swallowed vp in the apparance of a goodly Myne, aptly seated in the midst thereof. Therein Mulciber, the God of Mynes and Mettals (especially such as consist of Steele &amp; Iron) sheweth his personall attendance, with diuers of his one-eyed Cyclops about him, forming from the Mynes Oare, Gads of Steele, Barres of Iron, &amp; other such like matters out of the Mettals, for vse of the Ironmongers Societie, who are as Lords &amp; Maisters of the sayd Myne, and therefore it is called the Ironmongers Myne. These feigned Cyclops, suted according to their seruice and diligence (each with his Hammer busily imployed, while others attend the Fire and Bellowes) are nimble and dexterious youthes, such, as to the continuall fall of their Hammers, in sweet Musicall voyces, and delicate variety of pleasing changes; doe out-weare their worke merrily, as accounting no toyle tedious, thus bestowed in the Societies seruice: closing vp euery Stanza with Acier Dure, the worde or Motto belonging to the Companie. This Isle or Myne being seated quadrangel-wise, at the foure corners sit foure beautifull Nymphes or Graces; being named Chrusos, Argurion, Calcos and Sideros, figuring the foure ages of the world, and habited according to their true Carracters and natures. The Golden-Age, the Siluer-Age, and the Brazen-Age, hauing formerly triumphed, according to their seuerall turnes and times of eminency: doe now giue way to the Iron-Age (wherein wee liue) to haue her degree of soueraignty, as holding chiefe predominance in this daies Triumph. For, she being sole Commandresse, in Mettals of most vsuall imployment; affordeth out of her bounteous Myne, all kinds of Martiall and Military weapons, honouring with them Armes and Souldiers. Likewise, for Tillage and Husbandry, those instruments best agreeing therewith: because it is the sustentation of life, and supporter of all other manuary Trades. Being not vnmindfull also, of Nauigation &amp; C?merce with forraigne Nations, which can haue no consistence, but by her helpe. Beside, the Companies Creast, of two Lizzards, linked together with a Golden Terret (which in their Coate of Armes, is placed in the Cheueron) stands fairely figured vpon the Myne. Aboue them all is Iupiter, mounted vpon his Royall Eagle, with his three-forked Thunderbolt in his hand, made in the Isle of Lemnos by Mulciber. He is also clad in a faire Armour, intended for the seruice of Mars: but now bestowne on him, as an honourable present by Mulciber, because hee so graciously vouchsafed, to bee personally present in this Triumph, as Patron of all their pains, and protector from foule-mouthed slander and detraction. This deuise is drawne by two goodly Estridges, as being supporters of the Societies Armes, and therefore aptly alluded as Guides to Mulcibers Myne, befitting none other so well as that: for, naturally they digest both Steele and Iron, as is auouched by many credible Authors. One other Millitary Engine also, seeming to be forged in the same Myne, is appointed to the second place, which is a fair and goodly Cannon, strongly mounted vpon her Carriage, with all necessarie furnishment, for charging and discharging, by her, as also diuerse Chambers, to bee shot off as occasion serueth, and as the Maister Gunner and his Mate (there present) please to giue direction, or performe the seruice in their owne persons. Certaine gallant Knights in Armour, well mounted on their Coursers for seruice, and readily prepared with their Petronells; haue the charge or guiding of this Cannon: besides a braue troupe of Musketiers. This was first imployed on the water, in the mornings seruice, and afterward helpeth the dayes further Triumph. The Speeches betweene the Maister Gunner and his Mate, at the Cannon. Maist. Where are you Mate? Mate. Here Sir, at hand, To doe what ere the Maister shall command. Maist. This goodly Cannon, forged for this day In Lemnos, where great Mulciber beares sway, Hee and his Cyclops vsing all their skill, To frame it in best forme, and for good will They beare vnto that ancient Company, For whom their Hammers walke continually, Still to supply them from their plenteous Myne With Steele and Iron: which as they refine From the earths Oare; So to all Lands they send, And all Artes else do bounteously befrend. Because, where Steele and Iron goe to wrack: Those Lands doe feele a lamentable lack. Now Mate, thou seest, this is a Iouiall day, And euery Trade triumphes as best it may, (By yearly custome) gladly to expresse, Their free affection, in full chearfulnesse. Be not we idle then; Seeing to our charge, This Cannon is committed: But at large Declare our dilligence. Our Gunners Arte, In this Triumphall day must beare a part. Fall to thy paines. Mate. Maister, with all my heart. And no men shall deliuer (more then we) How much we honour this dayes dignity. All this hee speaketh answerable to his action.First then, Ile Spunge her, as she ought to be, Then Lade her, to Report her lustily. Next Ramme her. Now this Bullet passeth in, Which Ramd againe, lowder Report shall win. And shooting not Point blanck, but out at length: Ile mount her higher on her Carriage strength. Now I haue done Sir. Maister. Then will I giue Fire; And may all speed no worse then we desire. Next followeth a siluer Leopard, thickly bespotted with blacke Pellets, being the Creast of the Lord Maiors Armes. Vpon the Leopard rideth an ancient Brittish Barde; For Bardes were esteemed as Poets or Propheticall Sooth-sayers, and (in those reuerend times) held in no meane admiration and honour. Hee guideth the way to the Mount of Fame, being a Pageant, and aptly alluding to the other deuise; but in a more morrall and significant manner. For therein is figured, a modell of Londons happy Gouernement, in that supreame dignity of the Maioraltie. Being a true type of that most sacred Maiesty, by whose gracious fauour it is best supported, and borroweth (from thence) all beames of true light and splendor. In the most eminent place sitteth Fame, seeming as if shee sounded her Golden Trumpet, the Banner whereof, is plentifully powdred with Tongues, Eyes and Eares: implying, that all tongues should be silent, all eyes and eares wide open, when Fame filleth the world with her sacred memories. This day, shee seemeth to present the new sworne Lord Maior to Soueraigne Maiesty, whose Lieutenant and lawfull Deputy hee is now inuested for London. Shee sheweth him, what other gracious personages shee hath there attending her, for more honourable solemnity of this generall Triumph; presaging a happy and successefull course to his yeare of gouernment. By her is figured a goodly Shippe, whereby she conueighes all beatitudes of Kingdomes, Cities and Nations, to the furthest remoate Countries. Intimating thereby, how the Magistrate may honour his Prince, in that high trust and care committed to him, and supplying the State still with all needfull occasions, as by Trafficke and Commerce are continually required. Expectation (sitting somewhat lower on Fames right hand) intimateth to him, that there will be more then ordinary matter expecte from him: in regard, that hee is now mounted like a Beacon on an Hill, to flame forth brightly, and not to burne dimly. Whereof Hope (sitting on the other side) seemeth to giue a gracious perswasion. In regarde, that his worthy Father did formerly supply the same place, and left such sensible instructions to his Sonne, as cannot but edge his temper the more keenely, and quicken his spirits the more industriously. Because it is no comm? thing, for a Son, to succeed his Father in such eminencie, and therefore bindeth him to the more serious obseruance. Wherein to encourage him the more, shee sheweth him all those sacred Vertues, that gaue his Father comfort in his Magistracie, Iustice and Fortitude, who will as forwardly further him; treading downe those vile Incendiaries, Ambition, Treason, and Hostility, which seeke the subuersion of all estates, by Bribing, Corruption, and smoothing Insinuation, or else by open Fire and Sword. But because this yeare may be the better secured, against all their violences and treacherous attempts; they sit gyued, and manacled together in Iron shackles, purposely made and sent from the Ironmongers Myne, to binde such base villaines to their better behauiour. Now, because Fame cannot endure, that any part of her Mount should bee vnfitly furnished: In a degree more backward, &amp; somewhat lower then her Seat, sit her two sober Sisters, Feare and Modesty; both vailed, but so sharpe-sighted, that they can discerne through the darkest obscurities, when any disorder threatneth danger to Maiesty, or to his carefull Deputie. When any such inconuenience happeneth, forthwith they informe Vigilancy &amp; Prouidence, sitting next to them. Who hearing the Larum and striking clock in the Castle: they awake Care the Sentinell, to ring the Bell in the Watch-Tower, which calleth vp Courage &amp; Councel, that euery one may haue imploim?t, for safe preseruing the Mo?t of Fame. For better vnderstanding the true morality of this deuise, the personages haue all Emblemes and Properties in their hands, &amp; so neere them, that the weakest capacity may take knowledge of th?, which course in such solemne Triumphes hath alwaies beene allowed of best obseruation: both for auoiding trouble to the Magistrate, by tedious and impertinent speeches, and deuouring the time, which craueth diligent expedition. Concerning our Brittish Barde, raised to bee our Speaker, by sacred power of the Muses, hee reuoluing ouer his ancient volumes, concerning the course of times; findeth, that in this yeare of 1618. the letter H. shall haue predominance in three distinct persons, as eminent Gouernours, &amp; namely in the City of London, viz. the L. Maior, and both the Shieriffes. And if his predicting opinion doth not beguile it selfe, he saith that their names will be Haruey, Herne and Hamarsley, for so the booke of Fate hath concluded of them, against which can be no contradiction. Whereupon making triall of his diuination by his staffe (which vsually directed him in all such courses) as hee speaketh to the Lord Maior; he smiteth the Staffe vpon his foot, &amp; suddenly issueth forth the three seuerall letters of H. apparantly to be discerned of all. So, finding his iudgement to be fallen out true, &amp; that the persons figured by those three letters are also there present: he proceedeth on in the rest of his Speech, which according to the Brittish garbe, and as then he vttered it, is here set downe. The Bardes first speech, deliuered to my Lord Mayor, at his going to Saint Paules Church in the afternoone. Blithe and bonny bin yee aw, And meckle blissings still be faw Upon so faire and gudly meany, As thilke like, nere sawe Ieny. A Brittish Barde, that long hath slept, And in his Graue would still ha kept: But that the spirit of Poesie (Which haudeth highest Soueraigntie) Hath raisde me from my silent rest, To make ene in this Iouiall Feaste. Aw for your seke, most worthy man, (Lowting as lowly as I can) To creue your fauour, that I may, For your Society somewhat sey, Of thilke their buxome looue to you, Which they present but as your due. As often they haue done befere, To mickle of their Bretheren mere. Among wha was your Fether one, Which this high charge did vndergone. O, let me sey it to your fece, It is a signe of speciall grece, Yee to supply your Fethers plece: In sike an encient femous Citty, Under yer King, chiefe Deputie. And let me tell yee ey thing mere, Of Records haue I read good stere; Yet neere could find the like befere, As now hath hapt. Thilke dignitie, Of Meire and Shrieffes authoritie, Whilke London yearely greants to three: Eyne letter H beginnes them aw, And in so soote concordance faw: That Heruey, Herne and Hemersley, Maken ey pleasing Sympheny. Eyne Enegreme ilke neme mey blisse, With Honor, Heale and Happinesse. Honor to be sele Steffe and stey, Heale to vphaude all eirie wey, And Happinesse sa to attend, Yer yeare may heue a happy end. Thaese Shewes and Emblems ta expresse, Mayne trouble yee with tediousnes. And ay, wha wud na way offend, Yer kenning of them doe commend Untill thilke Buke, whilke speeks them aw, Mere large than to my lot does faw. Sa, Honor, Heale and Happinesse, Giue aw yer actions gud successe. At night at my Lords House. Thilke eye of day, whilke grec'de our spart, Being clased vp, mekes his resarte Till vnder-dwellers. Seble-night, Was gledly lengthen ant delight: But standeth fearefull of offending, Because aw ioyes mun heue an ending. Not, that we desire to lieue yee, But for yar awne heme mun receiue yee. And, thereto maken baulde intrusion, Was clase vp aw with rude confusion. Whilke fare my Leard, my perting is, Wishing yee mickle yeares of blisse, That Iustice, Zeale and Payetie, Mayne shine in yee with Meiesty, That he wha puts yee in thilke trust, Mey finde yer rule sa true and iust, That efter times may talke, and sey Whan Heruey, Herne and Hemersley As Meire and Sheriffes did beare swey: True Honor, Helth and Heppinesse, Thilke yeare did their endeauours blisse. Yer Bretherens loue I mun commend To yer acceptance, sa I end. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>