<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Lloyd, Charles, 1775-1839</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Lloyd, Charles, 1775-1839</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">lloyd charles 1775 1839</field>
      <field name="author_text">Lloyd, Charles, 1775-1839</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1810's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V3.0486.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1815</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460836</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The First Brutus ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The First Brutus ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="title_facet">first brutus</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">first brutus</field>
      <field name="title_text">The First Brutus ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="year_display">1815</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1815</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1815</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460836&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460836&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Lloyd, Charles, 1775-1839&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;lloyd charles 1775 1839&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The First Brutus ; A Tragedy&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;first brutus&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1815&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1815&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Lloyd, Charles&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1775&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1839&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The First Brutus&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for Longman, Hurst, Rees, Orme And Brown [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1815&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3873151-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv30486&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The First Brutus&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 113 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted&lt;lb/&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;lb/&gt;Dedicatory poem included with Philip. A Tragedy.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Brutus, part i.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1815.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Unknown.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE FIRST BRUTUS. A TRAGEDY.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Dedication, by Vittorio Alfieri, to THE FIRST BRUTUS. TO THE MOST ILLUSTRIOUS AND FREE CITIZEN, GENERAL WASHINGTON.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DRAMATIS PERSONÆ. Brutus. Collatinus. Titus. Tiberius. Mamilius. Valerius. People. Senators. Conspirators. Lictors.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Scene ,—The Forum in Rome.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT THE FIRST. SCENE THE FIRST. Brutus, Collatinus. Col. Ah where, ah where, oh Brutus, would'st thou thus Drag me by force? Quickly restore to me This sword of mine, which with beloved blood Is reeking yet ... —In my own breast ... Bru. Ah! first This sword, now sacred, in the breast of others Shall be immerged, I swear to thee.—Meanwhile 'Tis indispensable, that in this forum Thy boundless sorrow, and my just revenge, Burst unreservedly before the eyes Of universal Rome. Col. Ah no! I will Withdraw myself from every human eye. To my unparallel'd calamity All remedies are vain; the sword, this sword Alone can put an end to my distress. Bru. Oh Collatinus, a complete revenge Would surely be some solace; and I swear To thee, that that revenge thou shalt obtain.— Oh! of a chaste and innocent Roman lady Thou sacred blood, to-day shalt thou cement The edifice of Roman liberty. Col. Ah! could my heart indulge a hope like this! The hope, ere death, of universal vengeance ... Bru. Hope? Be assured of it. At length, behold The morn is dawning of the wish'd-for day: To-day my lofty, long-projected plan At length may gain a substance and a form. Thou, from a wrong'd unhappy spouse, may'st now Become the avenging citizen: e'en thou Shalt bless that innocent blood: and then if thou Wilt give thy own, it will not be in vain For a true country shed ... A country, yes, Which Brutus will to-day create with thee, Or die with thee in such an enterprise. Col. Oh! what a sacred name dost thou pronounce! I, for a genuine country's sake alone, Could now survive my immolated wife. Bru. Ah! then resolve to live; co-operate With me in this attempt. A God inspires me; A God infuses ardour in my breast, Who thus exhorts me: “It belongs to thee, “Oh Collatinus, and to thee, oh Brutus, “To give both life and liberty to Rome.” Col. Worthy of Brutus is thy lofty hope: I should be vile if I defeated it. Or, from the impious Tarquins wholly rescued, Our country shall from us new life obtain; Or we (but first avenged) with her will fall. Bru. Whether enslaved or free, we now shall fall Illustrious and revenged. My horrible oath Perhaps thou hast not well heard; the oath I utter'd, When from Lucretia's palpitating heart The dagger I dislodged which still I grasp. Deaf from thy mighty grief, thou, in thy house, Scarce heardest it; here once more wilt thou hear it, By my own lips, upon th'inanimate corse Of thy unhappy immolated wife, And in the presence of assembled Rome, More strenuously, more solemnly renew'd. Already, with the rising sun, the forum With apprehensive citizens is fill'd; Already, by Valerius' means, the cry Is to the multitude promulgated Of th'impious catastrophe: th'effect Will be far stronger on their heated hearts When they behold the chaste and beauteous lady With her own hands destroy'd. In their disdain, As much as in my own, shall I confide. But more than every man thou should'st be present: Thine eyes from the distracting spectacle Thou may'st avert: to thy affliction this May be allow'd: yet here should'st thou remain: E'en more than my impassion'd words, thy mute And boundless grief is fitted to excite Th'oppress'd spectators to indignant pity ... Col. Oh Brutus! the divinity which speaks In thee, to lofty and ferocious rage, Hath changed my grief already. The last words Of the magnanimous Lucretia, seem, In a more awful and impressive sound, To echo in my ears, and smite my heart. Can I be less inflexible t'avenge, Than she to inflict her voluntary death? In th'infamous Tarquinii's blood alone Can I wash out the stigma of the name, Common to me and them! Bru. Ah! I too spring From their impure and arbitrary blood: But Rome shall be convinced that I'm her son, Not of the Tarquin's sister: and as far As blood not Roman desecrates my veins, I swear to change it all by shedding it For my beloved country.—But, behold, The multitude increases: hitherward Numbers advance: now it is time to speak. SCENE THE SECOND. Brutus, Collatinus, People. Bru. Romans, to me, to me, oh Romans, come: Great things have I t'impart to you. People. Oh Brutus, Can that indeed which we have heard be true? Bru. Behold; this is the dagger reeking yet, Yet warm, with th'innocent blood-drops of a chaste And Roman lady, slain by her own hands. Behold her husband; he is mute; yet weeps And shudders. Yet he lives, but lives alone For vengeance, till he sees by your hands torn, The heart torn piece-meal of that impious Sextius, That sacrilegious ravisher and tyrant. And I live yet; but only till the day, When, wholly disencumber'd of the Tarquins, I see Rome free once more. People. Oh most unparallel'd, Calamitous catastrophe! ... Bru. I see That all of you upon th'unhappy spouse Have fix'd your motionless and speaking eyes, Swimming with tears, and by amazement glazed. Yes, Romans, look at him; ah see in him, Ye brothers, fathers, and ye husbands, see Your infamy reflected. Thus reduced, Death on himself he cannot now inflict; Nor can he life endure if unavenged ... But vain, inopportune, desist from tears, And from astonishment.—Romans, towards me, Turn towards me, Romans, your ferocious looks: Perhaps from my eyes, ardent with liberty, Ye may collect some animating spark Which may inflame you with its fostering heat. I Junius Brutus am; whom long ye deem'd, Since I so feign'd myself, bereft of reason; And such I feign'd myself, since doom'd to live The slave of tyrants, I indulged a hope One day to rescue, by a shock of vengeance, Myself and Rome from their ferocious claws. At length the day, predestined by the gods, The hour, for my exalted scheme is come. From this time forth 'tis in your power to rise From slaves (for such ye were) to men. I ask Alone to die for you; so that I die The first free man and citizen in Rome. People. What have we heard? What majesty, what force, Breathe in his words! ... But we, alas! are powerless: Can we confront arm'd and ferocious tyrants? ... Bru. Ye powerless, ye? What is it that you say? What? Do ye then so little know yourselves? The breast of each already was inflamed With just and inextinguishable hate Against the impious Tarquins: now, e'en now, Ye shall behold before your eyes display'd The last, most execrable, fatal proof, Of their flagitious arbitrary power. To-day to your exalted rage, the rage Of Collatinus, and my own, shall be A guide, an impulse, a pervading spirit. Ye have resolved on liberty; and ye Deem yourselves powerless? And do you esteem The tyrants arm'd? What force have they, what arms? The arms, the force of Romans? Who is there, The Roman who, that would not sooner die, Than here, or in the camp, for Rome's oppressors, Equip himself with arms?—By my advice, Lucretius with his daughter's blood aspersed, Hath to the camp repaired: this very moment By the brave men besieging hostile Ardea, Hath he been heard: and certainly In hearing him, and seeing him, those men Have turn'd their arms against their guilty tyrants, Or swift in our defence, abandoning Their impious banners, hitherward they fly. The honour of the earliest enterprise Against the tyrants, citizens, would ye Consent indeed to yield to other men? People. Oh, with what just and lofty hardihood Dost thou inflame our breasts!—What can we fear, If all have the same will? Col. Your noble rage, Your generous indignation, thoroughly Recall me back to life. Nothing can I Express ... to you ... for tears ... forbid ... my utterance ... But let my sword be my interpreter; I first unsheathe it, and to earth I cast, Irrevocably cast, the useless scabbard. Oh sword, I swear to plunge thee in my breast, Or in the breast of kings.—Oh husbands, fathers, Be ye the first to follow me! ... But ah! What spectacle is this? ... In the farther part of the stage the body of Lucretia is introduced, followed by a great multitude. People. Atrocious sight! Behold the murder'd lady in the forum ... Bru. Yes, Romans, fix, (if ye have power to do it,) Fix on that immolated form your eyes. That mute fair form, that horrible generous wound, That pure and sacred blood, ah! all exclaim, “To-day resolve on liberty, or ye “Are doom'd to death. Nought else remains.” People. All, all, Yes, free we all of us will be, or dead. Bru. Then listen now to Brutus.—The same dagger Which from her dying side he lately drew, Above that innocent illustrious lady Brutus now lifts; and to all Rome he swears That which first on her very dying form He swore already.—While I wear a sword, While vital air I breathe, in Rome henceforth No Tarquin e'er shall put his foot; I swear it: Nor the abominable name of king, Nor the authority, shall any man Ever again possess.—May the just Gods Annihilate him here, if Brutus is not Lofty and true of heart!—Further I swear, Many as are th'inhabitants of Rome, To make them equal, free, and citizens; Myself a citizen, and nothing more: The laws alone shall have authority, And I will be the first to yield them homage. People. The laws, the laws alone: we with one voice To thine our oaths unite. And be a fate, Worse than the fate of Collatinus, ours, If we are ever perjured! Bru. These, these are True Roman accents. Tyranny and tyrants, At your accordant hearty will alone, All, all have vanish'd. Nothing now is needful Except 'gainst them to close the city gates; Since fate to us propitious had already Sequester'd them from Rome. People. But you meanwhile Will be to us at once consuls and fathers; You to us wisdom, we our arms to you, Our swords, our hearts, will lend ... Bru. In your august And sacred presence, on each lofty cause, We always will deliberate: there cannot From the collected people's majesty Be any thing conceal'd. But it is just That the patricians and the senate bear A part in every thing. At the new tidings They are not all assembled here: enough (Alas! too much so) th'iron rod of power Has smitten them with terror: now yourselves To the sublime contention of great deeds Shall summon them. Here then we will unite, Patricians and plebeians; and by us Freedom a stable basis shall receive. People. From this day forth we shall begin to live.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT THE SECOND. SCENE THE FIRST. Brutus, Titus. Tit. All the patricians were invited, father, As thou commandedst, to th'august assembly. The fourth hour now approaches; thou wilt have The whole of Rome subservient to thy nod. It almost doth bereave me of my reason To see thee lord of Rome. Bru. Thou seest me Lord of myself, and not of Rome, oh Titus: Nor shall you have a lord in any shape In Rome henceforward. This by her I swear; I, who till now was a vile slave. Oh sons, Ye saw me such, while with the tyrant's children I educated you for servitude In a corrupted court. Alas! I could not Sow in your hearts the seeds of liberty, A trembling and degraded father: hence Ye are a cause, ye the most special cause, Whence I should triumph in recover'd freedom. My independent animating carriage Will instigate you more to excellence, Than my anterior servitude to baseness. Contented for my country shall I die, When I with confidence shall leave my sons The associates of free-born citizens. Tit. Father, there needed to thy lofty heart, Whose lustre always broke upon thy sons, A field no less magnificent for action Than that which fortune opens to thee now. Ah, might we in the noble enterprize Assist thee! But the obstacles are many, And they are terrible. The multitude Is in itself inconstant: to the Tarquins What manifold resources yet remain! ... Bru. Were there no obstacle remaining yet, The enterprize were dangerless, and thence Unworthy Brutus: but if Brutus fear'd them, He were unworthy to accomplish it.— To the immutable, lofty, austere, Peremptory decision of thy father, Do thou thy youthful vehemence unite; Thus at once son of Brutus and of Rome Shalt thou be, Titus.—But thy brother comes ... Hear we what news he brings. SCENE THE SECOND. Tiberius, Titus, Brutus. Tib. Beloved father, Never could I have met thee in the forum More opportunely. Wild with joy thou seest me: I sought for thee. Breathless from too much haste I am: with impulses ne'er felt before, I am at once transported and oppress'd. I have just seen the execrable Tarquins, And trembled not ... Tit. Where was it? Bru. Where? ... Tib. I am By my own eyes persuaded that the tyrant Is of all men the least. The haughty king, With impious Sextius, scarce had heard that Rome Had risen in tumult, ere he left the camp; And with a chosen escort towards the city Fled with full speed: and here were they arrived At the Carmental gate ... Tit. Precisely there Where thou wert sentinel. Tib. Blest that I am! I first against the tyrants, I the first My sword unsheathed.—The iron gate was closed, And fortified: in its defence myself, With twenty other armed Romans, paced, Accoutred all, exterior to the gate, With circumambient vigilance. Behold, With cries, with howlings, and with menaces, The troop, twice ours in number, rush'd towards us. To hear, to see, to recognize the miscreants, To fall upon them with our weapons, seem'd The labour of an instant. In ourselves There was a strength and rage unlike to theirs: Tyrants, they thought that they were meeting slaves: But soon they learn'd that liberty and death, Like twin-born instincts, hover'd round our swords. Already ten or more had we destroy'd; The residue, and Tarquin first of these, Betook themselves to flight. Upon their heels Fiercely and long we press'd, but press'd in vain; Fear gave them wings. I afterwards return'd To my appointed post beside the gate; And, warm yet with the victory, swift I come To thee to tell it. Bru. Trifling though it be, Such sample of our prowess should be deem'd An omen of prosperity to Rome. Fain would I in that fray have borne a part; For nothing so intensely do I covet As to confront them in the strife of blood. Oh! wherefore in the forum and the camp Cannot I tongue, and intellect, and sword, All, all at once exert! But with such sons I can with ease be many things at once. Tib. Still have I more to tell thee. When to flight I had these miscreants driven, as I return'd Towards the walls, the sound of steeds I heard Behind, advancing on our homeward path; Backward I look'd, and lo! there came towards us A single horseman from the tyrant's train. His right-hand weaponless he raised; no sword Guarded his side; an olive-branch he held In his left-hand; beckoning to me, he cried: I halted; he advanced; the messenger Of peace, in supplicating tones he ask'd Admission into Rome. T'enunciate Conditions and apologies, he comes To Brutus and the senate. Bru. To the people— For Brutus is a portion of the people, Or he is nothing. And the herald is? ... Tib. Mamilius: strict injunctions to my troops Without the gates I gave to guard him well. I came to know what must be done with him. Bru. He comes at the right time. This messenger Could not have chosen to present himself A day more solemn or more opportune. Go, to the gate return; seek him; with thee Quickly conduct him hither. If he dare, Here shall he speak to universal Rome: And here, an answer not of Rome unworthy He will, I hope, receive. Tib. To him I fly. SCENE THE THIRD. Brutus, Titus. Bru. Meanwhile go thou to meet the senators; See in the forum that they yield to them The most conspicuous places. Even now The concourse of the multitude increases; And several of the senators I see. Go hence; oh Titus, go without delay. SCENE THE FOURTH. Brutus, People, Senators, and Patricians, who place themselves successively in the Forum. Bru. Oh thou supreme discerner of those thoughts Which lurk most privily in human breasts! Thou who dost see and dost inflame my heart! Rome's great protector, everlasting Jove! Give me, I pray thee, language, sense, and ardour To the great cause proportion'd ... Yes, oh Jove, This wilt thou do, if it be true that thou Hast chosen me to be the instrument Of liberty, thy first and genuine blessing. SCENE THE FIFTH. Brutus, having mounted the Rostrum, Valerius, Titus, People, Senators, Patricians. Bru. I come, oh fellow-citizens, to make To you all strict confession of my deeds. With one consent you have appointed me And Collatinus to a dignity Without a precedent in Rome: the lictors, The fasces, and the hatchets (hitherto Th'insignia of kings) ye have been pleased T'annex to our elective annual office. Yet not for this hath the malignant taint Of mad ambition crept into my heart; With honours, no, (though yours are real ones,) I'm not transported; but with liberty, With love for Rome, and with implacable, Fierce, and eternal hatred for the Tarquins. These are my sole pretensions; and may each Of you in such a noble strife excel me; I have no wish beyond. People. Thy dignified And manly aspect, Brutus, thy frank speech, All, all announce in thee to us the sire Of Rome and of the Romans. Bru. Oh my sons, My genuine sons, (since with the name of father Ye have been pleased to honour me,) I hope Shortly to shew you, by no doubtful proofs, That beyond all things, e'en myself, I love you.— My colleague arm'd is from the city gone, With many heroes, to the camp, to meet And safely to collect those who have left Justly the standard of our vile oppressors. People, patricians, knights, and senators, I all of you assemble in the forum; Since the great cause of all I wish to treat Before you all convened. Now every Roman Is so inalienably a part of Rome, That nothing but his own degeneracy Can from her solemn meetings banish him.— Noble patricians, ye, the scanty remnant, Uninjured by th'exterminating sword Of the despotic king; and ye, their flower, Oh senators, ye will not be averse To mingle with a free and manly people. Ah no, ye are too lofty. All around, Far as I cast my eyes, I see all Romans; And there are none of them unworthy you, Since among us there are no longer kings.— Trembling and insecure, kings hitherto Our lips have seal'd: nor was there left for us Any alternative, except to load Ourselves with infamy, giving assent To their iniquitous flagitious laws; Or, if the courage rose in us, to oppose Ourselves to them in vain, to be the first To fall the luckless victims of their rage. Va. Brutus, thy words are true.—I, in the name Of all the senators, appeal to Rome. Too true indeed are they.—We a long time On Rome's obscurest citizens reduced To look with envy; more than any culprit Forced to despise ourselves; what need more words? Besides our portion in the common load Of execrable servitude, compell'd In the dark mysteries of tyranny To take a part, we, yes, we sunk ourselves Below the lowest people; and we were so. Nor to the multitude should one of us Hope to seem guiltless, save the many slain By th'impious royal axe. Nought else remains To us to-day, then, but to reunite Our heartiest efforts with the noble people's; Nor otherwise to covet to surpass them, Except in hate to kings. This sacred hate Will be th'eternal, sublime base of Rome. We then, yes, we, by the infernal gods, By our own blood, and by our children's blood, Swear it ferociously with one accord. People. Oh noble! oh magnanimous! Oh ye Alone now worthy to surpass us! We Gladly accept the noble strife of virtue. What people now will undertake to cope, Much less the vanquish'd execrable kings, (Already vanquish'd by their turpitude,) With us, at once Romans and citizens? Bru. Immortal contest! superhuman words! ... I die contented: I for once at least Have utter'd accents worthy of a Roman; And have indeed with these my ears once heard True Roman eloquence. Now since Rome trusts Herself to us wholly for her defence, Without her walls I instantly depart; And to you day by day of all our schemes My colleague or myself will give account; Until, our arms laid down, in perfect peace Ye give a stable government to Rome. People. 'Tis needful first wholly to disconcert Defeat, and slay the tyrants. Bru. I, in this, And nothing else, will be your chief.—Be pleased Briefly to hear a messenger of theirs; He, in their name, solicits to address you. Would you believe it? Tarquin, and with him The impious Sextius, and a few more, dared Erewhile to make incursion with full speed Almost to Rome; thinking to come to us As to a timorous flock, vain-glorious fools! But they in this were much deceived; my son Tiberius the honour robb'd from me Of first attacking them. The miscreants Betook themselves from him by sudden flight: Descending thence from force to art, they dare To send to you as an ambassador Mamilius. What may be the unworthy terms Will you be pleased to hear? People. There are 'twixt us No other terms except their death or ours. Bru. This let him hear then, and report. People. To us Now let this servile herald quickly come. Let him too hear the sentiments of Rome, And bear them back to him who sent him hither. SCENE THE SIXTH. Brutus, Titus, Tiberius, Mamilius, Valerius, People, Senators, Patricians. Bru. Mamilius, come, advance; examine well By whom thou art surrounded. In the court Of Tarquin thou, effeminately nursed, Hast never yet seen Rome; this, this is she, Behold her undisguised, and patiently Prepared to hear thy message. Now proceed. Ma. Oh Brutus, with no unimportant words Was I commission'd to bespeak thy hearing: But in this vast assembly, ... to divulge ... Without premeditation ... Bru. Audibly Address thyself to all, and not to me. Sublime announcer of the will of kings, Divulge it to the people, to the senate: Brutus will also hear thee with the rest. People. Speak, speak to all; and thou of all shalt hear, In a few words, the answer, from the mouth Of our great consul Brutus. See in him Our genuine interpreter; alone Worthy to be the organ of our thoughts. Make haste, proceed: and brief be thy harangue: Frank and explicit shall our answer be. Bru. Heard'st thou? Ma. I tremble. Tarquin, king ... People. Not king Of Rome ... Ma. —Of Rome, Tarquin the friend and father ... People. He is the father of the impious Sextius, And not of us ... Bru. Whate'er his words may be, May ye be pleased to hear him in complete Dignified silence. Ma. To yourselves erewhile Came Tarquin, at the earliest news that Rome Rebell'd; almost defenceless and alone, Fully relying on his innocence, And on his people's loyalty, he came: But armed men repell'd him. Hence he sent me, A messenger of peace; and by my means Enquires, what is the crime, whence in your sight So guilty, that to-day he's doom'd to lose The throne of Rome, once his by your consent ... People. Heard ye? Incredible audacity! Slain is Lucretia, and he asks his crime? Ma. That was the guilt of Sextius, not his ... Tib. And Sextius also at his father's side Erewhile repair'd to Rome: and had they not Both been compell'd to save their lives by flight, Here had ye seen him now. People. Ah why did ye Frustrate their wish to gain access to Rome? Already had we torn their scatter'd limbs In thousand thousand pieces. Ma. It is true, Sextius was also with his father there: But Tarquin, more a monarch than a father, Thither enticed his son, to subject him To a retributory punishment. Bru. This is an impudent unmanly lie; And robs me utterly of self-controul. If, to preserve his throne, the guilty father Offer'd to sacrifice his guilty son, Should we consent to it? The murder'd lady Hath brought, 'tis true, our sufferance to a crisis; But, without this, is not the haughty father, The mother, and the whole opprobrious race Of impure Sextius, stain'd with thousand crimes? Servius, that perfect king, and Tullia's father, Was by the husband of that Tullia slain: Tullia, detested monster! mounts the throne, Trampling beneath her horses feet the corse Of her slain father: afterwards their reign By bloodshed and oppression was distinguish'd; The senators and citizens destroy'd; And those not murder'd cruelly despoil'd; Dragg'd from the service of magnanimous war, (To which alone are Roman heroes born,) Vilely to hollow and to pile whole quarries, Which will remain eternal monument Both of their bondage and of regal pride. One after t'other, their so many crimes ... When, when should I conclude my narrative, If one by one I should enumerate The Tarquins' trespasses? Lucretia's death Was last of these; and their impiety, And our endurance, terminate with this. People. This is the last; Rome swears it is the last. Va. This we all swear: we all will rather die Ere impious Tarquin e'er return to Rome. Bru. Mamilius, well, thou art confused and mute; Thou mightest clearly have foreseen the answer. Go then, repeat it to thy lord, since thou To being a man, preferr'st to be a slave. Ma. I might urge many arguments; ... but none ... People. No, no! there are 'twixt citizens oppress'd And a despotic king no arguments, Save those which hurtle in the field of Mars. Heard he indeed our arguments and prayers When on the throne he sat, puff'd up with pride, And steel'd with cruelty? Did he not then Laugh at our tears, and scoff at our complaints? Ma. Then may another king with milder sway More satisfy your hearts.—My whole discourse I now shall terminate in one request.— Tarquin in Rome has left abundant wealth, Indisputably his; would it be just That ye, besides his honours, throne, and country, Should rob him of his substance? People. —Answer this, Brutus, for us. Bru. His country is not taken From Tarquin by the Romans: kings have not A country ever; nor deserve they one: They never were, nor are of Roman blood. They have themselves defrauded of their honour For a long time. Henceforth, by our decree, The monarch and the monarchy from Rome Are banish'd everlastingly; the throne Is, by the flames, consumed to noisome dust; Nor is a trace remaining of it now. 'Tis true in part, that, when they came to Rome, Their foreign innovating ancestors Infamous treasures brought, which, afterwards Insidiously dispersed, at first conduced To vitiate our simple ancient customs. Their wealth was afterwards the fruit of rapine, And was augmented by our sweat and blood; From whence the Romans equitably might Resume it for themselves. But Rome esteems The Tarquins only worthy to enjoy it, And gives it all to them. People. Oh heart sublime! The tutelary genius of Rome In Brutus speaks. Be his decree fulfill'd ... Let Tarquin have this guilty wealth ... Bru. With gold May vice and every royal feculence Depart.—Go hence, Mamilius, and collect Their treasures with all possible dispatch: My sons shall be to thee in this thy task, Both guardians and assistants. Go ye with him. SCENE THE SEVENTH. Brutus, People, Valerius, Senators, Patricians. Bru. Methinks, oh citizens, 'tis now high time The forum to abandon, to repair Arm'd to the camp. Let us, let us behold If Tarquin dare to challenge with his sword Another answer from us. People. Brutus, see Thy chosen followers are all accoutred. Bru. Let us then go to victory or death.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT THE THIRD. SCENE THE FIRST. Tiberius, Mamilius. Tib. Mamilius, come, I must obey my father: This moment hath he sent to me a message, Which peremptorily insists on this: Thou with the setting sun must go from hence. Ma. Oh! how can he presume to abrogate That which himself with universal Rome Granted to me this morning? ... Tib. He alone Forbids thy longer tarriance here: ere long The hoarded wealth, solicited and granted, Shall from the gates pursue thee.—Let us go ... Ma. Say, in what manner am I authorized To greet unhappy Aruns in thy name? Tib. Tell him, ... that he alone deserveth not To be by birth a Tarquin; and that I, Still mindful of our friendship, feel no small Compassion for his fate.—For him I can Do nothing ... Ma. For thyself, thou canst do much. Tib. What dost thou mean? Ma. That if compassion yet Find an admission in thy youthful breast, Thou for thyself and for thy friends should'st feel it. Tib. What sayest thou? Ma. That Aruns' pity, (and soon,) More than thine him, may benefit thyself. Dangers and obstacles thou seest not, Intoxicate with freedom: but canst thou Think that they ever can be permanent, These innovating, undigested plans, These mere chimeras of a government? Tib. I easily believe, since thou'rt a slave, That freedom seems impossible to thee: But the unanimous consent of Rome ... Ma. Th'authentic wishes of another Rome Have I since heard: thou dost excite my pity; Thou who with thy infatuated father Dost rush towards the fatal precipice.— But Titus comes to join us.—Ah! perchance, Thy brother may himself expose to thee, Better than me, the dubious state of things. SCENE THE SECOND. Titus, Mamilius, Tiberius. Tit. I ran in quest of thee; fain would I speak ... Tib. I cannot hear thee now. Ma. Immediately He ought to drag me forth from Rome: to this His father's absolute command compels him.— How much I pity you, oh youths! ... Tib. Meanwhile Let us depart.—I presently return To listen to thee, Titus. Tit. And this man, What would he say? Ma. Let us depart: perchance I may, as we proceed, communicate That which thy brother now would tell thee. Tit. Stop. To learn from thee ... Ma. More than thou know'st I'll tell thee. It all depends on me: I can, I only, Deliver you from mighty perils ... Tib. Thou Artfully speak'st ... Tit. And what depends on thee? Ma. Tiberius, and Titus, and your Brutus, And Collatinus, and e'en Rome herself. Tib. Vain-glorious fool! what sayest thou? Tit. I know The guilty hope ... Ma. Hope! it is certainty. Already a confederacy is form'd In favour of the Tarquins, and complete: Nor are the Aquilii the sole confederates, As thou dost think, oh Titus: with these are Th'Octavii, the Marcii, and others; Hundreds and hundreds of patrician rank; And many more, consummately esteem'd Among the very people ... Tib. What do I hear? ... Tit. 'Tis true, too true in part: there is in Rome A spirit of sedition. Numbers met In solemn conference where th'Aquilii dwell: As friend and relative, I sought their dwelling, And from th'assembly was alone excluded. A strong suspicion thence arose in me ... Ma. I was in conference with th'Aquilii, While thou wert thus excluded: finally, So strong, so certain, and so well assured Is the confederacy, that I fear not To reveal it to you. Tib. Perfidious ... Tit. There Hast thou employ'd thy abject arts ... Ma. Hear, hear, Ye sons of Brutus, that which I would say.— Had it been my contrivance thus to form So quickly such a formidable plot, I had not been on this account perfidious. For the most just and sanctimonious cause Of a legitimate king had I attempted To turn to equity and penitence His subjects, to their several duties blind, Seduced from truth; nor would this too have been Perfidious. But I neither ought, nor will, Take to myself the honour of a deed Which neither cost me labour or design. Scarce was the popular conventicle Dissolved, ere I clandestinely received An invitation to a secret council. Here with amazement was I overwhelm'd, Such and so many, and such ardent friends Of the expell'd, calumniated Tarquins To see united: emulously all They promised me far more than I from them Had ventured to demand. They all agreed For Sextius alone to stipulate The punishment he merited. And Sextius Is culpable; and, e'en more than Rome can be, His father is incensed 'gainst him; and swears On him an entire vengeance. I made known To them this resolution of the king: Then all with one voice cried, “We will lay down Our lives to reinstate him in the throne.” This of the noblest and best part of Rome, This was the cry.—Now ye, see ye not clearly, From this account, that artifice is not Embosom'd in me; I reveal the whole To save you, and to save at the same time, If he consent to it, your sire himself. Tib. Since thou already know'st so much, I deem That it were best, till Brutus's return, To urge thy stay in Rome. I now perceive Why Brutus sent so expeditiously The order to expel thee; but, alas! It came to me too late ... Tit. Thou thinkest justly: Meanwhile do thou watch over him with care. The most secure asylum in the which To place Mamilius, appears to me The house of the Vitellii, our cousins. I to the camp shall fly, to expedite My sire's return from thence. Ma. Since I esteem'd Your natures courteous, I have spoken frankly. Will it now please ye to betray me? Do it; Further if it please Brutus to infringe The sacred rights of hospitality, Let him, in my case, do it; but already So far have matters gone, that benefit, In consequence of aught that I may suffer, Cannot accrue to Brutus or yourselves. Already far beyond what ye suspect Is the confederacy advanced. E'en now Your father and his colleagues, and the dregs Of the vile populace alone remain The nerve and sinew of rebellion's cause. Go to thy father, Titus, if thou wilt: The more thou dost accelerate his return, So much the more dost thou accelerate His evil destiny.—Deposit me With the Vitellii quickly; I shall be Far safer in their custody than thou. Tib. What vile suspicion would'st thou thus? ... Ma. I speak Not from suspicion, but from certainty. E'en the Vitellii, the four faithful brothers Of Brutus' consort, of your mother, they, As much by amity to Brutus bound As by the ties of blood, e'en they desire To reinstate Tarquinius on the throne. Tit. Oh heaven! ... Tib. This is a lie ... Ma. This scroll, in which, Sign'd by themselves, the most illustrious names Of the confederates are at length inscribed, Will, without doubt, convince you.—Look at it: Beneath the Aquilii's names, now, one by one, Read there, their four names written. Tib. Dreadful sight! Tit. Oh heaven! what will become then of my father? ... Tib. Oh day of sorrow! Oh devoted Rome! Ma. Nor fondly dream ye, since this scroll I bear, That the success of the confederacy On my departure hangs. Clandestinely Already is a faithful messenger Of mine from Rome departed; and to Tarquin Already is the project fully known Th'Etrurians to his standard flock in numbers; The powerful king of Cutia takes his part; Tarquinia, Veia, lastly all Etruria, All Rome, except the consuls and yourselves. This scroll is written with no other purpose Than to obtain the clemency of Tarquin In favour of the names therein inscribed. Surrender me, and with myself this scroll, Into your father's hands; and ye perchance May for awhile cause your relations' blood To flow in rivers; but, or soon or late, Your father ye condemn to certain death; For, do ye what ye may, Tarquin will be, Ere long, inevitably king in Rome. Tit. Ah! I too clearly did anticipate What now I hear. I said it to my father ... Tib. Alas! we are driven to a perilous straight! What should we do? Ah! speak ... Tit. Peril immense Threatens our father ... Tib. And still greater Rome ... Ma. Wherefore this secret conference prolong? I am prepared for all, whether ye chuse To drag me forth from Rome, or, bound with chains, To keep me there a captive: but if love, True love for Rome, your father, and yourselves, Dwell in your bosom, ye at once will save Yourselves, your father, and your native Rome. All this is in your power. Tit. How? ... Tib. What hop'st thou? Ma. Add but your names with your own hand to these, And all will then be safe. Tib. Oh heaven! shall we Our father and our country thus betray? ... Ma. Your honour and your tutelary Gods, Your father and your country ye betray'd, Then when ye dared 'gainst your legitimate king Rebelliously to rise. Yet had your fate Granted a happy issue to your scheme, Ye had, at least, some recompense obtain'd For this your treachery: but since ye see That prospect vanish'd, (I again repeat it,) With further perseverance you will drag, And vainly drag, to dire calamity Your country, and your father, and yourselves. Tit. But, tell me, what would be our gain, should we Annex our names to those already written? To what do these subscribers pledge themselves? Ma. To things most just. First, from the king's own lips To hear his own defence; to make yourselves, The king being present, judges of the late And horrible misdemeanour of his son; To see him punish'd; to regenerate And reinstate, in splendour and in peace, Beneath the sway of less despotic laws, Your agitated country ... Doing this, Ah! ye will hear yourselves beyond all others Hail'd as the true deliverers of the state; Provided that 'twixt Brutus and Tarquinius Ye be the instruments of lasting friendship; The only means now to place Rome in safety. Tit. Assuredly we might do this ... Tib. Reflect ... Who knows? ... Perhaps other means ... Tit. What other means Remain for us now? The confederacy Too powerful is ... Tib. I'm younger than thyself; In so important a concern I will not, Nor can I, part myself from thee: too much I've always loved thee: but I feel at heart A horrible presage ... Tit. But the night approaches, Yet neither Collatinus nor my father Do I behold with their arm'd men return To Rome: his messenger already is To Tarquin gone; we are on all sides press'd; At least it now behoves us for the present To appease the king ... Ma. The hour is late; resolve: 'Tis vain this whispering apart from me. Whether for my advantage ye decide T'exert yourselves, or (with more truth) for yours, The swiftest now will be the best decision. Resolve; behold the scroll. Rich with your names, Ye'll make me speedily depart from Rome, That peace to Rome may speedily return. Tit. Heaven I attest; it seeth my pure heart; It knows that nothing but the good of others To this compels me ... Tib. Heaven! what art thou doing? ... Tit. Behold my name. Tib. —And be it, if thou wilt.— Behold my own name, oh Mamilius, sign'd. Ma. I go contented. Tit. Do thou then conduct him; While I ... SCENE THE THIRD. Lictors, Collatinus with a number of Soldiers, Titus, Mamilius, Tiberius. Col. What do I see? Mamilius yet In Rome? Tib. Oh heaven! ... Tit. Oh inauspicious meeting! Col. And ye, have ye thus kept the absolute And peremptory order of your father? But wherefore are ye agitated thus? Wherefore thus mute?—Ah, heaven be praised! perchance I yet arrive in time.—Lictors, advance; Be Titus and Tiberius instantly In fetters bound ... Tit. Ah, hear us! ... Col. Rome, ere long, Shall hear you, and the consul Brutus. Drag To their paternal dwelling the two brothers; And watch them there. Tib. Ah Titus! SCENE THE FOURTH. Collatinus, Mamilius, Soldiers. Col. (To the Soldiers.) And do you Escort Mamilius through the gates ... On things of loftiest consequence. Col. —Oh Brutus! ... Yet stay a little while.—Command thy troops, Yet keeping under arms, to draw aside: I ought to speak with thee in private here. Bru. Ah, wherefore? ... Col. The interests of Rome require it; I pray thee grant me this ... Bru. In double troop, At the entrance of the forum, wait for me, Oh soldiers.—Lictors, draw aside a little. Col. —Ah Brutus! ... Thou wilt vainly, vainly seek, Amid thy Lares, in this horrible night, Even a transient rest. Bru. What would'st thou tell me? ... Whence art thou troubled, anxious, trembling thus? Col. Yes, I indeed tremble for Brutus, Rome, And all of us.—This morning thou, oh Brutus, Didst, with compassionate hand, to my profound And recent wound a “flattering unction” lay Of vengeance and of hope: and I, alas! Am forced to give thee, as a recompence, To give thee in thy heart a wound more fatal. Why have I lived till now? ... Oh desolate, Distracted father! Thou art now compell'd, From a disconsolate and widow'd husband Tidings to hear, which in thy heart will fix A mortal wound! ... Yet neither can I hide them, Nor yet to thee delay their utterance. Bru. Alas! ... I shudder at thy words ... But yet Worse than the evil is its expectation. Speak. I that hitherto in servitude Have dragg'd a painful life, have long been used To tremble always for my dearest treasures. Private calamities, whate'er they be, So that the liberties of Rome be safe, I can endure to hear: speak. Col. On thyself, (But too emphatically,) on thyself The liberties of Rome are now dependent; But at a price so vast that I almost ... Oh dreadful day! ... I was the first that gave Occasion for the lofty enterprize, By a hard sacrifice; but to conclude it ... Oh heaven! ... 'tis indispensable that Brutus Prepare to manifest to assembled Rome A cruel, fierce, unparallel'd example Of desperate fortitude.—Amid thy Lares, (Would'st thou believe it?) thou liv'st not in safety. A powerful, numerous, fierce conspiracy In Rome now rages. Bru. I suspected it, In hearing of the strenuous cabals Of insincere Mamilius; and in haste I expedited to Tiberius hence An express order, ere the hour of three, T'expel him from the city. Col. When the sun Was sinking in the barriers of the west, I found Mamilius still had linger'd here With both thy sons.—It grieves me to repeat it; But it is too true; thou wert ill obey'd. Bru. Oh what a conflict dost thou raise in me Of fear and indignation! ... Col. Wretched Brutus! ... What wilt thou feel when the conspiracy To thee I publish? ... and when thou shalt hear The names of the conspirators? ... Then, first, Among a number of thy nearest friends And relatives, first the Vitellii are A part and instigators of the plot ... Bru. Alas! the brothers of my wife! Col. Who knows If also she be not seduced by them? And, ... then ... thy sons ... themselves! ... Bru. What do I hear? ... Oh heaven! my blood freezes in every vein! ... My sons conspirators! ... It cannot be! ... Col. Oh Brutus ... that it were not so!—And I, At first, would not believe it: afterwards My eyes compell'd me to implicit faith.— This is a paper fatal to our peace: Read it. Bru. ... My tremulous heart is chill'd with fear. What do I here behold? ... Name after name, With their own hand inscribed; the Aquilii first, Then the Vitellii, and the Martii; And others after others; ... and, at last, ... Titus, Tiberius! ... Ah! this is enough ... No more; ... I've seen too much.—Unhappy Brutus! Thou art no more a father ... —But, thou'rt yet Consul, no less than citizen of Rome.— Titus, ho, Titus, and Tiberius, quick, Let them be brought before me. Col. Ah! oh Brutus, It had been better hadst thou suffer'd me To die alone ... Bru. How fell into thy hands This terrible paper? Col. I myself beheld it, Though swiftly he conceal'd it, in the hands Of the infamous Mamilius I beheld it; Thence I, in his expulsion from the city, Constrain'd him to surrender it. Meanwhile, In thy own dwelling, to a faithful guard, Thy sons had I committed; in an instant 'Gainst every accident I had provided. And now, I hope, that all these machinations Will be completely baffled. Luckily I was informed of them in time; and Jove, In his compassion, certainly ordain'd That such a horrible mystery to me, Me, not a father, should be first divulged. I tell this to thee trembling and with tears. But yet 'tis fit that I reveal it to thee Ere to thy dwelling thou ... Bru. No other dwelling Except the forum and the tomb, remains For wretched Brutus.—'Tis my duty now To give, ere death to Brutus, life to Rome. Col. My heart thou rendest. Thy excessive grief Makes me almost insensible to mine ... But, who can tell? ... Perchance thy sons, e'en yet, May exculpate themselves ... Hear them thyself ... I have not yet of this conspiracy Spoken to any one except thyself: I will adopt the most effectual measures That no man, during this approaching night, Shall even quit his dwelling: all the people I have by day-break summon'd to the forum. Bru. And all the people, by to-morrow's dawn, The real truth, whate'er that truth may be, Shall from my lips receive. Col. I hear, methinks, The steps of the unhappy youths ... Bru. My sons! ... Such I this morning deem'd them; foes to me They're now become, and traitors to their country ..</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE THE THIRD. Titus, Tiberius, among Lictors, Brutus, Collatinus. Bru. Let every man retire: do ye alone Advance. Tit. Ah father! ... Bru. I of Rome am consul.— I ask of you if ye are citizens Of Rome. Tib. We are; and sons of Brutus yet ... Tit. And we will prove it, if the consul deign To hear us. Col. At their gestures, at their words, I feel my heart transpierced. Bru. —This is a scroll, Which the perfidious Mamilius bore To the proscribed Tarquinii. In that paper, With many other names, are yours inscribed. Ye to your country then are traitors; now No more the sons of Brutus, but the sons Of infamous expatriated tyrants. Tit. 'Tis true, (too true,) that I first added there 'Neath many other noble names, my name, And his my brother afterwards inscribed, By my example urged. He is not guilty: Be it whate'er it may, the penalty To me alone is due. He evermore Dissuaded me ... Tib. Yet I, perplex'd, confounded, Knew not what other council to propose: And it seem'd indispensable to us To save, at all events, our sire betray'd. Mamilius had so artfully perplex'd Falsehood and truth, that we, caught by his arts, Deeming our father by all men abandon'd, Were inadvertently ourselves constrain'd Thus to betray him, by our too great love. Ah! if we're criminal, alike have we Incurr'd the punishment annex'd to guilt: But the sole punishment we apprehend, The sole insufferable punishment, (Paternal hatred,) we call heaven to witness, And swear that neither of us merit this. Bru. Oh infamy! and have ye promised then To reinstate, with these confederate traitors, The banish'd tyrant? Tit. By my signature I hoped t'appease that tyrant towards my father ... Bru. To Brutus! Tarquin be appeased towards Brutus!— And even were it thus, perfidious youth! Should'st thou betray thy country e'en for me? Did ye not both erewhile, both swear with me, Rather to die than ever to submit, Let him be who he may, to any king? Tit. This I deny not, no ... Bru. Then ye are both Perjured and traitors! ... In this paper ye Have sign'd at once your own death ... and your father's! ... Tib. Thou weepest, father! ... If paternal tears, Moistening the stern eyes of the rigid judge, Attest at least that altogether we Are not unworthy of thy tenderness, We die exulting for the sake of Rome. Tit. But, though mistaken, Titus neither was Or vile or criminal ... Bru. Oh sons! oh sons! ... —Why do I call ye sons? Ye are my first, Ye are my sole dishonour. At the expense Both of his glory and his liberty, Ye, ye would purchase for your wretched father A despicable life! Ye would reduce me To pine with you in double slavery, Then when 'twas in your power to go with Free and unshackled, to a generous death! And to achieve an enterprize so base, Ye became traitors to your nascent country! To honour deaf, and perjured to the Gods!— And let me grant that I had been to-day Deserted and betray'd by every Roman; That, following your example, I had stoop'd The pity of the tyrant to implore; Ah fools! yet more, far more than guilty fools! Could you e'er think that the ferocious heart Of an expell'd, exasperated tyrant, Could aught imbibe except a raging thirst For bloodshed and revenge? To certain death, To an opprobrious and lingering death, Did ye, to save him, now reserve your father! Tit. Fear, I confess, in reading in that scroll So many, and so many potent names, My breast invaded, and made me esteem The lofty enterprize impossible. Already, as thou knowest, (although my heart Wish'd its success,) I thought it difficult, And in itself both perilous and doubtful: Hence, when I saw the aspect of events In such a short space absolutely change; Saw to the king the citizens return, And those the most illustrious, in a crowd; I fear'd for Rome, where much blood, and in vain, And first of all thy blood, was doom'd to run. A hope sprung in my heart, that, if our names Were added to the names already written, Thus, by our means, our father might at least Be rescued from the vengeance of the king: And this to us Mamilius craftily Promised in many words. Bru. What hast thou done? What hast thou done? Oh heaven! Ah, at that time Thou wert a citizen of Rome no longer; Since thou for me betrayedst Rome ... Nor then Wert thou a son of Brutus, since his honour Thou soldest at the price of servitude. Tib. Ah father, do not wreak on him alone Thy just disdain; I equally deserve it. I also fear'd for thee, I must confess it; We loved our father better than our country: Yes, father, this alone was our offence. Col. Ah wretched youths! ... Ah wretched father! Bru. Yes, Ye were indeed more than the sons of Rome, The sons of Brutus! Brought up as ye were In abject slavery, I indeed constrain'd From the complexion of the times to cheat you; With lofty and invigorating thoughts I could not foster you as it behoved A citizen and parent ... Oh my sons, I for your error seek no other cause. Myself, myself alone I blame for this, My silence and my pristine servitude; And, though assumed, my very fear itself, Which taught you also to be apprehensive. Ah! pity in my bosom is not mute; ... But, in a more authoritative voice, Tremendous justice to my conscience cries; And Rome now rightfully lays claim to it.— My sons, beloved sons, I am, alas! More wretched far than you ... Ah why, oh heaven! Since in your free arbitrement it lay Rome to betray, or doom your sire to death, Wherefore did ye forget that to avert From Brutus infamy (his only death) A sword was all sufficient? And he had one; This his sons knew; and how, when they knew this, Could they one moment tremble for their father? Col. Ah! for awhile, oh Brutus, somewhat calm Thy grief and indignation; yet who knows ... To save them perhaps ... Tit. Ah! ye would wish in vain To save me now: I could no longer live! I've lost my sire's esteem, perhaps his love ... No, 'tis not possible for me to live. But let my sad example exculpate My innocent, younger brother; save him, father ... Tib. Immense, oh father, is our guilt. But we Alike are guilty; and thou wert not just, If thou on us an equal punishment Inflictest not. Perchance expressly now The tutelary genius of Rome Decrees to liberty a lasting basis In our severe example. Bru. On my sons! ... Ah! let this now suffice. Your excellent, Sublime, immortalizing penitence Tears as by piecemeal my distracted heart ... Alas! e'en yet I am, e'en yet a father More than a consul ... Through my every vein I feel a horrid chillness creep ... Ah all, Yes, all my blood will, for my country's sake, Ere long be shed ... To re-establish Rome The last blood indispensable is mine: Provided that I enfranchise my country, I swear, oh sons, that I will not one day Survive your loss.—Let me for the last time, Beloved children, clasp you to my breast; ... Yet I can do it ... Tears, alas! forbid ... My further utterance ... Much-loved sons, farewell. Consul of Rome, to thee do I restore The fatal tablet. An imperious duty Wills, that to-morrow, without subterfuge, It be presented to assembled Rome. Meanwhile the guilty to thy custody Are all committed. I will also come, At early dawn, to meet thee in the forum. I cannot longer now endure the presence Of such an agonizing spectacle. SCENE THE FOURTH. Collatinus, Titus, Tiberius, Lictors. Col. Fatal necessity! Tit. Unhappy father! Tib. Provided Rome be saved ... Col. All follow me.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT THE FIFTH. SCENE THE FIRST. People, Valerius, Senators, Patricians, all seated. Collatinus and Brutus in the Rostrum. Col. Romans, to you the sun of yesterday Triumphantly and joyfully arose; When, at this hour exactly, from yourselves The earliest cries of liberty resounded Through the wide air; I, in my grief absorb'd, Meanwhile stood mute. But on this horrible day A part quite different, alas! on me Devolves by lot, since, with the noble Brutus, Ye have been pleased t'elect me for your consul.— All swore, (I hope ye recollect it well,) All of ye, in the forum, yesterday, Swore to the gods, that, sooner than return To the vile yoke of monarchs, ye would die. And not alone the execrable Tarquins, But every man that dared to make himself Superior to the laws, by this your oath Expressly was proscribed.—Would ye believe it? I, in your presence, I am now constrain'd, 'Mong the most powerful noble citizens, To impeach many, infamous and perjured, Who have, 'gainst Rome and 'gainst themselves, (too much so!) Been plotting for the Tarquins. People. For the Tarquins! Who are they? Who are the flagitious traitors, Unworthy to be Romans? Quickly, name them; We will, they all be slain ... Col. Ah! ... who can tell ... Perhaps ... when ye hear the names? ... When I attempt To utter them, I tremble ... And far more Shall I implore from you your clemency Than your stern justice. Almost all of these Are youths: they have not, from their unripe age, Yet felt the ills, so countless and so bitter, Of civil servitude: the greater part, Enervated by indolence, brought up In a corrupted court's pestiferous shade, Have only tasted tyranny's sweet bait, Yet unacquainted with the lurking poison. People. Whoe'er they be indeed, they're traitors, perjured; Compassion they deserve not; let them perish: The corrupt, putrid, vitiating members Of a new city, liberty decrees That they be first lopp'd off.—Pronounce their names. Va. And we, although too thoroughly convinced That this disgrace (their permanent dishonour) To the patrician tribe belongs, yet now We with the people emulously seek To know the culprits' names.—Oh noble people! For high achievements born! Oh happy ye! Ye only did sustain the tyrant's yoke; But to the coveted impediment Of fetters well deserved, in us were join'd, Debased patricians! their disgrace and shame. We, nearer to the tyrant, more enslaved, And less regretting slavery than you; We thence assuredly more worthy slavery: I feel the presage; yes, we, we have been The first in perjury.—Oh Collatinus, I ask it of thee, whosoe'er they be, Divulge the criminals. What terrible, What inextinguishable thirst of honour Pervades her citizens, Rome should to-day Acknowledge from a memorable proof. People. Oh worthy ye of better fate! ... May heaven Grant, that the few to servitude seduced, Either plebeian or patrician names No longer bear! The trait'rous and the perjured Cease to be Romans. Col. Many are the guilty; But different their degrees of guilt. There are Among them those who servitude abhor, And who have elevated courteous hearts; But in a thousand ways assail'd, entrapp'd, By base Mamilius ... People. Where is the impostor? Oh rage! where is he? ... Col. Ere the night was closed, From Rome I banish'd him; the sacred rights Of hospitality required his safety, Though he were culpable. Religiously The citizens of Rome each right observe: Faith is the basis of our sacred freedom. People. In truth thou hast done well from our first rage To wrest him: justice thus is not by us Attainted. We shall have, in fair array, The gods themselves and virtue with us listed: But round the banners of the heart-struck tyrants Treason, dissimulation, abject fear, The appalling ministers of heavenly vengeance, Eternally shall lour ... Va. But shall we give them, That so they may avail themselves of it To injure Rome, their vitiating wealth? Far more than steel, gold in the tyrant's hands We've reason now to deprecate. People. 'Tis true; We will not to their baseness lend such arms: But hence shall we another's make our own? What boots to us, who in our hands have swords, And at our breasts a mail of liberty, What boots to us the ministry of gold? Va. Let it be burn'd; let all the tyrant's wealth Be burn'd, or to the Tyber's whelming waves Committed. People. And with these eternally May their remembrance perish ... Va. Likewise perish All recollection of our servitude. Col. Magnanimous, and worthy of yourselves, Is the decision; your decree in this Shall quickly be fulfill'd. People. Yes; but meanwhile The names of the conspirators divulge, And the conspiracy. Col. ... Oh heaven! ... I tremble In undertaking such a cruel office ... People. And Brutus stands immoveable and silent. He seems to have his eyes suffused with tears, Though shedding none, and fierce his downcast looks He fixes on the earth.—Oh Collatinus, Do thou then quickly speak. Col. ... Oh heaven! ... Va. But what Then ails thee? The deliverer of Rome, The husband of Lucretia, and our consul, Art thou not, Collatinus? Canst thou be The traitors' friend? And canst thou feel compassion Towards those who for their country felt it not? Col. —When you shall hear me speak, those very pangs Which tear my heart and paralize my tongue Will speedily assail you: weeping, mute, Alarm'd, with pity and amazement stricken, Already I behold you—To the king Mamilius went the bearer of this scroll: I caused it to be taken from his hands, Ere he from Rome departed: and the traitor Confess'd, affrighted, that the citizens Herein inscribed had sworn, the following night To open to the king the gates of Rome. People. Oh treason! Let the guilty perish ... Va. Death Were a light punishment for such a crime. Col. The fatal paper let Valerius read To you assembled. See it; take it: ... I Cannot pronounce these names. Va. What do I see? ... Oh execrable list! ... With his own hand Each one his name has written? ... Romans, hear.— Aquilius the sire, and his six sons, Head the conspiracy; they first are written. Oh heaven! ... Col. To each of them, the paper shewn, They all confess'd it. They are now in chains; And ye will see them dragg'd, ere long, before you. Va. ... Alas! ... There follow ... People. Who does follow? Speak. Va. ... Alas! ... It is incredible. I read ... Four names ... People. Whose names? Proceed ... Va. They were the brothers Of Brutus' consort ... People. The Vitellii? Col. Ah! ... Soon will ye hear far other names than these. —And in your presence, one by one, ere long ... Va. What boots it then, that one by one I name them? Marcii, Octavii, Fabii, I read, And many, many more, alas!—The last Make e'en my hair to stand on end with horror ... Yes ... from my hands ... at such a sight as this ... The paper falls ... People. Who can they be? Va. Oh heaven! ... Ye ... never will believe ... (UNIVERSAL SILENCE.) Bru. —The names last written, Are Titus and Tiberius. People. Thy sons! ... Unhappy father! Inauspicious day! ... Bru. Oh day, to you auspicious! Brutus knows No other sons but Roman citizens; And these are such no longer. Yesterday I swore for Rome's sake to shed all my blood: This oath I'm ready, and at every risk, To-day to consummate ... People. Ah wretched father! (UNIVERSAL SILENCE.) Bru. —But what, with horror stupified, and dumb, Do I see universal Rome? For Brutus Does every individual tremble here?— But say, whom does the fiercest peril menace, Brutus or Rome? Each man that hears my voice Wills beyond all things, or he ought to will, To make his country free, secure, and great; Whate'er the consequence he ought to will it. Chains are in store for us, and cruel slaughter; For Rome her consul trembles; hence her people Cannot now tremble for a single father. The soft affections, and the gush of tears, (That in the forum from a Roman eye Can never start, save when they're shed for Rome,) The soft affections and the gush of tears, In the profound recesses of our hearts Are now suppress'd.—I first should shew to you (Thus destiny ordains) what permanent And lofty base 'tis indispensable For us to give to an eternal city.— Lictors, advance; and let the criminals Be quickly dragg'd in chains into the forum.— Now thou'rt the only, the true king of Rome, People of Mars. Thy majesty by these Hath been offended; signal punishment Is now their due; and the avenging thee Devolves upon the consuls ... Brutus is silent in seeing the lictors return with the conspirators. SCENE THE SECOND. Brutus and Collatinus in the Rostrum. Valerius, People, Senators, Patricians. The Conspirators all in Chains among the Lictors; the last of these Titus and Tiberius. People. Ah! how many, How many may the traitors be? ... Oh heaven! Behold the sons of Brutus! ... Col. Ah! I cannot Longer restrain my tears ... Bru. —A great day, A noble day is this, and evermore Will be a memorable one for Rome.— Oh ye, perfidiously base, who dared Your scarce-awaken'd country to betray, Behold ye all before assembled Rome. Let each of you, if it be possible, Defend himself before her.—All are silent.— Rome and the consuls ask of you yourselves, Whether to you, convicted criminals, The punishment of death be due?— (UNIVERSAL SILENCE.) Bru. —To death Then all of you are equitably sentenced. The people's majesty, with one consent, Pronounces th'irreversible decree. Why should we longer tarry?—Oh! my colleague Weeps, and is silent ... Silent is the senate ... Silent the citizens. People. Oh fatal moment! ... Yet just and necessary is their death. Tit. One innocent alone, amongst us all, Now dies; and this is he. People. Oh pity! See, He of his brother speaks. Tib. Believe him not: Or we are both equally innocent, Or equally transgressors. In the paper My name is written next to his. Bru. No one Whose name is written in that fatal scroll Can be call'd innocent. Some may, perchance, Have been less culpable in their intent, But only to the gods the intent is known; And it would be an arbitrary judgment, And thence unjust, the guilty to absolve, As to condemn them from the inference Drawn from profess'd intention. It would be A spurious judgment, such as kings assume; Not such as by a just and simple people Is held in reverence: people who alone To the tremendous sacred laws submit; And who, save of the letter of those laws, In their decrees, of nought avail themselves. Col. ... Romans, 'tis true, that these unhappy youths Were with the rest of the conspirators Involved; but that they were solicited, Confounded, tamper'd with, and finally, By the iniquitous Mamilius In an inextricable snare entrapp'd, Is also as indubitably true. He made them think that all was in the power Of the expell'd Tarquinii: thence their names (Would you believe it?) also they subscribed Only to save their sire from death ... People. Oh heaven! ... And is this true indeed? We should then save These two alone ... Bru. Alas! what do I hear? ... Is this the people's voice? Just, free, and strong, Ye now would make yourselves, and how? would ye Lay, as the base of such an edifice, A partial application of your laws? That I, a father, might not weep, would ye Now make so many other citizens, Sons, brothers, fathers, weep? To the keen axe, Which they have merited, shall now so many, So many others yield their passive necks, And shall two culprits only be exempt From this, because they seem not what they are? They were the consul's sons, although in deeds They were not so: 'mong the conspirators With their own hand were they enroll'd: or all Or none of them should die. Absolve them all, And at once ruin Rome; save two alone, And if it seem so, it would be unjust. Now, less a just than a compassionate judge, Hath Collatinus these two youths defended, Asserting, that they wish'd to save their father; Perhaps this was true; but perhaps the others wish'd, Their fathers some, their brothers some, and some Their sons to save; and not on this account Are they less guilty, since they rather chose To sacrifice their country than their friends. The father in his heart may weep for this; But in the first place should the genuine consul Secure the safety of his native country ... And afterwards, by mighty grief o'erwhelm'd, Fall on the bodies of his lifeless sons.— Ye will behold, ere many hours are past, To what excess of danger, by these men, Ye have been brought: to fortify our hearts In strength imparted by the strength of others, In individual strength to make us strong, Inflexible as champions of freedom, Cruel, though just, 'tis indispensable That we abide this memorable test.— Depart, oh lictors; be the culprits all Bound to the columns; let the hatchet fall Upon them.—I have not a heart of steel ... Brutus sinks on his seat, and turns his eyes from the spectacle.Ah! Collatinus, this is the time for thee To pity me: perform for me the rest. Collatinus sees the conspirators disposed in order, and bound to the columns. People. Oh cruel sight! ... The wretched father dare Not look at them ... And yet, their death is just. Bru. —The punishment approaches.—The delinquents Have heard the sentence of the consuls ... Now Think on the pangs of the distracted father ... The cleaving hatchet o'er each neck impends ... Oh heaven! my very heart is rent in twain! ... I with my mantle am constrain'd to hide Th'insufferable sight! ... This may, at least, Be granted to the father ... But ye, fix ye on them your eyes: now Rome Free and eternal rises from that blood. Col. Oh superhuman strength! ... Va. Of Rome is Brutus The father and the god ... People. Yes, Brutus is The father and the god of Rome ... Bru. I am The most unhappy man that ever lived. The curtain falls, while the lictors stand ready to strike the conspirators.</field>
   </doc>
</add>