<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Doyle, Francis Hastings, Sir, 1810-1888</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Doyle, Francis Hastings, Sir, 1810-1888</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">doyle francis hastings sir 1810 1888</field>
      <field name="author_text">Doyle, Francis Hastings, Sir, 1810-1888</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1840's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V3.0529.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1849</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460870</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Greek, Modern (1453- )</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Oedipus, King of Thebes</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Oedipus, King of Thebes</field>
      <field name="title_facet">oedipus king of thebes</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">oedipus king of thebes</field>
      <field name="title_text">Oedipus, King of Thebes</field>
      <field name="year_display">1849</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1849</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1849</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460870&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460870&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Doyle, Francis Hastings, Sir, 1810-1888&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;doyle francis hastings sir 1810 1888&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Oedipus, King of Thebes&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;oedipus, king of thebes&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1849&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1849&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Doyle, Francis Hastings, Sir&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1810&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1888&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Oedipus, King of Thebes&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;John Henry Parker&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1849&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3873202-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv30529&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;gre&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Oedipus, King of Thebes&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 160 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Oedipus, King of Thebes.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1849.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Unknown.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ŒDIPUS, KING OF THEBES. TRANSLATED FROM THE “ŒDIPUS TYRANNUS” OF SOPHOCLES.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">NOTICE. The plays of the Athenian dramatists, in spite of their great celebrity, are but little known in this country, except to those who can understand them in the original Greek: their intrinsic merits, however, are such, (to say nothing of their importance to the history of literature,) that they seem to me to deserve more attention from readers in general, than they have hitherto received. That large bodies of men, quite capable of appreciating the master-pieces of antiquity, are now more than ever anxious to share in the benefits and enjoyments of mental cultivation, the various literary institutions for the people, which are fast rising on every side, give abundant proof; and I see no reason why the great writers of Greece (so far as the thing can be done by careful and conscientious translation) should not be made known to that class of persons, of whom such associations are mainly composed. I have accordingly translated, to the best of my ability, the well-known tragedy of the Œdipus Tyrannus, and now publish it at as low a price as I can, in the hope of attracting some of those whom circumstances have shut out from a classical education. The manners and habits of thought prevalent among the Greeks, may, no doubt, be too remote from our own to enable any but those who have been more or less familiarized with them from early youth, to take much interest therein; and if so, my principal object in this publication will be defeated. I am not however without hope, that the sterling merits of Sophocles, faintly reflected as they must be in any translation, will come home to all genuine lovers of poetry, and make him welcome. If this be so, I trust in time to furnish a translation of the other six plays, but upon that subject it is unnecessary to say more at present. I have made my translation, upon the whole, as literal as I could: paraphrases are, no doubt, much easier to execute, and flow more smoothly, but it is so desirable to preserve, not only the thoughts, but also the style of an author unchanged, that no word, small or great, should, I think, be left out of any version, without an effort to bring it in. At the same time, I have endeavoured to bear in mind that I was translating, not only out of Greek, but also into English, and was equally responsible to both languages: whenever, therefore, after doing my best, any particular passage either baffled me altogether, or appeared, in its English dress, intolerably harsh and uncouth, I have not hesitated to give myself somewhat greater liberty. The few notes which I have added to the text, are addressed, almost entirely, to non-classical readers, for purposes of explanation. I cannot conclude this notice without offering my sincere thanks to my kind friend, the Rev. H. Liddell, for his valuable advice. That distinguished scholar was good enough, in spite of the many demands upon his time, to read my manuscript translation carefully through, and to suggest numerous improvements; many of which have been thankfully adopted. FRANCIS HASTINGS DOYLE. 1, Portugal Street, 1849.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DRAMATIS PERSONÆ. Œdipus, King of Thebes. High-priest of Jupiter. Creon, Brother-in-Law to Œdipus. Jocasta, Wife of Œdipus, discovered in the course of the Play to be also his Mother. Tiresias, the Prophet and Soothsayer. A Messenger from Corinth. A Messenger from Thebes. Chorus of aged Thebans. Ismene and Antigone, the Daughters of Œdipus, appear on the scene, but do not break silence.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Scene.—The Court before the Palace of Œdipus. Enter Œdipus addressing the Procession. Œdipus. —My children, the young brood of Cadmus old The Thebans are called the brood of Cadmus, because Cadmus, the son of Agenor, and brother of Europa, laid the foundations of their city, and built a citadel there B. C. 1493., Why sit ye in this posture? why come hither With boughs of supplication thus equipt It was the custom for suppliants to carry boughs of olive, wreathed with wool, as a symbol of their condition. Vid. Liddell and Scott's Lexicon, v. ??????.? Our streets too, wrapt in clouds of incense, ring At once, with sacred hymns, and lamentations. Of this, it suits me not through other men, As messengers, to learn the meaning; wherefore Known to you all as Œdipus the Great, I here in person come. Say then, old man, Since 'tis thy natural post to speak for these, Say, in what spirit are ye sitting here? In panic terror, or in deep submission? Be firm in faith, that every thought of mine Shall work to do you service; for in truth Ruthless of soul I should be, to behold So sad a company, nor pity them. Priest. —Oh Œdipus! king of my native land, Thou seest our ages here—the age of each That round thine altar sits,—these little ones, Of wing too weak as yet to flutter far, And others, weary with the weight of age.— The priest of Jove am I—and these the prime Of all our youth—for, lo, in like array The rest of Thebes before the double shrine Of Pallas, over the Ismenian ashes Ismenus, a river of Thebes, which gave name to the temple of the Ismenian Apollo. Mythologically speaking, Ismenus was the son of Apollo and the nymph Melia. Pindar, in his 11th Pythian, speaks of the temple thus— Haste to the Melian temples stately, Which in their secret places hold The golden tripods stor'd of old; A fane the Loxian honoureth greatly, And calls his own Ismenian shrine, Prophetic seat of truth divine. As a river, Ismenus is generally coupled with the fountain Dirce—as in Eurip. Hercules Furens, Ismenus shall be filled with floating corpses, And Dirce's silver stream run red with blood. And so in many other passages. Pausanias describes this temple in the 10th chapter of his Bœotica, and informs us that the statue of the Ismenian Apollo was the work of Canachus, and was similar in all respects to that, executed by the same sculptor, for the temple of the Branchidæ in Asia Minor, except that the Ismenian statue was of cedar, the Asiatic one of brass. Divination from the ashes of the victims. Pausanias, Bœotica, c. xi., mentions an altar of Apollo Spodius or Spondius which was built of the ashes of the victims, and from which oracles were delivered by the observation of ominous words, (??? ????????,) but this was within the walls of Thebes, and distinct from the Ismenian temple. Oracular, sits in our public halls. For, as thou seest, the state is tempest-tost Beyond her strength, nor can she lift her head Up from the depths of this ensanguin'd sea: She perishes, in all she perishes, Her fruitful crops are blasted in the bud, Her grazing herds are stricken, and the pangs Of teeming women come not to the birth; Whilst the flame-breathing god, loath'd Pestilence Ares or Mars, the god of war and destruction, is supposed to have taken upon himself the character of a pestilence, as a new method of satiating his appetite for human slaughter; the same idea is repeated in the chorus, line 205–208., Shatters the reeling city, touched by whom Desolate are the halls of Cadmus, and Black Hades Hades, the place of departed spirits; the invisible world. is enriched by sobs and groans. 'Tis not because we rank thee with the gods That we, these youths and I, surround thy door, But that we deem thee first of men, to face Life's common chances, and those ills which flow from Directer intervention of the gods: Thou who, to Thebes once come, didst cancel straight The rent to that grim songstress The Sphinx, a monster with a woman's head and breast, lion's paws, &amp;c., sent by Juno to persecute the Thebans; she proposed enigmas to them, which if they failed to solve, she devoured them at once. Œdipus, by solving one of these riddles, became, according to the decree of the gods, the master of her destiny, and compelled her to destroy herself, thereby rescuing the Thebans from complete extinction at her hands, in return for which he was elected to be their king, receiving at the same time Jocasta, the widow of Laius, in marriage., which we paid: And that by us untaught, unhelped, in truth Men say, and think, 'twas through some god's assistance Our life by thee was lifted from the earth; Come then, thou noblest nature, Œdipus. To thee we all bow down in supplication— Find out some means of help, if thou hast heard The voice of some one of the gods, or if Thy knowledge comes from man! 'Tis so—the counsels Of those with practis'd minds alone, are they Which in their issues shew a living force. Come, first of men, build up the state anew, Be wise for us, and though the land now call thee Her saviour, in reward of ancient zeal, Let not thy reign be memoriz'd, as one In which once righted, we but fell again; But seat the state in full security. If then by favouring omens led, thou broughtest A happy fortune, rival now thyself. Think too, if destined still to sway this land As now thou rulest it, how much more noble Is princedom over men, than empty realms? For what are towers? what navies? nothing worth— If barren of the life of man within them. Œd. —Ah! hapless children! all is known by me, Not undiscern'd, that ye have come to ask; Ye suffer all, yet in these sufferings, none Among you here now suffereth like myself; Your single sorrows on yourselves alone Come down, nor pass beyond.—This heart of mine Bleeds for the state at once, myself, and thee; No slumber is it that ye rouse me from; Much have I wept, believe me—long have tracked The many windings of the maze of thought, And the one cure which, searching well, I found, Already have I tried, for lo! the son Of old Meneceus, Creon, unto me Brother by marriage, to the Pythian halls The oracle of Apollo at Delphi, of which Pytho was the most ancient name. Of Phœbus I have sent, that he may learn What deeds or words of mine might save the state; And how he fares, this very present day, Computed by just measurement of hours, Fills me with anxious thought: for past all reason, He has been gone more than his destin'd time, But when he comes, I should be base indeed Did I not act in all as Heaven enjoins.— Pr. —Thou speak'st in season; these but now reported That Creon hasteth thither on his way. Œd. —Oh, King Apollo! grant that he may come With saving fortune, cheerful as his looks. Pr. —He brings glad news, methinks—would he march else His head thick-wreath'd with yon full-fruited bay The bay was sacred to Apollo, and Creon would not have worn a wreath of it, if the answer had not seemed to him favourable.? Œd. —Soon shall we know, for now my voice can reach him. Hail, kinsman! Hail, Meneceus' royal son! What answer hast thou borne us from the God? Enter Creon. Cr. —Good: for I think harsh measures, if they reach A prosperous end, are fortunate for all. Œd. —How runs the rede? for by thy present speech I am nor cheered nor more depressed as yet. Cr. —If 'tis thy will to hear with these in presence, To speak I'm ready, or to pass within. Œd. —Speak before all, for greater is the grief I feel for these, than for mine own poor life. Cr. —What from the God I heard then, I repeat: In words most clear, Phœbus the Great commands us To purge away, ere grown inveterate, The gross inbred pollution of this land. Œd. —Aye, with what drug? what turn has this to take? Cr. —Exile—or death for death—it is that blood Which beats, a wintry sea, upon the state. Œd. —And who the man whose fate he thus unfolds? Cr. —King, ere the state had righted underneath Thy steering, Laius ruled this land of ours. Œd. —I know by hearsay—for I saw him never. Cr. —Now for his death, the God doth clearly charge us To punish those who slew him with the sword. Œd. —And where on this wide earth lurk they? how track Each doubtful footmark of this ancient crime? Cr. —Here, in this land, he said: that which men seek They find, but that which all neglect, is lost. Œd. —At home? a-field? or in some distant land Did Laius to this murder fall a prey? Cr. —To seek some foreign shrine—for so he told us— He went, but came, as he went forth, no more. Œd. —Were there no messengers? none with him on That road, who know, that we might ask and learn? Cr. —All dead, save one: he, fugitive through fear, One thing alone, of all he saw, can tell. Œd. —And that—what is't? one thing might trace out much, Had we but this, a starting point for hope. Cr. —He said that robbers met and slew him, not By single strength, but with outnumbering hands. Œd. —And how could robbers, if not tampered with By gold from hence, to such a boldness soar? Cre. —Such thoughts were rife; but then when Laius died, No helper in those evil days arose. Œd. —Evil! what evil, when the sovereign power Sunk thus to earth, hindered your learning all? Cre. —The Sphinx of juggling song it was that forced us, Leaving dark things unsearched, to look at home. Œd. —But I, starting afresh, will lay all bare; Rightly has Phœbus, rightly hast thou too, Fixed this keen quest in honour of the dead, And justly may ye look to me for aid, As minister of vengeance, in behalf Of Thebes, and of the God; no distant friends Are those for whom I seek to pierce this gloom. 'Tis for myself, and mine own life I work, For he, whoe'er it was, that slew the man, With that same hand might seek to murder me. Thus, by avenging him, myself I serve. But haste ye now, my children, from these seats Rise up, and take your suppliant boughs away, Let others summon here the Theban people; Nought will I leave undone, and by God's help We will be saved, or we will fall together. Exit Œdipus. Pr. —Let us rise up, my children, for the sake Of what the king proclaims, hither we came, And now may he who sent these prophecies, Phœbus, draw near to save, and stay the plague. Argument to Chorus, l. 160–230. The Chorus deliver an address to the oracle just promulgated by Creon, l. 160–165. Offer up prayers for its happy issue, l. 165–170. Invoke the assistance of various deities, l. 170–182. Describe the ravages of the pestilence, and the grief and consternation of the citizens, l. 182–200. This pestilence they attribute to Ares or Mars, the god of war and destruction, who is represented as having forsaken his usual method of afflicting the human race (viz. battle and murder), in order to bring down death upon it in this new form, l. 204–208. In conclusion, Jupiter and other deities are implored to join in punishing him for his malevolence, and to deliver the people of Thebes from his persecutions. Chorus. —Oh voice from Jove, fraught with words sweet to hear,— What art thou, wondrous Voice? which hast To glittering Thebes, from gorgeous Pytho past? My mind is on the rack of fear,— I shiver all aghast. Hail! Delian Pæan Delian Pæan—as honouring Apollo, whose reputed birth-place was the island of Delos, one of the Cyclades., hail! I bow In reverential awe to learn What issues thou wilt perfect, Now, Or when the rolling hours return. Oh voice oracular of deathless Fame, Thou child of Golden Hope, declare the same! Oh thou, Immortal Pallas, first we call, Daughter of Jove, on thee for aid, Realm-ruling Dian next, thy sister-maid The temples of Diana Euclea, or The Glorious, of Apollo Bœdromius, or The Succourer, and of Minerva Zosteria, (she who arms for battle,) were near to each other in Thebes. Pausanias mentions a fourth temple, that of Hermes or Mercury Agoræus, (that is, presiding over the forum,) to which Sophocles does not allude.—Pausanias Bœotica, cap. xvii., Who on her round throne sitteth, clad With glory in our people's hall, To her our vows are paid, And thou, far-darting Phœbus, ye Shine forth three guardian gods on me: Yea, if of old, when former fate Rolled in to overwhelm the state, Ye quenched that ruin's flame, come now! For under countless ills I bow. The whole host sickens fast, nor can one find A single weapon of the mind To shield one's-self, for lo, the glorious earth Can now no increase give, Nor from the thrilling pangs that wait on birth, Do women rise—and live. Each after each, like swift-winged birds, we see Faster than flash the tameless lightnings, flee O'er the dim limits of the gloomy god Hades or Pluto, the god of the dead.; Thus numberless in these the nation dies, Whilst all that ruthless As causing inevitable death to those who brought them forth. brood, death-bringing, lies Itself unpitied on the sod: Wives too, and greyhaired mothers, round The high-raised shrine, in suppliant guise From every side have wended; Over these bitter agonies They lengthen out their mournful cries, Whilst the loud Pæan's The Pæan here and above, l. 5, is a choral chant, addressed to Apollo especially as a thanksgiving for deliverance from evil, and as such is opposed to cries for help, wailing, and the like.—See Liddell and Scott's Lexicon. sparkling sound, With sounds of wail is blended. Wherefore Jove's golden daughter hear us, Send smiling Help to cheer us; And Ares, the death-spirit dire, Who now, not armed for war, but still With savage shoutings, bent to kill, Raves round us, a consuming fire, Him, exiled from my country, force, Re-rushing on his rapid course, To turn him back again, and flee To the great chamber of the sea, Or where, around barbaric shores, The swell of Thracian surges roars Thrace, a wild country to the north of Greece, was supposed to be the chosen abode of Ares or Mars, the god of war. Virgil calls it “the land of Rhesus, dedicate to Mars.” And again, in the 3rd Æneid, To rustic nymphs I prayed who haunt the place, And to great Mars, who rules the land of Thrace. Thrax, from whom the country derived its name, was reputed to be a son of Mars.. Aught that night's close may leave entire, Just sees the light of day, and endeth; Wherefore, great Jove, on whom dependeth The lordship of the lightning fire, Blast down to death that demon, under Thine own annihilating thunder, And thee too, Oh Lyceian king An epithet of Apollo, either because he was born at Patara, in Lycia, or else meaning the wolf-slayer, an honourable distinction which he may have earned whilst acting as shepherd to Admetus., And thy unconquered shafts, that ring Sharp from the golden-twisted string, A present help—I fain would sing. Yea, and Diana's burning gleams, With which o'er Lycian hills she streams, And thee too with thy golden band, I call, thou namesake of the land Bacchus was the tutelary god of Thebes, which was called Bacchic Thebes from him. The Mœnades, Thyades, or Bacchanals, were the nymphs who celebrated his orgies; they were crowned with ivy, and held in their hands the thyrsus, a wand wreathed with ivy, and vine leaves, with a pine cone at the top; armed with this they danced and sung wildly, giving themselves up to frantic excitement in honour of the god. Cithæron, so often mentioned in this play, is represented as the first place upon which the rites of Bacchus were performed:— Selected first these orgies to fulfil, To that wild singing, and those clamours shrill Of Bacchic nymphs, rang loud Cithæron's hill. Ovid's Metam. He was called Evius from the cries of these women, the burden of their songs being Evoe Bacche., Bright-fronted Bacchus—Evian lord, Comrade of Mœnad nymphs, draw near, With thy great pine-brand blazing clear, So crush that god, among the gods abhorred. To them enter Œdipus. Œd. —Ye pray, but what ye pray for, help from heaven, And an alleviation of these ills, May yet be yours, if having heard my words Ye will adopt them—striving under me To stem the plague. A stranger to the tale, A stranger to the deed, I speak, for truly Having no clue, I scarce could track it far. But ranked since then among your citizens A citizen, to every Theban here I clearly now proclaim, that whoso knows The man, by whom the son of Labdacus, Laius, was slain, stands here enjoined by me To open out the whole, even though he fear To drag this charge to light against himself. Nought else of harshness shall he suffer, but Out of the land depart unharm'd, and if One here, perchance, should know the murderer To be some other from another land, Let him not hold his peace—for I will give him Reward—and thanks will wait on him besides. But if ye still are silent, and my words, In terror for yourselves or for your friends, Ye set at nought,—it is befitting then To learn from me, how I shall act thereon. That man, whoe'er he be, I do forbid Each dweller in this land, whose throne of power I fill as king, to speak to or receive; In prayers or victims offered to the gods Let him not share, nor in the hallowing use Of water; but join all to thrust him forth, Our foul pollution, as but now to me The Pythian oracle of God has shewn. So firm an ally to the powers divine, And to the spirit of the dead, am I. And on that doer's head I imprecate, Whether one only or with more he 'scaped, That wretchedly he spend his wretched life. Yea! in the self-same curse, if to my knowledge An inmate of my halls this man should be, I bind myself to suffer every ill I have invoked on him; and as for you, What I have said I charge you to fulfil For my sake, for the God's, and for this land Now withered up in godless desolation; Nay, though no deity had urged the quest, When that a king of his great race was slain, It were not right to leave it unaton'd. This must have been unravell'd; and since I Hold here the empire which he held of yore, Our nuptial bed the same—one wife for both— His children too, and mine, but that his seed Was luckless, would have sprung from common blood. Moved by all this, since fortune at his head Has swooped to strike, as though he were my father Will I do battle in his cause, and leave No means untried, until I seize upon The hand, that slew the son of Labdacus, Of Polydore, of Cadmus long ago, And of Agenor old This is the accredited pedigree: Agenor, king of Phœnicia. Cadmus, founder of Thebes. Polydorus. Labdacus. Laius.; and if there be Who will not act as I act, then ye gods Mature from out the earth no fruits for them, No children from their wives, but in this plague Uproot them, or in one more deadly still. But you, my Theban people, you to whom This seemeth good,—may earth-supporting Justice, And all the everlasting gods, protect. Chorus (speaking by the high-priest their chief.) Since in the compass of your curse I stand, My lord, I must say this, I slew him not, Nor do I know the slayer: but in truth This problem, who it was that did the deed, Phœbus, the prompter of the search, should solve. Œd. —Rightly you speak: but to force on the gods Against their will, is what no man can do. Cho. —My second thought thereon I could impart. Œd. —Were it the third, speak on; suppress it not. Cho. —Phœbus the Great, and great Tiresias Tiresias, the celebrated blind soothsayer of Thebes. Juno is supposed to have put out his eyes, and Jupiter to have bestowed upon him the gift of prophecy and length of days, as some compensation for their loss; he is made cotemporary with Cadmus in the Bacchæ of Euripides., With the same eyes see much we know, of him Enquiring one might learn the whole, my lord. Œd. —Nor is this left among the things undone, By Creon urged, two heralds have I sent, And long have marvelled that he is not here. Cho. —There were besides old rumours whispered low. Œd. —What were they? I shall have to weigh each word. Cho. —He was slain, say they, by some travellers. Œd. —Aye, so I heard, but none the witness name. Cho. —Still if his nature owns the touch of fear, He will not silently endure thy curse. Œd. —Who fears not deeds, words will not frighten him. Cho. —Here then at least comes one who will unveil him, For hitherwards they lead that holy seer In whom alone of men the truth abides. Enter Tiresias, the blind prophet, led by a slave. Œd. —Tiresias, master of all lore which men May teach, all which they dare not utter, all Which comes from heaven above or earth beneath, The plague that lies so heavy on our state, Though blind thou canst discern! 'gainst which, my lord Nor shield or champion can we find but thee. If from my messengers thou hast not heard it, Know this, that Phœbus when we sent, sent back That the remission of this curse should come Then only, when we should have clearly traced The men who slew King Laius,—slain them too, Or from the land as exiles thrust them forth; Then grudge not thou, or through the voice of birds Divination by the flight of birds, was one of the most usual methods practised by the Greeks; but there were other modes, as by dreams, by lots, by ominous words, &amp;c., Or by some other path of prophecy, To aid thyself, the state, and me; to aid In cleansing this whole blood-taint of the dead. On thee we lean, and to help fellow-men As one best can, is of all works the noblest. Tir. —Alas! alas! how sad is wisdom, when It profits not the wise, though I know all, All was forgotten, else I had not come. Œd. —Great God! in what a gloomy mood thou'rt here! Tir. —Send me home straight. Heark'ning in this to me Thy life thou best will govern, and I mine. Œd. —These words, which rob us of thy warning, are Nor just, nor to this land that bred thee, kind. Tir. —I see thy words to no good issue tend, And fear lest the same evil fall on mine. Cho. —In God's name, knowing this, turn not away, When all to thee bow down in supplication. Tir. —For all are void of wisdom: never—never, Lest when I speak, I bring thy ills to light. Œd. —What? mute though knowing all,—hast thou the heart Thus to betray us, and destroy the state? Tir. —Nor thee—nor yet myself I harm. Why waste These words of wrath? from me thou hearest nothing. Œd. —Basest of men, for this would rouse to wrath The spirit of a stone, wilt thou speak out, Not stand thus stern and unpersuadable? Tir. —My temper thou canst carp at, but thine own An ambiguous allusion to Jocasta, at once the mother and wife of Œdipus. Housed with thee thou seest not,—then blamest me. Œd. —Why? who would not be angered when he heard, The words wherewith thou laugh'st the land to scorn? Tir. —Though I in silence shroud it,—come it must. Œd. —Why not impart to me then what must come? Tir. —I speak no more, and therefore, if thou wilt, Rave on, let loose the wildest mood of wrath. Œd. —So keen that wrath, that I will leave unsaid Nought I can call to mind: know that I deem thee The planner of the crime—the actor—only Not with thy hand the slayer—hadst thou sight, I should have said the deed was thine alone. Tir. —Say'st thou? the edict thou hast just proclaimed, By it I call thee to abide, and from This day to speak no word to me or them— Thyself the foul pollutor of this realm. Œd. —Ha! after uttering shameless words like these, Where dost thou think to save thyself by flight? Tir. —Safe am I—resting on the strength of truth. Œd. —Who taught thee? 'twas not thine own art, at least Tir. —Thou; for thou mak'st me speak against my will! Œd. —Speak what? say it again: that I may know— Tir. —Dost thou not know enough? why tempt me further? Œd. —No—not to call it known—repeat it prithee. Tir. —Thou seek'st the monarch's murderer—thou art he Œd. —Unpunished thou shalt not repeat these insults. Tir. —Shall I say more, and make thee fiercer yet? Œd. —Say what thou wilt—we heed not idle words! Tir. —I say that linked with those most near and dear In horrible companionship, thou'rt blind, And dost not see thy miserable state. Œd. —And think'st thou to speak ever thus at ease? Tir. —I do; if there is any strength in truth. Œd. —To all but thee there is; but thou, thou hast No portion in the truth, for thee alike Thine ears, thy mind, thine eyes, are full of darkness. Tir. —Thou miserable man! reviling me For my calamity; not one stands here But he shall soon reproach thee with the same. Œd. —Thou art the nurseling of mere night, and canst not Hurt me nor any man who sees the sun. Tir. —To fall by me is not thy fate; for this Apollo will suffice, whose task it is. Œd. —Are these inventions Creon's, or thine own? Tir. —Nay, Creon harms thee not—'tis thou thyself. Œd. —O Wealth! O Power! and Art surpassing art, In life with all its jealousies and strifes, How vast the mass of Envy stored against you! If for this empire, which the state unasked Placed as a gift within these hands of mine, Creon, the trusty, my most ancient friend, Hopes now by secret working to expel me, Having suborned this scheming mountebank, This crafty juggler, who for gain alone Has eyes, to his own science blind of soul,— For tell me! I say, tell me—if so wise, Oh thou great prophet, how it was thou could'st not, When the Sphinx monster with her spells was here, Find aught to free thy fellow-citizens? And yet that riddle should not have been solved By a chance comer; some prophetic power Was needed; but that power, whether through birds, Or straight from heaven, thou shewd'st not. It was I, The unenlightened Œdipus, untaught Of omens,—by mine own clear spirit led, Set it at rest,—whom thou would'st banish,—hoping To take thy place near Creon on his throne; With tears, I wot, both thou, and he who framed These plots, shall rue the attempt to drive me forth. But for thine age, by suffering thou should'st learn Even now, how great the folly of thy thoughts. Cho. —In our poor judgment, both the prophet's words And thine, Lord Œdipus, in wrath were spoken: Not such are fitting, what we aim at, is How best to solve these oracles of God. Tir. —King though thou art, an equal right I claim To answer as an equal,—that I can do, Slave, not to thee, but to the Loxian god An epithet of Apollo, either from ?????, slanting, oblique, on account of the intricacy and ambiguity of his oracles, or else from ???? ?????, as interpreting to men the will of his father Jupiter. See Liddell and Scott's Lexicon, sub voce.. So that I need not now enrol myself With Creon for a patron. Mark my words! Thou, who now mockest at my blindness,—thou Seeing, perceivest not the misery In which thou art, nor where thou dwellest, nor With whom thy life is spent. Tell me—from whom Thou springest? thou unconscious enemy Of thine own blood under the earth, and on it. Soon with swift foot the double-branding curse Of father, and of mother, from this soil Shall hunt thee forth, beholding now the light, Then looking on gloom only—what place soon Shall not become a haven for thy groans? What crags in old Cithæron shall not ring, Re-echoing thy cries? when thou hast learnt The truth veiled by those nuptials, unto which As to a harbour, where no harbour is, Thou didst sail on through yonder palace halls, A voyage falsely fair—nor dost thou see The crowd of ills impending, which shall make thee As one with thine own children. Now go on, Heap insults both on Creon and on me, Since among mortal men no one that breathes Shall spend a life so wretched as thine own. Œd. —Is it endurable to hear such things? Wilt thou not hence to ruin? wilt thou not Turn back at once, and leave these halls of mine? Tir. —But for thy summons I should not have come. Œd. —I could not tell what folly thou wouldst speak, Or I had hardly called thee to my house. Tir. —Such is my nature—deemed a fool by thee, The father who begot thee thought me wise. Œd. —What father? stay—who among men begot me? Tir. —This day which finds thy father—ruins thee. Œd. —How dark and riddle-like each phrase of thine! Tir. —Well,—art not thou supreme in solving such? Œd. —Sneer, if thou wilt, at that which makes me great Tir. —And yet that seeming fortune is thy bane. Œd. —Well, I have saved this city,—so I care not. Tir. —I may depart then,—guide me, boy, from hence. Œd. —Ay, let him guide thee, here thou troublest all, And once removed thou canst not vex us farther. Tir. —When I have spoken what I came to speak, Then will I go—thy sullen looks I fear not,— Thou hast no power against me—therefore mark. I now declare, the man whom thou so long Hast hunted, with thy threats and proclamations Touching the death of Laius, standeth here. Pronounced a stranger and a sojourner, He shall come forth a native Theban soon, Yet take no pleasure in the change, for blind Where now he sees, and poor instead of rich, To a strange land, staff-guided, must he crawl. To his own children whom he liveth with A father and a brother, to the woman From whom he sprung a husband and a son; Assassin of his sire, yet his heir, And partner in one bed of love. Go ponder well These words within, and if thou find'st me erring, Say then—I know not how to prophesy. Argument of the second Chorus, l. 490–545. The Chorus describe the terrible punishment impending over the murderer of Laius, in spite of his despairing efforts to escape the pursuing deities, l. 490–513. Express their grief and perplexity that Tiresias should ascribe this crime to Œdipus Dwell upon the improbability of this being the truth, admitting at the same time that the workings of Providence are inscrutable l. 513–529. Hint a doubt whether prophets and soothsayers are as infallible as they claim to be, without however daring to do more than doubt, l. 530–536. Recall the former service of Œdipus, and determine to believe these accusations false, as long as possible, l. 536–545. Chorus, (headed by the high-priest as before.) Who is that man whom Delphi's rock Divinely uttering, brands Doer of deeds, whose horrors mock All speech, with blood-stained hands? 'Tis time for him, in flying course, More furious than the storm-paced horse, His foot to ply: Full-armed, with flashing bolts of fire, On him the Jove-born Apollo. leaps from high, And the dread Fates, that never tire, Are following nigh; Forth from Parnassus Parnassus, the Delphic mountain, sacred to Apollo., topped with snow, Like flame an utterance ran, Made clear but now, that all should go And track the shrouded man. For underneath the forest grim, Through crags and caves, like some wild bull, He drags along each wretched limb, All desolate and sorrowful; Since from the oracles that soar Out of mid earth's prophetic core Literally the centre or navel of the earth. Delphi was supposed to be exactly in the middle of the earth, which we must remember that the Greeks figured to themselves as a plane surface. Whether (especially since the oracles are represented, as infused into the minds of the priestesses, by the mysterious influence of intoxicating vapours, which streamed up from abysses of unknown depth) the phrase, “prophetic core,” be not an allowable adaptation of the original to our more correct cosmical views, I must leave to others to determine., To flee away He strives, but they Float round him, living evermore. Shuddering I hear those words of woe That from the mighty prophet flow, Their truth I dare not own, although They may not be by man denied. How I should speak I doubt, and glide On airy hopes along, nor see The present, nor the time to be. For that a death-feud ever burnt Between the house of Labdacus, And this, the son of Polybus, Nor now, nor yet of old I learnt. If any such there were in sooth To serve as touch-stone for the truth, I then might join the clamour loud 'Gainst Œdipus—avenging thus The undiscover'd deaths which shroud The progeny of Labdacus. Phœbus and Jove are wise, and aught That mortals e'er have done, they know. But, for the sons of human kind, That any prophet's soul is fraught With more of truth than mine, I find No pledge to trust, that this is so. And yet one man by deeper lore Another's skill may oversoar, But still, not yet will I, before I shall have seen these words come right, Lend my assent to those who blame; For manifest of old to sight, On him the wingèd virgin came, And by that touchstone tested through, Skilful and wise—he stood to view— And of the state a lover true— Wherefore my heart will bide its time, Ere it condemn him of a crime. To them enter Creon. My fellow-citizens, hearing but now, That Œdipus the king accuses me With bitter words, impatiently I come. For if he think in these calamities That he has suffered injury in aught Through deeds or words of mine, I feel no wish With guilt like this imputed, to live on. It is no trifle, but of utmost weight The penalty which follows such a charge, If as a traitor to the state, by you And by my nearest kinsmen, I am held. Cho. —Yet haply this invective issued, more Forced out by anger, than in sober judgment. Cr. —But how appeared it, that through arts of mine, The prophet was induced to frame a lie? Cho. —'Twas said—on what authority I know not. Cr. —And was this charge against me, uttered forth With eye uplifted, and unshrinking heart? Cho. —I know not—blind to all my rulers do— But see—from yonder halls he comes himself. Œd. —How now! thou here? where gott'st thou such a front Of boldness? as to come beneath my roof, Thou open thief of my authority, And manifest assassin of this man; Say, in God's name, hast thou discerned in me The bearing of a craven, or a fool, Led thence to frame these plots? or didst thou think The reptile onset of this traitorous fraud I should not trace to thee? or when I learnt The truth, I should not then protect myself? Is not thy project utter foolishness, Thus friendless and alone to chace a crown, Which nought but wealth by numbers backed, can win? Cr. —Think what thou dost—in answer to thy speech Hear me in turn, and having heard, decide. Œd. —Thy skill in words I know; but I who find thee My foe, shall not be easy to persuade.— Cr. —Nay, but just listen first to what I say. Œd. —Nay, but deny not this, that thou art base. Cr. —If thou conceivest stubborn arrogance Has worth, when void of wisdom, thou art wrong. Œd. —If thou conceivest, that a kinsman when He errs, will not be punished, thou'rt deceived. Cr. —These words I grant are just, but tell me now What wrongs thou dost assert thyself to suffer? Œd. —Didst thou, or didst thou not advise, that I Should send for that same pompous prophet here? Cr. —And by that counsel I as yet abide. Œd. —What time forsooth has passed—since Laius?— Cr. —Since he did what? I comprehend thee not. Œd. —Struck by the hand of murder, vanished hence? Cr. —Long are the years, and measured from of old. Œd. —Did not this prophet then profess his art? Cr. —He did, for wisdom honoured then, as now. Œd. —He mentioned me then, doubtless, at that time? Cr. —Never—at least whilst I was standing by. Œd. —And yet ye made enquiry for the dead? Cr. —We did, no doubt; but nothing could we learn. Œd. —Why spoke not thus your man of wisdom then? Cr. —I know not; therefore shall I hold my peace. Œd. —Yet this thou knowst—and couldst declare if willing. Cr. —This? what? I will not hide it if I know. Œd. —That never, had he not conspired with thee, Would he have charged me with the death of Laius. Cr. —If such his words thou knowest—as for me I claim to put my questions, as thou thine. Œd. —Proceed, I shall not prove a murderer. Cr. —Say then—hast thou my sister to thy wife? Œd. —So far thy questions must command assent. Cr. —Rul'st thou not here, sharing this realm with her? Œd. —She may have all from me—if such her will. Cr. —Rank I not third? held equal with you both? Œd. —Equal! why here the faithless friend appears. Cr. —Not so, but reason with thyself as I do; Think'st thou that any one would rather grasp At actual empire, in the midst of fear, Than sleep unshaken, and enjoy its fruits; Not mine the mood, (no, nor of any one Who has learnt wisdom,) that would wish to be A king, rather than lead a kingly life. Now without any fear I can obtain All things from thee; were I myself in power Oft must I act against my will: how then Should royal rule give me so much delight, As painless princedom and authority? I am not yet so utterly deceived As to seek more than honour and advantage: All love me now; all welcome me; all who Ask aught of thee, address themselves to me, Since through my favour comes success in all. What were I then to throw away these gifts For the mere name of power? Not so—a mind In wisdom trained, turns not to folly thus. No appetite have I for schemes like these, Nor if another urged me, would I bear it. And first in proof of this, to Pytho send And learn if I have truthfully announc'd These oracles to thee. Yea, more than this, Shouldst thou convict me of devising aught In common with the seer, then seize and slay me; Not by a single, but a double sentence; My own, as well as thine: but do not now Judge me unheard upon such doubtful grounds— Since without proof to hold the bad for good, The good in turn for bad, confounds all justice,— And to throw off a worthy friend is like Parting with life, the thing man holds most dear. But this in time full surely shalt thou see, Since time alone the good makes manifest, Whilst in one day thou mayst discern the bad. Cho. —Well speaks he king, to one who fears to fall; The hasty-minded man shall not be safe. Œd. —When secret traitors hastily move on, I must take hasty counsel in my turn; If at my ease I wait, this man's designs Will be achieved, my fortunes overthrown. Cr. —What is thy aim, then: from this land to drive me? Œd. —No,—not thy exile,—'tis thy death I need. Cr. —But shew me first good ground for this fierce hatred Œd. —Thou speak'st like one who means not to obey. Cr. —Thou art not sane— Œd.- Oh! for myself I am. Cr. —But I have equal claims. Œd.- Thou'rt a mere knave. Cr. —What if thou errest? Œd.- Still I must be ruler. Cr. —Not if thou rulest badly. Œd.- Oh my country! Cr. —Mine too that country is—not thine alone. Cho. —Cease, princes, cease: in time, from yonder halls I see Jocasta come to you; with whom T'were well to set this present quarrel straight. Enter to them Jocasta. Jo. —Oh! miserable men, why have ye raised This idle strife of tongues? feel ye no shame In this sick realm to stir a private grudge? Go in, my lord, and Creon, get thee hence, Fan not each petty grievance to a flame. Cr. —Thy husband, sister, is in savage mood, And orders me to choose between two evils, Or death, or exile from my native land. Œd. —'Tis so I grant, for woman, I have found him Weaving his baleful arts against my life. Cr. —May I ne'er thrive, but die a cursed thing, If aught he charges on me I have done. Jo. —Believe him, Œdipus, in this, for God's sake, Respecting first his oath unto that God, Me next, and then these good men present here. Cho. —To this belief I pray thee bring Thy reason and thy will, Oh king! Œd. —What wishest thou that I should grant to thee? Cho. —Respect this man, not weak before, Now by his oath confirmed the more. Œd. —And dost thou understand this wish of thine? Cho. —I do. Œd.- Then make it clear to me. Cho. —Oh! cast not off dishonourèd As guilty, by vague reasons led, A friend so pledged by oath as he. Œd. —Be well assured that asking this, ye ask My ruin, or my exile from this land. Cho. —No; by the sun I swear, That God of gods the first, May I, if such a mind I bear, All friendless, and of Heaven accurst, Die by whatever death is worst. To see my country to these plagues a prey, 'Tis that, which eats my wretched heart away. And now I fear, lest with old ills combine Fresh evils, springing from this strife of thine. Œd. —Let him go free then, even if utterly To perish I am doomed, or from this land To be forced headlong a dishonoured thing; 'Tis thy sad plaint that moves my heart to pity, But him, I hate him wheresoe'er he be. Cr. —Though yielding, yet thou hatest, conquering wrath Thou ragest still; but fitly minds like thine Unto themselves the heaviest burdens are. Œd. —Wilt thou not leave me and depart? Cr.- I go, Clear before these men, though thou know'st me not. Cho. —Oh lady, why art thou so slow Within yon halls to lead the king? Jo. —First, how it chanced I fain would know. Cho. —By some vague word Dark doubts were stirred, And all injustice has a sting. Jo. —Were both in fault? Cho.- They were. Jo. —What words were used? Cho. —Enough for me, with the land thus in pain, That where they died away they should remain. Œd. —See what, right-hearted as thou art, by blunting And taming down my spirit, thou hast done? Cho. —Not once alone, Oh king! Thus have I spoken, know That from all reason wandering And lost to thought myself I show, If ever I forsake thee so, Who, when my much-loved country lay, Tost on the waves of woe, In safety steered her on her way By overcoming and destroying the Sphinx.. Become again, if thou hast power, Her pilot in this fearful hour. Jo. —Tell me, my lord, in God's name, what the cause Which fills thee with so violent a wrath? Œd. —Lady, I will, for I esteem thee more Than I do these; 'tis Creon and his plots. Jo. —If thou canst throw true blame on him, speak on. Œd. —He says that I it was who murdered Laius. Jo. —Of his own knowledge? or have others told him? Œd. —He sent a scoundrel seer, for he would set, As far as he has power, all tongues in motion. Jo. —Withdraw thy mind from what thou speak'st of, and Listen to me, learn thence that nothing human Has any portion in prophetic art. Of this I'll give thee proofs compact and clear. Voices to Laius came of old, (from Phœbus, The god himself, I say not,) but his priests, That destiny should slay him by the hands Of his own child, bred betwixt him and me; Yet him as rumour words it, foreign robbers Slaughtered, where three cross roads are joined in one, Whilst for that infant blossom, not three days Had passed before his father pierced his feet, And cast him by the hands of others forth Upon a desert crag; thus for the child Apollo ruled not, that he should become His father's slayer, nor for Laius, Death, The evil which he feared, from his own son. Yet words of prophecy had marked this out. Then heed them not, for easily the God What he resolves himself will bring to light. Œd. —Yet woman, as I hear thee now, my heart Shakes, and my soul is tossèd to and fro. Jo. —Seized sudden by what terror speak'st thou thus! Œd. —I seemed to hear from thee these words, that Laius Was slain of old where three cross roads are joined. Jo. —So it was said, nor has the rumour ceased. Œd. —And where the place where this misfortune chanced? Jo. —Phocis the land is called; there separate roads From Delphi and from Daulis Daulis, a city of Phocis, celebrated as the scene of the murder of Itys by Procne and Philomela, to revenge themselves upon Tereus, who had outraged the latter. Some fragments of a tragedy by Sophocles upon the subject (the Tereus) are still extant. meet in one. Œd. —And what the time that has elapsed since then? Jo. —Shortly before thou cam'st to rule this land It was made public to our people here. Œd. —Oh Jove! what hast thou planned against me now? Jo. —Say what afflicts thy spirit, Œdipus? Œd. —Ask me not yet,—but tell me what a presence Had Laius, how much left of youthful strength? Jo. —Of mighty stature, but his whitening head Sprinkled as if with flowers of snow; his aspect Differed, methinks, but little from thine own. Œd. —Ah miserable me, I seem unknowingly t'have cast myself Into the trammels of an awful curse! Jo. —What now? I dread to look on thee, oh king! Œd. —Sadly I fear that prophet has his sight; But thou canst make all clearer by one word. Jo. —I tremble, but will tell thee what I can. Œd. —Went he with escort slight, or led he forth A long array of spearmen, Like a king? Jo. —Five men in all, a herald one of them, And Laius seated on a single car. Œd. —Ah me! 'tis all too manifest; and who Was he that brought these tidings hither, lady? Jo. —A certain slave, who came back safe alone. Œd. —Is he still living in these halls of ours? Jo. —Not so, for when he came and saw thee here Fixed on the throne of Laius, his dead lord, He as a suppliant touched my hand, and prayed That I would send him to far pasture-fields, Where he might never see this city more. I sent him straight, since, for a slave, he was Worthy of favours greater far than this. Œd. —Could he with speed return to us from thence? Jo. —He shall be here; but why is such thy wish? Œd. —I fear, oh woman, lest I may have said Too much of that for which I wish to see him. Jo. —He shall come straight; but surely I deserve To know what lies so heavy on thy heart? Œd. —Nor will I keep it back; since I am filled With such dread expectations, unto whom Should I tell all so soon as unto thee?— Of Corinth was my father Polybus Polybus was reputed to be the son of Mercury and Chthonophyle, daughter of the king of Sicyon., A Dorian—Merope She is also called Peribœa. my mother. I There first in rank among the citizens Was held, until this chanced, a cause for wonder, And yet not meriting the weight I gave it. A certain man at supper, full of wine, Over his cups called me a foundling—palmed Upon my father. I oppressed with wrath Scarcely throughout that day restrained myself; And on the next, confronting close my father And mother both, I put them to the proof. Incensed with him from whom those words had fallen, They felt the insult deeply; hence with them Was I well pleased, but not the less the wound Kept rankling, for the rumour spread apace: To Pytho went I then, keeping it hid From both of them, but Phœbus in respect Of what I came for, sent me back at once, Unhonoured with an answer, but he spoke Clearly of other things, things horrible, Dismal, and dark; that I should mix in love With my own mother, and rear thence in sight Of all men, an insufferable brood; Yea, slay the father who begot me. When I heard him, straight I fled, and henceforth viewed The land of Corinth only from afar; Seeking some place where I might never see These monstrous imputations brought to pass. As I went on, I reached the very spot Where thou hast told me that this king was slain, And woman, I will speak the truth to thee, A herald there, and on a car horse-drawn A man high-seated, just what thou hast said, Encountered me, and from the path his driver And the old man himself, by violence Would then have thrust me forth, but him that tried it, The charioteer, I in my anger struck; The old man, as he saw me pass the car, Watching his opportunity, came down Full on my head with his two-pointed goad. But more than equal my revenge, at once Struck by the staff in this right hand, he fell From his mid chariot rolling in the dust. In fine I slew them all. Now if this stranger Connect himself in aught with Laius, who Can be more wretched than the man before thee, More hateful to the gods; since 'tis forbid That sojourner or citizen should change One word with me, or take me to his home, But all must thrust me from their gates; and, more, The man who laid these curses on me, was No other than myself, and with these hands That slew him, on the dead man's nuptial couch I bring pollution? Am I not then base? Am I not all unclean? yet if I fly I may not by that flight approach mine own, Or plant my foot upon my native soil, Else am I doomed in marriage to be yoked With my own mother, and to slay my sire, Him who begot and bred me, Polybus. Who then can fail to see in this the hand, Against me set, of some relentless god? Oh hear me, Holy Majesty of heaven! Ere I behold that day, may I from earth Pass, and be seen no more, nor feel the brand Of such a curse strike deep into my soul! Cho. —These things perplex us sorely, king, but yet Till thou hast heard the witness, cherish hope. Œd. —Ay, just so much of hope remains to me To wait that herdsman here,—so much, no more. Jo. —And when he comes, what purpose holds with thee? Œd. —I'll tell thee, if he should be found to say The same as thou, I then escape this curse. Jo. —What word worth noting hast thou heard from me? Œd. —Thou say'st he mentioned robbers, as the men Who slew him, if in speech he still adhere To that same number, then I slew him not, For one to many cannot equal be. But if one person journeying alone He name, the deed comes clearly home to me. Jo. —Know that his tale was blazoned forth; know that He cannot now retract it. 'Twas not I Alone, but the whole city heard it thus. Nay, though he swerve from what he said of yore, He proves not that the death of Laius came As was foretold; for him the Loxian god Decreed to perish by a child of mine; And yet that hapless creature slew him not, But died himself before; so that for fear Of prophecies I would not turn my head A single hair-breadth to the right or left. Œd. —In this thou judgest well, and yet send one To fetch that herdsman here; neglect it not. Jo. —I'll send at once, but let us to the house, I will do nothing not approved by thee. Argument of the third Chorus, l. 915–969. The Chorus, shocked by the levity and irreligious spirit of Jocasta, pray to heaven to keep them pure and free from sin, l. 915–918. Do homage to those immutable principles of right, which are the moral foundations of the universe, l. 918–925. Enlarge on the danger of self-indulgence and worldly pride, and the dreadful end of presumptuous sinners, l. 925–933. Express their confidence in Divine Providence, and invoke judgment upon all those who trample upon the distinctions between right and wrong, and despise religious sanctions, in order that they may gratify their passions without restraint, l. 934–949. Appeal to the gods to vindicate their insulted majesty, to bring to pass the prophecies which they have uttered, and to arrest the decay of piety everywhere then visible, l. 950–969. Chorus, (headed as before by the high-priest.) Lend me, ye Fates, your strength sublime, Around each word and act of mine, To guard that purity divine, As aids to which, before all time Stood fixed those laws of lofty tread, In yon celestial ether bred. 'Twas not the death-doomed seed of man Compare Antigone's address to Creon:— Think not that these commands of thine with me Have so much weight, that upon their account I, a mere mortal, should presume to break The indestructible unwritten laws Of the great gods, that were not born to-day, Nor yesterday, but have eternal life, And none can tell from whence their day-spring rose. That called them into life, nor can Oblivion in its slumbers fold. Unchanged—unending—uncreate— It is through them that God is great, Through them, He grows not old.— The pride of life breeds tyrant will These lines are believed to refer to Alcibiades, to whom all the gifts of nature, fortune, and position, were rendered worse than useless by his ungovernable passions and want of steady principle. There is a striking passage in the Laws of Plato, conceived in a similar spirit, and aimed without doubt at the same person. The Athenian interlocutor (Plato himself) is speaking: “He, who in the season of youthful folly is filled with a spirit of pride, and intoxicated with his own greatness, because he is rich, or of high rank, or beautiful in person, by his impious contempt of God and man kindles a fire in his own soul; and pressing onwards, as if he needed no law to govern him, no wisdom to guide him, but, on the contrary, as if he himself were fully competent to guide and govern all others, is soon left alone, a man abandoned of God; and being thus abandoned, straightway he gathers to himself others of a like mind, tramples down all law, and throws every thing into confusion. For a time he may seem to many prosperous and renowned; before long, however, he is sure to suffer some just and memorable punishment, and to plunge himself, his family, and his native country, into irreparable ruin. Now then, since these things are so ordered of Heaven, what are the habits of thought, and action, which one who is truly wise should cultivate? what those which he must avoid?” Clinias answers, “This at least is clear, that each man should study how he may become one of those, who pass through life in companionship with God.”—Laws, B. iv. ed. Becker, vol. viii. p. 113., And pride, if gorged beyond its fill With joys that oft recur in vain, And suit not with our mortal strain, When it has scaled the loftiest rock Comes thundering down with sudden shock, And limbs that climbed at heaven of late, Lie palsied in the nets of fate.— Never, oh never, will I ask The God to lay aside his task That serves the state, nor cease to throw His shield before me as I go.— But if unscared by justice, and Unawed by shrines where gods abide, Men, insolent with word or hand, Press on in reckless pride; May black fate seize them as her prey, And thus ill-chosen joys repay. For how, unless his gains be just, Unless he shrink from godless lust, How, if he grasp in idle mirth Things sacred from the touch of earth, Should man from off his spirit keep The shafts of vengeance rankling deep? If deeds like theirs can meet with praise, Why need we hymns of worship raise? No longer will I take my way At earth's pure central shrine Delphi. to pray, Nor to the great Abantic fane Abæ, a city of Phocis, early celebrated for its oracle of Apollo. The temple was twice burnt, first by Xerxes, and afterwards by the Thebans in the sacred war, so that it was in a perfectly ruinous condition in the time of Pausanias. Phocica, c. xxxv. It was one of the oracles consulted by Crœsus, king of Lydia, before he made war on Cyrus, but does not seem to have succeeded in gaining his confidence so much as either the oracle at Delphi, or the oracle of Amphiaraus, at Oropos, on the frontiers of Attica and Bœotia., Nor to Olympian halls The great temple of the Olympian Jupiter in Elis, where he was represented sitting on a throne of ivory and gold, with a golden wreath of olive round his head; the original oracle there, as at many other places, was sacred to the Earth. again, Unless these words prophetic can Be fitted to the truth, and shewn, As with God's outstretched hand, to man More correctly perhaps “that he who runs may read, to man.’. Oh thou, that rulest all alone, Great Jove, if so we name thee well, Let not this pass unmarked, unknown Before thine everlasting throne, For now those words divine, which tell Of Laius, these would sweep away, As old and drooping, to decay. Nor is there found a place below, Where Phœbus with due honours given Shines forth, and all that breathes of heaven Lies sunk in ruin low. Enter Jocasta. Ye nobles of the land, I think it good Taking this incense, and these wreaths in hand, To seek the temple of some god, for now The heart of Œdipus on countless griefs Rides tossing to and fro, nor like a man In his right senses, does he test the new By what has passed of old; but hangs on each Fresh speaker, if his words but tell of fear. Since then, my counsels soothe and help him not, To thee, Lyceian Phœbus, for thou art The nearest god, this sacrifice I bring: Come down serene in power to succour us, For to behold the pilot at the helm Thus panic-struck, benumbs us all with fear. Enter a messenger from Corinth. Perchance, oh strangers, I may learn from you Where are the halls of Œdipus your king? Yea more, where he himself, if ye should know? Cho. —This house is his, he, stranger, is within, This woman is the mother of his sons. Mes. —May she, his all-accomplish'd wife, live on The happy parent of a happy race. Jo. —Thee too may fortune favour, friend; this well Thou meritest for that kind speech; but tell me With what demand or tidings hast thou come? Mes. —Good tidings to thy house and husband, lady. Jo. —What are they? at whose bidding wert thou sent? Mes. —From Corinth; with the words I speak thou may'st Be pleased! why not? thou may'st be angered too. Jo. —How so? what is this double power they have? Mes. —The natives of the place would make him lord Of th'Isthmian land Corinth.—so ran the rumour there. Jo. —How! is not Polybus the Old still king? Mes. —Not so, since death has laid him in the tomb. Jo. —What say'st thou? Polybus is dead? Mes.- Unless I speak the truth, I am content to die. Jo. —Oh maiden, stand'st thou thus? to tell thy lord Rush with all speed. Ye voices of the gods How is it with you now? Of old in dread Lest he should slay this man fled Œdipus, And now by nature, not by him, he dies. Enter Œdipus. Œd. —Jocasta, most beloved of women, say Why hast thou called me from the house within? Jo. —Listen to him, and having listened, learn The end of all these solemn prophecies. Œd. —Who can he be? what does he want with me? Jo. —From Corinth, to announce that Polybus Thy father lives no longer, but is dead. Œd. —How say'st thou? Stranger, tell the tale thyself. Mes. —If I am bound to place beyond all doubt This first, be thou assured that he is dead. Œd. —Through treason, or the action of disease? Mes. —A touch can send an aged frame to rest. Œd. —Poor man—by sickness then no doubt consumed. Mes. —Yes! and long years had measured out his life. Œd. —Most strange. Why then, oh woman, should one watch The Pythian hearth of prophecy, or birds That shriek on high—these were my teachers, that I was to slay my father, now in death Under the earth he rests, whilst I have aimed No weapon at his life, unless perchance Through his fond yearning for me he have drooped, And in that sense indeed was slain by me.— So Polybus in Hades lies; and with him Those futile oracles may sleep for ever. Jo. —Did I not say all this to thee before? Œd. —Thou didst, but I was led astray by fear. Jo. —Henceforth then, let no one of them torment thee. Œd. —How so, my mother's bed, must I not fear it? Jo. —Why should man fear in matters where blind fortune Has rule, and no clear forethought finds a place; There best to live at random as one can. Then fear not thou thy mother's spousal rites, For many of mankind ere this in dreams Have shared their mother's bed; but he with whom Such things weigh not, most easily lives on. Œd. —These words sound well, but still my mother lives, And whilst she lives, it is my doom, in spite Of these well-sounding words of thine, to tremble. Jo. —Yet what a light breaks from thy father's tomb. Œd. —True, but the living must be dreaded still. Mes. —Who is this woman whom ye fear? Œd.- Old man, 'Tis Merope the wife of Polybus. Mes. —And what in her can tend to waken terror? Œd. —Dark prophecies, oh stranger, sent from God. Mes. —May they be spoken? or is it perchance Unlawful for another man to hear them? Œd. —Not so: the Loxian told me long ago That I must marry with my mother, and Spill with these hands of mine my father's blood. Long have my countrymen in Corinth dwelt, With regions wide between us, from this cause; Prosperity no doubt was mine, but yet 'Tis sweet to look upon a parent's face. Mes. —Was it for fear of this thou fledd'st from home? Œd. —And wishing not to slay my sire, old man. Mes. —Oh that, my lord, I had at once released thee (Since as a friend I came) from such alarms. Œd. —Thou shouldst have been rewarded for thy pains. Mes. —In truth to this especial end I came, That on thy reaching home, I there might prosper. Œd. —Ah to my parents ne'er can I return. Mes. —My son, 'tis clear thou know'st not what thou'rt doing. Œd. —How so, old man? instruct me, in God's name. Mes. —If for their sake thou shun'st to seek thy home— Œd. —I fear lest Phœbus may come right at last— Mes. —Lest from thy parents some foul guilt be thine. Œd. —That, that, old man, fills me with endless dread. Mes. —With no just cause thou tremblest then, be sure. Œd. —How so? if these be they from whom I sprung— Mes. —For Polybus was naught in blood to thee. Œd. —How say'st thou, did not Polybus beget me? Mes. —No more than I myself, but just the same. Œd. —How can a father be the same as none? Mes. —Why he was not thy father, nor am I. Œd. —Then for what reason did he call me son? Mes. —Know, once he took thee from these hands—a gift. Œd. —How could he love another's seed so dearly? Mes. —His heart was softened by his childless state. Œd. —Didst thou, the giver—buy me, or beget? Mes. —I found thee in Cithæron's Cithæron, an elevated range of mountains dividing Bœotia first from Megaris and then from Attica. wooded glens. Œd. —And how cam'st thou to journey to that spot? Mes. —I there was guardian of the mountain flocks. Œd. —Wert thou a shepherd, sent to roam for pay? Mes. —My son, I saved thee at that time from death. Œd. —What pain or danger didst thou find me in? Mes. —The joints of both thy feet would witness that. Œd. —Ah! why dost thou recal that ancient grief. Mes. —I loosed thee with both feet pierced through and through. Œd. —With a base brand, as birth-mark, was I reared. Mes. —From this mischance then wert thou named, as now. Œd. —Ha! by my father or my mother? say. Mes. —I know not, he who gave thee may know more. Œd. —Thou didst but take me then? not find thyself? Mes. —Another shepherd placed thee in my hands. Œd. —And who was he? canst thou still point him out? Mes. —One of the house of Laius he was called. Œd. —Of him who erst was monarch of this land? Mes. —The same; he was the shepherd of that man. Œd. —And is he living still for me to question? Mes. —Ye people of the land should know that best. Œd. —Does any one of you now gathered round, From having seen him in the fields, or here, Know who this herdsman is, of whom he speaks? If so, declare it, for the time is come. Cho. —I think he is no other than the man, The countryman, whom thou didst wish to see Before, but that Jocasta best can tell. Œd. —Say, woman, is the man whom we await The same with him of whom the stranger speaks? Jo. —Who? what? whom names he thus? take thou no heed Nor dwell upon such idle words as his. Œd. —Not so; with such a clue I cannot shrink From seeking to discover who I am. Jo. —In God's name, if thou value life, be ruled, Make no search, let my wretchedness suffice. Œd. —Fear nothing; though I prove a triple slave Through mother-serfs for three whole generations, Thou wilt not therefore be pronounced low-born. Jo. —Be ruled—I do entreat thee—make no search. Œd. —I cannot rest until I know the whole. Jo. —Yet—as a friend I urge thee for thy good. Œd. —My good! no more of that, thou troublest me. Jo. —Poor wretch! God grant thee ne'er to know thyself. Œd. —Ho! some one bring that shepherd here to me; Leave her to triumph in her noble blood. Jo. —Oh horrible! I can but call thee once Most miserable man, then speak no more. Exit Jocasta hurriedly. Cho. —Why goes that woman hence, Lord Œdipus, By frantic passions driven? I fear me lest Forth from that silence burst a storm of woe. Œd. —Let it burst where it lists; however humble, I must trace home the fountain of my blood; She perhaps, a very woman filled with pride, Sees her dishonour in my humble birth, But I, who deem myself the child and heir Of favouring Fortune, shall not be disgraced. She is my rightful mother, and through her The months coeval with me, in their course Have raised me from obscurity to greatness. Since nature made me noble beyond change, Why should I fear to trace my lineage out? Argument of the fourth Chorus, l. 1150–1169. The Chorus, anxious to conceal from Œdipus as long as possible their anticipations of evil, suppose him to be of divine origin, and to have been brought forth on Cithæron by a nymph under the auspices of Bacchus, l. 1150–1169. This chorus is, I think, the feeblest thing in the whole play. Sophocles was probably reserving himself for the next, in which those favourite topics of the Greek dramatists, the instability of all human happiness, and the irresistible march of destiny, are handled with great power and spirit. Cho. —If I in aught a prophet be, Or wise of spirit to foresee, Oh thou Cithæron wild and bare, By old Olympus hear me swear, That ere to-morrow's moon is over, Thou shalt these joyful truths discover, Our songs shall honour thee, (compatriot true Of Œdipus, yea nurse and mother too,) As one that beareth to our lord delight, Phœbus, may this find favour in thy sight.— What daughter of the gods, my son, The gods who live for ever on, Approached by mountain-trampling Pan Pan is called mountain-trampling as being the god of shepherds, huntsmen, &amp;c., Or by the mighty Loxian, Who loves each rustic plain on earth, Somewhere in secret gave thee birth? Or else Cyllenè's king, or Bacchus bold, Who haunts the mountain-tops, took thee of old A foundling of those nymphs Bacchus is commonly represented as guiding and inspiring a band of subject nymphs. Horace calls him, Lord of the Naiads thou, and Bacchanals, With hands made strong tall ash-trees to uproot., with whom alway (The nymphs of Helicon) he loves to play. Enter Œdipus. If I may judge, old man, who never yet Have met him, that same herdsman whom we long Have sought, methinks I see, for his great age Chimes in, and keeps due measure with thine own; Those who conduct him too I recognise As of my house; but thou who hast of old Beheld him, in such knowledge wilt surpass me. Cho. —We know him well, faithful among the first To Laius, that is, for a shepherd swain. Œd. —Thee, oh Corinthian stranger, first I ask Mean'st thou this man? Mes.- Yea, even him thou seest. Enter the servants of Œdipus leading an aged Shepherd. Œdipus addresses him. Œd. —Look this way, aged man, and answer all I ask. To Laius didst thou once belong? Shep. —I was his slave, not bought but bred at home. Œd. —And what thy special task and course of life? Shep. —Most of that life I spent among the flocks. Œd. —And in what quarters didst thou chiefly dwell? Shep. —'Twas in Cithæron, and the country round. Œd. —Know'st thou this man from having met him there? Shep. —Under what guise? of what man dost thou speak? Œd. —Of him here present; have ye ever met? Shep. —I could not say at once from memory. Cor. Mes. —No wonder, good my lord, but I will clearly Remind him who forgets, for well I know He must recal, how in Cithæron's glens He with two flocks, and I with one, for three Whole seasons of six months, lived side by side, From spring-time till the star Arcturus rose, When winter came, to my own folds I drave My flocks, he to the stalls of Laius his. How say I? speak I not what happened there? Shep. —Thou speakest truth: though long the years since then. Mes. —Say on now, dost thou call to mind the child Thou gavest me to rear as if mine own? Shep. —How say'st thou? wherefore dost thou ask this question? Mes. —Here stands the man, friend, who was then a babe. Shep. —To hell with thee! canst thou not hold thy peace? Œd. —Ha! chide him not, old man, thy words than his Call rather for the hand of chastisement. Shep. —In what, oh best of masters, have I erred? Œd. —Not answering what he asks thee of the child. Shep. —He knows not what he says, and works at random. Œd. —Speak willingly, or thou shalt speak perforce. Shep. —Outrage me not, for God's sake, being old. Œd. —Ho! some one bind his hands behind his back! Shep. —Wretch that I am! for what? what wouldst thou know? Œd. —Gav'st thou the child to him, of which he asks? Shep. —I did. Would I had perished on that day! Œd. —Death waits thee now, unless thou answ'rest fairly. Shep. —Ah! still more surely if I do, I die. Œd. —This man it seems still seeks to put me off. Shep. —Not so: I have already said I gave it. Œd. —From whence received? from others, or thyself? Shep. —Not from myself, from some one else it came. Œd. —From what house taken? from what citizen? Shep. —In God's name, good my lord, urge this no more. Œd. —Thou diest, if I am forced to ask again. Shep. —Of one who dwelt with Laius it was born. Œd. —Some slave of his, or sprung from his own blood? Shep. —Alas! on danger's edge I stand and speak. Œd. —I stand there too and hear; still I will hear it. Shep. —The child was called his own, but she within, Thy wife, can tell thee best how these things were. Œd. —Did she then give it thee? Shep.- She did, my lord. Œd. —And to what end? Shep.- That I might take its life. Œd. —Unhappy mother! Shep.- Scared by evil omens— Œd. —What? Shep.- It was said that he should slay his sire. Œd. —Why then commit him to this aged man? Shep. —Through pity, my good lord; I thought that he Would bear him off to that far land from whence Himself had come; but he for deepest ills Has saved thee; for if thou art what he says, Oh! thou wert born to nameless misery! Œd. —Oh! miserable wretch!—all then is true! Oh light! for the last time I look on thee, Shewn to be sprung from those, and linked with those I should not have approached, and to have shed Blood that in me 'twas horrible to spill! Rushes out. Argument of the fifth Chorus, l. 1245–1284. The instability of human happiness enlarged upon, l. 1245–1250. Proved by the terrible ruin of Œdipus, after his unexampled prosperity, l. 1250–1262. His calamities described and pitied, l. 1262–1276. A wish that they had never known him, l. 1276–1280. Followed by an acknowledgment that gratitude is still due to him, on account of those former services which he alone was able to render, l. 1280–1284. Chorus, as before. Man, child of dust, your little life I deem No better than a baseless dream, For who of human birth has looked on bliss More stedfast to the eye than this; A something that may seem to shine, And in its seeming straight decline.— Thy fate, lost Œdipus, is strong to shew That none are blessèd here below, Thy arrowy flight, too fortunate in aim, Soared up, the pride of life to claim, And that oracular grim thing of prey, The virgin Sphinx, God gave thee power to slay.— When on my native land in that dark hour Death smote, like an imperial tower For refuge and defence, thou stood'st alone, So that we placed thee on a throne, And raised thee up to high renown, Lord of this mighty Theban town.— But who, from all we hear, more wretched now, High heart of Œdipus, than thou? Who by sad change of lot is forced to dwell With griefs and agonies more fell? Father and son, their nuptial gulph the same, Strike on one rock, and sink in death and shame.— Poor wretch! how could those limbs that were One flesh with thy slain father, bear Thy touch so long in silence? Lo, Time, that beholdeth all on earth, Tracked thee unconscious long ago, And now he sits in judgment on The spouseless marriage of the son, With her who gave him birth. Child of that ancient Laian race, Would that I ne'er had seen thy face, I should not then with piercing cries Have mourned for thee, lamenting sore. Yet, Let not truth forgotten be, Upheld and cheered of old by thee, 'Twas through thy help, I closed these eyes In peaceful sleep once more. Enter a Theban Messenger from the Palace. Mes. —Ye, who are still most honoured in this land, What dread things must ye hear, what see, how high Your sorrows must arise, if with true hearts Ye yet revere the house of Labdacus, Not Ister's stream, nor Phasis, as I think, Could wash yon palace-chambers clean It can hardly be necessary to quote from Macbeth, Will all great Neptune's ocean wash this blood Clean from my hand? Or from Richard II., Not all the waters in the rough rude sea Can wash the balm from an anointed king., of all That they conceal; and now new horrors straight Will brave the light of day—self-chosen, not Involuntary these—and of all ills Those which free choice inflicts sting keenest home. Cho. —What erst we knew falls short in nothing of The depths of woe; what hast thou new to add? Mes. —To learn the truth in fewest words, know this, Jocasta's sacred head lies low in death. Cho. —Oh wretched woman! how came that about? Mes. —By her own hands; but oh! the horror of The deed, ye cannot know that saw it not. Still, if I keep remembrance firm, ye shall Hear that poor lady's miserable end. A pause. Soon as she, passion-prompted, rushed within The vestibule, straight at the nuptial bed She bounded, rending with both hands her hair, As she passed through the doors, she dashed them to, Invoking Laius long since dead, recalling Their old forgotten offspring, by whose hands He fell, and left the mother to bring forth A doomèd brood to her own flesh and blood. Then wept she o'er that couch of love, twice-cursed, Where she, unhappy, from her husband bred A husband, and fresh children from her child. What thence her course towards death I know not, for With yells Lord Œdipus rushed in, so that We could not see her sorrows to their close; But watched him as he roamed infuriate round, Now clamorous for a sword, now asking where That wedded woman, that was not a wife, Though twice a mother, fruitful of himself And of his children, he might find. While thus He raved, some god was there to point her out, For no one stirred of all the men around. But he with awful cries as if he saw Some viewless guide before him, leapt at once Against the double doors, and shattering out The massive bars from their foundations, straight He staggered headlong to that inner room; Then, then, we saw the woman hanging there, Suspended by a rope that trembled still, Which when poor wretch he looked on, with fierce groans He loosed the cord; but when on earth she lay What then ensued was horrible to see; For wrenching from the robes each ??????? is generally construed as a single clasp-pin or buckle, but I have retained the plural number in this passage, because I think that Sophocles meant us to understand that Œdipus extinguished the sight of both his eyes at once, which would require a weapon in each hand. golden brooch Sharp-pointed, that adorned her dress, he raised them, And pierced the nerves of both his eyes therewith, With words like this, “that they should see no more The things he suffered, and the deeds he did, But through thick darkness look upon those whom They never should have seen or known,” and thus Raising his hand, amid such imprecations, He tore his eyes again, and yet again, Whose wounded orbs upon his beard distilled A sullen dye, and poured incessant forth Their clammy drops of gore, so that black blood With oozing humour mingled—fell in showers. Thus have these ills burst not on one, but two, Husband and wife are coiled in the same doom. Their former bliss in the good times of old Seemed bliss indeed, but now there is not one Of all the names of anguish, Lamentation, Woe, ruin, death, or infamy, found absent. Cho. —And has he now a breathing time, poor wretch? Mes. —“Open the gates,” he shouts, “and shew to all Of Theban blood, the parricide who with His mother”—uttering dread words I dare not.— Out of the land he seeks to cast himself, Not rest at home beneath the curse which he Invoked on his own head; but he wants strength, And some one to support and guide his steps; For his fierce plague is more than he can bear; As thou shalt see, for the gates open, and A sight thou wilt behold, which would awake Compassion in the bitterest foe he has. The scene opens, and discovers Œdipus standing over the dead body of Jocasta. Cho. —Oh sight of woe to man most dire, More terrible than aught by me Encountered yet, what frenzy-fire Hath rushed, oh hapless wretch, on thee? What god comes swooping, fiercer still, Upon the destiny of ill? Bent as I am, unhappy one, On asking, hearing, tracking much, Thy face I dare not look upon, The shock thou givest me is such.— Œd. —Alas! alas! for my despair! How bitter is the doom I bear; Unto what spot of earth am I Borne on in grief profound? And whither, does my voice on high Fly forth and float around? Say, thou dread God, into what ills unknown The impulse of thy onset hurls me down? Cho. —To horrors past all hearing, and all sight. Œd. —Grim cloud of mine, with hateful gloom imbued, On-rolling in thy blank infinitude, With what unconquerable force dost thou Sweep right before the storm, that drives me now. Woe, woe, once more, the sting of these pierced eyes How keen! with bitter memories conjoined! Cho. —Yes, 'tis not strange that in such pangs thou shouldst Grieve doubly, and endure a double ill. Œd. —Oh ministering friend, Alone found faithful now, for still Thou waitest on me here to tend, And shield the blind from ill,— Woe's me! ah, woe is me! Thou canst not 'scape my notice, for right well Though darkling, do I recognise thy voice! Cho. —Man of dark deeds, how hadst thou heart to quench These orbs of thine? what demon urged thee on? Œd. —Apollo, 'twas Apollo. Oh my friends, He brought about this woe on woe, These griefs of mine, to their appointed ends. But for the hand that struck the blow Unhappy, it was mine alone, For where the need of sight, to one With nothing sweet to look upon? Cho. —Alas! thou speakest sooth; 'tis even so. Œd. —What had I left for eye to scan? For spirit to hold dear? What utterance of a fellow man With pleasure could I hear? Lead me at once without delay, Lead me from hence, my friends, away, A living death, a thing accurst, By heaven, of all men hated worst. Cho. —Oh, wretched in thy mind as in thy doom, Oh how I wish that I had never known thee. Œd. —Whoe'er that man, death seize on him, Who chose to set me free again From that foot-fettering savage chain, That eat into the limb; His was no act of kindness, when He rescued me from thence, and bore me Safe from the bloody doom before me. For had I perished then, Nor I, nor those I love, would e'er Have known these horrors of despair. Cho. —Our wishes echo back thy prayer. Œd. —I should not then have trod the earth As my own father's murderer, Nor borne a husband's name to her From whom I drew my birth. Now by the gods abhorred, and son To that contaminated one, My race, begotten on a wife Who gave me my own wretched life, And if there be one horror, still More deadly than each other ill, That, fixed and noted as mine own, Comes down on Œdipus alone. Cho. —I know not how to call thy judgment wise, Better to cease to be, than live in blindness. Œd. —That these my deeds have not been fitly done Nor teach, nor counsel me. I know not how I could have raised these orbs to look upon My father when I pass to Hades, nor My wretched mother, against both of whom, Crimes not the vilest death can expiate Have been by me committed; then, my children! Their aspect doubtless must be sweet to see Upspringing from the root it does. No! No! Not to these eyes of mine at any rate. Or else the city with its towers, and all The solemn statues of the gods, of which Wretch that I am, (though once the noblest lot In Thebes was mine,) I stripped myself for ever, When I myself bade all men hunt from hence That impious wretch, proclaimed by powers divine A thing polluted: and of Laian blood. Having myself denounced against myself Such a contaminating curse, how could I Confront it here with an unshrinking eye? No, were there any power of crushing up The fountain-head of sound within mine ears, I would not rest till this afflicted frame Were clean walled out from nature; so I might Live without sight, and hearing nothing: for To keep all senses dead to pain were best. Cithæron! why accept me? why not straight Slay me when first received? I should not then Have e'er exposed my birth to mortal man. Oh Polybus! Oh Corinth! ye old halls In name alone paternal; how ye bred me Fair on the surface, one foul sore within, Found now to be vile off-shoot of the vile. O ye three pathways; thou, secluded grove, Thicket, and pass, where meet those triple roads, Ye that drank up the blood those hands had shed, The blood of my own father; have ye kept A memory of the deeds there done? and how Again, coming from thence, I acted here? Ye nuptials! oh ye nuptials! that produced me, Having produced, to me ye raised up seed Identical with mine own springs of life, Exhibiting to men our kindred blood Confused in strange commixtures! fathers, sons, And brothers, all in one; one too the bride, The wife, the mother; and whatever crimes Earth deems most horrible, by us fulfilled. But since to speak of what should not be done Suits not, in God's name, on some distant spot Conceal me—slay me—to the 'whelming sea Cast forth, that ye may never see me more. Come, shrink not back, from touching me, poor wretch, Obey, and fear not: for such griefs as mine None but myself is able to endure. Cho. —Here, in good time, for these thy wishes comes Creon, to act and counsel, who is now Left in thy stead, sole ruler of the land. Œd. —Ah me! what words shall I address to him? How shall my faith be rightly proved, who late Towards him in all things shewed myself so vile? Enter Creon. Cr. —Not as a scorner, Œdipus, I come, Nor to reproach thee with my former wrongs, But if of mortals ye “Ye,” I suppose, is addressed to the Chorus, who are rebuked for not urging Œdipus to retire into the palace the moment he appeared in public. no more regard The race, at least the all-sustaining fire Of yonder monarch sun revere, nor shew Unveiled such foul pollution, which, nor earth, Nor water's sacred stream, nor light can brook. Come lead him with all speed within the house, For it befits those near of kin alone To see and hear the sorrows of their kin. Œd. —In God's name, thou who in thy high estate Hast deigned to visit me, the dregs of man, Since thou hast wrenched me from all hope in life, Grant this; for thee, not for myself, I speak. Cr. —What favour art thou begging thus to gain? Œd. —From this land cast me forth at once; where I May never change a word with mortal man. Cr. —I would have done so, be assured: but first I wished to ask the God how I should act. Œd. —And yet his oracle in all was clear, That ye should crush me, parricide abhorred! Cr. —So it was said; still in the crisis where We stand, 'twere well to learn what must be done. Œd. —Will ye enquire about a wretch like me? Cr. —Why even thou wilt now believe the God! Œd. —This then I charge upon thee, this I pray, Of her—within the house—even as thou wilt The funeral rites perform, since for thine own Thou wilt all decent offices fulfil. But me, my father's city must not look Longer to keep a living habitant. Among the mountains suffer me to dwell, On my Cithæron, as they call it, where Mother and father marked me out a grave Whilst I was yet alive, that I may die Under their hands, even as they wished to kill me. And yet full well I know, that nor disease It appears to me as if Sophocles meant to imply in these lines, that as soon as the first frenzy fit of remorse had spent its force, the instinctive love of life returned to Œdipus, in spite of his anguish and despair. The whole passage gives me the idea, as if he suddenly recollected that the oracle had denounced banishment, or death, against the murderer of Laius, and that he was now getting anxious for the milder alternative., Nor aught besides will slay me. I should never Thus in the act of death have been preserved But to live on through dark calamities. But let my fate where'er it will, move on. My children, Creon, for the boys care not, As men, they will not, wheresoe'er they be, Come short in the necessities of life, But those young maids of mine, forlorn and sad, For whom the daily meal was never spread But at the board with me, so that whate'er I ate, they had their portion in it all, Be kind to them; and more than all, permit me To lay my hands on them, and weep my last: Come, royal friend, come, noble sir, grant this, If with these hands I touched them, I might dream That I possessed them still, as when I saw. A momentary pause. What words are these, in God's name His daughters, Antigone and Ismene, appear upon the stage.? hear I not The sobbing of the loved ones somewhere near? Has Creon in his pity brought to me The dearest of my offspring? say I well?— Cr. —Thou dost, I brought them, knowing the delight Thou tookest in their presence from of old. Œd. —Heaven prosper thee, more happily than me God shield and guide thee on the road of life. Where are ye? oh my children! hither, hither, Come to these hands of mine; a brother's hands Which caused the once bright eyes of him you see, The father of your blood, to be quenched thus. He seeing nought, my children, knowing nought, Became your father, in the self-same place Where he was once conceived. I can but weep, Having no power ever to see you more, To think how bitter that remaining life Which ye must spend among the sons of men. For in what meeting of the citizens Can ye mix? where are the festivities From which, in lieu of pleasant sights, ye will not Come home all bathed in tears? and when ye reach The fruitful hour of marriage, who is there, My children, bold enough to undergo The burden of those obloquies which crush Your parents, and entail a curse on you? What horror is not here! your father slew His father, took to wife his mother, her Whose seed he was, and called you into light From his own source of life. Such imputations Must be your lot; who can espouse you then? No man!—My children, clearly are ye doomed To waste in barren loneliness, unwed. Son of Meneceus, since to these thou'rt left Sole parent, for we two who bred them, lie Quenched in one death, I pray thee look not coldly Upon them, as they rove unmated, poor, Of thine own blood, nor suffer them to sink Down to the level of my wretchedness. Oh pity them! beholding them so young, So destitute of all save hope in thee. Grant this, and touch them with thy noble hand. To you, poor girls, were but your minds full-grown, I could say much in counsel, but now pray That ye may live where it befits you best, And, than your sire, enjoy a happier lot. Cr. —Enough of tears have passed. Go now within. Œd. —Though this is hard, I yield. Cr.- In their own season All things are well. Œd.- Know'st thou the point I aim at? Cr. —Speak, having heard thee I shall know it then. Œd. —Send me from hence an exile. Cr.- What the gods Alone can give, thou askest. Œd.- To the gods, Most hateful I. Cr.- Thy wish then thou wilt have Granted no doubt by them. Œd.- But what say'st thou? Cr. —When ignorant, I love not useless words. Œd. —Lead me from hence. Cr.- Go: leave thy children here. Œd. —Oh part us not! Cr.- Nay, think not now to keep The mastery of each wish; for where of old Mastery was given, it did not constant prove. Cho. —Sons of my native Thebes, the great lord Œdipus behold! Those riddles he (then first of men), world-famous, did unfold, Each citizen with envy viewed the glorious life he wore, Now into gulphs of doom he sinks, dark seas without a shore. Man therefore born to death, should watch life's last and crowning day, And call none happy till he pass unscathed from earth away A favourite sentiment with the Greeks; see Her., lib. i. c. 34, where Solon is introduced telling Crœsus, that no man, till he dies, can be called more than lucky as opposed to happy, because the gods so frequently send down sudden destruction upon those who have long enjoyed uninterrupted prosperity..</field>
   </doc>
</add>