<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Cooke, Thomas, 1703-1756</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Cooke, Thomas, 1703-1756</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">cooke thomas 1703 1756</field>
      <field name="author_text">Cooke, Thomas, 1703-1756</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">18th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1720's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V2.0609.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240355</field>
      <field name="date_text">1724</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460259</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Albion : Or, The Court of Neptune ; A Masque [by Thomas Cooke</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Albion : Or, The Court of Neptune ; A Masque [by Thomas Cooke</field>
      <field name="title_facet">albion or the court of neptune</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">albion or the court of neptune</field>
      <field name="title_text">Albion : Or, The Court of Neptune ; A Masque [by Thomas Cooke</field>
      <field name="year_display">1724</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1724</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1724</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460259&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460259&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Cooke, Thomas, 1703-1756&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;cooke thomas 1703 1756&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Albion : Or, The Court of Neptune ; A Masque [by Thomas Cooke&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;albion or, the court of neptune&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1724&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1724&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Cooke, Thomas&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1703&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1756&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Albion : Or, The Court of Neptune&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Masque [by Thomas Cooke]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for J. Roberts [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1724&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872574-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv20609&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 18th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;18th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Albion : Or, The Court of Neptune&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Masque [by Thomas Cooke]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 32 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Albion.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Masque.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1724.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Unknown.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ALBION: OR, THE COURT of NEPTUNE. A MASQUE.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Magnus ab integro seclorum nascitur ordo; Jam redit &amp; Virgo, redeunt Saturnia regna. Virgil.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">But now I see, since Albion is restor'd, Death has no Bus'ness, nor the 'vengeful Sword. Dryden.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">TO A? H?nd, Esq; Enrich'd by Conquest youthful Warriors come, Deck'd with proud Spoils, and crown'd with Laurels, home; The prancing Steed, the Sword, or well prov'd Shield, Falls to the Man who form'd them for the Field. Thus the young Heroes pay their Tutor's Care, With the first Trophies of the Toils of War. But I, who in a diff'rent Province live, Must offer Verse; 'tis all I have to give; 'Tis what, dear Sir, is to your Merits due; If here are Beauties they're deriv'd from you; 'Twas you who pointed out the Way to Fame, Bad me be bold, and dare deserve a Name. Young, and unskill'd, into the World I came, Could boast no Favours from the hood-wink'd Dame; Naked was thrown among the Sons of Earth; Such the malignant Stars that rul'd my Birth! Where could I steer my Course? What Methods use? An able Guide in Life—a Virgin Muse! Advent'rous Boy, with her to trust thy Fame, By boldly trifling with a Marlb'rough's Name! If through the Field disorderly I ran, And left undrawn much of the mighty Man; If the weak Produce of those early Days, Want of just Thought, or Harmony, betrays; If I am blam'd, I grant the Censure true; I labour'd singly, and in want of you. Let others boast the Privilege they have, In what you freely to the Publick gave; Which not to me, but to the World is due: I pride me in a greater Share of you. You shew'd me when to stoop, or be sublime; The Art of Thinking, and the Charms of Rhime; With other Myst'ries of the sacred Train, Found out by few, by many sought in vain. To paint the Prospect of great Brunswick's Sway, I call'd the Gods from Heav'n, and from the Sea. Weak was my Pow'r for such a Work divine; Weak was all Aid; till I was bless'd with thine. Moschus e'er long shall tread the British Plains, And chant in Albion Groves Sicilian Strains. Our Swains shall hear, while you Assistance bring, How Bion, lovely Bion, us'd to sing. With such a Friend, form'd and inclin'd like you, What may not I attempt, what hope to do!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The PERSONS. GODS. Jupiter. Neptune, God of the Seas. Æolus, God of the Winds. Triton, Neptune's Trumpeter. Nereus, Sea-God. Glaucus, Sea-God. Palœmon, Sea-God. GODDESSES. Amphitrite, Goddess of the Seas, and Neptune's Queen. Thetis, a Goddess of the Sea. Sea-Gods, and Sea-Nymphs. Scene, the British Seas.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Neptune arises, attended by Triton his Trumpeter, and other Sea-Gods. Æolus descends in a Cloud. NEPTUNE. Stern Æolus command your blust'ring Slaves, To exercise their Rage no more, Upon my peaceful Waves. Some distant Northern Rock unbar; Quick confine your Boreas there; Nor let him drive tempestuous Air, To blacken all the Sky: The God, my Brother God, descends from high. ÆOLUS. 'Tis done, 'tis done, nor have you spoke in vain; Now think him bound in Adamantine Chain: Zephyr too shall cease to blow; None shall ruffle you below. Eurus shall lend a gentle Breeze, Soft as Sleep, and calm as Ease; He shall serenely waft him o'er, And land him safe on Britain's Shore. To Jove submissive I'll obey, Nor let one Cloud oppose his Way, But every Mist expel, and clear the Face of Day. NEPTUNE. 'Tis in me the Floods to bind. ÆOLUS. 'Tis in me to curb the Wind. I'll choose a Cloud distinguishingly bright, And ride refulgent in the Blaze of Day; And (if it dares approach) dispel the Night; And chase the Darkness that obstructs the Way. Æolus ascends. NEPTUNE. He rides on a Cloud, We'll ride on a Flood. As the Winds all obey, So the Waves shall give Way, For Jove to cross the Main. Burst all ye Billows, and no longer roar, Lay by your Rage, and cease to lash the Shore. Since Æolus has laid the Winds asleep, With this Neptune shakes his Trident. I'll smooth the Surface of the Deep. Chorus of Sea-Gods. He rides on a Cloud, We'll ride on a Flood. As the Winds all obey, So the Waves shall give Way, For Jove to cross the Main. NEPTUNE. Sound, Triton, your Shell, sound, sound it aloud, Call all the Gods from their silent Abode; If in the Baltick, or the Euxine Sea, Or far beyond the Bounds of Ind they be, Summons them here once more to view the Day; 'Tis Jove and I command, they must obey. Triton sounds his Shell. Nereus, Glaucus, Palæmon, &amp;c. arise. NEPTUNE. Ye Gods, and Demi-Gods, draw near; 'Tis Jove, and I, command you here: Jove has descended once again, To cross my Seas, and grace the Main. Your Rev'rence justly he does claim, From Pow'r and Merit, as from Fame. You Glaucus, and Palæmon wait; And whilst I go, attend in State. I fetch my Amphitrite, my Queen, And Thetis' silver-footed Train. Both Gods and Goddesses shall prove That all their Glory's from above; And hail my Brother, mighty Jove. Neptune descends GLAUCUS. What God-inchanting Nymph has Jove betray'd? Say, my Palæmon, who's the wond'rous Maid? Whose Eyes allure the am'rous God below? And who the Fair that makes the Thund'rer bow? Comes he with his Europa's here again? Or with his Io's to disturb the Main? If Juno's Charms are not enough for Jove, But he admires Variety in Love, Let it suffice to act his Joys above: With his Amours not thus molest our Sea; We are, Palæmon, Gods as well as He. PALÆMON. We are; but, Glaucus, all below, To his superior Godhead bow, And owe to him our being so. He gives to each his proper Sway, Whether in Earth, in Air, or Sea; We are obey'd, and must obey. If Jove for Io vows a Flame; Or if he's charm'd with Leda's Frame; Or burns for the fair Alcmena. Grecian Dame; Or if for Semele he sighs; Or by another's brighter Eyes, The Deathless languishes, and dies; Why envy you propitious Jove? He hinders not that we should love; We draw Examples from above. If Jove has had his Loves divine, Neptune hath had his Nymphs marine, And Pluto has his Proserpine. And, Glaucus, we can love as well, But if our Charms can not prevail, Not Jove, the Nymph does us repel. Prophetick Nereus, say, for you Can tell what Jove designs to do; Or you, or none, I'm sure must know. NEREUS. To me, ye Gods marine, 'tis giv'n To know the secret Will of Heav'n. Oft I unfold the Book of Fate, And see what lies conceal'd in that. Cities to build are in my View, And tow'ring Castles, Kingdoms too, Princes unborn, Monarchs to come, I see their Rise, I see their Doom. Heroes with Heroes, Nations fight; And Champions pant to see the Light. Another Drake shall plow the Main; And Marlb'rough's sent to Hochstet's Plain. Dire Plots, and Murders, thick appear, But hold.—I dare no more for Fear— 'Twould chill Immortals' Blood to hear. But Albion, happy Albion, blest With Pleasures far above the rest: No such dark Hours for you I see; Immortal Joys reserv'd for thee! Far happier Days are near at Hand, Than those when William blest the Land. William, who weary of a Crown, Tir'd with an earthly Sceptre grown, Blessing the Place, he left th'Abode, And from a Man commenc'd a God. William, whose Designs were great, Too great for Mortal to compleat; And what a Man began you'll see, Must by a God concluded be. Venus has left th' Idalian Grove, Paphos no more's the Seat of Love; She's with her Sparrows, and her Doves, And with her Cestus, and her Loves, With Speed to Windsor's Forest gone, Where she intends to fix her Throne. There Britons daily Temples raise, And fill the Thickets with her Praise. Apollo, and the tuneful Nine, No longer on Parnassus shine; But Cooper's-Hill is now divine. Athens, Minerva's fav'rite Town, Yields to Augustia her Renown: She once made other Cities bow, Augustia's all the Goddess now. Since Ida's Mount, and Tempe's Field, To Kensington and Hampton yield; All Gods and Goddesses that are In Heav'n, or Earth; in Sea, or Air, To Albion's blissful Isle repair. But lo, our King and blue-ey'd Queen, And Thetis' silver-footed Train. I would, but can no more reveal— But Neptune he the rest will tell. Neptune, Amphitrite, Thetis, Sea-Gods, and Sea-Nymphs. NEPTUNE. Ye Gods behold, see with respectful Eye, The God, the God, great Jove himself is nigh; See how he tow'rs triumphant o'er the Sea; His own intrinsick Pow'r commands his Way. See how he rides along the watry Road, The Waves are conscious of their glorious Load; They know their Passenger, and feel the God. AMPHITRITE. Thetis, and all your Nymphs marine, Come, and prepare a Song divine; Ev'n Amphitrite, Neptune's Love, Will join the Chorus, 'tis for Jove. THETIS. Doris, and all my faithful Train, That sing, and dance about the Main; Come, and a Song divine prepare, It is for Jove; for Jove is near. Ev'n Amphitrite, Neptune's Love, Will join the Chorus; 'tis for Jove. Jupiter, and his attendant Gods appear at a Distance The Nymphs sing. SONG. I. Come, ye Nymphs, ye Nereids, come, Leave your Coral Roofs below; Leave your splendid pearly Room, Jove commands your Presence now. II. See, ye Nymphs, ye Nereids, see, See the Thund'rer in his Look; Th' Approach of awful Majesty; Too divine to be mistook. III. His distant Aspect shows the God, And his Brows Obedience move; So when all the Winds he rode, Ev'ry Motion spoke him Jove. CHORUS. Come, ye Nymphs, ye Nereids come, Leave your Coral Roofs below; Leave your splendid pearly Room, Jove commands your Presence now. Jupiter passes by, Neptune and his Train follow, while the Nymphs sing. SONG. Hail, hail to Jove! All hail to our great King! He brings his Blessings from above; To Jove alone we sing. Begin, ye Nymphs, the Song divine; Mortal Bards now tune their Lyres; To Jove they offer at his Shrine, Deathless Verse, as he inspires. Let not Mortals us excel; Sure Immortals sing as well. Hail, mighty Father, mighty Jove! Omnipotent! and Great! Thrice happy is the Land you love, Beyond the Reach of Fate. Tides of Joy, and Blessings flow, After you, where-e'er you go. Happy England, happy Shore, Where no less than Jove shall reign; Wars shall cease, and be no more; Saturnian Hours return again. There shall be the Seat of Rest, Where the Halcyon builds her Nest. Wars shall cease; Endless Peace Shall resume its downy Reign; Ev'ry Day with Love be crown'd; Joys in Circles take their Round; Saturnian Hours return again. Neptune, Nereus, Triton, &amp;c. return. NEPTUNE. The Time is come, ye Gods, and this the Land, Where 'twas foretold Immortals should command; Well I remember e'er this World began, Before the first-created-Birth of Man, Each God was summon'd to the Realms above, For some peculiar End; best known to Jove; His Orders giv'n, we to th'Olympick Court, Where the grand Council of the Gods resort, Swift, and obedient, fly at his Command; And big with Expectation round him stand. When he, slow rising from his awful Throne, Stroking his rev'rend Beard, in mystick Words begun. “Of the long War, ye Gods, I need not tell, “(You know the fatal Consequence too well.) “How the Gigantick Race attack'd my Wall; “And the Earth shudder'd at Æ geon's Fall: “But that is pass'd. This Day I did behold “In brazen Letters, wrote on Leaves of Gold, “In the large Book of Fate; and as I read, “These mystick Words I treasur'd in my Head. “The Days approach, when Saturn's Son shall reign, “On Earth, and bring Saturnian Hours again; “When Gods and Goddesses their Seats shall move, “And see a Golden Age brought back by Jove. “A Land distinguish'd from the grosser Earth, “Shall give the Golden Age a second Birth; “A Land distinguish'd in the Rolls of Fame, “That from its happy Clime derives its Name. These are the Fates; and thus divin'd the God, And then confirm'd it with the sacred Nod. Ye see, Immortals, now the Days are come, That brooding lay so long in Fate's dark Womb. As on the Land shall be great Jove's Resort, So here, ye Gods marine, shall keep your Court. To you I give your Em'rald Crowns to wear, And wield aloft your little Tridents here; While with due Care ye keep my strict Command, To guard with Vigilance Brittania's Land; And when her Fleet the Streamers spread in Air, Be that, and only that, your chiefest Care; From Rocks, be sure, the floating Town to save, And from the Insults of each furious Wave. Attend the Fleet, whene'er it launches forth, To either India, or the frozen North. You once to Troy's Remains alone were true, Let all your Guard be on Brittania now. The END.</field>
   </doc>
</add>