<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">FitzGerald, Edward, 1809-1883</field>
      <field name="author_facet">FitzGerald, Edward, 1809-1883</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">fitzgerald edward 1809 1883</field>
      <field name="author_text">FitzGerald, Edward, 1809-1883</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1900's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V3.0700.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240355</field>
      <field name="date_text">1903</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:461027</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Greek, Modern (1453- )</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Agamemnon</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Agamemnon</field>
      <field name="title_facet">agamemnon</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">agamemnon</field>
      <field name="title_text">Agamemnon</field>
      <field name="year_display">1903</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1903</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1903</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:461027&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:461027&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;FitzGerald, Edward, 1809-1883&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;fitzgerald edward 1809 1883&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Agamemnon&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;agamemnon&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1903&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1903&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;FitzGerald, Edward&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1809&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1883&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Agamemnon&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;New York&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;The Macmillan Company&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Macmillan and Co.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1903&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3873363-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv30700&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;gre&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 20th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;20th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Agamemnon&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 113 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;lb/&gt;Only verse drama included.&lt;lb/&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;lb/&gt;Preface toŒdipus at Athens included withŒdipus in Thebes.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Agamemnon.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1869.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Unknown.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">AGAMEMNON</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DRAMATIS PERSONÆ Agamemnon King of Argos. Clytemnestra his Queen. Ægisthus his Cousin. Cassandra Daughter of King Priam. Herald. Chorus of Ancient Councillors.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The scene is at Argos.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">[Agamemnon's Palace: a Warder on the Battlements.] Warder. [Once more, once more, and once again once more] I crave the Gods' compassion, and release From this inexorable watch, that now For one whole year, close as a couching dog, On Agamemnon's housetop I have kept, Contemplating the muster of the stars, And those transplendent Dynasties of Heav'n The commentators generally understand these ???????? ???????? to mean Sun and Moon. Blomfield, I believe, admits they may be the Constellations by which the seasons were anciently marked, as in the case of the Pleiades further on in the Play. The Moon, I suppose, had no part to play in such a computation; and, as for the Sun, the beacon-fire surely implies a night-watch. That, as alternately they rise and fall, Draw Warmth and Winter over mortal man. Thus, and thus long, I say, at the behest Of the man-minded Woman who here rules, Here have I watch'd till yonder mountain-top Shall kindle with a signal-light from Troy. And watch'd in vain, couch'd on the barren stone, Night after night, night after night, alone, Ev'n by a wandering dream unvisited, To which the terror of my post denies The customary passage of closed eyes. From which, when haply nodding, I would scare Forbidden sleep, or charm long night away With some old ballad of the good old times, The foolish song falls presently to tears, Remembering the glories of this House, Where all is not as all was wont to be,— No, nor as should—Alas, these royal walls, Had they but tongue (as ears and eyes, men say) Would tell strange stories!—but, for fear they should, Mine shall be mute as they are. Only this— And this no treason surely—might I but, But once more might I, see my lord again Safe home! But once more look upon his face! But once more take his hand in mine!— Hilloa! The words scarce from my lips.—Have the Gods heard? Or am I dreaming wide awake? as wide Awake I am—The Light! The Light! The Light Long look'd for, long despair'd of, on the Height! Oh more to me than all the stars of night! More than the Morning-star!—more than the Sun Who breaks my nightly watch, this rising one Which tells me that my year-long night is done! When, shaking off the collar of my watch, I first to Clytemnestra shall report Such news as, if indeed a lucky cast For her and Argos, sure a Main to me! But grant the Gods, to all! A master-cast, More than compensating all losses past; And lighting up our altars with a fire Of Victory that never shall expire! [Exit Warder. Daylight gradually dawns, and enter slowly Chorus. Chorus. I. Another rising of the sun That rolls another year away, Sees us through the portal dun Dividing night and day Like to phantoms from the crypt Of Morpheus or of Hades slipt, Through the sleeping city creeping, Murmuring an ancient song Of unvindicated wrong, Ten year told as ten year long. Since to revenge the great abuse To Themis done by Priam's son, The Brother-Princes that, co-heir Of Atreus, share his royal chair, And from the authentic hand of Zeus His delegated sceptre bear, Startled Greece with such a cry For Vengeance as a plunder'd pair Of Eagles, over their aerial lair Screaming, to whirlpool lash the waves of air. II. The Robber, blinded in his own conceit, Must needs think Retribution deaf and blind. Fool! not to know what tongue was in the wind, When Tellus shudder'd under flying feet, When stricken Ocean under alien wings; Was there no Phœbus to denounce the flight From Heav'n? Nor those ten thousand Eyes of Night? And, were no other eye nor ear of man Or God awake, yet universal Pan, For ever watching at the heart of things, And Zeus, the Warden of domestic Right, And the perennial sanctity of Kings, Let loose the Fury who, though late Retarded in the leash of Fate, Once loosed, after the Sinner springs; Over Ocean's heights and hollows, Into cave and forest follows, Into fastest guarded town, Close on the Sinner's heel insists, And, turn or baffle as he lists, Dogs him inexorably down. III. Therefore to revenge the debt To violated Justice due, Armèd Hellas hand in hand The iron toils of Ares drew Over water, over land, Over such a tract of years; Draught of blood abroad, of tears At home, and unexhausted yet: All the manhood Greece could muster, And her hollow ships enclose; All that Troy from her capacious Bosom pouring forth oppose; By the ships, beneath the wall, And about the sandy plain, Armour-glancing files advancing, Fighting, flying, slaying, slain: And among them, and above them, Crested Heroes, twain by twain, Lance to lance, and thrust to thrust, Front erect, and, in a moment, One or other roll'd in dust. Till the better blood of Argos Soaking in the Trojan sand, In her silent half dispeopled Cities, more than half unmann'd, Little more of man to meet Than the helpless child, or hoary Spectre of his second childhood, Tottering on triple feet, Like the idle waifs and strays Blown together from the ways Up and down the windy street. IV. But thus it is; All bides the destined Hour; And Man, albeit with Justice at his side, Fights in the dark against a secret Power Not to be conquer'd—and how pacified? V. For, before the Navy flush'd Wing from shore, or lifted oar To foam the purple brush'd; While about the altar hush'd Throng'd the ranks of Greece thick-fold, Ancient Chalcas in the bleeding Volume of the Future reading Evil things foresaw, foretold: That, to revenge some old disgrace Befall'n her sylvan train, Some dumb familiar of the Chace By Menelaus slain, The Goddess Artemis would vex The fleet of Greece with storms and checks: That Troy should not be reach'd at all; Or—as the Gods themselves divide In Heav'n to either mortal side— If ever reach'd, should never fall— Unless at such a loss and cost As counterpoises Won and Lost. VI. The Elder of the Royal Twain Listen'd in silence, daring not arraign Ill omen, or rebuke the raven lips: Then taking up the tangled skein Of Fate, he pointed to the ships; He sprang aboard: he gave the sign; And blazing in his golden arms ahead, Drew the long Navy in a glittering line After him like a meteor o'er the main. VII. So from Argos forth: and so O'er the rolling waters they, Till in the roaring To-and-fro Of rock-lock'd Aulis brought to stay: There the Goddess had them fast: With a bitter northern blast Blew ahead and block'd the way: Day by day delay; to ship And tackle damage and decay; Day by day to Prince and People Indignation and dismay. ‘All the while that in the ribb'd ‘Bosom of their vessels cribb'd, ‘Tower-crown'd Troy above the waters ‘Yonder, quaffing from the horn ‘Of Plenty, laughing them to scorn’— So would one to other say; And man and chief in rage and grief Fretted and consumed away. VIII. Then to Sacrifice anew: And again within the bleeding Volume of the Future reading, Once again the summon'd Seer Evil, Evil, still fore-drew. Day by day, delay, decay To ship and tackle, chief and crew: And but one way—one only way to appease The Goddess, and the wind of wrath subdue; One way of cure so worse than the disease, As, but to hear propound, The Atreidæ struck their sceptres to the ground. IX. After a death-deep pause, The Lord of man and armament his voice Lifted into the silence—‘Terrible choice! ‘To base imprisonment of wind and flood ‘Whether consign and sacrifice the band ‘Of heroes gather'd in my name and cause; ‘Or thence redeem them by a daughter's blood— ‘A daughter's blood shed by a father's hand; ‘Shed by a father's hand, and to atone ‘The guilt of One—who, could the God endure ‘Propitiation by the Life impure, ‘Should wash out her transgression with her own.’ X. But, breaking on that iron multitude, The Father's cry no kindred echo woke: And in the sullen silence that ensued An unrelenting iron asnwer spoke. XI. At last his neck to that unnatural yoke He bow'd: his hand to that unnatural stroke: With growing purpose, obstinate as the wind That block'd his fleet, so block'd his better mind, To all the Father's heart within him blind— For thus it fares with men; the seed Of Evil, sown by seeming Need, Grows, self-infatuation-nurst, From evil Thought to evil Deed, Incomprehensible at first, And to the end of Life accurst. XII. And thus, the blood of that one innocent Weigh'd light against one great accomplishment, At last—at last—in the meridian blaze Of Day, with all the Gods in Heaven agaze, And armed Greece below—he came to dare— After due preparation, pomp, and prayer, He came—the wretched father—came to dare— Himself—with sacrificial knife in hand,— Before the sacrificial altar stand, To which—her sweet lips, sweetly wont to sing Before him in the banquet-chamber, gagg'd, Lest one ill word should mar the impious thing; Her saffron scarf about her fluttering, Dumb as an all-but-speaking picture, dragg'd Through the remorseless soldiery— But soft!— While I tell the more than oft- Told Story, best in silence found, Incense-breathing fires aloft Up into the rising fire, Into which the stars expire, Of Morning mingle; and a sound As of Rumour at the heel Of some great tidings gathers ground; And from portals that disclose Before a fragrant air that blows Them open, what great matter, Sirs, Thus early Clytemnestra stirs, Hither through the palace gate Torch in hand, and step-elate, Advancing, with the kindled Eyes As of triumphant Sacrifice? Enter Clytemnestra. Oh, Clytemnestra, my obeisance Salutes your coming footstep, as her right Who rightly occupies the fellow-chair Of that now ten years widow'd of its Lord. But—be it at your pleasure ask'd, as answer'd— What great occasion, almost ere Night's self Rekindles into Morning from the Sun, Has woke your Altar-fire to Sacrifice? Clytemnestra. Oh, never yet did Night— Night of all Good the Mother, as men say, Conceive a fairer issue than To-day! Prepare your ears, Old man, for tidings such As youthful hope would scarce anticipate. Chorus. I have prepared them for such news as such Preamble argues. Clytemnestra. What if you be told— Oh mighty sum in one small figure cast!— That ten-year-toil'd-for Troy is ours at last? Chorus. ‘If told!’—Once more!—the word escaped our ears, With many a baffled rumour heretofore Slipp'd down the wind of wasted Expectation. Clytemnestra. Once more then; and with unconditional Assurance having hit the mark indeed That Rumour aim'd at—Troy, with all the towers Our burning vengeance leaves aloft, is ours. Now speak I plainly? Chorus. Oh! to make the tears, That waited to bear witness in the eye, Start, to convict our incredulity! Clytemnestra. Oh, blest conviction that enriches you That lose the cause with all the victory! Chorus. Ev'n so. But how yourself convinced before? Clytemnestra. By no less sure a witness than the God. Chorus. What, in a dream? Clytemnestra. I am not one to trust The vacillating witnesses of Sleep. Chorus. Ay—but as surely undeluded by The waking Will, that what we strongly would Imaginates? Clytemnestra. Ay, like a doating girl. Chorus. Oh, Clytemnestra, pardon mere Old Age That, after so long starving upon Hope, But slowly brooks his own Accomplishment. The Ten-year war is done then! Troy is taken! The Gods have told you, and the Gods tell true— But—how? and when? Clytemnestra. Ev'n with the very birth Of the good Night which mothers this best Day. Chorus. To-day! To-night! but of Night's work in Troy Who should inform the scarce awaken'd ear Of Morn in Argos? Clytemnestra. Hephaistos, the lame God, And spriteliest of mortal messengers; Who, springing from the bed of burning Troy, Hither, by fore-devised Intelligence Agreed upon between my Lord and me, Posted from dedicated Height to Height The reach of land and sea that lies between. And, first to catch him and begin the game, Did Ida fire her forest-pine, and, waving, Handed him on to that Hermæan steep Of Lemnos; Lemnos to the summit of Zeus-consecrated Athos lifted; whence, As by the giant taken, so despatch'd, The Torch of Conquest, traversing the wide Ægæan with a sunbeam-stretching stride, Struck up the drowsy watchers on Makistos; Who, flashing back the challenge, flash'd it on To those who watch'd on the Messapian height. With whose quick-kindling heather heap'd and fired The meteor-bearded messenger refresh'd, Clearing Asopus at a bound, struck fire From old Kithæron; and, so little tired As waxing even wanton with the sport, Over the sleeping water of Gorgopis Sprung to the Rock of Corinth; thence to the cliffs Which stare down the Saronic Gulf, that now Began to shiver in the creeping Dawn; Whence, for a moment on the neighbouring top Of Arachnæum lighting, one last bound Brought him to Agamemnon's battlements. By such gigantic strides in such a Race Where First and Last alike are Conquerors, Posted the travelling Fire, whose Father-light Ida conceived of burning Troy To-night. Chorus. Woman, your words man-metal ring, and strike Ev'n from the tuneless fibre of Old Age Such martial unison as from the lips Shall break into full Pæan by and by. Clytemnestra. Ay, think—think—think, old man, and in your soul, As if 'twere mirror'd in your outward eye, Imagine what wild work a-doing there— In Troy—to-night—to-day—this moment—how Harmoniously, as in one vessel meet Esil and Oil, meet Triumph and Despair, Sluiced by the sword along the reeking street, On which the Gods look down from burning air. Slain, slaying—dying, dead—about the dead Fighting to die themselves—maidens and wives Lock'd by the locks, with their barbarian young, And torn away to slavery and shame By hands all reeking with their Champion's blood. Until, with execution weary, we Fling down our slaughter-satiated swords, To gorge ourselves on the unfinish'd feasts Of poor old Priam and his sons; and then, Roll'd on rich couches never spread for us, Ev'n now our sleep-besotted foreheads turn Up to the very Sun that rises here. Such is the lawful game of those who win Upon so just a quarrel—so long fought: Provided always that, with jealous care, Retaliation wreaking upon those Who our insulted Gods upon them drew, We push not Riot to their Altar-foot; Remembering, on whichever mortal side Engaged, the Gods are Gods in heav'n and earth, And not to be insulted unavenged. This let us take to heart, and keep in sight; Lest, having run victoriously thus far, And turn'd the very pillar of our race, Before we reach the long'd-for goal of Home Nemesis overtake, or trip us up; Some ere safe shipp'd: or, launch'd upon the foam, Ere touch'd the threshold of their native shore; Yea, or that reach'd, the threshold of the door Of their own home; from whatsoever corner The jealous Power is ever on the watch To compass arrogant Prosperity. These are a woman's words; for men to take, Or disregarded drop them, as they will; Enough for me, if having won the stake, I pray the Gods with us to keep it still. [Exit Clytemnestra. Chorus. [I.] Oh, sacred Night, From whose unfathomable breast Creative Order formed and saw Chaos emerging into Law: And now, committed with Eternal Right, Who didst with star-entangled net invest So close the guilty City as she slept, That when the deadly fisher came to draw, Not one of all the guilty fry through crept. II. Oh, Nemesis, Night's daughter! in whose bosoming abyss Secretly sitting by the Sinner's sleeve, Thou didst with self-confusion counterweave His plot; and when the fool his arrow sped, Thine after-shot didst only not dismiss Till certain not to miss the guilty head. III. Some think the Godhead, couching at his ease Deep in the purple Heav'ns, serenely sees Insult the altar of Eternal Right. Fools! For though Fortune seem to misrequite, And Retribution for a while forget; Sooner or later she reclaims the debt With usury that triples the amount Of Nemesis with running Time's account. IV. For soon or late sardonic Fate With Man against himself conspires; Puts on the mask of his desires: Up the steps of Time elate Leads him blinded with his pride, And gathering as he goes along The fuel of his suicide: Until having topp'd the pyre Which Destiny permits no higher, Ambition sets himself on fire; In conflagration like the crime Conspicuous through the world and time Down amidst his brazen walls The accumulated Idol falls To shapeless ashes; Demigod Under the vulgar hoof down-trod Whose neck he trod on; not an eye To weep his fall, nor lip to sigh For him a prayer; or, if there were, No God to listen, or reply. V. And as the son his father's guilt may rue; And, by retort of justice, what the son Has sinn'd, to ruin on the father run; So may the many help to pay the due Of guilt, remotely implicate with one. And as the tree 'neath which a felon cowers, With all its branch is blasted by the bolt Of Justice launch'd from Heav'n at his revolt; Thus with old Priam, with his royal line, Kindred and people; yea, the very towers They crouch'd in, built by masonry divine. VI. Like a dream through sleep she glided Through the silent city gate, By a guilty Hermes guided On the feather'd feet of Theft; Leaving between those she left And those she fled to lighted Discord, Unextinguishable Hate; Leaving him whom least she should, Menelaus brave and good, Scarce believing in the mutter'd Rumour, in the worse than utter'd Omen of the wailing maidens, Of the shaken hoary head, Of deserted board and bed. For the phantom of the lost one Haunts him in the wonted places; Hall and Chamber, which he paces Hither, Thither, listening, looking, Phantom-like himself alone; Till he comes to loathe the faces Of the marble mute Colossi, Godlike Forms, and half-divine, Founders of the Royal line, Who with all unalter'd Quiet Witness all and make no sign. But the silence of the chambers, And the shaken hoary head, And the voices of the mourning Women, and of ocean wailing, Over which with unavailing Arms he reaches, as to hail The phantom of a flying sail— All but answer, Fled! fled! fled! False! dishonour'd! worse than dead! VII. At last the sun goes down along the bay, And with him drags detested Day. He sleeps; and, dream-like as she fled, beside His pillow, Dream indeed, behold! his Bride Once more in more than bridal beauty stands; But, ever as he reaches forth his hands, Slips from them back into the viewless deep, On those soft silent wings that walk the ways of sleep. VIII. Not beside thee in the chamber, Menelaus, any more; But with him she fled with, pillow'd On the summer softly-billow'd Ocean, into dimple wreathing Underneath a breeze of amber Air that, as from Eros breathing, Fill'd the sail and flew before; Floating on the summer seas Like some sweet Effigies Of Eirene's self, or sweeter Aphrodite, sweeter still: With the Shepherd, from whose luckless Hand upon the Phrygian hill, Of the three Immortals, She The fatal prize of Beauty bore, Floating with him o'er the foam She rose from, to the Shepherd's home On the Ionian shore. IX. Down from the City to the water-side Old Priam, with his princely retinue. By many a wondering Phrygian follow'd, drew To welcome and bear in the Goddess-bride, Whom some propitious wind of Fortune blew From whence they knew not o'er the waters wide Among the Trojan people to abide, A pledge of Love and Joy for ever—Yes; As one who drawing from the leopardess Her suckling cub, and, fascinated by The little Savage of the lustrous eye, Bears home, for all to fondle and caress, And be the very darling of the house It makes a den of blood of by and by. X. For the wind, that amber blew, Tempest in its bosom drew, Soon began to hiss and roar; And the sweet Effigies That amber breeze and summer seas Had wafted to the Ionian shore, By swift metamorphosis Turn'd into some hideous, hated, Fury of Revenge, and fated Hierophant of Nemesis; Who, growing with the day and hour, Grasp'd the wall, and topp'd the tower, And, when the time came, by its throat The victim City seized, and smote. XI. But now to be resolved, whether indeed Those fires of Night spoke truly, or mistold To cheat a doating woman; for, behold, Advancing from the shore with solemn speed, A Herald from the Fleet, his footsteps roll'd In dust, Haste's thirsty consort, but his brow Check-shadow'd with the nodding Olive-bough; Who shall interpret us the speechless sign Of the fork'd tongue that preys upon the pine. Herald. Oh, Fatherland of Argos, back to whom After ten years do I indeed return Under the dawn of this auspicious day! Of all the parted anchors of lost Hope That this, depended least on, yet should hold; Amid so many men to me so dear About me dying, yet myself exempt Return to live what yet of life remains Among my own; among my own at last To share the blest communion of the Dead! Oh, welcome, welcome, welcome once again My own dear Country and the light she draws From the benignant Heav'ns; and all the Gods Who guard her; Zeus Protector first of all; And Phœbus, by this all-restoring dawn Who heals the wounds his arrows dealt so fast Beside Scamander; and not last nor least Among the Powers engaged upon our side, Hermes, the Herald's Patron, and his Pride; Who, having brought me safely through the war, Now brings me back to tell the victory Into my own belovèd country's ear; Who, all the more by us, the more away, Beloved, will greet with Welcome no less dear This remnant of the unremorseful spear. And, oh, you Temples, Palaces, and throned Colossi, that affront the rising sun, If ever yet, your marble foreheads now Bathe in the splendour of returning Day To welcome back your so long absent Lord; Who by Zeus' self directed to the spot Of Vengeance, and the special instrument Of Retribution put into his hands, Has undermined, uprooted, and destroy'd, Till scarce one stone upon another stands, The famous Citadel, that, deeply cast For crime, has all the forfeit paid at last. Chorus. Oh hail and welcome, Herald of good news! Welcome and hail! and doubt not thy return As dear to us as thee. Herald. To me so dear, After so long despair'd of, that, for fear Life's after-draught the present should belie, One might implore the Gods ev'n now to die! Chorus. Oh, your soul hunger'd after home! Herald. So sore, That sudden satisfaction of once more Return weeps out its surfeit at my eyes. Chorus. And ours, you see, contagiously, no less The same long grief, and sudden joy, confess. Herald. What! Argos for her missing children yearn'd As they for her, then? Chorus. Ay; perhaps and more, Already pining with an inward sore. Herald. How so? Chorus. Nay, Silence, that has best endured The pain, may best dismiss the memory. Herald. Ev'n so. For who, unless the God himself, Expects to live his life without a flaw? Why, once begin to open that account, Might not we tell for ten good years to come Of all we suffer'd in the ten gone by? Not the mere course and casualty of war, Alarum, March, Battle, and such hard knocks As foe with foe expects to give and take; But all the complement of miseries That go to swell a long campaign's account. Cramm'd close aboard the ships, hard bed, hard board: Or worse perhaps while foraging ashore In winter time; when, if not from the walls, Pelted from Heav'n by Day, to couch by Night Between the falling dews and rising damps That elf'd the locks, and set the body fast With cramp and ague; or, to mend the matter, Good mother Ida from her winter top Flinging us down a coverlet of snow. Or worst perhaps in Summer, toiling in The bloody harvest-field of torrid sand, When not an air stirr'd the fierce Asian noon, And ev'n the sea sleep-sicken'd in his bed. But why lament the Past, as past it is? If idle for the Dead who feel no more, Idler for us to whom this blissful Dawn Shines doubly bright against the stormy Past; Who, after such predicament and toil, Boast, once more standing on our mother soil, That Zeus, who sent us to revenge the crime Upon the guilty people, now recalls To hang their trophies on our temple walls For monumental heir-looms to all time. Chorus. Oh, but Old age, however slow to learn, Not slow to learn, nor after you repeat, Lesson so welcome, Herald of the Fleet! But here is Clytemnestra; be you first To bless her ears, as mine, with news so sweet. Clytemnestra. I sang my Song of Triumph ere he came, Alone I sang it while the City slept, And these wise Senators, with winking eyes, Look'd grave, and weigh'd mistrustfully my word, As the light coinage of a woman's brain. And so they went their way. But not the less From those false fires I lit my altar up, And, woman-wise, held on my song, until The City taking up the note from me, Scarce knowing why, about that altar flock'd, Where, like the Priest of Victory, I stood, Torch-handed, drenching in triumphant wine The flame that from the smouldering incense rose. Now what more needs? This Herald of the Day Adds but another witness to the Night; And I will hear no more from other lips, Till from my husband Agamemnon all, Whom with all honour I prepare to meet. Oh, to a loyal woman what so sweet As once more wide the gate of welcome fling To the loved Husband whom the Gods once more After long travail home triumphant bring; Where he shall find her, as he left before, Fix'd like a trusty watchdog at the door, Tractable him-ward, but inveterate Against the doubtful stranger at the gate; And not a seal within the house but still Inviolate, under a woman's trust Incapable of taint as gold of rust. [Exit Clytemnestra. Herald. A boast not misbeseeming a true woman. Chorus. For then no boast at all. But she says well; And Time interprets all. Enough for us To praise the Gods for Agamemnon's safe, And more than safe return. And Menelaus, The other half of Argos—What of him? Herald. Those that I most would gladden with good news, And on a day like this—with fair but false I dare not. Chorus. What, must fair then needs be false? Herald. Old man, the Gods grant somewhat, and withhold As seems them good: a time there is for Praise, A time for Supplication: nor is it well To twit the celebration of their largess, Reminding them of somewhat they withhold. Chorus. Yet till we know how much withheld or granted, We know not how the balance to adjust Of Supplication or of Praise. Herald. Alas, The Herald who returns with downcast eyes, And leafless brow prophetic of Reverse, Let him at once—at once let him, I say, Lay the whole burden of Ill-tidings down In the mid-market place. But why should one Returning with the garland on his brow Be stopp'd to name the single missing leaf Of which the Gods have stinted us? Chorus. Alas, The putting of a fearful question by Is but to ill conjecture worse reply! You bring not back then—do not leave behind— What Menelaus was? Herald. The Gods forbid! Safe shipp'd with all the host. Chorus. Well but—how then? Surely no tempest— Herald. Ay! by that one word Hitting the centre of a boundless sorrow! Chorus. Well, but if peradventure from the fleet Parted—not lost? Herald. None but the eye of Day, Now woke, knows all the havoc of the Night. For Night it was; all safe aboard—sail set, And oars all beating home; when suddenly, As if those old antagonists had sworn New strife between themselves for our destruction, The sea, that tamely let us mount his back, Began to roar and plunge under a lash Of tempest from the thundering heavens so fierce As, falling on our fluttering navy, some Scatter'd, or whirl'd away like flakes of foam: Or, huddling wave on wave, so ship on ship Like fighting eagles on each other fell, And beak, and wing, and claws, entangled, tore To pieces one another, or dragg'd down. So when at last the tardy-rising Sun Survey'd, and show'd, the havoc Night had done, We, whom some God—or Fortune's self, I think— Seizing the helm, had steer'd as man could not, Beheld the waste Ægæan wilderness Strown with the shatter'd forest of the fleet, Trunk, branch, and foliage; and yet worse, I ween, The flower of Argos floating dead between. Then we, scarce trusting in our own escape, And saving such as yet had life to save, Along the heaving wilderness of wave Went ruminating, who of those we miss'd Might yet survive, who lost: the saved, no doubt, As sadly speculating after us. Of whom, if Menelaus—and the Sun (A prayer which all the Gods in Heav'n fulfil!) Behold him on the water breathing still; Doubt not that Zeus, under whose special showers And suns the royal growth of Atreus towers, Will not let perish stem, and branch, and fruit, By loss of one corroborating root. Chorus. [I.] Oh, Helen, Helen, Helen! oh, fair name And fatal, of the fatal-fairest dame That ever blest or blinded human eyes! Of mortal women Queen beyond compare, As she whom the foam lifted to the skies Is Queen of all who breathe immortal air! Whoever, and from whatsoever wells Of Divination, drew the syllables By which we name thee; who shall ever dare In after time the fatal name to wear, Or would, to be so fatal, be so fair? Whose dowry was a Husband's shame; Whose nuptial torch was Troy in flame; Whose bridal Chorus, groans and cries; Whose banquet, brave men's obsequies; Whose Hymenæal retinue, The winged dogs of War that flew Over lands and over seas, Following the tainted breeze, Till, Scamander reed among, Their fiery breath and bloody tongue The fatal quarry found and slew; And, having done the work to which The God himself halloo'd them, back Return a maim'd and scatter'd pack. II. And he for whose especial cause Zeus his winged instrument With the lightning in his claws From the throne of thunder sent: He for whom the sword was drawn: Mountain ashes fell'd and sawn; And the armed host of Hellas Cramm'd within them, to discharge On the shore to bleed at large; He, in mid accomplishment Of Justice, from his glory rent! What ten years had hardly won, In a single night undone; And on earth what saved and gain'd, By the ravin sea distrain'd. III. Such is the sorrow of this royal house; And none in all the City but forlorn Under its own peculiar sorrow bows. For the stern God who, deaf to human love, Grudges the least abridgment of the tale Of human blood once pledged to him, above The centre of the murder-dealing crowd Suspends in air his sanguinary scale; And for the blooming Hero gone a-field Homeward remits a beggarly return Of empty helmet, fallen sword and shield, And some light ashes in a little urn. IV. Then wild and high goes up the cry To heav'n, ‘So true! so brave! so fair! ‘The young colt of the flowing hair ‘And flaming eye, and now—look there! ‘Ashes and arms!’ or, ‘Left behind ‘Unburied, in the sun and wind ‘To wither, or become the feast ‘Of bird obscene, or unclean beast; ‘The good, the brave, without a grave— ‘All to redeem her from the shame ‘To which she sold her self and name!’— For such insinuation in the dark About the City travels like a spark; Till the pent tempest into lightning breaks, And takes the topmost pinnacle for mark. V. But avaunt all evil omen! Perish many, so the State They die for live inviolate; Which, were all her mortal leafage In the blast of Ares scatter'd, So herself at heart unshatter'd, In due season she retrieves All her wasted wealth of leaves, And age on age shall spread and rise To cover earth and breathe the skies. While the rival at her side Who the wrath of Heav'n defied, By the lashing blast, or flashing Bolt of Heav'n comes thunder-crashing, Top and lop, and trunk and bough, Down, for ever down. And now, He to whom the Zeus of Vengeance Did commit the bolt of Fate— Agamemnon—how shall I With a Pæan not too high For mortal glory, to provoke From the Gods a counter-stroke, Nor below desert so lofty, Suitably felicitate? Such as chasten'd Age for due May give, and Manhood take for true. For, as many men comply From founts no deeper than the eye With others' sorrows; many more, With a Welcome from the lips, That far the halting heart outstrips, Fortune's Idol fall before. Son of Atreus, I premise, When at first the means and manhood Of the cities thou didst stake For a wanton woman's sake, I might grudge the sacrifice; But, the warfare once begun, Hardly fought and hardly won, Now from Glory's overflowing Horn of Welcome all her glowing Honours, and with uninvidious Hand, before your advent throwing, I salute, and bid thee welcome, Son of Atreus, Agamemnon, Zeus' revenging Right-hand, Lord Of taken Troy and righted Greece: Bid thee from the roving throne Of War the reeking steed release; Leave the laurell'd ship to ride Anchor'd in her country's side, And resume the royal helm Of thy long-abandon'd realm: What about the State or Throne Of good or evil since has grown, Alter, cancel, or complete; And to well or evil-doer Even-handed Justice mete. Enter Agamemnon in his chariot, Cassandra following in another. Agamemnon. First, as first due, my Country I salute, And all her tutelary Gods; all those Who, having sent me forth, now bring me back, After full retribution wrought on those Who retribution owed us, and the Gods In full consistory determined; each, With scarce a swerving eye to Mercy's side, Dropping his vote into the urn of blood, Caught and consuming in whose fiery wrath, The stately City, from her panting ashes Into the nostril of revolted Heav'n Gusts of expiring opulence puffs up. Those who know the Greek will scarce accuse me of over-alliteration in this line, which runs in the original thus, Spodos propempei pionas ploutou pnoas. For which, I say, the Gods alone be thank'd; By whose contrivance round about the wall We drew the belt of Ares, and laid bare The flank of Ilium to the Lion-horse, Dr. Donaldson tells us in his Varronianus (says Paley), that the Lion was the symbol of the Atreidæ; and Pausanias writes that part of the ancient walls of Mycenæ was yet standing in his day, and Lions on the gate. Wordsworth (Athens and Attica) says the Lion was often set up to commemorate a victory. Who sprung by night over the city wall, And foal'd his iron progeny within, About the setting of the Pleiades. ‘About the setting of the Pleiades,’ is about the end of Autumn. Thus much by way of prelude to the Gods. For you, oh white-hair'd senators of Argos, Your measured Welcome I receive for just; Aware on what a tickle base of fortune The monument of human Glory stands; And, for humane congratulation, knowing How, smile as may the mask, the man behind Frets at the fortune that degrades his own. This, having heard of from the wise, myself, From long experience in the ways of men, Can vouch for—what a shadow of a shade Is human loyalty; and, as a proof, Of all the Host that fill'd the Grecian ship, And pour'd at large along the field of Troy, One only Chief—and he, too, like yourself, At first with little stomach for the cause— The wise Odysseus—once in harness, he With all his might pull'd in the yoke with me, Through envy, obloquy, and opposition: And in Odysseus' honour, live or dead— For yet we know not which—shall this be said. Of which enough. For other things of moment To which you point, or human or divine, We shall forthwith consider and adjudge In seasonable council; what is well, Or in our absence well deserving, well Establish and requite; what not, redress With salutary caution; or, if need, With the sharp edge of Justice; and to health Restore, and right, our ailing Commonwealth. Now, first of all, by my own altar-hearth To thank the Gods for my return, and pray That Victory, which thus far by my side Has flown with us, with us may still abide. Enter Clytemnestra from the Palace. Clytemnestra. Oh Men of Argos, count it not a shame If a fond wife, and one whom riper years From Youth's becoming bashfulness excuse, Dares own her love before the face of men; Nor leaving it for others to enhance, Simply declares the wretched widowhood Which these ten years she has endured, since first Her husband Agamemnon went to Troy. 'Tis no light matter, let me tell you, Sirs, A woman left in charge of house and home— And when that house and home a Kingdom—and She left alone to rule it—and ten years! Beside dissent and discontent at home, Storm'd from abroad with contrary reports, Now fair, now foul; but still as time wore on Growing more desperate; as dangerous Unto the widow'd kingdom as herself. Why, had my husband there but half the wounds Fame stabb'd him with, he were before me now, Not the whole man we see him, but a body Gash'd into network; ay, or had he died But half as often as Report gave out, He would have needed thrice the cloak of earth To cover him, that triple Geryon Lies buried under in the world below. Thus, back and forward baffled, and at last So desperate—that, if I be here alive To tell the tale, no thanks to me for that, Whose hands had twisted round my neck the noose Which others loosen'd—my Orestes too In whose expanding manhood day by day My Husband I perused—and, by the way, Whom wonder not, my Lord, not seeing here; My simple mother-love, and jealousy Of civic treason—ever as you know, Most apt to kindle when the lord away— Having bestow'd him, out of danger's reach, With Strophius of Phocis, wholly yours Bound by the generous usages of war, That make the once-won foe so fast a friend. Thus, widow'd of my son as of his sire, No wonder if I wept—not drops, but showers, The ten years' night through which I watch'd in vain The star that was to bring him back to me; Or, if I slept, a sleep so thin as scared Even at the slight incursion of the gnat; And yet more thick with visionary terrors Than thrice the waking while had occupied. Well, I have borne all this: all this have borne, Without a grudge against the wanderer, Whose now return makes more than rich amends For all ungrateful absence—Agamemnon, My Lord and Husband; Lord of Argos; Troy's Confounder: Mainstay of the realm of Greece; And Master-column of the house of Atreus— Oh wonder not if I accumulate All honour and endearment on his head! If to his country, how much more to me, Welcome, as land to sailors long at sea, Or water in the desert; whose return Is fire to the forsaken winter-hearth; Whose presence, like the rooted Household Tree That, winter-dead so long, anew puts forth To shield us from the Dogstar, what time Zeus Wrings the tart vintage into blissful juice. Down from the chariot thou standest in, Crown'd with the flaming towers of Troy, descend, And to this palace, rich indeed with thee, But beggar-poor without, return! And ye, My women, carpet all the way before, From the triumphal carriage to the door, With all the gold and purple in the chest Stored these ten years; and to what purpose stored, Unless to strew the footsteps of their Lord Returning to his unexpected rest! Agamemnon. Daughter of Leda, Mistress of my house, Beware lest loving Welcome of your Lord, Measuring itself by his protracted absence, Exceed the bound of rightful compliment, And better left to other lips than yours. Address me not, address me not, I say With dust-adoring adulation, meeter For some barbarian Despot from his slave; Nor with invidious Purple strew my way, Fit only for the footstep of a God Lighting from Heav'n to earth. Let whoso will Trample their glories underfoot, not I. Woman, I charge you, honour me no more Than as the man I am; if honour-worth, Needing no other trapping but the fame Of the good deed I clothe myself withal; And knowing that, of all their gifts to man, No greater gift than Self-sobriety The Gods vouchsafe him in the race of life: Which, after thus far running, if I reach The goal in peace, it shall be well for me. Clytemnestra. Why, how think you old Priam would have walk'd Had he return'd to Troy your conqueror, As you to Hellas his? Agamemnon. What then? Perhaps Voluptuary Asiatic-like, On gold and purple. Clytemnestra. Well, and grudging this, When all that out before your footstep flows Ebbs back into the treasury again; Think how much more, had Fate the tables turn'd, Irrevocably from those coffers gone, For those barbarian feet to walk upon, To buy your ransom back! Agamemnon. Enough, enough! I know my reason. Clytemnestra. What! the jealous God? Or, peradventure, yet more envious Man? Agamemnon. And that of no small moment. Clytemnestra. No; the one Sure proof of having won what others would. Agamemnon. No matter—Strife but ill becomes a woman. Clytemnestra. And frank submission to her simple wish How well becomes the Soldier in his strength! Agamemnon. And I must then submit? Clytemnestra. Ay, Agamemnon, Deny me not this first Desire on this First Morning of your long-desired Return. Agamemnon. But not till I have put these sandals off, That, slave-like, too officiously would pander Between the purple and my dainty feet. For fear, for fear indeed, some Jealous eye From heav'n above, or earth below, should strike The Man who walks the earth Immortal-like. So much for that. For this same royal maid, Cassandra, daughter of King Priamus, Whom, as the flower of all the spoil of Troy, The host of Hellas dedicates to me; Entreat her gently; knowing well that none But submit hardly to a foreign yoke; And those of Royal blood most hardly brook. That if I sin thus trampling underfoot A woof in which the Heav'ns themselves are dyed, The jealous God may less resent his crime, Who mingles human mercy with his pride. Clytemnestra. The Sea there is, and shall the sea be dried? Fount inexhaustibler of purple grain Than all the wardrobes of the world could drain; And Earth there is, whose dusky closets hide The precious metal wherewith not in vain The Gods themselves this Royal house provide; For what occasion worthier, or more meet, Than now to carpet the victorious feet Of Him who, thus far having done their will, Shall now their last About-to-be fulfil? [Agamemnon descends from his chariot, and goes with Clytemnestra into the house, Cassandra remaining.] Chorus. [I.] About the nations runs a saw, That Over-good ill-fortune breeds; And true that, by the mortal law, Fortune her spoilt children feeds To surfeit, such as sows the seeds Of Insolence, that, as it grows, The flower of Self-repentance blows. And true that Virtue often leaves The marble walls and roofs of kings, And underneath the poor man's eaves On smoky rafter folds her wings. II. Thus the famous city, flown With insolence, and overgrown, Is humbled: all her splendour blown To smoke: her glory laid in dust; Who shall say by doom unjust? But should He to whom the wrong Was done, and Zeus himself made strong To do the vengeance He decreed— At last returning with the meed He wrought for—should the jealous Eye That blights full-blown prosperity Pursue him—then indeed, indeed, Man should hoot and scare aloof Good-fortune lighting on the roof; Yea, even Virtue's self forsake If Glory follow'd in the wake; Seeing bravest, best, and wisest But the playthings of a day, Which a shadow can trip over, And a breath can puff away. Clytemnestra (re-entering). Yet for a moment let me look on her— This, then, is Priam's daughter— Cassandra, and a Prophetess, whom Zeus Has giv'n into my hands to minister Among my slaves. Didst thou prophesy that? Well—some more famous have so fall'n before— Ev'n Herakles, the son of Zeus, they say Was sold, and bow'd his shoulder to the yoke. Chorus. And, if needs must a captive, better far Of some old house that affluent Time himself Has taught the measure of prosperity, That drunk with sudden superfluity. Clytemnestra. Ev'n so. You hear? Therefore at once descend From that triumphal chariot—And yet She keeps her station still, her laurel on, Disdaining to make answer. Chorus. Nay, perhaps, Like some stray swallow blown across the seas, Interpreting no twitter but her own. Clytemnestra. But, if barbarian, still interpreting The universal language of the hand. Chorus. Which yet again she does not seem to see, Staring before her with wide-open eyes As in a trance. Clytemnestra. Ay, ay, a prophetess— Phœbus Apollo's minion once—Whose now? A time will come for her. See you to it: A greater business now is on my hands: For lo! the fire of Sacrifice is lit, And the grand victim by the altar stands. [Exit Clytemnestra. Chorus (continuing). Still a mutter'd and half-blind Superstition haunts mankind, That, by some divine decree Yet by mortal undivined, Mortal Fortune must not over- Leap the bound he cannot see; For that even wisest labour Lofty-building, builds to fall, Evermore a jealous neighbour Undermining floor and wall. So that on the smoothest water Sailing, in a cloudless sky, The wary merchant overboard Flings something of his precious hoard To pacify the jealous eye, That will not suffer man to swell Over human measure. Well, As the Gods have order'd we Must take—I know not—let it be. But, by rule of retribution, Hidden, too, from human eyes, Fortune in her revolution, If she fall, shall fall to rise: And the hand of Zeus dispenses Even measure in the main: One short harvest recompenses With a glut of golden grain; So but men in patience wait Fortune's counter-revolution Axled on eternal Fate; And the Sisters three that twine, Cut not short the vital line; For indeed the purple seed Of life once shed— Cassandra. Phœbus Apollo! Chorus. Hark! The lips at last unlocking. Cassandra. Phœbus! Phœbus! Chorus. Well, what of Phœbus, maiden? though a name 'Tis but disparagement to call upon In misery. Cassandra. Apollo! Apollo! Again! Oh, the burning arrow through the brain! Phœbus Apollo! Apollo! Chorus. Seemingly Possess'd indeed—whether by— Cassandra. Phœbus! Phœbus! Thorough trampled ashes, blood, and fiery rain, Over water seething, and behind the breathing Warhorse in the darkness—till you rose again— Took the helm—took the rein— Chorus. As one that half asleep at dawn recalls A night of Horror! Cassandra. Hither, whither, Phœbus? And with whom, Leading me, lighting me— Chorus. I can answer that— Cassandra. Down to what slaughter-house? Foh! the smell of carnage through the door Scares me from it—drags me tow'rd it— Phœbus! Apollo! Apollo! Chorus. One of the dismal prophet-pack, it seems, That hunt the trail of blood. But here at fault— This is no den of slaughter, but the house Of Agamemnon. Cassandra. Down upon the towers Phantoms of two mangled Children hover—and a famish'd man, At an empty table glaring, seizes and devours! Chorus. Thyestes and his children! Strange enough For any maiden from abroad to know, Or, knowing— Cassandra. And look! in the chamber below The terrible Woman, listening, watching, Under a mask, preparing the blow In the fold of her robe— Chorus. Nay, but again at fault: For in the tragic story of this House— Unless, indeed, the fatal Helen— No woman— Cassandra. No Woman—Tisiphone! Daughter Of Tartarus—love-grinning Woman above, Dragon-tail'd under—honey-tongued, Harpy-claw'd, Into the glittering meshes of slaughter She wheedles, entices, him into the poisonous Fold of the serpent— Chorus. Peace, mad woman, peace! Whose stony lips once open vomit out Such uncouth horrors. Cassandra. I tell you the lioness Slaughters the Lion asleep; and lifting Her blood-dripping fangs buried deep in his mane, Glaring about her insatiable, bellowing, Bounds hither—Phœbus, Apollo, Apollo, Apollo! Whither have you led me, under night alive with fire, Through the trampled ashes of the city of my sire, From my slaughter'd kinsmen, fallen throne, insulted shrine, Slave-like to be butcher'd, the daughter of a Royal line? Chorus. And so returning, like a nightingale Returning to the passionate note of woe By which the silence first was broken! Cassandra. Oh, A nightingale, a nightingale, indeed, That, as she ‘Itys! Itys! Itys!’ so I ‘Helen! Helen! Helen!’ having sung Amid my people, now to those who flung And trampled on the nest, and slew the young, Keep crying ‘Blood! blood! blood!’ and none will heed! Now what for me is this prophetic weed, And what for me is this immortal crown, Who like a wild swan from Scamander's reed Chaunting her death-song float Cocytus-down? There let the fatal Leaves to perish lie! To perish, or enrich some other brow With that all-fatal gift of Prophecy They palpitated under Him who now, Checking his flaming chariot in mid sky, With divine irony sees disadorn The wretch his love has made the people's scorn, The raving quean, the mountebank, the scold, Who, wrapt up in the ruin she foretold With those who would not listen, now descends To that dark kingdom where his empire ends. Chorus. Strange that Apollo should the laurel wreath Of Prophecy he crown'd your head withal Himself disgrace. But something have we heard Of some divine revenge for slighted love. Cassandra. Ay—and as if in malice to attest With one expiring beam of Second-sight Wherewith his victim he has cursed and blest, Ere quench'd for ever in descending night; As from behind a veil no longer peeps The Bride of Truth, nor from their hidden deeps Darkle the waves of Prophecy, but run Clear from the very fountain of the Sun. Ye call'd—and rightly call'd—me bloodhound; ye That like old lagging dogs in self-despite Must follow up the scent with me; with me, Who having smelt the blood about this house Already spilt, now bark of more to be. For, though you hear them not, the infernal Choir Whose dread antiphony forswears the lyre, Who now are chaunting of that grim carouse Of blood with which the children fed their Sire, Shall never from their dreadful chorus stop Till all be counter-pledged to the last drop. Chorus. Hinting at what indeed has long been done, And widely spoken, no Apollo needs; And for what else you aim at—still in dark And mystic language— Cassandra. Nay, then, in the speech, She that reproved me was so glib to teach— Before yon Sun a hand's-breadth in the skies He moves in shall have moved, those age-sick eyes Shall open wide on Agamemnon slain Before your very feet. Now, speak I plain? Chorus. Blasphemer, hush! Cassandra. Ay, hush the mouth you may, But not the murder. Chorus. Murder! But the Gods— Cassandra. The Gods! Who even now are their accomplices. Chorus. Woman!—Accomplices—With whom?— Cassandra. With Her, Who brandishing aloft the axe of doom, That just has laid one victim at her feet, Looks round her for that other, without whom The banquet of revenge were incomplete. Yet ere I fall will I prelude the strain Of Triumph, that in full I shall repeat When, looking from the twilight Underland, I welcome Her as she descends amain, Gash'd like myself, but by a dearer hand. For that old murder'd Lion with me slain, Rolling an awful eyeball through the gloom He stalks about of Hades up to Day, Shall rouse the whelp of exile far away, His only authentic offspring, ere the grim Wolf crept between his Lioness and him; Who with one stroke of Retribution, her Who did the deed, and her adulterer, Shall drive to hell; and then, himself pursued By the wing'd Furies of his Mother's blood, Shall drag about the yoke of Madness, till Released, when Nemesis has gorged her fill, By that same God, in whose prophetic ray Viewing To-morrow mirror'd as To-day, And that this House of Atreus the same wine Themselves must drink they brew'd for me and mine; I close my lips for ever with one prayer, That the dark Warder of the World below Would ope the portal at a single blow. Chorus. And the raving voice, that rose Out of silence into speech Over-shooting human reach, Back to silence foams and blows, Leaving all my bosom heaving— Wrath and raving all, one knows; Prophet-seeming, but if ever Of the Prophet-God possess'd, By the Prophet's self confess'd God-abandon'd—woman's shrill Anguish into tempest rising, Louder as less listen'd. Still— Spite of Reason, spite of Will, What unwelcome, what unholy, Vapour of Foreboding, slowly Rising from the central soul's Recesses, all in darkness rolls? What! shall Age's torpid ashes Kindle at the ransom spark Of a raving maiden?—Hark! What was that behind the wall? A heavy blow—a groan—a fall— Some one crying—Listen further— Hark again then, crying ‘Murder!’ Some one—who then? Agamemnon? Agamemnon?—Hark again! Murder! murder! murder! murder! Help within there! Help without there! Break the doors in!— Clytemnestra. (Appearing from within, where lies Agamemnon dead.) Hermann says, ‘Tractis tabulatis’—the scene drawing—‘conspicitur Clytemnestra in conclavi stans ad corpus Agamemnonis.’ Spare your pain. Look! I who but just now before you all Boasted of loyal wedlock unashamed, Now unashamed dare boast the contrary. Why, how else should one compass the defeat Of him who underhand contrives one's own, Unless by such a snare of circumstance As, once enmesh'd, he never should break through? The blow now struck was not the random blow Of sudden passion, but with slow device Prepared, and levell'd with the hand of time. I say it who devised it; I who did; And now stand here to face the consequence. Ay, in a deadlier web than of that loom In whose blood-purple he divined a doom, And fear'd to walk upon, but walk'd at last, Entangling him inextricably fast, I smote him, and he bellow'd; and again I smote, and with a groan his knees gave way; And, as he fell before me, with a third And last libation from the deadly mace I pledged the crowning draught to Hades due, That subterranean Saviour—of the Dead! At certain Ceremonies, the Third and crowning Libation was to Zeus Soter; and thus ironically to Pluto. At which he spouted up the Ghost in such A burst of purple as, bespatter'd with, No less did I rejoice than the green ear Rejoices in the largess of the skies That fleeting Iris follows as it flies. Chorus. Oh woman, woman, woman! By what accursèd root or weed Of Earth, or Sea, or Hell, inflamed, Darest stand before us unashamed And, daring do, dare glory in the deed! Clytemnestra. Oh, I that dream'd the fall of Troy, as you Belike of Troy's destroyer. Dream or not, Here lies your King—my Husband—Agamemnon, Slain by this right hand's righteous handicraft. Like you, or like it not, alike to me; To me alike whether or not you share In making due libation over this Great Sacrifice—if ever due, from him Who, having charged so deep a bowl of blood, Himself is forced to drink it to the dregs. Chorus. Woman, what blood but that of Troy, which Zeus Foredoom'd for expiation by his hand For whom the penalty was pledged? And now, Over his murder'd body, Thou Talk of libation!—Thou! Thou! Thou! But mark! Not thine of sacred wine Over his head, but ours on thine Of curse, and groan, and torn-up stone, To slay or storm thee from the gate, The City's curse, the People's hate, Execrate, exterminate— Clytemnestra. Ay, ay, to me how lightly you adjudge Exile or death, and never had a word Of counter-condemnation for Him there; Who, when the field throve with the proper flock For Sacrifice, forsooth let be the beast, And with his own hand his own innocent Blood, and the darling passion of my womb— Her slew—to lull a peevish wind of Thrace. And him who cursed the city with that crime You hail with acclamation; but on me, Who only do the work you should have done, You turn the axe of condemnation. Well; Threaten you me, I take the challenge up; Here stand we face to face; win Thou the game, And take the stake you aim at; but if I— Then, by the Godhead that for me decides, Another lesson you shall learn, though late. Chorus. Man-mettled evermore, and now Manslaughter-madden'd! Shameless brow! But do you think us deaf and blind Not to know, and long ago, What Passion under all the prate Of holy justice made thee hate Where Love was due, and love where— Clytemnestra. Nay, then, hear! By this dead Husband, and the reconciled Avenging Fury of my slaughter'd child, I swear I will not reign the slave of fear While he that holds me, as I hold him, dear, Kindles his fire upon this hearth: my fast Shield for the time to come, as of the past. Yonder lies he that in the honey'd arms Of his Chryseides under Troy walls Dishonour'd mine: and this last laurell'd wench, Prophetic messmate of the rower's bench, Thus far in triumph his, with him along Shall go, together chaunting one death-song To Hades—fitting garnish for the feast Which Fate's avenging hand through mine hath dress'd. Chorus. Woe, woe, woe, woe! That death as sudden as the blow That laid Thee low would me lay low Where low thou liest, my sovereign Lord! Who ten years long to Trojan sword Devoted, and to storm aboard, In one ill woman's cause accurst, Liest slain before thy palace door By one accursedest and worst! Clytemnestra. Call not on Death, old man, that, call'd or no, Comes quick; nor spend your ebbing breath on me, Nor Helena: who but as arrows be Shot by the hidden hand behind the bow. Chorus. Alas, alas! The Curse I know That round the House of Atreus clings, About the roof, about the walls, Shrouds it with his sable wings; And still as each new victim falls, And gorged with kingly gore, Down on the bleeding carcase flings, And croaks for ‘More, more, more!’ Clytemnestra. Ay, now, indeed, you harp on likelier strings. Not I, nor Helen, but that terrible Alastor of old Tantalus in Hell; Who, one sole actor in the scene begun By him, and carried down from sire to son, The mask of Victim and Avenger shifts; And, for a last catastrophe, that grim Guest of the abominable banquet lifts His head from Hell, and in my person cries For one full-grown sufficient sacrifice, Requital of the feast prepared for him Of his own flesh and blood—And there it lies. Chorus. Oh, Agamemnon! Oh, my Lord! Who, after ten years toil'd; After barbarian lance and sword Encounter'd, fought, and foil'd: Returning with the just award Of Glory, thus inglorious by Thine own domestic Altar die, Fast in the spider meshes coil'd Of Treason most abhorr'd! Clytemnestra. And by what retribution more complete, Than, having in the meshes of deceit Enticed my child, and slain her like a fawn Upon the altar; to that altar drawn Himself, like an unconscious beast, full-fed With Conquest, and the garland on his head, Is slain? and now, gone down among the Ghost, Of taken Troy indeed may make the most, But not one unrequited murder boast. Chorus. Oh Agamemnon, dead, dead, dead, dead, dead! What hand, what pious hand shall wash the wound Through which the sacred spirit ebb'd and fled! With reverend care compose, and to the ground Commit the mangled form of Majesty, And pour the due libation o'er the mound! Clytemnestra. This hand, that struck the guilty life away, The guiltless carcase in the dust shall lay With due solemnities: and if with no Mock tears, or howling counterfeit of woe, On this side earth; perhaps the innocent thing, Whom with paternal love he sent before, Meeting him by the melancholy shore, Her arms about him with a kiss shall fling, And lead him to his shadowy throne below. Chorus. Alas! alas! the fatal rent Which through the house of Atreus went, Gapes again; a purple rain Sweats the marble floor, and falls From the tottering roof and walls, The Dæmon heaving under; gone The master-prop they rested on: And the storm once more awake Of Nemesis; of Nemesis Whose fury who shall slake! Clytemnestra. Ev'n I; who by this last grand victim hope The Pyramid of Vengeance so to cope, That—and methinks I hear him in the deep Beneath us growling tow'rd his rest—the stern Alastor to some other roof may turn, Leaving us here at last in peace to keep What of life's harvest yet remains to reap. Chorus. Thou to talk of reaping Peace Who sowest Murder! Woman, cease! And, despite that iron face— Iron as the bloody mace Thou bearest—boasting as if Vengeance Centred in that hand alone; Know that, Fury pledged to Fury, Vengeance owes himself the debts He makes, and while he serves thee, whets His knife upon another stone, Against thyself, and him with thee Colleaguing, as you boast to be, The tools of Fate. But Fate is Zeus; Zeus—who for a while permitting Sin to prosper in his name, Shall vindicate his own abuse; And having brought his secret thought To light, shall break and fling to shame The baser tools with which he wrought. Ægisthus: Clytemnestra: Chorus. All hail, thou daybreak of my just revenge! In which, as waking from injurious sleep, Methinks I recognize the Gods enthroned In the bright conclave of eternal Justice, Revindicate the wrongs of man to man! For see this man—so dear to me now dead— Caught in the very meshes of the snare By which his father Atreus netted mine. For that same Atreus surely, was it not? Who, wrought by false Suspicion to fix'd Hate, Or, Who, first suspecting falsely, and anon Detesting him his false Suspicion wrong'd, etc. From Argos out his younger brother drove, My sire—Thyestes—drove him like a wolf, Keeping his cubs—save one—to better purpose. For when at last the home-heartbroken man Crept humbly back again, craving no more Of his own country than to breathe its air In liberty, and of her fruits as much As not to starve withal—the savage King, With damnable alacrity of hate, And reconciliation of revenge, Bade him, all smiles, to supper—such a supper, Where the prime dainty was—my brother's flesh, So maim'd and clipt of human likelihood, That the unsuspecting Father, light of heart, And quick of appetite, at once fell to, And ate—ate—what, with savage irony As soon as eaten, told—the wretched man Disgorging with a shriek, down to the ground The table with its curst utensil dash'd, And, grinding into pieces with his heel, Cried, loud enough for Heav'n and Hell to hear, ‘Thus perish all the race of Pleisthenes!’ And now behold! the son of that same Atreus By me the son of that Thyestes slain Whom the kind brother, sparing from the cook, Had with his victim pack'd to banishment; Where Nemesis—(so sinners from some nook, Whence least they think assailable, assail'd)— Rear'd me from infancy till fully grown, To claim in full my father's bloody due. Ay, I it was—none other—far away Who spun the thread, which gathering day by day Mesh after mesh, inch upon inch, at last Reach'd him, and wound about him, as he lay, And in the supper of his smoking Troy Devour'd his own destruction—scarce condign Return for that his Father forced on mine. Chorus. Ægisthus, only things of baser breed Insult the fallen; fall'n too, as you boast, By one who plann'd but dared not do the deed. This is your hour of triumph. But take heed; The blood of Atreus is not all outrun With this slain King, but flowing in a son, Who saved by such an exile as your own For such a counter-retribution— Ægisthus. Oh, You then, the nether benchers of the realm, Dare open tongue on those who rule the helm? Take heed yourselves; for, old and dull of wit, And harden'd as your mouth against the bit, Be wise in time; kick not against the spurs; Remembering Princes are shrewd taskmasters. Chorus. Beware thyself, bewaring me; Remembering that, too sharply stirr'd, The spurrer need beware the spurr'd; As thou of me; whose single word Shall rouse the City—yea, the very Stones you walk upon, in thunder Gathering o'er your head, to bury Thee and thine Adultress under! Ægisthus. Raven, that with croaking jaws Unorphean, undivine, After you no City draws; And if any vengeance, mine Upon your wither'd shoulders— Chorus. Thine! Who daring not to strike the blow Thy worse than woman-craft design'd, To worse than woman— Ægisthus. Soldiers, ho! Clytemnestra. Softly, good Ægisthus, softly; let the sword that has so deep Drunk of righteous Retribution now within the scabbard sleep! And if Nemesis be sated with the blood already spilt, Even so let us, nor carry lawful Justice into Guilt. Sheathe your sword; dismiss your spears; and you, Old men, your howling cease, And, ere ill blood come to running, each unto his home in peace, Recognizing what is done for done indeed, as done it is, And husbanding your scanty breath to pray that nothing more amiss. Farewell. Meanwhile, you and I, Ægisthus, shall deliberate, When the storm is blowing under, how to settle House and State.</field>
   </doc>
</add>