<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Hayley, William, 1745-1820</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Hayley, William, 1745-1820</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">hayley william 1745 1820</field>
      <field name="author_text">Hayley, William, 1745-1820</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">18th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1780's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V2.0492.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1784</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460167</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Mausoleum ; a Comedy, of three acts, in rhyme</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Mausoleum ; a Comedy, of three acts, in rhyme</field>
      <field name="title_facet">mausoleum</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">mausoleum</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Mausoleum ; a Comedy, of three acts, in rhyme</field>
      <field name="year_display">1784</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1784</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1784</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460167&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460167&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Hayley, William, 1745-1820&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;hayley william 1745 1820&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Mausoleum ; a Comedy, of three acts, in rhyme&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;mausoleum&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1784&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1784&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Hayley, William&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1745&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1820&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Mausoleum&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;a Comedy, of three acts, in rhyme&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for T. Cadell [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1784&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872497-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv20492&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 18th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;18th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Mausoleum&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;a Comedy, of three acts, in rhyme&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 117 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;lb/&gt;Dedicatory poem and epigraph included with</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">The Happy Prescription&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: The mausoleum.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Comedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1784.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Unknown.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE MAUSOLEUM; A COMEDY, OF THREE ACTS, IN RHYME.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Persons of the Drama. CAREY. JASPER. RUMBLE. FACIL. TROPE. GERRARD, the Butler. LADY SOPHIA SENTIMENT, Widow of Sir Simon Sentiment, a wealthy Merchant. FRANCES, Sister to Jasper, and a Relation of the deceased Sir Simon. MRS. RUMBLE. Servants, &amp;c.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE, the magnificent Villa of Lady Sophia.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. SCENE I. Carey and Frances. Frances. Pray temper with patience your warm indignation, And treat with more mercy my tender relation: Because with your passions her whims interfere, To her foibles, dear Carey, you're grossly severe. Carey. My patience, sweet Frances, I own is exhausted: She will wed the first suitor by whom she's accosted, Though in widowhood's dainty vagaries, her pride Forbids her fair cousin to shine as a bride; And keeps us, my Love, from that altar away, Where Hymen with justice upbraids our delay. But, in noble contempt of your unsettled dower, Let us seize on the bliss that is plac'd in our power; And, if such artful vanities yield her relief, Leave my Lady to play off fresh fountains of grief, While we, my sweet girl! pass our happier youth In delights that are hallow'd by Nature and Truth: Though my income is small, with your prudent direction, Dear Fanny— Frances. I'm pleas'd with this proof of affection: Yet before we our union, dear Carey, complete, As your love is so ardent—let mine be discreet. No honest return of regard should I feel, Could I suffer your heart, in its generous zeal, To abandon a portion your bride should obtain, And hazard by hurry what patience will gain. 'Tis unlucky, my cousin, Sir Simon, forgot To specify what he design'd as my lot: But I know this omission, by which I am left, At her Ladyship's mercy, of fortune bereft, Was the work of Old Vellum, whose foresight and skill Were employ'd for himself, when he made the Knight's will. Yet her Ladyship says, that my cousin told her The sum that he meant upon me to confer; And though she delays, from a delicate whim, Lest our marriage should seem disrespectful to him— Carey. Good God! my dear Fanny, how can you defend her? To refinement and faith she's an empty pretender. Have not twelve months elaps'd from Sir Simon's interment? Yet her sorrow still bubbles in ludicrous ferment; Though the farce of her grief, as our friends have all said, Is address'd to the living much more than the dead; And her vanity means, though she prizes not pelf, To keep you unmarried, and marry herself. Frances. Indeed you mistake all her harmless intentions; She will certainly give me the fortune she mentions; I know her kind heart, and its pure inclination. Carey. Say rather, we know her absurd affectation: And as for your portion, my dear, I as soon Shall expect an estate to drop out of the moon, As to see you receive from my Lady a shilling; Allowing, indeed, that her heart may be willing, She soon will have nothing, I fear, to bestow, So profuse is she grown in her whimsical woe. On the new Mausoleum what sums does she waste! That fantastical fabric of barbarous taste; Where all decorations that art can devise, To adorn the proud tombs of the valiant and wise, Are mix'd o'er the bones of a simple old cit, Who display'd not a sparkle of valor or wit; Who though rich, pass'd, I think, with small comfort through life, A mere slave to the whims of his high-blooded wife. Frances. That preposterous vault I have view'd with concern! And have cried and have laugh'd o'er Sir Simon's rich urn: But at length, having study'd her Ladyship's trim, And loving her virtue in spite of her whim, I've a scheme, that, I think, with success will be crown'd, On this folly itself her correction to found; By indulging her foible, that foible to banish, And make all her mournful absurdity vanish. Carey. To your judgment, dear Fanny, I often submit, And much could I hope from your goodness and wit; Yet I think you can't make, in her youth's giddy season, Such a vain wanton widow a creature of reason. Frances. You judges of nature, and lords of creation, Howe'er you pretend to profound speculation, Are exceedingly apt your wise selves to deceive In the judgments you pass on the daughters of Eve; And most when you reckon, in every transaction, One indelicate foible their sole spring of action. My Lady Sophia you greatly mistake; By nature she's neither a prude nor a rake: At present, I own, she appears too demure; But though her heart's tender, her bosom is pure: To a strong understanding she makes no pretence, But has many mild virtues, and does not want sense: One foible alone has o'erclouded her mind, The foible of seeming supremely refin'd: But if I succeed, this slight fault she will mend, And you'll find her a worthy agreeable friend. Carey. You may say of her purity what you think fit, But her case one specific alone will admit. Believe me, whene'er a young widow's so prim, And by quaint affectation so cramp'd in each limb, A new husband alone, by his pliant embrace, Can restore her starch'd form to its natural grace: Is this, my fair Quack! the new nostrum you've got? Frances. Indeed you shan't hear any part of my plot, Till I know its success. Carey. Ah! my dear, I'm afraid This is some coy device my request to evade, And to keep the wish'd day of our wedding still distant. Frances. No; in truth, by the aid of a secret assistant, I've a plan of great moment in high agitation, Which may happily end all our various vexation: Allow me three days for its perfect digestion, And if in that time you will ask me no question, I promise thenceforth, without murmur or strife, To obey your commands for the rest of my life. Carey. I gladly subscribe to this bargain of bliss; So allow me to seal the kind bond with a kiss! Remember, three days; I can't add a day more, And shall fancy those three in duration threescore. Frances. O they'll pass very quick:—much amus'd you will be With the three rival Bards whom to-day we shall see; To whom my sad cousin oblig'd me to write For sepulchral inscriptions in praise of her Knight: They have sent each an epitaph hither before 'em, And are coming themselves with all solemn decorum. As each, without contest, expects here the laurel, On her Ladyship's judgment they'll probably quarrel: As you know the whole group, you must wait on the choir, To soothe the irascible sons of the Lyre. Carey. As to Facil and Trope, if they're hurt, I'll engage That one glance of your eyes will extinguish their rage: You will find them two chearful and good-humour'd lads; And, whether their Pegasus gallops or pads, It will please me, I own, if her Ladyship's fancies May tend to recruit their declining finances: But for splenetic Rumble, who, grandly absurd, Never speaks without using a six-footed word, I care not how much he is mortified here. Frances. But the length of his words hits her Ladyships' ear. Carey. His stiff phrases indeed may accord with her sorrow, Yet his spleen will insult her ere this time to-morrow; For often he'll call, with quaint arrogant vanity, Every head but his own the abode of inanity: Because a great author's defects he has caught, He vainly pretends to his vigor of thought; Though, on similar grounds, he as well might suppose, That, because some dark spots may be seen on his nose, His face has the lustre and force of the sun. Frances. In our chorus of Bards I am glad he is one, For I'm curious, I own, the strange elf to survey; Though I'm rather afraid of his wife, who, they say, Reads all the rough verses her husband has penn'd, Till she stuns every ear she can tempt to attend. She's to come with her Poet. Carey. I fancy they're here, For I think I've the hum of his rhymes in my ear. Frances. No, no; 'tis her Ladyship, mightily smitten With the high-sounding epitaph Rumble has written. Enter Lady Sophia (reading). Lady Sophia. “This doleful domicile of dust contains “Sir Simon Sentiment's inert remains; “Though Death's cold stroke infrigidate his frame, “Commerce resounds his emporetic name.” Ah, my friends, here is verse truly grand and pathetic! How exceedingly fine is the word emporetic!— Why, Carey! you seem quite untouch'd by its beauty; Of friendship, I fear, you forget the last duty: You two giddy creatures, though both tender-hearted, Think more of yourselves than of my dear departed. Carey. As your Ladyship chuses to press me so hard, I confess, though his memory still I regard, That my thoughts from Sir Simon will frequently roam; And I hope, when you've deck'd his funereal dome, Your Ladyship's mind may, by Nature's direction, Assume a more lively and chearful complexion; That you'll mix once again— Lady Sophia. Never, Carey! no, never! No time from his grave my devotion shall sever; In my eye the fond tear of remembrance shall swim, And each sigh of my soul shall be sacred to him! Carey. Consider, dear Madam! that custom and reason Prescribe to our sorrows a natural season; You have mourn'd like a model of conjugal truth, Now attend to the claims of your beauty and youth; In the bloom of your graces— Lady Sophia. Hold, hold, you wild thing! In your fancy, I find, gross ideas will spring; 'Tis the fault of you men;—ere I chasten'd his mind, My Sir Simon himself to that failing inclin'd: But I taught him to change the loose laugh of futility, For the sweet melting tear of refin'd sensibility, Till through his mild frame such pure tenderness ran— To such delicate softness I brought the dear man— He would weep o'er the withering leaf of a rose, And smile at the thorn though it wounded his nose.— Ah, my gentle Sir Simon! Frances. Indeed, he was such, That your thoughts cannot dwell on his image too much. Lady Sophia. Your soothing, kind sympathy charms me, my dear: I now trust you will wait till the end of next year; Nor with Hymen's festivity, gross and indecent, Profane our chaste sorrow, so graceful and recent. Carey (aside to Frances). How can you so flatter her curst affectation? Between you I'm really half mad with vexation. Lady Sophia. As you, my good girl! with such feeling attend, When o'er the dear tomb of Sir Simon I bend, That your thoughts may not roam when our duty we pay To that most precious piece of inanimate clay, That you may not omit o'er his ashes to sigh, In considering what wedding-cloaths you must buy, I've determin'd, my dear, as I think it your due, To resign all my colour'd apparel to you; To wear it again I indeed am unable, And on earth while I linger my garb shall be sable. [Speaking to a Servant behind the scene.] Jenny, bring in the chest that I bid you prepare. Frances (aside to Carey). What d'ye think of this singular present? Carey. O rare! Her crisis is coming, without much delay; There might have been doubts had she fix'd upon grey: But a vow to wear black all the rest of her life Is a strong indication she'll soon be a wife. [Two Servants bring in a large Chest.] Lady Sophia (to Frances). I have told you, my dear, that, refin'd in my joy, The array of affection I ne'er could destroy: These are garments unsoil'd, that I beg you to take, Thus preserv'd for the conquest they help'd me to make. In the sweet days of courtship these garments I wore, Vain memorials of pleasure that now is no more! Of those dear days of triumph you'll now see the trophy, When Sir Simon first call'd me angelical Sophy:— The fond recollection subdues my soft breast! Frances. Dear Madam, forbear then to open the chest! Lady Sophia. No, no, my good girl; I will shew you the whole, And how colours express'd various shades in my soul; In soft variegation I vied with the dove, And reveal'd by my dress the gradations of love. Here is, first, a cold brown—in this gown I was nice, And repell'd my warm swain with the chillness of ice; But growing more soft, in this azure attire I allow'd him with hope to enliven desire; In this pale lilach lutestring he found me relent; And this rose-colour'd silk was the blush of consent. O I ne'er shall forget— Gerrard (entering). Would your Ladyship chuse To receive Mr. Rumble? Carey. The Bard and his Muse! Lady Sophia. No, not for the wealth that's below the chaste moon, Till I meet all the Bards in the sable saloon: By his sudden arrival I'm sadly confounded, And should faint if he saw me with colours surrounded! To Miss Jasper's apartment away with this chest;— Dear Frances, and Carey, pray wait on my guest, Till my poor shatter'd nerves are a little compos'd, And the fresh-bleeding wound of my bosom is clos'd. Stay, Gerrard.—If cards should be call'd for to-night, Place the new japann'd tables alone in my sight; For the pool of Quadrille set the black-bugle dish, And remember you bring us the ebony fish. [Exeunt Lady Sophia and Gerrard. Frances. What the deuce shall I do with the wife of the Poet? She may ruin my scheme, if she happen to know it: She may pry— Carey. Never fear it! I'll venture a wager That the rhymes of her husband will fully engage her: You have seen a proud Bantam crow over a pen, Where a small egg has dropt from his favorite hen, He crows, and he flutters, and struts round the yard: So engross'd by her joy is the wife of a Bard; And by similar bustle attention she begs, And crows o'er her partner's poetical eggs. But here come little Partlet and old Chanticleer. Enter Mr. and Mrs. Rumble. Carey. Mr. Rumble, I'm happy in seeing you here. Mrs. Rumble,—Miss Jasper;—you know, Ma'am, her brother— And you, Ladies, will soon be well known to each other. Mr. Rumble. Though we meet in the house of refin'd lamentation, In your presence, I feel, Sir, some exhilaration; Since I in this spot as a stranger appear, I rejoice in a friend who domesticates here. My Lady is lodg'd in a sumptuous mansion, And I'm pleas'd with her park's evanescent expansion; As my wife has a taste for the grand and stupendous, I am glad I complied with her wish to attend us. Miss Jasper. You have had, Ma'am, I hope, an agreeable ride; Our prospects are pleasant on every side, And our roads are soo good— Mrs. Rumble. That you'll wonder to learn We were stopt on our way by an odd overturn. Miss Jasper. Indeed! you surprize me. I hope that no harm Has ensued from the accident, save your alarm— But how could it happen? Mrs. Rumble. Sometimes, on the road, My dear Mr. Rumble composes an ode; For he says, in such motion his fancy shines most; And all true lyric poets, you know, travel post: But a chaise-boy, alas! is a sad ignoramus; And the poor honest booby, whose blunder o'ercame us, Mistook a Pindarical ejaculation For a horrible, vulgar, profane execration, And, turning to stare at my dear Mr. Rumble, Drove against a steep hillock, which gave us a tumble. Miss Jasper. A most cruel event! whence, I fear, we may lose The unfortunate fruit of the terrified Muse: 'Twas indeed most unlucky! Mrs. Rumble. Dear Ma'am, not at all: Such a genius is not to be crush'd by a fall; The accident brighten'd his fancy, and on it He gallantly gave me an amorous sonnet. As I know you love verse— Mr. Rumble. Mrs. Rumble, I vow This display of my trifles I cannot allow; You for ever mistake, to my endless vexation, Gay Levity's sparkle for Wit's cornscation. Mrs. Rumble. Ah, you dear, modest man! in a napkin you'd hide The talent my love must contemplate with pride; As Miss Jasper, I'm sure, is a lady of taste, She shall see some sweet things that I pack'd up in haste, A few satires and odes— [Takes out an enormous pocket-book stuffed with papers. Mr. Rumble. As you dread my displeasure, Put up that red volume! Mrs. Rumble. What, bury my treasure! Indeed I must read one sublime composition. Mr. Rumble. Mrs. Rumble! the part of a wife is submission— Silly woman! to whom for my sins I am yok'd, With pulveriz'd gravel you almost are choak'd; And, fatigu'd with vehicular dilaceration, You would murder my verses by rough recitation. Mrs. Rumble. No, indeed; do but hear me one stanza rehearse; 'Tis my favorite ode. Mr. Rumble. As you grow so perverse, To preserve my own temper from exacerbation, I must thus stop your organs of vociferation. [Lays his hand on her lips. Mrs. Rumble. Well, my dear, I defer it to some fitter time, And I kiss the sweet hand that has written such rhyme. Miss Jasper. Your connubial obedience, dear Ma'am, I admire; But I'm sure your fatigues some refreshment require— Give me leave to attend you. Mrs. Rumble. It gives me concern To trouble you, Ma'am; but I hope to return Your obliging attention, so kind and polite, By a peep at a satire which ne'er saw the light. [Exit Miss Jasper with Mrs. Rumble. Carey. Mr. Rumble, you're blest in an excellent wife, That superlative prize in the lott'ry of life; The vow of the altar she rises above, And adds admiration to duty and love. Mr. Rumble. My wife has, I think, the right feminine nerve: Her sex was created to wonder and serve; As their minds have from nature no ponderous powers, They have nothing to do but to venerate ours. Carey. O fie! can you estimate woman so low? To our fair female authors pray think what we owe. Mr. Rumble. I cannot read one, Sir, without oscitation: They don't understand antithetic vibration; Their ideas have nothing of height and profundity, Their conceptions want vigor, their periods rotundity; Their truth is too stale, or too feeble their fiction, And I cannot endure their anomalous diction: But enough of these garrulous wasters of ink— Her Ladyship likes my inscription, I think; That lugubrious poem no critic shall garble, And, I trust, you can shew it me graven on marble. Carey. It would please me to give you that pleasure, dear Sir; But, in truth, on this point there's a little demur, Her Ladyship means to consult on the case. Mr. Rumble. What, Sir! is my poem expos'd to disgrace? Her critical quacks does this woman engage, To slash my sound verse with empirical rage? Carey. Believe me, good Sir, all the homage that's due To poetical genius she offers to you; But her Ladyship's love for Sir Simon is such, She thinks that he cannot be honour'd too much; And, to give all his virtues their due celebration, She from diverse poetical pens of our nation Has a cargo of epitaphs. Mr. Rumble. Hah! is it so! Are there rivals to shoot in Apollo's strong bow? This should have been told me before;—but no matter: My concurrents, perhaps, may more lavishly flatter, Yet in funeral song they can't equal my tone; Where Pope has miscarried, I triumph alone.— Pray who are these Bards that with me are to cope? Carey. I think you're acquainted with Facil and Trope. Mr. Rumble. What, Facil! whose verse is the thread of tenuity, That fellow distinguish'd by flippant fatuity, Who nonsense and rhyme can incessantly mingle, A poet—if poetry's only a jingle. Carey. Poor Facil wants force; yet may frequently please By a light airy mixture of mirth and of ease; But Trope's lofty muse has a higher pretension. Mr. Rumble. Sir! Trope is a rhymer devoid of invention, Who talks in a high strutting style of the stars, And the eagle of Jove, and the chariot of Mars; And pompously tells, in elaborate lines, That now the moon glistens, and now the sun shines. Carey. How severe, my good friend, are you Bards to each other! Yet if each would indulgently look on a brother, For your general honor— Mr. Rumble. I cannot agree That these fellows have aught homogeneous with me; To contend with such scribblers I deem a disgrace, And my dignity bids me abandon the place: With her Ladyship's judgment I mean not to quarrel, But shall leave her to crown any monkey with laurel. Carey. Mr. Rumble! in points so exceedingly nice I do not presume to obtrude my advice; But allow me to mention, before you depart, What may tend to encourage your liberal art. Sir Simon, you know, had a passion for fame, And left a large sum to eternize his name By some structure of note; yet he never said what: So a grand Mausoleum is rais'd on this spot, At so vast an expence that my Lady, I find, Has surpast what the Knight for the building design'd; The superfluous cost, be it great as it may, From her own private purse she designs to defray; Though an annual fund by the will is adjusted, With the guidance of which she is also entrusted; But from this, as I hear, she has form'd an intention To give the best epitaph-writer a pension. Mr. Rumble. Has she so!—'tis a gracious, effulgent design; I protest, of her judgment I highly opine. Her face has been chiefly the subject of praise; But a splendor of intellect now she displays. I cannot abruptly depart from a scene Whose mistress discovers the mind of a queen, Nor rudely desert, though my time is precarious, A lady whose graces are so multifarious: But pray, lest some puppy should here circumvent me, To her Ladyship can't you directly present me? Though I fear, since my fall, I am hardly so clean as A Bard should be seen by a female Mæcenas. Carey. Never fear!—in your coat there is not so much dust As to blind the bright eye that to merit is just. If you'll step in this room, which is call'd the Apollo, And wait a few minutes, I'll speedily-follow, And acquaint you how soon we may hope for admission;— My Lady loves form, in her present condition: To amuse yourself there you'll, however, be able, For you'll find all the epitaphs rang'd on the table. Mr. Rumble. Are they so!—it is well!—I indeed love to slash An inane poetaster's incongruous trash. [Exit. Carey. There I'll venture to leave the old cynical Rumble, The prey he has seiz'd to growl over and mumble. If this Bard, whom my Lady regards as her darling, Has infus'd in his brothers his talent of snarling, I think she will find little room to admire The harmony form'd by her Lyrical Choir.— But lo! the kind Muse an example now sends, That two mortals at once may be poets and friends. Enter Facil and Trope. Carey. My dear lads of Parnassus! you're welcome together; I am glad you associate, like birds of a feather, That fools may not cry, “Every Bard hates a brother, “And Poets, like Pike, are the prey of each other.” How fare ye, my friends? have you prosper'd of late? I hope each has rais'd his Parnassian estate! In our last conversation I heard ye lament That your farms on the mountain produc'd a low rent. Facil. In truth 'tis a niggardly foil, at the best, As I and my brother can truly attest; But with hopes of a new golden æra, my friend, On your patroness here we are come to attend: To encourage the arts she has spirit and sense, And we're told, my dear Carey, her wealth is immense. Trope. In fortune and soul she's a queen, 'tis agreed, And of genius as fond as Christina the Swede; For the Public's dull taste she, we trust, will console us, And make our poor Helicon rich as Pactolus. Facil. Perhaps, my dear Carey, we owe to your care The favor of this truly liberal Fair: You are, doubtless, appriz'd that my Lady requires— Carey. I know she has paid due respect to your lyres; Yet, indeed, on that title no thanks can I claim; You're indebted alone to your common friend, Fame: Her Ladyship knows with what spirit you write, And has begg'd your two Muses to honor her Knight; And, I trust, to your mutual advantage and joy, She'll reward the rare talents she wish'd to employ. But be not too sanguine;—I know how you Bards Build the fabric of Hope like a castle of cards: Entre nous, our good Lady is odd in her taste, Tho' her mind is, no doubt, with munificence grac'd; Perhaps to one Bard she'll be lavishly kind, And appear to the other as utterly blind. Then let each be prepar'd. Facil. So we are, my good friend, And by mutual support shall each other defend: To tell you a secret, we both wrote in haste, And strangers alike to her Ladyship's taste; But agreed, as our purses are equally low, To divide what on either she deigns to bestow. Carey. The compact is friendly; I wish from my heart That all who pursue the poetical art Would learn, from you two, their mean rage to suppress, And not rave at the sight of a rival's success. Facil. There, indeed, they may copy from Trope and from me: From envy, thank Heaven! we are happily free; We rally each other as much as we please;— I laugh at his figures—he laughs at my ease; Yet with rancour we ne'er try each other to hit, But value Benevolence far above Wit. The art we still doat on has ruin'd us both; Yet to quit the deceiver we're equally loth: From Commerce and Law we were led to retire By the splendid illusions that wait on the Lyre; And though each has obtain'd a fair portion of praise, We have no golden fruit in our chaplet of bays; Still we look without spleen on our gains and our losses, Each endear'd to the other by similar crosses. Carey. In truth, my dear Bards, you're good-humour is rare; You're philosophers both, and a singular pair: With what excellent temper I've heard you rehearse A malicious burlesque of your innocent verse! Facil. O, with me 'tis a rule not to quarrel with those Who attack what I scribble in rhyme or in prose; To skirmish with you, how unjust should I be, If, perchance, of my verses you don't think with me; When, to tell you the truth, I'm so various an elf, I have twenty opinions about them myself! Carey. What an honest confession! Facil. 'Tis perfectly true; Yet my works, I must own, I too rarely review; And too quick in their birth are the brats of my brain: My Muse is no parent inur'd to long pain, Who dandles a rickety chit while it lives, And loves it the more for the trouble it gives; She with lively dispatch, like a provident mother, Soon as one child is born thinks of rearing another.— But enough of a jade that is merely ideal; Let us talk of a female, kind, lovely, and real; An inspirer of something much sweeter than verse, And, I hope, with a few thousand pounds in her purse: I allude, my good friend, to Miss Jasper, your flame; But, perhaps, she no longer is known by that name, And has wisely exchang'd it for Carey. Carey. Not so; The day of our wedding you'll certainly know, As I hope that your Muse will the altar attend With a rapturous ode on the bliss of your friend. Facil. I accept the gay office with infinite glee;— But at present, I hope, the fair Nymph we shall see: Trope and I were the intimate friends of her brother; What a genius was he!—I ne'er knew such another: At school we first saw him his talent display; I remember he modell'd our figures in clay. The trade of a sculptor we thought not his fate, But suppos'd he'd have half of Sir Simon's estate! Carey. So he would, had not Vellum's more provident care, When he made the Knight's will, nam'd himself as his heir. My Lady, indeed, has the rents for her life, But to Vellum yields half if again she's a wife; And if without issue her Ladyship dies, All this ample estate is old Latitat's prize. Facil. And what says poor Jasper, that spirited lad? Faith, I think such a will might have driven him mad! Though engag'd by his art, he, I'm sure, must be nettled; But in Russia, they say, he is happily settled. Carey. When a generous mind has embrac'd a fine art, With Fortune's vain gifts it can readily part; From the world's dirty cares it detaches itself, To contend for a prize far superior to pelf; And looks with contempt (I am sure that you feel it) Upon heart-hard'ning gold, and the villains who steal it. Such a mind, from his childhood, your friend has possest; And in Russia, I hear, he is busy and blest; For a patroness there, of imperial spirit, The munificent Catherine, honors his merit. Facil. I protest, in the different realms of the earth, There is no friend, like woman, to genius and worth! Trope. I wish you and I may a Catherine find. In the widow whose Knight in our verse is enshrin'd! Facil. You perhaps, my dear Carey, can tell us some news: Has her Ladyship told you her thoughts of our Muse? Carey. One thing, my good friends, I can tell you at present, But I fear you'll not think it exceedingly pleasant; Yet it's certainly fit you should instantly know it, And, indeed, emulation inspirits a poet: Nay, look not so grave!—'tis a rival—that's all, A candidate come at her Ladyship's call. Facil. A rival! who is it? Trope. A rival! pray who? Carey. One, I'll venture to say, fully known to you two, A Bard whose pretensions are not very humble. Facil. You surely don't mean the pedantical Rumble? Carey. Even so! that long-winded loud Stentor of song; And the ladies all think that his language is strong. Trope. 'Tis as strong and as knotty as Hercules' club, And as rough as the roll of the old Cynic's tub. Carey. Hush! hush!—in this chamber the Bear is inclos'd, Growling over the epitaphs you have compos'd. Facil. Is he so!—introduce us.—I long to partake In the courteous remarks that his candor will make. Carey. O, if such is your wish, to our guest I'll present you; But I fancy his comments will quickly content you. Facil. As for me, I defy him to give me vexation; And Trope will delight in some retaliation. End of ACT I.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. SCENE I. Miss Jasper and Gerrard. Miss Jasper. Pray watch for my brother, and bring him to me, And let no one, good Gerrard, my visitor see: On your faithful prudence I solely rely; We're undone if our guests should his person espy: From all but ourselves we must keep him unknown; And, if seen, he must pass for a friend of your own. I depend on your prudence. Gerrard. Dear Miss, never fear; To do him any good I would watch for a year: Heaven knows, I have pray'd for him early and late, Since the old lawyer robb'd him of this fine estate; And would give all I'm worth could I get him his due. Miss Jasper. Honest Gerrard! I know we've a good friend in you: But look out for my brother—he'll want your assistance. Gerrard. I think I shall know him at half a mile's distance. Miss Jasper. He'll be here ere you stir—prithee run to the gate. Gerrard. Dear Miss, you forget; I am past sixty-eight; But I'll make all the haste that I can, for your sake, And I'll pray for you both at each step that I take. [Exit. Miss Jasper. That's a worthy old creature, though rather too slow; He is trusty, and will not betray us, I know: But though he's secure, I still shudder to think How my hopes in a moment to nothing may sink. As the crisis comes on, in a hazardous scheme, With what infinite terrors the fancy will teem!— In my hopes of the match I was sanguine and hearty; But I now have my fears in regard to each party. Should my Gentleman turn out too squeamish and coy, How vain the kind art I have deign'd to employ! Should my Lady shew family-pride, at this season, I've depended in vain upon Nature and Reason. I have studied her well, and I clearly descry She's destin'd again to the conjugal tie: In spite of the whims false refinement has taught her, She is honest dame Nature's benevolent daughter: Though a truly good creature, in virtue so strong She would not for the world do a thing she thinks wrong, Yet of such yielding wax her soft bosom is form'd, It will melt in a moment, if properly warm'd; Provided her fancy, affectedly nice, Can delude her kind heart with some dainty device, Some delicate plea for becoming a wife To the youth, who conjures her to bless him for life. On this I have founded my whimsical plan, In hopes of producing this fortunate man: My brother, I know, has a passion for her; And she soon to all men would his person prefer. But in my rapid project he will not be steady, Unless I persuade him she loves him already; For men rarely know, though of knowledge they're vain, By a well-manag'd minute how much they may gain. And should he detect the kind art I employ, Farewell to my hopes of their conjugal joy!— I yesterday, thought that my plan could not fail; Now I think 'twill be marvellous should it prevail.— But away, cruel fears! hence, ye painful alarms! I behold my dear brother restor'd to my arms! Enter Jasper. Jasper. Heaven bless thee, dear girl!—you have got me once more, In spite of my vow not to visit this shore; And I joyfully fly, with affection's quick pace, To enfold thy kind heart in a brother's embrace: With that in my grasp, I true opulence feel, And my wealth in this casket no lawyer can steal. Miss Jasper. If love and esteem may be reckon'd as treasure, You indeed, my dear brother, are rich above measure! O how have I long'd all your feelings to learn! How ardently pray'd for your speedy return! How often accus'd your indignant delay! What a million of things had I ready to say! What questions to ask!—and yet now you are come, The confusion of joy has almost made me dumb! Jasper. My tender, good girl!—I perceive you retain All your lively sensations of pleasure and pain.— But these tears will relieve you—don't check them, my dear; 'Tis a tribute my heart is inclin'd to revere; All flattering language I prize them above, And hold them the truest expression of love: And indeed, when I think what distress and regret Have harrass'd your sensible mind since we met; When I think how, from sordid self-interest free, You forget your own wrongs in attention to me; I feel tears of gratitude ready to start, And confess my dear sister the pride of my heart! Miss Jasper. Yet, for life, you could talk of deserting this sister! Jasper. But you see, when she pleaded I could not resist her.— When I first was inform'd of old Vellum's vile fraud, In my rage I determin'd on living abroad: For Russia, you know, I departed from Rome; However, my dear, you may safely presume Such an absence from you I could never endure, Had you not brought me back by a different lure; And my friends of the Law with your wishes conspir'd, To make me return with the haste you desir'd, As they give me some hopes of soon changing our fate, And regaining from Vellum the pilfer'd estate.— But how fares my dear widow? whose partial affection Seems kindled by some friendly angel's direction, To redress half our wrongs, and defeat the old thief, Who impos'd on Sir Simon's too simple belief. A rascal! to feign a regard for my fame, And steal my estate, not to injure my name. I thought not my cousin so easy a fool; How the deuce could old Vellum so make him his tool For the Knight, on this plea, sign'd his will when in health, Not to spoil a great artist by giving me wealth.— But where's my kind widow?—I long to express— Miss Jasper. You must pardon a little demureness in dress, Nor expect her, though you to all men she prefers, To fly into your arms. Jasper. No; let me fly to her's. Miss Jasper. Not so fast, my dear brother; you surely forget By what vigilant enemies we are beset! Should Vellum, whose spies are now under this roof, And against whose vile art no affection is proof, Should he get the least hint of my Lady's attachment, He would rage like the wolf in that new-painted hatchment; Your mutual regard he would set at defiance, And move earth and hell to prevent your alliance. Jasper. Would he so?—By my faith, as the widow's so kind, I care not what mischiefs may lurk in his mind; Not a legion of imps, by a lawyer instructed, Shall mar the sweet business her heart has conducted.— But has she quite hid her connubial design? Has the rogue no surmise she will shortly be mine? Miss Jasper. No, not any. Jasper. Well manag'd, my dear fairy elf! Miss Jasper. To say truth, 'tis a secret not known to herself. Jasper. To herself!—am I dup'd then? Miss Jasper. Dear brother, be cool. Jasper. Have you sent for me home, but to make me a fool? Miss Jasper. No indeed! but to make you most happy for life, And give you a lovely and excellent wife; In so serious a point could you think that I jested?— Have you purchas'd the licence my letter requested? Jasper. Here it is—and our folly will finely expose, If the fair one escapes whom this chain should inclose. Miss Jasper. Implicitly trust to my care as your guide, And ere midnight, perhaps, you may clasp a kind bride. Jasper. You teaze me, dear girl! with much whimsical pain; But I beg that you'll clearly these riddles explain. I fear you have form'd some nonsensical plot: Has the Widow declar'd she will have me, or not? Miss Jasper. Dear brother! indulge me with patient attention, And our true situation I'll honestly mention: But, however my project may strike you at first, Into rage and despair do not hastily burst; To be bold in such points is, in truth, to be wise, And a widow's a fort to be won by surprize. Jasper. So she has not engag'd, then, to give me her hand? Miss Jasper. Have patience!—her state you shall soon understand. That she loves you, I know; and with innocent art I have cherish'd the passion still hid in her heart: For she fancies, good creature! that, safe from love's flashes, She's devoted for life to Sir Simon's cold ashes.— You know, she affects to be highly refin'd: And a project I've built on this cast of her mind, Which, if you'll obey me, I'll venture my life, Like a stroke of true magic, will make her your wife, And before any soul can suspect our intention. Jasper. Well, my girl! and pray what is your magic invention? Miss Jasper. You must know, she believes that you only return To oblige her, by gracing Sir Simon's rich urn: She thinks the Czarina, on this one condition, That you travel incog. gives you her kind permission; And her Ladyship's mind I have fill'd with these notions, As they form an excuse for concealing your motions: So she hopes from your hand, with the highest delight, To behold a fine statue of her noble Knight. Now, Sir Simon and you have been thought much alike; And, to make the resemblance more forcibly strike, I mean to array you, her heart to entrap, In his blue sattin night-gown and red velvet cap; The dress which, to humour his elegant Fair, The courteous old Cit was contented to wear. Jasper. And is this your fine plan! you impertinent jade? Dress me up as the Punch of a dull masquerade! Miss Jasper. Have patience!—my scheme must surprize you, no doubt, Yet I think you'll applaud, if you hear it throughout; And if you have spirit I know 'twill succeed. Jasper. To play the dead man—a fine project, indeed! Miss Jasper. Nay, but hear me!—your actions I will not controul. Jasper. Well, you've made me an idiot; so tell me the whole. Miss Jasper. No! I've taught you to make yourself all you desire, If you will but restrain this intemperate fire.— Come, attend to my plot:—You fond creatures shall meet In the new Mausoleum, that pensive retreat; On a pedestal there you your person must place, To shew how a statue the building may grace: To behold you so fixt I'll my Lady prepare: She'll be struck in surveying your figure and air; She with tender surprize will your features review, And fancy she sees her Sir Simon in you: Then spring from your pedestal, seize her sweet charms, And swear, as you fold her soft heart in your arms, You are like her Sir Simon in soul as in form, That your heart towards her is as tenderly warm; You may add—in a vision he bade you direct her To take you for life as her legal protector, And, to make her chaste love to his memory known, Chuse his living resemblance before one of stone.— There's a promising scheme for a widow's relief! Jasper. Set woman to woman, as thief to catch thief!— I confess in your plot there is spirit and soul; On her governing foible you've grounded the whole; And rapid success might attend on your plan, But for puppet-shew courtship I am not the man: I possess not the face that your stratagem needs, For so bold an attack on a widow in weeds; And I feel some reluctance, in truth, at my heart, To such an appearance of fraudulent art. Miss Jasper. Away, my dear brother, with scruples like these! Of the amorous heart doubt's a common disease, But one that my counsels may speedily cure: You both love each other—your meaning is pure— The gentle Sophia you'll tenderly treat, Her form is enchanting, her temper is sweet; And if your odd courtship appears like a jest, In your marriage, I'm sure, you'll be equally blest: Without it, indeed, our fair friend is undone, For old Vellum intends that the coxcomb his son, When he comes from his travels—But somebody's near; A sudden surprize in this quarter I fear, Let us haste to my room—I must school you above: And you'll act as I wish if you've one spark of love. If I find you have not—I shall honestly say, You must give up the part that I meant you to play. [Exeunt hastily. Enter Lady Sophia with Papers in her hand, attended by Carey. Lady Sophia. Unfold the great doors of the sable saloon. [The Scene opens, and discovers a large Apartment, with a black velvet Pavilion.] At the thoughts of this business I'm ready to swoon! But you, my good Carey, will lessen my pain, And aid my weak nerves the sad scene to sustain; As my Gentleman-usher you'll kindly attend, And bring the three Bards to an audience, my friend: I shall sit to receive them beneath my pavilion. To repay their sweet verse I could wish for a million; But I think that each Bard will be pleas'd with his lot: So bring them—Stay, Carey, one thing I've forgot; But now 'tis too late for my purpose, I fear; I meant to have order'd the horns to be here, With a little soft music these rites to begin, And to sound a dead march as the Poets walk in. Carey. Dear Madam, their verses will want no such aid; Let me haste to present them.—Fantastical jade! [Aside, as he goes out. Lady Sophia, (seating herself under the Pavilion, and looking over the Papers in her hand). From these epitaphs, thus, I may happily borrow The parts that most flatter my delicate sorrow; And while in one piece I harmoniously blend Four lines from each poem these authors have penn'd, I am pleas'd that on them no vexation can fall, That I shall not hurt one, and must gratify all.— But the Geniuses come. Enter Carey, introducing Rumble, Facil, and Trope, who advance with profound Bows towards the Pavilion. Lady Sophia. Ye kind friends to my grief! Who employ your fine parts in affliction's relief; My mournful distress by your talents ye calm, And my dear lost Sir Simon your verses embalm. As I ought, let me first Mr. Rumble address: What I owe to you, Sir, I can never express, Yet the force of your pen let my gratitude mention. Rumble (aside). I perceive she has sense—and I'm sure of the pension! Lady Sophia. In my choice I have done equal justice, I hope, To you, Mr. Facil—and you, Mr. Trope: From your various productions twelve verses I chuse, And I blend the rich sweets of each different Muse; Thus a wreath is completed to deck the dear shrine, And to honor Sir Simon three Poets combine. Here you'll see how I've manag'd this nice combination. [Distributing a Paper to each. Rumble. I protest I can't suffer this conglomeration Of marble and brick! this anomalous jumble! Carey (in a whisper to Rumble). Remember the pension, my good Mr. Rumble! Rumble. Sir! my admurmurations shall loudly be heard; I've a right to exclaim that my Lady's absur'd: In her cap she as well might conquassate together The down of green geese and an ostrich's feather. Facil. I think, Mr. Rumble, my Lady displays The most dexterous art in uniting our lays: Your elder Muse first, like the waggon of Night, Moves solemn and grand;—like the chariot of Light, Airy Trope then advances, with different pace;— And, like Twilight, between you I find my right place: Rumble. Remember, young man! while his splendor you brag on, That rich Ponderosity rides in a waggon.— But I will not descend to a vile contestation; Our minds were not fashion'd for reciprocation. My Lady I pardon, on this one condition, That she quickly proceeds to a decomposition: She may chuse of our epitaphs which she thinks fit; But a mixture so monstrous I will not admit. She as well with her scissars might hastily snip From different portraits the eye, nose, and lip, And think that her needle accomplish'd great matters, By compacting a face of the discrepant tatters. Lady Sophia. O mercy!—dear Sir, pray this business adjust, And do not disturb my Sir Simon's calm dust! If a squabble concerning his tomb you excite, I am sure his dear spirit will haunt us to-night: I feel in this terror new anguish arise, And a fresh flood of sorrow swells into my eyes! Carey (aside to Rumble). Mr. Rumble! I fear, if you do not submit, My Lady will have an hysterical fit. Rumble. Sir! in points that my credit and honor involve, A few drops of salt-water won't melt my resolve. Facil (aside to Carey.) I protest, though fantastic I own she appears, I can not bear the sight of such beauty in tears; And as I perceive she is really distrest, I'll at once put an end to the strife in her breast. [To Lady Sophia.] Dear Madam! that you on this point may not grieve, And your delicate mind from all doubt to relieve, Let me and my friend our pretensions resign, And leave one single Bard to embellish the shrine; We beg that alone Mr. Rumble may bear The honor he thinks that we ought not to share. Carey. No, no, my good friend; you're too modest, indeed! I've a plan for ye all, that I trust will succeed. Lady Sophia. What is it, good Carey? I wish to pursue Some happy expedient suggested by you. Carey. At Mecca, dear Ma'am, seven poems, we're told, O'er the Prophet's rich tomb were suspended in gold; Now, let three worthy Bards each an elegy write, And suspend all their works o'er the tomb of your Knight. Lady Sophia. O charming!—your thought is enchantingly fine!— Mr. Rumble! I hope you applaud his design? Rumble. From this proposition I will not revolt, Though my young rivals' pride it may serve to exalt; Of the honor you do them I will not be jealous; But I'll teach the vain youths to revere an Entellus. Lady Sophia. Well, I hope what has past will be kindly forgot, And that now you'll all deign to compose on the spot.— I commend, my good Carey, the Bards to your care, Entertain them, I beg, with the choicest of fare: And, as it grows late, you must leave me, my friend, In affliction's chaste rites my lone evening to spend.— Farewell, worthy Sirs;—you now leave me to sorrow, But I hope to attend you at dinner to-morrow. Carey. Come, my friends! now permit me to be your director.— Mr. Rumble, 'Rack Punch is your genuine nectar; As the night's coming on, I'll prepare a rich bowl, That shall give to you Poets fresh vigour of soul; For the Muse with new force, like the flying-fish, springs, When she stoops for the purpose of wetting her wings. [Exit Carey, with Rumble, Facil, and Trope. Lady Sophia alone. I am glad we have sooth'd Mr. Rumble's chagrin! Enter Miss Jasper. Lady Sophia. O, my dear, with the Poets I've had such a scene! They have shaken my nerves to that cruel degree, I shall quiver all night like a poor aspen-tree. Miss Jasper. My tidings new life in your heart will infuse; The young Sculptor's arriv'd! Lady Sophia. That, indeed, is sweet news! Then in effigy soon I shall clasp my dear Knight! Is the block too provided, and perfectly white? Of the true Parian marble, I trust, he will mold The statue my bosom so pants to behold. Miss Jasper. I assure you, the business engages his heart, And you'll see a fine work from his exquisite art. To my brother already the vault I have shewn; And of attitudes there he is thinking alone. As I mean to conceal his arrival at home, We went by the pass under ground to the dome. Lady Sophia. We will join him, dear Fanny, and go the same way. I long at the tomb my devotions to pay; To hear how your brother's fine fancy and skill With new decorations the structure may fill, And to see in what posture the statue may stand. Miss Jasper. Let us go—he'll be happy to kiss your fair hand. [Exeunt. [The Scene changes to the inside of a grand Mausoleum; on one side, a large oblong Tomb of white marble, on the other, some steps ascending from a subterraneous passage. Jasper appears in the Gown and Cap of Sir Simon.] Jasper. What a part has my sister induc'd me to play! I wish from the scene I could well slip away. I shall never succeed—surely love was ne'er made, Since the days of old Jove, in such odd masquerade! I scarce know myself, in this whimsical plight, But I fancy I look very like the old Knight: Yet if you, my sweet Widow, incline to my plan, This image will beat the original man.— Gad! I hope she won't fancy I'm really his ghost!— But I hear them below—I must leap to my post. [Jasper places himself in a striking attitude on the top of the marble Tomb, while Lady Sophia and Miss Jasper ascend the steps from the subterranean passage.] Lady Sophia (starting). O mercy!—what phantom amazes my sight! Has the grave to my love given back the dear Knight?— 'Tis himself I perceive—'tis no fanciful dream! O, I faint— [Falls on the arm of Miss Jasper. [Jasper flies to Lady Sophia in great agitation, and speaks at the same time to Miss Jasper.] See the end of your pitiful scheme!— As I live, her fond fears have suspended her breath! And I've frighten'd the delicate creature to death! Miss Jasper. Never fear, simple Charles! you will not lose your wife:— You understand marble much better than life! Lady Sophia (reviving). Where am I!—O, pray Sir, are you Mr. Jasper? Miss Jasper (whispering her brother). In your arms, you poor simpleton! hasten to clasp her!— If you stand so confounded, how can you succeed? I shall presently think you a statue indeed! Jasper (to Lady Sophia). How fare you, dear Lady?—'tis true that you see Your devoted affectionate Jasper in me: Of your beauty my heart has long felt the effect, In chaste admiration and tender respect: No licentious design with my passion could mingle; But the very first moment I heard you were single, All my foreign pursuits I resolv'd to disclaim; For your smiles are to me more attractive than fame. Though the wintry ocean was roaring between us, My love, with fond hope in the favor of Venus, Bade me cross the rough deep, and, disdaining controul, Fly with speed to the distant delight of my soul! Lady Sophia. How like my Sir Simon in person and air! The mild-turn of his lip, and his eye to a hair! Jasper. O think not the likeness lies only in feature! I've his soul, heart, and passions, my sweet, lovely creature! In me, then, O fancy you see him restor'd! And with fondness connubial be lov'd and ador'd! Instead of a senseless, cold image of stone, Make his living resemblance for ever your own! A soft statue of wax in your hand I will prove, You shall mold me to all the chaste fancies of love. Lady Sophia. I protest your idea is sweetly refin'd, To delight the pure warmth of a delicate mind! I could wish such a likeness to keep in my view, And for ever contemplate Sir Simon in you: But, though the mere offspring of tender sensation, Such a wish would be reckon'd a gross inclination; And I'm sure I should die at that horrid suggestion! Jasper (embracing her). Dear angel! no tongue shall thy purity question. Lady Sophia. O Charles! to my bosom you give such a flutter, All my reasons against you I want breath to utter. Jasper. By the eloquent glance of that dear melting eye, With my delicate purpose I know you'll comply. Miss Jasper. Hush! hush! I have heard some one step near the door; Pray be still, till the coast I can clearly explore. Lady Sophia. O my stars! should my people discover at home, That by night I converse with a man in this dome— Miss Jasper. Haste! away! under ground you must quickly retreat. Jasper (taking up Lady Sophia in his arms). Come, escape in my arms! Lady Sophia. Don't you feel my heart beat? Jasper. So does mine, lovely creature! my soul is on fire. Lady Sophia. But I never can yield to your sensual desire. [Exit Jasper, bearing off Lady Sophia down the subterranean staircase.] Carey, (speaking without the great door of the Mausoleum.) Miss Jasper! Miss Jasper! pray, are you within? Miss Jasper (opening the door). Is it you, Sir, who make so uncivil a din?— Pray what is the cause of this sudden intrusion? Have your Poets produc'd a new scene of confusion? Carey. Gerrard says you have lock'd up the key of the 'Rack, So to give the Bards punch be so kind to come back. Come, my dear.— Miss Jasper. The deuce take your poetical potion! You have spoil'd my poor Lady's nocturnal devotion.— How forgetful old Gerrard is suddenly grown! He has, surely, the key in some draw'r of his own. But you jest.—Get you gone!—I must hasten to her. Carey. But without a few kisses indeed I shan't stir. Miss Jasper. Pish!—nonsense!—make haste then—I've no time to spare. Carey. Can't you give me some minutes, my dear busy Fair? Miss Jasper. No, in truth, not a moment; my hurry is great— Meet me here in the morning precisely at eight, And perhaps I may make you some pleasing amends. Good-night! Carey. Let us part; though, like lovers and friends; I deserve this sweet kiss for my patience. Miss Jasper. Good-night! To-morrow, I hope, will bring wonders to light! [Exeunt different ways. End of ACT II.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. SCENE I. The Mausoleum. Enter Trope with Facil, laughing. Facil. In my life I ne'er knew an adventure so drole! Trope. But what is it, dear Facil, pray tell me the whole? Facil. So I will, when a little calm breath I can draw, In ceasing to laugh at the figure I saw. Trope. What figure? Facil. Why, Rumble: I now see him stand With his garments half-button'd, a scroll in his hand; And the poor frighted girl!— Trope. What the deuce do you mean? In an odd wanton frolic has Rumble been seen— To an Abigail's room did the old Bard repair? Facil. No, no, I'll relate to you all the affair.— You must know that our punch had so heated my brain, That to sleep half the night I endeavour'd in vain; But was just in a slumber, between three and four, When a half-array'd figure threw open my door: 'Twas a poor trembling damsel, who hastily said, “Rise! rise! or you'll surely be burnt in your bed!” And I heard Rumble's voice thrice repeat the word “Fire!” But as that dreadful word was soon follow'd by “Lyre,” I perceiv'd the good girl, I now held by the arm, Had mistaken his verse for a cry of alarm. Trope. Very good!—he has often these starts in the night. But how did you calm the poor girl in her fright? Facil. The wild little wench, like a poor frighted hare, Knew not which way to run, and did nothing but stare; When, holding the door of my chamber a-jar, We perceiv'd, by the aid of the bright morning-star, The old Bard, who of liquor had taken his fill, Sally forth from his quarters in odd dishabille; With punch and with poetry heated, he swaggers, And reels down the stairs, like a horse in the staggers, Repeating with emphasis, several times, The unfortunate word in his dangerous rhymes; And the girl, who now saw her mistake very clear, Laugh'd, in spite of her shame, at the source of her fear. Trope. And you, I suppose, when her terror was fled, Taught her bloom to revive by the warmth of your bed? Facil. No, indeed; had her panic been only affected, I perhaps had been foolish, as you have suspected; But her fear and her modesty both were so true That they won my regard, and she safely withdrew. Trope. But where's our friend Rumble? Facil. O, nobody knows. Trope. To some shady retreat he is gone to compose. Facil. On the house-top, perhaps, like a bird he may sit; He considers keen air as a friend to his wit. It would not surprize me this phœnix to see Oddly perch'd on a bough of an old lofty tree; For he thinks he writes best when he's nearest to heaven: But he'll soon want his breakfast—'tis much after seven. Trope. Hark! what is that noise, like the woodman's loud stroke? Facil. As I live, it is Rumble in yon shatter'd oak! Don't you see where he's sitting astride on the branch? He has crack'd that large limb by the weight of his paunch. Trope. I believe he's asleep!—shall we give him a call, Lest he chance in his slumber to get a bad fall? Facil. Never fear:—here is one to take care of his life, Here's the nurse of our Brobdignag baby, his wife. Enter Mrs. Rumble, hastily. Mrs. Rumble. Pray, Gentlemen, where is my dear Mr. Rumble?— I have news for you Poets, to make you all grumble!— But where is my husband?—I seek him in haste. Facil. Dear Ma'am! we're surpriz'd that, with singular taste, From the soft arms of Beauty he strangely has fled, To embrace the rough limbs of an oak in their stead!— On that bough you may see him. Mrs. Rumble. Ah! barbarous man! He will venture his life, let me say what I can. I am sure some mischance will his genius o'erwhelm, T'other day he fell down from the top of an elm.— Mr. Rumble! take care!—Mr. Rumble, my dear! Facil. In this case, my dear Madam, you've nothing to fear. Behold! 'tis an incident only for mirth, For the bough gently falling consigns him to earth. Mrs. Rumble. I rejoice he is landed! Enter Rumble, stretching himself and yawning. Mrs. Rumble. My dear Mr. Rumble! It is well you have met with so easy a tumble: I wish that your fancy was not so romantic; All the people will think you are perfectly frantic. Rumble. Peace, woman!—I care not for idle derision, I have had a superb elegiacal vision: Homer says, with great truth, “Onar ek dios esti.” Mrs. Rumble. On first waking, my dear, you are apt to be testy; But I'm glad if the Muse has been kind to your slumbers, And I hope we shall hear your mellifluous numbers. Rumble. In my dream I've compos'd, and with clear continuity, Such emollient verse for the grief of viduity, 'Twould have sooth'd the sad relict of old king Mausolus! Mrs. Rumble. In our passions the Nine may have charms to control us; But your Muse, I'm afraid, might as well have miscarried, For the lady you praise as a widow is married! Rumble. Peace, woman! you're crazy! Facil. How! married, dear Madam! Mrs. Rumble. Ay, married! as sure as we're children of Adam. You know, Sir, rich folks, with a licence, have power To marry without the canonical hour; And, leaving her guests o'er their punch to carouse, My Lady at midnight receiv'd a new spouse. Rumble. Mrs. Rumble, I fear 'tis our punch that has bred These nuptial phantasma's in your giddy head: Your story has nothing of concatenation. Mrs. Rumble. Mr. Rumble, you aways will doubt my narration! But I deal not in fiction, although a Bard's wife; On the truth of this secret I'd venture my life: From one of the house-maids I happen'd to worm it, And here comes a gentleman who will confirm it. Enter Carey. Mrs. Rumble. Your voice, Mr. Carey, will prove I am right; Pray was not her Ladyship married last night? Carey. Dear Madam! your question can hardly be serious. Mrs. Rumble. I am sure she was wed, though the wedding's mysterious. Carey. Do you really believe it?—dear Madam, to whom? It must be to one of these Bards, or a groom: For, excepting ourselves and the men of her train, Not a male did this mansion last night entertain: But whence your conjecture? on what is it grounded? Rumble. Silly woman! I tell you your brain is confounded; But I think we may guess, from your dream of this fact, How in widowhood you will be tempted to act; I suppose, when I've finish'd my scene of mortality, However you sorrow in shew and verbality, You soon will renounce all your dignified gravity; And, entic'd by some bellman's poetical suavity, Go to church with a fellow who deigns to rehearse A quatrain on your charms in his annual verse. Mrs. Rumble. O you barbarous man! by so cruel a jest Would you wound the chaste love of so tender a breast? You know me too well to believe what you say.— Thank my stars! here's an evidence coming this way; And you'll see truth and justice are both on my side. Enter Miss Jasper. Mrs. Rumble. (hastily). Miss Jasper! pray is not my Lady a Bride? Miss Jasper. You are right, my dear Madam. Carey. It cannot be real! Miss Jasper. From you Bards I request a sublime hymeneal. Trope. So suddenly married! Facil. You certainly joke. Miss Jasper. A word of more truth in my life I ne'er spoke. Carey. What d'ye mean, my dear Fanny? pray do not deceive us. Mrs. Rumble. What infidels, Madam! they will not believe us. Facil. Pray, to what happy man may so fair a prize fall? Miss Jasper. The Bridegroom I'll soon introduce to you all; And you Poets, I trust, will a new string employ, With singular pleasure to echo his joy. Rumble. So my fine elegiacs are now out of season;— I was mad, to think woman a creature of reason, And on widowhood's slippery virtues to raise The luminous fabric of rythmical praise! But I'll haste to be gone from this scene of fatuity: Come along, Mrs. Rumble; I've done with viduity.— My Lady may welcome more juvenile comers, I have no time to waste upon conjugal mummers. Miss Jasper. Mr. Rumble! pray stay, in our joy to partake. Mrs. Rumble. Stay, my dear Mr. Rumble! you'll stay for my sake. Though the grand and the gloomy is all your delight, I confess that festivity pleases my sight; Pray indulge me for once!—it would half break my heart Without seeing the Bridegroom were we to depart. Rumble. Curiosity ruin'd your grandmother Eve; And to gratify yours you shall not have my leave: From a farcical scene it is time we should go, And who plays the Jack Pudding I want not to know. Mrs. Rumble. My Lady may still wish your verse to peruse! Rumble. For Politics henceforth I give up the Muse; Though political paths may have some tortuosity, To enter on them I have less scrupulosity, Than to feed your vain sex with poetical flummery, And at last be the dupe of their amorous mummery. But I'll have my revenge, and, before my spleen cools, I will prove all the sex-flattering poets are fools.— Come away, Mrs. Rumble!—your duty's submission. [Exit, bearing off Mrs. Rumble. Miss Jasper. Poor woman! I pity her dismal condition, And am griev'd that so roughly he makes her return:— But here's one to console us for every concern. Enter Jasper. Miss Jasper. To you, my good friends, I the Bridegroom present, And you all will rejoice in this happy event. Carey. Dear Jasper! o'erwhelm'd by this joyous surprize, I am almost afraid to believe my own eyes! Are you really return'd? and, in truth, are you married? Has this excellent plan been so suddenly carried? Or, with potent illusion and artful pretences, Has this fair little sorceress cheated our senses? Jasper. You may trust in her magic, as honest and true; She has render'd me happy, and so she will you: To you, my dear Carey, I give her for life; So enchanting a sister must prove a sweet wife; And, with pleasure I add, you'll receive your fair Bride With the fortune she merits completely supplied. Carey. Her heart in itself is an opulent dower! Jasper (to Facil and Trope.) My worthy old friends! in this fortunate hour It increases my joy to meet you on this spot. Facil. I rejoice in your bliss! Trope. I am charm'd with your lot! Jasper. And with double delight the good fortune I view, Which may prove I retain a warm friendship for you: I've a scheme for ye both, my dear Facil and Trope, That will meet with your hearty concurrence, I hope. You must yield to my wish—I will not be denied From any vain scruples of generous pride. Facil. With hearts so enliven'd by seeing you blest, We shall hardly refuse whatsoe'er you request. Jasper. Though a few dainty whims, of a singular kind, Have o'erclouded the worth of her excellent mind, The soul of my Lady Sophia is fraught With the true mental treasures of generous thought. She perceives, and disclaims for the rest of her days, The foibles to which false refinement betrays: She now thinks this proud fabric of ill-applied art The ridiculous whim of too feeling a heart. Sir Simon had many calm virtues, whose claim From ungrateful Oblivion shall rescue his name: But all the distinctions of rank are confus'd, Fame herself is insulted, and Art is abus'd, When the plume and the laurel insultingly wave O'er the honest plain Merchant's preposterous grave: Convinc'd of this truth, 'tis my Lady's design To alter this dome on a new plan of mine. Here with Freedom and Ease you, my friends, may reside; Good apartments for each I shall quickly provide: For this dome, where the Founder shall rise in a nich, Is to prove an asylum for artists not rich. Carey. I am charm'd with your project, dear Jasper! Jasper. Yet hear:— By the will there's a fund of four hundred a year Of real hard cash, from incumbrances free, Which my Lady herself is to guide as trustee, To support any structure she chuses to plan, To perpetuate the name of her worthy good man; This between you, dear Bards, she is pleas'd to adjust: And when opulent Honesty sinks in the dust, May his heirs ever use what he leaves upon earth In securing calm comfort to Genius and Worth! Facil. We always have said, and your actions evince, You, Jasper, were born with the soul of a prince; But our gratitude how shall we utter to you? Jasper. By returning your thanks where they chiefly are due. My Lady's pure bounty, that scorns to be stinted, Surpast in your favour whatever I hinted:— To prove that I wed not from motives of pelf, I have settled her wealth on her generous self; She is rich, and intends to make use of her treasure In the purchase of noble and permanent pleasure: At the highest of interest our gold we employ, When it brings a return of benevolent joy.— Thank my stars! all my wishes are crown'd with success; Kind Fortune, I just now have learn'd by express, Outruns, in our favor, the slow step of Law: Old Vellum, alarm'd by our hints of a flaw In the base legal work that Fraud led him to frame, The reversion he stole has propos'd to disclaim, Upon terms which I now, for tranquillity's sake, At my Lady's request, shall be willing to take.— But come, my good friends, let us haste to the hall, Where the Bride will be happy to welcome you all. Carey. Well, my friend! I confess, in the course of my life, I have oft been provok'd with your new lovely wife; But for this her last act her late whims I forgive, And shall bless the kind creature as long as I live.— You will teach, as you mold her to life's sweetest duty, All her virtues to shine as complete as her beauty: And may each childless widow, in youth's lively state, Who has yielded an honest old husband to fate, In a partner like you find the surest relief, And to sensible joy turn fantastical grief! FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>