<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Serle, Thomas James, 1798-1889</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Serle, Thomas James, 1798-1889</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">serle thomas james 1798 1889</field>
      <field name="author_text">Serle, Thomas James, 1798-1889</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1810's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V3.0231.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1819</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460635</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Raffaelle Cimaro ; A Tragedy, In Five Acts</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Raffaelle Cimaro ; A Tragedy, In Five Acts</field>
      <field name="title_facet">raffaelle cimaro</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">raffaelle cimaro</field>
      <field name="title_text">Raffaelle Cimaro ; A Tragedy, In Five Acts</field>
      <field name="year_display">1819</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1819</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1819</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460635&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460635&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Serle, Thomas James, 1798-1889&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;serle thomas james 1798 1889&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Raffaelle Cimaro ; A Tragedy, In Five Acts&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;raffaelle cimaro&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1819&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1819&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Serle, Thomas James&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1798&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1889&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Raffaelle Cimaro&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy, In Five Acts&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Published by John Chappell [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1819&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872816-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv30231&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Raffaelle Cimaro&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy, In Five Acts&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 119 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Raffaelle Cimaro.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1819.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Unknown.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">RAFFAELLE CIMARO, A TRAGEDY, IN FIVE ACTS,</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PROLOGUE. (Enter the Genius of Prologue, habited in a black gown.) Once more, to greet a British Theatre, Do I, the genius of old prologue, come, From you to ask a boon due to my age, And those delights which, in a better time, I gave your forefathers: to you I come To beg your patient hearing of my cause. While Marlow painted, with a sweeping hand, The wond'rous workings of tumultuous minds, I held a plain, but just and useful, office, To shew the moral ere the play began, That men might catch instruction with delight, And view, indeed, a mirror of their minds. Shakspeare, whose soul of alchemy could turn The dullest dregs of nature into fire, Gave me a swelling and more lofty strain, And bade me, ere his martial king appeared, Announce his entry with high sounding words That breath'd the trumpet's voice in every line, And great imaginations that conveyed The soul back to the very field of war; And to his mast'ry who would not obey, And minister to his unearthly greatness? Jonson, severely conscious of his worth, Made me the organ of his bold appeal To reason and to learning, and by me Taught men to judge him by his own just rule; And sometimes, lifted past his usual nature, Condemn'd and brav'd the follies of the time. Then came a troop with Dryden at their head; He scarcely owning them, but they delighted With his example, that 'gan swell me up With high and bombast sentences, and mirth Began to steal upon my sober face. Meanwhile my sister Epilogue, debauch'd With low and ribald jests, no more address'd The town with Rosalind's mirthful innocence: Nor could the example of Pope's critic pen, Nor Johnson's just and noble sentiment, Redeem me from unworthy gaieties; From this the better morals of the age, Perchance its dulness, now have rescued me: But still the trembling sycophant by me Brays out in fears his unpoetic baseness, Or buys your suffrage with a very list Of weak excuses, which he hopes are needless. To you I come to save me from this fate, I was ordain'd for great men's greatest purpose; In me you should behold the power of truth Pointing with magic finger to the Scene, And tracing in't the heartfelt application, Making the guilty turn with paly cheek, As they consider of my fearful words, Shewing to man with nice discrimination The causes that provoke a tragic end; Speaking a noble, just, and moral truth, And then enforcing it by great example. To night we offer to your good attention, The picture of a selfish sensualist, One trick'd with many meretricious virtues— False courage, generosity and coolness, And able to do much—yet doing nought, Save for himself—a man of worldly wisdom— Mark him, and ponder deeply on the scene, And turn the mind from listless apathy To fit amusement for a human soul: This reward claims our author—I have done, And to your favor leave our bold attempt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DRAMATIS PERSONÆ. Duke of Mantua, Raffaelle Cimaro, Mantuan Nobleman. Claudio, Mantuan Nobleman. Alphonso, Mantuan Nobleman. Lodovico, Mantuan Nobleman. Manlio, Mantuan Nobleman. Lorenzo, Mantuan Nobleman. Venilla, Mantuan Nobleman. Julio. Servant to Raffaelle. Lawyer, Monk, and Peasant. Louisa de Commenes. Maria, her Servant. Senators, Gentlemen, Ladies, Attendants, &amp;c.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE, MANTUA.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. SCENE I. A STREET IN MANTUA. Enter Claudio and Lawyer. Claudio. And when, sir, will the duke decide this suit? Lawyer. 'Tis thought within two days. Claudio. I trust 'twill be so! To linger in incertitude's the sum Of human ills; the wreck'd and toil-spent shipman, Who meets a fix'd, inevitable fate, Feels less of agony, than he whose fortune Casts him upon a drear and desart rock, To watch, with credulous eye, th' horizon round, And form each vap'ry speck into a succour, And, sickening with hope, to die anew With every fading object of his fancy. I'd rather perish by the assassin's sword, Than live the gen'ral theme of sland'rous tongues, The mark for ev'ry dull plebeian's pity, The accus'd of murder. Lawyer. This will clear your fame, And free your honor from all stain. Claudio. Oh no! Honour, once wounded, never can be heal'd; It is all over vital, and the wound That stabs it—kills, 'tis tender as the down That paints the gay and sportive butterfly, Touch it—the bright and golden covering flies, And leaves an earth-born worm; As weak as is the timorous sensitive plant Than shrivels at the approach—and more inconstant Than weightless atoms trembling in the sunbeam Lawyer. 'Tis too fantastic for a lawyer's thought. 'Twas well, sir, that Lorenzo saw the affray, Your case were else more doubtful, as it is You've little cause for fear—two friends I think. Claudio. Aye, sir, they were so: if they be so now, Fortune perhaps has not deserted me: Men's minds are oft the index of our fates, And as our friendships slacken we may read Our downfall. Nay, stay with me; you'll much favour me, To cheer me with your company and counsel. Enter Lodovico and Alphonso. Lodovico. Good morrow, sir. Claudio. I thank you for the bidding, I've need of more good morrows. Lodovico. Nay, your cause As I have heard is clearly on your side, Your present liberty proves this, methinks. Alphonso. Aye, doubtless; trust me all things will be well. Hear you of Raffaelle, the new Count Cimaro, The proud and noble heir of dead Antonio? Claudio. Yes, sir, I know him well, he's truly noble. Lodovico. We're going to his palace straight; to night He doth eclipse his own magnificence, Which ne'er was yet equall'd in Mantua; His peerless spirit spurns all bounds of custom; His ample fortune ranges like his will; A thought with him's a deed. Claudio. 'Tis a brave gentleman. (To the Lawyer) Lorenzo did not speak with certainty. Lawyer. Most clearly, sir, and plainly. Alphonso. You'll be with us To night at Count Cimaro's. Claudio. No, sir, truly My thoughts are now my fitt'st companions; They leave me little time for gaiety. Alphonso. I would that I could tempt you to the Count's, All there are nobly welcome—he has a spirit, Like Antony, to banquet hosts of kings: Lodovico. But, since you will not, we must hasten thither,— I'm grieved at your anxieties. Alphonso. And I; But we must hasten to the festival. Claudio. I thank you, Your kind concern much moves me, my dear friends, But let me not detain you from your mirth: Farewell. Both. Farewell. (Exeunt Lod. and Alph.) Claudio. Such are the herd of men; 'tis not ourselves That are the objects of their vulgar friendship, The very outside dress gains more affection From them. The bubble fortune is their idol. But come, sir, for I fear I weary you: In grief we're scorpion-like, and writhing, turn Our venom 'gainst ourselves— I'll strive to be more cheerful, and to wean My thoughts from melancholy—will you please Come tow'rd my house. Lawyer. I wait upon you, sir. (Exeunt.) SCENE II. THE GARDEN OF CIMARO'S PALACE BY MOONLIGHT. A retired walk with a Grotto, in the distance illuminated temples, and every appearance of festivity—music without. Enter Louisa and Maria. Louisa. This is a scene more suited to my soul Than the dull glare of yon gay festival: Aye—it is true that music has a soul, And needs responsive feeling to be sweet. To me the melancholy mournful bird, That pours her pensive plaint in this recess, Is more harmonious in her soft lament Than the full chorus in yon glittering hall. It was not well to seek for Claudio here; With him, alas, mirth dwells not—'twas a fault To think he could be here. Maria. Nay, my dear lady, I wonder he should fail to seek you. Louisa. Oh! in his nature dwells so deep a sense Of truth and honour, he would scorn to seek My love—were't possible to think him guilty, And were he so,—I fear I yet should love him: He cannot doubt, should all the world condemn him, His name would live fair as this holy light In my affection. Maria. And yet you have never Assured him of it. Louisa. Oh! a thousand times By praising, loving, all he prais'd and lov'd— By timorous glances, check'd with many a blush, By the sigh half suppress'd, the fault'ring tongue, The mute embarassed silence;—are not these— Not love's assurances—but love itself? Enter Raffaelle habited as a Magician and masked. Raffaelle. I have amaz'd yon idle thoughtless crowd: Another sight like this would buy their voices, To make me duke—if they dar'd think so bravely. I do despise them, though I court their smile; And yet 'tis well, my state requires their homage, The homage that the fool or needy knave Pays to the man who knows to use his wealth,— Ha! who is this? she whom I mark'd just now, Whose simple graces even fools appeared To gaze on longer than on jewell'd dames, And that's a wonder: she is somewhat sad; I'll try a masking humour to revive her. (To her) I have been weaving spells in yonder halls, Calling thin sprites from forth the glassy deep, Decking with instant flow'rs the barren ground, And filling all the air with sweets ambrosial, So potent and so perfect was my art; But here a milder and more holy spell Controls my powers and bids me kneel your subject. Louisa. I have no spell save what my fancy gives To this inspired scene, and that's too pure For fulsome adulation or the homage Of one—the lord of yon festivity. Raffaelle. O'er me a woman and a beauteous one Possesses all the pow'r of strongest spells In one soft charm, the potency of love. Louisa. A charm indeed, like others but ideal. Raffaelle. My friends will scarce believe this doctrine now; But why prefer this sad and lonely shade To mirth and joy and social gaiety? Those beauties sure were formed for other gaze Than purblind night, or the unconscious moon; And to those ears the gentle tale of love Should sound more grateful than the owl's dull hoot; And that warm heart should beat with quicker pulse, More vivid soul should dart from those bright eyes Than scenes of weary solitude inspire. Louisa. Alas! sir, I can scarcely answer you In strains so courtly—I can gain no pleasure From a fool's smile,—nor can the tale of love, That's but a tale, spoken, but never felt, Give me delight—nor joys of courtly life, That tedious labour after sweets ne'er found, Repay me for the loss of gentler thoughts. Raffaelle. Tis well indeed, my sylvan deity, And lest your wit should change my nature too, And wrap me here in rural contemplation, Let me conduct you to my magic kingdom, And entertain you in my proud domain, With pomp that may outshine simplicity, Not in your thoughts,—nor e'en perchance in mine, But far indeed in theirs who wait my presence, To pamper to satiety their love Of wond'rous novelty—will't please you walk? (Exeunt.)</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. SCENE I. —AN APARTMENT IN CIMARO's PALACE. Enter Raffaelle and Servants. Raffaelle. Who waits this morning? Servant. Signior Lodovico Attends you, sir, and other gentlemen Are in the hall. Raffaelle. I'll see them; (Exit Servant.) They are industrious; my last night's feast Would weary stronger natures:—I am sick Of this dull round:—that fair one whom I saw Would give new zest unto my luxuries, Quicken the lazy current of my blood, And rouse my soul to energetic action. I cannot live in apathy, and crawl Unheeded and unknown; this vaulting spirit Fate never form'd to animate a worm. Enter Lodovico and Gentlemen. Good morrow, friends. Lodovico. We rise to greet you, sir, And pay the tribute of our wond'ring homage To the artificer of last night's glories. Raffaelle. Nay, my dear friend,— 1 Gent. No ducal pageant more Shall ever hold regard in Mantua. Raffaelle. You're pleasant, sir. 2 Gent. 'Tis far short of the truth: Nature was shamed with art's magnificence. Raffaelle. Nay, pray you— Lodovico. And the lady de Commenes Grac'd well the hand of Mantua's prime lord. Raffaelle. The lady de Commenes—I knew her not— Lodovico. The beauteous lady honor'd by your favour: Raffaelle. This is worth hearing;—she has beauty truly. 1 Gent. Mantua waits but your award to say so. Raffaelle. Her wealth and influence are great in Mantua. Lodovico. Next to my lord's. Raffaelle. Her wit is well enough. Lodovico. 'Tis counted rare. Raffaelle. And I suppose—to end This list of her perfections—she has suitors, A regiment or so. Lodovico. They are not few, sir, Alphonso—and the noble Claudio— He indeed is most favoured. Raffaelle. Claudio! My friend whose life's in danger; is't not he? Lodovico. The same, my lord. Raffaelle, He's worthy of her hand; And when the world gives out too that she loves him, Perchance, tho' she ne'er thought of it before, It may be that she'll marry him;—how think you? Lodovico. To-day, I guess, my lord—will prove the truth. Raffaelle. To-day? Lodovico. His cause to day the duke will judge; At noon the court will meet. Raffaelle. I will attend it: Faith I should feel an interest in their union; 'Tis very soon, yet 'twill be time enough. (Aside.) How stands he, think you? Lodovico. By the evidence Of lord Lorenzo he will sure be cleared. Raffaelle. (Aside) Not if a dagger's found in Mantua: Waits Julio there? Servant. He does, my lord. Raffaelle. 'Tis well; Perchance I may have need of him directly On urgent business. Then Lorenzo saw Vincentio attack him? Lodovico. So he says, sir, Raffaelle. I'm glad his life rests on so sure a cause; I would I were his judge; and yet I doubt not The duke will deal as nobly by him as I should: I would do much to serve him in his suit, Knew I the means—there was no other witness, Save this Lorenzo? Lodovico. None, my lord. Raffaelle. Nor needs there; I think that is his villa near the road, Where this encounter happened. Lodovico. Aye, my lord,— Raffaelle. It is a sweet retreat, and were it mine I should prefer it to the city—he, I think, is seldom from it? Lodovico. Very rarely; To-day he comes here to attend the trial. Raffaelle. 'Tis fortunate indeed, he is the witness: My friends, now I bethink me I have need Of a few minutes leisure, you will walk Into my gardens; last night's sports are gone; But there is yet some poor amusement for you: Open the doors there. (Folding doors are opened in the back ground and discover a natural and beautiful garden with rural seats, &amp;c.) Lodovico. The pageant's gone: 1 Gent. 'Tis wonder upon wonder! Raffaelle. Nay, nay, a trifle: I'd not have the ruin Of a fool's sport remain to mock my poverty When 'tis gone by a year; nay, pray you walk, I conjure not by day-light. (They go out very obsequiously, and with much wonder on their countenances.) Louisa de Commenes! the vaunt of Mantua! The pride of Italy! she's not for Claudio— Lorenzo shall not save him,—Julio! Enter Julio. Her wealth, her influence, 'bove all her beauty, Should grace no less than Raffaelle Cimaro— Curs are no mates for lions: Claudio! Beware my greater nature! little men Are but the cyphers that make up my sum Of power and greatness. Julio! Julio. My lord: Raffaelle. A beggar feed upon such royal cates! Julio, ere noon I must have one dispatch'd; Lorenzo—on his evidence depends The safety of my dear friend Claudio; And I would find some fearless evidence To swear that Claudio attacked Vincentio, And speak of other matters, which kind fortune Has giv'n me knowledge of. I saw Vincentio At lord Alphonso's on the very day, Where he conceal'd himself, and from that somewhat.— The needy monk I yesterday relieved Seek and bring to me. Hold! I must begone To the lady de Commenes—within a half-hour Call with him at her palace; but beware She sees him not. Here's money for the hand That takes Lorenzo's life—about it straight. Stay—if thou find'st another that may serve To fix his death on Claudio—bring him to me— Lorenzo will be passing from his palace— (Exit Julio.) She must be mine; with her I should outstep The ducal pomp; I'd pass on pleasure's wing The wildest flights of fancy; to my will All nature should be chain'd: methinks already I swell with the intoxicating thought. Come, for the means.—Oh! this indeed is power In its full use—to pile, and pile,—and heap, Till the proud temple, rising to the clouds, Leaves e'en the artificer in joyous wonder. I see—I see—ha! ha! when I have doted Awhile in waking dreams on the idea I'll rise and form it to reality. (Exit.) SCENE II. —AN APARTMENT IN THE PALACE DE COMMENES. Enter Louisa and Maria. Louisa. 'Tis near the time, Maria. Maria. It is, lady, Louisa. Oh this suspence! this tedious chasm of being, That so destroys our present faculties, And wraps them in the future.— This feast of yesternight was brighter far Than aught within my memory. Maria. Aye, madam, So noble and so brave a company, The music and the glorious temple.— Louisa. Peace! I think there is no doubt of Claudio's safety; Why dost not answer me? there can be none. Maria. I hope not, madam, nay, I'm sure there is none. Louisa. That's a kind word. Even flattery sometimes Is dear to us, although we know it is so, And yet, I trust, in this 'tis but the truth. Enter a Servant. Servant. Madam, the count Cimaro. Louisa. I am sick, I'll not be spoken with; yet stay, I know not, His countenance were great to save my Claudio, I wait his pleasure. (Ex. Servant) He should be right noble, And fond of such a spirit as my Claudio. Enter Raffaelle. Raffaelle. A fair good morrow to you, gentle lady; Your beauties do not fly the sun's quick beam, But shew like flowers, that, wond'rous as I thought them, But droop by night—and meet the brighter day With tenfold fairness. Louisa. You are jocund still, sir. Raffaelle. Sadness dwelt not in Paradise—and here, Eden's restored to me—beneath that smile Grief can no more exist than pow'rs of evil Within the light celestial. Louisa. You prove your wit, lord Raffaelle, not your truth. Raffaelle. Nay, that can never be, if saws be true, A lover's heart feels deeply, and his tongue Gives utterance to matter, more than words. Louisa. Your mirth's your love, Cimaro. Raffaelle. Not so, lady, Albeit I am not of that whining tribe, Who, having no other fortune than their words, Mete them out dolefully to a nasal tune, And strangle joy in their contorted faces. Lady, we both are revelling in the morn Of fair and sportive youth; on both of us Fortune has shed abundance; in our grasp Lie all 'neath sov'reign honours; we are plac'd So far above the underlings o' the world, Common events to us may be disport, And while the tide of fortune sweeps down fools, We stand the barriers of the puny flood, And overpeer its rage. Louisa. Life's accidents, If they harm not ourselves, may yet have power Upon our friends; and in their fate we feel The ills of being. Raffaelle. Why should we then link Our greatness to their frailty? nature shews In this, we should be faithful to ourselves. He who would save a drowning friend from death May topple headlong in, and die himself. Great minds with great should join—and wealth with wealth— And pow'r with pow'r—and all things with their equals. In this, I still am speaking 'gainst myself; For you, being peerless, never could be mine. You smile, dear lady, might I hope that smile Assur'd me favour in my bold attempt, I should then dare to say, that all unworthy, And poor, as I may seem, compared with you— Though those bright beauties, resting in these arms, Would shew as brilliant as the lustrous moon, On the deep vested bosom of still night— Though none can equal that all heav'nly sweetness, Second to none beneath yourself;—in Mantua, The richest, and most potent, as I am, I lay my love most humbly at your feet, And wait in hope your soft and gentle kindness To place it in your heart, to rest for aye. Louisa. Good words, well put together, lord Cimaro. Raffaelle. Say—a good meaning from an open heart; But will you deign an answer to them, lady? Louisa. I've not the wit to jest, as you have done— Raffaelle. But to be serious as I have been. Louisa. Oh! that were to say nothing. Raffaelle. Trust me, lady, I've said no more than my full heart has prompted; And ask from you a like sincerity. Louisa. Then, not to wrong your openness, beseech you Believe at once that I can ne'er be your's; And from all further suit—I do entreat You will refrain. Raffaelle. This is a lady's “nay,” And therefore I am bound to disbelieve it. Louisa. My lord Cimaro, 'tis no idle thought Makes me refuse you, if you love me truly You'll speak no more of this. Raffaelle. (Aside.) Is't so, 'tis well, Ha!—ha!—I'll try:—I would not, trust me, lady, Urge you beyond the deep respect I owe you; Yet, for your honour, may I tell you this, Injurious as I doubt not you will deem it, 'Tis said you will espouse the felon Claudio. (She endeavours to speak.) O! trust me—I could not give ear to it Beyond the observance of a smile—I see— I knew it must be false.— Louisa. No more, I pray you.— Raffalle. Nay, I, perchance, should not have spoken of it, But feeling a deep interest here to serve you, I would not that the slightest taint should rest One moment on your fame; and though I scorn'd Even to repel the foolish calumny.— Louisa. My lord Cimaro! Raffaelle. I would pursue the sland'rer to the death, If you but wish it:—'twas a sacrilege To join that spotless name with such reproach. Louisa. And why reproach? Cimaro. (Hesitatingly) Raffaelle. (Aside.) Yes, she loves him: Claudio thou diest: heav'n has no pow'r to save thee. Oh! t'was the very madness of their malice To link imperial blood with a murderer's. Louisa. A murderer's!—he is no murderer. Raffaelle. Nay, I know not—the duke will be his judge— No more of him—let us to sprightlier subjects. Louisa. I pray you pardon me—I am not well. Raffaelle. I'm sorry that I mentioned this report, But I am guiltless of belief in it. Louisa. Leave me, I pray you. Enter a Servant. Servant. My lord, you are enquired for. Raffaelle. 'Tis well: Madam I'll leave you—trust me I am grieved— Much grieved I spoke of it—farewell—farewell— This scene will change 'ere night—'tis done—he's dead. (Aside.) As I return from court I'll wait on you: He's not the first kill'd by a woman's kindness. (Aside.) (Exit.) Louisa. Come, come, Maria; come, my gentle girl, Lead me into my chamber—Oh! my heart It leaps into my throat, cruel Cimaro! Love him! oh Claudio! (Exeunt.)</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. SCENE I. —A HALL OF JUSTICE IN THE DUCAL PALACE. Enter on one side Claudio with Officers, &amp;c. and Venilla on the other, in mourning, and attended by Gentlemen. Venilla. My lord, I'm happy to encounter you Before I range myself as your accuser: I would not you should think me of a spirit Basely litigious, that would make this court The arbiter where honour should decide, And bear sole sway: still less should I desire To prosecute vexatiously my appeal, When you, had my lost kinsman been alive, Would stand most justly here as the appellant: But, as it is, beseech you, sir, to think This course is but pursued to clear your fame, And so remove all taint upon my love Due to my kinsman dead. Claudio. I thank you, sir, And trust that in the end I may shew worthy Of so much favor in your thought. Enter Raffaelle and Julio. Raffaelle. They understood me right? Julio. Doubt not, my lord. Raffaelle. Tell them to herd among the common rabble: Be not you seen too near them; when they're sworn, Let them go instant to my house. Lord Claudio, Good-day; I'm glad to find the time so near, For your deliverance: my lord Venilla, I think you doubt not of his innocence— This scarcely need be heard before the duke. Claudio. I thank you, lord Cimaro, for your kindness, But as I dread no malice, I would rather This trial should proceed; to crush it now Would favour rumour, not alone 'gainst me, But my good lord Venilla. Raffaelle. It may be; And truly 'twill be better since you doubt not A fortunate result. The duke is coming, And with him all the nobles. Enter Duke and Senators, they take their seats. Duke. Before we enter on the present business For which we are assembled, as an earnest Of our high favour to the lord Cimaro We do invest him with the sword of state, To bear it as our marshal in our city. Raffaelle. My lord, I humbly thank your grace; my service, Poor as it is—is freely yours; my zeal Shall strive to merit that your bounty now Has cast on me untried. Duke. 'Tis well, my lord; Now to your suit—proclaim the court begun— Crier. I do hereby cite the lord Venilla, the accuser in this case, to come forward and prove his charge registered in this court against the lord Claudio. Long live the Duke! Venilla. My lord, I will not tire with idle words The patience of this most august assembly: I stand here to accuse lord Claudio That he hath slain Vincentio, my kinsman; And crave your highness' hearing in this cause Rather for him than for myself; for I Will, with your pleasure, wait his open answer; First stating that which he hath not denied, That by his hand the dead Vincentio fell. If without reason, of a brutish rage, This deed hath been committed,—then I crave The vengeance of the law upon his head. That by lord Claudio's hand my kinsman died Needs no more proof than this, that he was found Standing beside the dead Vincentio's corpse, And his drawn rapier reeking in his blood; If he deny not this, let him reply, What cause he had to kill him: on his answer Prov'd by what witness he may call before you My subsequent proceeding will depend. Duke. Claudio! your answer to Venilla's charge. Claudio. First then, my lord, to save the court some time, I do confess by me Vincentio fell, And grieved I am at the occasion, yet To save myself this means alone remained. For on my life the attack was made by him; Lorenzo saw the onset, and I trust Is here to prove the truth of what I speak. Duke. Is lord Lorenzo here? Raffaelle. My lord, he is not, He may be waiting in the galleries— Let him be called. (Exit Attendant.) Duke. Are any others here That can bear witness upon this occasion. A Monk steps forward. Raffaelle. Did you expect this evidence, lord Claudio? Claudio. No, my good lord, Raffaelle. I thought you knew him not. Duke. (To the Monk.) Who art thou? Monk. Good my lord, of holy order: Paolo is my name; a Dominican. First may I ask—was't near my lord Lorenzo's The fray took place? Duke. It was; know'st thou of it? Monk. Near there, my lord, upon that fatal day, Chancing to walk in solitary thought, I saw this nobleman, with hurried step, Pacing behind the ruin's broken wall; Ever he rubb'd with trembling hand his brow That seem'd all pale and moist with agitation. At last I heard the sound of other feet; He rush'd half madly forth—I saw no more. Claudio. How! Raffaelle. Peace, lord Claudio!—the duke would speak. Duke. Follow'd you not?—how was't you saw no more? Monk. Alas! my lord, I am an aged man, Bent down with years, and fearful in my nature; He that would lay in ambush for a foe, Might murder me. Claudio. I murder thee! Raffaelle. (Half aside.) I would beseech you, my lord Claudio, peace: You know not the emotion you betray. Claudio. Can I hear this—and yet remain unmoved? Thou liest, old man. Raffaelle. (To the Monk.) Have you aught more to say? Monk. I have no more—and that I have spoken truly Methinks these years should witness: I have nought To hope for in this world: look, good my lord, And judge by him if I speak not the trhth. Raffaelle. (To Claudio.) I feared this from your rashness—be more calm— Has your grace aught to ask of this man more? Duke. Not now—let him stand by awhile. Raffaelle. Yet stay, Lord Claudio, would you I should try his truth— Or were it best to hear no more from him? Claudio. I have no cause to fear, my lord Cimaro, In shewing all the truth. Raffaelle. Then I've one question— In what dress was lord Claudio habited? Monk. He wore a large dark mantle which fell from him As he leapt out the gap. Venilla. There was one found. Monk. And as he drew aside his vest there beamed, In the moon's gentle ray—that fell upon it, A ruby bright and large—hung round his neck By a thin chain of gold. Duke. Is't so indeed? Sure that bright jewel, matchless in Mantua, Which was found near, and which had once belonged To the noble lady de Commenes was this. Raffaelle. I thought that this would work. (Aside) Lord Claudio: I know not what to say—ask somewhat of him That may dispel this fearful mystery. Duke. Lord Claudio, would you more with him? Claudio. My lord, I do disdain to question him—to all I do oppose Lorenzo's testimony: Would he were here: my advocate was sent To seek for him. Raffaelle. (Aside) If found he could not help you: Are there no others that can speak of this? I hope there may, to prove this old man's malice; And yet I know not what could tempt him to't. A Peasant steps forward. Duke. Come you to speak of this? Peasant. So please your highness, Going from Mantua homeward on that day, Two passed me on the road; and one was muffled In a black cloak: as they walk'd by, the other Said to him—“Two might do the business surer:” The one replied—“But you have no disguise, And, should Vincentio 'scape, that might be fatal.” More I heard not, for they went on full quickly, And I'd a heavy burden. Duke. Look around you, If any be of the same height with him You saw thus muffled. Peasant. 'Twas about the height Of yonder nobleman. (Pointing to Claudio.) Raffaelle. Art sure of that? Quite sure? Peasant. I am, my lord. Raffaelle. It cannot be: Were you, lord Claudio, thus habited? Who saw you on that day can prove you were not? Claudio. I was so dressed. Raffaelle. Yet there walked no one with you? Claudio. There was one; But for the rest I know but that 'tis false. Duke. Who was the other? Claudio. 'Twas the lord Lorenzo. Who left me near his villa. Duke. Whither went you? Claudio. Towards the villa of the lady Commenes. (With Hesitation) Duke. Your answer is confused: I fear Lorenzo Comes not lest he should witness too against you, Or else be prov'd accomplice in this guilt: Would you ask more of him? Claudio. My gracious lord, I am amazed at this evidence; 'Tis all a tissue of malicious falsehood; I know not who has moved them thus against me. Raffaelle. (Aside) He gasps within the eddy of a whirlpool, And his last struggles draw him to the gulph. Yes, he himself shall minister his fate. (To Claudio) Yet, my lord Claudio, you have one hope— If this arise from malice, I'll disprove it: Let all the witnesses be taken hence. (Exeunt Attendants with Witnesses.) My lord Alphonso, as I think, Vincentio Was with you here in Mantua privately, Upon some feigned business, a short time Before he made th' attempt on Claudio's life. Alphonso. He was, my lord, and from his secrecy Yourself and I alone could know of it. He passed forth disguised as a monk, And changed his habit at a little cottage, About a mile from Mantua. Raffaelle. 'Tis well; If there be any malice in their proof They will convict themselves: 'tis plain he went From Mantua thither; should the peasant swear He saw him undisguised, and near to Mantua; Or should they err, led by the gen'ral rumour, To think that he was coming from his villa. Claudio. I see it, good my lord, and thank you much. Duke. Call in the peasant. Enter Attendants with Peasant. How far was't from Mantua Lord Claudio pass'd you? Peasant. As I think, my lord, 'Twas half a mile. Duke. Saw you Vincentio after? Peasant. No, my lord, I saw none save an old monk. Duke. At what time did he pass you? Peasant. 'Twas at sun-set. Duke. Thence 'tis about two miles to where he fell. Let them bring in the monk. Enter Attendants with Monk. Whence came the sounds Of footsteps—from the side of Mantua Or from the villa of the lady Commenes? Monk. From that of Mantua, my lord, which seem'd Most strange to me, when I heard more of this: 'Twas said Vincentio was at his villa, But this way I am sure I heard his footsteps. Duke. Aye, At what time was't you saw the stranger rush From forth the ruin? Monk. Somewhat past an hour After the sun had set. Claudio. I know not how— This tale hangs well together, but 'tis false. Duke. My lord, the evidence is mighty 'gainst you, Unless you can excuse, or shew most clearly 'Twas in your own defence you did this deed, I have no power to turn the rigorous law From the dread doom of death. Claudio. My lord, I am o'erwhelm'd—I cannot speak More than—'tis false. (To the Monk) Old man, thy life is short, And heaven will require a strict account Of such blaspheming of thy holy office. Duke. Exclaims are vain, unless thou hast some proof, Or cause to urge to mitigate the law, Thy life is forfeit. Raffaelle. My gracious prince—if Claudio hath done this, As it appears, some reason of strong weight Urged him to such a deed: I cannot think Without some deep and heart-felt injury He would assassinate Vincentio. Speak, my lord Claudio—confess the truth, That justice may with mercy be attempered, Leave not thy name an infamy to man, For causeless murder. Speak, and shew thy wrongs, It nought avails to combat this strong proof. Claudio. No—I have said—some deadly unseen foe That dares not bear his cause upon his sword, Has prompted these to lie against my life. I will not compromise my innocence: They that have sworn this know that it is false. Duke. I grieve thy fate, but know not how to avoid it: Had I the power I would spare thee yet. (Consults with Senators.) Raffaelle. (Aside.) Now triumph, Claudio, in thy lady's love! The hands that should have clasp'd about thy neck, May now weave chaplets for thy timeless grave; Thy hymeneal song shall be a dirge; Thy nuptial bed—the cold and lifeless tomb: Whilst I shall revel in thy mistress' beauties, And quaff nectareous sweets from her soft lip, As the dull grave-worm draws itself o'er thine, My heart shall beat with ecstacy of joy As thine shall throb the last of agony. (To him) Oh! Claudio! dote not on the name of innocence; Confess, and boldly trust the duke with all: Thy state is at the worst—a milder sentence May greet repentant sorrow. (Claudio looks firm but distressed.) (Aside.) What! does this sting, lord Claudio? This is he Who would wed her I love. Duke. There is no hope— No power in the law—that can defer Your instant execution. Raffaelle. (Aside.) There is no hope! My dear friend, Claudio! (Aside) That such a thing Should be Cimaro's rival! Enter an Officer. Officer. The lord Lorenzo, faint and wounded, waits For entrance to the court. Duke. Lorenzo wounded! Let him come in at once—conduct him hither. Raffaelle. Curse on the fool that let him 'scape. (Aside) Make way there. Now my dear lord—I trust your honour's saved. (to Claudio.) Enter Lorenzo supported. Fool that I was to trust a common stabber!— So the man dies they think they've done enough— (to Lorenzo,) My lord, sit down, your wounds are painful to you (Seats him in the Marshal's chair.) Duke. Tell to the court how this befel, Lorenzo. Lorenzo. Pardon, my Lord, I'm faint with loss of blood— I scarce can speak, for, passing from my villa, Near to the spot where Claudio slew Vincentio, A ruffian blow left me for dead, 'till one Pass'd by and bound my wound—at my desire Procured conveyance hither— Duke. This is strange And looks indeed like malice against Claudio. My lord Cimaro, cause fit search be made To bring the villain to just punishment; For by his means we may discover more. Lorenzo. I saw him not—I fell by his first blow. Raaffelle. My lord I'll institute immediate quest, If these things are permitted, there's no safety For honest men in Mantua—I'll look to it. Duke. But what says lord Lorenzo?— Lorenzo. Good my lord, Upon the day—Oh I am faint! Raffaelle. He'll die; Would 't were before he could hear Claudio! Duke. Rest for a while. Lorenzo. My lord I yet have breath, And while I yet can speak—I will attest The innocence of Claudio— Duke. Thank Heaven Lorenzo. I parted with him near the abbey walls I tow'rd my villa, he tow'rd Commenes, When turning to observe the rising moon, Which shone full brightly o'er the mouldering arches, I saw Vincentio rush from forth the ruin And aim a deadly blow at Claudio; His sword pierc'd but the mantle of my friend, Who instant drew—and, ere I gain'd the spot, Had kill'd him—at the moment that I reach'd him, A Peasant too came up, who had not seen More than Vincentio's fall—I would be spared, For life ebbs with me— Duke. 'Tis enough, Lorenzo. Where are the Monk and Peasant? Raffaelle. Gone, my lord,— I see them not—. Duke. Let search be made for them: Meanwhile lord Claudio—you are free—and trust me, I am most thankful heav'n hath interfered To spare to me the sin of too rash judgment; Fearful indeed, is the dread task of rulers, Had not Lorenzo sped thus to your aid, I should have sent you to that fatal doom, Which all my sorrows could not have recall'd. Lord marshal see that search be made for all Who have abetted in this traiterous plot, And they shall feel the vengeance of the law. Raffaelle. Doubt not, my lord, with joy I undertake The task of vengeance on lord Claudio's foes. (Aside) For were't another's office 'twere my death. Duke. Break up the Court. (Exeunt Duke Senators, &amp;c.) Raffaelle. Pardon, my dear lord Claudio, That I have been so tardy in the offering Of my congratulations—but my joy, At your deliverance, was too full for speech, You know, I trust, my friendship. Claudio. Aye, my lord— I have not in my safety aught more pleasing Than is the power to return my thanks t'ye Raffaelle. I fear'd indeed I had been too officious But you will pardon it. Claudio. I knew your meaning, And therefore could not but be thankful for't. Raffaelle. That would be strange if you had known my meaning.—(Aside) I must begone to order instant search For these false witnesses—I will not fail To see you shortly, and I trust to bring them Within your power—so I'll take my leave. Farewell—damn'd—damn'd—damn'd chance—but I've not done. (Aside) (Exit.) Lodovico. That's a brave spirit—he's a true friend, Claudio! But that their cunning was past human wisdom He would have sure discovered it—as 'tis. You are indebted to him for the attempt. Claudio. I think so, sir: Come lords, we'll to my house, my cheer's the better For so much peril, will you with me homeward? (Exeunt) SCENE II. —A ROOM IN CIMARO'S PALACE. Enter Raffaelle and Julio Raffaelle. Tell me no more, he should have stabb'd and stabb'd Till all his body were a wound—that, had Each separate inch a life, he might die all, Henceforth I'll trust myself—the monk and peasant Conceal most closely: I must search for them; Convey this gold to them—they've done their work. Curse on the wayward fate that crosses me: All causes should conspire to form great ends: If I o'erleap the petty bound of justice, And doom the reptile Claudio to his ruin, What is the speck in the majestic world? A thing that was—and is beheld no more. It is all nature's custom, that the great Consume the small. Who views the cataract With less of thought sublime, because it drives Some little brook back to its puny source? 'Tis greater by its devastating power. Should one small cloud Dim the fair lustre of heaven's varied arch? Should the proud oak be rooted from the earth Because its growth displaces some dull weed? Claudio, my genius hath the mastery, And thine shall bow to it: this arm shall do it— I'll make occasion speedily; and if I fail, 'tis but to bid him to a banquet, And poison him in feasting. (Enter Servant) Servant. Lord Alphonso Waits you without, sir. Raffaelle. He may serve my purpose, For should I need the festal cup, his hand Shall be the bearer. I await him here, (Exit Servant. He too was Claudio's rival, and suspicion Were better upon him than me: let's see now— To bid this Claudio to a feast to-morrow, And on the way assault him. (Enter Alphonso.) Oh! my friend, I wish'd to see you. Alphonso. Oh! my lord, command me. Raffaelle. I have been thinking how to celebrate The noble Claudio's deliverance, And I design a feast to-morrow night. Alphonso. To-morrow he is married. Raffaelle. Married! married! To-morrow!—and to whom? Alphonso. The lady Commenes. Raffaelle. Indeed! Alphonso. Most true. Raffaelle. This is no little matter: I think it is as near to you as me; We both have lov'd the lady de Commenes; And both, as I should guess, were griev'd to lose her. Alphonso. Faith, somewhat. Raffaelle. Had not Claudio been her suitor, One or the other had had better fortune. Alphonso. I am content to yield. Raffaelle. (Aside) 'Twere easier To move a wren to combat with an eagle, Than urge this dolt to touch a hair of Claudio. (To him) Well, well, and so am I; a lady's love Cannot obey aught but her fantasy. I've an esteem for Claudio, and I've shewn it. I freely give Louisa to his love; And more to prove how well it pleases me, I will not be denied his presence here To-morrow night you shall go bid him for me. Alphonso. Most happily, my lord. Raffaelle. And to the lady, Who doubtless will not be so easily won, Say this—I spoke to her the other day To prove her love to Claudio, not meaning Any offence by it, but if she lov'd him To yield at once; and that I meant no wrong, Methinks my conduct at the trial proves; Were my heart rancorous 'gainst Claudio, I should not thus have sought to save him. Alphonso. Aye, sir, Doubt not I'll urge this. Raffaelle. Something further, in which I'll crave your kind assistance: some of us, You and myself, will, habited as peasants, Conduct the festival, and humbly shew The changes of the eve. Alphonso. With all my heart; I will engage some other noblemen To wear the habit, and attend your guests. Raffaelle. May I entreat you then to see them now, I will not fail t' eclipse what yet I've done, In honour of so happy an event: Farewell. Alphonso. I will about it: farewell, sir. (Exit.) Raffaelle. So, so—his nature formed him for a lacquey: He'll act it to the life:—to lose a lady, And such a lady, with a less concern Than monks bestow their scapularies: aye, This gen'ral habit will much aid my plan— It will divide suspicion, and I'll fix it— First at my rapier's point I will essay him In the dark portico beside my palace; There will I have my servant Julio Meet and detain him;—no delay—such deeds Are better in the doing than the thought. I'll bring her yet a virgin to my bed, And crop the prime of love in her sweet beauties. This marriage yet shall be a funeral. Fate, like a mettled steed, has started 'neath me, Only to prove the prowess of the rider; But I will curb and spur it to my will, And ride triumphant to the goal of bliss. Security has lost more fools than Claudio. I'll spare no pomp to greet his death; the glitter Will take th' attention of the common herd, And keep them from too deep a scrutiny;— This hand shall make sure work—'tis prompted here. (Exit.)</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT IV. SCENE I. —A ROOM IN THE PALACE OF COMMENES. Enter Claudio and Louisa, Claudio. We owe much thanks to our friend Cimaro, For honouring thus our nuptials. Louisa. Think you so? If so, his mind is chang'd tow'rd you and me. Claudio. I think as lord Alphonso spoke of him, That, finding he must never hope your hand, With a true generous spirit, and to serve you In aiding me, he came unto my trial. If I am skill'd in him—he's of that nature To gain an end he'd put forth all his means; Yet the end lost he envies not the winner. His pleasure is in the pursuit not gain. There are some men whose happiness is action— To whom repose is torture—who hold nought Indifferent to them;—such a man is Raffaelle. Louisa. I'm grieved your friend Lorenzo lingers yet In pain and sickness; but the wound's not mortal. Claudio. No, thanks to heaven, their malice there has failed; We'll to Cimaro's, love; I would not spurn His noble friendship; yet I would not go: I am to-day too full of quilet joys To love a boisterous tumult; methinks joy Dwells but in peace,—and such sweet solitude As the first pair in loveliest Eden knew; Such friends have yet a claim on our affections, Which 'twere a dotage to despise. Enter a Servant. Servant. My lord, Some gentlemen are waiting to conduct you To lord Cimaro's. Claudio. We'll attend them straight: Come, my Louisa.— (Exeunt.) SCENE II. —A DARK PORTICO BY RAFFAELLE'S PALACE. In the half distance, an illuminated Hall, music within. Enter Raffaelle cloak'd and mask'd. Raffaelle. 'Tis strange—a few short moments, and he dies! He that in pride of youth and happiness, Plumed up by beauty's smile, and trick'd in all The trappings of his new aspiring fortunes: He that would mate me in magnificence, Comes but adorned with all these shining glories As to a sacrifice; dull and unconscious As one who sleeps beneath a tottering rock, And dies ere ruin wake him:—I can play The spider with true art: he is enmesh'd Ev'n as he gambols, and my fell embrace Poisons his life-blood:—soft—is't he?— Enter Julio. Julio. My lord. Raffaelle. Peace on thy life, and wait for Claudio's coming. Enter Lodovico and others: Raffaelle draws back. Lodovico. All Mantua dotes upon lord Claudio; His very griefs have made him popular; And in magnificence I doubt he'll rival The lord Cimaro, though I hear he to-night Exceeds his former grandeur. 1 Gentleman. Let us in then. (Exeunt.) Raffaelle. Aye, aye, lord Claudio is their dear friend now, He whom some two days since they would think grac'd By half a look, they turn to him and court him; My pleasures pall and sicken on their tastes: 'Twere folly but to dream it could be else. Th' astronomer views not th' all-glorious sun, That immemorial pageant of the heavens, With half the fond delight with which he spies The scarce seen twinklings of a new-found star: Great things grow stale and common by oft seeing; And, with the common herd, are scarcely felt; Because the form, instinctive in their thoughts, Awakes no cause for vulgar contemplation. Yet I shall mar this pleasure—here he comes! Raffaelle stands back, Enter Claudio, Louisa and Gentlemen. Julio comes forward to Claudio. Julio. My lord, I'd crave a moment's word with you. Claudio. On then, my love!—on friends! I'll strait be with you. (Exeunt Louisa and Gentlemen) Julio. My lord, my master charg'd me to inform you, He thinks to have found some traces of those men Who bore false witness 'gainst you, at your trial. Claudio. Then let them go unheeded—I am free From any wish against them;—should they name The author of my ills, I would not harm them Let my lord know this— Julio. Sir, I'll do your bidding (Exit.) Raffaelle makes a pass at him as he is going out, which he wards with his hand—they fight— Raffaelle is disarm'd—he exits in the arch. Claudio. Help! help!—he must be here. Enter Gentlemen with torches. A villain ever now attacked me here— He must have pass'd this way. 1 Gentleman. Ha! see this door; Was't here he fled? 2 Gentleman. This leads but to the court, And no one's there. Claudio. Indeed this is most strange; But I beseech you say no more of it, It might affright Louisa. 1 Gentleman. We will not, sir, Claudio. Thanks! thanks! let's in, lest that my stay amaze them. (Exeunt.) SCENE III. —A SALOON OPENING BY FOLDING-DOORS INTO AN ILLUMINATED GARDEN, IN WHICH FOUNTAINS ARE SEEN PLAYING, THE VIEW TERMINATED BY A RUSTIC TEMPLE OF SILVER BOUGHS ENTWINED. Gentlemen and Ladies masked,—Alphonso with others, habited in rich Arcadian dresses discovered —among these Raffaelle, similiarly habited, steals unperceived—a dance—after which Raffaelle comes forward. Raffaelle. He'as 'scaped the lion's gripe; I'm held at bay; But I've another effort ere I fall: Thinks he to baffle my endeavours yet; I am urged on by millions of desires, And each desire hath many several hands, To gain the full completion of my wishes: Yet on one chance rests all my hopes—one chance!— If it be lost, I have no care but death: And both shall grace the glory of my ruin. I am not fool enough to die alone: I'll hold immortal int'rest in Louisa— My spirit shall o'ermatch her Claudio's. Enter Claudio and Gentlemen. Claudio. Nay, name it not; would I could find Cimaro, He might seek out the villain—but no matter; Do not, I pray you, interrupt the sport, By speaking of th' attack. 2 Gentleman. We will not, sir, Raffaelle. (To Alphonso) Our guests seem somewhat heated by the dance; Let us fill wine to them—pour out a bowl— For my lord Claudio. Claudio. Is it you, Cimaro? To-morrow I will speak with you, so please you: The ancient malice of my unknown foe Is not e'en yet appeas'd. Raffaelle. (Aside) Nor will it be, Until your life is made the atonement. How Has he again, attempted on your life? Claudio. Ev'n here beside your gates I was attack'd By one, who being disarm'd fled hither. Raffaelle. Hither! I'll search the palace. Claudio. Not so—pray you, Raffaelle; Louisa must not know this. (Alphonso brings wine which Raffaelle takes and puts a powder into it.) Raffaelle. (To Alphonso) My lord Manlio, I thank you, will you drink my gentle lord? (To Claudio.) Claudio. I'm somewhat heated by this strange encounter. Raffaelle. (Laying his hand on Claudio's, which holds the cup.) I must prepare the sights in yonder temple. One word—beware Alphonso!— (Raffaelle passes to the back ground, and is busied with the crowd—as Claudio raises the cup to his lips, Louisa comes up.) Claudio. I was about to taste this generous wine— Will't please you add a sweet to it Louisa? Your lips do breathe a blessing on the bowl, And make it sacred to the god of love. (She sips it—He drinks it.) Louisa. What was it that detained you, Claudio? Claudio. 'Twas but some matters that related to The treachery of my foes, my friend Cimaro Thinks he has found them—but no more of that— (Alphonso takes the bowl from Claudio. Claudio and Louisa walk up.) Raffaelle. (Viewing the bowl in Alphonso's hand) Yes, he has drain'd the venom to the bottom; His minutes now are measured, strait 'twill work. Enter Julio. Julian. (To Alphonso) My lord, will you permit me to conduct you Into the temple—to command the changes That wait but for your presence— Alphonso. Lead me thither, (Exeunt.) Raffaelle. Why this is brave—all's suited to my wishes. This is such joy—that were the fiery bolt Of vengeance winged already 'gainst my head I would exult in the short interim— And it is like I shall have longer time, For now-a-days are miracles disused, And man creates what prodigies he will, Without the answer of celestial portents. See, see, already is his cheek grown pale— His knees begin to totter—I will to him. (Meets Claudio, Louisa hanging upon Claudio's arm. During this speech many go out.) Louisa. Claudio, you tremble; what is't, my dear Claudio? Claudio. Nay, nothing, nothing. Louisa. And your speech is faint— Oh, heaven! your eyes! Raffaelle. Indeed I think your fears Are just—he is not well—a chair here quickly. (A chair is brought—Claudio sits. Louisa. Look, look up, Claudio— Raffaelle. Soft—his eye grows fix'd; A film grows o'er it: what a thrill was there! Look on his quiv'ring lip! Claudio. I'm faint, my love, And fear the grasp of death encircles me— His icy hand weighs heavy on my heart— Raffaelle. Oh speak not so:—here rest your head, my friend, (lifting his head) Say but another word—have hope, dear lady. Claudio. Louisa,—should I die,—my friend Cimaro—(a pause—he struggles for utterance) Raffaelle. He cannot—see—cold drops roll down his cheek; His heart beats low and softly— Louisa. Mercy, Heav'n! Raffaelle. She swoons—oh bear her from this fatal place; Feed her with hope should she revive— (Exit some with Louisa) Claudio. Cimaro! Protect Louisa—farewell—oh! (dies) Raffaelle. Great Heaven! My friend!—dear Claudio's! gone? aye, gone for ever—(a pause.) That goblet was I fear the fatal cause. 1 Gentleman. The goblet that Alphonso gave, my lord? Raffaelle. Alphonso! ha! Alphonso! 'twas lord Manlio. 2 Gentleman. No, good my lord—(discovering himself.) I did not— Raffaelle. Cursed fate! This was my fear;—ah me! should he be poison'd! Heav'ns peace be with thee, my unhappy friend; O that the wretch who did this damned act, May feel ev'n here the poison of that chalice. Dear Claudio! Good my friends; retire, I pray you; It were not well to noise this in the halls. My absence will not be remarked—Alphonso Will take the alarm;—therefore speak not of this— I hope he has not done't;—but if 'tis so— I pray you now retire and close the doors, My grief's to me companion—he is cold— (Kneeling and clasping his hand.) (Exeunt Gentlemen, and close the doors.) Yes, he is cold! the warmth of life is gone!— 'Twas kind too to commend me to Louisa: A dying husband's words will be obey'd, Who leaves the world upon his wedding-day; And his request, methinks, was not so harsh. Fond, doting, foolish Claudio! Ere I'd yield, Ev'n in death, Louisa to another, I'd see her reeking in her ruddy gore, And writhing in death's agony round my feet. Men say his nature though was soft and kindly, And what means that—that they could prey on him: No, while I live, I live unto myself; And seeming generosity's a part Of the great plan: for that I pitied Claudio— For that I feast yon tribe of empty fools; And done for that, his death upon my soul Weighs not the lightest flagging of the wind. Ho! Julio! (Enter Julio.) Remove this carrion hence, And lay it out with pomp upon a bed; Let there be mutes, tapers, and mummery, And store of monks, and masses, and all mourning. Dead, I will honour him beyond all parallel: And it is fit: he was Cimaro's rival. Hence! put my house into a shew of grief— Call in your fellows—let the rumour be, Alphonso poison'd him: for me, I am Retired to my chamber—I'll not spare Tears or laments—then to my sweet Louisa. (Exit Julio.) For her I wear this mockery of woe— In her my happiness will be more perfect, Than Paris', when he bore fair Helena In jocund triumph from the Spartan shore. He doted on a woman, and he gain'd her; But, at my beck, wealth, love, pre-eminence, Come crowding in confusion of delight; My fame not merely saved without a blemish, But greeted with the shouts of Mantua, For generous friendship, constancy and truth. (Exit.)</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT V. SCENE I. —A SALOON IN CIMARO'S PALACE, THROUGH THE WINDOWS OF WHICH THE DAY-BREAK IS DISCOVERED. Enter Raffaelle. Raffaelle. The drowsy pall of night is drawn aside By the fresh vigour of the jocund morn; So yields a widow to a second love And so Louisa strait shall greet Cimaro. Upon these dullards, sleep lies heavy yet: They have no wish to mock their weariness. Methinks the lark sounds merrily this morning, Chaunting proud Pæans through the upper air; And my full triumph very nature hails In gladsome aspect. I must rouse these sleepers. Ho! here comes Julio. Enter Julio. Julio—I have much Must be dispatch'd to-day—I trust Alphonso Will be suspected of this last night's business, And giv'n into my guard—'tis he must bear The hazard—so he be condemned for it I care not if he should escape—and yet His death were surer:—oh! these poor dull fools! Like cards in houses built by children—one Falls, and in tumbling strikes another down— But such are easily built up again—(a knock without) A knocking there! who is't? go to the door— I have been wailing over Claudio's corpse. (Exit Julio) Perchance the duke has news of this already; No matter—I'm prepar'd— Re-enter Julio. Julio. A messenger From the lady de Commenes. Raffaelle. So soon—what says she? Julio. But that she wishes your immediate presence. Raffaelle. What can this mean? she cannot be so fickle To love me yet—there's something more in this; But what care I? I have been used to meet And out-brave danger. Say that I obey her. (Exit.) SCENE II. —THE PALACE OF THE LADY DE COMMENES. Louisa and Maria discovered. Louisa on a couch. Louisa. If it be so—and sure I think it is— I am not sorry that I tasted of it: In death I shall rejoin my Claudio— It were no happiness to stay from him. Maria. And would you, lady, die? Louisa. Oh yes, Maria, Death is repose with Claudio; I have felt Even from then a gradual decay; It grows upon me in a stilly coldness; Yet ere it reaches to my heart, Cimaro, I trust, will come—I'd see him ere I die. Enter an Attendant. Attendant. Madam, the lords Lodovico and Manlio Enquire of your health. Louisa. 'Tis well; I'll see them. (Exit Att.) I would have witnesses. Enter Lodovico and Manlio. Lodovico. How fare you, lady? Louisa. Oh well beyond all hope; calm as the night; I've slept not—yet my mind has been with angels. Methought I saw my Claudio stretch his arm Tow'rds me from heav'n, and with sounds seraphic, Woo me to come to him—I shall obey him. Enter Attendant. Attendant. Madam, my lord Cimaro. Louisa. Let me see him. (Exit Attendant.) My lords, I pray you stay; I have some words To speak; and be you witness of his answers. Enter Raffaelle. Raffaelle. I cannot bid you a good morrow, lady; Your hope and mine is gone; and common greetings Sound dull, and heartless, in this wretched time. Louisa. Aye, my good lord, and sounds from hollow hearts Are poor indeed to me. Raffaelle. (Aside) This is most strange! And yet believe me 'tis a happiness Unhoped for, thus to see you: I thought not Even that mind so much above its sorrows. Louisa. No, didst thou think that I should wail my loss; 'Tis but a parting, and we all must die. My griefs are not of earth: should I invest My sorrows with the pageantry of woe? I have a hope too bright to mix with grief— Thou couldst not think that I should live, Cimaro. Raffaelle. Live! lady. Louisa. Live! didst thou not drug the bowl For me as well as Claudio? Raffaelle. I! dear lady! For thee! Louisa. Thou canst not look like innocence, Though thou art full of wiles, this is no time To mask my words—I am about to die. Raffaelle. To die! what mean you? you! you! die! die! Louisa. Yes, lord; I should not be so calm else; but the cup That kill'd my Claudio, lent its help to me. Raffaelle. Thou didst not drink—'twas poison! Louisa. Aye, I feel it. Raffaelle. Foil'd! foil'd! foil'd! foil'd! damnation! Louisa. Lord Cimaro, You put the poison there. Raffaelle. Who saw me do't? Yet I care not; did you drink much? no matter— A drop were a slow death to fifty men: But did you taste it? Louisa. Mark him, lords! my life But quivers on my lip. Claudio, I come. Cimaro, thou art guilty! Heav'n forgive thee; There was a strain of music, heard you not? Soft, soft and tender, of sweet melancholy; Nor see you there—but your's are mortal senses— Ah Claudio—I come—I come. (Dies.) Raffaelle. Dead! deep damnation rest on all the earth! Sweep from its face all things that dwell on it, And people it alone with direful plagues: I'd not kill thee, Louisa! O 'tis mockery: Pour down your fires, rive me to the earth, Ye dull unthinking heav'ns! why gaze you at me? Yes, 'twas I killed him—her—all— I have accomplish'd the decrees of fate. You, you, you, petty spirits, move half lifeless; And, being, are not—fools, fools, in my fortune, Things nobler were encompass'd. Lodovico. He is mad. Raffaelle. Mad! reptile! are all mad that tow'r above you, And do what you daren't dream? My deeds are spent, Idle as ether—vagrant as the wind— Hopeless and fineless—I have done my part— 'Tis ended—all, all—here: I had one hope, One end, one aim—the loadstar of my life— And it is gone;—my powers are gone with it; She's dead! Oh! would that I could weep one tear; It would allay the fever of my soul:— How—not one drop?—it gushes from my heart; There, there, there, there.—I'll not endure the gaze, And taunts, and gibes, that wait upon my fortunes; Each fool will bless himself he'as done no murder: And who would live, when thou and all are gone! (Stabs himself.) You wonder yet—'tis much; then I'm not fall'n Beneath myself; I yet can scorn your follies; While fate crouch'd to me I could live; and now Its pow'r is not so great but I can die: This, this is well (they offer to assist him): no, no—away, away— I did despise you living—and my death Is sacred to myself. Oh! (they observe him— he suppresses his agony.) ha! ha! ha! (Dies.) The Curtain Falls.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">EPILOGUE. (Enter Mrs. Epilogue, an old flirt, with a large fan, &amp;c.) Gentles good even, Mrs. Epilogue, I introduce myself; my brother Prologue Refused his countenance to me, the brute! And left me thus to hazard a debut: He is my elder brother,—or I'm sure He'd have no reason to be so demure. This is the way with antiquated folks; They're past the relish of our modern jokes, Preaching in dull blank verse!—if there's a poet Within the pit I call on him to shew it How much our speeches are improved by time, Since lucky fortune cast them into rhyme. For were't not for the jingle at the end Some works might be thought prose—which Heav'n forefend! Then such a fuss about instruction too, As though his canting stead of shew would do. For Heav'ns sake do not countenance the fellow, Or where we rant some Methodist may bellow. A play's a play, say I, and but give me A quantum suff: of roaring,—grief, or glee. Who is not mov'd when Alexander's mad? If not the scene—a head-ache makes him sad. In Comedy what difference in the case is, Whether we laugh at wit or Munden's faces? A play's a vehicle for striking action; And to bring folks together: though a faction May hold that they should have a moral with 'em, Some authors have no morals left to give 'em. Plays, to gain approbation in these times, Should be no more than speaking pantomimes: Or if there needs a theme to talk upon, The surest hit's to palliate crim. con. A lady in men's clothes has great effect; Plays that want noise you'll certainly reject; And then when all is done, and you have wonder'd Enough how actors fell, and jump'd, and flounder'd, And ran against the door posts, while you thought Soon to decide if in their heads were aught That so in princely parts they play'd the dog; Then let there come a sprightly Epilogue, No matter how 'tis written,—so 'tis said, That she who spoke 't was pretty and well-made, 'Twill catch some sure applause herself to praise, In half a hundred pretty, clap-trap ways. And so I told our moody author here; But he refused such practices to bear: “For me,” said he,—I've not forgot his speech, “If I can wisdom, truth, and virtue teach, “And gain my own applause as well as theirs, “The stage may claim my most exalted cares: “But if men come but with their sensual eyes, “I've shewn a mirror tells them how I prize “Their vain acclaims, if so—soul, and tongue and pen “May lie oblivious—and ne'er wake again.” FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>