<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Knowles, James Sheridan, 1784-1862</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Knowles, James Sheridan, 1784-1862</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">knowles james sheridan 1784 1862</field>
      <field name="author_text">Knowles, James Sheridan, 1784-1862</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1850's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V3.0289.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1859</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460689</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Wife ; A Tale of Mantua</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Wife ; A Tale of Mantua</field>
      <field name="title_facet">wife</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">wife</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Wife ; A Tale of Mantua</field>
      <field name="year_display">1859</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1859</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1859</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460689&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460689&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Knowles, James Sheridan, 1784-1862&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;knowles james sheridan 1784 1862&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Wife ; A Tale of Mantua&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;wife&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1859&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1859&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Knowles, James Sheridan&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1784&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1862&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Wife&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tale of Mantua&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London, New York&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Routledge, Warnes &amp;amp; Routledge&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1859&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3873217-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv30289&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Wife&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tale of Mantua&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 195 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted&lt;lb/&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;lb/&gt;Dedication included with Caius Gracchus.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: The wife.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Drama.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1833.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 24 Apr 1833.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE WIFE: A Tale of Mantua.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DEDICATED TO CAPTAIN THOMAS BLAIR (OF THE HON. COMPANY'S SHIP WILLIAM FAIRLIE).</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DRAMATIS PERSONÆ. (AS ORIGINALLY PERFORMED AT COVENT GARDEN, IN 1833.) Mariana Miss Ellen Tree. Floribel Miss Sydney. Leonardo Gonzaga Prince of Mantua Mr. C. Kean. Ferrardo Gonzaga Prince of Mantua Mr. Warde. Count Florio Mr. Diddear. Julian St. Pierre Mr. Sheridan Knowles. Antonio, a Curate Mr. G. Bennett. Lorenzo, an Advocate of Rome Mr. Abbott. Hugo, Guardian to Mariana Mr. Ransford. Bartolo Mr. Meadows. Bernardo Mr. Turnour. Carlo Mr. Barnes. Marco Mr. Henry. Pietro Mr. Payne. Stephano Mr. J. Cooper. First Lord Mr. Irwin. Advocate of Mantua Mr. Haines. First Officer Mr. T. Matthews. Second Officer Mr. Mears. Courier Mr. Heath.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE—MANTUA;—afterwards the Camp.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PROLOGUE, SPOKEN BY MR. WARDE. Untoward fate no luckless wight invades More sorely than the Man who drives two trades; Like Esop's bat, between two natures placed, Scowl'd at by mice, among the birds disgraced. Our author thus, of twofold fame exactor, Is doubly scouted,—both as Bard and Actor! Wanting in haste a Prologue, he applied To three poetic friends; was thrice denied. Each glared on him with supercilious glance, As on a Poor Relation met by chance; And one was heard, with more repulsive air, To mutter “Vagabond,” “Rogue,” “Strolling Player!” A poet once, he found—and look'd aghast— By turning actor, he had lost his caste. The verse patch'd up at length—with like ill fortune His friends behind the scenes he did importune To speak his lines. He found them all fight shy, Nodding their heads in cool civility. “Their service in the Drama was enough, The poet might recite the poet's stuff!” The rogues—they like him hugely—but it stung 'em, Somehow—to think a Bard had got among 'em. Their mind made up—no earthly pleading shook it, In pure compassion till I undertook it. Disown'd by Poets and by Actors too, Dear Patrons of both arts, he turns to you! If in your hearts some tender feelings dwell From sweet Virginia, or heroic Tell: If in the scenes which follow you can trace What once has pleased you—an unbidden grace— A touch of nature's work—an awkward start Or ebullition of an Irish heart— Cry, clap, commend it! If you like them not, Your former favours cannot be forgot. Condemn them—damn them—hiss them if you will— Their author is your grateful servant still!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. SCENE I. —A Street in Mantua. Enter Leonardo Gonzaga and Lorenzo. Leon. So in my native city, thanks to Heaven, Ten years and more elapsed, I stand again! A boy it sent me forth, takes back a man. Hail to it! 'Tis mine old acquaintance still, In nothing strange—unalter'd! To a stone The same I left it! Glad am I to see it— None better loves its venerable face! Lor. I'm glad to see you smile. Leon. I do so, signor. I am a boy again! The days come back When smallest things made wealth of happiness And ever were at hand! when I did watch With panting heart the striking of the clock, Which hardly sounded ere the book was shut. Then for the race—the leap—the game—O, signor, The vigour and endurance of such joy! Is't e'er to come again?—and care so light, That, looking back, I smile that thought it care, And call it part of pleasure! I'm again In Mantua! Lor. Then here we say farewell. Leon. Not so! Acquaintance, born and nurtured in Adversity, is worth the cherishing! 'Tis provéd steel which one may trust one's life to. You are a stranger here in Mantua. Which I am native to. What brings you hither? If 'tis a cause no scruple of just weight Forbids thee to unfold, unbosom thee; And, in return for what thou part'st with, take The zeal and honour of a hearty friend, And service too, to boot!—You pause from doubt Either of my ability or faith. If this, I'm sorry for't—If that, take heed! You know not by the eye the practised limb Where the inform'd and active sinew lies, That's equal to the feat. What, silent still? 'Sdeath, man! a dwarf is not to be despised, For he may have a giant for his friend, And so be master of a giant's strength! Come, come, have confidence!—'Tis the free rein Which takes the willing courser o'er the leap He'd miss, suppose you check'd him! Lor. There are men Whose habits in abeyance hold their natures, Which still remain themselves.—Your temperament Is of the sanguine kind, and so is mine; But lo, the difference! Thy frankness brooks No pause—thy wish is scarce conceived, ere told— As if men's hearts were open as their looks, And trust were due to all! The law hath been My study, signor; and, these three years past, My practice too; and it hath taught me this:— To doubt, with openness to be convinced, Is to remain on this side danger, yet No fraction lack of generosity, Which it becomes a noble mind to cherish. Leon. And doubt you me? Lor. No, signor; but drew back, When you, with instant promptness, made advance, Where I, with all the heart to take the step, Had still, I fear, been standing! You shall know My errand hither. I am nephew— Leon. Stop Till these pass on! Enter Bartolo, Carlo, Bernardo, and others. Carlo. Will not the duke postpone the cause? Bar. I tell thee no. Carlo. And wherefore? Bar. What's that to thee?—Is not he the duke? Shall such a piece of flesh and bone as thou art, question the duke? Carlo. Why not? Bar. Why not? Would any one believe he had been born in Mantua? Now mark how I shall answer him! Dost thou drink Burgundy? Carlo. No, but water. Bar. Then art thou, compared to the great duke, what water is to Burgundy. Carlo. He is but flesh and blood. Bar. But what kind of flesh and blood? Answer me that! Wouldst thou, that dinest upon garlic and coarse bread, and washest them down with water, compare thyself to one who sits down, every day of the week, to a table of three courses? Thou art no more than a head of garlic to the duke! Ber. Say on, Bartolo! Well! The duke refuses to postpone the cause; and what then? Bar. Why then the case must come on. Ber. And what will be the end on't? Bar. That knows the duke. Carlo. But what ought it to be? Bar. What the great duke wills. Carlo. Why so? Bar. Because that must be. Ber. She was a bold girl, when they forced her to the church, to refuse to give her hand there, and claim the protection of the curate. Bar. He was a bolder man to have anything to say to so mettlesome a piece of stuff. Carlo. And to refuse a count! Bar. Her cause will not thrive the better for that; unless, indeed, the duke be wroth with the count, for honourably affecting a commissary's ward. Leon. [Aside.] You seem intent on their discourse? Lor. [Aside.] I am so. Ber. You saw her, Bartolo, did you not? Bar. Yes, I was passing by, when they were forcing her into the church, and followed them in. Carlo. Is she as handsome as they say? Bar. Humph!—handsome?—Handsome is this, and handsome is that. I could sooner tell the absence of beauty than the presence of it. Now thou art not beautiful; but dress thee like a duke, and it might change thee. Thou that art an ugly craftsman, might become a beautiful duke. Notwithstanding I think I dare pronounce her handsome—very handsome! nay, I will go further, and confess that, were she a countess, or duchess, I would call her the most beautiful woman in Mantua. Ber. But why wishes the curate to have the cause postponed? Bar. To wait for a learned doctor of the law, for whom he has sent to Rome, but who has not yet arrived, though hourly looked for. Carlo. What! must one send for law to Rome? Bar. Yes, if one cannot find it in Mantua. Carlo. Cannot one find law in Mantua? Bar. Not if it be all bought up. There's not a legal man of note whom the count has not retained; so was the curate forced to send for his nephew to Rome—a man, it is reported, of great learning, and of profound skill in his profession, though hardly yet out of his nonage. Leon. [Aside.] You colour, signor! 'Tis of you he speaks? Carlo. Fears he to come to Mantua, or what? Bar. 'Tis thought the brigands have detained him—a plague upon the rascals! A word in your ears, signors. You all know that Bartolo is a loyal man? All. We do, Bartolo. Bar. Said I ever a word against the duke? All. No. Bar. You are right, signors; nor would I, though the duke were to hang every honest man in Mantua; for is he not the duke?—and is not Bartolo a loyal man! Now if I speak of the duke's cousin, whom the brigands, they say, have killed, speak I against the duke? All. No! Bar. Is't treason to say “a pity that he was killed?” All. No! Bar. Ah, signors, had he succeeded his father, he would have made a proper duke. Is this saying anything against his cousin that is the duke? All. No! Bar. I warrant me, no! Catch Bartolo talking treason! Who says a word against the duke? he dies, as Bartolo is a loyal man! But fare you well, signors. The trial comes on at noon—and noon will soon be here. Ber. We go your way. Bar. Come on, then. Remember I said not a word against the duke. [Bartolo and others go out. Leon. Of you he spoke—was it not so? Lor. It was. Leon. You come to Mantua to plead the cause Of this fair damsel. You were here before, But that the brigands intercepted you,— Your hurt, but my advantage, whose escape, Long time their captive, you contrived. And now, To prove my friendship more than wordy vaunting— I have the power to serve you. Take me with you. Your clerk, you said, opposing vain resistance, The hot-brain'd robber slew. Suppose me him. I have a smattering of his vocation, A notion of the mystery of yours; And I would hear, by their own lips recited, This worthy priest and beauteous damsel's cause, For reasons which—you smile? Lor. A thought just cross'd me. Leon. I know thy thought—'Tis wrong!—'Tis not the heat Of youthful blood which prompts—You smile again? Lor. Your pardon.—If I did, you have to thank The quickness of your apprehension. Leon. Mark me!— I have loved my last—and that love was my first! A passion like a seedling that did spring, Whose germ the winds had set; of stem so fine, And leaf so small, to inexperienced sight It pass'd for nought,—until, with swelling trunk, And spreading branches, bowing all around, It stood a goodly tree! Are you content? This was my sadness, signor, which the sight Of my dear native city briefly banish'd! Which thy misgiving hath brought back again; And which will be the clothing of my heart, While my heart calls this breast of mine its house. Lor. I pray you, pardon me! Leon. I pray you, peace! Time presses.—Once again, have confidence, And take me with you to your uncle's home. More than you credit me, I may bestead you. Wilt take my hand? Lor. I will! Leon. Have with you, then! [They go out. SCENE II. —Antonio's House. Enter Antonio and Pietro. Ant. What lacks it now of noon? Piet. An hour or more. Ant. No chance of his arrival!—This delay Perplexes me! Is it neglect?—I thought His answer would have been his presence here, Prompt as my summons; yet he neither comes Nor sends excuse. 'Tis very strange! She holds The same sedate, collected carriage still? Piet. She does, and native seems it to the maid As her fair brow, wherefrom it calmly looks, As from its custom'd and assuréd seat— A gentleness that smiles without a smile— For 'tis the sweetness, not of cheek, or lip Alone; but every feature—every act— Delights the heart that's near her. Silence is Her favourite mood, yet ne'er repels she converse, While every theme hath one unvaried close— A blessing on your reverence. Ant. Poor girl! She owes me nought. Why do I serve my Master, If not to do his bidding? Is it but To hold the crook? Nay, but to use the crook! To be, indeed, the shepherd of the flock— Wakeful and watchful—pitiful and faithful— My charitable life, and not my title, The badge and warrant of my sacred calling! She was afflicted, persecuted, and I succour'd her!—I, standing at the altar! Beneath my Master's roof! His livery, Blazon'd, as ne'er was earthly king's, upon me! What could I less? Piet. Fails he to come, for whom Your reverence looks, to plead the damsel's cause; Must it perforce go on? Ant. It must; and I Myself will be her advocate, before The haughty duke! For problems of deep law, Will give him axioms of plain truth; and paint Her thrilling grievance—to the life; with tears, Which, Pity seeing, shall to every heart That owns its influence, her cause commend, And gather tears to aid them! Enter Stephano. Ste. May it please you, Two strangers, craving audience, wait below. Ant. Admit them! 'Tis my nephew! Worthy Pietro, Have all in readiness, that we appear Before the duke when cited. [Pietro goes out. Enter Leonardo Gonzaga and Lorenzo. So, Lorenzo! Lor. Save you, my reverend uncle! Ant. Now a week I've look'd for you—but waive we explanations. Thou'rt come!—and to the business that has brought thee:— I have possess'd thee of the damsel's cause In all its bearings—Art prepared to plead it? Lor. I am, so please your reverence;—but, with us, That evidence is best which is direct. That the Count Florio seeks the damsel's hand,— That wills her guardian she bestow it on him,— That she resists her uncle and the count,— I know; but not the cause of her dissent. Children to guardians should obedience pay; A match, so lofty, warrants some enforcement, Which, not on slight grounds, should the maid resist. Ant. Ground know I none, save strong aversion. Lor. Pray you Vouchsafe us conference with the maid herself. Her deposition shall this gentleman That's come with me—my trusty clerk—set down. Ant. I'll bring her to you;—but, I charge you, boy, You keep in mind you are her advocate; For she, indeed, of those rare things of earth, Which of the debt that's due to it, rob Heaven, That men set earth before it, is the rarest! Then guard thee, nephew!—rather with thine ears And tongue discourse with her, than with thine eyes, Lest thou forget it was her cause, not she, That summon'd thee to Mantua! Lor. Fear me not! [Antonio goes out. Leon. A service of some danger, it should seem, Your reverend uncle has engaged you in; And, by his pardon, for your safety, uses Means which your peril more enhance than lessen. The soldier that is taught to fear his foe, Is half o'ercome before he takes the field. Lor. Is't from your own misgivings you doubt me! Leon. No!—As I said before, my heart is safe— Love-proof, with love!—which, if it be not, signor, A passion that can only once be felt— Hath but one object—lives and dies with us— And, while it lives, remains itself, while all Attachments else keep changing—it is nothing! I used to laugh at love, and deem it fancy. My heart would choose its mistress by mine eyes; Whom scarce they found before I sought a new one. I wooed not then the beauty of the soul— The passing loveliness which lodgeth there— A world beyond the charm of face or form! I found it! When or where—for weal or woe— It matters not! I found it!—wedded it! Never to be divorced from that true love Which taught me love, indeed! Lor. You wedded it?— Then was your passion blest? Leon. No, Signor, no! Question no further, prithee! Here's your uncle! Enter Antonio and Mariana. Ant. Lo, nephew! here's the maid, To answer for herself! Lor. [To Leonardo.] She's fair, indeed! Description ne'er could give her out the thing, One only glance avows her!—Prithee, look! Leon. Show her to him who has not seen the fairest! Remember, signor, Time's no gazer, but A traveller, whose eye is on his road, And feet in motion, ever! Noon's at hand! Lor. I thank you. Note my questions—her replies. Your guardian—Is he your relation too? Mari. No.—Would he were! That stay had needs be strong, Which failing, we've none other left, to cling to. Leon. Oh, music!— Lor. What's the matter? Leon. 'Twas a bird!— Whose throat, for sweetness, beggars all the grove! Yea, of its rich and faméd minstrel makes A poor and common chorister! Lor. Hear her! You'll have no ear for any other bird: Look at her, and you'll have no ear for her, Your trancéd vision every other sense Absorbing!—Gave you promise to the count? Mari. None! Lor. Nor encouragement? Mari. Such as aversion Gives to the thing it loathes! Lor. Have you a vow Or promise to another?—That were a plea To justify rejection. You are silent. And yet you speak—if blushes speak—and all Confess they do. Come, come, I know you love! Tell me, I pray, the story of your love! That, thereon, I may found my proper plea To show your opposition not a thing Of fantasy, caprice, or frowardness; But such as all men should commend you for. Prove it the joint result of heart and reason, Each other's act approving. Was't in Mantua You met? Mari. No, signor, in my native land! Lor. And that is— Mari. Switzerland! Lor. His country too? Mari. No, signor, he belong'd to Mantua. Lor. That's right!—You are collected and direct In your replies. I dare be sworn your passion Was such a thing, as by its neighbourhood Made even piety and virtue richer Than e'er they were before. How grew it? Come, Thou know'st thy heart! Look calmly into it, And see how innocent a thing it is Thou fear'st so much to show.—I wait your answer. How grew your passion? Mari. As my stature grew, Which rose without my noting it, until They said I was a woman. I kept watch Beside what seem'd his death-bed. From beneath An avalanche my father rescued him, The sole survivor of a company Who wander'd through our mountains. A long time His life was doubtful, signor, and he call'd For help, whence help alone could come, which I, Morning and night, invoked along with him.— Thus 'gan our souls to mingle! Lor. I perceive. You mingled souls until you mingled hearts? You loved at last.—Was't not the sequel, maid? Mari. I loved indeed! If I but nursed a flower Which, to the ground, the rain and wind had beaten, That flower of all our garden was my pride! What then was he to me, for whom I thought To make a shroud; when, tending on him, still, With hope, that, baffled still, still lost not heart, I saw at last the ruddy dawn of health Begin to mantle o'er his pallid form, And glow—and glow—till forth at last it burst Into confirméd, broad, and glorious day! Lor. You loved, and were beloved? Mari. To say I was, Were to affirm what oft his eyes avouch'd, What many an action testified—and yet— What wanted confirmation of his tongue. But if he loved—it brought him not content! 'Twas now abstraction—now a start—anon A pacing to and fro—anon, a stillness, As nought remain'd of life, save life itself, And feeling, thought, and motion, were extinct! Then all again was action!—disinclined To converse, save he held it with himself; Which oft he did, in gloomy mood discoursing, And ever and anon invoking Honour— As some high contest there were pending, 'twixt Himself and him, wherein her aid he needed. Lor. This spoke impediment! Or he was bound, By promise, to another; or had friends Whom it behoved him to consult, and doubted; Or 'twixt you lay disparity, too wide For love itself to leap. Mari. I saw a struggle, But knew not what it was!—I wonder'd, still, That what to me was all content, to him Was all disturbance; but my turn arrived. At length he talk'd of leaving us! At length, He fix'd the parting day!—but kept it not— How my heart bounded!—then I knew how low It had been sinking. Deeper still it sank When next he fix'd the day to go; and, then, It sank, to bound no more! He went, indeed! Lor. To follow him, you came to Mantua? Mari. What could I do but follow him, with whom My heart had gone; and, with it, everything— Cot, garden, vineyard, rivulet, and wood, Lake, sky, and mountain—e'en my father, signor,— Could I remain behind? That father found His child was not at home; he loved me, signor, And ask'd me, one day, whither we should go? I said, “To Mantua.” I follow'd him To Mantua!—to breathe the air he breathed, To walk upon the ground he walk'd upon, To look upon the things he look'd upon, To look, perchance, on him! perchance to hear him, To touch him!—never to be known to him, Till he was told, perhaps, I died, his love. Lor. I pray you, signor, how do you get on? I see you play the woman well as I! And, sooth to say, the eye were stone itself, From which her story could not call a tear! How get you on? indite you word for word As she delivers it? How's this!—The page As blank as first you found it!—All our pains Have gone to lose our time! Leon. I have a gift Of memory, signor, which belongs to few. What once I hear, stands as a written page Before me; which, if question'd, I could read Letter for letter.—You shall have anon The proof of this. I have a friend or two I fain would snatch a word with—That despatch'd, I'll meet you at the duke's, and bring with me The damsel's story, word for word set down, And win your full content; or give you leave To brand me an impostor, or aught else A man should blush to pass for! Will you trust me? Lor. I will. Leon. You may, for you shall ne'er repent you. I'll bring you aid you little count upon. [Aside.] [Goes out. Ant. Nay, nephew, urge your friend to stay. A space You have for brief refreshment; and, in sooth, You want it, who, from travel just alighted, Must needs to business go. Lor. Detain not him! Some needful avocations call him hence. I wait your pleasure, uncle. Ant. Daughter, come. Some effort has it cost to tell your story, But profit comes of it. Your cause is strong. Your vows, which virtually are another's, Heaven doth itself forbid you give the count! Is't not so, nephew? Lor. There I'll found the plea, Which to the conscience of the duke I'll put. Knows he, whom, at his death—which I'm advised Took place in Mantua—your father named Your guardian—knows the commissary this, Which thou hast now related? Mari. Not from me. My father's death was sudden.—Long time since! He and the commissary were mere acquaintance. What pass'd between them, save the testament Which left me ward unto the commissary, I am a stranger to. Lor. Since you came hither Him have you seen, for sake of whom you came? Mari. No! Lor. Nor hast clue direct, or indirect, To find him out? Mari. No, signor. Lor. And how long Have you sojourn'd in Mantua? Mari. Two years. Lor. And is your love the same? Mari. Am I the same? Lor. Such constancy should win a blessing. Ant. Yes! And strange as 'tis, what seems to us affliction Is oft the hand that helps us to our wish. So may it fall with thee—if Heaven approves! [They go out. END OF ACT I.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. SCENE I. —Hall of Justice in the Duke's Palace. On one side Bartolo, Bernardo, Carlo, and others; on the other, Lords and Ladies, &amp;c. &amp;c. Bar. Silence, signors! Keep order! The parties in the cause are coming—Here they are! Enter Mariana, leaning on Antonio, attended by Lorenzo; after them the Count Florio, and various Doctors of the Law. Bar. That is the maiden; and that the curate, upon whom she leans. Bern. And where's the count? Bar. Yonder, surrounded by the Doctors of the Law. Bern. The maid is very fair! Bar. Yes, for a burgher's daughter. Hush! The duke approaches. The cause will straight come on. Enter the Duke Ferrardo Gonzaga, and Attendants. [The whole assembly rise. Fer. Your seats! your seats! [The assembly sit. Bring on this cause! Who answers for our friend, The count? Advo. My lord, so please you, I. Fer. Proceed. Advo. The question lies between the count, and this, The guardian of the maid—whose froward act Your highness is possess'd of—on the one side; The maid herself, and that, the reverend man, Who countenances her resistance, on The other. Hereupon the count defends His right unto the maiden's hand—the will Her father left—the promise of the man Therein, declared her guardian, unto whom Behoves her choice to bow—for choice herself The maid, of right, hath none.—This were the case, Proposed her guardian to affiance her To one in rank as far beneath the maid As is the maid beneath the count. But lo The difference! By this alliance gains The maid a consort of a rank so high And wealth so broad, he were pretender fit To the hand of any maid in Italy! Such is our cause. In the first place, the right To give away the maid: and in the next That right, exerted for her highest good. Bar. He is a fair spokesman—The duke deliberates. Lor. My friend is lost, almost as soon as found. He has deceived me. No! he comes at last, And keeps indeed his promise, if he brings Such friends as these to back us! Enter Leonardo Gonzaga as Clerk to Lorenzo; followed by several persons of distinction. Bar. Observe you, signors! Are not those who just now entered, relatives and friends of him that were the duke, had not mishap stepped in 'twixt him and his father's seat? Ber. They are. Bar. Do they abet the maid? You see they take their station round her.—They are not wont, of late, to frequent the palace. Ber. Peace! The duke is going to speak. Fer. Count, on what plea claim you the maiden's hand? Florio. Her guardian hath affianced her to me. Fer. Speak you, her guardian,—states the count the fact? Hugo. He does, so please your highness! Fer. What's her age? Hugo. She lacks a year of her majority. Fer. Her rank? Hugo. Her father was a burgher. Fer. Wealth Has she been left? Hugo. What, charily enjoy'd, From manual labour might, perhaps, exempt her. Fer. And stoops the count so low to be despised— Rejected—spurn'd! For shame! The maid be given Back to her guardian's custody; and if Obedience be refused, let him enforce it! The cause is judged. Lor. Your highness' pardon, but The other side's to hear. Fer. Who's he that speaks? Lor. The counsel for the maid. Fer. Let him be wise, And not gainsay our pleasure.—It is told! The cause is over—finally adjudged. Lor. How far your highness' power extends I know! Yet though it reach unto my life, that life I hold to be my good, and husband not A minute longer than it ministers Unto mine honour's profitable use. The duty which I should discharge in vain,— Not through its own demerit, but defect In him, whose will availeth more than right,— I leave undone:—but 'gainst the power protest Which makes me—servant unto justice—slave Unto oppression. For the pangs that wring That maiden's heart, be answerable thou, Not I! Ant. Your highness— Fer. Peace! I will not hear thee, father! Ant. But Heaven will hear me! Lo! I do call upon it For judgment on the man who wrongs this maid! And surely as I call 'twill answer me,— And speak to thee—be thou that wicked man— When power thou hast no longer to cry “Peace!” Fer. That wicked man! Ant. O, poverty of earth— That men do deeds which win them evil names, And spurn the names, but not the deeds which win them! What Heaven commands me speak, I dare to speak! Suffer'd the maid, from any, violence, Should he not die? What callest thou the deed Which would condemn her to a loathéd bed? Think'st thou there's virtue in constrainéd vows, Half-utter'd—soulless—falter'd forth in fear, To purge the nauseousness of such a deed, That Heaven won't smell the damning odour on't? And if there is, then truth and grace are nought! Then sanctity is nought! yea, Heaven itself! And in its empyreäl essence lies No savour of its sweetness! Fer. Peace, I say! Ant. Thou canst not bid the thunder hold its peace— Why criest thou peace to me?—Nay, bid me speak— That thou mayst bear to hear the thunder speak— The herald, earth-accredited of Heaven— Which when men hear, they think upon Heaven's King, And run the items o'er of the account To which he's sure to call them. Fer. Dread my power! Ant. Dread thou—the power from which thou hold'st that power! Proud man, I brave thee where thou sitt'st, and in The ear of earth and heaven denounce the sentence Which gives that spotless maid to violation! Fer. I'll hear no more!—The cause is judged—the maid Her rightful guardian take! Mari. [Advancing to centre.] And if he does, He takes a corse! Lo! death is at my lips; [Taking a small phial from her bosom. The hand or foot that offers to approach, Commits a murder! In this phial bides The bane of fifty lives! Pass but a drop, Were now the sexton told to dig my grave, Were now his foot upon the shovel set, Ere he began, I should be ready for it! Who stirs? Lo, here I sink upon my knee! Or let the count his hateful suit forego, Or let my guardian his consent revoke, Or let the duke recall his foul decree, Or hence, by mine own limbs, I never rise! Fer. Why to the count this strong repugnance, girl? Mari. Giv'st thou thy oath that none shall stir, I'll tell thee. Fer. I give it thee. Mari. I am a maid betrothed! All but the rites, a wife! A wedded heart Although unwedded hand! Reflect on that! Making me give my hand unto the count, You make me give what is another's right;— Constraining me to an unrighteous act, Contenting him where it is base to wish, And doing violence to Heaven itself, Which curses lips that move 'gainst consciences! Fer. Lives he of whom you speak in Mantua? Mari. In Mantua, he told me he did live. Fer. What! know you not the place of his sojourn? Mari. Yes! where he still sojourns where'er he is! Fer. And where is that? Mari. My heart! Though travels he By land or sea—though I'm in Mantua, And he as distant as the pole away— I look but into that, and there he is, Its king enthroned, with every thought, wish, will, In waiting at his feet! Fer. This is the mood— The fantasy—of girlhood! Do we hold Our power on sufferance of a baby-maid, Who mocks us with a threat she durst not keep! Secure her! Mari. Lo, the phial's at my lips! Let him who would commit a murder, do it! Had he a thousand hands to wait upon thee, The slightest movement of this little one Would make them useless all! Leon. My Mariana! Fer. She has dropp'd the phial! Leon. [Coming forward.] Stir not, on your lives! My Mariana! Mari. 'Tis he! Leon. It is, my love! 'Tis he who won thy heart, not seeking it! 'Tis he whose heart thou wonn'st, not knowing it! Who saw thee rich in all but fortune's gifts, And—servant unto men, though lord of them— Balanced their poor esteem against thy wealth, Which kingdoms could not match! Accountable To others, never I reveal'd the love, I did not see the way for thee to bless; As only thou wouldst bless it! Now that way Is clear!—Is open!—lies before me straight, Without impediment, or anything Which, with the will, I cannot overleap! And now, my love before! my love till now! And still my love!—now, now, I call thee wife, And wed thee here—here—here—in Mantua! Fer. Remove that slave who knows not where he is! Leon. Descend, great duke, who know'st not where thou sitt'st! Fer. Where do I sit? Leon. Why in thy cousin's seat! Fer. He's dead! Leon. He's not! He lives, and claims his seat, Back'd by his kinsmen, friends, and every one That owns a loyal heart in Mantua! [Throws off his gown. Do you not know me, cousin? Fer. Leonardo! Leon. Six years have we been strangers, but I see You know my father's face, if not your cousin's. Fer. I do, and yield to you that father's seat. Leon. Cousin, the promptness of your abdication Invests it with a grace to which we bow. We'll spare your sight the pain of our accession, And pray that with the parties in this cause— I mean the count and guardian of the maid— You now withdraw, and at your former mansion, Wait intimation of our further pleasure. I would not have you speak, so please you, now; When we confer, it must be privily. Yet out of honour to our common blood, Well as in pledge of no unkind intent, Your hand before we go! [They shake hands. Fer. Nay, let me speak At least my welcome, and my thanks, your highness— Before I take my leave. [Ferrardo, Florio, and Hugo, go out. Ant. Rise, signors, rise! Live, Leonardo, duke of Mantua! Leon. We thank you, friends! This welcome is of the heart. For you we take this seat. Thou reverend man. Be confessor unto the duke of Mantua; Thou man of law and honour, be his friend, And advocate of state; and both of you Lead hither that abstracted maid! But no! That office should be mine. [Descends.] In Italy Shines there a brow on which my coronet Could find so proud a seat? My Mariana, Wilt be my bride? Nay, do not tax thy tongue With that, thy looks have scarce the power to speak! Come!—Share my throne with me! Come, Mariana! The consort of the duke of Mantua! [She faints in his arms as the scene closes. SCENE II. —A Room in the Palace. Enter Cosmo and Courier. Cos. The duke? which duke? I know now not which; we have had two within the last ten minutes; I know not which duke it is thou wantest. Cour. I tell thee, the duke of Mantua. Cos. Is thy business public or private? Cour. Dost thou not see I come from Rome? There are great matters on foot, which it behoves the duke to know; and herein, if I mistake not, he is apprised of them, Cos. Nay, then, thy business is public, and of course concerns the reigning duke. Cour. Of course it does. Cos. I'll bring thee to him. Cour. Lead on! Enter Bartolo, Bernardo, and Marco, meeting them. Bar. Signor Cosmo! Cos. Don't stop me, Signor Bartolo. I'm in haste. Bar. Nay, a word—only a word. Who is that? Cos. A courier from Rome. Bar. I was right, Bernardo. Save you, signor. You come, I hear, from Rome. How are they all at Rome? Cour. Well, signor—all that I am acquainted with. Bar. They have a great deal of news in Rome. Cour. Sufficient, signor. Bar. One likes to hear the news. Cour. I trouble myself little about it. Bar. That is because 'tis your vocation to hear it. Nobody is in love with his vocation. Now 'tis the reverse with me. I mind the news as much as I mind my meals. Pray you, signor, have mercy upon a hungry man, and tell me the news from Rome. Cour. Great news, signor,—there is going to be a war. Bar. A war! A war, Bernardo—Cosmo—and pray you, signor, with what power are they going to war? Cour. With the French. Bar. The devil! Cour. You will have a fine opportunity for showing your valour, signor. Bar. I thank you, signor. I was never an ostentatious man, I am content to be a man of valour—I don't care to show it; but I thank you for the news. Come along, Bernardo—Carlo. A war, signors, a war! What a glorious thing is a war! Here's news! [They go out severally. SCENE III. —The Vestibule before the Ducal Palace. Enter St. Pierre. St. P. Here be my seat upon the palace-steps, Although they hang me from the portico! Have a heart, Poverty, thou hast nought to lose,— Nor land, nor mansion, nor habiliments, That thou shouldst play the craven! That thou call'st Thy life—what is it?—Hunger!—Nakedness! A lodging 'neath the eaves! ten scornful looks For one of pity; and that one a proof That thou'rt an anguish to the sight of men! Then what carest thou for cuffs? Nay, cuff again, That they may fall the heavier!—satisfied That he who brains thee, does thee, Poverty, A thousand times the good, he does thee ill!— Come—keep the portal of the mighty duke, Who made thee what thou art; nor let him pass Till from his fear thou wring'st an alms, or else A quick release obtainest from his wrath! Fer. [without]. Be sure thou keep'st the hour. St. P. Talk of the fiend, They say, and here he comes! Here comes the duke. Fer. [Entering.] Hoa!—Clear the vestibule! St. P. Great duke, descend! No retinue impedes your gracious way! Here is no throng,—for Poverty sits here Craving a foot of your fair palace-steps, For lack of better resting-place. Fer. Who are you? What do you here! St. P. Wait, mighty duke, an alms! I could not ask the humble craftsman one, I used to cuff him;—nor the tradesman one, I used to make him doff his cap to me;— Nor yet the merchant one, he gave me way, Or I gave him my shoulder;—nor the courtier, My hilt I handled soon as he touch'd his;— In brief, I pass'd by all degrees of men, To beg an alms of the most gracious duke! Fer. Here! St. P. What! a florin? give it to the street, For the abaséd eye of vagrantry! I make no livelihood of raggedness! Fer. Scorn'st thou my gift? St. P. Thy gift and thee, great duke! Nay, frown not! Choler will disturb digestion, And mar thy pleasant afternoon's repast; Leave wrath to me, who have not tasted food Since Wednesday last,—nor look for meal to-day. Fer. Why, that would buy thee five! St. P. What were five meals— To starve anew! I should not light on thee A second time to beg another alms! Thou wouldst take care to shun me! Better starve Outright,—for, saving thee, most gracious duke, There's not a man in Mantua I'd stoop To ask a ducat of. Fer. Well, there's a ducat. St. P. It will not do! Fer. What hoa there! St. P. Softly, duke! Hush! better far that we confer alone, For thy sake! mark!—for thy sake, gracious duke! Fer. What means the villain? St. P. Right, duke, that's my name! What do I mean? I'll tell thee what I mean. My wardrobe wants replenishing; if puffs The wind, my hat is like to lose its crown; My robe is all the covering I have; My shoes are minus nearly all the soles! And, then, I fain would change my lodgings, duke— Which, sooth to say, is e'en the open street— Less spacious would content me; last of all I would be master of a larder, duke, Would serve me, at the shortest, good a month, That I might live so long at ease, and see If aught turn'd up would make it worth my while To shake a hand with the fair world again, And live on terms with it.—Most gracious duke, Give me a hundred ducats! Fer. Dost thou think To rob me at the palace-gates! St. P. Who robs, Provides him weapons. I have none, great duke, Nor pistol, rapier, poniard,—not a knife: I parted with them, one by one, for food! For weeks have they been provender to me! Think upon that, great duke, that at a meal Spend'st twenty times their produce; and, so please you, Give me a hundred ducats! Fer. Thou art mad! St. P. No, by St. Jago!—Try me! I have the use Of my wits. I'll neither leap into a flood, Nor run into a fire! I can tell The day of the week, the month of the year, the year; I'll name you which are fast-days, which are not— But that's no wonder, I have kept so many— To balance this, I'll name you feast-days too! I'll write and cipher for you;—finally, I'll give you all the fractions to a jot, That lie in a hundred ducats! Servants enter from the Palace. Fer. Seize him! St. P. Stop [Menacing the servants, who pause. Till you have learn'd my name! Imports you much To know it! 'Tis affix'd, most gracious duke, To certain documents which only wait Your leave to see the light. Fer. What documents? St. P. Shall these o'erhear, or private be our speech? Fer. [To Servants.] You may withdraw a pace or two. St. P. You see, Great duke, I am not mad! Fer. What documents? St. P. One memorandum for a hundred crowns, For whipping one that dared offend your grace. I paid me with the pleasure of the task, Nor ask'd the hire, but kept the document. Another, for enticing to a haunt Of interdicted play, a wealthy heir. I scorn'd the hire for that,—though shame to say it, I did not scorn to earn it—but I kept The document.—A third— Fer. Enough—St. Pierre! St. P. Aha! you know me now? Fer. How changed thou art,— I ne'er had known thee! St. P. It were strange if want Look'd like abundance—which was never yet Akin to it. Fer. Here take my purse! St. P. 'Tis rich— Holds it a hundred ducats? Fer. Twice the sum— I want thee—that suffice! St. P. That does suffice. Fer. Get thee habiliments more rich than these,— Appointments, too, fit to consort with them; And come thou to mine ancient mansion straight. St. P. I must dine first. Fer. Eat sparingly. St. P. Indeed! I see thou want'st me then—I'll go and dine. Fer. Thy tears are not a pledge for continence. St. P. I'll dine upon a crust! Nay, fear me not— What time am I to take in all?—Two hours? Fer. The half might serve thee. St. P. Well; we'll say the half,— The quarter shall suffice me, if thou wilt! Fer. Make it as brief as may be. St. P. Work that's sweet Is quickly done!—I'll come in half an hour. [Goes out. Fer. That which had been my bane, an hour ago, Is now my medicine! This fellow owns A quick and subtle wit; a reckless daring; And hath a winning tongue, withal, and 'haviour. Easy of conscience, too—yet, still, contrived To keep some credit with the court. I know The use of him. He has been mine, and mine He needs must be again. So!—Suddenly He quitted Mantua, and left with none A clue to find the cause,—nor lack'd he then Wardrobe or ducat! Misery has changed him;— Her work abundance quickly shall undo! I know the use of him, and I will use him. Enter Count Florio. Now, count, what brings you hither? Florio. News, my lord, That's sure of welcome! A brief honeymoon Hath fate decreed your cousin! Scarce he takes The seat were fitter yours, and weds his bride, Ere comes advice the states must take the field Against the power of France. Fer. Good news indeed! Florio. Forthwith he hies to Rome— Fer. Most welcome news! Florio. And by entreaty of his council, you— As next in rank and lineage—are appointed Our regent in his absence. Fer. That's the best news. Florio. His heart—that was against you—softened Or by prosperity, or your ready yielding, Or giving way on sudden exigence; He offers reconcilement, by your friends, And, straight, you are invited to his presence. Fer. I come!—Great news!—I thank you!—Glorious news! [They go out. END OF ACT II.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. SCENE I. —An Apartment in the Palace. Enter Ferrardo and Florio. Fer. Another victory! Florio. So the rumour runs. Fer. Why Fortune plays the minion to him!—does His wish not only, but anticipates it! Chief after chief she thrusts aside, that he May head the war; and, when he takes the lead, Her moody favour, wavering before— Alternate sun and cloud—shines fully forth With strong and steady beam. Have many fallen? Florio. A host, 'tis said, on either side. Fer. No wound, No hurt for him? Florio. 'Tis so reported. Fer. So— Florio. Though twice he changed his charger—one disabled, The second wounded, mortally! Fer. And he As safe, as sitting in his ducal chair! Why dangers, that are thorns to other men, For him convert to flowers! Florio. The duchess still Persists in her seclusion? Fer. There, again, I'm baffled! Would she mingle with the court, His home of peace might compass for me what I vainly hope for from the field of war,— The downfall of his rule! I know my cousin; For thoughtless boyhood often shows the man Which wary manhood hides. A sense he has, That's sickly tender to the touch of shame. I have seen him, at a slight imputed fault Colour to flame—anon grow ashy pale— The dew in drops upon his forehead starting,— His tongue without its use—his mouth agape— His universal frame, vacuity Of action and of power,—and, anon, The glare and din, and tossing of the tempest! To wound his honour to the quick, would be To sting his core of life! Florio. Thou couldst not hope To wound it through his wife; whose love for him, Gives, in his absence, all things to neglect! Her bounding palfrey cannot woo her forth! The palace vibrates with the dance, and still She keeps her chamber, like a lone recluse. Music, howe'er you try, can't tempt her from it, She shuns its harmony as though 'twould jar! She visits no one—no one she receives! What chance of practising upon a wife, Who for an only absent lord, observes A sterner widowhood, than many hold In honour of a dead one!—Why do you smile? Fer. To think, to what account a little art Might turn a little swerving, in a case Of self-denial, carried thus like hers To the admired extreme! I would St. Pierre Had kept his restless spirit more in check, Paid to my will submission, as he used, And not enlisted in my cousin's train, But stopp'd in Mantua! My plans were laid, Were sure, and long ere this had been matured, But for his wilfulness. Florio. Of what avail Had been his presence here? Fer. I should have found A use for him! Ne'er knew I yet the ear He could not keep a hold of, once he caught it. That fellow, with his tongue, has won more hearts Than any twenty men in Mantua, With tongues, and forms, and faces! I had contrived To throw him in her way! Florio. There were no chance— Fer. I know,—but I could make appearances Supply the place of facts—especially In her husband's absence—so that confidence, Itself, would construe guilt where no guilt was! So would I show her to the eyes of all, That, though she were like snow itself, new fallen, Men would believe her spotted! Florio. If 'twere true That he it was who hither brought the news Of this new victory— Fer. Saint Pierre? Florio. Saint Pierre. Fer. 'Tis so reported? Florio. 'Tis. Fer. Then, prove it true, Before he is an hour in Mantua He must be stripp'd of every ducat! Mind, Of that must thou take care! [Shouts. What mean those shouts? Florio. They herald, doubtless, the approach of him That's bearer of the news. Fer. Be it Saint Pierre, The moment he alights away with him To a house of play!—You are his master—Haste! Your beckon he will answer readily, As the game-bird his welcome challenger! Florio. I'll do my best. [Goes out. Fer. So do.—The confessor? [Looking out. The cards come round to me! A score to one, I hold the winning hand.—His reverence, I have contrived to make at last my friend. Your churchman dearly loves a convertite, And he believes me his. A kindly man, But, once confirm'd in error, positive; And, from his calling, credulous to weakness, Touching the proneness of the flesh to sin. I have well examined him. Enter Antonio. Your blessing, father. Ant. Thou hast it, son. Fer. Whence come you now? No doubt From the performance of some pious deed— The shriving of some sin-oppresséd soul— The soothing of some sorrow-stricken heart— Or sweet relieving of some needy child Of merciless adversity. Ant. No, my son,— But from a trespasser that's, yet, unshriven; A daughter who has swerved, and on whose soul I had thought as soon to find the soil of sin As tarnish upon new-refinéd gold! A wife, who in the absence of her lord, Lived like thy cousin's wife; with means to bless Desires incontinent, a miracle Of self-secluded, lonely chastity. Fer. He comes in the very vein! You spoke just now Of my cousin's wife. There's news of my dear cousin, And, with submission, I would recommend Her grace to show herself, to-day. Methinks, If only for her health, she keeps herself Too much alone. Ant. So have I told her grace. Fer. Indeed! I marvel that she perseveres In the face of your admonishment! More strict Would she be thought, than you, a holy man, Would counsel her to be? Forgive me, father, If 'tis uncharitable in me, but I never loved extremes! Your constant weather Is still the moderate, father. Storms and calms Are brief. Ant. You are right, my son. Fer. I had been pleased Less had she shown her fondness for her lord. Love, of its own fidelity assured, Ne'er studies the display on't! Ant. Nay; she loves Her lord. Fer. And yet 'tis the predicament Of love to wane upon possession. Where I note an over-acted guardedness, I still infer a consciousness of weakness; And look to find—and seldom look in vain— Some sudden giving way! Besides, in passion, Excess is sign of its decaying, rather Than lasting. Thus the frantic widow, who To-day would make her husband's grave her bed, A few months hence, enjoys another bed Beside another husband! Maids, new-wed, Who gloried in their choices, and with reason, Leave them for new ones, for no reason, but Because they are new! By love of novelty Is human happiness too oft ensnared. Mere novelty!—the common tempting bait, Which gives, too oft, a worth to worthless things; Luring us to forsake the good we have For something else, which, mostly, proves our bane! I would not doubt my cousin's wife, but wish She moved, like other honourable dames, Secure in her own truth. The life she leads Something too much, methinks, solicits note, Not by design, but in appearance only. Yet had she more confided in herself, Lived like herself—appear'd among the court— Courteous to all—particular to none, Save those to whom, next to her lord, she owes Her highest duty—my reliance on her Were stronger! Is't uncharitable, father, To say so?—speak, and frankly—Wherefore else Put I my heart into your saintly hands? Ant. Nay, son—I think you speak in charity, As one who blames through love. We'll see the duchess, And jointly recommend to her a life Of less severe restraint. Fer. I thank your reverence! You know I owe her grace some small amends, And trust me, father, gladly would I make them! [Exeunt. SCENE II. —Ante-Room to the Chamber of the Duchess— A Window overlooking the Street. Enter Floribel. Flo. A merry life for twenty-one to lead, And in a woman too! from morn till night Mew'd in a lonely tower! Heigho! It is My lady's will. I would she had been born In Mantua, where wives their husbands love In reason! Well!—We'll live in hope she'll learn In time. I used to lead a dozen kinds Of life, in a day!—Now, in a dozen days, I lead but one! Ere breakfast, was a nun; Then play'd the housewife; after that, to horse; Then, dinner o'er, a Naiad on the lake, Floating to music! Evening changed the scene Again; and night brought on the closing scene, With open casement, list'ning, by the moon, The melting cadence of the serenade! Now morning, evening, noon, and night are nought— But morning, evening, noon, and night. No change Save in their turns and names! What I get up, I last throughout the day, and so lie down; The solitary lady of the duchess! And how I bear it! Wonderfully! Past Belief! I'll do't no longer! If I do, Then never was I born in Mantua. [Shouts. What's that?—[Looks out.]—The city all astir!—A crowd Before the palace—I will ope the casement:— I feel as I could leap into the street! [Opens casement. Enter Mariana. Mari. What do you at the casement, Floribel? Flo. Look from it, madam. Mari. That I see. At what? Flo. At crowds of happy people, madam,— Some standing, others walking, others running; All doing what they list—like merry birds At liberty. Mari. Come from the casement!—Shut it. Flo. Nay, rather you approach it, madam! Do! And look from't too—There's news, and from your lord! Look—There's the courier! Mari. [Approaching the window.] Where? Flo. That cavalier, Who tries to pass along, but cannot, so The people press upon him. Enter Ferrardo and Antonio. Fer. [Aside to Antonio.] At the casement! Mari. Who is that cavalier? Flo. The courier, madam. Mari. I know—but who is he? His family—His name? I cannot take My eyes from his face! who is he? Can't you tell? I have a strange desire to know his name! Fer. [Aside to Antonio.] Father! Flo. I'll fly and learn it. Mari. Do, good girl! And soon as you have learn'd, fly back again! [Floribel goes out. Fer. [Aside to Antonio.] I pray you mark, but speak not— [Approaches the window on tiptoe, returns, and speaks to himself. It is Saint Pierre! Incredible! [To Antonio.] It is the courier, father. Of whom they were discoursing. Mari. I have lost him! He has enter'd the palace—I should like again To see him—I should like to speak to him! Fer. [Aside to Antonio.] My life on't, she will hold a court to-day— Accost her, father. Ant. Benedicite Fair daughter. Mari. Father!—What, his grace!—I think, Or I mistake, there's news from my dear lord? Ant. Madam, there is, and happy news.—Your lord Has won another victory! Fer. All Mantua Would have a heart of overflowing joy, Would but your highness notify your will To let it speak its happiness, and pay Congratulations to you.—May I hope You do not pause from doubt? Your confessor Approves your highness somewhat should relax Your life of close seclusion. Mari. [After a pause.] Be it so. Fer. [Aside to Antonio.] I told you, father— [Floribel re-enters. Flo. Madam, he is call'd— Fer. St. Pierre—You mean the courier That brought these happy tidings? Mari. Floribel, I want your aid. My lord, and reverend father, Soon as my toilet's made, I shall descend. [Mariana and Floribel go out. Ant. What kind of man is this? Fer. A kind of devil, That grasps you with his eye—as fascinate Serpents, 'tis said, their prey.—A tongue to match, In glosing speech, the master-fiend himself! I'm troubled, father. Was the dame you spoke of Indeed a pattern, like my cousin's wife, Of saintly self-denial? Ant. Yes, my son. Fer. I grieve we urged her highness with her presence To grace the court to-day. I tremble for her. Come! Shall I tell thee something—No, I will not! When you can lead the sea, you'll sound the depth Of woman's art.—Would you believe it—No— While there's a doubt, suspicion should be dumb. Think'st thou I would have back'd her guardian's suit But that I knew he had his reasons?—'Sdeath! What am I doing?—Come, your reverence, The man of proper charity condemns not, Except upon enforcement. All is right! [They go out. SCENE III. —A Room in the Palace. Enter Florio and Cosmo. Florio. Where is the regent? Cos. With the confessor In the chamber of the duchess. Nay, my lord, He has quitted it, and is here. Florio. You may withdraw. [Cosmo goes out on one side. Enter Ferrardo on the other. Fer. Well? where's St. Pierre?—I thought you were together! Florio. We were, but parted for a moment. Fortune, In the task you set me, kindly has forestalléd me. Halting to bait within some miles of this, He met a friend, whose hand he scarce had shaken Ere the ready dice were out. In brief, your grace, He has enter'd Mantua ducatless!—Of my own counsel I broke to him your need of his assistance, Touching your cousin's wife—and promised him— A pledge, I knew your highness will redeem— Replenish'd coffers, would he undertake To pleasure you. Fer. Will he do it? Florio. Sullenly, But fully he consented—He is here. Fer. Retire a little. [Count retires. Enter St. Pierre. Welcome, St. Pierre!—welcome my friend!—I'm glad To see you. St. P. Would you take me for a knave? Fer. What mean you? St. P. Would you take me for a knave? Fer. No. St. P. No? Why then I'm fit to do your pleasure. Come!—To my work!—When am I to begin? Fer. The matter? St. P. I have lived an honest life These six months—Knavery is new to me! I set about it feverishly. Fer. What! Is't knavery to net a pretty woman? They catch birds so. St. P. Pshaw!—I am past the time. Fer. Mind is the brightness of the body—lights it, When years, its proper but less subtle fire Begins to dim. Man, I could tell thee how She conn'd thy visage from her casement; sent Her confidante to learn thy name: seem'd lost At losing thee! Win thou discourse with her, And hold it when thou winn'st it.—'Twill content me Thou make her but the object of remark. Away! Go lean on yonder pedestal, And watch thy opportunity to draw Her notice towards thee—Thy obeisance does it; Or anything most slight; her lord's success Is plea that you accost her. She is new To the court,—a stranger to its law of distance, Which 'tis expedient thou infringe! Couldst master Aught that's about her person—say a ring, A brooch, a chain, in curiosity Besought of her for near inspection, then Mislaid or dropp'd—not to be found again,— It were a thousand ducats in thy hand! 'Sdeath, man, hold up thy head, and look at Fortune, That smiles on thee, and asks thee to embrace her! What dost thou gaze at? St. P. Who is that? Fer. The duchess. St. P. Indeed, a lady of surpassing beauty! Fer. An irksome task, methinks, I've set you—Come! About it!—To thy post! St. P. Surpassing fair! [Goes out. Fer. [Looking after him.] He has caught her eye already,—excellent! He bows to her! Does she curtsey?—yes, i' faith! And to the very ground! You're welcome, sir! He speaks to her! How takes she his advances? She entertains them! They pass on in converse! Hold it but on, she's lost! [Florio comes down. Do you see? Florio. So soon! I wish him fortune! As I loved her once, I even loathe her now! Fer. Could you believe it? He crosses her, and straight her eye is caught! He speaks, and straight is master of her ear! Solace for baffled hopes! From infancy I loathed my cousin for his elder right, And leap'd into his seat with lighter spring, Than he, I thought, had miss'd it! He returns, And I, with humbled brow, in sight of all Descend, that he may mount! I'll pay him shame For shame;—but he shall have't with interest! Where is the confessor? I must to him. Mix with the company, and point to them The eye of questioning remark. With looks Speak sentences!—More surely does not raise One wave another wave, than marvel grows On marvel.—Interjections have a world Of argument! “Incredible!”—“Odd!”—“Strange!” Will make a thousand hearers prick their ears, And conjure wonders out of commonest things! Then with commiseration you may do A murder easily! “Alack!” “Alas!” Use daggers that seem tears.—Away! Away! For now or never is the golden hour! [They go out. SCENE IV. —Another Room in the Palace. Enter Mariana and St. Pierre. Mari. I thank you for the story of your travels: You make me wish to see the world, of which Such wonders you relate. I think you said, You were but newly come to Mantua? You must have been in Mantua before, then, So many seem to know you? St. P. I have been Before in Mantua. Mari. 'Tis very strange, But when I saw thee first, I felt as if We were of old acquaintance! have we met Before? St. P. No, lady. Mari. It is very strange, You never were in Switzerland? St. P. Oh, yes! It is my birth-place. Mari. Ay! so is it mine. 'Tis a dear country! never met we there? St. P. No. Mari. No? 'Tis odd! How many years is't, since You were in Switzerland? St. P. Good fifteen years. Mari. So long! I was an infant then—No—No! We have not met before—'Tis odd!—At least You are my countryman! [Holding out her hands to him. [Visitors have been occasionally crossing the stage during this scene, observing Mariana and St. Pierre. Enter in the background, Antonio and Ferrardo. Fer. Had I been told it, I would not have believed it. Mari. Switzerland Is a dear country! Switzerland! St. P. It is The land of beauty, and of grandeur, lady, Where looks the cottage out on a domain The palace cannot boast of. Seas of lakes, And hills of forests! crystal waves that rise 'Midst mountains all of snow, and mock the sun, Returning him his flaming beams more thick And radiant than he sent them.—Torrents, there, Are bounding floods! and there the tempest roams At large, in all the terrors of its glory! And then our valleys! Ah, they are the homes For hearts! Our cottages, our vineyards, orchards!— Our pastures studded with the herd and fold! Our native strains that melt us as we sing them! A free—a gentle—simple—honest people! Mari. I see them, signor,—I'm in Switzerland! I do not stand in Mantua!—Dear country! Except in one thing, I'm not richer, signor, Than when I was a child in Switzerland, And mistress only of this little cross. [Pressing the cross to her breast. St. P. [anxiously]. Your pardon, lady! Pray you let me see That cross again! Mari. Right willingly. Ant. [Coming forward.] Hence, signor! Mari. Father! Ant. I pray your grace retire—but first Command that libertine from the apartment! St. P. [Sternly surveying alternately Antonio and Ferrardo.] I go, your reverence, of mine own accord. [Goes out, followed by Ferrardo. Mari. Father, what meant you by that word which turn'd My very blood to ice? Ant. Behoves your highness To keep your eye upon your husband's honour, If not upon your own! Mari. How! Ant. Heaven alone Can judge the heart.—Men must decide by actions, And yours, to-night, to all have given offence. Mari. Offence! Ant. A woman hath in every state Most need of circumspection;—most of all When she becomes a wife!—She is a spring Must not be doubted; if she is, no oath That earth can utter will so purge the stream That men will think it pure! Mari. Is this to me? Ant. Women who play the wanton— Mari. Father! Ant. Daughter! That look and tone of high command become Thy state indeed— Mari. No, father, not my state— They become me!—State greater—higher far, One who deserved that name I blush'd to hear— And thou, a reverend man, shouldst blush to use— Might fill! but though it were an empress's, I would defy her in her breast to seat The heart that's throned in mine! If 'tis a crime To boast—Heaven pardon you—you have made me sin! Ant. Behoves us heed appearances? Mari. No, father, Behoves us heed desires and thoughts, and let Appearances be what they may be!—You Shall never shape them so, that evil men Will not their own construction put upon them. Father, it was the precept of my father. Ant. He little knew the world. Mari. He knew what's better, Heaven, and the smile of his own conscience! What have I done? Ant. Given cause of scandal, daughter. Mari. How? Ant. By a preference, so mark'd, it drew The eyes of all upon you. Mari. Evil eyes, To see defect in frank and open deeds! The gentleman appear'd mine old acquaintance— That drew me towards him:—I discover'd now He was my countryman—that makes allies Of even foes that meet in foreign lands, Then well may couple strangers!—He discoursed Of my dear native country, till its peaks Began, methought, to cleave the sky, as there They stood before me!—I was happy—pleased With him that made me so—With what a straw You raise a conflagration! Ant. You forget You are not now the commissary's ward, But consort to the duke of Mantua.— You're a changed woman. Mari. No, i' faith, the same! My skin is not of other texture—This, My hand, is just the hand I knew before! If my glass tells the truth, the face and form I have to-day, I had to-day last year! My mind is not an inch the taller grown Than mellowing time hath made it in his course! And, for my heart—it beats not in my breast, If in the ducal chair of Mantua, 'Tis not the same I had, when I did sit On some wild turret of my native hills, And burn with love and gratitude to Heaven That made a land so fair, and me its daughter! Ant. Hear me!—You have wrong'd your lord! Mari. I have wrong'd my lord! How have I wrong'd my lord? Ant. By entertaining With mark'd and special preference, a man Until to-day a perfect stranger to you. Mari. Go on! Ant. He is a libertine! Mari. Go on! Ant. A woman who has such a friend, has nought To do with honest men! Mari. Go on! Ant. A wife Has done with friends!—Her heart, had it the room Of twenty hearts, her husband ought to fill,— A friend that leaves not space for other friends, Save such as nature's earliest warrant have To house there! Mari. You are right in that! Go on. Ant. A court's a place where men have need to watch Their acts and words not only, but their looks; For prying eyes beset them round about, That wait on aught but thoughts of charity. What were thy words I know not; but thy acts Have been the comment of the court to-day; Of eyes that gaped with marvel—groups that stood Gazing upon thee—leaning ears to lips, Whose whispers, were their import known to thee, Had stunn'd thee worse than thunder! Mari. So! Go on. Ant. What if they reach thy consort? Mari. What! Ant. Ay, What? Mari. He'll spurn them as he ought; as I do spurn them. For shame! for shame! Me thou shouldst not arraign, But rather those who basely question me! Father, the heart of innocence is bold! Tell me how comes your court to harbour one Whom I should blush to speak to? If its pride Be not the bearing that looks down on vice, What right has it to hold its head so high? Endure, at court, what, from our cottage door, My father would have spurn'd!—If that's your court, I'll be nor slave nor mistress of your court! Father, no more! E'en from thy reverend lips I will not hear what I've no right to list to! What!—taint my lord with question of my truth! Could he who proved my love on grounds so broad, As I have given my lord; on grounds so mean Descend to harbour question of my love— Though broke my heart in the disseverment, He were no longer lord or aught of mine! Father, no more! I will not hear thee! Frown— Heaven does not frown!—To Heaven I turn from thee. [Goes out. Ant. This confidence offends me.—Swerving virtue Endureth not rebuke! while that, that's steadfast, With smiling patience suns the doubt away, Wherewith mistrust would cloud it! 'Tis not right— An eye so firm-resentful—speech so lofty— Mariana enters unperceived, and kneels to him. An air of such defiance— Mari. Father! Ant. Daughter! Mari. I am thy daughter! O my father, bless me! Were I the best, I were not 'bove thy charity, Were I the worst, I should not be beneath it! Ant. Thou hast my blessing. Mari. Ere I break my fast To-morrow, father, I'll confess to thee, And thou shalt know how little or how much I merit what thou givest me! so, good night! Ant. Good night, fair daughter. Benedicite! [They go out severally. END OF ACT III.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT IV. SCENE I. —A Street. Enter Bartolo, Bernardo, Carlo, and others. Bar. Hush, signors! speak softly! 'Tis treason, and we may be hanged for it.—So the matter stands! The young duchess, I fear me, is an old sinner—and what a saint she looked! Let no man marry a wife who looks like a saint. Please Providence, mine shall be as ill-favoured as Satan! Ber. 'Tis the way to make sure of a wife. Bar. It is, signor. Such is the value of beauty. Let any man take his own case. Now myself, for instance—How many a scrape should I have avoided, had I been born as ill-favoured as some people! He is the happiest man, be assured, whom no one has reason to envy.—Now, thou art a happy man, Bernardo. Ber. I thank you, Signor Bartolo. Car. But when happened this? Bar. I told you it happened about half an hour ago. Ber. Prithee, signor, tell it us again? Bar. Well then, draw near; but remember you are sworn to secrecy. All. We are, we are! Bar. You know I am fond of the news—though I have as little curiosity as any man. Well, where can one get news if not at the palace? So, to the palace I went this morning, as I do every morning.—Few persons have constant admittance at the palace, as I have, for they are people of discretion at the palace, and suffer not rogues that come peeping and prying —spies and blabbers—scoundrels of no trust or honesty— but I have admittance to the palace, for they know me. Ber. Well! Bar. When I entered it, all was confusion! One running this way, another that way. One whispering this person, and every one with wonder in his looks! I warrant you I did not look the figure of wonder too! Car. Go on, good Bartolo. Bar. Well: I happen to have a friend or two at the palace —Lucky for me that I have so—There is no doing anything there without a friend.—“Would that such a one was here,” said I to myself; and scarce had I said it, when in runs the very man I was thinking of. Ber. Excellent! Bar. Just in the nick of time, or I verily believe I should have died of wonder. At the same time, every one knows I am the least curious man in all Mantua. Well, in runs my friend, just in the nick of time.—“The matter?” cried I. “Treason,” whispered he, “but I dare not breathe it for my life.”—“What is it?” said I; “I'll be as mute as the marble under my feet.”—“You shall hear it,” cried he, “for you are a lad of discretion, and have a guard upon your tongue.” You see, signors, that I have a character at the palace! Ber. Go on, Bartolo. Bar. Well! as I told you before, the substance was this— and nothing more nor less. Julian St. Pierre, who has lately returned to the court, and for his wild practices would have been dismissed from it many a year ago, but for the favour of the duke Ferrardo,—this Julian St. Pierre, I say, was half an hour ago discovered stealing from the ante-room that leads to the duchess's chamber, and secured upon the spot. Ber. and Carlo. Go on! Bar. I have no more to tell you—You know as much as I do.—But be discreet! A silent tongue betokens a wise head! I cannot stay with you longer. I have some friends in the next street to see; others in the street beyond!—more again, in the street beyond that! I know not how many I have to see! I have the whole city to see. Now be discreet!— remember I got it as I give it, on promise of secrecy—Be discreet!—discovered half an hour ago, stealing from the ante-room that leads to the duchess's chamber!—Be discreet, I say —A silent tongue, a wise head!—Be discreet—Be discreet! [They go out severally. SCENE II. —Ante-Room, leading to the Duchess's Apartment. Enter Mariana. Mari. Or I have had sweet dreams, whose fleeting forms Have but the charm of their fair visit left; Or by my couch hath some good angel watch'd, And on my lapsed unconscious spirit breathed The balmy fragrance of his heavenly presence; So light my heart, as it were clad with wings And floated in the sun! My lord—My lord!— How is this? 'Tis strange! At thought of my dear lord, My soaring heart hath dropp'd at once to earth. It is the incidents of yesternight The thought of him recalls!—I feel as though I fear'd my lord!—Or is't the world I fear? The world which yesternight I dared defy; But now begin to think upon its snares, And feel, as they beset me round, so thick, I cannot step, but in their fatal mesh, I'm straight entangled! Wherefore feel I thus? My heart as heavy as, just now, 'twas light! Enter Antonio. My confessor! Here's comfort! Welcome, father.— For mercy's sake what's this? I welcome thee, And thou, to me, giv'st aught, but an all hail! Why what's the matter?—Can I be awake? Father, I need kind looks and words to-day,— My heart is sick!—O earth, how sick! I look'd For thee to bring me peace—Alack—Alack! Why do your eyes of mercy turn to swords? Only they pierce where feeling is more quick! Father, be pitiful! 'Tis not the proud And forward wife that braved thee, yesternight; But thy repentant child that kneels to thee! Ant. Repentance is a grace—but it is one That grows upon deformity—fair child To an unsightly mother!—Nor, indeed, Always a grace!—'Tis oftentimes—too oft— The bootless terror of the stranded soul, When ebbing passion leaves it all alone, Upon the bleak and dreary shoal of sin!— So is't of different kinds—Which kind is thine? Mari. Father! Ant. Thy lord!—Thy lord! Mari. What of my lord? Ant. Nay, rather answer thou, what of thy lord? I know that he is duke of Mantua, Noble and, fair, and good!—hath high allies!— Heads the proud war, in wisdom, as in arms, The foremost plume of the van!—and, crown of all, I know he thinks himself, of every wish Which heaves that breast of thine, the paramount, The happy lord! Mari. He thinks himself— Ant. And presses The 'larum-curtain'd couch of restless war, In hopes to change it for that downy one Whereon he left, as he imagined, safe, His dearest honour, by thy side reposing,— And little dreams that stain has reach'd it there! Mari. That stain has reach'd it there! Ant. You slept alone Last night? Mari. I slept alone?—Yes, Father! Slept alone! What idle words are these?—I slept alone? I know I slept alone last night!—the night Before!—the night preceding that!—alone? How could I otherwise than sleep alone, When my dear lord's away? Ant. Thou lookest— Mari. How? Ant. And speakest— Mari. How?—How do I look and speak? Ant. Like innocence. Mari. Doubt'st thou my innocence? Ant. They say, Thou didst not sleep alone! Mari. Who say so? Ant. All The palace. Mari. They!—I cannot speak the word, Which indicates the acting of a part, Unparallel'd in shame! Ant. Another part, The which involves a tenfold deeper shame, Men freely name, and lay to thy account! Mari. Art thou my friend? Ant. Hast thou not proved me so? Mari. I have! Forgive me that I question'd thee! But when I know my heart's supreme content In its own clearness—not as to act alone, But wish; nor wish, alone, but thought of sin; When I know this, and think of yesternight; And, worse than yesternight, turns out to-day, I 'gin to think the world is made of hate, And doubt if thou—e'en thou!—art not my foe! Oh, do not be my foe! indeed—indeed The helpless maid that hung upon thy robe To beg protection, and received it there; Unchanged in all—save that she's now a wife, And, as a wife, more bound than e'er to Heaven— In strait more piteous than she knelt in then, Clings, kneeling to it now! What's said of me? And on what ground?—for not the robe I hold Less conscious is of ground for foul report, Than I am! Ant. Left thy chamber any one This morning, whom thy honour should forbid To cross its threshold? Mari. No! Ant. Art thou sure? 'Tis said There did—The man was seen! Mari. The man? Ant. The man! Departing from this ante-chamber!—this, Which none except thy lord, myself, and those Who wait upon thy person, may frequent. Mari. Who was the man? Ant. Seen in the very act Of slinking from your door! Mari. Who was the man? Ant. The same that, last night, held thee in discourse! Mari. I am lost! Ant. You're lost? Enter Ferrardo, Lorenzo, Cosmo, and others. Fer. Your highness, with your leave, We'll pass into your chamber. [Ferrardo and Lorenzo pass in, the others remain. Ant. You are lost! Mari. I'm lost—but I am innocent! Fer. [Returning with Lorenzo.] My lords, You know who owns this scarf? Cos. It is St. Pierre's! Fer. 'Twas found beneath the couch—our advocate Of state it was that saw it there. Are ye satisfied? Cos. We are, your grace; but would 'twere otherwise. Ant. Find earth where grows no weed, and you may find A heart wherein no error grows. I thought Thy heart without one—thought it was a garden So thickly set with flowers, no weed had room To shoot there! Who would sin, who knew how shame Confounds the trespasser! I cannot stay,— My tears be vouchers for me that I loved her, And fain would doubt the lapse I must allow. [Goes out. Fer. My worthy friends, follow the confessor. I wish to speak in private with her highness. [Lorenzo, Cosmo, and Lords, go out. I am your friend!—You are accused of treason,— The grounds against you are conclusive ones; Your judges will be those who will not spare! And soon and summary will be your trial; The penalty of your offence is death! You are now a prisoner—I pity you— Would save you!—Will!—As soon as dusk sets in, In a convenient spot without the town, To which in secret you shall be convey'd, I shall have horses waiting— [Mariana shrieks and starts up from her knee, on which she had remained in a state of mental stupefaction. Hush! Mari. For flight? Fer. For flight!—By dawn you shall be far away From Mantua. Mari. At dusk? Fer. At dusk. As soon As dusk begins to fall, expect me here, And thou shalt have supply of gold enough To pay the charges of thy journey—yea, Maintain thee in abundance where thou wilt. Mari. I may depend upon thee? Fer. Fear me not. Remember now—At dusk. Mari. I will!—At dusk. [They go out severally. SCENE III. —Another Chamber in the Palace. Enter Ferrardo. Fer. His heart is in my power as 'twere a thing, Which in my hand I held and I could crush With a grasp! Nor can it 'scape my power! her name— That flower of woman's pride, which ta'en away, From a bright paragon she turns a thing For basest eyes to look askant upon— Is blasted past the power of friend or lover To bring it to its pristine hue again. Now for St. Pierre—He also must, to-night, Take leave of Mantua. [Unlocks door.] Come forth, my friend! Enter St. Pierre. Dost thou not know me? What an air is this? A king could not a loftier assume At high offence! 'Twas thus with thee last night. Nothing but moody looks, until the count With much persuasion woo'd you to our feast. I wonder'd at thee! St. P. Are we alone? Fer. How's this? St. P. Are we alone?—Where are the craven minions That overpower'd me in the corridor, And at thy bidding dragg'd me hither? Fer. Pshaw! Art thou no wiser than to heed them? know'st not 'Twas done on my instruction—mine—thy friend's? St. P. Are we alone? Fer. We are alone. St. P. Art sure That door is unattended? that no minions Watch it without? Fer. I am. St. P. Wilt lock it? Fer. [Locking it and returning.] There! St. P. [Springing upon him.] Villain! Fer. What means this violence? St. P. You struck me! When I contended with the recreants— Who smite this moment what the one before They fawn'd upon!—across their arms you struck, And fell'd me with the blow!—Now take it back! Fer. Stop! you'll repent it if you strike! St. P. I tell thee, I ne'er received a blow from mortal man But 'twas return'd with interest!—One by one I have parted—thanks to thee!—with all those virtues Which wise and holy men inculcate! Not One grace I now am master of, save one That ever was my own! That single grace Remains—the growth of nature—the true shoot Abuse could not eradicate, and leave The trunk and root alive!—that virtue—manhood! Still lives, within my heart, disdain of threat, Defiance of aggression, and revenge For contumely.—Come!—You struck me!—Come! I must have blow for blow! Fer. [Drawing his dagger.] Let fall thy hand Upon my person—lo, my dagger's free, And I shall sheathe it in thy heart! St. P. I care not, So I die quits with thee! Fer. I would not kill thee, So don't advance thy hand! Nay, listen first, And then, if thou wilt, strike me!—Strike!—abuse Thy friend, who, when he struck thee, was thy friend As much as he is now, or ever was; Who struck thee, but that he might seem thy foe, To hide how much, indeed, he was thy friend! Nay, if the lack of quittance for a blow Which but in show was one—for the intent Establishes the act—must make us foes, My dagger's up!—Now give a blow, indeed, For one that seem'd but one. St. P. I take't, in thought, And let thy person unprofanéd go! Fer. No animal, so wild, it will not tame, Save man! Come, calm thyself!—Sit down!—As yet Thou know'st not whether to caress thy friend Or tear him! Shouldst thou tear him? Come, sit down. There's not a man in Italy save thee Would fret, and he the master, all at once, Of good ten thousand ducats! Still a brow! Odd's man, be merry!—Rub thy hands and laugh! Thou art rich!—look there! [Showing a casket. St. P. How came I yesternight To sleep in the chamber of the duke? And why This morning when I left the ante-room Was I assaulted by thy minions? Fer. Pshaw! Enough, thou slepst where thou didst sleep, next chamber To the duke's wife, and thereby madest thy fortune. For every ducat of the sum I named Is thine—but render me one service more! St. P. Name it. Fer. Just write for me in boasting vein, Confession thou didst pillow yesternight There, where the honour of the duke forbids That head save his should lie. Why do you gaze? 'Tis easily done! St. P. It is. Fer. It takes but pen and ink, and here they are; Make use of time! The hour that is not used Is lost, and might have been the luckiest, Converted to account. What ponder'st thou? St. P. The manner best to execute thy wish. I'm hardly in the vein! 'Twould put me into't Wouldst thou relate the means whereby I came To lie in the duke's chamber? Fer. 'Twould retard thee! St. P. No! It will rather help me. When I write, Ofttimes I miss the thought, too much intent On finding it,—looking at something else, Lo, there it stands before me of itself! How came I in the chamber of the duke? Fer. You supp'd, you may remember, with the count And me? St. P. I do. Fer. 'Twas plann'd between us. St. P. Well? Fer. And for our end we kept the revel up— I mean the count and I—for, as I said Before, thou wast not in the joyous vein,— Till all the palace had retired to rest. St. P. My lord, may't please you stop—My thought has come. [Writes. A fair commencement! excellent! most fair! You see how much you help me!—There!—Go on! You revell'd till the palace was at rest— What then? Fer. Why, then, finding thee jealous still Of the kindly grape, we drugg'd your cup; and, when The potion work'd, convey'd you in your sleep,— To sound or stir, profound as that of death,— Into the chamber of the duke—of the key Of which I keep a duplicate—and there We laid you in his bed. St. P. Break off again [Writes. While I go on!—You see, my lord, how great A help you are to me! It comes as fast As though I were inditing what your grace Rehearses to me.—So!—Most excellent! And now proceed again! Fer. Where left I off? St. P. How can I tell, intent on what's on hand, I list to you; but 'tis abstractedly, A man will sing and work; but more he heeds His work than song!—And yet I think, your grace, When you left off, was putting me—somewhere— To bed— Fer. You're right!—in the duke's bed! Thou slepst there, With a partition, only, 'twixt his wife And thee—and that made frailer by a door,— The lock of which I from its use absolved; And casting, 'neath her highness' couch, thy scarf, As proof of closer neighbourhood to her, Withdrew to feast on foretaste of revenge. St. P. Enough! Fer. Enough? St. P. Tut, tut! I only meant Your highness to break off, while I resume. My thoughts flow on, again—Better and better! Your grace,—a hundred ducats, I have done Almost as soon as you—[Writes and stops, again.]—Go on—What end Proposed your highness to yourself by this? Fer. To blast her name, and in the death of that Involve my cousin's life! Accordingly, By my direction wert thou watch'd and seized, And hither brought, as partner in a crime, Whose penalty is death!—which thou shalt 'scape!— 'Scape with enrichéd life—so ne'er again Thou show'st thy face in Mantua, and keep'st Thy counsel. St. P. [Writing.] Have you done? Fer. I have. St. P. And so Have I. [Peruses the writing.] A fair commencement! better far Continuation! and the winding up The fairest of the whole! Howe'er, of that Your highness must be judge. [Hands the writing, but suddenly checks himself.] 'Sdeath! here's a word I did not mean to write, for one I wanted! I needs must take it out,—I pray your highness Lend me a knife. Fer. I have not one. St. P. Well then Your dagger—if the edge of it is sharp. Fer. There 'tis. St. P. And there is the confession, duke; Sign it. Fer. Why this is my confession! St. P. Ay! Indeed! your highness. Fer. Word for word. St. P. You'll own I'm something of a clerk—I hardly hoped It would have pleased your highness! My lord duke, Sign the confession! Fer. Why? St. P. It pleases me. If that contents thee not, I'm in thy power, And I'd have thee in mine! Your highness sees I'm frank with you. Fer. Can it be you, St. Pierre? St. P. No—It is you!—and not the peasant lad, Whom fifteen years ago, in evil hour, You chanced to cross upon his native hills,— In whose quick eye you saw the subtle spirit Which suited you, and tempted it; who took Your hint, and follow'd you to Mantua Without his father's knowledge—his old father! Who, thinking that he had a prop in him Man could not rob him of, and Heaven would spare; Bless'd him one night, ere he laid down to sleep, And waking in the morning found him gone! [Ferrardo attempts to rise. Move not, or I shall move!—You know me! Fer. Nay, I'll keep my seat. St. Pierre, I train'd thee like A cavalier! St. P. You did—You gave me masters, And their instructions quickly I took up As they could lay them down! I got the start Of my contemporaries!—not a youth Of whom could read, write, speak, command a weapon, Or rule a horse, with me!—You gave me all— All the equipments of a man of honour,— But soon you found a use for me, and made A slave, a profligate, and pander of me! [Ferrardo about to rise. I charge you keep your seat! Fer. You see I do! St. Pierre, be reasonable!—you forget. There are ten thousand ducats. St. P. Give me, duke, The eyes that look'd upon my father's face! The hands that help'd my father to his wish! The feet that flew to do my father's will! The heart that bounded at my father's voice! And say that Mantua were built of ducats, And I could be its duke at cost of these, I would not give them for it! Mark me, duke! I saw a new-made grave in Mantua, And on the head-stone read my father's name:— To seek me, doubtless, hither he had come— To seek the child that had deserted him— And died here, ere I knew it. Heaven, alone, Can tell how far he stray'd in search of me! Upon that grave I knelt an alter'd man; And rising thence, I fled, nor had return'd, But tyrant hunger drove me back again To thee—to thee!—My body to relieve At cost of my dear soul! I have done thy work, Do mine! and sign me that confession straight. I'm in thy power, and I'll have thee in mine! Fer. Art thou indeed in earnest? St. P. Look in my eyes. Fer. St. Pierre, perhaps I have underpaid thee? St. P. Sign! Fer. I'll double the amount! St. P. Come, sign! Fer. St. Pierre, Will forty thousand ducats please thee? St. P. There's The dial, and the sun is shining on it— The shadow on the very point of twelve— My case is desperate! Your signature Of moment is most vital to my peace! My eye is on the dial! Pass the shadow The point of noon, the breadth of but a hair As can my eye discern—and, that unsign'd, The steel is in thy heart—I speak no more! Fer. Saint Pierre!—Not speak—Saint Pierre! St. P. Is it sign'd? Fer. [Writing hurriedly.] It is. St. P. Your signet, as a proof that I'm at large. Now take my station in that closet—No Attempt at an alarm—In, in, I say! Hold wind we'll make the port. [Opens the chamber-door—seems to recognise some one without, makes a profound bow, as though to the duke. I thank your highness! [Goes out. END OF ACT IV.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT V. SCENE THE LAST. —A Tent. Leonardo and Soldiers discovered. Leon. Indeed, a glorious close! Our brief campaign Has pass'd like sport upon a summer's day, Without a cloud—a game, where fortune lay All on one lucky side—and that was ours! Give order for the striking of our tents At earliest dawn—I'll but salute the sun, And straight for Mantua! [Soldiers go out. O sweet the sight Of his dear native land to him, who brings A brow, with honours laden, back to it! Dear Mantua, that twice has given me life; Once in the breath which first I drew in it, Now in the gift, without the having which That breath were given in vain! How does my wife? Bright crown of my bright fortunes! O, my heart— How does my love?—The plume of victory Though won, I wear not till I see it nod In the bright mirror of her glistening eye. When shall that be?—To-morrow?—Blest to-morrow! Would—would thou wast to-day! Enter Second Officer. Officer. Your cousin, and the nobles who compose Your highness' council, with your confessor, And advocate of state, attend without—in haste, and new From Mantua. Leon. The tidings of our truce Can scarce have reach'd them, yet? Bad news flies quick, I deem'd not good could boast so swift a wing. Admit them. Enter Ferrardo, Florio, Antonio, Lorenzo, and Nobles. Welcome, cousin—Welcome, all! Note of our victory, I see, has reach'd you; And ye are come to give me greeting, which I gladly should have journey'd to receive. But where's my duchess? She had been, methinks, A fair addition to your cavalcade— You might have brought her with you. [To Ferrardo, who drops his eyes. Strangers yet!— Nay, then, the fault, I'm positive, is yours. Had but you dropp'd a hint of your intent, Given but a glance of invitation to her; She would have ta'en it, as from a thoughtful friend, Given you her hand, and thank'd you for the leave To bear you company. Fer. Your highness' pardon; A man can't help his doubts, e'en if he would; And I have grounds, and solid ones, for mine. Leon. Fie, fie, offend in any other thing, And ere you ask you're pardon'd! Here are friends— Friends of my love's and mine—tried friends!—and, yet, Not friends in this—to leave my wife behind, Who loves me best; when they, in zeal of love Are here to give me joy of my high fortune. How does my lady, friend? [To Lor.] How does she, father? Why comes she not to greet me? You should be Her harbingers—a step or two before? Or bring ye charge from her to expedite My long'd return to Mantua? as if My heart were not remembrancer enough! For never speed me, Heaven, if life seems life, Until I stand in her sweet sight again. [Ferrardo and Florio whisper Why whisper ye? [Antonio and Lorenzo whisper. And ye do whisper, too— Hah! By your looks, I noted not before, Ye come to tell me of disaster!—Speak! The sum on't? Is it heavy?—What is it? Come, name me the amount! Is it my dukedom? Or what?—'Tis nothing of my wife?—Say that— And say ought else which stern misfortune wills! Blow wind! mount wave!—No rock to shut me thence, I see the strand to run my bark ashore, And smile upon my shipwreck. Fer. 'Tis of her We come to speak. Leon. 'Tis no mishap to her— For you appear to speak in wrath, not grief. If what you come to say affects reproach— Reproach of her! speak out!—Speak ye the truth, Ye cannot speak in anger! Fer. That our duty Permitted us to leave you in that mind! Leon. Pshaw! do thy duty!—be it duty—'Tis Beyond your power of other mind to make me. Fer. Thy lady is false to thee. Leon. [Drawing.] Thy tongue is false To thee!—It puts thy life in jeopardy; Recall thy words or die! Florio. My gracious liege, He speaks the truth! Leon. Thou too! Lor. Your highness' patience. What speaks your cousin, fain would I deny, But cannot. Leon. Sirs! I only doubt which way To point my sword! Ant. Your highness— Leon. What say'st thou? Speak out, thou reverend man!—There only wants Thy charitable tongue, to prove how prone Are mankind to allege defect, where e'en The shadow on't was never seen before! Say on!—Yet, ere thou speak'st convince thyself That she, who loved me, when a noteless man; And loved me still, when she believed me lost; And loved me on, when woo'd by rank and wealth; And, ere she'd yield to their enforcéd suit, Was ready to become the bride of death!— Convince thyself, I say, that finding me— Finding me still returning love for love, With rank, revenues, that she dream'd not of; And wedded to me, mistress of my all, This moment—Yet the very next, she swerved And cast herself, and me, and all away! Impossible!—Unimaginable! Now, Say on and shame thyself! Ant. My gracious liege, Restrain your ire at what you would not hear, And audience give to what you ought to hear. If facts, avouch'd by eyes, may be believed, I say, that would not say it—thou art wrong'd! Peruse that paper—There you have our grounds For saying what we say. Lor. O read, my liege! Think, 'tis our duty speaks, and what it says, Says at the cost of our unfeignéd love,— Which, sooner than mischance should undermine Thy towering happiness, would be itself The seaward mole, to meet the rushing wave And break its fury ere it bursts on thee! But wind and tide together setting in Will, sometimes, overwhelm all obstacles— So needs must fall this heavy surge on thee Which we let o'er, in drowning. Leon. I read it, sir, Not that I do fear it—or give credence to it. Fer. Your highness sees how hinges fact on fact. Leon. No!—I see nothing! Fer. Nothing! Leon. Not a jot That might not be contrived, and against which Improbability doth not set its face! My lord—my lord—you love me not—nor you— Nor you.—I doubt if any loves me here! I doubt all things but that my wife is true! I will to Mantua, this very hour, To crave her pardon that I listen'd to you. Fer. My lord, she's fled from Mantua. Leon. She is what? Fer. She's fled from Mantua, as also is Her paramour. Leon. Recall that word, or else Thou makest me do a murder! Is she fled? Cousin, thou murder'st me! Speaks he the truth? Gainsay him, and I heed not what ye say! Cousin, thou didst but hear that she was fled, Thou dost not speak from thine own knowledge? Fer. Else I had not spoken. Leon. Fled?—In company?— Fer. What else could I infer? Leon. Thou but inferr'st it, Come then, all's well!—Let her be fled or not, She has fled perhaps to friends, perhaps to me! Enter Second Officer, with Mariana. Second Officer. My liege, the duchess. Leon. Ha! I told you so! Welcome, my loved!—my wrong'd!—my innocent! Welcome, my loyal wife! Mari. My liege, stand off! Embrace me at the peril of your honour! Your cousin here?—The count?—Your confessor? And he?—and these the members of your council? My tongue may spare its labour then! Yet whose So fit to tell my husband, he's the lord Of a dishonour'd bed,—as hers, whose heart,— That ne'er admitted thought of man save him, Knew not its part that was not given to him, Before itself as dearer heart set him, Sun, earth, life, health, desire, knew nought but him,— Yet could not guard the jewel, paramount, Of him it loved so well, but by an act— Without a motive—monstrous to belief— Which reason unto madness would refer— Nay doubt that even madness' self could do! Whom it so loved, did spoil, and bring at once From proudest wealth to basest penury! Leon. No!—Thou didst never swerve!—Truth dwells in thee! Thou art all radiant with it! Mari. Not a doubt! My trusting lord! my loved and honour'd lord! [Throws herself at his feet. Leon. [Endeavouring to raise her.] Up to my heart! Mari. No—by thy love! Leon. I say I'll have thee up!—Thy place is here! Mari. [Preventing him.] My lord! What holds that paper?—Tell me, is it not My accusation? Let me see it. [Reads.] True From first to last.—The fact's not otherwise Than here set down. Wouldst take me to thy heart, And this against me? Leon. Yes! Mari. Nay, speak again, And think before you speak! Say that the duke, Your cousin, loves you not! Say that the count Still bears you grudge!—Say these, the members of Your highness' council, are suborn'd by them!— Here stand two honest men who take their side! Wouldst take me to thy heart, and this against me? Leon. I would. Mari. And if you would, you should not do it! Leon. 'Tis a plot! Mari. It is!— But thou, my lord, must prove it to be one! Else it hath oped a chasm, 'twixt thee and me, Which, till thou close it up, or bridge it o'er With stable-footed truth, that all may trust, May not be cross'd.—Leap it—and all is lost! Leon. Canst give me clue to find it out? Mari. Methinks I can. Thy cousin counsell'd me to fly, To 'scape, as he alleged, the penalty Of my imputed crime,—but, as I thought, To furnish of that crime conclusive proof!— Supplied me, too, with ample store of gold! Leon. Traitor! I see it all—and do not you? My cousin and my subject though thou art, To solemn mortal combat I defy thee! That from thy lips, at point of my true sword, Admission I extort of an attempt To slur my lady's honour!—for thy soul No shriving knows, no healing speech with priest, Till by confession it heaves off that sin. Come forth! Mari. No! no! let me be guilty thought, But, oh! in peril, place not thou thy life! Or let me prove, myself, my innocence By ordeal of poison or of fire. Do aught but put thy life in jeopardy! Leon. And she could injure me! Fer. It is the trick Of lapséd virtue to affect excess, Which sound desert would sooner suffer wrong, Than claim pretension to. Leon. It is the trick Of villany to lie! Come forth! Fer. Lead on! Mari. [Embracing his knees.] My lord! my lord! my husband! Leon. Loose thine arms! Mari. It is mine heart-strings hold thee, not mine arms. Wilt snap them? If thou wilt, thou hast a right, They are thine own!—but wilt thou use that right? Leon. Take her away! Mari. When fails our dearest friend, There may be refuge with our direst foe. [Rushing up to Fer. Oh! why art thou my foe? how lies my peace Between thy good and thee? Is it thy good To slay my peace? Wilt thou not look upon me? Alas! thine eyes are better turn'd away! For gazing on them, human as they are, I have a feeling of a heart of stone! And from my hopeless tears the spirit flies, That frozen on my lids I feel them hang! Thou rock! Affliction, did I plead to thee— I turn'd from thee, Despair! Leon. Come forth! Fer. Lead on! Enter St. Pierre behind. Mari. No way to hold thee from thy bloody purpose? Stop!—Thou wilt do a murder! Art thou sure Thy wife is innocent? Thou know'st not what Thou go'st to do! Whate'er befals, the sin Of all the deed 'tis I must answer for— The hapless wife that on thy house and thee Brought ruin!—Have compassion on her soul, If not upon thy own!—Yet hear me!—Stop— I'll put an end to all!—I am— Fer. Guilty! Mari. No! To save thy life—my own—and his that's heart Unto my life—I cannot speak the lie! Leon. And if thou couldst, I'd not believe thy tongue— Though Truth's as soon would lie. Fer. No tongue on earth Can clear her—She is false!—To eyes and ears Convicted!—She is an adultress! St. P. [Rushing forward.] Liar! She is as true as thou art false! Fer. A caitiff That robb'd me once, and put my life in peril— But I'll be quits with him! Leon. Prevent him! [Several interfere, but not until St. Pierre is wounded. St. P. Not Quite home, your grace—yet near, I hope, enough! Your highness, 'tis a dying man you hear; Your wife is innocent! Fer. A poor gallant That would not say as much! St. P. Your highness, read This paper!—Hold his grace! Fer. 'Twas forced from me. St. P. Only the signature, my lord—The rest Was voluntary—word for word, what fell From his own lips! Fer. You pass'd the night beside her— Alone—none near you—within whisper of her! Find pen to draw 'cross that! St. P. I pray your highness, Wears not your wife a little rustic cross, Carved by no craftsman's hand? Mari. I do!—the same I show'd thee when we spoke together. St. P. 'Twas Your brother gave it you. Mari. It was. St. P. I think, Some fifteen years ago? Mari. So many years Have pass'd since that dear brother gave it me. I was a child then—he almost a man! St. P. You woke one morning, did you not, and saw That brother standing, weeping by your bed: He bless'd you, put that cross upon your neck, Kiss'd you, and bade farewell to you, and went— You never saw him more. Pray you come near! O God! my mother's face! Mari. My brother—Ambrose! St. P. Yes, Mariana! Fer. It's a masque, your highness, They've got up to amuse you! Leon. Hence with him! The count too! [Soldiers bear off Ferrardo and Count. Mari. Brother, I said I knew thee! Thou forgott'st Thy sister's little face to woman's grown; But I remember'd thine enough to feel 'Twas something once had been familiar-dear! O that my memory had better kept What my heart treasured—thou didst prove how well! Wilt thou not speak to me? Hear'st thou, my brother? St. P. Our father's cottage, Mariana! Mari. Ha! Thou faintest! St. P. No—it is nothing, sister! What makes thee look so pale and vanishing? Don't go from me!—Alas—'tis I am going! I have confess'd myself! Pray for me, sister! Mine eyes have lost thee!—But I feel thee still, That's comfort!—yet—I have thee in my arms— Thou fadest too from them—fast! fast!—Thou art gone! [St. Pierre dies. END OF THE WIFE.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">EPILOGUE, WRITTEN BY CHARLES LAMB. SPOKEN BY MISS ELLEN TREE. When first our Bard his simple will express'd, That I should in his Heroine's robes be dress'd, My fears were with my vanity at strife, How I could act that untried part—a “Wife.” But Fancy to the Grison hills me drew, Where Mariana like a wild flower grew, Nursing her garden-kindred: so far I Liked her condition, willing to comply With that sweet single life: when, with a cranch, Down came that thundering, crashing avalanche, Startling my mountain-project! “Take this spade,” Said Fancy, then; “dig low, adventurous Maid, For hidden wealth.” I did: and, Ladies, lo! Was e'er romantic female's fortune so, To dig a life-warm lover from the—snow? A wife and Princess see me next, beset With subtle toils, in an Italian net; While knavish Courtiers, stung with rage or fear, Distill'd lip-poison in a husband's ear. I ponder'd on the boiling Southern vein; Racks, cords, stilettoes, rush'd upon my brain! By poor, good, weak Antonio, too, disownéd— I dream'd each night, I should be Desdemona'd: And, being in Mantua, thought upon the shop Whence fair Verona's youth his breath did stop: And what, if Leonardo, in foul scorn, Some lean Apothecary should suborn To take my hated life? A “tortoise” hung Before my eyes, and in my ears scaled “alligators” rung. But my Othello, to his vows more zealous— Twenty Iagos could not make him jealous! New raised to reputation, and to life— At your commands behold me, without strife, Well pleased, and ready to repeat “The Wife.”</field>
   </doc>
</add>