<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Boyce, Samuel</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Boyce, Samuel</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">boyce samuel</field>
      <field name="author_text">Boyce, Samuel</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">18th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1750's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V2.0772.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">[1752]</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460362</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Rover ; Or, Happiness at Last</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Rover ; Or, Happiness at Last</field>
      <field name="title_facet">rover or happiness at last</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">rover or happiness at last</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Rover ; Or, Happiness at Last</field>
      <field name="year_display">[1752]</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1752</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1752</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460362&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460362&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Boyce, Samuel&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;boyce samuel&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Rover ; Or, Happiness at Last&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;rover or, happiness at last&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;[1752]&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1752&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Boyce, Samuel&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Rover ; Or, Happiness at Last&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;[1752]&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872677-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv20772&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 18th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;18th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Rover ; Or, Happiness at Last&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 59 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: The rover.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Pastoral.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1752.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Unknown.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE ROVER; OR, HAPPINESS at Last.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">INTERLUDE I. SCENE I. COLIN. RECITATIVE. Sure we enjoy the happiest Lives of all, Who 'tend the Flocks, and ply the Rural Call! We dread no Change of fickle Fortune's Pow'r, But view Contentment ev'ry flying Hour. AIR. The various Beauties of Nature we see, And pass e'ery Season in Friendship and Glee; The Warblers, to cheer us, exult on each Spray, While Flowers their Fragrance around us display: We court our Nymphs kind, when they Wishes inspire, And center in them, the Delights we admire. RECITATIVE. But, ha! what Damsel bends her Steps this Way? Odso! this shou'd have been my Wedding Day! And hither Sylvia comes, forsaken Fair! To seek her Rover, with dejected Air. Wou'd I were somewhere from her Sight secure!— But what I can't avoid I must endure. SCENE II. To him, Sylvia. RECITATIVE. Sylvia. Deceitful Colin! Colin. So! Sylvia. Ungrateful Swain! Colin. What is it makes thee, Charmer, thus complain? Sylvia. What means this cold Neglect? did you not swear This Morn shou'd view us join'd a happy Pair? Colin. Ha! ha! my Sylvia, canst thou be so weak To build a Hope on aught a Youth shall speak? When ev'ry Sense was fondly lost in Joy, When all the Lover did my Soul employ, Ten thousand tender Things perhaps I spoke, As Pleasure form'd 'em, from my Tongue they broke; That then I made this Promise, I'll allow,— But must the Man perform the Lover's Vow? AIR. When first I sought your Heart to move, And urg'd my warm Address, You swore, by all the Pow'rs above, I ne'er shou'd gain Success: But long that Vow was not your Care, You did to Love incline: Then is it mighty strange, my Fair, That I shou'd, too, break mine? RECITATIVE. Sylvia. And must that Kindness meet with this Return? Is that the Cause which I must ever mourn? Sure I have to the falsest of Mankind O, shame! my Honour, and my Heart resign'd. Colin. Soon as the welcome Dawn spreads o'er the Skies, This doleful Ditty takes its awful Rise: Remains untold till Sol his Course has run, And often ends not with the setting Sun: Some other Subject, Sylvia, let me hear; The Cuckoo's Tone must tire the list'ning Ear. AIR. Consider discreeetly, ere Wedlock you choose, That nothing but Death can the Bondage unloose; As Fancy directs, you may now sport and play, And clasp a new Lover with e'ery Day; But then, One alone all your Beauty obtains, And who'd give their Freedom, to rattle in Chains? Six Months I have lov'd; 'tis too soon too believe In Man, that's so cunning, and prone to deceive; First judge well my Temper, my Humour, and Parts, For joining of Hands often seperates Hearts. And when I perceive no Objection remains I'll marry, and joyfully rattle my Chains. RECITATIVE. Sylvia. How shou'd we act, our certain Fate to shun? If coy we are disdain'd, If kind undone. AIR. When soft Ideas fill the Mind With pleasing am'rous Pain, What can a harmless Virgin do? Resistance is in vain: For, ah, to hear the deep-fetch'd Sigh, Behold the streaming wat'ry Eye, And not, through Sympathy, comply, Was past the Art of Sylvia. The Maid who never yet was try'd Knows not her Virtue's Pow'r; For oft' the Victim Conq'ror turns, In one unguarded Hour. Me, me! ye Nymphs forbear to blame! But shun the Rock that wrecks my Fame. Go strait, Betrayer, and proclaim To all, the Fate of Sylvia. RECITATIVE. Colin. That I'm above; conceal'd my Transports dwell; For know, sweet Maid, I scorn to kiss and tell. Now let's divide, my Sylvia, and repair You to some kinder Youth, I to as kind a Fair. Exit. SCENE III. SYLVIA. RECITATIVE. O, Tyrant Love! how partial is thy Reign! Why must I still admire the perjur'd Swain Ah! let thy Force, alike, to him be known, Inform his Heart, or send me back my Own. AIR. Thou bubbling Brook, didst thou not hear, My faithless Shepherd to me say, When I am false, to thee, my Dear, That gurgling Rill shall cease to play? Your murm'ring Course you still pursue, But Colin is, alas! untrue. The wing'd Musicians of the Air, Cry'd he, shall all their Notes suspend; And Spring forget the rising Year, Before my Constancy shall end. The Birds their tuneful Songs proclaim, And all, but Colin, is the same. Why is our Sex so tender fram'd? Why model'd on so frail a Plan? How vain the Art by Woman claim'd, Oppos'd to half the Wiles of Man! In what we most adore and prize; In Beauty, lurking Ruin lies. [Exit.] SCENE IV. Strephon, Delia. RECITATIVE. Streph. Jove form'd thee, Delia, in a Mold divine, And from an Angel's Beauties fashion'd thine; But still an Imperfection dulls the Whole, If gentle Love can never touch thy Soul. Delia. Strephon, 'tis vain, so flatter me no more, I bid Defiance to its tinsel Pow'r; Too many have embrac'd the fatal Bribe, But Delia ne'er shall grace th'unhappy Tribe. Th'Admirer's Hand the spangled Adder stings, Thus Grief to simple Maids, from Flatt'ry springs. Streph. Ah much, my Dear, you wrong your Swain, indeed, Full from my Heart my Sentiments proceed; My Passion's Merit let your Wisdom prove, And from Deceit distinguish honest Love. DUET. [Streph.] Let other Youths the Fair delude, Regardless of their future Good, Such Thoughts are far from me; Much gentler Views engage my Mind, And but in sacred Ties combin'd, Cou'd I be bless'd with thee. Delia. A Maiden should with Patience wait, And ponder well the Marriage State, Ere fasten'd in the Noose; A smiling Sky may cloud ere Noon, And in the wedded Youth too soon, We may the Lover lose. Streph. Whom worldly Toys to meet invite Ne'er Taste the Nuptial near Delight, Nor feel a real Joy: But, when a mutual Pair approve, In Hymen's silken Rein to move, Their Bliss can never cloy. Delia. Your Love, young Strephon, may be just, But 'tis imprudent soon to trust, Besides I'm yet not won. Who wed, in haste, in haste repent, They never know the Balm Content, But are in haste undone. RECITATIVE. Streph. How long must I in this Suspence remain? Delia. Hark! how my tender bleating Lambs complain! Streph. Oh, cheer your Shepherd with a parting Smile! Delia. The Game is sweetest when 'tis won with Toil. [Exit. SCENE V. STREPHON. AIR. Grant, Reason, thou unerring Guide! An am'rous Youth thy Aid, Nor let me sink beneath the Pride, Of a too-beauteous Maid. How simple he who, to possess, To Grief for Succour flies; That Love which Sighs and Tears express, The Nymphs of Sense despise. Ye ruling Pow'rs! who form'd the Fair, Shou'd Delia ne'er be mine, Let but a Glimpse of Hope appear, And I will not repine. But if I happier Fate shall see, To sooth these soft Alarms, When e'er it suits your just Decree, O, bless my longing Arms! SCENE VI. To him, Colin. RECITATIVE. Colin. Ha! Strephon! how! wrapt up in Thought profound? Has cruel Cupid given the fatal Wound? Streph. What is the Chance makes Colin come this Way? Is any of your fleecy Care astray? Colin. No, Strephon, faith I've better Sport in view, Which, wert thou not in Love, I'd tell thee too. Come say—the Charmer—how begins her Name? Nay, tell your Friend the Object of your Flame. Streph. If Signs of Passion stand in me confess'd, Know, that a Lover can't abide a Jest; Tho' yet you've scap'd, you may a Victim fall, For Love, like Death, is sure to visit all. Colin. Ha! ha! no I defy the brightest Fair To give my easy Heart an Hour's Care; What Love so strong but with Possession ends? A Maxim that, on which it fix'd depends. AIR. When e'er a beauteous Nymph I spy My Fancy's all on fire; I long to her Embrace to fly, And revel in Desire. My Faith I swear, and sigh my Pain, Tho' much for both too wise: For Conquest ne'er attends the Swain, Who can't himself disguise. Then shou'd the Fair-one haughty prove, And my fond Suit disdain; When Arts, nor bold, nor tender move, She's soon forgot again: But, if to crown me with Success She kindly does comply, I of the Nymph require, but this; To love as long as I. RECITATIVE. Streph. O, never style it by so great a Name! 'Tis Lust, mere Lust, a mean and dang'rous Flame: Love is divine! its Joys are never ceas'd, And what you think the greatest, I deem the least. Colin. Poor Youth! enraptur'd, past Recovery quite, Who wou'd but pity such a woful Plight! Young Strephon, dancing on the flow'ry Green, The other Morn, a pretty Maid was seen; Not far from hence, her little Flock she 'tends, On whom my present Happiness depends: Just now I'm going to attack the Fair, Sigh out my Soul and die away in Air: And tho' I'm conscious she was made for me, Quit this unseemly Mood, I'll yield her up to thee. Streph. Why really, Colin, now you're wond'rous kind, Pray keep your Favour, I'm to Fate resign'd. Colin. But prithee sigh and sob a little, do, That I may learn, when wounded, how to woo. Streph. My Ear I to such Fool'ry can't incline. Colin. He must be soft who gives himself to thine. Strephon, farewell, indulge your Melancholly, And may the scornful She correct your Folly. [Exeunt seperately. SCENE VII. DELIA. Strephon alone cou'd thus affect me here, No longer will I diffident appear. AIR. When Love inspires the female Heart, When through each Vein the trickling Smart, Its pleasing Course pursues, Tho' Custom bids our Sex be shy, When Virtue prompts us to comply, The home-felt mutual Bliss to try; How can we long refuse? RECITATIVE. Now here comes Shade to set my Shepherd off: One wins my Soul, the other makes me laugh. SCENE VIII. To her, Colin. Colin. Say heav'nly Maid! thou fairest of thy Kind! When shall thy ardent Suitor Comfort find? O, let Compassion heighten ev'ry Grace, And save a Youth, most wretched of his Race. Delia. If you'd divert me don't give over yet; Come, say what Charms I've got since last we met. Colin. Ah, Delia! cease to teaze your Lover so, Your captivating Beauty well you know; Young Cupid on your snowy Bosom lies, And ev'ry Arrow's hoarded in those Eyes: Their dire Effect I cannot long endure; You caus'd the Pain, and shou'd apply the Cure. AIR. Jove meant that Face to please the Sight, That graceful Shape to yield Delight, And all thy bright transcendent Charms, To bless some happy Lover's Arms: Let me on their mild Influence live, And Joy at once receive and give. RECITATIVE. Delia. Ah, Colin! Colin, I am much afraid That Tongue has ruin'd many a harmless Maid: If false to them, you'll not be true to me. Colin. Some other pretty Thoughts will do I see. (Aside.) Think! think, how much you all your Sex excell! Were I on that fair panting Breast to dwell, My Love and Life shou'd but together die. Delia. What Nymph but wou'd to such a Swain comply? (Aside.) Colin. O, never Pause! see yon inviting Bow'r, There let us offer Love a happy Hour; Screen'd in the Shade, where fanning Breezes blow, We'll taste the Transports Lovers only know. Delia. Ha! ha! vain Youth, stand off, at Distance keep, Give o'er th'Attempt, and watch your straggling Sheep. Colin. Does Delia glory in her Lover's Pain? Delia. The Trifler shou'd be trifled with again. Colin. Ha! have the Prospect full in view and miss! What a confounded Disappointment's This! (Aside.) DUET. [Colin.] Behold yon blooming Rose! Which scents the Morning Dew; Triumphing, as it grows, In Prime of Youth like you: But when cool Autumn takes his Round, Tho' now in Pomp array'd, 'Twill strow with blighted Leaves the Ground, While all its Beauties fade. Then snatch at Pleasure, e're too late, Lest, Delia, you receive such Fate. Delia. That Damask Rose, so bright, Upon its Stalk will thrive, And treat the Smell and Sight, While native Sweets survive: But pluck the Flow'r 'twill only please, A momentary Stay; Its Glories die, its Odours cease, 'Tis scorn'd, and thrown away. Thus when a Nymph to Folly's won, By all she's slighted when undone. RECITATIVE. Colin. This Modesty too far extends its Sway, That matchless Form was meant for Sport and Play; I ne'er before thus knew the Bait to fail. (Aside.) Delia. Such feeble Arguments will ne'er prevail. AIR. You've told me what Beauty appears in my Face, And how like a Goddess I'm shap'd, Yet, Colin, I'm certain I still have a Grace Your narrow Observance has 'scap'd. 'Tis Virtue that shines in the Virgin's bright Eyes, And adds to her Mein ev'ry Charm: 'Tis that which attracts the Regard of the Wise, But never a Fool can alarm. Here Virtue and Reason I hope are ally'd, With Passion united to both: And when you can conquer my Guard and my Pride, I am your's for ever! sweet Youth. [Exit. RECITATIVE. Colin. With Justice she contemns me!—Yet I fear, That very Scorn has struck me much too near. How a short Moment turns the varied Mind! How Virtue frustrates all by Vice design'd! Cou'd I betray her?—no,—the Thought's suppress'd, And what was once my Hope I now detest. O, Love!—if this be Love, I'm lost indeed, For such a Wretch as I, can ne'er succeed. [Exit. The End of the First Interlude.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">INTERLUDE II. SCENE I. SYLVIA. RECITATIVE. All Nature seems in universal Glee; How blithe the Songsters hop from Tree to Tree! What vernal Fragrance scents the ambient Air! Yet nought can soften my extreme Despair. AIR. Ye Warblers! no longer your liquid Throats strain, No longer your Sonnets can please, For such were the Sounds of the roving young Swain, Who robs my poor Bosom of Ease: When Phœbus makes Love in your little Hearts glow, A Song can your Meanings declare; The Sweets of the Passion untainted ye know, And never, like me, feel the Care. Tho' Blasts may destroy all the Flow'rets, that here Perfume the pure Æther around, Bright Spring shall again bid their Beauties appear, And paint, as before, the gay Ground: But when a poor Nymph's wrong'd of all she could boast, And left to lament and complain, Her greatest Charm's gone; when her Virtue is lost No Spring can renew it again. The Riv'lets run purling along the cool Mead, To sooth me in sorrowful Tone; The Zephyrs, affectedly, onward proceed To waft the Deceiver my Moan. Ye Powers! who govern the Works ye have made, Relieve the deep Woe of my Mind; As Sylvia through Pity alone was betray'd, In-pity let Colin, be kind. [Exit. SCENE II. Strephon, discover'd sitting thoughtfully. AIR. Man was in Paradise unbless'd, No social Bliss he knew, 'Till God-like Woman stood confess'd, Cœlestial to his View. With Awe he gaz'd, with Joy admir'd, His Maker's best Decree; Delights unknown his Bosom fir'd, And Love his Tongue set free. In ev'ry Age, in ev'ry Clime, The Sex is still renown'd; They raise the Soul to Heights sublime, And all the Passions bound: Like bright Aurora's genial Beam, They gild the anxious Mind: And Love and Beauty reign supreme, To charm and bless Mankind. RECITATIVE. Ah, loitring Youth! why idly thus proceed? The flying Minutes shou'd have better heed. (Rising.) But Colin comes, he looks in great Concern, I'll wait awhile the bad Mishap to learn. SCENE III. To him, Colin. COLIN (Not perceiving Strephon.) I, who was once the Glory of the Plain, The blithest Youth among the Rural Train; Who defly on my Oaten Read cou'd play, To chace the ling'ring Summer Hours away; Who cou'd so well the shifting-Trip advance, And was the Nimblest in the sprightly Dance; Who laugh'd at all the Power of the Fair, And ridiculed each Shepherd in the Snare, Alas, am caught! Oh, sad Reverse of Fate! Will any sympathize my hapless State? AIR. No more shall Eccho o'er the Plains Repeat my mirthful Song; Nor vocal Hills the tuneful Strains Of mellow Pipe prolong: For Oh, my Heart, so wont to stray, Is past recalling flown away, And Love at last enslaves me. How oft' in yonder conscious Grove I've woo'd each blooming Fair; How oft' wou'd Fate propitious prove, And Silence bless me there: But now no more such Scenes endear, I sigh for Raptures more sincere; For Love at last enslaves me. RECITATIVE. Ah, what will Strephon say when once he knows it? Streph. Lovers are blind, it seems, this plainly shows it. Colin. By Heav'n he's here! Streph. What Colin made a Tool? Who'd be a Slave to Cupid, but a Fool? “Ha! ha! no, I defy the brightest Fair “To give my easy Heart an Hour's Care.” Where's now your boasted Fortitude retir'd? Where's that Indiff'rence, you had long acquir'd? Behold the lawless Youth, so fam'd Abroad, Who made his vicious Appetite his God, Who cou'd so close his false Intentions cover, At last a simple, sighing, whining, Lover! AIR. The subtle Fox thus makes The cackling Brood his Prey, And, as he finds the Treat, Repeats the Crime each Day: But for the wily Thief A cunning Gin is cast; And, tho' he long escape, Sly Reynard's trapp'd at last. RECITATIVE. “Farewell, poor Youth! indulge your Melancholly, “And may the scornfull She correct your Folly.” Colin. Stay, Strephon, stay, I own I mock'd your Flame, But ne'er suspected I shou'd know the same. Your wonted gen'rous Temper let me see, Nor copy, Shepherd, what was wrong in me. Streph. Colin, thy ill-tim'd Jokes displeas'd my Ear, Yet still I thought them trifling,—as they were. I can partake another's Grief,—'tis true, And therefore pity all, where Pity's due. Colin. In thy Advice, my Friend, I balm shall find, To heal the Anguish of my Love-sick Mind. Streph. Why will this doleful Manner win thy Dear? In Wisdom's Garb thy Passion shou'd appear. The whining Woo'r the Nymph to smile may move, But 'tis the Youth of Spirit gains her Love. Be rul'd by me, the gentle Warmth I know, Long have I felt it in my Bosom glow, Submit with Patience, scorn a Sigh tho' cross'd, Nor in the Lover, let the Man be lost. Colin. Thy Love is mod'rate, mine's a raging Fire. Streph. A certain Sign 'twill very soon expire. What Damsel has this fatal Conquest made? Sure she's in more than mortal Charms array'd! Colin. Oh, she's an Angel! but her Name I'll keep Silent as Nature when lock'd fast in Sleep: Tho' I for thee from that Resolve cou'd swerve,— Yet, for the Present let Description serve. AIR. When yon bright Beam, the Source of Day, Which decks the verdant Landskip gay, Is rising from the Eastern Skies, View that, and see her radiant Eyes. When Philomela tunes the Air, Attend, her thrilling Voice you'll hear: Smell all the fragrant Flow'rs in bloom, Such is her gentle Breath's Perfume. Like this uncultivated Scene, The Beauties of her Face and Mien Excell the strongest Force of Art: No Language can her Charms impart. RECITATIVE. Streph. She must be heav'nly! but I always thought Thy Heart cou'd never be by Beauty caught. Colin. Tho' she's as Venus fair, as Pallas wise, A much superior Grace made me her Prize. Virtue, tho' claim'd by most, so seldom found, I long imagin'd only empty sound, But I in her beheld its real Pow'r: And must for that the matchless Nymph adore. Streph. That can give Light through all Deformity, But how had it such great Effect on thee? Colin. I'll tell thee Swain: with each inticing Art I try'd to make her Virgin Whims desert; She seem'd well pleas'd to listen to my Tale, And flatt'ring Smiles assur'd I shou'd prevail: Yet, when I thought she'd be no longer coy, And every Sense grew big with coming Joy, The Ballance turn'd! her Virtue won the Day! And who'd have been the Conq'ror, fell the Prey. Streph. I'm glad to hear it; such a Change as this, No doubt will yield thee everlasting Bliss. Baseness my very Soul with Horror strikes; None but a Brute would ruin what he likes. Colin. Yet, Strephon, such a one I've long Time been; Wild was my Hope when first this Nymph was seen: But when 'gainst more than Human Pow'r I strove, Each ruder Wish was melted into Love. Streph. Pursue her boldly, mean Endeavours shun, Perhaps, in Honour, she may yet be won: But if you find her not to be obtain'd Contented, bear the Lot by Heav'n ordain'd. Colin. Whatever Strephon says I must commend. Streph. Colin adieu! Success your Suit attend! [Exit. SCENE IV. COLIN. AIR. Ah! who can tell, What Tortures dwell, Within a doating Swain? What Doubts and Fear, In view appear, When Passion burns in vain? By Beauty charm'd, We oft' are warm'd, And sensual Wishes flow; But Love refin'd, Which fires the Mind, A Few are doom'd to know. [Exit. SCENE V. Strephon, Delia. RECITATIVE. Delia. How can you thus persist to plague one still? Streph. Delia, I must my Fortune know, and will. AIR. This Heart (if I may call it mine) Is fix'd eternally to thine: If Constancy can claim Regard, If Love sincere shou'd meet Reward, Then sooth my ev'ry am'rous Care: And be at once as kind as fair. Although thy Form has magick Pow'r, Thy inward graces touch me more: Thy Sense shall live when Beauty dies; Thy Wit shine longer than thy Eyes; Tho' Age thy youthful Bloom may blast, Thy more intrinsick Worth shall last. What can the gen'rous Flame controul, When Reason renders up the Soul? Thy Charms which ne'er can fade inspire My gentle Love, and soft Desire. These Town-bred teazing Arts refrain; Oh, please thyself! and bless thy Swain! RECITATIVE. Delia. Strephon, of all whom Hymen has ally'd, They fare the best, who Conduct make their Guide. AIR. A prudent Nymph shou'd try The Passion of her Youth, Nor on his Vows rely, Till Time has prov'd his Truth. But, ah! we all are weak, And to the Flame resign;— Forgive my glowing Cheek! I'm thine and only thine. RECITATIVE. Streph. Oh, Delia! Delia! Words can't speak my Bliss, Be gone my Fears! what Extacy is this! Boast, boast, your Joys ye lawless ranging Crew! They're stupid all! compar'd to mine in view! When shall the wish'd-for Knot be ty'd?—reveal. Delia. To-morrow then. Streph. Let this the Promise seal. (Kisses her.) DUET. [Streph.] Whilst, wanton, on the verdant Plain, Our snowy Flocks shall play, I'll tune my swelling oaten Read, To please thee all the Day; Or speak of some fond hapless Youth, Who vainly draws each Sigh; Then snatch perhaps a tender Kiss, And say how bless'd am I. Delia. If e'er, in am'rous Talk, you tell The Tale of some poor Fair, Decoy'd by an ungentle Swain, To Shame and deep Despair, While Pity in my Bosom moves, I'll cast a Smile on thee; Then thank the kind propitious Gods, Who made so happy me, Streph. At Noon-Tide, when faint Nature pants, With Sol's excessive Heat, Straight, to some thick-set Shade we'll hie, And 'joy the calm Retreat: There if a gentle Slumber shou'd Thy wearied Senses take, I'll softly steal my Face to thine, And watch thee till awake. Delia. When dusky Clouds the Æther skim, And vernal Show'rs descend; When scarce a feather'd Warbler flies, And none their Musick lend: While shelter'd, in the leafy Scene, Around our Lambkins lye, I'll listen to thy Pipe or Song, And cheat the gloomy Sky. Streph. When Phæbus does with golden Hue The ruddy West adorn, We'll penn our fleecy Care in Fold, 'Till next enliv'ning Morn; And safe, within my circling Arms, Shalt thou recline to Rest; I'll screen thee from from the noxious Air, Clasp'd to my faithful Breast. Delia. When Hills and Dales, with wint'ry Frosts, Shall silver'd o'er appear; When all seem dull, our Loves shall smile, And glad us thro' the Year. Together. Tho' Time all Nature's Works can change, Our Passion scorns his Pow'r; Beyond the Date of Life we'll love, Till Time shall be no more. SCENE VI. To them, Colin. RECITATIVE. Colin. Protect me Heav'ns! what play a treach'rous Part? Is this my Friend, who bore an open Heart? A sly Design I thought thou wert above: Know to that Nymph I dedicate my Love. Streph. That may be Colin,—yet I b'lieve she's mine. Colin. I'm much the better for Advice of thine; I freely told her Charms, you guess'd the Maid, And have in haste my Confidence repaid. Streph. Was that my Delia?—had you nam'd the Fair, When you so kindly offer'd me your Share, When puff'd in Self-Conceit she was your own, You then from me your poor Success had known. Colin. Celestial Nymph! your humble Suppliant hear, I bring an off'ring am'rous and sincere. Delia. Shepherd, your fond-dissembling now suspend; I can no longer to your Tale attend. Streph. Colin, if Wisdom be no Foe to thee, Incline, and hear the welcome Truth from me: Month after Month have I this Maid ador'd; Day after Day have I her Love implor'd; This present Hour my happy Fate commands; Our Souls are one, To-morrow joins our Hands. Colin. O monstrous! monstrous! it can never be; Let me from here receive my Destiny. (To Delia) Delia. If you had really Hopes my Heart to gain. I gave not one, they were self-form'd and vain; Long was it fix'd ere you pretended Passion, And lik'd its Choice too well for Alteration. Colin. How strange is this!—it is!—it mast be true! (after a Pause.) Streph. Are you convinc'd? Colin. Strephon, she is thy due. What have I done? ah, silly, silly Swain! How cou'd I hope such Beauties to obtain? Do I deserve such Excellence, such Worth? From Vanity the Notion had its Birth. Hail happy Pair! but for each other meant. For an Example you to Earth were sent. My Flame in stronger Friendship shall expire, And tho' I can't enjoy, I'll still admire. AIR. Oh, Strephon! every Joy will spring, From Love's perpetual Fount on thee: Small Pleasure Liberty can bring, When Hymen makes us more than free. RECITATIVE. Streph. Worthy a Shepherd is thy Sense express'd, But, Colin, formerly—“'Twas all a Jest!” Colin. True, long I was a faithless wand'ring Swain, And Folly saw me busy in her Train, But, Strephon, when for thy bright Fair I burn'd, I by her Virtue was a Convert turn'd, Delia, thou Goddess! pardon each Essay I try'd, to lead thee in the Wanton's Way: You baffled all, my fruitless Wiles cou'd see, And what I would have vanquish'd, conquer'd me. O cou'd I find a Nymph that wou'd respect! This honest Heart which justly you reject! Delia. Go seek her, whom your Falshoods have distress'd, And banish'd Peace and Comfort from her Breast; Implore a Pardon for the worst Offence, And for wrong'd Innocence make Recompence. A melting Story's whisper'd round the Plain, Of a young Maid, woo'd by a youthful Swain: She knew the Passion with a Warmth divine, But he conceiv'd a fatal black Design; And ruin'd her, whose Love was so sincere. Colin. Oh, Conscience; view that hated Monster here! AIR. Delia. Think of the deep-felt anxious Cares, Which ever wait upon her: Think what a tender Soul she bears. To love tho' you've undone her. RECITATIVE. Colin. I'll seek her straight, for thine is Wisdom's Voice. But see! she comes the Object of your Choice. SCENE the Last. To them, Sylvia. AIR. When from the Lark some Peasant takes Her nestling Young away, She pines and hovers round the Place, Which held her little tuneful Race, Where all her Comfort lay. Thus am I doom'd to haunt the Swain, Who once was all my Joy. What can avail my pining Grief! No Gleam of Hope admits Relief: Ah, cruel, faithless Boy. RECITATIVE. Colin. Much injur'd Nymph forbear nor tell thy Woes, Through Sympathy, thy Grief my Bosom knows: Sylvia, I own I have been much unkind, False as the Stream, and fickle as the Wind; But now I'll make Attonement for my Crime, And fix'd to thee pass my allotted Time. No more with Tears bedim thy radiant Eyes, But in thy Face let blooming Pleasure rise: From Sorrow ev'ry wonted Grace retrieve, And, with a Smile, thy “faithless Boy” forgive. Sylvia. This sudden Change can never be sincere; 'Twere Flatt'ry to believe it so, I fear. Colin. Nay doubt me not, I can be false no more, Indeed, my Sylvia, all my Folly's o'er: Hearken, my Friend, and witness what I vow, To-morrow (if the Gods my Life allow) With this dear Nymph, I will in Wedlock join; So, Strephon, shall thy Wedding-Day be mine. Streph. Heav'n must an Act so generous approve. Colin. From them, my Fair, we'll learn to live and love. Sylvia. Then Fortune's kind!—Oh, Colin mine at last! (embracing.) Colin. Let dull Remembrance die of what is past. DUET. [Colin.] The Bee, that haunts the fragrant Bow'r, Extracts the Sweets of ev'ry Flow'r, And sips an Hundred in an Hour, But when the Fit is o'er to roam, Returning to the luscious Comb, He finds the richest Sweets at Home. Thus did my fickle Fancy stray, And restless all the live-long Day, Cou'd never with one Object stay: Now tir'd at length with being free, It can no more inconstant be, But finds all Joy alone in thee. Sylvia. When Night asserts her awful Reign, No Sylvan Prospects entertain, While Horror deepens o'er the Plain: Yet when Aurora darts her Ray, The Sun dispels the Gloom away, And Nature smiles, and all is gay. Thus thy returning Flame has chac'd Despair and Anguish from my Breast, And all within is Peace and Rest. The Bliss that Passion can bestow, The Care-touch'd Soul alone can know; All Pleasure takes its Rise from Woe. RECITATIVE. Streph. The happiest Mortals we shall be on Earth; We'll yield the Day that makes us so to Mirth; And, Colin, while in each revolving Year, We are indulg'd in viewing it appear, A jocund Treat to all our Friends we'll give, And Rural Sports shall crown the blithsome Eve. Colin. Strephon, whatever you propose shall be: My Joys will flow from Delia and from thee. CHORUS. Oh, Marriage! Oh, Marriage! thou heavenly State! Thy Bonds must be easy, where Rapture's so great; They ne'er can be bless'd who the Station despise, In Wedlock alone all true Happiness lies. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>