<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">, , Theobald, (Lewis), Mr, 1688-1744</field>
      <field name="author_facet">, , Theobald, (Lewis), Mr, 1688-1744</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">  theobald lewis mr 1688 1744</field>
      <field name="author_text">, , Theobald, (Lewis), Mr, 1688-1744</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">18th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1710's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V2.0346.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1719</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460051</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Decius and Paulina ; A Masque</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Decius and Paulina ; A Masque</field>
      <field name="title_facet">decius and paulina</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">decius and paulina</field>
      <field name="title_text">Decius and Paulina ; A Masque</field>
      <field name="year_display">1719</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1719</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1719</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460051&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460051&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;, , Theobald, (Lewis), Mr, 1688-1744&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt; theobald lewis mr 1688 1744&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Decius and Paulina ; A Masque&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;decius and paulina&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1719&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1719&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;, , Theobald, (Lewis), Mr&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1688&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1744&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Decius and Paulina&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Masque&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for W. Mears, [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1719&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872727-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv20346&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 18th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;18th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Decius and Paulina&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Masque&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 37 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;lb/&gt;Only Decius and Paulina included.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Decius and Paulina.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Masque.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1718.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Mar 1718.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Decius and Paulina, A MASQUE,</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Dramatis Personæ. Marcellus, Signa. Marguerita. Decius Mundus, Mrs. Barbier. Paulina, Mrs. Pulman. Priestess of Isis, Mrs. Fletcher. Simo, an Attendant on Decius, Mr. Leveridge. Ida, an Attendant on Paulina, Mr. Pack.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE, The Temple of Isis, and adjacent Parts in Rome.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE I. A Garden. Marcellus, and Paulina. Marc. O lovely Maid! while I repeat My ardent Vows, thus gazing on thy Charms, The flatt'ring Hours uncounted fly, And Life dissolves in Bliss away, Be grateful to my Flame; Nor let a Rival's Pow'r prevail To rob me of the Heart, in which I live. Paul. Have I not sworn?— And do you still suspect! Marc. Alas! my tender Fears forgive; Doubts still divide the Breast, where Passion reigns. Ten thousand Pains surround me, When from thy Sight I go. Think, Absence needs must wound me, Since Pleasures round thee flow. Ten thousand Pains surround me, When from thy Sight I go. [Ex. Marcellus.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE II. Simo, Ida, and Paulina. Ida. See, where she stands, all pensive and alone, Occasion favours your Address. Simo. Decius by me, his humblest Slave, To bright Paulina, Mistress of his Vows, Health and the tendrest Wishes sends, That Love did e'er inspire. Paul. No more,— Cease your importunate Address. In vain you strive my Breast to move, I'm arm'd against the Force of Love: No more can Flatt'ries here prevail, Than Winds that stubborn Oaks assail, And idly murmur thro' the Grove. In vain you strive my Breast to move, I'm arm'd against the Force of Love. Simo. Ah, fair Paulina! if the Charms Of Decius touch not your relentless Soul, Yet weigh his Wealth, and boundless Pow'r, And see how bright these Jewels blaze! [Shews a Bracelet. Here Cupid plays with wondrous Art, And ev'ry sparkling Gem's a Dart. Paul. Back to thy Lord his treach'rous Presents bear, And, with them, say how much I scorn his Love. Ida, The solemn Hour's at hand When we at Isis' hallow'd Shrine must bow. Yet here?— [Looking on Simo. Then I must shun the Place, For Virtue suffers when it treats with Shame. Rage, and just Disdain inspire me, Both contend my Breast t'inflame. Pride, and conscious Blushes fire me To protect my injur'd Fame. Rage, and just Disdain inspire me, Both contend my Breast t'inflame. [Ex. Paulina.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE III. Simo, and Ida. Simo. Ida,— Ida. What says my Simo dear? Sim. The Golden Hopes are fled: Fantastick Sex! Ah, silly Pride, A Gift of such a Price to scorn! 'Tis not Virtue, but 'tis Vice To be so reserv'd and nice: When they are so richly hir'd, Why should they doubt, And why stand out, When so little is requir'd? 'Tis not Virtue, but 'tis Vice To be so reserv'd and nice. Id. Must Women then, because they bloom in Charms, Strait fall into th'expecting Lover's Arms? Sim. Why not?—The mellow Pear, we see, If over-ripe, forsakes the Tree. Ida. Were we so courteous, and so forward found, We soon might lie neglected on the Ground. I would that Woman Should yield to no Man, Or Love like Autumn-Fruit bestow; No, no, 'tis Reason, You nick the Season, And take the Trouble to shake the Bough. Sim. Can cruel Ida then consent To give her Simo Discontent? And let him dwindle, till he but discover The meagre Shadow of a lusty Lover? Take me, while this Bloom and Grace Give a Lustre to my Face: E'er this Shape and Mien forsake me, Age unnerve, or Palsies shake me, E'er Old Time my Strength destroy, And I grow unfit for Joy. Take me, while this Bloom and Grace Give a Lustre to my Face. Ida. Simo, thou know'st how much I love, How much thy beauteous Form I prize, But, ah! 'tis wond'rous, wond'rous sweet, To have a Lover Some Pains discover, And sigh, and languish at our Feet. Freely would I to thy Arms Give up all my youthful Charms, And thy gen'rous Passion meet: But, ah! 'tis wondrous, wondrous sweet, To have a Lover Some Pains discover, And sigh, and languish at our Feet. Sim. Soft! Decius comes; my Duck, retire: 'Twere well to be unseen, till we Can with more welcome Tidings greet him. [Exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE IV. A Chamber. Decius. Dec. O Love, thou anxious, pleasing Guest! How are we pain'd, how are we blest! Now we feel Despair and Anguish, Now with Joy we sweetly languish, Hope and Fear divide the Breast. O Love, thou anxious, pleasing Guest! How are we pain'd, how are we blest!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE V. Marcellus, Decius. Marc. Talks he of Love? and idly dreams, Perhaps, of Joys Paulina may bestow? Dec. Ha!— Did I not hear Paulina's Name? But from a Rival's Tongue what Name can please! Marc. Yes, Decius, I a favour'd Rival boast; And thy Pretensions dare despise. Dec. Insult not on a Woman's Vows, Whose Faith is short-liv'd as her Charms. Marc. Unequal'd Insolence! forbear With thy licentious Breath to wound her Fame: Or from my Rage a just Revenge expect. Fly, e'er the Tempest shake me, E'er Patience quite forsake me; Fierce Resentment gives th'Alarm. Love, that sooths to soft Desire, If Disdain or Vengeance fire, Can the Soul with Fury arm. Fly, e'er the Tempest shake me, E'er Patience quite forsake me, Fierce Resentment gives th'Alarm. Dec. I have not Leisure to dispute, But can thy empty Threats contemn; And know, I ev'ry Art will try To make the stubborn Maid comply. [Ex. Decius.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE VI. Marcellus. Marc. All Arts on Virtue try'd are vain; For Innocence, in its own Strength secure, Stands like a Rock that breaks the dashing Waves, And baffles ev'ry Storm.— But see, she comes:—</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE VII. Marcellus, Paulina. Paul. To Thee, as to a Guardian God, I fly, To shelter me from Care: Decius with hated Love pursues me. Marc. My Spirits start at Decius' Name; He threatens ev'ry Art to use, To make thee yield to his licentious Love. Paul. Give not a Thought to Fear; I'm Constant, and his Arts despise: Marc. O virtuous Maid!—Teach me, ye Pow'rs, Such wondrous Goodness to repay. M. Fate now no more can wound me, P. With no Suspicions wound me, M. Since you so constant prove. P. I still will constant prove. M. Content and Joy surround me, P. Misfortunes then surround me, M. My Soul is tun'd to love. P. When I forbear to love. M. Fate now no more can wound me, P. With no Suspicions wound me, M. Since you so constant prove. P. I still will constant prove. [Exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE VIII. Decius, Simo. Dec. Simo, what says the charming Maid? Will she be kind, and yield to Love? Simo. 'Tis hard a Woman's Will to find, Or by her Words expound her Mind. Dec. Keep me not in Suspense, But say, at once, what Hopes remain? Simo. Then longer not in Doubt to hold you, Take This—and think my Story told you. [Gives Decius the Bracelet. Dec. Does she my Presents and my Love despise? Proud and disdainful Fair! Thus to requite the Pains I've bore! O Realms of Night! O gloomy Pow'rs! Receive me to your peaceful Bow'rs: A Wretch, whom cruel Fate has made Unfit for Light and upper Day, Grows sick of you resplendent Ray, And, courting Death, invokes your Aid. O Realms of Night! O gloomy Pow'rs! Receive me to your peaceful Bow'rs. Simo. My Lord, I grieve for your Distress; Live, and in Hope, at least, possess. Paulina, tho' of Love afraid, Is still a superstitious Maid, And by her Zeal may be betray'd. Dec. Say on;—thy mystick Words explain. Sim. Oft she to Isis' Temple goes, And piously renews her Vows; With Gold suborn th'attending Tribe Of Priests, (for Priests will take a Bribe,) And they, by some well-wrought Device, Will Her to your Embrace entice. Dec. Thou kindest, best Assistant! Receive this Earnest of my Love. [Gives Simo a Purse with Gold. Still serve my Flame, and Decius is thy Friend. But to the sacred Dome I'll strait repair, And execute the great Design. Simo, this Signet quick to Fulvius bear, And from him fifty Talents bring; I at the Temple shall be found. [Ex. Simo.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE IX. Decius. Dec. Bright Cytherea! Queen of Love! The cold, relentless Charmer move: O let her feel thy pleasing Fire, And breath into her Soul Desire. Bright Cytherea! Queen of Love! The cold, relentless Charmer move. [Ex. Decius.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE X. Simo, and Ida. Ida. Simo;— Simo. My Love;—I must not stay, But to the Temple strait away: Yet hold;—receive this glitt'ring Store; [Gives her Gold. And think, if Things hit right, of more. My Genius now is busie grown, And Fate's resolv'd my Worth to crown. I'm fill'd with Thoughts of sudden State; 'Tis Jove inspires These big Desires, This strange Ambition to be great. My Genius now is busie grown, And Fate's resolv'd my Worth to crown. Ida. Ah! Simo, if thy Wits remain, If no bad Star has hurt thy Brain; Let such vain Whimsies stand confin'd, And to thy Fortunes fit thy Mind: These Raptures would more welcome be, If right employ'd on Love, and Me. The Nymph, that boasts the happy Charms To win a Lover to her Arms, Is pleas'd to hear her Beauty's Praise: When with artful Complaisance You our Beauty's Praise enhance, O then you most our Liking raise. The Nymph, that boasts the happy Charms To win a Lover to her Arms, Is pleas'd to hear her Beauty's Praise. Simo. For This some other Time allow, Decius demands my Service now; In short, his Suit, as best thou may'st, promote, And I to thee myself for Life devote. Sim. And then, O then, my Ida dear, Ida. And then, O then, my Simo dear, Both. 'Twill all be Transport, Love, and Joy: Sim. Then at Will I'll revel here, Ida. Thou at Will shalt revel here, Sim. Then I'll take unnumber'd Kisses, Ida. Thou shalt take unnumber'd Kisses, Sim. Then I'll reap unnumber'd Blisses, Ida. Thou shalt reap unnumber'd Blisses, Both. And each Hour in Love employ. [Exeunt severally.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE XI. The Temple. Priestess, and Priests attending. Priestess. Blind God of Love, and of Disguise, What various Changes crown thy Pow'r! Jove has for thee forsook his Skies, A mortal Beauty to adore. Blind God of Love, and of Disguise, What various Changes crown thy Pow'r! But Decius, (impious Pride!) To personate a God aspires: And could his Passion point out none but Me, To aid his wild Desires? But shall it be? No; the licentious Boy With Justice is betray'd: He from his Hopes at once shall fall, And Disappointment, Scorn, and Shame shall wait him. Paulina comes;—It must be tried, How She the God will entertain.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE XII. Priestess, Priests, Paulina, and Ida. Priestess. Paulina, hail! O happy Maid, Whose mortal Beauties have a God inflam'd, Divine Anubis sighs for thy Embrace, And to possess Thee from his Heav'n descends. Paul. Ye gracious Pow'rs! am I awake? Alas! I tremble:— Priestess. Calm these Fears, And to the Purpose of the Gods resign. To obtain the envied Treasure Of eternal Youth and Pleasure, Yield to the God's Embrace. Beauties blooming, Unconsuming, So thy heav'nly Form shall grace. To obtain the envied Treasure Of eternal Youth and Pleasure; Yield to the God's Embrace. Paul. Give me some Proof that by the God's Command Thou do'st these Words pronounce. Priestess. So, when by Vision he his Will reveal'd, Was I commission'd to confirm thy Doubts: And know, Anubis will with Pomp appear, And from thyself thy self demand. Paul. New Transports all my Pow'rs controul, They croud, and take up all my Soul; Thro' ev'ry throbbing Vein I feel An unacquainted Pleasure steal: New Transports all my Pow'rs controul, They croud, and take up all my Soul. Priestess. Prepare; Anubis is at hand; Sound all your Instruments of Joy, And celebrate the God's Approach. [The Priestess waves her Wand, and the Temple opens, and discovers a rising Sun.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE XIII. Decius as the God Anubis, Paulina, Priestess and Priests. Dec. Celestial Maid! O far more bright Than Beauty's Queen, how great thy Charms! The Graces view thee with Delight, And Cupid revelt in thy Arms. Celestial Maid! O far more bright Than Beauty's Queen, how great thy Charms!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE XIV. Decius, Paulina, Ida, Priestess, Priests, and Simo. Simo. Say Ida, does the pious Fraud succeed? Ida. Peace, Fool, I would thou wer't not here, That Face does too much Business wear. Simo. I stand corrected, and to shew I value your Advice, I'll go. [Simo going, is stopt by Marcellus.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE XV. Decius, Marcellus, Paulina, Ida, Priestess, Priests, and Simo. Dec. Again, in Honour of Paulina's Name, The solemn Rights perform. Bright Maid! with me retire. Mar. Hold, Decius, hold; not this Disguise Can hide Thee from Marcellus' Eyes. Dec. Ha!—I'm betray'd:— Paul. Propitious Pow'rs! from what am I escap'd? Dec. Was this well done? [To the Priestess. Priestess. To thy own Honour I appeal. Dec. No more:—I was to blame. Marcellus, take Paulina to thy Arms; Decius henceforth shall give Thee no Alarms. Mar. As from the Gods this Blessing I receive, My future Life to crown. CHORUS. Thus alone we happy prove, Blest with Beauty, and with Love. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>