<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Mottley, John, 1692-1750</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Mottley, John, 1692-1750</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">mottley john 1692 1750</field>
      <field name="author_text">Mottley, John, 1692-1750</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">18th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1720's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V2.0312.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1720</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460022</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Imperial Captives ; A tragedy</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Imperial Captives ; A tragedy</field>
      <field name="title_facet">imperial captives</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">imperial captives</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Imperial Captives ; A tragedy</field>
      <field name="year_display">1720</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1720</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1720</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460022&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460022&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Mottley, John, 1692-1750&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;mottley john 1692 1750&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Imperial Captives ; A tragedy&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;imperial captives&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1720&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1720&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Mottley, John&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1692&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1750&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Imperial Captives&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for T. Jauncy ... W. Meadows ... J. Roberts [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1720&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872358-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv20312&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 18th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;18th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Imperial Captives&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 155 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: The imperial captives.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1720.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 29 Feb 1720.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE IMPERIAL CAPTIVES: A TRAGEDY.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">TO The Right Honourable the Ld Viscount Castlemain.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PROLOGUE; Written by Mr. Beckingham. In this Projecting, this Censorious Age, So many diff'rent Schemes your Minds engage, You've scarce left room for any on the Stage. Whilst Pulpits war, and Stock-jobbers debate, How doubtful is the slighted Poet's Fate? His idle Plans you carelesly survey, And find but scanty Interest from a Play; For Poor Returns he plies his tortur'd Brain, And great Examples swell the Scene in vain. Is this the Land of Freedom and of Sense? And shall the pining Muse be banish'd hence? Once your fair Fav'rite, now discourag'd lie, And British Poetry in Britain die? Shall then the Tragick Bard unheeded tell How Ammon conquer'd, or how Cæsar fell? How Tyrants by their own Injustice bleed, And happy Realms have been by great Deliv'rers freed, Just Parallels of Times before you cast, To teach the present—while he draws the past? Recover with your Taste your antient Fame, Nor let what was your Glory be your Shame; Let it not now reproach you to have made Those Pens that us'd to celebrate—upbraid. In spight of Disadvantages like these, Our Author yet has humble Hopes to please; By proper Strokes he studies to impart Instructive Morals to the generous Heart. If to Despotick Sway you scorn to bow, He bids you shew your just Abhorrence now: His Captives—(if Distress commands a Tear) Can never sue in vain for Mercy here. If he desires, account it not his Pride, That standard Judgement should his Cause decide; His Faults he owns, if Men of Sense condemn, For Wounds are Wounds of Honour given by them. Attend impartial to his honest Claim, Applaud with Justice, and with Justice blame.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">EPILOGUE; Spoken by Miss Stone. By Mr. Christopher Bullock. Our Author just now whisper'd in my Ear, My Play and I are surely damn'd, my Dear, Unless, my Charmer, you will now engage, And save me from the dreadful Criticks Rage; By Way of Epilogue, beg they'd excuse The first Attempt of my unskilful Muse. I strait comply'd; and ev'n without more urging Swore that I would succeed—or die a Virgin. Now, what a Story would that be to tell! Did Play-house Damsel e'er lead Apes in Hell? What, die a Maid! and in this loving City, You cruel Fellows, would it not be pity? Now when my Charms might captivate a Nation, Now when I'm just arriv'd to—Speculation! Be forc'd to hear my Lovers sigh in vain, Have Pow'r to wish, but not assuage their Pain? My Youth and Beauty sicken with the Spleen! Just in the wishing Crisis of Fifteen! Pray spare our Poet—Come,—you must be good: Pity my Case,—I'm Play-house Flesh and Blood. My Oath was rash,—but since I chanc'd to take it, Nor Beau, nor Critick e'er shall make me break it. Therefore you Monsters, that make Girls afraid, Who ev'ry Morning must devour a Maid, You Men of Sense, and you sweet-scented Beaux, To you who Charm with Wit, and you with Clothes, To all I speak, that ever hope to find I to their Wishes may not prove unkind, Must to our Author's Faults be very—very blind.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Dramatis Personæ. MEN. Genseric, King of the Vandals. Mr. Quin. Thrasimond, his eldest Son. Mr. Ryan. Honoric, his younger Son. Mr. Egleton. Aspar, Minister of State. Mr. Boheme. Narbal, Attendant on Thrasimond. Mr. Diggs. WOMEN. The Empress Mrs. Giffard. Eudosia, her Daughter. Mrs. Seymour. Sophronia Mrs. Bullock. Justina, her Confident. Mrs Gulick. Guards, Officers, and Attendants. SCENE, the Palace of Genseric in Carthage.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. SCENE I. Eudosia and Aspar. Eud. How long, malicious Instrument of Power, Say, for thou know'st the Tyrant's Counsels well; How long will thy insulting Master hold In Carthaginian Bonds great Cæsar's House? His impious Fortune's Boast, and Rome's Disgrace! Unshock'd can he survey a guilty Reign Blacken'd with Perfidy, and stain'd with Blood? Can he behold the Empress and myself Sink with the Weight of these detested Chains, Nor Honour, nor Humanity upbraid His treach'rous Arms, and violated Faith? Say, subtle Minister of that proud Prince, Say, Aspar, yet does Genseric relent? What may we hope? or stands he still resolv'd To wage with Justice, and with Nature War, And meditating still continu'd Mischiefs, Add to our Woes, and pride him in his Crimes? Asp. To make those Chains sit lighter on your Mind, Lose the Remembrance of your Birth, and Rome; Resign with Patience to the Will of Fate, For fix'd as Fate are Genseric's Decrees: From Patience, not from him, expect Redress. Eud. Patience! the sovereign Balm to lesser Woes, But useless to Eudosia's! Think, cruel Aspar, Can I be patient in this abject State, Nor hope again to see my Native Rome? Imperial Rome! where my great Ancestors Have led, to grace their Triumphs, vanquish'd Kings, Chain'd and attending on their Chariot-Wheels: Will Heaven consent, within the Walls of Carthage, That Cæsar's Daughter be confin'd a Slave? No, tho its Eye seems winking for a while It can't approve the Guilt that it permits; Nor longer shall thy Master's faithless Pride Mock at the tardy Thunder unchastiz'd, But feel redoubled Vengeance from that Hand, That Power, his Infidelity despis'd; For all the Ravage of his barb'rous Arms, For our harsh Bonds, for Nations Rights infring'd, Sack'd Cities, and depopulated Lands. Asp. Madam, regardless of a Captive's Mein, The Empress' and your own unbridled Rage Breaks forth too oft in Language suiting ill— Eud. Ha! suiting ill! What suits it ill with these, These Bonds, to murmur at the Tyrant Hand That puts 'em on? No, Aspar, thou'rt deceiv'd, My Mother will be Cæsar's Widow still, True to her Blood, and every where herself: Should Fortune once more change, or Fate relent, She in her turn may triumph, in her turn Rise (from Captivity) again to Empire, And shew thy haughty Lord, and all the World, What distant Awe Rome's Empress may command. Is there a Chief renown'd for manly Daring, So deaf to Glory, or to Woman's Wrongs, That will not at th'Alarm our Fetters sound, From shameful Inactivity arise, To vindicate the Cause of injur'd Majesty? Asp. Madam, you rail, but by my Master's Fortune It seems full plain, that Heaven thinks otherwise Than your vain Hopes suggest: but henceforth, Madam, I would advise you to restrain this Phrenzy, Or you may find more reason to complain. But here's the Prince; already has he mov'd The King in your behalf, of him you'll know His Father's last Resolves, and his Success. [Exit Aspar. Enter Thrasimond and Narbal. Thr. Oh my Eudosia! Oh my Father! Eud. Enough, my Lord, I see what we must hope; The cruel Genseric is known too well. Thr. Why, why, ye Gods! of him must I complain, My rigid, deaf, inexorable Father! Believe me, thou much-lov'd, unhappy Maid! I spoke, I labour'd strongly in your Cause, Urg'd him with all the Violence of Grief That Love could utter, or your Wrongs inspire; Urg'd him by all th'indissoluble Tyes Of Honour, Force of Vows, and Faith of Kings: In vain, to move his Pity, did I plead Your Sex, the due Regard that Sex does claim, Your House, your Country, ruin'd by his Arms; Weak Motives all! yet all but that chaste Flame Which keeps thy Godlike Image ever here, Did I employ to move the stubborn King. Eud. Farewel then every Dawn of future Hope, Since Thrasimond could plead, but plead in vain. Oh Son too worthy thy remorsless Sire! On cruel Maximus to seek Revenge, Why did the injur'd Empress fondly court A false Ally in thy more cruel Father? Or if it was decreed his Hand alone Should be the Means of our Destruction, why Has erring Fate made thee the Tyrant's Son? Thr. Is this, ungenerous Princess! this Eudosia, That once indulgent, tender-hearted Maid? Roll back, ye Hours, that saw our early Loves, And witness'd to our Vows, when first I came Hostage of Peace, from Genseric to Rome; Tell my forgetful Fair she is unkind, My Father's Treatment to resent on me. Could not a Lover's tributary Heart, Hard Lot! atone the Error of my Birth? But why do I dispute with Fate, or Thee, When such a Train of Circumstances join To bar my Wishes, and oppose my Joy? Eud. Alas! what threatning Cloud of farther Ills Can this sad Mystery of Grief portend? Tell me, my Lord, can I have more to fear? Thr. Why dost thou ask? Thy Bonds, thy Mother's Bonds, Are both the Foes to Thrasimond, and Love. The Captive Empress! thence is my Despair, Can she look back upon the black Account Of one continued Scene of adverse Fate, Of Wrongs on Wrongs, and complicated Woes, And Genseric the Cause? Will she approve Alliance with the Son? No, there I'm lost. Eud. Ill do you judge; my Mother is a Roman, Too noble to be blind to Worth like thine; Wrong'd as she is, she weighs with Justice still, As well thy Virtues, as thy Father's Crimes: Nay, in her utmost Bitterness of Soul, When her revolving Sorrows bear upon her, Rise fresh to Thought, with aggravated Horror, When she complains of Genseric and Fate, With Joy have I observ'd her Griefs forbear To rank the Son of Genseric with her Foes. Thr. And how could I deserve this wond'rous Goodness? Eud. Is there not cause? When thy insidious Father Reeking with Guilt, and hot with human Gore, Spread Devastation thro the Streets of Rome, By Fire and Sword made Conquests terrible, Then did she see my Thrasimond stand forth To curb th'unruly Insolence of Victory, And pitying that Imperial City's Fate, Grant an Asylum to its guiltless Sons. Thr. But what does this avail my hopeless Love? Eud. These Benefits she knows, to these she adds A nearer, nobler Goodness than them all: Since Captives here, with what industrious Pity You labour'd with your Father for our Freedom. (Mercy, tho fruitless, valuable still!) Propose, deserving Prince, your own Reward. Thr. Tempt me not, Princess, what I now must ask, To claim profanely as my Merit's Due, 'Tis Height of Sin, Impiety in Love: To Beauty, as to Heaven, its Votaries dare No farther than in modest Hopes aspire. Eud. Then, Thrasimond, hope on, and be as blest, As, witness for me Heaven, Eudosia wishes In happier Times, she may have power to make thee. Thr. Well, well, dost thou reprove my sluggard Genius, So slow to teach my willing Heart the Means T'assure thy Liberty, and fix thee mine. By all the Gods of Glory and of Love, I will engage my Faith, you shall be free; Yes, yes, my suff'ring Fair, I've yet a Thought May aid our Hopes, and gain the wish'd Success: Sophronia to my Brother's Bed betroth'd, Whom I have ever mark'd with wondring Eyes, A ready, faithful, tho uncourted Friend, Shall yield us now a seasonable Service, And move my Brother Honoric, who stands. No less the Son, than Fav'rite of the King, To use his Interest, where my own has fail'd. Eud. 'Tis generously thought, my Thrasimond; But take not an Advantage of my Weakness, Yourself the only Witness of my Love. Go on and prosper in the friendly Office, Eudosia's the Reward: But oh! beware, Trust not too far that fierce, that haughty Fair-One; (Forgive these jealous Fears) for much I doubt Or her Sincerity, or our Success. [Exit Eudosia. Thr. Causeless are all thy Doubts, too fearful Princess: Why, let her know the Secret of our Loves, 'Tis safe repos'd, Sophronia has a Soul, Fierce as it is, too noble to betray us. Nar. My Lord, might Narbal speak his humble Thoughts, The Princess' Fears are not without a Cause: Sophronia views you with a Lover's Eye, Your Presence gives new Lustre to her Charms, And heightens every Beauty in her Face; She wears this Shew of Friendship, to conceal The struggling Efforts of a stronger Flame. Thr. Narbal, forbear, and check that impious Thought, Which moves thy Tongue to this unlicens'd Freedom; Her Faith's already given to Honoric: If she regards me with peculiar Friendship, 'Tis as a Sister to a Brother's Claim. Nar. If my suspicious Eyes inform me wrong, Or you, my Lord, yourself are most deceiv'd, A little Time will shew—But see, she comes! Enter Sophronia and Justina. Thr. Welcome, Sophronia, doubly welcome now, Thou Pride, thou Lustre of our Africk Courts; Deign, like the great enlivening God of Day, T'extend thy healing Influence to a Wretch O'erwhelm'd with heaviest Woe, and chain'd in Doubt: Ha! said I, Doubt? forgive the rash Complaint; What should I doubt thy Goodness, or my Cure, When you, and only you, can yield the Means? Soph. My Lord, yourself prolong your own Despair; If 'tis Sophronia's Hand must reach you Aid, Why thus do your ambiguous Words amuse The readiest of your Friends? Demand that Aid. Thr. No longer can my burning Heart support This furious Anarchy of warring Passions; Like some poor Wretch turn'd loose to Fortune's Frowns, To clam'rous Foes, and vile deserting Friends, The Curse of Thought, Reflection, and Despair, Too much I doubt each Remedy I wish; And yet I must, I will reveal my Pain: But let me first adjure you, summon up Each Faculty of Goodness in your Soul; By your great Self, and by your Sex I beg you, By all the softning Force of Sighs and Tears, With Pity hear, with gen'rous Speed redress A Prince, the Heir of Africk, and a Lover. Soph. Pleasing Surprize! he loves; o'erwhelming Rapture! [Aside. What means, my Lord, this frantick Dress of Words? Thr. It means the sharpest Sorrow Man can feel, The bitt'rest Pangs desponding Love can mourn. Soph. Love, Prince! and is it possible that you, Whose Infant Soul was practis'd in the School Of hardy Toils, and the rough Trade of War, Can own a Woman's Conquest, and resign Your Martial Fires to Love's enfeebling Flame. Thr. 'Tis Beauty, Madam, animates the Warriour, And Love that spurs him to the Tracts of Glory: Lay the World's several Empires in his Grasp, The Conquest would be judg'd a trivial Purchase, If Love, as well as Fame, were not to crown The Victor's Brow, and heighten his Reward. Soph. When Princes form'd like Thrasimond shall love, Their Passion may command their own Reward. Let Fear, Contempt, Distrustings, and Disdain, Be the due Portion of th'inferiour World, Dull, vulgar Courtship, and mechanick Love, Tortures unworthy you, young valiant Prince, The Fav'rite Son of Empire and of Glory: What Beauty worth your Passion, but with Pride Will meet the Proffer, and compleat your Hopes? Thr. Those Hopes must still rest uncompleated all, If you withhold your Aid; I would request it, But yet I fear: (curs'd Diffidence of Love!) Soph. Fear nought, but let me know, I'll soon convince you, How much you injure both yourself and me. Thr. Then at your Feet, thus humble'd I implore. [Kneeling. Soph. Nay, rise, my Lord, I must not see you thus, This Posture shames the Friend you may command. Did you but weigh this Torment of Suspense, With half the Transport that Sophronia's Soul Will know in labouring for your Ease, you would not, You could not thus delay, be thus unkind. Thr. Bless'd be the Tongue that utters so much Goodness, Gives such Presages of my future Bliss. Soph. Bless'd be the happy Hour Sophronia hears it. [Aside. Come, Prince, impatient I attend the Means, That, prosp'ring your Desires, may crown my own. Thr. Thus hear my Woes, and thence resolve my Fate: My Brother, Madam, is contracted yours, Both by my Father's, and the People's Voice. Soph. And what of that? Tho Honoric's your Foe, Sophronia may deserve a kinder Name. Thr. To you then I appeal for instant Justice: Or by your Goodness let this Anguish die, Or shall this Sword, the Soldier's brave Companion, Which has so oft in the red Sweat of War Made fierce Opposers fly their certain Fate, And bore the glorious Triumph of the Day, Now to a nobler Triumph turn its Point, And set its suff'ring Master free at once From his worst Foes, his Misery and his Life? You, Madam, have the Sway o'er Honoric's Heart, And may employ your Int'rest to procure (For he can have at will my Father's Ear) Th'unhappy Captive Princesses their Freedom. Soph. Ha! Thr. This is the Boon that Thrasimond petitions, This must resolve your Friendship, or my Doom. Soph. Perdition! Daggers! Hell! I die, Justina. [Aside. Thr. Nay, start not, Madam; but consider well What you've engag'd, what Thrasimond requests: Eudosia, she the fair Imperial Captive, Is mine by every Tye of mutual Love, Consenting Passions, and Cementing Hearts: 'Tis you that hold their Fates within your power, And 'tis of you that I demand their Liberty. Soph. Amazement! Horror! Now support me all Our Sex's Arts, their Pride, and their Dissemblings, Disguis'd Resentments, and suspended Rage, Nor let me shew myself the Wretch I am. Thr. Madam! Soph. My Lord, I'll make your Interest mine, You have Sophronia's Word, on that confide; But name th'unhappy Princesses no more. You love Eudosia, she returns the Flame; I have the Trust, depend upon Success, I will exceed my Promise in your favour. Thr. Then, Thrasimond, again hope, live, and love, Sophronia and the Gods declare thee happy. So when amidst the warring Surges Foam, The trembling Sailor sees his threaten'd Doom, When scatt'ring Billows o'er the Vessel lave, And Death's grim Terrors frown in every Wave; He to the pitying Gods commends his Prayer, They still the Storm, and save him from Despair. [Exit Thrasimond. Soph. He's gone! Now burst forth all the Rage, the smother'd Rage Of injur'd, thwarted, disappointed Woman, And let this Fury have its Loose of Raving: On this ungrateful, blind, deceiving Man, Let my full Bosom level all its Vengeance, Let me forget his Charms, and curse my own, My own too weak, too impotent Allurements. He loves! for ever let me curse the Sound, Since not the kind, the languishing Sophronia. What Guilt so heinous has my Soul conceiv'd, That could call down a Punishment so great, Successless Burnings, and a Man's Disdain! Alas! Justina, did I hear him right? And am I thrown beside all Hope for ever? By all my Wrongs I must, I will have Vengeance; But where, on whom, or how shall I direct it? Just. Madam, have happier Thoughts. Soph. Peace! poor Adviser. Eudosia, she the fair Imperial Captive, Is mine by every Tye of mutual Love! These were the direful, killing, damning Words. Eudosia! which? the Empress or her Daughter? 'Tis both their Names, and both are but too fair. Let me disown my Nature and my Sex, If ever I forget this worst of Wrongs, My slighted Beauty and neglected Charms: By Heaven I'll wreak my Vengeance on them both, Then this curs'd, happy Rival can't escape it; I'm justify'd by Love, 'tis his Revenge. Just. This Transport of your Passion runs too far; What has the Empress, or her Daughter done, To kindle up such Wrath? Soph. Done, done, Justina! They've ravish'd from me all, my Life, my Soul, The brightest Object of the fiercest Love, My Prince, my darling Hope, my Thrasimond. Just. Till now then was the Prince's Heart your own? Soph. Nor mine, nor any other's, till the Time, (Curse on the late Success of Gens'ric's Arms, That brought her first to Carthage to undo me!) When this detested Rival made it hers. Am I the first in Africk Courts for Beauty? And can I bear with Patience, think, Justina, That Curse of Curses to a Woman's Soul, To see myself out-worship'd and out-shone; That Youth my burning Wishes sought so long, Possess'd and panting in another's Arms? Just. Madam, if Reason— Soph. What of Reason? ha! Let Reason travel hence to distant Climes, To dastard Souls that court its feeble Aid; Love, Love, and dire Revenge have all my Heart. Just. If that the Prince had been unfaithful, then— Soph. Ah! if he were, I then might be belov'd. Nay, for another had he quitted me, So full, so just a Cause for my Complaints, Had made my Anguish less: but he is faithful, So faithful, that his Virtue is my Ruin; And faithful might his Soul have been to me, If I had dar'd to put it in his power, Nor kept this fatal Flame so long disguis'd. Why blame I him? my Miseries to myself Are owing all: Could Thrasimond divine But Honoric alone possess'd my Heart? Just. And is not Honoric destin'd for your Lord? Can you break thro th'Engagements bind you to him? Or unresenting would he bear the Wrong? He who so often murmurs at his Fate, Nor brooks, but with Repinings and Disdain, An Elder Brother's Right in Thrasimond, Could he behold the Center of his Wishes Snatch'd from him by the Object of his Hate, Nor hurried by his proud Ambition, vow His too successful Brother's instant Ruin? Soph. Thou art a Stranger here, nor know'st, Justina, With what indifferent Eyes, what cold Regard This Promise of a future Husband views me: No, Honoric's Heart is sensless of these Charms, His Love nought more than Policy of State. When to suppress the Insults on our Realm, My Father call'd in Genseric to his Aid, To engage him firmer, offer'd for Reward The Dividend of all his rescu'd Regions; Tempted by such a Prospect of Advantage, This proud aspiring Vandal soon approv'd The Enterprize, and with a thousand Vessels Darken'd the Shores of Africk, rais'd afresh Each drooping Heart, and chas'd away the Foe But, (faithless, false Appearance of Relief!) He sav'd us from one Enemy, to prove A greater, more encroaching Foe himself: Puff'd up with Conquest, and but ill content With the due Limits of my Father's Promise, This false confederate Friend, this Tyrant Victor, As fortunate in Arms, grew great in Guilt, Broke Oath on Oath, usurp'd the whole Dominion, Forc'd him to fly his now subjected Country, And end his miserable Days an Exile. Just. Disastrous Turn of Fortune! sad Relation! Soph. Yet Conquest gain'd not Love; the People still, True to my Father and his Injur'd House, Restless in Bondage, rose in my behalf, Revolting daily from th'Usurper's Side: Then Genseric, too subtle Politician, T'unite the jarring Int'rests of our Houses, Appease the People, and secure himself, Propos'd this Son, this Honoric for my Husband; Then scarcely six Years old; alas! too young To know the Imposition on my Fate: Since when I've liv'd as Honoric's Wife. But oh! Too oft, to my Destruction and Despair, With full desiring Eyes, and bleeding Heart, With anxious Joy, fierce Doubts, and fiercer Hopes, (The dang'rous Warfare of imperious Love!) I saw the elder Sunshine of the Court, The lovely Thrasimond; the rest you know. Just. I do, and share with you in all your Griefs. Soph. I thank thy Pity, Grief and Pity's all That Friendship can expect, or Friendship pay. But thy unhappy Mistress must do more, She must have Thoughts that swell beyond Complainings, Thoughts equal to her Miseries and herself: Justice and Vengeance! Just. How to compass them? Sop. That Thought's already mine; the cunning Aspar, The first in Trust, and second in the Empire, Owes to the Bounty of my Father's Hand His present Greatness and exalted Power, He'll scorn to prove ungrateful to the Daughter: And him will I employ, my glorious Engine To push my Wrath, and model my Resentments Through all the Windings of a Statesman's Brain, To dart their meditated Fury home On this disdainful, charming, hated Prince; To ruin Thrasimond, and break the more Detested Nuptials with his Brother off. Go, go, Justina, find the Statesman out, Tell him within an hour Sophronia waits him At private in her Closet; tell him all Her Fears, Despondings, Agonies and Wrongs Tell him the Source of all, and let him know How much I need his Friendship and his Aid. Just. And have you weigh'd with Caution the Result, These jarring Thoughts and puzzl'd Resolutions? You would break thro th'Engagements of a Match That thwarts your Inclination, and yet him For whom you break it, Thrasimond, you doom To an eternal Wretchedness: First think, And will you love him less? Soph. What, love him still! Witness ye Powers, and punish or approve As I pursue my Purpose, or desert it. What, languish for the Cause of all my Ruin! Then by severest Justice let me perish, Lightning or Thunder dash this Frame to nothing; Let suffocating Earth devour my Guilt, If I forget implacably to pay With bitt'rest Malice and eternal Hate This unregarding Insult to my Love; Or, what is worse, let me again be scorn'd, And live to feel my present Pangs for ever. Just. And yet I fear— Soph. Fear nothing for Sophronia: As on the Racks of jealous Love I die, With equal Fury shall my Justice fly; Unaw'd by Fear, by Danger, or by Shame, I'll brave my Ruin to avenge my Flame, Throw off my Sex e'er I'll my Rage abate, And be a Woman only in my Hate.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. Sophronia, Justina. Soph. Aspar has promis'd all my Rage could wish, And this Eudosia's Thrasimond shall find His Hopes like sickly Flow'rs abortive Pride, But feel an adverse Blast, and disappear. He who could slight Sophronia's proffer'd Charms, To doat and languish for a Slave's Embrace, Shall with an unsuspected Tempest shake, A Rival (in his Father) bear her from him: Genseric for weighty Arguments of State Shall court the Empress to his Crown and Bed, And leave the groveling Thrasimond to know Sophronia's dire Extremity of Anguish, Divided Loves, and separated Hearts! Just. And how are you assur'd his Heart is hers? Perhaps the Daughter's Charms may tempt him most. Soph. To think so, were to call him base indeed, Add to my Torments, and to his Reproach. No, 'tis th'Imperial Mother's fuller Bloom Of perfect Beauties, Majesty and Soul, That blinds the doating Thrasimond to me. The Empress has him all, and curse me Jove, If I could form a Wish of nobler Vengeance, Than to stand by a Witness to each Pang, Convulsive Throb, and rending of the Heart, This Separation by his Duty aw'd, This forc'd Concession to a Father's Joy, Will from his Soul extort with Tears of Blood. To view him plunder'd thus, his Heaven renounc'd, Another in his place, great Gods! his Torture! Just. That, that would be Revenge! Soph. It would indeed; Such as could only be improv'd by this, To see the young, resenting, amorous Prince, Throw the ungrateful Charmer from his Breast; And to torment her Pride with new Desires, Fierce Pangs, and anxious Burnings, languish here, Here at my feet, Justina. Just. Yes, Madam, then To triumph in your turn, to spurn him from you, And pay with Interest back his first Disdain. Soph. There thou hast struck me in the tend'rest Vein, The Woman and the Lover jar within me, I cannot, dare not answer for my Constancy, Put to so great a Trial; no, Justina, I fear to say what Thoughts or what Resolves, A Sight like that might teach me. Soph. How! what you? Soph. That former Burst of imprecating Rage That pour'd forth all the direst, fiercest Vows Of Malice, Vengeance, Cruelty, and Hate, Was but, I fear, too much th'impetuous Proof Of Passions unsuppress'd, and Love disguis'd; And hottest was that Love, by how much more My Rage was heighten'd and the Phrenzy swell'd. Just. Madam, the King is here. Soph. Confusion! how Shall I conceal my Blushes and Disorder? Enter Genseric, Honoric, and Aspar. Gen. You fly us, Madam, and indeed of late To our no less Amazement than Concern, We have remark'd a discontented Frown Still gathering on your Brow at our Approach. Have you or Grounds or Subject of Complaint? Speak, and we hear thee: But I guess the Cause, The Nuptial Rites have been delay'd too long, The promis'd Pleasure sickens to the Thought, And Expectation is at last grown weary. I doubt not but you wonder at the Reason; But rest assur'd we had a powerful Reason. Soph. Who shall controul your Will? You wrong my Soul, To think from thence that I contract my Brow, Accuse delaying Fate, or scowl at thee: No, 'tis the Pride and Greatness of my Mind, That knows whene'er my Presence is offensive, And learns me thus to ease myself and you. [Exit Sophronia. Gen. Act as you please, and tremble they who fear Thy feeble Rage, and impotent Designs; A more important Care takes up my Thoughts. Say, Honoric, canst thou love this haughty Maid? Open thy Mind, unaw'd and unreserv'd; 'Tis true I found it for my Safety once, When Africk's murmuring Regions brook'd but ill A Conqueror's Reign, and stood in Arms against me, To heal the publick Difference and the War, T'engage thy Faith to this Sophronia, then Heiress o'th' Realm; but now those Days are past, The City's free from Mutiny, the Court Unpoison'd by Cabals or State-Intrigues, The Party-Clamours hush'd, and Faction dead: Nor, tho this Calm has cost us Seas of Blood, Can I descend to think the Purchase dear. Here, Honoric, I acquit thee from each Tye, Each prior Obligation of my own, Chuse for thyself of all our Beauties one, To be the happy Partner of thy Bed, As Nature dictates, and thy Heart inclines. Hon. My ever-gracious Lord, that Choice be yours: My Heart, my Soul, my Passions and Desires Are all resign'd and wait on your Commands; Propose the Object of my Love or Hate, Your Will and Honoric's Duty are the same. Or to Sophronia, or another join This Son, or keep him unacquainted still With the enervate Joys of Hymen's Slaves, You'll find him Honoric, and your Son in all: Ambition is my Fav'rite Mistress now, The rugged Camp, shrill Fife, or glitt'ring Spear, The darling Conversation I adore. Gen. By Heav'n I like this mounting of the Soul, That far out-soars thy Father's lavish Hopes, That hunts bright Honour thro each puzzl'd Path; And bravely prizes Glory by the Toils That block the dang'rous, terrible Ascent. Yet Thrasimond by Birth succeeds to Empire, An elder Brother snatches thy Reward; And tho my Heart prefers thee in my Love, I yet, in spite of me, foresee the Day That thou must pay a Subject's Homage there, Unless we make the present Minutes ours, And add a foreign Sceptre to our own: I'll lay the golden Prospect to thy view; Pursue the great Temptation, fix Success, And satiate thy Ambition with a Crown. Hon. 'Tis greatly thought. Gen. And may be greatly executed too: Weigh but each Circumstance of Time and Things, All correspond, and promise certain Aid. Our Magazines are stor'd, Fleet stoutly mann'd, Our Coffers rich, each warlike Sinew strong; The neighb'ring Princes weak in every Part, Exhausted by the Length of former Wars, Enjoy the present Truce, indulge secure The short-liv'd Slumbers of a fancy'd Peace, Themselves and their Suspicions all asleep, What hinders but we make th'Advantage sure? But then, my Son, what Colour shall we use, To gild this Rupture with a Face of Justice? How can we draw the giddy Rabble in, But with the subtle Countenance of Right? Hon. What Right but that of Conquest can we claim? Gen. I have, my Son, a Marriage in my Thoughts, Would give a glorious Sanction to our Cause, And yield us all our Hopes: You shall be join'd, Not to Sophronia, alt'ring Time has render'd A Match impolitick and useless there: Eudosia, Daughter to Rome's Captive Empress (Gain but her Hand) can justify a War, And give thee Title to the Roman Empire: Her Father's Death, her Mother's forc'd Alliance With Maximus, his Tyranny and Guilt, Great Motives of Revenge, and Spurs to Conquest. That boasted Mistress of the World lies now Dispirited beneath a Load of Woes, Open to War, and prostrate to thy Sword, Shews but a Mournful Remnant of its Greatness; Where Grandeur swell'd, and Temples blaz'd with Gold, A pillag'd Country, and a desart World. Hon. And how will they admit that Son to reign, Whose Father's Hands struck deepest in their Ruin, And ravag'd 'mongst the foremost of their Foes? Gen. The Name of Foe will be expung'd in thee, When wedded to that Roman Monarch's Blood, Whose Memory lives worship'd with their Gods. Nay more, I've secret Friends, and great ones too, By Birth tho Romans, Vandals in their Hearts, And to our Int'rest firm: it rests in you To make the Princess yours, but that's a Task Where all the pow'rful Eloquence of Love, Insinuating Arts, and Court-Address, Must be apply'd to melt her to your Wishes; For know, her Pride is equal to her Birth. Hon. She knows not then— Gen. 'Twas never yet propos'd; Aspar himself, the foremost in our Trust, Was till this Hour a Stranger to the Secret: Not that my Soul defided in the Man, Who ever has approv'd himself with Honour The worthiest in his Service to our Throne; But till this Time uncertain how, or where, Your Heart might be engag'd and thwart my Scheme, I have conceal'd my well-concerted View; And had I found a Bar like that, myself, Rather than lose this golden Opportunity, This Height and Crown of my aspiring Hopes, Would have espous'd the Princess in your stead, Thrown off the Crime of disproportion'd Years, And sprung to second Youth in her Embrace. Our Fleet's already in th'Italian Seas; The Throne of Maximus is vacant still; And tho Avitus is proclaim'd in Gaul, Rome's yet without a Lord; the jarring Senate, Confounded in their Counsels and their Fears: Let but Eudosia head the Enterprize, With one consenting, general Vote declare Her Husband Emperor. Go, Honoric, go Fall at her Feet, woo, languish, press her warm, And think obtaining her, obtains a Crown. [Exit Honoric. What Lengths, what Hazards, and what Bars of Guilt, Would I not pass regardless, dauntless by, To compass this Extent of all my Hopes, And see him seated strong in Cæsar's Throne? 'Tis true, his Brother's generous and brave: But there's a Bent in Nature bears against him, And sways to Honoric most my yielding Heart. Say, Aspar, Can'st thou think the Princess dares Refuse, or not refusing, Rome decline To pay him Homage, and salute him Lord? Asp. To make both more propitious to their Vows, Then join your Houses by a double Match, Whilst Hon'ric woos the Princess to his Bed, Suppose the Mother worthy of your own: Her Soul, her Beauty, and illustrious Birth, All answer to your Honour and your Rank. Gen. Ill-judging Policy! A Marriage there Would be the surest Bar to my Designs! Can the yet-bleeding States of Italy So soon forget whose Invitation drew My Sword of Desolation thro the Land, Then to behold the Authors of their Woes So close ally'd?—Distraction would ensue! Would their imbitter'd Wounds then teach them aught But Curses, Hate, and Vengeance on us both? Asp. Their Hate, so deeply grounded, might as well Extend to all the Family. Gen. Aspar, No. What has Rome suffer'd from the Daughter's Hand? How can it then impute its Wrongs to her? Of Years too young, too innocent to mix In such important enterprizing Counsels, Urg'd by no Views of vengeful Malice; she Into its Bosom call'd no foreign Foe. But, Aspar, I have farther Reasons still, And foreign to the Policies of State: My Humour and my Age oppose the Match. The Empress is a Woman fierce and proud, Nor to be won with ease the common Way: 'Tis not a Sigh, sad Look, or soft'ning Tear Can again upon her Soul; her Pride expects An Age of awful Servitude and Homage, Assiduous Watchings, Languishments, and Racks, To recommend the Slave she deigns to hear. Asp. Think not, my Lord, she can, or dare be cruel. Gen. Aspar, I'd tear my Heart out sooner, far, Than yield Dominion to this Rebel Passion! If I have lov'd, I lov'd but for an Hour; Instant Fruition gave me present ease: I cannot, will not wait a slow Return. Dull Expectations are for vulgar Lovers, A Monarch's Time wears precious, and disdains To be expended at a Woman's Feet! Asp. But tell her that you love, and leave to me To let her know the Worth of such a Conquest. Gen. All thy Endeavours are superfluous still T'enslave thy Master, and enflame my Breast: I am not to be talk'd into a Lover. Aspar, 'tis time you seek the Empress out, And let her know my Purpose to procure The Union of our Houses: But she comes! Now Courtesy and Flatt'ry, aid me all To bend this stubborn, this imperious Spirit, That has withstood a Series of Misfortunes; Unyielding, unsubdu'd, and still the same. Enter Empress. Gen. Madam, at length our Hatred dates its End; On a King's Word, you shall again be free, Again shall you enjoy the Banks of Tyber: A hundred thousand of my choicest Troops Shall be your Safeguard, and conduct you there; All forfeit Life, or re-establish you: Myself in Person swear to lead them on. Nay, doubt not this; for by the God of War, By ev'ry Pow'r of Heav'n and Earth, I here— Emp. Gens'ric, Reserve those Oaths t'impose on Minds More easy, and more credulous than mine. They cannot cheat Resentments like my own, Too much already, and too long deceiv'd! Let Chains, and Deaths, and Lybia's groaning States, And all thy Tyrant Impositions there, Teach me to credit an Usurper's Faith. Gen. Is Faith that poor imaginary Virtue, That Dream, to preach a King into a Slave? The Statesman only makes it serve a Turn, And soon dispenses with the brittle Tie. But, Madam, your Afflictions are not yet Past Remedy; you shall be carry'd back In Pomp and Honour to your native Rome: To do you Grace, myself will wait you there. Emp. Has Rome more Treasures left to pillage, then? Gen. You do me wrong, 'tis for your sake alone. Emp. For mine! 'Tis falsly judg'd, to think that I Can give you Colour for a second War. Would you revisit Rome, resolve on some New Motive, some more plausible Pretence. Gen. I here propose the Union of our Houses; To join our Int'rests, and conclude our Jars: Let this evince how much I am sincere. Emp. Unite with thee! Oh! sooner, sooner far, The Poles shall meet, and Contraries agree; Th'Antipathies of Nature be forgot; Wolves graze with Lambs, and Vultures roost with Doves; The Wretch that's stung, with fatal Mercy nurse The Viper in his Breast, than we forget To hate eternally thy Race, and thee. Gen. Nay, storm not, this is what I gladly wish Accomplish'd for the Int'rest of us both; And in behalf of Honoric, my Son, The Benefit I offer to your House, With Joy attend, with Gratitude embrace. I make you Mistress of the Roman Empire, As soon as Hymen's sacred Rites unite The Princess and my Son. Emp. My Daughter, ha! I'd rather plunge a Dagger in her Breast, And save the Glory of our spotless Race, Than see the hated Coupling: curs'd Idea! Change, change, my Lord, this generous Design, 'Tis too much Honour for our hopeless State: For shame! what, Honoric wed his Father's Slave! And will he stoop to such Indignity? He cannot, sure, approve it: For myself, I could with fuller Satisfaction meet Befriending Death, than such a wond'rous Bounty. Gen. This is too much; but I advise you, Madam, Henceforth beware, nor urge my Fury more: Learn, with becoming Thanks, to prize the Glory A Victor and a King descends to proffer. Ha! know you, with one Nod, like Jove, I could— Emp. What could'st thou do? Speak out, I scorn to tremble; And, Blusterer, dare thy Menaces their worst. Oh! would thy Rage be once severely kind, And end this hated, this inglorious Life, I'd bless relenting Fate, and pardon thee; But thou'rt my Tyrant, and my Curse in all: I beg but Death, and thou deny'st me that. Gen. Those only wish to die who fear to live, Fetter'd with Guilt, Reflection, and Remorse, Made Cowards by an Age of former Crimes: Hence this Distaste of Life, these desperate Thoughts. Emp. But those who know no Crimes, know no Remorse. Gen. Can'st thou acquit thyself? Think, think again, What was the Death of Maximus? He was— Emp. A Villain, and a Tyrant like thyself. Oh! could I, to th'all-searching Conscience here, But answer ev'ry Action of my Life With equal Boldness, as that glorious Deed That compass'd my resolv'd, my just Revenge On him by whom my former Husband fell, That durst aspire, and did by Force succeed My Valentinian in his Throne and Bed! I suffer'd him to wed me, gave my Hand, When most my Heart was meditating Vengeance, I yielded to his Wishes and Embrace, But as the surest Method to destroy: And let the future World learn this from me, Where Injuries deeply strike, those patient Slaves That feel their Smart, yet dare not to revenge 'em, Like flying Soldiers, mark'd with shameful Scars, Disgrace their Beings, and deserve their Wounds. Gen. I understand you, Madam, and, indeed, This Spirit of Revenge, and Thirst of Blood, Speak the ambitious Race from whence you sprung; All Italy has curs'd its fatal Guilt. Emp. And Carthage may have cause to curse it too. The Princess is my Daughter, and, be cautious: Each Maxim of her Mother's was impress'd And grafted early on her Infant Mind. She knows the noble Soul that suffers Wrong Demands as great a Vengeance to appease it: Timely retract the Honour you vouchsafe her; Nor rashly covet an Alliance there, The Blood of Theodosius swells her Veins. Know you what Opportunity of Justice Her Rage may seize to vindicate our Wrongs? That Head may be in danger even here. Gen. This Insolence instructs me to beware. Yes, I will guard this Head. But, Madam, hear me; Look to't, your Daughter, e'er the Morning's Dawn. Vouchsafes a quick Compliance to our Will, Or I may take my turn to threaten next: Know, 'tis enough that I command it so. She comes! I'll leave you to consult yourselves. [Exeunt Gen. and Aspar. Enter Eudosia. Emp. Daughter, you're yet a Stranger to your Fate: Gens'ric has chose a Husband for your Bed. Eud. For mine! From whence this insolent Proceeding? Am I at his Dispose? Emp. He thinks, indeed, He does thee too much Honour by his Choice, When he prefers thee to a Son of his. Eud. A Son of his, ha! Honoric's betroth'd; And Thrasimond—But, Madam, to your Will, I am a Daughter, and Obedience all. Emp. I see the fond Delusion of thy Hopes: Daughter, you love the Prince, and love him still. Thy Mother gives Consent; nay, bids thee bless A Youth, so well deserving of us both, Who views our Mis'ries, and his Father's Crimes, With just Disdain, and sympathizing Woe, Sever'd by Virtue from his barbarous Race. But, oh! prepare thee for a Shock beyond His former Insults, or these servile Chains. Maugre the Faith of Oaths, this Tyrant King, In bold defiance to the Gods and Justice, Breaks with Sophronia thro each sacred Tie, And gives her promis'd Honoric to you. Eud. Unhappy Revolution! Can it be? Emp. So sure, so dreadful is it, only he, That Prince you love, is able to prevent it: Tell him the threatned Wrong, implore his Aid; He is the Idol in the publick Eye, The Promise and the Hope of ev'ry Heart: And if he loves, what dares not Love attempt, To force thy Rescue from a Rival's Triumph? Eud. Instead of hazarding a Life so dear, Should I explain my Sorrows to his Brother; Could he then dare— Emp. Alas! What dares he not? 'Tis not for Love that he aspires to thee, But as the Ladder to the Roman Empire. His Race, his Pride, and his Ambition's known: We know him, base, and cruel as he is, The fav'rite Heir of all his Father's Crimes. Eud. And can we count so many neigb'ring Realms, Confederate Nations, and Allies to Rome, Yet none to rescue her Imperial Blood From these Barbarian Insults? Where is fled That dreaded Roman Spirit, that of old Inform'd her Heroes with the Souls of Gods? Emp. That Glory is eclips'd; the present Rome Is but a shameful Shadow of the old: We're beaten and despis'd, the Roman Virtue, And far-fam'd Roman Grandeur, are no more. Oh, Italy! Oh miserable Country! Once was't thou stil'd the Arbiter of Kings, Th'expanded Globe, all bending to thy Laws; But Heav'n has now forsook thee in its Vengeance: Thy Crimes have made thee weak; yes, yes, 'twas those, Not Genseric raz'd thy Temples to the ground; By those thy costly Palaces have blaz'd, And we, tho guiltless, feel the Guilty's Fate: Not one Ally will arm in our Defence; The Wife and Daughters of those Godlike Men, That were the boasted Masters of the World, Groan unassisted in a State of Bondage. Eud. Oh! that a speedy Death would give us that The Coward Martian dares not undertake! Emp. Slave to an Oath, which once redeem'd his Life, He vainly pities what he fears to aid. Go, Daughter, find out Thrasimond, make him The Witness of thy Tears, and thy Distress, Let him the Father's Tyranny atone, Espouse thy Cause, and make thy Wrongs his own.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. Thrasimond and Narbal. Thr. Am I reserv'd to be th'eternal Mark Of Heaven's Resentment, and the Slave of Fate? Tyrannick Sentence! Anguish undeserv'd! Ha! Narbal, speak: say, did'st thou tell me right? Or am I only tortur'd by my Fears? Have I then lov'd so fiercely, and so long, To find a Rival Brother dash my Hopes? He quits Sophronia, he forsakes his own, To prove himself a Villain, me a Wretch: Why must I suffer from a Brother's Guilt? Where are his Oaths, that to Eudosia thus He pays the Tribute of a perjur'd Heart? Why were Sophronia's Charms too weak to hold him, Bar his Revolting, and prevent his Crimes? Or why was my Eudosia form'd so fair? Nar. My Lord, he acts not of himself alone, But counsell'd and supported by your Father. Thr. Does he then, partial Parent, barb'rous King! Act so unworthy both those sacred Names? I see, great Gods! you are Confederates all, Join in my Ruin, and conspire to curse me. But heard you how the Empress did receive This rash Proposal? for my Princess, she, I know, opposes their unjust Designs; And would they force her to their Tyrant Wills? Nar. My Lord, she comes herself, to her I leave you, To gain a further Knowledge of your Fate. Enter Eudosia. Eud. (After a long Pause.) Thus strangely fix'd, thus silent to your Friend, Not speak to your Eudosia? Cruel Fate! Then I sorefee my Wretchedness indeed. Thr. Alas! my Fair, I'm searching in thy Eyes To teach me what to say. Eud. Oh Thrasimond! Needs then thy Heart an idle Prompter there, To teach you how to greet the Maid that loves you? But that, my Lord, I fear, like faithless Friendship, Unkindly now abandons the Distress'd, Nor shares Eudosia's Griefs, nor bleeds with mine; Else sooner had it taught thy frozen Tongue To make me some amends for all my Pains, To tell me thou wert true, and felt my Woes. How art thou chang'd! I see my Ruin plain; Now welcome Death, thou far more generous Friend To her that loves, but is belov'd no more. Thr. Belov'd no more! retract the Accusation! Say'st thou I love thee not? Let every Pang Of Doubt, Confusion, Anguish and Despair, That shews the present Tumult of my Soul, In speaking Sadness, and expressive Looks, Upbraid thy Charge, and witness for my Truth. No, I would ask Instruction from those Eyes, How I must now address myself, to whom, My Sister or my faithful Princess still. Eud. Ha! barb'rous Thrasimond, and can you then Suspect me yielding to a Crime like that? Thr. No, when I do, may I deserve to lose thee; Then may this Rival, this exulting Brother, With Heart dilated, Eyes of fiery Transport, In all the furious Throbs of blending Love, Snatch thy rich, panting Beauties to himself, Act all my hop'd-for Pleasures in my stead, And in the Folds of thy luxuriant Charms Shew every jealous, envying, wishing God, A Rebel Mortal happier than themselves: May I be doom'd to see it, may I serve To aid his Raptures by my own Disgrace. But thou art true, and all those Joys are mine; Eudosia says she loves: repeat it, Winds; Ye Rocks in Echoes catch the blissful Sound, And in eternal Harmony relate How fair, how constant she; how happy I. To fear, is impious! Hence, vain boding Terrors! Thus strengthen'd, what are all the mighty Names Of Brother, Rival, Father, Monarch now? Eud. But, Oh alas! my Lord, we have to fear Much cause indeed, much more than you foresee; The Brutal Threats and Fury of the King, These are your Rival Brother's dreadful Arms, These Honoric's Boasts; and what for my Defence, But Woman's feeble Refuge, Sighs and Tears? Thr. What d'you account th'Assistance of this Arm? Eud. What, rais'd against a Brother! No, my Lord, Were my Resentments doubled with my Wrongs, I would not covet a Revenge so dear, To buy it with the Guilt of him I love. Thr. Would you then have me bear with coward Patience A happy Rival's Insults? No, my Princess, Your Beauties and your Wrongs shall cancel all Th'Affinity of Birth, or Ties of Blood: Should he but dare the Violence you fear, What Awe, what Duty, should deter this Arm From vindicating thee with ample Justice? No, tho' upheld by Genseric, to his Eye I'd scourge his minion Son, thro' all the Court Proclaim my Cause, and own no Pow'r but Love. Eud. My Lord, restrain your Anger, Gens'ric comes. Enter Genseric. Gen. Madam, I sought you out, to let you know, What Honours I've design'd your House in you, To give your Term of lengthen'd Sorrows End, How far my Pity reaches. Eud. Pity, ye Gods! Thr. Sad Mockery of Words! Barbarian Pity! [Aside. Gen. Why, Madam, flow these Tears, or whence your Pain? Eud. Insulter! do you view me here, and ask, With feign'd Surprize, the Reason of my Tears? Am I a Roman? Can I call to mind Afflictions and Disgraces heap'd upon me; My self a Captive, and my Country's Pride Levell'd and Ravag'd by thy guilty Sword, And wear a Face of Smiles amidst my Ruin? Or have these Chains sufficient Harmony To lull and sooth my Bitterness of Soul, Put Balm into my Wounds, and dry my Tears? Gen. Mistaken Princess! why d'you cherish still, With idle Piety, and guilty Fondness, The sad Remembrance of a Place so fatal? Of Rome, yet reeking with your Father's Blood! Disclaim th'ungrateful Land, forget your Birth, Wed Honoric, and Africk be your Country. Eud. The Guilt of Italy at length is clear'd, Its Stains are by its Punishments effac'd; Its Crimes were great, and infinite its Woes; Short were the Traitor's Triumphs; certain Death Soon paid his Treasons their deserv'd Reward. Should Carthage pay Rome's Price for all its Guilt, Then I might change my Form, and smile indeed. Gen. Madam, my Favours brook not this Return. Eud. Resent it as you may, I never can Nor will forget thy Cruelties. Gen. Is this, This to be cruel? (Give me Patience, Gods!) To raise thee from a Slave, ungrateful Woman! And join thee to the Royal Blood of Genseric? To change thy Bonds for Diadems and Power, And lay thy Passage open to the Empire? Eud. What are to me these vain Temptations? what The Charms of Empire, Diadems, or Power, But glitt'ring Bubbles, with a mimick Splendour? What from the gilded Prospect can I hope, But added Woes, and multiply'd Distress? What would it aid my Miseries, to trace My great Forefathers down from distant Time, And number all the Kindred Cæsars out, But make me more unhappy than I am? Compare my present Fortune with my past! Shew me the glorious Height from which I fell, A Princess to a Slave! the racking Thought! Oh! had I sprung from some less noble Race, Of humble Parents, in a Peasant Roof, Then might I suit my Temper to my State! Then might I learn to brook Captivity, Own Gens'ric for a Lord, and cringe to thee! Gen. This is the haughty Language of the great, The noble Sentiments of Royal Pride, And Minds distinguish'd from Plebeian thinking; But spite of all thy boasted Pedigree, Know 'tis my Will, that Honoric espouse thee; Dispute not my Commands, for by my Crown I'll use the glorious Privilege of Power, And shew my self thy Master. Eud. Tyrant, well Boast'st thou the Sway that Fortune gives thee o'er me: But you deceive your Vanity, to think That Fortune has the Power to make me less The Daughter of an Emperor; I know I am your Captive, but I know withal, That being so, I am a Princess still. Indulge the glorious Privilege of Guilt, What Chance and Infidelity have gain'd thee; Be cruel to the utmost of thy Power, My Heart is still my own, and scorns thy Threats. [Exit Eudosia. Gen. Ha! Am I Africk's Lord, and hear I this? Or but the Shadow of Authority? What! have I conquer'd to be disobey'd, Thus brav'd, thus spurn'd, thus slighted by my Slave? I've been too patient, and debas'd the Monarch, But will assert him: This imperious Captive Shall soon be taught to know herself and me. 'Tis not a List of Ancestors shall fright me, Or authorize her Arrogance. Thr. Oh, Sir! If on my Knees I might be heard, Your Honour— Gen. My Honour! 'Tis no longer to be worn, Than useful to the Int'rest of my Crown: Wisdom consults the Welfare of the State, And not the Glory of a barren Virtue. Thr. But see them twisted in each other now, Like kindred Plants, to rise or fall together: Maintain your Honour, you support your Crown. Have you forgot the Time, this stubborn Land Disputed ev'ry Step by which you rose, And made your doubtful Claim of Conquest shake? What could your Armies to secure Possession? What but the promis'd Marriage of my Brother With young Sophronia, could appease their Clamours, And fix you on the Throne? You gave your Oath. Tho' till her riper Years defer'd so long, Should not the Nuptials be concluded now, What may we not foresee? I dread to think! Gen. The Gods that disapprov'd th'imprudent Oath, Have given me Power to disengage me now, And have absolv'd me from each slavish Tie: Yet for a Colour, in some neighb'ring Prince I will provide a Husband for the Maid; To that she shall consent. Thr. By such a Step, Africk is given up to endless Woes; Divisions growl afresh, new Factions rage: You sully all the Fame you have atchiev'd, In well-fought Battles, and successful Councils: You leave a Name to late Posterity, Odious, and mark'd for violated Oaths. Gen. Ha! wherefore dar'st thou thus rebellious Boy! Whence does thy Vanity derive Pretence To awe my Actions, or reform my Conduct? Owe I to thee the Glories of my Reign? To thee the great Success of all my Toils, Th'Exploits that lift me up above the soar Of common Kings, and fix me with the Gods? Is't from your Valour, or your Prudence, ha? That tributary Worlds revere my Name, And shudder at the Thunder of my Arms? Where is the Homage, the Respect, you owe Ungrateful! to a Father and a King? Thr. Yes, Sir, I am your Son; nor have so soon Forgot the Duty that I owe a Parent: Nor does that pious Rev'rence less appear, In this Concern, this Boldness that inspires me, To save the Glory you so rashly hazard. Sophronia has a deep ingrafted Sway; The Mistress of the adoring Peoples Hearts; Who weds her, makes a dangerous Advantage. Gen. 'Tis well: She must be married then in Carthage. Thr. She'll ne'er consent a Subject should enjoy, The Charms she hoarded for a Prince's Bed. Gen. I do believe it. Thr. Who shall wed her? Gen. You. Thr. Forbid it, righteous Gods! I wed Sophronia! What have you said? Gen. Is she unworthy of you? Is Africk's Heiress one to be despis'd? Can you be more, more happy than in her? Thr. Shall I espouse my Brother's plighted Bride? Sophronia ever claim'd my just Esteem; I view'd her as a Sister; gaz'd upon her, But with the Chastness of a Brother's Love. Could I exceed those Bounds, and not incur That Guilt recoiling Nature most abhors? Would you not chuse to hate me do not make My Disobedience rise from your Constraint. Gen. Impertinent Excuse! But hear, base Boy, Nor dare the Fury of an anger'd Monarch, Whose Pride is to be absolute, as those Who thought me fit to reign, my Partner Gods, Whose Will is Wisdom, and whose Word is Fate, Jealous of Pow'r, impatient of Controul: Know, Rebel, this is Genseric's Decree, To Morrow, when the Nuptial Forms have made Your Brother Honoric, and Eudosia One, The Priest shall join Sophronia and thy self. Forfeit thy Duty; dare dispute my Doom! Thr. My Duty and my Reason, both direct A ready blind Obedience to your Will; But Love, sole Lord and Monarch o'er it self, Allows no Ties, no Dictates but its own. To that mysterious arbitrary Power, Reason points out, and Duty pleads in vain. Gen. Aspar, to you I leave it to provide The necessary Ceremonies strait: I'll not be trifled with; who disobey, Their Life shall pay the Forfeit. Think on that. I leave you, Prince, but torture not thy self, To study more Evasions to delay me; For, by the Gods, I'll not be satisfied With less than a Compliance, by to Morrow Receive thy Bride, or Gens'ric may throw off The Father, and exert the King indeed. [Exeunt Gen. Asp. Thr. Gods! how I labour with this civil War, Of Duty and of Love! ill-fated Prince! On what canst thou resolve? weigh justly what Thou ow'st the Names of Father, and of King: Much to them both, I owe; but much, much more, To the deserving Object of my Vows. To her my conquer'd Inclination bends, And each subsiding Duty yields to Love. Then let us fly th'inhospitable Realm; Fly with Eudosia from my Father's Rage: Oh where, but Dangers will pursue me still? Where, but to change one Mis'ry for a worse, And tempt a thousand Rivals, flying one? Her undesigning Beauty will undo us. She is so fair, that each enamour'd Prince, Will envy me the Blessing he protects. Ha! is not Honoric the cruel Source Of my severe inextricable Woes? I'll tear him from my Breast, no more my Brother: I'll chase him as an Alien, and a Foe. Nar. But not attempt his Life? Thr. Thus low reduc'd, Push'd to the Terrors of extream Despair, By an inhuman Father's partial Hate: What may not Wretchedness like mine attempt? What can I hope, but Death and my Revenge? Is't not enough, I'm tortur'd to behold My Princess drag her ignominious Chains? Is't not enough that I receiv'd my Life From him, that King, that Foe, that has betray'd her? Is't not enough, that I am still repuls'd, When at his Feet I bend for her Release? Is't not enough the Tyrant gives her from me? T'enrich my rival Brother, ruins me! But must he shew me yet a fiercer Proof Of his unnatural Hatred, force my Hand To act so adverse to my bleeding Heart, And wed the wrong'd Sophronia? Oh, ye Gods! Does Perjury to him appear no Crime? Or seems no Crime unlawful, that affords The pleasing, cruel Means to injure me? Enter Sophronia. Soph. I come, my Lord—but find you much surpriz'd! Say, may I credit what the King has told me? Thr. To your Misfortune, 'tis a Truth too fatal. The King is too sincere, he cancels all The Ties that bound my Brother and your self; And chuses out a Husband in his stead, Whose Heart's unworthy of you. Soph. Ha! unworthy of me! I was in hopes, my Lord, since he design'd To break the destin'd Match with Honoric, He would have kindly given me to a Prince, Who from admiring Infancy has reign'd The constant Object of my wishing Soul: Whom Love has made the Ruin of my Peace: The Master of such Virtues, and such Charms, As justify that Love, excuse my Fondness, And draw in ev'ry captivated Heart. Thr. I thought my Brother had Success enough, To have secur'd that Heart, and fix'd it his. Soph. Did you but think, my Lord, how much I strove, To force it to my Duty; did you know The hard, vain Strugglings of a love-sick Maid, In this desponding agonizing Conflict; By all my present Pangs, you'd not condemn me. Oh! what's Resistance, when the Foe is Love? But since a happier Fate has set me free, And Honoric's call'd away by other Ties, Why must I find my Bliss oppos'd by You? 'Tis You that have the Pow'r o'er him I love; From You I wait my Destiny. Thr. From me? Soph. From You, my Lord. Need I discover more? Is not my Meaning plain? You hold my Fate. How slow you are to save a Virgin's Blushes! But oh! be kind; prevent th'unequal Match, To which you say the cruel King condemns me. Yet (strange Effect of ever-wishing Love!) So much the Image of that Godlike Youth Fills my adoring Thoughts, and reigns in all my Hopes, That tho' you kindly undeceive me now, Some Throbs auspicious in my flutt'ring Heart, Insinuate, that 'twas him your Father nam'd: Resolve these Doubts, and tell me who he is, This Undeserver; arm me to reject him, And to repay the falseness of his Vows, With Scorn, with Indignation and Disdain. Thr. His greatest Fault, alas! is want of Love; No other way unworthy to espouse you: He has some Merit, and a Royal Birth, But wears a Heart that never can be yours. He wooes another, for another burns, And with a Flame so constant and so fierce, That to remove its stubborn settled Sway, My Father threats, your own bright Beauties shine, And Death, in all its Horrors, frowns in vain; Behold the Husband. Soph. Hell! do I hear all this, Yet trifle in the height of my Destruction! My Lord, I know the Husband is design'd me, And longer to disguise my self is vain. [Ex. Soph. Nar. Her Eyes, at parting, shot a dreadful Gleam Of Indignation, Passion, and Revenge. Thr. Ha! can I answer for the Turns of Fate? Sophronia now believes—unthought of Horror! How one Misfortune rises on another! One dismal lengthen'd Scene of endless Woe! Oh! my Eudosia! there's my deepest Wound! My Brother haunts thee with malignant Love, With savage Lust he marks thee for his Prey. Sophronia's ill-tim'd frantick Passion makes My Torments more inextricable still. Since th'angry Gods thus meditate my Ruin, Wound by so many Foes my injur'd Hopes, And aim a separate Bolt at ev'ry part; On me alone the Burthen shall not fall, I'll spread their Horrors, and involve us all.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT IV. Honoric and Aspar. Asp. You are too rash, consider well, my Lord, And weigh the value of Eudosia's Love; Think not the Toils of Courtship ill bestow'd, Nor quit the glorious Chase for one Repulse, An artful Coyness, or dissembled Frown. Go on, my Lord, pursue the Princess close; If Love is silent, let Ambition speak; No less than Rome's the Purchase of your Pains. Hon. My warlike Soul disdains the servile Task, And bends not to the softning Arts of Love, Fondly to gaze upon a Woman's Face, Fling my self prostrate at her Feet, and waste, In Sighs and Languishments, the tedious Hours. I cannot brook her insolent Denial. Nor more, tho' Genseric himself commands, Will I endure this haughty Captive's Scorn. Asp. Can you, my Prince, so easily resign The tow'ring Hopes of Sov'reignty and Power, And for the peevish Coyness of a Girl? Forbid it all ye Gods! renounce an Empire? Hon. I'll find an easier Passage to a Throne. But hold, my Brother Thrasimond appears. Enter Thrasimond. Thr. My Lord, I would request your private Ear. Hon. Aspar, retire.—And let my Father know, With what disdain the Princess heard my Suit. [Aside. [Ex. Aspar. Now, Sir, your Will, and why this angry Brow? Thr. You know, young Prince, I am Sophronia's Friend; You know those Ties that are for ever held To Honour, Virtue, and to Justice sacred, Plighted your mutual Faiths, and made you One. Hon. T'appease the wild Disorders of the State, I know, long since, my Hand was promis'd there. Thr. But yet, my Lord, well-grounded Fame reports, That you have broke those Ties, Set Justice, Honour, and the Gods at nought; And have abandon'd the deluded Maid, To make an Off'ring of your Heart elsewhere. The Roman Princess, fair Eudosia, shines The present Object of your faithless Vows; Her conq'ring Beauties have seduc'd your Virtue, Misled your Fame, and prompted you to Perjury. Hon. Whoe'er could tell you this, was ill advis'd; He misinterpreted my nobler Views, And wrong'd the Greatness of my mounting Soul. If I have stoop'd to court Eudosia's Love, As the chief Bliss to which my hopes aspire, Yet were her Beauties the least pow'rful Motives. Thr. Whate'er those Motives are, I'll term them base, When thou pursu'st them with a perjur'd Heart. Prince, I have undertook Sophronia's Cause; Nor can she suffer, but when I am wrong'd: Reflect on that, and know, tho' certain Ruin Attend my just Resentment, I am still Prepar'd to strike on suff'ring Honour's Side, And take on me the Inj'ries offer'd her. Hon. What Right has Thrasimond to curb my Will, Whilst Gens'ric counsels and approves my Deeds? But this is not the first nor only Mark, Of your fixt Hatred to the King and me. With Eyes malevolent you view me soar, On Eagles Wings, above thy feeble Daring; Envy my happy State, and curse thy own; It galls, a younger Brother stands before thee, In a King's Favour, and a Father's Heart. Thr. Hence, Insolence! thou know'st that Heav'n and Nature Have giv'n me Pow'r to scorn thy pigmy Boasts, And, by my Birthright, plac'd me in the Rank Of thy Superiors: Vain presumptuous Stripling! Know, I've the Pref'rence o'er thee ev'ry way. Hon. Such was the Pref'rence Heav'n bestow'd on Gundric; But Genseric, like me, his Father's Favourite, By him supported, could with Smiles look down On his resenting Rival's harmless Envy: Whilst Heav'n, at length repenting of its work, Rais'd him above that elder Brother's reach. Thr. Are these the Hopes that flatter thy Ambition? No more vain Boastings; to the Field of Honour Adjourn the Contest; let our Swords decide, Who best deserves the Pref'rence, Thou or I? Maintain the Glories that thy Pride assum'd; Shew how thou soar'st above me, make it out, Or else retract thy Error with thy Shame, And own the Coward, and thy borrow'd Plumes: Come, let us try if Heav'n will now repent. Hon. With joyful Confidence I meet the Challenge. But see, the Princess! I avoid her now, For certain Reasons; we may meet again. [Ex. Hon. Thr. I'll follow thee; and Fate shall now determine Whose Cause is worthiest, whose the happiest Arm? [Going out. Enter Eudosia. Eud. Oh! whither do you fly, my Thrasimond? Turn back, turn back, and ease Eudosia's Pain: Assure me thou art true, that still thou lov'st. Thr. What reason has my Princess to distrust it? Eud. I know I ought not to distrust thy Truth. What tho' thy cruel Father harshly dooms, Another should be happy in thy Arms, Yet sure my Thrasimond can ne'er comply With this Injustice to Eudosia's Love! No! to suspect thee, is not to deserve thee. Thr. To tell my doubting Fair how much I love, Gestures are weak, and Eloquence is cold; Judge by his Actions, of the Man that loves you, Let them speak for me, them confirm my Truth; Ev'n now the Coward precious Moments fly, That should be all laid out for Love and thee. Eud. Where would you run? see, see, my Mother's here! Thr. Gods! still another Bar to my Revenge? Enter Empress. Emp. You seem displeas'd, my Lord, and in your Looks Glares fiercest Rage: What can disquiet you? You that are set above the rest of Men, On a fair Mount of rich encircl'ing Honours, As Favourite of Heav'n, and Pride of Earth: Your Father's Africk is in full Repose, Both foreign and intestine Dangers curb'd; The neighb'ring Princes dread his powerful Arms, They court his Friendship with submissive Offers, And bribe him with the Wealth of half their Kingdoms: With prosp'rous Gales his Vessels reach the Port, And pour the Eastern Treasures at his Feet. Can you, the Son of Empire, then have Cause To frown, when such unnumber'd Glories wait you, As Indian Monarchs on the rising Sun, And emulate each other to adorn you? And to compleat your Joys when Hymen's Torch Prepares to light you to the nuptial Bed? Thr. Sooner let all Mankind be arm'd against me, I'll stand the Shock; sooner shall these Hands Tear out my Heart, and cast the Traitor from me, Than I consent to be the Wretch they'd make me, Blaspheme the glorious Object of my Vows, And forfeit the rich Center of my Hopes. Madam, I could no longer, if I would, Conceal this Secret, of my faithful Flame, And her who blew it up: Can you forgive The Rashness of a Prince, that dares aspire To your fair Daughter's Love? Or will you now Improve this Opportunity of Vengeance, And for the Father, crush the suffering Son? If so, behold my Bosom, strike, my Fate Will be too glorious, when I fall by you, A bleeding Victim at my Princess Feet. Emp. To talk so, is to charge me with a Vice, That never found Abode in Roman Breast. Bound by an equal Duty, to repay An Obligation, as revenge a Wrong, I know thy Value, and have heard thy Love, And whilst I give my Daughter to thy Wishes, So much the Merit of thy Virtue weighs, I scarce agree to think the Balance just, And blush to find my self thy Debtor still. Thr. Oh! what Injustice do you offer here! Who but your self could justify the Crime, To put my blushing Merit in the Scale, With Beauties, full Reward for sighing Gods? What have I done, another would not do? What have I done that's worthy of my Cause? Such Charms t'inspire, such Glories to requite me! Or oh! against a Father and a King, What! can I thus a Slave to Duty dare? Gods! were your Bonds put on by other Lords, That Thrasimond might arm without a Guilt! Emp. Partake this Ardour which your self inspir'd, Daughter, Love only is by Love repaid. Thr. If you obey the Empress, think you raise A Mortal to a God: You give those Joys, Would make me look on Perils, Toils, and Death, With elevated Heart, and pleas'd Disdain! Charm'd with Elyzian Paradise in view, Vent'rous I'd dare a thousand Stygian Lakes, And leave my Fears to shiv'ring Crowds behind; But give me your Commands, and they are done: What's Opposition to surmounting Love? Eud. Alas! 'gainst Genseric what can be done? Arm'd with the Names of Father and of King, The Aid Love proffers, Duty still controuls. Thr. My Princess, no! I'll serve you uncontroul'd; Your Eyes that prompt, can authorize my Crimes; Love is my God, let those who feel his Sway, Excuse the mighty Pow'r he shews by me: Madam, this Night your Freedom I engage; I'll bear you from your Bonds, and Carthage too: I'll animate my Friends to aid your Flight, Intrepid Men, Strangers to pausing Fear, That grudge no Toils, when Thrasimond's their Leader: Narbal shall wait you at th'appointed Hour: I go—mean while beware, Our Looks prove not Betrayers of our Purpose. [Exit. Eud. Oh! Thrasimond, I feel I love thee now! By this severe Anxiety of Soul, By all this rising Tenderness, that checks, And spreads a chilling Damp, o'er all my Hopes, I fear thy Danger, whilst I wish my Freedom; And rather let me groan in Bondage still, Than from the hazard of thy Life, derive Unwelcome Liberty, and sully'd Joys! Emp. Needless Alarms! when arbitrary Fortune, Constant in changing, shifts her fickle Scene, Informs us, she is tired with torturing on; To dissipate the darker Clouds she spread, Salutes us with a fairer Prospect now. Sophronia comes, 'tis fitting we engage Her seasonable Aid in our Designs; By Hon'rick slighted, by the King betray'd, She'll join with willing Heart, in all our Schemes, And make her Int'rest in the People ours. Enter Sophronia. Soph. Forsaken as I am, I come not now To vent the Taunts of Jealousy on you; In spite of my Dishonours, view me still, No fierce resenting Rival, but a Friend; I have bewail'd your Mis'ries long, and now Would have you take th'Advantage of your Fate; I would assist my perjur'd Honoric's Flame, And, for your sake, would sue in his Behalf. Consent to make him happy, as the Means To make your own Misfortunes short; oh! weigh The Benefits Compliance will obtain, The Danger a Denial will incur! The King is ever resolute in Vengeance, If now provok'd, I dread the dire Event! Emp. We owe these kind Professions of your Friendship And Zeal to our unhappy Fortune much; But ease your Fears, you need not, I assure you, Distrust a Rival here; the Tyrant's Son, Honoric, may still be faithful, and your own; I'll ne'er degenerate below my self, Nor, in whatever Forms they sternly menace, Will I be aw'd by Dangers, to consent To mix the Blood of Genseric with Cæsar's. Soph. Is Thrasimond a Stranger to that Blood That makes his Brother odious? No, there is A Difference, there is a Line that parts them In your Affections; Thrasimond himself Has told me all, and 'tis in vain for you To study to conceal his plighted Joy: Mov'd by a Flame so tender, and so true, I swear to join in ought to set you free: Madam, this Day shall shew how much I'll dare, To be reveng'd on an ungrateful Man. Emp. If Thrasimond has told you his Success, He told you what was true, and well deserv'd; His Generosity of Soul spoke for him; His Mercy on our abject State extended, When all could spurn the wretched, but himself, Oblig'd the scanty and too mean Reward; All he has done for us at Rome, and here, Declare him worthy of my Daughter's Heart: Worthy to fill my great Forefather's Throne: And could I with my Daughter give him that, I'd count it as my Pride, to have reviv'd The dwindled Glories of degenerate Rome. Soph. 'Tis well; I know my Rival then at last! [Aside. Emp. Madam, your Friends are powerful and many, And may assist Prince Thrasimond's Designs: This Night for our Escape. Soph. Then where's Sophronia? Abandon'd, left behind, and lost for ever! It must not be! (Aside) Yes, Madam, you shall see How I will use the Man that has despis'd me: His proud Refusal of my proffer'd Love, Shall cost him dear. Emp. Be silent; here's the King! Enter Genseric, Aspar, &amp;c. Soph. Silent, when barefac'd Treasons are avow'd! I an Accomplice! You are betray'd, my Lord! Conspiracies are brooding too too near you! Who the Fomenters, but your beautious Captives? And who the rebel Leader, but your Son? This Night he vows to shake off his Allegiance, And bear these Pris'ners from his Father's Chains. Emp. Distraction! all is ruin'd! [Aside. Eud. Oh! my Fate! [Aside. Soph. No doubt, to prove the fierceness of his Love, And sate their Lust of Vengeance, he agreed To ev'ry Term propos'd, with ready Guilt; Nor in the trait'rous Consult spar'd your Life. [Ex. Soph. Gen. Yes, we suppose our Life must be the Price That your Resentments ask. We thank ye, Gods! Who have defeated all the Villain's Hopes, And sav'd us from the threaten'd impious Stroke! Go, find the Traitor out, secure his Person; And if he offers to resist, dispatch him. [Ex. Capt. of the Guard. Eud. Inhuman Monster! [Aside. Emp. Genseric, Is this The suiting Conduct of so great a King, To yield a dangerous Belief so soon, To this mad, slighted, vengeful Woman's Tale? No, Sir, I tell you 'tis a false Alarm, My Daughter has a Roman Soul, like me, And is not to be bought by him who makes His Parricide a Merit to her Love. Re-enter Aspar. Asp. Your Orders are obey'd, the Prince is seiz'd; Chylax the Captain of your Guard surpriz'd him, Encounter'd with his Brother. Gen. O the finish'd Villain! What! do his daring Treasons spread so far, And will he strike at all his Line at once? But say, was Honoric safe? Aspar. Disarm'd, but yet unhurt. Gen. Thank Heav'n for that! But for this Stain, this Blot to all our Race, This most consummate Traitor of a Son, The sharpest, fiercest Torments are too weak. Load him with double Chains, and in a Dungeon Shew him the Image of his future Hell: (His Crimes would sully the fair Face of Day, And make the abhorring Sun draw back his Beams;) Whilst we in Council meditate a Sentence, If possible, proportion'd to his Guilt: His Execution's fixt before we sleep; You, Madam, who seduc'd him to this height Of Sin, and prompted his Rebellion; you Shall be the chief Spectator of my Justice, Assist my Vengeance with those guilty Eyes, Sharpen each Pang, and give th'expiring Traitor, In his last Gasps, an Earnest of Damnation. Then learn to trifle with a Monarch's Rage. [Ex. Gen. &amp;c. Emp. Go, Monster! challenge all thy Africk round, The glorious Range of arbitrary Brutes! To shew a Brute more savage than thy self. If Curses can o'ertake thee, thou hast mine, With Rage unlimited, and ample weight. [Ex. Emp. Eud. He's lost! he's lost, for ever, and for ever, To these expecting Arms, that stretch in vain To clasp my Hero round! for me he dies! Perfidious, base Sophronia! Tyrant King! But wherefore do I rave, when Words but injure The fierce Confusion of my tortur'd Brain? And shall I be upbraided with his Fall? Choak me, my Sorrows, let us die together. I'll fly, I'll fly, and meet my suff'ring Lord! One Sentence shall to both one Fate afford! And since our Stars are purpos'd to destroy, We'll baulk their Malice, and our Pangs enjoy: We'll make the Bed of Death the Bed of Love, And shame those adverse Gods we could not move. The End of the Fourth Act.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT V. SCENE, A Prison. Thrasimond, and an Officer. Off. My Lord, I grieve to tell you, that this Hour, You must resolve to die; behold the Mandate, Sign'd by your Father's Hand! Thr. I doubt it not: I've known the Gods and Genseric too well; Let me not blame 'em now; for this Dispatch Is some atoning Kindness to my Fate; I would be swept from Earth without a Thought, Nor give my slumb'ring Passions time to wake, And shiver at the doubtful, distant Stroke: Let guilty Wretches, and Plebeian Souls, Cling on the joyless Precipice of Life, And tremble on the Racks of Hope and Fear; I scorn to fondle the precarious Moments, And envy Death the Glory of a Conquest. (Eudosia entering, Thrasimond starts.) Eud. Where is he? Neither Bars, nor Guards shall hide him from me! Our Mis'ries may obtain one last Embrace; I'll do the dreadful Office of the Wheel, And kill him in these Arms, with cruel Fondness! He lives! malicious Pow'rs, be still a while, And justify your Sentence if you can! Thr. There was but this, ingenious hostile Stars! That could reduce me to a Man again. But now, I soar'd to Liberty and Bliss! Uninterrupted Bliss! and happier Worlds! And now the Dream's dissolv'd, and Hell's before me. Why, my fair Love! why thus severely kind? Dost thou come here to rouze me to Despair, Revive each Pang of Wretchedness within me, Recal my settled Spirits to Confusion, And aid the Horrors of embitter'd Death? Eud. Am I so shocking to thee! but indeed, I have deserv'd the worst thy Wrongs can call me. 'Tis I, not Genseric, have pass'd thy Doom! I fix the Wheel, and sluice thy bleeding Veins! Upbraid me, do; and I will bless thy Justice. Wither this fatal mischief-making Face! Curs'd be this Beauty! this alluring Ruin, That drew thy stagger'd Virtue to Destruction! And yet I lov'd thee: Tho' you think me still, The Cause of thy Undoing, yet I nurs'd These guiltless guilty Beauties, but for thee: With thee, the Sun that cheer'd 'em, shall they die. Thr. Gods! Cut me off this Moment, balance all Your Tyrannies, with that one Act of Mercy! I am unworthy this prodigious Proof Of your vast Power to punish. Oh, Eudosia! By all our mutual Agonies, I swear, Thou—(must I say it!) art my greatest Foe! But save me from my present Wounds, I'll count Flames, Racks, and murd'ring Engines, Beds of Down. Off. My Lord, When Death's appointed Hour's so nigh, Lose not the few remaining Minutes thus. Thr. Lose them not! No, I will employ 'em here! I tell thee, Slave, those Tortures are for Children. Basely I wrong'd my Father and the Gods, To say it was unkind to send thee here; To fall attended by such costly Tears, Suff'ring for thee, and thus by thee bemoan'd, Is glorious Torture, and a Death for Princes. Eud. Ha! Death, again that Sound! alas! what is it! Daggers to th'Heart! and Thunder to the Ear! A sad, eternal Separation's in it! Where are our Hopes, our Wishes, and Desires! That met each other with a mutual Heat, And flatter'd us with Ages of sweet Transport! All shorten'd by the sweeping Scythe of Death, And stinted to a doubtful Minute's Space? Thr. Then let us lay this Minute out with Prudence, And give it all to Love: I should have said, To Love's severest Task, and learn to part, As such unhappy, faithful Lovers ought. Eud. Were we to do indeed as Lovers ought, Together should we brave the Bolt of Fate, Lock'd in each other's fond Embraces; thus Lay down the Burthen of encumbring Life, In the extatic Struggle, unregretted. Thr. A little longer, and I shall be quite That Coward Fate would wish me: Oh! forbear! Each Look, each Word, each Touch of Kindness from thee, Unnerves me, melts me to th'Assaults of Fear, And almost makes me grow in Love with Life. Eud. And who would take it from thee? What! thy Father! Ha! must thou die, attempting to restore To me, that Fredom thou hast lost thy self! I cannot bear it! no! I yet will save thee, If all the wretchedness of prostrate Grief Can have the least Effect; if Tears, or Pray'rs, Can gain on thy Barbarian Father's Heart, I'll sooth him to Humanity; he shall Retract his Sentence, and forgive his Son: Or if nought else can sate his curs'd Design, But Blood, I'll slake his horrid Thirst with mine. [Ex. Eud. Thr. Farewel, my Love! I know th'Attempt is vain, And will embrace this Opportunity, Of cutting short the thousand thousand Pangs Of parting, all the fierce reluctant Strugglings, That make this Death the dreaded Guest he is. Come, lead me to the Scaffold, where my Soul Must work her Way thro' Tortures, to her Freedom: Your Expedition will be welcome now. [Exeunt. Scene changes to the Palace. Enter Sophronia and Justina. Soph. Where am I? Where's the King? Where's Thrasimond? Distraction! Horror! Hell! what have I done? Oh the rash Act! Oh most abandon'd Woman! Impeach'd my Love! and doom'd him to the Rack! Where shall I fly, to skreen me from my self, And bury the Reflection of my Guilt? Fatal Resentment! Oh severe Event! Oh Thrasimond! my Love was all my Crime, I fear'd to lose thee, therefore have destroy'd thee! Curs'd female Rashness! whilst my false Revenge Recoils with double Fury on my self: Justina see, shroud me as eternal Darkness! A pale, a bleeding Spectre glides before me, Rolling his ghastly Eye-balls full on mine, As he would say, Sophronia is my Murderer! Where is the King? Why name I him? The King Has not one human Virtue in his Soul: Nay, even now's impatient till the Deed, The horrid Deed's accomplish'd, and he gluts With filial Blood his unappeas'd Barbarity! Just. Madam, the King is here; some new Alarm Glooms on his angry Brow with fierce Surprize. Enter Genseric. Gen. All Carthage is in Arms; the mut'nous Crowd, Under the Colour of your Name, presume To countenance Rebellion, and demand The Traitor Thrasimond's devoted Life; Basely confound your Interest with his, And say he dies for vindicating you, From the Injustice of our broken Vows. This is th'opprobrious Language of the Curs That bark at Pow'r, but I will soon chastize Their Insolence, and let my Thunder loose On ev'ry Rebel Head: Sophronia, first Go you, and shew the Rabble their Mistake; Pronounce a general Pardon, in my Name, Upon a quick Return to their Obedience. But if they dare persist, let Hon'ric shew The Terror of our Arms, and make the Slaves That slight our Mercy, tremble at our Sword. Ha! are you mute? Do you approve their Treasons? Obey my Orders, or I'll use e'en thee As a Confederate, and a Trait'ress too. Soph. Well, Tyrant! dost thou make a full Return For my rash Loyalty and foolish Honour? Do you suspect me? Have I then secur'd Thy tott'ring Throne, to be distrusted now? Unravell'd all thy Enemies Cabals, Murder'd thy Godlike Son, and damn'd my self, To be accus'd as an Accomplice now? But thou at last instruct'st me how to do Justice to Thrasimond, my Self, and Thee. [Ex. Soph. Gen. This Woman's Temper puzzles and confounds My nicest Politicks: Methought her Words Swell'd with a doubtful Meaning; 'tis not fit We leave this dangerous Spirit unobserv'd. (Gen. going out meets Eudosia.) Eud. Where go you? Stay, oh stay, inhuman King! Do not delight in Murder; spare your Son! I am the Criminal, on me take Vengeance. 'Tis Justice; drench your Hands in hostile Blood, But do not, do not stain them with your own. Behold! the Daughter of an Emp'ror sues! The Line of Theodosius deigns to kneel! Would you be Great and Glorious? Think on Mercy! Mercy! the brightest Diadem of Empire! Mercy! that does distinguish Men from Brutes! And Kings that use it right, from common Men! Say, Gens'ric, say that you revoke his Doom, And Thrasimond shall live! Gen. Off, Syren! off. I am above thy Arts: By Jove, he dies. No more; but thank my Mercy thou surviv'st him. Eud. But save him, I forgive thee all the Wrongs Offer'd our injur'd House. [Shouting without. Gen. Ha! whence this Shout? Eud. Ha! dost thou start! it is a guilty Shout! And oh! my sympathizing Heart suggests, That it proclaims the Murder of thy Son! And see, the bloody Tyding-bearer comes! Now, Tyrant! glut thee with the horrid News! [She swoons. Enter Aspar hastily. Asp. Arm, arm, my Lord, the Torrent rises high! Sophronia animates the rebel Croud, Prince Thrasimond's releas'd, and at their Head! Your Guards are beat, and Honoric is slain! Be reconcil'd to Thrasimond, nought else Can quell the Tumult, and preserve your Crown. Gen. Perdition! all my Pride at once o'erthrown, And shall I cringe to this seditious Herd! And with extorted Mercy bless this Traitor Son! Let their Arms thunder at my Palace-Gate, I'll be a Monarch still in spight of Fate: Thus weaken'd I will yet defend my Throne, For Kings are guarded by themselves alone; Rather than poorly quit the Regal Sway, Add to the Tempest that I cannot lay. [Ex. Gen. and Asp. Eud. (Raising her self up) Why wake I? wherefore could I not for ever Shut out the hated Day? Since he, alas! That added to its Lustre is no more! And must I number Death among my Foes! Was he so nigh me, and at last withdrew, As loth to bring his ghastly Comfort yet! Enter Empress. Emp. Rise, Daughter, Sorrows are untimely now, And Tears ungrateful, the revolving Tide Of flowing Fortune is again our own; You mourn the Prince in vain; he lives, and flies Swift at a willing Army's Head to save thee: Snatch'd from th'impending Stroke of Death, his Name, Thro' the loud Trumpet of exulting Crowds, Swells in the Air, and pierces to the Skies. [A mixt Shout is heard of Thras. and Soph. And hear, the Sound's repeated! Eud. 'Tis indeed! And yet methinks 'tis ominous, Sophronia! Was not her hated Name repeated too? And wafted upwards in one blended Shout? Enter Sophronia and Narbal. Nar. At length the great Event of Battle's o'er, By his own Crime perfidious Gens'ric's dead. When, by his Presence aw'd, his duteous Son Check'd his impatient Friends uplifted Arms, And bid the War stand still; upon his Knees With pious Rev'rence fell, as he disown'd The Conquest he had won, and humbly begg'd Those Terms, that by Success he might command: Strait on his prostrate Son, with double Rage, Th'implacable revengeful Father rush'd, And aim'd a guilty Dagger at his Heart; But Heav'n, the watchful Guardian of the Good, Misled the erring Weapon's Point, and turn'd The Death he doom'd his Son, upon himself: Shock'd at the horrid Act, the raging People Breath'd on the Instant, with one Voice, Revenge! And at th'Alarm as soon the Monster fell. Soph. Now, Prince, I hope I have aton'd my Rashness; Nor shall my Bosom longer glow in vain, With jealous Scorchings, and tormenting Wishes, But find at last, my well-deserv'd Return. Ha! Is that Sorc'ress here! by Heav'n, her Eyes Ferment the Wounds of Jealousy anew, And chafe each vanish'd Torture to fresh Madness! I know her by the Tumult of my Blood, That swells with Rival Hatred at her Sight. But what should I distrust, since Thrasimond, By Gratitude and Honour, is my own! Let me indulge the Woman, let me plague her With taunting Triumphs, and insulting Joy; I'll talk of the dear Prince, since hers no longer; I'll mortify her Pride ten thousand ways; Extol his ev'ry Charm, and give her all That Hell of Torments I endur'd so long. Eud. Madam, I see an envious Pleasure smiles On your big Brow, that you can now upbraid me, That whilst I only had the Pow'r to mourn The direful Sentence of my absent Lord, To you I owe his Rescue and his Life. Soph. Poison destroy th'insinuating Witch! Does she expect I rescu'd him for her? To aid her Passion, and assist her Transports? He comes! the lovely Royal Charmer comes! And looks as ev'ry Deity had join'd, To dress their Fav'rite with distinguish'd Brightness; Majestically terrible as Mars, Yet soft and graceful as the Queen of Love. Enter Thrasimond running and embracing Eudosia. Thr. My Life! my Soul! Eudosia! my fond Arms Open spontaneous to receive thee home, And strain thee to my Heart! I fear I shall Grow impious in my Joy, and quite forget The dreadful Price this sully'd Pleasure costs, My Royal Father's and my Brother's Blood! Unnatural as they were, my Kindred still! Soph. Furies and Scorpions! I am torn to pieces, And Hell is an Elyzium, if compar'd With half the Frenzy of my present Pains! Yes, I have conquer'd to a noble Purpose, To bless my Rival, and to sink my self To the extreamest Depth of burning Woe! Do you, at last, vouchsafe a Look on me! It is, I must confess, a kind Return For Life, for Love, for Liberty, and Empire, Restor'd by me! ungrateful, barb'rous Wretch! Thr. Madam! Soph. Nay, do not varnish o'er thy Baseness, With all the treach'rous Rhetoric of Words: I know my self and thee too plainly now! I know I have been bounteous to a Serpent, That thankless bites its Benefactor first! I know for whom I live to be despis'd! But think not my proud Rival e'er shall reap What never could be mine! thus, lovely Traitor! Since then in Life we never could be join'd, Death shall unite; this Minute ends us both! [She first stabs Thrasimond, and then her self. Thr. What could provoke this Rashness! my own Wound Is slight, but to thy Breast, unhappy Maid! The Dagger carry'd a too fatal Point! She faints! the Blood forsakes her lifeless Cheek! Support her! fly for Aid! Soph. 'Tis needless all. I feel the thrilling Guest thro' ev'ry Vein! My Death is just for my Attempt on thee! Forgive me, Thrasimond, and thank'd be Heav'n, The Dagger only enter'd where it should. Oh Prince! if I have lov'd thee with a Flame, Beyond the nice Restraints of Virgin's Love, It was the Fault of Fate, and not Sophronia! [Dies. Thr. Not to allow thy hapless Fall a Tear, Were barbarous indeed! Peace to thy Maiden Shade. Emp. Bloody Effect of Passion! Eud. Fatal Deed! Thr. Yet ev'n amidst the Horrors of this Day, When I look here, a Gleam of Brightness dawns Thro' the deep Gloom, auspicious to my Love. [Taking Eudosia by the Hand. Emp. Her Mother thus confirms your promis'd Joys. Thr. Let me receive them thus, from Heav'n and You. [Kneeling. I know beyond the Bliss of Monarchs now; With joyless Heart I mount my Father's Throne, My truest Empire is in Thee alone. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>