<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">The John Hopkins Press</field>
      <field name="author_facet">The John Hopkins Press</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">the john hopkins press</field>
      <field name="author_text">The John Hopkins Press</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1920's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V1.1063.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1920</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:459692</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The 11. pagean of Iephte</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The 11. pagean of Iephte</field>
      <field name="title_facet">11 pagean of iephte</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">11 pagean of iephte</field>
      <field name="title_text">The 11. pagean of Iephte</field>
      <field name="year_display">1920</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1920</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1920</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459692&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459692&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The 11. pagean of Iephte&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;11 pagean of iephte&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1920&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1920&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The 11. pagean of Iephte&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Baltimore&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;The John Hopkins Press&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1920&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3873636-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv11063&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 20th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;20th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The 11. pagean of Iephte&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 33 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Medieval verse drama.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and editorial matter including introduction omitted&lt;lb/&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;lb/&gt;Source texts incomplete&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: The pageant of Iephte.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: English mystery and miracle plays.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1610 ?</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 1610–1625.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The 11 pagean. of Iephte. Square brackets represent additions by the current editor</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Actors Names Mobal Galaads sonne legitimate Gryphus Galaads sonne legitimate Polax Galaads sonne legitimate Iephte Galaads sonne &amp; Iudge of Israell Nuncius Ardellio Nobleman of Galaad Burbo Nobleman of Galaad God Legatus Kinge of Ammon. filia Iephte</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Mobal Iephte though we can not deny but thou art Galaads sonne a Galaadite, &amp; lusty warrier, whose valure is well knowne to vs thy brethren &amp; thy countrymen, yet syth thou art a Harlotts sonne, &amp; not our mothers, thou must from hence depart &amp; no inheritance haue wt h vs, wc h to legittimate children of right belonges, &amp; not to such as basely are begotten. Iephte. Brothers I sory am to leaue my fathers house &amp; country by th'Ammonits perplexed thus: But syth there ys no other remedy I'l both forsake, &amp; to the land of Tob go, &amp; there dwell an other land's as good for me as this. So fare you well. Gryphus. So now we are rydd of this Harlotts bratt: yf that we were as well shutt of the sonnes of Ammon we might lyue out of feare: But how that may be brought to passe I hardly can deuyse because their number's very greate, &amp; they are potent enemyes. polax Yt's true: &amp; yet to free our selues · yt standeth vs vpon wherefore about yt to consult let's forth wt h hence begone Iephte. Now am I in the Land of Tob aryu'd where I do fynde the people vnto me (though lately come) frendly &amp; kynde &amp; many of them willinge are to serue me in the warres (though of the Baser sort) whom I haue intertayn'd as Souldiers &amp; will do mo, yf they make suite, for I shall haue imployment I hope for them: wherefore I'l go, &amp; geue mo intertaynment. Nuncius Since Iair the Galaadite dyed who twenty two yeares Israell iudged &amp; was wt h thirty sonnes princes of thirty cettyes blessed The Israelits as you haue heard, are fallen to Idolatry agayne, &amp; our Lord god forsaken haue, for wc h they bee by hym into the philisthimes &amp; the Ammonits hands deliuered by whome they haue the space of Eightene yeares bene sore oppressed wc h hath inforct them to repent, &amp; cry to god for mercy &amp; what successe their suite will haue shall straight apparent bee yf you will but geue eare a while, &amp; listen wt h attention. to what shall be here after sayd. And so I will be gone Ardellio, Mobal, Burbo, Gryphus et ceteri. Lord wt h one heart &amp; voyce we prostrate here before thee fall confessinge our synne in forsakeinge thee, &amp; seruinge Baal God. Haue you not bene oppressed both by th'Amorrheits &amp; th'Ægiptians &amp; by the Ammonits Phylisthins, Amelec, Chananits &amp; Sidonians? &amp; when you cry'd to mee, out of their hands I you deliuered, &amp; yet you haue forsaken mee, &amp; other strange gods worshipped. Wherefore I will deliuer you no more. Go now &amp; call vpon the gods wc h for me you haue chosen Astoroth &amp; Baal Let them saue &amp; deliuer you in the tyme of your distresse Ardellio, Mobal et ceteri. Lord we haue sinn'd: render to vs what s'euer doth the please. only deliuer vs now, &amp; wee'l cast our strange gods away out of our coasts &amp; serue our Lord for euer &amp; for ay Lo Lord all th'Idolls of strange gods away we haue now hurled God And for your miseries I am sory: &amp; you shall be releeued. Mobal, Burbo et ceteri. Thankes Lord. Ardellio. Princes &amp; Neighbours now let's go agaynst our enemies syth god's our frende, &amp; promised hath for to releeue our myseryes. And let hym be Duke of our people that first begins to fight &amp; shall incounter wt h our foe &amp; aduersary the Ammonite who in our country Galaad hath allready pitcht his Tent Burbo By my aduise let's go &amp; fetch to vs Iephte incontinent agayne out of the Land of Tob, for hee's a gallant souldier &amp; none's so fitt amongst vs all as he to be our Leader yf we can hym persuade to come agayne backe to his country Ardellio, Moball et ceteri. Your counsayle's good, we lyke yt well, Let's go send for hym presently Come Iephte be our prince, &amp; fight agaynst children of Ammon Iephte. Are not you they that hated mee? &amp; did you not abandon &amp; dryue me from my fathers house? And forced by necessity are you come to me now for ayde &amp; help in your extremity? Mobal for this cause we are come to thee, that thou mayst wt h vs go agaynst children of Ammon for to fight our mortall foe. &amp; be the captayne of our people that in galaad dwell Iephte Yf vnto mee you be sincerely come to craue my counsell &amp; help agaynst children of Ammon, yf our lord should deliuer them vp into your hands, Shall I then be your prince &amp; leader? Ardellio Our Lord that heareth all these thinges hym selfe shall witnesse bee that we will faythfully performe all that we haue now promis'd thee Iephte. Then will I wt h you go &amp; Ammon send a messenger some questions to propose to hym ere wt h hym I incounter. In the meane space we'l ready make all things that needfull bee for the resistinge of so potent &amp; so stronge an enemy Legatus Great kinge of Ammon I am come to thee for to demaund in Iephte prince of Galaads name why thou dost waist his land? Kinge of Ammon Because Israel my land tooke when as out of Ægypt hee ascended, wc h from Arnon to Iaboc &amp; Iordan lye wherefore let hym wt h peace now of the same make restitution Legatus. Israel tooke not the land of Moab nor the childrens of Ammon But when he out of Ægypt came he through the desert walked vnto the redd sea &amp; to cades, &amp; thence messengers directed vnto the kinge of Edom sayinge: Let me passe through thy land. The lyke request he made to Moab: but neyther his demaund would graunt: wherefore he stay'd in cades; &amp; afterward he compassed the Lands of Edom &amp; of moab, &amp; beyond Arnon camped where on Moab borders, &amp; he would not into Moab enter. He sent to Sehon kinge of th'Amorrheits also, who would not suffer hym to passe through his land but rays'd agaynst hym a great army &amp; our Lord vnto Israel deliuered hym &amp; his country. And wilt thou now possesse his land wc h god to hym deliuered? Are not those things due to the wc h chamos thy god possessed? why then shall not these things be ours wc h god obtaynd as conquerour? vnlesse perhaps thou better be then Balac sonne of sephor the kinge of Moab, or canst shew that he agaynst Israel wrangled or fought wt h hym whylst he in ye litle Towns of Hesebon dwelled or in all the citties nere to Iordan for three hundred yeares in all wc h tyme thou hast not yt reclaym'd as appeares &amp; therefore he in keepinge yt no wronge at all doth offer thee but in denouncinge vniust warrs thou dost to hym great iniury. Our lord be Arbiter this day betwene Israel, &amp; Ammon. Kinge of Ammon. What we haue done we will mantayne: &amp; so thou may be gone &amp; vnto Iephte signify so much in Ammons name, who not wt h standinge his prescription agayne those countries clayme, where now he dwells, &amp; will them repossesse by dint of sword in spyte of Iephte &amp; the Israelits: So bringe them word from mee: &amp; tell hym I his message scorne, &amp; so adewe Legatus. Ammon I will, &amp; thou perhaps this thy contempt may rewe. To Iephte Iudge of Israel now this message I'l go beare. But stay in as fitt tyme as I could wish he cometh here Iephte most valiant prince thy worthy message Ammon scorneth &amp; sayth the land wc h you possesse to hym self apperteyneth &amp; hautely vnto your honour he sendes by me this worde that in dispite of you he'l winne the same by dint of sworde Iephte He might haue sayd yf god will hym permitt, whose powerfull spyrit imboldneth me wt h out delay hym in the field to meete. And to our Lord I make a vow yf he graunt me the victory &amp; make the sonnes of Ammon in these warres subiect vnto mee who s'euer first out of the dores of my house comes &amp; meetes mee in peace returninge, to our lord shall sacrificed bee in token of my thankfull mynd, for I assured am that yf I gett the victory yt's god that geues the same In whom puttinge my confidence agaynst Amon I'l go although my Army is but smale, &amp; he a potent foe I see thou neuer fayles them lord who do relye vpon thee &amp; I most humble thankes vnto thee render for this victory agaynst the sonnes of Ammon, whom thou by thy mighty power subdued hast, for wc h thy holy name be prays'd for euer And the vow that I made to thee I'l faythfully performe by sacrificinge the first thinge I meete at my returne that out of my house dore shall come. Alas &amp; wayle a day first out at dores my daughter comes before me for to play vpon her timbrell wt h her maydes, who dauncinge follow after in token of the ioy they haue conceiued for the slaughter of th'Ammonitts, wc h I haue made, &amp; for my glorious victory. Alas pore soule shee litle dreames that shee must dye so shortly. Yf my owne death would satisfy my vow I would dye for her: But shee yt ys that meetes me first that must dye &amp; no other. for sorrow I can not choose but rent the garments of my backe: syth no meanes there ys lefte to saue her lyffe, alack, alack. my vow ys made &amp; that to god who looketh for performance there of, &amp; yf I breake yt may iustly take on me vengeance. Offence yt ys wt h the performance of my vow to linger &amp; griefe yt will be to vs both yf I there wt h acquaint her. But rather then I'l god offend, my lyfe I hazard will &amp; for a sacrifice to god myne only daughter kill. filia Iephte Lord god of hosts for euer more let thy name praysed bee who to my father geuen hast so glorious a victory agaynst children of Ammon who are now quite ouerthrowne for wc h through all coasts of the world thy fame shall be made knowne Iephte If that I were not comfortlesse this musicke would delight mee shee plays so well, obserues such tyme, &amp; singeth so melodiously. Yf I geue eare there to a while I shall my self forgett wherefore the tyme no longer I'l delay, but forth wt h lett her vnderstand what I haue done. Daughter thou hast deceiu'd mee &amp; art deceiu'd thy self, for my word's past to god almighty that who so euer mett me first returninge back wt h victory (as thou hast done) vnto our lord should sacrificed bee and the word may not be recald that to our lord ys passed filia Iephte father vnto mee do what s'euer you to god haue promised Syth he hath graunted you the victory ouer your enemyes only I one petition do request of you, wc h ys that in the mountaynes wt h my fellowes I may suffred bee for the space of two monthes to go &amp; bewayle my virginity Iephte Daughter I'l geue the leaue to go, &amp; that wt h all my heart &amp; when that tyme's expird returne to mee: so hence depart garments for mourninge to prepare for thee &amp; all thy followers &amp; I'l returne vnto my campe, &amp; see my wearyed souldiers who ventred haue their lyues wt h me agaynst the sonnes of Ammon whom vtterly we ouerthrew &amp; brought to our subiection, &amp; twenty citties taken haue that vnto them belonged wt h losse of few our owne men: for wc h gods name be praysed: yet all this will not make my ioy complete, when I remember &amp; thinke vpon the death that's imminent of myne only daughter, who now hath but two monthes to lyue, &amp; bewayle her virginity wt h her companions in the mountaynes, &amp; then returne vnto mee for to receiue the fatall stroke wc h I haue vow'd to geue. But I'l no longer talke there of for yt doth mee but greeue, &amp; will do her no good: wherefore these thoughts for to expell I into Maspha will returne to the children of Israel. filia Iephte fellow virgins you acquainted are how the case standeth wt h me &amp; I haue chosen you for companions to bewayle my virginity here in the mountaynes, for yt is opprobrious to be barren &amp; to depart out of thys world before that one haue children as yt must be my happ to do, for my father hath vowed that after two monthes space I must vnto our lord be sacrificed for I mett hym the first of all returninge home wt h victory wc h me more comfort brought then my owne death doth make me sory for I was borne wt h bond to make of my lyfe restitution &amp; by my death I also shall discharge the obligation where wt h my father tyed hym self: &amp; we shall both be free he for to lyue wt h Israell, &amp; I wt h god almighty &amp; besyds that our country ys from th'Amonits deliuered by whom in former tymes exceedinge sore yt was oppressed So that although yt be my happ for to bringe forth no children yet many in my country may be borne of other women to recompence my barrennes, wc h to haue come to passe but that my father gott this victory vnlykly was &amp; he the conquest had not wonne perhaps but that he vowed out of his zeale, that the first thinge that mett hym should be offred by hym in sacrifice to god: &amp; therefore yt's conuenient that he the couenant should performe he made to god omnipotent. And the dearer I am to hym so much more loue he sheweth to god in that he will not spare me whom he so much loueth. And lykewyse I will shew my loue both to god &amp; my father &amp; death at their goodwill &amp; pleasure most willingly will suffer for satisfaction of the debt wc h to them both I owe to th'one by reason of my sinne, to th'other for his vow Wherefore till these two monthes be past I'l wt h you virgins mourne here in the hills, &amp; then vnto my father backe returne. &amp; to expresse our sorrowfull hearts some dolefull tune lett's play vpon our instruments there wt h to passe the tyme away. So now the tyme of my returne's expir'd, I will be gone vnto my father whom I lefte makeinge for me greate mone Iephte Daughter I pray thee patience haue, &amp; take death in good parte as I do hope thou wilt syth for the same prepar'd thou art filia Iephte father performe your vow to god, &amp; that wt h all alacrity for vnto me death welcome ys syth you haue gott the victory agaynst your foes by gods good help, who lookes that you lykewyse accordinge to your vow should offer me to hym in sacrifice. wherefore no longer make delay for to dye I am willinge &amp; for your last farewell father bestow on me your blessinge Iephte Thy words sweete daughter pearce my heart &amp; make me for to sheede teares from myne eyes, &amp; will not lett my hands performe this deede. filia Iephte. What father will you not performe the vow to god you made, who was the cause so good successe agaynst your foes you had? So may you god offend: &amp; thinkeinge my lyfe for to saue both loose yt &amp; your owne, &amp; all the subiects els you haue, as in the late warres you had done, but that god fought for you, &amp; lykely ys you shall here after yf you breake your vow Wherefore deare father courage take, for I am no whit daunted wt h death, but wish wt h all my heart your vow may be obserued Iephte. Thy resolution daughter's great: &amp; glad I am to see (a thinge rare in the femal sexe) the willinge for to dye &amp; syth thou art resolued so to do, lyke wyse I will the offer vp in sacrifice my vow for to fulfill where fore prepare thy selffe. Daught[er]. father, I will. Now I am ready Iephte. Then here ly downe. Daught[er]. Wt h all my heart: now father do your duty Iephte God lord receiue this sacrifice of this my only daughter whom as a token of my thankfulnes to the I offer for that thou hast the Ammonits into my hands deliuered by whom for many yeares together my country was oppressed &amp; for this conquest thy fame shall throughout the world be blowne syth but for thy assistance lord we had bene ouerthrowne &amp; the daughters of Israel shall assembled be together once euery yeare, &amp; mourne foure days for the death of my daughter wc h I my self, &amp; those that in my place succeede shall see perform'd in memory of my daughters death &amp; my great victory. And that this custome may the better be obseru'd, I'l go &amp; here wt h both acquaint the peares &amp; people of Israel also Nuncius Now Iephtes vow you haue both heard &amp; seene yt also executed &amp; some amongst you may perhaps there at be scandalized thinkinge that yt was rashly made, &amp; perform'd vnaduisedly but in your censures of hym I could wish you to be wary for though in vowinge for to sacrifice who or what s'euer first mett hym comminge home wt h victory (wc h by hap was his daughter Syth he no speciall warrant had from god) yt's very probable he did offend: for some thinges were by the Law not sacrificable of wc h sort men &amp; women bee, yet all this not wt h standinge he synned not but rather gods wrath pacifie'd by performinge his vow, whose will for punishment of his synne yt sem'd to bee that he should sacrifice his owne daughter, whom he did loue so dearly syth by his diuine prouidence she mett hym the first of all, whose lyfe yf he had spar'd he might haue bene thought to be partiall rather out of his naturall loue &amp; fatherly affection vnto his only child, then for th'vnlawfulnes of th'action Sith god before this tyme had Abraham commanded lykwyse vnto hym for to offer vp his only sonne in sacrifice though afterward he would not yt permit for to be done when he his promptnes saw to put the same in execution but in his place an other host he out of hand prepared though here not so. And by her death no iniury she sustayned but rather profitt got there by, for all mankynd must dye through Adams synne, at gods appoynted tyme: &amp; from much misery here in this world shee's freed. And she died wt h her owne consent (wc h seemes to be by gods instinct) &amp; shee was also innocent &amp; there fore now her blessed soule ys in a ioyfull place: where as yf she had longer lyu'd, though but a litle space she might haue fallen into synne, beinge prone there to by nature &amp; both in this world &amp; the next haue lost gods loue &amp; fauour. And though her father did offend by vowinge vnaduisedly as his repentance meetinge first his daughter shewed playnly: yet hym wt h godly feare &amp; dreede god did permitt &amp; suffer to his owne bitter payne, to sacrifice his only daugther &amp; for to institute for her a yearly lamentation to th'ende that others might make their vowes wt h more circumspection And her promptnes in offeringe of her selffe for to be sacrificed her fathers fault did much extenuat, or his fact wholly iustified Where fore I wish ech one to iudge indifferently of his action &amp; leaue yt vnto god to whom the secret'st thinges are knowne &amp; shall reuealed be, &amp; iustly as they haue deserued receiue rewarde, in their due tyme &amp; place by god appoynted So hopinge you your censures will suspend, or iudge the best I will be gone &amp; leaue to tyme discouery of the rest.</field>
   </doc>
</add>