<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">MacCarthy, Denis Florence, 1817-1882</field>
      <field name="author_facet">MacCarthy, Denis Florence, 1817-1882</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">maccarthy denis florence 1817 1882</field>
      <field name="author_text">MacCarthy, Denis Florence, 1817-1882</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1870's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V3.0772.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1873</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:461062</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Wonder-Working Magician</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Wonder-Working Magician</field>
      <field name="title_facet">wonder working magician</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">wonder working magician</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Wonder-Working Magician</field>
      <field name="year_display">1873</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1873</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1873</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:461062&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:461062&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;MacCarthy, Denis Florence, 1817-1882&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;maccarthy denis florence 1817 1882&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Wonder-Working Magician&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;wonder working magician&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1873&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1873&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;MacCarthy, Denis Florence&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1817&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1882&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Wonder-Working Magician&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Henry S. King &amp;amp; Co.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1873&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3873401-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv30772&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Wonder-Working Magician&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 242 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted.&lt;lb/&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;lb/&gt;Play reproduced elsewhere in English Verse Drama omitted&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: The wonder-working magician.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Drama.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1873.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Unknown.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE WONDER-WORKING MAGICIAN.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">TO THE MEMORY OF SHELLEY, WHOSE ADMIRATION FOR “THE LIGHT AND ODOUR OF THE FLOWERY AND STARRY AUTOS” IS THE HIGHEST TRIBUTE TO THE BEAUTY OF CALDERON'S POETRY, This Drama IS INSCRIBED.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PERSONS. Cyprian. The Demon. Lelius, the Governor of Antioch's Son. Florus, friend of Lelius. Moscon, Servant of Cyprian. Clarin, Servant of Cyprian. The Governor of Antioch. Fabius, his Servant. Lysander, the reputed Father of Justina. Justina. Livia, her Maid. A Servant. A Soldier. Attendants, Soldiers, People.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Scene—Antioch and its environs.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT THE FIRST. Scene I. A WOOD NEAR ANTIOCH. Enter Cyprian in a Student's gown, followed by Clarin and Moscon, as poor Scholars, carrying books. Cyprian. In the pleasant solitude Of this tranquil spot, this thicket Formed of interlacing boughs, Buds, and flowers, and shrubs commingled, You may leave me, leaving also, As my best companions, with me, (For I need none else) those books Which I bade you to bring hither From the house; for while, to-day, Antioch, the mighty city, Celebrates with such rejoicing The great temple newly finished Unto Jupiter, the bearing Thither, also, of his image Publicly, in grand procession, To its shrine to be uplifted;— I, escaping the confusion Of the streets and squares, have flitted Hitherward, to spend in study What of daylight yet may glimmer. Go, enjoy the festival, Go to Antioch and mingle In its various sports, returning When the sun descending sinketh To be buried in the waves, Which, beneath the dark clouds' fringes, Round the royal corse of gold, Shine like sepulchres of silver. Here you'll find me. Moscon. Sir, although Most decidedly my wish is To behold the sports, yet I Cannot go without a whisper Of some few five thousand words, Which I'll give you in a jiffy. Can it be that on a day Of such free, such unrestricted Revelry, and mirth, and fun, You with your old books come hither To this country place, rejecting All the frolic of the city? Clarin. Well, I think my master's right; For there's nothing more insipid Than a grand procession day, Half fandangos, priests, and fiddles. Moscon. Clarin, from the first to last, All your life you've been a trickster, A smart, temporizing toady, A bold flatterer, a trimmer, Since you praise the thoughts of others, And ne'er speak your own. Clarin. The civil Way to tell a man he lies Is to say he's wrong:—you twig me, Now I think I speak my mind. Cyprian. Moscon, Clarin, both I bid ye Cease this silly altercation. It is ever thus betwixt ye, Puffed up with your little knowledge Each maintains his own opinion. Go, and (as I've said) here seek me When night falls, and with the thickness Of its shadows veils from view This most fair and wondrous system Of the universe. Moscon. How comes it, That although you have admitted 'Tis not right to see the feast, Yet you go to see it? Clarin. Simple Is the answer: no one follows The advice which he has given To another. Moscon (aside). To see Livia, Would the gods that I were wingéd. [Exit. Clarin (aside). If the honest truth were told Livia is the girl that gives me Something worth the living for. Even her very name has in it This assurance: Livia, yes, Minus a, I live for Livi. This, of course, is a paraphrase of the original, which, perhaps, may be given as an explanation. “Ilega, Livia. Al na, y sé, Livia, liviana.” [Exit. Scene II. Cyprian. Now I am alone, and may, If my mind can be so lifted, Study the great problem which Keeps my soul disturbed, bewilder'd, Since I read in Pliny's page The mysterious words there written, Which define a god; because It doth seem beyond the limits Of my intellect to find One who all these signs exhibits. This mysterious hidden truth Must I seek for. [Reads. Scene III. Enter the Demon, in gala dress. Cyprian. Demon (aside). Though thou givest All thy thoughts to the research, Cyprian, thou must ever miss it, Since I'll hide it from thy mind. Cyprian. There's a rustling in this thicket. Who is there? who art thou? Demon. Sir, A mere stranger, who has ridden All this morning up and down These dark groves, not knowing whither, Having lost my way, my horse, To the emerald that encircles, With a tapestry of green, These lone hills, I've loosed, it gives him At the same time food and rest. I'm to Antioch bound, on business Of importance, my companions I have parted from; through listless Lapse of thought (a thing that happens To the most of earthly pilgrims), I have lost my way, and lost Comrades, servants, and assistants. Cyprian. I am much surprised to learn That in view of the uplifted Towers of Antioch, you thus Lost your way. There's not a single Path that on this mountain side, More or less by feet imprinted, But doth lead unto its walls, As to its one central limit. By whatever path you take, You'll go right. Demon. It is an instance Of that ignorance which in sight Even of truth the true goal misses. And as it appears not wise Thus to enter a strange city Unattended and unknown, Asking even my way, 'tis fitter That 'till night doth conquer day, Here while light doth last, to linger; By your dress and by these books Round you, like a learned circle Of wise friends, I see you are A great student, and the instinct Of my soul doth ever draw me Unto men to books addicted. Cyprian. Have you studied much? Demon. Well, no; But I've knowledge quite sufficient Not to be deemed ignorant. Cyprian. Then, what sciences know you? Demon. Many. Cyprian. Why, we cannot reach even one After years of studious vigil, And can you (what vanity!) Without study know so many? Demon. Yes; for I am of a country Where the most exalted science Needs no study to be known. Cyprian. Would I were a happy inmate Of that country! Here our studies Prove our ignorance more. Demon. No figment Is the fact that without study. I had the superb ambition For the first Professor's chair To compete, and thought to win it, Having very numerous votes. And although I failed, sufficient Glory is it to have tried. For not always to the winner Is the fame. If this you doubt, Name the subject of your study, And then let us argue on it; I not knowing your opinion, Even although it be the right, Shall the opposite view insist on. Cyprian. I am greatly gratified That you make this proposition. Here in Plinius is a passage Which much anxious thought doth give me How to understand, to know Who's the God of whom he has written. Demon. 'Tis that passage which declares (Well I know the words) this dictum: “God is one supremest good, One pure essence, one existence, Self-sustained, all sight, all hands.” Cyprian. Yes, 'tis true. Demon. And what is in it So abstruse? Cyprian. I cannot find Such a god as Plinius figures. If he be the highest good, Then is Jupiter deficient In that attribute; we see him Acting like a mortal sinner Many a time,—this, Danae, This, Europa, too, doth witness. Can then, by the Highest Good, All whose actions, all whose instincts, Should be sacred and divine, Human frailty be committed? Demon. These are fables which the learned First made use of, to exhibit Underneath the names of gods What in truth was but a hidden System of philosophy. Cyprian. This reply is not sufficient, Since such awe is due to God, None should dare to Him attribute, None should stain His name with sins. Though these sins should be fictitious. And considering well the case, If the highest good is figured By the gods, of course, they must Will what is the best and fittest; How, then, can some gods wish one thing, Some another? This we witness In the dubious responses Which are by their statues given. Here you cannot say I speak of Learned abstractions of the ideal. To two armies, if two shrines Promise give of being victors, One, of course, must lose the battle: The conclusion is so simple,— Need I say it? that two wills, Mutually antagonistic, Cannot lead unto one end. They being thus in opposition, One we must consider good, One as bad we must consider. But an evil will in God Would imply a contradiction: Then the highest good can dwell not Among gods who know division. Demon. I deny your major, since These responses may be given, By the oracles, for ends Which our intellectual vision Cannot reach: 'tis providence. Thus more good may have arisen To the loser in that battle Than its gain could bring the winner. Cyprian. Granted; but that god ought not, For the gods are not malicious, To have promised victory;— It would have been quite sufficient, Without this most false assurance, The defeat to have permitted. Then if God must be all sight, Every god should see distinctly With clear vision to the end; Seeing that, he erred in fixing On a false conclusion; then Though the deity may with fitness Be divided into persons. Yet His essence must be single In the smallest circumstance. Demon. It was needful for this business, That the oracle should rouse The two hosts alike. Cyprian. If fitting, There were genii that could rouse them (Good and bad, as they're distinguished By the learned), who are, in fact, Spirits who among us mingle, And who good and evil acts, Evil thoughts, suggest and whisper, A convincing argument For the immortal soul's existence: Of these ministers could God Have made use, nor thus exhibit He was capable of a lie To effect his ends? Demon. Consider, That these seeming contradictions Cannot our firm faith diminish In the oneness of the gods, If in things of higher import They know naught of dissonance. Take man's wondrous frame, for instance, Surely that majestic structure One conception doth exhibit. Cyprian. If man's maker then were one He some vantage must have given him O'er the others; and if they All are equal,—'tis admitted That they are so, from the fact Of their mutual opposition To each other,—when the thought Of creating man was hinted By one god, another could Say, “No, no, I do not wish it.” Then if God must be all hands, Time might come when they would differ, One creating, one undoing, Ere the other's work was finished, Since the power of each was equal, But unequal were their wishes. Which of these two powers would conquer? Demon. On impossible and false issues There can be no argument;— But your premises admitting, Say what then? Cyprian. That there must be One sole God, all hands, all vision, Good Supreme, supreme in grace, One who cannot err, omniscient, One the highest, none can equal, Not beginning, yet the Beginner, One pure essence, one sole substance, One wise worker, one sole willer;— And though He in one or two Or more persons be distinguished, Yet the sovereign Deity Must be one, sublime and single, The first cause of every cause, The first germ of all existence. Demon. How can I deny so clear, [They rise. So conclusive a position? Cyprian. Do you feel it? Demon. Who would not Feel to find another quicker In the rivalry of wit?— And though I am not deficient In an answer, I restrain it, Hearing steps approaching hither Through the wood; besides 'tis time I proceeded to the city. Cyprian. Go in peace. Demon. Remain in peace.— So involved in study is he, [Aside. That I now must wean him from it, Weaving round him the bewitchment Of rare beauty. Since I have leave To attempt my fires to kindle In Justina's breast, one stroke, Thus, two vengeances shall give me. [Exit. Cyprian. Never saw I such a man. But since still my people linger, I, the cause of so much doubt, Will now strive to reconsider. [He resumes his reading, without perceiving the approach of those who enter. Scene IV. Enter Lelius and Florus.—Cyprian. Lelius. Further let us not proceed; For these rocks, these boughs so thickly Interwoven, that the sun Cannot even find admittance, Shall be the sole witnesses Of our duel. Florus. Then, this instant Draw your sword; for here are deeds, If in words elsewhere we've striven. Lelius. Yes, I know that in the field, While the tongue is mute, the glitter Of the sword speaks thus. [They fight. Cyprian. What's this? Hold, good Florus! Lelius, listen!— Here until your rage is calmed, Even unarmed I stand betwixt ye. Lelius. Thus to interrupt my vengeance, Whence, O Cyprian, have you risen Like a spectre? Florus. A wild wood-god, Have you from these tree-trunks issued? Scene V. Enter Moscon and Clarin. Moscon. Yonder, where we left our master, I hear sword-strokes; run, run quickly. Clarin. Well, except to run away, I am anything but nimble;— Truly a retiring person. Moscon and Clarin. Sir. ... Cyprian. No more: your gabble irks me.— How? What's this? Two noble friends, Who in blood, in birth, in lineage, Are to-day of Antioch all Its expectancy, the city's Eye of fashion, one the son Of the Governor, of the princely House Colalto, one the heir, Thus to peril, as of little Value, two such precious lives To their country and their kindred? Lelius. Cyprian, although respect Which on many grounds I give thee, Holds my sword suspended thus In due deference for an instant,— To the scabbard's calm repose It hath got no power to win it. Thou of science knowest more, Than the duel, pretermitting This, that when two nobles meet In the field, no power can link them Friends again, save this, that one Must his life give as a victim. Florus. This I also say, and ask thee, With thy people, that thou quittest, Leaving us to end our quarrel Without any help or hindrance. Cyprian. Though it seems to you my calling Makes me know the laws but little Of the duel—that strict code Valour and vain pride have written, You are wrong, for I was born With the obligations fitting Rank like yours, to know in truth Infamy and honour's limits. The devotion to my studies Has my courage not diminished, For they oftentimes shake hands Arms and letters as though kinsmen. If to meet here in the field Was the quarrel's first condition, Having met and fought, its lies Calumny can never whisper. And the cause you thus can tell me Of the feud that brings you hither; For I promise, if, on hearing What to me is thus committed, I perceive that satisfaction Must on either side be given, Here to leave you both alone, Unobserved by any witness. Lelius. Then on this condition solely, That you leave us, when the bitter Truth is told, to end our quarrel, I to tell the cause am willing. I a certain lady love, The same lady as his mistress Florus also loves; now see, How incompatible are our wishes!— Since betwixt two jealous nobles No mediation is admitted. Florus. I this lady love so much, That the sunlight I would hinder From beholding her sweet face. Since then all interposition Is in vain, pray stand aside, And our quarrel let us finish. Cyprian. Stay, for one more thing I'd know. Tell me this of your fair mistress, Is she possible to your hopes, Or impossible to your wishes?— Lelius. Oh: she is so good and wise, That if even the sun enkindled Jealousy in the heart of Florus, It was jealousy pure and simple, Without cause, for even the sun Dare not look upon her visage. Cyprian. Would you marry with her, then? Florus. This is all my heart's ambition. Cyprian. And would you? Lelius. Ah, would to heaven, I were destined for such blisses!— For although she's very poor, Virtue dowers her with its riches. Cyprian. If you both aspire to wed her, Is it not an act most wicked, Most unworthy, thus beforehand Her unspotted fame to injure? What will say the world, if one Of you two shall marry with her After having killed the other For her sake? The supposition Is not probable in fact, To imagine it is sufficient. I by no means say you should Each your chances try to win her At one time, for I would blush Such a craven proposition Came from me, because the lover Who could keep his jealousy hidden, Would condone even shame thereafter, Were the opportunity given; But I say that you should learn Which of you it is your mistress Gives the preference to, then. ... Lelius. Stay!— For it were an act too timid, Too faint-hearted thus to ask Of a lady such admission As the choosing him or me. For if me she chose, more fixéd Is my call for satisfaction; For his fault has this addition, He loves one who loves but me. If to him the choice is given, This intensifies my anger All the more, that she, my mistress, Whom I love, should love another. Her selection could do little In the matter, which at last To our swords should be committed,— The accepted for his honour, The refused for his dismissal. Florus. I confess that I adopt Altogether that opinion, Still the privilege of selection May to ladies be permitted; So to-day I mean to ask her Of her father. 'Tis sufficient To have come here to the field, And my naked sword uplifted, (Specially as one is by Who the further fight resisteth,) For my honour;—so to sheathe, Lelius, my sword I'm willing. [Sheathes his sword. Lelius. By your argument and action, Florus, you have half convinced me; I forego the remaining half— True or false, I thus act with you. [Sheathes his sword. I to-day will seek her father. Cyprian. On, of course, the supposition, That this lady you pay court to Suffers naught by the admission, Since you both have spoken proudly Of her virtue and her strictness, Tell me who she is; for I, Who am held throughout the city In esteem, would for you both Speak to her at first a little, That she thus may be prepared When her father tells your wishes. Lelius. You are right. Cyprian. Her name? Florus. Justina, Daughter of Lysander. Cyprian. Little, Now that I have heard her name, Seem the praises you have given her; She is virtuous as she's noble. Instantly I'll pay my visit. Florus (aside). May heaven grant that in my favour Her cold heart be moved to pity! [Exit. Lelius. Love, my hopes with laurels crown When they are to her submitted! [Exit. Cyprian. Further mischief or misfortune, Grant me, heaven, that I may hinder! [Exit. Scene VI. Moscon, Clarin. Moscon. Has your worship heard our master Now is gone to pay a visit To Justina? Clarin. Yes, my lord. But what matter if he didn't? Moscon. Matter quite enough, your worship; He has no business there. Clarin. Why, prithee? Moscon. Why? because I die for Livia, Who is maid to this Justina, And I wouldn't have even the sun Get a glimpse of her through the window. Clarin. Well, that's good; but, for a lady, To contend were worse than silly, Whom I mean to make my wife. Moscon. Excellent, faith! the fancy tickles Quite my fancy. Let her say Who it is that annoys or nicks her To a nicety. Let's go see her, And she'll choose. Clarin. A good idea!— Though I fear she'll pitch on you. Moscon. Have you then that wise suspicion? Clarin. Yes; for always these same Livias Choose the worst, th'ungrateful minxes. The asonante versification in i—e, which has been kept up through these six scenes, ends here. The seventh scene commences in rhymed five-line stanzas, which change to the asonante in e—e at the beginning of Lysander's long speech. [Exeunt. Scene VII. A HALL IN THE HOUSE OF LYSANDER. Enter Justina and Lysander. Justina. Consolation, sir, is vain, After what I've seen to-day: The whole city, madly gay, Error-blinded and insane, Consecrating shrine and fane To an image, which, I know, Cannot be a god, although Some demoniac power may pass, Making breathe the silent brass As a proof that it is so. Lysander. Fair Justina, thou indeed, Wert not who thou art, if thou Didst not weep as thou dost now, Didst not in thy pure heart bleed For what Christ's divinest creed Suffers on this sinful day. Justina. Thus my lineage I display:— For thy child I could not be, Could I without weeping see This idolatrous display. Lysander. Ah, my good, my gentle maid! Thou art not my daughter, no, 'Twere too happy, if 'twere so. But, O God! what's this I've said?— My life's secret is betrayed! 'Twas my soul that spoke aloud. Justina. What do you say, sir? Lysander. Oh! a crowd Of old thoughts my heart hath stirred. Justina. Many times methought I heard What but now you have avowed, And yet never wished to hear, At the risk perchance of paining, A more accurate explaining Of your sorrow and my fear; But since now it doth appear Right that I should be possess'd Of the whole truth half confess'd, Let me say, though bold appearing,— Trust your secret to my hearing, Since it hath escaped your breast. Lysander. Ah! Justina, I have long Kept this secret from your ears, Fearing from your tender years That the telling might be wrong; But now seeing you are strong, Firm in thought, in action brave, Seeing too, that with this stave, I go creeping o'er the ground, Rapping with a hollow sound At the portals of the grave, Knowing that my time is brief, I would not here leave you, no, In your ignorance; I owe My own peace, too, this relief: Then attentive to my grief Let your pleasure list. Justina. A fear Struggles in my breast. Lysander. Severe Is the test my duty pays. Justina. From this most perplexing maze Oh, sir, rescue me. Lysander. Then hear. I, most beautiful Justina, Am Lysander. ... This commencement With my name need not surprise you; For though known to you already, It is right, for all that follows, That it should be well remembered, Since of me you know no more Than what this my name presenteth. Yes, I am Lysander, son Of that city which on Seven Hills a hydra seems of stone, Since it seven proud heads erecteth; Of that city now the seat Of the mighty Roman empire, Cradle of Christ's wider realm,— Boon that Rome alone could merit. There of poor and humble parents I was born, if “poor” expresses Well their rank who left behind them Virtues, not vain earthly treasures. Both of them by birth were Christians, Joyful both to be descended From brave sires who with their blood Happily life's page had reddened, Terminating the dull scroll With death's bright emblazoned letters In the Christian faith well grounded I grew up, and so well learnt it, That I would, in its defence, Even a thousand lives surrender. I was young still, when to Rome, In disguise and ill attended, Came our good Pope Alexander, Who then prudently directed The high apostolic see, Though its place there was not settled; For, as the despotic power Of the stern and cruel gentiles Satisfies its thirst with blood From the martyrs' veins that shed it, So must still the primitive church Keep concealed its sons and servants; Not that they decline to die, Not that martyrdom is dreaded But that rebel rage should not, At one stroke, one hour of vengeance, Triumph o'er the ruined church, So that no one should be left it Who could preach and teach the word, Who could catechise the gentile. Alexander being in Rome, I was secretly presented To him there, and from his hand Which was graciously extended, With his blessing I received Holy Orders, which the seraphs Well might envy me, since man Only such an honour merits. Alexander, as my mission, Unto Antioch then sent me, Where the law of Christ in secret I should preach. With glad contentment I obeyed, and at their mercy, Through so many nations wending, Came at length to Antioch; And when I, these hills ascending, Saw beneath me in the valley All its golden towers and temples, The sun failed me, and down-sinking Drew with him the day, presenting For my solace a companion, And a substitute for his presence In the light of stars, a pledge That he'd soon return to bless me. With the sun I lost my way, And then wandering dejected Through the windings of the forest, Found me in the dim recesses Of a natural bower, wherein Even the numerous rays that trembled Downward from each living torch Could in noways find an entrance, For to black clouds turned the leaves That by day were green with freshness. Here arranging to await The new sun's reviving presence, Giving fancy that full scope, That wide range which it possesses, I in solitude indulged Many and many a deep reflection. Thus absorbed was I in thought When there came to me the echo Of a sigh half heard, for half To its owner retroverted. Then collecting in mine ear All my senses joined together, I again heard more distinctly That weak cry, that faint expression, That mute idiom of the sad, Since by it they're comprehended. From a woman came that groan To whose sigh so low and gentle Followed a man's deeper voice, Who thus speaking low addressed her: “Thou first stain of noblest blood By my hands this moment perish, Ere thou meetest with thy death 'Neath the hands of infamous headsmen.”— Then the hapless woman said In a voice that sobbed and trembled, “Ah, lament for thine own blood, But for me do not lament thee!”— I attempted then to reach them, That the stroke might be prevented, But I could not, since the voices At that moment ceased and ended, And a horseman rode away 'Mong the tree-trunks undetected. Loadstone of my deep compassion Was that voice which still exerted All its failing powers to speak Amid groans and tears this sentence,— “Dying innocent and a Christian I a martyr's death may merit.”— Following the polar-star Of the voice, I came directly Where the gloom revealed a woman, Though I could not well observe her, Who in life's despairing struggle, Hand to hand with death contended. Scarcely was I heard, when she Summoning up her strength addressed me,— “Blood-stained murderer mine, come back, Nor in this last hour desert me Of my life.”—“I am,” said I, “Only one whom chance hath sent here, Guided it may be by heaven, To assist you in this dreadful Hour of trial.”—“Vain,” she said, “Is the favour that your mercy Offers to my life, for see, Drop by drop the life-stream ebbeth, Let this hapless one enjoy it, Who it seems that heaven intendeth, Being born upon my grave, All my miseries should inherit.”— So she died, and then I ... Scene VIII. Livia, Justina, and Lysander. Enter Livia. Livia. Sir, The same tradesman who so presses To be paid, comes here to seek you, By the magistrate attended. That you were not in, I told him: By that door you have an exit. Justina. This untimely interruption By their coming, how it frets me! For upon your tragic story Life, soul, reason, all depended!— But retire, sir, lest the justice Should here meet you, if he enters. Lysander. Ah! with what indignities Poverty must be contented! [Exit. Justina. They are coming here, no doubt, Outside I can hear some persons. Livia. No, they are not they. I see It is Cyprian. Justina. How? what sendeth Cyprian here? Scene IX. Enter Cyprian, Clarin, and Moscon. Cyprian. A wish to serve you Is the sole cause of my presence. For on seeing the officials Issuing from your house, the friendship Which I owe unto Lysander Made me bold herein to enter; But to know (Aside. Disturbed, bewildered Am I.) if by chance (Aside. What gelid Frost is freezing up my veins!) I in any way could help you. (Aside. Ah, how badly have I spoken!— Fire not frost my blood possesses!) Justina. May heaven guard you many years, Since in his more grave concernments, Thus you honour my dear father With your favours. Cyprian. I shall ever Be most gratified to serve you. (Aside. What disturbs me, what unnerves me?) Justina. He is not just now at home. Cyprian. Thus then, lady, I can better Tell you what is the true cause That doth bring me here at present; For the cause that you have heard Is not that which wholly led me Here to see you. Justina. Then, what is it? Cyprian. This, which craves your brief attention.— Fair Justina, beauty's shrine, The five-lined stanza here recommences, and continues to the end of the scene. To whose human loveliness Nature, with a fond excess, Adds such marks of the divine, 'Tis your rest that doth incline Hither my desire to-day; But see what the tyrant sway Of despotic fate can do,— While I bring your rest to you, You from me take mine away. Lelius, of his passion proud, (Never less was love to blame!) Florus, burning with love's flame, (Ne'er could flame be more allowed!) Each of them by vows they vowed Sought to kill his friend for you: I for you disturbed the two, (Woe is me!) but see the end; While from death I saved my friend, You my own death give in lieu. Lest the scandal-monger's hum Should be buzzed about your name, Here to speak with you I came, (Would that I had never come!) That your choice might strike it dumb, Being the umpire in the cause, Being the judge in love's sweet laws;— But behold what I endure, While I their sick hearts may cure, Jealousy mine own heart gnaws. Lady, I proposed to be Their bold spokesman here, that you Might decide betwixt the two Which you would select (ah, me!) That I might (oh, misery!) Ask you of your father: vain This pretence. No more I'll feign:— For you see while I am speaking About them, my heart is seeking But a vent for its own pain. Justina. Half in wonder and dismay At the vile address you make me, Reason, speech, alike forsake me, And I know not what to say. Never in the slightest way Have your clients had from me Encouragement for this embassy— Florus never—Lelius no:— Of the scorn that I can show Let then this a warning be. Cyprian. If I, knowing that you loved Some one else, would dare to seek Your regard, my love were weak, And could justly be reproved. But here seeing you stand unmoved, Like a rock mid raging seas, No extraneous miseries Make me say I love you now. 'Tis not for my friends I bow, So your warning hear with ease.— To Lelius what shall I say? Justina. That he Well may trust the boding fears Of his love of many years. Cyprian. To Florus? Justina. Not my face to see. Cyprian. And to myself? Justina. Your love should be Not so bold. Cyprian. Though a god should woo? Justina. Will a god do more for you Than for those I have denied? Cyprian. Yes. Justina. Well then, I have replied To Lelius, Florus, and to you. [Exeunt Justina and Cyprian at opposite sides. Scene X. Clarin, Moscon, and Livia. Clarin. Livia, heigh! Moscon. And Livia, ho!— List good lass. Clarin. We're here, we two. Livia. Well, what want you, sir? And you, What do you want? Clarin. We both would show, If perchance you do not know, That we love you to distraction. On a murderous transaction We came here, to kill each other:— So to put an end to the bother, Just choose one for satisfaction. Livia. Why the thing that you're demanding Is so great, it hath bereft me Of my wits. My grief hath left me Without sense or understanding. Choose but one! My heart expanding, Beats so hard a strait to shun! I one only! 'Tis for fun That you ask me so to do. For with heart enough for two, Why require that I choose one? Clarin. Two at once would you have to woo? Would not two embarrass you, pray? Livia. No, we women have a way To dispose of them two by two. Moscon. What's the way? do tell us, do;— What is it? speak. Livia. You put one out!— I would love them, do not doubt. ... Moscon. How? Livia. tively. Clarin. Eh, What's alternatively? Livia. 'Tis to say, That I would love them day about. [Exit. Moscon. Well, I choose to-day: good-bye. Clarin. I, to-morrow, the better part. So I give it with all my heart. Moscon. Livia, in fine, for whom I die, To-day loves me, and to-day love I. Happy is he who so much can say. Clarin. Hearken, my friend: you know my way. Moscon. Why this speech? Does a threat lie in it? Clarin. Mind, she is not yours a minute After the clock strikes twelve to-day. [Exeunt. Scene XI. THE STREET BEFORE LYSANDER'S HOUSE: NIGHT. Enter Florus and Lelius at opposite sides, not seeing each other. Lelius (aside). Scarcely has the darksome night O'er the brow of heaven extended Asonante in e—e, to the end of the Act. Its black veil, when I come hither To adore this sacred threshold; For although at Cyprian's prayer, I my sharp sword have suspended, I have not my love, for love Cannot be suspended ever. Florus (aside). Here the dawn will find me waiting:— Here, because 'tis force compels me To go hence, for I, elsewhere, Am away from my true centre. Would to love the day had come, And with it the dear, expected Answer Cyprian may bring me, Risking all upon that venture. Lelius (aside). I have surely in that window Heard a noise. Florus (aside). Some sound descends here From that balcony. Scene XII. The Demon appears at a window in the house of Lysander. Lelius (aside). A figure Issues from it, whose dim presence I distinguish. Florus (aside). Through the darkness I can there perceive some person. Demon (aside). For the many persecutions O'er Justina's head impending, Her pure honour to defame Thus I make a bold commencement. [He descends by a ladder. Lelius (aside). But, O woe! what's this I witness!— Florus (aside). What do I see! Oh, wretched! wretched!— Lelius (aside). From the balcony to the ground The dark figure has descended. Florus (aside). From her house a man comes forth!— Jealousy kill me not, preserve me, 'Till I discover who he is. Lelius (aside). I will try to intercept him And find out at once who thus Tastes the bliss I've lost for ever. [They advance with drawn swords to recognise the person who has descended. Demon (aside). Not alone Justina's fame Do I by this act discredit, But dissensions, perhaps murders, Thus provoke. Ope, earth's dark centre, And receive me, leaving here This confusion. [He disappears between Florus and Lelius, who meet together. Scene XIII. Florus and Lelius. Lelius. Sir, whoever You may be, it doth import me To know who you are directly; So at every risk I come here, On this resolute quest determined. Say who are you. Florus. If the accident Of my having been the observer Of your secret love, compels you To this valorous aggression, More than it can you concern Me to know, it doth concern me To know you; for to be curious Is far less than to be jealous. Yes, by Heaven! for who is master Of the house have I to learn here, Who it is at such an hour, By this balcony ascending, Gaineth that which I lose weeping At these gratings. Lelius. This excelleth, Good, in faith, is it thus to dim The clear light of my resentment, By attributing to me That which solely your offence is!— Who you are I have to know, Death to give to him who has left me Dead with jealousy here, by coming From this balcony. Florus. How excessive, How superfluous is this caution, Proving what it would dissemble! Lelius. Vainly would the tongue untangle That which the keen sword can better Thus cut through. Florus. With it I answer. [They fight. Lelius. In this way I'll know for certain Who is the admitted lover Of Justina. Florus. My intention Is the same. I'll die or know you. Scene XIV. Enter Cyprian, Moscon, and Clarin. Cyprian. Gentlemen, I pray you let me Interpose in this your quarrel, Since by accident I am present. Florus. You cannot oblige me more Than by letting the fight be ended. Cyprian. Florus? Florus. Yes, for sword in hand, I my name deny not ever To who asks. Cyprian. I'm at your side, Death to him who would offend you. Lelius. You produce in me less fear, Both of you thus joined together, Than did he alone. Cyprian. What! Lelius? Lelius. Yes. Cyprian. I am prevented Now from standing at your side, [To Florus. Since between you I present me. How is this? In one day twice Have I your disputes to settle!— Lelius. Then this time will be the last, For we've settled them already; Since in knowing who is he Who Justina's heart possesses, Now no more my hope remaineth, Even the thought of it hath left me. If you have not to Justina Spoken yet, do not address her; This I ask you in the name Of my wrongs and my resentments, Having seen her secret favours Florus' happier fate deserveth. From this balcony I saw him, From my lost delight descending; And my heart is not so base As to meanly love, in presence Of such jealousies so well proved, Of disillusions, ah! so certain. [Exit. Florus. Stay. Scene XV. Cyprian. You must not follow him, (Oh, this news with death o'erwhelms me!) [Aside. Since if he who is the loser Of what you have gained, expressly Says he would forget it, you Should not try his patient temper. Florus. Both by you and him at once Has mine own been too well tested. Speak not now unto Justina About me; for though full vengeance I propose to take for being Thus supplanted and rejected, Every hope of her being mine Now has ceased, for shameful were it, In the face of such proved facts, To persist in my addresses. [Exit. Scene XVI. Cyprian, Moscon, and Clarin. Cyprian (aside). What is this, O heavens! I hear? Can it be the two are jealous Of each other at one time? And I too of both together?— Doubtless from some strange delusion The two suffer, which I welcome With a sort of satisfaction, For to it I am indebted For the fact of their desisting From their suit and their pretension.— Moscon, have for me by morning A rich court-suit; sword and feathers, Clarin, be thy care; for love In a certain airy splendour Takes delight; for now no longer Books or studies give me pleasure;— Love they say doth murder mind, Learning dies when he is present. [Exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT THE SECOND. Scene I. THE STREET IN FRONT OF LYSANDER'S HOUSE. Enter Cyprian, Moscon, and Clarin, in gala dresses. Cyprian (aside). Where, presumptuous thoughts, ah! where, Would you lead me, whither go? If for certain now you know That the high attempts you dare Are delusive dreams of bliss, Since you strive to scale heaven's wall, But from that proud height to fall Headlong down a dark abyss? I Justina saw ..... So near Would to God I had not seen her, Nor in her divine demeanour All the light of heaven's fourth sphere. Lovers twain for her contend, Both being jealous each should woo, And I, jealous of the two, Know not which doth most offend. All I know is, that suspicion, Her disdain, my own desires, Fill my heart with furious fires— Drive me, ah! to my perdition. This I know, and know no more, This I feel in all my strait; Heavens! Justina is my fate! Heavens! Justina I adore!— Moscon. Moscon. Sir. Cyprian. Inquire, I pray, If Lysander's in. Moscon. I fly. Clarin. No, sir, no. On me rely,— Moscon can't go there to-day. Cyprian. Ever wrangling in this way, How ye both my patience try! Why can he not go? Say why? Clarin. Because to-day is not his day. Mine it is, sir, to his sorrow. So your message I will bear. Moscon can't to-day go there; He will have his turn to-morrow. Cyprian. What new madness can this be Which your usual feud doth show? But now neither of you go, Since in all her brilliancy Comes Justina. Clarin. From the street To her house she goes. Scene II. Enter Justina and Livia, veiled.—Cyprian, Moscon, and Clarin. Justina. Ah, me! Cyprian's here. See, Livia, see! [Aside to her. Cyprian (aside). I must strive and be discreet, Feigning with a ready wit, Till my jealousy I can prove. I will only speak of love, If my jealousy will permit. Not in vain, señora sweet,— Have I changed my student's dress, The livery of thy loveliness, As a servant at thy feet, Thus I wear. If sighs could move thee I would labour to deserve thee; Give me leave at least to serve thee, Since thou wilt not let me love thee. Justina. Slight effect, sir, as I see, Have my words produced on you, Since they have not brought. ... Cyprian. Too true! Justina. A forgetfulness of me. In what way must I explain Clearer than I have done before, That persistence at my door Is and ever must be vain? If a day, a month, a year, If for ages there you stay, Naught but this that now I say Ever can you hope to hear. As it were my latest breath, Let this sad assurance move thee,— Fate forbids that I should love thee, Cyprian, except in death. [She moves towards the house. Cyprian. At these words my hopes revive:— Sad! no, no, to joy they move me, For if thou in death canst love me, Soon for me will death arrive. Be it so; and since so nigh Comes the hour your words to prove— Ah! even now begin to love, Since I now begin to die. [Justina enters. Scene III. Cyprian, Moscon, Clarin, and Livia. Clarin. Livia, while my master yonder, Like a living skeleton, Life and motion being gone, On his luckless love doth ponder, Give me an embrace. Livia. Stay, stay. Patience, man! until I see, For I like my conscience free, If to-day is your right day.— Tuesday, yes, and Wednesday, no. Clarin. What are you counting there? Awake! Moscon's mum. Livia. He might mistake, And I wish not to act so. For, desiring to pursue A just course betwixt you both, Turn about, I would be loth Not to give you each his due. But I see that you are right, 'Tis your day. Clarin. Embrace me, then. Livia. Yes, again, and yet again. Moscon. Hark to me, my lady bright, May I from your ardour borrow A good omen in my case; And as Clarin you embrace, Moscon you'll embrace to-morrow? Livia. Your suspicion is, in fact, Quite absurd; on me rely. Jupiter forbid that I Should commit so bad an act As to be cool in any way To a friend. I will to thee Give an embrace in equity, When it is your worship's day. [Exit. Scene IV. Cyprian, Moscon, and Clarin. Clarin. Well, I'll not be by to see, That's a comfort. Moscon. How? why so? Need I be chagrined to know, If the girl's not mine, that she Thus to you her debt did pay. Clarin. No. Moscon. This makes my point more strong, Since to me it were no wrong If it chanced not on my day. But our master yonder, see, How absorbed he seems. Clarin. More near, If he speaks I'd like to hear. Moscon. And I, too, would like. Cyprian. Ah, me! [As Moscon and Clarin approach Cyprian from opposite sides, he gesticulates with his arms, and accidentally strikes both. Love, how great thy agonies!— Clarin. Ah! ah, me! Moscon. Ah, me! I bawl. Clarin. Well, I think that we may call This the land of the sigh-ah-mes! Cyprian. What! and have you both been here? Clarin. I, at least, was here, I'll swear. Moscon. And I, also. Cyprian. O, despair End at once my sad career! Ah, what human heart to woe Like to mine has given a home? Scene V. THE COUNTRY. Cyprian, Clarin, and Moscon. Clarin. Whither Moscon, do we roam? Moscon. When we've reached the end, we'll know. Leagues behind us lies the town, Still we go. Clarin. A strange proceeding!— Little time have we for reading, Idly pacing up and down. Cyprian. Clarin, get thee home. Moscon. And I? Clarin. Sly-boots, would you rather stay? Cyprian. Go: here leave me both; away! Clarin. Mind, he tells us both to fly. [Exeunt Clarin and Moscon. Scene VI. Cyprian. Memory of a maddened brain, Do not with such strong control Make me think another soul Is what in my heart doth reign. Blind idolator I have been— Lost in love's ambitious flight, Since such beauty met my sight, Since a goddess I have seen. Yet in such a maze of woe Rigorous fate doth make me move, That I know but whom I love, And of whom I am jealous—no. Yet this passion is so strong— Ah, so sweet this fascination, Driving my imagination With resistless force along— That I would (I know too well How this madness doth degrade me) To some devilish power to aid me, Were it even to rise from hell, Where some mightier power hath kept it,— Sharing all its pains in common,— I would, to possess this woman, Give my soul. Scene VII. The Demon and Cyprian. Demon (within). And I accept it. [A great tempest is heard, with thunder and lightning. Cyprian. What's this, ye heavens so pure? Clear but a moment hence and now obscure, Ye fright the gentle day! The thunder-balls, the lightning's forkéd ray, Leap from its riven breast— Terrific shapes it cannot keep at rest; All the whole heaven a crown of clouds doth wear, And with the curling mist, like streaming hair, This mountain's brow is bound. Outspread below, the whole horizon round Is one volcanic pyre. The sun is dead, the air is smoke, heaven fire. Philosophy, how far from thee I stray, When I cannot explain the marvels of this day! And now the sea, upborne on clouds the while, Seems like some ruined pile, That crumbling down the wind as 'twere a wall, In dust not foam doth fall. And struggling through the gloom, Facing the storm, a mighty ship seeks room On the open sea, whose rage it seems to court, Flying the dangerous pity of the port. The noise, the terror, and that fearful cry, Give fatal augury Of the impending stroke. Death hesitates, For each already dies who death awaits. With portents the whole atmosphere is rife, Nor is it all the effect of elemental strife. The ship is rigged with tempest as it flies. Hartzenbusch remarks that there is no corresponding rhyme for this line in the original, and that both the sense and the versification are defective.—Comedias de Calderon, t. 2, p. 178. It rushes on the lee, The war is now no longer of the sea; Upon a hidden rock It strikes: it breaks as with a thunder shock. Blood flakes the foam where helpless it is tost. [The sound of the tempest increases, and voices are heard within. Voices within. We sink! we sink! we're lost! Demon (within). For what I have in hand, I'll trust this plank to bear me to the land. Cyprian. As scorning the wild wave One man alone his life attempts to save. While lurching over, mid the billows' swell, The great ship sinks to where the Tritons dwell; There, with its mighty ribs asunder rent, It lies a corse of the sea, its grave and monument. Enter The Demon, dripping with wet, as if escaped from the sea. Demon (aside). For the end I wish to gain It was of necessity That upon this sapphire sea I this fearful storm should feign, And in form unlike that one Which in this wild wood I wore, When I found my deepest lore By his keener wit outdone, Come again to assail him here, Trusting better now to prove Both his intellect and his love.— Earth, loved earth, O mother dear, [Aloud. From this monster, this wild sea, Give me shelter in thy arms. Cyprian. Lose, my friend, the dread alarms, And the cruel memory Of thy peril happily past; Since we learn or late or soon, That beneath the inconstant moon Human bliss doth never last. Demon. Who art thou, at whose kind feet Has my fortune cast me here? Cyprian. One who with a pitying tear, For a ruin so complete, Would alleviate your woe. Demon. Ah, impossible!—for me Never, never, can there be Any solace. Cyprian. How, why so? Demon. All my priceless wealth I've lost ... But I'm wrong to thus complain, I'll forget, nay, think it gain, Since my life it hath not cost. Cyprian. Now that the wild whirl malign Of this earthquake storm doth cease, And the sky returns to peace, Quiet, calm, and crystalline, And the bright succeeds the dark With such strange rapidity, That the storm would seem to be Only raised to sink thy bark, Tell me who thou art, repay Thus a sympathy so sincere. Demon. It has cost me to come here More than you have seen to-day, More than I can well express; Of the miseries I recall This ship's loss is least of all. Would you see that clearly? Cyprian. Yes. Demon. I am, since you wish to know it, An epitome, a wonder Asonante in o—e, to the end of the speech. Of all happiness and misfortune, One I have lost, I weep the other. By my gifts was I so glorious, So conspicuous in my order, Of a lineage so illustrious, With a mind so well informéd, That my rare endowments feeling, A great king (in truth the noblest King of Kings, for all would tremble If he looked in anger on them,) In his palace roofed with diamonds And with gems as bright as morning, (If I called them stars, 'tis certain The comparison were too modest,) His especial favourite called me. Which high epithet of honour So enflamed my pride, as rival For his royal seat I plotted, Hoping soon my victor footsteps Would his golden thrones have trodden. It was an unheard-of daring, That, chastized I must acknowledge, I was mad; but then repentance Were a still insaner folly. Obstinate in my resistance, With my spirit yet unconquered, I preferred to fall with courage Than surrender with dishonour. If the attempt was rash, the rashness Was not solely my misfortune, For among his numerous vassals Not a few my standard followed. From his court, in fine, thus vanquished, Though part victor in the contest, I went forth, my eyes outflashing Flames of anger and abhorrence, And my lips proclaiming vengeance For the public insult offered To my pride, among his people Scattering murder, rapine, horror. Then a bloody pirate, I The wide plains of the sea ran over, Argus of its dangerous shallows, Lynx-eyed where the reefs lay covered; In that vessel which the wind Bit by bit so soon demolished, In that vessel which the sea As a dustless ruin swallowed, I to-day these fields of crystal Eagerly ran o'er, my object Being stone by stone to examine, Tree by tree to search this forest:— For a man in it is living, Whom it is of great importance I should see, this day expecting The fulfilment of a promise Which he gave and I accepted. This infuriate tempest stopped me. And although my powerful genius Could chain up east, south, and north wind, I cared not, as if despairing Of success, with other objects, Other aims in view, to turn them To the west wind's summer softness.— (I have said I could, but did not, [Aside. For I note the dangerous workings Of his mind, and thus to magic Bind him by these hints the stronger.) Let not my wild fury fright thee, Nor be at my power astonished, For I could my own death give me, If I were by rage so prompted, And so great that power, the sunlight, By my science could be blotted. I, in magic am so mighty, That I can describe the orbits Of the stars, for I have travelled Through the farthest and beyond them. And in order that this boasting May not seem to you mere bombast, Look, if at this very instant You desire it, this untrodden Nimrod of rude rocks more savage Than of Babylon is recorded, Shall without a leaf being shaken, Show the most horrific portents. I am, then, the orphan guest here Of these ash-trees, of these poplars, And though what I am, assistance At thy feet here I ask from thee: And I wish the good I purchase To repay thee with the product Of unnumbered years of study, Though it now slight effort costs me, Giving to your wildest wishes (Aside. Here I touch his love,) the fondest Longings of your heart, whatever Passion can desire or covet. If through courtesy or caution You should not accept my offer, Let my good intentions pay you, If from greater acts you stop me. For the pity that you show me, Which I thankfully acknowledge, I will be a friend so faithful, That henceforth the changeful monster Of events and acts, called Fortune, Which 'twixt flattering words and scornful, Generous now, and now a miser, Shows a friendly face or hostile, Neither it nor that laborious Ever flying, running worker, Time, the loadstone of the ages, Nor even heaven itself, heaven proper, To whose stars the dark world oweth All its most divine adornment, Will have power to separate me From your side a single moment, Since you here have given me welcome. And even this is almost nothing When compared with what my wishes Hope hereafter to accomplish. Cyprian. Well to the sea, my thanks are due, that bore You struggling to the shore, And led you to this grove, Where you will quickly prove The friendly feelings that inflame my breast, If happily I merit such a guest. Then let us homeward wend, For I esteem you now as an old friend. My guest you are, and so you must not leave me While my house suits you. Demon. Do you then receive me Wholly as yours? Cyprian (embracing him). This act doth prove it true, That seals an eternal bond betwixt us two.— Oh! if I could win o'er [Aside. This man to instruct me in his magic lore! Since by that art my love might gain Some solaee for its pain; Or yielding to its mighty laws My love at length might win my love's sweet cause— The cause of all my torment, madness, rage. Demon (aside). The working of his mind and love I gauge. Scene VIII. Clarin and Moscon enter running from opposite sides. Cyprian, and The Demon. Clarin. Oh! are you, sir, alive? Moscon. My friend, do you Speak civilly for once as something new? That he's alive requires no demonstration. Clarin. I struck this lofty note of admiration, Thou noble lackey, to express my wonder, How from this storm of lightning, rain, and thunder, Without a miracle he could survive. Moscon. Will you stop wondering, now you see him alive? Cyprian. These are my servants, sir.— What brings you here? Moscon. Your spleen once more to stir. Demon. They have a pleasant humour. Cyprian. Foolish pair, Their weary wit is oft too hard to bear. Moscon. This man, sir, waiting here, Who is he? Cyprian. He's my guest, so do not fear. Clarin. Wherefore have guests at such a time as this? Cyprian (to The Demon). Your worth is lost on ignorance such as his. Moscon. My master's right. Are you, forsooth, his heir? Clarin. No; but our new friend there, Looks like a guest, unless I deceive me, who Will honour our poor house a year or two. Moscon. Why? Clarin. When a guest soon means to go away, Well, he'll not make much smoke in the house, we say. But this. ... Moscon. Speak out. Clarin. Will make, I do not joke ... Moscon. What? Clarin. In the house a deucéd deal of smoke. Cyprian. In order to repair The danger done by the rude sea and air, Come thou with me. Demon. I'm thine, while thou hast breath. [Aside. Cyprian. I go to prepare thy rest. Demon (aside). And I thy death:— An entrance having gained Within his breast, and thus my end obtained; My rage insatiate now without control Seeks by another way to win Justina's soul. [Exit. Clarin. Guess, if you can, what I am thinking about. Moscon. What is it? Clarin. That a new volcano has burst out In the late storm, there's such a sulphur smell. Moscon. It came from the guest, as my good nose could tell. Clarin. He uses bad pastilles, then; but I can Infer the cause. Moscon. What is it? Clarin. The poor gentleman Has a slight rash on his skin, a ticklish glow, And uses sulphur ointment. Moscon. Gad! 'tis so. [Exeunt. Scene IX. THE STREET. Lelius and Fabius. Fabius. You return, then, to this street. Lelius. Yes; the life that I deplore I return to seek once more Where 'twas lost. Ah! guide my feet, Love, to find it!— Fabius. That house there Is Justina's; come away. Lelius. Wherefore, when I will to-day Once again my love declare. And as she, I saw it plain, Trusted some one else at night, 'Tis not strange, in open light, That I try to soothe my pain. Leave me, go; for it is best That I enter here alone. My rank in Antioch is known, My father Governor; thus drest In his robe as 'twere, my strong Passion listening to no mentor, I Justina's house will enter To protest against my wrong. [Exeunt. Scene X. A HALL IN THE HOUSE OF LYSANDER. Justina, and afterwards Lelius. Justina. Livia. ... But a step! who's there? Lelius enters. Lelius. It is I. Justina. What novelty, What extreme temerity, Thus, my lord, compels you? ... Lelius. Spare Your reproaches. Jealous-grown, I can bear that you reprove. Pardon me, for with my love My respect has also flown. Justina. Why, at such a perilous cost Have you dared ... Lelius. Because I'm mad. Justina. To intrude. ... Lelius. Heart-broken, sad. Justina. Here. ... Lelius. Because, in truth, I'm lost. Justina. Nor perceive how scandal views Such an act as now you do 'Gainst. ... Lelius. Be not so moved, for you Little honour now can lose. Justina. Lelius, spare at least my fame. Lelius. Ah, Justina, it were best That this language you addressed Unto him who nightly came Down here from this balcony;— 'Tis enough for me to show All your lightness that I know, That less coy and cold to me Your pretended honour prove. If I am disdained, displaced, 'Tis another suits your taste, Not that you your honour love. Justina. Silence, cease, your words withhold. Who with insult e'er before Dared to pass my threshold's door? Are you then so blind and bold, So audacious, so insane, As my pure light to eclipse, Through the libel of your lips, By chimeras false and vain?— In my house a man? Lelius. 'Tis so. Justina. From my balcony? Lelius. With shame I repeat it. Justina. O, my fame, O'er us twain your Ægis throw. Scene XI. THE SAME. The Demon appears at the door which is behind Justina. Demon (aside). For the deep design I handle, For my double plot I come Raging to this simple home, Now to work the greatest scandal Ever seen. Here, brooding o'er him, This wild lover mad with ire, I will fan his jealous fire, I will place myself before him, Catch his eye, and then as fleeing, In invisible gloom array me. [He affects to come in, and being seen by Lelius muffles himself in his cloak, and re-enters the inner apartment. Justina. Man, do you come here to slay me? Lelius. No, to die. Justina. What object seeing Paralyses thus your senses? Lelius. What I see is your untruth. Tell me now, the wish, forsooth, Has invented my offences. From that very chamber there Came a man, I turned my head, When he saw my face he fled Back into the room. Justina. The air Must this phantasy display— This illusion. Lelius. Oh, that sight! Justina. Is it not enough by night, Lelius, but in open day Thus fictitious forms to see? Lelius. Phantom shape or real lover, Now the truth I will discover. [He goes into the room where The Demon had disappeared. Justina. I no hindrance offer thee, For my innocence, a way, At the cost of this permission, Thus finds out the night's submission To correct by the light of day. Scene XII. Lysander and Justina; Lelius, within. Lysander. My Justina. Justina (aside). Woe is me! Ah, if here before Lysander Asonante in a—e, to the end of Scene XVII. Lelius from that room comes forth! Lysander. My misfortunes, my disasters Fly to be consoled by thee. Justina. What can be the grief, the sadness, That your face betrays so plainly? Lysander. And no wonder, when the pallor Springs even from the heart. This sobbing Stops my weak words in their passage. [Lelius appears at the door of the apartment. Lelius (aside). I begin now to believe, Since he is not in this chamber, Jealousy can cause these spectres. He, the man I saw, has vanished, How I know not. Justina (aside to Lelius). Come not forth, Lelius, here before my father. Lelius. Convalescent in my sickness I will wait till he is absent. [Retires. Justina. Why this weeping? why this sighing? What, sir, moves thee, what unmans thee? Lysander. I am moved by a misfortune, I'm unmanned by a disaster, Greater far than tender pity Ever wept,—the dread example Cruelty has sworn to make In the innocent blood of martyrs. To the Governor of this city Decius Cæsar a strict mandate Has despatched ... I can speak no more. Justina (aside). What position e'er was harder? Moved with pity for the Christians Hither comes to me Lysander The sad news to tell, not knowing Lelius to his words may hearken,— Lelius, the Governor's son. Lysander. So, Justina ... Justina. Sir, no farther, Since you feel it so acutely, Speak upon this painful matter. Lysander. Let me, for I'll feel some solace When to thee it is imparted. In it he commands ... Justina. Proceed not Further now, when you should rather Cheat your years with more repose. Lysander. How? when I, to make you partner In those lively fears whose bodings Are sufficient to despatch me, Would inform you of the edict, The most cruel that the margin Of the Tiber ever saw Writ in blood to stain its waters, Do you stop me? Ah, Justina, You were wont in another manner Once to listen to me. Justina. Sir, Different were the circumstances. Lelius (at the door, aside). I can hear but indistinctly Half-formed words and broken accents. Scene XIII. Florus enters.—Justina and Lysander; Lelius, peeping at the door of the inner room. Florus (aside). Licence has a jealous lover, Who but enters to unmask here A pretended purity, To forego politer manners. I come here with that intention ... But as she is with her father I will wait a new occasion. Lysander. Who is there? Some footstep passes. Florus (aside). Ah! 'tis now impossible Without speaking to get back here. Some excuse I'll try to offer:— I am ... Lysander. You here, sir? Florus. Your pardon. I ask leave, sir, to speak with you On a most important matter. Justina (aside). Oh! take pity on me, fortune, For these trials are too many. Lysander. Well, sir, speak. Florus (aside). What shall I say? Never was I so embarassed. Lelius (aside, at the door). Florus in Justina's house Leaves and enters like a master!— These are not unfounded jealousies, These are real and substantial. Lysander. You grow pale, you change your colour. Florus. Do not wonder, be not startled, For I came to give a warning, To your life of utmost value, Of an enemy that you have, Who your swift destruction planneth. What I've said is quite sufficient. Lysander (aside). Florus, doubtless, must have gathered Somehow that I am a Christian, And thus comes in kindliest manner Of my danger to apprise me.— Speak, hide nothing in this matter. [Aloud. Scene XIV. Livia enters.—Justina, Lysander, and Florus; Lelius at the door of the room. Livia. Sir, the Governor, who is waiting At the door of the house, commanded Me to call you to his presence. Florus. Best I wait for his departure:— (Meantime my excuse I'll think of.) [Aside. So 'tis well that you despatch him. Lysander. I appreciate your politeness. Here I will return instanter. [Exeunt Lysander and Livia. Scene XV. Justina and Florus; Lelius at the door. Florus. Are you then that virtuous maiden, Who, the very breeze that flatters With its soft and sweet caresses, You would call rude, bold, unmannered? How then is it you surrendered Even the very keys of the casket Of your honour? Justina. Hold, hold, Florus, Do not dare to throw a shadow On that honour which the sun After the most strict examen Has proved bright and pure. Florus. Too late Comes this idle boast. It happens That I know to whom you have given Free access ... Justina. You dare this scandal?— Florus. By a balcony ... Justina. Do not say it. Florus. To your honour. Justina. Thus will you blast me? Florus. Yes, for hypocritical virtue Merits something even harsher. Lelius (at the door, aside). Florus was not then the hero Of the balcony; some more happy Lover than us twain she welcomes. Justina. Oh! defame not noble damsels, Since you noble blood inherit. Florus. Noble damsel, dar'st thou call thee, When thy very arms received him, And from thy balcony he departed? Power subdued thee; from the fact That the Governor is his father, Vanity led thee on to show That in Antioch he commanded ... Lelius (aside). Here he speaks of me. Florus. Not seeing Any graver defect of manner, Than what in his birth and breeding Rank may cover with its mantle, But not so. ... Lelius enters. Lelius. Be silent, Florus, Nor attack me in my absence; For of a rival to speak ill, Is the act but of a dastard. 'Tis to stop this I come forward, Angry after so many passes Which my sword has had with thine, That I have not yet dispatched thee. Justina. Who, not guilty, ever saw her In such dangerous straits entangled? Florus. What behind your back was spoken, I before you will establish, Truth is truth where'er 'tis uttered. [They grasp their swords. Justina. Florus! Lelius! what would you have then. Lelius. I would have full satisfaction Where I heard th'insulting language. Florus. I'll maintain what I have said Where I said it. Justina. From so many Strokes of fortune, free me, Heaven!— Florus. And I'll learn to chastise your rashness. Scene XVI. The Governor enters with Lysander and attendants.— Justina, Lelius, and Florus. All who enter. Hold! stand back! Justina. Unhappy me! Governor. What is this? But empty scabbards, Naked swords, are quite sufficient To inform me what has happened. Justina. What misfortune! Lysander. What affliction!— Lelius. Ah, my lord ... Governor. Enough, no farther. Lelius, thou a son of mine, A disturber? Thou a scandal To all Antioch through my favour? Lelius. Think, my lord ... Governor. Arrest, disarm them, Take them hence. Make no distinction On account of blood or rank here. Let them suffer both alike, Since in guilt alike they acted. Lelius (aside). I came jealous, and go outraged. Florus (aside). To my pains new pains are added. Governor. In distinct and separate prisons, And with watchful eyes to guard them, Place the two.—And you, Lysander, Is it possible you have tarnished Such a noble reputation, Suffering. ... Lysander. No; let not these dazzling False appearances mislead you, For Justina in what happened Was quite blameless. Governor. In her house here, Would you have her live regardless Of the fact that they were young, And that she was fair? My anger I restrain, lest people say, I, an interested party, Sentence passed as partial judge.— But of you who caused this quarrel, Now that maiden shame has left you, Well I know that you will glad me With the occasion I desire, Of exposing, of unmasking, In the light of actual vices, The false virtuous part you've acted. [Exeunt The Governor and his attendants; Lelius and Florus follow as prisoners. Scene XVII. Justina and Lysander. Justina. I reply but with my tears. Lysander. Tears as vain as they are tardy. What an act was mine, Justina, When to thee my lips imparted Who thou art! Oh, would I never Told thee, that upon the margin Of a rivulet in this forest, A dead mother's womb here cast thee! Justina. I. ... Lysander. Do not attempt excuses. Justina. Heaven will make them, then, hereafter Lysander. When too late, perhaps. Justina. No limit Can be late here while life lasteth. Lysander. For the punishment of crimes. Justina. Injured truth to re-establish. Lysander. I, from what I have seen, condemn thee. Justina. I thee, from what thou knowest not, rather. Lysander. Leave me; I go forth to die Where my grief will soon dispatch me. Justina. At thy feet I would lose my life; But do not reject me, father. [Exeunt. Scene XVIII. A HALL IN CYPRIAN'S HOUSE. AT THE END IS AN OPEN GALLERY, THROUGH WHICH IS SEEN THE COUNTRY. Cyprian, The Demon, Moscon, and Clarin. Demon. Since the hour that I have been In your house a guest, you ne'er Show a gay and cheerful air. Sadness in your face is seen. It is wrong your cure to shun, Seeking to mislead mine eyes, Since I would unsphere the skies, Shake the stars, and shroud the sun, For the least desire you feel That more pleasantly you might live. Cyprian. Magic has no power to give The impossible I conceal, Though the misery I betray. Demon. Come, confess the longed-for bliss. Cyprian. I love a woman. Demon. And is this The impossible that you say? Cyprian. If you knew her, you'd agree. Demon. Well, describe her, I'm resigned; Though I can't but smile to find What a coward you must be. Cyprian. The fair cradle of the skies, Where the infant sun reposes, Ere he rises, decked with roses, Robed in snow, to dry heaven's eyes. The green prison-bud that tries To restrain the conscious rose, When the crimson captive knows April treads its gardens near, Turning dawn's half frozen tear To a smile where sunshine glows. The sweet streamlet gliding by, Though it scarcely dares to breathe Softest murmurs through its teeth, From the frosts that on it lie. The bright pink, in its small sky Shining like a coral star. The blithe bird that flies afar, Drest in shifting shades and blooms— Soaring cithern of plumes Harping high o'er heaven's blue bar. The white rock that cheats the sun When it tries to melt it down, What it melts is but the crown Which from winter's snow it won. The green bay that will not shun, Though the heavens are all aglow, For its feet a bath of snow,— Green Narcissus of the brook, Fearless leaning o'er to look, Though the stream runs chill below. In a word, the crimson dawn, Sun, mead, streamlet, rosebud, May, Bird that sings his amorous lay, April's laugh that gems the lawn, Pink that sips the dews up-drawn, Rock that stands in storm and shine, Bay-tree that delights to twine Round its fadeless leaves the sun, All are parts which met in one Form this woman most divine. For myself, in blind unrest, (Guess my madness if you can) I, to seem another man, In these courtly robes am drest. Studious calm I now detest, Fame no longer fires my mind, Passion reigns where thought refined, I my firmness fling to tears, Courage I resign to fears, And my hopes I give the wind. I have said, and so will do, That to some infernal sprite I would offer with delight (And the pledge I now renew) Even my soul for her I woo. But my offer is in vain, Hell rejects it with disdain, For my soul, it may allege, Is a disproportionate pledge For the interest I would gain. Demon. Is this, then, your boasted courage, In the footsteps of dejected Asonante in e—e, to the end of the Act. Swains to follow, who grow timid When their first assault's rejected? Are examples then so distant Of fair ladies who surrender All their vanities to entreaties, All their pride to fond addresses? Would you make your breast the prison Of your love, your arms her fetters? Cyprian. Can you doubt it? Demon. Then command them To retire, those two, your servants, So that we remain here only. Cyprian. Go: both leave me for the present. Moscon. I obey. [Exit. Clarin. And I as well.— Such a guest must be the devil. [Aside, concealing himself. Cyprian. They are gone. Demon (aside). That Clarin's hiding, Is to me of small concernment. Cyprian. What more wish you now? Demon. First fasten Well this door. Cyprian. Yes; none can enter. Demon. For the possession of this woman, With your lips you have asserted You would give your soul. Cyprian. 'Tis so. Demon. Then the contract is accepted. Cyprian. What do you say? Demon. That I accept it. Cyprian. How? Demon. So much have I effected By my science, that I will teach you How by it to get possession Of the woman that you worship; For I (though so wise and learnéd) Have no other means to win her. Let us now in writing settle What we have resolved between us. Cyprian. Do you wish by new pretences To prolong the pains I suffer? In my hand is what I tender, But in yours is not the offer That you make me; no, for never Conjurations or enchantments Can free will control or fetter. Demon. Give me, on the terms you spoke of, Your signed bond. Clarin (peeping). The deuce! This fellow Is no fool, I see. No greenhorn In his business is this devil. I give him my bond! No, truly, Though my lodgings wanted a tenant For the space of twenty ages, I wouldn't do it. Cyprian. Sir, such jesting May with merry friends be pastime, Not with those who are dejected. Demon. I, in proof of what I am able To effect, will now present you With an example, though it faintly Shows the power my art possesses. From this gallery what is seen? Cyprian. Much of sky, and much of meadow, Wood, a rivulet, and a mountain. Demon. Which to you doth seem most pleasant? Cyprian. The proud mountain, for in it Is my adored one represented. Demon. Proud competitor of time, Rival of the years for ever, Who as king of fields and plains Crown'st thee with the cloud and tempest, Move thyself, change earth and air; Look, see who I am that tell thee.— And, look thou, too, since a mountain I can move, thou mayest a maiden. [The mountain moves from one side to the other in the perspective of the theatre. Cyprian. Never saw I such a wonder! Ne'er a sight of so much terror! Clarin (peeping). With the fright and with the fear, I enjoy a twofold tremble. Cyprian. Mighty mountain bird that fliest, Trees for wings replacing feathers, Boat, whose rocks supply the tackle, As thou furrowest through the zephyr, To thy centre back return thee, And so end this fear, this terror. [The mountain returns to its original position. Demon. If one proof is not sufficient, I will give you then a second. Do you wish to see the woman You adore? Cyprian. Yes. Demon. Then, thy entrails Ope, thou monster, to whose being The four elements are servants. Show to us the perfect beauty That thou hidest in thy centre. [A rock opens and Justina is seen sleeping. Is this she whom you adore? Cyprian. Whom I idolize beyond measure. Demon. But since I have power to give her, I can take her too, remember. Cyprian. Now impossible dream of mine, Now thy arms will be the centre Of my love, thy lips the sun, Burning, brimming as with nectar. Demon. Stay; for till the word you gave me Is affirmed, and well attested, You can touch her not. [Cyprian rushes towards the rock, which closes. Cyprian. Oh, stay Cloud that hides the most resplendent Sun, that on my bliss e'er dawned!— But 'tis air my void arm presses.— I believe you art, acknowledge Now I am your slave for ever. What do you wish I do for thee? What do you ask? Demon. To be protected By your signature here written In your blood, at the foot of a letter. Clarin (peeping). Oh! I'd give my soul that I To stay here had not been tempted. Cyprian. For my pen I use this dagger, Paper let this white cloth serve for, And the ink wherewith I write it, Be the blood my arm presents me. [He writes with the point of a dagger upon a piece of linen, having drawn blood from one of his arms. Oh! I freeze with fear, with horror! [Aside. I, great Cyprian, say expressly I will give my immortal soul, (Oh! what lethargy, what frenzy!) Unto him whose art will teach me (What confusion! what strange terror!) How I may of fair Justina, Haughty mistress mine, possess me. I have signed it with my name. Demon (aside). Now to my deceits is rendered Valid homage, when such reason, When discourse like his must tremble Even when my help is sought for.— Have you written? Cyprian. And signed the letter. Demon. Then the sun you adore is thine. Cyprian. Thine too, for the years eternal, Is the soul I offer thee. Demon. Soul for soul I pay my debtors, Then for thine I give to thee Thy Justina's. Cyprian. In what term then, Think you you can teach to me All your magic art? Demon. A twelvemonth; But on this condition. ... Cyprian. Speak. Demon. That within a cavern buried, Without any other study, We may live there both together, In our service having no one For us two but this attendant, [Drags out Clarin. Who being curious hid him here;— By securing thus his person That our secret is well kept, We, I think, may be quite certain. Clarin (aside). Oh, that I had never waited! How does it happen though, so many Neighbours prone to pry, as I am, Are not caught thus by the devil? Cyprian. So far well. My love, my genius Have this happy end effected: First Justina will be mine, Then by my new lights, new learning, I will wake the world's surprise. Demon. I have gained what I intended. Clarin. I not so. Demon. You come with us.— O'er my great foe I've got the better. [Aside. Cyprian. Ah, how happy my desires, If I reach to such possession!— Demon (aside). Never will my envy rest Till I gain both souls to serve me.— Let us go, and in the deepest Cavern this wild world presenteth You to-day will learn in magic Your first lesson. Cyprian. Let us enter, For my mind with such a master, For my love with such incentive, Will the sorcerer Cyprian's name Live before the world for ever.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT THE THIRD. Scene I. A WOOD; AT THE EXTREMITY A GROTTO. Cyprian. Cyprian. Ungrateful beauty mine, At length the day, the happy day doth shine— My hope's remotest range, The limits of my love and of thy change, Since I to-day will gain At last my triumph over thy disdain. This lofty mountain nigh, Raised to the star-lit palace of the sky, And this dark cavern's gloom, Of two that live, so long the dismal tomb, Are the rough school wherein From magic art its mystic lore I win, And such perfection reach That I can now my mighty master teach. Seeing, that on this day, since I came here The sun completes its course from sphere to sphere, I from my prison cell come forth to view What in the light I now have power to do. Ye skies of cloudless day List to my magic spell-words and obey; Swift zephyrs that rejoice In heaven's warm light, stand still and hear my voice; Stupendous mountain rock Shake at my words as at an earthquake shock; Ye trees in rough bark drest Be frightened at the groanings of my breast; Ye flowers so fair and frail Faint at the echoing terror of my wail; Ye sweet melodious birds Hush all your songs before my awful words; Ye cruel beasts of prey See the first fruits of my long toil to-day; For blinded, dazzled, dazed, Confused, disturbed, astonished and amazed, Ye skies and zephyrs, rocks, and trees, and flowers, And birds, and beasts, behold my magic powers, And thus to all make plain Cyprian's infernal study is not vain. Scene II. The Demon and Cyprian. Demon. Cyprian! Cyprian. Wise friend and master still! Demon. Why, how is this, that using your free-will More than my precept meant, Say for what end, what object, what intent, Through ignorance or boldness can it be, You thus come forth the sun's bright face to see? Cyprian. Seeing that now my spell Can fill with fear, with horror even hell, Since I, with so much care Have studied magic and its depths laid bare, So that yourself can scarcely tell Whether 'tis I or you that most excel, Seeing that now there is no place or part That I with study, diligence and art, Have not attained, Since necromancy's secret I have gained, That art whose lines of gloom Can ope to me the dark funereal tomb, And bring before mine eyes Each corpse that in it lies, Regaining them, as 'twere by a new birth From the hard avarice of the grasping earth. The pale ghosts, one and all, Rise and respond my call;— And seeing that at length the sun My goal of life had won, Since from its innate force Swift-speeding on its course, Climbing the heavens each day, It turns as 'twere reluctantly away, And with a natural fear Completes to-day the lifetime of a year, I wish to attain the scope At last of all my dreams, of all my hope. To-day the rare, the beautiful, the divine Justina will be mine, Here summoned by my charms, Here lured by love she'll come unto my arms, For you from me no longer can require Postponement of my hope's, my heart's desire. Demon. Nor do I wish to do it, no, Since thus so earnestly you wish it so. Now trace upon the ground Mute mystic symbols, and the deep profound Of air, with powerful incantations move Obedient to your hope and to your love. Cyprian. For that I will retire; You soon shall see the heaven and earth admire. [Exit. Demon. I give you leave to go, Because our science being the same, I know That the abyss of hell Obedient to your spell Will yield through me, this way, The fair Justina to your arms to-day: For, though my mighty power Cannot enslave free-will even for an hour, It may present The outward show of rapture and content, Suggesting thoughts impure:— If force I cannot use, at least I lure. Scene III. Clarin and The Demon. Clarin. Ungrateful fair, who still my heart doth hold, Not burning Libya sure, but Livia cold, The time is come to show Whether in love you have been true or no, Whether, since I within this cave was placed, Not chased by me you have yourself been chaste; For I have studied here At second hand some magic for a year, Just to find out (alack! I can't but wince) Whether with Moscon you have wronged me since:— Ye watery skies (some people call them pure) List to my conjurations I conjure, Mountains. ... Demon. How, Clarin? Clarin. Oh! my master wise! By the concomitance of my hands and eyes, I've learned some magic, and would know by it If Livia, that ungrateful little chit, Has played me false since I have been away, Embracing that rogue Moscon on my day. Demon. Have done with these buffooneries: leave me, go. And 'mid these intricate rocks whose paths you know, Assist your master, who will let you see (If you would witness such a prodigy) The end of all his woe. I wish to be alone. Clarin. And I not so. I now perceive Why to use magic I have not your leave, The fault was mine, neglecting to attest My bond, and sign it with the blood of my breast.— Upon this linen handkerchief [He takes out a soiled pocket-handkerchief. (None cleaner he can have who cries for grief) I'll sign it now, the method I propose Is but to give myself a box on the nose, For there is little harm Whether the blood is drawn from nose or arm. [He writes with his finger on the handkerchief, after having drawn some blood. I, the great Clarin, say, if I can level Pert Livia's cruel pride, whom I give to the devil. ... Demon. Leave me, I say again, Go seek your master and with him remain. Clarin. Yes, I will do so, don't get angry though. The reason you reject my bond I know: 'Tis this, because you see, Do what I will that you are sure of me. Scene IV. The Demon. Demon. Abyss of hell prepare! Thyself the region of thine own despair.— From out each dungeon's dark recess Let loose the spirits of voluptuousness, To ruin and o'erthrow Justina's virgin fabric pure as snow. A thousand filthy phantoms with thee brought So people her chaste thought That all her maiden fancies may be filled With their deceits; let sweetest notes be trilled From every tuneful grove, And all, birds, plants, and flowers, provoke to love. Let nothing meet her eyes But spoils of love's delicious victories, Let nothing meet her ears But languid sighs that listening passion hears: That thus unguarded by the faith, and weak, She here may Cyprian seek Invoked by his strong spell, And by my blinding spirit lured as well. Begin, in silence I will here remain Unseen, that you may now begin the strain. [Exit. Scene V. Justina; music within. (They sing within.) A Voice. What is the glory far above, All else that life can give? Chorus of Various Voices. Love, love. A Voice. No creature lives on which love's flame Has not impressed its burning seal, The man feels more who love doth feel Than when Love's breath first warmed his frame. Love owns one universal claim,— To Love, it only needs To Be,— Whether a bird, a flower, a tree: Then the chief glory, far above All else in life must be ... Chorus (within). Love, love. Justina (alarmed and restless). Fancy, flatterer that thou art, Though thou should'st be sad to-day, When did I to thee impart, In this strange and sudden way, Licence to afflict my heart? What thus makes my pulses move? What strange fire is this I prove Which each moment doth increase? Ah! this pain that ends my peace, This sweet unrest, ah, what? Chorus. Love, love. Justina (more composed). 'Tis that enamoured nightingale Who thus gives me the reply:— To his partner in the vale Listening on a bough hard by Warbling thus his tuneful wail. Cease, sweet nightingale, nor show By thy softly witching strain Trilling forth thy bliss and woe, How a man might feel love's pain, When a bird can feel his so. No: it was that wanton vine That in fond pursuit has sought The tall tree it doth entwine, Till the green weight it hath brought Makes the noble trunk decline. Green entwining boughs that hold What you love in your embrace, Make my fancy not too bold:— Ah, if boughs thus interlace, How would clasping arms infold!— And if not the vine, 'twill be That bright sunflower which we see Turning with its tearful eyes To its sun-god in the skies, Whatsoe'er his movements be. Flower, thy watch no longer keep, Drooping leaflets fold in sleep, For the fond thought reappears, Ah, if leaves can shed such tears, What are those that eyes can weep! Cease then, lyrist of the grove, Leafy vine, unclasp thy arms, Fickle flower, no longer move, And declare, these poisoned charms That you use, what yields? Chorus (within). Love, love. Justina. Love! it cannot be. Its chain Have I ever worn for man? No, the fond deceit is vain. All received a like disdain, Lelius, Florus, Cyprian. Lelius did I not despise? Florus did I not detest? Cyprian, the good and wise, [She pauses at Cyprian's name and resumes for a time her unquiet manner. Spurn with such a haughty breast, That he vanished from my eyes, As if frightened by their ire?— Where he went I do not know. But save this, the faintest fire Love e'er lit, ne'er dared to glow In the depths of my desire. Yes, for since I said that he Should submit without appeal Never more my face to see, Ah, I know not what I feel!—[She grows calmer. Pity it must surely be, That a man so widely known Should through love of me be lost, When he pays at such a cost For the preference he has shown. [She becomes troubled again. Were it pity though, 'tis true, The same pity I should give Lelius and to Florus too, Who in separate dungeons live, Ah! for daring me to woo. [She grows calmer. But my thoughts, ye mutinous crew, If my pity is enough It should not be clogged by you. Still your promptings press me so, That I feel in my despair, Where he is, if I could know, I to seek him now would go. Scene VI. The Demon and Justina. Demon. Come, and I will tell thee where. Justina. Who art thou who hast procured Entrance to this lone retreat, Though the entrance is secured? Or, my senses being obscured, Art thou but delusion's cheat? Demon. No, not so; but having known How this passion pressed thee so, I have sought thee here alone, Having promised thee to show Whither Cyprian has flown. Justina. Then thou'lt reach not thy intent; For this passion, this strange pain, Which my thought doth so torment, Though my fancy it may gain, It will never my consent. Demon. But in thought to enter in Shows that half the deed is done; Since accomplished is the sin:— Stop not half way, ere is won What the wish desired to win. Justina. Even in this desponding hour, Though to think may taint the flower, Thy suggestion comes to nought,— In my power is not my thought, But my act is in my power. I can follow to the brink, Free to pause or to pursue, Move my foot, or backward shrink, For it is one thing to do, And another thing to think. Demon. If a stronger power than thine, Drawn from a profounder source, With thine own desires combine, How resist the double force Which with force thy steps incline? Justina. I will trust a safer spell:— My free will suffices me. Demon. But my power will it excel. Justina. Then the will no more were free If a force could it compel. Demon. Come where every bliss thou'lt meet. [Attempts to draw her with him, but cannot move her. Justina. Ah! the bliss were bought too dear. Demon. It is peace, serene and sweet. Justina. 'Tis a slavery most severe. Demon. Life, 'tis joy. Justina. 'Tis death, deceit. Demon. Thy defence, what can it be, If my power thus forces thee? [Drags her with more force. Justina. In my God it doth consist. Demon. By persisting to resist, Woman, thou hast conquered me. [Releases her. Thy defence to God is due, And my counsel is disdained; Yes, but raging I'll renew My attempt and have thee feigned, If I cannot have thee true. To a spirit I will give Shape like thine though fugitive, It will counterfeit thy form, As with seeming life be warm, And in it disgraced thou'lt live. Thus two triumphs at one time I am sure to win by this, Be thy virtue so sublime, Since through an ideal bliss I will consummate a crime. [Exit. Scene VII. Justina. Justina. 'Gainst the clouds that round me lower I appeal to heaven's high power; Let this spectre of my fame— As before the wind the flame— As before the frost the flower, Vanish, die. ... But, woe is me! Who is here to heed my moan? Was there not a man with me? Yes. But no: I am alone: No. But yes: for I could see. Where so quickly could he fly? Was he born of my unrest? Oh! my danger's manifest ... Father! friend! Lysander! I Call. ... Scene VIII. Lysander and Livia enter from opposite doors.—Justina. Lysander. My child? Livia. What means this cry? Justina. Saw you not a man (ah, me!) Who but left me instantly? I can scarce express my thought. Lysander. A man here? Justina. You saw him not? Livia. No, señora. Justina. I could see. Lysander. Saw a man here? That is hard, When the place was locked and barred. Livia (aside). Moscon sure she must have seen, Whom I have contrived to screen In my chamber. Lysander. I regard What you saw but as the play Of your fancy and your fear. Melancholy surely may Have, the man that you saw here, Formed from atoms of the day. Livia. Yes, I think my master's right. Justina. No, 'twas no defect of sight, No illusion: since my heart,— Ah! too well I feel the smart— Has been broken by the fright. Some strange witchery of my will Must have been effected here. And with such consummate skill, That if God had not been near I might have pursued my ill. He who at such timely hour Helped me to resist the power Of this fearful violence, Will my humble innocence Guard, whatever dangers lower.— Livia, my cloak: whene'er [Exit Livia. Overwhelming griefs oppress, I to holy church repair, Where we secretly confess The true faith. [Livia returns with the cloak, which she places on Justina. Livia. 'Tis this you wear. Justina. There perchance I may appease This strange fire that burns me so. Lysander. I desire with thee to go. Livia (aside). I will breathe much more at ease When they're out of the house, I know. Justina. Since I wholly trust to thee Heaven, thy hold to me afford. Save me. ... Lysander. Come: so it may be. Justina. Since the cause is thine, O Lord! Oh, defend Thyself and me! [Exeunt Justina and Lysander. Scene IX. Moscon and Livia. Moscon. Have they gone? Livia. They're gone: all right. Moscon. Why, I'm almost dead with fright. Livia. Were you of your sense bereft When but now my room you left And appeared before her sight? Moscon. Left your room? Be seen by her? Why, I swear it, Livia dear, Not one moment did I stir. Livia. Who then was it she saw here? Moscon. Well, the devil, as I infer. How know I? But then do not Take it so to heart, my soul. Livia. Oh! that's not the cause. [She weeps. Moscon. Then what? Livia. Such a question, when the whole Of a day it was his lot With me here locked up to stay? For his comrade far away Must I not a tear then shed, Though I take this day instead, Having wept not yesterday? Would I have him think of me As a woman who could be So forgetful and so frail, As for half a year to fail In what we did both agree? Moscon. Half a year? It is above One whole year since he went away. Livia. Quite an error, as I'll prove. Mind, I cannot count a day When I Clarin could not love. This being so, if I to thee Gave up half the year (ah, me!), It would give a false amount To place all to his account. Moscon. Ah, ungrateful! can it be When my heart on thee depends For its peace, that thine attends To such trifles? Livia. Moscon, yes, For I find, I must confess, Short accounts make longest friends. Moscon. Such being then thy constancy, Livia, I must say good-bye, Till to-morrow. Ah! if he Is thy two-day fever, I Hope he's not thy syncope. Livia. Well, my friend, from this you know I no malice bear. Moscon. Just so. Livia. See me then no more to-day, But to-morrow, sir, you may: I'll not need to send. Heigho! [Exeunt. Scene X. A WOOD. Cyprian, as frightened; Clarin, stealthily after him. Cyprian. Doubtless something must have happened 'Mong the stars' imperial clusters, Asonante in u—e to the end of Scene XV. Since I find their influences To my wishes so repugnant. Up from the profound abysses Some dark caveat must be uttered, Which prohibits the obedience Which they owe me as my subjects. I, a thousand times, with spell-words Made the winds of heaven to shudder, I, a thousand times, the bosom Of the earth with symbols furrowed, Yet mine eyes have not been gladdened By the human sun refulgent That I seek, nor in mine arms Hold that human heaven. Clarin. What wonder? When a thousand times have I Scraped the earth as if for nuggets, When a thousand times the wind By my screeching was perturbéd, And yet Livia was oblivious. Cyprian. Once again then I am humbled To invoke her thus. Oh, listen, Beautiful Justina. ... Scene XI. A phantom Figure of Justina appears. The Figure, Cyprian, and Clarin. Figure. Summoned, As I wander through these mountains, I obey a call so urgent. What, then, wouldst thou? what, then, wouldst thou, Cyprian, with me? Cyprian. Oh, I shudder! Figure. And since now. ... Cyprian. I am astonished! Figure. I have come. ... Cyprian. What thus disturbs me? Figure. To this place. ... Cyprian. What makes me tremble? Figure. Where. ... Cyprian. Oh! whence this doubt that numbs me? Figure. Love doth call me. ... Cyprian. Why, this terror? Figure. And the powerful spell thou workest Thus complied with, to this forest's Deepest depths I fly to shun thee. [Exit, covering her face with the cloak. Cyprian. Listen, hear me, stay, Justina! But why linger spell-bound, stunned here? I'll pursue her, and this forest, Whither by my spells conducted She has flown, will be the leafy Theatre, the rude-constructed Bride-bed of the strangest bridal Heaven e'er witnessed. [Exit. Scene XII. Clarin. Stop: Renuncio Bride like this who smells of smoke Stronger than a blacksmith's furnace. But perhaps the incantation, Being so extremely sudden, Caught her leaning o'er the lye-tub, If not cooking tripe for supper. No. Thus cloaked and in a kitchen! That excuse won't do: another Let me try. (I have it now, For an honourable woman Never smells then any sweeter,) She with fright must have been flustered.— He has overtaken her now, And from that rude vale uncultured, Struggling in closed clasping arms, (For I think when lovers struggle, Open arms are not the weapon Even for the lustiest lover,) To this very spot they come: I will watch them under cover, For I wish for once to witness How young women are abducted. [Conceals himself. Scene XIII. Cyprian embracing the Figure of Justina, which he carries in his arms. Cyprian. Now, O beautiful Justina, In this sweet and secret covert, Where no beam of sun can enter, Nor the breeze of heaven blow roughly, Now the trophy of thy beauty Makes my magic toils triumphant, For here folding thee, no longer Have I need to fear disturbance. Fair Justina, thou hast cost me Even my soul. But in my judgment, Since the gain has been so glorious, Not so dear has been the purchase. Oh! unveil thyself, fair goddess, Not in clouds obscure and murky, Not in vapours hide the sun, Show its golden rays refulgent. [He draws aside the cloak and discovers a skeleton. But, O woe! what's this I see? Is it a cold corse, mute, pulseless, That within its arms expects me? Who, in one brief moment's compass, Could upon these faded features, Pallid, motionless, and shrunken, Have extinguished the bright beauties Of the blush-rose and the purple? The Skeleton. Cyprian, such are all the glories Of the world that you so covet. [The Skeleton disappears. Clarin rushes in frightened, and embraces Cyprian. Scene XIV. Clarin and Cyprian. Clarin. Fear, for any one who wants it, Wholesale or retail I'll furnish. Cyprian. Stay! funereal shadow, stay! Now for other ends I urge thee. Clarin. I am a funereal body:— Don't you see it by my bulk here? Cyprian. Ah! who are you? Clarin. Who I am, sir, Or am not, myself doth puzzle. Cyprian. Did you in the air's void spaces, Or earth's caverns yawning under, See an icy corse here vanish, See to dust and ashes turning All the freshness and the beauty That it promised in its coming? Clarin. Do you take me, sir, for one Of those pitiful poor lurkers Men call spies? Cyprian. What could it be? Clarin. And not be, in such a hurry. Cyprian. Let us seek it. Clarin. Let's not seek it. Cyprian. I must sift this matter further. Clarin. I would rather not. Scene XV. The Demon, Cyprian, and Clarin. Demon (aside). Just heavens, If my nature, in conjunction, Once possessed both grace and science, When 'mongst angels I was numbered, Grace alone is what I've lost, Science no. Then why unjustly, If 'tis so, deprive my science Of its proper power and function? Cyprian. Lucifer, wise master mine. Clarin. Pray don't call him: for he'll come here In another corse, I warrant. Demon. Speak, what would you? Cyprian. The annulling, The redemption of those pledges, At whose very thought I shudder. Clarin. As I don't redeem my pledges, I'll slip off here through the bushes. [Exit. Scene XVI. Cyprian and The Demon. Cyprian. Scarcely o'er earth's wounded bosom Had I the true spell-word uttered, When in the ensuing action, She, of all my dreams the subject, My adored, divine Justina. ... But why take the useless trouble, That to tell you know already? I embraced her, would unmuffle Her fair face, when (woe is me!) In her beauty I discovered A gaunt skeleton, a statue, A pale image, a sepulchral Show of death, which in these measured Words thus spoke (even yet I shudder), “Cyprian, such are all the glories Of the world that you so covet.”— To assert, that on thy magic As expressed by me, the burden Of the fault should lie, is vain, For I, point by point, so worked it, That of all its silent symbols There was not a line but somewhere Had its place, of all its spell-words Not one word that was not uttered. Then, 'tis plain thou hast deceived me, For though acting as instructed, I but found an empty phantom Where I sought a blissful substance. Demon. Cyprian, this defect from thee, Nor from me, in truth, resulted: Not from thee, because the magic Thou didst exercise with subtle Thought and skill; and not from me, For I could not teach thee further. From a higher cause, believe me, Came this injury thou hast suffered. But be not cast down: for I, Who in tranquil rest would lull thee, Will to thee unite Justina, By a different way and juster. Cyprian. That is not my intention now. For this strange event has struck me With such terror and confusion, That thy ways I do not covet. And since thou hast not complied with The conditions, the assumptions Of my love, I only ask thee, Now that from thy face I'm rushing, As the contract is annulled, That my bond thou shouldst return me. Demon. What I promised was to teach thee, By a course of secret study, How to draw to thee Justina By the potent power impulsive Of thy words: and since the wind Here Justina hath conducted, I have then fulfilled my contract, I have kept my plighted word then. Cyprian. What was offered to my love Was that I should surely pluck here The sweet fruit whose seeds my hope Had to these wild wastes entrusted. Demon. Cyprian, I was only bound Her to bring here. Cyprian. A mere shuffle: To my arms you swore to give her. Demon. In thy arms I saw her struggle. Cyprian. 'Twas a phantom. Demon. 'Twas a portent. Cyprian. Worked by whom? Demon. By one who worked it To protect her. Cyprian. Who was he? Demon (trembling). I don't wish the name to utter. Cyprian. I will turn my magic science 'Gainst thyself. By its compulsion Speak, inform me who he is. Demon. Well, a god who takes this trouble For Justina. Cyprian. What's one God, When of gods there's such a number? Demon. All their power in Him is centred. Cyprian. Then One only, sole and Sovereign, Must He be, whose single will Their united wills outworketh. Demon. I know nothing, I know nothing. Cyprian. I renounce then with my utmost Power the pact that I made with thee; What compelled Him (this I urge thee In that God's great name) to guard her? Demon (after having struggled ineffectually not to say it). To preserve her pure, unsullied. Cyprian. Then He is the sovereign goodness Since a wrong He will not suffer. But if she remained here hidden Say what loss would have resulted? Demon. Loss of honour, if the secret Leaked out to the gossiping vulgar. Cyprian. Then that God must be all sight, Since he could foresee these troubles. But, why could not thy enchantment Be as potent and consummate? Demon. Ah! His power is ampler, fuller. Cyprian. Then that God must be all hands, Since whate'er He wills He worketh. Tell me then who is that God, Whom to-day I have discovered The supreme of good to be, The Creator, the Annuller, The Omniscient, the All-seeing, Whom I've sought for years unnumbered? Demon. Him I know not. Cyprian. Speak, who is He? Demon. As I speak it, how I shudder! He—He is the God of the Christians. Cyprian. Say what moved Him to obstruct me In my wish? Demon. Her Christian faith. Cyprian. Does He guard so those who love Him? Demon. Yes; but now too late, too late, Dost thou hope to gain His succour, Since, in being my slave, thou canst not Claim the privilege of His subject. Cyprian. I thy slave? Demon. In my possession Is thy signature. Cyprian. I'll struggle To regain it from thee, since 'Twas conditional at the utmost. I don't doubt I will get it. Demon. How? Cyprian. In this way. [He draws his sword, strikes at The Demon, but cannot touch him. Demon. Although the lunges Of thy naked sword against me Are well aimed, thou hast not struck me, Fierce as were thy blows. And now, Even in more despair to plunge thee, I would have thee learn at last That the Devil is thy instructor. Cyprian. What do you say? Demon. That I am he. Cyprian. Oh! to hear thee how I shudder!— Demon. Not alone a slave art thou, But my slave; be that thy comfort. Cyprian. I the slave of the Devil! I Own a master so unworthy? Demon. Yes; for since thy soul thou gav'st me, Thenceforth it to me was subject. Cyprian. Is there then no gleam of hope, No appeal, no aid, no succour, By which I so great a crime Can blot out? Demon. No. Cyprian. Why doubt further? Let not this sharp sword rest idly In my hand, but swiftly cutting Through my breast, become the willing Instrument of mine own murder. But what say I? He who could Snatch Justina from thy clutches, Can He not, too, rescue me? Demon. No. By choice thou wert a culprit, And He does not favour crimes, Virtues only. Cyprian. If the summit Of all power He be, to pardon Is as easy as to punish. Demon. He rewardeth by His power, He chastiseth from His justice. Cyprian. One who yields He'll not chastise. I am one, since I am humbled. Demon. Thou art mine, my slave: no master Canst thou have but me. Cyprian. I trust not. Demon. How, when still in my possession Is that bond of thine, that bloody Scroll inscribed by thine own hand? Cyprian. He who is supreme and sovereign, And depends not on another, Will yet bear me through triumphant. Demon. In what way? Cyprian. He is all sight, And will see the fitting juncture. Demon. It I hold. Cyprian. He is all hands, And will burst my bonds asunder. Demon. Ere that comes I'll see thee dead: Thus my clasping arms shall crush thee. [They struggle together. Cyprian. Thou great God, the Christians' God, Oh, assist me in this struggle! Demon (flinging Cyprian from his arms). It is He who has saved thy life. Cyprian. More He'll do since I seek Him humbly. [Exeunt. Scene XVII. HALL IN THE PALACE OF THE GOVERNOR. The Governor, Fabius, and Soldiers. Governor. How then was the capture made? Fabius. In their church, as we suspected, We discovered them collected, Where before their God they prayed. With an armed guard I traced them To this secret sacred hall, Made them prisoners one and all, And in different prisons placed them. But, your patience not to tire, The chief point I may declare,— Captured is Justina fair, And Lysander her old sire. Governor. If for gold, a fair pretence, If for rank, you would not miss, Wherefore bring me news like this And not claim your recompense? Fabius. If you deign to value thus My poor service, you may pay it. Governor. How? Fabius. With great respect I say it, Florus free, and Lelius. Governor. Though I seemed austere and cold, Them chastising without pity To strike terror through the city, Yet if the whole truth were told, Then the cause were plain why they Have been prisoned a whole year. It is this, a father's fear Lelius would preserve this way. Florus was his rival, he Had a host of powerful friends, Each was jealous, and his ends Would attain whate'er might be. I was fearful a collision Would ensue if they should meet, So I thought it more discreet Not to come to a decision. So with this intent I sought Some pretext, Justina's face To expel from out this place, But I could discover nought. But since this event to-day, With her damaged character, Gives a right to banish her, Nay, to take her life away, Let them be released. No fear Need you have about their fate; Go, and Lelius liberate, Go, and Florus bring me here. Fabius. Myriad times I kiss thy feet For a favour so immense. [Exit. Scene XVIII. The Governor and Soldiers. Governor. And since now this fair pretence, This hypocritical deceit, In my power at last doth lie, Wherefore my revenge postpone For the sorrows I have known Through her fault? Yes, she shall die By the bloody headsman's hand. Bring her hither in my name, [To a Soldier. Let her punishment and shame Be a terror to the land. Let the palace she thought sweet But her scaffold scene present. [Exit the Soldier with others. Scene XIX. Fabius, Lelius, and Florus.—The Same. Fabius. Sir, the two for whom you sent Here are kneeling at your feet. Lelius. I, whose wish it is to be Welcomed as thy son this time, With no consciousness of crime Do not see a judge in thee, I an angry sire may see With a son's respectful fear And obedience. Florus. Being here, I infer that it must be (Though no guilt can I discern) Thy chastising hand to feel. See. Submissive here I kneel. Governor. Lelius, Florus, I was stern, Justly stern against ye two, For as judge or father I Could not unchastised pass by Your offence. But then I knew That in noble hearts the feeling Of resentment does not last, And as now the cause is past, I resolved, to both appealing, Friends to make of you once more. So to consecrate the tie Now embrace in amity. Lelius. I am glad that, as of yore, Florus is my friend to-day. Florus. That thou'rt mine this act may show. Here's my hand. Governor. This being so, You are free to go or stay:— When I tell you of the sad Fall of her you once admired, Nothing further is required. Scene XX. The Demon, a crowd of People.—The Same. Demon (within). Ware! beware! He's mad! he's mad! Governor. What is this? Lelius. I'll go and see. [He goes to the door, and after a pause returns. Governor. In this palace hall these cries, From what cause can they arise? Florus. Something serious it must be. Lelius. This confusion is occasioned (Hear a singular adventure), Sir, by Cyprian, who being absent Many days again has entered Asonante in e—e, which continues to the end. Antioch completely mad. Florus. It was doubtless the fine essence Of his mind that thus has brought him To this lamentable ending. People (within). Ware the madman! ware the madman! Scene XXI. Cyprian, half naked; People.—The Same. Cyprian. Never was I more collected; It is you yourselves are mad. Governor. Cyprian, what is all this ferment? Cyprian. Governor of Antioch, Viceroy of great Cæsar Decius, Florus, Lelius, my young friends, Whom I valued and respected, Proud nobility, great people, To my words be all attentive: I am Cyprian, I am he Once so studious, and so learnëd, I the wonder of the schools, Of the sciences the centre. What I gained from all my studies Was one doubt, a doubt that never Left my wildered mind a moment, Ever troubling and perplexing. I Justina saw, and seeing, To her charms my soul surrendered, And for soft voluptuous Venus Left the wise and learn'd Minerva. Baffled by Justina's virtue, I, pursuing though rejected, And from one extreme to another Passing on as passion led me, To my guest, who from the sea Found my feet a port of shelter, For Justina pledged my soul, Since at once he charmed my senses And my intellect, by giving Love its hopes, and thought its treasures. From that hour, as his disciple Lived I in these lonely deserts, And to his laborious teaching I am for a power indebted, By which I can move even mountains And in different places set them: Yet although these mighty wonders I can do to-day, I'm helpless By the voice of my desire To draw towards me one fair vestal. And the cause why I am powerless To subdue that beauteous virgin Is that by a God she's guarded, Whom, now knowing by His blesséd Grace bestowed, I come to acknowledge As the Infinite, the Eternal. Yes, the great God of the Christians I now openly confess here. And though true it is I am Still of hell the slave and servant, Having with my very blood Signed a certain secret cedule, Yet my blood that blood may blot out In the martyrdom I'm expecting. If you are a judge, if Christians You pursue with bloody vengeance, I am one: for in these mountains A grave venerable elder The first sacrament conferring With its sacred sign impressed me. This being so, why wait? Your orders Give unto the bloody headsman, Tell him here to strike this neck And from it my head dissever. Try my firmness as you will, For I, resolute and determined, Will endure a thousand deaths Since this truth at last I've learnéd, That without the great God, whom Now I seek, adore, and reverence, Human glories are but ashes, Dust, smoke, wind, delusive, empty. [He falls as if in a swoon, with his face to the ground. Governor. So absorbed, so lost in wonder, Cyprian, has thy daring left me, That considering modes of torture I have yet not one selected. Rise. Bestir thee. [Spurns him with his foot. Florus. As a statue Formed of ice he lies extended. Scene XXII. Soldiers, Justina.—The Same. A Soldier. Here, your Highness, is Justina. Governor (aside). I must go; her face unnerves me.— With this living corse here lying Let us leave her for the present. [Aside to his retinue. For the two being here confined, It may alter their intentions, Seeing that they are condemned Both to die: if not, 'tis certain, That unless they adore our gods Frightful torments soon shall end them. Lelius (aside). I remain, 'twixt love and fear Quite bewildered and suspended. Florus (aside). So affected have I been, I scarce know what most affects me. [Exeunt all, except Justina. Scene XXIII. Justina; Cyprian, insensible on the ground. Justina. What! without a word you leave me? When I come here, calm, contented, Even to die. Ah! wishing death, Am I then of death prevented?— [She perceives Cyprian. But my punishment is, doubtless, Thus locked up to face the terrors Of a slow and lingering death, With the body of this wretch here Left alone, my sole companion Being a corse. O thou, re-entered Into thy original earth, Happy wert thou, if thy sentence Was passed on thee for the faith I adore! Cyprian (recovering consciousness). O proud avenger Of your gods, why wait, the thread Of my life to cut? ... [He perceives Justina, and rises. Heaven bless me!— Can I trust my eyes? Justina! [Aside. Justina (aside). Cyprian, do I see? O Heaven! Cyprian (aside). No, it is not she, my thought Fills the void air with her presence. Justina (aside). No, it is not he, the wind Forms this phantom to divert me. Cyprian. Shadow of my fantasy ... Justina. Of my wish, delusive spectre ... Cyprian. Terror of my startled senses ... Justina. Horror of my heart's dejection ... Cyprian. What, then, wouldst thou? Justina. What, then, wouldst thou? Cyprian. I invoked thee not. What errand Hast thou come on? Justina. Why thus seek me? I to thee no thought directed. Cyprian. Ah! I sought thee not, Justina. Justina. Nor here at thy call I entered. Cyprian. Then, why here? Justina. I am a prisoner.— Thou? Cyprian. I, too, have been arrested. But, Justina, say what crime Could thy virtue have effected? Justina. It is not for any crime, It is from their deep resentment, Their abhorrence of Christ's faith, Whom I as my God confess here. Cyprian. Thou dost owe Him that, Justina, For thy God was thy defender, He watched o'er thee in His goodness. Get my prayers to Him accepted. Justina. Pray with faith, and He will listen. Cyprian. Then with that I will address Him. Though a fear, that's not despair, Makes me for my great sins tremble. Justina. Oh! have confidence. Cyprian. My crimes are So immense. Justina. But more immense are His great mercies. Cyprian. Then, will He Pardon have on me? Justina. 'Tis certain. Cyprian. How, if I my soul surrendered To the Demon's self, as purchase Of thy beauty? Justina. Oh, there are not Stars as many in the heavens, Sands as many on the shore, Sparks within the fire as many, Motes as many in the beam, On the winds so many feathers, As the sins He can forgive. Cyprian. I believe it, and am ready Now a thousand lives to give Him.— But I hear some people enter. Scene XXIV. Fabius, leading in Moscon, Clarin, and Livia, as prisoners; Cyprian and Justina. Fabius. With your master and your mistress Here remain confined together. [Exit. Livia. If they fancy to be Christians, What have we done to offend them? Moscon. Much: 'tis crime enough for us That we happen to be servants. Clarin. Flying peril in the mountain, I find here a greater peril. Scene XXV. A Servant.—The Same. Servant. The Lord Governor Aurelius Summons Cyprian to his presence, And Justina. Justina. Ah! how happy, If 'tis for the wished-for ending. Do not, Cyprian, be disheartened. Cyprian. Faith, zeal, courage, all possess me: For if life must be the ransom Of my slavery to the devil, He who gave his soul for thee, Will he not give God his person? Justina. I once said that I could love thee But in death, and since together, Cyprian, we now must die, What I promised I present thee. [They are led out by the Servant. Scene XXVI. Moscon, Livia, and Clarin. Moscon. How contentedly to die They go forth. Livia. Much more contented Are we three to remain alive. Clarin. Not much more; for we must settle Our account now, though I own The occasion might be better, And the place too, still 'twere wrong To neglect the time that's present. Moscon. What account pray? Clarin. I have been Absent ... Livia. Speak. Clarin. The whole of a twelvemonth, When without my intermission Moscon in possession held thee. Now my quota in the business, If we both have equal measure, Is that I must have my year. Livia. Can it be that I'm suspected Of thus wronging thee so basely? Why, I wept whole days together When it was the day for weeping. Moscon. Yes, for I myself was present: Every day that was not mine She thy friendship quite respected. Clarin. That's a bounce; for not a tear, When this day her house I entered, Did she shed, and there I found thee Sitting with her quite contented. Livia. But this day is not a fast. Clarin. Yes, it is; for I remember That the day I went away Was my day. Livia. Oh! that's an error. Moscon. Yes, I see how that arises, This year is a year bissextile, And our days are now the same. Clarin. Well, I'm satisfied, 'tis better That a man should not too deeply Pry into such things.—Good heavens!— [The sound of a great tempest is heard. Scene XXVII. The Governor, a crowd of People; then Fabius, Lelius, and Florus, all astonished; afterwards The Demon. Livia. Sure the house is tumbling down. Moscon. How terrific! what a tempest! Governor. Doubtless in disastrous ruin Topple down the walls of heaven. [The tempest is renewed, and enter Fabius, Lelius, and Florus. Fabius. Scarcely on the public scaffold Had the headsman's hand dissevered Cyprian and Justina's necks, When the earth, even to its centre, Seemed to tremble. Lelius. And a cloud, From whose burning womb extended The wild lightnings, the loud thunders, Awful embryos were projected, Fell upon us. Florus. From which issued A most horrid, most repelling Shape, who on the scaly shells Of a mailed and mighty serpent, O'er the scaffold made a sign Motioning silence and attention. [The Scene opens, and a scaffold with the heads and bodies of Justina and Cyprian is seen. Over it in the air, upon a winged serpent, is The Demon. Demon. Hear, O mortals, hear what I, By the orders of high Heaven, For Justina's exculpation, Must declare to all here present. I it was, who to dishonour Her pure fame, in form dissembled For the purpose, scaled her house, And her very chamber entered. And in order that her fame Should not by that fraud be lessened, I come here her injured honour To exhibit pure and perfect. Cyprian, who with her lieth On a happy bier at rest there, Was my slave. But he effacing, With the blood his neck outsheddeth, The red signature, the linen Is now spotless and unblemished. And the two, in spite of me, Having to the spheres ascended Of the sacred throne of God, Live there in a world far better.— This, then, is the truth, which I Tell, because God makes me tell it, Much against my will, my practice Not being great as a truth-teller. [He falls swiftly, and sinks into the earth. Livia. Oh! what horror! Florus. What confusion! Livia. What a prodigy! Moscon. What terror! Governor. These are all but the enchantments Which this sorcerer effected At his death. Florus. I am in doubt To believe them or reject them. Lelius. The mere thought of them confounds me. Clarin. If magician, it is certain, As I hold, he must have been The magician then of heaven. Moscon. Leaving our partitioned love In a rather odd dilemma, For The Wonderful Magician Ask the pardon of its errors.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">A Voice. What is the glory far above, All else that life can give? Chorus of Various Voices. Love, love. A Voice. No creature lives on which love's flame Has not impressed its burning seal, The man feels more who love doth feel Than when Love's breath first warmed his frame. Love owns one universal claim,— To Love, it only needs To Be,— Whether a bird, a flower, a tree: Then the chief glory, far above All else in life must be ... Chorus (within). Love, love.</field>
   </doc>
</add>