<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Murphy, Arthur, 1727-1805</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Murphy, Arthur, 1727-1805</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">murphy arthur 1727 1805</field>
      <field name="author_text">Murphy, Arthur, 1727-1805</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1810's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V2.0570.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1811</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460228</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Hamlet</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Hamlet</field>
      <field name="title_facet">hamlet</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">hamlet</field>
      <field name="title_text">Hamlet</field>
      <field name="year_display">1811</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1811</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1811</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460228&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460228&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Murphy, Arthur, 1727-1805&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;murphy arthur 1727 1805&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Hamlet&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;hamlet&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1811&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1811&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Murphy, Arthur&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1727&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1805&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Hamlet&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed For J. Faulder ... By John Nichols [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1811&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872550-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv20570&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Hamlet&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 48 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Only verse drama included&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Hamlet.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Burlesque.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1772.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Unknown.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">HAMLET, WITH ALTERATIONS; A TRAGEDY, IN THREE ACTS.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DATED DECEMBER 15, 1772.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Parce pias scelerare manus— Virg.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Ennium (sicut sacros vetustate Lucos) adoremus in quibus grandia &amp; antiqua robora jam non tantam habent speciem, quantam religionem. Quint. lib. x. cap. 1.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DRAMATIS PERSONÆ. Mr. Garrick. George; his Brother, and Assistant Manager. Mr. Becket; his Bookseller. Mr. Hopkins; Prompter. Mr. Johnson; Property-man.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. Scene—Drury Lane Play-house. [Johnson on the Stage, with a lanthorn in his hand:] Hopkins. Who's there? Johnson. Nay, answer me; stand and unfold Yourself. Hopkins. Long live the King of Drury! Johnson. Hopkins? Hopkins. He. Johnson. You come most punctually:—how is your gout? Hopkins. I hobble, as you see; get thee to bed; 'Tis now struck twelve; farewell, Johnson:—good night. Johnson. For this relief, I thank you—Here's a quid To chew upon your watch. 'Tis bitter cold, And I am craw-sick.— Hopkins. Has the stage to-night been quiet? Johnson. Yes: as quiet as I've known it; Not a mouse stirring. Hopkins. Well, good night, my friend. But hark, a word; are all the places let For the next night of Hamlet? Johnson. How should I Resolve your question? 'Tis the Manager Settles that matter: it is he that lets The boxes for those nights; it makes our King Of greater pith and moment. Lords and ladies All send their cards to him; he plays those parts, Not for the public, but his private friends. Hopkins. Johnson, that's right: our Monarch is so great, It now befits him to select his audience. Johnson. But this must not transpire: 'tis ours, you know, Still to deceive the town, and make 'em think The boxes are with equity disposed. Hopkins. Well, well, good night. If in your way you meet Becket and George, The rivals of my watch, bid 'em make haste. Johnson. I think, I hear them.—Stand, ho! Who's there? Enter George and Becket. George. Friends to this house. Becket. And true to Drury's Monarch. Johnson. Give you good night. Becket. O, farewell, honest Johnson: Who hath reliev'd you? Johnson. Friend Hopkins has my place. Give you good night. [Exit Johnson. Becket. Holla! Hopkins! Hopkins. Say, What, is David there? George. A piece of him! Hopkins. I'm glad you're come, sir; Becket, you are welcome. Becket. What, has this thing appear'd again to-night? Hopkins. I have seen nothing. Becket. George says, 'tis but our phantasy, And will not let belief take hold of him, Touching this dreadful sight, twice seen of us: Therefore I have entreated him along, That, if again this apparition come, He may make affidavit of it to his brother. George. Tush! tush! 't will not appear. Becket. Patience awhile; And let us once again assail those ears That are so fortified against our story, With what we have two nights seen. George. Well, sit we down, And let us hear what Becket says of this. Becket. Last night of all, When yon same candle, that now dimly burns Upon a save-all, had so downward wrought As to rise up and sink on that same point, Where now 'tis off and on by fits, myself, And my friend Hopkins, both a little muddled, The bell then beating one— Hopkins. Peace, break thee off; [Enter Ghost.] Look, where it comes again! Becket. In the same figure, like to Shakespear's self Upon his monument— Hopkins. Speak to it, George. Thou 'rt an attorney. Becket. Looks it not like Shakespear? Mark it well, George. George. Most like:—go, call a Constable. Becket. It would be spoke to. Hopkins. Speak to it, good George. George. What art thou, that usurp'st this time of night, Together with that fair poetic form In which the majesty of buried Shakespear Did sometime march? Now in my brother's name I charge thee speak. Hopkins. It is offended. Becket. See! it stalks away. George. Stay; speak; I charge thee, speak; Or I will go and swear the peace against thee: Thou art no renter, and not free o' th' house. [Exit Ghost. Hopkins. 'Tis gone, and will not answer. Becket. How now, George? why you tremble, and look pale: Is not this something more than phantasy? What think you of it?— George. Before a Master in Chancery, Or Sir John Fielding, I might not this believe, Without the sensible and true avouch Of my own eyes. Becket. It's like immortal Shakespear. George. As thou art to St. Vitus' dance. 'Tis strange. Hopkins. Thus, twice before, and just at this dead hour, With dreadful stride hath he walk'd o'er the Stage. George. In what particular thought to work, I know not; But, in the gross and scope of mine opinion, This bodes some strange event to Harlequin, The Irish Widow, and the Pigmy Revels. Hopkins. Good now, sit down, and tell me, he that knows, Why this same strict and most observant watch Of our theatric state in daily papers? And why such constant vent of brazen lies, And epigrams as implements of scandal? Why such impress of scribblers, whose sore task Doth scarce deserve the freedom of the house? Who is 't, that can inform me? Becket. That can I; At least the whisper goes so. Drury's King Was, as you know, by the Author of Alzuma, Thereto prick'd on by a most emulate pride, Dar'd to the fight; in which our prudent Monarch (For so the green-room and the world esteem him) Declining open combat, most wisely chooses, By covert stratagem to annoy his foe. George. But, soft; behold! lo, where it comes again! I'll cross it, though it blast me.—Stay, illusion! If thou hast any sound, or use of voice, Speak to me: If there be any good play to be acted, That may give ease to thee, or coin to David, Speak to me: If thou art privy to what Foote's about, Which, happily, foreknowing may avoid, O, speak! Or, if thou hast uphoarded in thy life Some hidden manuscript, some virgin play, Which you, dread sprite, would wish to have perform'd, O, speak!—But stay;—my brother is in bed, And sleeps, if anxious thought will let him sleep. Hopkins. I am the prompter: shall I give the word? George. Do, if it will but stand. Becket. 'Tis here. George. 'Tis here. Hopkins. 'Tis gone. [Exit Ghost. Perhaps to Covent Garden. George. I'll engage it. It cannot eat,—'t will want no salary;— The Managers will like the Ghost of Wit. Becket. It was about to speak when the cat mew'd. Hopkins. And then it started, like a mouse from cheese, Upon a fearful summons. I have heard, The cock, that is the trumpet to the morn, Doth with his lofty and shrill-sounding throat Awake the god of day; and, at his warning, Whether in ale-house, punch-house, round-house, baguio, Th' extravagant and drunken poet hies To his confine; and the bum-bailiff comes, With prying look, to execute his writ; And then all day no bard dares stir abroad, And our glad Monarch's happy not to see A poet's face, unless it be his own Upon a painter's canvas well pourtray'd. Becket. So have I heard, and do in part believe it. George. But, see, the morn, with besom in her hand, Walks o'er the benches of yon Upper Gallery. Break we our watch up; and, by my advice, Let us impart what we have seen to-night Unto our Sov'reign. Hopkins. Be it so— Let's do 't, I pray; and I this evening know When we shall find him most conveniently; Ere the play ends at night, he will be here. 'Tis fit he know it; for, upon my life, This spirit, dumb to us, will speak to him. END OF THE FIRST ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. The same Scene continued. Enter Garrick and Johnson. Garrick. Well! The play's over, Johnson. Johnson. Sir, it is. Garrick. What for to-morrow night did they give out? Johnson. The Fashionable Lover. Garrick. And they all Went off contented: did they not? Johnson. To me It seem'd so. Garrick. Ha!—that's well—and so they think The Fashionable Lover, which I once So cherish'd in my bosom, but now say Deals nought but sentiment; 'tis that they think We mean to act. Johnson. That is their present expectation, Sir. Garrick. Came any round to you for places? Johnson. None: There's not a single being wants a place. Garrick. If we had let them know that I play Hamlet To-morrow night, then the whole crowd had rush'd To you for places, urging loud demands; And then the friends to whom I've given my word, Had all been disappointed. When they see, At nine to-morrow, Hamlet is the play, With those fam'd alterations I have made, Servants will come in crowds: do you prepare The book, and fill it as this paper marks. Johnson. Your orders, Sir, Shall be with all attention due perform'd. [Exit Johnson. Garrick, solus. Though yet of Shakespear our great poet's name The memory be green, and that it us befitted To bear his Jubilee to Avon's banks; Yet so far hath discretion fought with nature, That we think now to alter all his plays. O, that that too, too solid house, which Foote Has in the Haymarket, would melt at once, Thaw, and resolve itself into a dew! Or that the Royal Pleasure had not fix'd A patent for the summer in his hands! Fie on 't! O fie!—Foote's an unweeded garden, That grows to seed; things rank, and gross in nature, Possess him merely. That it should come to this! But nine months giv'n to me! nay, not so much— Not nine!—So excellent an actor! and to him Hyperion to a Satyr. Heav'n and earth! Must I remember? why, the town hangs on me As if increase of appetite did grow By what it fed on.—Yet, eight little months! But thirty weeks—a play'r no more like me Than I to Hercules!—Most wicked speed, To post with such dexterity from me To him, and on this mountain leave to feed, To batten on that moor! to quit with scorn My Neck or Nothing for his Major Sturgeon! It is not, nor it cannot come to good, But break, my heart: for I must hold my tongue! Enter George, Hopkins, and Becket. George. Hail to you, brother! Garrick. George!—or I cannot see. George. The same, and your poor servant ever. Garrick. Hopkins! Hopkins. My good master! Garrick. I am very glad to see you; good even, Sir.— But what, in faith, doth make you out of bed? Hopkins. I came to hear what you will act to-morrow. Garrick. Hamlet, with Alterations.—I am glad To lose no drop of that immortal man. Shakespear—Methinks, I see my Shakespear. George. Where, My brother? Garrick. In my mind's eye, dear George. He was a man, take him for all in all, I shall not look upon his like again. George. I think I saw him yesternight. Garrick. Saw whom? George. Your favourite Shakespear. Garrick. My favourite Shakespear! George. Season your admiration for a while With an attentive ear; till I deliver, Upon the witness of these gentlemen, This marvel to you. Garrick. For Heav'n's love, let me hear. George. Two nights together had these gentlemen, Hopkins and Becket, both upon the watch, In the dead waste and middle of the night, Been thus encounter'd. The form of Shakespear Appears before them, and, with solemn march, Goes slow and stately by them: they, distill'd, As if with jalap, by the act of fear, Stand dumb and speak not to him. This to me In dreadful secrecy they did impart; And I with them, the third night, kept the watch: Where, as they had deliver'd, both in time And form of the thing, each word made true and good, The apparition comes: I've Shakespear seen Both in the Abbey, and that curious carving In mulberry, which dangled at your breast; These hands are not more like. Garrick. But where was this? George. Here, between trap and lamp, where we all watch'd. Garrick. Did you not speak to it? George. At length I did; But answer made it none: yet, once methought, It lifted up its head, and did address Itself to motion, like as it would speak: But, even then, the playhouse cock crew loud; And at the sound it shrunk in haste away, And vanish'd from our sight. Garrick. 'Tis very strange. Indeed, indeed, Sirs, but this troubles me. Hold you the watch to-night? Both. We do, good Sir. Garrick. What, look'd he frowningly? George. A count'nance more In sorrow than in anger. Garrick. Pale, or red? George. Nay, very pale. Garrick. And fix'd his eyes upon you? George. Most certainly. Garrick. A branch of mulberry bore he in his hand? Becket. He did; of which I'll take my Bible oath. Garrick. I would I had been there. George. It would have much amaz'd you. Garrick. 'Tis very like. Pray, stay'd it long? Becket. While one, with moderate haste, might fairly tell An hundred lies. Hopkins. Oh, longer; longer. George. Not when I saw it. Garrick. His collar, say, was it unbutton'd? George. It was, as I have seen it in the Abbey, Quite loose and open. Garrick. I'll watch to-night. Perchance 't will walk again. George. I'll enter bail for its appearance. Garrick. If it assume immortal Shakespear's person, I'll speak to it, though ev'ry trap-door gape, And bid me hold my peace. I pray you all, If you have hitherto conceal'd this sight, Let it be tenable in your silence still; And whatsoever shall befall to-night, Give it an understanding, but no tongue. You shall dine with me; so, all, fare ye well. Upon the stage here, 'twixt eleven and twelve, I'll visit you. All. Our duty to you, Sir. [Exeunt. Garrick. Your loves, as mine to you. Farewell. The Ghost of Shakespear seen! all is not well. There's something rotten in the state o' th' stage: Something offends him. Would the time were come! Till then sit still, my soul. His Plays will rise, Though ev'n my pen o'erwhelm them, to men's eyes. END OF THE SECOND ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. The same Scene continues. Enter Garrick, George, and Becket. Garrick. The air bites shrewdly; it is very cold. George. It is a nipping and an eager air. Garrick. What hour now? George. I think, it lacks of twelve. Becket. No; it has struck. George. I heard it not:—it then draws near the season Wherein the spirit held his wont to walk. [Fiddles are heard. What does this mean? Garrick. At the fam'd house that's kept by Weatherby, The rake-hells wake to night, and take their prouse; And, as they drain their draughts of rumbo down, Their volley'd oaths and fiddles thus bray out The triumph of their vices. George. Is it a custom? Garrick. You know it is: But, to my mind, It is a custom More honour'd in the breach than the observance. Enter Ghost. George. Look where it comes! Garrick. Ye ministers of Drury Lane defend us! Be thou a spirit of health, or poet damn'd, Bring with thee laurel-wreath, or catcalls shrill, Be thy intents wicked or charitable, Thou com'st in so theatrical a shape, That I will speak to thee. I'll call thee Shakespear, Warwickshire lad, sweet Willy-o!—O answer me: Let me not burst in ignorance! but tell me Why thus thy jubilee'd bones, deck'd out with ode, Have burst their cerements! why the sepulchre, Which thee at Stratford quietly inurn'd, Hath oped its ponderous and marble jaws, To cast thee up again? What may this mean, That thou, dead corse, again upon the stage Revisit'st thus the glimpses of the lamps, Making night hideous, and us fools of art So horribly to shake our dispositions With thoughts beyond the reaches of our souls? Say, why is this? wherefore? what should we do? George. It beckons you to go away with it, As if it some impartment did desire To you alone. Becket. Look, with what courteous action It waves you to a more removed ground: But do not go with it. George. No, by no means. Garrick. It will not speak; then I will follow it. George. Do not, dear brother. Garrick. Why, what should be the fear? It wants not a third night; and for my patent, What can it do to that? It is a parchment To which the Chancellor hath set the seal. It waves me forth again;—I'll follow it. George. What, if it tempt you tow'rd the thunder-box, Or to the summit of yon canvas clouds, That wave about their tatters like rag-fair, And there assume some other horrible form, Perhaps the shape of some departed play, And draw you into madness? Garrick. It waves me still—Go on, I'll follow thee. Becket. You shall not go— Garrick. Hold off your hands. George. Be rul'd; you shall not go. Garrick. My fate cries out, And makes each petty artery in this body As hard as is the flint that paves the streets. Still am I call'd.—Unhand me, gentlemen: By Heav'n, I'll low'r the pay of him that lets me. I say, away:—Go on,—I'll follow thee. [Exit after the Ghost. George. He waxes desperate with imagination. Becket. Let's follow; 'tis not fit thus to obey him. George. Have after:—To what issue will this come? Becket. Nay, let's follow him. Scene,—another part of the Theatre. Enter Ghost, and Garrick. Garrick. Where wilt thou lead me? speak, I'll go no further. Ghost. Mark me. Garrick. I will. Ghost. The hour at length is come, When you, for your late insult to my name, Must render an account. Garrick. Oh! cruel Ghost! Ghost. Accuse me not, but lend thy serious hearing To what I shall unfold. Garrick. Speak, I am bound to hear. Ghost. So art thou to atone what thou shalt hear. Garrick. What? Ghost. I am Shakespear's Ghost, For my foul sins, done in my days of nature, Doom'd for a certain term to leave my works Obscure and uncorrected; to endure The ignorance of players; the barbarous hand Of Gothic editors; the ponderous weight Of leaden commentator; fast confin'd In critic fires, till errors, not my own, Are done away, and sorely I the while Wish'd I had blotted for myself before: But that I am forbid to tell the pangs, Which Genius feels from ev'ry blockhead's pen, I could a tale unfold, whose lightest word Would make that idiot-laughter keep the cheeks Of ev'ry scribler; thaw thy frozen blood, And bid a puny whipster's pen, like thine, Deal out thy paragraphs and crude conceits In Morning Chronicles, till ev'ry name Should be begrim'd, and black as Barry's face, When he, my best Othello, walks the stage. But this effect of malice must not be To ears of modern scriblers. List, list, O list! If thou didst ever the fam'd Shakespear love— Garrick. O Heav'n! “my little loves like bees Cluster and climb about your knees!” Ghost. Revenge his foul and most unnatural murder. Garrick. Murder? Ghost. Murder most foul, as in the best it is; But this most foul, strange, and unnatural. Garrick. Haste me to know it; that I, with haste as great As Stratford's town-clerk at the Jubilee, May sweep to my revenge. Ghost. I find thee apt; And duller shouldst thou be than the flat lines That coldly creep in modern playwrights' page, Wouldst thou not stir in this. Now, Garrick, hear: 'Tis giv'n out, that in a barb'rous age Shakespear arose, and made th' unskilful stare At monstrous farces: so the ear of Europe Is by the forged process of a Frenchman Rankly abus'd. But know, ungrateful man! The serpent that did sting thy poet's fame Has made his fortune by him. O think what a sad falling-off was there! From me, whose name was of that dignity That it went hand in hand with time himself, My honour blooming fresh:—and to decline Upon a wretch, whose natural gifts were poor To those of mine! But public taste, the sport of fickle fashion, May sate itself in a celestial page, And prey on garbage. But, soft!—methinks, I scent the morning air;— Brief let me be:—My works have made your fortune; And Hamlet brought to you, the mere reciter, The organ of another's sense, more money, Than e'er it did to me, who wrought the tale. Yet on my scenes, by ages sanctified, In evil hour thy restless spirit stole, With juice of cursed nonsense in an inkhorn, And o'er my fair applauded page did pour A Manager's distilment, whose effect Holds such an enmity with wit of man, That each interpolating word of thine Annihilates the sense, and courses through The natural turns of fable and of thought; And, with a sudden stupor, it doth damp And chill, like sheets of water on a fire, The clear and glowing lines: so did it mine; And a most instant numbness crept about, Most blockhead-like, with vile and paltry phrase, All my smooth writings. Thus was I, ev'n by thy unhallow'd hand, Of both my grave-diggers at once dispatch'd, Cut off in the luxuriance of my wit, Unstudied, undigested, and bemawl'd: No critic ask'd,—but brought upon the stage With all your imperfections on my head! Garrick. O, horrible! O, horrible! most horrible! Ghost. If thou hast nature in thee, dare it not; Let not th' immortal page of Shakespear be A place for ev'ry puny whipster's trash. But, howsoever thou pursuest this act, Attempt no more, nor let your soul conceive Aught 'gainst my other plays; I leave thee now To the just vengeance critics will inflict, And to the thorns that in your bosom lodge, To goad and sting thee. Fare thee well at once! Yon window shews the morning to be near, And thy once glow-worm eyes, with age grown dim, Begin to pale their ineffectual fire. Reflect in time; farewell! remember me. [Exit Ghost. Garrick. Hold, hold my heart; And you, my sinews, though you are grown old, Yet bear me stiffly up.—Remember thee? Ay, thou fierce ghost! while memory holds a seat In this distracted globe. Remember thee? Yea, from the stock of plays i' th' Prompter's list, I'll wipe away all trivial modern bards, And thy remembrance all alone shall live Within the book and volume of my brain, Unmix'd with other matter than my own. 'Tis gone, and now I am myself again. My tables,—meet it is, I set it down, That, by the alteration of a play, I can demand a benefit from Lacy. I'm sure it's so, while I can act myself. George and Becket. within. Illo! ho, ho! Garrick. Illo! ho, ho! come, boy, come. Enter George and Becket. George. How is 't? what news? Becket. Good Sir, tell it— Garrick. No, you'll reveal it. George. Not I. Becket. Nor I. Garrick. How say you then? would heart of man once think it? But you'll be secret? Both. By Heav'n, we will! Garrick. There's ne'er an actor strutting on the stage That can do Shakespear justice, but myself. Becket. There needs no ghost, good Sir, come from the grave To tell us this. Garrick. Why right; you say right; And so, without more circumstance at all, Insert it in the St. James's Chronicle; And circulate it wide in ev'ry paper. I'll draw the paragraphs; and be it yours, My trusty Becket, in your own fair hand To copy all, and give it to the press. This Ghost is pleas'd with this my alteration, And now he bids me alter all his Plays. His plays are out of joint;—O cursed spite! That ever I was born to set them right! END OF THE TRAGEDY.</field>
   </doc>
</add>