<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Tate, Nahum, 1652-1715</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Tate, Nahum, 1652-1715</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">tate nahum 1652 1715</field>
      <field name="author_text">Tate, Nahum, 1652-1715</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">18th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1700's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V2.0185.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1707</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:459907</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Injur'd Love : or, The Cruel Husband ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Injur'd Love : or, The Cruel Husband ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="title_facet">injurd love or the cruel husband</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">injurd love or the cruel husband</field>
      <field name="title_text">Injur'd Love : or, The Cruel Husband ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="year_display">1707</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1707</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1707</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459907&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459907&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Tate, Nahum, 1652-1715&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;tate nahum 1652 1715&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Injur'd Love : or, The Cruel Husband ; A Tragedy&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;injurd love or, the cruel husband&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1707&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1707&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Tate, Nahum&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1652&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1715&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Injur'd Love : or, The Cruel Husband&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for Richard Wellington [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1707&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872239-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv20185&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 18th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;18th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Injur'd Love : or, The Cruel Husband&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 219 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Injur'd love.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1707.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Unknown.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Injur'd Love: OR, THE CRUEL HUSBAND. A TRAGEDY.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PROLOGUE. I've lookt and lookt and still the Coast is clear; I see not one Brach'ano Husband here. Then since in neither Pit, nor Box, nor Gallery, The cruel Character's all Sham and Raillery. Well! Grant our wicked Husband and wrong'd Wife Are Figures somewhat larger than the Life: Yet were our Females pleas'd to speak their Mind, I've shrew'd Suspicion, that we shou'd find Few Dames complain of Husbands over-kind. Tho' you who have not turn'd meer Brutes of Beaus, Like well-bred Deer are civil to your Does. When roving Fancy's wanton Freaks prevail, Like pamper'd Deer y'are apt to leap the Pale. Of such wild Bucks I have been told indeed, From James's Park and Covent-Garden Breed. But now we meet with Younkers from the City, Like You turn'd Libertines, the more's the pity, Wicked as You, and, Sirs, almost as witty. How diff'rent from their Dads the Course they run? Stock-jobbing Sire gets rich; the graceless Son, Writes Madrigals, games, whores, and is undone. Rare Reformation! to see Prentice-Prig Adjust the Cravat, and careen the Wig. Thus Vice and Vanity are Conqu'rors grown, Our Outworks first they gain'd, and now the Town. What Refuge then's for Virtue left? What Fort? You Virtuous Ladies, and a Pious Court. [To the Boxes. There English Principles their Posts maintain; There Morals, Piety, and Hymen reign. Therefore, for Interest now, if not for Shame, To the Pit. You'll tack about, and play the prudent Game, I see it in your Looks, you'll all reclaim. All did I say? hold, that's a bold Pretence, I mean all you that have a Grain of Sense: Tho' hair-brain'd Rakes slight Royal Reason's Rules, And Fools to th'End of th'Chapter will be Fools; You Wits the Sov'reign Summons will obey, And, First, to shew you're in a mending way, You'll often visit our Reforming Play.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Persons. Duke Brachiano, The cruel Husband, in Love with Vittoria. Francisco, Duke of Florence, Brother to Isabella. Montacelsi, Cardinal, his Kinsman. Giovanni, The young Prince, Son to Brach. Julio, A Count of broken Fortune. Antonio, His Follower. Gasparo, His Follower. Flamineo, Brother to Vittoria, the Court-Villain. Marcello, His Brother, an honest Soldier. Camillo, Husband to Vittoria. Isabella, The injur'd Wife. Cornelia, Her Mother. Vittoria, The Court-Mistress, Wife to Camillo. Zanche, A Moor, her Confident. Officers, &amp;c.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE, ROME.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. SCENE A Garden to Vittoria's Appartments. Enter Ludovico, Antonio, Gasparo. Lud. Banisht! Ant. It griev'd me much to hear the Sentence. Lud. Ha, ha!—O Democritus! thy Gods, That manage this mad World, Courtly Rewards And Punishments— This 'tis to have great Enemies. Gasp. You term those Enemies are Men of Princely Rank. Lud. Oh! I pray for 'em— The violent Thunder is ador'd by those Are dash'd in pieces by it. Ant. Come my Lord, Y'are justly doom'd; look but a little back Into your former Life; you have in three Years Ruin'd the noblest Earldoms— Gasp. Your Followers have swallow'd you like Mummy— Ant. One Citizen Is Lord of two fair Mannors Only for Caveaire. Gasp. Those Noblemen, Who were invited to your prodigal Feasts (Wherein the Phœnix scarce cou'd 'scape your Throats) Laugh at your Misery— Ant. Jest upon you; And say you were begotten in an Earthquake, You have ruin'd such fair Lordships. Lud. Very good, This Well goes with two Buckets; I must tend The pouring out of either. Gasp. Worse than this; You have acted certain Murders here in Rome, Bloody and full of Horror! Lud. So, I wonder then some of your great Men escape This Banishment. There's Paulo Giordiano, Ursini The Duke of Brachiano, now in Rome, By Rev'ling Visits seek to prostitute The Honour of Vittoria on pretence To raise her ruin'd Family, and make Her Husband a great Man. Gasp. Judge Charitably; 'tis generous in Him. Lud. Generous? Ant. Come, bear a Manly Patience. Lud. I'le make Italian cut Works in their Skinns, If ever I return. Gasp. O Sir! Lud. I am Patient—Patient!— I've seen some ready to be Executed Give pleasant Looks, and Money to their Hangman. Ant. Fare you well my Lord; We shall find time I doubt not, to get Your Banishment Repeal'd. Lud. I am ever bound to you: This is the Worlds Alms (pray make use of it.) Great Men sell Sheep thus to be cut in pieces, When first they have shorn 'em bare and sold their Fleeces. [Exeunt. Enter Brachiano, Flamineo, Vittoria; (Flamin. with a dark Lanthorn.) Bra. The best of Rest t'ye. Vitt. To my Lord Brachiano The best of Welcome: More Lights attend the Duke. Bra. Flamineo! Fla. My Lord. Bra. Quite lost Flamineo! Fla. Pursue your Noble Wishes, I am prompt As Lightning to your Service: O my Lord, This fair Vittoria here, my happy Sister, Shall give you present Audience: Gentlemen, Let the Chariot go on: It is his Highness Pleasure You put out all the Lights, and so depart. Bra. Are we so Happy? Fla. 'T can't be otherwise, I've dealt already with her Waiting Woman, Zanche the Moor, and she is wondrous proud, To be the Agent for so high a Spirit. Bra. But still her Jealous Husband— Fla. Her Jealous Husband, hang him— Shroud you within this Banquetting House good my Lord. Some Trick must now be thought on to divide This Brother-in Law, from his fair Bedfellow. Bra. O should she fail to come— [Enter Camillo. Fla. I must not have your Lordship thus desponding, Away, away my Lord, see here he comes; this Fellow, By his Apparel and Movement, Some Men would judge a Politician. —How now Brother; travelling to Bed to your kind Wife? Cam. I assure you Brother, No my Voyage lies More Northerly in a far colder Clime. Cam. The Duke, your Master Visits me—I thank him. Fla. I hope you do not think— Cam. I have observ'd him. Fla. Will you be an Ass, Spight of your Aristotle? Or a Cuckold Contrary to your Ephemerides? Cam. Pew, mew, Sir tell not me Of Planets, nor Ephemerides; A Man may be made a Cuckold in the Day-time, When the Stars Eyes are out. Fla. Sir, Fare you well; I do Commit you to your pittiful Pillow Stufft with Horn Shaveings. Cam. Brother— Fla. Hope refuse me, Might I advise you now, your only Course Were to lock up your Wife. Cam. 'Twere very good. Fla. And so shall you be certain in one Fortnight Despight of Chastity or Innocence to be Cuckolded, Which yet is in Suspence. Cam. Come Sir, you know not where my Night-Cap wrings me. Fla. What you are Jealous then? See she comes—What reason have you to be Enter Vittoria. Jealous of this Creature—Be wise I'le make you Friends, and you shall to Bed together: Marry Look you, it shall not be of your seeking, do you stand Upon that by any means—Walk a loof; I would Not have you be seen in it—Sister, my Lord attends you in the Banquetting House— [Aside to Vitt. Your Husband is wondrous Discontented. [Aloud. Vitt. I did nothing to displease him. Fla. I must now seemingly fall out with you, [Aside. And shall a Gentleman so well Descended as [Aloud Camillo—a Paltry Slave, that within these [Aside. Two years rode with the Duke's Carriages. Cam. Now he begins to tickle her. Fla. An excellent Scholar— Cam. He'll make her know what's in me. Fla. Come, my Lord attends; thou shalt to my Lord. Cam. Now he comes to't. Fla. With a Relish as Curious as a Vintner going to Turning to Camillo. Tast new Wine: I am opening your case Hard. Cam. A virtuous Brother-in-Law on my Credit! Fla. Thou shalt lie on a Bed stuff't with Turtles Feathers, swoon in Perfumes, stifled in Roses—shall meet him, 'tis fixt. Vitt. Yes I will meet him, but for other Ends [Aside. Than their vile Purposes. Fla. I have almost wrought her to't, I find her Coming— But might I advise you now, for this Night I would not Lodge with Her—I would cross her Humour, to make her more humble. Cam. Shall I, shall I? Fla. It will shew in you Supremacy of Judgment. Cam. True; a Mind elevated above the tumultuary Opinion. Fla. Right; you are the Adamant shall draw her to you, tho' you keep at Distance. Cam. A Philosophical Reason! Fla. Walk by her Negligently, of the Quality fashion; and tell her you will visit her at the end of the Progress. Cam. Vittoria—I cannot be induced, or, as a Man would say, incited, Vitt. To what Sir? Cam. To sleep with you to Night— Fla. But d'ye hear—I shall have you steal to her for all this about Midnight. Cam. Think you so? Why look you Brother, because you shall find me stick to my Authority, take my Keys, look me fast into my Chamber, and so you shall be sure of me. Fla. In troth and so I will: I'le be your Goaler for once. But have you ne'er a false Door? Cam. tell me to Morrow how scurvily she takes my unkind parting. Fla. I will? Cam. I will use these tricks often; Fla. Do, Do, Do, Do. So now you are safe, Ha, ha, ha. Come Sister, Darkness hides your Blushes; my Lord, my Lord, [Enter Brachiano. Bra. Believe me I could wish time would stand still, And never end this Interview— Let me into your Bosom, dearest Charmer, Pour out instead of Eloquence, my Passion? Loose me not Madam, for if you forgoe Me, I'me lost indeed. Vitt. Sir in way of Charity I wish you at Heart's ease. Bra. You are a sweet Physician. Vitt. Sure deadly Cruelties in Ladies, Are as to Doctors many Funerals; It takes away their Credit. Bra. Excellent Creature, We call the Cruel, Fair; what Name for you, That are so Merciful? Zan. See now they Close. Fla. I apprehend you; When Principals engage, 'tis scandalous For Seconds to be Idle. Vitt. You call'd me your Physician, and I make This Visit to prescribe your Grief a Cure; A certain speedy Cure. Bra. That's double Charity. Vitt. 'Tis Resolutely at once to quench and stifle This hopeless Passion. Bra. That's too rough a Method, And suits not with my Constitution. These Minutes are too Precious— Vitt. Sir, I know their Value, And shall improve 'em to our mutual Benefit; 'Twas that I purpos'd in this Interview, We now are wander'd to the brink of Ruin, And must turn short, or perish. Bra. Where's the Danger? Vitt. It was my Lot To be high born and bred, and then reduc'd To fortune's Ebb, and (to compleat my Woes) Made Hymen's Martyr, Wedded to Aversion; Yet still the Name of Husband's Venerable; My Vow was Sacred, and let Hope forsake me When first— Bra. Hold; 'twas no Match, And I pronounce it void; unnatural Contracts Dissolve themselves. [Enter Cornelia observing them at a Distance. Vitt. Yours was at least Religious; You have a Princess, Sir, the Pride of Nature, And Paradise of Vertues; worth your Prizing If Monarch of the World; and Sir, this Charmer, Your Lover, and almost your Worshipper. Cor. My fears are fall'n upon me! Oh my Heart, My Son, their Pandar? Vitt. Beware my Lord! Orphans and Widows cries, Defrauded Labour's starving Sighs are loud; But none, to draw down Vengeance from Above, No! None like the Complaints of injur'd Love. Bra. You have both said and answer'd, call'd her Wife And Mine. Vitt. So are your Dukedoms, Sir—I own these Beauties Mean as my Fortune, yet above the Purchase Of Crowns and Scepters; brighter too than they, While deck't with Innocence—That Jewel lost The Mountain Nymph, that dresses at a Fountain Her inn'cent Head with Daisies, wou'd out-shine me Blazing with Diamonds. [Cornelia comes near to 'em. Bra. Consent, and who shall dare to call't a Crime? Vitt. Were Censure aw'd, what Troops can you Command, What Guards to silence the Accuser here? The rev'ling gaudy Scene in time will change, Furies succeed the flatt'ring Cupid's fled, And howling Horrour haunt the guilty Bed. Bra. Phantoms and Dreams! Awake and find your self Lodg'd in his powerful Arms, that can protect you From all the Fevers of a Jealous Husband, From the poor envy of our Phlegmatick Dutchess; I'le seat you above Law, and above Scandal: Give to your Thoughts Invention of Delights, And the Fruition: Nor shall Affairs of State Divide me longer from you, than due Care To keep you great; you shall to me at once Be Dukedom, Health, Wife, Children, Friends and all. Corn. Wo to light Hearts, they still fore-run our Fall. Fla. Ha! What fury rais'd thee up? Away, away. Corn. What makes you here my Lord, at this dead time of Night? Never dropt Mildew on Flow'r here, till now. Fla. I pray will you to Bed then, least you be Blasted. Corn. O that this fair Garden Had with all poisned Herbs of Thessaly At first been Planted, made a Nursery For Witchcraft, rather than a Burial Plat For both your Honours. Vitt. Dearest Mother hear me. Corn. O thou dost make my Brow bend down to Earth, Sooner than Nature— Where is thy Dutchess now Adulterous Duke? Thou little dream'st shee's come this Night to Rome. Fla. Ha! Come to Rome. Vitt. The Dutchess! Bra. Sh'ad been better— Cor. The Lives of Princes should like Dials move, Whose Regular Example is so strong, They make the Times by them go right or wrong. Fla. So—have you done? Cor. Unfortunate Camillo? Vitt. Yet, Madam hear me— [Kneeling. Cor. I will joyn with thee To the most woful end e'er Mother kneel'd; If thou dishonour once thy Husband's Bed, Be thy Life short; as are the Funeral Tears Of Great Men's Heirs. Bra. She Raves, the old Lady's Distracted. Fla. This 'tis for ancient Folks to keep ill Hours. Cor. Be your Love's every Kiss a Scorpion; May'st thou be envy'd, during his short Breath, To be the more despis'd when he is dead. Vitt. Mistaken Zeal, but 'tis a Parent's Care, And Duty bids me wait for her Conviction; Tho' mists of Errour Innocence may shroud, Truth and the Sun shine brighter from a Cloud. [Ex. Vitt. [Manent Flam. Cornel. Fla. Are you out of your Wits? My Lord I'le fetch her back again. Bra. No, I'le to Bed— Send Doctor Julio to me instantly, The Poysoning Doctor Julio. Uncharitable Woman, thy rash Tongue Has rais'd a dreadful and prodigious Storm, Be thou the cause of all ensuing Harm. [Ex. Bra. Fla. Now, you that stand so much upon your Honour, Is this a fitting time of Night think you To send a Duke home without Attendance? I would fain know where lies the Mass of Wealth Which you have hoarded for my Maintenance, That I may bear my State above the Level Of my Lord's Stirrup. Cor. What; because we're poor, Must we be vicious? Fla. Pray what Means have you, To keep me from the Gallies, or the Gallows? My Father prov'd himself a Gentleman, Sold all his Lands, and like a fort'nate Father dy'd Before the Money was spent—You brought me up At Padua, I confess; Thence to the Duke's Service, I visited the Court—And shall I, Having a Path so open and so free To my Preferment, still retain your Milk In my pale Forehead? Cor. O that I ne'er had born thee! Fla. So would I; I wou'd the common'st Courtezan in Rome, Had been my Mother, rather than thy self: Nature is very pitiful to Whores, In giving them few Children, And those few Plurality of Fathers; They are sure they shall not want—go, go, Complain to my great Lord Cardinal, It may be he will justify the Act. Cor. Misery of Miseries! [Exit. Fla. The Dutchess come to Town; I like not that; I am engag'd in Mischief, and must go on. [Exit. SCENE III. Enter Duke Francisco de Medicis, Cardinal Monticelsi, Marcello, Isabella, with young Giovanni. Fra. Have you not seen your Husband since your Arrival? Isa. Not yet, Sir. Fra. Surely he's wondrous kind. If he had such a Dove-house as Camillo's, I would set fire to't, were't but to destroy Such Poul-Cats as Brachiano,—my sweet Cosin— Gio. Uncle, you promis'd me a Horse, And Armour. Fra. That I did my pretty Cuz: Marcello, see it fitted. Mar. My Lord, the Duke Brachiano's here. Fra. Sister retire, you must not be seen by him yet. Isa. I do beseech you to entreat him mildly, Lest your rough Tongue Set us at greater Variance; all my Wrongs Are freely pardon'd: and I make no doubt By Gentleness to win him back, And keep him ever mine. Fra. I wish it may. Withdraw. [Exit Isab. with Giov. and Flam. [Enter Brachiano. Guards and Attendants go out. Clear the Presence— You are welcome: Will you sit?—I pray, my Lord, Be you my Orator, my Heart's too full, I'll second you anon, Mont. Ere I begin, Let me intreat your Grace forego all Passion, Which may be raised by my free Discourse. Bra. As silent as in the Church you may proceed. Mont. It is a Wonder to your noble Friends, That you having nobly entred on the World With a free Scepter in your able hand, And have to Gifts of Nature, well apply'd, Rare Parts and Learning; should, in your prime Age, Neglect your awful Throne, for the soft Downe Of an unsatiate Bed—Oh, my Lord! When you awake from the lascivious Dream, Repentance then will follow, like a Sting Plac'd in the Adder's Stern. Bra. You have said, my Lord? Mont. Enough to give you Tast How far I am from flattering your Greatness. Bra. Now, you that are his Second; What say you? Do not, like young Hawks, fetch a Course about, Your Game flies fair. Fra. Do not fear it; He answers you in your own hawking Phrase: Some Eagles that should soar against the Sun Seldom mount high, but take their lustful Ease, Since they from Dunghil Birds their Prey can seize. You know Vittoria. Bra. Yes— Mont. Her Husband's Lord of a poor Fortune, Yet she wears Cloth of Tissue. Bra. What of that? Will you urge this, my good Lord Cardinal, At the next Shrift, as part of her Confession? Fra. She's your— Bra. Uncivil, Sir: there's Hemlock in your Breath. And that black Slander, were she my Mistress, All your loud Cannons, and your borrow'd Switzers, Your Gallies, nor your sworn Confederates, Durst not supplant her. Fra. You have a Wife our Sister, wou'd I had given Both her white Hands to Death bound and lockt fast In her last winding Sheet, when I gave thee but one. Bra. Spit thy Poison. Fra. I shall not need, Vice carries her sharp Whip at her own Girdle— Look to't, our Anger's making Thunderbolts. Bra. Thunder they are but Crackers. Fra. We'll end it with the Cannon. Bra. Thou'lt get nothing by't, but Iron in thy Wounds, And Gunpowder in thy Nostrils. Fra. Better that Than change Perfumes for Plaisters. Bra. Pity on thee! 'Twere well you'd show your Slaves, or Men condemn'd, Your new plow'd Forehead—Defiance: I'll meet thee Even in a Thicket of thy ablest Men. Mon. My Lord, you shall not word it any farther, Without a milder Limit. Fra. Willingly. Bra. Have you proclaim'd a Trumpet, that you bait A Lion thus? Mont. My Lord— Bra. I am tame, I am tame, Sir. Fra. We send to the Duke for Conference 'Bout Levies gainst the Pyrates, my Lord Duke Is not at home—We come our self in Person, Still my Lord Duke is busy—but we fear When Tyler to each proling Passenger Discovers Flocks of wild Ducks, then my Lord (In Moulting time I mean) we shall be certain To find you safe laid up, and speak with you. Bra. Ha! [Enter Giovanni. Mon. No more, my Lord, Here comes a Champion, Shall end the Difference, between you both, Your Son the Prince Giovanni—See, my Lords, What Hopes you have in him? This is a Casket For both your Crowns, and should be held as dear. Bra. Your Hand, Boy; growing to a Soldier? Giov. Give me a Pike. Fra. What, practising your Arms so young? Giov. Suppose me one of Homer's Frogs, my Lord, Tossing my Bulrush thus; pray, Sir, tell me, Might not a Child of good Discretion, Be Leader to an Army? Fra. Yes, Cosin, a young Prince of good Discretion may. Giov. Say you so: If I live to be a General, I'll charge all the Foe my self, i'th' very Front Of all my Troops the foremost Man. Bra. Forward Lapwing! He flies with Shell on's Head. Fra. Pretty Cosin! Giov. The first Year, Uncle, that I go to War, All Prisoners that I take, I'll set free Without their Ransom. Fra. How then will you reward your Soldiers That took those Prisoners for you? Giov. Thus, my Lord: I'll marry 'em to all the wealthy Widows That fall that Year. Fra. Why then the next Year following You'll have no Men go with you to the War. Giov. Why then I'll press the Women to the War, And then the Men will follow. Mont. Witty Prince! Fra. See a good Habit makes a Child a Man, Whilst a bad Habit makes a Man a Beast. Come, you and I are Friends. Bra. Most willingly. Fra. You have receiv'd the Rumour how Count Ludovico is turn'd Pyrate. Bra. Yes. Fra. We are now preparing Some Ships to fetch him in.—But, Sir, Your Dutchess waits you, and we expect from you Nothing but kind Treatment of her. [Francisco, Montacelsi, go to the Table again. Bra. You have charm'd me. Mar. Camillo's come, my Lord. Enter Cam. and Mar. Flam. from another side to Brach. Fra. Where's the Commission? Mar. 'Tis here, Sir. Fra. Give me the Signet. Fla. My Lord, did you mark their Whispering? [Enter Dr. Julio. I will compound a Medicine out of their two Heads Stronger than Garlick; deadlier than Stibium. Bar. O the Doctor! Fla. They are sending him to Naples, but I'll send him to Pluto. Bra. About the Murder— Fla. He will shoot you Pills into a Man's Guts, shall Make him have more Vent than a Cornet, or Lamprey; He will poison with a Kiss. Doct. Your Secretary is merry, my Lord. Fla. O thou cursed Antipathy to Nature! Let me imbrace thee Toad, and love thee Thou abominable Gargarism, that will fetch up Lungs, Lights, Heart, Liver and all by Scruples. Bra. No more. I must employ thee, honest Doctor; [To Julio. You must to Padua, and by the Way Use some of your Skill for us. Doct. Sir, I shall. Bra. But for Camillo— Fla. I shall take care of him. But for your Dutchess— Doct. I will make her sure. Bra. Small Mischiefs are by greater made secure. [Exit. Mont. Look you, Cosin, The good Marcello is chosen with you joint Commissioner, For relieving our Italian Coasts From Pyrates. Mar. I am much honour'd with it. Fra. Farewel, good Marcello; All the best Fortunes of a Soldier's Wish Bring you a ship-board. Cam. Were I not best, now I am turn'd Soldier, Ere that I leave my Wife, sell all she has, And then take leave of her. Mon. I expect good from you, Your Parting is so merry. Cam. Merry, my Lord, o'th' Captain's Humour right, I am resolved to be dead drunk to Night. Fla. Drunk dead, III promise you. [Aside. [Exeunt Marcello, Camillo, Flamineo. Fra. So 'twas well fitted; now shall we discern How his wish'd Absence will give violent way To Duke Brachiano's Passion. Mon. Why that was it; To what scorn'd purpose else should we make choice Of him for a Sea Captain; and besides, Count Lod'wick, who was rumour'd for a Pyrate, Is now in Padua. Fra. Is't true? Mont. Most certain, I have Letters from him which are suppliant To work his quick Repeal from Banishment: Fra. O 'tis well; we shall have need of him. Mont. It may be thought I am dishonourable To play thus with my Kinsman: but I answer, For my Revenge I'd stake a Brother's Life, That being wrong'd, durst not revenge himself. Fra. Come to observe this Sorceress. Mont. Sure he'll not leave her? Fra. There's small Pity in't; Like Misle-toe on sear'd Elmes, spent with Weather, Let him cleave to her, and both rot together. [Exeunt. End of the first Act.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. SCENE I. A Grotto, Isabella leaning over a Fountain, Brachiano enters with a surly Deportment, she makes him a low Reverence, and moving forward a second or third time. Bra. You are in health, I see. Isa. And above health to see my Lord well. Bra. So: I wonder much What amourous Whirlwind hurry'd you to Rome? Isa. Devotion, my Lord. Bra. Devotion! Is your Soul charg'd with any grievous Sin? Isa. 'Tis burthen'd with too many, I think: The oftner that we make up our Accounts, Our Sleeps will be the sounder. Bra. Take your Chamber. Isa. Nay, my dear Lord, I must not have you angry— Does not my Absence from you two whole Months, Merit one Smile? Bra. I smile upon no Females. If that will dispossess your Jealousy, I'll swear it too. Isa. O my dear Lord, I do not come to chide. My Jealousy! alas, I am to learn What that Italian means. You are as welcome to these longing Arms [Offers to embrace him. As I to yours a Virgin. Bra. O your Breath! Out upon Sweet-meats and continual Physick. [Flings her off. Isa. You have for these neglected Cassia, And early Sweets of the Spring Violet; They are not yet much wither'd— My Lord, you should be gentle now; these Frowns Shew in a Helmet lovely; but not on me— [Weeps. Bra. O Crocodile! Isa. Had I, who am the Sufferer, Been the Offender, this submissive Posture Might plead a Pardon and prevail— Behold, my Lord, upon her humble Knees Your injur'd Wife suing for Reconcilement! Return to me, and to your self return; Shake off this sullen Cloud and shine again The dazling Wonder of the World; return, If not to me, to Fame, Content, and Quiet. Bra. Content and Quiet! 'twas for that I left My haunted House, and see! the Goblin follows me. I cry ye mercy; you are Flesh and Blood, Your Business, Assignation with some Gallant, That must supply our Discontinuance. Isa. Support me Love! this is a stunning Blow, To stagger Duty, and make Patience start! I pray, Sir, break my Heart, and in my Death Turn to your former Pity, tho' not Love. Bra. Or was't your Politicks? for you have learnt To bandy, faction with me and complain To your Kindred. Isa. Never, my dear Lord: So far from such Remonstrance of my Wrongs, That, Oh! I strive to hide 'em from my self, And chide my Memory when it turns Informer. Bra. Because your Brother Is the Great Duke, that is, the Corpulent Duke of Florence. 'Twas he first made this Match; Accurst the Priest That sung the Wedding Mass, and for my Issue— Isa. O too too far you have Curst— Bra. Your Hand I'le kiss. This is the last Ceremony of my Love, Henceforth I'le never Bed with you; be this my Witness, This Wedding Ring; I'le ne'er more sleep with you— And this Divorce shall be as duly kept, As if the Judge had doom'd it; Fare you well, Our Sleeps are sever'd. Isa. Forbid it the sweet Union Of all things Sacred; why the listning Stars [A Noise under Ground. Will start at this! The Stars! Earth groan'd to hear it. Is it firm Ground we tread— Or the Convulsion here— [Laying her Hand at her Breasts. Bra. Let not thy Love Make thee an Unbeliever, this my Vow Shall never on my Life be disannull'd By Recantation, let thy Brother Rage Beyond a Lapland Tempest, or Sea Fight, My Vow is fix'd. Isa. O my Winding Sheet! For I shall need thee shortly; dear my Lord, Let me hear once more, what I wou'd not hear; never? Bra. Never. [Lightning and Thunder. Isa. Nay then 'twas more than Fancy, Earth did groan, And answer'd now with Vengeance from above. O my unkind Lord, may you for this find Mercy, As I upon my woful Widdow'd Bed Shall pray for you; that you wou'd turn your Eyes, If not upon your wretched Wife and Son, Yet that in time you'd fix 'em upon Heaven; In time, before the gracious Season's o'er, And Mercy's Gate shall never open more. Bra. Ha! Isa. Our Sacred Band dissolv'd, methinks we look Like the Transgressing Pair from Eden chas'd, A dreadful Vow fix'd, like the flaming Sword, High brandisht and divorcing our Return; But here's the Disproportion, Exil'd Eve Fled with her Consort; I condemn'd Forlorn, To wander a wide World of Woe alone! Bra. Go, Go, Complain to the great Duke your Brother, And now's your time, He's sailing down the Walk With his loud Mouth'd Church-Second; Go, ply him With a Broad Side; he has Bulk to bear it. Isa. No my dear Lord, you shall have present Proof, How I'le work Peace between you—I will make My self the Author of your cruel Vow; I have some Cause to do it, you have none! Bra. Her self the Author, that's no ill Conitrvance. Isa. Conceal it I beseech you for the weale Of both your Kingdoms, how 'twas you that wrought This Separation, let the Fault and Blame Remain with my imagin'd Jealousie. Bra. Well, take your Course. Isa. To make you Friends, I will to Shades Retire, (Like an unmatched Turtle there to Mourn) For your Repose I weigh not the World's Censure, The World and I have done—yet I cou'd wish At this last Scene, a crowded Theatre To gazing Statues with Attention charm'd, Till rouz'd with more than personated Moans, [Enter Francisco and Montacelsi. They rung my Plaudit with a peal of Groans. Bra. My Honourable Brother, Fra. Honour'd indeed, if on fair terms permitted To hold your Friendship—Ha? Why Sister! Is this well? Sister—My Lord—she merits not this Welcome. Bra. Welcome said ye? She's given me a sharp Welcome. Mont. How pass'd the Interview betwixt you? Was Your Husband loud? Fra. What e'er he was, she's Dumb. Isa. What's that Dumb! A Woman Dumb? And under Provocation—Go Sir, And preach this Passive Nonsence to your Slaves, Try how the Charm will work—This is hard Penance [Aside. To Insult my kindest Friend, and more than Brother. Are all these Ruines of my former Beauties, [To Bra. Laid out on a Whore's Triumph? Fra. Do you hear, Look upon other Women, with what Patience They suffer these slight Wrongs. Isa. Tell me of Precedents? Let Politicians, Poets, Pedants, Physicians, Petty-foggers, follow Precedents; I'm an Original. Fra. Not worth the Copying. Isa. O that I were a Man, or now had Power To execute my Wishes, I wou'd whip some with Scorpions. Mont. What! turn'd Fury? Isa. Hold; I'le publish a Decree, That Ladies look well to their Hearts—Marriage is A Lottery! Ten Blanks to a Prize; the Bride will turn to Wife, Queen for a Day, and Slave for all her Life. Bra. What can you make of this? Mont. I know not, Mystery or Madness. Isa. If you'll bind me down to Presidents, Your Modern are too mean—Let me have Musick, Banquets and Revels, all the pomp of Pleasure, T'out-shine Semiramis and Cleopatra— Fra. Witchcraft and Sorcery! Isa. I pray Sir tell me, [Aside to Bra. How like you my Performances? Bra. Admirable, and like a topping Actress. Isa. The Part's new, And never to be play'd again. Mont. Distraction! Phrensy! Isa. Sir, by your reverend Leave, Church-men shou'd never be Censorious; Phrensy? You shall have Proofs I am in sober Sadness— Brother draw near, and you my Lord Cardinal— Sir, let me borrow of you but one Kiss, [To Bra. Aside. Henceforth I'le never Bed with you; be this my Witness, This Wedding Ring. Fra. How? Isa. And this Divorce shall be as duly kept, As if in throng'd Court thousand Ears had heard, And thousand Lawyers seal'd the Separation. Bra. Never more Bed with me! Isa. Let not my former Dotage, Make thee an Unbeliever, this my Vow Shall never be Repeal'd by Recantation. Bra. Support me Love, this is a stunning Blow! Who waits there fetch the Prince, Come Sir for pitty's sake—And you, my Lord, [To Francisco to Mont. Your Word shou'd carry Authority. Fra. I've done—Enjoy your Rashness, keep your Vow, And take your Chamber. Isa. No Sir, I'le instantly to Padua. Mont. To Bedlam. Fra. The only Cure is to Indulge her Humour. Bra. You see 'tis none of my seeking! [Enter Giovanni. Fra. To have her come To my Lord Cardinal to beg a Dispensation Of her rash Vow! O 'twill breed excellent Laughter! Bra. O Isabella my perpetual Bride! What must our Loves before our Life divide? Had I, who am the Sufferer, been the Offender What cou'd I more? See on his bended Knee, The injur'd Husband sues for Reconcilement! Gio. Speak Madam, why d'ye Weep? [Isabella looks by Turns upon her Husband and Child, then Swoons with Passion. I've seen you Weep before; but these are angry Tears: If I'm in fault, I come to ask Forgiveness; Chide me, but tenderly, as you were wont to do, And so be Friends again! Bra. Help, Help all! But all I fear too late! My Isabella, will you, can you leave me? Like an unmatched Turtle to retire And pine in Shades? Isa. That was my dear Lord's Voice, and sounded kind, Where is my Love—Ah! flattering Vision! So slumbring Prisoners of a Pardon Dream, And wake to Execution! Off! Unhand me; I was your Bond-slave; but the Contract's cancel'd: Now free as Air, and wilder than the Wind. Ha! My poor Boy! O 'tis too much to bear! [Aside. Bra. That's well retriev'd. Isa. Have you not heard how Cloud compelling Jove, With hizzing Bolts the rattling Tempest drove; But Juno, when she did a Rival see, Lighten'd and thunder'd twice as loud as He? Bra. Rare Counterfeit, how it makes my politick Engins stare, Ha, ha! Isa. So the Gulph's shot; the raving Feaver spent, And I grow sick at Heart! Now for the parting Pang, one dear last Look; And yet another last—Down stubborn Woe, Break suffering Heart, in silent Sorrow break: Those are the killing Griefs that dare not speak. [Exit with Giov. Bra. You see, my Lord, 'tis possible For ablest Politicians to mistake; I was th'Aggressor. Fra. Well, Sir, we beg your Pardon, if in Fault. Mont. And, Sir, be you advis'd how dangerous 'tis To insult too soon. [Officers of the Inquisition Court appear. Fra. O, you are welcome: Is your Court summon'd? Off. All in Readiness, the Prisoner's brought to th'Bar. Mont. Vittoria apprehended? Off. In Custody, my Lord. Bra. Ha! Pris'ners, Custody, Vittoria! The matter Lords? These Ravens never croak But Mischief's near. Mont. The Mischief's come already; Our drowzy Politicks have watcht, it seems, While yours was fast—Camillo our Commission'd Kinsman With other Captains met to pass the last Night In Sailors Merriment, and drinking Healths, To their boon Voyage—A long Night for him— He's dead. Bra. What's that to the Lady? Was she Commission'd too? Fra. Nor was your Flamineo, Yet he was present—If y'are disposed For further Information—you may grace The Tryal with your Presence. Bra. If 'twas Design, your swift Intelligence Carries a scurvy Face. Mont. Honest Marcello Sent instant notice for a Guard to come And seize the Company. [Ex. Franc. and Mont. Bra. The Riddle's out. Flamineo charg'd as Agent, and Vittoria As accessary—Be't as 'twill, Such over-speedy Justice is Injustice: I will make't my Precedent. With me th'endang'ring of a Mistress's Life, Is ample Warrant to dispatch a Wife. SCENE changes to a Court of Justice shew'd as sitting for Vittoria's Arraignment, six Lieger Ambassadors as Auditors. Enter Francisco, Montacelsi, with a Chancellor and Register. Fra. You have dealt discreetly to obtain the Presence Of all the Lords Ambassadors, to hear Vittoria's Tryal. Mont. 'Twas not ill: For, Sir, you know we have only Circumstances To charge her with, about her Husband's Death; Their Approbations therefore to the Proofs, Will put the better Face on our Proceedings, To all our Neighbouring States—Think you, Sir, That Brachiano will be here? Fra. O, Sir, 'twere Impudence too palpable. [Vittoria brought in guarded, Marcello, Flamineo, Zanche, and after them Brachiano enters. Mont. Forbear, my Lord, here is no Place assign'd you; This Business by the Conclave is left wholly To our Examination. Bra. May it thrive with you. Fra. A Chair there for his Grace. Bra. Forbear your Kindness: an unbidden Guest [Lays a rich Gown under him. Brings his own Seat. Mont. At your Pleasure, Sir. Stand to the Table, Lady—Now, Segnior, Fall to your Plea. Lawy. Domine, Judex, Converte Oculos— Vitt. What's He? Mont. A Lawyer that pleads against you. Vitt. Then let him speak his usual Tongue, I'll make no Answer else. Mont. Why, you understand Latin? Vitt. I do, Sir, but some o'th' Auditory Are ign'rant in't. I will not have my Accusation clouded With a strange Tongue—All this Assembly Shall know the worst that you can charge me with. Mont. Then since you force me to assume the Charge, I shall be plainer with you, and paint out Your Follies in more natural Red and White, Than that upon your Cheeks. Vitt. O you mistake: You raise a Blood more virtuous, on this Cheek, Than ever was your Mother's. Mont. I must spare you till Proof; Observe this Person here, my Honourable Lords, A Woman of a most prodigious Spirit— Vitt. My Honourable Lords, It does not suit a Reverend Cardinal To play the Lawyer thus. Mont. You see, my Lords, what goodly Fruit she seems, Yet I'll but touch her, and you strait shall see She'll fall to Soot and Ashes. Vitt. Your poisoning Apothecary should do that. Mont. Who knows not how, when several Nights together Her Gates were choakt with Coaches, and her Room Out-brav'd the Stars with sundry kinds of Lights, When she did counterfeit a Prince's Court With musical Banquets and most riotous Revels: This Curtezan— Vitt. Ha! What's that? Mont. Shall I expound it to you? What are Harlots? What are They?—They are first Sweet-meats that rot the Eater; in Man's Nostrils Poison'd Perfumes: They are couzening Alchymy: Shipwrecks in calmest Weather—What are Harlots? They are those flattering Bells have all one Tune For Weddings and for Funerals— Vitt. This Character 'scapes me. Mont. You Sorceress? who have extracted Into your own hot Veins, From venom'd Beasts and rankest Minerals, The deadliest Poison— Fr. Emb. She has liv'd sumptuously. Sp. Emb. True, but the Cardinal's too bitter. Mont. You know what's next the Devil; Adultry First enters, and then Murder. Fra. Your unhappy Husband Is dead. Vitt. O, he's a happy Husband! He now owes Nature nothing. Fra. And by a vaulting Engine, an active Plot, He jumpt into his Grave. Vit. What's this to Me? Mont. Now mark each Circumstance, And look upon this Creature was his Wife; She comes not like a Widow, she comes arm'd With Scorn and State. Is this a Mourning Habit? Vitt. Had I fore-known his Death, as you suggest, I'd have bespoke my Mourning. Mont. O, you are cunning. Vitt. You shame your Wit and Judgment To call that so, which is my just Defence. Let me appeal then from this Civil Court, To the uncivil Tartar. Mont. See, my Lords, she scandals Our Proceedings. Vitt. Humbly thus, Thus low to the most Worthy and Respected [Kneels. The Lords Embassadors; in Modesty (Our Sex's Badge) I bow; but am withal So intangl'd in a spightful Accusation, That my Defence of force, like Perseus, Must personate Masculine Virtue— [Rises. Find me but Guilty, sever Head and Body, We'll part good Friends—I scorn to hold my Life At your's, or any Man's Intreaty. E. Emb. She has a brave Spirit. Vitt. Terrifie Babes my Lords with painted Goblins; I'm past such childish Usage—for your Names Of Harlot, Whore and Murd'ress, they proceed from you, As if a Man should spit against the Wind, The filth returns in's Face. Mon. Pray satisfie the Court of one short Question, Who visited you on that fatal Night Your Husband's Neck was broke? Bra. That Question, touches me; I was there [Rising up. Mon. Your Business? Bra. I came to Comfort her, And take some course for setlling her Estate, Because I knew her Husband was in Debt, To you my Lord. Mon. Who made you Overseer? Bra. Charity, my Charity, which should flow From every Generous and Noble Spirit, To Orphans and to Widows. Mon. Charity! your Lust— Bra. Cowardly Dogs bark loudest; Reverend Sir, I shall talk with you hereafter—do you hear, The Sword you frame of such an excellent Temper, I'le sheath in your own Bowels. [Going out. Serv. My Lord your Gown— Bra. Thou Lyest; 'twas my Cushion; I scorn to take a Cushion Out of another's Lodging; let him make Vallance For's Bed on't, or a Demi-Foot-Cloth For his most reverend Mule—Montacelsi, Nemo me impune Lacessit [Ex Bra. Mon. your Champion's gone. Vitt. The Woolf may prey the better. Fra. My Lord there's strong suspicion of the Murder, But no sound Proof who did it: For my part I do not think she has a Soul so Black; Let pass the Charge of Blood, only descend To matter of Incontinence. Vitt. I discern Poyson, Under your guilded Pills. Mon. Now the Dukes gone, I will produce a Letter Wherein it was Plotted, I pray read it, I shame to speak the rest? Vitt. Grant I was Tempted, Temptation proves not Guilt. You read his hot Love to me, but you want My frosty Answer. Mon. Frost in Dog-days. Vitt. Sum up my Faults, I pray, and you shall find, That Beauty, and gay Cloaths, a chearful Heart, Are all the Crimes that you can charge me with. Mon. If a Fury, Did ever take fair shape behold it's Picture. Vitt. You have one Vertue left; you will not flatter me. Mon. My Lord Duke sent to you a thousand Duckets The twelfth of August. Vitt. 'Twas to keep my Husband your Cousin From Prison. Mon. And you paid Use for it. Vitt. Who says so but your Self? If you be my Accuser, Pray cease to be my Judge; come from the Bench. Mon. You were born in Venice, honourably Descended From the Vitteli, 'twas my Cousin's fate, (Ill may I name the Hour) to Marry you. Vitt. Ha? Mon. I yet but draw the Curtain; now to your Picture. You came from Venice with suspected Fame. Vitt. My Lord; Mon. Nay hear me, You shall have time to Talk—My Lord Brachiano's, Alas! I make but Repetition? Of what is common and Rialto Talk— You Gentlemen, Marcello and Flamineo, The Court has nothing now to charge you with, Only you must remain upon your Sureties, For your Appearance. Fra. I stand for Marcello, Fla. And my Lord Duke for me. Mon. For you Vittoria, your insolent Demeanour Joyn'd to the Circumstances of the Charge, Takes from you all the fruits of noble Pity, As you are judg'd an ominous Blazing Star To Princes, hear your Sentence, you're confin'd Unto a House of Converts; and your Minion: Fla. Who I? Mon. The Moor. Fla. O! I am a sound Man again. Vitt. A House of Converts! What's that? Mon. A House of Penitent Whores. Vitt. Do the Noblemen in Rome, Erect it for their Wives? Fra. You must have Patience. Vitt. I must first have Vengeance. Mon. Away with her; take her hence. Vitt. A Rape, a Rape— Mon. What? Vitt. Yes, you have ravish'd Justice, Forc'd her to do your Pleasure. Mon. O she's Distracted! Vitt. Dye with those Pills in your perfidious Breast, Should bring you Health, or while you sit o'th Bench, Let your own Venom choak you. Mon. She's turn'd Fury! Vitt. O Woman's poor Revenge, Which dwells but in the Tongue—I will not Weep, No; I do scorn to call up one poor Tear To fawn on your Injustice; bear me hence, Unto this House of—What's your mitigating Title? Mon. Of Converts. Vitt. It shall not be a House of Converts, My Mind shall make it honester to me, Than the Pope's Pallace; and more peaceable Than thy Soul, tho' thou art a Cardinal: Know this, and let it somewhat raise your Spight Through Darkness, Di'monds spread the richest Light. [Exit Vitt. guarded. The End of the Second Act.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. SCENE I. Enter Brachiano and a Magician. Bra. Now Sir I claim your Promise, 'tis dead Midnight, The time prefix't to shew me by your Art How the intended Murder of our Dutchess Proceeds to Action. Mag. Noble Sir, You've won me by your Bounty to a Deed, I do not care to Practise. Bra. Do you boggle? What is it you mistrust, your Skill or me? Mag. Neither; tho' some there are, I do confess, Who by Sophistick Tricks aspire the Name That I would gladly loose of Necromancer; But this is such a woful Scene, and you So principal an Actor, that I fear 'Twill strike you Sir with Horrour. Bra. Venture that— Mag. Then Sir sit down—Here in this Chair 'tis charm'd, I'll shew you now by my commanding Art The Circumstance that breaks your Dutchess's Heart. A Dumb Shew. Enter suspiciously Julio and Guiccardo; They draw a Curtain where Brachiano's Picture is; they put on Spectacles of Glass that cover their Eyes and Noses, then burn Perfumes before the Picture, and wash the Lips; then, quenching the Fire, and putting off their Spectacles, go out Laughing. Enter Isabella as from her Devotion, a Light afore her, Count Loduvico, Antonio, Giovanni and others waiting on her, she draws the Curtain of the Picture, and having Giovanni by the Hand, looks first on the one, then on the other; after paying Reverence, she kisses the Picture, immediately faints, and will not suffer them to come near it. Dies. Sorrow exprest in Giovanni, Lodovico, &amp;c. They carry her out Solemnly. Bra. Excellent! then she's Dead. Mag. Yes; Poyson'd By the sum'd Picture; 'twas her Custom Nightly Before she went to Bed, to come and visit Your Picture, and to feed her Eyes and Lips, On the lov'd shadow: Doctor Julio Observing this, infects it with an Oil, And other poyson'd Stuff, which instantly Did suffocate her Spirits. Bra. Methought I saw Count Lodwick there. Mag. He was, and though unknown to her, A passionate Admirer of the Dutchess. Bra. Most skilful Sir, you've bound me ever to you; And let this stand my pledge of farther Payment. [Ex. Bra. Mag. Yes! Dearly hast thou paid, And dearer yet shalt pay for injur'd Love, Wretched Brachiano!—Oh cou'dst thou foresee Thy own, as now, thy Dutchess Tragedy— But 'tis the Fate of Vice on shelves to run, And never see the Danger till undone. [Exit. SCENE II. Enter Flamineo. Flam. I've scap'd the Storm, but left Vittoria Stranded, and bound in Honour to get her off; but personal Safety is the first Point of Politicks. I must shift my Flag that's certain; but what Colours to put up, whether Merry, Melancholy or Mad, is the Question. The last has most Priviledges belonging: I'll counterfeit Distraction for the Disgrace of my Sister, 'twill keep of dangerous Questions. I will talk to any Man, answer no Man; and for a time be a politick Mad-man. [Exit. Enter Ludovico, Antonio, Gasparo. Ant. My Lord, we griev'd for your Departure; But more for your Return being so dangerous. 'Twas giv'n out here, you were turn'd Pyrat— Lud. I was engag'd in such an Expedition, But summon'd off by the politick Cardinal And Duke of Florence to some Land-Service, Some dry State-Mischief, and in such a Post, Where I'd serve Volunteer. Gasp. Against Brachiano. Lud. Driv'n by the double force of Love and Spight; Hatred to him, Love to his Murder'd Dutchess. Re-enter Flamineo. Fla. W' indure the stroaks of Fortune like hard Steel, Till Pain it self, makes us no Pain to feel. Who shall do me Right now? Is this the end of Service. Lud. What can this mean. Fla. O they have wrought their Purpose cunningly, As if they wou'd not seem to do't of Malice. Gasp. Yes, it will out at last I question not By Proofs most Manifest. Fla. Proofs—'Twas Corruption—Gold, what a Prince art thou! Man, what a Slave art thou—Knaves turn Informers, as Maggots turn to Flies: You may catch Gudgeons with either— A Cardinal? What is there so demure, but Money will Corrupt. Ant. Can this be Artifice. Fla. Savages are honest Folk; here they sell Justice by those Weights they press Men to Death withal. Gasp. Fie Flamineo. Fla. Bells never ring well, till they come to their full Pitch; and the Cardinal never speaks well, till he comes to the Scaffold. Ant. Ha! ha! ha! Fla. —Farewel—Let others live by Begging, it's none of am—dost hear me? Practise the Art of Carrion-Eaters, swallow all's giv'n thee: One Purge will make thee as Lank, as he that works in a Saw-Pit—I'le go hear the Screech-Owl. [Exit in a wild manner. Lud. This was Brachiano's Pandar, and 'tis strange That in such open and apparent Guilt Of his Adulterous Sister, he dares utter So scandalous a Passion—I must mind him. Re-enter Flamineo. Fla. How dares this Banish't Count return to Rome, His Pardon not yet purchas'd? I have heard. [Aside. The deceas'd Dutchess gave him Pension: And that he came along from Padua, I'th' Train of the young Prince—There's somewhat in't, Physicians that cure Poysons, still do work with Counter-Poysons. Mark this strange Encounter. Melancholy turn thy Gall to Poyson, And let the stigmatick Wrinkles in thy Face, Like to the boysterous Waves in a rough Tide, One still overtake another. Lud. I do thank thee; and I do wish ingeniously, For thy sake, the Dog-days all the year long. Fla. How croaks the Raven? Is our good Dutchess dead? Lud. Dead. Fla. O Fate! Misfortune comes like the Coroner's Business, Huddle upon Huddle. Lud. Shall thou and I joyn House-keeping? Fla. Yes, Content. Lett's be unsociably Sociable. Lud. Sit some three days together and Discourse— Fla. Only with making faces, Lye in our Cloaths. Lud. With Faggots for our Pillows— Fla. And be Lousie— Lud. In Taffata Linings; that's gentile Melancholy: Sleep all Day. Fla. Yes: And like your melancholy Hare, Feed after Midnight. Lud. We'l never part. Fla. Never, till the Beggary of Courtiers, The Discontent of Church-men, Want of Soldiers, Be taught in our two Lives, [Enter Antonio and Gaspara. To Scorn that World, which Life of means deprives. Ant. My Lord I bring good News: The Pope on's Death-bed, At the earnest Suit of the great Duke of Florence, Hath sign'd your Pardon, and restor'd unto you— Lud. I thank you for your News, look up again Flamineo, see my Pardon. Fla. Why do you Laugh? There was no such Condition in our Covenant. Lud. Why? Fla. You shall not seem a happier Man than I, You know our Vow Sir, if you will be Merry, Do't with a sabby Politician's Face. Lud. Your Sister is a damnable Whore. Fla. Ha? Lud. Look you, I spake that Laughing. Fla. Dost ever think to speak again. Lud. Do you hear? Wil't sell me forty Ounces of her Blood, To water a Mandrake. Fla. I do not greatly wonder you did break, Your Lordship learnt long since, but I'le tell you. Lud. What? Fla. And't shall stick by you. Lud. I long for it. Fla. This Laughter scurvily becomes your Face, [Strikes him. If you will not be melancholy be Angry. Mar. You're to blame, I'le force you hence. [Ex. Mar. and Fla. Lud. Unhand me, That e'er I should be forc'd to right my self Upon a Pandar! Ant. My Lord! Lud. H'had as good met with his Fist a Thunder-bolt. Gasp. How this shews? Lud. Misfortune, how did my Sword miss him? These Rogues that are most weary of their Lives, Still scape the greatest Dangers. But let him go, all his Reputation, Nay, all the Goodness of his Family, Is not worth half this Earthquake; I learnt it of no Fencer to shake thus: Come Sirs—the next turn's Mine. [Exeunt. SCENE III. Enter Brachiano at one Door, Francisco and Montacelsi at the contrary. Bra. Now you and I are Friends, Sir, we'll shake hands, In a Friend's Grave together; a fit Place, Being the Emblem of soft Peace, to atone our Hatred. Fra. Sir, what's the Matter? Bra. I will not chase more Blood from that lov'd Cheek: You have lost too much already—Fare you well. [Exit. Fra. How strange these Words sound! What's th'Interpretation? Fla. Good: This is a Preface to the Discovery of the Dutchess's Death; he carries it well—Because now I cannot counterfeit a whining Passion for the Death of my Lady, I will feign a mad Humour for the Disgrace of my Sister, and that will keep off idle Questions: I will talk to any Man, hear no Man, and for a time appear a Politick Madman. [Exit. Enter Giovanni in Mourning, Ludovico, Gasparo, Antonio, Attendants. Fra. How now my noble Cosin? What, in Black? Giov. Yes, Uncle; I was taught to imitate you In Virtue, and you must imitate me In Colour of your Garments; my sweet Mother Is— Fra. How! Where? Giov. Is there—no, yonder:—Indeed, Sir, I'll not tell you, For I shall make you weep. Fra. Is dead. Giov. Do not blame me now, I did not tell you so. Lud. She's dead, my Lord. Mont. Unhappy Lady! Thou art now above thy Woes. Wil't please your Lordships to withdraw a little. Giov. What do the Dead do, Uncle? Do they eat, Hear Musick, go a Hunting and be merry, As we that live? Fra. No, Cuz, they sleep. Giov. Sleep!—That I were dead then, I have not slept these six Nights—When do they awake? Fra. Sweet Innocence! Giov. Let her sleep ever, for I have known her wake a hundred Nights; When all the Pillow where she laid her Head, Was brine wet with her Tears—I am to complain to you, Sir. I'll tell you how they've us'd her now she's dead They wrapt her in a cruel Fold of Lead, And would not let me kiss her. Fra. Thou did'st love her. Giov. I've often heard her say she gave me suck, And it should seem by that she dearly lov'd me, Since Princes seldom do it. Fra. O All of my poor Sister that remains! Take him away for pity. Mon. How now, my Lord? Fra. Believe me, I am nothing but her Grave, And I shall keep her blessed Memory, Longer than thousand Epitaphs. Mont. Come, my Lord, now we are alone let me entreat you, Untie your folded Thoughts, and let them dangle loose, as a Bride's Hair. Your Sister's poison'd. Fra. Far be it from my Thoughts to seek Revenge. Mon. What, Are you turn'd all Marble? Fra. Shall I defy him, and impose a War Most burthensom on my poor Subjects Necks, Which at my Will I have not Power to end. Mon. That's not the Course I'de wish you; pray observe, We see that Undermining more prevails, Than doth the Cannon. Bear your Wrongs conceal'd, And patient as the Tortoise; let this Camel Stalk o'er your Back unbruis'd: Sleep with the Lion, And let this Brood of secure foolish Mice, Play with your Nostrils, till the time be ripe For th'bloody Audit, and the fatal Gripe. Fra. Free me, my Innocence, from treacherous Acts, I know there's Thunder yonder: and I'll stand, Like a safe Valley, which low bends the Knee To some aspiring Mountain: To pass away these Thoughts, my honour'd Lord, It is reported you possess a Book Wherein you have quoted, by Intelligence, The Names of all notorious Offenders, Lurking about the City. Mon. Sir, I do; and some there are, who call it my black Book. Fra. Pray let's see it. Mon. I will not trust thee, but in all my Plots, [Aside. I'll rest as jealous as a Town besieg'd; Thou canst not reach what I intend to act; Your Flax soon kindles, soon is out again, But Gold slow heats, and long will hot remain. 'Tis here, my Lord. [Presents a Book to Fran. Fra. First your Intelligencers, pray let's see, Their Number rises strangely. Mon. And some of them, You'd take for honest Men, the rest are Panders; These are your Pyrates; and these following Leaves For base Rogues, that undo young Gentlemen By taking up Commodities; for Politick Bankrupts, For Fellows that are Bawds to their own Wives. Fra. Are there such? Mon. These are impudent Bawds, That go in Man's Apparel; for Usurers That share with Scriv'ners for a good Report; For Lawyers that will antedate their Deeds; Here is a general Catalogue of Knaves: A Man might study all the Prisons o'er, Yet never attain this Knowledge. Fra. Murderers; fold down the Leaf I pray: Good my Lord, let me borrow this strange Doctrine, Mon. Pray use't my Lord. Fra. I do assure your Lordship, You are a worthy Member of the State, And have done vast good in your Discovery, Of these Offenders. Mon. Somewhat Sir. Fra. Better than Tribute of Wolves paid in England. 'Twill hang their Skins o'th Hedge. Mon. I must make bold, To leave your Lordship. [Exit Monticelso. Fra. Dear Sir I thank you. If any ask for me at Court, report, You have left me in the Company of Knaves. Now to the use I'll make of it, it shall serve To point me out a List of Murderers, Agents for any Villany. To fashion my Revenge more seriously, Let me remember my dead Sister's Face, Call for her Picture? No, I'll close my Eyes, And in a melancholy Thought I'll frame Her Figure for me. Now I hav't—how strong [Enter Ghost of Isabella. Imagination works! How she can frame Things which are not! Methinks she stands afore me, And by the quick Idea of my Mind, Were my skill Pregnant, I could draw her Picture; 'Tis my Melancholy. How cam'st thou by thy Death?—How idle am I, To question my own Idleness!—Did ever Man dream awake till now? Remove this Object Out of my Brain with't, what have I to do With Tombs and Death-bed's, Funerals or Tears, That have to meditate upon Revenge! So now 'tis ended, like an old Wife's Story: [Ghost sinks. Statesmen think often they see stranger Sights, Than Mad-men, come to this weighty Business; My Tragedy must have some idle Mirth in't, Else it will never pass. I am in Love, [Sits down thinks. In Love with Corombona; and my Suit Thus halts to her in Verse— [He Writes. I have done it rarely, O the Fate of Princes! I am so us'd to frequent Flattery my self; But it will serve, 'tis Seal'd; who waits bear this To'th House of Converts; and watch your Leisure, [Enter Serv. To give it to the hands of Corombona, Or to the Matron, when some Followers Of Brachiano may be by. Away, [Exit Servant. The Engine for my Business, bold Count Ludowick, 'Tis Gold must such an Instrument procure, With empty Fist no Man doth Falcon's Lure. Brachiano I am now fit for thy Encounter, Like gathering Thunder my Revenge seems slow, But fatal when it breaks, you'l find the Blow. [Ex. Francisco. SCENE IV. A Court-Yard before a Cloyster. Enter Matron of the Converts and Flamineo. Mat. Should it be known the Duke has such Recourse To your imprison'd Sister, I were like T'incur much Damage by it. Fla. Not a Scruple. The Pope is now expir'd, and their wise Heads, Are troubled now with Business of more Weight, Than guarding of Ladies. [Ent. a Servant. Serv. Yonder's Flamineo in Conference with the Matron. Let me speak with you— I would intreat you to deliver for me, This Letter to the fair Vittoria: Hereafter you shall know me, and receive Thanks for this Curtesy. [Exit. Fla. How now, what's that? Mat. A Letter. [Enter Brachiano. Fla. To my Sister! I'll see't deliver'd. Bra. What's that you read Flamineo? Fla. Look. Bra. Ha! To the most unfortunate his best respected Vittoria. Who was the Messenger? Fla. I know not. Bra. No? Who sent it? Fla. You speak as if a Man Should know what Fowl is coffin'd in a baked Meat, Before you cut it up. Bra. I'll open't, wer't his Heart—What's here Subscrib'd Florence, This Juggling is too gross and palpable. Read it. Fla. Your Fears I'll turn to Triumphs, be but Mine, Your Prop is fall'n, it grieves me that a Vine, Which Princes heretofore have wish'd to gather, Wanting Supporters, now shou'd fade and wither. Bra. Wine, Wine, with Lees would serve his turn. Fla. Your sad Imprisonment, I'll soon uncharm, And with a Princely unresisted Arm, Bear you to Florence, where my Love and Care, Shall hang your Wishes in my Silver Heir. Bra. A Halter on his damn'd Equivocation. Flo. Nor for my years return me the sad Willow, None prefer Blossoms before fruit that's Mellow. Bra. Rotten to my knowledge with lying too long 'ith Beadstraw. Fla. And all the Lines of Age, this Line Convinces, The God's never wax Old, no more do Princes. Bra. Tear it, let's ha'no more Atheism. I have a lucky and surprizing Thought To Counter-blast this undermining Mole, O're-reach this Politick Duke in his own Plot. Fla. As how my Lord? Bra. The self same Project, which the Duke of Florence Lays down for her Escape, will I Pursue. Fla. To steal Vittoria hence. Bra. Immediately. Fla. And no time fitter than this Night my Lord, The Pope being Dead, and all the Cardinals entred The Conclave for Electing a new Pope. The City in a great Confusion, We may attire her in a Page's Habit, And Post away for Padua. Bra. We lose Time. Instantly steal forth the Prince Giovanni, And straight for Padua—You two with the old Mother, And young Marcello that attends on Florence, [If you can work him to it] follow me. I will Advance you all—for you my dear Vittoria, Think of a Dutchess Title. Fla. This has a Spirit, And Wings us all like Lightning. [Exit. SCENE Continues. Enter Captain with Guards and a Courtier. Court. Here Captain is your Post, your Charge is great, So be your Care. Capt. Sir I shall do my Duty. Enter Francisco on the other side with Ludovico, Gasparo and Ant. He steps over to the Officer. Fran. So my Lord, I do commend your Diligence, Guard well the Conclave, and as the Order is, Let none have Conference with the Cardinals. [He comes back to Lud. Gasp. and Ant. Remember Gentlemen, you have all sworn To prosecute the Murder of Brachiano. Ant. We have Sir. Lud. Your bounty Sir will mind 'em of their Promise, They never fail'd at Mischief. And for me, Revenge will be your best Remembrancer. I was enamour'd on Brachiano's Dutchess, The virtuous Isabella, your fair Sister, Tho' she ne'er knew it—she was poison'd Sir, Upon my Life she was, for which I've Sworn Long since, to avenge her Murder on Brachiano. Enter Servant. Fra. Peace, here comes a Messenger; If hopes deceive me not, I guess his Errand. Well Sir, your Business. Serv. Vittoria my Lord— Fra. What of her? Serv. Is fled the City. Fra. Fled? Serv. With Duke Brachiano. Fra. Where's the Prince? Serv. Gone with his Father. Fra. Let the Matron of the Converts be Apprehended. Go signifie Our Orders, and see 'em executed— Exit Servant. How fortunate are my Wishes! Why 'twas this I labour'd for; 'twas I that sent the Letter, T'instruct him what to do, and point the way To Marry his own Whore. Gas. 'Twill blast his Fame, But renders our Attempt more difficult. Lud. Already my quick Thoughts suggest the way How to approach his Person unsuspected In his own Palace, and amidst his Guards. Fra. Most of his Court of my Faction. Lud. We but lose time, let's after him to Padua, Where like a cautious Statesman, I'll instruct you What your Commission is, when you arrive The Place of Action. Fra. I approve that Method. I only recommend Dispatch, and leave The rest to Fate and you. Ant. Depend upon't, Fra. Success attend your Enterprize. Gasp. We carry that along with us In our own firm Resolves. Fra. Farewel. [Exeunt. Court. Back there, clear the Way, Room for the Embassadors. [Embassadors enter to the Conclave.] Capt. They are wondrous brave to day, why do they wear These several Habits. Court. O Sir, they are Knights of the several Orders; That Lord 'ith' black Cloak with the Silver Cross, Is Knight of Rhodes: The next Knight of St. Michael, That of the Golden Fleece: The Frenchman there, Knight of the Sacred Order, my Lord of Savoy Knight of the Annuntiation; the Englishman Is Knight of the Honoured Garter. I could describe to you Their several Institutions, with their Laws Annexed to their Orders: But you see The Cardinals Service Marshall'd, and the Officer Appointed to inspect each Mess that's serv'd in. [Servants enter with several cover'd Dishes, an Officer Inspecting.] Off. Stand, let me search your Dish; Who's this for? Serv. For my Lord Cardinal Montacelsi. Off. Who's this? Serv. For my Lord Cardinal of Bourbon. Capt. Why does he search their Dishes? Court. To prevent foul Practice. Lest any Letters should be convey'd in To bribe or to sollicit the Advancement Of any Cardinal: When first they enter, 'Tis lawful for the Embassadors of Princes To enter with them, and to make their Suit For any Candidate their Prince affects. But after till a general Election, No man may speak with them. Capt. 'Tis orderly. Court. You that attend the Lords Cardinals, Open the Window and receive their Viands. [A Cardinal appears.] Card. You must return the Service, the Lords Cardinals are busy in electing a new Pope. They have giv'n over Scrutiny, and now are fall'n to Nomination. Court. I'll lay a thousand Duckets you hear News of of a Pope presently,—Hark! surely he's elected. Behold my Lord of Arragon appears On the Church Battlements. Arr. Annuntio vobis Gaudium, Reverendissimus Cardinalis Lozenzo de Montacelsi electus est, &amp; elegit sibi Nomen Quartum. [Flourish and Shouts. Montacelsi in State, follow'd by the Conclave. A Paper deliver'd to him.] Mont. Vittoria, my Lords, is fled the City: Stol'n from the House of Converts, by Brachiano. Now tho' this be the first Day of our Seat, We cannot do a more Religious Service Than by sequestring these two cursed Persons. Make therefore Publication of our Sentence Against them both: All that are theirs in Rome, We likewise banish: On, set on. [Exeunt. End of the Third Act.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT IV. SCENE I. Brachiano's Palace. Enter Flamineo and Marcello. Flamineo in a Masquerading Dress, a Vizard in his Hand. Fla. Brother, good welcome to us, welcome to Padua: In all the weary Minutes of our Life, Day ne'er broke out till now— This Marriage of our Sister with the Duke, Confirms us happy—Still that soure Camp Look! Consider you're at Court, Man—You intend To make one in the Masquerade to Night? Mar. I relish not these Fooleries of Court: Methinks a foppish mumming Dress and Vizard, As ill becomes a Soldier as a Priest. Fla. It worse becomes a Soldier to turn Cynick. Mar. O this unfortunate Sister! I wou'd my Dagger's Point had cleft her Heart, When first she saw Brachiano—You ['tis said] Were made his Engine and his stalking Horse To undo my Sister. Fla. I was a kind of Path To Her's and my own Preferment. Mar. To your Ruine. Fla. Hum! Thou art a Soldier: What has't got by't? Mar. Sir. Fla. Thou hast scarce Maintenance To keep thee in fresh Shammoyes. Mar. Brother. Fla. Hear me: Thou feed'st thy Master's Victories, As Witches do their serviceable Spirits, Even with thy prodigal Blood; Where's the Reward? Fame, Service to the Publick; a wise Reckoning! Can'st purchase Land with't?—come, when Age shall turn thee White as a blooming Hawthorn— Mar. I'll interrupt you. For love of Virtue, bear an honest Heart, And stride o'er ev'ry politick Respect, Which where they most advance, they most infect. Were I your Father, as I am your Brother, I should not be ambitious to leave you A better Patrimony. Fla. Well, I'll think on't. Enter Ludovico disguis'd like a Moor, Antonio and Gasparo in Capuchin's Habits, bearing their Swords and Helmets before 'em. Mar. More Mimickry? Fla. Why, that's the valiant Moore, A Man of your own Function. Mar. Mulinassar? Fla. The same newly Arriv'd. Mar. Have you confer'd with him? Fla. Yes in the Duke's Closet. Mar. I have not seen a goodlier Personage. Fla. Nor ever talk'd Man better experienc'd In State Affairs, or Rudiments of War: He has by Report serv'd the Venetian In Candy, these twice seven years, and been Chief In many a bold Design. Mar. What are these two that bear him Company? Fla. Two Noblemen of Hungary [that living in the Emperor's Service as Commanders eight Years, since contrary to the expectation of all the Court] enter'd into Religion in the strict Order of Capuchine's; but being not well settled in their Resolution, they left their Order, and return'd to Court; for which being afterwards troubled in Conscience, they vow'd their Service against Infidels, went to Malta, and were there Knighted, and in their return back, [at this great Solemnity] they resolve for ever to forsake the World, and settle themselves here in a House of Capuchines, in Padua. Mar. 'Tis strange. Fla. One thing makes it so; they have vow'd for ever to wear, next to their bare Bodies, those very Coats of Male they serv'd in. Mar. Hard Penance—The Moor's Business? Fla. To offer his Service to our Duke; Because he understands there's like to grow War betwixt us and the great Duke of Florence, In which he hopes Preferment. Florish, Enter in State Brachiano, Vittoria, with Guards and Train. Bra. You are nobly welcome, we have heard at full, Your Honourable Service 'gainst the Turk. To you brave Mulinassar we assign A compleat Pension, and are only sorry, The Vows of these two worthy Gentlemen, Make them incapable of our proffer'd Bounty: Your Wish is, you may leave your Warlike Sword, For Monuments in our Chappel; I accept it As a great Honour done me, and must crave Your leave to furnish out our Dutchess Revels Only one as the last Vanity, You e'er shall view, deny me not to stay To see a a Barriers perform'd to Night, You shall have private Standings. Lud. I shall perswade 'em. Bra. I formerly have known To touch a Lance, 'twas our Youth's Exercise, Our self will make one at these Turnaments: Set on then to the Presence. [Exit. Manent Conspirators, and Flamineo on the other side. Several Ladies Masqu'd, pass over the Stage. Fla. There goes the Covey, I must single out one before the Ball begins, 'Tis the right use of Masquerading. Exit. Lud. Ha, ha, ha! Thus far our Plot thrives well, A Barrier fought to Night to grace his Nuptials; He could not have invented his own Ruine, [Had he despair'd] with more Dexterity. Ant. As how my Lord? Lud. T'have poyson'd his Prayer-Book or Beads, Or Pummel of his Saddle, his Looking-Glass, Or handle of his Racket; had been Vulgar. I'll take him off in all his Pomp and Bravery: These Turnaments shall be his Obsequies; You have Implements of Death in readiness. Gasp. Ponyard or Poyson, for, like dext'rous Artists, We carry still our Instruments about us. Lud. Along with me, I'll set you soon to Work. [Exeunt. [As they go off, Zanche enters in a Vizard and Masquerade Dress.] Zanch. That Moor's my Country-man, a goodly Person, I will at leasure Discourse with him in our Language—What's here, Flamineo encountring with a Masque? That's well, The Lady slights him. [Flamineo returns, dragging in one of the Masque-Women, she breaks from him. Fla. Coyness in a Masque? Zan. I'll take advantage of the Accident, And this Disguise to try his Constancy. If he has flatter'd me, Revenge shall teach him, What 'tis to wrong the Moor. [Goes up to him. Despair not slighted Sir, ye're in a Court, Love's Market, Where all Wares goes off to one or other. Fla. I'me for the first kind Bidder. Zan. You are Flamineo. Fla. You are a Witch. Zan. I know you are Flamineo, I saw you unvizarded but now. Fla. You saw a worse Face then: 'Twas my ill Fortune. Zan. Neither your Face nor Fortune are to blame, This Accident may turn to your Advantage; Retire with me, and I'll instruct you. Fla. You'l find me an apt Scholar, my Apartment's Here i'th' Gallery, very private,—never Was Thief that had stol'n a rich Cabinet, So impatient to unease it. Zan. Soft Sir, you first must satisfie me about a small Scruple, Fla. What? Zan. Of Conscience. Fla. How Conscience in Vizard? Zan. 'Tis said you have been Carnal with a Moor. Fla. You mean Zanche? Zan. And are Enamour'd on her. Fla. That's Carbonado'd. Zan. You love the Infidel, have sworn it to her. Fla. I own I have made Love to the Moor, And I do Love her—just as a Man holds A Wolf by the Ears— Zan. And but for her turning upon you, and tearing your Throat. Fla. You are an Oracle. Zan. She's Conscious then, I guess, of some sweet Pranks of yours—It must be so— —Come be a kind Flatterer at least, and Make me believe your Protestations to her Were not the effect of Love, but Interest. Fla. What shall I swear by Friends, or Fury's? Or by that more Infernal Moor herself. Zan. Yet 'tis reported she claims Marriage of you. Fla. Why, I have made her such a dark Promise, and in seeking to fly from it, I run like a frighted Dog with a Bottle at his Tail. Zan. So. Fla. Not a word more of that Succubus, in presence of my Venus. Your Face must answer the Character, that Mien and Shape and Wit are Sureties for it. Zan. You'l swear that too. Fla. What should Beauty do in a Vail—unshroud my Cynthia, And bless me with your illustrious Face. Zan. To gratifie my dear Endymion. [Unmasques. Fla. A most illustrious Face indeed. Zan. Villain, perfideous Villain. Fla. Ha, ha, ha, my charming Daughter of Darkness, I think I have met with you for your Jealousy—Did not I act it rarely? Zan. You knew me then? Fla. Knew thee? There's Sympathy in true Affection, that sees thro' all Disguises—I should chide you now—But this foolish easie Nature of mine,—Well 'twas great Mark Anthony's weakness, with his Sun-burnt Mistress—Come my Cleopatra, our bickering, like theirs, must end in kind Embraces. Zan. Go, go, you know too well my easie Nature. [Whilst he unlocks the Door, she speaks under. Now will I put on another Vizard of Dissimulation. Enter the Room with him, And study a Moor's Revenge, whilst in his very Arms. Fla. Consider my dear Child of Night, time's pretious. Zan. Dear Tempter, why will you press me thus knowing my Frailty. Fla. For that reason, come thou shalt. [Kisses her. Enter Marcello. Mar. I'm sick of this Court-Air, stifl'd with Perfumes, And must have Breathing-room—Ha. [Sees Flam. Fla. Where are ye, you lying Poets, you that daub'd o'er a Phillis or Cloris's Green-Sickness Face with Poetical Paint, Here's Rose and Lilly; Nector and Ambrosia. [Kisses her again, and pulls to the Door. Mar. Brother, Fla. Ha! Mar. Is this your Pearch you Haggard? Hence to th'Stew's. Zan. Ruffian, you shall be clapt by th'Heels for this, For thus affronting one of Quality. Mar. Quality! I saw your hellish Face unmasqu'd, More frightful than your Vizzard. Zan. Rogue in Shammy, Is this your Camp-breeding, to play the Russian in Court? Mar. You're a Strumpet, an impudent one. Fla. Why d'y' kick her? Mar. She brags you're to marry her. Fla. What then? Mar. I had rather she were pitch'd upon a Stake In some new seeded Garden, to affright Her Sister's Crow's thence. Fla. You're a Boy, a Fool; Be Guardian to your Hound, I am of Age. Mar. If I take her near you, I'll cut her Throat. Fla. With a Tun of Feathers. Mar. And for You, I'll whip this Folly from you. Fla. Are ye cholerick, Bully? I'll purge't with Rhubarb. Mar. This to your elder Brother! Fla. Brother! Hang ye. You wrong me most that should offend me least. Brother! I do suspect my Mother play'd foul play When she conceiv'd thee. Mar. Now (forgive me Nature!) Like the two slaughter'd Sons of Oedipus The very Flames of our Affection Shall turn two ways—revile our Mother's Honour! These execrable! I'll make thee expiate With thy Heart's Blood. Fla. White-liver'd Dastard—Bully. You see I am unarm'd, and take your time. Mar. If thou art Brave, as thou art Insolent, Here take my Sword, and sit the Length of 't. Fla. I shall, Sir. [Exit with the Sword. Enter Cornelia. Cor. Marcello, stay; wherefore were you so loud? Who brok'ring with? Who was your Opposite? And what's your Quarrel? Mar. You see here's no Antagonist. Cor. Nay, Sir, I heard your Brother's Voice too. Mar. 'Twas your Fancy. Cor. Will you dissemble? Son, you do not well, To fright me thus; you never look thus pale, But when you are most angry—I do charge you Upon my Blessing—nay, I'll call the Duke, And he shall chide you. Mar. Publish not a Fear Which will convert to Laughter—Hear me, Madam, This was my Father's Picture. Cor. Yes. Mar. I have heard you say when in your Arms you carry'd My younger Brother, how he took this Picture, And by portentous Force with's Infant Hands Half tore it as in Scorn and Indignation. Cor. Yes, but 'twas mended. Mar. Such early Sacriledge was surely ominous And most ill-boding; what! those awful Features! Pray mark 'em! I cou'd dwell an Age upon 'em, And almost pay this Image Adoration. Cor. Thrice pious Youth, and Comfort of my Soul. Fla. I have brought your Weapon back. [Re-enter Flam. Cor. O Horror! Mar. You have brought it home indeed. Cor. Help, Murder, Help. Fla. D'ye turn your Gill up? I'll to Sanctuary, And send a Surgeon to you. [Exit. Mar. O Mother! now remember what I told you [Enter Lud. Gasp. and Ant. About the mangled Picture of my Father. There are some Sins, that have their Punishment In a whole Family—This it is to rise By base dishonest means—Farewel. [Dies Cor. O my perpetual Sorrow! Lud. Read you here, The Meaning of the Outcry—Virtuous Marcello. Gasp. He's dead; pray leave him Lady. Ant. Come, you must. [They take him up. Cor. Alas! he is not dead, he's but in a Trance; why, Sir, here's no body shall get any thing by his Death, let me call him again for pity sake. Lud. I wish you were deceiv'd. Cor. O! you abuse me; how many have gone away thus for lack of Tendance—Rear up his Head, his Bleeding inward kills him. Ant. You see he is departed. Cor. Let me come to him: Give me him as he is. If he be turn'd to Earth, I'll moulder with him in one Tomb. Reach a Glass hither, and see if's Breath will stain it. Cordials quickly. O Savages! will you loose him for a little Pains taking? Lud. Your kindest Office, is to pray for him. Cor. Alas! He's young enough to lay me in the Ground, let me come to him. Enter Brachiano in Armour, all but his Head, a Page bearing his Beaver, Flamineo driven in before 'em. Bra. Where were you posting with such guilty Haste, [To Flam. And those distracted Looks? Wherefore on wing, After a hideous Outcry in our Court? Who call'd out Murder? [To the Company. Lud. That speechless Oracle can best resolve That Question. Bra. Was this your Handy-work? Fla. 'Twas my Misfortune: Cor. He lies, he lies, he did not kill him; 'twas these that murder'd him, who wou'd not suffer him to be better look'd to. Bra. Take Comfort, my griev'd Mother. Cor. Out Screech-Owl. Lud. Forbear, good Madam. Cor. Let me go— [Breaks from them, runs to Flamineo with her Ponyard drawn, coming to him gazes, and lets it fall. The injur'd Powers forgive thee: Do'st not wonder I pray for thee—I'll tell thee what's the Reason: I have scarce Breath to number twenty Minutes, And would not have them spent in Cursing: Fare thee well: Half of thy self lies there: And may'st thou live To fill an Hour-glass with his moulder'd Ashes, To tell how thou should'st pass thy time to come, In sad Repentance. Bra. Pray tell me, Madam, How came he by his Death? Cor. Indeed my Boy that's dead, presum'd too much Upon his Manhood; gave him bitter Words, Drew his Sword first, and so I know not how [For I was past my Sences] fell with's Head Just in my Bosom. Page. This is not true, Sir; For as I cross'd the Passage with your Beaver, I saw at distance— Cor. Peace, I pray thee Peace; One Arrow's graz'd already, and 'twere vain To loose the Shaft is left, For that which never will be found again. Bra. Hence bear the Body to Cornelia's Lodging, And we command that none acquaint our Dutchess With this sad Accident, Flamineo. Fla. Now for a dextrous Lye, of good Complection, A wicked, read and commodious Lye: [Here the Conspirators Antonio and Gasparo take the Beaver aside and venom'd Powder. I ha't. I see, Sir, by your questioning stern Looks, You would be satisfi'd about this Quarrel; Take it in brief—He was my younger Brother. Bra. What of that? Fla. And gave me insolent Language. Bra. A Brother's Blood for a rash Word? Fla. Such Words Would call down Thunder, he traduc'd The Honour of my Mother, call'd me Bastard. Bra. How, Sir? Fla. He said he did suspect My Mother play'd foul play when she conceiv'd me. Bra. This was too gross, if true—but Be it as 'twill, I grant you not your Pardon. Fla. No! Bra. Only a Lease of Life, and that shall last But for one Day— Thou shalt be forc'd each Evening to renew it. Fla. At your pleasure—your Will is now a Law. [Trumpet. Bra. Hark there, the Summons to the Barrier, We make the Sport wait for us: Where's my Beaver? Page. The Beaver there: His Highness's Beaver. Gasp. He calls for his Destruction. Lud. Are you sure on't? [Exeunt all but the Conspirators. Ant. I'll trust th'Ingredients, were he Cerberus, Or tho' three-liv'd Geryon, 'twould dispatch him. Lud. This is, methinks, the Triumph of Revenge, To arrest and seize him in the height of Revelling, And on his Bridal Night too. Gasp. Add but this; To sink him lower in th'Infernal Lake, That the last Deed he did he pardon'd Murder. [Exeunt. SCENE changes to the Tilt-yard. Charges and Shouts. Enter hastily Brachiano, Flamineo, and others. Bra. An Armourer, Blood, Fire, an Armourer. Fla. The Armourer, fly, call the Armourer. Bra. Tear off my Beaver. [Enter Armourer. Fla. Are you hurt, my Lord? Bra. O my Brain's on Fire. Arm. Upon my Life, my Lord— Bra. Away with him to Torture. There are some great ones have a hand in this, And near about me. [Enter Vittoria. Vitt. O my lov'd Lord! Fla. Remove the Barr: Here are unfortunate Revels. Call the Physicians. [Enter Physicians. Your own Art confound you, We have too much of your Cunning here already. Bra. O I am gone past help; the curst Infection Flies to the Brain and Heart. O thou strong Heart, There's such a strong League 'twixt the World and thee, You're loath to part. [Enter Giovanni. Giov. How fares my noble Father? Bra. Remove the Boy away. Where's this good Woman? Had I a thousand World's, They were too little for thee: Must I leave thee? What say you Screech Owls, is the Venom mortal? Phy. Most deadly. Bra. Most corrupted politick Hangmen, You kill without Book, but your Art to save Fails you as sure as great Men needy Friends. I that have given Life to offending Slaves, To wretched Murderers, have I not Power To lengthen my own out for one Twelve-month? Off, Do not kiss me, for I shall poison thee: This Unction's sent from the great Duke of Florence. Vitt. Sir, be of Comfort. Bra. O thou soft natural Death that art Joint-twin To softest Slumber; no rough bearded Comet Shares in thy mild Departure; the dull Raven Beats not against thy Casement; the hoarse Wolf Scents not thy Carrion; Pity windes thy Course, Whilst Horror waits on Princes. Vitt. I'm lost for ever. [Conspirators enter. Bra. How miserable a thing it is to die 'Mongst Women howling. What are these? Fla. Franciscans; Come to perform you their last Office. Bra. On Pain of Death, let no Man name Death to me; It is a Word infinitely terrible. Withdraw into our Cabinet. [They carry him off. Ant. We have struck mortally this royal Stag. Gasp. Let's follow to his Bay. Ant. And see him worry'd by his own Quack Dogs. Gasp. And wash our Hands in's Gore. Lud. O 'twill compleat the Sport. [Exeunt. End of the Fourth Act.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT V. SCENE opens and discovers Brachiano in Bed, Vittoria, Flamineo, Ludovico and Attendants. Vitt. O my good Lord! Bra. Away, you have abus'd me: You have convey'd Coin from our Territories, Bought and sold Offices, opprest the Poor, And I ne'er dreamt on't: Make up your Accounts, I'll now be my own Steward. Lud. Sir, have Patience. Bra. Indeed I am to blame; For did you ever hear the dusky Raven Chide Blackness? Was it ever known the Devil Rail'd against cloven Creatures? Vitt. O my Lord! Bra. Let me have Quails to Supper. Fla. Sir, you shall. Bra. No; some fry'd Dog-fish; your Quails feed on Poison; That old Dog-fish, that Politician Florence. I'll forswear Hunting, and turn Dog-killer. Rare! I'll be Friends with him, for (mark ye) one Dog Still sets another another a barking—Peace, peace, Yonder's a fine Slave come in now. Fla. Where? Bra. Why there, In a blew Bonnet, and a Pair of Breeches with a great Codpice: Ha! ha! ha! Look you, his Codpice is stuck full of Pins With Pearls o'th' Head of 'em. Do not you know him? Fla. No my Lord. Bra. I'll Dispute with him, he's a rare Linguist. Vitt. My Lord here's nothing. Bra. Nothing? Rare? Nothing when I want Money? Our Treasury is empty, there is nothing, I'll not be used thus. Vitt. Good my Lord lye still. Bra. See, see, Flamineo that kill'd his Brother, Is dancing on the Ropes there; And he carry's a Money-bag in each Hand to keep him even, For fear of breaking's Neck: And there's a Lawyer In a Gown whipt with Velvet, stares and gapes When the Money will fall: How the Rogue cuts Capers, It should ha' been a Halter. 'Tis there what's shee. Fla. Vittoria my Lord. Bra. Ha, ha: Her Hair is sprinkled with Arras Powder, Which makes her look as she had sinn'd 'ith Pastry. Vitt. This is desperate Frenzy. Bra. Look you, Six gray Catts that have lost their Tails, Crawl up the Pillow, and send for a Rattcatcher. I'll free the Court From all foul Vermin. Where Flamineo. Fla. I do not like that, he names me so often, Especially on's Death-bed, 'tis a Sign I shall not live long. Vitt. He has rav'd himself quite out of Spirits; Cordial here; rear up his Head gently. [Antonio and Gasp. enter in their Capuchins Habit. Ant. Now Sir, To Ludovico. How speeds our Operation? Lud. Beyond our Wishes, He has had strange Deliriums; Talkt of Battles Monopolies, and leavying of Taxes, Issuing Proclamations; and from thence descends To the most Brain sick Language; now hee's still With meer expence of Spirits. Gasp. A sure Sign that he draws near his End. Ant. A fit time For us to practise our last Tortures on him. Gasp. Lett's to work then, before he's spent too far, For should he first grow Sensless, our Sport's marr'd. Ant. By your leave Sirs, you see he's just departing, His Speech has left him, you must do so too, And leave us two to whisper in his Ear Some private Meditations, which our Order Permits not you to hear. [The Company goes out. Lud. Be sure you worry him. Gasp. Prometheus, When languishing in Chains had but one Vulture, He shall have two. [The Company being gone out, Antonio and Gasp. discover themselves, and seize Brachiano. Ant. Brachiano. Gasp. Miscreant. Ant. Hell-hound. Gasp. Hear you Slave, You that were held the famous Politician, Whose Art was Poyson, Ant. And whose Conscience Murder. Gasp. That would have broke your Wive's Neck down Stairs, Ere she was poyson'd. Ant. That had your Villanous Sallads, Gasp. And fine embroider'd Bottles and Perfumes, Equally mortal with a Winter Plague. Ant. Now there's Mercury, Gasp. And Coprose, Ant. And Quicksilver, With other divelish Apothecary's Stuff, A Jumbling in your Politick Brains—Dost hear? Gasp. I am Gasparo. Ant. Antonio I. Gasp. Thou shalt dye like a Scoundril, Vagabond Rogue. Ant. Stink like a Fly-blow, Dead-Ditch Dog; Gas. And be forgotten ere thy Funeral Sermon. Bra. Vittoria, Vittoria! Ant. O the cursed Negromancer Comes to himself again; we are undone. [They put on their Cowls again hastily. Gasp. What shall's do now? Ant. Take this and strangle him in Private, [The Company return. What will you call him again to suffer treble Torments, O for Charity, for Charity avoid the Chamber. [they go out again. Gasp. You would prate Sir, This is a true Love's Knot Sent from the Duke of Florence. [Strangles him. Ant. What is't done? Gasp. The Snuff is out; no Woman-keeper i'th' World, Tho' she had practis'd seven years at the Pest-House, Could have don't quaintlier. [The Company return. My Lord he's dead. Omn. Peace to his Grace. Vitt. O me! This Place is Hell. Lud. How heartily she takes it. Fla. Yes, yes, Had Women Navigable Rivers in their Eyes, They would dispend them all. I'll tell thee, These are but Moonish shades of Griefs and Fears, There's nothing sooner dry, than Women's Tears. Lud. This must be Florence's doing, Fla. Very likely. Yet how demure his Looks are! O the Art, The modest Form of greatness that does sit Like Brides at Wedding Dinners. Lud. Whosoever sent him his Dispatch, he's dead, And now— The People have full liberty to talk And discant on his Vices. Fla. Misery of Princes? That must of force be censured by their Slaves: Nor only blam'd for doing things are ill, But for not doing all that all Men will. One had better be a Thresher, Blood, Fire, I'd fain speak with this Duke yet. Lud. What now he's dead? Fla. I'll speak to him, and shake him by the Hand, Tho' I be blasted. [Exit Flam. Lud. At your own Peril Sir. Now Gentlemen we are private tell me truly, Did you both terrifie him at his last Gasp. Ant. Yes, and so rudely, that the Duke had like To have terrify'd us. Lud. As how, I pray? [Enter Zanch. Gasp. You shall know that hereafter— See yonder your black Succubus that haunts you, She rolls her hideous Eye-balls, and looks big With some Infernal Message. Lud. She has promis'd me, The Revelation of some dreadful Secret. I long for the dark Oracle: Stand by, You are passionately met in this sad World. [To Zanch. Zan. You should look up, Sir; these Court Tears, Claim not that Tribute to 'em. Let those Weep, That guiltily partake in the sad Cause. I knew last Night by a sad Dream I had, Some Mischief would ensue; yet to say Truth, My Dream was most of you. Gasp. Mark her, I prithee, how she Simpers like [To Ant. The Suds a Collier had been wash'd in. Zan. Come, Sir, good Fortune tends you; I did tell you, I would reveal a Secret to you—Isabella, The Duke of Florence's Sister, was Poison'd By a fum'd Picture, and Camillo's Neck Was broke by curst Flamineo: The Mischance Laid on a Vaulting-Horse. Lud. Most Strange! Zan. Most True! Lud. The Bed of Snakes is broke. Zanch. I sadly do confess I had a hand In the black Deed. Lud. Thou kept'st their Counsel. Zan. Right. For which to make amends, I intend, This night to Rob Vittoria. Lod. Excellent Amends! Usurers Dream on't when they sleep out Sermons. Zanch. To farther our Escape, I have entreated Leave to retire me till the Funeral's o're, To a Friend i'th Country: That excuse Will succour our Escape: In Coin and Jewels, I shall at least make good to our own Use, A hundred thousand Crowns. Lod. These Crowns we'l share. Zan. It is a Dowry, Methinks should make the Sun-burnt Proverb false, And wash the Ethiop White. Lod. It shall; away. Zan. Be ready for our Flight. Ex. Zanch. An hour 'fore Day. A strange Discovery. Why Gentlemen, till now we knew not The Circumstance of Isabella's Death, And of Camillo's less. Zan. You'l wait at Midnight; i'th Chappel. Zan. comes back. Lod. There. Ex. Zan. Ant. Now, Sir, what News from Pluto's Court! Lod. Retire with me and I'll inform you all, More Food for our Revenge, that I can tell you, We must to work again—the Presence Enters. Enter Giovani weeping, Attendants after him, from the other side Flamineo. Fla. 'Tis a dull sullen Corps, he take States on him, and would not answer me one word. Ha! the young Prince. Prince 'Tis a sweet Prince. Yet have I known a poor Woman's Bastard better favoured. This behind him; for to his Face I shall use other Language. Wise was the Court Peacock, who being compared for Beauty to the Kingly Eagle, said, the respect of her Feathers, but in respect of her long Tallons—His will grow out in time.— My gracious Lord— Gio. I pray Sir leave me. Fla. Your Grace must be Merry, 'tis we have cause to Weep. For wot you Sir, what said the little Boy that rode behind his Father a Horseback— Gio. Away Buffoon. But that's not your worst Character—I charge you on Forfeiture of Life to quit our Palace. Exit Giov. and Attendants. Fla. Do's he make a Court Ejectment of me? A flaming Firebrand casts more Smoak without a Chimney than within; I'll smother some of them. How now! thou art sad. [Enter a Servant. Serv. I melt even now with the most piteous Sight. Fla. Thou meet'st another here, a pitiful degraded Courtier. Servt. Your Reverend Mother, Is grown a very old Woman in two hours: I found them winding of Marcello's Coarse; And there is such a solemn Melody, 'Tween doleful Songs, Tears and sad Elegies. Such as old Grandams watching by the dead were won't to out were the Nights with; that believe me, I had no Eyes to guide me forth the room. They were so'ore charg'd with Water. Fla. I will see them. Serv. 'Twill be uncharitable in you, for your sight will add unto their Tears. Fla. I will see them. They are behind the Travers; I'll discover Their superstitious Howlings. Ha! I can stand thee. Nearer, nearer yet. What a mockery hath Death made thee? thou look'st sad. In what place art thou? in your starry Gallery, Enter Brachianos Ghost in his Leather Cassock, and Breeches, Boots, a Coal. A pan of Lilly Flowers with a Scull in't. Or in the cursed Dungeon? no! not speak? Pray Sir, resolve me, is it in your knowledge To answer me how long I have to live? Not answer? Are you still like some great Men, That only walk like Shadows up and down, And to no purpose? say,— The Ghost throws Earth upon him and shews him the Scull What's that? O Fatal! he throws dirt upon me. A dead man's Scull beneath the roots of Flowers, I pray speak, Sir, Our Italian Church-men Make us believe, dead men hold Conference With their Familiars, and many times Will come to bed to them, and eat with them. He's gone; and see, the Scull and Earth are vanish'd. Exit Ghost. This is beyond melancholy; I do dare my fate To do it's worst. Now to my Sister's Lodging, And sum up all these horrors; the disgrace The Prince threw on me; next the piteous sight of my dead Brother; and my Mother's Dotage; And last, this terrible Vision; all these Shall with Vittoria's Bounty turn to good, Or I will drown this Weapon in her Blood. Exit. SCENE 3d Vittoria's Apartment. Vittoria to Zanche. Vitt. with a Book in her hand. Song. Flamineo Enters. Fla. What! are you at your Prayers? give o're. Vitt. How Ruffian? Fla. I come to you about worldly business. Sit down, sit down, nay stay Blouse, you may hear it, The doors are fast enough. Vitt. Ha, are you drunk? Fla. Yes, yes, with Wormwood Water, you shall tast Some of it presently. Vitt. What intends the Fury? Fla. You are my Lord's Executrix, and I claim Reward for my long Service. Vitt. For your Service? Fla. Come therefore, here is a Pen and Ink, set down What you will give me. Vitt. There. [She writes. Fla. Ha! have you done already? 'Tis a most short Conveyance. Vitt. I will read it. I give that Portion to thee, and no other Which Cain groan'd under, having slain his Brother. Fla. A most courtly Patent to beg by. Vitt. You are a Villain. Fla. Is't come to this? They say Affrights cure Agues: Thou hast a Devil in thee, I will try If I can scare him from thee; nay, sit still. My Lord hath left me two Case of Jewels Shall make me scorn your Bounty, you shall see them. [Exit. Vitt. Sure he's distracted. Zan. O he's desparate. [Returns with two Case of Pistols. For your own Safety give him gentle Language. Fla. Look, these are better far at a dead Lift, Than all your Jewel-house. Vitt. And yet methinks, These Stones have no fair Lustre, they are ill set. Fla. I'll turn the right side towards you; you shall see how they will sparkle, Vitt. Turn the Horrour from me: What do you want? What would you have me do? Is not all mine yours, have I any Children? Fla. Trouble me not With this vain worldly Business; say your Prayers. I made a Vow to my deceased Lord, Neither your self nor I should out-live him The Numbring of four hours. Vitt. Did he enjoyn it? Fla. He did, and 'twas a deadly Jealousie, Lest any should enjoy you after him, That urg'd him to vow me to it; for my own Death, I did propound it voluntarily; knowing, If he could not be safe in his own Court, Being a great Duke, what hope then for us? Vitt. This is your Melancholy and Despair. Fla. Away; Fool thou art, to think that Politicians, Do use to kill the Effects of Injuries, And let the Cause live. Shall we groan in Irons, Or be a shameful, and a weighty Burthen To a publick Scaffold? This is my Resolve; I would not live at any Man's Intreaty, Nor dye at any's bidding. Vitt. Will you hear me? Fla. My Life hath done Service to other Men, My Death shall serve my own turn, make you ready. Vitt. Do you mean to die indeed? Fla. With as much Pleasure as 'ere my Father 'gat me. Vitt. Are the Doors lockt? Zan. Yes, Madam. Vitt. Are you grown an Atheist? Will you turn your Body Which is the goodly Palace of the Soul, To the Soul's Slaughter-house. Cry out for help. Zan. Help, help. Fla. I'll stop your Throat with Winter-Plums. Vitt. I prethee yet remember. Fla. Leave your prating, it moves not me. Zan. Gentle Madam, Seem to consent, only perswade him to teach The way to Death; let him dye first. Vitt. 'Tis good, I apprehend it; To kill ones self is Food that we must take Like Pills; not chew't, but quickly swallow it: The Smart o'th' Wound, or Weakness of the Hand, May else bring treble Torments. Fla. I have held it A wretched and most miserable Life Which cannot dare to dye. Vitt. O, but Frailty! Yet I am now resolv'd: Farewel Affliction: Behold Brachiano, I that while you liv'd, Did make a Flaming Altar of my Heart, To sacrifice unto you; now am ready To sacrifice Heart and all. Farewel Zanche. Zan. How Madam, do you think that I'll out-live you? Especially when my best self, Flamineo, Goes the same Voyage. Fla. O most lov'd Moor! Zan. Only for all my Love let me intreat you, Since it is most necessary one of us Do Violence on our selves, let you or I, Be her sad Taster, teach her how to dye. Fla. Thou dost instruct me nobly; take these Pistols, Because my Hand is stain'd with Blood already, Two of these you shall level at my Breast; Th'other against your own; and so we'll dye Most equally contented: but first promise, Not to out-live me. Vitt. &amp; Zan. Most Religiously. Fla. Then here's an end of me, Farewel Day-light. Are you ready? Both. Ready. Fla. Whither shall I go now? Whether I resolve to Fire, Earth, Water, Air, Or all the Elements, by Scruples, I know not, Shoot, shoot. Of all Deaths, the violent Death is best; [They shoot, he falls. For from our selves it steals our selves so fast, The Pain once apprehended, is quite past. Vitt. What, are you dropt? Fla. I am mixt with Earth already! As you are Noble, Perform your Vows, and bravely follow me: Vitt. Whither? Zan. To most assured Destruction? Vitt. O thou perfidious! Zan. Thou art caught— Vitt. In thy own Engine: Thus I tread the Fire out [They tread upon him. That would have been my Ruin. Fla. Will you be perjur'd? Vitt. Think whither thou art going. Zan. And remember what Villanies Thou hast acted. Fla. O, I am caught with a Springe! Kill'd by a Brace of Lurchers. O the way's dark and horrid! I cannot see; Shall I have no Company; Wilt thou out-live me? Zan. Yes, and drive a Stake Through thy Carcass; for we'll give it out, Thou did'st this Violence upon thy self. Fla. O cunning Furies, now I have try'd your Love, [He rises. And double all your Reaches; I am not wounded; The Pistols held no Bullets; 'twas a Plot To prove your Kindness to me; and I live To punish your Ingratitude. O Men that lie upon your Death-beds, and are haunted With howling Wives; ne'er trust them, they'll Re-marry, Eat the Worm-piece your Winding-sheet, 'ere the Spider Make a thin Curtain for your Epitaphs. Vitt. Help, help! Fla. What Noise is that? Ha! false Keys i'th' Court! Lod. We have brought you a Mask. [Noise without, enter Lod. Ant. Gasp. A Machine it seems By your drawn Swords. Church-men turn'd Revellers! Gas. Isabella! Isabella! Lod. Do you know us now? Fla. Lodovica! and Gasparo! Vitt. O, we are lost! Fla. You shall not take Justice from forth my Hands. O let me kill her,—else I'll cut my Safety Through your Coats of Steel: Fate's a Spaniel, We cannot beat it from us; What remains now? Let all that do ill take this President: Gas. Bind him to the Pillar. Vitt. O your gentle Pity: I have seen a Black-bird that would sooner fly To a Man's Bosom, than to stay the Gripe Of the fierce Sparrow-Hawk. Gas. Your Hope deceives you. Vitt. If Florence were i'th' Court, he would not kill me, Gas. Fool! Princes give Rewards with their own Hands, But Death, or Punishment, by the Hands of others. Lod. Sarrah, you once did strike me; I'll strike you now to the Center. Fla. Thou'lt do it like a Hang-man, a base Hang-man, I cannot strike again. Lod. Dost laugh? Fla. Would'st have me die, as I was born whining? Lod. O could I kill you forty times a Day, And use it for Years together. What dost think on? Fla. Nothing, of nothing; leave thy idle Questions; I am i'th' way to study a long Silence; To prate were idle. Lod. O thou glorious Strumpet! Could I divide thy Breath, from this pure Air, When't Leaves thy Body, I would suck it up, And breath't upon some Dunghill, Vitt. You my Deaths—man! Methinks thou dost not look horrid enough, Thou ha'st too good a Face to be a Hangman: If thou be, do thy Office, in right Form; Fall down upon thy knees and ask Forgiveness. Lod. O thou hast been a most prodigious Comet, But 'Ile cut off your Train: kill the Moor first. Vitt. You shall not kill her First, behold my Breast, I will be waited on in Death, my Servant Shall never go before me. Gas. Are you so brave? Vitt. Yes, I shall welcome Death, As Princes do some great Embassadors, Meet him half way. Lod. Do'st thou not tremble? Methinks fear should dissolve thee into Air. Vitt. O thou art deceiv'd, I am too true a Woman: Conceit will never kill me: Il'e tell thee what, I will not in my Death shed one base tear, Or if look pale for want of blood, not fear. Gas. Thou art my Task, black Fury. I have Blood As red as either of theirs. Wilt drink some? 'Tis good for the Falling Sickness. I am proud Death cannot alter my Complection: For I shall near look pale. Lod. Strike with a joint motion. Vitt. It was a Manly blow; The next thou give'st, murder some sucking Infant, And then thou wil't be Famous. Fla. That's well put: Thou art a Noble Sister; I love thee now: Vitt. My Soul, like to a Ship in a black Storm Is driven I know not whither. Fla. Then cast Anchor. We cease to grieve, cease to be Fortunes Slaves; Nay, cease to Dye, by Dying. Thou art gon, and I am in a mist. Vitt. O, happy they that never saw a Court, Nor never knew great men, but by Report. [Vitt. Dies. Fla. I recover like a spent Taper, for a Flash, And instantly go out. My Life was a black Charnel: I have caught, An Everlasting Cold. I have lost my Voice. Most irrecoverably: Farewell glorious Villains; Let no harsh Flattering Bells resound my knell, Strike Thunder and Strike Loud to my Farwell. [Dies. Enter Embassador and Giovian. Eng. Em: This way, this way, break open the Doors this way. Lod: Ha, are we betray'd? Why then Let's instantly Dye altogether, And having Finish'd this most Noble Deed, Defie the worst of Fate, nor Fear to Bleed. Eng. Em. Keep back the Prince; Shoot, Shoot, Lod. O, I am wounded; I fear I shall be ta'ne. Gio. You bloody Villains, By what Authority have you Committed This Massacre? Lod. By mine. Gio. Thine! Gas. Yes. Lod. Thy Unkle, which is part of thee, enjoyn'd us to't. Thou knows't me I am sure; I am Count Loderick, Gio. Ha! Gas. Yes: That Moor, thy Father chose his Pensioner. Gio. He turn'd Murtherer. Away with them to Prison and to Torture. All that have hands in this, shall taste our Justice. Lod. I doe Glory yet, That I can call this Act my own. For my part, The Rack, the Gallows, and the tortrous Wheel. Shall be but sound Sleep to me! here's my Rest: I Limb'd this Night-piece, and it is my best. Gio. Remove the Bodies; see my Honour'd Lord, What use we ought to make of their punishment. Let Guilty Men remember, their Black Deeds, Do lean on Crutches, made of Slender Reeds</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE EPILOGUE. Our Author's pleas'd, that English Judges sit Upon a home-spun PLAY, and English writ, And could with less Expence i'th' Modern Way, Have fitted out a slight New-fashion'd PLAY To Leak, and Bulge, and Founder in the Bay; But chose a Vessel that would bear the shock Of Censure; Yes, old Built, but Heart of Oak; Besides, 'twas an ESSAY worth all his Cost If your old Relish of Stage Wit were lost. And if he finds stead of th'Old Draft and True Y' are fond of your Sophisticated New, Can, (like his Brethren) Balderdash and Brew; Cou'd jumble ye Ingredients, cheaper got Than Methods, Morals, Character and Plot, Which he pretends to sell ye in this Lott; We vouch our Ware for good, and if debarr'd From a fair Market, stand upon our Guard: And if our Scout-boat Prologue fails to take ye, We have our Epilogue Chase-guns to rake ye; We know upon what Bottom we engage, Nor blush to set our Monsters of the Stage By more Enormous Follies of this Age. Coach suited to Complexion! a whole Shop Disfurnish'd to rigg out one first Rate Fopp: Nymphs shorn t' equip a brainless Beau with Hair, And brawny Booby lugg'd in Lady-Chair. Thus rather than we'll see our Stage run down By Nonsense, we'll let fly at the whole Town. You've seen the Joy and Terrour of your Life, Our wanton Wife, and Devil of a Wife; If that won't mortify and make ye sorry, We have a Devil of a Husband for ye, Doom'd by just Fate to die of raving Fits, To fright Ill-natur'd Husbands to their Wits: If you'll make this for Challenge a Pretence, We'll answer ye like Masters of Defence. Blustering and Bluff, with Bear-Garden Behaviour, Let's have a clear Stage, and from you no Favour. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>