<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Duffett, Thomas</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Duffett, Thomas</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">duffett thomas</field>
      <field name="author_text">Duffett, Thomas</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">17th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V2.0058.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1674</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:459812</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Spanish Rogue</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 17th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 17th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Spanish Rogue</field>
      <field name="title_facet">spanish rogue</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">spanish rogue</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Spanish Rogue</field>
      <field name="year_display">1674</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1674</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1674</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459812&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459812&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Duffett, Thomas&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;duffett thomas&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Spanish Rogue&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;spanish rogue&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1674&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1674&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Duffett, Thomas&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Spanish Rogue&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for William Cademan [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1674&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872159-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv20058&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 17th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;17th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Spanish Rogue&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 206 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: The Spanish rogue.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Comedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1674.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Mar 1673 ?&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE SPANISH ROGUE.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">? O bone! ne te Frustrere: Insanis &amp; tu, Stultique prope omnes. Hor. Serm.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">TO MADAM ELLEN GUYN.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Persons Names. Don Fenise—Mr. Harris. Don Alonzo—Mr. Lyddal. Don Manuel—Mr. Watson. Larasco—Mr. Powell. Mingo—Mr. Cash. Sanchez—Mr. Griffin. Alcinda—Mrs. Boutell. Rosella—Mrs. Uphill. Teresa—Mrs. Corye. Leonella—Mrs. Kneppe. Neighbours, &amp;c.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PROLOGUE Spoken by Mrs. BOUTELL. Our poor forsaken Stage does now appear, Like some cast Mistriss that has once been fair: In ev'ry part a sad decay we find, Yet fondly look, that you should still be kind; At least we hope, what our Defects deny, Your eager want will at this time supply: For, as fierce Captain that from Camp returns, Flies at each Vizard-mask he sees,—and burns: So, in this Dearth of Wit, methinks to Night You should not stand to mind if all be right. None sure will rail at faults we Women make, When the kind failing's onely for your sake. And, tell me Gallants! which would you like best? The tedious Fool that stayes 'till she is drest, Or the kind Girl, who when the hour is come, Slips on the Morning Gown, and steals from home? After the good old English way we treat, Though it be plain, we give you wholesom Meat. Our Friends of th'other House, do often take ye With such Ragousts as nasty French Cooks make ye. With garnish'd Dishes they delight your Eyes, And give you nought but Vermine in disguise. 'Tis not a Ladies Paint, can gain her Hearts, Nor silly Lords fine Cloaths, can mend his Parts: Loaded with Liv'ries, the Gilt Coach may roul, And yet the Spark within may be a Fool. To your own Cost, most of you Gallants know, That is not alwayes best that makes a Show. Were the Truth known, here's many a Spark I fear, That has been lewdly Chous'd in fine Semar. Thus Fools are caught, but the old crafty Sinner, Takes the sound Wench; though in Straw-Hat and Pinner.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. Scene 1. Enter Don Fenise and Larasco in Fenise's House. Fen. Despairing Merchants, when their Fleets appear, After the dangers of a stormy year, Have swelling hopes like mine; yet doubt their Fate, 'Till in their greedy arms they hug their freight. Assist me Fortune! fix thy rouling wheel Some few short minutes, and for ever reel. Not yet!—how dull and lazily it creeps? [Looks on his Watch. O Expectation! how each moment sleeps! Lar. Sleep on, old time! for thou hast need of Rest, Who art for ev'ry Lovers service prest. Had my grave Courage been as rash as his, We both had slep'd eternally ere this. These Lovers, whom the Devil cannot fright, When near enjoyment fires their appetite; Design'd to meet like Cats, i'th dead of night: But I told him, whom nothing else cou'd stay, 'Twas her command he should not stir till day. This time much better fits my peaceful mind, Though Love wo'nt, let them see, must I be blind? She has, poor thing! expected him all night, And, though he's freed from's peevish Mistriss by't, I know he'll Rant; but my resolve is set— These valiant Friends did never fail me yet. [His Feet. Fen. Ev'n in consent, she's cruel too, the night Much better wou'd disguise a Lovers flight. None but her self can such delayes repair; Impatience is as restless as despair.— Exeunt Fenise and Larasco. Scene 2. Enter Alcinda and Leonella in Don Manuel's Hall. Alc. Is this a Lovers haste? Did he not say, Each minute in my absence seem'd a day? False man! unworthy of my meanest thought! To slight a Love he has so dearly bought— My flame increases by his cold delay; Revenge shall lead me off, though love wou'd stay. Exit Alcinda. Leon. The language of those begging eyes I know, Implores a reason that she may not go: I'll rather make her hate him if I can, For she's too good for such a faithless man.— [Going out, she sees Fenise and Larasco coming; and returns with a dark Lanthorn. Enter Fenise and Larasco. Fen. The King of Planets from his daz'ling Crown, With more than common Red gilds ore the Town: Blushing to see Loves secrets trust the Light. Leon. Stand! Who goes there? what sturdy mortal Wight, When dismal shades the sleeping World orespread, And yawning Graves let out their wandring dead, Disturbs the silent night? and rashly pryes Into pale Hecates drowsie sacrifice! Speak daring Mortal! say, what makes thee creep Through unknown paths, when time it self's asleep? Declare thy dire intent— Fen. Let's make all sure, And play these Frolicks when we are secure. Leon. This voyce I know; deceive me not pale Moon! 'Tis he!—hey ho! what made you come so soon? This Love's a restless Bedfellow; take heed, Tread soft and sure; this shews you love indeed, T'adventure out this dreadful stormy Night, You might have taken cold, or met a Spright— Lar. A Spright! where! where! Ah good Sir! dear Sir! stay no longer here— Fen. Pry'thee release my patience, I'll approve This sport another time—But where's my Love? Leon. Where is your Love indeed? to make her wait, Were it not lost, you had not come so late. Go boast your Treachery, and then declare How long you woo'd, how oft you perjur'd are; When you consult your Conquest, sum your Cost Of precious time, and Oaths; See who has lost. She will your scorn with interest return, And, for your falseness, Heav'n will make you mourn. Fen. Thy Looks are well, but in thy Words I find The certain signs of a distemper'd mind; Is it to me you speak? and can you prove My wandring Faith, or my decaying Love? Disperse these wonders which your words create; It was my Penance to attend so late; And if I suffer, for your own designe, Your loud Complaints more justly will be mine. Leon. Ah Sir! Excuses which so weak appear, Betray too little Love, or too much Fear: Do jealous Lovers, which abhor the light, Call Phœbus to attest their secret flight? She summon'd you ere Night wax'd grey, as soon As the Antipodes enjoy'd their Noon. Fen. Thou heartless Fool! what mischief hast thou done, Instructing me to wait the rising Sun; Kneel to good Fortune, for thy Life's the stake; Raise not my Ruine on this Rogues mistake, I'll lead her hence, or perish at her feet. Leon. Sooner the Eve and Infant day may meet; This injury reviv'd her dying scorn, And stay'd me here to hasten your return. Ill Tydings flie, too soon you'll hear the rest— Fen. The rest! Can my Misfortune be increast? I know too little, since there's more behind. Leon. If she can hate you, to your self be kind. Fen. Villain be gone! thy swiftest fears out-flie— Leon. Your Sword would blush to wear so base a Die. Fen. In such extremes of Fate, I want a guide: None can securely stem wild passions Tyde. Proceed!—hold!—(curs'd fortune) dispatch the rest— Leon. Y'are banish'd from her presence, and her brest. Fen. His baseness is too weak a guard—He dyes! For such a Saint too poor a Sacrifice. Fenise draws, and Larasco runs in crying. Lar. Dear! Dear! merciful! pardon my mistake, For Heavens, Oh Sir! for fair Alcinda's sake— [Within. Murther! Murther! I'm dead! I'm dead! Exit Larasco. Fen. Nothing to stop his Throat? no hearty Curse? Leon. O for an Irish Wolf to make him hoarse. Thieves! Thieves! Thieves! Rogues! Villains! Dogs! Thieves! [Manuel within. Leon. The Blood-hounds up, no cunning can relieves. Fen. Curse on his yelping Jaws! what shall we do? Leon. Here, here! quickly Sir, step in here— Exeunt Fenise and Leonella. Enter Don Manuel in a ridiculous Morning dress. Man. Thieves! Thieves! Wife! Daughter! Maid! nobody hear? All the dores open, undone! rob'd! undone! All the World asleep? am I heard by none? Murther! murther! I'm dead, down right stone dead. Ha! 'tis so, 'tis so, my wild girls are fled. Pray Heav'n it be no worse, I'll raise the Town. [Exit Manuel locking the dore after him. Enter Don Fenise and Leonella. Leon. Consult her safety, though you slight your own; Her Honour suffers in your longer stay, No dull consideration; but away— Still more unhappy! he has lock'd the dore. Exit Leonella. Fen. Never to see, nor think of me no more! Why can she not my Love transform to hate? And rule my Passion, as she rules my Fate? Why did those mighty Powers we adore, Give Beauty so much strength, and give no more? Have I for this, outwatch'd a Tyrants Spie? A Hermits Zeal, or Statesmans Jealousie? When Mad-men sleep, and madder Chymists rest, Loves greater madness still annoyes my Brest. Repent! too cruel Fair thy Vow repent! Let the Offender bear the punishment— Unkind Alcinda! Must we ever part? Can She so easily command her heart? To my insulting Fate too much I bow: If I must never more, I'll see her now— I dare not go; Dull Fenise! canst thou bear These injuries from Love, and blame his fear? He's innocent, or thou must guilty prove; As he to fear submits, thou yeild'st to Love. Enter Leonella pulling Larasco in. Leon. Among the Women you can domineer— Lar. Kill me Sir! Kill me! rid me of my fear. Fen. This Fellow may his frighten'd sense regain, The Object once remov'd, removes his pain; Love, like an angry Ghost, allows no rest, But still torments the guilty Lovers Brest. Yet I'll shak't off! [Alcinda at a Window. Ha! 'tis she! treacherous sense! A Thousand Devils cannot force me hence. Urge it no more, but to her lead the way. Leon. Her strict Commands I dare not disobey. Fen. The saddest prospect of my Fate I see, She being lost, much worse it cannot be. Thou shalt relent—here's gold— Leon. Who can resist the charms your tongue affords? This is a language sweeter far than words. Lar. O Wondrous Virtue of imperious gold! For thee is Honour bought, and Heaven sold. Yet, had I all ere fruitful Peru bred, I'd give it freely to be safe in Bed. What new design? something she talks of me, I fear some plot upon my Chastity. Fen. Sirrah! Observe her Orders— Lar. More Catterwouling yet! Hell stop her breath! Fen. Another Murmur shall foretel thy death. Lar. I wish'd a task, whose danger might declare What I dare do, my Folly to repair. Leon. Watch, and inform us when he comes, See right, Let not your shadow put you in a fright. Lar. I'll fight the proudest he that wears a head. Leon. What darest thou stake against my Maidenhead? I do not take thy rusty Sword away. Thou a Fighter! Lar. Donna! your beauty may, That man is mad that will with Women fight, Your loss by day you can revenge at night. Fen. Dispatch his charge, my dearest blood I'd pay To buy each minute which you throw away. Villain! be watchful— [Exeunt Fenise and Leonella. Lar. Sir! I will—not stay— If all my art and strength can get away. This Lock is vengeance strong, No passage here: No Window big enough for creeping Fear? Ne'r talk on't! I can't endure to be kill'd, He cares not so his wild desire's fulfill'd. I'll try the Garden wall—is this door fast? Then life adieu! the fatal Die is cast. A Kingdom to secure my life!—he's there! [A Noise within. Oh my dear pretty heart! thy end draws near. O Death what shall I do? where shall I hide? No cunning place to tye my self aside! A little stay—my knife! yet do not come:— Pox on't! now I have left my knife at home: Else I could cut my throat. Poor carkass! how Must thou be Slic'd and Carbonado'd now? I might have stop'd the Lock too, fool that I was! Oh my belly! good Lock don't let him pass! Dear Lock stand too't! sweet Lock don't let 'em come! 'Wounds! how I shall be Slash'd? there's forty o'm— Enter Don Manuel and Neighbours ridiculously arm'd; They see Larasco, and run off again. So, so, now they consult about my End— Enter again Don Manuel and Neighbours. Man. You that such daring courage did pretend, What made you run? I'll bravely go before, Come Neighbours! enter all, and shut the dore. What all gone agen? my case is hard, [Larasco stands up like a Statue. I dare not see, my house without a guard. Ha! one of the Villains! or but a shape Set up to fright me, while the Rogues escape; It does not move, nor breath, it must be so— Were it a Man, thus wou'd I forward go— Lar. Now must I go to Pot!—how my bones aske!— [Aside. Man. And Slash him thus,—ha! did not something shake? What shall a Scarecrow make me thus afraid? Yet, by this light! 'tis very neatly made; Substance! true mortal substance too!—I'le swear, Not one convenient member wanting here. This shape may any maid alive deceive— Lar. I am a very Image I believe, But I have heard that Images can't feel. [Aside. Man. I fear no flesh alive, by this bright steel! O for a Cæsar now, or for that brave Undaunted Soul that did the world enslave; Like Tennis-balls I'd whirl them about, And thus make way to let their Courage out [He strikes Larasco. Lar. Oh! Curse on your valour!— [Aside. Man. I'll try to place His head upright, and paint some red in's face. The nose too should be mended, and the eyes— Lar. How to escape this dog I can't devise— Now he has turn'd his back, I'le cut his throat— [Larasco draws, Manuel sees him, and runs off; then Larasco falls grov'ling on the ground. Man. Murther! murther! murther! Lar. Oh dismal note! Enter Leonella hastily. Leon. What noise was that? what's the disturbance here? Lar. Mercy! good Sir, Mercy! Oh do but hear, I'll confess all—Noble Don Manuel! Your cursed Wench, by some infernal Spell Entic'd Don Fenise hither, and has sold The fair Alcinda to him for his gold. He's now within persuading her away; I am a servant, Sir,—forc'd to obey— Dear Sir be merciful! Leon. Rise, and be free— Lar. Ha! is it you? confound such Sorcerie! The Hall's inchanted, or this cou'd not be. Enter Fenise and Alcinda. Fen. Since that blest hour I gave my heart to you, My busie thoughts no other object knew. My Eyes ne'r stray'd to any other face, My heart ne'r fram'd a wish beyond this place. I plead no merit, Madam! for I know My Service weak, and my desert too low. Alcin. Fenise! Upbraid me not with your desert, I know 'tis great, and well deserves my heart; Were you unworthy, my obliging Vow Has made me yours, nor will I break it now. Yet Gratitude (for Love ne'r reach'd my Brest, Nor yet had power to disturb my rest) Makes me your Pris'ner now; and lets me see, You prize your fading pleasures more than me. Your satisfaction you resolve to buy, Though at the price of my dear liberty. Fen. By what you want, judge not the love I have, You cannot be a Pris'ner to your Slave. If Love cannot incite you to depart, Trust gratitude awhile to guide your heart. Alc. Give Reason yours, and an Example shew, Or ask no more what you refuse to do. You cannot cease to Love; I can't begin; You cannot break the Snare, nor I get in; Yet, to content your self, you'll punish me— Alas! this is not Love, but Cruelty. Fen. How strangely Madam! at the self-same time, You do excuse, and charge me with a Crime. If Love can't be compell'd, as 'tis most true, Fenise adores, but Fortune injures you. Alc. Justly your Passion may suspected grow, Since you demand those proofs you dare not show. You gain my Faith by leaving me behind, Lessen your Love, and practise to be kind. Leon. Tempt not your Destiny, but let's be gone, Her wandring Fancy must return anon: Madam! if you will go, let's haste away, To flie those Dangers which attend your stay. Alc. Thou know'st my heart, let Fenise be our Guide— Leon. Spread all your Sails, you have the Wind and Tide. Alc. What Noise is that? [A Noise at the dore. Leon. This comes of your delay— O Heav'ns! Don Manuel has stop'd your way. Alc. What will Don Fenise do? persuade him in. Lar. Now does my storm of misery begin. Alc. Haste to the Garden, there's a private dore. Ah Fenise! now we part to meet no more. Lar. Sweet Master! Dear Master! Alc. Once more farewel! [Exeunt Alcinda and Leonella. Lar. Pray! pray for us!—Now Toll the Passing-bell— Oh that I had but dy'd, Ten years before My Mothers onely hopeful Son was bore: I had been car'd for, I had happy been, This Catterwouling I had never seen. Will you be murther'd in your Muse? Dye here! Fen. It must be so, this shews my Love so clear, She can no more deny me— Lar. What, more heroick Tricks?—Oh how I shake! Is this a time for Love, when Life's at stake? Now will he dye to shew this Cat his heart— Fen. She knows I may compel her to depart; And now, just at this time, to let her stay— Enter Don Manuel and his Friends. Man. Here be the Rogues, Now Neighbours kill and slay— Lar. How fierce and big the Suck-bloods look? I'll spread My Carkass on the ground, and say I'm dead. [Larasco lies down. Fen. Her Vows I'll give her back, and when she's free, Justice will bind her to love none but me. Since all my Vows so unsuccessful prove, That even yet you seem to doubt my Love: I hope this single Act will make it plain, Here Fenise gives you back your self again— Man. How's this? Don Fenise! sure it cannot be— Fen. Ha! where is Alcinda? what's this I see? Larasco murther'd by these Cowards Swords! This Tempest must not be allay'd with words. Have at your hearts; lie there; are you so quick? [One falls as kill'd; Manuel and the rest flie, Fenise pursues them. Lar. Oh my poor heart! I'm very stomack sick. Are they all gone? this was a brave Design; Cowardly Rogues! to strike a Man behind— If I had not been dead, I'd fain have seen, Who durst affront one of my haughty meen. Sure he has wounded me, but I'm alive yet, And pretty sound; but most confounded wet. I'll take advice to know where 'tis I bleed; Ha are you there? here's one lies dead indeed. Quite mortal dead: Well Fellow! go thy way, I'd Rifle thee, but that I dare not stay— Had'st thou been wise, but all have not the gift, [Exit Larasco. 'Tis pity he shou'd live, that has no shift. Neighbour. Yes Coxcomb! I can shift as well as you— I think I am the sweeter of the two. Send me well home, I'll ne'r come here agin, I think him wisest that preserves his Skin. [Exit. Scene 3. Enter Mingo alone. Mingo. Where am I now! But 'tis no wonder if I've lost my way, My Master bad me near the Temple stay; A place I seldom seek; The Donna's Road To choose new Servants, and the newest Mode. Where earthly Saints are pray'd to, those above Sometimes are call'd on, in Intrigues of Love. Where pious Dons with zealous Wives conspire, To raise the fortunes of their Husbands higher. I'th' Temple I was Christen'd, but my fear Tells me! 'twill fall if I agen come there— Hold, my Master!— Enter Alonzo. Alon. What didst thou find the place? Min. Yes Sir, and saw your Friend, but thus it was; After my hasty steps had found the dore, All that I met, Nights silent liv'ry wore. A Servant led me, where I saw Despair, Just like Don Fenise, sitting in a Chair. Not that Don Fenise, who did use to be The life of Mirth, and all good Company. Not he, whose Soul was free as boundless Air, Whose very name could chase away Despair. Alon. Rack me not with these delayes! Min. Sir I saw, A form would make a frozen Tartar thaw, And melt his rocky Heart th'rough weeping Eyes: His heavy Head upon his Shoulder lies, His crossed Arms supported by his Brest, He had no motion, yet he had no rest. His busie Eyes fix'd to the earth—in brief, He was the lively shape of killing grief. At last as if the Dream had had an end, He cry'd, Alonzo! Where's my dearest Friend? Then did I your approach and message tell, That did his eager grief a while repel, But Sorrow soon did repossess his Face; As Currents' stop'd, more swiftly end their Race. Alon. It is not sure within the pow'r of Fate, To cause those Wonders which thou dost relate. His heart ne'r entertain'd the—boldest fear, And how could base Despair find entrance there. What ever cause such strange effects create, I will avert, or help to bear his Fate. True Friendship, like rich Diamonds, we mark, Whose rayes are most resplendant in the dark. Mingo! make haste, and sum up thy account, Thy merits may to higher Service mount; Yet I have alwayes us'd thee well— Min. Most true— Alon. And have I not been oft abus'd by you? Your wild Debaucheries in ev'ry place, Made me a mark of Scorn, and rude Disgrace. I need not number up your Faults again, Yet I resolv'd to bring thee back to Spain: Here I dismiss you Sir; but ere you goe, [Kicks him, and gives him Money. I'll pay thee less, and more than I do owe. Min. Ah Sir! I am a Rogue, but pray forgive— Alon. Forget your saucy Tricks, and Civil live, Perhaps you may be mine, if you amend— Exit Alonzo. Min. This Gold is dear—Well! go thy wayes old Friend! Revenge sink deep, torment my injur'd—brest, 'Till on his Ruine I have built my rest. How, turn honest! turn Beggar, give me Gold: I'll think on Honesty when I grow old. For feeble helpless Age it may be good, 'Tis but a dull disease in youthfull blood. Among the modish French 'tis plain disgrace, Some of our Signiors too come on apace; When they take up, the Tradesman must not wait, But hears the News, and has the courteous Hat, Talks handsom Sense, is heard like a Divine; Pray Mistre! stay and take a Glass of Wine— But when he Dunns, and Cringes like a Slave, Dam'ee! what would this paltry Fellow have? Now I'm for any thing, all wayes I'll tread, To find the path that does to Mischief lead. Kick'd! and turn'd off! I am a Rogue I know, But to my Master I was never so. Cashier'd! and quite thrown by! well Don take heed, Ere all be done, thy heart or mine shall bleed. [Exit.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. Scene 1. Enter Don Manuel and Teresa in the street. Man. A meer mischievous Plot, without all doubt; Would any come to force a Woman out? He could not do it but by her consent, No! no! I'll ne'r believe her innocent. Ter. Are you sure 'twas Don Fenise? Think agen— Man. Poh! think; I know him from a Thousand men. Ter. You may mistake. Man. Mistake!—pray is it day if the Sun shine? That Question's less impertinent than thine. Enter Mingo. Mingo. I've rack'd my Brains, and yet no way can find To act a close Revenge, Mischief be kind! And help me at a pinch— [Aside. Oh this dull Head, this barren Scull of mine! Will nothing come? no Project? no Design? Ha! what are these?— Man. Yes you are; foolish and impertinent— Ter. Ingrateful Rascal! I was not impertinent, When I help'd thee to my Masters wealth, And to two pretty little Girls, without one stroke of thy Own labour; Heaven knows, and I have found To my sorrow, it will be long enough before thou Wilt see one little, little Child, of thy own getting. Man. No, nor thou wert not impertinent, when thou Didst most inhumanely murther honest Sanchez. Ter. Out thou Villain! was it not for thy sake? Thy hands too were as deep in as mine, Heaven knows I meant no harm. Ingrateful! dost upbraid me with my good will? I'll be reveng'd though I dye for't— Thy Cheats and Villanies I will confess, Thy punishment, will make my pain seem less. Man. Poh! you take Jesting so unkindly—You know Honey that I love you, And if my life onely Were to be lost, it should go rather than I Would see thee troubl'd thus: But— It grieves my heart to think of losing thee. Ter. Ay, ay, these are your old wheedling Tricks.— Man. One can't praise you for your Contrivance, Or your Courage, but y'are so angry— Pry'thee my Dearest! forgive me—I love The very ground you tread on, And had rather see Thee than my own heart-blood—Come you shall be kind Ter. My poor dear Rogue! I will forgive thee! I will be kind, don't trouble thy self. [She weeps, and kisses him. What shall we do about Don Fenise Dear! Man. That bus'ness must not be disputed here; Let's hasten home, least some observing Eye Should ruine us, Nay pry'thee no Reply— I'll serve thee Honey with my dearest blood. Ter. My dear, dear Don! I'll dye to do thee good. [Exit Teresa. Man. I mean no less; in ev'ry foolish strife, She threatens me to take away my life; When she's dispatch'd aside, I shall be free And then, my coy Alcinda! I'm for thee— With more then common madness—he's possest, That layes up secrets in a female Brest. [Exit Manuel. Mingo. Thanks! Satan thanks!— These bloody Murthers, Cheats, and Villanies, And something more that undiscover'd lies, Are Riddles very dark, and intricate; Teach me the rest, and I'll adore thee Fate! What I've already heard, commands a share For secresie, as great as their parts are: But I am injur'd, since he's wicked grown, For I resolv'd to be a Rogue alone. Some way their bus'ness shall my own advance, I'll follow them, and leave the rest to chance. At least their Crimes will teach me to invent, A Rogue in mischief is in's Element. [Exit Mingo. Scene 2. Don Manuel's House. Enter Rosella, Alcinda, and Leonella. Alc. What Visage wears my Fate? what have they done? The noise was very loud, Is Fenise gone? Safely got off or no? Why don't you speak? Should he be kill'd, my sullen heart would break. Leon. He's safely gone, but all I fear is known— Alc. Sure I heard their Swords; had he no wounds? Leon. None— Alc. Henceforth we never meet. Rosel. Did acts of Love, I'th' Sphere of Justice as of Power move, Asharp repentance wou'd succeed your Fact; And you would suffer what you late did Act. Some worthless object, on your self would throw That cruel scorn, you did to Fenise show. Alc. Justice is blind, and grown so modish too, Like other Females, bribes must make her do: Her Sword, Self-interest and Passion swayes, But Love and beauty ev'ry thing obeyes. Rosel. She runs the common fate of all our Sex, Whom natures too imperious Law, subjects To her great Master-peice, victorious man: And you Alcinda! know, you'r beauty can Command so large a pow'r ore any heart, As will oppose Astræa's weaker part. Alc. Beauty, the Toy you talk of, I disown: To my dull sense it still had been unknown, If to your self I had a stranger been; Where all those charming Vanities are seen, Those rare Chymæra's, flatt'ring Poets place In the description of a beautious face; Those that want faith, the fair Rosella view; All Lovers write is verify'd in you. Rosel. Each wandring glance you make, a heart your prize, By the Magnetick Vertue of your Eyes; The am'rous Gallants here their service pay, You are their Saint, and at your feet they pray. Leon. The longest day would seem a midnights dream, While they continue on this pleasing theam. Is not one Minute to Don Fenise due? Rosel. Once more I must that hopeless suit renew. Alc. Desist Rosella! from a Sute so vain— The Earth may move, before we meet again. Ros. So brave a choice your Reason may approve. Alc. Reason was ne'r the messenger of Love. Ros. Think, think Alcinda! you may Love too late— Alc. My humor's fix'd above the pow'r of Fate. Leon. Madam! My zeal to serve you, shews my troubl'd mind, To see you flie the Blessings Heav'n design'd; O! could you think the joyes, that do attend A marry'd life, this humor soon would end. Think what entrancing pleasure 'tis, to hold Your Lover in your arms, and sweetly fold With close embraces, and more lovely Twines, Than clasping Ivy, or the winding Vines. This idle peevish thing call'd Modesty, Is Womans most invet'rate Enemy: Lay it aside, none but our selves are here, Blushes are vain when none but Women hear. Sleep with a Man! what joy the thought of't brings, This is no World to refuse good things. There needs no words, Your Eyes speak your intent, A Womans silence shews her full consent. Alc. Perpetual silence seize thee! I admire What leprous Dæmon does thy Soul inspire. Ros. Base!—I know not what to call her, sure Nature wants Definitions so impure. [Exeunt Alcinda and Rosella. Leon. Truth seldom is accepted when 'tis plain; But hang't! I'll soon retrieve their love again. Enter Don Manuel and Teresa, and Mingo after, observing them. Ter. If you consent, we yet may lose our Fears, And with their Bodies, cloyster up our Cares, Send them to th'Nunnery, and let's pretend Zeal to Religion is our onely end. Let them drop Beads— Man. From thence what can arise? Ter. In their Concealment all our safety-lies. Man. Can that contribute ought to hide our Crimes? Ter. Yes, very much these Superstitious times; 'Twill gain their highest praise, who can depaint Mischief so fair, it may deceive a Saint. In this quick-sighted Age that we live in, Religion is the safest Veil for Sin. While they do breathe an unconfined Air, Our Ruines imminent, Objects so fair Endure the search of many prying Eyes; You know what Dangers may from thence arise. Man. I like thy counsel well—but— Ter. But!—but what? Vengeance pursues us, yet his blood seems hot And reeking for Revenge, methinks I hear The wind cry Murther in my guilty Ear— Man. Dear Duck! enough, th'art wise; it shall be so— Rosella to the Nunnery shall go, That will secure us, though Alcinda stay, On her side there's no danger in delay. Ter. Steal to your ruine; do!—let both be gone; Why should one go, or t'other stay alone? Man. Nay no great matter, but 'tis chargeable; Truth is, I love Alcinda yet too well. [Aside. Ter. What should this mean? the charge will be but small— Better lose part, than give account for all. Man. Let's in and think upon't— Exeunt Manuel and Teresa. Leon. What can this be? Vengeance and Blood, this is too hard for me— Some monstrous mischief, though 'tis close as Night, Time will reveal it, That brings all to light. Exit Leonella. Mingo. Strange! above wonder strange! and falls so right As if the gods themselves lov'd deeds of Night. To bring me there, just at that minute too; I'll talk no more, but study what to do. In vain you strive to prop your falling State, Your Lives are mine, this Tongue commands your Fate. Sure that was Leonilla stai'd behind— My quondam Mistriss; I'll soon make her kind. What sights are here? Enter Alcinda and Leonella, Rosella following them. Alc. Receive no answer, nor no message hear. Ros. Examine ore your heart, she shall not go: You too much malice with your power show. Alc. Are you unkind? then who can be believ'd? I had commanded had my Father liv'd. [Exit Alcinda weeping. Ros. Go, serve her will, 'tis strange, a gallant man Should love so truly, and so long in vain; Dearly I love him, yet I know not why, I'm ne'r so happy as when he is nigh. Yet, for a husband if I make my choice, His Interest will never win my voice. And yet I love him still—ha! to what end? Were it not virtuous I should hate my friend; Love is as yet a stranger in my brest. I will not like a Tyrant treat a guest: Yet, to secure my heart from a surprize, I'll set a guard of Virtue in my Eyes, And while my Love to Virtue does submit, I will believe it fair, and welcome it. And love him still— Enter Alcinda. Alc. Will you my Rival grow? Ros. Ne'r did a Sister love a Brother so. Alc. You shall not love him, nor shall he love you, His Vows have made him mine, sure Vows are true. Ros. You slight his Vows, his Courtship disapprove; This Jealousie shews the excess of Love— [Aside. Because You hate him must I do so too? Alc. Fool not your self, I love him more than you: You love! this News shall to your Father's ear— Ros. Pray Heav'n your flame does not too late appear; On you Alcinda! he has fix'd his Love Too constantly to suffer a Remove. Disperse your jealous frowns, I have my end, When He your Husband is, and you my friend. May you enjoy him still, and happy be, Above the fears of Infelicity. Alc. Take him you, if you please, for I know none So fond to dye for him— Exit Alcinda. Ros. So coyly gone? What sickly Fancies do this Maid possess? She seems to hate, yet loves to an excess. Ah Fenise! from my heart I pity thee— [Exit Rosella. Mingo. Both are exactly fair in ev'ry part; A virtuous flame seems to assault my heart, And prompts me to be good; bids me declare All I have heard; But they are both too fair— Ha! if things fall right, One may be my own; So Innocent!—I dare not stay alone— My better Genius tempts me to be just, 'Twill gain their Favours, and oblige their Trust: Death! I am ruin'd by a longer stay— The Maid I'll follow now, she went this way. [Exit Mingo. Scene 3. Fenise's House. Enter Don Fenise alone. Fen. When giddy Fortune ceases to be coy, The storms we past, increase our present joy. But when her various Front grows black again, That very joy adds to succeeding pain. This day I have convers'd with each extream, Despair is fix'd, hope vanish'd like a dream. Ah Alcinda! why should I think on her, On that ungrateful, cruel murtherer? 'Tis she. That values not my constancy, nor Me— Dispises all my Vows; yet could she prove More cruel than her self, still I must love. Enter Larasco fearfully, and shuts the dore after him. Fen. What means this saucy haste? what makes you run? Lar. O Sir! Sir! you are ruin'd! lost! undone! Fly Sir! fly, the,—O—O—Of—Off—Officer— Fen. What Officer? pry'thee ask leave of fear To tell the Cause— Lar. Oh Sir! they are at the dore— That I had been but fairly kill'd before! Now we shall be Hang'd; both, both Hang'd, I know't, Methinks I feel the Slip about my Throat— Good honest Dun! don't strain the Rope so hard— O let a little time to pray be spar'd!— Fen. Villain! what ayles the fellow?— Lar. Dear Christian friends! If you'll avoid such base, such shameful ends, Beware of Wenching, and Ill company; Wenching! 'tis Wenching brings me here to dye. Curse on such folly—pry'thee let me pray; One little minute!—Oh! he drives away— Fen. Nay if y'are going to take my blessing too— This fear has made him mad; what wouldst thou do Speak! where hast thou been!— Lar. Mercy good my Lord! I ne'r had Courage to behold a Sword. Fen. Recall your sense, and tell me what you mean. Lar. Ah Sir! I ne'r shall have my Sense agen. The dreadfull roaring Officers, without Are sent to seize you, Look you all about. Fen. To seize me! for what?— Lar. They'l tell you if you stay— Have you forgot the Man you kill'd to day? Fen. Is the man dead?— Lar. I! I! Sir! dead's a stone— A happy, happy man, his Cares are done. [Exeunt Fenise and Larasco. Enter Alonzo. Alon. What am I like, the Servants fly me so? I am resolv'd to find him e'r I go— Don Fenise! Don Fenise! [Exit Alonzo. Enter Fenise and Larasco. Lar. Hark how they Roar!— Pray Sir be gone before they force the dore. Fen. Rascal! go you, tell the Officious slaves, Those that do enter here, do seek their graves. I never fear'd thee death! thy fiercest brow Cou'd ne'r disturb me; but th'art lovely now. With greedy armes, such as glad Bridegrooms wear, When full enjoyments drown their wooing fear, I'll meet my Destiny, and hug my fate: [Fenise. draws. To end our Cares death alwayes comes too late. Now will her scorn, now will my Love have end— [A noise within, Alonzo forces the dore, and enters with his Sword drawn. Here here's Fenise! Alon. Is't thus you meet your Friend? Fen. With my Alonzo, thus I will contend. Fate I despise, and Love I will forget; In spight of both I may be happy yet. Welcome dear Friend!— Alon. But can my Fenise be Still constant to that friendship vow'd to me? Has not some nobler Object stole that part, Alonzo once possest in Fenise heart? Fen. No more of this; Alonzo wrongs me much, To think my Vows, or friendship can be such. But I may justly think your kindness lost, That would not let me meet you on the Coast. Alon. I suffer'd stricter penance than was due, For that which injur'd me much more than you. When tedious absence had endear'd your sight, And rais'd Impatience to the utmost height: Yet then, then did I for admittance wait; And now, you chide me 'cause I come so late. When spight of Locks and Dores I made my way, You interpos'd your Sword to make me stay. I thought it some Inchanted House; for here One Servant flies, another hides him there: Scarce could I reach one with my doubting eyes, But like some false deluding shade he flies; At last I turn'd, and saw the armed Rout Begin to march— Lar. 'Twas time to look about. Fen. This way I made, how I got off you saw; Unveil these Mysteries, what made you draw? Alon. Come Sir! I will inform you all within; Discourse so sad, will soon enough begin. Oh my Alonzo! That my whole Estate Could call this Morning back; but 'tis too late. [Exeunt Fenise, Alonzo and Larasco. Enter Mingo and Leonella in the Street. Min. My Dear! this very Morning did my feet Salute this ground; where all my wishes meet, Finding my lovely Leonella here: More beautiful than when I last did see her— Leon. Your old dissembling Tricks— Min. By th'light I see, My love is dead to all the World, but thee. Had spiteful Death extinguish'd thy dear light, I had pursu'd thee to eternal Night. Leon. O fie on you men! for y'are all false— Min. Look here, though men are false, Angels are true. [Gives her Mony. These, and some hundreds more are kept for you; Pry'thee be mollify'd, Love made me trace Ten thousand miles, to see thy pretty face. Leon. Since here we parted not, this can't be true. Min. That you liv'd here, by meer instinct I knew; Divided wormes their parts will reunite, Although the loving creatures have no sight. But Nature did in me much stronger prove, Assisted by my reason, and my Love. Within thy breast I left my better part, And now my body comes to find my heart. Speak my dear Oracle! pronounce my Fate! Leon. Well, I'll consider on't— Min. Where shall I wait To hear my Sentence? I'll attend thee home— Leon. O by no means; You must not thither come: Our House to Men will no admittance give. Min. See thee I must, or else I cannot live— Leon. A Small disturbance we this morning made, Has made my Master jealous of his shade. Man, and Male-kind so mortally he hates, His Malice doth extend to Dogs and Cats: My Ladies Lapdog, and the Cat were found Contriving of a Rape, and both were drown'd. A Massacre's design'd against the Mice— Min. No way to cheat this Tyrant?—no device! Leon. No;—Yes there is, if you can counterfeit An Eunuch handsomely, 'twill do the feat. For some such property he'll entertain, To guard his dore; lest men should come again— Min. An Eunuch! all your Sex will loath my sight, More than She-Papists do a Lenten night. And treat me, as the angry Welchmen prey On Puppets, that affront Saint David's day: Yet, I'll about it strait, that thou may'st see, I dare do any thing to purchase thee. Lend me one kiss, nay fie! hold up thy head: I'll pay thee Interest when we meet a Bed. [Exit Mingo. Leon. Fie! fie! I hate you now—I must be coy, Though he's sharp set, too easie Love will cloy: Men are so Femaliz'd, so idle grown, They court the Coy, and slight what may be won. [Exit Leonella. The End of the Second Act.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. Scene 1. Enter Larasco alone in Fenis's House. Lar. Malicious Rogues lie close, lurk any where; Men may be kill'd, yet see no danger near. Would all like wiser Schoolmen fight with words, I could be Valiant; but I hate these Swords— I can eat like a Lyon; and for Drink, Bacchus himself should never make me shrink. These are rare parts, the Virtues in request, What pity 'tis I cannot reach the rest? O had I but the heart, to thunder out A Roaring Oath, look big, and stare about: Cry Damm'ee! with a Grace; then stamp, and frown, I were the most accomplish'd Blade in Town. (A silent Noise methinks invades my Ear) Enter Leonella. Old Tormenter! I'll be reveng'd on her— Dreadful Toledo! forth, thou trusty Blade, That o're the Head and Ears in blood canst wade. Come out! here's food to fill thy hungry Maw— I'll kill thee Villain! if thou wilt not draw. Draw thou Son of a Whore! Leon. Good Signior hold! Lar. Signior thy Sister, thou paltry sneaking Scold— O I could swinge you now, I tell you that— What now you Sir? ha! what would you be at? Coward! I could eat thee— Leon. Brave Sir! you fight Prodigiously, and kill as oft as smite. Lar. Mortal! Thou say'st the Truth, come buss me now— Leon. Stay Sir! You hold your Sword I know not how, I could instruct you in a better way. Lar. Do't; I command thee— [He gives her his Sword. Leon. Then I must obey— Rascal! I'll teach you how to fight, I will, [She beats him. Draw on your Friends? Sirrah I charge you kneel. Lar. Ah Madam Captain! my first Fault forgive— Leon. Ne'r draw Toledo more as long's you live: Next, I command thee that thou never fight, But with our Sex— Lar. That too shall be at Night. Leon. Lest you are kick'd to Men give no affront; Lar. Ah! you are merciful! indeed I wo'nt. Leon. Thy word shall serve— [Gives him his Sword. Lar. Your Wars I'd fain be at— I know already how to manage that. Vollies of sighs must first approach the Town, To clear the brow of the defendant frown; Kisses for Cannons, but my shot should fall Thicker than cannon bullets 'gainst your Wall. The sturdy batt'ring Ram should charge her home, While her faint No's-supply the absent drum. The breach once made, e'r I attacque the fort, I would dismantl't, and peruse my sport: And, if no modeish fireworks do remain, I'll pitch my standard, and fall on again— Leon. But stay rash Sir! suppose that you are beat, A right stout man takes care for a retreat— Lar. For a retreat? O prythee name it not— I will o'recome;—Or perish on the spot. Leon. Poh! where's your Master? cease this idle Talk. Lar. He's musing in his melancholly walk: Let's to the Pantry first, for some relief; There's heavenly Wine, and mighty glorious Beef. Leon. Thy heart lies in thy guts, Sirrah march on— Lar. Love is a Dish I cannot live upon; Like my Camelion Master feed on looks, If e'r I do, my guts will curse the Cooks. [Exeunt Larasco and Leonella. Scene 2. Enter Don Fenise and Don Alonzo in a Garden. Fen. Hast thou ne'r seen a stately well rig'd Ship, Charge through the foaming billows of the deep? Whose batter'd Fabrick, stormy Neptune drawes Into the ruines of his frothy Jawes; Then shoots him up aloft, swift as a spear, Sent to affront th'Olimpick Thunderer: Jove loudly speaks his scorn of Neptunes brave, And lights the ship back to his watry grave. From ev'ry point rough winds each other call, Hasting to share the glory of his fall: The Vessell still bears up, though thus opprest, The Wind grown weary, gives the water rest; The skies serene, and all the storm blown ore, The longing Vessel makes the wish'd for shore; When, on a lurking Rock, so near the coast, She splits; and just i'th' harbour all is lost. So Fortune plaid with me, I triumph'd ore The storms of her disdain, had sight of shore; That happy port of which my Love did steer, If Earth has yet a paradise, 'tis there— But now Alonzo!— Mark the decree of my too cruel fate, Just on th'arrival of this glorious state, Ev'n in the prospect of my utmost joyes, It shipwracks all my bliss, my hope destroyes. Which now lyes sunck in th'Ocean of despair; Sunck! for ever sunck!— Alon. Time may repair Thy heavy loss, and raise thy drooping fate. Fen. Never!— Alon. This passion's too effeminate; A helpless Woman can, like thee, depaint Impatient sorrow in a weak complaint; Rayl on Sinister stars, and execrate The dire effects of her misguided fate. Such passive Soules teach fate to tyrannize. Fen. What is't your active spirit would advise? Alon. Despise thy mistriss, and thy Rival kill; This way to doat will be excuseable. Do but the difference of passions prove, You'l find revenge is sweeter far then Love. Thy more successful Rival must be slain— Fen. I have no Rival, but her just disdain. Alon. If it be just, you ought not to complain. Fen. Were it not so my case were not so sad, Then hope might live; and pity might be had. Alon. If not to thee, where will she give her heart? The sun ne'r saw a man of more desert. Fen. Should thrifty nature spend her precious store. T'enrich one Heroe, 'till her self grow poor; She has not worth enough to buy the prise Of one rich smile, from her resistless Eyes. Alon. A gallant Woman! were these fancies true: But as she's fair, so she is Cruel too. Fen. There I'm lost— Alon. Yes, to any thing of man, Or reason thou art lost; recal again That royal Exile; where wild passions sway, The Empire of the Soul will soon decay. So Ships without a knowing Guide are toss'd, By ev'ry Gust in danger to be lost. Distraction in thy fancy needs must raign, Since it is form'd by a distracted Brain. Reason would tell thee, Nature did design The female sex slaves to the Masculine; 'Till we are pleas'd to take them into grace, And bring the rib back to its proper place. Fen. But love, the King of passions, wont allow, His subjects should to reasons Scepter bow. Alon. Unreasonable love is Lust; a beast May with a brutish passion be possest. Fen. You say you never lov'd, then how can you Define a passion which you never knew? Alon. I love good horses, sport or sprightly Wine; This reason does allow, there's none for thine. If thou lov'st Beauty, view the forward spring: Seek it in Books if Virtue be the thing. Canst thou with ladders scale the starry grove, And mount the aery battlements of Jove? That, and much more thou sooner may'st fulfil, Then court a froward Woman from her Will. She makes thy sighs and miseries her sport, Thou, like a fawning Span'el lov'st her for't. How vain, how foolish? how ridiculous? Poor and contemptible this passion shows? All for a Woman too; a false delight, First fram'd by Natures drowzy oversight: Begot by giddy drunkards, whose sick braines And reeling thoughts, their riper Age explaines. A painted nothing, gaudy butterfly; Black at the heart, though pleasing to the Eye. This is thy Goddess, Mistriss of thy Fate, Henceforth we will persue them with a hate As great as was thy Love, and thou and I Will from their charmes, as from diseases fly. Summon thy exil'd reason to her throne. Fen. Your witty malice you in vain have shown; Your counsel is a senseless dream to me, Love knows no reason, no Philosophy. Alon. Your ruine faces you, yet you run on Like loseing Gamsters, ev'n when hope is gon. True friends no close distinction make, one fate In joy and grief they both participate. But I am troublesome, unwelcome grown, You will be happy when you are alone— [Going out. Fen. Stay! stay Alonzo. pr'ythee pardon me; To pettish age, or young simplicity We more allow—Loves dotage I confess, But have not power yet to make it less. Enter Leonella with a Letter. Leon. O my goodness! what a sweet man is here? A lovely tempting shape!— [She gives the Letter to Fenise. Fen. Is it from her? Thou bringst a blessing in each Character. Alon. What's the decree? does she propose a peace? Thy looks are sad, pry'thee explain the case. Fen. Read there— Alonzo reads the Letter. Alon. The first part of my promise being past, You must assist me to perform the last. When I did yield to go, you did agree, This day orepast I should be ever free. That done, which Gratitude oblig'd me to, I'll to my self be just, as well's to you. You must forget me, never see me more: 'Tis fit you keep, what you so freely swore. Alcinda. Alon. Before we number many flying houres, This blustring March shall melt in April showres. Hear me— [Fenise and Alonzo whisper. Leon. Oh that I were a Lady for his sake! A man made up in wax— Alon. How Sir not take? Then I doat too; come, worse it cannot be; Laugh heartily, and leave the rest to me. Fen. O I cannot— Alon. What will you still be mad? You cannot win her by your looking sad. Fen. Well, I submit, but if your project fail— Alon. Assure thy self that nothing can prevail. Fen. Never see me more!—ha ha he! How imperiously these Ladies write? Must forget me!—ha ha he! Alon. Bravely done, by this light. Yet leaves thy choice as free as heretofore, 'Tis fit you keep what you so freely swore. Fen. Go tell the Toy you came from, I'm above The power of her malice or her love. Leon. Alack alack good Gentleman! these fits Of Love, have put him quite beside his wits. He is become insensible of's pain. Fen. O No! my sense is just return'd again— Thy Lady Circe's charming spells are broke, And now I'm free'd from her inchanting Yoke. As one, that's by an Ignis fatuus led To some aspiring Rock, whose craggy head, Hangs drooping ore the deep unmeasur'd Main, Flyes with amazed horrour back again; So I, misled by those false lights her Eyes, Was like to fall loves foolish Sacrifice; But now my Soul see's clear, I'll doat no more, But fly those dangers I pursu'd before. Leon. If I return this message Sir! I'll add That when you spoke it, you were raving mad. Fen. Woman! I'm calm and serious, say from me That light and darkness sooner may agree, Than we two meet—Oh what do I intend! I shall undo my self to please my friend. Alon. No flinching now, I'll warrant thee she's thine. Read her Note agen. Fen. This is very fine! [Reads. Pray let no more enticeing Notes be brought, 'Tis loss of time to read her idle thought. Yet, this I will preserve, as slaves made free Keep that which justifies their libertie. Oh Alonzo!— Alon. No more, 'tis bravely done. March off—I'll finish what's so well begun [Exit Fenise. Go tell your foolish Lady how you sped, Her snare is broken, and the Bird is fled— [Exit Leonella. Enter Don Fenise. Fen. One scorching glance, If from her eyes it came, Would set a frozen Scythian in a flame. Alon. How's this? relaps'd agen! can you be free, Yet hug those Chains that cause your miserie? Y'are like a poor Idolater, betray'd To serve that Idol which your self have made. Think all are beauitful, and 'twill appear, You love your own fond fancy more then her. You may as soon forget her if you please— Fen. Fancy can be no cure for Loves disease: We cannot of our selves, or love, or hate, Love shoots his golden Arrows sure as fate, Why do I talk!—I may as soon declare To one born blind, what light and colours are. Alon. If y'are so fix'd, you will not be remov'd, Leave nought untry'd to make your self belov'd. And, as you hope your wishes think on this, Don't cringe and Idolize her for a kiss, But ravish't from her lips, for to entreat Makes her aversion seemingly more great; A careless confidence makes Women yeild. Thus you'l win honour, though you lose the field. Fen. Her constant virtue, seats her heart above The mad attempts you use in looser love. Nor must we try those idle wayes, to gain A Sovereigns smiles, that do ore others raign. Alon. A Sovereign! why you disown'd her pow'r, In sending back her dear Embassadour With so much scorn, as shew'd less love then hate. Princes with slaves will ne'r capitulate. Think you to win her now? be not so vain— You vow'd a passion, and forswor't again; If, all your love and Courtship would not do, Now y'are a Rebel 'tis in vain to wooe. Fen. Treacherous man! was this thy policy? Think'st thou to grow, where th'ast supplanted me. So basely to betray me—ye just pow'rs! 'Tis not my own revenge I act but yours, Direct my trembling Arme, teach it an art To search the secret passages of's heart— Did troops of Devils guard thy perjur'd brest, (As sure they do) for wert thou not possess't With hellish hopes, thou couldst not be so base) Thus would I ruin their abiding place. Defend thy self— Alon. Dear Fenise! hear me, if my blood may give Ease to thy passion, I'll not wish to live: Strike boldly here, and kill thy truest friend. Fen. Think'st thou, this poor evasion shall defend Thy life? 'Thas rais'd my rage to such a height, That now I'll kill thee though thou wilt not fight. Traytor to friendships and to honours law! Coward! Alonzo's a Coward! now draw— Alon. Your strange distemper does my pity raise, But not my anger— Fen. Ha! what is't he says? His pity! Heav'ns his pity! that word Wounds me more sensibly then can thy sword. Draw! or I'll murther thee, by Heav'n I will! Though Angells guard thy life— Alon. He's madder still— Hold Sir! I will fight— Fen. Then thou art Generous, and I'll destroy Thy tainted life with so much gallantry, 'Twill be less happiness to live then dye, Alon. First hear my Reason, though your own you slight Nay hear me speak, or else I will not fight. Fen. Say on— Alon. The Crime you charge me with is Love, But 'tis the strangest Love that man can own, To doat upon a Beauty yet unknown: An object, which ne'r entertain'd my Eyes, Nor fancy yet,—O sensless jealousies! Time is not, two houres older grown since fame First reach'd my Eares with your Alcindas name. Have you such pow'rful Rhet'rick, to enforce So strange a passion with your mad discourse? She never had a thought, nor wish from me, But what I paid as one concern'd for thee. Believe thy friend, recal thy wandring sense, Own thy mistake, and see my Innocence. Fen. Ye drouzy stars! how long will yee permit, That I such gross absurdities commit? Thou cruel Woman, and more cruel Fate, Am I the mark of Loves, and Fortunes hate? Forgive me Sir! and if y'are yet my friend, Helpe me to give my Love and care an end. Peirce this rebellious heart, one little thrust Will pay deaths tribute; then my peaceful dust Wrapp'd in the cold imbraces of the grave, Where it can nothing wish, will all things have. Turn not away—will you be cruel too? Why should I beg what I my self can do [Offers to fall on his Sword. Alon. Strange madness!—Heavens! what do you intend— [Alonzo hinders him. Fen. To spight my fortune, are not you my friend? Alon. I'll seale it with my dearest blood. Fen. Then why Will you oppose my latest remedy? Alon. How can death be the end of miserie, When 'tis the greatest pain of all to dye? Fen. O death is short, and after there's no pain; Alon. But when we dye we hope to live again, You rob the gods of their prerogative, If you should dye when they would have you live. By acts so desperate, and so injust, You will renew your sorrows in the dust. Be yet your self, bravely resolve to slight The worst effects of Loves, and Fortunes spight. He rules his stars, though never so unkind, That bears misfortunes with an equal mind. Fen. Ye pow'rs above! pity my sad Estate: And guide me th'rough this Labyrinth of Fate. [Exeunt Don Fenise and Alonzo. Scene 3. Enter Larasco, with three Neighbours. Lar. No quarrels Gentlemen! that's my decree, For I'm a Tyrant if you anger me: A Lyon incarnate—for the least word, I must have satisfaction with the sword. This Bilboe, simple as it hangs, has sped Whole dozens in a morning at Madrid. Heark ye! this bold French boy that made such work In Flanders, and the huge Venetian Turk. Both pay a pension to this dreadful Sword— You know more then the King does; not a Word— 1. Neigh. O wonderful how strongly is he made? 2. Neigh. Well we are blest to meet this noble blade. Lar. The King imployes so many flatt'ring Spies, I could not rest but for this base disguise. You are all true— All. 3. I! I! I!— Lar. Nay were you base, Not one of you should live to leave this place. Would you be Souldiers? men of great command? Shew but a line from this victorious hand Though I'm so feirce; sometimes I'm pleasant too, And fool with mortals, as I dance with you. The Dance Lar. Hold! hold! this boxing may my courage raise, Which only blood and gapeing wounds alaies. When the dog Turk was at Lepanto beat, Who was it think ye gave him that defeat? The wings were lost, the plain with dead was fill'd, The Cannon taken and the body reeld, But never was there so much horrour seen, As when my single troop of horse fell in. Th'rough Guns, Swords, fire and blood I led the way, Ralli'd the flying troops and won the day. The Turkes like fearful sheep we overcame, You could not hear the Cannons for my name, Larasco! Larasco! Victoria! All. Larasco! Victoria! Larasco! Enter Fenise and Alonzo. Fen. Sirrah! what saucy noise is this I hear? [Neighbors run off. Lar. Only a little harmeless musick Sir— Fen. Haste, haste, Larasco! and prepare my horse; To your advice I now will have recourse. Woman farewel! Glory and Fame I'll court; Alonzo! see her not, the time's too short: My passion may revive by longer stay. Alon. Bravely resolv'd— When you are ready, I'll soon lead the way [Exit Fenise. This murth'ring beauty I must needs survey What's your bus'ness here? Enter Sanchez. San. Hearing that you wanted a man I came, To tender my service to you Alon. Where hast thou liv'd? San. I serv'd a wealthy man in India last: Signior Don Pedro— Alon. De Valiza was't? San. The same; I serv'd him 'till his latest breath. Alon. Why, he was shiprack'd; how did'st thou 'scape death? San. No Sir he did at Sea pay Natures debt— So good a master, I shall ne'r forget. Alon. Canst tell what Port the Vessel made, and where Those little Ladies are, which he had there. San. The ship arriv'd in Spain, I know no more; I was next day found dead upon the shore: My sense so long was lost, I ne'r did know How I came there, or who had us'd me so. Alon. I'll take thee for that Masters sake, go in [Exit Sanchez. This news will much upon Don Fenise win, Don Pedra de Valiza was my Father; One of the Ladies was sister to Don Fenise, The other was my sister. Nine years they have been missing, and 'till now We never heard where they were lost, or how— Grant they may yet survive, ye powr's divine! Then Fenise is oblig'd by vows to mine, And I'm as strictly ty'd to marry his: Which will confirm his thoughts of quitting this. I will not see her, but wee'l strait to horse: And yet I must, compel'd by hidden force— What should this mean Devil! to let thee see, None of thy female sprights have pow'r o're me. I will go see her; Woman do thy worst! Who courts, or feares thee, equally is curst. The End of the Third Act.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT IV. Scene 1. Enter Don Fenise and Don Alonzo. Fen. How! our sisters, and on the coast of Spain! Each hour's an age 'till you return again. If fair Laurina lives, once more I vow, On none but her I will my heart bestow. Alon. May all the curses of the Trojan Queen, Upon my head be doubl'd ore agen, If any beauty living has a part But my Calista, in Alonzo's heart. Fen. Wee'l search where careful mortals never trod. Where birds or sullen beasts make no aboad— Alon. No melancholy grove,—no hollow tree— Fen. No Creek i'th' briney region of the Sea— Though deep as hell, secret as lustful night, Alon. Or traytors thoughts— Fen. Shall 'scape our peirceing sight. Alon. I'll find Calista— Fen. And Laurina I— Alon. Wee'll in a bed or grave together lie. [Exeunt Fenise and Alonzo. Scene 2. Enter Don Manuel and Alcinda, in Don Manuel's House. Man. Your Genius fair Alcinda! takes a flight, Above the common reach of Womens sight. You are discreet, and can instruct me best, How to resolve a doubt which breaks my rest. Alc. Good Sir spare my blushes: What is my crime? Man. Lay by-such thoughts, for I would lose no time— Pray hear me! Suppose a harmless child were left alone, Wandring and lost upon some pathless down. Forsaken by her Parents, and expos'd To fortunes mercy; this is but suppos'd— Alc. No parents could possess such flinty minds. Man. A gentleman this little wand'rer finds, Dejected, weary, hopeless, starv'd, and weak, Where none could see her weep, or hear her speak. Alc. O Heavens! would he not relieve the child? Man. Necessity already made her wild: He kindly takes her up, and brings her home. Alc. A noble pious man, Ages to come Will bless his Charity— Man. Pray hear the rest! She with his daughter shares his equal brest: Their cloathes alike, alike their breeding is, Onely his thoughts distinguish'd that from this. Suppose my self the man, and you were she, Imagine it; how would you answer me? Alc. As Heaven Sir! and justice do command, My heart would not permit you to demand, But I should freely offer what you gave; To buy your liberty, become a slave. Man. Then know, that you are she: that child whom I Found so cast off to want, and miserie: 'Twas I preserv'd you; what has since befel, How I have lov'd you, your own self can tell. Alc. You tell me wonders Sir! why did you name Your self my guardian? Man, Thy spotless fame Had else been blasted, with the busie air Of envious tongues, which nothing can repair. Besides, Rosella justly might repine, To see her welfare pris'd no more then thine. Alc. Good Sir! informe me who my Parents were, Whose hopeless state forc'd them to leave me there With bended knees, low as the humble earth, I'd pay that duty which I owe my birth. Man. Some Oracle must answer your request, But if that tenderness I have exprest, Deserve your grateful thoughts, if ought be due, Restore me back that life I then gave you. Alc. Explain your secret language Sir! from me You may command my life, and liberty! With careful duty I'll your care repay, My narrow fate permits no other way. Man. In short, Love has so far posses't my mind, I cannot live unless you will be kind. Alc. Heavens! what do I hear? excess of care Desturbs your sense, you are not well I fear. Man. Nourish no more this idle misbelief, Let your reply be positive, and brief; I love you, to enjoy you, come be wise, My closet's private from the Worlds eyes; None dares disturb our joyes, and what's unknown, Untold by babling fame, is still undone. Alc. O Sir! can you find out a privacy, Shut from the sight of Heavens peircing eye? That will behold us, and though justice stayes, 'Twill grow the more severe by those delayes. Divine revenge will seize you, in a time When y'are pursuing this unhappy crime; Nor can it be unknown, the dazling sun Will write upon my forehead what is done. Thus low I beg your pity—O forbear! Your guilt will like a gnawing Vultur, tear Your fright'ned Conscience; and the action past, The beastly pleasure dies: the guilt will last. Man. Fairly accept my love and my estate, Or I'll enjoy you at a cheaper rate. I'll force your stubborn wilfulness, and then Return you to your vagrant life ag'en. Alc. Turn me a beging Sir! and I'll proclame You for a Saint, I'll canonzie your name. You cannot force me though I am your slave, Death will preserve me and my honour save. Just Heaven! hear my vow, if you proceed, May I be curs'd, if I survive the dead. Man. I'll talk no more, so cruel and so young! Force shall supply the weakness of my tongue. [Alcinda runs out at one dore, and Mingo enters hastily at another, disguis'd. Alc. Help! help! help! Man. Cross luck! speak what art thou? Min. It is the same; dear mischief help me now! Man. Whether would'st go? what do'st seek? what do'st fear? Min. Most noble Sir! afford your curteous ear, The chance of War, guided by fates decree, Made me a slave to Turkish tyranie. I serv'd a'prentiship in chayns, became An Eunuch to assist their beastly flames: Kind Heav'n at last appeas'd, did freedom grant, But in my flight I was surpris'd by want. Some envious females having known my case, And all my losses, had me strait in Chase. I took this Sanctuary, and from you Entreat protection from this rageing crew. By all you value most, by all that's dear; And by your Innocence preserve me here. On your sweet mercies Altar I lay hold, No disrespect but danger makes me bold. Man. But art thou a very Eunuch indeed? Min. As I tell true, so may you help my need. Man. I'll entertain thee, if thou wilt be mine, Thy bus'ness shall be easie. Min. I resigne, My life t'ee, and if I've done ill in ought, My diligence shall expiate my fault. I have him fast; He's full of thoughts, plot on Projecting Sot! thou fool! thou cheating Don! [Aside. Blest saints reward you, you have sav'd my life. Man. This Eunuchs help will soon conclude the strife, I'll in and teach him how to play his part, Her body's mine, although I lose her heart. Follow me in— [Exeunt Manuel and Mingo. Scene 3. Enter Rosella, Alcinda, Leonella. Rosel. A ravisher! O strange and horrid Crime! Alc. 'Tis a sad truth, if at that very time, Heav'n had not sent that unexpected aid; His Lust most fiercely rag'd, when most I pray'd. Oh that Don Fenise would agen be kind! Leon. Madam! ne'r hope that he will change his mind; You easily may guess at his intent, By this fine song his worthy friend has sent. Rosel. Sing it Leonella— Leonella sings this Song. Down with this Love that has made such a pother, This Jack with a Lanthorn that leads us a round, 'Till with dull Marri'ge we Cheat one another, For joyes that do vanish, as soon as th'are found. Repent ye proud Nymphs! for your Tricks shall not pass, We'll change no more Gold, and good Stones for your Glass. While so severely you rail at the pleasure, And kill the poor Lover that's at your command; Like Doctors, you turn your heads from the Treasure, But Oh how you grasp what is put in your hand. Repent, &amp;c. When the short minute we sigh'd for is over, The Nymph is more kind, and more brisk than before; But how dejected and dull is her Lover, To find all his Passion can purchase no more? Repent ye proud Nymphs! for your Tricks shall not pass, We'll change no more Gold, and good Stones for your Glass. Rosel. Let not a rash despair invade thy heart, Continue kind, and let me play my part. Leon. Madam! here's a messenger from Don Fenise. Rosel. My life on't he repents; withdraw a while, When you return my news shall make ye smile. [Exit Alcinda. I'll punish him; go fetch my Vizard mask, And tell him I'm Alcinda if he ask. Now bring him in; Enter Alonzo. Reason protect my heart! A sweeter shape was never feign'd by art. Alin. Must I discourse with masks? with sableshrouds? I dare peruse your beauty free from clouds. Could you outshine the morning, could your rayes Obscure the glorious sun in clearest dayes; Could your insinuating flames, inspire A Stoicks flinty heart with loves soft fire: To me your boasted Excellence is dim, Those foolish toyes have pow'r on none but him, Fenise, that lov'd you once, mark me Lady! That lov'd you once, and such a Beauty made ye; But he's converted, and he vows, no more Your well mix'd paint and patches to adore. Ros. Pray hear me Sir!— Alon. Madam! I am not come To feign sad stories of your servants death; Your charming name fil'd up his latest breath, He dy'd for love of you,—and when your tears Witness repentance, Ease you of your fears. No! I resolv'd some minutes to bestow, To slight those charmes that had bewitch'd him so. [Exit Alonzo. Ros. As you are truly Noble hear me speak; Should he be cruel, sure my heart must break. Is he gone? quickly call him back, run, fly— Leon. 'Slife what ailes you Madam? Ros. Make no reply— Perswade him back, or never see my face; Ha! what have I done? in so short a space To lose my heart? This for Alcinda I did undertake, Now she may do it for Rosellas sake. A gallant man! Enter Alonzo. Alon. What does your message mean? Rosel. Reallity, let Fenise love ag'en, [She takes off her mask. Alcinda shall be his; I give my hand, A sign the contract shall most firmly stand. Use all the interest that you can make To stay him, for the sad Alcindas sake. Alon. Ha! what do I see? Angel! or Saint! or whatsoe'r you be! That take frail Womans shape, low on the ground, I beg that pardon you from Heaven found. Leon. The gentleman's smitt'n, he's caught i'saith! How he surveyes each beauty that she hath? 'Tis German clockwork sure, how its eyes roul? Look ye the mouth on't moves; alas pretty Soul! A very rare motion— I long to see some tricks, his peirceing eye Declares him Skilful in Astrologie; Can you cast nativities Sir? Alon. Begone! Let me and my nativity alone— O happy friend! Rosel. Near night he'l find her at the Cypress grove; He will not fail if he pretend to love. Good thoughts attend you— Alon. Though you design Your self for him, your picture may be mine— Think me not rude, by your fair self I vow, I ne'r beg'd favour from your Sex 'till now. The Indies shall not buy it from my eyes— Ros. Though what you ask my modesty denies, Nay though I've made a vow never to part From this, but to the man that has my heart— Yet y'have prevail'd; take it, and all content. Alon. As I would take aguift from Heaven sent. Ros. Oh my heart! farewel! Sir!—pray don't forget, Fie, fie, Rosella! this once—he's there yet— [Exeunt Alonzo and Rosella at several dores. Enter presently Alonzo and Mingo. Alon. Mingo! why this disguise? what mak'st thou here? Min. I strive to live—y, are angry still I fear. Pray pardon me; you alwayes found me just. In your affairs, though led aside by lust. Alon. Pry'thee no more, lest Protestations raise Suspition of thy faith, without a cause. Min. Now Sir! I am from all my faults reclaim'd, And blush with anger when I hear them nam'd. Pray let me serve you here Sir! my great care Shall testifie, what my intentions are. Alon. I'll think upon't; there's earnest of my love. [gives him mony. Min. May you receive this bounty from above, [Exit Alonzo. In ten thousand—Curses; and when Heavens store Exausted is, I'll coyn as many more. This was a happy disguise— I've gain'd so much upon Don Manuel's wife, She has discover'd to me all his life. He's mine, to gain Alcinda by my Ayd; And my pretended Love has gain'd the maid. From her I'll learn what brought Alonzo on, And then I'll do your work, my angry Don! Here she comes— Enter Leonella. Enter Don Manuel observing them. O my dear Rogue! what dangers have I trod? How many weary steps? how often rode Ore hill and dale? through fire and frost. Through frights and foes? what Wives? what fortunes lost? Leon. Time has not chang'd thee, thou art Mingo still. Mingo. Thy slave my Sultaness! both heart and will: O let me ever hold thee thus— Man. Here's sport!— An Eunuch? a Stalion! I'll spoyl your Court. D'ee hear Sirrah! Villain! Rogue! what are you? [Exit Leonella. Min. Thy evil Angel, Gorzell! nay tis true: Gorzell I say! hast thou forgot thy name? Thy Cheats, thy Murthers too, I can proclame, Man. Mercy, sweet Devil mercy! pity me! Min. Rise mortal, and give ear to my decree; One beauty shall be mine, the other thine, And equally we'll share the pilfer'd coyn; Dispatch thy answer quick; consent, and live— Man. Y'are merciful, take all that I can give. Min. Then I'm thy friend, and Mingo. [Discovers himself. Man. Catch'd agen? 'Sdeath how didst thou discover, me or when? Min. O never question that, let it suffice, I know you now, and all your Subtleties. Hold to your bargain, we'll go hand in hand, And raise such plots Fate shall not countermand. That wench will tell me news if you retire— Man. Th'art my good Angel, take thy own desire. Min. You must not see it, though I seem too kind To your Teresa— Man. No! no! use thy mind— [Exit Manuel. Min. Yes, and thy soft pate, long prosperity Has lull'd the rascal in security. Here comes his fellow trader— Enter Teresa. Ter. Dear Eunuch! this has been a tedious day. Min. How eagerly this Creature longs for prey? Time's lazy grown, 'tis yet an hour to night. Ter. That hour's eternity—let's lose our sight, And make it ever night— Min. O hold! you prophesie your death I fear. Ter. Death! prythee let's go in—and meet it there. Min. Know then in short, I'm hir'd to murther you; here's earnest for't: [Shews the money Alonzo gave him. Your husband loves Alcinda— Ter. O base slave! Villain! I'll to him strait; I'll tear the knave— Min. Stay! you'l undo us both; but if you will, You may preserve us both, and Manuel kill. Dispatch him roundly, if you love me then I'll marry you— Ter. I'll doe't! thou best of men! [Exit Teresa. Leonella peeps in and Enters. Min. Nay she's gone; My best saint! my wise Medea! what spell Wilt thou invent, old Manuel's rage to quell? Leon. A powerful charm which he can ne'r withstand. Min. Teresa doats, doats on me, by this hand! She's so jealous of thee too, we shall ne'r Enjoy in quiet while we tarry here. Leon. Come, come, there's Villany on foot; my ear Gave me intellgence, though none appear. They look like saints; for all their pious show, There may be Murthers, Whores, and Rogues, or so. Min. I understand, therefore 'tis our best way, To make a handsome pack, and march away. Leon. Our Ladies do prepare to meet their Loves, I must along too— Min. Mark well how it proves; And let me know, it may produce a light, To guide us on in our intended flight. Leon. I'll observe, adieu!— Min. Ioy of my life, farewell! thus far I thrive; I must be suddain, lest so many Eyes As I imploy, may find my Subtilties. I'm stor'd with Wives, and with a helping friend, I'll make true use o'm; to my propper end. On fair Rosella lyes my aim, though here Is my circumference, my centre's there. [Exit. Mingo. Scene 4. Enter Alonzo, with a picture in his hand. Alon. The blasting light'ning darted from the Sky, Kills not so sure as this transpiercing Eye. Coward Alonzo! shall thy Courage sinck, At white and red? a Woman make thee shrinck. That thing which I despis'd; do I not know, Beauties like flowr's do fade as fast as grow? Why should I love, and think of this? nay more, That when we have enjoy'd, the passions o're, And w'are asham'd of that we did adore. Unruly force of wild desire!—this frame Is beautiful as she, this face the same, This I can break, deform it when I please; Intruding Age, or any weak disease, Will make her pow'rful charms as soon decline; Minds oft' are wicked, though the shapes divine. Folly farewel! this Idle senceless toy, And all my passion too, thus I destroy— [Alonzo throwes away the Picture, Fenise Enters and takes it up.— Fen. What suddain change is this? Alon. O happy Fenise! fair Alcinda's thine, Fly to the Cypress grove, there she'l resign Her self into thy armes—be ever blest, I'll seek a grave, while thou enjoy'st thy rest. Fen. Hate me for ever— If I seek Joy while you have Discontent. Alon. I love your Mistriss Sir! and to prevent Any unworthy Act, so base a flame May tempt me to, I'le fly to hide my shame. Fen. More unto Friendship, than to Love I ow, If you unhappy are, I must be so. You made her mine, when all my hope was gone, 'Tis just you should enjoy what you have won. Alon. Let it suffice in Love I yield to you, Strive not to conquer me in friendship too: Conceal that tempting Shadow from my sight; Those that would cure weak Eyes, should fly the Light. Fen. Is this the Form you love? Alon. No Painters Art, Could e'r infuse more life in ev'ry part. Fen. Fortune is kind, her Blessings to divide, Both may be happy yet, Both satisfi'd. 'Tis not Alcinda Sir! but may she be As kind, as fair Alcinda was to me. Alon. Who is it then? There was no other by. Fen. Let's to the place, and there the difference try. But stay they are here— Enter Alcinda, Rosella, Leonella. Alon. Two Suns at once in Beauties glorious Sphere, Denote some change in Loves high State draws near. Fen. Pray Heav'n his Tyranny may now decay. Alon. In me it shall, I'll die or win the day. Fen. Encourag'd by your Goodness, I am come To meet a Blessing, or receive my Doom. More to my Love, then my Offence, is due; My Change was feigned, but my Love is true. It is the practice of the Pow'rs above, To pardon Errors, and accept of Love: Your Beautie's heav'nly, make your Language so: Will you that pardon which you ask bestow? Though you so well your easie change disguise, I see the marks of Anger in your Eyes. Remember Fenise! you did use to wooe, Despise not Love because 'tis offer'd you. Will you refuse me then? Where shall I hide? I blush to ask, but dye to be deny'd. Fen. Refuse you Madam! Will a swelling heart Refuse a Kingdom? Will a Hermit part With want, and misery? by his remove, To share the blessed happiness above? My Soul is so transported with her Bliss, I fear, it will believe no Heav'n but this. Rosel. But Fire that's slowly rais'd, as late decayes. Alon. Let common Beauties reign by common wayes: Too much your Beauty, and my Love you wrong, Light'ning is sudden, yet no Flame more strong. Ros. Powder that swiftly fires, as soon does wast. Alon. Yet does the Fire, as long's the Subject last. So shall my Love, and never know decay, But in the Grave, where no Affections stay. That tedious way of Courtship you approve, Shews much of Patience, and but little Love. Extremes of Passion, such as Love inspires, As ill are suffer'd, as devouring fires: Mine, grown too pow'rful for my narrow Breast, Presumes already to disturb your Rest. Fen. Madam! one charge from you, would make her yield. Alc. Love has the Day, but Shame would keep the Field. Your heart is hers, pray trust me with your hand, Come Sister! lend me yours, though Hymen's Band May be more Ceremonious, may this Endure as long, and be as firm as his. Now I pronounce you one— Rosel. Remember Sister! you compel my Love. Alc. The Earth shall vanish, e're my Faith remove. Rosel. With equal joy I meet your noble flame, I will be ever yours—Pray hide my shame. Alon. That lovely blush, looks like the Ev'ning Air, Whose Scarlet-dye proclaims the next day fair: And so may this Prophetickly appear, For here begins my bliss, and ends my fear. With purer Zeal a Heathen never paid Vows to his Idol, for supposed Aid, Then I present my Heart, a Gift too low To speak the Service I will ever owe. Fen. Ladies! Since we are Conquerors thus far, The great Affairs of Love, as those of War, Call for Advice to make the Conquest good. Alon. That from our Leaders must be understood. Command us Ladies! We will execute. Ros. This place is most unfit for such dispute. Alc. No Treaty will be heard, to think of that Will be in vain, the Foe is obstinate. Alon. Now let us lead you off a glorious Prize, Why should we trust our fatal Destinies? Rosel. Brave Enemies! you shall command our Lives, But hasty resolution seldom thrives. Alon. My lovely Mistriss! where all Beauties dwell, True honour of your worthy—Sex, farewel! [Exeunt several wayes. Scene 5. Enter Don Manuel and Mingo. Ming. Most certain 'tis they are resolv'd to fly, And only wait an Opportunity; Pretend to make a Journey, and take Horse; 'Tis Policy must do't, in vain is Force. Now Leonella is dispatch'd with that, Shall raise between their Servants mortal hate. They both shall die before to Morrows Sun; Nay more, by their own Swords it shall be done. Man. Excellent Mingo!— Ming. With Leonella, I'me to meet this night, I'th' Summer-house, for an intended flight. That must be your Retreat, on her lay hold, For she'll be furnish'd with a Mine of Gold. Make haste away!—be sure you fail her not. Man. Wit prosper thee, brave Rogue! [Exit Manuel. Ming. O fear it not. Poor Fool! I'll make thee sensible e're long, That thou hast sold thy Welfare for a Song. An idle senseless Tale, can thy dull Brain Believe, that for thy ease I'll take this pain? Enter Teresa. Ming. Here comes my Midnights Ghost— Teres. My best delight! Fate can't deny us happiness; this night Old Manuel rides abroad. Ming. But is it true? Teres. Just now we parted, as I came to you. Ming. How Goodness is abus'd! a meer pretence; How Rogues may work upon your Innocence? Alas good Soul! This Night he means to spend I'th' Summer-house, there's his long Journeys end: There he, and modest Leonella meet. Teres. Leonella too, bless me! Ming. Nay, go see't; And if you love me, now you may be mine; He once remov'd, I will be ever thine: Here's that will do the work, revenge your wrong: [Gives her a Pistol and a Dagger. Resolve it suddenly, the time's not long. Teres. Think not, my little Silence did proceed From foolish pity, no! they both shall bleed. Ming. The Woman you may pardon if you will. Teres. To rob me of thy love, no! both I'll kill. Ming. My dear Infanta! Teres. I'll do't! and meet thee in the Lodge, farewell! [Exit Teresa. Ming. Curses pursue thee, how she flyes to Hell? This one Night past, to Morrow all's my own, And this kind Wretch shall die for what I've done: In Blood I'll wade ere Phebus leave his Bed, And make my Crimes out-blush the Mornings red. Great Nemesis! refuse me not thy Aid Thy Sacrifice is lost, if I'm betrai'd. [Exit Mingo. Scene 6. Enter Don Fenise alone in his own House. Fen. How sweet are all my Sorrows now! how dear My Suffrings are, now Happiness draws near! Though in my Love I met with so much trouble, My Pleasure will be, as my Care was, double. Alonzo may have doubts, and jealous fears, My long experience all suspition clears. Rosella's Heart, like parched Straw, took fire, And did as swiftly blaze into desire: Such flames are soonest quench'd, and have least heat; My Happiness as constant is as great; Like noble Metal, which doth long repel Assaulting Flames, that round about it dwell, But once made hot, does long retain the fire, So did my dear Alcinda meet desire; Her Love came slowly, but will sure remain; She will be constant, though I change again. Most happy Fenise! [Enter Leonella, and passing by him, carelesly drops a Letter. Ha! sure it was she; What makes she here? Why should she fly from me? This may inform me, (to my hearts delight The brave Alonzo) pray Heav'n all is right! Friendship allows me liberty to see. He reads the Letter. Fail not to meet me, as we did agree; The hour precisely Twelve, the place you know, Blind Fenise still, no sign of Friendship show. He may observe you with a Lovers Eye, The time seems lazy now our joyes are nigh. My dear Alonzo! haste, you have my heart; When once we meet again, we'll never part. Thine ever Alcinda. Alcinda! Alcinda! Alcinda! It cannot be, sure my distemper'd Joy Distracts my thoughts, and does my sense destroy: Or her fair shape which in my fancy lyes, Sends bright reflections to abuse my Eyes. Ha! 'tis, by Heav'n 'tis so! And if it be, [Leonella peeps into to observe him. O that I wanted Faith, or could not see. Thine-ever-Alcinda! my Tongue speaks this, To cheat my Heart; or else I hear amiss. Alcinda false! it cannot, shall not be; Yet who can doubt, what they so plainly see? O shameless Woman! to destroy so soon A happiness I have so hardly won. The wild Hibernian Waves, and Winter Air, Are constanter than these frail Women are: Like thin Cameleons still they change their hue, And take fresh flames from ev'ry sight that's new. Leon. The Fish is caught, I must allow him line. Fen. Hell upon Earth! I'll spoil their damn'd design. Leon. Now I'll upon him while he looks this way— Fen. What, can you run so well? I'll make you stay. Leon. Mercy dear Sir! Oh Heavens! I'm undone; I see my Sentence in your hand,—I'm gone— Ah noble Sir! you know I must obey, Punish not me, if they have gone astray. Gentle Sir pity me!— Fen. Hear me, thou dismal Messenger of Fate! Here, take your Charm, giv't to Alonzo strait: If thou betray'st me, with one look, or word, Thy Sex shall not protect thee from my Sword: Wipe your dissembling eyes, and get you gone, Look undisturb'd as if it were unknown. Come Fiend! along, see here he comes, take heed: I'll watch you— [Alonzo enters. Leon. Fear me not. I'll do the deed. Fen. This may be yet a damn'd malicious plot, 'Till he confirm it, I believe it not [Fenise hides himself. Alon. Ha! welcome Loves pretty Envoy! Must this Night make us happy? Must we go? Leon. There's my bus'ness, if that inform you so. [She gives him another Letter. Alon. I will not fail, let this engage thee mine. My Service to my Mistriss— [Exeunt Alonzo and Leonella severally. Fen. So, to thine, That is, Alcinda; Ah false perjur'd Friend! Thy heart shall bleed for this e'r this Night end. I'll watch thee to thy Saint, before her Eyes, Thou shalt be punish'd for thy Perjuries. [Exit Fenise. The End of the Fourth Act.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT V. Scene 1. Don Manuel's Hall. Enter Mingo and Leonella. Mingo. Above my highest hope! it needs must hit, I love thy Beauty, and adore thy Wit: But we must try to send their Men aside, They'l sooner fall, if we their force divide. Though both are Cowards, yet for thy Loves sake, Any strange Project they will undertake. Can'st think of no Design? no little Plot? Hell take 'em Hounds! they are not worth a Thought. But it must be— Leon. O that's already done. They are, by this time, in so great a fright, They'l have no sense to trouble us to night. Ming. Thou'st Policy enough to rule a State: Let's to our bus'ness, for the Night grows late. Fail not to be i'th' Summer-house, adieu! I must not any more be seen with you, For fear of old Teresa's jealous Head. Leon. But, when my Ladies ask me how I sped, What shall I answer them? you know they meant To fly this Night, and therefore was I sent. Ming. Say they'l attend them, and 'tis ten to one They'l put up all their Jewels to be gone. Where to secure them, and how, you know. Leon, 'Tis done, my Dear! But whither shall we go? Ming. The time's too short to tell, nor need you ask, Leave that to me, 't has been my chiefest Task To set you on your way; your Pasport's made, [Exit Leonella. Charon shall drag you to the Stygian Shade. Pluto will get a Cooler for your Lust, There's roaring Company, and go you must. Ive taken care you shall not go alone— O what a gallant plotting Rogue I'm grown! I kill but five to night; 'tis true, my hand Is unconcern'd, I do it by command: Like stately Tyrants, on my pow'rful Breath Depends the Thred of Life, the Key of Death. Suppose I fall, if Hell payes me a Shame, Yet shall I leave an everlasting Name. The hour draws on apace, the Moon shines bright, I'll stain her Horns with Blood if all hit right. Exit Mingo. Scene 2. In the Field. Enter Larasco loaden with ridiculous Armour. Leon. The hour is past, and yet she does not come; My Heart fails me—O that I were at home! Yes, I do love her, and this Act does show't, Do I not hazard here my naked Throat? For ought I know, it may be Planet strook: Heav'ns! it thunders; no 'twas my Armour shook. I would go home but for the noise I make: What dreadful Acts we Lovers undertake? Ha! what's that pursues me? a Spright! a Spright! It follows me, I shall be kill'd this Night, Mercy! sweet Spright, mercy! It haunts me yet— Yes 'tis my Shadow: I am blind with Sweat. O whoreson Love! what do I undertake To suffer here, for Leonella's sake! Did but a wandring Child now ask the way, Or harmless Sheep pass by that's gone astray, Were this true Cannon proof, down must it lye, My Sword and all, I should the faster fly. O Death! a Lyon roars, farewell my Friend! Ha! 'tis a Beetle; surely she intends To murther me, else why should I stay here, Like stout Knight-errant, and no Creature near. Now if I could but pray— But how can such poor Rogues as I come to't? When Gentlemen themselves now cannot do't. Enter Sanchez in a Shroud. Sanc. If she were come, 'twould be a pleasant Night; No noise stirring! I'm in a woful fright! All in a clammy sweat; did she not swear, At ten precisely she would meet me here? Well Sanchez! if some Brother Spright should come To scrape Acquaintance, and conduct thee home; Some Lovers meagre Ghost, some crafty Fiend, Should by thy Garb mistake thee for a Friend; Think thee some idle Spirit, and command Thee down to darkness, how could'st thou withstand? Danger from Men, I think I need not fear, I fright my very self—Ha! who's this here? In Arms from head to foot! then I'm betrai'd, Drawn to my Ruine by this wicked Maid. False deluding Woman! is this thy Love? Didst thou not vow to meet me in this Grove? I may steal off, he has not seen me yet— Lar. Fear won't let me pray; Ha! the noise of feet! Oh the Devil! the Devil! Sanch. Where! where! where! [Larasco runs out, and Sanchez after him. Scene 3. Enter Mingo alone. Mingo. 'Tis late, Alonzo does not yet appear; He promis'd faithfully he would be here. I hear him coming— Enter Alonzo. Sir! you are fairly met— This Credit does increase your Servants Debt. Pardon my boldness Sir! before you go, I will discharge part of the Debt I ow. Alon. Honest Mingo! although I cannot guess Thy earnest bus'ness, I believe no less; I will reward thy care, now speak it out— Min. The Story is so strange, that I much doubt Your want of Faith; and wish withall my heart, That I had better tidings to impart. Call all that's Man about you, this will make The strongest of your Resolutions shake. Alon. Thy strange beginning makes me fear the end. Min. Y'are cheated by a Mistriss, and a Friend: They both are false— Alon. Malicious Fool beware: Think not to take me in a jealous Snare. Thou ly'st, ne'r did a Mortal meet with two Such blessings as they are; so kind, so true: Repeat it not again, this I forgive; After a second blasphemy thou shalt not live. Min. So, this is my reward. What will you do? Pray draw upon your Servant, kill me too. Yet I'll pronounce it true, and on your Sword, My loss of life shall justifie my word. This night he takes her with her own consent, Yet trust me not, swear they are innocent: Your Faith's at liberty—Yet go but home, And kill me there, if Fenise does not come. Alon. Take heed! I take thy word; but if he do, I'll kill that faithless Friend, and cherish you. Min. You need not kill him Sir! that's too severe, He may repent it when he meets you there. Remember Sir! his Faith ne'r knew a Crime, Nor wandring thought, till this unhappy time. Will you destroy a Friend so often prov'd, Because your Mistriss has so falsely lov'd? Perhaps the Lady first began to Wooe; 'Tis not so strange, to find their Sex untrue. Alon. No more! th'ast rais'd an Earthquake in my breast, But through his Blood, I know no way to rest. Yet I would spare him, but the Crimes too foul, A strange Convulsion tears my wav'ring Soul: 'Tis but a faithless Woman at the most, She soon was won, and is as quickly lost. Min. He cools too fast, I must renew his heat; This brave Resolve has made you truly great, Perhaps they'l glory in their base success, And call your Mercy stupid Easiness— But let them laugh; your Conscience still is clear. Alon. Friendship be gone! thou hast no int'rest here. Yet, witness Heaven! how unwillingly I take his Life, for He (or I) must dye. 'Tis Honour murthers him, that gilded Air, No other way remains to keep it fair. Min. Pray think again Alon. I've thought too much, away!— Min. Thou wilt repent thy rashness e'r 'tis day. [Aside. Exeunt Alonzo and Mingo. Enter Fenise as watching them. Fen. That base contriving Eunuch leads him on; Well Renegado! we shall meet anon. Ye Gods!— But why should I invoke your partial aid? By whose permission 'tis that I'm betray'd? These little Crimes of perjur'd Love, you slight, That you may punish them— I know your aim, Revenge is your delight. But since you use me thus, I'll seize your right, I will not for your drowzy Justice wait, Ev'n now your Vengeance I'le anticipate. Ezit Fenise with his Sword drawn. Scene 4. A Summer-house in a Garden. Enter Don Manuel alone. Man. In this close Summer-house, I keep my State, And like a Prince, dispose of others Fate. My General stout Mingo takes the care To manage my Affairs of Peace, and War: If any danger springs, from blood that's spilt, I shall the profit reap, and he the guilt. Enter Leonella with a Cabinet. Leon. What mutt'ring voice is that which strikes my Ear? O my unhappy Fate! Don Manuel here! Man. Is your bus'ness to me Lady? Let's see, What have you here? pray spare your modesty; This is too troublesome for you to bear, Deliver up your Charge, and walk in here. Exeunt Manuel and Leonella. Enter Teresa with a Pistol in one hand, and a Dagger in t'other. Ter. Are you so nimble? are your Bloods so hot? Here's Coolers for you—These will marr your Plot. O my dear Mingo! that thou could'st but see, What dangers I despise to merit thee. Exit Teresa after Man. and Leon. Scene 5. Enter Alonzo and Mingo. Min. This way he'll come— Pray Sir! think on the sacred name of Friend, May this sad difference have a happy end. Alon. Ha! here he comes! be gone! by Heav'n 'tis he, My seeming Friend: Good Mingo pardon me; I'll study how to recompence thy care. Min. In your success my pains rewarded are. Exit Mingo, but returns again, watching them with his drawn Sword. Enter Fenise. Fen. O have I found thee Traytor! Alon. Sir no words— Our diffrence hears no Umpire but our Swords. They fight. Min. peeping. Bravely fought Boyes! So, that thrust was home, When one is fall'n, then does bold Mingo come. I'll soon dispatch the other; how, not yet? [Alonzo disarms Fenise. Sure they'r immortal, that was kindly met: Mischief! what damn'd luck have I? his Sword's lost. Fen. O my curst fortune—Truth is ever crost. Alon. Now, if th'hast any thing to say make hast; But know this very Minute is thy last. Fen. Use thy advantage, kill me, do base man! I will have Justice when we meet again: There thou shalt suffer for thy treachery, And that false Woman too for whom I die. Alon. What means this language Sir? did I not wooe Thy Mistriss for thee, and obtain her too? Fen. Must I hear this and live! no way to die! Do'st thou upbraid me with thy Villany? Alon. Thy Crime does in thy ill success appear; Did'st thou not come to meet Rosella here? I knew thy foul intent, I knew it well, What Charms did'st thou imploy? what cursed Spell, To rob me of her Heart? What canst thou say? Fen. Thou kill'st me ten times o're in this delay. Pr'ythee dispatch, lest I some blushes show, To think those Crimes, thou canst not blush to do. Let me not stand a Witness to my shame, Since you, to meet the false Alcinda came. Alon. Then we are both abus'd— Ming. O hellish spight! Yet I'll get something, if the rest hit right. [Exit Mingo. Fen. Abus'd! am I awake? did I not see, When Leonella gave a note to thee? A Letter from Alcinda? and when you Vow'd not to fail, Ha! is not this true? Alon. That very Letter you may here peruse. Fenise takes the Letter and reads it. To Signior Alonzo. My breast is loaded with unhappy News, Which onely in your Ears I dare relate; If you vouchsafe your presence when 'tis late, Conceal it from your Friend, and come alone; Else you will lose, and I shall be undone. Your Slave Mingo. Fen. O subtle Villain! And thou crafty Maid! What have I done? That I should be betraid? I fear this is not all,—sure they intend Some mischief to the Ladies e're it end. Alon. Mingo just parted hence, we may with speed Prevent all danger, 'sdeath how fast you bleed? Forgive my rash belief!— Fen. I must from you The same entreat: But let's the Rogue pursue— Alon. He shall not 'scape, I'm sure he went this way. My fears grow stronger by the least delay. [A Pistol fir'd within. Fen. Ha! a Pistol! I fear we are too late. Alon. We will prevent, or we'll revenge their Fate. [Exeunt Alonzo and Fenise. Scene 6. Enter Manuel wounded. Man. Oh cruel Witch! inhumane Sorceress! I'm pepper'd now for all my wickedness: Incarnate Devil! for my Ruine sent! All Curses Men and Devils can invent, And mine besides, fall on thy bloody Heart— Enter Teresa with a Dagger in her hand, dragging in Leonella. Ter. Come! come along, I'll teach you a new Art To couple; do ye roar in consort now? Dry'd Dog! I was not good enough for you: Would ye be yoak'd? I'll see ye yoak'd, I will, You shall be joyn'd; what are you roaring still? Silence! and hear your heavy Doom: Now Dame! Now bold Hussey! was there no other Game? No Pipe but mine to make you dance? I'll try Who shall be Mistriss now, of you or I. Leon. Dear Madam! O Heav'ns! hear what I can say— Ter. Noble Signior! pray bow your head this way, See your Ven'son quarter'd, and when that's done, With you I'll finish what I have begun. Man. My Royal Donna! dear Teresa hold! I'll be thy Slave— Ter. Poor Fool! thou art too old: In Prayers spend thy time, for 'tis but short, Or curse me if thou wilt, I care not for't. Have at thee— Enter Larasco running in his Armour, and Perez following him in his Shroud. Lar. Oh a Ghost! a Ghost away!— Perez. No Ghost! I am no Ghost! good Neighbors stay— All run off in a fright, Perez pursuing them. Scene 7. Don Manuel's House. Enter Mingo with Bags of Money. Ming. Now Fortune, if thou hast not sworn my fall, Grant me one happy hour, and have at all. The House is yet my own; and here's my Mint— If all my Plots should fail; the Devil's in't. Exit Mingo. Enter Alcinda and Rosella. Alc. Now Madam! does the tedious time draw nigh, When we shall have our long wish'd Liberty. Ros. May this blest Night, like some auspicious Star, Shine bright in Fames Eternal Calendar. May it produce no sad unhappy Birth, But be to all the World a Night of Mirth. Alc. May after times, when they would sum their bliss, Wish happy Dayes, and all their Nights like this. Enter Mingo. Ming. This way, your Servants wonder at your stay— The watchful Cock foretells approaching day. Rosel. Good Mingo! lead the way; how my heart beats? Alc. This little trouble all our joy compleats. What noise is that? [A noise at the dore. Ming. Hell! they have forc'd the dore— Alc. If Fate frown now, I'll never trust it more. Rosel. That noise has made me fear we are undone. Ming. Yet, through this other dore we may be gone. Mingo going out, meets Fenise and Alonzo, with their Swords drawn. Ming. Then to my last shift— [He draws a pair of Pistols. Alon. Sir! y' are fairly met— This favor does encrease your Servants debt. Ming. Not so well met as you imagine yet. Alon. Yes Hell-hound! you are; And ere you part, I will reward your care, Your care to ruin us—thou canst not fly. Ming. If you but stir a foot, they both shall dye. [He presents the Pistols. Fen. Inhuman Dog! Ming. Good words, stand further yet— What I have done, I need not now repeat. I know you'll kill me, but before I dye, I'll make you sharers in my misery. Your Mistrisses shall lead the way: D' ye stare! Their Destinies within my power are; And thus I'll ruine them— Fen. Hold! good Rogue hold! We'll be thy Slaves, thou shalt have Mines of Gold. Ming. A Kingdom shall not buy one hours delay: Yet, to torment you more, a while I'll stay. Alon. Art thou so heartless. and so childish grown, To fight with Women? when this Act is known, Thou wilt be branded with a Cowards name, A fearful Rogue, Art thou so lost to shame? Fen. So lost to policy? For if to mischief th'art so firmly bent, By killing us thou may'st thy death prevent. Ming. That's well advis'd— Rosel. I dare thy sharpest spight, and will not grieve To dye, so my Alonzo may but live. Alc. See what thou doest, thou bloody Devil! do! Min. Seal up your lips, or I'll begin with you. Alc. Brave Villain do! I will requite thy pain, If spight won't make thee shoot, yet do't for gain. Here's Gold and Jewels, if these will not do, I'll call thee Coward; nay I'll curse thee too. Min. No more! I'll quickly end this Generous strife. These Ladies never injur'd me, 'tis true, But I'll kill them, to be reveng'd of you. [He flashes in the pan; and Alonzo and Fenise disarm him. Alon. Thou cruel Rogue! now we'll command thy fate. Min. I will not beg your love, nor fear your hate. Had not my foolish pity staid my hand, My Life had never been at your command. [A great noise within. Rosel. Another Storm begins, ere this is gone. Alc. If 'tis your Father, we are yet undone. Larasco within. For pity's sake let's in, who ere you be. Fen. That's my Rascal's voice. Lar. within. Ay Sir! 'tis me! 'tis me! [Enter Larasco arm'd. Fen. What does this folly mean? Lar. O Sir! as I to meet my Love did go forth, The very Devil follow'd me; and so forth— Enter Manuel, Leonella, Teresa, falling over one another for haste—followed by Sanchez in a Shroud— Alon. What tricks are these? Speak Devil! or I'll kill thee if I can. San. Hold! good Sir hold! I am your very Man. [Pulls off his Shroud. Leon. There's the Original of all this Rout. Ming. Were ever things so crosly brought about? Nay Sir 'tis true; and had my Plots hit right, There had not one of you surviv'd this Night. Rosel. O my dear Father!— Ming. Lady you mistake, nay I'll make you known: Since I am lost, I will not fall alone. He's not your Father, he's a Rogue, a Cheat, He is in nothing, but in Mischief, great. Man. Malicious Rogue! dear Daughter hear him not: He's raving mad now he has miss'd his Plot. Dear Child lead me to Bed, I'm very sick— Ming. To Bed! to th'Gallows; this is a meer trick, To get off— Rosel. Let him not use my Father so— Ming. Madam! he's a Villain, and your mortal Foe. Alon. Mingo speak out, what is it thou canst say? Teres. Damn'd Lyes! mischievous Lyes! lead him away— Ming. Woman hear thy Charge— My Crime's so great, and so prodigious grown, Though I beg pardon, I can hope for none. But when their faults in competition come, Mine are but Cyphers, theirs a total Sum. Had you not Sisters once, whom you think lost? Fen. Nay, more than think, we know that they were drown'd. Ming. Sir? spare your Sighs, the Ladies soon are found. When Don Valasco your brave Father dy'd, You being too young to be your Sisters Guide, Were left with her, to noble Pedro's care, Your honour'd Father Sir— [To Alonzo. Fen. Thou seek'st delayes in Story fetch'd so far. Alon. All this we know, and how my Father strove, To joyn our Families with Bonds of Love. Fen. Then how our Sisters with Don Pedro went, When in Peru he had a Government: We know the time when they took Ship again, But never heard when they return'd to Spain. Ming. The rest I can relate, and mean to do, More in Revenge to them, than Love to you. The Sea mov'd gently, and with flatt'ring Gales, The am'rous Wind did court the flying Sails. But Fate, that knows a thousand paths to Death, Sent a Disease to take your Father's Breath. To Sanchez his old Servant, and a Maid, He left your Sisters, and the Wealth he had; With careful duty, to restore again Their Charge to you, when they return'd to Spain. But in the very Port, they met with one Gorzell, a cruel tatter'd Pickaroon; Sanchez they murther'd, made the rest their prey, And took your Sisters very names away. What they did since is partly known to you, None but themselves know what they meant to do: This is the Villain, that the cursed Maid, By whose infernal Plots they were betrai'd: This Womans names Guttarze, that Mans Gorzell, By whose inhuman hands poor Sanchez fell. And those your Sisters are, those Ladies there! What Heav'n decrees, cannot be alter'd here. Alon. O that we could believe thee— Fen. What say you? Man. and Teres. Mercy! mercy Gentlemen! 'tis too true. Alon. Which is my Sister? which must be my Bride? Teres. Y'have fix'd those Knots your Father long since ty'd; Madam Alcinda, Sir, your Sister is, And you Rosella are Don Fenis's. Fen. Excess of happiness! thy Life's thy own, [To Mingo Dangers so great, so suddenly o'reblown, Make all our joyes like pleasing Dreams appear. Rosel. I cannot look this way without a Tear. Can I see him, I once call'd Father, kneel, And weep to me?— Alc. Methinks I fear him still. Rosel. You shall forgive him— Alon. The greatest Injuries were yours; if you Can pardon them, with all my Heart I do. Fen. But we forget the blackest Crime they did, Although we pardon them, for that they'll bleed. Poor murther'd Sanchez does for Vengeance cry, The Law will seize them, and for that they'll dye. Man. Cruel Woman! had not thy restless Will Urg'd on his death, he had been living still. Ter. Thou foolish Man! why wouldst thou hear me then? Nature allows our Sex less Wit than Men, That you may rule us when we go aside; Had I been govern'd, Sanchez had not dy'd. Rosel. No other wayes to save their lives? pray try. Sanch. Madam! there is, this time they shall not dye. Look on me well, have you not known this Face? Time has not chang'd it much from what it was. Man. 'Tis he! 'tis he! good Sanchez pardon me. Ter. O Sanchez! we confess our cruelty: Pray forgive us— Sanch. May your forgiveness be, From all the World as hearty as from me. Since I have seen my Mistrisses again, No more remembrance of my Wounds remain. Fen. Then you are free, but ere this Sun goes down, We charge ye every one to leave the Town. Alon. Where we reside be never seen again, The Law shall seize ye if we meet in Spain. Ming. Pox o' thy trembling Paw! hadst thou but dy'd, Or done thy work, I had been satisfi'd. Ter. Curse on thy plotting pate, and wheedling tongue, Hadst thou been hang'd we yet had flourish'd long. Leon. Hard-hearted Mingo! wouldst thou murther me? Ming. No pretty Rogue! I was to marry thee. Save your Lordship mighty Manuel hight! And eke your fair La-dee Teresa bright. Great Don! pray shut your Lordly Gate, 'gainst all Of your own Sex; hate ev'rything that's Male. Such tempting trash would make a Saint grow vain: Take heed no smooth face't Eunuch come again— Bezo las mannos Signior! Alon. No more Sanchez I to his former place restore. Let's to the Sacred Temple haste, and pay Glad thanks to Heaven for this happy day. Fen. Let smiling Hymen, with his Nuptial bands, As we have joyn'd our Hearts, unite our Hands. Now all our Doubts and Fears, with joyes are crown'd, Our Cares are lost, and our lost Sisters found. FINIS.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">EPILOGUE Spoken by Mrs. KNEPPE. When Wit, and Native Beauty found Success, Without a daz'ling Scene, or gaudy Dress, Then Playes were good, and wholesom your Amour; But when these downright Blessings pleas'd no more, Poets, from France, fetch'd new Intrigue, and Plot, Kind Women, new French Words, and Fashions got: And finding all French Tricks so much did please, 'T oblige ye more, They got—ev'n their Disease. That too did take—and as much Honour gets As breaking Windows, or not paying Debts. O 'tis so gente! So modish! and so fine! To shrug and cry, Faith Jack! I drink no Wine: For I've a swinging Clap this very time— Poets saw this, and brought their Stages Crimes, Chang'd Comedy to Farce, and Sense to Rimes. That took your very Souls— But now, you are so strangely hum'rous grown, That even these, your dear Regalio's will not down: The newest Miss, with all her little Arts, Sometimes can't soften your obdurate hearts: At other times, you are so far from Pride, A swarthy Gipsie would be deify'd. Then, to your Friends, you tell such horrid Lyes, You had a Pers'n of Honour in disguise! Dam'ee the pretty'st Creature! O such Eyes— No Play without a new Machine will do, Shortly, Your Miss must act with Engine to: For brisk, and pretty, you will cry at last, Can she Curvet? and is she Thorough-pac't? Y'have Fiddle, and Motion now, and all That— 'Zbud! I wonder what a Devil you'd be at. If you persist in these lewd damning wayes, You'll have no more new Misses; nor new Playes.</field>
   </doc>
</add>