<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Denny, William, Sir, 1603-1676</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Denny, William, Sir, 1603-1676</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">denny william sir 1603 1676</field>
      <field name="author_text">Denny, William, Sir, 1603-1676</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1870's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V1.0696.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1870</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:459394</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Greek, Modern (1453- )</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The shepherd's holiday</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The shepherd's holiday</field>
      <field name="title_facet">shepherds holiday</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">shepherds holiday</field>
      <field name="title_text">The shepherd's holiday</field>
      <field name="year_display">1870</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1870</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1870</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459394&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459394&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Denny, William, Sir, 1603 or 4-1676&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;denny william sir 1603 or 4 1676&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The shepherd's holiday&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;shepherds holiday&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1870&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1870&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Denny, William, Sir&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1603&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1676&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The shepherd's holiday&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chiswick Press : - Printed by Whittingham and Wilkins [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1870&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3871923-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv10696&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;gre&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The shepherd's holiday&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 78 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries, introductory and editorial matter omitted.&lt;lb/&gt;Only verse drama included.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: The shepherd's holiday.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Pastoral.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1870.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 1651.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE SHEPHERD'S HOLIDAY.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">To the Virtuous The Lady Kemp, Mrs. Thornton.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Moral. In Dactylon, which is Digitus, a finger, please to receive direction to the whole discourse, as the key to the Cabinet, or Observation of Times and Humours. Wherein taking the habit of a palmer (who is a religious traveller), under that umbrage of gravity he is the fitter to discover dispositions. He lives with old Geron, and is pretended Geron's heir; signifying, that Observation is the pretended heir of Age; but Areton (which is Virtue), that travails, lives abroad, and is active, is the proper inheritor of the goods of Time. That he is the genius of those plains, signifies the intelligence of affairs, which conduceth to observation. Dalon is Titio, a brand that is fired at one end; denoting conjugal love. And, as a brand is lasting, shows constancy of affection. A brand is to set other fuel on fire, burning not well alone; conjugal affection in like manner kindleth each other's chaste flame. That they keep the feast some time after the marriage, is the sobriety of their affection, as well as continuance. The feast is the happiness of each other's enjoyment. The best lamb of their flock is a religious example. Dalon is wisdom. Beta is the second letter of the Greek alphabet. The alphabet deciphers a family. Alpha is Pater-familias, the lord and master. Beta is the lady, mistress, or dame of the house. The other vowels are the children. The rest of the consonants are the servants. And as these joined make proper and distinct significations, so the other, severally employed in œconomical use or household affairs, conduce to general action and benefit. In Beta you may read the understanding. Or, if you please to undraw the curtain, you may behold love, modesty and obedience, and the proper portrait of a wife, who seeks knowledge from wisdom as the husband. The shepherd's bower is the shadow of sober pleasure and contentment. Bilkin is the character of temperance, moderation, discretion and judgment, who, under the shepherd's life, commends innocence of life and retirement from the world. That Bilkin and Vida with Dalon and Beta sit as moderators, shews that Dalon's wisdom and knowledge, Beta's love and modesty, Vida's experience, and Bilkin's discretion, are all conducent to the fair decision of controversy, which cannot be ended till they go to Pega's fountain, which is the root of the cause and the clear evidence of Truth. Vida is experience. Vota intimates virginity, innocence in single life, devotion and contemplation, delighting in freedom, and avoiding marriage, as the commixture with the cares of the world. It signifies also liberty and a desire to command. She is lost in Lover's Maze, that is, amused amidst the passions of the mind. The Lover's Maze represents the world, wherein there are varieties of paths, of temptations, and turnings. Echo is flattery. She finds her company by a song; which is, that consideration does reduce her to herself again, but not without Divine Grace. Her garland is bordered with primrose, signifying timorousness: briar's rose, modesty: sky-coloured virgin's-bower, serenity: violets, gracefulness of look and sweet report: hyacinths, steadiness or constancy, which prevents levity and wantonness: Ros Solis, beauty, youth, comeliness: golden-flower-gentles, courtesy and wariness, resisting temptations: scarlet-Ione silver-pin, comely adornment and convenient portion. Lipsona signifies chaste desire, inclines to a married life, and defends lawful subjection. It is derived from the figure Liptote, which is the shortness of expression according to greatness of matter, and Sonus, a sound: which is the nature of chaste desire, that its modesty is difficult of speech to deliver the largeness of its apprehensions and the greatness of its subject. Her garland of marriage is bordered with marigolds, that is, duty and obedience. The ground is made of pinks, that is, modesty which appears in blushes. It is made of mother-of-time, good housewifery. Much-good specifies virtue: money-wort, a proper portion and reasonable maintenance: all-heal is meekness: angelica, charity: rose-willow, continence: roses, love and piety, which live in the fragrance of their perfumes, and are said to be a medicine for all things: Iris, as named for its various colours from the rainbow, denotes the covenant of matrimony, the mindfulness whereof doth help the convulsion of disorderly passions, and strengthens or confirms resolution, which is the sinews of the mind: asphodels, conjugal love, which allays the inflammation of their breasts, and by its assistance or application cures the pain in the side, which is, heals and helps each other's infirmities: gold-of-pleasure, contentment: gardener's-delight, cheerfulness: and eglantine, confidence. Tompkin shows youth and natural affection and inclination, too much led away with worldly human desires and intemperate passions, in whom you may read such excess of love. Jaclin mentioneth humour and pleasance of wit: a despiser of love. Sylvans are rustic neighbourhood, that frolic it at solemnities. Geron is Age or Time. Pega shadows out Truth. As springs rise from underground, so truth, though some time in obscurity, at last appeareth as clear as those springs, flowing continually. Pega appears by invocation, and the light of truth is obtained from the Divine Hand by prayer. Pega is a fountain. She is a virgin for her purity, yet married to Cumathalas, a Triton of the seas. ???? is Unda, a wave; ???????? MS. reads ????????. is Mare, the sea. She is married to a wave of the sea, that is, subject to be tossed and tumbled up and down the wide ocean of error and sea of the world. Cumathalas is a favourite to Ops, because the earth receives the waters into her bosom through her many caverns. Cumathalas warms her with embraces, both in respect of the saltness of the water, coming first from sea, and that troubles seem to make Truth appear the more lively. By this time, ladies, I have led you a long walk. Tis time to rest you, and for me to kiss your hands with my best wishes, and with most cordial thanks to render you acknowledgment for all your noble favours to Your most obliged friend and humble servant, Wm. Denny. June 1, 1651.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">A Palmer. Look not with wand'ring eyes to find Such pleasures here, as spot the mind, Nor in the shining dish to see A costly surfeit's cookery. No! Harmless shepherds do not ken The dark-born vice of other men. Here friendly Bilkin shows the way, As maps do veinèd lands portray. Sweet innocence unsoil'd by strife, He pencils in the shepherd's life. But lest this swain disturbèd be, I'll make a curtain of this tree. [Palmer withdraws behind a tree. Bilkin enters, and takes a seat under the side of the grove called Lovers' Maze. Birds singing. This is the seat of sweet repose for swains, Back'd with a grove, and faced with smoothèd plains. This boscarie of souls, the Lovers' Maze, With music gives new birth to dawning days. Hark! every spray tunes forth a various note; While all concording seem one warbling throat. Thus as they all together sing and vie, Each wins, each loses, the supremacy. So azure heaven, with thin clouds chamleted, Which borrow scarlet from Sol's rising head, Who gilds Aurora's blushes that do play And dance upon her cheeks, to sport the day. Rest on this green silk shag of camomil; Now thou'rt an emperor upon this hill. Thy crown excelleth that of beaten gold: Sweet-briar's rose, flower'd eglantine, behold, Which, twining o'er thy head, show forth their gems: Their fragrant lustre outshines diadems. Rest here thy undisturbèd limbs. Here rest In contemplation of a life most blest. Happy, thrice happy shepherds, that do dwell Clothèd with russet in a lowly cell. Our frequent vigils 'mint us hours to pray; Accosting heaven, when we salute the day, When freely we unfold our spreading sheep, Observing stepping time, and them to keep. Our loneliness is clept philosophy, By which we read th'Almighty's power on high: Sun, moon and stars, placed in the lofty sphere, Are the bright almanacs for day and year; Those flaming torches we y-clepe by names— Custom han made us kin unto their flames. Is't not a wise man's part to guard the flocks From rage of cruel wolf or wily fox? The lambs do skip, while pipes their dams allure; More than physicians, shepherds safely cure. Our chaste-hatch'd love is warm'd by pure desire, Our shame-fac't embers kindle modest fire, Which mind-enchanting songs do quickly turn To rising flames, that constancy makes burn. Our friendship kens ne fraud ne subtile saw; Our blameless life is to itself a law. We seldom spend, for well we know to spare: Our sleep is sound, 'tis back to back to care. Our beds are softer than those nests of down, Content's best riches: a good name, renown. A peaceful conscience sings within the breast, Which gain'd, no labour but enjoyeth rest. Ne list we what is envy's venom'd dart, Ne con we pride, that fills with barm the heart. Our seldomness of feasts does whet our joy, And easy dainties do no health destroy. Our comely sports, shown unto freedom's eye, Do lovely innocence to sweetness tie. But wethers' bells do ring. Time wings each hour To Dalon's feast: flocks drive to th'shepherds' bower: Dalon and Beta, of the lovely lay, Your marriage makes our feast, this holiday. The world to this our unknown bliss is but a gay:— I mon away. [Exit. The Palmer appears again. O giddy, stormy course of times, That muffle truths of shepherds' rhymes! O the unsteady state of things! The world has talons, as 't has wings. As Bilkin lined your ears with lays That made all night but shepherds' days, Now Dalon kind, sweet Beta, see A Duo here is harmony. Their love those parts does make but one, Which so becomes an unison. Old Custom's in their garments drest, Who married last must heyne the feast. Mark you the rest. [He withdraws again upon the other side of the stage. Dalon. Beta. Dalon. The glorious day puts on his golden dress, Beta. The more to show the world our happiness. Dalon. My lovely Beta, thou like it dost shine; Beta. I have no splendour, but what first was thine. Dalon. Nor have I mind to darken thy fair story; Beta. Nor can my heart diminish ought thy glory. Dalon. Then since w'are both in one, one love we live. Beta. Then since w'are one in both, love life we give— Dalon. Till fate shall both divide, so knit in one; Beta. Till unkind destiny leaves either none. Dalon. But may not Fortune's frown the knot untie? Beta. Death sure must cut the thread that both live by. Dalon. Is love and life, then, twisted in one thread? Beta. The riddle's known: its sense is ever hid. Dalon. Then all our love is a still-slowing bliss. Beta. Then all our life a new enjoyment is. Dalon. Blest bodies, Beta, that do thus inarm! Beta. Blest minds, dear Dalon, that have such a charm! Dalon. Thou know'st, my love, the custom of the day. Beta. Our guests will come, and we must haste away. Dalon. Others have busier parts to sing and play. Beta. The question and the disputants, I pray? Dalon. My love, Th'ast heard, and partly know'st, that on these plains Old customs live as well as youthful swains. Customs are rules that lines of life do draw, Which 'mongst us shepherds stand instead of law The Feast of Rites upon this Ide of May Our living books ordain a holiday, Wherein the couple, youngest and last wed, At Shepherd's Bower the garnish'd cloth shall spread, And on the turfy table with the best Of lambs in all their flock shall heyne the feast, Which neighb'ring swains and lasses of next place Shall, present, with due ceremonies grace; 'Mongst which, two youths, two maids, of equal years To th'bride and bridegroom, chosen by their peers, Shall 'bout a question by their songs contend, Two moderators are the cause to end. Of each sex one: one youth, one maid maintain, While their two like do cross the same again. Each virgin brings a garland of device, Which near the bower on poplar riband ties: To highest worth, as moderators see, Are given these garland-signs of victory. But if their equal merits so divide That neither moderator can decide, Then in procession to the holy grove At Pega's fount they seek for what they strove: Where, rites perform'd, the nymph invoked does show Who best deserves, as they desire to know. Vota, nice Vota is the challenger, And jolting Jachin's second unto her; While bright Lipsona sings the counterpart, Tomkin keeps time with his true-beating heart; Vida discreet, the widow like a maid, And Bilkin, are the moderators said. But for the question, that suits not my tongue, Nor is it fit you know, except you long. Beta. My busy thoughts caused me too much enquire. Dalon. Come, Beta, thou shalt soon have thy desire. [Exeunt. The Palmer appears again. No knot so fast as that which ties Lovers by hearts and not by eyes; Nor is there such a constant fire As kindled by a pure desire. Blest they whose sense such warmth does know, As from a flame of burning snow! In furnace so the crystal shows Transparent clearness as it glows: Such love grows ever, never dies This phœnix does from ashes rise. 'Tis spicy incense, that by turns The fuel is and flame that burns. So sweet a hand has virtue's power, As turns the glass from hour to hour, That when the sand of one has done, It makes the other freshly run. Blest peers, that thus given moments pass, Till Time from's hand lets fall the glass. Lipsona, Vota, Vida, see, Coming for flowers. I'll to my tree. [He withdraws again. Vida, Lipsona, Vota. Vida. At last our nimble-moving feet do gain This grove, whose height does seem to top the plain. Vota. How properly the swains of former days Have called this musing place the Lovers' Maze! Lipsona. This is the place that lovers so much fame, Whose changeable delights do suit its name. Vida. This way, Lipsona! [Vida turns off Lipsona from Vota. Vota. Guard me, pure thoughts! what sudden turning's here? Lipsona! Echo. O nay! [Vota.] Vida! Echo. Heyda! [Vota.] Are no spirits near? Echo. Here. Lipsona (aloud). If chanting birds affright you, there they play. Echo. Play. Vida (aloud). 'Tis fit and pleasant now to lose your way. Echo. Your way. Vota. What mock-soul art thou, that dost haunt this place? Art thou an evil genius, or some Grace? Echo. Some Grace. Vota. Some Grace? Then guide my hand to crop each choicest flower, The fancy shall be mine, the favour your. Echo. Or your. Be primrose peerless garland's border then. Why look'st so pale? Dost fear the sight of men? Vota. My ground be blushes of sweet-briar's rose, While letters for my word I thus dispose: VIRGINITIE Purple-blue virgin's bower compose a Gemmed with sweet violets of purple hue. Blue-flower'd iacinths neigh'bring these work 'Gainst falling sickness does your virtue lie. Ros solis, sun-dew, youth-wort, all one These in my circle be another star. Golden-flower-gentles, now enweave a Resisting belly-worms, you physic be. Scarlet-Ione-silverpin in next place Do in its comely rank in doubles tie Incarnate Lady's-navel form an Seldom in woods, on walls most found by men. Of yellow jasmine, of the white an For rheums and swellings artists these apply. White Traveller's Joy may now be flowered Who have their plumes to prank their climbing tree. Imperial lilies' steepled bells next Your yellowish-purple-streakèd beauties tie. White eyebright's yellow-purple specks an Which sight preserve, and make the dim to see. Thus my device in garland gay made good, I'll seek my company within the wood. [Vota wanders. Lipsona. See, Vida, the variety of flowers In ranks do light us unto several bowers. Each seems in love with other, and does cast An amorous glance upon its fair next plac't. So all together, dazzling pleasure's eye, Do look like glistering stars in a green sky. Vida. The place has robbed thy memory of time, While I by song delight thee with my rhyme, Select thou gather'd flowers, thy garland make; So thou my fancy shalt, I thine, partake. Lipsona. Thanks, woo thy song to wed to my desire. Vida. Tire you your fingers, I thine ear will tire. Vida's song. This is the place where night does cosen day, Where love does play; This is the place where glimm'ring light Does search for shades, Cool daughters of the night; Where pleasure's won, while she each sense invades. Here please your fancies, choose your bowers; Here lose in by-paths wasting hours. Be charmed here with each musician's note And warbling throat; Here curious lovers nicely choose 'Mongst beauties rare, With cunning judgment lose, And pass by truer for a brighter fair. So in a labyrinth your blaze Shall lead you wild in Lover's Maze. Lipsona. With golden fringe of marigolds I make My garland's hem: then flowers for letters take; And on the ground of pinks, which blush forth grace, Each proper flower I to its letter place. MARRIAGE Mother-of-Time's sweet flowers be a fair Much-good's and Money-wort's gilt mixed with them. White-spotted purple hoods of All-heal Mixed with white and great angelica. Greenish rose-willow's flowers, that cooling Refreshing sick folks with their doubled star. Then blushing roses good for all things To loose, bind, sleep, they medicines prepare. The various iris makes a rainbow These cramps help, joints and sinews fortify. White asphodels compose another Inflam'd breasts curing, side's pain drive away. White little flowers dress Gold-of-pleasures Gardener's-delight with these entwinèd be. Sweet eglantine befriend me for an Now, Vida, my trimmed garland finished see. Vida. I do by this as in a picture find Thine arguments portrayèd in thy mind. Lipsona. And by thy song thy thoughts I well may guess, What was delight is not now happiness. Vida. Then try thy pleasant breast: sing thou a lay, We'll then seek Vota, and make haste away. Lipsona's song. I. Beauty late did seem to stray, Love o'ertook, and bade good-day. Leads not this (Does Beauty say) Unto bliss I pray? Not so, sweet lass; thou'st lost thy way. 2. This is too strait. Go through that grove, Thy steps then winding move To the left, then the right, Until thou meet a wight: Listen to him, and him obey. He'll teach thee, where that bliss thou seek'st does lay. She after that does mend her pace, And finds the man in Lovers' Maze. Vida. Ha, ha, ha! This was a merry note. Vota. At last you're found by fortune and your song. Vida. Her heart is light, and dwells upon her tongue. Lipsona. You raise my blushes for a harmless air. Vida. Let's home. Such blushes make you look more fair. Vota. Unto the Shepherds' Bower let's then repair. [Exeunt. The Palmer. The various sorts of humours be As several fruits upon one tree. And passions in their diverse kind Do chequer fancies in the mind. So poets [are] said to represent Things as if done, though only meant. But if Brains should questions move About our flowers, about our grove, They needs must know that every place Bears not such plants as Lovers' Maze. Where winding paths and twinèd bowers, Sweet singing birds and springing flowers, Are the describers of such passion, As lovers most account in fashion. Which further still shall be descried In those come now. Wink you. I hide. [Exit. The scene alters, shewing Jaclin laid asleep under willows by a brook, the waters making a noise within. Tomkin comes thither, finds him, and lies down not far from him. Tomkin. This was the place, where late my two blest eyes Lipsona saw—Lipsona, beauty's prize. Her folded garments here, the ground did kiss, Entranc't with the joy'd sense of present bliss. See! where she sat, the grass more livelier shews, And, as it were enriched, it thicker grows. So rarely sang she to the gliding stream, That the scarce-moving waters seem'd to dream; Which, as they in their shallow bottoms crept, Made noise as if they talked, the while they slept. Ah, woful willows! you do shew to me, As if her absence gave your livery. How pleasantly her flock did round her feed, Now cropping grass, and then to her gave heed! Conceiving sure their nourishment did lie, Not in the fresh green grass, but in her eye. How prettily the lambs did sport and play! Before their saint they must keep holiday. Profane not then this, by her hallowed, ground! Some less regarded place is better found, Which neighbours this, so little way from hence That, lying down, I may pay reverence. [He lies down and museth. Jaclin awakes. Jaclin [aside]. 'Tis Tomkin, with his noddle full of love, Has waked me; but I will not seem to move. So shall I hear the gambols of his mind, The strange expressions of one overkind. Methought I heard him in his former fits. See! Now cross-armed, as if transformed, he sits. Heaven guard his wits! Tomkin. She answered sweetly though. How's that? her tongue Was above speech. 'Twas harmony; she sung Honour is virtue's meed. E'en all must give Obedience to true love's prerogative. If so, thy constant faith, when well surveyed, Will claim from her reward, which must be paid. Jaclin. What wand'ring fancies do this wild man feed? Sure he no other company does need. [Aside. Tomkin. But, O, my struggling heart in stifling breast! Where, Tomkin, is the pillow of thy rest? Is it Lipsona? Then, why dost complain? She quits not service with unjust disdain. I feel yet something in me burns like fire; It can't be jealousy; 'tmust be desire. Sometimes I'm anguish all with shudd'ring fear Of something that I cannot make appear. Jaclin. Alack-a-day! What pity 'tis to see Reason o'erweighed by so much foolery! [Aside. Tomkin. And now my rising hope does fear destroy; My cap'ring heart does seem to leap for joy. Poor Jaclin there?— Jaclin. I'm near. Tomkin. Thou ligst in senseless sleep, And in love's music ken'st no time to keep. Thy drowsiness has all benumb'd thy head, And turn'd thy life into a lump of lead. Thou canst not taste the sweets of lover's bliss: 'Twere somewhat, if thou knew'st but what it is; Which, if th'ast any life, my pipe and tongue Shall let thee know. I'll try thee with my song. Tomkin's song. When winged darts more swift than wind, Made of each thought That liking caught Through eyes b' each love-drawn mind; At first the dart Does pierce the heart Till th'one th'other's cure's assigned; Then either sends a ray To t'other's bright'ning day, And joys alike of both in one them bind. Such happy and untasting bliss, When minds do kiss, And bodies know not what it is, Is true love's paradise, But hard to find. Thus minds do minds embrace, And hearts do change their place. So winds winds meet With motion fleet: Unbodied essences do twine By subtlety so fine That, angel-like, in joy and bliss they join. Jaclin seems to awake. Jaclin. Heigho! Riddle me, riddle me, what's this? Why, Tomkin! Here's a wild-goose chase, I wis. Tomkin. Dull Jaclin! Could thy thoughts in love's world land, Thou then its unknown wealth might understand. If that be true, that I've heard seamen say, Who sails too far may soon be cast away. Jaclin. But, Tomkin, where didst meet such skill? Tomkin. The eyes Of shepherds plain may see such mysteries; This doctrine Cupid brought upon his wings, And scatterèd as news of heavenly things. Jaclin. Cupid? What's that, which so has wings, you say? Is it an owl by night, or kite by day? Tomkin. Thy talk, vain Jaclin, 's like thy too weak skill: Such things as these no empty brains do fill. Jaclin. Full oft th'unkenning swain words misapplies, And call those mysteries for mists-arise. Tomkin. Such quibblings, witness-like, do plainly prove Thy scorn proceeds from ignorance of love. Jaclin. For your sake, friend, methinks I love advance, For now I fall in love with ignorance. But see! Sol's lofty coursers climb mid-day: We shall come late to th'Shepherds' Bower. Away! [Exeunt. The Palmer. Such change have minds, as oft you see In spring-born April-days to be Now is one gilded all with rays, Till a thick cloud its black displays; Then what did shine so bright before, Is bye-and-bye dark-mantled o'er. The winds rise, [and] the cloud does strain Vapour-filled sponges into rain. Or as the lover's faining dreams Conceive, cold mouldeth pearly gems. When reason does dispose the air, Then looks the mind most clear, most fair. But when the passions get above, There riseth then that storm of love Which, as their heat or cold prevail, Revel[s] in showers or pour[s] down hail. O aguish wildness of desire, Sometimes as ice, and sometimes fire! Fear-shudd'ring chill and lifeless fit Has burning hope succeeding it. But when a temper comes between, In the even mean is virtue seen. Now th'undrawn [curtain] does disclose What has lain hid in former shows. The flock, that far off did appear All day, at even to th'fold draws near. So travellers their pace do mend, When they come towards their journey's end. [Exit. Enter Dalon and Beta with chaplets of Myrtle set with Roses upon their heads, handing a basket of provisions and bottles. Then Tomkin follows Jaclin with a Horn-pipe in his hand, and with him Vota with her Garland on her arm, seeming merrily discoursing. Then Tomkin with a Recorder in his hand, as courting Lipsona with a Garland in her hand. Then Bilkin, as soberly discoursing with Vida. While Music plays, they change the Scene thrice. The basket is left within at the first round. Dalon and Beta take their seats upon the grassy bank before the Bower, while the Shepherdesses, Vida in the midst, cast themselves into a rank. Jaclin on the right hand a little advanced, and Tomkin on the left, facing the Bower. Bilkin standing before them. Bilkin. Most lovely pair, to whom so friendly fate Has full contentment given in married state, May it grow ever fresh, never be out of date! Jaclin. May all your minutes smile forth merriment, And may you ne'er, as oft betides, repent. Tomkin. May you ne'er wish for more than you possess, In your embrace enclasping happiness. This is the glorious and the solemn day, In which this tribute to your rites we pay. Vota. This is the custom of the Shepherds' Bower, To frolic in the sunshine you call your. Lipsona. This is our joy (O best of joys!), to sing Unto your May notes suiting such a spring. Dalon. Welcome, kind swains and shepherdesses fair, May you like bliss enjoy! may your joys pair. Beta. And in due thankfulness for these your pains. May all your hopeful labours turn to gains. Dalon. Rest now your courteous limbs on proper place, And try whose song shall bear away the grace; Friend Bilkin and Vida wise, It 'longs to you to moderate the case. Bilkin and Vida place themselves on either side of Dalon and Beta. Vida on the right. Upon the right side of the stage on a Flower-strewed Hurdle sits Vota, upon Jaclin's right hand. Bilkin on the left. Upon the left side of the stage sits Lipsona, as the other, upon Tomkin's right hand. Two Nymphs arise on either side of the Stage, behind the Hurdles; one with a Lute behind Vota, the other with a Theorbo behind Lipsona. 1 Nymph. Thus hither come, we from our springs do rise, Being sent for news to these solemnities. 2 Nymph. Pega, bright lady of the holy grove, Commands us grace this feast of shepherds' love; And her musicians under ground must play, The more to honour this their holiday. Vota's song for Virginity. 1. The feather'd snow so white, When touch'd its candour fades away; The ruddy blushes of the morning's light Like not bold looks of the broad-facèd day; Rose-sweets in buds are dight: Then where does lie Whiteness, beauty, sweetness, but in virginity? 2. Clear pureness would ye find In harmless innocence to know? Would you attain a body like a mind? Without care would you business show, Or freedom have right-lined? Then cast your eye, And in fair print read all in blest virginity. 3. Which better to command Or with servility obey, Would choose 'fore a bright flame a burning brand? Hadst rather fall than stand? Ah no! O fie! Sense would, but Reason must, prefer virginity. Lipsona's song for Marriage. 1. Tell me but how the world began; Was't peopled by one maid or man? Or why does nature draw By its own secret force, and move? Ordaining such a law Of adamant, that we must love? 'Twas marriage, sure, Heaven first in hearts did write, That our ripe years might read at the first sight. 2. Make a third sex! for, if but two, Nature will find a way to woo: Or, if you two divide, Society dwells not alone: One will not so reside; But two will come to one. 'Tis marriage, sure, that ties by hand divine Our heart-strings, in true love-knots fast to join. 3. Is marriage good to all, or none? If unto none, then nature's gone: But if affirm'd to all, Pray, tell me, what will then become, If any nicely shall Change rules to take a single room? To marriage, then, w'are led by pointing sense, By reason more, to give pre-eminence. Tomkin's reply for Marriage. 1. What loss to lily-snow When touched, if turn'd to crystal clear? More bright than morning's fading blushes show Sun's gilding, spreading everywhere. Rose-sweets when blown we know. Then where does lie What's clear, fair, sweet? In marriage or virginity? 2. If innocence you'd find In chastity, behold the dove; The wife-like body's wedded to the mind: Not care their business is, but love: In yoke is freedom kind. Then cast your eye; All these in marriage read, not in virginity. 3. Is't best that one command, Or in sweet fellowship they sway? A flame's from number'd sticks, when one's a brand; Flowers gather'd keep, on stalks decay; 'Tis better sit, than stand. Then do not try By sense and reason to prefer virginity. Jaclin's reply for Virginity. 1. And if thou needs first time wouldst span, Product of all was but one man: Corruption then did draw Abused nature forced to move; If virtue did not awe, We should be led by lust, not love; For that does give a clear and single light, One sun the day does rule, one moon the night. 2. What need[s] third sex? Enough are two; And let them vow, they ne'er shall woo; So two will two abide. Sweet contemplation dwells alone, And while that that is guide, Free bliss companion's to each one. Not marriage then, virginity's divine: That ties to flesh, this unto Heaven does join. 3. Marriage nor good to all, nor none; But unto such can't live alone: Or if that all must wed, Pray what would then of all become! Our life would keep its bed. Our burial's next in living tomb. Then let virginity abandon sense, And take by reason the pre-eminence. [Nymphs descend. Dalon. The pleased powers have deign'd to grace our joys: Now, moderators, we attend your judgment's voice. Bilkin. Ye smooth contenders 'bout a weighty cause! A cause so weighty as the ground of laws: A cause so high that in this friendly strife Consists the happiness of human life. Virginity and marriage are in scale, Which both sides have maintained with fairest tale. So sweetly Vota tunes her pleasing song, And has of such clear instances a throng, That 'tis not easy to withstand her tongue. So fully in rare strains Lipsona's note Does charm, as with her reason makes sense dote, And as on streams, on arguments does float. Tomkin refutes what Vota does maintain; Raising his wit, he shows his strength of brain, And so leads captive every list'ning swain. Jaclin with all his force does make reply, Rasing out marriage with virginity: Then of his mind seem all the sitters by. What maze is this? Tell, whither shall I turn? [Bilkin speaks to Vota. Partake your snow? [Then to Lipsona. Or take your fire to burn? See, how both ways unkindly rhet'ric draws, That 'fore decision you have split a cause. Your argument to contraries so tends, It seems 'bove human art to make you friends, Which, which way shall I take? This, or that side? [He turns to either side. Marriage by th'hand, or virgin-life for guide? Lend me for candour your pure whitening snow; [To Vota. For clearness, pray lend me your crystal too. [To Lipsona. Lend modest blushes of the morning's light, [To Vota. Nor keep back your sun's rays to gild the right. [To Lipsona. Lend me your rosy buds to tip my tongue, [To Vota. And let them blow, when I discourse your song. [To Lipsona. Virginity pure innocence does love, [To Vota. The like (says Marriage) builds with the chaste dove. [To Tomkin. You free a body would have, like a mind: [To Vota. (Says he), that body she shall wedded find. [To Tomkin. You speak of single business, void of care: [To Vota. He that love's the chief business of a pair. [To Tomkin. You freedom do commend in a right line, [To Vota. He to the circling yoke does freedom join. [To Tomkin. You love command, call 't servile to obey, [To Vota. And he does place in fellowship the sway. [To Tomkin. You hint a flame more worthy than a brand; [To Vota. He them transposes with his art's command. [To Tomkin. You praise the fresh green grass, not changed hay; [To Vota. Flowers gather'd keep, unpluck'd they die, you say. [To Tomkin. Your high esteem holds better stand than fall: [To Vota. The better he to sit than stand doth call. [To Tomkin. Would you, Lipsona, know [how] th'world began; [To Lipsona. All's product, Jaclin says, was but one man. [To Jaclin. And if you urge that nature made a law [To Lipsona. Of adamantine love, forced hearts to draw, Nature's corruption Jaclin that does prove: [To Jaclin. If virtue were not, 'twere more lust than love. Think you, that if but sexes two there be, [To Lipsona. They will together for society? No third sex needs, says Jaclin, if a vow [To Jaclin. For mate bliss contemplation doth allow. You nature give as lost, if married none; [To Lipsona. He grants them marriage, that can't live alone. [To Jaclin. If all must marry, then you stand upon [To Lipsona. That to that rule there's no exception. He thinks them dead to all, if matched to one. [To Jaclin. Each for their cause so subtly do defend, And to their art such strength, such forces, bend, I find this only: ravelled reason has no end. Vida. Ye comely swains and lovely lasses, sent As from some schools to bandy argument, So excellently wit has wrestling tried, That victory inclines to either side. So have I seen an unresolvèd brook First to that mead run, then to this to look, As if each several beauty so o'erpowers By the temptation of their various flowers; And in his turning bouts thus oft did stray, Unable to decide, then slipt away. So fares my judgment in this argued case; First reason takes, till t'other gains the place; That my experience and best judging wit Do find aim's spoil'd, when I the mark would hit. Wherefore since favouring custom now doth move, 'Tis best to bend our steps to th'holy grove, Invoking Pega from her truth-like spring To clear the point that you so well did sing. For sure those nymphs, her messengers, did come To give her hints so to prepare her doom. Dalon. In order, then, first let each welcome guest Partake the freedom of the present feast; And after such refreshing we'll all go With rev'rent steps to Pega's fount to know. The Scene opens, and discovers a Round Table with Provisions within the Shepherds' Bower, where they take their seats. Enter Palmer. Thus like a palmer being drest I do accost the shepherds' feast. Though in this strange uncouth disguise I seem to cozen others' eyes, This habit sometimes do I own To keep myself from being known. So I observe each form, each face, Each pranking humour of the place. I Genius am unto these plains, Where sometimes sport I with these swains. Then Dactylon, a shepherd, am, That live with Geron, old and lame. His flock with care and keep I tend, Am voiced his heir, though for my friend, His nephew hight, now in disgrace And wander'd hence, I take his place: Famed Areton, beloved of all, Of lovely mind and stature tall. But sprightly youth and age, I see, Are seld' so fortunate t'agree. Then thus, my case, I cast thee by; [He puts off Palmer's Gown. And take my crook, that here doth lie. [Takes his Crook. Thus in fit time I seem new drest. All happiness betide your feast! Dalon. What! Dactylon! Where hast thou wand'ring been? That th'hast the pleasure of this day not seen? Dactylon. You ken, sire Geron being all cramped and cold, 'Tis I mon care for him, his flock and fold. Dalon. Then happy now, partake our feast, our fare; Beta. And in our mirth take you your welcome share. Dactylon. Thanks, gracious Beta. As I passed woods, I heard some sylvans say To your famed feast they would some music pay; And lo! they're here. Enter six Sylvans as in Masquerade thus: Three on the one side of the Stage, three on the other side of the Stage. All facing inward as their leading man. One of either three standing somewhat forward. The two of either side place themselves some reasonable distance behind their leading man. The Festival Song. 1 Sylvan. Tune your desires unto the charming spring! 2 Sylvan. Let hearts keep time, while Love doth sing. 3 Sylvan. Let fancy nimbly dance! 4 Sylvan. Come choristers, away! 5 Sylvan. While each sense pleasure does entrance; 6 Sylvan. And all the nymphs on silver strings now play. Chorus. Fair virgins, bring flowers, And strew your made bowers: This is the shepherds' holiday, This is the shepherds' holiday. 2 Sylvan. Whistle, boxen-bill'd blackbird, on the top 1 Sylvan. Of the tree; 4 Sylvan. Jenny wren, at the foot 3 Sylvan. Of the melancholy root; 6 Sylvan. Let it hop, 5 Sylvan. And sing forth its glee. 3 Sylvan. Let the warbling thrush 2 Sylvan. On the quavering rush, 1 Sylvan. And the lark on the spray; Chorus. While virgins bring flowers, And strew their made bowers: This is the shepherds' holiday, This is the shepherds' holiday. 3 Sylvan. Sweet robin redbreast, with changeable note, 1 Sylvan. And linnet so shrill, 4 Sylvan. Rare Philomel, come, with thy ravishing throat, 2 Sylvan. Songs melting distil. 5 Sylvan. Be not forlorn, 6 Sylvan. Nor fear threat'ning thorn. 1 Sylvan. With chirping finches sing all, it is May. Chorus. While virgins bring flowers, And strew their made bowers: This is the shepherds' holiday, This is the shepherds' holiday. They dance. [Exeunt. Dalon. Take now your garlands from th'appointed place: With order'd steps to th'holy grove let's pace, While the declining sun makes haste to end his race. [Exeunt omnes, manente Dactylon. Dactylon. Geron, I come. Mishap may chance by stay; For time and fate admit of no delay. [Exit. Geron with a Stilt under one arm. Cold crazy age in every joint doen reel, I all the weader of the welkin feel. My mickle time han likewise mickle pain. Be not youth coy, I wis? Won't come again? O youth! brimful of sprite and wanton guise! With cap'ring shoon and giddy rolling eyes! O youth! that praten more than wisdom's child! Thou mon been eld as I, though now so wild! Fond Areton han left mine homely pen, And ta'en his leap among a world of men, Where he mon see devices, hear their saws. He tattled Virtue been him thus that draws. Ah fou! Been not the shepherd's flock and fold Anough of place and company to hold? But thou mon wander every where so wide? Fou! Take thy run! Ch'ave got another guide, Ycleped Dactylon, a subtler lad; He kens full well to keep, but ne to gad. Ch'am wondred though, that he so long doen stay— None mar'le: this been our sheep-folks' holiday. But I mun to my cot. Ah! Death's before! Full sick I feel; my bed mon be my shore. Come, Dactylon! Feare fayne, I won abroad ne more; Ay, fall in, and shut the door. [Exit. Tomkin. Jaclin. Bilkin. Handing the Garlands. Vida. Vota. Lipsona. Dalon. Beta. The Scene opens and shows a Fountain, &amp;c. They pace round the place before the Fountain. Bilkin singing. Thrice does our comely order pace The flowery carpet of this place; The swains and lasses, as in rank, Do tread a circle on this bank. Chorus. Thrice bend we, and with voices sing A sweet salute to Pega's spring. Thrice we, by custom guided all, Thee from thy privy chamber call, And through thy gelid galleries, All hung with 'stilling gems like ice. Chorus. Thrice we invoke our nymph to rise, Clepe, Pega! Pega! Pega! thrice. Pega appears. Upon thy golden shore we lay [They lay down the garlands before her. Th'enamell'd question of the day. Questions are fast-run knots of sense: Solve ours by thine intelligence: And, as the crystal does appear, So let thy judgment be as clear. Pega speaks. Kind lads, fair lasses, that are come (I know your custom) for your doom, Th'occasion that you hither draws, Your witty arguments and cause. Know therefore, I, whom you attend, Am unto either equal friend. I virgin am and married both, Am free, and yet have plighted troth. For in my cloisters, all of stone, I seem to lead a life alone; And yet a Triton nightly warms My pure embraces in his arms: Cumathalas my dear he hight, That is to Ops a favourite; And in solemnities does sport At revels in high Neptune's court; And in the light a maid I play On pavèd paths and golden way. Wherefore 'tis I can best relate The best condition of each state: Or single or the married life: Which seemeth best, the maid or wife. Reason, queen-regent of the mind, Gives praise to both, to both is kind, But in the highest way of sense Hands marriage to pre-eminence. For how should virgins ever be? Expect you fruit without a tree, Whose blossoms sweetly seem to show, But give to fruit the place they owe? Love-pair'd defendants, unto you The glory of the day is due: She puts the Marriage Garland upon Tomkin's and Lipsona's arms. Whom with this garland I encharm, As with my streams each circled arm, And in this flowery compass bind Knit arms to an united mind, And that thy virtue, Vota, may Not lose reward, thy flowers so gay I'll plant upon my verdant banks, And water oft their growing ranks. So shall thy memory appear In their renewing every year. Virginity my nosegay be: Marriage decks you with chastity! But hear you not Nereides? I must haste down, descend MS. reads to send. to seas. She descends. Lipsona. And we, obeying thy behest, Shall be th'occasion of next feast. Home. Fold. And rest. [Exeunt.</field>
   </doc>
</add>