<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Enprynted by me Wynkyn de Worde</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Enprynted by me Wynkyn de Worde</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">enprynted by me wynkyn de worde</field>
      <field name="author_text">Enprynted by me Wynkyn de Worde</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">16th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V1.0537.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">[c.1515]</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:459255</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Hyckescorner</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- Early modern and Elizabethan, 1500-1600</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- Early modern and Elizabethan, 1500-1600</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Hyckescorner</field>
      <field name="title_facet">hyckescorner</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">hyckescorner</field>
      <field name="title_text">Hyckescorner</field>
      <field name="year_display">[c.1515]</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1515</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1515</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459255&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459255&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Hyckescorner&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;hyckescorner&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;[c.1515]&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1515&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Hyckescorner&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Enprynted by me Wynkyn de Worde&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;[c.1515]&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3873447-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv10537&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- Early modern and Elizabethan, 1500-1600&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;Early modern and Elizabethan, 1500-1600&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Hyckescorner&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 69 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Moralities.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Hyckescorner.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Moralities.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1515 ?</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 1513–1516 ?&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Hyckescorner.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Pyte. Now Ih? ye gentyll yt bought Adam fro hell Saue you all soueraynes &amp; solas you sende And or this mater that I begynne to tell I praye you of audyence tyll I haue made an ende For I saye to you my name is pyte That euer yet hath ben mannes frende In the bosome of the seconde persone in trynyte I sprange as a plante mannes mysse to amende You for to helpe I put to my honde Recorde I take of mary that wepte teres of blode I pyte within her herte dyde stonde whan she sawe her sone on the rode The swerde of sorowe gaue that lady wounde whan a spere claue her sones herte a sondre She cryed out and fell to the grounde Thoughe she was woo hyt was lytell wonder This delycate colour that goodly lady Full pale and wanne she sawe her sone all deed Splayed on a crosse with the fyue welles of pyte Of purple veluet poudred with roses reed Lo I pyte thus made your erande to be spede Or elles man for euer sholde haue ben forlorne A mayden so layde his lyfe to wedde Crowned as a kynge the thornes prycked hym sore Charyte and I of true loue ledes the double rayne who so me loueth dampned neuer shall be Of some vertuous company I wolde be fayne For all that wyll to heuen nedes must come by me Chefe porter I am in that heuenly cyte And now here wyll I rest me a lytell space Tyll hyt please Ihesu of his grace Some vertuous felyshyp for to sende Contemplacyon. Cryste that was crystened crucyfyed &amp; crowned In his bosum true loue was gaged with a spere His vaynes braste &amp; brosed and to a pyller bounde with scourges he was lasshed ye knottes ye skyn tare On his necke to caluary the grete crosse he bare His blode ran to the grounde as scrypture doth tel His burden was so heuy that downe vnder it he fel Lo I am kynne to the lorde whiche is goddes sone My name is wryten formest in the boke of lyfe For I am perfyte contemplacyon And brother to holy chyrche yt is our lordes wyfe Iohan baptyst Anthony &amp; Iherome wt many mo Folowed me here in holte hethe and in wyldernes I euer with them went where they dyde go Nyght &amp; daye towarde the waye of ryghtwysenes I am the chefe lanterne of all holynes Of prelates and preestes I am theyr patron No armure so stronge in no dystresse Habergyon helme ne yet no Ieltron To fyght with sathan I am the champyon That dare abyde and manfully stonde Fendes fle awaye where they se me come But I wyll shewe you why I came to this londe For to preche and teche of goddes soth sawes Ayenst vyce ye dothe rebell ayenst hym &amp; his lawes. Pyte. God spede good broder fro wh?s came you now Contem. Syr I came frome perseueraunce to seke you Pyte. Why syr knowe you me Contem. Ye syr and haue done longe your name is pyte Pyte. Your name fayne wolde I knowe Contem. In dede I am called contemplacyon That vseth to lyue solytaryly In wodes and in wyldernesse I walke alone Bycause I wolde saye my prayers deuoutly I loue not with me to haue moche company But perseueraunce ofte with me doth mete Whan I thynke on thoughtes that is full heuenly Thus he and I togyder full swetely doth slepe Pyte. I thanke god that we be mette togyder Contem. Syr I trust yt ?seuer?ce shortly wyll come hyder Pyte. Than I thynke to here some good tydynge Contem. I warant you brother that he is comynge Perseue. The eternall god that named was was messyas He gyue you grace to come to his glorye Wher euer is Ioye in the celestyall place Whan you of sathan wynneth the vyctorye Euery man ought to be gladde to haue in company For I am named good perseueraunce That euer is guyded by vertuous gouernaunce I am neuer varyable but doth contynue Styll goynge vpwarde the ladder of grace And lode in me planted is so true And fro yt poore man I wyll neuer tourne my face Whan I go by my selfe ofte I do remembre The grete knydnes that god shewed vnto man For to be borne in the moneth of decembre Whan the daye waxeth shorte and the nyght longt Of his goodnesse that champyon stronge Descended downe fro the fader of ryghtwysnes And rested in mary the floure of mekenes Now to this place hyder come I am To seke contemplacyon my knynnesman Contem. what brother perseueraunce ye be welcome Perseue. And so be you also contemplacyon Contem. Loo here is our mayster pyte Perseue. Now truly ye be welcome in to this countre Pyte. I thanke you hertely syr perseueraunce Perseue. Mayst pyte one th?ge is com to my rem?bra?ce what tythynges here you now Pyte. Syr suche as I can I shall shewe you I haue herde many men complayne pyteously They saye they be smyten wt the swerde of pouerty In euery place where I do go Fewe frendes pouerte dooth fynde And these ryche men ben vnkynde For theyr neyghboures they wyll nought do wydowes dooth curse lordes and gentyll men For they constrayne them to mary with theyr men ye wheder they wyll or no Men mary for good and that is dampnable ye with olde women that is fyfty and beyonde The peryll now no man drede wyll All is not goddes lawe that is vsed in londe Beware wyll they not tyll deth in his honde Taketh his swerde &amp; smyteth asonder ye lyfe vayne And wt his mortall stroke cleueth ye herte atwayne They trust so in mercy the lanterne of bryghtnesse That no thynge do they drede goddes ryghtwysnes Perseue. O Ihesu syr here is a heuy tydynge Pyte. Syr this is trewe that I do brynge Contem. How am I beloued mayster pyte where ye come Pyte. In good faythe people haue now small deuocyon And as for with you brother contemplacyon There medleth fewe or none Contem. Yes I trust that prestes loue me wele Pyte. But a fewe Iwys and some neuer adele Contem. Why syr without me they maye not lyue clene Pyte. Nay yt is yt leest thoughe ye they haue of fyftene And that maketh me full heuy Contem. How trowe you that there be no remedy Pyte. Full harde for synne is now so greuous and yll That I thynke that it be growen to an impossyble And yet one thynge maketh me euer mournynge That prestes lack vttera?ce to showe theyr c?n?ge And al the whyle that clerkes do vse so grete synne Amonge the lay people loke neuer for no mend?ge Perseue. Alas that is a heuy case That so grete synnne is vsed in euery place I praye god hyt amende Contem. Now god that euer hath ben mannes frende Some better tydynges soone vs sende For now I must be gone Fare well good bretherne here A grete erande I haue elles where That must nedes be done I trust I wyll not longe tary Theder wyll I hye me shortely And come agayne whan I haue done Perseue. Hyder agayne I trust you wyll come Therfore god be with you Contem. Syr nedes I must departe now Ihesu me spede this daye Perseue. Now brother contemplacyon let vs go our waye Frewyll Aware felowes and stande a roume How saye you am not I a goodly personue I trowe you knowe not suche ageste What syrres I tell you my name is frewyll I maye chose wheder I do good or yll But for all that I wyll do as me lyst My condycyons ye knowe not perde I can fyght chyde and be mery Full soone of my company ye wolde be wery And you knewe all What fyll the cup and make good chere I trowe I haue a noble here who lente hyt me by cryste a frere And I gaue hym a fall where be ye syr be ye at home Kockes passyon my noble is tourned to a stone Where laye I last beshrewe your herte Ione Now by these bones she hathe begyled me Let se a peny my souper a pece of flesshe .x. pence My bedde ryght uought let all this expence Now by these bones I haue lost an halfpeny Who ye there my felowe Imagynacyon He and I had good communycacyon Of syr Iohan and sybbell How they were spyed in bedde togyder And he prayed her ofte to come thyder For to synge lo le lo lowe They twayne togyder had good sporte But at the stewes syde I lost a grote I trowe I shall nener ythe My felowe promysed me here to mete But I trowe the horesone be a slepe With a wenche some where How Imagynacyon come hyder And you thryue I lose a feder Beshrowe your herte appere Imagy. what how how who called after me Frewyll Come nere ye shall neuer I the where haue ye be so longe Imagy. By god with me hyt is all wronge I haue apayre of sore buttockes All in Irons was my songe Euen now I satte gyued in a payre of stockes Frewyll Cockes passyon and how so Imagy. Syr I wyll tell you what I haue do I mette with a wenche and she was fayre And of loue hertely I dyde praye her And so promysed her monaye Syr she wynked on me and sayd nought But by her loke I knewe her thought Than in to loues daunce we were brought That we played the pyrdewy I wote not what we dyde togyder But a knaue catchpoll nyghed vs nere And so dyde vs aspye A strype he gaue me I fledde my touche And frome my gyrdle he plucked my pouche By your leue he lefte me neuer a peny Loo nought haue I but a buckyll Ane yet I can Imagen thynges sotyll For to get monaye plenty In westmynster hall euery terme I am To me is kynne many a grete gentyll man I am knowen in euery countre And I were deed the lawyers thryfte were lost For this wyll I do yf men wolde do cost Proue ryght wronge and all by reason And make men lese bothe hous and londe For all that they can do in a lytell season Peche men of treason preuyly I can And whan me lyst to hange a trewe man If they wyll me monaye tell Theues I can helpe out of pryson And in to lordes fauours I can get me soone And be of theyr preuy counseyll But frewyll my dere broder Sawe you not of hyckscorner He promysed me to come hyder Frewyll. why syr knowest thou hym Imagy. ye ye man he is full nye of my kynne And in newgate we dwelled togyder For he and I were bothe shakeled in a fetter Frewyll Syr laye you beneth or on hye on the seller Imagy. Nay ywys am?ge ye thyckest of yem? of the coller Frewyll By god than ye were in grete fere Imagy. Syr had not I be .cc. had be thrast in an haltere Frewyll And what lyfe haue they there al that grete sorte Imagy. By god syr ones a yere som taw halts of burport ye at tyburne there stondeth the grrte frame And some take a fall that maketh theyr neck lame Frewyll. ye but can they than go nomore Imagy. O no man the wrest is twyste so sore For as soone as they haue sayd in man? tuas ones By god theyr brethe is stopped at ones Frewyll Why do they praye in that place there Imagy. Ye syr they stonde in grete fere And so fast tangled in that snare Hyt falleth to theyr lotte to haue the same share Frewyll That is a knauisshe syght to se th? tote on a beme Imagy. Syr the horesones coude not conuaye clene For and they coude haue caryed by crafte as I can In ?cesse of yeres eche of th? sholde be a g?tyll m? yet as for me I was neuer thefe Yf my h?des were smyt? of I can stele wt my tethe For ye knowe well there is crafte in daubynge I can loke in a mannes face and pycke his purse And tell newe tydynges yt was neuer trewe ywys For my hood is all lyned with lesynge Frewyll. ye but wente ye neuer to tyburne a pylgrymage Imagy. No ywys nor none of my lygnages For we be clerkes all and can our necke verse And wt an oyntment the Iuges h?de I can grece That wyll hele sores that be vncurable Frewyll Why were ye neuer founde reprouable Imagy. yes ones I stall a hors in the felde And lepte on hym for to haue ryden my waye At the last a bayly me mette and behelde And badde me stonde than was I in a fraye He asked wheder with that horse I wolde gon And than I tolde hym hyt was myne owne He sayd I hadde stollen hym and I sayde naye This is sayd he my brothers hacknaye For and I had not scused me without fayle By our lady he wolde haue lad me strayte to Iayle And than I tolde hym ye horse was lyke myne A browne baye a longe mane &amp; dyde halte behyne Thus I tolde h? yt such an other hors I dyde lacke And yet I neuer sawe hym nor came on his backe So I delyuered hym the hors agayne And whan he was gone than was I fayne For and I had not scused me the better I knowe well I sholde haue daunsed in a fetter Frewyll And sayd he nomore to the but so Imagy. Yes he pretended me moche harme to do But I tolde h? that mornynge wns a grete myste That what horse hyt was I ne wyste Also I sayd that in my heed I had the megryne That made me dasell so in myne eyen That I myght not well se And thus he departed shortely frome me Frewyll Ye but where is hyckscorner now Imagy. Some of these yonge men hathe hydde hym in theyr bosomes I warraunt you Imagy. Let vs make a crye that he maye vs here Frewyll. How how hyckscorner appere I trowe thou be hyde in some cornere Hyckscor. Ale the helme ale vere shot of vere sayle vera Frewyll Cockes body herke he is in a shyppe on the see Hyckscor. God spede god spede who called after me Imagy. what brother welcome by this precyous body I am gladde that I you se Hyt was tolde me that ye were hanged But out of what countre come ye Hytkscor. Syr I haue ben in many a countre As in fraunce Irlonde and in spayne Portyngale seuyll also in almayne Freslonde flaunders and in burgoyne Calabre poyle and erragoyne Brytayne byske and also in gascoyne Naples grece and in myddes of scotlonde At cape saynt vyncent &amp; in the newe fo?de Ilonde I haue ben in gene and in cowe Also in the londe of rumbelowe Thre myle out of hell At rodes constantyne and in babylonde In cornewale and in no northumberlonde Where men sethe russhes in gruell Ye syr in caldey tartare and Iude And in ye londe of women yt fewe men dothe fynde In all these countres haue I be Frewyll. Syr what tydynges here ye now on the see Hyckscor. We mette of shyppes a grete naue Full of people that wolde in to Irlonde And they came out of this countre They wyll neuer more come to englonde Imagy. Whens were ye shyppes of them knowest yu none Hyckscor. Herk? &amp; I wyll shewe you theyr names eche one Fyrst was the regent with the myghell of brykylse The george with the gabryell and the anne of foye The starre of salte asshe with the Ihesus of pl?oth Also the hermytage with the barbara of darmouth The nycolas and the mary bellouse of brystowe With the elyn of london and Iames also Grete was the people that was in them All true relygyous and holy women There was trouthe and his kynnesman with pacyence mekenes and humylyte And all true maydens with theyr vyrgynyte Ryall prechers sadnes and charyte Ryght conscyence and fayth with deuocyon And all true monkes that kepte theyr relyon True byers and sellers and almes dede doers Pyteous people that be of synne destroyers with Iust abstynence and good counseyllers Mourners for synne with lamentacyon And good ryche men yt helpeth folke out of pryson True wedlocke was there also with yonge men that euer in prayer dyde go The shyppes were lad? wt suche vnhappy company But at the laste god shope a remedy For they all in the see were drounde And on a quycke sonde they strake to grounde The see swalowed them euerychone I wote wote well alyue there scaped none Imagy. Lo now my herte is gladde and mery For Ioye now let vs synge dery dery Hyckscor Felowes they shall neuer more vs withstonde For I se them all drwned in the rase of Irlonde Frewyll. ye but yet herke hyckescorner what company was in your shyppe that came ouer Hyckscor. Syr I wyll sayd you to vnderstande There were good felawes aboue fyue thousande And all they ben kynne to vs thre There was falshode fauell and sotylte ye theues and hores with other good company Lyers bacbyters and flaterers the whyle Braulers lyers getters and chyders Walkers by nyght with gret e murderers Ouerthwarte gyle and Ioly carders Oppressers of people with many swerers There was false lawe with oryble vengeaunce Frowarde obstynacy? wt myseheuous gouerna?ce Wanton wenches and also mychers With many other of the deuylles offycers And haterede that is so myghty and stronge Hath made auowe for euer to dwell in englonde Imagy. But is that true that thou doste shewe now Hyckscor. Syr euery worde as I do tell you Frewyll. Of whens is your shyppe of london Hyckscor. Ye ywys frome thens dyde she come And she is named the enuy I tell you a grete vessell and a myghty The owner of her is called yll wyll Brother to Iacke poller of shoters hyll Imagy. Syr what offyce in the shyppe bare ye Hyckscor Mary I kepte a fayre shoppe of baudrye I had thre wenches that were full praty Iane true and thryftles and wanton sybble If ye ryde her a Iournay she wyll make you wery For she is trusty at nede If ye wyll hyre her for your pleasure I warraunt tere her shall ye neuer She is so sure in dede Ryde and you wyll ten tymes adaye I warraunt you she wyll neuer saye naye My lyfe I dare laye to wedde Imagy. Now plucke vp your hertes &amp; make good chere These tydynges lyketh me wonder wele Now vertu shall drawe arere arere Herke felous a good sporte I can you tell At the stues we wyll lye to nyght And by my trouth yf all go aryght I wyll begyle some praty wenche To gette me monaye at a pynche How saye you shall we go thyder Let vs kepe company all togyder And I wolde that we had goddes curse If we some where do not get a purse Euery man bere his dagger naked in his honde And yf we mete a treue man make hym stonde Or elles that he bere a strype If that he struggle ond make ony werke Lyghtly stryke hym to the herte And throwe hym into temmes quyte Frewyll. Naye thre knaues in a lease is good at nale But thou lubber Imagynacyon That cukcolde thy fader where is he become At newgate dothe he ly styll at gayle Imagy. Auaut horesone thou shalte bere me a strype Sayst thou that my moder was a hore Frewyll. Naye syr but the last nyght I sawe syr Iohne and she tombled on the flore Imagy. Now by kockes herte thou shalte lose an arme Hyckscor Naye syr I charge you do hym no harme Imagy. And yu make to moche I wyll breke thy heed to Hyckscor By saynt mary and I wyst that I wolde be ago Imagy. Aware aware the horsone shall aby His preest wyll I be by cockes body Hyckscor. Kepe pease lest knaues blode be shedde Frewyll. By god yf his was nought m? was as badde Imagy. By kockes herte he shall dye on this dager Hyckscor By our lady than wyll ye be stra?gled in a halter Imagy. The horesone shall ete h? as fer as he shyll wade Hyckscor. Beshrewe your herte and put vp your blade Shethe your whytell or by hy? yt was neuer borne I wyll rappe you on the costarde with my horne What wyll ye playe all the knaue Imagy. By kockes herte and thou a buffet shalte haue Frewyll. Lo syrres here is afayre company god vs saue For yf ony of vs thre be mayre of london Iwys ywys I wyll ryde to rome on my thom Alas a se is not this a grete feres I wolde they were in a myll pole aboue the eres And th? I durst warra?t they wold departe anone Hyckscor Helpe helpe for the passyon of my soule He hath made a grete hole in my poule That all my wytte is set to the grounde Alas a leche for to helpe my wounde Imagy. Naye ywys horesone I wyll bete the or I go Frewyll. Alas good syr what haue I do Imagy. Ware make rome he shall haue a strype I trowe Pyte. Peas peas syrres I commaunde you Imagy. Auaunt olde churle whens comest thou And thou make to moche I shall breke thy browe And sende the home agayne Pyte. A good syr the peas I wolde haue kepte fayne Myne offyce is to se no man slayne And where they do amyse to gyue th? good co?seyl Synne to forsake and goddes lawe them tell Imagy. A syr I wende thou haddest ben drowned &amp; gone But I haue spyed that there scaped one Hyckscor. Imagynacyon do by the counseyll of me Be a greed with frewyll &amp; lette vs good felowes be And than as for this chorle pyte Shall curse the tyme that euer he came to londe Imagy. Brother frewyll gyue me your honde And all myne yll wyll I forgyue the Frewyll. Syr I thanke you hertely But what shall we do with this chorle pyte Imagy. I wyll go to hym and pyke a quarell And make hym a thefe and saye he dyde stele Of myne forty pounde in a bagge Frewyll. By god that tydynges wyll make hym sadde And I wyll go fetche apayre of gyues For in good faythe he shall besette fast by the heles Hyckscor. Haue ado lyghtly and be gone And let vs twayne with hym alone Frewyll. Now farewell I beshrewe you euery chone Hyckscor. Ho ho frewyll you threwe and no mo Imagy. Thou lewde felowe sayst yu that thy name is pite Who sente the hyder to controll me Pyte. Good syr hyt is my properte For to dyspyse synfull lyuynge And vnto vertu men to brynge If that they wyll do after me Imagy. What syr arte thou so pope holy A se this caytyfe wolde be praysed I trowe And you thryue this yere I wyll lose a peny Lo syrres outwarde he bereth a fayre face But and he mette with a wenche in a preuy place I trowe he wolde shewe her but lytell grace By god ye maye trust me Hyckscor. Loo wyll ye not se this caytyues menynge He wolde destroye vs all and all our kynne yet had I leuer se hym hanged by the chynne Rather than that sholde be brought aboute And with this dager thou shalte haue a cloute without thou wylte be lyghtly be gone Imagy. Naye brother laye honde on hym soone For he Iaped my wyfe and made me cukolde And yet the traytoue was so bolde That he stale forty pounde of myne in monaye Hyckscor By sa ynt mary than he shall not scape we wyll lede hym streyght to newgate For euer there shall he lye Frewyll. A se a se syrres what I haue brought A medycyne for a payre of sore shynnes At the kynges benche syrres I haue you sought But I praye you who shall were these Hyckscor. By god this felowe that maye not go hence I wyll go gyue hym these hose rynges Now yfaythe they be worth forty pence But to his hondes I lacke two bondes Imagy. Holde horesone here is an halter Bynde hym fast and make hym sure Pyte. O men let trouth that is the trewe man Be your guyder or elles ye be forlorne Laye no fals wytnes as nye as ye can On none for afterwarde ye wyll repent hyt full sore Frewyll. Naye naye I care not therfore Hyckscor ye whan my soule h?geth on ye hedge cast stones. For I tell the playnly by kockes bones Thou shalte be guyded and layd in Irons They fared euen so Pyte. Awaye syr what haue I do Imagy. Well well that thou shalte knowe or thou go Pyte. O syrres I se hyt can not be amended you do me wronge for I haue not offended Remembre god that is our heuen kynge For he wyll rewarde you after your deseruynge Whan deth with his mace dooth you areest We all to hym owe fewte and seruyce Fro the ladder of lyfe downe he wyll the threste Than maystershyp may not helpe nor grete offyce Frewyll. What dethe and he were here he sholde syt by ye Trowest thou that he be able to stryue wt vs thre Nay nay nay Imagy. Well felawes now let vs go our waye For at shoters hyll we haue agame to playe Hyckscor. In good fayth I wyll tary no lender space Frewyll. Byshrewe hym for me yt is last out of this place Pyte. Lo lordes they may curs ye tyme they were borne For the wedes that ouer groweth the corne They troubled me gyltelesse and wote not why For goddes loue yet wyll I suffre pacyently we all may say weleaway for synne yt is now adaye Loo vertue is banysshed for euer and aye Worse was hyt neuer We haue plente of grete othes And clothe ynoughe in our clothes But charyte many men lothes Worse was hyt neuer Alas now is lechery called loue in dede And murdure named manhode in euery nede Extorsyon is called lawe so god me spede Worse was hyt neuer Youth walketh by nyght with swerdes &amp; knyues And euer amonge true men leseth theyr lyues Lyke heretykes we occupy other mennes wyues Now a dayes in englonde Baudes be ye dystryers of many yonge women And full lewde counseyll they gyue vnto them How you do mary beware you yonge men The wyfe neuer taryeth to longe There be many grete scorners But for synne there be fewe mourners We haue but fewe true louers In no place now a dayes There be many goodly gylte knyues And I trowe as well apparaylled wyues Yet many of them be vntthryfty of theyr lyues And all set in pryde to go gaye. Mayers on synne dooth no correccyon With gentyll men bereth trouthe adowne Auoutry is fuffred in euery towne Amendyment is there none And goddes c?ma?dementes we breke them all .x. Deuocyon is gone many dayes syn Let vs amende vs we trewe crysten men Or deth make you grone Courtyers go gaye and take lytell wages And many with harlottes at the tauerne hauntes They be yemen of the wrethe yt be shakled in gyues On themselfe they haue no pyte God punyssheth full sore with grete sekenesse As pockes pestylence purple and axes Some dyeth sodeynly that deth full peryllous Yet was there neuer so grete pouerte There be some sermones made by noble doctoures But truly the fende dothe stoppe mennes eres For god nor good man some people not feres worse was hyt neuer All trouth is not best sayd And our prechers now adayes be halfe afrayde whan we do amende god wolde be well apayde worse was hyt neuer Contem. what mayster pyte how is hyt with you Perseue. Syr we be sory to se you in this case now Pyte. Bretherne here were thre peryllous men Frewyll hyckscorner and Imagynacyon They sayd I was a thefe and layd felony vpon me And bounde we in Irons as ye maye se Contem. where be the traytours become nowe Pyte. In good faythe I can not shewe you Perseue. Brother let vs vnbynde hym of his bondes Contem. Unlose the fete and the hondes Pyte. I thanke you for your grete kyndnes That you two shewe in this dystresse For they were men without ony mercy That delyteth all in myschefe and tyranny Perseue. I thynke they wyll come hyder agayne Frewyll and Imagynacyon bothe twayne Them wyll I exorte to vertuous lyuynge And vnto vertu them to brynge By the helpe of you contemplacyon Contem. Do my counseyll brother pyte Go you and seke them throughe the countre In vyllage towne bourghe and cyte Throughe out all the realme of englonde Whan you them mete lyghtly them arest And in pryson put them faste Bynde them sure in Irons stronge For they be so faste and sotyle That they wyll you begyle And do true men wronge Perseue. Brother pyte do as he hath sayd In euery quarter loke you aspye And let good watche for them be layde In all the haast that thou can and that pryuely For and they come hyder they shall not scape For all the crafte that they can make Pyte. Well than wyll I hye me as fast as I maye And trauayle throughe euery countre Good watche shall be layde in euery waye That they stele not in to sentwary Now fare wele bretherne and praye for me For I must go hens in dede Perseue. Now god be your good spende Contem. And euer you defende whan you haue nede Pyte. Now bretherne bothe I thanke you Frewyll. Make you rome for a gentylman syrs and pease Duegarde seygnours tout le preasse And of your Iangelynge yf ye wyll sease I wyll tell you where I haue bene Syrres I was at the tauerne and dronke wyne Me thought I sawe a pece that was lyke myne And syr all my fyngers were arayed with lyme So I conuayued a cuppe manerly And yet ywys I played all the fole For there was a scoler of myne owne scole And syr the horesone aspyed me Than was I rested and brought in pryson For woo than I wyste not what to haue done And all Bycause I lacked monaye But a frende in courte is worthe a peny in purs For Imagynacyon myne owne felowe Iwys He dyde helpe me out full craftely Syrres he walked thrughe holborne Thre houres after the sonne was downe And walked vp towarde saynte gyles in the felde He houed styll and there behelde But there he coude not spede of his praye And strayght to ludgate he toke the waye ye wote well that potycaryes walke very late He came to a dore and pryuely spake To a prentes for a peny worth of vforbyum And also for a halfpeny worth of alom plomme This good seruaunte serued hym shortely And sayd is there ought elles that you wolde bye Th? he asked for a mouthfull of quycke brymstone And downe in to ye seller wh? the seru?t was gone Asyde as he kest his eye A grete bagge of monaye dyde he spye Therin was an hondred pounde He trussed hym to his fete and yede his waye ro?de He was lodged at newgate at the swanne And euery man toke hym for a gentyll man So on the morowe he delyuered me Out of newgate by this polyce And now wyll I daunce an make ryall chere But I wolde Imagynacyon were here For he is pereles at nede Labour to hym syrres yf ye wyl your maters spede Now wyll I synge and lustely sprynge But whan my feters on my leges dyde rynge I was not gladde perde but now hey trolly lolly Let vs se who can descaunt on this same To laughe and gete manaye hyt were a goed game What whome haue we here A preest a douctoure or elles a frere What mayster doctour dotypoll Can not you preche well in a blacke boll Or dyspute ony dyuynyte If ye be cunnynge I wyll put hyt in a prefe Good syr why do men ete mustarde with befe My questyon can you assoyle me Perseue. Peas man thou talkest lewdly And of thy lyuynge I reed amende the Frewyll. Auaunt catyfe doost thou thou me I am come of good kynne I tell the My moder was a lady of the stewes blode borne And knyght of the halter my fader ware an horne Therfore I take hyt in full grete scorne That thou sholdest thus cheke me Contem. Abyde felowe thou cast lytell curtesye Thou shalte be charmed or thou hens pase For thou troubled pyte and layd on hym felonye Where is Imagynacyon thy felawe that wa s Frewyll I defy you bothe wyll you arest me Perseue. Naye naye thy grete wordes maye not helpe the Fro vs thou shalte not escape Frewyll. Make rome syrres that I maye breke his pate I wyll not be taken for them bothe Contem. Thou shalt abyde whether thou be leue or lothe Therfore good sone lysten vnto me And marke these wordes that I do tell the Thou hast folowed thyne one wyll many a daye And lyued in synne without amendement Therfore in thy conceyte assaye To axe god mercy and kepe his c?maundement Than on the he wyll haue pyte And brynge the to heuen that Ioyfull cyte Frewyll What horesone wyll ye haue me now a fole Naye yet had I leuer be captayne of calays For and I sholde do after your scole To lerne to pater to make me peuysse Yet had I leuer loke with a face full theuysshe And therfore prate no lenger here Leest my knaues fyste hytte you vnder the yere what ye dawes wolde ye reed me For to lesese my pleasure in youth and Iolyte To basse and kysse my swete trully mully As Iane cate besse and sybble I wolde that hell were full of suche prymmes Than wolde I renne thyder on my pynnes As fast as I myght go Perseue. Why syr wylte thou not loue vertu And forsake thy synne for the loue of god almyghty Frewyll What god almyghty by goddes fast at salysbury And I trowe eester day fell on whytsonday yt yere There were .v. score saue an hondred in my c?pany And at pety Iudas we made ryall chere There had we good ale of myghelmas bruyng Chere heuen hye lepynge and spryngynge And thus dyde I Lepe out of burdeaus vnto caunterbury Almost ten myle bytwene Contem. Frewyll forsake all this worlde wylfully here And chaunge by tyme yu oughtest to stonde in fere For fortune wyll tourne her whele to swyfte That clene fro thy welthe she wyll the lyfte Frewyll what lift me who &amp; Imaginac?n were here now Iwys with his fyst he wolde all tocloute you Hens horesone tary no lenger here For by saynt pyntell the apostell I swere That I wyll dryue you bothe home And yet I was neuer wonte to fyght alone Alas that I had not one to bolde me Than you sholde se me playe the man shamfully Alas hyt wolde do me good to fyght How saye you lordes shall I smyte Haue amonge you by this lyght Hens horesones and home at ones Or with my wepen I shall breke your bones Auaunt you knaue walke by my counseyll Perseue. Sone remembre the grete paynes of hell They are so horryble that no tonge can tell Beware lest thou thyder do go Frewyll. Naye by saynt mary I hope not so I wyll not go to ye deuyll whyle I haue my lyberte He shall take ye laboure to fet me &amp; he wyl haue me For he that wyll go to hell by his wyll voluntary The deuyll and the worlewynde go with hym I wyll you neuer fro thens tydynges brynge Go you before and shewe me the waye And as to folowe you I wyll not saye naye For by goddes body and you be in ones By the masse I wyll shytte the dore at ones And than ye be take in a pytfall Contem. Now Ihesus soone defende vs frome that hole For (qui est in inferno nulla est redemptio) Holy Iob spake these wordes full longe ago Frewyll. Nay I haue done &amp; you lade out latyn wt scopes But therwith can you cloute me a payre of botes By our lady ye sholde haue some werke of me I wolde haue them well vnderlayd and easely For I vse alwaye to go one the one syde And trowe ye how by god in the stockes I sate tyde I trowe a thre wekes and more a lytell stounde And there I laboured sore daye by daye And so I tred my shone inwarde in good faye Lo therfore me thynke you must soule them ro?de If you haue ony newe botes apayre I wolde by But I thynke your pryce be to hye Syr ones at newgate I bought a payre of sterrups A myghty payre and a stronge A hole yere I ware them so longe But they came not fully to my knee And to cloute them hyt cost not me a peny Euen now &amp; ye go thyder ye shall fynde a grete hepe And you speke ? my name ye shall haue good chepe Perseue. Syr we came neuer there ne neuer shall do Frewyll Mary I was taken in a trap there &amp; tyde by ye to That I halted a grete whyle and myght not go I wolde ye bothe sate as fast there Than sholde ye daunce as a bere And all all by gangelynge of your chaynes Contem. why syr were ye there Frewyll. ye and that is sene by my braynes For or I came there I was as wyse as a woodcock And I thanke god as wytte as a haddocke yet I trust to recouer as other dose For and I had ones as moche wytte as a gose I sholde be marchaunt of the banke Of golde than I sholde haue many a franke For yf I my?t make .iii. good vyages to shoters hyl And haue wynde and weder at my wyll Than wolde I neuer trauell the see more But hyt is harde to kepe the shyppe fro the shore And yf hyt happe to ryse a storme Than throwen in a rase and so aboute borne On rockes or brachis for to ronne Elles to stryke a grounde at tyborne That were a myscheuous case For that rocke of tyborne is so peryllous a place Yonge galauntes dare not venture in to kente But whan theyr monaye is gone and spente with theyr longe botes they rowe on the baye And ony man of warre lye by the waye They must take a bote and throwe the helme ale And full harde hyt is to scape that grete Ieopardye For at sa?t thomas of watr?ge &amp; they stryke a sayle Th? muste they ryde in ye hau? of hepe wtout fayle And were not these two Ieoperdo? places in dede Ther is many a marcha?t that thyder wolde spede But yet we haue a sure canell at westmynster A thous?de shyppes of theues therin may ryde sure For yf they may haue ankerholde &amp; grete sp?dynge They maye lyue as mery as ony kynge Perseue. Good woote syr there is a pyteous lyuynge Than ye drede not the grete mayster aboue Sone forsake thy mysse for his loue And than mayst thou come to the blysse also Frewyll. Why what wolde you that I sholde do Contem. For to go towarde heuen Frewyll. Mary and you wyll me thyder brynge I wolde do after you Perseue. I praye you remembre my wordes now Frewyll bethynke the that thou shalte dye And of the houre thou arte vncertayne Yet by thy lyfe thou mayst fynde a remedy For and thou dye in synne all laboure is in vayne Than shall thy soule be styll in payne Loste and dampned for euermore Helpe is past thoughe thou wolde fayne Than thou wylte curse ye tyme that thou were bore Frewyll. Syr yf ye wyll vndertake that I saued shall be I wyll do all the penaunce that you wyll sette me Contem. If that thou for thy synnes be sory Our lorde wyll forgyue the them Frewyll. Now of all my synnes I axe god mercy Here I forsake synne and trust to amende I beseche Ihesu that is moost myghty To forgyue all that I haue offende Perseue. Our lorde now wyll shewe the his mercy A newe name thou nede none haue For all that wyll to heuen hye By his owne frewyll he must forsake folye Than is he sure and saue Contem. Holde here a newe garment And here after lyue deuoutly And for thy synnes do euer repente Sorowe for thy synnes is very remedy And frewyll euer to vertue applye Also to sadnes gyue ye attendaunce Let hym neuer out of remembraunce Frewyll I Wyll neuer frome you syr perseueraunce With you wyll I abyde bothe daye and nyght Of mynde neuer to be varyable And goddes c?mandementes to kepe them ryght In deed and worde and euer full stable Perseue. Than heuen thou shalte haue without fable But loke that thou be stedfaste And let thy mynde with good wyll laste Imagy. Huffe huffe huffe who sent after me I am Imagynacyon full of Iolyte Lorde that my herte is lyght Whan shall I perysshe I trowe neuer By cryst I recke not a feder Euen now I was dubbed a knyght where at tyborne of the coller And of the stewes I am made controller Of all the houses of lechery There shall no man playe doccy there At the bell hertes horne ne elles where without they haue leue of me But syrres wote ye why I am come hyder By our lady togyder good company togyder Saue ye not of my felawe frewyll I am aferde lest he be serchynge on a hyll By god than one of vs is begyled what felawe is this that in this cote is fyled Kockes deth whome haue we here what Frewyll myn owne fere Arte thou out of thy mynde Frewyll God gra?te the way to heuen that I may fynde For I forsake thy company Imagy. Goddes armes my company and why Frewyll For thou lyuest to synfully Imagy. Alas tell me how hyt is with the Frewyll. Forsake thy synne for the loue of me Imagy. Kockes herte arte thou waxed made Frewyll wh? I thynke on my synne it makes me ful sade Imagy. Goddes woundes who gaue the that counsell Frewyll. Perseueraunce and contemplacyon I the tell Imagy. A vengea?ce on them I wolde they were in hell Frewyll Amende Imagynacyon and mercy crye Imagy. By goddes sydes I hadde leuer be h?ged on hye Naye that wolde I not do I hadde leuer dye By goddes passyon and I hadde alonge knyfe I wolde bereue these two horesones of theyr lyfe How how twenty pounde for a dagger Contem. Peas peas good sone and speke softer And amende or deth drawe his draught For on the he wyl stele full softe He gyueth neuer no man warnynge And euer to the he is comynge Therfore remembre the well Imagy. A horesone yf I were Iayler of hell Iwys some sorowe sholde thou fele For to the deuyll I wolde the sell Than sholde ye haue many a sory mele I wyll neuer gyue you mete ne drynke Ye sholde fast horesones tyll ye dyde styncke Euen as a roten dogge ye by saynt tyburne of kent Perseue. Imagynacyon thynke what god dyd for the On good frydaye he hanged on a tre And spent all his precyous blode A spere dyde ryue his herte a sonder The gates he brake vp with a clappe of thunder And Adam and eue there delyuered he Imagy. What deuyll what is that to me By goodes fast I was ten yere in newgate And many more felawes with me sate Yet he neuer came there to helpe me ne my c?pany Contem. yes he holpe the or thou haddest not ben here now Imagy. By the masse I can not shewe you For he and I neuer dranke togyder yet I knowe many an ale stake Neyther at ye stues I wyste h? neuer come thyder Gooth he arayed in whyte or in blacke For and he out of pryson hadde holpe me I knowe well ones I sholde hym se What gowne wereth he I praye you Perseue. Syr he halpe you out by his myght Imagy. I can not tell you by this lyght But me thought that I laye there to longe And the horesone fetters were so stronge That hadde almost brought my necke out of Ioynt Perseue. Amende sone and thou shalt knowe hym That delyuered the out of pryson And yf thou wylt forsake thy mysse Surely thou shalt come to the blysse And be inherytoure of heuen Imagy. What syr aboue the mone Naye by the masse than sholde I fall soone Yet I kepe not to clymme so hye But to clymme for a byrdes neste There is none bytwene eest and weste That dare therto ventre better than I But to ventre to heuen what and my fete slyppe I knowe well than I sholde breke my necke And by god than hadde I the worse syde yet had I leuer be by the nose tyde In a wenches ars somewhere Rather than I wolde stande in that grete fere For to go vp to heuen naye I praye you lette be Frewyll Imagynacyon wylte yu do by the co?seyll of me Imagy. ye syr by my trouthe what someuer it be Frewyll. Amende yet for my sake Hyt is better be tyme than to late How saye you wyll you goddes hestes fulfyll Imagy. I wyll do syr euen as you wyll But I praye you let me haue a newe cote Whan I haue nede and in my purse a grote Than wyll I dwell with you styll Frewyll Beware for whan yu arte buryed in the grounde Fewe frendes for the wyll be founde Remembre this styll Imagy. No thynge drede I so sore as deth Therfore to amende I thynke hyt be tyme Synne haue I vsed all the dayes of my breth With pleasure lechery and mysusynge And spent amys my .v. wyttes therfore I am sory Here of all my synnes I are god mercy Perseue. Holde here is a better clothynge for the And loke that thou forsake thy foly Be stedfast loke that thou fall neuer Imagy. Now here I forsake my synne for euer Frewyll. Syr wayte thou now on perseueraunce For thy name shall be called good remembraunce And I wyll dwell with contemplacyon And folowe hym where euer he become Contem. Well are ye so bothe agrede Imagy. Ye syr so god me spede Perseue. Syr ye shall wete on me soone And be goddes seruaunt daye and nyght And in euery place where ye become Gyue good counseyle to euery wyght And men axe your name tell you remembraunce That goddes lawe kepeth truly euery daye And loke that ye forget not repentaunce Than to heuen ye shall go the nexte waye Where ye shall se in the heuenly quere The blessyd company of sayntes so holy That lyued deuouly whyle they were here Unto the whiche blysse I beseche god almyghty To brynge there your soules that here be present And vnto vertuous lyuynge that ye maye applye Truly for to kepe his commaundemente Of all our myrthes here we make an ende Unto the blysse of heuen Ihesu your soules brynge</field>
      <field name="fulltext">AMEN.</field>
   </doc>
</add>