<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">D'Avenant, William, Sir, 1606-1668</field>
      <field name="author_facet">D'Avenant, William, Sir, 1606-1668</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">davenant william sir 1606 1668</field>
      <field name="author_text">D'Avenant, William, Sir, 1606-1668</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">17th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V1.0309.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1673</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:459056</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Law against Lovers</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 17th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 17th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Law against Lovers</field>
      <field name="title_facet">law against lovers</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">law against lovers</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Law against Lovers</field>
      <field name="year_display">1673</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1673</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1673</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459056&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459056&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;D'Avenant, William, Sir, 1606-1668&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;davenant william sir 1606 1668&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Law against Lovers&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;law against lovers&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1673&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1673&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;D'Avenant, William, Sir&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1606&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1668&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Law against Lovers&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed by T. N. for Henry Herringman [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1673&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3871707-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv10309&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 17th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;17th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Law against Lovers&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 249 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted&lt;lb/&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;lb/&gt;Dedication included with The Play-House to be Let&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: The law against lovers.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Comedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1673.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 15 Feb 1662.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE Law against Lovers.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Names of the Persons. The Duke of Savoy. Lord Angelo, his Deputy. Benedict, Brother to Angelo. Lucio His Friend. Balthazar His Friend. Eschalus, a Counsellor. Claudio, in love with Julietta. Provost. Fryer Thomas. Bernardine, a Prisoner. Jaylor. Fool. Hangman. Pages. Beatrice, a great Heiress Isabella, Sister to Claudio. Julietta, Mistress to Claudio. Viola, Sister to Beatrice; very young. Francisca, a Nun.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE Turin.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. SCENE I. Enter Duke, Angelo, and Attendants. Duke. I'm sure in this your science does exceed The measures of advice; and to your skill, By deputation, I resolve to leave a while My place and strength. Ang. Your Highness does amaze me with your trust. Duke. Your Brother will be here to night; and brings His share of Victory and fair renown. That Victory gives me now free leisure to Pursue my old design of travelling; Whilst, hiding what I am, in fit disguise, I may compare the Customs, prudent Laws, And managements of foreign States with ours. Ang. Your Highness has a plenteous choice of men, Whom you may here depute with more success, Than my abilities can promise. Duke. Here, take our Commission— In which we have enabled you with all The sev'ral strengths and organs of my Pow'r: Your youth may bear that weight, which tires my Age. Ang. In this acceptance, Sir, I do with some Unwillingness obey your pleasure. Duke. Heaven does with us, as we with Torches do, Not light them for themselves, but others use. For if our virtues go not forth of us, It were alike as if we had them not. Be thou at full our self, whilst we are absent From our Seat in Turin. Ang. Sir, I could wish There were more tryal of my mettle made, Before so noble and so great A Figure as your own be stampt on it. Duke. No more evasion, I have proceeded towards you with choice, [Enter Eschalus. Sufficiently prepar'd. Good Eschalus Your ceremony now of taking leave Must needs be short. You know the purpose of My trust to Angelo, who here has my Commission seal'd. Esch. Your Highness having been So long resolv'd to travel, could not leave A Deputation of your Pow'r in better hands. Duke. Farewel! our haste from hence is of import. You shall, as time and fit occasion serves, Have Letters from us; and I hope to know, With equal care, what does befall you here. Ang. Will not your Highness give us leave to bring You onward on the way? Duke. My haste permits it not. You need not (on mine honour) have to do With scruple, for your scope is as mine own; So to inforce, or qualifie the Laws, As to your soul seems good. Give me your hand, I'll privately away; I love the People; But would not on a Stage salute the Crowd. I never relisht their applause; nor think the Prince has true discretion who affects it. Be kind still to your Brother Benedick, And give him that respect which he Hath by his share in Victory deserv'd. Once more farewell. Ang. The Heavens give safety to your purposes. Esch. Lead forth, and bring you back in happiness. [Ex. Duke. Ang. I shall desire you Eschalus, to let Me have free speech with you: for it concerns Me much to see the bottom of my place. The Duke has left me pow'r, but of what strength And nature it will prove, may haply Require your friendship to consider. Esch. My Lord, if it shall please you to withdraw, You may command my secresie and service. [Exeunt. Enter Beatrice, Julietta, Viola, Balthazar. Beat. Does Signior Benedick return to night? Balt. We may expect him presently. He brings A share of conquest with him, and intends To make a modest Entry here by stealth: But he is still as pleasant as you left him. Beat. How many has he kill'd, and eaten, in These Wars? but pray, how many has he kill'd? For I promis'd to eat all of his killing. Balt. He has done great service in these Wars, Lady. Beat. Sure you had musty victual then; And he has helpt to eat it. I know, Sir, He is a valiant Trencher-man, and has A good stomach. Balt. He is a good Souldier, Lady. Beat. A good Souldier To a Lady, but what is he to a Lord? Balt. A Lord to a Lord, a man to a man: Stuft with all honourable virtues. Beat. He is, indeed, no less than a stuft man. But for the stuffing—Well, we are all mortal. Jul. Do not mistake my Cousin Beatrice, Sir, There is a kind of a merry war between Count Benedick and her: they never meet, But there is a skirmish of wit between 'em. Beat. He got nothing by that. In our last encounter Four of his five wits did go halting off; And now the whole man is govern'd by one. I pray, Sir, who's his Companion now? for he was wont, Every Month to have a new sworn Brother. Balt. Is't possible? Beat. Very possible. He wears his faith but as the fashion of His Hat; it still changes with the next Block. Balt. Madam, the Gentleman is not in your Books. Viol. If he were, I have heard my Sister say She would burn her Study. Balt. Small Mistress, have you learnt that in your Primer? This, Madam, is your pretty Bud of wit. Viol. A Bud that has some prickles, Sir. Take heed; You cannot gather me. Beat. But, Signior Balthazar, I pray who is Count Benedicks Companion? Balt. At idle seasons, Madam, he is pleas'd To use no better company than mine. Beat. He will hang on you like a disease, He's sooner caught than the Pestilence; And the taker does run presently mad. Heaven help you Balthazar, if you have caught The Benedickt, for it will cost you more Than a thousand pounds to be cur'd. Balt. I wish I may hold friendship with you, Lady. Beat. Y'ave the wit, Sir, to wish for your self. Jul. You'll never run mad Cousin. Beat. Not till a hot January. [Enter Servant. Serv. Madam, your Guardian's Brother, Count Benedick, Is newly enter'd. Beat. The man of War, having been flesht In the last Battel, will bear all before him. Let us sound a retreat, and hide our selves Behind the Hangings, to mark his behaviour. Viol. Dear Sister, let me hide my self too— [Beatrice, Viola, Juliet, step behind the Hangings. Balt. O pray do, with a Bongrace from the Sun. Madam, I'll leave you to your Ambush. Enter Benedick, Eschalus. Ben. My Brother private in affairs of State? Esch. My Lord, he's at this instant much reserv'd; But, when I shall acquaint him you are here, He will dismiss his business to receive, And welcome you? Ben. Signior Eschalus, I thank you: but it Is fit our private love should give free way To service which concerns the publick profit. I am, Sir, in some trouble, that I could Not have the happiness of paying my Obedience to his Highness e're he went. Will he be absent long? Esch. That is unknown Even to your Brother Angelo; who is his full Vicegerent here, and hath receiv'd commands To let you taste his Pow'r, to every use That can procure you any benefit, In memory of your last service. [Enter Lucio. Luc. My Lord you are most happily return'd, And met with all the joys we can express. Ben. Lucio, I am much pleas'd to see you well; It gives me hope that I shall have but few Sad Evenings here in Turin, if the Beauties which I left be not quite wither'd, Their Voices cract, and their Lutes hung on Willows. Luc. My Lord, I am not only hasten'd hither by My Love to be the first that shall congratulate Your good success abroad, but to entreat Your aid at home. If you will please but to Take leave of that grave Magistrate a while, I shall deliver you a message from mankind. Ben. How, Lucio? That is of concern indeed. Signior, I shall beseech you to observe My Brother's leisure, that I may attend him. Esch. Your Lordship is most welcome to Turin. [Exit Eschalus. Ben. Now, Lucio, speak your affair from that great Common-Wealth which sent you, Mankind. Balth. They are too many for you to enquire Particularly after their healths; therefore He may without Ceremony proceed. Luc. You have heard of the Supream Pow'r plac'd in Count Angelo your Brother? Ben. I have, Lucio. Luc. Under your favour, Sir, I may say the beginning of his rule Is not pleasing to the best sort of men, He deals very hardly with Lovers. Ben. I am sorry to hear that of a Brother. Luc. My Lord, I am more sorry to report it. He has already reviv'd an old Law, Which condemns any man to death, who gets, Being unmarry'd, a Woman with Child. Ben. How Lucio? does he mean to govern like The Tyrant Turk, with Ev'nuchs of his Council? Luc. You must asswage the choler of his wisdom, And put him in mind that men are frail. Ben. This business, Balthazar, requires our care; For we having professed against the bonds Of Marriage, and he, restraining The liberty of Lovers, the good Duke When he returns, will find no Children left In Turin. Luc. For my part, Sir, I only fear the destruction of Learning: For if there be no Children, farewel Gramar-Schools. Ben. Come, we must sit in Council, Balthazar, Increase our party, and still desie marriage. Beat. We cannot hear 'em, Juliet; let us enter. [Enter Beat. Jul. Viol. Ben. My dear Lady disdain! are you yet living? Beat. Can disdain dye when she has so fit food To feed it as Benedick? Ben. I am belov'd of all Ladies, only You excepted; and I am sorry they must lose Their sighs; for I have a hard heart, And can love none. Beat. A happiness to Women; who would else Be troubled with a most pernicious Suitor? But I can answer your humour; for I Had rather hear my Dog bark at a Crow, Than a Man swear he loves me. Ben. Keep in that mind, Lady, for then some of my Friends may scape a predestinate scratcht face. Beat. Scratching could not make it worse, If it were such a Face as Benedick's. Ben. You are a rare Parrot-teacher. Beat. A Bird of my tongue, is better than a Beast of yours. Ben. I would my Horse had the speed of your Tongue; But keep your way: I have done. Beat. Juliet, he always ends with a Jades trick. Jul. The Gentleman's wit is tir'd after spurring. Vio. Y'are welcome home my Lord. Have you brought Any Pendants, and fine Fans, from the Wars? Ben. What my sweet Bud, you are grown to a Blossom! Vio. My Sister has promis'd me that I shall be A Woman, and that you shall make love to me, When you are old enough to have a Wife. Ben. This is not a chip of the old Block, but will prove A smart Twig of the young Branch. [Enter Esch. and Serv. Esch. Lord Angelo expects you, Sir, and this Fair Company. [Ex. Beat. Ben. Balth. Jul. Esch. Vio. Serv. Signior Claudio, now under an Arrest, Desires to speak with you. Luc. How! under Arrest? The Governour's house Is no proper place for a Prisoners visit. Pray favour me so much as to tell him that I'll come down to receive his commands. [Ex. Serv. Luc. Enter Provost, Claudio, Officers. Claud. Thus can the Demi-god Authority make Us pay down for our offence by weight [Enter Lucio. Luc. Claudio! how now! from whence comes this restraint? Claud. From too much liberty. As Surfet is the father of a Fast, So Liberty by the immoderate use, Turns to restraint. Our Nature does pursue An evil Thirst, and when we drink we dye. Luc. If I could speak as wisely under Arrest, I would send for some of my Creditors; Yet (to say truth) I had rather enjoy The foppery of freedom, than the wise Morality of Imprisonment. What Is thy offence Claudio? Claud. To speak of it were to offend again. Luc. What is it, Murder? Claud. No. Luc. I believe 'tis that which the precise call Incontinence. Claud. You may call it so. [Enter Balthazar. Bal. I am told Claudio is Arrested. Luc. 'Tis too true, Balthazar. Bal. What is his crime? Luc. Lord Angelo has taught us so much modesty, That I am asham'd to name it. Balth. What, is there a Maid with Child by him? Luc. No, but I fear there is a Woman with Maid by him. Prov. Signior, I shall offend if you stay here: Be pleas'd to go. Claud. Provost, allow me but a few words more. Luc. Pray Claudio speak your mind: we are your friends. Claud. I grieve to tell you, Gentlemen, that I Have got possession of Julietta's bed. She is my Wife by sacred vows, and by. A contract seal'd with form of witnesses. But we the ceremony lack of marriage, And that, unhappily, we did defer Only for the assurance of a Dowry, Remaining in the Coffers of her Friends; From whom we thought it fit to hide our love, Till time had master'd their consent to it. But so it happens, that Our oft stoln pleasure is now writ With Characters too gross in Juliet. Bal. With Child perhaps. Claud. 'Tis so; And the new Deputy Awakens all the enroll'd penalties, Which have been Nineteen years unread, and makes Me feel the long neglected punishment, By such a Law, as three days after Arrest, requires the forfeit of my head. Luc. Thy head stands now so slightly On thy shoulders, that a Milk-maid, if she Be in love, may sigh it off. Bal. Lucio, you are a stranger to Lord Angelo, But I well know the sowreness of his Soul: And I was told in passing to you hither, That Juliet is Arrested in his house, And forc'd from the protection of The Lady Beatrice his fair Ward. Luc. I like it not: send quickly to the Duke, And then appeal to him. Claud. I have done so; but he's not to be found. I prethee, Lucio, lend me thy assistance; This day my Sister should the Cloister enter, And there receive her approbation. Acquaint her with the danger I am in. Implore her in my name, that she make friends To the strict Deputy: she must her self assay him; I have great hope in that; for in her youth There is a sweet and speechless dialect, Such as moves men; and well she can perswade. Luc. I wish she may. I would be loth That any of my friends should foolishly Play away their lives at a Game of Tick-tack. Bal. We will both to her presently. Claud. Come Officers, away! [Exeunt. Enter Duke and Fryer Thomas. Duke. No, Holy Father; throw away that thought; Lov's too tender to dwell in my cold bosom. I desire you to give me secret harbour, For a design more grave and wrinkled than The aims of giddy youth can have. Fryer. May your Grace speak of it? Duke. None, Holy Father, better knows than you, How I have ever lik'd a life retir'd; And still have weary of Assemblies been, Where witless youth comes drest to be ador'd. I have deliver'd to Lord Angelo (A man of strictness, and firm abstinence) My absolute pow'r and place here in Turin; And he believes me travelling to Spain; Now (pious Sir) you will demand of me Why I did this? Fryer. I fain would know. Duke. We have strict Statutes, and chastising Laws, Which I have suffer'd Nineteen years to sleep, Even like an o'regrown Lyon in a Cave That goes not out to Prey. But as fond Fathers Bind up the threatning Rod, and stick it in Their Childrens sight, for terror more than use, Till it in time become more markt than fear'd; So our decrees, dead to infliction, to Themselves are dead, and froward liberty, Does Justice strike, as Infants beat the Nurse. Fryer. This ty'd-up Justice, Sir, you might have soon Let loose, which would have seem'd more dreadful Than in Angelo. Duke. Too dreadful, Sir. For since It was my fault to give the People scope, It may seem tyranny to punish them, For what I bid them act. We do no less Than bid unlawful actions to be done, When evil deeds have their permissive Pass. Fry. I am convinc'd. Duke. I have on Angelo impos'd Th'unpleasant pow'r of punishing; who may Within the Ambush of my name,—strike home. And to behold how he does rule, I will, As if I were a Brother of your Order, Visit both Prince and People. Therefore, I pray, Supply me with the Habit, and instruct me how I may in person a true Fryar seem. I can allow you no more reasons for This action now, than that Lord Angelo Stands at a Guard with Envy, and does scarce Confess that his bloud flows; The Man seems singular, but we shall see, If Pow'r change purpose, what our seemers be. [Exeunt. Enter Isabella, and Francisca a Nun. Isa. But have you Nuns no further priviledge? Nun. Are not these large enough? Isa. They are; I speak not as desiring more, But rather wishing a more strict restraint Were on the Sisterhood vow'd to Saint Clare. Luc. Ho! peace be in this place! [Lucio, Balthazar within. Isab. Who is it that does call? Nun. It is a mans voice. Gentle Isabella, Pray turn the Key, and know his business of him: You may, I may not; you are yet unsworn. When you have vow'd you must not speak with men, But in the presence of the Prioress; Then if you speak, you must not shew your face; Or if you shew your face, you must not speak. Luc. Ho! the Sisterhood. Nun. He calls again; I pray you answer him. Isab. Peace and Prosperity. Who is't that calls? [Enter Luc. Balt. Luc. Hail Virgin! please you befriend us so, As to permit us to the sight of Isabell, A novice of this place, and Sister to Young Claudio, her unhappy Brother. Isab. Why her unhappy Brother? Let me ask; The rather since I now must make it known I am that Isabella, and his Sister. Luc. Gentle, and fair; your Brother kindly greets you. Bal. We cannot, Lucio, come too suddenly With sorrows to a mind prepar'd; 'tis fit You tell her that her Brother is in Prison. Isab. Ay me! for what? Luc. For that which cannot be excus'd; And yet, perhaps if he were try'd By Judges not much older than himself, Would have an easie punishment. He has, I hope unwillingly, got his friend with Child. Is. Sir, make me not your scorn. Luc. I would not, though 'tis my familiar sin, To jest with Maids, play with all Vigins so. I hold you as a thing inshrin'd, and to Be talkt with as a Saint in all sincerity. Is. You hurt the good in mocking me. Bal. Believe what he has said is truth. Isab. Some one with Child by him? my Cousin Juliet? Luc. Is she your Cousin? Isab. Adoptedly, as School-maids change their names. Luc. She it is. Isab. Let him marry her. Bal. Marry'd, they are in sight of Heaven, though not With such apparent forms, as makes the Law Approve and witness it. Luc. The Duke is very strangely gone from hence; And with full force of his authority, Lord Angelo now Rules; a man whose bloud Is very Snow-broth, one who never feels The wanton motions of the sense; but does Rebate and blunt his natural edge, With Morals, Lady. He studies much, And fasts. Balt. To frighten Libertines (who long have scap'd, And silently have run by th'sleeping face Of hideous Law, as Mice by Lyons steal) Lord Angelo has hastily awak'd A dreadful act, under whose heavy sense, Your Brothers life falls into desperate forfeit. Luc. All hope is gone, unless you have the grace, By moving Prayers, to soften Angelo. Isab. Does he so sternly seek his life? Luc. He has already sentenc'd him, and (as I hear) the Provost has a Warrant for His Execution. Isab. Alas, what poor abilities Have I to do him good? Balt. Make tryal of what pow'r you have. Isab. My pow'r alas I doubt! Luc. Go to Lord Angelo, and let him know, When Virgins sue, men give like Gods; But when they weep and kneel, no pow'r has then So much of Devil in't, as not to yield. Isab. I'll see what I can do. Luc. But speedily. Isab. I will about it straight; Not staying longer, than to give the Mother Notice of my business. I humbly thank you. Commend me to my Brother. Soon at night I'll send him certain word of my success. Luc. We take our leaves. Isab. Heaven guide you, Gentlemen; And so prepare to Angelo my way, As if Saint Clare did prompt me how to pray. [Exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. SCENE I. Enter Angelo, Benedick. Ben. But for ill doing, Sir, must Claudio dye? Ang. The Law appoints that he Who gets a Child unlawfully must dye. Ben. But must a man be requited with death, For giving life to another? Ang. We must not make a scare-crow of the Law; Setting it up to fright our Birds of prey; And let it keep one shape, till custom makes it Not their terrour, but their Pearch. Ben. Call, Sir, your own affections to accompt. Had time concur'd with place, or place with wishing; And had the resolution of your blood, Found means t'attain th'effect of your own purpose, Perhaps, in some hot season of your life, Even you, Sir, would have err'd in that, For which you censure him. Ang. 'Tis one thing to be tempted, Benedick, Another thing to fall. I not deny The Jury passing on a Prisoners life, May in the sworn twelve, have a Thief or two Guiltier than him they try. What knows the Law, Whether Thieves pass on Thieves? You cannot lessen his offence, because I have offended too: but tell me at That time, when I, who censure him, do so Offend; and my own judgment then shall be A pattern for my death. Brother, he must dye. Ben. Sir, when I heard you had the place of Justice, I did not think your gravity did mean To swagger with her broad Sword. Can Dame Justice Become, so soon, so notable a Cutter? Ang. You have leave to be pleasant; but I pray Listen to Eschalus, he'll give you counsel. [Exit, and Enter Eschalus. Ben. Good Eschalus, I should have found you out. Is there no means to save poor Claudio's life? Esch. Your Brother has given order to the Provost, To see his Execution punctually Perform'd, by nine to morrow morning. Ben. A short warning for a terrible long Journey. Esch. A Confessor will be sent to prepare him. Ben. I'm told, Signior Eschalus, you have counsel for me. Esch. My Lord, I'll not presume to call it mine; 'Tis from your Brother, who does well advise, That you would please to think of marriage. You know the Lady Beatrice was his Ward; And now her Wardship is expir'd. Ben. Marry? What to beget Boys for the Headsman? Esch. Good my Lord, leaving your severity, You needs must think her beauty worth your praise. Ben. She's too low for a high praise, and too little For a great praise; but thus far I'll commend her; Were she other than she is, she were then Unhandsom, and being no other but As she is, I do not like her. Esch. My proposal deserves a steady answer. Ben. My Brother, Sir, and I, walk several ways. He takes care to destroy unlawful Lovers; And I'll endeavour to prevent th'increase Of lawful Cuckolds. Esch. None of the beauteous Sex can have more virtue, Than fair Beatrice. Ben. Sir, I sincerely allow your opinion. She is yet very exceedingly virtuous, And has a laziness towards love: but, Sir, She has too much wit, and great Wits will not long Lye idle. Esch. You have too much mirth to have suspicion. Ben. As I will not do Ladies so much wrong To mistrust any, so I'll do my self The right to trust none. Esch. This sutes not with your Brothers purpose. [Enter Lucio, Balth. Ben. Welcome, are either of you inclin'd to marriage? Balt. How, marriage? it is a noose for Ninnies; Do you think I will have a Recheat winded In my forehead, or hang my Bugle in An invisible Baldrick? Luc. If I ever marry, let mine eyes be Pickt out with the Pen of a Ballad-maker, And hang me up at the door of a Brothel, For the Sign of blind Cupid. Ben. You see, Signior Eschalus, my Brother makes So many Enemies to propagation, That if the Duke stay long, he may chance find A Dominion without Subjects. Luc. If he have any, they will need No Governour, for they will all be old Enough to govern themselves. [Enter Beatrice, Viola. Ben. Here comes the Lady April, whose fair face Is always incident to some foul weather. Beat. I wonder you will still be talking, Benedick; No body marks you. Ben. I mean to drink Opium before I come in your Company, That you may excuse my follies, With saying, I talk in my sleep. Beat. Where is Lord Angelo? Esch. Madam, he is retir'd. Beat. What to his Prayers? As Executioners kneel down and ask pardon, Before they handle the Axe. Ben. Hale in Maine-Bolin! the storm begins! Beat. Heaven send the good Duke here again! do you Not hear, Signior, Eschalus, of the Mutiny In Town? Esch. No, Madam, is there a Mutiny? Beat. All the Midwives, Nurses, and Milk-women Are up in Arms, because the Governour Has made a Law against Lovers. Ben. True, the Law is, that none who have not been Bound Prentices to Hymen, shall set up In the trade of making Children. Esch. Madam, you will marry, and have your freedom. Beat. Marry? yes, if you'll fashion me a man Of a middle constitution, between Lord Angelo's Carthusian gravity, And his Brother Benedick; the one is Too like a State-Image and says nothing; And the other, too like a Country Lady's Eldest Son, evermore talking. Ben. Nay do but persecute my Brother, And I am satisfy'd. Beat. Signior Eschalus, is not my Wardship out? Esch. Yes, Madam. Beat. And this House, where the Governour lives, mine own? Esch. Madam, it is. Beat. Methinks my Guardian Is but a rude Tenant. How durst he with Unmanly power, force my Cousin Juliet from me? Esch. Lady, it was the Law that us'd that force. Beat. The Law? is she not married by such Vows As will stand firm in Heaven? that's the substantial part Which carries the effect, and must she then Be punisht for neglect of form? Must conscience be made good by compliment? Ben. My Brother will have men behave themselves To Heaven, as Boys do to their Pedants: they Must not say grace, without making their legs. Beat. I am glad Benedick, to hear you Sometimes in the right. Ben. I'm in the right, Lady, only As often as you are in the wrong. Beat. Pray, Signior Eschalus, desire my Guardian To let the Divines govern the Civilians. I would have my Cousins spiritual marriage Stand good in conscience, though 'tis bad in Law. She must not be lockt up within thick Walls, And Iron Grates. A Wood-bine Arbour will Prove strong enough to hold a Lady, when She is grown so weak as to be in love. Viol. Pray, Sister, why is Juliet in Prison? Beat. Peace, Viola, you are too young to know. Ben. She play'd with a bearded Baby, Mistress, Contrary to Law. Viol. Alas, poor Juliet! I'll sing no more To the Governour, till he lets her out. Beat. Sir, the Deputy drinks too much Vinegar; It makes his disposition sowr. Esch. Pray, Madam, tell him so. Beat. No, Sir, you States-men manage your discourse Amongst your selves by signs. I am not mute Enough to understand your Mysteries. Come, Viola, I'll write to the Duke. [Exeunt Beat. Viol. Ben. This would make a rare Wife, were she not A woman. Balt. You with the men, and she with the maids, will Quickly forbid all Banes. Luc. If we do not Bring ill Poesies of Wedding Rings out of Fashion, let's not be numbred with the Wits. [Exeunt. Enter Angelo and Provost. Ang. What is your business, Provost? Prov. Is it your will Claudio shall dye to morrow? Ang. Did I not say he should? had you not order? Why do you ask again? Prov. Lest I might be too rash. Under your good correction, I have seen When, after execution, the wise Judge Has his rash doom repented. Ang. Do you your office, or else give it up, And you shall well be spar'd. Prov. I crave your Excellencies pardon. What shall be done with the weeping Juliet? Ang. Dispose of her to some apartment in The Prison, where Claudio may not see her. [Enter Servant. Serv. Here is a Sister of the man condemn'd, Desires access to you. Ang. Already is his Sister come, She has the reputation, Provost, of A virtuous Maid. Prov. I, my good Lord, a very virtuous Maid, And to be shortly of a Sisterhood. Ang. Let her be admitted. [Exit Servant. Provost take care that Juliet be remov'd At distance from her Lover. [Enter Lucio, Isabella. Prov. Heaven still preserve your Excellence. Ang. Stay here awhile. Y'are welcome, what's your will? Isab. I am a woful Sutor to your Excellence, If you in goodness will vouchsafe to hear me. Ang. What is your suit? Isab. There is a vice which most I do abhor, And most desire that it should meet rebuke; For which I would not plead, but that I must. Ang. Well, come to the matter. Isab. I have a Brother is condemn'd to dye. I would beseech you to condemn the fault, and not My Brother. Prov. Heaven give thee moving graces! Ang. Is not each fault condemn'd e're it be done? I were the very Cipher of Authority, If I should fine the fault, whose fine stands in Record, and yet forgive the Actor. Isab. Oh just! but yet severe Law! I had a Brother then. Heaven keep you, Sir. Luc. Give it not over so, to him again: Kneel down before him; y'are too cold. Isab. Must he needs dye? Ang. Virgin, no remedy. Isab. Yes, I believe that you might pardon him; And neither Heaven, nor man, would at The mercy grieve. Ang. I will not do't. Isab. You can then if you would? Ang. That which I should not do, I cannot do. Isab. But you may do it, Sir, and do the world No hurt: I would your heart were toucht with such Remorse, as mine is to him. Ang. He's sentenc'd, 'tis too late. Luc. You are too tame. Isab. Too late? I who have spoke a word, may call The meaning back. No Ceremony, No Ornament which to the Great belongs; Not the Kings Crown, nor the deputed Sword, The Martial's Truncheon, nor the Judges Robe, Become them with so beautiful a grace As mercy does. If he had been as you, And you as he, you might have err'd like him; But he like you, would not have been so stern. Ang. I pray be gone. Isab. Would Heaven, if you were Isabell, that I A while might have your pow'r, to let you see How soon the sorrow of a Sisters tears, Should clense the soulness of a Brothers fault. Luc. That is the Vain, touch it boldly. Ang. Your Brother is a forfeit of the Law; And you but waste your words. Isab. Alas, alas, all Souls were forfeit once; And he who might the vantage best have took, Found out the remedy. What would you do If he, who on the utmost top of heights, On Judges sits, should judge you as you are? Ang. Be you content, fair Maid, It was the Law, not I, condemn'd your Brother; Were he my Kinsman or my Son, it should Be with him thus. And he must dye to morrow. Isab. To morrow? Oh that's sudden! spare him! spare him! He's not prepar'd. Even for our Kitchins we The Fowl of Season kill. Shall we serve Heaven With less respect, than we would minister To our gross selves? My Lord, in mercy speak! Who is it that has dy'd for this offence? Too many have committed it. Luc. Well said. Ang. The Law has not been dead, though it has slept. Those many had not dar'd to act that crime, If he who first did the edict infringe, Had answer'd for his deed. 'Tis now awake; Takes note of what is done, and Prophet-like, Looks in a Glass, which shows what future ills, Might by remissness be in progress hatcht. Isab. Yet show some pity. Ang. I show it most, when I most Justice show, For I commiserate then, even those whom I Shall never know; and whose offences, if They were forgiven, might afterwards destroy them. And also do him right, who, punisht for One pleasing crime, lives not to act another. Be satisfy'd; your Brother dies to morrow. Isab. So you, my Lord, must be the first that e're This sentence gave, and he the first that suffers it. 'Tis excellent to have a Giants strength; But Tyrannous to use it like a Giant. Luc. Well said again. Isab. If men could thunder As great Jove does, Jove ne'er would quiet be; For every cholerick petty Officer, Would use his Magazine in Heaven for Thunder: We nothing should but Thunder hear. Sweet Heaven! Thou rather with thy stiff and sulph'rous bolt Dost split the knotty and obdurate Oak, Than the soft Mirtle. O but man, proud man! (Drest in a little brief authority, Most ignorant of what he thinks himself Assur'd) does in his glassy essence, like An angry Ape, play such fantastick tricks Before high Heaven, as would make Angels laugh If they were mortal, and had spleens like us. Luc. To him, he will relent, I feel him coming. Prov. Pray Heaven she gain him! Ang. Why do you use this passion before me? Isab. Authority, though it does err like others, Yet has a kind of Med'cine in it self, Which skins the top of every vice. Knock at your bosom, Sir, and ask your heart If it contains no crime, resembling my Poor Brothers fault, and then, if it confess A natural guiltiness, such as his is, Let it not sound a sentence from your tongue, Against my Brothers life. Ang. She speaks such sense As with my reason breeds such Images, As she has excellently form'd. Farewel. Isab. Gentle, my Lord, turn back! Ang. I will bethink me, come again to morrow. Isab. Heark, how I'll bribe you; good my Lord turn back. Ang. How! bribe me? Isab. I, with such gifts that Heaven shall share with you. Luc. You had marr'd all else. Isab. With early Prayers that shall be up at Heaven, And enter there before The mornings Casement opens to the World; The Prayers of fasting maids. Ang. Well, come to me to morrow. Luc. Enough, away! Isab. All that is good be near your Excellence. Ang. I thank you. Isab. At what hour shall I attend you. Ang. At any time e're noon. Isab. The Angels still preserve you. [Exeunt all but Angelo. Ang. From all, but from thy virtue maid! I love her virtue. But, temptation! O! Thou false and cunning guide! who in disguise Of Virtues shape lead'st us through Heaven to Hell. No vitious Beauty could with practis'd Art Subdue, like Virgin-innocence, my heart. [Exit. Enter Duke in disguise of a Fryar, and Provost. Duke. Hail to you, Provost, so I think you are. Prov. I am the Provost. What's your will, good Father? Duke. Bound by my charity, and my blessed Orders, I come to visit the afflicted minds In Prison here. Do me the common right, To let me see them; and to let me know The nature of their crimes; that I may minister Accordingly to their relief. Prov. I would do more than that, if more were needful. Look, here comes one, who in her flames of youth [Enter Juliet. Has blister'd her fair fame. She is with Child, And he that got it sentenc'd. Duke. When must he dye? Prov. As I believe, to morrow. I'll go in, and prepare him for your visit: In the mean time bestow your counsel here. [Exit Provost. Duke. Repent you (fair one) of the sin you carry? Jul. I bear my punishment most patiently. Duke. I'll teach you how you shall arraign your conscience, And try your penitence. Jul. I'll gladly learn. Duke. Lov'd you the man that wrong'd you? Jul. Yes, as I lov'd the woman that wrong'd him. Duke. So then it seems you mutually have sin'd? Jul. We mutually have sin'd against the Law: And I repent for it, but am as much Afflicted at my ignorance, Not knowing 'twas a sin when I transgrest, As at the sin it self. Duke. If Daughter you repent that sin, because It brings you shame, it is a common, and An erring grief, which looks more at our selves, Than towards Heaven; not sparing Heaven for love, But fear. Jul. As 'tis an evil I repent, and grieve not for The shame, because you think it is deserv'd. Duke. There rest. Your Partner (as I hear) must dye to morrow; And I am going with instructions to him. Grace go with you. [Exit. Jul. Must dye to morrow? oh injurious love! It respites me a life whose very best Is still a dying horror. [Exit. Enter Claudio, Lucio, Balthazar. Balth. Claudio, to tarry longer with you now, Were but to lose that time which we Must husband for your benefit. No care Is wanting in your Sister, nor in us. Luc. Our Lawyers make good Merchandise of Women, The head of a man pays for a maidenhead. Claud. There is no rack so painful in this Prison, As that which stretches me 'tween hope and doubt. All I desire is certainty. Balt. You speak as if you were already in Another world; for there's no certainty In this. We'll see you hourly, so farewel. Luc. When I leave this wanting world, to meet death, I'll ride Post to him on a Hobby-horse, And fence against his Dart with a Fools Bauble. Claud. By all your loyal friendship, Balthazar, Let Juliet be protected with your care, And courage, from injurious tongues. Balt. I will deserve your trust. Claud. Pray serve her with a noble tenderness, In all that her afflictions shall require. Balt. I need not such a strict command. Away, let's leave him to his meditations. Luc. Remember Claudio, This wicked world does homage to rich Fools, And witty men want money. Enter Provost. Prov. A Father desires to speak with you. [Ex. Claudio, Provost. Luc. Methinks it is too late for Claudio to Expect a Reprieve. Balt. Hope is so familiar an acquaintance, That though she stays with us all day, yet we Are loth to part with her at night. Luc. Where is Benedick? Balt. Gone to Beatrice, she just now sent for him. Luc. We shall never out-face the world with our Invectives against marriage, for I find Sexes will meet, though Mountains and rough Seas Make a long space between them. Our design On Benedick and Beatrice must be pursu'd. Balt. Let's to the Governours, and in the way I'll tell thee how we ought to manage it. [Exeunt. Enter Angelo. Ang. My weighty Office I can value now, But as an idle plume worn in the wind. [Enter Servant. Serv. The Sister, Sir, of Claudio desires access. Ang. Shew her the way into the Gallery. [Exit Servant. Why does my blood, thus flowing to my heart, Make it unable for it self, whilst then It dispossesses other parts of that Which they in lesser streams would useful make? So deal officious throngs, with him who swounds; They come to help him, and they stop the air By which he should revive; and so The numerous Subjects to a well-wisht King, Quit their own home, and in rude fondness to His presence crowd, where their unwelcome love, Does an offence, and an oppression prove. [Exit.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. Scene I. Enter Isabel, Angelo. Isab. I am come to know your pleasure. Ang. That you might know it would much better please me, Than to demand what 'tis: your Brother cannot live. Isab. Even so, Heaven keep your Excellence. Ang. Stay a little, For he perhaps may live awhile: nay, and As long as you or I, since none can know Their own appointed ends. Yet, he must dye. Isab. Under your sentence? Ang. Yes. Isab. When, I beseech you? that in his Reprieve (Longer or Shorter) he may be so fitted That his Soul may not suffer with his body. Ang. He had a filthy vice. It were as good To pardon him that has from Nature stoln A man already made, as to permit Their sawcy sweetness, who Heavens Image coyn In Stamps which are forbid. Isab. That is set down in Heaven, but not on Earth. Ang. How? say you so? then I shall quickly poze you. Which had you rather, that the most just Law Should take your Brothers life, or to redeem him, Give up your pretious self to such a blemish As she permitted whom he stain'd? Isab. I'll rather give my Body than my Soul. Ang. I talk not of your soul. Our compell'd sins Do more for number stand, than for account. Isab. How say you, Sir? Ang. Nay, I'll not warrant that: for I can speak Against the thing I say: answer to this. I (now the voice of the recorded Law) Pronounce a sentence on your Brothers life, Might there not be a charity in sin, To save this Brother's life? Isab. Please you to do't, I'll take it as a peril to my soul, It is no sin at all, but charity. Ang. You doing it at peril of your soul, Make equal poize of sin and charity. Isab. That I do beg his life, if it be sin, Heav'n let me bear't. If it be sin for you To grant my suit, I'll make it still my Prayer, To have it added to the faults of mine, And not to your account. Ang. Nay, but hear me. Your sense pursues not mine; sure you are ignorant; Or seem so craftily, and that's not good. Isab. Let me be ignorant, and in nothing good, But graciously to know I am no better. Ang. Thus Wisdom wishes to appear most bright, When it does tax it self; as a black Mask Often proclaims a cover'd beauty more, Than beauty does it self, when openly Displaid. But mark me Isabell, Or if I may more plainly be receiv'd, I'll speak more home. Your Brother is to dye. Isab. So! Ang. And his offence is such, as it appears Accountant to the Law. Isab. True! Ang. Admit no other way could save his life, (As I subscribe not that, nor any other, Unless by way of question) but that you (Finding your self desir'd of such a man Whose credit with the Judge, could free your Brother) Must either yield the treasures of your youth, Or else must let him dye: what would you do? Isab. As much for my poor Brother, as for Isabell. Th'impression of sharp whips I gladly would As Rubies wear, and strip my self Even for a Grave, as for a Bed, e're I Would yield my honour up to shame. Ang. Then must your Brother dye. Isab. And 'twere the cheaper way. Better it were a Brother dye a while, Than that a Sister, by redeeming him, Should dye for ever. Ang. Are you not then as cruel as that sentence Which you have slander'd so? Isab. Ignoble ransom, no proportion bears To pardon freely given; and lawful mercy, Is not at all akin to foul redemption. Ang. You seem'd of late to make the Law a Tyrant; And so your Brothers guiltiness excus'd, As if it rather might be stil'd A recreation than a vice. Isab. O pardon me my Lord. Oft it falls out, That Pleaders speak not what they mean, In hope to get what they would have. I sometimes may excuse the thing I hate, For his advantage, whom I dearly love. Ang. We are all frail. Isab. Else let my Brother dye. Ang. Nay, Women are frail too. Isab. I, as the glasses where they see themselves, Which are as eas'ly broke, as they make forms. Women? help Heaven! pray call us ten times frail, For we are soft, as our complexions are, And soon a bad impression take. Ang. And from this testimony of your own Sex, (Since I suppose we are not made so strong, But that our faults, may shake our frames) let me Be bold t'arrest your words. Be what you are, That is, a woman, if y'are more, y'are none, If you be one (as you are well exprest By all external warrants) shew it now. Isab. I have no Tongue but one. Gentle my Lord, Let me intreat you speak the former language. Ang. Plainly conceive, I love you. Isab. My Brother did love Juliet; And you tell me he shall dye for it. Ang. He shall not, Isabel, if you give me love. Isab. Your pow'r may your discretion licence give, And make you seem much fouler than you are, To draw on others. Ang. Believe me on mine honour, My words express my purpose. Isab. Ha! little honour, to be much believ'd, Your purpose is pernicious now discern'd. I will proclaim thee Angelo, look for't; Sign me a present pardon for my Brother, Or I will tell the world aloud What man thou art. Ang. Who will believe you Isabell? My unsoil'd name, austerity of life, My word against you, and my place i'th' State, Will so your accusation overweigh, That you'll be stifled in your own report. And now I give my sensual race the rains. Yield to my passion, or your Brother must Not only dye, but your unkindness shall Draw out his death to lingring pains. To morrow answer me, or by that love Which now does guide me, I will be A Tyrant to him. [Exit. Isab. To whom shall I complain? If I tell this, who will believ't? I'll to my Brother straight, That he may know false Angelo's request, And then prepare for his eternal rest. [Exit. Enter Benedick and Beatrice, several ways. Ben. I was told, Lady, you would speak with me. Beat. I would, and I would not. Ben. Then I'll stay, or I will not stay; 'Tis all one to me. Beat. Nay, I know you are but an indifferent man: Yet now by chance, I rather am inclin'd That you should stay. Ben. And 'tis a greater chance That our inclinations should so soon meet; For I will stay. Beat. Your Brother is a proper Prince, he rules With a Rod in's hand instead of a Scepter, Like a Country School-Master in a Church; He keeps a large Palace with no Attendants, And is fit to have none but Boys for his Subjects. Ben. As ill as he governs (if my Design thrive against the Fetters of marriage, As his does against the liberty of Lovers) This rule may last till the end of the world; For there will be no next Generation. Beat. Would I might trust you Benedick. Ben. Madam, you believe me to have some honour. If you have most secretly invented A new Dressing, can you think I'll reveal The fashion, before you wear it? Beat. Notwithstanding your seeming indisposition To inventions of Fashions, yet there be Those in Turin, who have intercepted Packets between you and Taylors of Paris. Well, though those are but light correspondents, Yet I would trust you in matter of weight. Ben. I hope, Lady, you have no plot upon me. I'll marry no woman. Beat. I did not think you had been so well natur'd, As to prevent the having any of Your breed. Marry you? what should I do with you? Dress you in my old Gown, and make you my Waiting Woman? Ben. A waiting Woman with a Beard? Beat. I shall ne'er endure a Husband with a Beard. I had rather lye in woolen. Ben. Though you disguise matrimonial pretensions, With pretty scorn, yet I am glad I have A Beard for my own defence. And though fashion Makes me shave much (and that you believe me A lover of fashions) yet mine shall grow To a very bush, for my greater security. But, pray proceed to your matter of weight. Beat. I will trust you; not as a man of love, But a man of Arms. Ben. At your own peril. And more t'encourage you, I will declare That though I'm very loth to come within The narrow compass of a Wedding Ring; Yet I owe every fair Lady a good turn. But to the business. Beat. In brief you must Renew familiarity with your Brother; And steal the use of his Signet to seal Julietta's pardon and her liberty, And Claudio's too: this done, they shall practise Their escape, I'll endeavour mine; and you Signior may shift for your self. Ben. This is but betraying an ill Brother, For a good purpose; I'll do't if I can. Beat. You shall give me the Signet, for I'll have All in my own management. Ben. No, though I rob my Brother of the Signet; You shall not rob me of the danger. Beat. Then I'll proceed no further. Ben. That as you please. Beat. You would have the honour of the business. Ben. 'Tis due to my Sex. Beat. Fare you well Sir—yet you May come again an hour hence, to receive An ill look. Ben. That will not fright me much; for you can look No better than you use to do. [Ex. Ben. at one door. Enter Viola at another. Viol. Sister, I have got Verses. Signior Lucio Made them: he and Balthazar are within. Beat. Is Lucio become a man of meetre? That's the next degree upward to the giddy Station of a foolish Lover. They are Compos'd into a Song too. Sing it Viola. Viola sings the SONG. Viol. [1.] Wake all the dead! what hoa! what hoa! How soundly they sleep whose Pillows lye low? They mind not poor Lovers who walk above On the Decks of the World in storms of love. No whisper now nor glance can pass Through Wickets or through Panes of Glass; For our Windows and Doors are shut and barr'd. Lye close in the Church, and in the Church-yard. In ev'ry Grave make room, make room! The Worlds at an end, and we come, we come. 2. The State is now Love's foe, Love's foe; Has seiz'd on his Arms, his Quiver and Bow; Has pinion'd his wings, and fetter'd his feet, Because he made way for Lovers to meet. But O sad chance, his Judge was old; Hearts cruel grow, when blood grows cold. No man being young, his process would draw. O Heavens that love should be subject to law! Lovers go woo the dead, the dead! Lye two in a Grave, and to Bed, to Bed! Enter Lucio, Balthazar. Beat. Signior Lucio, you are grown so desp'rate As to write Verses. Luc. Very little business, much love, And no money makes up a parcel-Poet. But the Verses are not mine. Beat. Whose are they? Luc. Balthazar knows the Author. Balt. Not better than you, who had them from him. Luc. Pray, Madam, let him tell you. Balt. Excuse me, Sir, I am as chary of Getting my friend the ill name of a Poet, As you are. Beat. Why Gentlemen, you will not make A secret of telling the hour of the day, When your Watches are ready to strike? Pray whose are the Verses? Luc. Madam, the Author's name is Benedick. Beat. Is't possible? I am glad he lies bare Under the lash of the Wits. There are now No such Tormentors in Turin as the Wits. Poor Benedick, they'll have him on the Rack E're night; why they will draw a strong line, to The subtle weakness of a Spinners thred. Balth. I fear he will be quickly liable To a greater torment, than any that The Wits can inflict. Luc. Madam, we are your vow'd Servants, We cannot chuse but tell you all. Balthazar, You made the first discovery, you may speak it. Balt. Madam, 'tis not civil to lengthen your Expectation. He is in love. Beat. In love? that were a sudden change, and would shew More of the Moon in him, than is in a Mad-woman. Good Balthazar with whom? Balt. Lucio was ready to dye laughing when He found it, and swore then he would tell you. Beat. Keep your oath, Lucio; who is't that has caught him? Luc. Nay, Madam, you now impose upon me. Beat. Let me intreat you. Luc. Why then, as sure as you can love no Lover, He loves you. Beat. This sounds like fiction and design. Good Balthazar, he is but newly gone From hence, go seek him out, and bring him back; Your friendship may prevail with him. Luc. It will beget more mirth, than belongs To a Morrice, in the month of May. Balt. But I beseech you no words of our discov'ry. Beat. Signior, you may trust me. [Exit Balthazar. Perhaps, Lucio, you cannot think it strange, That I believe you of my Party; And fitter for my trust than Balthazar. Luc. O no, Madam, I have been trusted by Young Ladies e're now. Beat. Are you sure Benedick loves me? he has No fashion of a Lover in publick. Luc. Poor man, he has two contrary extreams Of Love-madness. He is in company As fantastical as a Fencer after His victory in a Prize; but in private He will sigh more than an old Dutch Pilot That has lost his Ship. Beat. I shall have rare diversion if his fit holds. Luc. It is not good to jest away mens lives. Beat. I see you are serious: but will you swear this? Luc. If you can endure the coorseness of swearing; I've been unlucky at play in my time, And shall quickly swear like a losing Gamester. Beat. Stay Sir, you may take up the fools commodity Of belief, without ingaging of oaths: I know you are a man of excellent temper. Luc. Madam, I swear by— Beat. I pray Sir hold!— Luc. Nay if you would put me to't. Beat. Lucio, you must diswade him from his love; And I must trust you. I have but one heart, And that is already dispos'd off. Luc. Madam, all Lovers compar'd to Benedick, Are but lamentable Courtiers in old Cloaths. Beat. Truly, he was wont to be merry. Luc. E're he felt Love, his heart was as sound As any Bell, and his Tongue was the Clapper: For what his Heart thought, his Tongue would speak. Take heed, you must not lose him. Beat. Lucio, my heart is design'd to another. Luc. Madam, may I be bold t'enquire to whom? Beat. You know the man. Luc. Be he what he will, he must shew as ugly As a tall man, sitting on a low stool Before a Chimney, compar'd to Benedick. Beat. You ought not to say so, when I name him. Luc. Madam, I dare justifie my friend. Beat. I shall be angry if you compare him To him whom I can name. Suppose it is Signior Lucio. Luc. Madam, I confess Comparisons Are somewhat odious. Beat. O, are they so? I pray let me advise you Not to lessen your self; though I perceive You canot chuse but make much of your friend. Luc. Sits the wind on that side? I must hoise sail With Top, and Top-gallant. Beat. But are you not ty'd, Sir, by some deep vow To wooe for Benedick? I am very tender Of Mens vows. Luc. Will you believe me, Madam? Beat. Without oaths I beseech you. Luc. He knows as much the matter of this visit, As I do of the Great Turk's particular Inclination to Red Herring. Beat. Are you in earnest? Luc. Balthazar and I Were only over officious to serve him. Beat. Nor he is not in love? Luc. No more than a man that goes continually To Sea to make discoveries. Beat. Then it appears a little strange, That you made this hearty address for him. Luc. On my honour, Madam, it was to get Some opportunity to move for my self. Beat. And you think him no extraordinary wit? Luc. So, so, a modest wit, somewhat out of countenance Being laught at; for then he grows as melancholy As a Lodge in a Warren. Beat. Right, I use to laugh at him. And then there's a Partridge wing sav'd at night; For the Fool will eat no Supper. Luc. Madam, I see you know him. Beat. Signior Lucio, be kind to your self. [Exit. Luc. Lucio, if thou were't any thing but Lucio, I would hug thee to death. Some men in choler Rail against Fortune, but I adore her: She has made her sail of my Mothers Smock. I would the Poets would send us a dozen Such Goddesses. [Enter Balthazar. Bal. I have been seeking Benedick: and I Am told now, he's gone up the back-stairs, And is in private with the Deputy. Where's the Lady Beatrice? Luc. Balthazar, trouble not your self, for men May often lose their labour. Balt. How so? Luc. Benedick is not the man she aims at. Balt. He's very singular and eminent. But I confess, this angling for Ladies Is a very subtle sport. Luc. They are Fishes of fantastical palats; And will sometimes sooner bite at a Worm, Than at a May-Flye. Balt. She has a full fortune. Twelve thousand Crowns A year. Luc. He will be safe from Creditors that has her. [Enter Viola. Viol. Signior Lucio, my Sister would speak with you. [Exit. Luc. Balthazar, I must e'en retire from business; You see I cannot rest for Ladies. Balt. I prethee put the matter home. [Exeunt several ways. Enter Duke in Fryers Habit, Claudio, and Provost. Claud. Father, I thank you! I am now of Death's Small party, 'gainst the Crowd who strife for life. [Enter Isab. Isab. What hoa! Grace dwell within! Prov. Who's there? the wish deserves a welcome. Duke. Dear Sir, e're long I'll visit you again. Claud. Most rev'rend Sir, I thank you. Isab. My business is a word or two with Claudio. Prov. You are welcome. Look Signior, here's your Sister. Duke. Provost, a word. Prov. As many as you please. Duke. Bring me, where I conceal'd May hear them speak. [Ex. Duke, Provost. Claud. Now Sister, what's the comfort? Isab. 'Tis such as earthly comforts use to be, Lord Angelo, having affairs to Heaven, Intends you for his swift Ambassador. Therefore your best appointment make with speed; To morrow you set on. Claud. Is there no remedy? Isab. Yes Brother, you may live; There is a devillish mercy in the Judge If you'll implore it, that will free your life, But fetter you till death. Claud. Perpetual durance? Isab. 'Tis worse than close restraint, and painful too Beyond all tortures which afflict the body; For 'tis a Rack invented for the mind. Claud. But of what nature is it? Isab. 'Tis such, as should you give it your consent, Would leave you stript of all the wreaths of War, All ornaments my Father's valour gain'd, And shew you naked to the scornful world. Claud. Acquaint me with my doom. Isab. If I could fear thee, Claudio, I should weep Lest thou a shameful life shouldst entertain, And six or seven short Winters more respect, Than a perpetual honour. Dar'st thou dye? The sense of death is most in apprehension; And the small Beetle, when we tread on it, In corp'ral suff'rance, finds a pang as great, As when a Gyant dyes. Claud. Why give you me this shame? Think you I can a resolution fetch From tenderness? If I must dye, I'll welcome darkness as a shining Bride. Isab. There spoke my Brother: there my Fathers Grave Utter'd a chearful voice. Yes, you must dye, You are too noble to conserve a life By wretched remedies. Our outward Saint Does in his gracious looks disguise the Devil. His filth within being cast, he would appear A Pond, as foul as Hell. Claud. The princely Angelo? Isab. Oh, he is uglier than the frightful Fiend, By Pencils of our cloyster'd Virgins drawn. Speak, Claudio, could you think, you might on earth Be guiltless made by him, if I would Heaven (Which never injur'd us) fouly offend? Claud. Infernal Angelo! can this be true? Isab. Yes, he would clear you from your blackest crimes, By making me much blacker than himself, This night's the time, when he would have me do What I abhor to name, or else you must Be dead to morrow. Claud. Thou shalt not do't. Isab. O, were it but my life, I would for your deliverance throw it down, Most frankly, Claudio. Claud. Thanks dear Isabella. Isab. Be ready, Claudio, for your death to morrow. Claud. Has he Religion in him? sure he thinks It is no sin, or of the deadly seven He does believe it is the least. Isab. Which is the least? Claud. If it were damnable, he being wise Why would he for the momentary taste Of lust, eternally be fed with fire? But Isabell— Isab. What says my Brother? Claud. Death is a fearful thing. Isab. And living shame more hateful. Sure you have study'd what it is to dye. Claud. Oh Sister, 'tis to go we know not whither. We lye in silent darkness, and we rot; Where long our motion is not stopt; for though In Graves none walk upright (proudly to face The Stars) yet there we move again, when our Corruption makes those worms in whom we crawl. Perhaps the Spirit (which is future life) Dwells Salamander-like, unharm'd in fire: Or else with wand'ring winds is blown about The world. But if condemn'd like those Whom our incertain thought imagines howling; Than the most loath'd and the most weary life Which Age, or Ache, want, or imprisonment Can lay on Nature, is a Paradise To what we fear of death. Isab. Alas, alas! Claud. Sweet Sister! I would live, Were not the ransom of my life much more Than all your honour and your virtue too (By which you are maintain'd) can ever pay, Without undoing both. Isab. Prepare your self, your line of life is short. Claud. I am prepar'd: but Sister, if Your Brother you did ever love; or if Our Mothers pity may your pattern be, Let Juliet in your tender bosom dwell; Who has no blemish, if such Laws As innocent antiquity allow'd, Were now of force, or if Religion here In Turin, did not more subsist By publick form, than private use. Isab. You want Authority to tax the Law. Let your submission your last virtue be. Claud. Will you be good to Juliet? Isab. I will invite her to my breast, and to A cloyster'd shade, where we with mutual grief Will mourn, in sad remembrance of our loss. Claud. Your promise is now register'd in Heaven. Bear her this fatal pledge of our first Vows. [Gives her a Ring. Farewel. To cloyst'rall kindness both Retire, where you may ever live above The rage of pow'r, and injuries of love. [Exit, and the Duke steps in. Duke. Vouchsafe a word, young Sister, but one word. Isab. What is your will? Duke. I would some satisfaction crave of that, In which you likewise may have benefit. Isab. My sorrows, Father, hasten me away. I must beseech you to be brief. Duke. The hand which made you fair, has made you good. Th'assault which Angelo has to Your virtue given, chance to my knowledge brings. I have o'reheard you, and with much astonishment I gaze on th'Image you have made of Angelo. Isab. How is the noble Duke deceiv'd in such A Substitute? whose wickedness I will Proclaim to all the world. Duke. Your accusation he will soon avoid, By saying he but tryal of Your virtue made; therefore I wish you would Conceal his horrid purpose till fit time Shall serve you at the Duke's return: Do you conceive my counsel good? Isab. Father I am oblig'd to follow it. Duke. Where lodge you, virtuous Maid? Isab. The Sisterhood of Saint Clare will soon inform you. I lodge in the Apartment for probation. Duke. There I'll attend you Daughter. Grace preserve you. [Exeunt several ways. Enter Benedick and Beatrice at several doors, and Viola with her. Beat. O Sir! you are a very princely Lover! You cannot woo but by Ambassadors; And may chance to marry by Proxy. Ben. Your wit flows so fast That I'll not stem the tyde; I'll cast Anchor, And consult in your Cabin how t'avoid Danger. The Rocks are very near us. Beat. How now? afraid of the Deputy's Ghost E're he be dead? my Sister shall lead you Through the dark. Ben. There is the Pardon Sign'd for Juliet and for Claudio too. Beat. I thank you, Benedick. Give it me. Ben. You are as nimble as a Squirrel, but The Nuts are not so soon crackt. Beat. Unless I have it I'll take back my thanks. Ben. If it be possible to fix Quick-silver Stay but a little. Beat. What would you say? Ben. Eschalus is in the Plot, And was brought to't with more fears, than a furr'd Alderman to an insurrection Of Prentices. Beat. Signior Eschalus? could his gravity Venture to change his Gold Chain for a Halter? Ben. I was fain to pretend hourly correspondence With th'absent Duke; which gain'd me his respect. I assur'd him of promotion, and then He grew willing to betray his Friend And fellow-States-man my Brother. For men Of that Tribe are very loving, but especially To themselves. He surpriz'd the Signet, And counterfeited the hand. Beat. Give it me, I long to be about it. Ben. A little patience; You would make your self Ready without your Glass. Beat. These male-Conspirators are so tedious. Ben. I must convey it to the Provost, and Engage his secrecy. Beat. Make haste, you must not stay So long as to be civil to him at parting. Ben. My Coach attends me at the Gate. Beat. O, I forgot! your two Confed'rates have Been here, and brought verses from you. Ben. Verses? and from me? Beat. Yes, and they woo'd for you, but Lucio Was soon perswaded to speak for himself. He says you are a meer Country-Wit. Ben. I'll dip him in this Plot, till he grow solemn With business. If it were fit To be malitious, that Caytiff, Lucio, should have his Coxcomb cut off for foolish Treason. [Exeunt several ways. Enter Eschalus meeting Benedick. Esch. My Lord, the Warrant for the Pardon? have you it? Ben. Why ask you, Sir? Esch. Still wear it in your hand, and watch it there. Ben. I keep it 'tween my Finger and my Thumb, As close as a catcht Flea. Are you afraid it will skip from me? Esch. The matter is of dreadful consequence. Ben. Fear nothing, Sir; the World would still Run swiftly round; but for you State-Cripples, Who make it halt with your politick stops Of too much caution. Esch. If your Brother, the Deputy, Circumvent us, you'll secure me by the Duke? Ben. You shall add a lease of my life to your own. Be resolute, I am in haste. [Exeunt several ways. Enter Jailor, Juliet. Viola knocking within. Viol. within. My Cousin Juliet, are you here? [Jailor opens the door. This fellow looks like a man boyl'd [Enter Viola. In Pomp-water. Is he marry'd. Jul. Are you not frighted with this dismal place? How does your Sister? speak, does she not blush When she remembers me? Viol. I bring you good news! Cousin, I would not meet that man in the dark. Does he dwell here to lock up children That are imprison'd for crying? Jul. Tell me your happy news; Dear Viola! Viol. Nay I can tell you none, yet 'tis very good. You shall hear all to morrow. Jul. To morrow is the last in my short Calendar. Viol. I have heard more than I will speak. You shall Come forth and lye with me, and dream all night Of new Dressings, and dance all day. Jul. Would I had ne're outliv'd this innocence. Viol. Do your Judges dwell here? were I that man, I would walk in the dark and fright 'em. Jul. That man does do you hurt. Let us retire. Had I been wither'd at her Beauties spring, And stay'd from growing at her growth of mind, I had not known, the cruel nor the kind. Those who outlive her years do but improve The knowledge of those griefs which grow with Love. [Exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT IV. SCENE I. Enter Benedick, Lucio, Balthazar. Ben. Lucio, you broke from our confed'racy Against marriage, then woo'd in my behalf; And afterwards for your self. Luc. Do but hear me. Ben. Excuses are like weak Reserves after a Battel is lost. Luc. Let me be heard; for if poor Truth Have a tongue of her own and must not use it; Why then she may retire into a corner, And weep out her eyes. Ben. What can you say? Luc. I meant no more love to the Lady Beatrice, Than I do to wooe an arrested Widow, With a Serenade at a Prison Grate. Balthazar knows my heart. Balt. I know sev'ral of your hearts. Men are not i'th' fashion unless they have Change of ev'ry thing. Luc. I ever thought her a Mermaid. Ben. How so? Luc. From the Breasts downward she's as cold as a Fish. Ben. Well Lucio, I'll call none but the Four Winds T'accompt for what is past. Look, Sir,—thus I Blow away your offences: but you must Be steddy now, and diligent. I told You my design for Claudio's preservation. The Provost was your Unkles Creature, and By him prefer'd. Balt. The Provost will make good Our trust, and ev'ry character of gratitude. Ben. You must engage him, Lucio, and discern By what pretext or obstacle the Fryar Proceeds so far to interrupt our hopes. Luc. I'll bind the Provost to your service in His own shackles. And, concerning the Fryar, I'll straight confess him, and you shall know all. Ben. Be sudden and successful, go. [Exit Lucio. Enter Beatrice, and Page. Beat. O, are you come? I would have cry'd you as A lost thing, but that I knew I should have The ill luck to find you again. Ben. You trip it too fast. You need not be so swift to meet misfortune. I had just now a Letter from the Provost; Who either suspects the truth of the Pardon, Because I enjoin'd him to secresie, Or else is led by a Fryer to some fresh Design. Beat. Are we circumvented by a Fryer? Rather than not vex that Fryer, I'll invent A new Sect, and preach in a Hat and Feather. Ben. 'Tis strange that men of their discretion, Should come abroad in old fashion Gowns, And drest with abominable negligence. Beat. Bus'ness makes them great slovens, and they love To be busie. Ben. And never observe The right seasons when they are necessary. For though we are content with their company When we are old and dying; yet (methinks) They should not trouble us with their good counsel, When we are young, and in good health. Balt. Alas poor Book-men! they want breeding. Beat. Can we not separate the wicked Provost, From this scrupulous Fryer? Ben. I have sent Lucio to him. Beat. Benedick, We will cast off the serious faces of Conspirators, and appear to the Deputy As merry, and as gay, as Nature in The Spring. This House shall be all Carnaval, All Masquerade. Ben. Good! we will laugh him out Of's Politicks, till he make Paper-Kites Of Machiavel's Books, and play with his Pages In the Fields. Balt. And shall we sing and dance. Beat. 'Till the old Senators lead forth The Burghers Widows, and cry out for a Pawn. Page, call Viola with her Castanietos; And bid Bernardo bring his Guittar. [Exit Page. Ben. My Brother will not endure this habitation. Balt. He'll rather to Sea, and dwell in a Gun-room. Ben. Or lye round like a Sextons Dog, beneath The great Bell in a Steeple. [Viola strikes the Castaniets within. Beat. Heark! Viola has ta'ne th'alarm. Ben. Those Castanietos sound Like a Consort of Squirrels cracking of Nuts. Enter Viola dancing a Saraband awhile with Castanietos. Beat. Shall we stand idle in seasons of business? You have Feathers on your head Benedick; Have you none at your heels? Ben. I am, Lady, So very a Kid at cap'ring, that you May make Gloves of my skin. Balthazar! Call for more Musick. Balt. Not for me, Sir. I can dance at the meer tolling of a Bell. [They dance. After the Dance, enter Eschalus. Esch. Have you no apprehension of the Deputy? Are you insensible? Beat. Do you suspect We are insensible by our want of motion? Ben. You should provide my Brother-Deputy A Polititians quilted Cap to cover His ears. 'Twill preserve him from noise. Beat. These politick men should keep company With their fellow-Foxes in deep holes. Balt. He'll grow so angry, that he'll lay the punishments Of Law aside, and Pistol us with his own hand. Esch. This, Signior, is not the right way to meet Your Brothers temper. Ben. Signior, my meaning is T'avoid the way where I may meet my Brother. I'll prove a very Crab to him; for still As he proceeds, I purpose to go backward. Esch. I hope you'll be cautious about the Pardon. Ben. Pray mingle so much courage with your wisdom, As may bring you into the possibility Of sleep again. Esch. Sir, I more than beseech you Not to provoke your Brothers gravity With fantastical noises. Ben. Believe me, we Are politick; and do it to disguise That melancholly which belongs to design. Esch. That may do well. Ben. Go up and retire with him. If you stay here, he'll take you for a man Of mirth; and then you'll lose his favour. [Exit Eschalus. Beat. 'Tis fit, Benedick, you seek Lucio out, To learn quickly the Provosts resolution. I'll go change my scene to the Garden-Terras, Under your Brother's Window, that I may Torment him with new noises. Viol. Shall I fetch the great Girls that make Bone-Lace, To sing out of tune to their Bobbins? Beat. Do, Viola. Let them be long lean Wenches. Viol. And we'll hang a dozen Cages of Parrots At his Window, to tell him what's a Clock. [Exeunt several ways. Enter Lucio and Provost. Luc. I'd speak with that Fryer who obstructs the Pardon. Prov. His business with Claudio being done, he shall attend you. [Enter Fool in a Shackle. Luc. Fool! what, a Pris'ner? I thought fooling had Been free. Fool. Fooling is free before the wise: But truly, Signior, a Fool can no more Suffer a Fool, than one of the Wits can Endure another Wit. Prov. You, Sirrah, are committed for the worst Kind of fooling. You have brought both Sexes Together. Luc. A Bawd? alas poor Fool! instead of being In jeast, you have been in earnest! Fool. I dealt with persons of quality, With whom I thought fit to be mannerly. Was't civil to let them meet to no purpose? Prov. You have been civil indeed. Fool. All deeds must submit to interpretation. For my part to prevent all animosities And heart-burnings between young men and women, I brought them lovingly together. Luc. A Bawd in a Fools Coat? Prov. Mistress Mitigation gave him the Livery. Luc. 'Tis a villainous new disguise For the good old Cause. How does Mother Midnight? what, she grows rich? Fool. Signior, sh'as eaten up all her Beef now, And is her self in the Tub. Luc. Powder'd to make her last. 'Tis not amiss. But prethee, what mean those Keys at thy Girdle? Prov. I have preferr'd him. He's an under-Jaylor. Luc. You have but chang'd your dwelling, Fool; your office Is the same; for you were wont to keep doors. [Enter Duke. Prov. Sirrah, look to your Pris'ners. Signior Lucio, I shall leave you with this rev'rend Father. [Ex. Provost, Fool. Luc. Good day, Father. Duke. And to you, Sir, a long and a good life. Luc. Father, I aim at no difficult things: If it be short and sweet, I'm satisfy'd. Duke. How mean you, Sir? Luc. Nay, I'm not now prepar'd for confession; besides I'm in great haste. You must needs prevail With the Provost to let the Pardon pass. Duke. Some hours after the date of the Pardon, An Order came hither for Execution, Which had proceeded too, if Fryer Thomas Had not, by help of the Deputy's Confessor, Got a Reprieve till to morrow. Luc. Th'absent Duke was a true friend to Lovers. Duke. It seems you know the Duke? Luc. Know him? yes Fryar, very well. I had th'honour To be of his Council: but I mean, Sir, In midnight matters. He was about once To raise a charitable foundation; Not for lousie learning, or such Cripples As creep from lost Battels, but for poor Diseas'd Lovers. Duke. I did not think he had been amorous. Luc. Who, he? yes as far as to your Begger Of fifty: and he us'd to put a Ducket In her Clack-Dish. Duke. Is't possible? He was not, sure, in's youth this way inclin'd. Luc. No, he began to steer The right course about forty; but, good man, He repented the lost time of his youth. [Exit. Duke. Virtue's defensive Armour must be strong, To scape the merry, and malicious Tongue. [Exit. Enter Jaylor, Isabella. Isab. Good Friend be courteous, and let Juliet know My name is Isabella, and I come To serve her. Will you so much favour me? There's for your pains— Jayl. You must stay here, till I shall send her to you. [Exit Jaylor. Isab. A Prison is too good a Den for This rude Beast. [Enter Juliet. Have comfort Sister! I must call you so; [Isab. salutes her. Though the uncivil Law will not allow You yet that name. Jul. I am not worthy of it. Isab. Since you have spoke so humbly of your self, You must and shall be comforted: perhaps Like conscience, love, when satisfy'd within, May oft offend the Law, and yet not sin. Jul. I find the greatest love is an offence; For greatest love is greatest confidence; When, trusting those who for our credence woo, We trust them with our love and honour too. Isab. I come to bring your sorrows some relief; And would your crime not lessen but your grief. Jul. How can I lose that honour which I gave To him, who can and will that honour save? Isab. When you your honour did to Claudio give, Coz'ning your self, you did our Sex deceive. Honour is publick treasure, and 'tis fit Law should in publick form dispose of it. Jul. Oh Isabella! you are cruel grown. Isab. Sister! you gave much more than was your own. Jul. I lov'd too much; yet for your Brother's sake, Who had that love, you my excuse should make. Isab. My Mothers life did fair example give How, after death we might unpunisht live. She, dying, did my Childhood then assign To Claudio's care; he leaves you now to mine. Jul. Oh Heav'n! you mean that Claudio now must dye; And I am now become a Legacy? Isab. My friends are suing for your liberty, And that you may secure from penance be. Jul. What need I for the shame of Penance care? No blush e're dy'd the paleness of dispair. Isab. Do not, with weeping, vainly quench your eyes. Tears are to Heaven a useful Sacrifice Where ev'ry drop moves mercy; but they gain On Earth no more remorse than common Rain. Jul. Is there no means your Brother's life to save? Isab. None that I would afford, or he would have? Yet can I not affirm that there is none. Jul. Oh call back Hope, which faste does from us run. Isab. Sister, you call in vain; for when you know How wicked now Saint Angelo does grow, You will rejoice that Death makes Claudio free; And think your Bonds more safe than liberty. Jul. Is Angelo as wicked as severe? Isab. I more his kindness now than anger fear. Jul. To what would Tyrant-force kindly perswade! Isab. He gently treats, then rudely does invade. I dare not give his purpos'd sin a name; It is too hard a word for untaught shame. Jul. False Image of refin'd authority! Isab. Unless I yield my Brother is to dye. Just now I left the Guards drawn up, who wait For Execution at the Prison Gate. Jul. Oh Isabell! why are we useless made? Too weak t'inforce, and artless to perswade: Nor you nor I can any help afford To your dear Brother, and my plighted Lord. Yet you have means; but must not have the will By evil to prevent a greater ill. Isab. Have I the means? your grief misleads your tongue.— [She is going out. Jul. I would do Claudio good, and you no wrong. Your vertue is severe! hear me but speak! My heart will else out of my bosom break. Isab. Speak clearly then. You are not understood. May none do ill, that so they may do good? Nature no greater gift than life can give. Isab. By vertue we our nature long outlive. Jul. Can it be vertue to let Claudio dye? Isab. His life should not be sav'd by infamy. Jul. Loath'd Infamy consists of evils grown So impudent as covet to be known. But those seem least which bashfully we shun, At first, and then for good intent are done. Isab. Sister, you argue wildly in your grief. You are too good to seek a bad relief For Claudio; therefore look for no reply. Jul. I look for none; yet would not have him dye.— [Going out. Isab. You seem'd to intimate that bashfulness At evil doing makes the evil less; That when we good intend by doing ill, We bring necessity t'excuse our will: And that our faults, when hidden by our shame, Pass free from blemish, if they scape from blame. Jul. Forget my words. How could they be but weak, When grief did make those thoughts which fear did speak. Isab. Suppose I can a likely way devise; That you, assisted aptly by disguise, May take to night my place with Angelo: The means is not remote: what will you do? Jul. I am amaz'd and apprehend you not. Isab. Your sudden ignorance is strangely got. I now am going to the Deputy; To make to his request my last reply; And I perhaps may promise willingness, But on conditions made for my access With bashful privacy retir'd from light; From ev'ry witness too but secret night; Whose thickest Curtains shall immure the Room; Where for my promist person you may come. Thus Claudio's life you save and lose no fame; For where none sees we cannot feel our shame. Ascribe to dire necessity the ill, The good of it belongs then to your will. Quickly resolve and I'll prepare your way. Jul. E're I will Claudio in my self betray, I will the torment of his death endure: His sickness more becomes him than the cure. Isab. How Juliet? can you righteously refuse Th'expedient which you plead that I should use? Go chide the passion which would have me do, That which, though ill in both, seems least in you: The good or ill redemption of his life, Does less concern his Sister than his Wife. Jul. Alas, we know not what is good or ill. Isab. Perhaps we should not learn that fatal skill. The Serpent taught it first. Sister, away! We'll more for patience, than for knowledge pray. [Ex. several ways. Enter Balthazar, Beatrice, Jaylor, Page. Beat. Where's Viola? have I lost her? that scare-crow Makes a very Bird of her. Balt. She's run up stairs, Madam, to inform Your Cousin Juliet of your being here. Beat. Methinks this Fellow looks not only ill, But saucily ill. Balt. How so Madam? Beat. 'Tis impudence to shew so bad a face In good company—Friend, I'll reward you. Jayl. The sooner the better. Beat. You shall wear my Colours; Boy, when he comes abroad Bid my Lacquies be careful to cudjel him. Jayl. I thank you. Exit Jaylor. Enter Viola. Viol. My Cousin Juliet has lockt her self in Her Chamber. I saw her through the Keyhole, Weeping like Nurse when she lost her Wedding Ring. Beat. Juliet, I cannot but Pity thy private friendship, but am more Vext at our publick Enemy, thy Judge— Balt. Your tears, Madam, shew more pity than anger. Beat. No, Sir, great storms do oft begin with Rain. [Enter Benedick. Ben. I saw your Coach at the Prison Gate, Lady, And thought y'had been arrested on Suspicion of love; which now is made high-Treason Natural Bodies by the Body politick. Beat. I should marvel, Benedick, how you had The face to come within sight of my Sex. But that ill faces, being common, are No cause of wonder. Ben. Mine's a politick face; and few of that sort Are held handsom: so politick that it Will hardly be seduc'd to make another In these dangerous times. Beat. So politick, as I'd have you walk only At night, and with a dark Lanthorn before you; That, though you see others, none may see you. You are one of those whom I think unlucky. Ben. This gloomy place presents you with strange visions, Your Coach attends you. I pray change the Scene. Beat. Whither? to see your Brothers Guards drawn up For Claudio's execution, 'las poor women They get much by you men. Ben. Truly, 'tis thought they might get more; For men are always civilly willing, Though ever blam'd. But patience, and we shall Have right when we are heard. Beat. Heard? yes, may she Who henceforth listens to your sighing Sex, Have her Ass-ears in publick bor'd, as Love's Known Slave, and wear for Pendants Morrice-Bells As his fantastick Fool. Ben. No whisp'ring the Platonick way? Beat. Platonick way? my Cousin has Plato'd it Profoundly; has she not? i'th' name of mischief, Make friendship with your selves, and not with us. Let ev'ry Damon of you, chuse his Pitheas, And tattle Romantick Philosophy Together, like bearded Gossips. Ben. Though such conversation might breed peace in A Palace, yet 'twould make but a thin Court. Beat. Discourse all day, lolling like lazy ill- Bred-Wits, with your right Legs o're your left Knees: Defining love, 'till he become as raw, As if he were defected by Anatomists. Give Balls and Serenades to your dear selves. Ben. That were (as we are taught by the old Proverb) To Be merry and wise. [Enter Lucio. Luc. We shall be more Troubled with this fidling Fryer, than with ten Lay-Fools. He has so infected the Provost With good counsel, that there is no hope from him. The Guards are doubled at the Prison Gate; And Claudio is to dye at break of day. Beat. Where's now your valour, Sir? Is furious Benedick like Beasts of prey, Couragious only in the Field, And with familiar tameness creep in Towns Beneath the anger of your Feeders Law? Jaylor, where are you? bring me to my Cousin? [Ex. Beat. Viol. Ben. She's rais'd to a most amiable humour. Now is your time, Lucio, to make love to her. Luc. I am now for the Platonick way of billing Like meek Turtles, without the noise of passion. Balt. We, Lucio, who are parcel-Lovers, should Mourn like Turtles over a Bottle in These days of persecution. Ben. Signiors prepare t'offend the Laws, I find I must grow rude, and make bold with my Brother. [Ex. Omnes. Enter Provost, Duke. Prov. The Guards thus doubled at the Prison Gate, Confirms my doubt that Signior Benedick Did counterfeit the pardon which he brought. Duke. You have another Prisoner here Condemn'd to dye? Prov. The wicked Bernardin, hath long Been a most painful, and a watchful Robber, But now the short remainder of his life, He lazily consumes in sleep. Duke. Is he so careless before death. Prov. He minds Not what is past, or present, or to come. Duke. He wants advice. Prov. We oft have wakened him, as if he were To go to execution, and shew'd him too A seeming Warrant, but he seem'd not mov'd. [Enter Fool. Fool. The Hangman waits to dispatch his business With your Worship. Prov. Sirrah, his business is with you. Fool. My Worship will hardly be at leisure for him. Prov. Call him in. [Enter Hangman. This Fellow early in the morning is To help you in your execution. He cannot plead a quality above Your service, he has been a noted Bawd. Hang. A Bawd! fye on him, he'll disgrace our Mystery. Fool. Sir, by your good favour (for surely, Sir, You would have a good favour, had you not A hanging look) d'you call your trade a Mystery? Hang. Yes, you will find it so. Fool. What mystery there should be in hanging, if I were to be hang'd, I cannot imagine. Hang. It is a Mystery: but you must be hang'd E're you can find it out. Prov. Provide your Block and Ax; And call Bernardine. [Exit Hangman. Duke. What horrid Instruments are us'd by pow'r. Fool. Mr. Bernardine you must rise and be hang'd. Mr. Bernardine. Bern. within. Curse on your throat! who makes that noise? What are you? Fool. Your friend the Hangman; you must be so good As to rise, and be put to death. Bern. Away you Rogue, I am sleepy. Prov. Tell him he must wake. Fool. Pray Mr. Bernardine awake till you Are executed and sleep afterwards. Prov. Go in and fetch him out. Fool. He's coming, Sir, for I hear his straw rustle. Enter Bernardine. Bern. How now, Fool, what's the news with you? Fool. Truly, Sir, I would desire you to clap close to. Your prayers, for the Warrant's come. Bern. Y'are a Rogue, I've been drinking all night, And am not fitted for the Warrant Fool. The better, Sir; for he that drinks all night, And is hang'd very betimes in the morning, May sleep the soundlier all the next day. Prov. Look, Sir, here comes your Ghostly father. D'you think we jest now? Duke. Induc'd, Sir, by my charity, and hearing how Hastily you are to depart, I am come to advise you, Comfort you, and pray with you. Bern. Fryer, not I, I've been drinking hard all night, And will have more time to prepare me, or they Shall beat out my brains with Billets. I'll not dye to day. Duke. O, Sir, you must, and therefore, I beseech you, Look forward on the Journey you shall go. Bern: I'll not dye till I have slept for any Mans perswasion. Duke. But hear you. Bern. Not a word; if you have any thing to speak Come to my Ward, for I'll not thence to day. [Ex. Bern. Fool. Prov. What think you of this Prisoner, Father? Duke. Nature did never make a thing more wretched. He is unfit to live or dye. 'Twere want Of common charity to transport him In the mind he is, let him have more time, And be restrain'd from ev'ry nourishment but sleep Till I have made him fit for death. [Enter Jaylor. Jayl. Sir, a Messenger at the Prison Gate Knocks hard, and says that he must speak with you. Prov. I come! Father, if it please you, let's retire. Enter Claudio and Fool. Claud. Bolting the door we are unheard and safe. Thou art a man, though in an ill disguise; And should'st support thy being worthily. Fool. Why, truly Sir, though I have had a couple Of Ill callings, yet I would live as well As I could by both. Claud. Thou hast a Servant been to shame, and now Art but an Officer to cruelty. There, take this Gold; it is a thousand Crowns. Wilt thou not run a little hazard for Much happiness. The venter is not great; And it may probably produce at once Thy freedom and support. Fool. Sir, mine is but A thin Summer-skin; 't has been often cut And slasht with whipping. I would very fain Sleep whole in it now. Claud. Have courage, friend, 'tis Gold. Fool. My Grandam left me nothing at her death But a good old Proverb, that's Touch and Take. And I may say 't has been a lucky Proverb To me. What would you have me do? Claud, I have within a Pages habit, pact up Close. Prethee convey it by your friend, The Jaylor, to Julietta, whose escape, In that disguise, I newly have contriv'd, By correspondence with an Officer Who has the foremost station of The Guards without, and has been servant to My Father. If thou hast any tenderness Do this, that she may scape from publick penance. Fool. But how shall I scape, Sir? I shall do Penance Without a Sheet or Shirt: for my kind Tutor, The Hangman, will strip me stark naked When I'm swinging, though the wind blow northerly. Claud. The Law for thy offence can doom thee But to Fetters during life, and half that Gold May purchase thy release. Fool. A sore whipping may come into the bargain. But 'tis a poor back that cannot sometimes Pay for the maint'nance of the belly. I'll do't. Claud. Pray lose no time; I have but little left. Fool. Have you no more Gold? sure you might scape too. Claud. Friend, I have given you all I have, nor could My greater plenty work my liberty; For my Confederate dares not undertake To make the passage clear for more than one, Or if he could, I want disguise for two. Fool. If you get out, Sir, you then scape from Death. Claud. And she by freedom scapes from dreadful shame Of doing Penance. Pray dispute it not. [Knocking within. What hand is that? if you prove faithful now You'll gain forgiveness for your past offences. Fool. My golden guests retire you straight into The closet of my Breeches. Much in all ages, good innocent Gold, Has been lay'd to your charge— [Puts up the Bag and looks (through the Key-hole. It is the Lady Juliets Maid, I'll let Her in; and bear the Habit to her Mistress. [Exit Fool. Enter Maid Maid. My Lady with this Letter, Sir, sends you Her dearest prayers and love. Claud. Heaven value both, so much as they Are priz'd by me— [Reads the Letter. The Provost's wife, in pity of your distress; or perhaps out of love to your person, or rather, (as I hope) out of respect to your vertue, has devis'd means for your escape. She has by large gifts prevail'd with my Keeper to leave your passage free to my Chamber. I beseech you, with the efficacy of my last breath, to make use of this occasion and to hasten hither. Your way to liberty must be out of my Window, from whence by a small Engine she will wrench the Bars. Maid. Can you find leisure to consider, Sir, Of that which by my Lady is so well Resolv'd? Claud. The Provost's wife? will she facilitate Your Ladies liberty with mine? Maid. She says, she cannot undertake so far. Claud. Then I'll refuse her courtesie. Maid. My Lady sends you this request in tears. Will you deny it her? Claud. If my escape I from her Chamber make, The Law will lay the guilt of it on her; And she remains behind to bear The punishment. Maid. She hath agreed to that Condition with the Provost's wife. Claud. Your Lady makes me an unkind request. Maid. Have you the heart to judge it so? Claud. Can she be ign'rant that the rigid Law Does judge it in a Prisoner forfeiture Of life, to help another Prisoner to Escape, who is condemn'd to dye? Maid. That forfeiture she cheerfully will pay: But has so govern'd me with desp'rate vows, That I lackt courage to refuse to bring This message to you. Claud. How pow'rful, fatal Juliet, is thy love? Yet must it not more valiant be than mine— [Weeps. Tell her, I've newly sent her a request More just than that which she has sent by you; It will be brought her with a Present too: Which if, unkindly, she denys to take, She does by example my denial make. [Ex. several ways. Enter Angelo, Servant. Ang. Attend her in, and then wait you at distance. [Ex. Serv. O Love! how much thy borrow'd shapes disguise, Even to themselves, the valiant and the wise? Enter Isabella. Ang. Had you not fear'd th'approach of Claudio's fate (Which shews you are to him compassionate, Though not to me) I had not seen you here. He may your pity thank, and I your fear. Isab. My Lord, I hardly could my self forgive For suing still to have my Brother live, But that a higher hope directs my aim; Which, saving his frail life, would yours reclaim. Ang. How desp'rate all your hopeful visits prove! You bring me counsel still instead of love. And would in storms of passion make me wise. Bid Pilots preach to winds when tempests rise. Isab. But yet as tempests are by showers allay'd, So may your anger by my tears be sway'd. Ang. You must by yielding teach me to relent. Make haste! the Mourners tears are almost spent, Courtiers to Tyrant-Death who basely wait, To do that Tyrant honour whom they hate. Inviting formal Fools to see his Feast To which your Brother is th'unwilling Guest. And the absolving Priest must say the Grace: Nights progress done, Claudio begins his Race. Isab. And with the mornings wings your cruel doom He shall convey where you must trembling come, Before that Judge, whose pow'r you use so ill, As if, like Law, 'twere subject to your will. The cruel there shall wish they had been just, And that their seeming love had not been lust. Ang. These useless sayings were from Cloysters brought: You cannot teach so soon as you were taught. You must example to my mercy give; First save my life, and then let Claudio live. Isab. Have you no words but what are only good, Because their ill is quickly understood? Dispose of Claudio's life! whilst cruel you Seem dead, by being deaf to all that sue. Till by long custom of forgiving none Y'are so averse to all forgiveness grown. That in your own behalf you shall deny, To hear of absolution when you dye. Ang. How Isabel! from calms of bashfulness (Even such as suppliant Saints to Heaven express, When patience makes her self a Sacrifice) Can you to storms of execration rise? [Isabel is going out. Leave me not full of evil wonder, stay! Isab. Can it be good to hear what you would say? [He steps in and reaches a Cabinet. Ang. In this behold Nature's Reserves of light, When the lost day yields to advancing night. When that black Goddess fine in Frosts appears, Then starry Jewels bright as these she wears. The wealth of many Parents who did spare In plenteous peace, and get by prosperous War. Isab. Of that which evil life may get, you make A wonder in a monstrous boast; Which death from you as certainly will take, As 'tis already by your Parents lost. Ang. Be in this world, like other mortals, wise; And take this treasure as your Beauty's prize. Wealth draws a Curtain o're the face of shame; Restores lost beauty, and recovers fame. Isab. Catch Fools in Nets without a Covert laid; Can I, who see the treason, be betray'd? [Going out. Ang. Stay Isabel! stay but a moments space! You know me not by knowing but my face. My heart does differ from my looks and tongue. To know you much, I have deceiv'd you long. Isab. Have you more shapes, or would you new devise? Ang. I'll now at once cast off my whole disguise. Keep still your virtue, which is dignify'd And has new value got by being try'd. Claudio shall live longer than I can do, Who was his Judge, but am condemn'd by you. The martial of the Guards keeps secretly His pardon seal'd; nor meant I he should dye. Isab. By shifting your disguise, you seem much more In borrow'd darkness than you were before. Ang. Forgive me who, till now, thought I should find Too many of your beauteous Sex too kind. I strove, as jealous Lovers curious grow, Vainly to learn, what I was loth to know. And of your virtue I was doubtful grown, As men judge womens frailties by their own. But since you fully have endur'd the test, And are not only good, but prove the best Of all your Sex, submissively I woo To be your Lover, and your Husband too. Isab. Can I when free, be by your words subdu'd, Whose actions have my Brother's life pursu'd? Ang. I never meant to take your Brother's life; But if in tryal how to chuse a wife, I have too diffident, too curious been, I'll pardon ask for folly, as for sin; I lov'd you e're your pretious beauties were In your probation shaded at Saint Clare: And when with sacred Sisterhood confin'd, A double enterprise perplext my mind; By Claudio's danger to provoke you forth From that blest shade, and then to try your worth. Isab. She that can credit give to things so strange, And can comply with such a sudden change, Has mighty faith, and kindness too so strong, That the extream cannot continue long. I am so pleas'd with Claudio's liberty, That the example shall preserve me free. Ang. Was I when bad so quickly understood; And cannot be believ'd when I am good. Isab. In favour of my Sex and not of you, I wish your love so violent and true, That those who shall hereafter curious be, To seek that frailty, which they would not see, May by your punishment become afraid, To use those Nets which you ignobly laid. Ang. Ah Isabel! you blam'd my cruelty! Will you, when I shew mercy, cruel be? Isab. You might have met a weaker breast than mine, Which at approach to parley would incline: How little honour then you had obtain'd, If, where but little was, you that had stain'd? Had you been great of mind, you would have strove T'have hid, or helpt the weaknesses of love; And not have us'd temptations to the frail, Or pow'r, where 'twas dishonour to prevail. You will (if now your love dissembled be) Deceive your self, in not deceiving me. If it be true, you shall not be believ'd, Lest you should think me apt to be deceiv'd. [Exit. Ang. Break heart! farewel the cruel and the just! Fools seek belief, where they have bred distrust: Because she doubts my virtue I must dye; Who did with vitious arts her virtue try. [Exit.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT V. SCENE I. Enter Duke and Isabel. Duke. You told me, Daughter, that the Marshal has Your Brother's pardon seal'd, and I shall watch All means to keep him safe, lest Angelo Should turn his clemency into revenge. Do not th'assurance of his freedom buy With hazard of a Virgins liberty. Isab. I shall with patience follow your instruction. Duke. Night's shady Curtains are already drawn; And you shall hear strange news before the dawn. [Exit Duke. Enter Francisca. Franc. Is the good Father gone? Isab. Yes, Sister, and has left my breast in peace. [A Bell rings. Franc. This Bell does nightly warn us e're we sleep, T'appease offended Heaven. Let us go pray, That the worlds crimes may vanish with the day. [Exeunt. Enter Benedick, Eschalus, Beatrice, Viola, Lucio, singing a Chorus within. Esch. Your Brother, Sir, has an unquiet mind: 'Tis late, and he would take his rest. Viol. We'll sing him asleep. Ben. Shall he who should Live lean with care of the whole Common-wealth, Grow fat with sleep like a Groenland-Bear? Esch. Rulers are but mortal; and should have rest. Ben. A States-man should take a nap in his Chair, And only dream of sleep. Beat. These great tame Lions of the Law (Who make Offenders of the weak) Should still seem watchful, and like wild Lions Sleep with their eyes open. Esch. Is night a season for singing? Viol. We'll sing like Nightingales, and they sing at night. Esch. Take heed; for the Grand-Watch does walk the Round. Beat. Signior, when did you hear of Nightingales Taken by the Watch? Luc. Madam, we'll sing. The Governour May come (if he please) and sigh to the Chorus. Esch. I'll bear no part, Sir, in your Song, Nor in your punishment. [Exit Eschalus. The SONG. Luc. [1.] Our Ruler has got the vertigo of State; The world turns round in his politick pate. He stears in a Sea, where his Course cannot last; And bears too much Sail for the strength of his Mast. Cho. Let him plot all he can, Like a politick man, Yet Love though a Child may fit him. The small Archer though blind, Such an Arrow will find, As with an old trick shall hit him. Beat. 2. Sure Angelo knows Loves party is strong; Love melts, like soft wax, the hearts of the young. And none are so old but they think on the taste, And weep with remembrance of kindnesses past. Cho. Let him plot all he can, &amp;c. Ben. 3. Love in the wisest is held a mad fit; And madness in Fools is reckon'd for Wit. The Wise value Love, just as Fools Wisdom prize; Which when they cann't gain, they seem to dispise. Cho. Let him plot all he can, &amp;c. Viol. 4. Cold Cowards all perils of anger shun; To dangers of Love they leap when they run. The valiant in frolicks did follow the Boy, When he led them a Dance from Greece to old Troy. Cho. Let him plot all he can, &amp;c. Enter Balthazar. Balt. Behind the Garden of the Augustines Your friends attend. You must be sudden if You'll be successful. Ben. I come. Bid Lucio in a whisper to Retire, and to expect my Orders at Saint Laurence Gate. Lady, though you deny Sleep to my Brother, yet, you may do well Y'allow a little of it to your self. It grows late; and Viola, methinks, begins To lose an eye with watching in your service. Viol. I love watching and dancing too in Moon-shine nights, Like any Fairy. Beat. Can whispers hide your bus'ness, Benedick, When you are such a Weather-Cock, that with But looking on you I can quickly find Where the wind sits. Well, I wish you some danger, That you may get the more honour. [Exeunt several ways. Enter Angelo, Eschalus. Ang. It is not just I should rebuke them for Their harmony of mind; that were to shew The rage, and envious malice of the Devil, Who quarrels with the good, because they have That happiness, which he can ne'er enjoy. Esch. My Lord, I find you sick for want of rest; And grieve to heare you say, the cause of your Disease is in your self. Ang. No sickness, Eschalus, Can be more dangerous than mine, of which The cause is known to that Physician, who Enjoins me to dispair of cure. Esch. Your words amaze me. [Enter 1. Servant. 1. Serv. To Arms, my Lord, to Arms! The ancient Citizens are wakt in terrour By the insulting youth; who in loud throngs March through the Streets to the Parade. Ang. Hence Coward! thou art frighted by thy dream. [Ex. Serv. Enter 2. Servant. 2. Serv. Arm, arm, my Lord! your Brother is revolted, Heading a Body of disbanded Officers. He is in skirmish with your Guards, To rescue Claudio from the Law. Ang. My Brother grown my publick Enemy? This iteration sounds like truth. I was Just now sending to declare Claudio's Pardon, And to hasten his and Juliet's liberty. Esch. You purpos'd well, but your performance was Too slow. [Enter 1. Servant. 1. Serv. 'Tis said the Marshal of your Guards is slain. Ang. That's a surprise of fortune; for he had Claudio's Pardon, and, had he shewn it, might Perhaps have quencht the mutiny. My Armour! and command my Guard of Switzs To march, and to make good the Pass, which leads To Saint Jago's Port. Haste, Eschalus, And bid Montano make a sally from The Citadel. [Exeunt several ways. Enter Duke, Provost. Duk. Lock up your Pris'ners, and secure the Gates. Prov. I did suspect by Lucio's menacings, That Benedick would Claudio's liberty Attempt by force; and therefore did provide For opposition to attend th'assault. Forty selected from the Guards without, I have drawn in. Duke. Are they enter'd? Prov. They are, and bold Ursinoa does command 'em. Duke. Th'expedient which, in haste, I have prescrib'd, Will in extremity be fit to use; Though when you threaten't men may think you cruel. Prov. Father, I'll strictly follow your advice. Duke. Offer a parly from the Battlements. Be careful, valiant Provost, of your charge, And Heaven take care of you. Prov. I'll through the Postern lead you out: Your function will protect you. [Exeunt. Enter Benedick, Balthazar, Officers. Ben. Remove the Martial straight where Surgeons may Attend his wound, which is not mortal, though His loss of blood deprive him of his speech. Balt. A Squadron of the Guards at our approach, Retir'd into the Prison, to make good The Gates against assault. Ben. Their sudden fear begot that policy, Rather to make conditions for themselves, Than for the place. Balt. The Provost will be obstinate. Ben. It may be safer for him to preserve His courage for some other use. Enter Lucio, Duke. Luc. Father Fox the Fryer, is stoln out of his hole; And is going to make a visit to The Geese of his Parish. Ben. Lucio, let him pass. Luc. If you give quarter to the Enemies Of Lovers, you will be follow'd in your Next War, by none but decrepid old Souldiers; The youth will all forsake you. Ben. Unhand him straight: we must in rev'rence to His function make him free. Duke. Peace be with your Lordship. Luc. Take care of Lovers in your Orizons, And the rather, because praying for them, You pray for the Duke. Remember that Fryer. Duke. If e're I see the Duke, Sir, he shall know How much he is oblig'd to you. Ben. Lucio, be stedfast in your station. [Exeunt Duke, Lucio. Provost from the Battlements. Ben. Look up! the Provost does relent: he seems Inclin'd to parly. Prov. May Fortune serve the valiant Benedick In all attempts, but when he does invade The Forts of Law, where Justice would secure The Trophies of her Victories. Ben. Provost, I take your greeting well, and wish Your courage more success, than you in your Resistance now are like to find. You are Too wise to talk of Law to those who mean To justifie their actions by their Swords. Prov. My Lord, some honour I have gotten in The face of Enemies; and will not lose It in the sight of friends. Ben. You must give Claudio and Julietta liberty; And then your other Pris'ners, and your self, Shall, undisturb'd, be at your own dispose. Prov. Claudio by sentence is condemn'd; and sure My Office does engage my honour to Make good the sentence of the Law. Balt. Provost, we come not here to make a War, Like Women, with vain words. Ben. Accept of peace by yielding that which I Would gain by a request, or else expect The worst event of force. Prov. Your force I will Oppose; and when my temper is too much Provokt, perhaps the extremity may make Me shew you such an object, as will hurt Your eyes. [Enter Lucio. Luc. My Lord retire to face your Brother's pow'r, Which now is doubled by a sally from The Citadel. Ben. Make good the passage at Saint Laurence Gate: And, whilst my Squadron does advance, You, Balthazar, must march at distance with The Reer. Prov. Ursino! range your Partizans! 'Tis now our time to make a sally too. [Exeunt. [Clashing of Arms within. Enter Beatrice, Viola, Lacquay. Viol. Sister! Sister! can we not hide our selves? Beat. Fear nothing, Viola, till you are in love. But then our Faces we like Wood-Cocks hide; Whilst foolish fear (which is in women shame) Makes us but tempt the Fowler to give aim. Enter 1. Page. 1. Page. Madam, all's our own. Beat. Well, speak! you are one of those Messengers Who lost his Wages by his diligence; Running so fast to bring good news, that he Wanted breath to utter it. 1. Page. Count Benedick's a most substantial man. Would the Sun were up, that his friends might see How he stands to't, whilst his Enemies flye from him. Beat. He is a substance fit to stand i'th' Sun To make a shadow. And being the substance, Lucio must be the shadow? if Benedick Flye first, Lucio will not fail to follow him. 1. Page. There is no end of Count Benedicks valour. Beat. Valiant without end; that is, stout to no purpose. Enter 2. Page. 2. Page. Oh Madam! Count Benedick is lost. Beat. How? this foolish Boy was ever given to lying. Lacquay, go out, and bring me truth; such truth As I shall like, or else return no more. 2. Page. Madam, all the Maids— Beat. Peace! your Intelligence comes from the Laundry. Viol. Well, I fear the news may be too true then; They know what they say. Carlo, tell it me. [Page and Viola whisper. Beat. My eyes are not prophetical; perhaps They melt too soon. Lost, valiant Benedick, Lost by thy noble kindness for my sake; Who whilst I pity'd Claudio in his danger, Had of thy safety no indulgent care. Enter Balthazar. Balt. Madam, pardon my haste, which is as rude As my unseasonable visit. Beat. Tell me, I pray, the business of this night? Balt. Count Benedick began it with success; Who to redeem unhappy Claudio from The arms of death, and Juliet from the shame Of publick penance, did assault the Guards Attending near the Prison Gate; and at The first encounter did disperse that force. Beat. This is no wonder; for in Honours Game (Where many throw at the last great stake, life, As if 'twere but light Gold) young Gamesters oft Are lucky. Balt. The Provost offer'd parly, but deny'd To yield the Pris'ners, and the cause which made Him obstinate grew quickly evident; By old Montano's sally from the Citadel, And Angelo's advance with all his Zwits. These were by valiant Benedick repulst. Beat. I'm not sorry now that I have his Picture: For the vain Gentleman will quickly grow So alter'd by success, that without his Image I should hardly know him. Balt. Lord Angelo would have retir'd into the Citadel; But in the strife of that retreat Brave Benedick receiv'd a wound. Beat. A wound—Excuse me, Balthazar, if I Assume the feeling of your friendship to him, And pity him for your sake. Balt. The wound was slight; And rather serv'd t'augment his courage, than To waste his strength. Beat. Well, I'll allow him courage. Pray proceed. Balt. With many shouts saluted, he again Summon'd the Provost; who enraged at our Resistance of his sally from the Prison, Licens'd his anger even to cruelty; For, as a dire expedient to prevent Th'occasion of a new assault, he doom'd Young Claudio to endure the bloody Axe; And from the Battlements shew'd us his head. Beat. Enough! your story grows too dismal to Be heard. Dead Claudio, yet more happy is Than living Juliet. Pray be brief, if you Have any other sorrows to reveal! Balt. The cruel Provost having thus provokt Count Benedick; he straight prepares to storm The Prison; and th'assault was scarce begun, When suddenly our Sov'raign Duke breaks forth, From the dark Cloud of that disguise, in which, It seems, he hath remain'd conceal'd in Turin. Beat. The Duke in Town? Balt. Most visibly in person, and in pow'r. For by his high command victorious Benedick, Is now with conquer'd Angelo, and both Are Pris'ners to the Provost. Beat. Sudden and strange. Balt. Lord Angelo is kept from Visitants, To make him ignorant of what is past; And by the strictness of the Guards to Benedick, 'Tis whisper'd and suspected, that he will Be sentenc'd for Rebellion. Beat. I'll to the Duke. He's full of clemency: A Prince who by forgiving does reclaim, And tenderly preserve for noble use, Many whom rigid Justice, by exemplar death, Would make for ever useless to the world. Balt. 'Tis fit you hasten to him. Beat. In his own arms he bred my infancy. He ever yielded to me when I su'd For men who had no other plea to get Their pardon but their misery; and sure He'll not deny me when in tears I kneel, For valiant Benedick. [Exeunt. Enter Duke in his own Habit, Eschalus, Provost, Fryer Thomas, Attendants. Duke. In favour of that pow'r, which I did leave In Angelo's possession, as my Substitute, I have reliev'd him from his Brother's fury. But Angelo in his short Government, Disfigur'd and disgrac'd that fair Resemblance which he wore of me, By many blemishes. Esch. Though your accustom'd clemency should give Him leave to use his eloquence, in's own Defence, yet he would silence it, and hope For no relief, but from your gracious mercy. Duke. Provost, he is your Pris'ner now, With Benedick. Take care they do not meet. Prov. Sir, they are sever'd under watchful Guards. Duke. 'Tis well. Go do what further I enjoin'd you. Prov. I humbly beg your Highness pardon, for my Ignorance of what you were when you Were pleas'd to make your visits in disguise. Duke. You need no pardon, but have merited My thanks and favour. [Exit Provost. Fry. Tho. Is it your Highness will that I attend you? Duke. I've left your habit, but will ne'er forsake Your company nor counsel. Father now You must make haste, and do as I directed. Fry. Tho. I shall be diligent in both of your Commands. [Exit Fryer Thomas. Duke. You, Eschalus, complain of being wrong'd By having been made ignorant of all These evils past. I left you not to sleep Away your time. Esch. If you vouchsafe me not your pardon, I shall with shame receive my punishment; Though it is better to be ignorant, Than to be guilty. Enter Beatrice, Viola, 2 Pages, Lacquay. Beat. As virtuous Virgins, by their vows to Heaven, Have brought you here, so may their Prayers Preserve you long amongst us. Duke. I thank you, beauteous Maid. But I perceive Affliction in your Eyes. Whence does it come? Beat. I am a lowly Sutor to your Highness. Duke. I hope you are not so unfortunate, As to desire a benefit, which I Unwillingly shall grant. Beat. If no offenders were, then Sov'raign Pow'r Would have no use of mercy: Though Benedick has much offended, yet Forgive that valour which by yours was bred; And let him not be lost who was misled. Duke. Your heart is alter'd since I saw you last. Can Benedick in his affliction now Prevail; and be petition'd for by you Who scorn'd him when he did in triumph sue? This riddle I will leave to Eschalus. Give me a quick account of it. I shall Consider and take care of your request. [Exeunt several ways. Enter Angelo, Fryer Thomas. Ang. In the perplexity of Fight, when I Was forc'd to a retreat, I did suppose My Brother (to procure the people to His side) had publish'd but in artifice The Dukes return. Fry. Tho. The Duke is certainly in Town, and has, During the time of your Vicegerency, Remain'd here in disguise, he did converse, With Isabella, and continually Receiv'd from her, true knowledge of her griefs, And by what art you have afflicted her. Ang. Oh, Father, I am lost. Fryer Tho. Could you suppose You were your Brother's Prisoner here? Ang. In the dark mist of our encounter, I was led to that mistake. Fryer Tho. 'Twas a mistake indeed; For Benedick's your fellow prisoner now, And under strict command. Ang. I know him noble, though by passion urg'd To this outragious violence, against My ill dispos'd authority: and had He now been free, I easily should have hop'd His favour with the Duke, might have procur'd My peace and pardon too. But, in my strickt Restraint, how, Father, did you get this visit? Fryer Tho. By an especial leave to comfort you. [Enter Provost. The Provost has perhaps occasion of concernment With you. I'll take leave a while. [Exit Fryer. Prov. My Lord, with blushes I appear I'th' presence of your most unhappy fortune, Asham'd of my authority; but 'tis His Highness will, that you should now Be subject to my pow'r, who have been long Govern'd by yours. Ang. You will be civil to me, Provost, if You think I am contented with this change. Prov. You are so well prepar'd for grief, That I may now ask leave, to tell you, he, whom You did hastily condemn, was with dispatch, As fatal as your sentence, executed. Ang. who can you mean? Prov. Th'unhappy Claudio. Ang. Is he executed? The Marshal had his Pardon seal'd. Prov. The Marshal (who is now in hope of cure) Was by his wound last night in the first charge Depriv'd of speech; so by the Law of destiny, Your purpos'd remedy against your Law Was known too late: for (to divert The fury of th'assault, by taking from His friends that hope which was the cause of strife) I did appoint him for the Ax; and from Our Battlements shew'd them his head. Ang. All my sinister Stars, have met at once, In consultation how to ruine me. Prov. A moment e're his death, a Fryer who was Official here, did marry him to Juliet: And therefore now I come to know, how far You by your plentiful Estate, will please To give subsistance to his mourning Widow? You know that his Possessions, and her Dowry, (He dying guilty by the sentence of The Law) are both confiscate to the Duke. Ang. My bosom is too narrow for this grief; I give her all I have. Enter Eschalus. Esch. My Lord, I grieve to tell you, that the Duke As a reward to Isabella's vertue for Her suff'rings, has already by his promise, Given her th'intended confiscation of Your Lands and Treasure. Ang. 'Tis righteously bestow'd. But where alas, She having all, is Juliet's recompence? Prov. Let's leave him, Signior, to his thoughts. [Ex. Provost. Ang. How wisely Fate ordain'd for humane kind Calamity, which is the perfect Glass Wherein we truly see and know our selves. How justly it created life but short; For being incident to many griefs, Had it been destin'd to continue long, Fate, to please Fools, had done the Wise great wrong. Enter Isabella. Isab. I come, my Lord, to see you in eclipse: You did too hurtful to mine eyes appear, When with your glory you did fill your Sphear. Ang. Is it revenge that hath this visit bred; Or are you hither by compassion led? Isab. With no revenge nor pity I comply; But come, perhaps, in curiosity; As in a great Eclipse the curious run T'inform themselves exactly of the Sun: For when his light is lessen'd, they see more Of his unevenness, than they saw before. Ang. The spots in him only imagin'd be; But all reported stains are true in me. Isab. As your confession of the worst of you Seems now to utter more than does seem true, So of the best of you, which is your love, Perhaps you told much more than you could prove. Ang. In an ill season you require a test, T'assure you of that love which I profest; When I can offer nothing that is fit, To be a pledge to make you credit it; Since all I had is by the Duke (as due To injur'd virtue) freely given to you. Isab. Take back your wealth; improperly consign'd To me, who prize no wealth, but of the mind. Ang. How Isabell? would you a present make Of such a gift, as you disdain to take. It would more worthy of your bounty prove, To keep such trifles, and to give me love. But I would have what you can never give; Claudio is dead, whose life should make me live. Isab. I shall redeem you now from half your fear; I must be gone, but Claudio shall appear. [Exit. Ang. What may this mean? Virgins so soft as she Can never pleasure take in cruelty. Heav'n oft in wonders does propitious grow, Fortune no faster ebbs than it can flow. Enter Claudio, Julietta. Claud. Let those who lost their youth retire to Graves, Deaths Closets, where, though there be privacy, Yet there is never use of thoughts. Let us thank Heaven that we have life, since we together May enjoy it. Jul. From a wild Tempest, where we both were lost, Heaven lands us strangely on a Floury coast. Claud. Since none could thus recover'd be by Heaven, Were not the crimes which lost them quite forgiven, Let us express a kind forgiveness too; Jul. Honour would that without Religion do. Ang. Are you the mortal substances of forms Which you resemble, Claudio and Julietta; Yet, like immortal Angels, can so much Of good forgiveness speak? Claud. What act hath Angelo severely done, For which his Brother Benedick hath not By kindness ample satisfaction given? Ang. How is this wonder to be understood? [Enter Benedick. Ben. The Provost, Brother, has to happy purpose Deceiv'd us by the death of Bernardine. Let us embrace and mutually exchange Forgiveness. Ang. Sure our offences to each other will Admit excuse, since the authority of mighty love Did sway us both. This meeting has much comfort In it though it be in Prison. [Enter Beatrice, Viola. Beat. Where is the Rebel? Ben. No Rebel, Lady, to your pow'r. Beat. If you had err'd that way, y'had never been Forgiven; but you may offend your Prince As often as you please. There's your Pardon— [Gives him a Paper seal'd. Ben. I hope you will not undo me. Beat. How so, Sir? Ben. I am afraid 'tis a Licence for Marriage. Beat. No, Sir, Plays that end so, begin to be Out of fashion. Ben. Do you not see your Cousin Juliet? She has been advis'd by a bauld Dramatick Poet Of the next Cloister, to end her Tragy-Comedy With Hymen the old way. [Beatrice salutes Juliet. Beat. Alas poor Cousin! Love has led thee a Dance Through a Brake of Thorns and Briers. Jul. Madam, take heed; though he be blind He may find the way to lead you too. Viol. 'Warrant ye I'll run from that foolish Boy, And then let him try to overtake me. [A shout within. Within. The Duke! the Duke! Enter Duke, Isabella, Eschalus, Provost, Fryar Thomas, Guards, Attendants, Balthazar, Lucio, behind the rest. Duke. The motive which last caus'd my visits To this Prison, was to give good counsel and to Reclaim the ill advis'd. But now I come To count'nance the Reclaim'd. I can relate Your latter Story, Angelo; and am Not ignorant, Benedick, of yours; but in Remembrance of your former merits I Forget your late attempts. Ang. Your Highness makes An hourly conquest of our hearts, and we Most humbly bow in thankfulness for your Continual clemency. Duke. The eye of Pow'r does not alone observe The heights, but lower Regions of the world. I have a Convert here, whom I would see. Prov. Call Bernardine. Ben. Is he alive? Duke. I am more willingly appeas'd, because The fury of the last encounter has Not lost me any of my Subjects lives. The Martial's free from danger of his wound; And as the military Sword has not Prevail'd so far as life, so Justice, with Contrition satisfy'd, did sheath up hers. [Enter Jaylor, Fool, Bernardine. Balt. There's no harm yet. Luc. I hope we shall all scape. Duke. The Provost (whose fidelity I shall Reward) did in the storm preserve from wrack This Penitent: and from the Battlements Deceiv'd you with a Head of one, who of A natural sickness dy'd i'th' Prison. Luc. Under your Highness favour I suspected Afar off, that 'twas not Bernardine's, by A small Wart upon his left eye-lid. Duke. You were not bid to speak. Luc. No an't please your Highness, Nor wisht to hold my peace. Balt. Lucio, you will be talking. Duke. Remember, Bernardine, your Vows to Heaven; And so behave your self in future life, That I shall ne'er repent my mercy. Bern. I am your Highness Debtor for this life, And for th'occasion of that happiness, Which may succeed it after death. Duke. Is there not, Father, in this Company One too much troubled with a lib'ral tongue, Who hath traduc'd me to a Brother of Your Cloister? Fry. Tho. Yes, Sir, and here behold the man. Luc. Who I, Father? I know you not. Fry. Tho. No, Sir, but I know you. Luc. I shall be glad, Sir, of your acquaintance, For my Confessor is lately dead. Duke. But, Lucio, you perhaps, would know me too, Should I again put on the Habit which I wore, when boldly to my face you did Traduce me in this Prison. Luc. If your Highness, forgiving now so many, Will pardon me too, I'll hereafter hang A Padlock at my lips, and this good Father Shall keep the Key of it. Duke. Your slanders, Lucio, cannot do me harm. Be sorrowful, and be forgiven. Balt. Thy Mother hath bewitcht thee the right way, For no Sword can pierce thee. Duke. Think me not singular, because I did my self a while depose; For many Monarchs have their Thrones Forsaken for a Cloistral life; and I, Perhaps, may really that Habit take, Which I have worn but in disguise. Ang. That were t'undo the world by leaving it. Ben. Whilst so you seek imagin'd happiness, We all shall find essential misery. Duke. My resolutions are not soon remov'd: I'm old and weary of authority. But, e're I leave it quite (since I have no Successors of my own) let me dispose Of best advantages to those whom I Esteem, who may enjoy my pow'r. Lend me, Chast Isabella, your fair hand; which with Your heart I dedicate to Angelo; He now sufficiently that virtue knows, Which he too much, too curiously has try'd. Isab. I have so long your counsel follow'd with Success, as I am taught not to suspect Much happiness will still attend Th'obedience which does yield To your command. Ang. I fear my joys are grown too great to last. Duke. I have a good occasion, Benedick, To thank you now for your successful toils And Victory in the Millain War; for which, In ample recompence, I give you but The heart, which I perceive you had before. The witty war which you so long have had With virtuous Be'trice, now must gently end, In joyful triumphs of a nuptial peace. Beat. Take heed! our quarrel will begin again; And th'end of this long Treaty will but bring The war home to your own doors. Ben. I'll venture. 'Tis but providing good store of Cradles for Barracadoes to line my Chamber. Duke. Be happy, Claudio, in your faithful Juliet, The persecutions of your loves are past. Claud. They feel not joy who have not sorrow felt. We through afflictions make our way to Heaven. Luc. Fool, I've a mind to marry your Grandmother. Fool. She stays for you in the Church, and will prove A sweet Bed-fellow, for she has not been Bury'd above a Month. Duke. Provost, open your Prison Gates, and make Your Pris'ners free. The story of this day, When 'tis to future Ages told, will seem A moral drawn from a poetick Dream. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>