<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">D'Avenant, William, Sir, 1606-1668</field>
      <field name="author_facet">D'Avenant, William, Sir, 1606-1668</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">davenant william sir 1606 1668</field>
      <field name="author_text">D'Avenant, William, Sir, 1606-1668</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">17th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V1.0301.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1637 for 1638</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:459049</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Britannia Trivmphans ; A Masque</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 17th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 17th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Britannia Trivmphans ; A Masque</field>
      <field name="title_facet">britannia trivmphans</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">britannia trivmphans</field>
      <field name="title_text">Britannia Trivmphans ; A Masque</field>
      <field name="year_display">1637 for 1638</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1637</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1637</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459049&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459049&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;D'Avenant, William, Sir, 1606-1668&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;davenant william sir 1606 1668&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Britannia Trivmphans ; A Masque&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;britannia trivmphans&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1637 for 1638&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1637&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;D'Avenant, William, Sir&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1606&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1668&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Britannia Trivmphans&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Masque&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed by Iohn Haviland for Thomas Walkley [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1637 for 1638&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3871702-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv10301&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 17th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;17th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Britannia Trivmphans&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Masque&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 60 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Britannia trivmphans.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Masque.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1638.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Jan 1638.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">BRITANNIA TRIVMPHANS: A Masque, Presented at White Hall, by the Kings Majestie and his Lords, on the Sunday after Twelfth-night, 1637.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Princes of sweet and humane Natures have ever both amongst the Ancients and Modernes in the best times, presented spectacles, and personall representations, to recreate their Spirits wasted in grave affaires of State, and for the entertainment of their Nobilitie, Ladies, and Courts. There being now past three yeers of Intermission, that the King and Queenes Majesties have not made Masques with shewes and Intermedij, by reason the roome where formerly they were presented, having the feeling since richly adorn'd with peeces of painting of great value, figuring the acts of King Iames of happy memory, and other inrichments: lest this might suffer by the smoake of many lights, his Majestie commanded the Surveyor of his workes, that a new temporary roome of Timber, both for strength and capacitie of spectators, should bee suddenly built for that use; which being performed in two moneths, the Scenes for this Masque were prepared.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Subject of this Masque. Britanocles, the glory of the Westerne world, hath by his wisedome, valour, and pietie, not onely vindicated his owne, but farre distant Seas, infested with Pyrats, and reduc'd the land (by his example) to a reall knowledge of all good Arts and Sciences. These eminent Acts Bellerophon in a wise pittie willingly would preserve from devouring time, and therefore to make them last to our Posteritie, gives a command to Fame, (who hath already spred them abroad) that shee should now at home (if there can bee any maliciously insensible) awake them from their pretended sleepe, that even they with the large yet still increasing number of the good and loyall, may mutually admire and rejoyce in our happinesse.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Queens Majestie being seated under the State, and the roome fild with Spectators of qualitie, at the lower end of the roome was a Stage raised of a convenient height, and an Ovall staire downe into the roome: That which first presented it selfe to the eye, was the Ornament that enclosed the Scene. In the under part of this were two pedestalls of a solid order whereon captives lay bound, above sate two figures in neeches; on the right hand a woman in a watchet drapery, heightned with silver, on her head a Corona Rostrata, with one hand holding the rudder of a ship, &amp; in the other a little winged figure with a branch of Palme, and a Girland; this woman represented Navall victory. Opposite to this in the other neech sate the figure of a man bearing a Scepter with a hand and an eye in the Palme, and in the other hand a booke, on his head a Girland of Amaranthus, his Curace was of gold, with a Palludamentum of blue and Antike bases of Crimson, his foot treading on the head of a Serpent; by this figure was signified right government: above these were other composed ornaments cut out like cloth of silver, tied up in knots with scarfings all touch'd with gold. These Pillasters bore up a large Freese with a Sea triumph of naked children, riding on sea horses &amp; fishes, and young Tritons with writhen trumpets, and other maritime fancies. In the midst was placed a great compartiment of gold, with branches of Palme comming out of the scrowles, and within that a lesser of silver with this inscription, VIRTVTIS OPVS, proper to the subject of this Masque, and alluding to that of Virgil—Sed famaor extendere factis, &amp;c. from this came a drapery of Crimson, which tied up with great knots in the corners hung downe in foulds on the sides of the Pillasters. A curtaine flying up discovered the first Scene, wherein were English houses of the old and newer formes, intermixt with trees, and a farre off a prospect of the Citie of London, and the River of Thames, which being a principall part, might bee taken for all great Britaine. From severall parts of the Scene came Action and Imposture. Action a young man in a rich habit downe to his knees, with a large gard of purple about the skirt, wherein was written with silver letters, MEDIO TVTISSIMA, on his head a girland of Laurell, and in one hand a branch of willow: Imposture in a coar with hanging sleeves and great skirts, little breeches, a high crownd hat one side pind up, a little ruffe, and a formall beard, and an angling rod in his hand with a fish at the hooke, with a bag and a horne at his girdle. Action. My variable Sir; Ith' name of Heaven, What makes your falshood here where fame intends Her triumphs all of Truth? her Trumpet she Hath chosen new and cleane, lest it should taint Her breath; Thou art so uselesse to the world That thou art impudent, when thou dost share What is most cheape, and common unto all The Aire and Light; I doe beseech thee my Fine, false Artificer, hide both thy faces (For thou art double every where) steale hence And I'le take care, thou shalt no more be miss'd Than shadowes are at night. Imposture. Be patient Sir! This valiant humour of disdaine workes not So powerfully as you beleeve, I hide my selfe? The reasons must bee strong, that shall perswade Me under ground: The Badger loves his hole, Yet is not so bashfull, but dares looke out And shew himselfe, when there is prey abroad: Then strangely arrogant, I pittie thee As Politickes doe men too humble, for Their care, much more for their redresse; that is, I smile at thee (the Graver way of scorne) For should I laugh, I feare 'twould make thee thinke Thy impudence had somewhat in't of wit, Didst ever hope to be so usefull in The manage and support of humane workes As I? Action. Proceed, Proceed, make up your History. Imposture. Wisely the jealous sceptickes did suspect Realitie in every thing, for every thing but seemes, And borrowes the existence it appeares To have: Imposture governs all, even from The gilded Ethnicke Miter, to the painted staffe Oth' Christian Constable, all but pretend Th'resemblance of that power which inwardly They but deride, and whisper merry questions to themselves Which may it comes. Action. Y' have cunningly observ'd This is a pleasant new Philosophie: Imposture. Right Sir, and what is pleasant unto all Is generally good, Troth I could wish Our reason were as certaine as our sense Would alter in dispute, as little bee As soone confirm'd, but since it is not so, That universally shall take, which most Doth please, not what pretends at profit, and Imaginarie good, Is it not fit And almost saf'st to cosen all, when all Delight still to bee cosen'd. Action. These Lectures would Subdue a numerous sect, wert thou to preach To young soft Courtisans, unpractis'd heires Of over practis'd Vsurers, silken And fine feathered gallants, whose easie eares Still open to delights, and shut at truths: But Fate takes not so little care of those For whom it doth preserve the Elements: That what is chiefe within us should bee quite Deprav'd, as we were onely borne to aime At trifles here, like children in their first Estate of using legs, to run at sight Of bubbles, and to leap at noise of bels. Imposture. Even so beleev't, and in their chiefest growth They follow but my Grandsire Mahomets Divinitie, who doth allow the good a handsome Girle On earth, the valiant two in Paradise. Action. Thou art so read in humane appetites That were the Divell licenc'd to assume A body, thou might'st bee his Cooke, yet know If you endevour it, you may perswade Your selfe, there are some few 'mongst men That as our making is erect, looke up To face the Starres, and fancy nobler hopes Than you allow, not downward hang their heads Like Beasts to meditate on earth, on abject things Beneath their feet. Imposture. T'is a thinne number sure, And much disperst, for they will hardly meet In Councels and in Synods to enact Their Doctrine by consent, That the next age May say they parted friends. Action. 'Tis possible 'Lesse you steale in amongst them to disturbe Their peace, disguisd in a Canonick weed, Nor are these such, that by their reasons strict And rigid discipline, must fright nice Court Philosophers from their beleefe, such as impute A tyrannous intent to heavenly powers, And that their tyrannie alone did point At men, as if the Fawne and Kid were made To friske and caper out their time, and it Were sinne in us to dance, the Nightingale To sing her tragick tales of love, and wee To recreate our selves with Groanes, as if All perfumes for the Tyger were ordain'd Cause he excels in scent: colours, and gaudy tinctures for The Easterne birds, whilst all our ornament Are russet robes, like melancholy Monks. Imposture. There are Sir of this rigid sect, and much They governe too, that thinke the Godwit and The Rayle were meant the Eagles food, and men Design'd to feed on Salads in a meade, As if we were created but a great And larger kinde of Frogs. Action. It is confess'd; There are some sullen Clarkes that love To injure and to scant themselves, yet you May finde a few whose wisedomes merit greater sway That will allow us pleasures 'bove our cares, Yet these wee must not compasse with our guilt, But every Act bee squar'd by vertues rule. Imposture. Vertue, 'tis a meere name, Virgins that want A dowry, learn't by rote, to raise the price Of old unhansome lookes: admit, ther's one Or two allow in nature such a thing, And that it is no dreame: These mighty Lords Of reason have but a few followers, And those goe ragged too, the prosperous, brave Increasing multitude pursue my steps. The great devourer of mysterious bookes Is come, Merlin, whose deepe Prophetick Art Foretold that at this particle of Time He would forsake's unbodied friends below And waste one usuall circuit of the Moone On earth, to trie how Natures face is chang'd Since his decease. Merlin enters. Merlin the Propheticke Magitian enters apparel'd in a gowne of light purple, downe to his ankles, slackly girt, with wide sleeves turned up with powdred Ermines, and a roll on his head of the same, with a tippet hanging downe be hinde, in his hand a silverd rod. Action. Your eyes encounter him As you would make great use of's visit here. Imposture. With reason Sir, for he hath power to wake Those that have many ages slept, such as When busie in their flesh, were my Disciples. Haile thou most ancient Prophet of this Isle, I that have practis'd superstitious rites Vnto thy memory, beg thy immortall aid, To raise their figures that in times forgot Were in the world predominant; Helpe to Confute this righteous foole, that boasts his small Neglected stocke of wisedome, comes from Heaven, and shew How little it prevail'd on earth, since all The mightie here, are of my sect. Merlin. 'Tis long Since this my Magicke rod hath struck the Aire Yet losse of practice can no Art impaire, That soares above the reach of natures might, Thus then I charme the Spirits of the night, And unto Hell conjure their wings to steere, And streight collect from dismall corners there The great seducers of this Isle, that by Their baits of pleasure strove to multiply Those sad Inhabitants, who curse that truth below Which here on Earth they tooke no paines to know, Appeare! Appeare! nimbly obey my will T'expresse I di'd t'increase my Magicke skill. The whole Scene was transformed into a horrid Hell, the further part terminating in a flaming precipice, and the neerer parts expressing the Suburbs, from when enter the severall Antimasques. 1. Entrie. Of mock musick of 5. persons. One with a Violl, the rest with Taber and Pipe, Knackers and bells, Tongs and key, Gridiron and shooing horne. 2. Entrie. A ballad singer, his companion with their Auditorie. A Porter laden, A Vintners boy, A Kitchin maid with a handbasket, A Saylor. 3. Entrie. A crier of mouse-traps, bearing the Engines belonging to their trades. A seller of tinderboxes, bearing the Engines belonging to their trades. The master of Two Baboones and An Ape. 4. Entrie. A Mountebanke in the habit of a grave Doctor, A Zany, his men. A Harlekin his men. An old lame Charewoman. Two Pale wenches presenting their urinals, and hee distributing his printed receits out of a Budget. 5. Entrie. Foure old fashioned Parasiticall Courtiers. 6. Entrie. Of rebellious Leaders in warre. Cade, Kett, Jack Straw and their souldiers. The apparell of these in part shewed their base professions, mixt with some souldier-like Accoutrements. These Antimasques being past, Bellerophon entered riding on Pegasus, in a cote armour of silver scales, and on his head an Antique Helme with Plumes, his Bases watchet with labels of gold, a golden Javelin in his hand, the point of lead. The Pegasus was covered all with white close to his skin, his main and tail of silver, with large white wings, his reines and saddle of carnation trimd with silver. Hee riding up into the middle of the roome with an attendant alighted. Action. Bellerophon? Thou that the of-spring art of Heaven, Most timely, and by Inspiration sure, Thou com'st to helpe me to despise and scorne These Ayry mimick Apparitions, which This cosening Prophet would present as great Examples for succeeding times to imitate. Bellerophon. Through thick assembled clouds, through mists that would Choke up the Eagles eye, I in my swift And sudden journey through the Aire, have seene All these fantasticks objects, which but shew How dull the Impious were to be so sillily Misled, and how the good did ever need But little Care, and lesse of Braine, to scape Th'apparant bayts of such grosse Fooles. Imposture. I Sir, T'were easy to subdue if Cholerick scorne Might make up confutation without helpe Of Arguments, the virtuous Sir of late Have got a fine Feminine trick to rayle At all they will dislike, referre what is Not easily understood unto a kind Obedient Faith, and then call reason but A new and saucie Heretick, those that My reverend Prophet rais'd, which you Sir in A virtuous fury have cal'd Fooles, I'me sure Did governe when alive, and by Imposture made their estimation thrive. Bellerophon. Monster! thou know'st 'tis not thy strange defence Of Reason that provokes my rage, but thou Wouldst cunningly disguise thy sense In Reasons shape, cosening thy willing selfe, And giving seeming pleasures, reall Attributes: These taking tunes, to which the numerous world Doe dance (when your false-sullennesse shall please) You may compare, to'th dangerous Musique of The swan, a merry preparation still To Melancholy death. Imposture. Cry mercy, Sir! You are Heroique virtue, who pretend An Embassy from Heaven, and that y'are sent To make new lovers heere on Earth, you will Refine the waies of wooing, and prescribe To valor, nobler exercise, than what The Ancient Knights Advent'rers taught, but first See these of th'old Heroique race, Merlin Assist me once more with thy charming rod, To shew this strict Corrector of delights What Ladies were of yore, and what their Knights, Although their shapes and manners now grow strange, Make him admire, what he would strive to change. Bellerophon. Alas, how weake and easie would you make Our intellectuall strength, when you have hope It may be overcome with noyse and shews. Imposture. Yes, and this morall Magistrate; your strict O'r solemne Friend, that in such comely Phrase Disputes for active virtue, and declares Himselfe the mark of all vnrighteous opposites, His Magnanimity shall yeeld at last, Streight take my Angle in his hand, then bait The hooke with guilded Flies, to fish in troubled Seas: For all the world is such, and in a storme; Where the Philosopher (that still swimmes in Profoundest depths) will (Sir) as easily Bee snapt, as fooles that float on shallow streames And taken with a Lyne, no stronger sir, than what Will teare a little Gudgeons Iawes. Action. The Knight Adventurer that you intend To raise, must then adventure far, and make His valour captivate, surer and soone As his lamenting Ladies lookes, I'le not Be taken else. Imposture. Most reverend Lord of Dark Vnusuall sciences begin thy charme. Merlin. Like furious Rivers meeting under ground, So hollow and so dismall is the sound Of all my inward murmures, which no eare But with a wild astonishment can heare; Though not so loud as Thunder, Thunders are A slower noyse, and not amaze so far. Which to expresse, that distant spirits heare, And willingly obey: Appeare, Appeare! At this the Hell suddainly vanisheth, and there appeares a vast Forest, in which stood part of an old Castle kept by a Giant, proper for the Scene of the Mock Romansa which followed: Out of this Forest comes running and affrighted, a Dwarf and Damsell; The Dwarfe in blue and white, the Damsell in a streight bodied gown and wide sleeves of changeable, with a safegard of Silver stuffe, and a past and partlet like a Morall figure in old hangings: to these a Knight in old fashioned Armour, with Speare and Shield, his Squire apparell'd in a yellow Coat, with wide sleeves, and strossers cut in paines of yellow and watchet; After them a Giant in a Coat of Mayle, his bases red and silver, with a Fauchion hanging in a Chaine, and in his hand an iron mace, a great roll of black and white on his head: A Saracens face with great black mustachoes. The Mock Romansa. Dwarfe, Squire. Dwar. Fly from this Forest, Squire! Fly trusty sparke! I feare like child, whom maid hath left ith' darke. Squire. O Coward base! whose feare will never Lynne Till 't shrinke thy heart as small as head of Pynne! Lady, with pretty finger in her eye Laments her Lamkin Knight, and shall I flye? Is this a time for blade to shift for's selfe, When Gyant vile, cals Knight a sneaking Elfe? This day, (a Day as faire as heart could wish) This Gyant stood on shore of sea to fish, For Angling rod hee tooke a sturdy Oake, For line a Cable that in storme n'er broke; His hook was such as heads the end of Pole, To pluck down house ere fire consumes it whole. This hooke was baited with a Dragons taile, And then on Rock he stood to bob for Whale: Which streight he caught and nimbly home did pack, With ten Cart load of dinner on his back: Thus homward bent, his eye too rude and cunning, Spies Knight and Lady by an hedge a sunning. That Modicum of meat he downe did lay (For it was all he eat on fasting day) Enter Giant, Knight and Damsell. Dwarfe They come, in's rage he spurn's up huge tree roots, Now stick to Lady Knight, and up with boots. Giant. Bold recr'ant wight! what Fate did hither call thee, To tempt his strength, that hath such power to maule thee? How durst thy puling Damsell hither wander? What was the talke you by yon'd hedge did maunder? Damsell. Patience sweet man of might! alas Heaven knowes We onely hither came to gather sloes, And Bullies two or three; for truth to tell ye I've long'd six weeks with these to fill my belly: I' fecks if you'l beleev't, nought else was meant sure By this our Iaunt, which Errants call Adventure. Giant. Shall I grow meeke as Babe when ev'ry Trull is So bold to steale my sloes and pluck my bullyes? Knight. Feare not! let him storme on, and still grow rougher, Thou that art bright as candle cleer'd by snuffer, Canst n'ere endure a blemish or Eclipse From such a hookt nose foule mouth'd Bobber lips: Ere he shall boast, he us'd thee thus to's People, I'le see him first hang'd high as any steeple. Giant. If I but upward heave my oaken Twig, Ile teach thee play the Tom-boy, her the Rig, Within my Forest bounds: what doth shee aile But shee may serve as Cooke to dresse my whale? In this her Damsels tire and robe of sarcenet Shee shall souce bore, fry tripes, and wild hogs harsnet. Knight. O monster vile, thou mighty ill bred Lubber, Art thou not mov'd to see her whine and blubber? Shall Damsell faire (as thou must needs confesse her) With Canvas apron, dresse thy meat at dresser? Shall shee that is of soft and pliant mettle, Whose Fingers silke would gaule, now scowre a Kettle? Though not to scuffle giv'n, now Ile thwart thee, Let Blowze thy daughter serve for shillings forty. T' is meeter (I thinke) such ugly baggages Should in a Kitchin drudge for yearly wages, Than gentle Shee who hath been bred to stand Neere chaire of Queene with Island shock in hand. At Questions and commands, all night to play, And Amber Possits eat at breake of Day, Or score out Husbands in the charcole ashes. With Courtly Knights, not roaring country swashes, Hath beene her breeding still, and's more fit far To play on Virginals, and the Gittar, Than stir a seacole fire, or scumme a Cauldron, When thou shalt breake thy fast on a buls Chaudron. Giant. Then I perceive I must lift up my Pole, And deale your love-sick noddle such a dole That ev'ry blow shall make so huge a clatter, Men ten leagues off shall aske, Hah! what's the matter? Damsell. Kind grumbling youth! I know that thou art able, And want of breeding makes thee prone to squable, Yet sure thy Nature doth compunction meane Though ('las) thy mother was a sturdy Queane: Let not meeke lovers kindle thy fierce wrath, But keepe thy blustring breath to coole thy broth. Knight. Whine not my love, his fury streight will waste him, Stand off a while and see how Ile lambaste him. Squire. Now looke to't Knight, this such a desp'rate blade is, In Gaule he swing'd the valiant sir Amadis! Dwarfe. With bow, now Cupid shoot this sonne of Puncke With crosse-bowelse, or pellet out of trunke! Giant. Ile strike thee till thou sink where the abode is Of wights that sneake below, cald Antipodis. Merlin. My Art will turne this Combat to delight They shall unto fantastick Musick fight. They fall into a dance and depart. Bellerophon. How triviall and how lost thy visions are! Did thy Propheticke Science take such care (When thou wert mortal) with unlawfull power To recollect thy ashes, 'gainst this houre, And all for such import? surrender strait This usurpation of thy warmth and weight, And turne to Aire, thy Spirit to a winde: Blow thine owne dust about, untill we finde No small remainder of ill gatherd thee And like to it, so waste thy memorie. Action. Thou Imposture to some darke Region steale The light is killing, cause it doth reveale Thy thin disguise, I'th darke thou ne're wilt fade, For dismall plants still prosper in the shade; Thou art a shadow, and observe how all Vaine shadowes to our eyes stretch and grow tall, Iust when the Sunne declines to bring in night, So thou dost thrive in darknesse, waste in light. Bellerophon. Away! Fame (still obedient unto Fate) This happy houre is call'd to celebrate Britanocles, and those that in this Isle The old with moderne vertues reconcile. Away! Fames universall voyce I heare, A trumpet within. Tis fit you vanish quite when they appeare. Exeunt Merlin, Imposture. In the further part of the Scene, the earth open'd and there rose up a richly adorn'd Palace, seeming all of Gold smiths worke, with Portico's vaulted on Pillasters running farre in: the Pillasters were silver of rusticke worke, their bases and capitels of gold, in the midst was the principall entrance, and a gate; the doores leaves with figures of Basse-relieve, with Jambs and frontispice all of gold, above these ran an Architraue Freese and Coronis of the same; the Freese enricht with Jewels; this bore up a Ballestrata, in the midst of which, upon an high Tower with many windowes stood Fame in a Carnation garment, trimd with gold, with white wings and flaxen haire, In one hand a golden Trumpet, and in the other an Olive Girland. In the lower part leaning on the Rayle of the Ballesters were two Persons, that on the right hand personating Arms with a Curace and plumed Helme, and a broken Lance in his hand. On the left hand, a woman in a watchet robe trim'd with silver, on her head a Bend, with little wings like those of Mercury, and a scrowle of parchment in her hand, representing Science. When this Palace was arrived to the height, the whole Scene was changed into a Peristilium of two orders, Dorick and Ionick with their severall Ornaments seeming of white marble, the Bases and Capitals of gold; this joyning with the former having so many returnes, openings, and windowes, might well be knowne for the glorious Palace of Fame. The Chorus of Poets entred in rich habits of severall colours, with Laurels on their heads guilt. Musicke. Fame sings. [1] Breake forth thou Treasure of our sight, That are the hopefull morne of every day, Whose faire example makes the light, By which Heroique vertue findes her way. (2) O thou, our cheerfull morning rise And strait those mistie clouds of errour cleere, Which long have overcast our eyes, And else will darken all this Hemisphere: (3) What to thy Power is hard or strange? Since not alone confinde unto the land; Thy Scepter to a trident change, And strait unruly Seas thou canst command! (4) How hath thy wisedome rais'd this Isle? Or thee, by what new title shall we call Since it were lessning of thy stile, If we should name thee natures Admirall! (5) Thou universall wonder know We all in darknesse mourne till thou appeare, And by thy absence dull'd may grow, To make a doubt if day were ever here! The Masquers came forth of the Peristilium, and stood on each side, and at that instant the gate of the Palace open'd, and Britanocles appear'd. The habit of the Masquers was close bodies of Carnation, embroydered with silver, their arming sleeves of the same; about their waste two rowes of severall fashioned leaves, and under this their bases of white, reaching to the middle of their thigh, on this was an under basis with labels of Carnation embroidered with silver, and betwixt every paine were pufts of silver fastned in knots to the labels, the trimming of the shoulders was as that of the Basis, their long stockins set up were Carnation with white shooes, and roses, their bands and cuffes made of purles of Cutworke, upon their heads little carnation caps embroydered as the rest, with a slit turned up before, out of the midst came severall falls of white feathers diminishing upwards in a Pyramidall forme. This habit was beautifull, rich, and light for dancing, and proper for the Subject of this Masque. Musick. The Palace sinkes, and Fame remaining hovering in the Aire, rose on her wings singing, and was hidden in the Clouds. Chorus. Britanocles, the great and good appeares, His Person fils our eyes, his name our eare, His vertue every drooping spirit cheers! Fame. Why move these Princes of his traine so slow As taking root, they would to Statues grow, But that their wonder of his vertue turnes them so! 'Tis fit you mix that wonder with delight, As you were warm'd to motion with his sight, So pay the expectation of this night. Chorus. Move then in such a noble order here, As if you each his governed Planet were, And he mov'd first, to move you in each spheare. Chorus. O with what joy you'l measure out the time? Each breast like his still free from every crime, Whose pensive weight might hinder you to clime! The Masquers descend into the roome. The song ended, the Scene returnes to that of Brittaine: The Masquers dance their entrie. Which ended, a new Chorus of our owne moderne Poets rais'd by Merlin, in rich habits differing from the rest, with Laurels on their heads guilt, make their addresse to the Queene. (1) Our eyes (long since dissolv'd to Ayre) To thee for Day must now repaire, Though rais'd to life by Merlins might, Thy stocke of Beautie will supply Enough of Sunne from either eye, To fill the Organs of our sight! (2) Yet first thy pittie should have drawne A Cloud of Cypresse or of Lawne, To come betweene thy radiant Beams: Our eyes (long darkned in a shade) When first they so much light invade Must ake and sicken with extreams. (3) Yet wiser reason hath prevail'd To wish thy beauties still unvail'd, 'Tis better that it blinde should make us, Than wee should want such heavenly Fire, That is so usefull to inspire Those Raptures which would else forsake us. (4) Who knowes but Homer got his Flame From some Refulgent Græcian Dame Whose beauty gave his Muse supplies: And would not trust in humble Prose His noble thoughts, but rather chose High numbers, though with losse of eies? Here the Scene changed, and in the farthest part the sea was seene, terminating the sight with the Horizon; on the one side was a Haven, with a Citadell, and on the other broken grounds and Rocks; from whence the sea-Nimph Galatea came waving forth, riding on the back of a Dolphin, in a loose snow white garment, about her neck chaines of Pearle, and her armes adorn'd with bracelets of the same; her faire haire disheveled and mixt with silver, and in some part covered with a veile which she with one hand graciously held up, being arrived to the midst of the sea, the Dolphin stayed, and she sung with a Chorus of musick. Galateas song. (1) So well Britanocles o're seas doth Raigne, Reducing what was wild before, That fairest sea-Nymphs leave the troubled maine, And haste to visit him on shore. (2) What are they lesse than Nymphs since each make shew Of wondrous Immortality? And each those sparckling Treasures weares that grow Where breathlesse Divers cannot Prie? (3) On ever moving waves they us'd to dance Vnto the whistling of the wind; Whose measures hit and meet by erring chance, Where Musick can no concord find. (4) But now for their Majestick welcome trie How ev'n, and equally they'le meet, When you shall lead them by such Harmony, As can direct their eares, and feet. Which done, she gently past away, floating on the waves as shee came in. After this some ships were discern'd sayling afar off severall wayes, and in the end a great Fleet was discovered, which passing by with a side wind tackt about, and with a prosperous gale entred into the Haven, this continuing to entertaine the sight whilst the dancing lasted. The Valediction. (1) Wise Nature, that the Dew of sleepe prepares To intermit our joyes, and ease our cares, Invites you from these Triumphs to your rest. May ev'ry whisper that is made be chast, Each Lady slowly yeeld, yet yeeld at last; Her Heart a Prisner to her Lovers breast! (2) To wish unto our Royall Lover more Of youthfull blessings than he had before, Were but to tempt old Nature bove her might, Since all the Odor, Musique, Beauteous Fire, We in the spring, the spheares, the stars, admire Is his renew'd, and betterd ev'ry night! (3) To Bed, to Bed, may ev'ry Lady dreame From that chiefe beauty shee hath stollen a Beame, Which will amaze her Lovers curious Eyes! Each lawfull Lover to advance his youth, Dreame he hath stolne, his Vigor, Love, and Truth; Then all will haste to Bed, but none to Rise! The Kings Majestie, Duke of Lenox, L. Wil. Hamilton, Earle of Carlile, Earle of Elgin, L. Phil. Herbert, Lord Russell, Mr. Francis Russell, L. Lodowick Stuart, Earle of Devonshire, Earle of Newport Lord Pagit, Lord Wharton, Lord Andevor, Mr. Tho. Howard,</field>
   </doc>
</add>