<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Hoole, John, 1727-1803</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Hoole, John, 1727-1803</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">hoole john 1727 1803</field>
      <field name="author_text">Hoole, John, 1727-1803</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1800's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V2.0513.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1800</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460184</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Demetrius</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Demetrius</field>
      <field name="title_facet">demetrius</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">demetrius</field>
      <field name="title_text">Demetrius</field>
      <field name="year_display">1800</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1800</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1800</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460184&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460184&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Hoole, John, 1727-1803&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;hoole john 1727 1803&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Demetrius&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;demetrius&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1800&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1800&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Hoole, John&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1727&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1803&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Demetrius&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for Otridge and Son ; R. Faulder [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1800&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872748-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv20513&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Demetrius&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 152 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted&lt;lb/&gt;Poetry omitted&lt;lb/&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Demetrius.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Opera.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1768.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Unknown.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DEMETRIUS.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PERSONS OF THE DRAMA. Cleonice, Queen of Syria, in love with Alcestes. Alcestes, in love with Cleonice. Phenicius, a Grandee of the Kingdom, Tutor to Alcestes, and Father of Olinthus. Olinthus, a Grandee of the Kingdom, rival to Alcestes. Barsene, the Confidante of Cleonice, secretly in love with Alcestes. Mithranes, Captain of the Royal Guards, Friend to Phenicius.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Scene lies in Seleucia.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. SCENE I. An apartment illuminated: a seat; a table on one side and a sceptre and crown upon it. Cleonice seated, leaning upon the table, Olinthus. Cleo. Enough, Olinthus, in a few short moments The impatient people at the destin'd place Shall see their queen: they ask of me to choose A husband and a king—yes, I will choose A king and husband: give me but an instant To recollect my thoughts. Why am I press'd With such unmanner'd zeal? Have then my vassals No more respect? And was it but to enslave, You rais'd me to the throne? Or do you scorn To yield subjection to a female sway? But Cleonice is not yet the first Example of her sex; Scythia has own'd The rule of Thomyris and of Thalestris; And Babylon and Carthage have confess'd The reigns of Dido and Semiramis. Olin. Forgive me, queen, unjustly you complain: Say, has not Syria witness'd to your virtues? Remember, when your mighty father died, She plac'd you on the throne; to you intrusted Th' election of her king; allow'd you time For counsel and reflection: ever since She strives in vain to hasten on the hour, Long promis'd by yourself to make her happy: Yet you reproach your people. O! my queen, Unjustly you complain. Cleo. In Cleonice If thus the realm confide, you cannot sure Refuse her now some minutes of delay. Olin. O Heaven! so oft our hopes have been deceiv'd, With reason 'tis we fear. Two moons entire Seleucia gave your pious grief to weep A father's loss; the third is in its wane, Yet are you unresolv'd. Sometimes to excuse Your long delay, you plead a fatal dream, Or unpropitious day: now from the right You see the lightning flash; now from the altar Oblique ascends the flame: the bird of night Now breaks your slumbers with his funeral song; And now your eyes involuntary pour The sudden tear. Cleo. Alas! my fears were true. Olin. After such fond pretences, urg'd in vain, At length this day you promis'd for your choice: Your subjects all assembled, with impatience Prevent the rising morn: each decks his person With utmost pomp to appear before his queen. Some clothe their limbs in costly silken vests, Wrought by Sidonian virgins; some in wool, Of deepest Tyrian dye; while o'er the brows Of some the pride of foreign plumage nods Amid the turban's folds; or from their temples Depend the costly strings of Indian pearl. Others with gems and burnish'd gold adorn The stately trappings of the Parthian steed. This day whate'er is precious Syria shows; And every treasure now is brought to light, Which fearful avarice had for years conceal'd. Cleo. How little this avails to ease my heart! Olin. But wherefore all these cares, this useless pomp, If from the morn till noon, in expectation, From noon till eve they wait, yet wait in vain? The night declines apace, but still you come not. Irresolute, uncertain, still you're lost In anxious doubts, while each delay seems short And insufficient to confirm your thoughts: Yet you reproach your people. O my queen, Unjustly you complain. Cleo. 'Tis all too true; Yes, I must yield to hard necessity: Go then, and I will follow: I will choose My husband, and content my kingdom's wishes. Olin. Reflect—remember that your faithful subject Olinthus loves you—that my blood— Cleo. I know It flows unsullied from a race of heroes. Olin. Then add to this the virtues of Phenicius. Cleo. Of these I'm not to learn. Olin. His prudent counsels— Cleo. Oft have I prov'd their worth, and tried his faith; Whate'er thou say'st, Olinthus, I confess. Olin. And yet you know not all—unnoted long, Enamour'd of your beauties, have I pin'd A secret lover— Cleo. O forbear, and leave me! Olin. Can I forbear? Cleo. Is this a time, Olinthus, To talk of love? [rises. Olin. Why swells your indignation, If pleading here forgiveness— Cleo. Cease, and leave me. Olin. What cause can now your anger move, What may those looks intend? I knew not that to speak of love Would thus my queen offend. 'Tis from your charms my error flows, These passions you impart; Love freedom on my tongue bestows, But binds in chains my heart. [Exit. SCENE II. Enter Barsene. Cleo. Alcestes, O! where art thou? Lov'd Alcestes, Dost thou not hear me? Still in vain I call, In vain expect thy presence.—My Barsene, Perchance thou bring'st me news of glad import; Say, is my dear Alcestes yet return'd? Bar. O would to Heaven he were! I come, my queen, To hasten your approach: the populace Begin to murmur loud at your delay, Nor can you longer, but with utmost danger, Protract your stay. Cleo. O me unhappy! come [going, she stops. Let us depart to choose this husband—Heaven! My courage fails, Barsene: vainly reason Would point me out that course my dubious heart And tardy feet refuse—Is there a wretch So curs'd, so tortur'd, so forlorn as I? [throws herself in the chair. Bar. Why thus ingenious to torment yourself, By feigning woes that are not? Cleo. Feigning woes? Is it a fiction then that tyrant duty Constrains me now to bind myself in marriage, A slave till death to one I cannot love? To one perhaps who while with seeming transport He seeks my hand, laments the hard condition On which he buys the throne? Bar. 'Tis true; but yet The sacred ties, the dear succeeding pledges That bless the nuptial bed; and stealing time Whose course can reconcile two hearts averse; All these, by slow degrees, will change aversion To love, or soften it at least to friendship. Cleo. And what if my Alcestes should again Return, and find me in another's arms! What must become of both?—The thought distracts me— How shall I then repent my breach of faith! What torment must be his to see me false! Alas! I figure to myself his rage, His just reproaches, and his jealous pangs, And in his features every thought I read His secret heart conceals. Bar. And can you hope That ever he'll return? A season now Is past, since 'midst the Cretan ranks, in battle Your father fell; you know that by his side, Alcestes fought, nor has been heard of since. Or now he groans in chains, or 'midst the waves He found his fate, or was in combat slain. Cleo. No, my heart tells me that Alcestes lives, Alcestes will return. Bar. Should he return You must be more unhappy. If to him You give your hand, you slight a hundred lovers That claim regard; or should you choose another, Alcestes present at your fatal choice, You kill the man you love: thus his arrival But offers you this hard alternative, To show your cruelty to one, or prove Unjust to many. Cleo. Let him but return, Some way may yet be found— SCENE III. Enter Mithranes. Mith. O queen, what means Your long delay? The peril grows more pressing: The people's patience now by slow degrees Degenerates into tumult; nought can stop The threatening mischief but your speedy presence. Cleo. Behold Barsene how Alcestes comes! Let us depart. [rises. Bar. Is then your choice determin'd? Cleo. 'Tis not determin'd. Bar. What is then your purpose? Cleo. I know not what. Bar. Will you thus unresolv'd, Expose yourself to such a dangerous trial? Cleo. I go, Barsene, whither fate compels me, Without a friend to counsel or support. While thus a thousand doubts I feel, With empire and with love distrest, My heart afflicted scarce can tell If hope or fear inspire my breast. A sovereign's duty I confess; I own the gentler passion's sway: I now resolve, and now no less Repent, and both by turns obey. [Exit. SCENE IV. Barsene, Mithranes. Bar. Unhappy queen! her woes excite my pity. Mith. Have you so much compassion for her pains, And yet for me, Barsene, feel so little? Bar. If pity's all you seek, I freely grant it; But if you hope for love, your hopes are vain. Mith. And have I not enough to make me wretched, That thou would'st now deprive me even of hope? Bar. Light are the sufferings that you prove; You freely may complain: And if you cannot waken love, At least you pity gain. But I, alas! in secret mourn, All hopeless of relief; Nor the dear youth, for whom I burn, Is conscious of my grief. [Exit. SCENE V. Enter Phenicius. Mith. Fruitless compassion! Phen. Say, Mithranes, where Is Cleonice? Mith. She at length compell'd, Is gone to make th' election. Phen. Then, my friend, My cares are all in vain. Mith. What dost thou mean? Phen. Yes, to thy well known faith I must reveal A mighty secret; hear, and give me counsel. Mith. Confide in me, I plight my truth, my honour Ne'er to reveal it. Phen. Thou remember'st well That Alexander, Cleonice's father, Drove from the throne our lawful king Demetrius. Mith. Near thirty years have since elaps'd, but still The event is present to my mind. Phen. Thou know'st In cruel banishment Demetrius died: Thou must have heard that with him died his son, As yet an infant. Mith. Yes, I recollect He too was call'd Demetrius. Phen. Now, my friend, Learn that this royal offspring still survives, Nor is to thee unknown. Mith. May I believe thee, Or is it but a dream? Phen. I'll tell thee further; He in Alcestes lives. Mith. Immortal powers! What do I hear! Phen. His father, when he fled, Intrusted him to me, and gave me charge To have him nam'd Alcestes: to his bosom He press'd me tenderly, his fond embraces Dividing thus betwixt his son and me, With sighs he cry'd: “Receive this precious pledge; “Preserve him for his father's sake, preserve him “To assert a glorious vengeance and to reign.” Mith. Now I perceive the motive of your zeal: But wherefore was he thus so long conceal'd? Phen. Fearful to hazard yet a life so valu'd, I spread the tidings that Demetrius liv'd, But kept it secret that he was Alcestes. Thou need'st not here be told that this report On Alexander brought the Cretan arms; And that the tyrant in the battle fell. But different was th' effect Demetrius' name Produc'd in Syria; there the ambitious nobles Refus'd their credit to the voice of rumour. And hence a foreign aid was requisite To fix him on the throne: this aid from Crete Is now expected; but it comes in vain. Alcestes is from hence—and, ah! I know not If yet he lives—meantime our Cleonice Elects a king.— Mith. Should Cleonice now Elect him, let Alcestes but return, Let him from Crete receive the promis'd succours, And vengeance still is in his power. Phen. Mithranes, Far different my designs: I hop'd Alcestes Some future day to Cleonice join'd In nuptial bands, with her might share the throne; For sure the princess well deserves to reign. To this intent, in both their hearts I cherish'd A growing passion; and had destiny— But I neglect the hours in vain complaints. My friend, I call'd thee to partake my cares, Could we gain time we yet might reap the fruit Of all our toils—Then let us go, and seek To interrupt the choice; if nought beside Avail, I'll venture to disclose the secret: Do thou before the assembly second me, And if the great occasion call for arms, With arms assist me. Mith. Here's my hand, my sword, In such a cause my blood shall freely flow; I ne'er can shed it in a nobler quarrel. O! 'twere an envied death to lose my life In fighting for my king. Phen. Come to my breast Thou generous subject! thy fidelity Brings tears into my eyes; within my heart I feel new hopes, and by thy courage see The Gods withdraw not yet their favour from us. Safe through the storm my vessel flies, The dangerous course while Virtue guides; While Reason, near, her aid supplies; While Glory in my breast resides. 'Tis Virtue that my truth ensures; 'Tis Reason makes my courage more; And Glory, after death, secures My name from time's oblivious power. [Exit. SCENE VI. Mithranes alone. One like Alcestes never could be born In lowly cottages; his looks, his air, His speech betray'd him: even in humble state His actions all proclaim'd a princely heart. A soul exalted, form'd to reign, In lonely woods conceal'd in vain, Still darts, by fortune though depress'd, A ray of majesty distress'd. The blazing fire, though deeply hid, Can never wholly cease to shine: Huge rivers in the narrow bed Refuse their currents to confine. [Exit. SCENE VII. A magnificent place with a throne on one side; seats opposite the throne for the Grandees of the kingdom. A prospect of the principal port of Seleucia, with the harbour. Ships illuminated to solemnize the election of the new king. Cleonice preceded by the Grandees of the kingdom, followed by Phenicius and Olinthus. Guards and People. Chorus. Each God, and every Goddess hear! Be present at our prayer: Behold the important moment near That must our king declare. First Chorus. Hear! Mars and Cupid, now descend; Your eyes unbind, your falchion sheathe. Second Chorus. Let Peace and Hymen here attend, With kindled torch, and olive wreath. First Chorus. Come, Jove, and close beside thee wait The subject Gods, with Chance and Fate. Second Chorus. Benignant come to bless mankind, And leave thy angry bolts behind. Chorus. Each God, and every Goddess hear! Be present at our prayer; Behold the important moment near, That must our king declare. [while this Chorus is sung, Cleonice, attended by Phenicius, ascends the throne. Olin. O queen! all Syria with impatient zeal Waits from your lips to hear their monarch nam'd, At length resolve—each, by respectful silence, Would hasten on th' event. Cleo. Sit then—O Gods! How cruel is this day! [aside. [Phenicius, Olinthus and the rest of the Grandees take their places. Phen. What means she now! [aside. Cleo. Syrians attend: you rais'd me to the throne; Your love deserves my thanks; and yet your gift Is clogg'd with hard conditions: midst so many Equal in birth, and equal in desert, Like me, who would not pause? In all my thoughts Doubtful, irresolute, now this, now that, I choose, reject; a thousand times an hour I change my will. Behold I come to choose, Yet still I come uncertain, unresolv'd. Phen. Take then, O queen! a longer time to fix Your undetermin'd mind. Olin. A longer time? Phen. Be silent—think not Syria means to press you With zeal importunate: we all confess How great must be your trial. Olin. Is the course Of three long moons so little? Thus indeed May Cleonice still proceed to promise, And never yet resolve. Phen. Presumptuous boy! Whence springs this insolence? Olin. 'Tis zeal, 'tis justice, 'Tis sense of danger for my queen. Should Syria This day be baffled in her hopes, I know not To what extremes impatience may proceed. Phen. They may repent their rashness: those who sit Supreme on thrones can brook compulsion ill. Though length of years unnerve my body's strength, It has not damp'd the vigour of my soul: No—these old veins shall pour forth all their blood To guard my sovereign's freedom— Cleo. O Phenicius! Forbear to furnish cause for new contention. What now avails it to defer th' election, I still shall be uncertain—Hear me then, I now declare my choice— Phen. You must not choose. 'Tis time we should discover all. [aside. Cleo. What brings Mithranes here with hasty steps? SCENE VIII. Enter Mithranes. Mith. This instant, In a small bark, Alcestes is arriv'd. Cleo. Ye powers! Phen. I breathe again. Cleo. Where is Alcestes? Mith. He comes from yonder port. Cleo. Phenicius, go; And thou, Olinthus—O my fluttering heart! Meet and embrace your now returning friend. [rises, the rest rise at the same time. I had almost forgot I was a queen. [aside. [resumes her seat. [Phenicius and Mithranes go to meet Alcestes, who is seen to approach the shore in a small vessel; he lands, and they embrace. Olin. Unfortunate arrival! [aside. Cleo. See Alcestes! And dost thou throb, my heart, to view the conqueror That binds thee in his chains? SCENE IX. Enter Alcestes from the port. Alc. At length has fate Given me the wish'd-for happiness, my queen, To throw me at your feet: yes, Heaven allows me Thus with these faithful lips to pay you here The tribute of my constancy; most happy, If 'midst the cares that still surround a throne, You deign one royal look to grace my welcome. Cleo. Whate'er I am, or private, or a queen, Still shalt thou find the same in Cleonice. And art thou then Alcestes now return'd, So long expected, and so long bewail'd? Phen. My hopes again revive. [aside. Cleo. But what disaster Has thus withheld thee from us? Olin. Patience, Heaven! [aside. Alc. You know that my departure with your father— Olin. Alcestes, we've been told the sight, the storm, The death of Alexander— Cleo. Let him yet Relate the rest—Proceed. [to Alcestes. Olin. O pain to suffer! [aside. Alc. The courage of our troops began to sink When Alexander died: the adverse bands Already leap'd triumphant on our ships, And horrid slaughter rag'd amidst the vanquish'd. Death stalk'd around in various ghastly forms; Some in the waves expir'd; some breath'd their last Transfix'd with hostile darts; and oft 'twas doubtful If seas or foes destroy'd them. I meanwhile, Preserv'd amid the havock, hating life, Stood on the vessel's shatter'd prow, expos'd To many a thousand shaft: there long I fought, Till my blood streaming fast from every wound, My senses fail'd, and headlong from the height, Into the seas I fell. Cleo. My pitying heart! [aside. Alc. How long I floated on the waves I know not; But when again I rais'd my heavy eyes, They saw the ship no more; but I perceiv'd Myself upon a homely bed reclin'd, Beneath a simple roof: the walls around Were hung with nets; and close beside me stood, With gentle looks, a hoary fisherman, Bent by the weight of years. Cleo. But say, what land Had then receiv'd thee? Alc. 'Twas the land of Crete, A Cretan was my host; he found me cast Half dead upon the shore, and with compassion Convey'd me to his dwelling; then with care Restor'd my fainting sense, and to my wounds Applied the sovereign balm of healing plants: With him I long remain'd; 'twas he provided The bark that brought me hither. Phen. Strange events! Olin. At length the tale is done—'tis time— Cleo. Olinthus, I understand thee—I will choose my husband: Let all be seated and attend. [Phenicius, Olinthus and the rest of the Grandees take their places. Alc. I come Most opportunely to the choice. [Alcestes going to seat himself, is prevented by Olinthus. Olin. Forbear, What would'st thou do? Alc. Obey the queen's command. Olin. And shall it be? Shall Syria then behold A low-born shepherd seated by Olinthus? Alc. Already Syria has enough distinguish'd Alcestes from the shepherd. Know, Alcestes Cast off his former state, when he resign'd The shepherd's crook to grasp the warrior's arms. Olin. But in those veins still runs a peasant's blood. Alc. No—in these veins far different flows the stream; For when I shed my blood in your defence, I made it noble. Olin. Which of all thy race Hast thou to boast? What now inspires this boldness? Alc. My own right hand, my courage, and my sword. Olin. Since then— Phen. Be silent yet— Olin. Let us at least Be told the glory of his ancestors. Phen. The glory of thy race with thee concludes, But his begins with him. Cleo. No more—By virtue Of my command Alcestes is ennobled. Olin. Yet in this place must none presume to sit, But those of highest rank. Cleo. Well then, Alcestes Shall sit as general of the Syrian armies; Shall sit as keeper of the royal signet: Will this suffice, Olinthus? [Alcestes seats himself. Olin. 'Tis too much— [rising. Give next yourself away; elect him king; For all must see to what your purpose tends. Phen. And dar'st thou rashly answer thus thy sovereign? Hear me, O queen! to me commit the task To punish this presumptuous— Cleo. To his merits, And inexperienc'd youth, I pardon all: But let him curb his speech. Phen. Sit then, and learn [to Olinthus. At least in silence to suppress thy temper. Hear'st thou, Olinthus? Olin. Sir—I will obey— [sits. I burn with rage. [aside. Cleo. Already in my heart My choice is fix'd, but ere I speak my thoughts, This one condition grant: each present here Must swear allegiance to th' elected king, Whether a Syrian, or a stranger born, Of blood illustrious, or of race obscure. Olin. Can I hear this? [aside. Phen. Whate'er he be, O queen! I swear to obey him. Cleo. Now, Olinthus, speak. Phen. Wilt thou not answer? Olin. Let me still be silent. Cleo. Thou dost perhaps refuse it? Olin. I have cause; Nor I alone oppose the oath enjoin'd; Others there are— Cleo. 'Tis well—let those who seek On terms like these to reign, ascend the throne: I will not bear controlment in dominion. [rises from the throne; all the rest rise from their seats at the same time. Phen. Heed not, O queen! the few that dare rebel; But see the faithful many that obey. Cleo. Phenicius, no—I never in my presence Must bear even from a few the voice of faction. [descends from the throne. Then let the general council of the state Determine for me. Suffer me to choose Without the law's compulsion, or permit me To quit this throne, which at your own request I first ascended. In a private station I may, without a crime, on whom I please Bestow my heart; and be indeed a queen. If on the throne I must obey, Resume again the pageant sway, For such my soul disdains. The prince whose power to will is lost, Is but a titled slave at most, And but in fancy reigns. [Exit followed by Mithranes, Grandees, guards and people. SCENE X. Phenicius, Olinthus, Alcestes. Phen. And must thy passions ever make me blush, Nor wilt thou from the converse of the wise, Or their example, learn to rule thy conduct? Olin. My father, wherefore are you thus unkind To me your son? The power is yours to raise Olinthus to the throne, and you oppose him. Phen. Yes, Syria then would doubtless have a king With every virtue; turbulent and rash, Unjust and violent— Olin. Your lov'd Alcestes Would then be humble, generous, mild and prudent! Ah! who will teach me now the art to gain A father's dear affection? Phen. Would'st thou gain On my affection, imitate Alcestes. The careful peasant when he spies A tender tree that kindly grows; His pains full gladly there applies, And all his culture there bestows. But with regret he turns aside, Whene'er his nursling he perceives His former cares and toil deride, With fruitless boughs and barren leaves. [Exit. SCENE XI. Olinthus, Alcestes. Olin. My father bids me in Alcestes' school Learn to be virtuous—Come, begin to teach me: And Heaven so frame my genius to receive Instruction, not to shame so great a master. Alc. My lord, from you alone I can support Such bitter taunts—the son of good Phenicius May speak without rebuke. Olin. I was too bold To dally with my king: forgive me, sir, If I offend the regal dignity. Alc. Farewell, Olinthus, for you put my patience To too severe a trial; you insult me, And trust too much in that respect I owe you. The seaman mocks the rising breeze, When first it blows a gentle gale; But trembles, when the wind he sees With dreadful rage that waves assail. The pilgrim, with regardless view, Aloft a fleecy cloud espies; 'Till thence unlook'd-for storms ensue, And thunders rattle through the skies. [Exit. SCENE XII. Olinthus alone. What man, unconscious of Alcestes' birth, And race obscure, but by his proud demeanour Would deem him sprung from Pelops or Alcides? Yet, spite of rank, with shame I own, Alcestes Is still a rival that Olinthus fears. What now avails a noble name, The boasted stock from which I came, If, 'midst the various turns of fate, A shepherd-swain, of lowly state, With me for Syria's throne contends? Blind Fortune! I the gift despise, That in your changeful favour lies, That on your partial smile depends. [Exit. SCENE XIII. An inner garden of the royal palace. Cleonice, Barsene. Cleo. Is it because I love him that the world Are all Alcestes' foes? To oppose me thus, But adds to my affection. Bar. Now perhaps The council has decided in your favour. Why then before the time— Cleo. Full well I know The power of envy: at this very instant Perhaps my empire's ended: yet, Barsene, Think not that malice e'er can make me wretched: In my Alcestes' heart I more than reign. Bar. O pangs of jealousy! [aside. SCENE XIV. Enter Phenicius. Cleo. Phenicius, speak, Has yet the council settled? Phen. All is done. Cleo. The rest I understand without thy telling: My reign is finish'd. Phen. Better judge, my queen, Of Syria and yourself: your faithful vassals Have more respect and love. The power is yours To raise the man you please, to share the throne: Whate'er may prove your choice, of high degree, Or race obscure, all swear to yield obedience. Cleo. And can it be? What! in a few short moments, So chang'd from what they were? Phen. Alas! you know not How dear your subjects prize you: all appear'd On this important day. With transport some Extoll'd your form, where goodness seem'd to dwell: Your wisdom some, and some your virtues prais'd: Some offer'd all their blood in your defence; And, 'midst their mingled raptures of applause, O queen! how many eager tongues at once Pronounc'd the pleasing name of Cleonice. Bar. O my disastrous love! [aside. Cleo. Go—to the council Declare this message—tell them that my heart Is not insensible to such high proofs Of duteous zeal; that still my care shall be The kingdom never may repent the trust Plac'd in their queen; that Cleonice ever With gratitude shall own it. Phen. [aside.] In Alcestes The rightful heir will now ascend the throne. [Exit. SCENE XV. Cleonice, Barsene. Bar. Behold how fortune seconds all your wishes: See your desires accomplish'd; every sorrow Is now dispers'd. Cleo. O Heaven! Bar. What means that sigh? Is there a cause of grief? This happy hour The man you love is yours; and still your eyes Are dimm'd with streaming tears. Cleo. My dear Barsene, Alcestes now is lost! Bar. How lost, my queen! Cleo. Shall then my subjects be more generous found Than I their queen? And would'st thou Cleonice Should by her partial fondness judge of merit, Without regarding that illustrious throng Of nobles that surround her? Shall she raise A shepherd to the throne to rule the world? O! can I even in thought—It must not be. Till now my glory urg'd me to subdue The opposing voice of faction; that repell'd, It now inspires me to subdue myself. Bar. How will Alcestes bear it? Cleo. If Alcestes Still love me as he ought, he'll love my glory. O! he'll exult to find his Cleonice Thus shine with native lustre o'er her sex, Above the vulgar herd of common lovers. Bar. I fear your best resolves will shrink before him. Cleo. Alas! my friend, I dare not meet the trial; I know not if my virtue could support it; For O! my heart is fix'd too firmly his. If I would conquer, I no more must view That dear lov'd face. SCENE XVI. Enter Mithranes. Mith. Alcestes seeks admittance. Cleo. O Heaven! Barsene! Bar. Now, confirm your strength. Cleo. Go—'tis no longer time— [to Mithranes. Mith. Alcestes comes. [Exit. Cleo. Be resolute my soul. [aside. SCENE XVII. Enter Alcestes. Alc. And is it given me Without a blush, before my beauteous queen To breathe my vows of constancy; to tell her That absent from her sight I found no peace? To tell her that my thoughts were only hers, That she's my love, my glory, and my life? Cleo. Ah! speak not thus. Alc. Not speak! can then these fond, These true professions of my heart's affection, That once were wont to please, offend thee now? And is it thus, O Heaven! I find again The same in Cleonice? Or am I The same Alcestes, that at length return'd, So long expected, and so long bewail'd? Cleo. O torture! [aside. Alc. Yes, I see, I see it now; A few short moons of absence have suffic'd To freeze the hopes of ten years faithful love. Cleo. Ah! would to Heaven— Alc. What means that exclamation? Tell me my crime; if ever I have wrong'd thee, Let fate resume whate'er thy lavish hand Has heap'd upon me: may those beauteous eyes, Those eyes that rule my heart, that guide my life, Still on Alcestes dart their angry beams. Look on me—speak— Cleo. I can endure no more— Farewell!— [Exit. SCENE XVIII. Barsene, Alcestes. Alc. Ye powers! what can this mean? Her words Confus'd, her frequent sighs, her looks of sorrow, All make me tremble—tell me then, Barsene, Say whence this new, this cruel change proceeds? From the dark workings of some secret foe? Or is it but her own inconstancy, The stars' injustice, or Alcestes' guilt? Bar. Even from my soul I pity your distraction: Perchance some other beauty may be found To make Alcestes happier. Alc. First my life Shall reach its latest period—still I'll love her, Though 'tis decreed I must no more have peace. 'Tis better far to suffer every torment For Cleonice's sake, than to receive From other lips affection's tenderest vows. Her charms, that kindled first my flame, The fuel still supply: Through life my passion burns the same, With me alone shall die. Should Love the fairest maid incline To hear and soothe my pain: In vain to me her beauties shine, Her pity sooths in vain. [Exit. SCENE XIX. Barsene alone. What would'st thou more, my heart? Subject thyself To be refus'd, contemn'd! thy hopes are fruitless To overcome Alcestes' constancy. Yet who can tell th' event? Long time and suffering Perhaps may conquer—by repeated drops The obdurate rock is worn; and stubborn oaks Yield to the sounding axe's frequent blows. But should I be deceiv'd? Alas! I fear The youth I dote on, constant to his purpose, Will more relentless prove than stones or trees. My soul her freedom seeks to gain, Would fain resolve to break her chain, But this the flatterer Hope denies. Of all the passions in our breast, This first is born, an early guest, And is the last that dies. Yet, ah! to heal distemper'd minds How little Hope conspires, But only constant fuel finds For credulous desires. [Exit. END OF THE FIRST ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. SCENE I. A gallery. Alcestes, Olinthus. Alc. And wherefore dost thou now oppose my passage? I haste to the apartment of the queen. Olin. Thou must not enter there, the queen forbids thee: Olinthus says it. Alc. Here at least I'll wait Till I'm again permitted to behold her. Olin. My word may sure suffice: thou must not now Attempt to appear in Cleonice's presence: She has forbidden thee to be admitted, Nor e'er will see thee more.—Yet dost thou hear me? Alc. See me no more?—O Heaven! Olin. I see, Alcestes, Thou art struck at this command. Alc. Olinthus, no. Forgive me, but I cannot yet believe thee: To me my queen can ne'er be so unjust. O! wherefore should she doom to such affliction The man whose faith to her has prov'd unshaken? Olinthus, either thou deceiv'st thyself, Or me thou would'st deceive. Olin. And dar'st thou then Still doubt my truth? Alc. If I have dar'd too far, I shall know all from her. [going. Olin. Yet stay. SCENE II. Enter Mithranes. Mith. Alcestes, Say, whither would'st thou go? Alc. Detain me not; I fly to Cleonice. Mith. O! my friend, Thou art denied admittance to her sight. Alc. Is it then true that I'm forbid— Mith. Too true. Alc. For pity's sake, Mithranes, plead my cause; Return, and tell her that this cruel stroke Is more than all my firmness can support: Tell her some envious tongue has wrong'd my fame, That still I'm true, that should she think me guilty, I at her feet can clear my sullied honour. Mith. I dare not now obey you; for the queen Has given us charge to speak of you no more, And makes it criminal to name Alcestes. Alc. But say the cause. Mith. From me she keeps it secret. Alc. Alas! I am betray'd: some impious wretch Belies me to her: but whoe'er thou art Tremble, thou traitor; think not thou shalt long Be hid from my resentment: in the temple I'll pierce thy heart, nor shall the sacred altar Preserve thee from my rage. Olin. These threats, Alcestes, Are spent in vain. Alc. Alas!—forgive, my friends, The transport of a mind disturb'd: my state Deserves compassion, and I ask it of you. O! speak in my behalf: at least with pity Reflect that, midst his many griefs, Alcestes Is now reduc'd to place his trust in you. Is there a man whose savage heart No sense of soft compassion proves, For one, though guiltless, doom'd to part For ever from the fair he loves? Though cruel stars my death decree, Yet nothing from my soul can tear Her image which I ever see, Which ever in my breast I bear. [Exit. SCENE III. Olinthus, Mithranes. Olin. At length 'tis done—the ruin of Alcestes Secures to me the empire—Yes, Mithranes, Already hope anticipates my joy. Mith. The wise rely not easily on hope. A happiness, in confidence expected, When 'tis withheld, afflicts us like a loss: Thou art deceiv'd, if thus thy hopes allure thee. It were a happiness indeed to reign, If headstrong passions would respect the throne: If nothing more remain'd for him to wish, Who once had worn the vest of royalty; But one desire extinct, another springs, The object chang'd it loses not its strength. If now thou find'st not peace within thyself, Learn thou wilt still be wretched in the state Of wish'd-for empire. Olin. Think'st thou not the pleasure Is mighty, to command? Mith. The good we seek By custom grows familiar; every joy Is more in expectation than possession. Thou canst not tell the burden of a crown, Nor what it costs to attain the arts of sway. Olin. By reigning, 'tis we learn to rule. Mith. 'Tis true: But he, who learns by ruling, oft must err, And every little error in a king, Is criminal esteem'd. Olin. Of this, Mithranes, I cannot speak; for taught alone to wield The sword and spear, 'tis not for me to fathom The passions of mankind: such deep researches Demand maturer years, and frequent converse In Egypt's temples, or the Athenian porch. Mith. There needs not sure the wisdom taught at Athens Or Egypt, to preserve our faith unbroken? Hast thou not lov'd Barsene till this hour? Olin. And still I love her. Mith. Canst thou, loving her, Desire a throne that certain makes her loss. Olin. And wilt thou, with a kingdom gain'd, compare The losing of a heart? Mith. By proofs like these Fidelity is known. Olin. In love, Mithranes, What faith is to be found? Through every part 'Tis vaunted oft, but little 'tis preserv'd. See the boasted truth of lovers Like the Arabian bird renown'd, Vouch'd by all, but none discovers Where the wonder may be found. Canst thou tell what climes conceal him, Where he dies and lives again? When to me thou wilt reveal him, Then my love shall fix'd remain. [Exit. SCENE IV. Mithranes alone. The lightest breath of Fortune's doubtful gale Can elevate his thoughtless youth: already Olinthus seems to grasp the regal sceptre; Already sees himself on Syria's throne; How weak is man when passion blinds the soul! SCENE V. Mithranes, Cleonice. Cleo. Who waits there? I would write. [speaks to a page as entering. Depart, Mithranes. Mith. I shall obey you. [going. Cleo. Hear me—Has Alcestes Again enquir'd of me? Mith. He has, O queen! No other care—but still the unhappy youth— Cleo. Depart—enough—yet hear, what could he say? Mith. He vows that still he's true to love, That treacherous arts your bosom move, That ne'er your heart could cruel prove, Where goodness once was wont to rest. He dies to see your anger past, Before your feet to breathe his last, The victim of his love distrest. [Exit. SCENE VI. Enter Barsene. Bar. All is prepar'd, my queen: here in this paper You to Alcestes may reveal your purpose. Cleo. And shall I not in this be most inhuman To him and to myself? Yet would I fain Subdue my heart, would fain estrange him from me: For this the realm expects, my glory prompts, Heaven wills, and Cleonice must obey. But from my lips at least he may be told it; 'Tis tyranny by letter to convey Such cruel tidings to him—No, my friend, What other consolation can remain For two unhappy lovers, doom'd to part, Than to complain at least with mutual sorrow, To dwell on all their former tenderness, And mourn together in their last adieu? Bar. Is this a consolation then?—O no, A wish to see Alcestes has betray'd you. Trust not yourself again to such a trial: Resisting once you have enough perform'd, You lose the fruit of your first victory Should you attempt a second—Well I know One interview would weaken your resolves, And stronger make the foe. Complete, my queen, The generous work: in you your subjects hope: Reflect that on your constancy to bear This cruel stroke, that fills your soul with anguish, Must now depend your glory. Cleo. Tyrant glory! And must I die to keep my fame unsullied? Or, while I live, for ever mourn the loss Of all I hold most dear?—Inhuman duty! Thou shalt be satisfied—yes, I will write. Bar. My fate begins to smile; I still have hopes Alcestes may be mine. [aside. Cleo. “Belov'd Alcestes,”— [writing. Bar. Yes, I may boast of happiness indeed, If 'midst th' emotions of her troubled mind, For some few moments glory keeps her seat. [aside. Cleo. “Our fate permits us not to live in peace.”— [writing. Bar. My hopes increase—O Heaven! she now withdraws Her trembling hand, and leans her pensive cheek: Alas! her first affections are return'd! [aside. Cleo. My poor undone Alcestes! [speaks, then writes again. Bar. How I tremble Lest she repent: yet were I Cleonice I know not how my heart could bear the conflict. [aside. Cleo. [writing.] “Still live, my best belov'd, but not for me.”— 'Tis done, Barsene. [rising. Bar. We have reach'd the port. [aside. Yes, justly Heaven has destin'd for the throne A mind like yours exalted. Cleo. Take this paper: The care be thine— [about to give her the paper. SCENE VII. Enter Phenicius. Phen. Have pity, gracious queen! Cleo. For whom dost thou implore it? Phen. For Alcestes. But now I met him pale, and scarce alive, Half frantic with his grief: the harsh decree That dooms him never to behold you more, Is such a stroke as stabs him to the heart. By turns he sighs, he raves, he prays, he threatens, But 'midst his rage and grief remembers you, And you alone; each moment he repeats Your much lov'd name, that even obdurate rocks Might pity his distress. Cleo. Unjust Phenicius, From thee my staggering virtue hop'd to find A kind support, but ne'er from thee expected A motive to betray it. Why, ah! why Dost thou return, with barbarous cruelty, To search the wound still bleeding in my breast? Phen. Forgive the warmth of fond paternal love, That prompts me thus: Alcestes is my son, Son of my choice, son of my dearest cares, The happy plant which I have foster'd long, That flourish'd in the beams of princely favour, Beneath your royal eye; the kingdom's hope; The hope and stay of my declining age. Bar. O ill-tim'd zeal! [aside. Phen. And must I now behold My expectations in a moment blasted? Ah! queen, I cannot boast such strength in age As will enable me a single day To outlive this fatal shock. Cleo. What can I do? What would Alcestes? Say, what consolation Does he from me require to ease his sufferings? Phen. To view you once again and die. Cleo. O Heaven! Phen. Fairest of queens! I see your heart is mov'd: Have pity on Alcestes, on Phenicius; Think on these silver hairs, these years of service; My well-tried faith sure merits some indulgence. Cleo. Who longer could resist?—Go, bid him enter. [tears the paper, and rises. Bar. Behold my kindling hopes again extinguish'd. [aside. Phen. It is enough—let her but see Alcestes, Alcestes will o'ercome. [going, meets Olinthus. SCENE VIII. Enter Olinthus. Olin. My queen, my father, Alcestes is no longer in Seleucia; By my device already he's departed. Cleo. What say'st thou? Phen. Wherefore? Olin. With ungovern'd warmth Importunate he sought once more to see you; Hence, in your name, I gave him strict command Instant to quit the realm. Cleo. And when from me Didst thou receive such orders?—Guards! O Heaven! [Guards enter. Haste, be Alcestes found and brought before us. [Guards go out. Phen. Unhappy me! [aside. Cleo. But should their search be vain, Tremble, rash youth, 'tis thou shalt pay the forfeit Of thy presumption. Olin. I but hop'd to serve you, Removing thus a dangerous obstacle, That might obstruct your glory. Cleo. Who made thee The guardian of my glory? Could I ever Have but foreseen, Phenicius, this misfortune? Sure all the world conspire against my peace. In sorrow's lap my infant years Were from the hapless cradle bred; And Fortune still averse appears; In sorrow still my days are led. While Love each vain resolve destroys; No longer fix'd my thoughts remain; Yet Love, alas! no peace enjoys, Nor finds the bliss he seeks to gain. [Exit. SCENE IX. Barsene, Phenicius, Olinthus. Olin. Tell me, my lord, when have you known a mind Changeful like Cleonice's? At one instant She loves, and hates; now asks to see Alcestes, And now forbids his presence; while on others She lays the blame of her still wavering purpose. Phen. Rash boy! and dost thou thus respect thy sovereign? At least for once be taught to curb thy speech. O! I despair to amend him! [to Barsene. Bar. Ripening days Will bring maturer thought: as yet Olinthus Is but in life's first spring. Phen. I too, Barsene, Have known the spring of life: these locks that now Are thinn'd and white with time, were beauteous once; Then, happy times! 'twas not with such contempt Youth heard the wholesome counsels of the wise: But now the world declines, and growing old Degenerates from its virtue. [Exit. SCENE X. Barsene, Olinthus. Olin. To content The austerity of age, we must begin To act the hero from our infant years; But, ah! Barsene, different is the plan Of sprightly youth. Say, does Olinthus still Share in thy tenderness? Bar. Alas! my lord, Why would you mock me thus? Since long ere this Mine have been shaken off for nobler chains, And, to her sovereign, pleas'd Barsene yields? I know in sport thou seek'st my love: Know too, but few the tears I shed; But little grief my soul can move, To find a faithless lover fled. Another now my heart inspires; To him my fond affections turn; And in my breast the pleasing fires Still burn, and shall for ever burn. [Exit. SCENE XI. Olinthus alone. Barsene's scorn, and Cleonice's anger, Alcestes' fortune, and the harsh rebukes Of a stern father might have damp'd the fire In every common mind: but 'tis not these Can terrify Olinthus. Great attempts Demand an equal courage: noble spirits Start not at perils, nor refuse fatigues; And favouring fortune oft befriends the bold. He ne'er with venturous vessel braves The sea, when loud the tempest raves, Who, pale with fear, the distant waves In safety from the land surveys. He ne'er attempts to mix in fight, Who trembles at the glittering light Of armour, and the falchion's blaze. [Exit. SCENE XII. A room with seats. Cleonice alone. Now, Cleonice, now, thy trial comes: To see thy lov'd Alcestes once again, And see him for the last! and hast thou courage To speak thyself the fatal sentence to him? To bid him leave thee, drive thee from his thoughts? Far better had it been to let him go. SCENE XIII. Enter Mithranes. Mith. My gracious queen, Alcestes is at hand, After such pangs restor'd again to life, He waits once more impatient to behold you. Cleo. How my heart throbs! [aside. Mith. Phenicius saw and cheer'd him, Told him the power he still had in your breast, At this recovering, like a tender flower That rises to the sun, surcharg'd with dew, He clear'd his brow, again the colour flush'd His glowing cheek, and every look was chang'd; While fill'd with hope and unexpected joy, Love mix'd with transport brighten'd in his face. Cleo. And must I lose him then? [aside. Depart, Mithranes, Bid him approach, I here expect his coming. Mith. O fortunate Alcestes! [Exit. SCENE XIV. Cleonice alone. Where, ah! where Are now the boasted thoughts of fame and empire? Ah! what has driven you hence? To guard my soul In this dire trial, this approaching conflict, I seek you in my breast but cannot find you; This is the dreadful moment—Can I place My hopes in you, when at the name alone Of him I love, you thus at once forsake me? Return, O Heaven! return: assemble all, Confirm my weak resolves, and teach my heart To bear unmov'd the last assaults of love. SCENE XV. Enter Alcestes. Alc. O queen ador'd! no longer I'll believe That grief destroys us: 'tis deception all, To say affliction's iron hand cuts short The lingering hapless hours of painful life. O! were it true, Alcestes had not liv'd: But if my woes have purchas'd this reward, This wish'd-for meeting, happy are my sufferings; Whate'er I've felt is amply now repaid. Cleo. Heart-breaking tenderness! [aside. Alc. If thou art still To me the same as I am still to thee; If it indeed be true that I may yet Hope every thing from Cleonice's goodness; O! tell me now by what unknown offence Have I deserv'd such rigour from my queen? Cleo. Thou shalt know all, Alcestes; sit, and hear me. [sits. Alc. I shall obey my sovereign. [sits. Cleo. Chilling fear Benumbs my heart. [aside. Alc. I feel my hopes revive. [aside. Cleo. Alcestes, dost thou love indeed thy queen? Or art thou but enamour'd of her rank, Her regal fortune, and illustrious race? Alc. And can you think such motives urge Alcestes? Or, by your doubts, would you reproach my birth, My low paternal cottage? 'Midst the woods That gave me life, that nurs'd my early years, I left such abject thoughts; or rather say I never knew them—No—In Cleonice I love the charms, subjected not to change Of fortune or of age, her noble mind That in its native virtues bright, reflects More splendor on the crown and regal sceptre, Than royal dignity on her bestows. Cleo. May I not then from such a generous lover Expect some glorious proof of fortitude? Alc. Speak your command, Alcestes shall obey. Cleo. You promise much. Alc. And I'll perform it all. Each danger must be light, when prov'd for thee. Securely will I dare the tempest's rage; Or if thou bidst me go, expose my bosom Unarm'd, defenceless, to th' embattled foes. Cleo. I ask much more, Alcestes—thou must leave me. Alc. Leave thee!—O Heaven!—what is it thou hast said? Cleo. Yes, thou must leave me, must for ever leave me, And live without me in some distant clime. Alc. But who prescribes this cruel doom? Cleo. My honour, The genius of my subjects, justice, duty; That virtue you admire in Cleonice, Which gives more brightness to the diadem, Than royal dignity on her bestows. Alc. And can you then, with constancy unmov'd, Command me to forsake you? Cleo. Ah! thou know'st not— Alc. I've known enough; I see thou lov'st me not. [rises. Appease thy glory, satisfy thy vassals, And carry to the throne the stain of falsehood; While wandering through the world I bear in mind The deep remembrance of thy faith betray'd; If grief permit Alcestes to survive. [going. Cleo. Leave me not yet. Alc. O! I too much respect Great Cleonice's rank: a base-born shepherd, By staying longer here, will but debase Her royal dignity. Cleo. Thou dost deride me, Ungrateful man! Alc. And am I then ungrateful? Have I forsaken thee, and sacrific'd My faith, my promises, my oaths, my love, To pomp and state?—Inhuman, perjur'd woman! Cleo. Yes, from thy lips I will endure it all: If thou hast more to utter, give it vent; But when thou art weary of insulting me, Let Cleonice in her turn reply. Alc. What canst thou say, ingrate, for thy defence? Dost thou then hope to varnish o'er the guilt Of falsehood black as thine? Cleo. O yet, Alcestes, Forbear to judge too rashly—sit and hear me. Alc. Heavens! in her power how much she still confides! [aside, sits again. Cleo. Alcestes, if thou wilt but recollect That ten revolving years thou hast been still The dearest object of my constant wishes, Thou wilt believe what anguish I must feel In parting from thee now: but Cleonice, Before the world constrain'd to choose a king, No longer can consult her secret heart; But, such her rigid fate, must sacrifice Each fond affection to her tyrant glory, And to the peace of others. Alc. Did not then The council make thee mistress of thy choice? Cleo. They did; and I might now abuse my power And raise thee to the throne: but canst thou think So many peers, unjustly thus excluded, Would tamely bear the wrong? Insidious plots, And open insults, with eternal discord, Would shake the realm, distract thyself and me. The weakness of my sex, thy youth, thy birth Would furnish arms for calumny: our names Through Asia, in a thousand mouths, would prove Foul matter for derision. No, Alcestes, Let envy want its food, and let our virtue Example be to others: let the world Behold and wonder at our fortitude; While pity's eye shall drop a tender tear To see the fate of two unhappy lovers, Who thus for glory break the pleasing ties Of love so just, by length of years confirm'd. Alc. Why was I, cruel Gods! a shepherd born! Cleo. Go—let us yield to fate—far, far from me Live and be happy—moderate thy sorrows, Thou shalt have little cause, my dear Alcestes, To grieve that I remain unfaithful to thee. No—from this moment I begin to die: These tears perhaps the last I shed—farewell! No longer call me perjur'd and inhuman. Alc. O Heaven!—forgive me, thou exalted fair one, [kneels. Live still, my queen, preserve thy fame unsullied: I blush to own my folly—yes, I am happy If from so dear a teacher I can learn Such constancy and virtue. Cleo. Rise, and leave me, If it indeed be true thou lov'st my virtue. Alc. Here, on this hand that must no more be mine, At least permit my trembling lips to seal One parting kiss, ere yet I go— Both. Adieu! Alc. I cannot curb the tear that falls, While on my tongue the farewell dies; Yet 'tis not grief alone that calls These trickling waters from my eyes. Repentance, wonder, hope, and love, Th' emotion, which I feel, impart: At once a thousand thoughts I prove, That crowd tumultuous to my heart. [Exit. SCENE XVI. Cleonice alone. At length ambitious views be satisfied: See me forsaken, see me now depriv'd Of all I priz'd!—what unpropitious power Implanted in mankind this thirst of honour? What to the world avails this tyrant glory, If purchas'd with such pain? If we to live For that, must die to every bliss beside? SCENE XVII. Enter Barsene and Phenicius. Bar. Is it then true, my queen, that you have gain'd So great a triumph o'er your fond affection, Even in the presence of the man you love? Phen. And is it true that Cleonice proves So barbarous to herself and to Alcestes? Cleo. 'Tis all too true. Phen. I thought such cruelty Ne'er harbour'd in your breast. Bar. I hop'd no less From constancy like yours. Phen. The inhuman deed All will detest who feel a touch of pity. Bar. Each generous mind that owns the force of virtue, Must praise the glorious action. Phen. By your rigour What have you lost? Bar. What lasting honour won? Phen. Ah! yet revoke— Bar. Still persevere— Cleo. O Heaven! Be silent; wherefore would you thus distress me? What would you more? Phen. I would, while yet 'tis time, Free you from this delusion. Bar. I would still Preserve the triumph of your constancy. Cleo. Meanwhile you kill me both, my mind alike Detests its sufferings, and detests the cure; Who seeks to aid me, hastens on my death. Though fann'd by gentle breath of air, The torch, when ready to expire, Demands a more than wonted care To keep alive its dying fire. If now your pity would bestow Some ease to my afflicted heart; Why will you add new force to woe, And but increase my secret smart? [Exit. SCENE XVIII. Phenicius, Barsene. Phen. I cannot tell, Barsene, what to think Of this excess of zeal: thy watchful care To guard her glory carries thee too far. It cannot be that maxims so severe Inspire thy gentle sex: thou dost conceal Some private interest in thy breast, beneath These specious shows of honour—Thou art silent— A blush o'erspreads thy cheek—speak—can it be? Art thou the rival then of Cleonice? Even now I saw thee on Alcestes turn Thy looks by stealth, nor did thy sighs escape me. But no, thou canst not thus ungrateful prove; Thy sovereign then with justice might reproach thee. Bar. Is it my fault, Phenicius, if I love? From love's dominion would be found Our pleasure, not our pain, If every heart, which he has bound, Could break at will its chain. But entering love's alluring state, We know not half his wiles; And when we know, 'tis then too late To struggle in the toils. [Exit. SCENE XIX. Phenicius alone. What canst thou more, Phenicius? Every thing Opposes thy designs—Protecting Gods! Ye just asserters of the rights of kings, To you my heart is known—I do not ask A sceptre for this hand; such selfish views Would ill deserve your favour—no—I seek Your heavenly succour for an injur'd prince: Yet let me not despair; for oft we find A day serene succeed a lowering morn. Sometimes beneath tempestuous skies, When round him mountain-surges rise, The trembling sailor's vessel flies, And safely gains the port at last. Beside the margin of the strand, In happier days behold him stand, And to his friends, upon the sand, Describe his toils and dangers past. [Exit. END OF THE SECOND ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. SCENE I. A gate of the palace facing the sea shore: a vessel with sailors ready for the departure of Alcestes. Olinthus alone. 'Tis so—I shall be soon without a rival: At length Alcestes must forsake these shores: But yet I tremble at his long delay; And what if Cleonice should repent! O! I would never—no—it cannot be: 'Tis but his friends, perhaps, who loth to part, With many a fond embrace protract his stay. SCENE II. Enter Alcestes and Phenicius conversing. Alc. My lord, forbear; since 'tis in vain you hope To keep me longer here. Olin. Behold, Alcestes, The vessel is prepar'd, the sailors wait, The wind is friendly, and serene the sea. Phen. Olinthus, peace—[to Olinthus.] At least but for awhile Defer thy parting hence; 'tis not for nought I ask it—stay—thou never shalt have cause To wish thou hadst not heard me—till this hour Thou know'st I've been a friend, a parent to thee. Olin. Was then my father wanting to detain him? [aside. Alc. What can I say? The queen's command forbids me To hearken to thy counsel. Olin. 'Tis most true; Alcestes speaks with reason. Phen. Canst thou leave me? Wilt thou depart, and shall Phenicius stay? I hop'd thou better would'st return my love. Alc. My dearest father: such I sure may call thee: Such hast thou been—O say not I'm ungrateful: Thou stabb'st me to the heart: I little thought To see these hapless fruits of all thy cares. Alas! I hop'd that, bred beneath thy sight, And treading in thy steps the paths of honour, I might some day have call'd into thine eyes The tender tears of pleasure not of grief. But who can change the purpose of the stars? Permit me to be gone; departing thus, I may be less ungrateful to thy love. Perchance the fellowship of the unhappy Communicates misfortune. Yet at least, Since I'm become so hateful to the Gods, Let them disturb no other days than mine; Let fortune's angry darts on me be spent, Nor one be left to pierce thy reverend age. Phen. O speak not thus, my son: thou dost not know The vast importance of a life like thine: Mine is a burden useless to myself, Unless it can avail to serve Alcestes. Alc. You weep, my lord: I merit not these tears. Alas! I should not thus prolong your sorrows— Farewell!—farewell, to both! [going. Olin. Thanks to the Gods! [aside. Alc. [returning.] To you, my friends, I recommend the care Of my afflicted queen—O she will need Your kind support in her distressful state. Who knows how dear her virtue may have cost! What anguish may have rent her tender heart, To find herself forsaken; to despair Of ever seeing her Alcestes more! To bear still present in her memory The happy moments past, each place—O Heaven! Speak comfort to her grief—my friends, farewell! [as he is going out, he meets Cleonice. SCENE III. Enter Cleonice. Cleo. Alcestes, stay. Alc. Ye powers! Olin. Another bar To his departure! [aside. Alc. Wherefore, O! my queen, Come you again to make my pains revive? Cleo. Phenicius and Olinthus, for awhile Retire apart, and leave me with Alcestes. Olin. My duty bids me with my friend remain. Cleo. Thou may'st return to take thy last farewell. Olin. I will obey—but cannot now believe Alcestes ever will depart. [aside.] [Exit. SCENE IV. Cleonice, Alcestes, Phenicius. Phen. O queen! You come in time, 'tis not in vain that Heaven Prolong'd his stay: you yet may make him happy. Reflect how cruel must you prove, From all you prize, to part; Reflect you live but in his love, He lives but in your heart. Remember still the gentle flame That made you once so blest: Remember still it burns the same Within his faithful breast. [Exit. SCENE V. Cleonice, Alcestes. Cleo. Alcestes, O! how different is the task To form resolves and to complete our purpose! Remote from thee, I deem'd the conquest easy, And love to glory seem'd to yield the prize: Yet when I find myself of thee depriv'd, My heart enfeebled loses all its firmness; And glory, O ye powers! submits to love. Alc. What would'st thou therefore tell me? Cleo. That without thee I cannot live; that since my stars forbid me, To enjoy at once Alcestes and the crown, The crown be left, and not Alcestes lost. Alc. What dost thou mean? Cleo. No longer on these shores fits us to remain: with thee I'll fly To breathe in other climes a happier air. Alc. Ha! fly with me! but where?—No, Cleonice; Had I the deeds of ancestors to trace; O! could I boast of subjects and a throne, I might perhaps be led to accept the proofs Thy generous love would give: but all the kingdom And subjects niggard fate to me affords, Are some few flocks, and a poor simple cottage. Cleo. Yet in that cottage shall I feel the peace Which in a stately palace, far from thee, My breast must never find. No guards indeed Will watch me whilst I sleep; but in return Jealous suspicions never will disturb My calm unbroken rest: though precious viands, In costly gold, deck not our homely board, Yet from the bending boughs my hand shall pluck The ripen'd fruit, where lurks no deadly juice To chill my veins with unexpected death. I'll wander o'er the hills and meads, but still Alcestes at my side: my feet shall trace The forest gloom, but still Alcestes with me: Each sun that sets shall leave me with Alcestes; And when again he rises in the east To gild the morn, shall find me still with thee. Alc. O! Cleonice most ador'd! amidst These scenes of happiness, the pleasing dreams Of one whose soul o'erflows with love's excess, I read the goodness of thy generous heart: Yet these, alas! are only vain illusions Sprung from the warmth of passion— Cleo. Vain illusions! Dost thou believe me then incapable To quit the throne? Alc. And can you think that ever Alcestes will permit it?—No, my queen, You should have then conceal'd your virtues more, And made me less enamour'd of your glory. Great souls were never form'd to live retir'd In calm inactive rest. Shall I defraud All Asia of the long-expected peace, Which, in the tumults of our troubled state, Your constancy and wisdom must bestow? Let us not, Cleonice, lose the fruit Of all our tears and anguish: thy example Taught me this pure affection—Yes, my life, Who would not suffer in so bright a cause? The story of our loves remotest times Shall learn, and with our loves our fortitude. If we're deny'd to lead our days together In mutual happiness, at least our names Shall live conjoin'd, and share one common glory. Cleo. And wherefore is not here all Asia met, That, hearing thee, they might excuse the passion Which once in Cleonice they condemn'd? But now I falter'd; thou, my dear Alcestes, Hast strengthen'd my resolves, and from thy words The virtue they excite receives more charms. Go then—but first in me behold th' effects Of fortitude like thine: yes, thou shalt see How I can imitate thy great example. Come, let us to the palace; there, Alcestes, Shalt thou be told the consort I will choose: Thou shalt be present at the royal nuptials. Alc. It must not be—you put my constancy To too severe a proof. Cleo. No—let us try To emulate each other in our sufferings. Alc. O Heaven! thou little know'st what cruel anguish The constant lover feels, who pines with envy To see another blest in the possession Of what himself must never hope to enjoy. Cleo. I see full well the deep distress Which jealous hearts endure; But since I still consult thy peace, In me confide secure. Yes, when I leave thee thou shalt know What thoughts my bosom move: And while I faithless seem, I'll show The strongest proof of love. [Exit. SCENE VI. Alcestes alone. What mean these mystic words of Cleonice? She bids me yield her to another's arms, Yet tells me that she still consults my peace. This is to bid me die ere I depart: But let her be obey'd; for her I'm ready To suffer every pang the mind can feel; Nor will I question aught that she commands. SCENE VII. Enter Olinthus. Olin. Once more thou art alone, and nothing now Remains that can oppose thy going hence; Permit Olinthus thus, in pledge of friendship, To take this last embrace. Alc. Thy noble nature With generous goodness honours my departure, But know I shall not leave thee yet. Olin. What say'st thou? Speak—wherefore? Alc. 'Tis the queen's command. Olin. Each moment Thy purpose changes. Alc. 'Tis my sovereign's will, And what she wills Alcestes must obey. Olin. What next would Cleonice? Does she purpose To elect thee for our king? Alc. To such a height My hopes aspire not. Olin. Would she have thee present At these new nuptials? O! 'twere most inhuman, Nor ought you to consent. Alc. Thou art deceiv'd: Whate'er my fate I will endure it all; And call that happiness which she bestows. Those lovely lips I still adore, Whate'er the doom they give; Whether by hope, they life restore, Or bid me cease to live. But little can the lover prove, Of beauty's sovereign sway, Who the dear object of his love Refuses to obey. [Exit. SCENE VIII. Olinthus alone. This I foresaw; 'twas but a seeming virtue Incited Cleonice to appease The people's clamours, while she for herself And her Alcestes would secure the throne. I am but little fear'd—the rigid curb Of a stern father, that restrains his son, Gives sanction to their rashness. Could I once Shake off this servile yoke, we soon should see A change of fortune; yes, Olinthus then Might o'er his rival boast a full revenge. The lion, long a prisoner held, To bear the servile bonds compell'd, Appears with native strength no more: Yet if by chance he burst his chain, His former rage awakes again, And he that durst but late assail The generous beast, with terror pale Now trembles at his roar. [Exit. SCENE IX. The apartments of Phenicius in the palace. Phenicius alone. How are my thoughts confounded! Cleonice Enjoins me to return to my apartment, And bids me here await her high command, When I, impatient, ask'd her of Alcestes, Her answer was, “Alcestes yet departs not.” What can this secret be, which thus the queen Against her custom has from me conceal'd? Alas! I fear that all my former cares Were spent in vain. SCENE X. Enter Mithranes. Mith. Be comforted, my lord, The Cretan forces now are near the port; I from the summit of the palace, view'd The billows whitening with a thousand prows. Phen. Behold, my friend, the aid we long desir'd: At last to Syria's sons we may reveal The lawful successor. Find out Alcestes; Conduct him to me. Of thy trusty friends Select whate'er thou canst—Yes, dear Mithranes, I now require the last, the greatest proof Of thy fidelity. Mith. I fly this instant To execute your will. Phen. But hear, Mithranes, Proceed with caution, and conceal the cause For which the numerous force— SCENE XI. Enter Olinthus. Olin. Great news, my father, I bring. Phen. What tidings bring'st thou? Olin. Cleonice At length has fix'd her choice. Phen. And nam'd Alcestes? Olin. If thus Alcestes hop'd, he hop'd in vain. Phen. What strange, what unexpected stroke is this? SCENE XII. Enter Alcestes with two attendants bearing the crown and royal mantle. Alc. Low at your feet, permit me— [kneels. Phen. Heavens!—Alcestes, What can this mean? Alc. Thou art our king, Phenicius. Phen. Your king!—O rise! Alc. The virtuous Cleonice By me has sent these ensigns of dominion: She waits till you, my lord, adorn'd with these, Shall meet her in the temple, there to join Your hand with hers: you cannot sure reject The glorious present which Alcestes brings: I know alike are by Phenicius priz'd The ambassador, the giver, and the gift. Phen. Does not the queen reflect how far unequal Phenicius' age to hers? Alc. The queen reflects That in another never can she find More loyal faith, and more consummate wisdom. Th' exalted fair, by choosing thus, avoids A thousand evils: she rewards your worth, Prevents the tongue of calumny, provides For Syria's welfare, and deludes in many A fond ambitious hope. Mith. And calms in part The jealous tempest which distress'd Alcestes May feel within his breast. Phen. [aside.] For this event, And this alone my soul was unprepar'd. Olin. Each is impatient to behold his king: My father, haste: content your longing friends, The eager populace, and all Seleucia Enraptur'd with the choice. Phen. Proceed, Olinthus, Before me to the temple; say that soon They shall behold their king—with me behind Remain awhile Mithranes and Alcestes. Olin. [aside.] Let not Alcestes gain the queen or throne, And I am satisfied. [Exit. SCENE XIII. Phenicius, Mithranes, Alcestes. Phen. Propitious powers! I never hop'd so much from your indulgence; Most blest event of all my cares and toils! Alcestes, thou no more must call me father; No longer by th' endearing name of son, Must thou be press'd within these aged arms: These are the last embraces I must give thee. [embraces him. Alc. What crime of mine can forfeit such a blessing? Phen. I am your subject—you are Syria's king. [kneels. Alc. O rise!—what hast thou said? Mith. Transcendent faith! Phen. At length know who you are; in you still breathes The offspring of Demetrius; you in Alcestes Survives the undoubted heir of Syria's throne. I have preserv'd you for this happy day: If you distrust my truth, believe yourself, Your princely genius, your exalted soul; Believe Phenicius who rejects for you A profferr'd crown: believe these tears of joy That trickle down my cheek. Alc. But wherefore, sir, Have you so long conceal'd my fortune from me? Phen. You shall know all, give me a moment's respite: My heart, o'ercharg'd with such a tide of pleasure, Scarce gives the vital functions leave to play. Immortal powers! from you no more My loyal faith her meed desires: My truth is crown'd, my toils are o'er, My prince no more my zeal requires. I fear not now the frowns of fate, No happier fortune wish to find; But calmly death's approach I wait, Nor death's approach can damp my mind. [Exit with attendants. SCENE XIV. Alcestes, Mithranes. Alc. Do I then dream or wake? Mith. Permit Mithranes, As the first homage of a faithful subject— [kneels. Alc. My best Mithranes, yet awhile forbear; Leave me in peace, for still my soul's in doubt. Mith. Hence be every thought distrest; Fairer prospects fill your breast: Fortune brings a happier hour, Seize the occasion in your power: 'Tis time at length to breathe from pain. Through life accustom'd still to bear The sting of grief, and pining care, Though lodg'd in port, you yet despair, And dread the perils of the main. [Exit. SCENE XV. Alcestes alone. Can it be possible? Am I Demetrius, Heir to Seleucia's crown? And have I been Even to myself till now so little known? What changes have I seen? In one short day Behold me here a monarch and a shepherd, An exile and a husband. Who, Alcestes, Can yet ensure thee that malicious fortune May not once more transform thee to a shepherd? SCENE XVI. Enter Barsene. Bar. Phenicius is our sovereign? Alc. Cleonice Has fix'd on him to fill Seleucia's throne. Bar. Alcestes, I compassionate your loss; But since your hopes to espouse the queen are vain, No longer I despair to find your heart Admit Barsene's love. Alc. Barsene's love! Bar. 'Till now respectful I conceal'd my flame: A throne and queen were rivals far too mighty For poor Barsene; but at length I see Phenicius king, and Cleonice wedded; Your hopes extinct: a more propitious hour I ne'er could choose to tell you that I love. Alc. Ill hast thou fix'd thy choice, unhappy maid! Could'st thou, Barsene, but discern What thoughts this bosom move, Thy lips might other accents learn, And never speak of love. Lament not then that in your pain I bear so little part, For while your words my feet detain, Far distant is my heart. [Exit. SCENE XVII. Barsene alone. And wherefore did I not continue silent? Alas! I hop'd at least by my confession Alcestes might have felt a kindred flame; That little hope is now for ever lost, Alcestes knows my passion, and contemns it. While the harmless turtle-dove Sees not where the danger lies, To 'scape the falcon from above, To the fowler's hand she flies. Thus I, who sought to shun the pain Of smother'd grief and love conceal'd, Must every shame and woe sustain, Which proffer'd love, refus'd, can yield. [Exit. SCENE XVIII. A stately temple dedicated to the Sun: an altar, an image of the Sun in the middle, and a throne on one side. Cleonice attended, Phenicius accompanied by two nobles, bearing the royal mantle, crown and sceptre. Phen. Believe me, I deceive you not, Alcestes Is rightful heir of Syria; and to him Belong these royal ensigns. Cleo. In his looks Methought I trac'd a soul above the vulgar, That spoke a kingly race. Phen. I know my care To cherish thus a foe was criminal: But yet the merits of so dear a foe, And my refusal to accept a crown, At once must plead excuse, and seal my pardon. Cleo. What strange events has fate this day produc'd! When I believ'd myself of peace depriv'd— Phen. Demetrius comes. [They advance to meet Alcestes. SCENE XIX. Enter Alcestes, Mithranes and Guards. Alc. And have I found at length This first, this happy time when I may see thee, Nor fear that thou wilt blush to own our passion. Of all the blessings royalty may yield, This is the greatest that Alcestes ever Can find upon the throne. Cleo. Let us, my lord, Exchange our fortune: you are now the king, And I the subject; every doubt that late Your breast divided, passes now to mine. Demetrius, go—behold the regal seat Your ancestors have press'd—even with that pleasure I once would have bestow'd it on Alcestes, I now restore it to him. May you long Possess it happier far than I have done. E'er since I knew it, barren has it prov'd Of all content to me, and only now I lose it, do I find it gives me joy. Mith. Exalted virtue! Alc. I will mount the throne, But 'tis your hand shall guide me; and this hand Reward my truth. Cleo. So grateful a command Takes from my heart the merit of obedience. [they approach the altar, and join hands. Phen. O! how excess of transport fills my soul! Alc., Cleo. Hail! powerful God! indulgent prove, And shine propitious on our love! Alc. Like me a lover have you been, And on the turfy shore, Where fam'd Thessalia's stream is seen, A shepherd's likeness wore. Cleo. My constant faith was taught by you; Whose breast unchang'd remains; And to your laurel ever true, Its ancient flame retains. Alc., Cleo. Hail! powerful God! indulgent prove, And shine propitious on our love! Phen. Heaven thunders to the left. SCENE XX. Enter Barsene. Bar. O queen! Seleucia Is all in tumult. Cleo. Wherefore? Bar. Know the envoy Is now arriv'd from Crete, and with him brings A hundred ships. Cleo. 'Tis well, he shall be heard. Bar. But rash Olinthus, whose impatient pride Can never brook Alcestes on the throne, Has join'd the ambassador, and 'midst the people Proclaims aloud Phenicius has deceiv'd them, Declares that he can prove his saying just, And that to him is known the true Demetrius. Cleo. Alas! Phenicius. Phen. Banish every fear, And with security ascend the throne: It shall be seen on which side falsehood lies. SCENE LAST. Enter Olinthus with a paper sealed in his hand, and the Cretan Ambassador, with a train of Greeks. Olin. Stay your rash steps, forbear. [to Cleonice and Alcestes, as they advance towards the throne. No longer Heaven Permits deceit to flourish. In this paper Will be reveal'd the heir of dead Demetrius: This paper written by our king Demetrius Before his death, while in the land of Crete He liv'd an exile: with the royal signet Behold it seal'd: this Cretan saw him sign it; [points to the ambassador. He brings it hither by the state's decree, And with him brings the united force of Crete, To assert the honours of the royal blood. Cleo. O heavenly powers! Phen. Olinthus, read the secret. Olin. Alcestes now must end his towering pride. [opens the paper and reads. “People of Syria, learn that 'midst you lives “My son conceal'd; a future day will come “To make him known: if by no other token “He stand discover'd, know in feign'd Alcestes “Phenicius educates his youth. Demetrius.” Cleo. My life returns. Phen. Olinthus, thy confusion Phenicius well foresaw. Olin. I am all amazement! Mith. How is his rashness damp'd! [aside. Olin. My lord, in you I own my sovereign, and repent my folly. [to Alcestes. Alc. Olinthus, I remember nothing now But that thou art the son of my Phenicius. Phen. Permit me once to view you on the throne; My vows are then complete. Alc. Whate'er I have Is but the gift of your fidelity; This from Alcestes' lips the world shall learn. Phen. And from your virtues shall the world be taught, That in one heart may love and glory reign. [Alcestes and Cleonice ascend the throne. Chorus. Love that to noble breasts extends, Is not a rival to control Fair virtue's sway; but, mutual friends, To generous deeds they raise the soul. Rest happy pair in peace secure; Henceforth may every favouring power To you that happiness ensure, Which Heaven averse denied before. END OF THE THIRD ACT.</field>
   </doc>
</add>