<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Galt, John, 1779-1839</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Galt, John, 1779-1839</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">galt john 1779 1839</field>
      <field name="author_text">Galt, John, 1779-1839</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1810's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V3.0376.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1814-1815</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460739</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Love, Honour And Interest ; A Comedy. In Three Acts</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Love, Honour And Interest ; A Comedy. In Three Acts</field>
      <field name="title_facet">love honour and interest</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">love honour and interest</field>
      <field name="title_text">Love, Honour And Interest ; A Comedy. In Three Acts</field>
      <field name="year_display">1814-1815</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1814</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1814</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460739&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460739&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Galt, John, 1779-1839&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;galt john 1779 1839&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Love, Honour And Interest ; A Comedy. In Three Acts&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;love, honour and interest&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1814-1815&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1814&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Galt, John&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1779&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1839&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Love, Honour And Interest&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Comedy. In Three Acts&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed For The Proprietors by A. J. Valpy ... Published by Henry Colbum ... G. Goldie ... and J. Cumming [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1814-1815&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3873082-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv30376&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Love, Honour And Interest&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Comedy. In Three Acts&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 107 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted&lt;lb/&gt;Preface included with The Witness; A Tragedy, In Three Acts&lt;lb/&gt;Only verse drama included&lt;lb/&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Love, honour, and interest.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Comedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1814.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Unknown.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">LOVE, HONOR, AND INTEREST; A Comedy. IN THREE ACTS.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHARACTERS. Maddervan, a Merchant in Amsterdam. Vanderclufe an Army Contractor. La Gloire, a French Officer. Gascogne, Servant to La Gloire. Beatrice, Daughter to Maddervan. Constance, Daughter to Vanderclufe. Marian, Maid to Beatrice.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Scene, in a House in Rotterdam.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. SCENE I. A Room. Gascogne, packing a trunk, and Marian. Marian. May one good morning say to you, Gascogne? Gas. Fair Marian, that from you, is ever sweet; But this good morning is, alas! good night. Marian. And must I, Gascogne, bid you then farewell? Gas. I grieve to part. O that I but might stay! Six happy months in your dear comp'ny spent Have made my heart as 'twere take root with you, And to depart is tearing it away. Marian. No one compels you surely to depart. Gas. My master does. Marian. Sure others might be found, And better payers too, in Amsterdam, Than a penurious, wounded officer. Gas. Such sentiments accord not with your beauty. For many years I have my master serv'd; His father gave me to him for my honor; Nor in the wars, where I could prove myself, Has he e'er found me failing in my duty. True he is poor, poor in the world's geer, But rich in heart, the truest wealth of man. In all his good there is a share for me; And would you counsel me to quit his service? Marian. You speak, Gascogne, like a true-hearted fellow; But wherefore makes your master all this haste? Mine, it is true, seems not displeas'd at it, But much I doubt if Miss be as content. Gas. My master, you may see, is deep in love; He pines in misery, and cannot long Conceal the flame that feeds upon his heart. Old Maddervan, who only has one daughter, Will never give her to a younger brother, A soldier too, who must live on her dower. La Gloire is poor, but of a noble soul, And consecrates the house where he has found Such free and hospitable entertainment. Rather than violate your master's friendship, He has resolv'd to sacrifice his heart— It is for this that we must go away. Marian. Such handsome heroism some may praise, But few would practise. Gas. See, my master comes. [Exit Marian. [Enter La Gloire.] La Gloire. I am the most unfortunate of men. Gas. Sir, all is pack'd. La Gloire. O! I am in despair. Gas. Alas! sir, what has chanc'd? La Gloire. The worst that could. Gas. Ah, sir, misfortunes never come alone. La Gloire. Mine is a single one, but so immense That nothing more can happen to distress.— O I have seen my Beatrice in tears. Gas. I thought, sir, that it must be something worse; That she but little car'd for our departure. La Gloire. Plebeian soul, what worse can be imagin'd Than the reproaches of a heavenly maid For wanting love, while love is mining down The strength and virtue of my own esteem? My wounds, a prisoner, my poverty, All, all, combine to drive me to despair. Loving and thus so tenderly belov'd— Oh! I must fly, or act a scoundrel's part. Gas. Consider, sir, you have not been dismiss'd, Nor by your wounds are for the journey fit. Old Maddervan will, for so good a reason, Be none surpris'd that you prolong our stay. La Gloire. You counsel well. O fain I would resolve. Gas. Then, with permission, I'll unpack the trunk. (he unpacks.) La Gloire. What must he think? for I have taken leave. If I feign sick, my grief will give it color; And yet delay will but indulge the flame, And aid th'incendiary in my bosom. Death is in going, and in staying, shame, Love and the devil! what are you about? Gas. Unpacking, sir. La Gloire. Who bade you to do that? Gas. I ask'd for leave, and you gave no denial. La Gloire. Stupid! repack. I will, yes, I will go. Gas. I have undone so much, sir, and 'tis late. La Gloire. Provoke me not, but do as you are bidden. Gas. I'll do it all again in time to-night. La Gloire. Pack instantly; the horses will be here. Gas. But the sad tears of sweet Miss Beatrice.— La Gloire. What see you there? O Heav'ns! it is herself. Gas. I'll leave the room. La Gloire. Stop, stop. O let me not Again encounter her seducing sorrow. She seems to hesitate. I will withdraw. Gas. You cannot, sir, you cannot be so rude. I will retire. La Gloire. Stay where you are. Ah me! [Exit Gascogne. [Enter Beatrice.] Hear me, Gascogne. Where does the fellow run? Beat. What do you want? If Gascogne be not near, Some other servant will obey your order. Shall I call one? La Gloire. No, thank you; I but wish'd That he would finish this unhappy packing. Beat. Are you so anxious then to go away? Do you lose time? or does the courier wait? Or is our air pernicious to your health? Perhaps this house, or something in't annoys. La Gloire. O have compassion, nor afflict me further. Beat. What has afflicted you? tell me, I pray. La Gloire. You, only you, your fatal, dangerous, self. Beat. Have I become so odious, then, to you? La Gloire. O Heavens! ever dearer still and dearer. Beat. If this were true, why should you haste away? La Gloire. Was it your beauty only that I lov'd? But more than beauty I revere your fame, That fame so truly to your father dear. O! for that fame and his esteem'd regard, My heart must sacrifice its fondest feeling. Beat. My love for you has never made me blush; It is a steady and a temperate fire; If never seen in flaming violence, It has not been the less intensely warm; 'Tis of a kind that we may safely live In easy intercourse, as we have done; But when you go, it will consume my peace. We are not children that should play the fool. My father loves me as his only child, And will not see me long remain distress'd. 'Tis true our marriage yet he won't appove, But time will aid us, stay and trust to time. La Gloire. Ah, how shall I excuse this new delay? He may suspect, if I could feign relapse, Where the wound pains that makes me linger here. Beat. We must so act as not to give him cause. La Gloire. Soldiers, he knows, are beauty's worshippers, And cannot think me proof against your worth. Beatrice. Men like my father easily believe The hearts of others open as their own. He gives you the full freedom of his house, Sure in your honor of a safe protector, Nor is he without confidence in me. La Gloire. You think in time then that he will consent? Beat. Yes; but his prejudices must be won. Were you a merchant, though of humble fortune And meaner manners, but of steady dealing, You might have had me long before this time, And many thousand florins to the bargain. But you're a Frenchman, and an officer, Two staple faults in the commodity, And what to one that loves his child as he does Is more against our wishes than them both, You are the scion of an ancient stock, Beneath whose shade his plant may pine obscur'd. La Gloire. But how shall we convert him to our wish? Beat. Love kept by patience should be fed by hope. The English, tir'd of profitless renown, Have call'd the Duke of Marlborough from the war, And many-tongued rumor speaks of peace. Peace will subtract from French and soldiership; My father's heart is warmer than his head, And we must only not excite suspicion. La Gloire. But how? Beat. Find you some other sweetheart. La Gloire. I understand you not. Beat. I will explain. Constance comes often to our house of late, And mourns your wounds too tenderly at times; My father must be led into that track— But hark, his tread—Haste!—for the present leave me. [Exit La Gloire. I never thought to have been brought to this, To make solicitation for his stay: But here my father comes—Would he had not Found me at this time here. [Enter Maddervan.] Mad. How, daughter, how? What do you, Beatrice, here in this room? Beat. To see the master help the servants packing. Mad. Do you know when he means to go away? Beat. He did intend this morning; but his wound Pains him so much, that he begins to fear Himself as yet unable for the journey. Mad. Which wound is it? Beat. He had but one you know. Mad. He has another than the doctor knows. Beat. Indeed? Mad. Ay, one that doctors cannot cure. Beat. You speak in parable—pray, sir, what mean you? Mad. Beatrice, you are both wise and clever, And know full well what I suspect and say; Go to, go to— Beat. (aside) His manner frightens me. Mad. Your color mends, I think. Perfidious baggage. Beat. Sir, you say things that truly make me blush. I do begin to comprehend your meaning; But what is the mysterious wound to me? Mad. Come, daughter, daughter, let us freely speak: Monsieur was getting hearty, well, and ruddy; He was the cheering spirit of my table; But soon by little he began to droop, Grew dull, fell languid, and his pensive talk Was full of sighs and other doleful pauses, Like th'ahs and ohs and points of admiration, In a Parisian sentimental tale. I am in some things a philosopher; And by my skill, I think Monsieur in love. Beat. It may be so; but if his love were here, He would not be in such a haste to leave us. Mad. Yes, even in that philosophy instructs; For if his love be rich, an only daughter, Dependant on her father, and that father Not like to give her to so poor a fellow— Monsieur's a man of such a gallant spirit, That he would rather his own passion stifle Than seek to marry by dishonest means: And philosophically too, I think, That Monsieur's sweetheart is just you, my daughter. Beat. O dear, excuse me, sir, I must—must laugh. Am I too dull and languid, pale and sighing? Mad. I have two thoughts: and you, I think, have either Wit to resist, or cunning to conceal. Beat. Am I alone of all the captain knows, The only one that suits the proving tests Of your divining and philosophy? Mad. He went but little out, and knows but few, Therefore I think his love is in this house. Beat. But we have handsome neighbours— Mad. Very true. Are you a party then? Beat. If I should be, It were not fit that you should seek to know. Mad. A duteous daughter should obey her father, And keep no secrets that he asks to learn. Beat. Then—but you must not tell—I hope you will not: Monsieur, poor soul, is pining at the heart, Alas! Mad. For whom? Beat. For Constance Vanderclufe. Mad. For Constance Vanderclufe! Beat. Alack, poor swain! Mad. And how is Constance? loves she in return? Beat. O yes, sir, with such fond and tender softness!— Out on the golden rubbish of the world, That two such gentle gravitating hearts Should be so held, in spite of Heaven's kind impulse, From the blest junction that their nature claims. Mad. But what is the impediment?—poor souls! Beat. Her father, sir, is rich! O monstrous rich! And gallant Monsieur—ah, sir, he is poor: And a rich father never will bestow His only child, you know, on one so poor. Mad. Fine pride forsooth. Who is this Vanderclufe That he should stand upon such etiquette? What is he else but a foul-fed contractor? He must, indeed, advance his rounded paunch Among our merchants, like a sleeky snail That climbs into a hive. To such as he, The marriage of an officer is honor; Nor can he spend his easy-gather'd gain To better purpose, than to make this match. Beat. Were you like him, you would not then refuse? Mad. No, certainly. Beat. But as a wealthy merchant, The case is different? Mad. And is it not? I would have you to know the difference. Beat. I thought so, sir. Mad. I will exert myself— Beat. Sir, to what end? Mad. To gain old Vanderclufe. But where is Monsieur? Beat. In the room below. Mad. Haste, send him to me; he's an honest fellow, I like him much—he shall not want a friend. Beat. (aside) O I am in a labyrinth bewilder'd! [Exit. Mad. Rank with the one, and riches with the other, Should make a merry and a happy union. [Enter Marian.] Mar. I thought my mistress had been with you, sir. Mad. No, she is gone.—But where in such a hurry? Marian. To seek her, sir. Mad. Then you have news to tell? Marian. Yes, sir, Miss Constance Vanderclufe has call'd. Mad. Oho. Marian. And coming, sir, at such an hour, She must have something very strange to tell. Mad. Yes, yes, she has; ay, ay, 'tis plain enough: Go, send Miss Constance instantly to me. [Exit Marian. I'll do my best: it is a virtuous work, And every gen'rous heart will give me praise. [Enter Constance.] Cons. Sir, I attend you— Mad. Ha, Miss Constance, ha, Do you know, Miss, that I rejoice to find You and my daughter friends and confidents. Cons. I love her, sir, indeed, with all my heart. Mad. No fibs, Miss Constance; not with all your heart. Cons. How! think you, sir, I do not truly love her? Mad. Truly, no doubt, but not with all your heart. Cons. Why this distinction, sir? Mad. If you lov'd her With all your heart, you could not love another. Cons. Dear me, sir, what is it you would be at? Mad. Ah, cunning baggage—but I'll to the point. Cons. La, sir, what point? Mad. Go to; come here—Pshaw! Hark ye: Put bashfulness aside— Cons. Good Heavens! what mean you? Mad. Speak to me frankly: Do you seek my daughter? Cons. Yes, sir. Mad. No, no, 'tis not for her you come. Learn, Miss, that I am an astrologer; I have a spirit that obeys my call— An airy spirit, that with subtile skill Can pick the secrets from young ladies' bosoms And bring them to me folded in a sigh. Know my familiar, Miss, has been with you, And found the reason of this early visit: Not for the merry maid that stays behind, But the poor youth that languishes and flies. Cons. (aside) Surely some wicked imp has blabb'd the truth. Mad. Is it not so?—deny, deny—aha! I see the flame of pretty Cupid's torch Warming your cheek and glancing in your eye. Cons. If I perform, sir, what politeness claims, Sure I deserve not to be so reproach'd. Mad. Reproach'd! no, Miss, applauded to the skies! Cons. Methinks, sir, you have cause for mirth to-day. Mad. And you for sadness—But cheer up, sweetheart, I'll make you happy in despite of fate. Cons. Indeed! Mad. In truth. Cons. With what? Mad. Two little words. Cons. They must be words of magic potency. Mad. Monsieur stays! Cons. Stays! Mad. What say you to my spirit? Cons. You think me then in love? Mad. Dare you say no? Cons. I do deny it. Mad. Swear. Cons. For such a trifle! Mad. No, no, the truth is plain enough to me; I'll do you good, and comfort your poor swain. Cons. How! my poor swain! Mad. I have found out his love; And the proud motive that makes him depart. Your father in the arrogance of wealth, Will not give his consent—O I know all. Cons. Much more than I do, or than I have heard. Mad. Tell me the truth now; do you love Monsieur? Cons. I will not longer, sir, refuse confession. Mad. Then thank your stars that he loves in return. Cons. This, sir, I do not know. Mad. I know he does, I tell you, to distraction. Cons. Possibly. But I have seen no verifying signs. Mad. I am employed to influence your father. Cons. My father knows that I esteem La Gloire. Mad. But he must know it more assuredly. Cons. Nor has he, sir, once said a word to me. Mad. O, to be sure he should debate with you.— But here comes Monsieur. Cons. Give me leave to go. Mad. Stay where you are. Cons. I pray you, give me leave. [Exit. [Enter La Gloire.] La Gloire. I come, obedient to your summons, sir. Mad. Pray, have you seen my daughter?—What a sigh! You look as wan and drooping as a lily, Depicted in a hopeless lover's ditty. I'm sorry, friend, to see you so dejected. La Gloire. Alas! sir, wanting health, who can be gay? It is the sweet that tempers fortune's sour, And cheers the contrarieties of life. Mad. And oft the dimpled cheek of buxom health Is Cupid's target. Captain, pardon me, I am a doctor, somewhat skill'd in wounds, And yours, though deep and sore, I'll try to cure. La Gloire. My wound, dear sir, is not my only ail. Mad. I know it well; my daughter has inform'd me. La Gloire. What! has she had the courage to disclose? I pray you, sir, then pity my distress. Mad. I do, I do. La Gloire. I cannot, Sir, remain. Already as the infant Hercules Seiz'd the two serpents in his vigorous grasp; The baby Cupid, cradled in my bosom, Holds truth and honor struggling with their death. Mad. But wherefore should they die?—we must relieve them. Sir, the girl loves you, she herself has told me; And your high blood and nobler qualities Are worth a better price than all her dower, Though with her father they may lightly weigh. La Gloire. Her father! Heav'ns, Sir! Who is her father? Mad. What, don't you know him then? La Gloire. Ah me, who is he? Mad. Old frosty-faced, gruff-speaking, Vanderclufe, The beef-contractor, who thrives by the war; A purse-proud fellow of gross appetites, Who, fed and fatten'd by the laborer's sweat, Stalks with the state of old nobility. La Gloire. O I am lost, bereft of every hope! Mad. This Vanderclufe comes seldom to my house, Therefore I wonder not at your surprise— But come, take heart, I'll try what can be done: I am your friend, and as a friend command me. [Exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. SCENE I. A Room. Constance. I cannot think La Gloire feels love for me; He is, 'tis true, still gentle and polite, Attentive to each little want or need, But never shows the common signs of love: The soft solicitation of the eyes; The wish to whisper and be ever near; The languishing prolongment of adieu When we have parted—never have I seen.— But here he comes, and with him Beatrice. [Enter Beatrice and La Gloire.] Beat. Forgive me, Constance, for detaining you. Cons. Make no apologies, my friend; believe me, I always find your company so pleasant, That I at any time wait willingly, And feel myself rewarded when you come. Beat. There, captain, hear you that?—Batavian maids, 'Spite of their dull and foggy atmosphere, You see, have spirits bright and generous. La Gloire. That I have felt and known, and must remember. Cons. I do her but the justice that she merits. Beat. But let us not dispute of our own merits; Monsieur shall judge. La Gloire. Nay, you must find a better. Beat. I know not where we should a better find. Cons. He must perforce decide for the appellant. Beat. In Paris, strangers always are preferr'd. La Gloire. The Dutch, in that respect, are not less civil. Beat. Ah! Constance, Constance, you have won the day. But where so soon? Cons. 'Tis almost dinner-time, And my aunt Hidelberg expects my coming. Beat. 'Tis yet too early; stay with us awhile. La Gloire. Softly, dear Beatrice, do let her go. Cons. What does he say? Beat. Dear Constance, be not jealous; He only whispers me to bid you stay. Cons. I know not what to think!— La Gloire. O let her go. Beat. Do, Constance, stay—Sir, I take pains to please you. La Gloire. In truth, in truth, I must be so consol'd. Beat. Hear, Constance, hear; he says he is consol'd. Cons. Dear Beatrice, I know your friendship for me, And here, before you, I may freely speak: Your father tells me news so very strange, That without confirmation from La Gloire, I dare not credit them. Beat. Now this is frank. I love you dearer, Constance, for this frankness— I know what you would say. La Gloire. O Beatrice! What new perplexity is this you weave? Cons. A few short words will be enough for me. Beat. But, Constance, have you time to hear him now? Your aunt, I'm sure, must wonder at your stay!— O tell her, captain, do, pray tell her all. La Gloire. Would that I might, but I have not the heart. Beat. You see, my friend, how much he is distress'd— Alas! he has a thousand things to say. Cons. One little sentence is all I desire. But one short word, if it be true he loves me? Beat. Merciful me! art thou beside thyself, To ask a question so unmaidenly? I'm sure La Gloire, at least, has more discretion. But lovers never wish for witnesses, And I should leave you. La Gloire. Stay, in mercy stay! [Enter Maddervan.] Mad. Aha, aha! a pleasant party this. But why afoot; do, pray be seated, do. Beat. Constance must go. Mad. Must she?—Why must she go? Beat. Her aunt expects her. Mad. Constance, sit you down, We may have need of you, and aunts can wait: Your father will be here; I've sent for him. He will no doubt look both with mouth and eyes; But never mind—we want but his consent, Which if he grant, 'tis fit you be at hand, We'll call you in and finish the affair. La Gloire. O Heavens! O Heavens! Mad. How she is agitated! Beat. She is indeed, and with excess of joy. Mad. Leave all to me; stay here and dine with us. Beat. She cannot, sir, to-day. Mad. Can't she?—how's that? Beat. Because—because her aunt expects her, sir. Mad. Poh! nonsense, nonsense!—What! a fusty aunt,— A parsimonious, prim, inquisitive,— Spare in her feasts, and plenteous in her talk, Not leave her for a fond and youthful lover!— You shall not go. Cons. I will, sir, soon return. La Gloire. How shall I extricate myself from this? Beat. Fye, fye, La Gloire! A man bred in the wars, One who has walk'd the utmost edge of danger, And in the very whirl of life and death, Accustom'd still to bear a mind prepar'd, And yet in such a crisis, here to stand Stunn'd and amaz'd!—fye, fye, attend your duty. La Gloire. What do you mean? Beat. See Constance to the door. [Exit Const. Mad. Daughter, daughter, I say, Beatrice, Why do you meddle with them in this way? He cannot speak to her while you are bye. Beat. He has, I do assure you, said enough. Mad. Has he? What said he?—Did you hear it all? Beat. Softly and low they spoke as lovers woo. Mad. Go, Monsieur, go, and say what you would say. La Gloire. O that I might! [Exit and soon returns. Mad. Daughter, daughter, I say. This conduct, Miss, I do not much approve. Beat. La, sir, allow me but a little sport; Lovers' perplexities are lawful game. How pleasant 'tis to see La Gloire's despair— Was it not I that first their flame discover'd? And if all end as well as I desire, I'm sure the captain will forgive my pranks. Mad. O woman, woman, every day we see Men learn from you; but you the serpent taught. Ah, Beatrice, your time will soon come round; The first good match that I can find, prepare: What say you, Monsieur, to't? La Gloire. All right, all right. Beat. What business, sir, have you to say all right? Mad. Do you expect I will not choose your husband? Beat. Choose if you will, but find one to my taste. Mad. Your fortune may ensure the very best. Beat. Sir, Constance' father, may expect the same. Mad. Think you, my daughter, but like Vanderclufe's. Beat. But, sir,— Mad. Go to, go to, I'll hear no more. [Exit Maddervan. La Gloire. Well, Beatrice, what think you of your scheme? Beat. Who could have thought that he would have done so— La Gloire. There is no remedy; I must depart. Beat. This time I will not interfere. La Gloire. O Heavens! And must I marry Constance? Beat. If you can. La Gloire. What shall I do—must I disclose the plot? Beat. And make me pastime for the scand'lous world! All I can say—to go—no certainly— Marry Constance!—Surely, never, never. Divulge our plan—that would indeed crown all. I can no more—But as you are a lover, Find means to rescue— La Gloire. I am in despair! [Exeunt. SCENE II. Enter Maddervan. Mad. I think old Vanderclufe will surely come. He is obliged to me; I lent him once Ten thousand ducats to preserve his credit: But now he's rich, he needs my aid no more; And favors granted to such minds as his, Fade like a name traced idly with a stick, Upon the ebbed sea's unstable sand. [Enter Marian.] Marian. If not intrusive, I would speak with you. Mad. Well, what would ye? Marian. A small affair of mine. Sir, with your leave and pleasure, I would marry. Mad. Do, when you will, and much good may it do you. Marian. I thank you, sir; but may I venture, sir— Ten years and more I have been in your house, I hope my service merits some reward. Mad. It does, it does. But have you found a man? Marian. Yes, sir. Mad. Aha! and who is he?—I guess 'Tis Monsieur's servant, is it not? Marian. It is. I could not live so long nor know his worth: He is a good, true-hearted, kind, young man. Mad. And you would go the world over with him? Marian. I could,—but, sir, I hope we shall stay here. Mad. Yes, if his master too were fixed, you might. Marian. No one knows better than yourself of that: If you are satisfied, the thing is done. Mad. But there are other bars—I hope removable. Marian. Upon the lady's part, I'm sure there's none. Mad. No, no, poor wench, she's past all cure I think. Marian. I think so too. Mad. But when would you be married? Marian. Sir, if you please, the same day with my mistress. Mad. How!— Marian. Sir, with Miss Beatrice. Mad. Softly, softly; If so, there's time enough—you yet must wait— Speak of the marriage ere the match be made! Marian. And dont you know? Mad. Know! what?—O I know nothing. Marian. Did not you tell me, sir, that you knew all? Is not the captain— Mad. Poh! you're all awry: Think you that I would give my only child, With such a dow'r as I may give with her, To one who has not wherewithal to live! Marian. You told me, sir, his marriage would content you. Mad. Well, well, what then?—I say again it will. Marian. And who shall be his wife, if not your daughter? Mad. Is there no other girl in Amsterdam? Marian. He never goes to any other house. Mad. Comes no one here—not Constance Vanderclufe? Marian. Am I mistaken, or are you deceived? Mad. What confidence has Beatrice in you? Marian. She speaks of Monsieur always soft and kindly. Mad. And so you thought her kindness came from love. Marian. I did—I do— Mad. You're wrong. Marian. I also know That he had in despair resolved to leave her, Fearing her father never would consent. Mad. Good, good! Marian. And are not you her father? Mad. Am I the only father in the town?— Was Constance Vanderclufe bred in an egg, And like a chicken only knows her nurse?— Away, you minx! respect your mistress more. Marian. Sir, I could stake my head that you are wrong. Mad. Hence, impudence, away! go, get you gone. [Exit Marian. I will discharge this gipsy—saucy slut, To think so meanly of her mistress. Ha!— [Enter Vanderclufe.] Van. Your servant, sir— Mad. Welcome, my worthy friend. Here, sit you down— Van. My time will not permit. Mad. Nay, do sit down; you have a deal to do— 'Tis long, methinks, since I have seen you, sir, But you thrive well, I hear. 'Tis seven years Since we have dealt, and then, like many others, You had your own adoes against the world. Van. Well—May I ask, sir, what you want with me? Mad. You have a daughter,— Van. Sir! Mad. A worthy daughter, As good as fair, and modest as she's fair, Mild as she's modest, and as kind as mild:— Do you not wish to see her fix'd in life? Van. No, sir, not yet. Mad. May I inquire your reason? Van. I cannot yet afford to spare her dower. Mad. (aside) A bad beginning. But, sir, if she love, And to her choice you can make no objection, It is, I think, your duty to consent. Van. It may be so; but with one of two things, Without a dowery, if she please herself, And with a rich one if she pleases me. Mad. I have, sir, something to propose to you. Van. You will oblige me now by being brief. Mad. You know La Gloire, the officer, my guest? Van. Do you propose him for my daughter, sir? Mad. And, sir, why not? Van. A soldier and a Frenchman! Nor with nor without dower!— Mad. Why such aversion? Van. To country and profession I object: I loathe the French—they are our enemies: Tygers in war, and worse than apes in peace— A fickle race, as changeable in heart, As lax in principles—made to be slaves Alike to vices and to tyranny. I have paid dear for learning what they are; And never, while I can, shall they from me Have aught but hate and heartfelt detestation. Mad. But he of whom I speak is good and noble. Van. Is he rich too? Mad. He is a younger son. Van. Sir, if not rich, what boots nobility? Mad. Friend, not so fast; let us be calm, consider That no one hears us, therefore give me leave: A man like you, excuse my freedom, sir, Blest with the means, could not bestow amiss Part of his wealth for good relationship. Van. I would not give a stiver for such geer. Mad. Then pray for whom do you intend your daughter? Van. The sum that I can give her should procure As good a match as any in the land. Mad. I doubt, I doubt, such matches will not have her. Van. No!—why not, sir? Mad. Because they will not take her. Van. Why, sir, should they object to take my money? Mad. They will not take your daughter— Van. You grow warm. Mad. I do, that you should scorn so good a match. Van. Why don't you give the officer your own? Mad. Because I won't. Van. That is my very reason. Mad. There is some difference, sir, I think, between us. Van. In what does it consist? Mad. All know your rise. Van. Well, and what then?—Who knows your end? Mad. You grow impertinent. Van. You are at home. Mad. Sir, you may know and feel to whom you speak. Van. I fear you not. Mad. Go to the devil, sir! [Exeunt. SCENE III. A Room. Maddervan and La Gloire. Mad. Ass! scoundrel! savage! brute! to use me so! If it were not—gods! I could knock him down! La Gloire. Sir— Mad. Beast! La Gloire. Sir! Mad. Dog! cur! toad! La Gloire. Speak to me! Mad. I beg your pardon, captain, but that—that— La Gloire. May I inquire with whom you are offended? Mad. With whom but Vanderclufe, the mud-worm, Vanderclufe! La Gloire. How, sir! and will he not consent?—Alas! Mad. Poor soul, my heart is very sore to see him! Come, Monsieur, come, pluck up a soldier's heart. La Gloire. Tell me at once the truth, has he refused? Mad. Ah, Monsieur, Monsieur—but we mortal men Should ever be prepared for evil chance. La Gloire. Sir, by your leave,— Mad. Stop! fly not to despair. La Gloire. Have you not said enough? Mad. Dont be cast down— Poor Monsieur—Come, lad, cheer thyself, there's hope: He is an old conceited, purse-proud dog; But there are ways to be revenged on him. La Gloire. Would you have me deceive her father, sir? Mad. What will you do? La Gloire. Return at once to France. Mad. And can you leave her, and for ever too? La Gloire. Ah, my good sir, you know not what you say. Mad. My word is given to promote your suit— But you surprise me, that so bold a man Should lack of enterprise at such a time. La Gloire. Sir, if you knew, you would not urge me so. Mad. I do know this, that you'll not be the first Who won a wife against her father's will. La Gloire. May I, sir, marry without his consent? Mad. This is the case—Let us consider well— Here are his riches,—there your noble birth— His wealth assists you, and your blood confers Honor and quality on all his race. La Gloire. But how, sir, can I ever look for pardon? Mad. When it is done, and there's no help,— His anger, doubtless, will awhile burn fiercely; But when a few short days are past and gone, His back and bristle will again be smooth, And he must do as better men have done, Receive you home, promote you as his son, And joke at lovers' tricks. La Gloire. May I hope this? Mad. Yes, if you have the spirit to attempt. La Gloire. I want not spirit. Mad. Soft! I understand. La Gloire. O Heavens! what will he next? Mad. Here, here, make haste, There's money for a jaunt—no thanks, no thanks. Find Constance, fly; away, away to France. No words, but fly—Write me when all is done— Courage, my boy! La Gloire. Fate is in this. Mad. Away! [Exit La Gloire. I have done wrong, but that curs'd Vanderclufe— I have myself an only darling child— How should I feel had he done so to me?— But poor young Monsieur is a worthy soul, Deserves assistance, and is nobly born— And Vanderclufe is blind to his own good— But Constance comes. [Enter Constance.] Away! what do you here? Cons. Did you not, sir, invite me back? Mad. Aye, aye. But where is Monsieur? Cons. How! is he not here? Mad. He seeks for you—he's running to your aunt's— Away, away. Cons. Do you discard me, sir? Mad. No, no, no, no; but quickly, quickly run. Cons. For goodness, sir, tell me what means this haste? Mad. Go to your aunt's, see Monsieur, he will tell— Cons. Has something chanc'd anew? Mad. Yes, yes, make haste. Cons. What is it? tell me. Mad. To your aunt's, I say. Cons. My father has been here? Mad. He has, he has. Cons. Have you ask'd his consent? Mad. I have. Cons. For marriage? Mad. Yes, yes, for marriage. Fly! Cons. And with La Gloire? Mad. And with La Gloire. Cons. May I believe you, sir? Mad. Go to your aunt's, I say; make haste, away. Cons. For love and charity do tell me why. Mad. Time flies, time flies, away, away, away! [Exit Constance. [Enter Beatrice.] Beat. Can it be true, sir, what La Gloire has told me? Mad. What has he told? Beat. That you advise elopement. Mad. Eh! has he had this confidence in you? Beat. He has. And that you too have lent him money. Mad. He is a fool, and I repent my warmth. Beat. Your silence, sir, confirms what he has said. Mad. What is't to you? Beat. I only wish'd to know. Your humble servant, sir. Mad. Where now? where now? Beat. To Monsieur's wedding, and with joyous heart. Mad. The ceremony can't be yet perform'd. Beat. It will be soon. Mad. I charge you, Beatrice, As you have life, speak not a word of this. Beat. O trust me, sir, but it will soon be known, And you shall then have all the merit, sir. Mad. Thou art, I see, a blithe, good-hearted knave; Thy father's child, a chip of the old block. [Exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. SCENE I. A Room. Maddervan and Marian. Marian. Excuse me, sir, if I again intrude. Mad. Well, what new nonsense have you got to talk? Marian. You cannot say that I am now mistaken. Mad. If 'tis not what you have already said. Marian. I would speak only, sir, of what concerns My own affair; and, as a faithful servant, Humbly expect that when my marriage happens, You will not think me undeserving favor. Mad. You wait not for your mistress' marriage then? Marian. No, sir, but— Mad. What? Marian. If it take place to-day, Mine, with your leave, may be perform'd to-morrow. Mad. Is this not nonsense? Marian. Sir, I still must think— Mad. In verity you have great need to think. Marian. Do you still say my mistress is not— Mad. Stuff. Go get you gone, and hatch some other fancies. Marian. You soon shall see, sir, who is the deceiv'd. Did I not hear the Captain speak with Miss? Hear them resolve to marry out of hand? And saw not I, with these my looking eyes, The purse of gold you gave, part of her dower? Mad. Part of her dower! Marian. I saw the purse, I did. Mad. Go to, go to, thou art beside thyself. Marian. Are these hands mine that I do look upon? Mad. They are indeed a pair of ugly paws. Marian. Then as I see these hands, I saw the purse. Mad. (aside) Monsieur was wrong to risk discovery thus. Marian. You slur my honesty, by not believing. Mad. Go, hear the truth, and understanding ill, Come brim-full back to me, and tattle nonsense. Marian. I know, sir, what I know, and that is truth. Mad. Go, get you gone; speak not so pertly, minx, Or I may make you sing your oldest song. Mar. Allow me, sir, to ask one simple question. Mad. Now you are rational, you act discreetly; To ask is to obtain, and wisdom comes By sober questioning. Marian. Where is my mistress? Mad. Where should she be? Marian. Is she not with the captain Gone to her aunt's—to your own sister gone? Mad. Ha! who comes here?—all's well enough, but Monsieur Has not been prudent, that he must allow— My sister lives not far from Constance' aunt, And Beatrice is doubtless waiting there. [Enter Gascogne.] Gas. Your servant, sir. Mad. Good morning, friend, what news? Gas. My master sends his compliments, and says That this will tell you all. (Gives a letter.) Mad. Let's see, let's see— How does he?—where is he?—How goes it, friend?— Ha, here's another letter—from my daughter: But let me see first what poor Monsieur says: “Sir, your advice gave me the heart to do—” There he says right; 'twas I that gave him heart. “What all the force of love had never done. “I have conducted, as you bade, the daughter,—” He has met Constance in the street, ay, ay! “And here we are. The aunt, moved by her tears, “At last consented, and our hands were join'd.” As good as could be—All my doing this “I can add nothing but implore your kindness.” What would he farther, he is married now, And wants no help of me.—Now Beatrice: “Dear father,”—What a pretty hand she writes! A clever girl—thank Heav'n!—but let me see: “I ask permission to fall at your feet,— “Implore your pardon. It was only the advice “You gave yourself that”—Slut! Slut! traitors! traitors! Marian. Sir, what has chanced— Mad. Help! help! support me, friends! Marian. Heavens! what is this? Mad. Undone, undone, undone! Friends, quit me not! Marian. Who was mistaken, sir? Mad. Hold out your fingers at me, laugh and sneer, Spit in my face, and call me old curmugeon!— Hiss at me, call the rabble in to shout!— I merit all—I give you liberty. Marian. No, sir, no, no, we pity your distress. Mad. I won't be pitied; I do not deserve it. Gas. My master, sir, is worthy of his choice. Mad. He has undone my daughter, ruin'd me! Marian. Sir, you may soon put all to rights again. Gas. Appease yourself with what you would have said To Vanderclufe. Mad. Do you upbraid me, scoundrel? Marian. Sir, he speaks well—you merit his upbraiding. Mad. And you too, gipsy—but ye serve me right. Marian. Indeed, indeed, we pity you sincerely. Gas. You prove the punishment of bad advice. Mad. But they deceiv'd me, told me lies, all lies. Marian. Love, sir, is cunning, and will find the way To filch the happiness it is denied. Mad. Had Vanderclufe consented to my wish, O what a thing should I have been to look at? Gas. Were you employ'd to ask for his consent? Mad. They knew of all I did, and stopp'd me not. Gas. Say rather, sir, you understood amiss. Mad. They have betray'd me—they have cheated me— My daughter is a good-for-nothing toad, And Monsieur is— Gas. Be cautious what you say; Soldiers have swords, and know, sir, how to use them. Mad. A proper finish it will be to kill me. Gas. No, sir, my master will do no such things. He'll ask your pardon, sir, I'm sure he will. Mad. I will not see him. Gas. He will bring his lady. Mad. Lady! what lady?—Beatrice my daughter— Oh Beatrice! and have I now no daughter!— Perfidious girl! she was my pride and joy. Gas. There is no remedy. Mad. Peace, peace, I know't. Gas. If you grow angry, sir, I must depart. Marian. Oh, pity him, Gascogne—My poor dear master! I hop'd my mistress would have liv'd with him, Spent all her days in comforting his age, And breeding little babes for him to dandle. But dear, good soul, now he must mope alone. Mad. I'm lost to happiness, to hope, and all. Gas. How! think you, sir, my master can't provide His wife with little ones for you to dandle? Marian. Would they but stay, before a year goes round, O what a pretty grandson you might see! Mad. I hate the father, and would hate the child. Marian. But blood is blood, sir, your own flesh and blood. Mad. My heart is breaking! Marian. Gascogne, now's the time. Mad. What do you whisper— Marian. I discard Gascogne— Yes, he may go with his ungrateful master. Mad. Go where? Marian. To France. Mad. To France!—my Beatrice!— Gas. Sir, fare you well. Mad. Ah me! when will they go? Gas. They told me if I brought no happy answer, To order horses; and I must obey. Mad. And will they go so soon? Marian. Alack, alack!— Sad news, sad news for such a good, kind father— Never to see his lovely, lovely daughter!— Mad. Is not your master, sir, a savage born?— A wolf—a wolf that robs me of my lamb. Gas. No, sir, he'll bring her here if you permit. Mad. How! what! does he expect my thanks for this? Does he expect reward for his deceit?— Go, tell him from me—tell him he's a wolf! Gas. I understand you, sir; I take my leave. Mad. And tell my daughter that I hate her name: I will not see them, I will shut my eyes— But stop, no:—go—yes, I will shut my eyes. [Exit Gascogne. Ah, Marian, how well I merit all! Marian. Suppose, for pastime, just to keep you calm, We talk a little more of my affair. Mad. What! speak of marriage! I detest the word; I'll ever listen to it while I live. Marian. Alas! the world must then be near its end. Mad. To me it is. Marian. And who shall be your heir? Mad. The devil! Marian. What! not your own darling daughter!— Your sweet, sweet daughter—your own looking child— The very mind and picture of yourself— Must she, O must she live in poverty? Mad. Ah poor unfortunate—My Beatrice! Marian. O will you die and not be reconciled? [Enter Constance.] Cons. This is a pretty trick, I needs must say. Mad. I wanted only this—O I shall sink. Cons. Did you not send me to my aunt's, and say That I should find the captain waiting there?— I waited till my very heart grew sick.— Marian. Let me explain, and I will tell you all: He told the captain to go to the aunt's; And to the aunt's the gallant captain went To meet his love, and his true-love he met; And they are married—What a shocking thing! The bride's not Constance call'd, but Beatrice! Cons. How! is this true? Have I been so deceived— Speak, sir, and tell me if she tells the truth? Mad. If I endure it, surely you may. Cons. Sir! Mad. For you, for you, O I have lost my daughter! Cons. What! how! for me? Mad. Yes, yes, for you, for you, I plann'd the fabric that has crush'd myself. Cons. I understand you not; what is't you mean? Mad. Be calm, Miss Constance, I will tell you all.— Who have we here?—Would I were in my grave Close covered up and underneath a stone! [Enter Vanderclufe.] Van. What do you here? Home, instantly home, home! Cons. You never, sir, forbade my visits here. Van. But I do now—I know for what you come. Mad. Sir, you know nothing: O if you but knew What I have met with, you would chide her not. Van. I know but only what you said yourself; Enough 'tis surely to make me resolve That she shall cease to visit at your house. Marian. Think you that she may marry without leave? Van. Perhaps I do. Marian. Unless my master there Take her himself, she'll find no husband here. Van. Where is the Frenchman? Mad. Ah, he knows not yet! Marian. Why, sir, the captain has my mistress married. Van. Eh! Mad. Oh! Van. How now!—married—married, did you say? Cons. Revenge the wrong and insult done to me. They flatter'd, lied, deceived; indeed they did. Van. O yes, your wrong and insult shall be punish'd As close as four stone walls can keep you in. And my good neighbour, for his hasty speech, Shall do me justice with his shame and blushes. Mad. I know, I feel, how much I did you wrong. Alas! my dear friend, I have lost my child! Van. Lost! if but married, sir, she is not lost. Mad. I doubt, I doubt, I ne'er shall see her more. Who knows but she is on the road to France! [Enter Beatrice, La Gloire, &amp;c. &amp;c.] Beat. O my dear father,— Mad. You deceitful baggage! Beat. Forgive, forgive, in charity forgive me. Mad. You merit nothing, cunning, cheating baggage! Beat. I must confess your anger justly rous'd. Cons. Were I her father I would not forgive her. Mad. Rise, Beatrice. Beat. O not without your pardon. Mad. Daughter, daughter, you have been my death. Beat. Alas! you know it was your own advice. Mad. Hush, hush! for mercy's sake, speak not of that! Be silence the condition of forgiveness. Beat. But, my dear father, without farther grace,— Mad. Monsieur! not Monsieur, mention not his name. Beat. Forgive him too, or we have met to part. Mad. Perfidious hussy! can you tell me so! Beat. My hand is his, and he may lead me hence. Van. The deed is done, and cannot be undone— Come, come, forget, forgive, be friends again, And make all up before the story spreads. Beat. Here, husband, kneel, entreat my father's blessing. Here, father, here is Monsieur, take his hand— Be quick, be quick, and nothing shall be known. Mad. Well then, God bless thee, son—Alack! my son. Cons. I cannot bear to look at that French knave. Beat. Thanks, thanks, dear father, blessings crown your goodness. THE END.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">REMARKS ON LOVE, HONOR, AND INTEREST. In a former number we presented our readers, in The Word of Honor, with a free translation into blank verse of one of the best comedies of Goldoni. In that sprightly drama, the author has depicted the workings of jealousy under ludicrous impressions, with so much skill that the play has long been considered as one of the best comic delineations of any passion. In Love, Honor, and Interest, we have a similar version of another drama by the Venetian Advocate. The character of the piece belongs to a different class, but the simplicity of the plot, the distinctive features of the dramatic persons, and the true sentiment which pervades it, have made it be regarded by many critics, as none inferior to the other in point of contrivance, and much better adapted for stage effect. The Genius of Goldoni had rather the power of discovering what was ludicrous in the actions and thoughts of mankind, than of painting them with humor. In the originals of his plays there is no wit, and the language of the dialogue is as familiar as the verbiage of the parlour fireside, but when the incidents which he embodies are considered with attention, the variety and delicacy of his metaphysical tact will be fully admitted to the extent of all the claim that his most ardent admirers put in for the superiority of his talents. What we chiefly respect in the two pieces that we have been enabled to publish, is a kind of classical purity of arrangement which is much wanted at present on the English stage. No artifice is employed to produce the effects of the design, but the plot and result are developed by the moral collision of the characters as naturally as in affairs of common life, and the excrescence of an under plot does not disgrace this beauty. There is such an austere simplicity in Nature that her physical operations cannot be changed but by the interference of a moral cause, nor the necessary course of her moral proceedings altered without employing physical force. The underplot in the drama is what the magical sword of Harlequin is in pantomime, and the phenomena which it produces are equally contrary to nature. To tell us that they are nevertheless interesting proves nothing. The transformations of the pantomime both interest and delight in despite of the understanding, but the delight and the interest is very different from those enjoyments which we expect from the drama. Mechanical effects are not legitimate dramatic incidents. They are contrary to the first principles of the drama, which is an imitation of those actions of men which originate in moral considerations. But while we object to incidents which are made to arise from the arrangement of furniture or unexpected discoveries produced by stratagems of the minor characters, we are well aware that unless occurrences are represented on the stage, the spectacle must be as monotonous as a lecture. But such occurrences must obviously spring from the moral feelings of the characters, and the surprises which they may produce must be the consequences of the unexpected collision of effects which have arisen from the operation of the same cause on different characters. Thus it may happen that one man is led to prosecute a particular course of action in believing that he is justified in doing so by the conduct of another, and in the course of the play it may be brought about that he shall find himself in error, and the conviction of his error may be the effect of a sudden disclosure of the truth, as in the case of Maddervan in Love, Honor, and Interest, but in all this there ought to be no apparent predetermined result. While therefore we admire the exquisite artifice with which the screen scene is managed in the School for Scandal, we cannot but regret that the incident itself is not truly dramatic, and lament that the author had not chosen to produce an equal impression by some more legitimate arrangement. There surely might have been another way of convincing Lady Teazle of Sir Peter's worth, and of Joseph's baseness. But the truth is that the comedy is deficient in its original structure in not being founded on some event that had taken place before the point of time at which the performance is made to commence, and it therefore wanted something to produce a determinate result. The richness of the dialogue, however, conceals every defect in the construction of the plot. The fable of the School for Scandal is like the prop that supports a vine loaded with grapes. It has no value but by its connexion with the foliage and delightful clusters which it sustains.</field>
   </doc>
</add>