<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Lloyd, Charles, 1775-1839</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Lloyd, Charles, 1775-1839</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">lloyd charles 1775 1839</field>
      <field name="author_text">Lloyd, Charles, 1775-1839</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1810's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V3.0474.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1815</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460824</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Agamemnon ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Agamemnon ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="title_facet">agamemnon</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">agamemnon</field>
      <field name="title_text">Agamemnon ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="year_display">1815</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1815</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1815</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460824&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460824&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Lloyd, Charles, 1775-1839&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;lloyd charles 1775 1839&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Agamemnon ; A Tragedy&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;agamemnon&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1815&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1815&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Lloyd, Charles&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1775&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1839&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Agamemnon&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for Longman, Hurst, Rees, Orme And Brown [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1815&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3873148-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv30474&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Agamemnon&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 121 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted&lt;lb/&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;lb/&gt;Dedicatory poem included with Philip. A Tragedy.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Agamemnon.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1815.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Unknown.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">AGAMEMNON. A TRAGEDY.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DRAMATIS PERSONÆ. Agamemnon. Ægisthus. Clytemnestra. Electra. People. Soldiers.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Scene,—The Palace in Argos.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT THE FIRST. SCENE THE FIRST. Ægisthus. Ægis. Oh bloody, angry, discontented shade Of unavenged Thyestes, why pursue me? Leave me, oh leave me, nor torment me thus; Visit once more the sluggish Stygian waves. All, all thy furies fill my breast; thy blood, Too surely, runs through all my veins. I know That I am the offspring of flagitious incest, To guilt predoomed; nor is it requisite, To bring this to my mind, that I should see thee. That Agamemnon now returns to Argos A haughty conqueror from Troy, I know. Within his palace I expect him here; Let him return; his triumph will be short, I swear to thee. Vengeance shall guide my steps: Vengeance resounds within my heart; the time Approaches for it; thou shalt have it; here More than one victim thou shalt have, Thyestes; The blood of Atreus thou shalt drink in streams. But I must have recourse to art, or ere I use the sword: unaided, and alone, Against a powerful king I stand: can I, If in my breast my fury and my hate I do not hide, victory o'er him obtain? SCENE THE SECOND. Ægisthus, Clytemnestra. Cly. Ægisthus, evermore I find thee thus A prey to gloomy thoughts in solitude? From me thou hidest thy corroding cares, From me? ... Must I then see thee fly from her Who breathes alone for thee? Ægis. I do confess I am too much an alien in this palace. 'Tis true, thou trustest to me; and my foot Within these thresholds I had never planted, Hadst thou not fill'd the throne: I hither came, Thou knowest, for thy sake, and here remain For thee. But ah, the day, the fatal day, Already is approaching, on the which, Thou ... e'en thyself ... wilt banish me from hence. Cly. What saidst thou? I? and dost thou think it? no! But little, nothing, do my oaths avail; Thou for thyself shalt witness, if I cherish, In this enamour'd bosom, any thought Except of thee alone. Ægis. And though I were Thy heart's sole object, yet, if I esteem Thy honour more important than my life, I should destroy, and will destroy myself, Ere I disturb thy peace; or be the means To obscure thy fame, or rob thee but in part Of Agamemnon's love. From hence to go A fugitive, neglected, and obscure, This is the destiny to which I am doomed, The unhappy offspring of accursed Thyestes. I am accounted of an infamous sire, Though innocent, the son more infamous still. I want wealth, power, and arrogance of carriage, To cancel the misfortune of my birth, And the opprobrium of my father's name. Not thus Atrides ... He returns renowned, The conqueror of Troy; and can I hope That he will e'er endure the sight in Argos, Of the detested offspring of Thyestes, His most implacable and mortal foe? Cly. If he return, his recent victories Will, from his mind, obliterate all thought Of animosities in years long past. A conquering king will banish from his breast Hatred towards one whom he no longer fears. Ægis. 'Tis true, that, on my own account, I cannot By any one be feared; alone, an exile, Oppressed with wretchedness, bereft of power, Atrides will not condescend to hate me; But perhaps he may despise me; and would'st thou That I stay'd here exposed to such an outrage? Dost thou exhort me to do this, and love me? Cly. Thou lovest me, and yet canst entertain The cruel thought of leaving me for ever? Ægis. 'Tis useless now, oh queen, to flatter thee. By hard necessity, I am compelled To make a declaration of my thoughts. Provided that Atrides could forget The injuries of my father, canst thou hope That he would not discover, or if he Discovered, would dissemble his disgrace, Feign not to see, or feign not to believe, Our guilty outrage of his nuptial love? If I stayed here I ought to avoid thy presence; And should drag on a melancholy life, Worse than the worst of deaths. If now and then I came into thy sight, one sigh alone, One gesture, might betray me: what would be The consequence? 'Tis too, too true! The least, Slightest suspicion in a proud king's heart Makes those who are its objects culpable Of every crime. I think not of myself; Nought for myself I fear; I ought indeed To give thee of true love this terrible proof. Cly. Perchance, who knows? more than thou dost suspect The peril may be distant, or be past: Many revolving moons have now return'd Since fell the walls of Troy; yet still Atrides Tarries, and still arrives not. Thou know'st well It is reported, that the Grecian fleet, By violent winds long driven, at length were scatter'd. Perchance the day is come that brings to me A sure revenge at last, though long delay'd, For the unnatural murder of my daughter. Ægis. And if this were the day, ah would'st thou deign, The illustrious widow of the king of kings, To cast a look on me, the obscure branch Of an abhorred blood? on me, the sport Of inauspicious fate? on me, deprived Of wealth, of arms, of subjects, and of friends? Cly. And add, of crimes.—'Tis true thou graspest not The sceptre of Atrides; but the dagger, Trickling and reeking with my daughter's blood, I see not in thy hands. Ere from my breast He dared to wrest my daughter, and to drag her A bleeding victim to the impious altar, I call the gods to witness, that my heart Received Atrides for its sovereign lord; Nor did another wake a wandering thought. But the remembrance of that fatal day, That horrible moment, with eternal grief, And unimaginable rage, consumes me. The literal translation of this passage is as follows: “From the vain dreams of a fallacious augur, From the more true ambition of an inhuman father, I saw,” &amp;c. But some amplification was necessary to give perspicuity to the passage.To give completion to the futile dreams Of a crazed augur, as it was alleged, But rather, I suspect, to gratify The more atrocious, but less visionary, Frantic ambition of a cruel father, I saw my daughter immolated, torn By stealth from me, under the false pretext Of simulated marriage. From that day, Down to this very time, I feel myself Shudder with horror at the name alone Of such a father. I have not since seen him; And if to-day, at length, fortune betray'd him ... Ægis. Fortune will never turn her back on him, Except he should have wearied her. 'Twas she That to the shores of Xanthus led Atrides Conductor of the Greeks; 'twas she that made him, Rather than virtue, overcome, when there, Th'implacable resentment of Achilles, And Hector's valour: lastly, we shall see her Once more enthrone him in expecting Argos, Laden with trophies, arrogant from conquest. A long time, no, shall not elapse ere thou Shalt have Atrides by thy side; and he Shall well know how thy anger to extinguish. Pledges are living of your former love, Electra and Orestes; pledges still Of interchangeable and lasting peace: E'en as the clouds disperse before the sun, At his return the ill-starr'd love will fly, Which now for me thou fosterest in thy breast. Cly. Orestes is conducive to my safety, And to my heart Electra is most dear. But still the tones of thy expiring voice, Iphigenia, echo in my heart: I hear thee cry, in supplicating accents, Oh, mother! canst thou love my murderer? No, no; I love him not.—Ægisthus, thou Hadst been a different father to my children. Ægis. Ah, could I one day clasp them in my arms! But that I ne'er must hope. In the dread future I have nothing to expect but grief and shame, Calamity and ruin. Yet my fate, Whatever it may be, I here expect, If 'tis thy will. Yes, here I will remain, Since mine the danger is; if it were thine, I should know how alone to fall the victim Of an unhappy love. Cly. Ere that hour comes I will inseparably join our fates. Thy frank and modest language hath inflamed My bosom more than ever: more and more I see thou art worthy of a better fate. But see, Electra comes; leave me with her: I love her; and would fain attempt, at least, To mould her inclinations in thy favour. SCENE THE THIRD. Electra, Clytemnestra. Elec. Mother, and must it be, that we are condemned By unpropitious fate always to tremble; That thou, in vain, should'st languish for thy husband; I for my father? If day after day Perpetual impediments arise To keep from Argos her victorious monarch, What profits it that we have long since heard That Ilion's towers lie levelled with the dust? Cly. Is the report well founded, then, that told us The Grecian fleet were shipwrecked or dispersed? Elec. Different reports are prevalent in Argos: Some say, that even to the Hellespont, By turbid and impetuous south winds, Our fleet was driven; while others swear to have seen Their white sails glimmering on the coast of Argos; Too many, also, are there who affirm That 'gainst a rock the royal prow was dash'd, And that they all who sail'd in her were drown'd, Together with our king. Unhappy we! Mother, to whom now must we credence yield? How rid ourselves of doubt? How be exempt From fear's disquietude? Cly. The rebel winds, That would not be appeased, except with blood, At his departure, now, at his return, Perchance require a human sacrifice. My children, what a solace to my heart Is it that you are in safety by my side! At least, as I did ten years since, I need not Now tremble for your sake. Elec. What do I hear? And doth the memory of that sacrifice Still press upon thy heart? tremendous, fatal, But indispensable it was. If Heaven One of thy daughters as a sacrifice To-day required, exultingly to-day Would I approach the sacred altar; I; To save for thee thy consort, for the Greeks Their chief, for Argos its imperial splendour. Cly. I know how dear to thee thy father is: Ah, didst thou equally thy mother love! Elec. Alike I love you: but my father is In imminent danger; ... yet when thou dost hear His hard vicissitudes, not only I Do never see thee weep, but scarce, alas! I see thy countenance change? Ah, didst thou love him, Mother, as much as I! ... Cly. Too well I know him. Elec. Oh Heaven! what say'st thou? thus thou didst not speak Of him some months ago? Till there had past Almost a lustre from the time when first The Grecians sail'd from hence, I myself heard thee Each day sigh more and more for his return. To us thou talked'st of our father's exploits: In these thou lived'st; foster'd us with these; Speaking of him, I saw thy cheeks bedewed With tears of genuine sorrow ... Thou hast not Seen him since then; he is what then he was: But thou art changed too much; ah! is there then Any new cause, that thus may render him So different to his former self, to thee? Cly. What dost thou mean? new cause? ... my unchanged heart Was always thus an alien from his love. Ah! thou know'st not ... what shall I say? ... Oh daughter, If I revealed to thee of this sad heart The inmost thoughts ... Elec. Oh, that I knew them not! Cly. Alas! what do I hear? My secret, then, Has she discover'd? ... Elec. Oh, that I, at least, And only I, thy secret had discover'd! But know'st thou not, that, in external semblance, Those who most reverently surround the great, Malignantly, intensely, greedily, Their every motion watch? Thou, and thou only, Now hearest not the murmur of the people; Thinking that that from every man is hidden Which thou but ill concealest, which alone To thee none dare impart. Love makes thee blind. Cly. Love? Ah me! who hath betray'd me thus? Elec. Thyself; And long has it been so. From thy own lips It was not likely that I e'er should hear Of such a flame. To speak of it to me Would have cost thee too much. Beloved mother, What art thou doing? I do not believe That a flagitious passion fires thy breast, Involuntary fondness, sprung from pity, Which youth, especially when 'tis unhappy, Is apt to inspire; these, mother, are the baits By which, without thyself suspecting it, Thou hast been caught. Thou hast not, hitherto, Each secret impulse rigorously examined; A bosom conscious of its rectitude, Hardly admits suspicion of itself; And here, perchance, there is no ground for it: Perchance thy fame thou yet hast scarcely sullied, Much less thy virtue: and there still is time To make atonement with one easy step. Ah, by the sacred shade, so dear to thee, Of thy devoted daughter; by that love, Which thou hast ever shewn and felt for me, That love, of which to-day I am not unworthy; How can I more persuasively adjure thee? By thy son's life, Orestes' life, I pray thee, Pause on the brink of this tremendous gulph, Beloved mother, pause. Afar from Argos Banish Ægisthus: stop malignant tongues By thy deportment: with thy children weep The hardships of Atrides: and frequent With them the sacred temples of the gods To implore his swift return. Cly. Banish Ægisthus? Elec. Wilt thou not do it? but thy king, my father, Merits not thus to be by thee betray'd: Nor will he suffer it. Cly. But; grant ... that he ... No longer lives? Elec. Thou mak'st my blood run cold. Cly. What do I say? ... Alas! ... What do I wish? Ah, weep the errors of a misled mother, A mother, past recovery misled. The lengthen'd absence of a cruel husband, ... The merit of Ægisthus ... the decrees Of an o'erruling destiny ... Elec. Oh Heaven! What sayest thou? The merit of Ægisthus? Ah! thou know'st not the vices of his heart: Springing from such a blood, it cannot be That of one genuine virtue he's possest. An exile, vile, the fruit of horrid incest; Dost thou a successor like him project For the king of kings? Cly. Alas, and who am I? Am not I Leda's daughter, Helen's sister? A blood impure as their's runs in my veins. An unknown force, of which I am not mistress, And maddening impulses from vengeful gods, By arts ensnare me, or by force compel. Elec. Helen? and dost thou yet account her sister? Ah, if thou wilt, try to resemble her; But do not be more culpable than she. She had no son, though she betray'd a husband. She fled, but did not from her own descendants The sceptre snatch. And to Ægisthus' hands Would'st thou not only yield thyself, but yield Thy sceptre, and thy children? Cly. If that fate, Oh daughter, wills, that I should be bereft Of Agamemnon, dost thou think that I Should from Orestes seize his father's throne? To me a husband, but not thence a king, Would be Ægisthus; rather he would be A father, a protector, to Orestes. Elec. Rather would he be an atrocious tyrant; Of thy defenceless son the foe; and (ah! I shudder as I think of it!) perchance The murderer. Oh my mother, wouldst thou trust Thy son to one who pants t'usurp his throne? Trust Atreus grandchild to Thyestes' son? ... But I transgress with thee in vain the bounds Of filial duty. Both of us indulge The hope that still the great Atrides lives; My heart assures me of it. His appearance Will of itself suffice in thee t'extinguish Each less illustrious flame; and I, as ought A duteous daughter, swear to thee, for ever To hide th'important secret in my breast. Cly. Wretch that I am! In all thy words I own The voice of truth: but in my darken'd breast The flash of reason shines so transiently, Leaving no track behind it, that I tremble.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT THE SECOND. SCENE THE FIRST. Clytemnestra, Ægisthus. Ægis. Of this erewhile I warn'd thee; now, behold The time for hope is gone, and come for fear. Fortune, the gods, and favourable winds, Bring, with full sail, Atrides into port. I who, a short time since, might have withdrawn From Argos, and have left thy fame unspotted, Now must avoid the presence of the king; Of his imperial and despotic will Leave thee the victim: and myself shrink back I know not whither, banish'd from thy sight, And die of grief. Behold, to what I am, By thy exaggerating hopes, reduced. Cly. Why should'st thou fly? Of what fault art thou guilty? Why should'st thou fear? 'Tis I that am the culprit; But in my heart alone; how can Atrides Discern what passes there? Ægis. True love, like ours, How can it e'er be hid? Alas! already 'Tis but too manifest: how, then, hop'st thou The king should never know it? Cly. Who would dare To tell it to the king, before he knew Whether he should be punish'd or rewarded For the infamous disclosure? Thou know'st not The endless artifices of a court Invented crimes are often there alleged; But real ones, and those especially Which may offend his pride, are oftentimes Not to a king divulged. Although from fear I am not quite exempt, yet not for this Is hope entirely banish'd from my breast. I only ask of thee, Ægisthus, now, Do not deny it me, a single day. The danger I have hitherto conceived Distant and doubtful; hence I find myself With an appropriate remedy unfurnish'd. Leave me to shape expedients to the time; I'll scrutinize the monarch's looks and gestures.— Thou might'st, perhaps, some time remain in Argos Unknown to any one. Ægis. Thyestes son, Unknown in Argos? Cly. For a day at least I hope he may; and, to mature my projects, A day will be sufficient. On my faith Do thou meanwhile implicitly depend. Know thou, that, sooner than abandon thee, I am resolved to tread in Helen's footsteps. Ægis. Know, that I rather would a thousand times Perish, than e'er contaminate thy name. Of mine I do not speak; by unjust fate That is condemn'd to eternal infamy. Ah, could I be assured, that I should lose Nothing but life, if I remain'd in Argos! Son of Thyestes, in Atrides' court I must expect contempt and insolence. And what would be the consequence, if he Discover'd afterwards that I adored thee? Inevitably then I should obtain That death so much desired, how infamous. Who knows? To witness me, in horrid torments, Thou would'st then be compell'd; at the same time, By that vain-glorious insolent, to hear Thyself most bitterly reviled; if that Indeed contented him. 'Tis love alone That thus instructs me to be apprehensive; For thee I tremble. Thou should'st quite forget me; Thou yet hast time. I am obscure by birth; Leave me to perish in obscurity. Yes, to my fate, whate'er that fate may be, Abandon me. I to myself from thee Prescribe eternal exile. For thy spouse Resume thy former fondness; though not love, Yet heaven and fortune make him worthier of thee. Cly. Heaven, reason, fortune, all, and all in vain, Oppose my love. Grant this day to my prayers, Or by my frantic words I shall defeat All thy contrivances to guard my honour. With a deliberate recklessness I rush To death, and e'en to infamy: I rush, Defying all restraint, myself to pierce In tones of agony, Atrides' ears With our unholy flame, and by one stroke Thee and myself to ruin. 'Tis in vain To wish thy destiny from mine dissever'd. Fly, and I likewise fly; die, and I perish. Ægis. Unfortunate Ægisthus! Cly. Quickly, speak, Can'st thou deny a day to so much love? Ægis. And can'st thou ask it? What ought I to do? Cly. Swear that thou wilt not leave the walls of Argos Before to-morrow's dawn. Ægis. Dost thou to this Compel me?—with an oath I promise it. SCENE THE SECOND. Electra, Clytemnestra, Ægisthus. Elec. The day is calm; the passion of the winds And of the roaring billows is no more; Our hope is now matured to certainty, And every apprehension changed to joy. The wish'd-for port to gain th'Argive prows Advance; and at a distance one beholds Their sail-yards tower, dense as a moving wood. Mother, thy spouse is safe; my father lives. I learn, that first he leap'd upon the strand, And, with swift step, advances towards Argos: Already he is almost at the gates, And yet thou standest here. Cly. Remember thou Thy oath, Ægisthus. Elec. Will Ægisthus, too, Go forth with us to meet the king of kings? Cly. 'Tis an unworthy triumph thus, O daughter, With bitter words to wound the unfortunate. Ægis. Perhaps to Electra's ears, Ægisthus' name Is too offensive. With Ægisthus' heart She is yet unacquainted. Elec. With that heart Better am I acquainted than thou think'st. Were it as well known to my blinded mother! Cly. By the fierce discord of thy ancestors, O daughter, thou art blinded. Of Ægisthus, Save that he is the offspring of Thyestes, Thou knowest nothing. Wherefore, then, disdain To hear how pious, humble, and discreet, He is, how worthy of a birth less guilty? Conscious of that disgrace, erewhile he wished To fly from Argos, and withdraw himself From prosperous Agamemnon's haughty presence. Elec. Why does he not go now? what keeps him here? Ægis. Be calm: I stay but for a little while. The sight of one who never hated thee, But whom so much thou hatest, by to-morrow Shall be for ever from thine eyes removed. I swore it to the queen a short time since, And shall make good my words. Cly. What a hard heart Dost thou possess! Ah see, to the fierce rancour Which all thy accents breathe, he nought opposes But patience and humility. Elec. I came not His rare perfections to investigate. My duty led me hither to acquaint thee With Agamemnon's coming; and to tell thee That all the Argives, of all ranks, all ages, With joyful plaudits, festively, in crowds, With emulous haste, rush forth to escort him hither. Ere now I should have rush'd into the arms Of my long-wished-for father; but could I, A daughter only, thus anticipate A mother's footsteps? Thus the first usurp The fond embraces to a consort due? Why dost thou now delay? Ah let us go, 'Twould be almost a crime to tarry longer. Cly. Electra, thou dost know, and know too well, The infirm state of my afflicted heart. Canst thou exult thus to transfix that heart With these repeated blows? Elec. The gods can witness How much I love thee, mother; how my breast Bleeds with compassion for thee: love impels, And pity likewise, to whate'er I do. Would'st thou be found thus at Ægisthus' side When first the king accosts thee? Thou disclosest, By longer tarriance, what thou wouldest conceal.— Let us depart. Ægis. Ah! lady, I beseech thee, Go; and persist not in thy own destruction. Cly. I could not tremble as I tremble now, If t'inevitable death I went. Oh dreadful meeting! moment of despair! Whence can I summon such a fund of courage, That 'twill not at his presence all forsake me. He is my lord; and though I have not wrong'd him, Except in thought, I cannot, cannot see him, Without, at the first glance, betraying all. I cannot, and I will not, feign affection ... Oh day! to me of woe unutterable! Elec. Rather to us a day of consolation! I feel that I shall now regain my mother. Feel'st thou remorse? no longer art thou guilty. Ægis. Wert thou e'er guilty? Thou hadst cause to think Thy husband dead; and, mistress of thy actions, Thoughtest to give to me thy bridal hand— Who can ascribe a thought like this to guilt? He knows it not, except thou tell him of it. Thou art not guilty; nor, when in his presence, Hast cause to tremble. Thou wilt soon discover, That his invulnerable breast retains, For thy slain daughter, no compunctious pangs, From his example learn to be secure. Elec. Dar'st thou with thy mortiferous tongue assperse The name of Agamemnon? Let us go. Ah, mother, let this be the last advice That thou wilt hear from him. Cly. Thy oath, Ægisthus: Remember thou hast sworn. Ægis. One day remains. Cly. Oh heavens! one day? ... Elec. Too long for one that's impious. SCENE THE THIRD. Ægisthus. Ægis. Hate me, Electra, hate me; by Ægisthus More fervently and fatally thou art hated: And thou wilt learn, that my tremendous hate In imprecations does not spend itself. Ægisthus curses whom he hates ... by death. At last, in all thy branches, thou art fallen Within my power, abominable race! With what regretful pungency I thought The angry waves had feasted on Atrides! Had it been so, oh how had I been robb'd By greedy billows of a mighty vengeance! 'Tis true, that, by their death, Atrides' children, For Atreus' execrable deadly feast Had made atonement: thus, Thyestes, thus I had in part thy bloody thirst appeased. Thy vengeful and retributory oath In part I should have ratified ... But what? Shall this revival of their sire redeem From death his offspring? Lo! the train here comes Of the victorious king. Hence, hence, and yield To the tumultuary, insensate joy Of the giddy people; glad they know not why. Your triumph shall be transient. I am here A stranger to all feasts but those of blood. SCENE THE FOURTH. People, Agamemnon, Electra, Clytemnestra, Soldiers. Aga. At last I see the wish'd-for walls of Argos: This ground which now I tread is the loved spot Where once I wander'd with my infant feet. All that I see around me are my friends; My wife, my daughter, and my faithful people, And you, ye household gods, whom I at last Return to worship. What have I to wish? What does there now remain for me to hope? How long and tedious do ten years appear Spent in a foreign country, far from all The heart holds dear! With what profound delight, After the labours of a bloody war, Shall I repose? Oh home, beloved asylum, Where peace alone awaits us, with what joy Thee I revisit! But am I, alas! The only one that tastes of comfort here? My wife, my daughter, silently ye stand, Fixing upon the ground unquietly Your conscious eyes? Oh heaven, do ye not feel A joy that equals mine, in being thus Restored to my embrace? Elec. Ah, honour'd father! Cly. My lord ... to-day we have felt vicissitudes Too rapid and too opposite .... Now driven From hope to grief, and now from grief driven back To unexpected joy ... Ill can the heart Emotions bear so sudden and discordant. Elec. For thee till now we have trembled. Here report Spread of thee various and tremendous tidings, To which the turbulent and stormy winds, Which have for many days the ocean vex'd, Made us yield credence; to ourselves a source Of deep anxiety. At last thou art safe; At last from Troy a conqueror thou return'st, So much desired, and for so many months So much desired in vain. Father, at last Upon this hand, upon this hand of thine, On which, before thou didst depart from hence, I, but a child, infantine kisses printed; I, now a woman grown, more fervently, More reverently, the adult kiss impress. That warlike hand, which made all Asia tremble, Will not disdain a simple virgin's homage. Ah no! I feel assured, that, to the heart Of my most tender father, to behold Once more, to clasp his well-beloved daughter, Matured in age, devoted to his will, Will be a grateful spectacle, far more Than vanquish'd kingdoms, and submissive monarchs. Aga. Yes, daughter, dearer to me far than fame Are the fond ties of blood; ah! could I be As happy as a father and a husband As I am as a warrior and a king! But I reproach not you; myself alone And my hard destiny. Already heaven Has robb'd me of one daughter: to complete My measure of parental happiness At my return, she only now was wanting. But heaven forbids it, and I must divert From the dire subject my regretful thoughts. Electra, thou art left to me; art left To thy unhappy and afflicted mother. How, as a fond companion, by her side, Her only solace in my tedious absence, Her endless tears, her anxious restlessness, And all her sufferings, hast thou shared with her, Thou tenderest of daughters! How many days, How many nights, in calling me to mind, Have ye consumed together! Likewise, I, Amid the frequent fierce vicissitudes Of military enterprise; 'mid blood, 'Mid glory, and 'mid death, for ever saw Your image present, your anxieties, Your tears, conjectures, and inquietudes. Oft in my helmet bonnetted I wept In silence; but, except the father, none Were conscious of these tears. But now the time For grief is at an end: and Clytemnestra, From her dejected look, and tearful eye, Alone I do not recognize. Cly. I sad? ... Elec. Joy, when it is excessive, overcomes As much as grief. Father, allow her time To calm her scatter'd spirits. She would fain Say more than I can say, and hence says less. Aga. Nor has she spoken to me of Orestes. Cly. Orestes? Elec. Ah! come to embrace him, father. Aga. Heir of my throne, my only hope, Orestes, Support and consolation of my life; Till in these arms a thousand times I've clasp'd thee, I will not to these weary limbs allow A moment's rest... My consort, let us go; Let us make haste t'embrace him: that dear son, Of whom, though thou speak'st not, thou art the mother; Him, whom I left an infant at the breast, Quitting him with reluctance... Is he grown? What are his sports? resembleth he his father? Hath he the seeds of future virtue in him? Do his eyes sparkle with a noble ardour, If he beholds a brandish'd sword, or hears Of glorious exploits, or heroic deeds? Cly. I cannot any longer check my tears! Elec. Ah, father, come, and thou shalt see him: he Expressly is thy image; since from hence Thou wentest, never have I quitted him. Age of simplicity! oft as he heard His father named by us—“When, when,” he cried, “Shall I behold him?” Hearing afterwards Of Troy, and arms, and foes, in thy defence, With childish eagerness, he would aspire, Equipp'd with arms, to brave thy enemies. Aga. Ah! say no more; let us depart. Each instant Seems death to me that I delay to see him.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT THE THIRD. SCENE THE FIRST. Agamemnon, Electra. Aga. Am I return'd to my own family? Or have I only changed my enemies By change of place? Electra, do thou calm Thy father's horrid doubts. Within my palace I find a new reception; to my consort I am become a stranger; yet, methinks, She might ere now composure have regain'd. Each word of her's, each gesture, and each look, Art, alienation, diffidence, constraint, Successively announce. Am I become To her so terrible, that, in her heart, No genial feelings I can now excite, Nothing but terror? Where are they all gone, Those chaste yet warm embraces? whither flown Those soft and artless accents? those dear proofs By thousands, and by thousands, of a love Indubitable, which, with such a pang I left—where are they? which, with such a hope So fond, so flatt'ring, and so dearly cherish'd, I wish'd to see again; ah! tell me why, Instead of finding them in more abundance, They are all fled, no traces of them left? Elec. My king, my father, thou dost in thyself Unite such attributes, that thou excitest Reverence no less than love. Thy wife hath lived A prey to sorrow for ten tedious years: It is not possible, in one brief day, To shake off grief confirm'd to habitude. Her silence ... Aga. How much less was I at first Confounded by that silence, than I now Am by her studied artificial phrases. How seldom is a genuine tenderness Wrapt in the pomp of words! There is a silence, The child of love, more eloquent than speech, Conveying meanings language cannot utter: And there are gestures fraught with thought, and feeling, The heart's involuntary messengers: But neither are her silence or her speech Suggested by affection: that is certain. What boots the glory now with which I'm laden? The laurels, 'mid such dire vicissitudes, With so much bloodshed gain'd; if I have lost In gaining them—a blessing far more precious— My peace of mind. Elec. Ah banish such a thought! As far as it depends on me, as far As on my mother it depends, shalt thou Enjoy among us perfect peace. Aga. Yet whence Is she become so different to herself? Ah tell me whence? erewhile, when in my arms She placed Orestes, didst thou then observe? While I was fill'd with transport, and ne'er thought That I enough had kiss'd him, or embraced him, Didst thou perchance behold her sympathize In my paternal joy? who would have thought The child was her's as much as it was mine? Our common hope, Orestes, the last pledge Of our affection; or I am much mistaken, Or these were not the unconcealable Spontaneous symptoms of a gladden'd heart, Nor the affections of a tender mother, Nor the endearments of a loving consort. Elec. Somewhat 'tis true she's changed from what she was. The sunshine of pure joy has ne'er return'd Since that tremendous day, when thou wert forced, As a condition of the general safety, To immolate thy daughter. Such a wound, If in a mother's heart 'tis ever heal'd, Is heal'd with difficulty; from her mind Ten years have not yet banish'd the remembrance Of the inevitable stratagem, At the same time compassionate and cruel, By which her daughter from her breast was torn. Aga. Unhappy me! Does not my recollection Of that event suffice to punish me? Was I, than she, on that tremendous day Less wretched? Was not I as much a father As she a mother? But could I alone Deny her to the exasperated cries, The rabid turbulence, the menaces Of multitudinous and madden'd warriors; Who, from a cruel oracle, received Potent incentives to their fiery rage? What could I do alone 'mid such a crowd Of haughty kings, thirsting for fame and vengeance, All equally impatient of restraint? Those barbarous kings all heard a father's groans, Yet with that father not one shed a tear: For when the angry gods in thunders speak, Nature is silent, innocence in vain Lifts up her voice: the gods alone are heard. Elec. Ah trouble not with bitter recollections This joyful day, the day of thy return! If I spoke of it, 'twas but to diminish The just amazement which arises in thee At the constrain'd deportment of my mother. Add to her former grief, that her sad mind, Thrown back upon itself, in solitude Has prey'd upon its powers: she has not had, Except her children, any one to whom She might impart, and thus assuage her grief. One was too young, and I perhaps, though willing, Was ill adapted for a comforter. Thou knowst, that bitterness of soul, when smother'd Inwardly festers, and augments itself. Thou know'st, that, to drag on in loneliness A heavy heart, is death, not to joy only, But e'en the power of joy, is life and being To every phantasy of sickly minds. Th'expecting thee so long, and every day Trembling for thy security, thou see'st it, How can she ever be what once she was? Pardon, I pray thee, the infirmities Of an enfeebled mind; all brooding thoughts Drive from thee. Quickly, at thy cheering presence The spectres of despondency will vanish. Believe it, father, ere long thou wilt see Her tenderness, her faith, her love, return. Aga. At least it cheers me to indulge the hope. How would it sooth me, if, without restraint, She would unfold to me her inmost thoughts? But, meanwhile, tell me, to what purpose comes, Where I am king, the offspring of Thyestes? What does he do here? What does he expect? I only have learn'd here that he's in Argos. It seems to me, as if, in naming him, All felt embarrassment. Elec. Of Atreus thou, He of Thyestes is the offspring; hence Springs this embarrassment? Ægisthus exiled, Here came for an asylum; he has foes E'en in his very brethren. Aga. In that race Fraternal hatred is hereditary; Perchance the imprecations of my sire, The anger of the gods, occasion this. But that he should, near to the son of Atreus Seek an asylum, not a little strange To me appears. Already I've commanded That he forthwith should come into my presence; I wish to see him, from himself to learn His present fortunes and his future projects. Elec. Father, there is no doubt that he's unhappy; But thou who dost discriminate at once The various characters of men, wilt learn Whether or not he merits to be so. Aga. Behold, he comes. Who knows if he conceals A base or noble heart, beneath a form Of more than ordinary gracefulness. SCENE THE SECOND. Agamemnon, Electra, Ægisthus. Ægis. Can I, devoid of fear, present myself Before the glorious conqueror of Troy, The sublime king of kings? I contemplate The majesty, the splendour of a god On thy august and all-commanding brow ... August, but at the same time merciful: And from their thrones the gods oft bend their looks On the unhappy. Such Ægisthus is. Ægisthus, hitherto the sport of fortune, Has common ancestors with thee: one blood Runs in our veins, from whence I dare to seek, Within these walls, if not relief, a shelter, Which might avail, from my oppressive foes, Who also are my brethren, to protect me. Aga. Thou mak'st me shudder, when thou thus recall'st That we from one blood spring; 'twere surely better For all of us to turn our thoughts from thence. Thyestes' sons, by a decree of birth, Are interchangeably condemn'd to hate; But not condemn'd to chuse for an asylum The court of Atreus. Hitherto, Ægisthus, Thou wert, and still thou art, to me unknown; I neither hate nor love thee; yet, though willing To lay aside hereditary discord, I cannot, without feeling in my breast, I know not what, of strange and perplex'd feeling, Behold the countenance, nor hear the voice, Of one that is the offspring of Thyestes. Ægis. That the magnanimous Atrides cannot, E'en knows not how, to hate without disclosure, This I well knew: a heart sublime like thine Is inaccessible to base designs. The valour thou, and not the enmities Of thy forefathers, hast inherited. Thou knowest how to punish, ... or to pardon, Who dares offend thee; but who, like myself, Is wretched, and, to thee unknown, might claim Thy pity, though he were a son of Troy. Thee Greece selected, not by accident, The leader of its lofty enterprise; But deem'd thee monarch of all kings that were, In courtesy, in valour, justice, faith. Such I repute thee also, nor e'er deem'd Myself more safe, than when beneath the shade Of thy renown; nor did I recollect That I was born the offspring of Thyestes, But that I was the victim of misfortune. It seem'd to me, that, in adversity, My blood's defilement had been thoroughly cleansed: And if thou shudderedst at Ægisthus name, I hoped that afterwards thou wouldest feel, Within thy royal and generous breast, Profound compassion for me, at the names Of exile, wretched, mendicant, oppress'd. Aga. And if I felt compassion, wouldest thou From me endure it? Ægis. Who am I, to dare Despise a gift of thine? Aga. Thou? Thou art sprung From the most deadly enemy of my father: Thou hatest me, and, more, art bound to hate me. Nor can I blame thee for it; our forefathers Eternally have separated us; Not us alone; our sons, and our sons' sons, To all posterity. Thou knowest well, The impious Thyestes did defile, Ravish'd the spouse of Atreus. My father, When he had slain them, at a horrid banquet, Gorged the adulterer with his children's flesh. Why should I utter more? Legends of blood, Ah, why recal thy dire vicissitudes? The bare recital stiffens me with horror. I see in thee Thyestes and his furies. Canst thou with other eyes contemplate me? Do not I represent to thee the image Of sanguinary Atreus? 'Mid these walls, Which thou dost see stain'd with thy brothers' blood, Oh, canst thou linger, nor in every vein Throb with the recollection of the past? Ægis. Horrid, 'tis true, was the revenge of Atreus, But it was just: Those children that Thyestes Saw at the execrable banquet placed Were fruit of incest. He their father was. Yes; but clandestinely the faithless spouse Of the unavenged and too much injured Atreus Bore them to him. The outrage was enormous, But greater was the punishment. Brethren they were, 'Tis true, but, to forget this sacred tie Thyestes was the first, Atreus the second. It seems as if the anger of the heavens 'Gainst me had not yet ceased: thy race, less guilty, Is crown'd with every blessing. Other brethren Thyestes gave to me; and, not as I, Are these from incest sprung; the wives of these I never ravish'd from them; yet towards me, Far more than Atreus was, are they incensed. They have entirely driven me from the throne: And, more, to injure me, from me have taken My portion of hereditary wealth; Nor that suffices: cruelly they seek, Having depriv'd me of my heritage, To take my life. Thou see'st, if, without cause, I seek for an asylum. Aga. Thou hast cause To seek one, but thy choice is ill directed. Ægis. Where'er I drag my feet, the infamy Of my paternal name and of my birth With me I drag; but where should I less blush, When I give utterance to Thyestes' name, Than in the presence of the son of Atreus? Thou, wert thou less elated by success; Thou, wert thou friendless as Ægisthus is, The weight thou then would'st feel, feel all the horror Which is annex'd no less to a descent From Atreus than Thyestes. Do thou then Participate in my calamities. Atrides, act thou towards me, as thou would'st That others should towards thee, wert thou Ægisthus. Aga. Ægisthus I? .. Know, whatso'er had been, However adverse, desperate my fortune, I never would have turn'd my feet, no, never, To seek Thyestes' throne. I hear a voice, And such a voice proclaiming in my heart, That I should not place confidence in thee, That 'tis to pity closed. Yet, since thou wilt Solicit my compassion, which I am not Accustomed to refuse, I will endeavour, (Far as my name and power have influence In Greece,) in thy hereditary rights To re-instate thee. Meanwhile, go thou far From Argos. Near to thee I should drag on Days of anxiety, and restless nights. The son of Atreus and Thyestes' son One city cannot hold. Perhaps e'en within The boundaries of Greece, we still should be Too near each other. Ægis. Dost thou drive me hence? What crime dost thou impute to me? Aga. Thy father. Ægis. Does that suffice? Aga. It is too much. Go hence; Nor let to-morrow's dawn find thee in Argos. The help solicited thou shalt obtain, Provided that I hear thou hast obey'd me. SCENE THE THIRD. Agamemnon, Electra. Aga. Electra, would'st thou think it? in his presence I felt throughout my soul a shrinking back I never felt before. Elec. Thou hast done well Thus to dismiss him: never do I see him Without a strange antipathy. Aga. Our sires, In characters of blood, in us have graven An interchangeable and lasting hate. Reason, perhaps, may teach me to suppress, What neither time nor reason can destroy. SCENE THE FOURTH. Clytemnestra, Agamemnon, Electra. Cly. Ah, why with fresh delays protract the hopes Of thy expecting people? Even now, Upon the sacred altars, incense smokes. Along the paths, engarlanded with flowers, That to the temple lead, innumerous crowds, Like waves, succeed each other, who, to heaven, With loud acclaim, shout Agamemnon's praise. Aga. I should, ere now, not only have indulged The wishes of my people, but my own, Had not Ægisthus, in a conference, Detain'd me here, perhaps longer than I wished. Cly. Ægisthus? Aga. Yes, Ægisthus. Tell me now, Why heard I not from thee he was in Argos? Cly. My lord ... I deem'd not he would find a place 'Mid thy so many other cares. Aga. Ægisthus Is on his own account to me indifferent. But he, thou knowest, from a blood descends Fatal to mine. I do not now suspect That he came here to injure me, (and could he?) But yet it seems to me that his appearance Is ill adapted to the festal homage That waits on my return. I have commanded, That ere to-morrow's dawn he goes from hence. Meanwhile, let joy unmingled revel here. Oh, consort, to the temple now I go, Thus to propitiate the heavenly powers. Ah! let the genial smile return to illume Thy countenance. Those smiles were once to me Pledges of peace, and of beatitude;— This heart can never rest till they return. SCENE THE FIFTH. Electra, Clytemnestra. Elec. Oh better consort of the best of kings! Cly. Alas! I am betray'd: thou hast betray'd me. Electra, didst thou thus observe thy promise? Thou to the king revealedst that Ægisthus— Or whence ... Elec. I never named him to the king; Elsewhere he learn'd it. All are emulous To gain his favour in a thousand ways. All wish to make themselves important to him. Rather should'st thou feel wonder, that he did not Know this before. Cly. But what imputes he to him? Of what does he suspect him? Didst thou hear Their conference? Why does he drive him hence? And he, what did he answer? Did Atrides Of me make mention to him? Elec. Be composed, Oh mother; in the bosom of Atrides Suspicion hath not enter'd. He ne'er dreams Thou could'st betray him; and from hence art thou Bound never to betray him. To Ægisthus His words were not those of an enemy. Cly. But yet he's banish'd instantly from Argos. Elec. Oh, happy queen! thus from the brink thou art snatch'd Of a tremendous precipice at once, Ere thou advancest farther. Cly. He will go! Elec. By his departure will thy secret be Effectually conceal'd; thou yet enjoyest Th'entire affection of Atrides' heart. More than aught else he wishes for thy love: Impious detractors have not yet infected His bosom with their poison; all is yet Untouch'd. But woe, if those base miscreants, And wicked as they are base, but, for a moment, Discover in your confidence a flaw! They then will emulously tell him all ... Ah, mother! ... let compassion for thyself, For us, and even for Ægisthus, move thee! Banish'd from Argos, he will be secure From the king's vengeance. Cly. If I lose Ægisthus, What have I then to shrink from? Elec. Infamy. Cly. Leave me, Electra, to my terrible fate. Elec. Ah no! What hop'st thou? what would'st thou attempt? Cly. Thou innocent daughter of a guilty mother, Leave me. Thou never more shalt hear me name Ægisthus. Thee I'll not contaminate; My poor, unhappy daughter, should not share In my flagitious sighs. Elec. Ah, mother! Cly. Go. Leave me to my own thoughts, and to the flame That now devours me.—I insist upon it. SCENE THE SIXTH. Electra. Elec. Unhappy me! ... unhappy mother! ... Ah What a dire tempest gathers o'er our heads: If ye, celestial powers, do not disperse it, What will become of our devoted house?</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT THE FOURTH. SCENE THE FIRST. Ægisthus, Clytemnestra. Ægis. Oh, queen, this is our last, our last farewell! Alas! from whence I fain would have withdrawn, I see myself proscribed. Yet do I not Regret, remaining thus, to have obey'd thee. At thy command, and for thy dear love's sake, T'have suffer'd such an outrage, pleases me, If thou accept the homage. But my heart Feels a far different and severer grief, In thus forsaking thee, and never more To have the hope of seeing thee; no, never. Cly. I feel, Ægisthus, that I well deserve The most severe rebukes; yet from thy lips Since no rebuke I hear, thy wretchedness, The horrors of thy unjust destiny, Too keenly rend my self-accusing heart. On my account thou suffer'st such disgrace; And I am ready, for thy sake, t'endure Outrages, anguish, death, and, if need be, E'en infamy itself... Now is the time For action. Shall I ever leave thee? Ah, Think, while I breathe, that this can never be. Ægis. Perhaps, then, thou art determined with thyself To ruin me. What else canst thou perform? Ah, cease! it is in vain to contradict The absolute will of monarch absolute. Thou know'st his arguments consist in arms; Nor hears he other arguments from others. Cly. We may, if not oppose, at least delude him: Grateful the attempt would be. He has decreed To-morrow's dawn for thy departure hence; And that to-morrow's dawn shall witness me Companion of thy flight. Ægis. Oh, heaven! what say'st thou? Thou mak'st me tremble. Dear as is thy love, So much, and more, thy fame to me is dear. Ah no! I ought not, nor will I permit it. A day would come, though late, would come at last; A fatal day, when I should be constrain'd To hear thee call—e'en to hear thee pronounce— Ægisthus author of thy infamy. Banishment, death, (towards which, from thee scarce severed, I rush with hasty steps,) would be to me Less hard, than, wretched me! ever to hear Such dire recrimination from thy lips. Cly. Thou only art the author of my life: And shall I ever be compell'd to name thee The author of my infamy? e'en thou, Who in my bosom dost a dagger plunge, If thou possess the heart t'abandon me ... Ægis. Rather should I most wantonly immerge That dagger in thy breast, if I constrain'd thee To share my fate. Alas! were it accomplish'd, This meditated flight, who could secure us From the avenging anger of Atrides? What refuge is there from his powerful arm? What shelter? Was not Helen fugitive? Into his realm a powerful monarch's son Conducted her; but what did it avail That the seducer had both arms and courage, Ramparts and battlements? By dint of force, Within his very palace, and beneath The eyes of his own father, at the foot Of sacred altars, 'mid the cries, the tears, The bloodshed, and the menace of his subjects, Was not his mistress wrested from his arms, And with her both his kingdom and his life? I, destitute of all alliances, A wanderer, and an exile, what can I Perform? Thou see'st it clearly, thy design Is in itself abortive. Thou alone Would'st have defied the infamy in vain Of ignominious flight: and I, possess'd And destitute of thee at once, should gain The eternal blot, the merited disgrace Of a seducer. In this ill-judged flight, If thou persist, this is the destiny That stares us in the face. Cly. Thou clearly see'st The obstacles, and nothing else: true love Ne'er condescended to be so discreet. Ægis. Never, oh never, did true lover drag To certain ruin the beloved object. Suffer that I alone in peril be; And thou wilt learn whether I condescend To know, much less to care for obstacles. I see most clearly, that at less than nothing Thou valuest thy life: I see most clearly Thy love is dearer to thee far than fame. Yes, more, far more, than I deserve, thou lovest. Ah! could I heal again thy wounded heart, Heaven knows that at the risk of all I prize, I fain would heal it! ... all ... all ... would I do ... But cease to love thee: that I cannot do: I can die easily; and now I wish it. But if I am constrain'd, at a great risk, To see thy fame and life exposed for me, Oh, lady, chuse more certain means than flight. Cly. More certain means? what other means are left? Ægis. To be a banish'd man ... to fly ... t'expire; ... These are the only means that I have left. Thou, far from me, deprived of every hope Of seeing me again, wilt, from thy heart, Have quickly driven my image; great Atrides Will wake a far superior passion there. Thou, in his presence, many happy days Wilt yet enjoy. These auspices may heaven Confirm. Now can I not to thee evince A surer proof of love than by my flight. Terrible, hard, irrevocable proof. Cly. If there be need of death, I'm fix'd to die. But is there nothing left to try ere this? Ægis. Another step, perhaps, e'en now remains ... But unbecoming ... Cly. And it is? Ægis. Too cruel. Cly. But certain? Ægis. Certain, ah too much so! Cly. How Canst thou then hide it from me? Ægis. How canst thou Of me demand it? Cly. What then may it be? ... I know not ... speak: I am too far advanced ... I cannot now retract: perchance already I am suspected by Atrides: perhaps He has the right already to contemn me: Hence do I feel constrain'd, e'en now, t'abhor him: I cannot longer in his presence live: I neither will nor dare. Do thou, Ægisthus, Teach me, and be it whatsoe'er it may, A means, by which I may withdraw myself From him for ever. Ægis. Thou withdraw thyself From him? I have already said to thee That now 'tis utterly impossible. Cly. What other step remains for me to take? Ægis. None. Cly. Now, I understand thee. What a flash Oh what a deadly, instantaneous flash Of criminal conviction, rushes through My obtuse mind? What throbbing turbulence In every vein I feel!—I understand thee:— The cruel remedy ... the only remedy ... Is Agamemnon's life-blood. Ægis. I am silent. Cly. Yet silently thou askest for that blood. Ægis. Nay, rather I forbid it. To our love, And to thy life, (of mine I do not speak,) His living is the only obstacle; But yet thou knowest that his life is sacred: To love, respect, defend it, thou art bound, And I to tremble at it. Let us cease. The hour advances now; my long discourse Might give occasion to suspicious thoughts.— At length receive Ægisthus' last farewell. Cly. Ah! hear me ... Agamemnon to our love ... And to thy life? .. ah, yes, there are, besides him, No other obstacles: too certainly His life is death to us. Ægis. Ah! do not heed My words: they sprang from too much love. Cly. And love Reveal'd to me their meaning. Ægis. Hast thou not Thy mind o'erwhelm'd with horror? Cly. Horror? ... yes ... But to part from thee! ... Ægis. Would'st thou have the courage? Cly. So vast my love it puts an end to fear. Ægis. But the king lives surrounded by his friends What sword could find a passage to his heart? Cly. What sword? ... Ægis. Here open violence were vain. Cly. Yet ... treachery ... Ægis. 'Tis true, he merits not To be betrayed ... Atrides ... he who loves His wife so well ... he who, enchained from Troy, In semblance of a slave in fetters, brought Cassandra, whom he loves, to whom he is Himself a slave. Cly. What do I hear? Ægis. Meanwhile Expect, that when of thee his love is wearied, He will divide with her his throne and bed: Expect that, to thy many other wrongs, Shame will be added; and do thou alone Not be exasperated at a deed That rouses every Argive. Cly. What said'st thou? ... Cassandra doom'd to be my rival? ... Ægis. So Atrides wills. Cly. Then let Atrides perish. Ægis. How? by what hand? Cly. By mine, this very night, Within that bed which he expects to share With this abhorred slave. Ægis. Oh, heavens! but think ... Cly. I am resolved ... Ægis. Should'st thou repent? ... Cly. I do That I have so long delayed. Ægis. And yet ... Cly. I do it; I, e'en if thou wilt not. Shall I let thee, Who only dost deserve my love, be dragg'd To cruel death? And shall I let him live Who cares not for my love? I swear to thee, To-morrow, thou shalt be the king in Argos. Nor shall my hand, nor shall my bosom tremble— But who approaches? Ægis. 'Tis Electra ... Cly. Ah! Let us avoid her. Do thou trust in me. SCENE THE SECOND. Electra. Elec. Ægisthus flies from me, and he does well: But I behold that likewise from my sight My mother seeks t'escape! Infatuate And wretched mother! She could not resist The blameable desire for the last time To see Ægisthus. They have here, at length, Conferr'd together... But Ægisthus seems Too much elated, and too confident, For one condemn'd to exile. She appear'd Like one disturb'd in thought, but more possest With anger and resentment, than with grief. Oh heavens! who knows, to what that miscreant, With his infernal arts, may have impell'd her! To what extremities have wrought her up! .. Now, now, indeed, I tremble! .. What misdeeds, How black in kind, how manifold in number, Do I behold! .. Yet, if I speak, I kill My mother: .. If I am silent? ... SCENE THE THIRD. Electra, Agamemnon. Elec. Oh, my father, Tell me, hast thou seen Clytemnestra? Aga. I Thought she already was in these apartments. But she will soon be here. Elec. I wish she may. Aga. 'Tis certain I expect her here: she knows That here I would awhile converse with her. Elec. Father, Ægisthus lingers yet in Argos. Aga. One entire day, thou know'st, I have allow'd him: 'Tis almost spent: to-morrow he will go Far from our sight for ever. But, what thought, Oh daughter, thus disturbs thee? Restless looks Thou castest round thee, and a mortal paleness Steals o'er thy face! Whence this inquietude? A thousand times upon thy faultering tongue I have heard Ægisthus' name, and then thou pausest. Elec. I know not why; yet do I wish him gone... Believe me, that a night is a long space For one that perhaps watches both place and time For mischief; in the darkness of the night, Guilt from its lurking place creeps forth, that shunn'd The eye of day. My father, I conjure thee, Ere the sun rises, banish him from Argos. Aga. What dost thou say, Electra? Is he then Hostile to me? Hast thou discovered this? Dost thou suspect him of projecting plots? Elec. No plots have I discover'd .. yet .. I think not. But he's Thyestes' son... Upon my heart There weighs an unknown, and a fatal presage. Perchance my terrors are extravagant, Yet they are not without a cause. Oh father, Thou art call'd upon, believe me, not to scorn them, Although I cannot, and perhaps know not how To give them utterance. Meanwhile I retire To guard the dear Orestes. Once more, father, I do assure thee, that, to speed his absence, Is to accelerate thy peace, and ours. SCENE THE FOURTH. Agamemnon. Aga. Fierce and implacable revenge of Atreus! How dost thou live connatural with the blood Of thy descendants! At Thyestes' name They shudder. But ought I to be amazed, If merely at the presence of Ægisthus Troy's conqueror is dismay'd, that seeing him A simple maid should fear?—If he has plotted One nod of mine annihilates at once Himself, and all his plots. But, is it fitting, That, from suspicion only, I should steel My heart against him? 'Twould be cruelty, Thus his already intimated exile For a few hours to hasten. If I tremble, Lastly, is this his fault? Should he for this Be punish'd? SCENE THE FIFTH. Agamemnon, Clytemnestra. Aga. Come, consort, come; and from my heart dispel, For thou alone canst do it, every doubt, Which, on that heart, Electra hath impress'd. Cly. Electra? ... Doubt? ... What has she said to thee? ... Oh heaven! ... She loves thee so; ... yet on this day With false suggestions she oppresses thee? ... And yet, what doubts? ... Aga. Ægisthus ... Cly. What of him? ... Aga. Ægisthus, he, of whom thou ne'er to me, As yet, hast spoken, seems to interrupt Electra's comfort and tranquillity. Cly. Hast thou not sentenced him to banishment? What can Electra fear from him? Aga. Ah, thou Art not, as we are, of the blood of Atreus: A stranger's mind cannot conceive the horror That, in our race, Thyestes' race excites. Yet to the terrors of a timid damsel I do not yield, so as to change the hour Fix'd for his banishment: I am content To know that he is going to a distance. I now shall have my heart relieved from care. It now is time, full time, beloved consort, That thou unfoldest to me the deep grief, That weighs upon thy heart, and which I read, In spite of all thy efforts, on thy face. If not to me, to whom wilt thou reveal it? If I be the occasion of thy grief, Who better than myself can mitigate, Or expiate it, or divide it with thee? ... Oh heaven! but thou art silent? From the earth Thine eyes dost never raise? Immoveably, Suffused with tears, they're fix'd... Alas! what thou, Electra saidst to me was too, too true. Cly. Too true? ... Electra? ... Did she speak of me? ... Dost thou believe her? Aga. Yes, she has, to me, Betray'd thee; and she has reveal'd to me The fountain of thy grief. Cly. Oh heaven! ... Perchance She has described my faith toward thee as dubious? ... I clearly see it all; Electra always Little regarded me. Aga. Thou art mistaken. She spoke to me, of thee, as it behoved A duteous daughter of a much-loved mother: If otherwise, should I have listen'd to her? Cly. What did she say then? Aga. What, without a blush, Thou should'st have told me of thine own accord: That bitter recollections, in thy heart, Of thy devoted daughter haunt thee yet. Cly. Of Iphigenia? ... Now I breathe....—Ah, yes, That day will ever more be fatal to me. ... Aga. What can I say, that thou already know'st not? In every heart, except in thine, I find Pity for my misfortunes: but if tears, Maternal tears, or bitterest reproach, Could mitigate thy unconsumed affliction, In tears, or in recriminating words, Why not indulge? Though I deserve it not, I would endure it. Why not weep with me? Dost thou despise my tears? Thou knowest well I were not able to refrain from them, At the remembrance of my luckless daughter. Further, oh consort, if thou hatest me, Ah tell me so: avow'd dissatisfaction Is more endurable than feign'd regard. Cly. Perchance the cause that in thine eyes I seem So much more alter'd than I am, arises From thy not being what thou wert before. I will e'en speak it out: perchance Cassandra, Ah, yes, Cassandra, is the cause, whence I Am now less acceptable to Atrides... Aga. Oh heaven! Cassandra? Consort, what dost thou Impute to me? and canst thou think this true? When the best spoils among us were divided Of ravaged Troy, to me th'illustrious damsel, Deprived by the victorious Grecian sword Of parents and of country, was awarded. The accustom'd, and the fatal, law of conquest, Ordain'd, that, bound in fetters, I should bring her With me to Argos; an affecting instance Of the uncertainty of human greatness. I pity, it is true, Cassandra's fate, But thee alone I love. Know'st thou not this? And as a proof of this, to thee I yield The royal captive: if it be thy will, Withdraw her from my sight, and exercise, Over her lot, unlimited controul. Thee I conjure alone to recollect That she's the wretched daughter of a king Once powerful; that to treat her with disdain, Would be unworthy of thy lofty station. Cly. Dost thou not love her? ... wretched me ... oh heaven! And dost thou yet so faithfully love me? But can I e'er consent to take from thee Thy lawful spoil? Ah! no; she's thine by right: She has already cost thee too much toil, And too much jeopardy, and too much blood. Aga. What boots it to insinuate, and speak not? Rather disburthen by severe rebukes Thy pent-up bitterness, than thus convey Unutter'd, yet intelligible meanings. If it be such a thought that troubles thee, And in thy heart if jealous phantasies Find a reception, thy inquietudes Are by the roots effectually torn up. Come, consort, come, and be by thine own eyes Persuaded, that Cassandra, in thy palace, Can be alone thy first obedient handmaid.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT THE FIFTH. SCENE THE FIRST. Clytemnestra. Cly. Behold the hour.—Now Agamemnon lies Buried in sleep... And shall he never more Unclose his eye-lids to the cheerful light? This my right hand, the pledge of chaste affection, Pledge of connubial faith, now arms itself His death t'accomplish? ... This I have sworn to do? Yes, too irrevocably sworn: ... Alas! ... Now is the time to consummate my oath .. My feet, my heart, my hands, throughout I tremble: What do I undertake? .. What have I promised? .. Oh! how in me hath all my fortitude At the departure of Ægisthus vanish'd! I see alone th'immense atrocity Of my enormous crime: I see alone The blood-besprinkled spectre of Atrides... Ah what a sight! ... Crimes I impute in vain To thee. Ah! no, thou lovest not Cassandra: Far more than I deserve thou lovest me; And me alone. The smallest crime thou hast not, Except that thou art my husband. Ah Atrides! And shalt thou from the arms of quiet sleep, By me, be hurried to the arms of death? ... Where shall I hide me when the deed is done? ... Oh treason! ... Can I ever hope again For peace? Oh what a horrid life of tears, Of rage, and of remorse? .. How can Ægisthus, In an ensanguined bed, and at the side Of an atrocious, parricidal spouse, Dare to repose? Will he not start to find A murderer there? And tremble for his safety?— Of all my shame, and all my wretchedness, Abominable instrument, far, far From me, thou instrument of death, oh far! My lover I will lose, and lose with him My life: but such a hero shall not fall, Murder'd by me. Thou ornament of Greece, Terror of Asia, live t'enjoy thy fame; For thy beloved children ... and a wife More worthy of thy love.—What do I hear? ... What stealing footsteps? ... Who could venture hither At this dead hour of night? ... Ægisthus? ... Ah! All is then lost! ... SCENE THE SECOND. Ægisthus, Clytemnestra. Ægis. Hast thou perform'd the deed? Cly. Ægisthus ... Ægis. What do I behold? Oh, lady, What dost thou here, dissolved in useless tears? Tears are unprofitable now, and vain, And they may cost us dear. Cly. Thou here? ... but how? Wretch that I am! what have I promised thee? What impious counsel? ... Ægis. Was not thine this counsel? Love gave it thee, and fear recants it.—Now, Since thou art repentant, I am satisfied; Soothed by reflecting that thou art not guilty, I shall at least expire. To thee I said How difficult the enterprize would be; But thou, depending, more than it became thee, On that, which is not in thee, virile courage, Daredst thyself thy own unwarlike hand For such a blow select. May heaven permit, That the mere project of a deed like this, May not be fatal to thee! I by stealth, Protected by the darkness, hither came, And I hope unobserved. I was constrain'd To announce to thee, myself, that now my life Is irrecoverably forfeited To the king's vengeance. ... Cly. What is this I hear? Whence didst thou learn it? Ægis. More than he would wish, Atrides hath discover'd of our love; And I already from him have received A strict command not to depart from Argos. And further, I am summon'd to his presence Soon as to-morrow dawns. Thou art convinced That such a conference to me is death. But fear not; for I will all means contrive To draw the blame entirely on myself. Cly. What do I hear? Atrides knows it all? Ægis. He knows too much. I have but one choice left: It will be best for me to evade by death, By self-inflicted death, this perilous inquest. I save thy honour thus, and free myself From an opprobrious end. I hither came To give thee my last warning, and to take My last farewell... Oh live, and may thy fame Live with thee, unimpeach'd! Pity no more, Whom pity cannot aid: if I'm allow'd By my own hand, for thy sake, to expire, I am supremely blest. Cly. Alas! ... Ægisthus ... What a tumultuary rage I feel Within my bosom, when I hear thee speak! ... And is it true? ... Thy death? ... Ægis. 'Tis more than certain ... Cly. And I am thy murderer! ... Ægis. I desire thy safety. Cly. What beckoning fury from Avernus' shore Accompanies thy steps? Oh, I had died, If I had never seen thee more, of grief; But guiltless I had died: spite of myself, Now, by thy presence, I already am Again impell'd to this tremendous crime... An anguish, an unutterable anguish, Lives in my bones; in every fibre lives. And can it be, that this alone can save thee? But who reveal'd our love? Ægis. To speak of thee, Who, but Electra, to her father, dare? Who, to the monarch, breathe thy name, but she? Thy impious daughter in thy bosom thrusts The fatal sword; and ere she takes thy life Would rob thee of thy honour. Cly. And ought I This to believe? ... Alas! Ægis. Believe it thou On the authority of my sword, if thou Believest it not on mine. Ah, may I die At least in time ... Cly. Oh heaven! what wouldst thou do? Sheathe, I command thee, sheathe that fatal sword. Oh night of horrors! ... hear me ... perhaps Atrides Has not resolved. Ægis. What boots this hesitation? Atrides injured, and Atrides king, Meditates nothing in his haughty mind But blood and vengeance. Certain is my death; Thine is uncertain: but reflect, oh queen, To what thou art destined, if he spare thy life. And were I seen to enter here alone, And at so late an hour ... Alas, what fears Harrow my bosom when I think on thee! Soon will the dawn of day deliver thee From racking doubt: that dawn I ne'er shall see; I am resolved to die. Farewell ... for ever! Cly. Stay, stay ... Thou shalt not die. Ægis. By no man's hand, Assuredly, except my own; or thine, If so thou wilt. Ah, perpetrate the deed; Kill me, and drag me, palpitating yet, Before thy austere judge: my blood will be A glorious acquittance. Cly. Maddening thought! Wretch that I am! ... Shall I be thy assassin? Ægis. Shame on thy hand, that cannot either kill Who most adores thee, or who most detests thee. Mine then must serve. ... Cly. Ah! no. ... Ægis. Dost thou desire Me, or Atrides, dead? Cly. Ah! what a choice! Ægis. Thou art compell'd to chuse. Cly. I inflict death? ... Ægis. Or death receive; when thou hast witness'd mine. Cly. Ah, then the crime is too inevitable! Ægis. The time now presses. Cly. But the courage, ... strength? ... Ægis. Strength, courage, all, will love impart to thee. Cly. Must I then with this trembling hand of mine Plunge ... in my husband's heart ... the sword? Ægis. The blows Thou wilt redouble with a steady hand, In the hard heart of him who slew thy daughter. Cly. Far ... from my hand ... I hurl'd the sword ... in anguish ... Ægis. Behold a sword, and of another temper: The clotted blood-drops of Thyestes' sons Still stiffen on its frame. Do not delay To furbish it once more in th'impious blood Of Atreus; be quick: there now remain But a few moments; go. If awkwardly The blow thou aimest, or if thou should'st be Again repentant, lady, ere thou givest it, Do not thou any more toward these apartments Thy footsteps turn: by my own hands destroy'd, Here would'st thou find me in a sea of blood Immersed. ... Ah go, and tremble not; be bold, Enter, and save us by his death. SCENE THE THIRD. Ægisthus, Agamemnon within. Ægis. Come forth, Thyestes, from profound Avernus; come, Now is the time: within this palace now Display thy horrible shade. A copious banquet Of blood is now prepared for thee, enjoy it: Already o'er the heart of thy foe's son Hangs the suspended sword; now, now he feels it: An impious consort grasps it: it was fitting That she, not I, did this: so much more sweet To thee will be the vengeance, as the crime Is more atrocious. An attentive ear Lend to the dire catastrophe with me; Doubt not she will accomplish it: disdain, Love, terror, to the necessary crime Compel the impious lady. Aga. Traitress! Ah! ... My wife? ... Oh heaven ... I die ... ah trait'rous deed! ... Ægis. Die thou, yes, die. And thou redouble, lady, The blows redouble; all the weapon hide Within his heart; shed, to the latest drop, The blood of that fell miscreant: in our blood He would have bathed his hands. SCENE THE FOURTH. Clytemnestra, Ægisthus. Cly. What have I done? ... Where am I? ... Ægis. Hast thou slain the tyrant? Now At length thou art worthy of me. Cly. See, with blood The dagger drops; ... my hands, my face, my garments, All, all are blood. ... Ah, for a deed like this What vengeance shall be wreak'd? .. I see already, Already to my breast that very sword I see hurl'd back ... and by what hand! .. I freeze .. I faint ... I shudder ... I dissolve with horror! My strength ... my utterance ... fail me ... where am I? ... What have I done? ... Alas! ... Ægis. Tremendous cries Resound on every side throughout the palace: 'Tis time to shew the Argives what I am, And reap the harvest of my long endurance. SCENE THE FIFTH. Electra, Ægisthus, Clytemnestra. Elec. It still remains for thee to murder me, Thou impious, vile assassin of my father... But what do I behold? Oh heaven! my mother? Flagitious lady, dost thou grasp the sword? Did'st thou commit the murder? Ægis. Hold thy peace. Stop not my path thus; quickly I return; Tremble: for now I am the King of Argos. Far more important is it that I kill Orestes, than Electra. SCENE THE SIXTH. Clytemnestra, Electra. Cly. Oh heaven! ... Orestes? ... Ægisthus, now I know thee... Elec. Give it me: Give me that sword. ... Cly. Ægisthus! ... stop ... wilt thou Murder my son? ... First shalt thou murder me. SCENE THE SEVENTH. Electra. Elec. Oh night! ... Oh father! ... Ah, it was your deed, Ye gods, this thought of mine to place Orestes In safety first. Thou wilt not find him, traitor. Ah live, Orestes, live; and I will keep This impious sword for thy adult right hand. The day, I hope, will come, when I in Argos Shall see thee, the avenger of thy father.</field>
   </doc>
</add>