<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Marston, Westland, 1819-1890</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Marston, Westland, 1819-1890</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">marston westland 1819 1890</field>
      <field name="author_text">Marston, Westland, 1819-1890</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1870's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V3.0154.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1876</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460583</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Strathmore ; or, Love and Duty</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Strathmore ; or, Love and Duty</field>
      <field name="title_facet">strathmore or love and duty</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">strathmore or love and duty</field>
      <field name="title_text">Strathmore ; or, Love and Duty</field>
      <field name="year_display">1876</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1876</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1876</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460583&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460583&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Marston, Westland, 1819-1890&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;marston westland 1819 1890&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Strathmore ; or, Love and Duty&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;strathmore or, love and duty&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1876&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1876&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Marston, Westland&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1819&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1890&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Strathmore ; or, Love and Duty&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chatto and Windus&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1876&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872935-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv30154&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Strathmore ; or, Love and Duty&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 164 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted&lt;lb/&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;lb/&gt;Dedication included with Strathmore.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Strathmore.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1849.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 20 Jun 1849.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">STRATHMORE; OR, LOVE AND DUTY. A Tragedy, IN FOUR ACTS.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">These poor fruits of many years are offered to the Memory of one who had the best claim to any tribute of mine.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">First performed at the Theatre Royal, Haymarket, 20th of June 1849. CHARACTERS. Sir Rupert Lorn, a Loyalist, . Mr H. Hughes. Henry Lorn, his son, . . . Mr H. Vandenhoff. Halbert Strathmore, a gentleman of loyal family, . . . . Mr Charles Kean. John Balfour, of Burley, insurgent Covenanter, Mr Rogers. Robert Hamilton, insurgent Covenanter, Mr Stuart. Craigburn, insurgent Covenanter, Mr Holl. Brycefield, an English gentleman of decayed fortunes, in league with the Covenanters, . . . . Mr Howe. Roland, his servant, . . . Mr Buckstone. Allan, servant to Hamilton, . . Mr Coe. Keith, an aged minister, . . Mr Bland. Robert, retainer of Sir Rupert, Mr. Caulfield. Simon, retainer of Sir Rupert, Mr Brindal. Other Retainers, Soldiers, Covenanters. Katharine Lorn, betrothed to Strathmore, . . . . . . Mrs Charles Kean. Isabel Lorn, wife of Henry Lorn, . Miss Reynolds. Janet, her maid, . . . . Mrs Fitzwilliam.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Scene, Scotland. Time, 1679.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. SCENE I. A room in Hamilton's country house, near the mountains. Craigburn, Brycefield, and Hamilton discovered. Bryce. The night is bitter. Ham. Heap the fagots higher, Let's have a glow as fierce as the brave hearts That kindle at the stroke of wrong, to fire! Craig. Was that the tramp of horse? Bryce. No; but the roar Of the swoll'n torrent in the pausing wind. Ham. How long, just Heaven, wilt Thou forbear to smite These sons of Belial? In the book of time No page of bloody tyranny is writ More foul than theirs. Our people hunted down, Put to the sword, or from the cruel rack. Borne to the scaffold! Why? Because they cleave To Scotland's ancient faith, and will not brook The claim of England's Church to bind their souls. Craig. Woe to these wolves of Edom! Double woe To this licentious king, who desolates The sanctuary he swore to spare! Bryce. To spare! Nay, to defend. But what to Charles are oaths? False to his friend as to his land, what boon Requites the wealth my father lost for his? Our home, seized by his foes, Charles repossess'd But not restored. A wanton and a flatterer Divide our fief between them! Ham. Peace, John Brycefield! Too much thou broodest on a private wrong, Too little on a suffering Church. Bryce. My injuries Are warrant for my truth. [A distant report of carbines. Ah! now your ears, That was no brawl of rivers. [Another and nearer volley. There again! Mars, sirs, is up! I've known his strain from boyhood. Ham. Put by this heathenish lingo. Bryce. Heathen names Consort with heathen deeds. The ring of hoofs— They come! Ham. [Drawing.] Then death to him who enters first! Craig. Too hasty, Robert! What are cloaks for? See! [He snatches his cloak, and conceals his sword under it; the rest do the like. Bryce. The tramp grows fainter—now it dies away; They hawk at other quarry. Ham. Footsteps! [A low knocking is heard at door, and twice repeated. Craig. Hist! 'Tis Allan's signal. Quick! unbar the door. [Brycefield opens the door, and admits John Balfour of Burley, and Andrew Keith. Ham. Burley! Bur. The same. Ham. [Giving his hand.] You're welcome, and your comrade— What, Andrew Keith! More outrage! Bur. [To Keith.] Speak thou, pastor, And be thy speech the trumpet which proclaims The pouring forth of vials. Keith. To the vale Our scatter'd children, eager for the food Which more than bread sustains, their footsteps bent; A strain of supplication blent with praise Rose with one voice from hundreds, when a cry Rang from the hills—“The foe!—the oppressor!—hence!” Unarmed, we fled; but malice, swifter far Than love of life, pursued. From throats of fire The deadly missile leapt. Some sank in flight: Others with upraised hands, whose happy souls O'ertook their mounting prayers. Then midst our band Plunged the destroyers. With fierce yells they cried, “The Test, the Test!” The lifted sabre fell On all who spurned that oath; the goodly youth— The old man's prop—dropped from him and expired; The mother's arm, locked round her boy, relaxed, And left the orphan to the orphan's God! Ham. And how escaped you? Keith. Their impetuous haste O'erleaped the spot I stood on, and the thirst Of carnage drove them onwards. When they passed By the ravine, I sought for shelter here, And so encountered Burley. Ham. Have we hearts, And hands, and bear this? Shall no blow be struck To tell the oppressors we are men? Craig. There shall: But yet be wary, learn our strength. How stand we? Bur. Hundreds await my signal, humble folk The most part; but in resolution fixed, By trial bred to patience. Most we need Wealth and high names to aid; and yet I count On Cochrane, Mowbray, Hume, and you methinks [To Hamilton. A convert pledged whose aid outweighs them all. Craig. Whom? Bur. Halbert Strathmore. Craig. Strathmore! are you mad? You never broke this enterprise to him! Ham. I did—why not? Craig. He's of a line whose boast Is fealty to the Stewart—the near friend Of that malignant Rupert Lorn, betrothed Unto his daughter! Ham. Grant this, and then add What Strathmore is himself. I know him best, So best can speak him—generous, firm, and just. Keith. My much-loved pupil While he was yet a child. He still hath been Temperate and mild, and though by birth allied To the oppressors, oft hath curb'd their hate. Bur. What answer made he? Ham. That he needed time And thought for his decision. In deep strife 'Twas plain his spirit travailed. Custom, name, The ties of kindred and of love—that sense Of nearer kin than blood—together leagued Against his struggling conscience. Bryce. Of such war, Too clear the issue. Strathmore will disown us, Perhaps betray. Ham. Betray! You think of Brycefield And speak of Strathmore. [A low knocking, as before. Allan! Hush! [He admits Allan. Your news? Allan. A messenger from Strathmore; he brings letters. [He goes out. Ham. From Strathmore! Did you heed? He has decided: The issue shall condemn, or free me. Come, Our frugal meal is spread; while that recruits Our bodily strength, I trust for news shall fire Our souls with hope and vigour! Keith. Peace prevail If peace consist with duty. [All go out but Brycefield, who lingers behind. Bryce. So, so, friends, 'Tis thus ye guerdon service! Hamilton Distrusts and taunts me; Craigburn just endures; The vengeance that I bear to ingrate Charles Had need be deep, that I should brook these taunts And write my soldier name upon the list Of these fierce bigots. Yet, will I be true For my own ends. Oh, bitter curse when pride Is slave to want, and crawls; but crawls to climb! [He goes out. SCENE II. A spacious apartment in Lorn Castle. Katharine Lorn seated at embroidery; on the opposite side, Isabel. Henry Lorn stands by his wife's chair. Sir Rupert paces the room in thought. Hen. And you knew Grammont? Isa. The dear Count! These eyes Have brightened in his glance, this hand has lain Within his own a good half-hour—don't frown; We danced together at the Court, the dance, That dear cotillon! [Rising as if to practise it.] I've quite lost the step. 'Twas said in London I'd a well-turned foot; It did look fairly in tight amber hose, With sky-blue cloaks. Ah me! I dance not now! And what's the worth of a fine instep here, With no one to admire it but one's husband? London, rare London! Oh, what days, what nights, What dresses, what gallants! Think—Buckingham, Rochester, Robert Sydney, Jermyn, Russell, The peerless Hamilton! Hen. [Laughing.] Add fifty more, And ask if all be worth one husband, Bell; Am I not constant to thee? Isa. Yes, in sooth. Your love's the proper pattern; but one dress Makes not a wardrobe. Hen. Jilt! Isa. I wore my lovers Even as my robes—a change for every mood. To-day I put on scarlet—in a soldier; A courtier—for my purple velvet, next; The third, a skirt of spangles—in a wit. You frown again! nay, love, for common wear There's nought like that drab constancy of thine! You'll not be angry? Hen. Can I, when you smile? Oh, what a vassal is this despot—man, Rul'd by a smile, his sceptre but the sign Of an imperial slave! Isa. That's the true faith Which, prythee Kate, teach Strathmore when you wed. Dost mark me, girl? He has long been a truant, And must be punished. Kath. [Looking up.] Punished! That might make him Still more the truant. Sir Rupert appears at door at back. Isa. Well, you bear it meekly! Kath. Bear what? Isa. His absence, which in other maids Would waken doubt. Kath. Doubt! Do we doubt the sun When he is absent? Know we not he shines, Though unbeheld awhile, and will return In his bright course, to cheer us? So will Strathmore! Sir R. [Coming forward and breaking in.] Heaven grant it, and in time to save his honour! Myself, your brother—all true hearts go forth To serve the king, while only Halbert Strathmore, The royal trumpet sounding in his ear, Forbears a soldier's answer. Hen. Pardon, sir! You judge my friend too harshly. Isa. So I think. Strathmore's of noble lineage, and in him Sedition were more treason to his blood Than to his monarch. Sir R. So it should be. Yet, He shows too fair a front to schism, hints At mediation and redress—redress For this base swarm of canters gendering wrong From their own spleen to charge it on the law! Oh, I'd redress them! Hen. I own Strathmore lenient, But not disloyal. Sir R. What withholds him, then, From us—from me, his father's friend—from her His late betrothed? She is the fairest shoot Of this rude trunk; yet would I rather blight Should canker root and bough, than see one leaf Plucked for a traitor's garland. Isa. Katharine, You love this man; defend him! Kath. You have said I love him. Isa. Well? Kath. That's my defence. I'll not Assert in words the truth on which I've cast The stake of life! I love him, and am silent. Sir R. These doubts torment me. He, brave Strathmore's son! I'll to his house at daybreak, and extort His hidden purpose. Strathmore enters behind, unperceived. I'll be answered; nought Shall serve but yes or no. Speak, Strathmore—thus Will I demand him—friend or foe? true man, Or recreant? You shall not evade me, Strathmore! Strath. [Coming forward.] And did I ever? You'll not take my hand? Sir R. First tell me, can it grasp a sword? Strath. [After a moment's pause.] It can, When duty bids it. Hen. Ah, I said so. [Katharine rushes up to Strathmore. Strath. Wait, Wait, Katharine! I said I never stooped To subterfuge, nor will I. What is duty? Sir R. We owe it first to Heaven; next to the powers Which Heaven ordains on earth. Strath. When these conflict— The earthly with the heavenly—where points duty? Sir R. Serve you the king? Strath. I'd shed my blood to guard him. Sir R. Your father did. Strath. I'd guard his life, but still more guard his justice. When cruel impious men in the king's name, As I believe without his gracious will, Slaughter his subjects for no crime but this, That they would worship Heaven as conscience prompts, I hold him loyal who takes heart to say— “This blot on the king's honour goes no further.” Sir R. Enough, you stand a traitor by my hearth, And yet I draw not! Sir, I cannot pledge This temperance long; the path of safety's there. [Pointing to the door. Strath. He who has dared your anger and her grief Can meet all after-perils. Hen. Strathmore—friend, You are deluded: these mad hypocrites Provoke their fate. The Government exacts No heavy tribute—a mere change of form And ritual in the Church. How little then Submission costs. Strath. It costs no gold, no sweat Of brow, no toil of limb. It costs the man. What is man without conscience? Sir R. Talk no more! Hen. Misguided, lost, farewell for ever! Kath. Stay! [To Sir Rupert.] Will you surrender thus the only son Of your lost friend? Let me plead with him; leave us! You'll not refuse me, Halbert, some brief words, Perhaps our last! [To Sir Rupert.] Oh, by your ancient love, Permit this intercession! Sir R. Be it short. So much I grant his father in the grave: Resolve you soon, I shall return anon. My gallant boy! My precious Isabel! [He leads her out, followed by Henry. Kath. [After a pause, laying her hand on Strathmore's arm.] Halbert, speak to me! You'll not speak, shall I? Strath. Yes, speak. Kath. Then answer; but not rashly, for my doom Is in your breath—you love me? Strath. Katharine! Kath. You do, and know what love is—that it draws Into itself all passion, hope, and thought, The heart of life, to which all currents flow Through every vein of being, which if chill'd The streams are ice for ever? Strath. Even so. Kath. Was this your love for me? Strath. Was it? Kath. It is! Thanks for that dear rebuke. You'll not renounce me? No, I defy you, Strathmore! Strath. Ah! you may; Discords may sever, pathways may divide, 'Midst all God's creatures I may never more Gaze on that unit which could fill for me A vacant world—yourself! And you may learn— I do not think you will, but you may learn— The strain of bitter tongues, reproach or scorn For him who quits you now; but through all change, Time, distance, suffering, shall this tide of love Sweep ebbless to your memory! Kath. Yet you quit me! Love speaks in deeds, not words; you never loved me. Strath. I never loved you, Katharine! Kath. Oh, forgive me! My anguish spoke. Strath. And would there not befall A keener anguish, could the man you loved Prove false to right? [Taking her in his arms.] So, on my shoulder, sweet, The old way yet once more. We know that grief Must try true hearts; but from its fire they're plucked Here or hereafter, and the stamp of God Is set on them for ever. All is well At last for those who do well; nothing well For those who, to be well, would shrink from duty. Kath. From duty? Strath. Katharine, duty. I have seen Men pious, loyal, brave; do I say men? Nay, wives and children perish, gashed by stabs, Or pierced by ball, or drop into the grave A-swoon from the rack's torture, their sole claim To serve in freedom Him who made them free. Could I see this, and know that gallant hearts Were leagued against such wrong, and stifle mine? I struggled, for I loved; but everywhere My conscience tracked me. In the woods the leaves Quivered reproaches; the peaks frowned; the stars Gleamed down in wrath, and life with every tongue Cried, “Man, do right; be worthy of thy world!” I turned in thought to thee; thine eyes of truth Rebuked my swerving spirit, “Man, do right; Be worthy of thy love!” Kath. Delirium Has warped thy reason. Halbert, strive, oh strive Against this madness! It will pass, but think That it may pass too late! Strath. Farewell! Kath. Be silent? I will be heard. Perhaps I might have borne To lose thee; but thou leav'st me for dishonour, And that's past sufferance! Base and traitorous men Must henceforth be thy comrades—shouldst thou fall, I cannot weep a hero! Strath. Katharine! Life rarely knows its heroes. Obloquy, Like dust, defiles the champion; still he strives, And at the grave, the sullied vesture falls From his worn limbs, his memory takes its stand Upon the tomb, and the world shouts—“A Hero!” Re-enter Sir Rupert. Sir R. Have you decided? Kath. [Clinging to Strathmore.] Oh, no—no! Strath. I have. Sweet, we must part! What strength is in the clasp Of these soft arms! I must unwind them, love, These fibres of my heart that bleeds to rend them. There, gently! Take her, sir! Farewell—farewell! [He rushes out; she sinks into Sir Rupert's arms.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. SCENE I. The interior of a hut, in which Brycefield is discovered in his horseman's cloak, asleep. The open door admits a view of the field of battle. A solemn strain of voices in the distance, and occasional acclamations. Enter Roland, Brycefield's servant. Rol. Ho! my good master, Master Brycefield! Faith, He's sound asleep, and well has earned the rest Our sour-faced captains grudge!—It irks my will To rouse him; but then orders! What, your honour! [Waking him. Bryce. [Who springs up and snatches his sword.] Who's there? Rol. A friend! Bryce. You, Roland! Rol. Even myself! Here's Hamilton and Craigburn, sorely pricked— That's pricked in conscience—that you were not seen At the thanksgiving. Bryce. For their victory! What, if I called it mine? But for my brain They could not wag their envious tongues—these churls! Who forced them, who, but I, a soldier bred, To keep their vantage-ground? They else had rushed Into the marsh, and, overwhelmed by Claverhouse, Have choked it with their bodies? By my aid They won their triumph, drove the foremost troops In Scotland from the field, and thus they thank me! Rol. To hear them talk this morning! One would guess They'd king and country under lock. Cried some— “We'll treat with Charles!” Then others—“No, the Kirk Alone shall rule in Britain!” Some were hot To march on Babylon; some to pull down The carved work and the idols; but all swore That Claverhouse should be hung;—that's when they caught him! Bryce. Silence! Was't thou not snatched from the Philistines To be a chosen vessel? Rol. Maybe so. I know I've often been an empty vessel, For our new masters, whew! their diet's thin, And their she vessels—by which I intend The covenanting damsels—are not comely. No, sir; give me the days, the good old days When your brave father rode in arms for Stewart In merry England, when the cup and song Filled up the pause of cannon, and bright eyes Rained blessings on our march! Bryce. Ah! fix my belt. Those times are over. Rol. Not forgotten, sir. A can to those old times! It's ill going forth Without your draught; good wine's the soldier's porridge, And here's your meal-cask. [He produces a flask, fills two drinking-cans, and presents one to Brycefield. Bryce. Varlet! Well the years That chill the blood mature the grape. [Both drink. Rol. And that Thaws the chill blood, and makes us young again, As young as when we sang—how runs it?—so! [Sings. “Here's an arm for my king, and a curse for old Noll, And a smile for all danger that chances;” Fall in, sir! [Both sing. “Here's an arm for my king, and a curse for old Noll, And a smile for all danger that chances; Here's a throat for my glass, and a lip for my lass, And a bright eye to pay back her glances! Merrily! merrily! shall my life pass— Hurrah for my king, and my glass, and my lass!” [They repeat the chorus, “Merrily! merrily!” &amp;c. Rol. Hist! here come no friends to mirth. Bryce. Hamilton, Craigburn, and that recreant, Strathmore! Why do I prate of recreants? Little guessed Our fathers we should wear this livery. Yet, In one point, Strathmore justifies his stock, No coward he! He fought as if the fray Hung on his single arm. Enter Hamilton, Craigburn, and Strathmore. Ham. [To Brycefield.] We've waited for you, Whence rose those sounds of revel? Ill befit Such strains our sober camp. Rol. Just a wee crow, My masters, over Moab! Craig. Hence! begone! Rol. Well, well! Ye're not such pleasant company. [Goes out, muttering the chorus, “Merrily! merrily!” &amp;c. Ham. It is the hour for council. For you, Strathmore, Who helped this great deliverance, and whose post In our victorious ranks we might have known Best by its peril—in acknowledgment Burley has named you captain in our host, Next to himself in power. Strath. Methinks to-day Our Scotland hails her children, that their praise Breaks from her torrent tongues and to the plain Leaps down exulting, that this morning's sun, Rending the mist, pressed on her mountain brow His warmest kiss, for he found Freedom's there— Heaven send with Freedom—Peace! Craig. See, here comes Burley! Enter Burley. Ham. With so dark a brow, When Ammon flies our arm! Bur. It is a race Must be chastised with scorpions. Our main force I lead towards Glasgow; but some choicer few A nearer duty summons. Covenant blood Again hath flowed, and asks a separate vengeance. Craig. Speak! what new horror? Bur. Cruel in their flight, As in their strength, the foe who 'scaped the sword Came on a handful of our people, met By a burnside for worship. Mark, our friends Were met in peace, unarmed; all, all were slaughtered, Save two who bore the tidings, and amongst them Fell Keith, the Pastor! Strath. Andrew Keith!—The good, The venerable man! He was my friend, Preceptor, almost father! In my breast There springs no grain for good, but he did sow it. Bur. What doom pronounce you on his murderer? Strath. A stern one. We are bound to warn these tigers From further havoc. For a deed so foul, Earth's law and heaven's have but one sentence—death. Bur. Thou sayest well; and now, be firm! Whose, think you, Was the fell hate to which that gentle mein, Those silver hairs, appealed in vain for life? Who murdered Andrew Keith? Strath. Why ask of me? Am I the mate of wretches? Bur. No, thy feet Now shun their path of blood; yet, didst thou walk Consenting for a season even with him Who wrought this deed accursed. Strath. His name? Bur. Again, I say, be firm! The hand that slaughter'd Keith Was Rupert Lorn's. Strath. Sir Rupert Lorn's? Bur. I said it. Strath. Man, you profane that name if but in thought You slur it with such charge. You know him not. Sir Rupert is a soldier—no assassin! Bur. He was your friend; you therefore may be blind. Strath. He is my foe; I therefore would be just. Bur. As we would. Though I little doubt his guilt, Strict proof alone shall harm him. Public weal Requires, meanwhile, we seize upon his hold— The hilly towers of Lorn, by nature girt With rare defences; thus, if beaten back, We gain a strong retreat and time for succour. Craig. An enterprise of peril. Bur. No; the castle Is slightly guarded. Its chief strength has marched Under young Lorn to Claverhouse. Sir Rupert Lies, aidless, in his fortress. Ere remanned We must surprise and take it. Craig. Such a post Some few determined men might hold from thousands. Bur. A secret path winds rearward to the heights, And one who knew the route might thereby gain An unsuspected entrance. [All turn their eyes on Strathmore. Ham. [After a pause.] Strathmore! Strath. Speak. Ham. Familiar from your boyhood with this pass, 'Tis you must lead us. Strath. I! Bur. Do we demand More than a leader's duty? Strath. You have said Sir Rupert was my friend! Ham. Have you not sworn To be your country's? Strath. 'Twas my oath—I'll keep it! Give me the van of some most desperate hope, Some breach to force even in the cannon's mouth; Or bid me singly breast the tide of war, With honour beckoning on the further shore, And I will plunge! But do not arm my conscience Against my will, and make my truth to duty A treason to my heart! Craig. [To Burley.] You see his bent. To choose such guidance were to risk our end. Bur. [Apart to him.] Peace! None but he, who knows each separate step, So well can thread the passage. Hamilton, With Brycefield and yourself, shall share his march; So, if he falter, justice rests with you. [To Strathmore.] I grieve to find thee in the snare emeshed Of creature yearnings. Howbeit, we yoke No doubting spirit to this work. You, Craigburn And Hamilton, must undertake the task! If Lorn be guilty of this crime, he dies. Strath. He dies! Bur. Decreed you not his death? Strath. But how, If he prove innocent? Craig. A slender hope. Strath. Why, see! You do prejudge him. In your face I read his doom already. Bur. You have shunned A leader's office; else your hand had borne The scales of judgment here. Craig. A partial hand Should never hold the balance. Strath. [Apart.] It is fixed— The old man's fate! To their impatient eyes Film'd with a brother's blood, all evidence Will take that sanguine colour. He will perish! Bur. Time speeds; I part for Glasgow! You— Strath. Stay, Burley! [Aside.] My presence would ensure him justice; this At least, he claims; for this his child appeals, His Katharine—once my own! Ham. See, he is racked By a sore conflict. Bur. Note him not; he'll yield! Strath. [Still apart.] But say what yet I hold incredible Were true, that Lorn were guilty, and had dyed His soul in stains more crimson than his sword's, Shedding the pastor's life! say this were proved, And I the judge, Heaven's eye upon me, men Exacting righteous sentence, while old love, Plucking my heart-strings, cried for mercy! Bur. [To Craigburn and Hamilton.] Forth With faces set like flints against the slayer; Blood only expiates blood! Craig. We will not fail. Strath. Mad with the thirst of vengeance, faintest hints Will read like damning proof! no arm but mine Can save him innocent; if guilty, why Even that risk of horror for his sake Must be encountered.—Burley, Hamilton, I take my office—I will head this charge. Bur. You'll march on Lorn? Strath. I will. Craig. Ere you resolve— Dare you fulfil this task? Strath. Dare I assume it? See, Brycefield, that our force be straight equipped! We march at noon. Craig. We need the mask of night And will not stir till sunset. Strath. Heed my orders, Brycefield! we march at noon. Your captain wills it. [Strathmore and Brycefield go out. Bur. He's right; delay might give them time for aid. Come, friends. You know your duty should he fail. [They go out. SCENE II. Before Lorn Castle. A terrace with ramparts overlooking an extensive prospect bounded by the hills. Enter Katharine and Isabel meeting. Katharine is passing on without perceiving Isabel, who intercepts her. Isa. No, no, sweet Kate, you are my lawful prize, Won dearly, not to be relinquished soon! These lonely walks and indoor solitudes Fit meditative age; but you are young. Kath. Ay, by the kalendar! Isa. Ill suit such moods With loyal maiden's pride—this grief for him Who in one breath disowned his double oath To you and to his king. For shame—abjure him! Kath. Idolatry abjures not! It despairs. Isa. Tut, tut! despair's a word, a good broad phrase To signify the heartache or weak nerves. All women have it ere they wed. It means That epidemic of young blood called love, And only asks time's lancet for its cure; It takes a thousand shapes! The schoolboy has it At close of holidays; the maiden feels it When her pet pigeon dies! Sometimes it comes As a November fog! Count Grammont had it— And sharply, when his valet brought not home His suit for the Court ball; but—he recovered! [Aside.] Poor Katharine! I know she thinks me heartless, And yet, to humour were to feed her grief. Here comes your father! Enter Sir Rupert. Dear Sir Rupert—smile! Sir R. In times like these, when the king's flag retires Before a horde of rebels! Isa. Your defeat, If such it may be termed, chanced, as you said, From inconsiderate zeal. So strong a post The foe secured. You fought at desperate odds. Sir R. 'Tis a disaster we shall soon retrieve. What can a wild, ungoverned mob effect 'Gainst the trained force of kingdoms? Isa. Well then, smile! Sir R. [Taking her hand.] There, there! Isa. Your lips smiled, not your eyes. Sir R. I know it. A foolish thought distracts me! Long inured To the stern trade of war, I've seen armed men Fall in a heap before me, and then slept Unvexed by conscience; but that aged face I spake of—haunts my sight. I never drew Before on the defenceless! Isa. Not a heart But mourns the old man's fate; but still reflect 'Twas in an act denounced by law— [Hesitates. Sir R. The law Required, at least, that we should warn ere strike. I struck and warned not, and my sword became A knife for shambles. Keith had been my friend, Sat at my board, clasped hand with me. Girl, girl, As I rode thence, I felt as feels a murderer! Isa. [Aside.] How hard to strive with self-reproach when just. Sir R. Stung by defeat, we found them in our path, And ere reflection cooled our boiling rage, It overflowed in fury. Isa. It is done, Repented, and must be forgotten. Sir R. Come; Some other them then! [They walk up the terrace. Kath. Does my father stand Thus self-condemned of cruelty? My kind, My generous father! Who shall vouch for pity. In sterner hearts, or that the cause is just Which casts it out? O Halbert! Were you right? Have those whom—tutored in a loyal faith My heart denounced as traitors, been indeed Ground down by injury? O, were you right? So noble, so discerning, could you arm In a base quarrel? No; it is a thought To soothe my anguish. If thou wert deceived, 'Twas by misconstrued duty. So thy worth Shines through my gloom, and, though for ever gone, Thou art not lost while I can still adore! [She goes out. Sir Rupert and Isabel return to front. Isa. Brave Henry! Worthy of his name and sire My gallant husband! Sir R. Should the royal troops Be duly reinforced, we may expect him The traitors who infest us to dislodge. Our garrison is scanty, and we need Some score stout fellows yet. Isa. These girding hills Are a sure rampart. Sir R. True; we may defy The knaves for weeks, and mock them till they starve. [Shouts are heard, and the bell of the Castle sounds an alarm. What mean those shouts? They ring the alarm! Enter several Retainers. How now! Simon. The castle is surprised. Sir R. Who kept the watch? Robert. Each man was at his post; the enemy Assailed us under cover of the woods. Sir R. The bell is silenced; 'sdeath, they've forced the gates! Ring round me, lads, for honour and your king! Isa. I'll with you. Sir R. No, to Katharine! If I fall Bear her a father's blessing. On, brave hearts! Stone bulwarks yield;—brave hearts are adamant. On, cheerily, Lorn, for the king! [He rushes out, followed by Retainers. Discharge of musketry, and shouts of conflict without. Isa. Heaven speed you! Would I were of them! Yet our Katharine's safety? The clamour's at its height. [A pause.] Now conflict's thunder Mutters itself away; the bolt has fallen. On whom? Dear Katharine! What, beset! As she is going, enter Soldiers, headed by Brycefield. Bryce. [Advancing to her.] Fear not! Sir Rupert, lady, is our prisoner; But his fair daughter—such I deem you are— Needs dread no violence. Isa. We do not dread, sir, The thing we scorn. Bryce. Harsh payment for harsh duty. Isa. Fulfil it without words. Bryce. That you are safe. Accept this proof—our band is led by Strathmore. Isa. By Strathmore! Bryce. Once your father's friend. Isa. Is't true? [He signifies assent. Why then forgive my scorn. Your treason's white Beside his foulness. Bryce. [Aside.] She is wondrous fair! Isa. A something in your mien Denotes you foreign to these boors: you learned not This courtly grace from them. Bryce. [Aside.] By heaven, a wench Of rare discernment! Beauty's presence, lady, Can civilise the savage. Isa. Speech so bland I fain would couple with a name, and yours is— Bryce. One that was honourable till I bore it; My name is Brycefield. Isa. You were ill baptized; That name is writ in loyal annals. Bryce. Ay! And by my father's sword. Isa. If this be so, You bear within more keen reproach than mine. Is't possible? Your escort to the castle! Bryce. Way, there; fall back! I am your beauty's debtor. [She gives him her hand; martial music heard behind; he conducts her out. SCENE III. Corridor in Lorn Castle. A small table, with writing materials, and lighted taper, chair, &amp;c. Enter Hamilton and Craigburn. Ham. Thus far no signs of flinching. By his guidance We've gained the fortress, seized the man of blood, And straight proceed to trial. Craig. Yet I fear, Lest creature pity should in Strathmore's heart O'ermaster duty. It devolves on him, As chief in rank, to be the prisoner's judge. Ham. Let's to him. Craig. And remember, if he fail, We must assume his office. Lorn must die. [Hamilton and Craigburn go out. Enter Roland, followed hastily by Janet. Janet. Not that way, Master, Master—what's your name? Rol. [Clasping his hands with a Puritanical air.] In the flesh, Roland: and thy name, young damsel? Janet. [Imitating him.] In the flesh, Janet. If a saint like you Can e'er feel hunger, there's good beef and ale Waiting your pleasure. Rol. I've no creature wants. Janet. [Aside.] Now must I ply him as my mistress bade. [Aloud.] I prythee come; I find such benefit In devout company; and grant one favour. There are, 'midst Strathmore's followers, some brave hearts My mistress knew of old, and fain would speak with. Rol. She'll bring me into trouble. Hence, avoid thee! See'st thou not I'm a vessel? [Aside.] Of a surety The damsel's comely. Janet. Nay, thou'lt not refuse? Rol. [Aside.] I fear the carnal man is strong within me. Lo, I will testify! Thou shalt no more Entice me with thine eyes, which are a snare. Janet. I will not. Rol. Nor entice me with thy lips, Which are a net. Janet. I say I will not. Rol. Neither Shalt thou gaze in my face unlawfully; Nor take my hand thus. [Taking her hand. Janet. You surprise me. Rol. No; Nor, worst of all— Janet. [Struggling.] I will not, sir— Rol. Do this. [Kisses her. Janet. [Breaking away.] Shame! shame! you have forgot you are a vessel. [Janet goes out. Rol. Faith, I half like the jade; and little like The work that brings me here. I saw the old man Torn from his children's arms. I fear the worst. Enter Brycefield. Bryce. This is a sorry business. Rol. Sorry, sir; It takes away all relish for my food. 'Twill break my sleep. Think of the old knight's daughters. Bryce. [Musing.] So fair, 'tis strange that neither yet are wed. Rol. There's Lady Isabel. What eyes! Their flash Half blinds you, till a hazy sorrow comes To let one see their brightness. Then her voice! 'Tis the proud sad smile speaking. Time has been You would have risked your life for her least whisper. Bryce. What say you, rogue? Rol. That she's a helpless woman, And you a soldier. Bryce. [Aside.] Does he read my thought? I have drunk in her beauty till it floods Each vein and pulse. To call her mine—to grasp At once both love and fortune—'twere a prize Indeed for the spurned beggared cavalier! She comes! Withdraw, sir. Rol. Hey, they're winsome dears! [Roland goes out. Enter Isabel and Katharine; the latter sits apart absorbed. Isa. How, Master Brycefield! We entreat a boon. Bryce. You grant one if you grant the right to serve you. Isa. [Aside.] I like not those smooth tones. My sister, too. Bryce. [Bowing low.] Lady, she is your sister. Isa. [Aside.] There again! I took him for a friend; but ours, I fear, Must be a game of wits; we'll say, a game At chess. Bryce. [Aside, catching her last words.] A game at chess! What does she mean? Isa. You have the ordering of Sir Rupert's guard. Our prayer is this—that you set over him Strathmore's own followers. They're of better nurture Than their rude comrades, and at least will show Sorrow, respect. Bryce. 'Tis done. Isa. [Aside.] So the game opens. That's move the first. Bryce. Your next command? Isa. Request— That privately you send for and admit Sir Rupert's chaplain. The good man dwells near. [Shows a letter. Bryce. That letter's for him? Isa. Read it. Bryce. If you insist. [Reads, then aside.] No danger. This concealment Is against my captain's orders; but— Isa. Well, friend? Bryce. [Significantly.] I obey yours. Isa. I thank you. Shall I seal The letter? [She takes it to the lighted taper, and, watching him narrowly, drops the seal—a ring.] The seal's fallen. Bryce. Madam! [He stoops for the seal. Isa. [Aside.] Now, To drop these lines in. [She takes from her bosom a note, and places it in the letter, which she quickly folds. Brycefield rises and gives her the seal.] Sir, I trouble you. [Aside.] He has not seen it. Move the second! Bryce. Trouble! And to your friend! Isa. [Sealing the letter, and giving it to him.] Who saved my father's life Were more than friend—a brother! Bryce. That's a joy Beyond my hope. And yet, I would outwear My brain in plots, my knee in prayers to Strathmore, If that might save Sir Rupert. Meanwhile, duties— In which I rank your interest chief—demand me. [Offers his hand. Isa. [After a pause, giving him her hand.] Farewell! I will not thank your zeal with words. Bryce. [Who bows and retires, aside.] No! not with words, bright siren, save they pledge A richer payment; not thy gifts, but thee. [He goes out. Isa. [To Katharine.] He deems your father mine, and, as I think, Suspects not I am married; these thick gems Have hid so well the slender marriage pledge. It might be well to fix him in his error, I see his selfish game. Had he been worthy, I'd trusted all with him; being false, I'll use him. I stoop but for your father. Kath. Ah, my father! Isa. Laments are vain. When danger threats, they hinder; Should the worst chance, yourself must plead with Strath- And when it bursts, avail not. Katharine, more! Kath. Nay, not that name! Isa. Remember, though you loathe him, He holds your father's life. Kath. My father! Strathmore! My sense drifts helpless on this tide of horror! Loathe him! loathe Strathmore! Why? He's here, you say; Why came he? Isa. Well you know—with bloody men In league against your father. Kath. To destroy him? Isa. Why ask? Kath. And Strathmore was his friend? Isa. His friend! Kath. And knew their purpose, yet he came! Isa. To aid it. Kath. Wait—wait! Ha, ha! The blackness bursts, 'tis day! Isa. What mean you? Kath. That he came, a friend with foes, Knowing their hate to curb it. He is here To save my father! Loathe thee, loathe thee, Halbert! I trust and bless thee. Isa. This is madness! Kath. No, Tis reason's safeguard, the last hold it grasps; Uproot it, and I perish. In, dear sister, Wait but this hour's event! Isa. Alas! Kath. Remonstrance But kills where it would save. Come, come, let's in. [They go out. SCENE IV. A room in Lorn Castle, as in Act I. The apartment arranged for the trial of Sir Rupert. An antique elbow-chair is placed near the front. Strathmore alone, and seated. Strath. There was no way but this. My comrades bent To find him guilty, thirsting for revenge, His fate was certain. Either I must judge, If guilty doom him; or, to 'scape that pang, A dastard, yield him to their blind tribunal And murder by my silence. Could he slay The meek and pious Keith? O friend beloved, First fosterer of my thought! as thou didst stand On Time's far brink, and Death forbore to snatch thee, Was he than Death less pitying? This foul charge He can refute—he will! If—that if wrongs him. Enter Hamilton and Craigburn. Ham. Already here! you're prompt in your commission. Strath. Justice delayed is half denied. Ham. Most true. The guilt that's late avenged is almost sanctioned. Craig. Strathmore, be warned and hear me! If you hope Disproof of crime will free the prisoner And make your office light, your hope is vain. Most clear and certain evidence convicts him. Strath. Am I judge here? Craig. You know it. Strath. Then, if judge, I take no counsel with the accuser while The accused is absent. Ham. Mark, our people cry For vengeance on the murderer; if withheld, Thou wilt provoke revolt, and stab the cause Which thou hast sworn to guard. Craig. If I but thought He dared to tamper with his trust, I'd— [Approaches Strathmore menacingly. Strath. [Stamping twice.] Ho, there! The door opens. Enter Brycefield; Soldiers are discovered in waiting. [To Brycefield.] Your guard's in waiting? I may need you, sir. Craigburn, you stand too near—fall back. [To Brycefield as Craigburn obeys.] Not now. Bryce. The prisoner, Sir Rupert, waits without. Strath. [After a pause.] Conduct him hither. [Brycefield goes out. Apart.] Oh, the time is sudden; Sustain me, Heaven; let proof like thine own beams Shine on his innocence; for sake of him I thought to call a father, for her sake I dare not name, scarce think of, hear me, hear me! Ham. They come; prepare! [Strathmore motions them to the table, and sits. Enter Sir Rupert, preceded by Guards; Brycefield walking by his side; a number of the Covenanting Soldiers follow, uttering menacing exclamations, and line either side of the apartment. Sol. Justice! we will have justice! Death to the murderer! Ham. Peace! Strath. Sir Rupert Lorn! Sir R. [Aside.] It is the face in which I once read honour. Still frank, no covert glance, no craven bend. Thou forgery on nature! Strath. Pray you, sit! Sir R. In your illustrious presence and your colleagues'? My modesty forbids! What would you with me? Strath. The chance of these stern times, when savage power Tramples on life and freedom, makes us foes, Not to yourself, but wrong which you abet. That wrong to curb, we have possessed your castle, And held you in restraint. No penalty Harsher than this impends, if you confute, As I must hope you will, a crime so black Your name denies it credence! You are charged That, not in heat of war or private feud, By you and yours, unarmed and simple men, In exercise devout, were foully slain. No warning given, no order to disperse— A right which even your cruel laws demand— And, chief, that by your hand fell Andrew Keith, The gracious shepherd of this ravaged fold! What answer make you? [Sir Rupert regards him in stern silence. Craig. He is dumb. Strath. Produce Your evidence. Sir R. Hold there. [To Hamilton and Craigburn.] I speak Not to this man—perjured to king, name, friend, Whose baseness Heaven permits that men may know, And loathe a traitor;—but to your more human And moderate infamies. Hear this! I mourned,— A sickly fool!—because his locks were white, The death of Andrew Keith; but now, beholding The pestilent harvest of his seed, rejoice, Both that I mowed the ear and slew the sower. The deed was mine,—I slew him! Ham. He avows it! Craig. Justice! Sol. Ay, justice! we'll have justice! Strath. Who Calls upon justice, and with clamour wakes Her sacred halls, that should be hushed as heaven, Ere doom's dread book be opened? Peace!—Sir Rupert, If, guiltless of this crime, it be avowed In hasty scorn, or from security, Since I have been your friend—reflect, recant! My heart is frozen—and it cannot beat; My memory stifled—and it cannot plead; I am a pen in the great hand of Conscience, To write its bidding merely! Sir R. [To Hamilton and Craigburn.] Pray interpret Me to your master. Tell him that we rate Gifts by the givers; that could he give me life, I would not own it, branded by his pity! Bryce. Pshaw, pshaw, you rave! Sir R. Place me upon the heath, My good sword in my gripe! The deed I've done I'll do again, and grind beneath my heel This brood of canting priests and armed revolt! Sol. His sentence! Quick, his sentence! Ham. By his own lips Is he condemned. For further proof we hold This letter, written by the prisoner, And found upon his servant. 'Tis addressed Unto that man of wrath, Ralph Malcolm! Listen! [Reads.] “These, good friends, shall bring you to know that I have been entrapped by a gang of Puritan traitors. If you can give the alarm, and send help, well. Once free, on the faith of a loyal man, I will show the knaves no mercy. I will hunt them down, whether they bear sword or psalter, by the hearth or in the field, in conventicle or by the hill-side.—Yours in the king's cause—Rupert Lorn.” [Gives letter to Strathmore. Sol. Vengeance! Tear him to pieces! Judgment! Sentence! Bryce. Sheer lunacy! You would not heed a maniac; Try fasting and the dungeon. Ham. Ay! and wait Until some rescue, mightier than our stop, Loose him to carnage. We are weak; our foes Are strong, and may redeem him. Strathmore, think; 'Tis not alone the life that he has quenched, But those his cruel purpose yearns to strike, That claim his death? If they through him expire, Thy voice that frees him—murders them! Then, stand Between this black soul and thy brethren's lives, And tell us which shall perish! Sol. Justice! Death! Strath. That shout again! [To Sir Rupert.] List to that shout, old man! I hear it and I live; but do not check it! Who dares? Who stays the planets or arrests The wheels of destiny? They roll, they roll! [He rises and comes forward. Ham. [To Craigburn.] He's rapt as in a trance. [To Strathmore.] What hear'st thou, brother? Strath. [To Sir R.] The cry of thy great sin, performed and purposed, Has entered heaven, and space reverberates Thy doom in thunder! Murder's doom is death! Craig. [To Sir Rupert.] Thy sentence! [To Strathmore.] And it's hour? Ham. He does not heed thee. Remove the prisoner. Thy farewell take Of earth to-day! Thou diest on the morrow! [Sir Rupert goes out guarded, followed by Brycefield and Soldiers. Strathmore remains standing in abstraction. Ham. [To Strathmore.] My friend! my brother! Craig. Pray you, speak not to him. Leave him to silence. Ham. Oh, this sacrifice Outweighed a thousand lives; my friend! my friend! [Hamilton and Craigburn go out. Strath. Where am I? Is this earth, or has the world Swerved from its path in terror, and recoiled To the first chaos? Is yon light the sun? Are those green hills? And is yon roar that swells, And sinks and swells, the sea? That's the oak roof; A slanting sunbeam strikes it. I stand here, Alone; yet do not turn, lest fearful shapes Should give the lie to sense. Alone! ah, see, That old man stalks before me! Speak? I'll answer. He's dumb. And now from the quick-breeding air There looms another form—dark, stern—my father's! He points to him, and asks me for his friend! And 'twixt the two there glides a cold face, blanched With a child's agony! Katharine, away! I cannot bear those eyes! [Rallying himself.] Nay, gaze! I'll front them.— Dim spectres of the living and the dead Cite me, impeach me! As I then shall answer, When Heaven waits breathless, and its shining ranks Fix me at once with their demanding eyes, I answer now. Truth has no choice: it must Be true or not be! Duty claimed my heart; I plucked it forth and gave! . . . . Ah, now ye fade— I am alone—alone with fate and heaven! [He stands motionless. The curtain slowly descends.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. SCENE I. Ante-room in Lorn Castle, opening on terrace. Brycefield and Roland discovered. Bryce. I' faith, rare wine. Rol. You're merry, sir. Bryce. Such juice, Drunk in Elysium, would make nectar cheap And all the gods forswear it. Rol. Ah! you laugh; You could not if you thought that brave Sir Rupert Would die to-morrow. Bryce. Humph! Rol. [Significantly.] You head the watch. Bryce. How, sirrah? Rol. For his children, for the sake Of Lady Isabel, whose grateful smiles Hail you as her deliverer, you will save him? Bryce. Humph! Is that sure? Rol. Why did you bid her hope? Bryce. Concerns that you? For my own ends. Rol. A brave man, Who sees a woman's grief, can have no ends— None of his own, I mean—he acts for her. Bryce. Away, sir! Rol. [Aside.] No; he cannot be a man, And deaf to grief like hers. [He goes out. Bryce. So for her sake, I shall corrupt the watch. By my connivance, Nay, special aid, Sir Rupert shall escape— That's if none scent the plot, while for my thanks There's gratitude, a curtsey, and good morrow! Not so. Her spells have charmed me—the proud carriage And quick eye battling with reverse, the smile That breeze-like ripples her still face, and flits 'Twixt love and scorn, her hand, whose lingering touch Can make its farewell kinder than its clasp! She must be mine! Yet if she spurn me—me, Though kindly born a thriftless outcast now?— No, no, her father's life at stake, she dares not. Enter Isabel, looking cautiously round. Isa. My friend, preserver! Bryce. 'Tis a title, lady, As yet unearned. Isa. But gratitude and faith Forestall thy deed, and pay it in intent. Bryce. [Aside.] There, gratitude! You're liberal, but not prudent. Intents are known by acts; intents may change— Mere vanes to winds of humour! Isa. Good intents Are fixed like goodness: you did give me hope That by your means Sir Rupert should be free— A bless'd intent! Bryce. Still, a mere vane! Isa. Where points it? Bryce. To summer, if the wind be southerly. Isa. Southerly? Bryce. Ay; what brings the South Wind, lady? Isa. Pray tell me! Bryce. Warmth and odour! Her soft arms Twine round the vigorous Spring, a perfume steals Upon him from her locks, her glowing breath Fires his cold cheek with blushes, while she weaves A chain of garlands round him, and he sinks Before her feet—a slave! Isa. 'Tis a deep riddle. I pray you solve it. Bryce. Be thy love this wind To my bleak life, which then shall teem with acts Obedient to thy will. Bright Isabel, I love thee, and would wed thee! Isa. Wed me, sirrah!— [Restraining herself. How if my hand were pledged? Bryce. Had it been given, Ay, to a husband, he should lose his clasp. Consent—your father's free. Isa. If I refuse? Bryce. Why, then, the wind sets northerly; I'm ice! I've solved the meaning of your words to-day, You'd play a game at chess! 'Tis my move now. Isa. [With indignation, immediately repressed.] Oh, thou— Bryce. Nay, speak it, madam! Isa. Oh, thou soldier! [With assumed laughter. Which fit thee best, thy tactics or thy valour? Bryce. Make me thy soldier, and with those ripe lips Seal my commission. Even now I've dared Much peril for you, tampering with the guard. Come, we rough soldiers capture hearts like forts— By storm! Isa. Sir, for the credit of the fort, I'd make a show of conflict. Grant me time! Bryce. Have you so much to spare. But be it so; In an hour I will return. I do but deal By the world's commerce, lady. All men fix Their price on service. For my own, I ask Yourself, your hand. If you deny me, say Why I should venture aught for her that scorns me. [He goes out. Isa. Ay! scorns thee, wretch, the more that terror choked Scorn's utterance! But that I did control My struggling heart, he had betrayed our hope— Our hope on such conditions? There's no hope. Stay—Katharine! She must at once to Strathmore! Heaven aid the wrestling of a child's despair. [Goes out. Enter Roland and Janet. Rol. Poor lady, in what haste she went! Janet. What grief! Thy master bears himself unkindly to her. Rol. [Musing.] It may be so. Janet. It may be so! Where is thy wit to help? You say you love me; where's the proof of love? Rol. What can I do? Sir Rupert's too well guarded. Janet. Entice the guard away. Rol. Impossible! 'Twere death to quit their post. Janet. I'll drug their drink. Rol. They dare not drink on duty. Janet. Be valiant, then. Provide my master's men With swords, and use thine own. Rol. My master's men Would use their carbines, then. I should be shot. Janet. Well, I should weep for thee. Rol. I should not see thee. Janet. Jest on; I was mistaken; you've no heart. Rol. Exactly so. Janet. The brave knight will be murdered, My ladies—orphans! What is that to thee? Thou'lt sleep as soundly. Rol. Mistress, you have ta'en My very measure. Janet. Thou'lt be rid of me. What matters that? There'll still be ale and beef, And thou'lt be merry with the cup and trencher. Why talk to thee of courage, love, or glory? Rol. Thou hast it; yes, thou hast it; I am just The thing thou say'st I am. Oh, shame on me, To let the light lash of thy tongue draw tears! [Wiping his eyes. Janet. Forgive me, Roland! Rol. Set me some plain task. Talk not to me of glory. Say but this— An old man's life in danger; two young hearts, Just breaking for his sake, implore your help; Show me the way to save them—any way That's likely, possible—and though the odds Be such as risk my neck, I'll take that way, Vile trencherman as I am! Janet. I see too well, However brave, thou canst do little here. Yet grant the boon I asked before. Conduct My mistress, in disguise, to Strathmore's followers, Sir Rupert's guard. Rol. And what will that avail? Janet. Nothing, I fear; but still, 'tis her desire. Rol. I'll manage it, this hour. Janet. You have a heart. Forgive me! Rol. And have you a heart? Janet. [Archly.] Ah, Roland! [They go out hand in hand. SCENE II. Spacious room as before. An armed Soldier waits with despatches. Enter Hamilton and Craigburn. Craig. Comes Strathmore hither? Ham. Yes, you see despatches Await him from the camp. Craig. Has he yet eyes To spell the text of war with, or does grief For yon malignant, who to-morrow dies, Blind his friend's sight? Ham. Shame, shame, thou ruthless man! No vain laments express his mighty woe; But a calm reigns, like the immovable heavens When they look down on earthquake. Peace, he comes! Enter Strathmore. Despatches wait you, sir, from Burley. Sol. [Presenting despatches to Strathmore.] Ay, From godly Burley. Strath. [In a low level tone, and with passionless dignity.] Hold you ready then For prompt return. No, stay, you're worn with travel. Bid young Moncrieff with some six more to horse, Then ask my orders here. [Soldier goes out, Strathmore sits and reads despatches. Craig. What's Burley's news? Strath. He wishes reinforcements. Craig. And should have them straightway. Ham. Can you grant them? Strath. No; Our slender force would weigh but as a grain In the great balance, and would nothing stead him, While foes would seize on these deserted walls, And our retreat spread panic through our friends. Ham. 'Tis well resolved. Strath. [Writing.] Are yet those stores arrived Of corn and cattle? Ham. Not yet. Strath. Hasten them. Ham. I will betimes to-morrow, sir. Strath. [Dropping the pen, and sitting motionless.] Tomorrow! Ham. I know what that dread morrow brings; yet think Even had you wavered, you could not have saved him; The attempt had roused rebellion through our band. Your truth as man, your oath as judge, your duty As chief enforced, and Heaven ordained his death. Strath. [Rising.] Then leave it, friend, to Heaven to grant the strength For that which Heaven ordains. [He again writes; beckons to Soldier who has re-entered; seals and gives him despatch. Straight to the camp! [Soldier goes out. Enter Roland. Rol. [To Strathmore.] Your pardon, noble sir! [Sees Hamilton—he hesitates.] I bear a message. Ham. Speak it! Rol. 'Tis only for your captain's ear. Craig. A mystery! Strath. Friend, your business? Rol. Nay, sir; 'Tis with yourself in private. Craig. [To Hamilton.] Marked you that? Strath. Declare your errand to these gentlemen. Rol. [Reluctantly.] The Lady Katharine would see your honour. Strath. See me! Craig. It cannot be: go. Rol. Friend, I'll take Your answers when I ask them. [To Strathmore.] Sir, she pleads Most weighty reasons. Craig. Are you gone? Rol. Such reasons As touch her father's life! Strath. Say you, his life? Rol. [Doggedly.] 'Twas thus she charged me—say, by Strathmore's oath, As upright judge, as he would 'scape the curse Of needless blood, I claim to speak with him Alone, and instantly. Strath. [To Craigburn.] You hear! Craig. Again I do deny her suit. What afterproof Can clear the self-condemned? Strath. We know not that Until we know the proof. What if her father Vaunted in rage an uncommitted deed, Or hid its provocation? Craig. Do you hope it? Strath. I dare not; but as little dare refuse The right to prove it. We must meet alone. Ham. Alone? Strath. It is her will. Craig. Her will! Strath. Then mine. [To Roland.] Say that I wait the Lady Katharine. [Roland goes out. Ham. [Aside.] Is he true? The waves of Ashdod poison those of Canaan Whene'er they mingle. [To Craigburn.] Fear not, we'll observe him; Ere night I will compel him change the watch. [Hamilton and Craigburn go out. Strath. [Alone, dropping into a chair.] See her! . . . See Katharine! . . . Katharine! . . . That name Comes to my ear as though I long had passed Into the realm of souls, and caught, perplexed, A sound once dear on earth. . . . Katharine! . . . A face Gleams on me as through mist—brows wide and white 'Neath rippling auburn; eyes like springs, that hint Love's soundless depths! . . . Speak, speak! . . . do I not hear That voice which was thy heart made audible Answering to mine—to mine, as when we stood Last by the scutcheon'd gate while tremulous love Broke through the hush as through the dusk—the star! Again, good night! we clasp, part, linger still. Now she glides homeward; but her low farewell Sums all the unseen sweetness of her face, And follows me in blessing. Ay, 'tis she, My joy incarnate, self of self, love, life. Katharine, my Katharine! [He pauses, overwhelmed with emotion, then suddenly restrains himself.] What if she should come, And find me thus swept down by this wild flood Of bursting grief, and from that sight draw hope, When hope there's none, and I should so delude her! [Starting up.] Freeze, freeze, ye naked heavens, and keep me stone— For her sake, freeze! Re-enter Roland, followed by Katharine. Kath. Retire! [Roland goes out. 'Tis he—he moves not, speaks not! [Advancing to him] Strathmore! Strath. What would you with me, lady? Kath. Is it thus That Halbert speaks to Katharine? Strath. Hush! those names Belong to a past world. Kath. False! there's no past To fates so knit as ours. Thou may'st stab love, But not love's ever-haunting ghost, remembrance. Strath. Your errand? Kath. I'm a child: my father's life Hangs on your breath. My errand! Strath. Hark! yon sea; You hear it break? Kath. Ay, on a rock. Strath. A rock That shivers it and dashes it to spray. Still the tide flows; 'tis ocean's law. So man Obeys his law—the conscience. Though it drive On ruin, he obeys. Kath. On ruin! Ay, You feel it such. You'd save my father; but Your comrades hem you round and force your hand— Your shrinking hand—to strike. It is not Strathmore Who with a double murder stabs the sire, And, through the sire, the child! Strath. No, 'tis not Strathmore. You look on Justice. Kath. [Softening.] Halbert, no; thou still Art human. Human woe has ploughed thy cheek; Thine eyes crave human tears. Before them glides A dream of our past love—perchance that sunset When on thy breast I leaned and took thy ring— The ring which pledged us! [Showing a ring which she wears.] Ah! thou know'st it—start, And feel thou art a man! Strath. [Involuntarily.] I am, I am! Kath. Then save my father. Strath. Can I? Kath. Yes! Strath. Oh, cruel to ask that question of thee. Kath. Yes! Strath. Mistake not— His innocence must save him. Dared I dream That thou couldst prove it—that his pride belied him When he avowed the crime; or that, withstood, He smote but in defence—aught that disproves Or can excuse the deed—how would I clasp Thy feet in transport! Not the cry, “A sail!” To gasping swimmers; not the shout, “Reprieve!” When gleams the axe; not the wife's sudden face, From far-off home, beside the dying exile— Oh, I but mock my joy, comparing it! Give earth a new bliss, give my dead hope life, By one word—“Innocent!” Speak, if thou canst. Kath. Why you have spoken. Since you will his life, Effect your will. Strath. Your evidence? Kath. 'Tis here. You were almost his son. Strath. Your evidence? Kath. [Desperately.] I have none! Wilt thou save him? There are means Which yet you guess not—we can balk the hounds Even at their spring. Defer Sir Rupert's fate A week—nay, grant three days; ere then my brother— Strath. Ah! Kath. Now you guess. My brother may return Head of a force with which your scanty band Must cope in vain. As you would spare their blood, Preserve this secret. Strath. That the enemy May find us unprepared? Kath. Your followers few—ill-armed, undisciplined— Must perish in the conflict. But submit, No hair of theirs shall suffer! 'tis my oath. Strath. [Aside.] Another moment, and I'm lost! Right, conscience, Like lapsing earth, slip from me! Ere three days The foe may be upon us! even to-night! The storm may gather while we dream of safety, And wake us with its bolt! Scouts, scouts, forthwith On every road, bid others watch the coast, And each man sleep in arms! Ho, Hamilton! Craigburn! [He rushes towards the door. Kath. [Intercepting him.] You shall not pass! Strath. I must! Kath. My arms are frail; They cannot bar thee! Canst thou pass these eyes Once lit by thine? Strath. I pass! Kath. [Still confronting him.] Thou canst not; Nature Revolts against the deed! Thy feet are fixed To the detaining earth; thy face is stone; A cry peals from these shuddering walls to pierce The vault of Time; and, lo, the shrouded years Leap from their graves! [Grasping his arm.] Here, by the old man's side, Thy boyish steps have pattered; by yon hearth He held thee at his knee—his playful hand Entangled in thy hair—and stooped his ear To catch thy prattle! Dost thou still advance? Then over me! Look, by that chair we knelt To plight our troth before him, while his voice— A soldier's voice, weak with the weight of love— Faltered his blessing! Come, be bold! Fulfil Thy work! Stand on my father's hearth, and there, There where he blessed us, speak his doom! [Dragging him to the hearth. Strath. [Breaking from her.] Craigburn! [He extends his hands towards the door, and falls senseless.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT IV. SCENE I. Ante-room in Lorn Castle, opening upon terrace as in Act III. Moonlight. Enter Isabel and Roland. Isa. How shall I thank thee—how repay this debt? Rol. With one of your kind smiles. Isa. And Janet's love; Is it not so? Though generous hearts like thine Find in themselves reward. Yet, if Heaven help me, Thy lot shall match thy worth. Now to my sister, And bid her join me. Rol. Straight. [Going.] Stay, I'd forgot. In our discourse this letter. [Gives it. Isa. Ah, for me? Rol. One, whom I think his peasant's garb disguised, Gave it me at the gate. His suit was urgent That it should reach you. Isa. [Aside, opening letter.] From my husband! 'Tis precious news, my Henry comes. Speed, speed! Rol. Madam, your sister! [Roland goes out. Enter Katharine. Isa. Well, your face tells all. You sued to Strathmore, and in vain! Kath. He swooned In anguish at my feet—his frame a reed, But, oh! his honour—rock! Isa. His honour, girl! Kath. 'Tis not for minds like ours to judge of Strathmore. Isa. You love him! Kath. Peace, I say! You speak to one Frenzied by grief! Isa. There may be hope. Kath. Hope! Isa. Ay! Strathmore's dependants form Sir Rupert's guard— Men whom your father did of old befriend. I've seen them, thanks to Roland, moved their hearts By memories of past kindness. Let but Henry Appear before the walls, my life on't, these Go over to his banner! Kath. O my brother! If he could guess our strait! Isa. He does, and waits But to collect his force;—here's tidings from him. See, by the date, with those in his command, He should be here already! Kath. If he fail! Ah me! an inner voice knells in my heart. My brother vanquished—where's my father's life? Victorious—where is Strathmore's? Not a wind But drives me on the rock: Isa. Your gloom infects me. Forth upon the terrace; There watch you; 'tis a balmy night. Nay, sweet, I'll have it so, for I must plan alone. [She leads Katharine to the terrace, and returns. To gain delay. How best to compass that? Who comes? Brycefield, the caitiff who would trade With a wrung heart! Must I dissemble yet? Enter Brycefield. Bryce. Rebuke me not, fair sorceress, with a frown, That I o'erstaid my time. Isa. Sir, I most freely Forgive your absence. Bryce. [Approaching her.] Scorner! I must woo Those lips to seal my bliss, must hear them pledge The prize my own for which I venture life— Your hand, your love! Isa. But love, sir, has its duties, And these ask time to learn. Bryce. No need of time To teach thee how to love. Isa. Oh, it needs much To love you after your desert! So brave, So stamped with honour are you, modesty, Summing your riches, is abashed to claim them. Bryce. What! do you trifle, lady—do you mock My flag of amity? Then I hoist war's! If that fond siege be war which would subdue Only to cherish thee. I know your wiles— That you have practised on my guard! A word Of that—suspicion roused—your father's fate Waits not for dawn: he dies this hour! Isa. O heartless— Bryce. Madam, the game at chess grows critical. I move again. Isa. [Aside.] On what a brink I stand! [She moves to terrace and returns. Fly, Henry, fly! [With feigned gaiety.] So you play boldly, sir. Bryce. You dally with me, while each moment lost Doubles our risk. I have provided all For instant flight. Be thou but kind, the bolt Falls from Sir Rupert's dungeon! In his name I seize that beauteous hand! Isa. [Turning to the terrace.] How looks the night? Bryce. Sweet, 'tis a night for love! Isa. The moon doth wear Her full-orbed crown, and through a special court Of stars, moves queenlike. [Intently gazing from the terrace. Bryce. Turn thee to the earth, Thy glance makes brighter! gaze not at the stars! Isa. Of old, men read their fate there. I seek mine. Bryce. What dost thou ask them? Isa. If it be my lot To find a husband. Bryce. And with one accord They answer— Isa. Hush! [Aside.] Methought I heard a sound. [A pause. 'Tis but the far sea flowing. Bryce. Are the skies Dumb, or thou blind? Thou canst not read their speech! Isa. Canst thou? Bryce. Plainly; why, look! love's radiant star— Bright Venus—laughs reply; and all the spheres Around her echo—Thou shalt find a husband! Say they not so? Isa. [With sudden transport.] They do—they do! Bryce. [Sinking on his knee.] Behold him! Isa. Up, up, and give him welcome! See, he comes First in a tide of plumes! a thousand swords Flash in his wake! He will requite your love, Doubt not! Katharine rushes in. Kath. 'Tis Henry—my brother! [Martial music heard in the distance. Bryce. How! Isa. My husband! Bryce. Husband! Isa. Summoned by you. That letter to the chaplain, By you despatched, contained another scroll! 'Twas superscribed, “To Henry Lorn; ride, ride For life!”—he's here. I won on you to change Sir Rupert's guard, and you unwittingly Placed friends for gaolers. The game's won—checkmate! Bryce. I like thy spirit, wench! but I have yet A pawn to move perchance may queen the board; The game's not over. Tremble if I win. [Rushes out by the terrace. Kath. He may devise some evil to my father! Isa. Well thought of, girl! Let's seek out honest Roland. Fear not! the guard are ours. Kath. Quick, to Sir Rupert! [They go out. SCENE II. Spacious room in Lorn Castle, as before. Enter Hamilton and Craigburn. Craig. I tell thee, I mistrust him! He gave audience To the malignant's daughter; yea, we found him, When she went forth, prone on the very ground! Thence, being raised, there struggled through his speech Vague hints of coming rescue. [Artillery heard without, repeatedly. Ham. 'Gainst which he had provided. See, he comes. That head erect, and frank eye, speak no traitor! Enter Strathmore, his sword drawn. Strath. Forth, brothers, forth! the foe is at the gates! Craig. Is there no foe within the walls? Strath. What mean you? Enter Brycefield. Bryce. Revolt and treason! Your dependants, Strathmore, Throw off the yoke of fealty, and join hands With the invaders! Terror strikes the rest. Ham. Have you betrayed us? Craig. Answer, at what price Is Israel sold to Edom? Strath. Craigburn! [Restraining himself.] No, 'Tis not for thee at such an hour to move me. Think of our cause! Ham. Your cause? Strath. Have we not staked Name, home, love, life—the sum of all our being— On freedom's ransom? Craig. Heed him not, retreat! Retreat, I say! As yet the rearward path Lies open. Strath. Quit your ground of vantage? No, Forth with me to the ramparts! Those who doubt Shall trust again, and our live torch of honour Rekindle those in ashes, till the walls Blaze with one glory! Ham. He says well. Craig. Beware! Strath. Alone I'll meet them! Bryce. I'm your mate. Ham. Nay, follow. [All go out. Alarums. Isa. [Without.] Forth to the fray! Then to me with your tidings. Enter Isabel. Still they contend. Would that the fight were o'er, And Henry safe. A lull! ah, many a wreck That sanguine tide shall leave upon the strand! Enter Roland. What news? Rol. Brave news. They yield! Isa. Who yield? the rebels? Rol. Panic has seized them, and your husband's troops Force easy passage. Brave Sir Rupert's free! Isa. Where is my sister? Rol. At her father's side. By her command I brought her where he is. [Hurried steps and voices heard without. Isa. The tramp of hurrying steps. That voice! Rol. Sir Rupert's! Isa. My husband with him! Enter Henry Lorn, Sir Rupert, and Katharine leaning on her father. Roland goes out. Hen. Isabel! Isa. My hero! [They embrace.] Dear Sir Rupert! [Taking his hand. Sir R. So, lass! my brave boy's succour has postponed Your heritage awhile. But for that aid, Another sun had seen him Lord of Lorn! How went it with the knaves? Hen. Some few were slain, Some taken; but their leaders, by the steeps Where horsemen might not follow, have escaped— Save one I shrink to name. Isa. Strathmore! Hen. Yes, wounded. Our force had beat him down: he must have perished But for my rescue. Sir R. Though he merits death, Yet am I glad he fell not by our sword. Hen. Alas! his doom is but delayed. Fierce Dalzell, Who, under Monmouth, through a bloody field Has chased the rebels, hither hastes his march. He will demand the prisoners at our hands. Kath. My father! Hen. Dalzell bears a heart of flint That ne'er knew pity; I have heard him name Strathmore with those whose doom, when seized, is death— Without reprieve or trial. Kath. Do you hear? Sir R. My child! I would not cloud this day with grief, Nor can thy father stoop to base revenge. Yet, mark! I will not shield persisting treason. If Halbert Strathmore formally subscribe Such recantation of his guilt as I Will forthwith frame, and, to atone it, pledge A loyal future, by our tried allegiance I will beseech his life. I think even Dalzell Will grant that boon to service proved like ours. But heed me, Katharine, if Strathmore spurn These terms of mercy, though he were my son, I would not waste a breath! Hen. His party crushed, Persistence now were madness. Kath. One more boon— That your conditions I may bear to Strathmore. Sir R. Be it so, girl! He may prove obdurate. Remember, though, this meeting is your last. You parley with the rebel, not the friend! Come! I'll prepare the bond. Kath. I'll follow you. [Sir Rupert, Henry, and Isabel go out. Rebel! what means that word? Fear for my father Has blinded me to truth: now I see all! Right trampled on—pure conscience counted crime— And hatred banqueting on good men's groans! My brother owned it! And the man who beards This wrong's a rebel! Sure, the courts of heaven Are peopled with the outcasts of this world! My Halbert! Oh, he will reject these terms! I dare not think on that. One last farewell— One prayer to save him ends my dream of life! [She goes out. Enter Strathmore, wounded, supported by Roland. Rol. Lean on me, sir; lean on me! You are faint, I saw you struck. Your wound needs rest and quiet. Strath. [Sitting.] Good friend, I feel it not! Rol. So sharp a hurt Asks better surgery than you afford. Strath. Dalzell, you say, comes hither? Rol. Ay, sir! Strath. Then Each captive's fate is sealed. Beseech Sir Rupert To give me audience. [Aside.] My offence being chief, My death should free the rest. Rol. I'll do your bidding. [He goes out. Strath. Could I save the rest, I'd know no other care! My soul breathes freely— Leaving all with God. As through half-open gates Of Death's grim arch, I catch the fields of day. Yet, Katharine! there earth's fond, last weakness clings. To her my name must be a thought to shrink from. I shall not have a tomb in that fair realm Where I had once a home. Enter Katharine, with a paper. [Rising.] Has my heart's cry To look on thee been heard? Kath. We meet once more— To part for ever! Strath. With a faltering voice You say it—not in hatred! Kath. Hatred! [Looking mournfully in his face.] Oh, how fierce Has been thy struggle! Strath. Can you feel That I have struggled? Kath. Nobly! Yes, I know it. Strath. You know it, and absolve me! You will bear To think upon my memory! Kath. Thy memory! While I can bear to think. Strath. I did not hope For this. I shall die smiling! Kath. Die! thou shalt not! My father and my brother, who have served The royal cause so well, will plead with Dalzell. Sign but this scroll! [Gives it to him. Strath. [Feebly, after perusing it.] Ah! know'st thou what conditions The bond demands? Kath. I do. Strath. That I confess My treason, and abjure it, never more Further my righteous cause by tongue or sword, In act become a traitor—to escape A traitor's sentence! Kath. But your cause is crushed! Strath. Crushed! No, it triumphs still. Though freedom's hosts Bleach the green earth with death, that cause is safe That has its Chief above? Kath. You will not sign? Strath. And canst thou ask me? Kath. Ay, while I have breath. Who gave thee right to quench my life in thine? Though we must part, 'tis comfort still to think One world contains us. I should curse the sun If it could light a world that held not thee! Strath. My Katharine! Kath. 'Twas you upheld my steps When we were children. On the hill-side flowers The golden gorse, from which you plucked the thorn That else had harmed me. In the brook still float Lilies like those we wove. Another spring Will find them there—but thou! [Falling on his neck. Strath. My truth! my truth! Kath. I will not let thee go. Ere see thee perish, I'll burst all ties of duty, dare all shame, Renounce all kindred! They are gone! Be thou Friend, father, brother, home, and universe! Strath. Forbear, forbear! [Sinks into chair. Kath. Whate'er I know or feel Of good, you taught me. You relent; you'll sign? Strath. [Feebly, but with increasing energy as he proceeds.] You shall decide. [She kneels by his side.] Two paths before me lie, The one through death to honour— Kath. Halbert! Strath. Nay, There are but two! First, say we choose the nobler— Then wilt thou think of Strathmore as of one Who, by his last act, fitly sealed a life He would bequeath thee spotless. Kath. Ah, bequeath! And I shall never see thee more! Strath. [Pointing upwards.] Yes, Katharine! Kath. The other path? Strath. It leads to life through shame. Wouldst have me take it—live to own no bond But with dishonour; when I catch the tale Of heroes, vainly groan—“Such once I was!” And when the coward's shudder—“Such I am!” Kath. This gloom will melt in a bright future. Strath. No; He has no future who betrays his past. Kath. Still live! Strath. To give the lie To my true youth; find every stream of joy, When I would drink, reflect my branded brow, And so recoil; shrink, when thy straining breast Throbs to a traitor's; read in those dear eyes The temptress, not the wife! Kath. Cease, Halbert! cease! Strath. [Rising.] Speak, shall I sign? Kath. [Starting to her feet.] No—die! Strath. [Embracing her.] My wife! my Katharine! we are one for ever. Kath. Teach Fate that truth, that we may die together. Strath. Fount of my peace! my own! Kath. I am at rest. How is it with thee? Strath. Sweet, sharp care has mined The bulwarks of my life, and thy great sea Of love doth overflow it! Enter Henry Lorn, Sir Rupert, and Isabel. Hen. Where's the confession? Dalzell comes; your judge! Kath. Help, Henry! Hen. Strathmore! [Supporting him as he sinks. Kath. You are come too late! Strath. No, love is ne'er too late. Harry! old playmate! Is that Sir Rupert? Hen. Speak to him! Sir R. A night Deepens upon his face. Halbert, this hour Blots all our rancours, and I but behold Thy father in thee! Strath. We're at peace—all, all! I pray you to deal gently with my brethren. Isa. Lean on my bosom, sister! Kath. No; 'tis well! Strath. Where art thou, Katharine? [She kneels, and places her hand in his.] So—I turn my life To the bright East, where all its beauty rose, And sleep beneath its beam—we do not part! [Dies. Isabel and Sir Rupert advance as if to remove Katharine, who motions them away. Kath. I am his now—I am his own in death! [She falls prostrate on the body. END OF STRATHMORE.</field>
   </doc>
</add>