<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Munday, Anthony, 1553-1633</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Munday, Anthony, 1553-1633</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">munday anthony 1553 1633</field>
      <field name="author_text">Munday, Anthony, 1553-1633</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1920's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V1.0640.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1923</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:459346</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">John a Kent &amp;amp; John a Cumber</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">John a Kent &amp; John a Cumber</field>
      <field name="title_facet">john a kent &amp; john a cumber</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">john a kent john a cumber</field>
      <field name="title_text">John a Kent &amp; John a Cumber</field>
      <field name="year_display">1923</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1923</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1923</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459346&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459346&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Munday, Anthony, 1553-1633&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;munday anthony 1553 1633&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;John a Kent &amp;amp; John a Cumber&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;john a kent &amp;amp; john a cumber&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1923&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1923&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Munday, Anthony&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1553&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1633&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;John a Kent &amp;amp; John a Cumber&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Oxford&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University Press&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1923&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3871904-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv10640&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 20th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;20th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;John a Kent &amp;amp; John a Cumber&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 146 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries, introductory and editorial Matter omitted.&lt;lb/&gt;Source text incomplete&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Copyright (c) 1923 The Malone Society. This text may not be reproduced, except for fair dealing purposes, without the express permission of Chadwyck-Healey and the copyright holder.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: John a Kent and John a Cumber.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: History.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1851.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 1587–1590 ?&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Square brackets represent sections of text which have been deleted or added at different stages in the evolution of the manuscript.&lt;lb/&gt;Angle brackets represent sections of text unclear in the original and supplied by the current editor.&lt;lb/&gt;Source text incomplete&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Book of John a Kent &amp; John a Cumber</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Act«u» Scena i Enter Sir Griffin Meriddock of Sowales, &amp; Ieffreyow S. Griffin. Powesse, in vayne perswadste thou patience, In vayne thou dream'ste of lykely remedies, In vayne thou«e»lst of this or that conceit. winde breath«e»woordes, are vayner then the winde, Only our wepons must effect our weale. Powesse As hitherto my Lord I haue entreatred, So for a whyle, I pray ye be aduisde. S. Griffin. Aduisde? why what aduise can Powesse yeeld? Is not Sidanen with the Earles consent, and Prince Llwellens graunt, affyed to Moorton? Powesse. yea, so Pembrooke hath their graunt for Marian: But. S. Griffin. But what? Euen while we thus stand wasting idle woordes, Pembrook and Moorton shall possesse our looues. Our looues exclaime against our cowardise, Our cowardise to our eternal shame, In England wales &amp; Scotland shall be sung, by euery iygging mate, our foes among. Powesse. Nor English, welshe or Scottish shall reprooue, Lord Ieffrey Powesse with base cowardise. As much (Prince Griffin) as the proudest dare dares Powesse for his Marians libertie. yet not with rashnes or vnbrideled heat, discretion must be vsde, the cause is great. S. Griffin. Great cause indeed, when fayre Sidanens eyes, dimde with the sourse of her continuall teares, mixing those teares amongst the mournefull ynck, That writ the cause of her lament and mine, seemes in this paper weeping to intreat: And then no meruayle though the cause be great he shewes letter Powesse. But greater cause, our countreyes cause I meane, If we should manage «a»rmes, as you still vrge, And so by force, from noble Chesters Courte, agaynst his will, fetche our well-willing looues; we may be held as traytours to the King, that durst inuade his townes in time of peace. S. Griffin. To see how Powesse casts beyond the Moone, As if the King would deale in these affayres. Or if he did, ist like his Maiestie, would suffer fathers by compelling awe: to force their children from their soules affect? Powesse. But if his highnesse subiects should be slayne, as in rough rescue it must needes fall out, he will not haue the meanest guiltlesse dye: but blood for blood shall duely be repayde. S. Griffin. Then Powesse, least such daunger should betyde: you are content the Ladyes shall be lost? Powesse. Not so Prince Griffin, then I would haue stayd, and not haue come so neere to Chesters Courte. S. Griffin. Bir Lady Sir, and we are much the neere. we two belyke, by your complotting wit, shall front the Earle of Chester in his Courte, And spight of Chesters strong inhabitants, Thorow west chester, meekely in our handes, lead my Sidanen and your Marian, while bothe our Riualles, and their following trayne, Sheeplyke stand shiuering at our wrathfull lookes. Beshrewe me, but ye haue a passing head, All natrall are your reasons, full of sence. Powesse. If we obtayne them, youle leaue iesting t«h»en S. Griffin. yea that I will. But can ye tell me whe? Enter Sr. Gosselin denvyle, Sr. Euan Griff, and I«?» Gosselen what «??????????????» ord haue company, «t»rust will purge your melancholly. welcom Gentlemen, you seeme no lesse, be not offended at my salutations, that bid ye stand, before I say God speed. ffor in playne tearmes, speed what your speed may be, Such coyne you haue, bothe must and shall with me. S. Griffin. How now Lord Ieffrey? what companion haue we heere? he seemes some theefe. Iohn. No theefe Sir, but an honest bon companion. Nere drawe your weapons, rather trust your feete, And yet ye cannot hence, but at my pleasure. what needes all this? yeeld, if I bid ye yeeld. Powesse. Thou shouldst be Iohn a Kent, thou art so peremptorie, for Iohn a Kent is a bolde merry knaue. Iohn Tis happie then he is no very knaue. I am the man, what say ye to Iohn a Kent? Powesse I am Ieffrey Lord Powesse, thy maisters freend, And this Sr. Griffin Meriddock, Prince of Southwales. Iohn. why then I knowe ye bothe, and welcome bothe, Mr. these are the guests you looke for, whom had I not well gest at, they had for welcome got a cudgelling. Gosselen. welcome my Lord, and welcome noble Prince. Powesse. Thankes good Sr. Gosselen denvyle, and Sr. Euan Griffin, I trust the men you promisde me are readie. Gosselen. ffor my parte, seuen score bowemen, wight and tall, haue I lodgde in the woode, nere to the riuer of dee. Euan. And I threescore as strong, with hookes and billes, that to three hundred will not turne their backs. Powesse. But can ye tell vs any newes from Chester? Iohn. Colde newes for you my Lordes, there is at Chester, The Earle of Pembrooke, and the Scottish Moorton, the one shall haue Llwellens fayre Sidanen, the other Marian, good olde Chesters daughter. and bothe these weddings finished to morrowe. Griffin. No more of that my freend, thou sleyst me wt h these newe. hearst thou this Powesse? this did I foredoome: now all your wise deuises come too late. Gosselen Content ye good my Lord, no whit too late, heere is a lad on whom we doo relye, for slye conueyaunce of the Ladyes hither, full of conceit he is, and deeply seene, «i»n secret artes, to woork for your auayle. . Griffin. Canst thou my freend, from foorth the vaultes beneathe, call vp the ghostes of those long since deceast? Or from the vpper region of the ayre: fetche swift wingde spirits to effect thy will? Iohn. Can you my Lord, and you, and you, and you, goe to the venson, for your suppers drest: and afterward goe lay ye downe to rest? Powesse how then sweet Iohn? all this thou knowest we can, and what thou canst we haue no doubt at all: but what thou wilt, that gladly would we learne. Iohn. I will to morrow bring you Marian, and you Prince Griffin your beloou'de Sidanen. will this content ye? S. Griffin As all the world cannot content me more. Iohn. why then I pray ye be content to goe, And frollick cheerely, for it shall be so Gosselen. I warrant ye my Lords, come let vs in. exeunt. Ihn. So, they must banquet, I vnto my busines. But let me muse a little on this looue, full of many feares, so sundry ioyes, now hence, now hither diuersly distract, «????????????????????????» But Iohn a Kent what talkest thou rather minde thou the pleasing ioyese. And since so good a subiect they present, vppon these loouers practise thou thy wit. help, hinder, giue, take back, turne, ouerturne, deceiue, bestowe, breed pleasure, discontent. yet comickly conclude, like Iohn a Kent. exit. Enter at one doore Ranulphe Earle of Chester, Oswen his son«n» young Amery Lord Mortaigue, wt h them the Countesse, her daught Marian, and fayre Sidanen. At another doore enter the Earles Pembrooke, Moorton and their trayne. Moorton. All health be to the noble Earle of Chester, his Countesse and these honorable Ladyes, whom one by one I humbly gratulate, wishing to them their happy hartes content. Pemb. The Lyke dooth Pembrook to this goodly trayne. Chester. Earle Moorton, and my noble Lord of Pembrooke, whose presence bringes contentment to my soule and adds true honor to your noble names: for hauing kept your vowes inuiolate, how you are welcome, woordes shall not explaine, but such as best beseemes your entertaine. [your father Madame, will be heere this night,] [Or early in the morning, well I wot,] [ffor such prouision hath he sent before,] [as shewes him selfe will not be farre behinde.] And sith it is our auncient Englishe guyse, the Bridegroomes should vppon the wedding day, come from some distant place to fetche their Brydes, my house at [S[illeg.]ey] Plessye is for you preparde. Thence to the Castell shall [ye] you walke along And at St Iohns shall be sollemnized, the nuptialles of your honors, and these virgens. ffor to that Churche, Edgar, once Englands King, was by eight Kinges, conquerd by him in warres: rowed royally on St. Iohn Baptist day. In memory of which pompe, the Earles our auncestours, haue to that Churche beene noble benefactours. Moorton Eight Kings rowe one? that was great pompe indeed. Pemb. One of them was of Scotland, as I read, the Irishe, and the dane two more besyde, and fiue of Brittayne, all subdued by him. To see that Church will greatly ioy my minde, because I there a greater ioy shall fynde. Moorton. why lookes Sidanen sad? why sighes she so? Sidanen Pardon my Lord, such thinges you may not knowe. Moorton She not mislykes her choyse I hope of me. Sidanen No God forbid. although you are not he. /asyde. Moorton. why then looke cheerly, as Sidanen should, Sidanen. I doo my Lord. And better if I could. asyde. Pemb. Madame, the Scottish Lord hath got a gracious looke, but Pembrooke is not halfe so happy yet. Oswen. Sister, you wrong the noble Earle with frownes Amery My Lord content ye, women fayne dislyke, where their affections beare the higest regard. Marian You are too young my Lord, to iudge so soundly, Amery I finde it writ by them that iudgde profoundly Marian Bookes may beguyle ye. Oswen. My Lord, that cut came roundly. Pemb. Your sadnes tell, if I may knowe the cause, Marian. Me thinkes my Lord the custome is too hard, when loouers meet, so suddenly to parte, Pemb. To morrowes ioy will end that bitter smart, Marian To see ye no more, how would it ease my hart? /asyde Chester well noble Lordes, for this time break we of, Sonne and Lord Amery, you will be their guyde. Oswen. yea my good Lord, then goe we Gentlemen. exeunt. Countesse Sida &amp; «Ma», d Cossen, now we are alone, Let treat to knowe the secret cause, that mooues these passions more then ouerpensiue, which were not wunt in you to woorke such chaunge. If in my power to councell, or preuent, there rest a meane, let me but knowe your mindes, and what I may shall surely be effected, to either of your longing harts, content. Sydanan. Madame, your tender care and kinde affect, assures Sidanen of your honors faith. In breefe my noble Aunte, this is the cause, why poore Sydanen is disconsolate, That she must leaue her countrey and her kinne, and passe to Scotland with the Earle of Moorton. Countesse Cossen, his kindnesse soone will calme this greefe, and therfore cast these cares behinde thy back. But what olde man is this comes toward vs? Enter Iohn a Kent like an aged Hermit Iohn. Ladyes, if crooked age, and homely weedes, breed not contempt, vouchsafe I humbly pray, your charitable comfort to sustayne, a little longer these spent withred limbes, that numbde through chilnesse of my frost-bit blood, which six score winters hath resisted stormes, and iust so many times the summers heate. Now quaking lyke the winde-blowen bough for strength, witnesse that all thinges yeeld to time at length. Countesse. how much I greeue that these thy siluer hayres, should in extreamest age feele taste of want, And this thy furrowed face, with teares distaynd, shall well appeare: ffor thou shalt in wt h vs. These feeble limbes with age so ouerworne, shall fynde repose, and not be left forlorne. Marian. ffather, receiue this little gifte of me. giue him somewha«t» Sydanen. And heere olde man, take this to comfort thee. Iohn. As [may] many blessings light vppon you three, as cares and crosses haue befalne to me. But much I feare, if arte may iudge aright some ill is toward these twayne this present night. Sydanen what sayst thou father? art thou a man of skill? Iohn. Lady, in youth I studyed hidden artes, and proffited in Chiromancye much, «I»f sight be not obscurde through natures weaknesse, I can, for once I could discourse by fauour, and rules of palmistrie ensuing chaunces. Marian Good ffather tell my fortune if thou canst. Sydanen Nay mine I pray thee first, I askte thee first. Iohn. Striue not fayre Ladyes, shewe me bothe your handes for your complexions seeme to be alyke. Nay let me see, bothe your affections are alyke. he sees their handes Blush not, but tell me, are ye not bothe betrothde, to two great Lordes, without your parents knowledge? Countesse They are betrothde indeed, but with their parents knowledge, and bothe to morrow must be maryed. Iohn. Now God forbid, woes me to thinke theron. Countesse. why father? I pray thee speake Iohn. Good Madame pardon me, let me be gon, and leaue the God of heauen to woorke his will /he offers to depart Sydanen Nay stay good father, I pray thee tell the wurst. Marian My hart dooth throb, sweet father then resolue vs. Iohn Sith you compell me Ladyes, I will speak, and what I say, beleeue it on your liues. If ere the Sun to morrowe cheere the earth, you washe not at Saint winifrides fayre spring, your lilly handes, and list the holy voyce, which will resolue ye of your looues sweet choyse: I may not say what shall ye bothe betyde, but harder fortune nere befell fayre Bryde. Countesse. Alas the spring is three myles hence at least and now thou seest the night approcheth on Iohn. Let not the distaunce hinder them to goe, least they and you wishe that ye had doone so. Countesse. ffather, I haue some reason to beleeue thee, by what I must keep secret to my selfe, And but my Lord condemnes these auncient rules, religiously obserued in these partes: I would craue leaue for them to trauell thither, for many haue misdoone that did it not. Sydanen rather then hard mishap should vs befall, twere good we were acquainted therwithall. Marian. Good mother, this fayre euening let vs goe, weele come agayne before my father knowe. Countesse well, goe ye shall, and I along with ye, had we some trusty freend to be our guyde. Iohn Ladyes, although my limbes be not so strong, my bones neere marrowlesse, bloodlesse my veynes: yet vse hath made me perfect in the way. And if your honors deigne so olde a guyde: So speed my soule as shall to you betyde. Countesse. None better. But what houre of night is best? Iohn. when twise two houres the daughters of the night, haue driuen their Eban chariot thorow the ayre, and with their duskie winges breathde calmie rest, vppon the eyeliddes of eche liuing thing: The siluer shyning horned lamp dooth rise, by whose cleere light we may discerne the pathe, wherin though lamely now I seeme to plod yet will I guyde ye safely to the spring. And for your c?ming at the back gate wayte, till when Gods benison protect ye all. Coutesse. well father, we will come, vppon mine honor. Sydanen. The houre is one at midnight, fayle vs not. exeunt. Iohn ffayle ye? infaith that were a sillie iest, Our sporte would fayle, if I should fayle mine houre But husht, heere comes my hotspurre, &amp; Lord Powesse he pulles his beard Enter Sr. Griffin, and Lord Powesse. S. Griffin. See Powesse, heers Iohn a Kent, dect in a Pilgrimes weede Powesse. why how now Iohn? turnd greene to ffryers gray? Iohn what madnes makes ye come so farre this way? The town's beset, our purpose is descryde and now I see your c?ming made all spyde. S. Griffin help vs to scape vnto thy maisters caue. yet ere we goe, tell me, sawest thou Sydanen Iohn. I sawe her: but you shall neuer see her more. S. Griffin. why so sweet Iohn? what? is Sydanen dead? Iohn No. S. Griffin Is she fled? Iohn No. S. Griffin Is Moorton and Sydanen maryed? Iohn. Neither. S. Griffin. wherefore then shall not I agayne beholde her? Iohn. Because your honor is too full of heate, and by your rashnes will discouer all, wherfore shift as ye can, for I will leaue ye. Powesse. Nay I pray thee Iohn, tell vs the trueth of all. Iohn. The troth is, if ye meane to meete the Ladyes Blde, and goe along where I shall lead ye, And as I shall appoynt, so followe my directions. S. Griffin But will they come? Iohn They will, if you will goe. S. Griffin. But how? Iohn. why on their feet, I knowe no other way. S. Griffin. But when? Iohn. Nay then we shall be troubled, when? how? where? Powesse. I pray thee tell vs Iohn without delay. Iohn. Content ye Lordes, Ile tell ye on the way, come let vs goe. Sr. Griffin Iohn, Ile renowne thee, if it fall out so. exeunt. Enter Turnop wt h his crewe of Clownes, &amp; a Minstrell. Turnop. Nay neuer talke of it, Hugh the Sexten stutters, let him read the first lyne, or see if he can say the speeche, that dawes our Churchwarden made in prayse of his Mill horsse. Hugh It makes no matter, I think my selfe the wisest because I am Sexten, and being Sexten, I will say the speeche I made my selfe. Tom tabrer heare ye Hugh, be not so forward, take a little vise of your minstrell. Omnes. And well sayd Thomas Tabrer, you haue scression, speak on. Tom. One of the wisest of vs must speak, and either [he] it must be Hugh or Turnop. Now, Hugh is Sexten, an office of retoritie I tell ye. Turnop. yea, thats when he is in the Belfrie, not else. Omnes. Hugh Hugh, Hugh shall speak the speache to the Lordes. Tom. But Turnop beeing my Lordes man, his hogheard, his familiaritie seruaunt, he in my minde is not only fit, but also accessary for the ration making, then Turnop say I. Omnes. Turnop, Turnop, weele haue none but Turnop. Turnop. well, for your wisedomes, in chusing me, I rest quoniam dig nitatis vestrum primarion, as the Poet Pediculus sayth, at the next vestrie, bound to deferre ye to seuerall locall places. Spurling. how now Hugh? are ye put downe infaith? Hugh. Thats because he has a little more learning, an«d» has borrowe the vshers olde coat to grace him selfe withall Tom O, take heed of learning while ye liue, it is a gandly matter. Turnop. ffrater meum amantissime Hugo the Belringer, the hebrew epitheton Barra cans, as much to say, no man can barre his chaunce, perswadeth you to remit, or submit or admit your selfe, to the crye of your bretheren. How say ye then fellow mates in armes, in this our showe, who shalbe the speaker? Omnes. Turnop Turnop, weele haue none but Turnop. Turnop. Then let vs set forward, for now it is vppon the Lordes coming. Thomas, firk it with your fiddle. Spurling, you play the Moore, vaunce vp your Tun, and Robert, holde your porrenger right, least you spill the conceit, for heere they come. Enter Pembrook, Moorton, Oswen, Amery, to them this crew marching, one drest lik a Moore, wt h a Tun painted with yellow oker, another with a Porrenger full of water an a pen in it, Turnop speaketh the Oration. Turnop. Lyke to the Cedar in the loftie Sea, or milke white mast vppon the humble mount: So hearing that your honors came this way, Of our rare wittes we came to giue account. ffor when as princes passe through pettie townes they must be welcomd, least they tearme vs clownes. Our presents precious, first the golden Tunne, borne by that monstrous Murrian black a Moore, Mortonus Earlus in thy prayse is doone. This shining brook hemd in with this fierce shoare That hath Is peerelesse Penbrook, if I roue not «w»yd«e» As for the two last rymes, right woorshipfull, «an»d m wise, by the error of the Authour ouerslipped, is th mothie Turnop the Oratour newly corrected, to wit This princely pen vp prauncing by the sydes, And so we wishe ye bothe two blessed brydes. Oswen. My Lordes, my fathers tennants after their homely guise, welcome ye with their countrey merriment, How bad so ere, yet must ye needes accept it. Pemb. Else Oswen were we very much to blame, thankes gentle freendes, heere drinke this for my sake Moorton. And this [of] for me, c?mending your great paynes, which in more liberall sorte we will requite. Amery May it please ye Lordes to walk into the Castell and there at full weele see their other sportes. Pemb. with all my hart, goe, we will followe ye. exeunt Lordes. Turnop. Before you goe, in name of all this trayne Turnop accepts your golde, and thankes you for your payne. Thomas, lead the vawward with your easement, you with our hiperbolicall deuises, martche in the middest. And if the Lordes will see vs make them merry, ere we will want deuis«e» weele make them weary, marche on. exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Actus secundus. Scena Prima. Enter at one doore Iohn a Kent, hermit lyke, as before, at anoth«e» enter the Countesse, Sydanen and Marian Iohn. Promise is kept, the Laydes are come foorth, the ambush readie that shall soone surprize them. See Madame; I am readie to attend ye. Countesse. Gramercyes father, lead thou on the way, and giue good councell to my sweet young Cossen. Iohn. Madame I warrant ye sheele take none bad. Sydanen &amp; h conferre. Marian. Or good or bad, she taketh all from me. Madame, would you vouchsafe me so much fauour: as she, so I would gladly talke wt h him. Coutesse. Let them alone, ye shall haue time enough. Sydan«en». Nay forward father, let me heare the rest. Iohn. Then Madame, to omit all ambages, I knowe it, for mine Arte assureth me, you are contracted to the South wales Prince: and wronging him, you wrong your selfe much more. Sydanen. ffor Gods sake softly, least the Countesse heare. True hast thou sayd, but by my fathers graunt, The Earle of Moorton must Sydanen wed. Iohn. Thats as Sydanen will, as I suppose Sydanen will I, or nill I, all is one to him, he is a Prince, and he hath promisde it. Iohn. you are a Princesse, and haue promisde no. Sydanen. Earle Moorton with my father is in fauour, and hath his woord, that I shalbe his wife. Iohn. But hath he yours? Sydanen. Neuer in all my Life. Iohn. I knowe not Lady how the world is chaungde. when I was young they wooed the daughter first, and then the father, when they had her graunt, which could they get, why so, if not, why then, her woord was woorth the meeting where and when. Countesse why how now daughter? why drawe you so neere? Marian. She talkes too long, and somewhat would I heare. Countesse. Byde you with me, till she haue made an end Marian. Pray God this talke to our desyre may tend. Iohn. But would you goe with him, if he were heere? Sydanen would I desyre to be accounted chaste? reuerenst for virtue, as for natrall giftes? wou«d» I aske strength for these my feeble limbes, if some fierce Tiger had me in pursuite? would I shun feare? would I require content? or wishe the endlesse happines of heauen? If these I would, then that as much I would. for what is fame, health, ioy, or ought to me, except with him that giues them all to me? Iohn. Madame enough, is Marian of your minde? Sydanen. yea father. She to Powesse, I to Prince Griffin writ, but when no answere either could receiue, resoluedly thus we set downe our rest. To morrowe when the nuptiall feast is past, And that the Bridegroomes doo expect their Brydes: A strong confection bothe we haue preparde, of deadly Aconite wt h them to drinke. Besydes, a letter drawen, to shewe the cause, why so reuendgefully we sought their deathes, and so despairingly lost our owne liues. This made vs bothe holde thee in such regarde, when thou foretoldste of daungers to ensue. Iohn. This resolution dooth renowne ye bothe, but your fayre starres affoordes ye better fortune. And for my woordes may yeeld but dallying hope, see what is doone in twinckling of an eye. /winde his horn Enter denvyle, Griff. Powesse, [Euan,] and trayne Those Lordes for whom you twayne would loose your liues, Come boldly heere [come] to challendge their faire wiues. Madame dismay not, heere no harme is meant, Bothe they and you, welcome to Iohn a Kent. he puts of his disguyse. Countesse. vilde Sorcerer, hast thou betrayde vs thus? hydyng thy treason with so good pretence? Prince Griffin, and Lord Powesse, be assurde, If otherwise then nobly you intreate, My princely Cossen, and my noble childe; it will be wreakte on your presuming heades. Iohn. you wrong them Madame, if you misconceite, that you or they shall be vnnobly vsde. you are brought hither to no other end, but that their hauiour [shall] you might all c?mend. Aske but the Laydes, if they will departe, Ile bring ye where I had ye, yea, wt h all my hart. Countesse. Then goe sweete Cossen, daughter, let vs hence, for feare wursse happen on this foule offence. S. Griffin. The wurst is past, let happen now what shall, Ile keep Sidanen, or loose life and all. Sydanen. And if Sydanen willingly departe, from her prince Griffin, ioy nere haue her hart. Powesse. I hope my Marian is of selfe same minde, Marian. Else were thy looue requited too vnkinde. Now mother, would you were at home agayne, we bothe are where we wisht our selues full fayne. Countesse. Then questionlesse, this hapte by your consent, And well I wot, these noble Gentlemen, Are honored in your hartes before the other, Sith your endeuours then so happy prooue. Neuer let me be hinderer of true looue. Iohn. Madame, now speake ye lyke a loouing mother, And lyke Sydanens honorable Aunte. Oppose this question, and be iudge your selfe, Say you were troth plight where you lyked best, could ye infaith so great a wrong digest:[?] As but for me had happened to these Ladyes? In to the Castell then, and frollique there And what should haue beene doone, to these sweetes sorrowe, shall to their ioy be finishte heere to morrowe. Gosselen. Come Madame, fauour me to be your guyde, you shall finde all thinges heere to your content. And though my Lorde the Earle holde off aloofe, and may dislyke what we doo for his honor: Be you but pleasde, weele neuer seeke no other, for though we w the father yet we haue the m Sydanen. Let it be so good Aunte, and I shall praye, ffor this good walke, you may liue many a day. Iohn. These speeches are in vayne, I pray ye be gon, and entertayne them, as this kindnes merits. Leaue me awhyle, to gratulate your feast, with some rare merriment, or pleasing iest. will ye be gon? yee doo the Ladyes wrong, heere in the ayre to chat wt h them so long. S. Griffin. Come sweet Sydanen I will be thy guyde, Moorton shall looke him now another Bryde. Powesse. And so shall Pembrooke, now I am possest Of Marian, whom I euer looued best exeunt—manet Iohn. Iohn. Heer's looue and looue, Good Lord, was nere the lyke, but must these ioyes so quickly be concluded? Must the first Scene make absolute a play? no crosse? no chaunge? what? no varietie? One brunt is past, alas, whats that in looue? where firme affection is moste truely knit, the looue is sweetest, that moste tryes the wit. And by my troth, to sporte my selfe awhyle, The disappoynted Brydegroomes, these possesst, the fathers, freendes, and other more besyde, that may be vsde to furnishe vp conceite, Ile set on woorke in such an amourous warre, as they shall wunder whence ensues this iarre. O that I had some other lyke my selfe, to driue me to sound pollicyes indeed. Thers one in Scotland, tearmed Iohn a Cumber, that ouerreachte the deuill by his skill, had Moorton brought him to haue sped his looue, I would haue tryde which should the maister prooue. But since my selfe must pastime wt h my selfe, Ile anger them, bee't but to please my selfe. Sirra Shrimpe. Enter Shrimp a boy. Shrimp. Anon Sir, what is your will wt h me? Iohn. Thus Sirra. To Chester get ye gon, /round in his eare They are yet asleep, that shall be wakte anon. Shrimp. I goe sir. exeunt seuerally. Enter Turnop, Hugh, Tom Tabrer, [will the boy,] and Spurling wt h their Consort Tom. Nay either let it be as M r. Turnop will haue, or by my troth, faire and f I will goe no further, either let vs haue credit or no credit Hugh. You haue sayd as much as be sayd neighbour Thomas, and that not «???» learnedly, but loouingly withall. Maister Turnop, the Lordes we pontiffically pleased with your roration yesterday, that the Ladyes p morrow remayneth altogether at your dispositation. Turnop. why then thus my muse hath magestically, or minstricallically written «??» in prayse of fayre Sydanen, and she beeing appoynted to be maryed this «??y» she ought to haue the maydenhead of my muse, before she loose the benef«??» abselutidico, as much to say in welsh or english, as her rose mary braunche. Spurling. But has will learnd it perfectly? I tell you, she is a Lady of some scression, and lookes that the song of Sydanen should be well performd Turnop. Goodman Spurling, though you be spurblinde, and therby are fauoured for the grosse errours c?mitted in your vocation; yet I pray ye, c?mit your selfe to your musique, as for the song, let it passe vppon my preroga- striue, w t h this addition, He mihi quod domino, non licet ire tuo Tom. when then tune all, for it drawes toward day; and if we wake not the Brydes, why then it is woorth nothing. To add one good morrowe more to your bed sydes, they play, the boy sings the welsh song. Turnop. Timothie Turnop bids, Good morrow bothe the Brydes. Now to the Brydegroomes, and then my harts looke for a largesse Enter Shrimpe the boy Shrimpe. why now is Shrimpe in the height of his brauery, that he may execute some parte of his maisters knauery. Sound foorth your musique to the Brydegroomes sorrowe, for I will sing them but a sower good morrowe. a Song of the Brydes losse. They play, and the boy singes, wheart the Bridegroomes come foorth in their nightgownes and kerchers on their heades, to them Oswen Amery making them selues ready. Moorton what song is this, to flout me to my face? is fayre Sydanen gon, and left me in disgrace? Pemb. Peazants, what meane ye to delude vs so? Is Marian and Sydanen gon, say yea, or no? Shrimpe. Are ye so hot? chafe ye so suddenly? Nay pause awhyle, Ile fetche ye company. exit Turnop. why my Lordes, doo ye aske vs if the Ladyes be gon or no? If they be not in theyr beddes it is more then we knowe. «illa»yne thou lyest, thou sungst a song of sorrowe. urnop. my Lord you lye, we playd ye but a good morrowe. And seeing for our good willes, ye doo vs this wrong: Lets to the Brydes, to haue mony for our song. Heere enter Amery &amp; Oswen vnbraste. Oswen How now my Lordes, what sudden noyse is this? Pemb. Is fayre Sydanen and my Sister fled? [Powesse.] These wretches that so sung, doo now deny it. Turnop. Lets talke a woord or two awhyle, I pray ye be quiet. did ye not yesternight disturb your head, wt h winum vinum ere ye went to bed? That makes ye in your sleep to rise and walke, or at the least, thus idiot lyke to talke? Enter the Earle of Chester in his night gowne, and Shrimpe following aloofe of, some seruaunts wt h him. Chester. Can their departure be to all vnknowen? Villaynes why speake ye not? did no one see them? [i. Seruaunt.] [Not any one my Lord that we can heare of.] [Belyke they went foorth at the garden gate,] [we found it open, therfore we suspect it.] Oswen. My Lord and father, are you vp so soone? where is my Sister? where is fayre Sydanen? Chester. ?Nay, wher's thy mother boy, aske that withall, for she, thy Sister, and my loouely Niece, this night are gon, and no one can tell whether. As I lay slumbring, well neere halfe awake, vnder my windowe did I heare a voyce, saying, rise Chester, for this wedding day, is disappointed now another way. Moorton. And in a Song, the lyke was tolde to vs, by these base slaues, that now deny the same. But yet my Lord, I hope it is not so? Chester. That they are gon my Lordes, tis true, I knowe. But camse these newes from you? why speake ye not? Hugh. Thomas, you are the auncient'st man, I pray ye make answer for vs all. Thomas My Lord, I hope it is not vnknowen to your woorships hor; that I haue liu'de a poore professer of musique in this parish this forty yeeres, and no man could euer burden me w t h the valewe of two pence, that ye should now lay three wenches at once to my charge, I will not say: how much it greeues me, but betweene God &amp; your conscience be it. Turnop. Nay but heare ye my Lord, doo ye as it were seeme in good soun«d» sadnes, to tell vs for a certaintie that the Brydes are gon? an«d» that we, as it were should haue some occasion to knowe therof? Chester. So say these Lordes, they lay it to your charge. Turnop. why then my Lordes bothe great and small, knowe that ye wrong not one, but all which way so ere they haue betooke them, If they be gon, you may goe looke them. And if they be not to be found, «y»ou haue lost your wiues Ile holde ye a pound. Chester. Away then villaynes, rayse vp all my men, bid them take horsse, and poste foorth euery way. By some foule treason are they led from hence, My wife else would not wt h this faulte dispence. Away I say, and trouble vs no longer, exeunt clownes &amp; seruaunts. Shrimp. why now this geere dooth cotten in right kinde, these newes I wot will please my maisters mynde. exit boy. Enter Llwellen, his trayne, and Iohn a Cumber a loofe of. Moorton But heere comes one whom this concernes so neere, that he will searche the depth of this bolde wrong. Princely Llwellen, and my noble freend, hither thou c?mest by loyall promise bound, to sollemnise thy daughters nuptiall rightes But fayre Sydanen and Earle Chesters daughter[s], are with the aged Countesse parted hence, whether or how, as yet we cannot learne. Llwellen. why then my freend, thy tydings are too true, /to Iohn a Cumber. Pemb vnhappy man, is this my welcome hither? [Powesse] My Lord, can he say any thing of their departure? Speak gentle freend, and ease our doubtfull mindes. Cumber. Ease them I cannot, but disease them more, They are where you shall neuer see them more. Moorton. how meanste thou freend? dally not I beseeche thee. Cumber. Prince Griffin of Southwales hath got Sydanen, Lord Powesse hath your daughter Marian. And at Sr. Gosselen d?uyles Castell, not farre hence, Before your Countesse, who went with them thither: this day their mariage must be consumate. Chester. what sayst thou? hath my Countesse wrongd me so? and is this tretcherie by her consent? Cumber. No my good Lord, Knowe ye one Iohn a Kent? A man whom all this Brittishe Isle admyres: for his rare knowledge in the deepest artes? By pollicye he traynd them from this place, they simply thinking no such hidden guyle, but at Saint winifrides fayre hallowed spring, to pay last tribute of their mayden vowes, went with the Countesse, and that subtill guyde, So eache of you may now goe looke his Bryde. Llwellen. Let vs to horsse, and gather able troupes, that may engirt the Castell round about. Proud Griffin, Powesse, and the rest shall knowe, I will not pocket this iniurious wrong, which I will rate at price of their best blood, And his that hath so ouerreachte vs all. Cumber. ffye my good Lord, nay now ye growe too hot. talke ye of horsse, of men and multitudes? when rayse the very powerfulst strength ye can, yet all's too weak to deale with that one man? Had ye a freend could equall him in Arte, controll his cunning, which he boasts so on: then were there hope of their recouerie, what else ye doo, will help but slenderly. Moorton. Ile poste to Scotland for braue Iohn a Cumber, the only man renownde for magick skill. Oft haue I heard, he once beguylde the deuill, and in his Arte could neuer finde his matche. Come he with me, I dare say, Iohn a Kent, And all the rest shall this foule fact repent. Cumber. were he heere now my Lord, it would doo well. But if he come when euery thing is doone No credit by the matter can be wun. Chester. My Lord, goe you and fetche that famous man, The Prince and I will foorthwith to the Castell, where calling them to parle on the walles, wee'le promise that they shall enioy the Ladyes with our consent, if but a sennight space they will adiorne the day of mariage, sound reasons wee'le alleadge to vrge them to it. then you returnd with him that neuer faylde, you haue your wishe, and Iohn in cunning quaylde. Pemb. Be it so. My Lord, Ile beare ye company, not doubting but to speed successefully. Cumber. Ile saue my Lord that labour. Heers Iohn a Cumber, entiste to England by the wundrous fame, that euery where is spread of Iohn a Kent, And seeing occasion falleth out so well, I may doo seruice to my Lord heerby: I make him my protectour in this case. what he hath doone for many dayes together, by Arte I knowe, as you haue seene some proofe. Ile make no bragges, but we two Iohns together, will tug for maistrie, therfore came I hither. Moorton. The welcomste man that euer came to me, all embrace him And this kinde looue will Moorton well requite ffor Gods sake let vs loose no time in vayne, tis broad day light, sweet Iohn bestirre thee now. for nere thy help could come in greater need. Cumber. All you to horsse. Ile meet ye on the way. My Lord, some of those merry lads gaue you good morrowe, c?maund to followe ye, I must imploy them. So get ye gon, and leaue me to my selfe. Chester we goe Iohn. Come Gentlemen, away. Exeunt, ma«n» Cumber Now Iohn a Kent, much haue I heard of thee enuying th fame do«???????????????» what «a»rt thou dooing? very seriously, look in his glasse. plotting downes pastimes to delight the Ladyes. Then haue amongst ye, you Sir haue begun, My turne is next before your sportes be doone. exit.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">tertius. Enter Sr. Griffin, Powesse, Gosselen and Euan Gosselen. I can not blame ye Lordes to stirre so early, considering what occasions are in hand. Loues long pursuit, at length to be requited wt h the due guerdon to continued hope And such by meanes of freendly Iohn a Kent, shall yeeld you bothe your seuerall harts content. Euan. yea, but the Countesse and the other Ladyes, I doubt were wearied with so late a walke. ffor as it seemes they are not stirring yet, And little kindnesse were it to disease them, before them selues think best to leaue their chamber. But say Prince Griffin, wheron doo ye muse? you not mislyke Sydanen is so neere? Nor you, that Marian beares her company. S. Griffin. Sir Euan, Ile be playne, &amp; tell ye what I thought. I deeply did conceit within my selfe, Lord Moortons passions he will act this morning: when newes is brought him that his bryde is gon. Think ye he will not cursse the fatall houre: began so sweete, &amp; now falles out so sower? Powesse. Nay let my Riuall beare him company, And good olde Chester, for his forwardnes: in seeking to deceiue me of my wife. But what will he imagine of his Countesse? Shee's gon from Courte, and no man can tell whether: and colde their sute, should they pursue them hether. Gosselen Therof you may be bolde; but much I muse where Iohn a Kent bestowes him all this whyle. He is so carefull of his coy conceites, to sute this sollemne day as it should be: that for your sakes, I knowe it shall excell, at least he labours all thinges may be well. Enter Iohn a Cumber lyke Iohn a Kent. S. Griffin. See where he comes, deep pondering wt h him selfe, important matters, we must not disturb him, but giue him leaue, till his owne leysure him. [musique] Silence, me thinkes I heare sweet melodie, And see he sets the Castell gate wyde ope, Stand we aloofe, and note what followeth. Musique whi he opens the doore ffrom one end of the Stage enter an antique queintly disguysde and c?ming dauncing before them, singes. i. Antique. when wanton looue had walkte astray, then good regard began to chide: And meeting her vppon the way, sayes wanton lasse you must abyde. ffor I haue seene in many yeares, That sudden looue breedes sullen feares; Shall I neuer while I liue keep my girle at schoole: She hath wandred too and fro, ffurder then a Mayde should goe, Shall she neuer while she liues make me more a foole a ducking curtesy— exit into the «C» Cumber. you little thinke who it is that sung this song? S. Griffin No Iohn, I pray thee tell vs who it is. Cumber. why Prince Llwellen, come to his daughters wedding Is he her father, and not woorth the bidding? S. Griffin Thou doost but iest Iohn, I hope it is not so. Cumber. I say it is. Heere comes another, lets see if him I knowe. ffrom the other end of the Stage, enter another antique, as the first. 2. Antique. In a silent shade, as I sate a sunning, there I heard a Mayd greeuously complayne: Many mones she made mongst her sighes still c?ming all wo«???????????????????????» Then her aged father, counceld her the ra«th» to consent where he had plaste his mynde: But her peeuish mother, brought her to another, though it was agaynst bothe course and kynde. Then like a father will I, come to check my filly, for her gadding foorth without my leaue: And if she repent it, I am well contented, home agayne my darling to receiue. exit into the Castell Cumber. Lord Powesse, you may guesse by the song who this is. Powesse. If thother was Llwellen as thou saydst, I doubt then this Ranulphe Earle of Chester, Or some deuise figured by thee for theem, to fright vs when we are in surest safetie. Cumber. Content ye Lordes, the fathers beeing by, you may be sure nothing shall goe awry. Heere comes another, listen what he is. ffrom vnder the Stage the third Antique. 3 Antique. you that seek to sunder looue, learne a lesson ere you goe: And as others paynes doo prooue, so abyde your selues lyke woe. ffor I fynde, and you shall feele: selfe same turne of ffortunes wheele. Then if wrong be repayde: say deserued mends is made. exit into the Castell. Cumber. what say ye to Earle Moorton, Prince Griffin? lyke ye his company or no? S. Griffin. Come Iohn, thou loou'st to iest, I perswade me it is not so. Gosselen. Tush no such matter, this antique disguise, Is but to giue the Brydes a good morrow so soone as they rise. Euan. And to make you despaire in the course of his arte, he giues these names to euery seuerall parte. Cumber. what another yet? who should this be? The fourth out of a tree, if possible it may be. 4 Antiq. you stole my looue, fye vppon ye, fye, [a] you stole my looue, fye fye a. guest you but what, a paine it is to prooue, you for your looue would dye a. And hencefoorth neuer longer, Be such a craftie wronger. But when deceit takes such a fall, Then farewell sly deuise and all. you stole my looue, fye vppon ye fye, you stole my looue, fye fye a. exit into the Castell. Cumber. My Lord of Pembrooke? may it be possible? by my faith we lookte for no such guests: Nay then Ile in to make vp the messe. exit into the Castell, &amp; makes fast the dore Euan. what meaneth Iohn by this mad merrie humour? he namde the Prince Llwellen, and the Earle of Chester, the Earles of Moorton and of Pembrook; bothe your Riualles It seemes he would entise vs to beleeue, that in these antique shewes of queint deuise, they seuerally are entred in the Castell. Tis hard for vs to iudge of his intent Enter Iohn a Kent talking with his boy. S Griffin. heere now he comes agayne, but not from foorth the Castell: Ile be so bolde as break his serious talke, for these deuises make me much misdoubt, further then I as yet will seeme to speak on. Now gentle Iohn, shall we intreat to knowe, the meaning of your merrie antique showe? Iohn. what shewe my Lord? what meaning should I tell? Powesse. why Iohn those antiques went into the Castell. foure was there of them, and eche seuerally, both daunc'ste and sung heere very pleasantly. The first thou toldst vs was the Prince Llwellen, The second, noble Ranulphe Earle of Chester, whom thou hadst brought to grace this day withall. Moorton and Pembrook were the other twayne, In all which Iohn, I knowe thou didst but fayne. then more at large d«????????????????» «??????????»why Lordes, I pray ye say, till this instant, sawe ye me today? len. Sawe thee sweet Iohn? I pray thee leaue this iesting, thy feyned straungenes makes these Lordes amazde. didst thou not first set ope the Castell gate? and then from sundry places issued foorth, the skipping antiques, singing seuerall songs, as loouers vse, that haue endurde some wrongs? And when they all were entred at the gate, thou followedst, seeming then to barre it fast. whence now thou com'ste, to make vs more admyre: I cannot guesse, tell vs, I thee desyre. Iohn. Maister, Ile credit ye, because you speak it. But on my faith, all this is straunge to me. My boy and I haue for these two houres space, beene greatly busyed in an other place, To tell ye trueth, against the Brydes should rise, to sporte them with some pleasing vanities. S. Griffin. Then Iohn lets in for feare of tretcherie, my hart misgiues there is some villainie. Iohn. The gate is fast my Lordes, bound wt h such charmes, /he tryes the doore as very easily will not be vndoone. I hope the learned Owen Glenderwellin, is not come hither [as] in the Lordes behalfe, that are your Riualles, and at this aduauntage: hath ouerreachte me, when I least misdoubted. Is it not he, I cannot guesse the man. Enter Iohn a Cumber on the walles lyke Iohn a Kent Powesse. My Lordes, see one appeareth on the walles. It's Iohn a Kent, how? Iohn a Kent is heere. Some sly Magitian hath vsurpte thy shape, and this day made vs all vnfortunate. Iohn. what ere thou be, I charge thee tell thy name. Cumber. My name is Iohn, what sayst thou to the same? Iohn. I would thou wert the Iohn that I could wish Cumber If Iohn a Cumber? then the same it is. In thy proud thoughtes Iohn, did I heare thee say, thou wantedst one to thwart thy deep desseignes, layd cunningly to countercheck this looue, because it should not take successe so soone. And me thou namdste, freendly, or how I care not, heere am I now. And what those Lordes haue tolde thee, is very true, thine eyes shall witness it. Musique Sound musique, while I shewe to Iohn a Kent, those hither come, for whom he neuer sent. whyle the musique playes, enters on the walles Llwellen Chester wt h his Countesse, Moorton with Sydanen, Pemb. with Marian, Oswen and Amerye. S. Griffin. Ah Iohn, if these be not illusions, but the same partyes, all our hope is dashte. Llewellen, Ranulphe and our hatefull foes, help Iohn, or now afreshe beginnes our woes. Llwellen. And are ye taken tardy in your shames? Proude Southwales Prince, and ouerdaring Powesse? See now the issue of your enterprise, requites ye with your well deseruing merits, And my Sydanen thus restord agayne, shall wt h Earle Moorton safely now remayne Chester. Madame, I iudg'de [ye] you guiltie in this wrong, till Iohn a Cumber [resolu'de] heere resolu'de the doubt. Now Powesse brag of thy late gotten conquest, Let Iohn a Kent wt h all the witte he hath, restore thee Marian if he can from me. Heere Earle of Pembrook, take her, she is thine, And thank kinde Iohn whose cunning is diuine. Pemb. Thankes vnto him, and you moste noble Lord, And shame to them, such as their deedes deserue, that would haue seuerd me from my sweet choyse. I hope heer's one hath met wt h Iohn a Kent To teache him how true looue he dooth preuent [S] Mooreton was there no way to yeeld your looue successe, but by that fellowes sillie practises? let him heerafter meddle wt h his mates, heere's one hath giuen me Marian back agayne let him attempt to fetche her if he dare. Sydanen was euer Lady wronged thus before? Marian thou knowest my minde, I say no more. Marian. Sweet Cossen, what we may not now impart, heere let vs bury it, closely in our hart. Countesse. This sudden chaunge hath altred quite your hope. what was at first concluded, now must be, Cossen &amp; daughter, help none else ye see. Cumber. Now Iohn without, listen to Iohn wt hin, the mariage thou appoyntedst for those Lordes, shalbe effected now with these two Lordes. [And for they would not let vs] be their guests, [They nor thy selfe gets any of our] feastes, In mockerie wishe for me another day, So fare ye well, we haue no more to say. Iohn. Good Iohn within, heare Iohn without a little, winners may bragge, loosers haue leaue to speak. vnder my shaddowe haue you doone all this, much greater cunning had it beene thine owne. As yet thou doost but rob me of my selfe, Good honest Ihon, let me beholde thy selfe. Perhaps my shape makes thee thus boldly vaunte, and armes thee with this ablenes of skill, wheras thine owne beeing insufficient, may make thee feare to deale wt h Iohn a Kent. Cumber. Lordes and fayre Ladyes, goe disporte your selues, about the walkes and gardens of this Castell. And for thou ween'st so gayly of thy selfe, within this hower Iohn Ile meete with thee, in myne owne shape, vppon this Castell greene, where I will dare thee, and out dare thee too, in whatsoeuer Iohn a Kent can doo. Iohn I take thy woord, Ladyes to you alone, wishe I all good, but to the others, none. /they discend. S. «G»riffin. why say sweet Iohn, what shall betyde vs now? Now are we wursse then ere we were before. Iohn. Sirra, get ye to the back gate of the Castell, and through the key hole quickly wring thee in, marke well, and bring me woord what stratageme, this cumbring Iohn meanes next to enterprise ffor I am sure he will not leaue me so, At least I meane, not him, away then, goe. Shrimp. I fly Sir, and am there alreadie exit boy. Powesse. No comfort Iohn? what standst thou all a mort? tis only we that haue the greatest cause. Thou canst I knowe cope wt h this Iohn a Cumber and maister him, maugre his vtmoste skill, if thou wilt searche into thy deepe conceites. Gosselen. Iohn, I my selfe haue oft times heard thee wishe, that thou mightst buckle with this Iohn a Cumber. Come is he now to all our deep disgrace, except thou help it ere he scape this place. Iohn. Maister, what? he that went beyond the deuill, And made him [sell] serue him seuen yeares prentiship: ist possible for me to conquer him? tis better take this foyle, and so to end. S. Griffin. why then our Ladyes this day shall be wed, If or thou canst or wilt not stand vs now in sted. Iohn. Nay there's no wedding toward, that I can see, And when tis doone, yet heere it must not be. Content your selues, and walke the woodes about, [you see] heere is no getting in, we are fayre lockt out. Enter shrimpe. I cannot tell, but if I hit aright ffor walking heere all day, Ile make them some walke all night manet Iohn. Be gon I pray ye, I must be «a»lo«ne» Enter Shrimpe skipping. me on Sirra, tell me, what newes? mp. Sir, yonder's great preparation for a play, which by the shaddowes of the Lordes and Ladyes, heere on the greene shall foorthwith be enacted. And Iohn a Cumbers whole intent heerin, Is that your selfe shall see before your face, his arte made currant to your deep disgrace. Iohn. But wher's the Countesse, Marian and Sydanen? they are not in the Castell, that I knowe. Shrimpe. Earle Chesters sonne, and young Lord Amerye are merily conducting them to Chester, And thither will the Lordes them selues this night, when they haue seene this play in your dispight. Iohn Be gon, and bring the Ladyes back agayne, with them likewise are sent to be their guydes, Stay with them at the Chestnut tree hard by till I come for them. Now bestirre thee Iohn, /exit boy for in thy play I purpose to make one. exit. Enter Iohn a Cumber in his owne habit, with him Turnop Hugh, and Thomas the tabrer. Turnop. doo ye heare Sir? we can be content as it were to furnish ye w t h our facilitie in your play or enterlude, marie where ye would vs to flout, scoff and scorne at Iohn a Kent, for my part, let Hugh Sexten and Thomas Tabrer doo as they see occasion, I am not to mock him, that is able to make a man a Munkey in lesse then halfe a minute of an houre. Hugh. Ile tell ye what Sir, if it be true that is spoken, marie I will not stand to it, a man were better deale w t h the best man in the countrey, then w t h Maister Iohn a Kent, he neuer goes abroad with out a bushell of deuilles about him, that if one speak but an ill woord of him, he knowes it by and by, and it is no more, but send out one of his deuilles, and whers the man then? nay, God blesse me from him. Thomas. Harkeye Sir, you are a Gentleman, and weele doo as much for «y» Lord, the Earle as poore man may doo, If it be to doo or say any thing agaynst him selfe, or any other, weele doo it, marie Thomas Taberrer will neuer meddle w t h Mr. Iohn, no, not I. Cumber. why sillie soules, Ile be your warrantise Iohn shall not touche ye, doo the best he can, Ile make ye scorne him to his very face. And let him [how] vendge it, how he will or dare En Iohn a Kt listning. Turnop. By my troth Sir, ye seeme an honest man, and so faith, could ye be as good as your woord, there be that perhaps would come somewhat roundly to ye. Indeed Sir, Maister Iohn hath dealt but euen so so w t h me in times past, harke ye Sir, I neuer kist wenc«h» or playd the good fellowe, as sometimes ye knowe fleshe &amp; bloode will be frayle, but my wife hath knowen on it ere I came home, and it could not be but by some of his flying deuilles. Cumber. [Nay I could tell ye other thinges besyde,] [what dayly wronges he dooth vnto ye all,] [which for they aske some leysure to reporte,] [Ile vrge no more, but that ye ioyne wt h me,] [in such an action as I haue in hand,] [when you shall see him so disabled,] [not daring to offend the wurst of you,] [as hencefoorth will he hyde his head for shame,] [weele make him such a scoffing iesting game.] Hugh. But shall he neither send his deuilles to pinche vs? nor doo any other harme if we doo as you bid vs? Cumber. harke me, Ile make him fret him selfe to death, with very anger that he cannot touche ye, Bob, buffet him, doo him what wrong ye will, And feare not Ile defend ye by my skill. Thomas. well Sir, Ile stand by &amp; giue aime, and if I see them speed well, Ile bring ye such a crewe of wenches on whom his deuilles haue tolde lyes and tales, that your hart would burst to heare how they will vse him Cumber. why this is excellent, you fit me now. Come in with me, Ile giue ye apt enstructions, according to the purpose I entend. That Iohn a Kent was nere so courst before, Our time is short, come lette vs in about it. exeunt. Iohn. Poore Iohn a Kent, heer's making roddes for Many haue doone the lyke, to whip them selue But Iohn a Cumber is more wise then so he will doo nothing, but shall take successe. This walke I made, to see this wundrous man, Now hauing seene him, I am satisfyed. I know not what this play of his will prooue, But his intent to deale with shaddowes only, I meane to alter, weele haue the substaunces. And least he should want Actors in his play, Prince Griffin, Lord Powesse and my merrie Maister, Ile introduce as I shall finde due cause. And if it chaunce as some of vs doo looke, One of vs Iohns must play besyde the booke. exit.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Actus Quartus Scena Prima. Enter Shrimp playing on some instrument, a prettie way befo the Countesse, Sydanen, Marian, Oswen and Amerye. Oswen. Madame, this sound is of some instrument, [this] for two houres space it still hath haunted vs, The boye[s] playes roundabout them. now heere, now there, on eche syde round about vs, And questionlesse, either we followe it, Or it guydes vs, least we mistake our way. Amerye. It may be that this famous man of Arte, doubting least Iohn a Kent should crosse our iourney, and seeke reuendge for his receiu'de disgrace: [That] he by this musique [he] dooth direct[s] our course, more redyly to hit the way to Chester. Countesse. what ere it be, I would we were at Chester. My loouely Niece I see is malcontent So is my Maryan, but what remedye? when thinges you see fall out so contrary? Sydanen. Ay poore Sydanen, let no more sweet song, be made by Poet for Sidanen sake, her fine trim day is turn to black cole night, and she hath lost her sweetest looue delight. Shrimp. But let Sydanen cast away this care, /to her asyde comfort is neerer her then shees aware. Sydanen. what say you Cossen? did you speak to me? Ma«i»an Not I Sydanen, I with you complayne On fortunes spight and ouer deep disdayne Shrimp. But Marian with Sydanen may reioyse, for time will let them haue their owne harts choyse. they look about Sydanen. Pray God amen, O Cossen did you heare, a voyce still buzzeth comfort in mine eare. Marian And so in mine, but I no shape can see Tis Iohn a Cumber mocks bothe you and me Sydanen. Cursse on his hart for cumber true looue so, which else had made full end of all our woe. Enter Sr. Gosselen, Griffin, Powesse and Euan. Gosselen. How say ye Lordes? now credit Iohn a Kent. See where they are, and at the selfe same tree, where he assurde vs all of them would be. S. Griffin. Sweetest Sydanen, how thy happie sight, makes me forget all former sorrowe quyte. Powesse. The lyke dooth Marians presence yeeld to me, for all greefes past assurde felicitie. Musique Chime Euan. Listen my Lordes, me thinkes I heare the chyme, A daynt of musi which Iohn did promise, ere you should presume: to venture for recouerie of the Ladyes. Gosselen. The very same, stay till the power therof, haue layd the sleepie charge on bothe their eyes, that should haue guyded them from hence to Chester. The boy trips round about Oswen and Amery, sing chyme, and they the one after the other, lay them vsing very sluggish gestures, the Ladyes amazed about them. Song, to the Musique wt hin. ep sweetly: sleep sweetly, sweetly take rest, be sun«g» ll eche goe with her choyse, where she lykes best. Ladyes cheere vp your despayring mindes, for your freendes are neere, that will answere true looue in due kinde, then neuer more feare. rimp. Lordes take aduauntage, for they bothe are fast, bid Iohn a Cumber mend this cunning cast. Gosselen. ffeare not good Madame, for you must with me, to end the ioyes these loouers long to see. The chyme playes, &amp; Gosselen wt h the Countesse goes turning out. S. Griffin. And fayre Sydanen I dare boldely say, rather with me will goe, then heere to stay The chyme agayne, and they turne out in like manner. exeunt. Powesse. I not misdoubt, but Marian beares lyke mynde, this is the way our sweet content to fynd. The chyme agayne, and so they. exeunt. Shrimp Sir Euan, follow you the way they take, for now I must these sleepie Lordes awake. /exit Euan. ffye Gentlemen, what meanes this slothfulnes? /they start vp. you sleep securely, while the subtill foe, hath got your charge, and bred a greater woe. Oswen. Lord Amerye, how fell we thus asleep? My mother, sister, and Sidanen's gon. Amery. Canst thou my boy tell which way they haue tane? or by what meanes they are thus gon from hence? Shrimp. when as my maister, Iohn a Cumber, sawe, how carelessly you did respect your charge, and lay asleep, while as Sr. Gosselen denvyle, Prince Griffin, Powesse, and another Knight, bare hence the Ladyes toward proud Iohn a Kent: he sent me posting thorow the duskye ayre, to wake ye, and to cause ye followe me, to fetche them back ere they haue got too farre. If then youle speed, follow me presently. Oswen. Thankes to thy maister, we will followe thee, to make amends for our fond negligence. Shrimp And I will lead ye such a merrie walke, as you therof[ore] shall at more leysure talke. Come Gent«l»emen. exeut. Enter Iohn a Kent lyke Iohn a Cumber, with him Llwellen, Chester, Moorton and Pembrook, foorth of the Castell. Iohn. Lordes, take your places as you are appoynted. Though once I minded but to vse your shaddowes, pardon me now I may imploy your persons, because that your delight shall be the greater, and his disgrace the more to you apparant: that durst attempt so bolde an enterprise. Now shall ye see if famous Iohn a Kent, be able to auoyde disparagement. Llwellen. But shall Sydanen and Earle Chesters daughter, be heere in person lykewise as we are? Iohn. No my good Lord, their figures shall suffise, because you see they are disconsolate, And, to speak trueth, beare more affection, To Griffin of Southwales, and the Lord Powesse, then to Earle Moorton and the Earle of Pembrooke. ?whose shaddowes when those other Lordes shall see, so farre estraunged from their former course; how it will quayle their hope, your selues shall iudge, and make poore Iohn a Kent mad to beholde it. Chester. But long ere this I hope they are at Chester, and bothe their guydes in safetie at my house. ohn. I warrant ye my Lord, they'r safe enough, from Iohn, and all the vtmoste he can doo. See my good Lord, what I doo for your sake, /to Mooreton. who only may dispose of me &amp; mine. I knowe it Iohn, and should I not confesse, thy kyndnes to exceed on my behalfe: and guerdon it, I greatly were too blame. Pemb. The lyk say I, wherof whme my thankfulnes shall more at large assure thee. Iohn. Needlesse my Lordes are all these ceremonyes, ffor as I furder you in looues affayres: So I expect some credit by mine Arte. Now silence Lordes, for all the sportes begin, And see where Iohn a Kent is first come in. Enter Iohn a Cumber lyke Iohn a Kent. Cumber. As he that with vnsatiate thyrst of fame, [followes] pursues an action of some high applause, to conquer his vsurping enemye, and add renowne for euer to his deedes: So Iohn a Cumber followes his intent, to conquer, sit, and laugh at Iohn a Kent. Llwellen what sayes he? will he laugh him selfe to scorne? Iohn. My Lord, you little thinke the scope of his intent, he dooth imagine, he hath tane my shape, and you shall heare him speak, as he were Iohn a Cumber. Note all his actions, and, let it suffise, heele prooue him selfe a foole before your eyes. Chester. And yet imagine that he scorneth thee? Iohn. why that is all, ffor Gods sake, sit and see. Cumber. Alreadie are my shaddowes set in order, ffor Prince Llwellen, Chester, Pembrooke, Moorton, And see poore Ioh«n» a Kent is walking by, he poyntes to them. as one that cannot yeeld a reason why. [S. Griffin.] He poyntes to thee, and tearmes thee Iohn a Kent, Moorton let him heerafter brag with Iohn a Cumber: Pemb. when men of Arte thus striue in merriment it needes must rayse in meaner wittes some wunder. Iohn. Begin your Scene, and if he be not vext, I doubt not but he shalbe wt h the next. Llwellen. ffye Iohn a Kent, what iniurie is this, /he riseth and goeth to Iohn a Cumber. that thou hast offered to this noble man. Sydanen, my fayre daughter, whom I looue, wouldst thou haue wedded to the Southwales Prince, And brought'st her hither to thy maisters Castell, from whence she was recouered to thy shame. ffye Iohn a Kent, for this most sillie parte, heerafter tearme thy selfe no man of Arte. Chester. Thy subtill wandring in an Hermits weede, wherby thou didst seduce my aged wife, to let her daughter, and my loouely Niece, suddenly starting to him, after the other hath doe walke wt h her to Saint winifrydes fayre spring to offer vp theyr latest mayden vowes, and thou, like to an hippocrite, their guyde. Say foollish man, what hast thou wun heer by: but such dishonor as will neuer dye? Moorton. Iohn, Iohn, call thou to minde the Antiques, /he sudden«y» t that in thy absence got into the Castell, And ore the walles returnd vnto thy face the only argument of thy disgrace. Alas good Iohn, account it then no wunder, Such is thy luck to deale wt h Iohn a Cumber. Pemb. well Iohn a Kent, wilt thou be rulde by me? /he suddenly too. leaue wales, leaue England, and be seene no more, this monstrous blemish grauen vppon thy browe, will be but greefe to vs thy countrey men, Then seeing that so tardy thou wert catcht, yeeld him the bucklers that thee ouermatcht. Cumber. how now? whats this? my shaddowes taught to speak, that to my face, they should vnto my foe? Llwellen. Shaddowes prooue substaunce Iohn, thou art too weak, then like a sillie fellowe, pack and goe. Cumber. Speak heere to Iohn a Kent, speak ye to me? Chester. we speak to Iohn the foole, and thou art he. Cumber. Spirits, Ile torture ye for this abuse. Moorton Torture thy selfe«????????????» «???» «????????????p»poynted you Pemb. Al poore sillie soule, thou mayst appoynt, and all thy poynting is not woorth a poynt. Cumber. whence am I crost? may it be Iohn a Kent, hath ouerreachte me in myne owne deuise? The more I striue to knowe, the further of, I am from compassing what fayne I would. Ile sit awhyle, and meditate heeron. he sits down«e» Iohn. what? in a study? nay I must awake him, with other thinges more angry yet must make him. Enter Sr Gosselen denvyle, Griffin, Powesse, [Euan,] the Countesse Sydanen and Marian. S. Gosselen. Alas alas, why droupeth Iohn a Kent? /to Cumber Looke cheerely man, for see, Earle Chesters wife, through power of thine incomparable skill, is back returnd from deuillish Iohn a Cumber, and no man hath the shame but he alone. Iohn a Cumber stamps about. S. Griffin. I knowe this sadnes is but thy conceite, because he crost thee ere thou wast aware. But may not this cheere vp thy minde agayne: that thou hast brought me sweet Sydanen back? Powesse. And heere is Marian too, my soules delight, who but for thee had beene Earle Pembrookes bryde. let Iohn a Cumbers foyle then be of force, sithe we enioy what we can most desyre: to make thee leaue this discontented humour. Cumber. Sleep I? or wake I? dreame I? or doo I dote? Looke what I poynted all these shapes to doo, agaynst the man that I doo enuye moste: they doo it to me, and he sits laughing by, as if there were no Iohn a Kent but I. Countesse. why frollique Iohn, thy arte prooues excellent, let not one simple foyle make thee dismay, thou art reuendgde vnto thine owne content, let Iohn a Cumber doo the wurst he may. Sydanen. And will sweet Iohn a Kent not look so sad, Sydanen will intreat all Brittaine Poet, to wride large volume of thy learned skill, for bringing her where she desyre to be, and from that Iohn a Cumber set her free. Marian. Look what my Cossen sayth, the lyke doo I, and will extoll thy fame continually. Euan. Into the Castell then, and frollique there. I knowe that Iohn will not stay long behinde, since your successe dooth answere thus his mynde. exeunt into the Castell Iohn how say ye now my Lord, did not these shaddowes; make him halfe thinke they were the same indeed? Llwellen what ere they did in him, beleeue me freend, but that I more relye vppon thine arte, then the opinion this hath raysde in me: I should haue sworne that that was my Sydanen. Moorton. In sooth my Lord, I iump with your conceite. And trust me I was not a little moou'de, Prince Griffins shape so led her by the hand: but that I credit arte, more then mine eye. Powesse. [will ye beleeue me? but that Iohn is by,] [And dooth all this to plague yon Iohn a Kent:] [these semblaunces would make me much misdeeme.] [Pardon me Iohn, for looue is full of feare,] [and such illusions neither please eye not eare.] Chester. Then well fare me that differ from you all. should I haue tooke that shaddowe for my Countesse? or else the other for my daughter Marian? Nay, what he did already so resolues me, that I am dreadlesse now of Iohn a Kent. Iohn. I thanke ye good my Lord, so holde ye still, for Iohn's no Iohn I see without good skill. Ther's one fit more of merriment behinde, that ift hit right, will serue him in his kinde. Enter Turnop «&amp; ???» his trayne w Turnop. A pause maisters, a pause, we are not come only t to doo somewhat else besyde, for we are of the Ent nick nock Iohn a Kent, if the honest Gentleman woord. Thomas As good as his woord? why looke ye yonder where he standes honors woorship, euen as he sayd he would. he noddes hi head at as one would say, Maisters, fall to your busines, or doo that ye come fo Hugh. Good Lord looke how Iohn a Kent sits in a browne study as it were, who«s» begin now? come lets knowe that. Turnop. who shall begin? what a question is that? let mayde Marian haue the f flurt at him, to set an edge on our stomacks, and let me alone in faith to ierke it after her. Spurling. Now by my troth well aduisde good neighbour Turnop, Ile turne her to him if he were a farre better man then is, too him, too him, touch him roundly. Boy. what? think ye I am afrayde of him? infaith Sir no. Precise Iohn, or rather peeuish peeld paltrie Iohn, doost thou remember how many iniuries from time to time thou hast doone me? first in sending thy deuilles to tell lyes and tales of me, then making my dame to cudgell me, and lastly to pinche me black and blewe when I neuer offended thee, for which I defye thee to thy face, and dare thee to meete me in any place. Turnop. Heare ye Sir? you Sir, as one would say, good man you Sir, because breuitie is best in such a queazie action, it is concluded or conditioned among vs that haue some authoritie in this case, that because our Morris lacks a foole, and we knowe none fitter for it then you M r. Iohn heeres a coat spick and span new, it neuer came on any mans back since it was made, therfore for your further credit, we will giue you hanse of it, and where we took ye for a wise man before, we are contented to account of ye as our foole for euer heerafter. Hugh. In witnesse wherof, we the youthes of the parishe, put it on ye with put it on him. our owne handes. Nay, neuer striue or wunder, for thus we are appoynted by great Iohn a Cumber. Turnop. At it now Thomas lustily, and let vs ierk it ouer the greene, seeing we haue got such a goodly foole as M r. Iohn a Kent. exeunt dauncing Chester. why this will make poore Iohn a Kent stark mad, and questionlesse heele nere more shewe his face, to be reprooued with this deep disgrace Iohn Lordes, sit ye still, Ile come agayne anon, I am prettily reuengde on Cumbring Iohn. exit. Enter Shrimpe leading Oswen and Amery about the tree. Oswen. were euer men thus led about a Tree? still circkling it, and neuer getting thence? My braynes doo ake, and I am growen so faynt, that I must needes lye downe on meere constraynt. /he lyes do Amery. This villayne boy is out of doubt some spirit, still he cryes follow, but we get no further, then in a ring to daunce about this tree. In all my life I neuer was so wearie. follow that list, for I can goe no longer. /he lyes down Shrimp. There lye and rest ye, for I think your walke, hath not beene altogether to your ease. Now I must hence, I heare my maisters call, it standes vppon the push of opening all. exit boy. Oswen. Lord Amery, is not yon my father? the Prince Llwellen, Moorton and Earle Pembrook? Amery Tis they indeed, O let vs call to them, to trye if they can get vs from this tree. Help Prince of wales, ah help vs Earle of Chester, Or else thy sonne and I are lyke to perishe. Chester. Oswen my Sonne? and young Lord Amery? shaddowes they be not, for tis they indeed. Tell me, ah tell me, wherfore lye ye heere? They« e» them where are the Ladyes that you had in charge? Llwellen? Ah speak young Lordes, my hart dooth dread some ill, ye looke so gastly, and so full of feare. Oswen Lend vs your ayde to rayse vs on our feete, that we may get from this accurssed tr «????»ll h«eoste» vnhappy newes. /they help th «N»o ill to my Sidanen, then I care not, Be Marian well, be what it may besyde. where is the villayne boy, that thus misled vs? Boy was he not, but questionlesse some fiend, that hath tormented vs, as nere was lyke. ellen.? Aske for no boyes aske for no fiends or furyes, But tell me quickly, where is my Sydanen? liuing or dead, or how she is bereft ye? Oswen. Breefely to answere all of ye together, Nor of my mother, Marian or Sydanen. lyes it in vs to tell ye whats become, other then this, as it was tolde to vs, That Griffin, Powesse and Sr. Gosselen denvyle, reskewed them from vs, how or when we knowe not, so sayd a deuill or boy sent to vs from Iohn a Cumber. Enter Iohn a Cumber pulling of his foole coat, lyke Kent still. Cumber ffrom me young Lordes? alas you were deceiu'd, as you likewise, and all haue beene together. Looke not so straunge Lordes, deeme not me Iohn a Kent, that in his sted haue beene so much misusde, scorned by you, then flouted by the Ladyes, last made a foole heere in a morris daunce, and all preparde gaynst him, turnd on my selfe In breefe then to abridge all further wunder, yonder is Iohn a Kent, [I] heere Iohn a Cumber. Iohn a Kent in his owne habit, denvyle, Griffin, Powesse, Euan, Countesse, Sydanen, Marian and Shrimp on the walles. Iohn. Now Iohn within, may speak to Iohn without, And Lordes to you that frumped him so finely. Once you were heere, and shut vs out of doore, you had these Ladyes, but ye could not keep them. where are those twayne that daunc'st about the Tree? Look on your Minstrell heere Sirs, this was he. /to Shrimp But as for you Iohn, that vsurpte my shape, And promisde you would meet me on the greene, O you were busyed too much with your play, but you knowe best who went the foole away. That I am quit with thee thou wilt confesse? Cumber. I doo Iohn, for twere shame to yeeld thee lesse, but I may liue to meet with ye heerafter. I pray thee Iohn, shall we haue one cast more? Iohn So thoul't deale wyser then thou didst before. Promise me one thing Lordes, and you shall see, Ile offer him more oddes, then he dare me. Llwellen Lets heare it Iohn, and as we like, weele answere. Iohn. It is so reasonable, you cannot deny me. ffayne would ye that your daughters were combinde, in sacred wedlock with those noble Lordes. Promise me that it shall be doone this day, without more dallying, Ile deliuer them, /the Ladyes to Iohn a Cumber, so he will bestowe, his very deepest skill to make it sure. But if he fayle, and be my luck to speed, to ceasse contention, and confesse him foyld, [And] As I will doo the lyke, if he preuayle. Llwellen? I am agreed, what sayes my Lord of Chester? Chester. The motion is so good, that I consent. Cumber. Lordes and fayre Laydes, you likewise agree, to take your fortune how so ere it be? O«mn»es. we doo. Iohn. Then, not so churl-like, as when you were Lordes, Of this our Castell, to allow no fauour, «b»ut euen to hunger starue vs at the doore, «nter» all freely, and toake parte with vs, d cheere, for some of you haue need. Then????????????? ???» And aftrward ere night we meane to try who shall haue conquest, either he or I. Cumber. Brauely resolu'de Iohn, I must needes c?m«d t»h thoul't haue the wurst if fortune but befrd m«e».</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Actus Quintus Scena Prima. Enter the Abbot of Chester read«ig» a letter, &amp; one of Abbot. My honest freend, this letter from thy Lord, shewes that the mariages, so long deferd, betweene the Ladyes and their seuerall suters: must now at length be finished this day. And at this Abbey is the place appoynted. ffurther he sayth, that all the Abbey gates, not only must be fast, but strongly mand, with his owne guard appoynted for the purpose, that none may issue foorth, or enter in, but such as first must by him selfe be seene. what? is there daunger of preuention? or that resistaunce will be offered? Seruaunt. daunger there is, but what, in sooth I knowe not, Lord Abbot, I haue performde my charge to you, I must goe warne his guarde in readines, and then returne to certefye my Lord. Abbot. Assure his honor, what he hath referd, vnto my trustie care and secrecie in euery poynt shall answere his content. Our Lord forbid, but he should heere c?maund, that is our patrone, and so good an Earle. Seruaunt. his honor will be thankfull for this kindnes, which Ile not fayle at full to let him knowe. exit Seruaunt. Abbot ffarewell my freend, Ile bout my busines strayte, and gaynst his c?ming giue my due attendaunce. exit Abbot. Enter Iohn a Kent, denvyle, Griffin and Powesse. S. Griffin. would any man but you haue beene so fond, to yeeld the Ladyes, when we might haue kept them? poore soules, with what vnwillingnes they went, pray God this rashnes all we not repent. Pwesse. what though that once ye proou'de too hard for him? still are ye certaine of the lyke successe? Remember how he crost vs at first, once warnde, dooth make a man to dread the wurst. denvyle.? I will suspend my iudgement in this case, and rather hope, then feare what may befall. Once this I knowe, it will goe wundrous hard, Ere Iohn a Kent be in his purpose bard. Iohn. ffeare you, hope you, for my parte, Ile doo neither, but track his steppes that treades the way before, to doo the thing he can vndoo no more. These weddings then must be at Chester Abbey, the Gates wherof moste strongly will be mand, Entraunce there is allowed [to] at none but one, And Iohn a Cumber there must be the Porter, Tis very lyke then, none of you get in. And yet in faith it would be very prettie, to prooue his eye sight, whether he doo knowe, the men that should be let in, yea or no. would not you laugh to see him let you in, and keep them out that [mst] should his wager winne? S. Griffin Oh that were excellent, might it be so, and if thou list, doubtlesse it shall be so. Iohn. Lord Powesse, what think you? Powesse. Euen as Prince Griffin, so sweet Iohn say thou art the man mayst make vs liue or dy denvyle.? If it should fall out so successefully, besyde the endlesse that thou shalt winne pud Iohn a Cumbers foyle will be the«??» «????»shall b«????», Iohn a Cumber euen him selfe say no. «B»ut how can we disguyse our selues so soone, euery poynt lyke Mooreton and Earle Pembrook? «f» otherwise of force we must be knowen? Tu«sh» weele no shapes, nor none of these disguysings, they «ht»ofore seru'de bothe his turne and myne, As no ye are, so shall ye passe the gate. And for the blame shall not relye alone, on poore Iohn Cumber, when the faulte is spyed, albeit his skill will be the lesse therby: The Prince Llwellen, and the Earle of Chester, shall bothe be by, and graunt as much as he. Nay more, them selues shall bring ye to the Chappell, and at their handes shall you receiue your Brydes. If this I doo not ere two houres be spent, Neuer let me be calld more Iohn a Kent. Powesse. [Ah peerelesse Iohn, wt h looue, with life and landes,] [will we requyte this kindnes at thy hands.] /embracing. S. Griffin [And sing sweet Sonnets in thy endlesse prayse,] [while our fayre looues and we enioy our dayes] Iohn. [Let vs away, it is vppon their c?ming.] [ffor they think long vntill the deed be doone,] [wherby Iohn hopes his credit will be wun.] exeunt. Enter Llwellen, Chester, Countesse, Sydanen, Marian, Oswen, Amery, Iohn a Cumber, and Abbot. Chester. ffeare not my Lord, my selfe haue beene about, and seene the gates mand as they ought to be, with spyes besyde that shall regard the walles. And with the Abbot haue I tane this order, Only this gate shall serue for enteraunce. Llwellen.? But by your leaue my Lord, we will entreat, that Iohn a Cumber, till it be dispatchte, will sit as porter, then we may be sure, that practise Iohn a Kent what ere he dare, while he is there the lesse neede be our care. Cumber. Alas my Lordes, I see what he intends, to come in person like this reuerend Abbot, therby to get in Griffin and Lord Powesse. but therin Ile preuent him, feare ye not. ffather take you the Ladyes to your charge, and wt h the Countesse lead them to the Chappell you twayne will stay vntill the Brydegroomes come. then afterward let all the charge be mine. Countesse. [Come loouely Niece and Marian, wend with me,] [this day will end the greefes wherin you be.] Sydanen [But may it prooue as poore Sidanen wish,] [else her hart cares will farre surmount her blisse.] Marian [Now Iohn a Kent if euer thou shewedst skill, doo it at this instant, and our ioyes fulfill.] exeunt Coun. Syd. Ma. Ab. Llwellen.? I wunder that these Lordes doo stay so long, so soone as we they sayd they would be heere. Enter Iohn a Kent a loof of, Griffin and Lord Powesse. Iohn. Goe on and feare not, now Iohn we shall see, if ye can help your eyes infirmitie. Chester O heere they be, fye Lordes why stay ye so? the other would haue made more haste I knowe. Cumber. Be thou their guyde, goe, quickly make an end, and then let Iohn a Kent my skill c?mend. exeunt. O rare Magitian that hast not the power, to beat asyde a sillie dazeling mist, which a mere abce scholler in the arte, can doo it with the least facillitie. But I will ease him when the other come, «T»o see how then he will bestirre him selfe. Enter Moorton and Pembrooke «??sti?l» doe «my» Lord that there «????» «??????????????» d me wh«??»e r I had not parted wt h them but By thy leaue Iohn, say, are the Cu«m»ber. Alas, alas, hath cunning Iohn no wiser way then this to f«??» Goe aske of him whether the and he will say they are wed Moorton. wedded? to whom? I hope Cumber. To them whose counterfeite to noble Earle Pembrook Pemb. Are not we they? what? a Cumber. how ere I am, no passage w for you or him, although he d Iohn. why Gentlemen, can ye thi Is this the man whose kno«w» to face ye downe ye be no Enter Chester. Llw Cumber why how now Lordes, wh Llwellen. At that which now is to Prince Griffin and vnto our daughter we tooke them f Chester. heere you (my Lor while you h«o» you come to Moorton. Oswen, sp Oswen. Iest tho Earle you m for «?» «E» Amery [Here probably 35 lines are lost.] «???? ? ???y????????» «ha»d beene to haue wrongde them. doo the lyke confesse, «??»d Sydanen nere the lesse. lds as toward me you meant, «t»hanke thee Iohn a Kent. «?» must yeeld her « ???? t»oo «?» you had so much to doo. «??» make ye waste the time in vayne, «??»e as [these times] this day requires, «??»er, be not thou displeasde, least these amourous cares hath easde. «t»o be disgraste by thee, r bothe of mine and me. des, and euer more heerafter vow continuall looue. «f»ortune was not euill, ouermatchte the deuill. exeunt. is. Anthony Mundy Decembris 1596.</field>
   </doc>
</add>