<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Fletcher, John, 1579-1625</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Fletcher, John, 1579-1625</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">fletcher john 1579 1625</field>
      <field name="author_text">Fletcher, John, 1579-1625</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">17th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V1.0165.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1647</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:458924</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Tragedie of Valentinian</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 17th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 17th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Tragedie of Valentinian</field>
      <field name="title_facet">tragedie of valentinian</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">tragedie of valentinian</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Tragedie of Valentinian</field>
      <field name="year_display">1647</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1647</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1647</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:458924&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:458924&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Fletcher, John, 1579-1625&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;fletcher john 1579 1625&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Tragedie of Valentinian&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;tragedie of valentinian&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1647&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1647&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Fletcher, John&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1579&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1625&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Tragedie of Valentinian&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for Humphrey Robinson ... and for Humphrey Moseley [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1647&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3871593-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv10165&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 17th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;17th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Tragedie of Valentinian&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 267 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted. Plays reproduced elsewhere in English Verse Drama omitted&lt;lb/&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;lb/&gt;Epigraph, dedication and commendatory poems included with The Mad Lover&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Valentinian.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1647.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 1610–1614.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE TRAGEDIE OF VALENTINIAN.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Actus primus. Scæna prima. Enter Balbus, Proculus, Chilax, Licinius. Bal. I never saw the like, shee's no more stirr'd, No more another woman, no more alter'd, With any hopes or promises layd to her (Let 'em be nev'r so waighty, nev'r so winning, Then I am with the motion of my owner legs. Pro. Chilax. You are a stranger yet in these designes, At least in Rome; tell me, and tell me truth, Did you ere know in all your course of practise, In all the wayes of woman you have runne through (For I presume you have been brought up Chilax, As we to fetch and carry.) Chi. True I have so: Pro. Did you I say againe in all this progresse, Ever discover such a peece of beauty, Ever so rare a Creature, and no doubt One that must know her worth too, and affect it, I and be flatter'd, else tis none: and honest? Honest against the tide of all temptations, Honest to one man, to her husband only, And yet not eighteene, not of age to know Why she is honest? Chi. I confesse it freely, I never saw her fellow, nor er'e shall, For all our Græcian Dames, all I have tri'd, (And sure I have tri'd a hunderd, if I say two I speake within my compasse) all these beauties, And all the constancy of all these faces, Mayds, Widdows, Wives, of what degree or calling, So they be Greekes, and fat, for there's my cunning, I would undertake and not sweat for't, Proculus, Were they to try againe, say twice as many, Vnder a thousand pound, to lay 'em bedrid; But this Wench staggers me. Lyc. Doe you see these Iewells? You would thinke these pretty baytes; now Ile assure ye Here's halfe the wealth of Asia. Bal. These are nothing To the full honours I propounded to her; I bid her think, and be, and presently What ever her ambition, what the Councell Of others would adde to her, what her dreames Could more enlarge, what any President Of any woman rising up to glory, And standing certaine there, and in the highest, Could give her more, nay to be Empresse. Pro. And cold at all these offers? Bal. Cold as Christall, Never to be thaw'd again, Chi. I trid her further, And so farre, that I think she is no woman, At least as women goe now. Lyc. Why what did you? Chi. I offerd that, that had she been but Mistris Of as much spleene as Doves have, I had reach'd her; A safe revenge of all that ever hates her, The crying down for ever all beauties That may be thought come neare her. Pro. That was pretty. Chi. I never knew that way faile, yet Ile tell ye I offerd her a gift beyond all yours, That, that had made a Saiuct start, well considerd, The Law to be her creature, she to make it, Her mouth to give it, every creature living From her aspect, to draw their good or evill Fixd in 'em spight of Fortune; a new Nature She should be called, and mother of all ages, Time should be hers, and what she did lame vertue Should blesse to all posterities: her aire Should give us life, her earth and water feed us. And last, to none but to the Emperour, (And then but when she pleas'd to have it so,) She should be held for mortall. Lyc. And she heard you? Chi. Yes, as a Sick man heares a noise, or he That stands condemn'd his Iudgment, let me perish, But if there can be vertue, if that name Be any thing but name and emptie title, If it be so as fooles have been pleas'd to faigne it, A power that can preserve us after ashes, And make the names of men out-reckon ages, This Woman has a God of vertue in her. Bal. I would the Emperor were that God. Chi. She has in her All the contempt of glory and vaine seeming Of all the Stoicks, all the truth of Christians, And all their Constancy: Modesty was made When she was first intended: When she blushes It is the holyest thing to looke upon; The purest temple of her sect, that ever Made nature a blest Founder. Pro. Is there no way To take this Phenix? Lyc. None but in her ashes. Chi. If she were fat, or any way inclining To ease or pleasure, or affected glory, Proud to be seene and worship'd, t'were a venture; But on my soule she is chaster then cold Camphire. Bal. I thinke so too; for all the wayes of woman, Like a full saile she bears against: I aske her After my many offers, walking with her, And her as many down-denyals, how If the Emperor grown mad with love should force her; She pointed to a Lucrece, that hung by, And with an angry looke, that from her eyes Shot Vestall fire against me, she departed. Pro. This is the first wench I was ever pos'd in, Yet I have brought young loving things together This two and thirty yeare. Chi. I find by this wench The calling of a Bawd to be a strange, A wife, and subtile calling; and for none But staid, discreet, and understanding people: And as the Tutor to great Alexander, Would say a young man should not dare to read His morall books, till after five and twenty; So must that he or she, that will be bawdy, (I meane discreetly bawdy, and be trusted) If they will rise, and gaine experience, Wel steept in yeares, and discipline, begin it, I take it tis no boys play. Bal. Well, what's thought off? Pro. The Emperour must know it. Lyc. If the women should chance to faile too, Chi. As tis ten to one, Pro. Why what remaines, but new nets for the purchase? Chi. Let's goe consider then: and if all faile, This is the first quick Eele, that sav'd her taile. Exeunt. Scæne 2. Enter Lucina, Ardelia, and Phorba. Ardelia. You still insist upon that Idoll, Honour, Can it renue your youth, can it adde wealth, That takes off wrinkles: can it draw mens eyes, To gaze upon you in your age? can honour, That truly is a Saint to none but Souldiers, And lookd into, beare no reward but danger, Leave you the most respected person living? Or can the common kisses of a husband, (Which to a sprightly Lady is a labour) Make ye almost Immortall? ye are cozend, The honour of a woman is her praises; The way to get these, to be seene, and sought too, And not to bury such a happy sweetnesse Vnder a smoaky roofe. Luci. Ile heare no more: Phor. That white, and red, and all that blessed beauty, Kept from the eyes, that make it so, is nothing; Then you are rarely faire, when men proclaime it; The Phenix, were she never seene, were doubted, That most unvalued Horne the Vnicorne Beares to oppose the Huntsman, were it nothing But tale, and meere tradition, would help no man, But when the vertue's knowne, the honor's dobled: Vertue, is either lame, or not at all, And Love a sacriledge, and not a Saint, When it bars up the way to mens Petitions. Ard. Nay ye shal love your husband too; we come not To make a Monster of yee; Luc. Are ye women? Ard. You'l find us so, and women you shall think too, If you have grace to make your use. Luc. Fye on yee, Phor. Alas poore bashfull Lady, by my soule, Had ye no other vertue, but your blushes, And I a man, I should run mad for those: How daintlily they set her off, how sweetly? Ard. Come Goddesse, come, you move too neer the earth, It must not be, a better or be staies for you: Here: be a mayd, and take 'en, Luc. Pray leave me. Phor. That were a sin sweet Lady, and a way To make us guilty of your melancholly; You must not be alone; In conversation Doubts are resolv'd, and what sticks neer the conscience Made easie, and allowable. Luc. Ye are Devills, Ard. That you may one day blesse for your damnation. Luc. I charge ye in the name of Chastity, Tempt me no more; how ugly ye seem to me? There is no wonder men defame our Sex, And lay the vices of all ages on us, When such as you shall beare the names of women; If ye had eyes to see your selves, or sence Above the base rewards ye play the bawds for: If ever in your lives ye heard of goodnesse, (Though many Regions off, as men heare thunder) If ever ye had Mothers, and they soules: If ever Fathers, and not such as you are; If ever any thing were constant in you, Beside your sins, or comming but your curses, If ever any of your Ancestors Dyde worth a noble deed, that would be cherishd, Soule-frighted with this black infection, You would run from one another, to repentance, And from your guilty eyes drop out those sins, That made ye blind, and beasts. Phor. Ye speak well Lady; A signe of fruitfull education, If your religious Zeale had wisdome with it. Ard. This Lady was ordain'd to blesse the Empire, And we may all give thanks for't. Phor. I beleive ye, Ard. If any thing redeem the Emperour, From his wild flying courses, this is she; She can instruct him if ye mark; she is wise too. Phor. Exceeding wise, which is a wonder in her, And so religious, that I well believe, Though she would sinne she cannot. Ard. And, besides She has the Empires cause in hand, not loves; There lies the maine consideration, For which she is chiefly borne. Phor. She finds that point Stronger then we can tell her, and believe it I look by her meanes for a reformation, And such a one, and such a rare way carried That all the world shall wonder at. Ard. Tis true; I never thought the Emperor had wisdom, Pittie, or faire affection to his Country, Till he profest this love: gods give'em Children, Such as her vertues merit, and his zeale. I looke to see a Numa from this Lady, Or greater then Octavius. Phor. Do you mark too, Which is a Noble vertue, how she blushes, And what a flowing modesty runs through her, When we but name the Emperour? Ard. But mark it, Yes, and admire it too, for she considers, Though she be faire as heaven, and vertuous As holy truth, yet to the Emperour She is a kind of nothing but her service, Which she is bound to offer, and shee'l do it, And when her Countries cause commands affection; She knows obedience is the key of vertues, Then flye the blushes out like Cupids arrowes. And though the tye of marriage to her Lord, Would faine cry stay Lucina, yet the cause And generall wisdom of the Princes love, Makes her find surer ends and happier, And if the first were chaste, this is twice dobled. Phor. Her tartnes unto us too. Ard. That's a wise one. Phor. I rarely like, it shewes a rising wisdom, That chides all common fooles as dare enquire What Princes would have private. Ard. What a Lady Shall we be blest to serve? Luc. Goe get ye from me. Ye are your purses Agents, not the Princes: Is this the vertuous Lore yee traind me out too? Am I a woman fit to imp your vices? But that I had a Mother, and a woman Whose ever living fame turnes all it touches, Into the good it selfe is, I should now Even doubt my selfe, I have been search't so neere The very soule of honour: why should you two, That happily have been as chast as I am, Fairer, I think, by much, for yet your faces, Like ancient well built piles, shew worthy ruines, After that Angell age, turne mortall Devills? For shame, for woman-hood, for what ye have been, For rotten Cedars have borne goodly branches, If ye have hope of any Heaven, but Court, Which like a Dreame, you'l find hereafter vanish, Or at the best but subject to repentance, Study no more to be ill spoken of; Let women live themselves, if they must fall, Their owne destruction find 'em, not your fevours. Ard. Madam, yee are so excellent in all, And I must tell it you with admiration, So true a joy ye have, so sweet a feare, And when ye come to anger, tis so noble, That for mine own part, I could still offend, To heare you angry; women that want that, And your way guided (else I count it nothing) Are either Fooles, or Cowards. Phor. She were a Mistris for no private greatnesse, Could she not frowne a ravishd kisse from anger, And such an anger as this Lady learnes us, Stuck with such pleasing dangers. Gods (I aske ye) Which of ye all could hold from? Luc. I perceive ye, Your owne dark sins dwell with yee, and that price You sell the chastitie of modest wives at Runs to diseases with your bones: I scorne ye, And all the nets ye have pitcht to catch my vertues Like Spiders Webs, I sweep away before me. Goe tell the Emperour, yee have met a woman, That neither his owne person, which is God-like, The world he rules, nor what that world can purchase, Nor all the glories subject to a Cesar, The honours that he offers for my body, The hopes, gifts, everlasting flatteries, Nor any thing that's his, and apt to tempt me, No not to be the Mother of the Empire, And Queene of all the holy fires he worships, Can make a Whore of. Ard. You mistake us Lady. Luc. Yet tell him this ha's thus much weakend me, That I have here his knaves, and you his Matrons, Fit Nurses for his sins, which gods forgive me, But ever to be leaning to his folly, Or to be brought to love his lust, assure him, And from her mouth, whose life shal make it certain I never can: I have a Noble husband, Pray tell him that too, yet a noble name, A Noble Family, and last a Conscience: Thus much for your answer: For your selves, Ye have liv'd the shame of women, dye the better, Exit Lucina. Phor. What's now to doe? Ard. Ev'n as she said, to dye, For ther's no living here, and women thus, I am sure for us two. Phor. Nothing stick upon her? Ard. We have lost a masse of mony; wel Dame vertue, Yet ye may halt if good luck serve. Phor. Wormes take her, She has almost spoil'd our trade, Ard. So godly; This is ill breeding Phorba. Phor. If the women Should have a longing now to see this Monster, And she convert 'em all. Ard. That may be Phorba, But if it be, Ile have the young men gelded: Come, let's goe think, she must not scape us thus; There is a certain season, if we hit, That women may be rid without a bit. Exeunt. Scæn. 3. Enter Maximus and Æcius. Max. I cannot blame the Nations noble friend, That they fall off so fast from this wild man, When (under our Allegeance be it spoken, And the most happy tye of our affections) The worlds weight groanes beneath him; where lives vertue, Honour, discretion, wisdom? who are cald And chosen to the steering of the Empire But Baudes, and singing Girles? ô my Aecius, The glory of a Souldier, and the truth Of men made up for goodnesse sake, like shells Grow to the ragged walls for want of action: Only your happy selfe, and I that love ye, Which is a larger meanes to me then favour. Æcius. No more my worthy friend, though these be truths, And though these truthes would aske a Reformation, At least a little squaring; yet remember, We are but subjects Maximus; obedience To what is done, and griefe for what is ill done, Is all we can call ours: the hearts of Princes Are like the Temples of the gods; pure incense, Vntill vnhallowed hands defile those offrings, Burnes ever there; we must not put 'em out, Because the Priests that touch those sweetes are wicked; We dare not deerest friend, nay more we cannot, While we consider why we are, and how, To what lawes bound, much more to what Law-giver; Whilest majestie is made to be obeyed, And not inquired into, whilest Gods and Angels Make but a rule as we do, though a stricter; Like desperate and unseason'd fooles let fly Our killing angers, and forsake our honors. Max. My noble Freind, from whose Instructions I never yet tooke surfet, weigh but thus much, Nor thinke I speake it with ambition, For by the Gods I do not, why Æcius, Why are we thus, or how become thus wretched? Æcius. You'l fall againe into your fit. Max. I will not. Or are we now no more the sons of Romanes, No more the followers of their happy fortunes, But conquer'd Gaules, or Quivers for the Parthians? Why is this Emperor, this man we honor, This God that ought to be? Æcius. You are too curious. Max. Good, give me leave, why is this Author of us? Æci. I dare not heare ye speake thus. Max. Ile be modest, Thus led away, thus vainly led away, And we beholders, misconceive me not, I sow no danger in my words; but wherefore And to what end, are we the sonnes of Fathers Famous, and fast to Rome? Why are their vertues Stampt in the dangers of a thousand Battailes, For goodnesse sake, their honors, time out daring, I thinke for our example. Æci. Ye speake nobly. Mac. Why are we seeds of these then, to shake hands With Bawdes and base Informers, kisse discredit, And court her like a Mistris? pray, your leave yet; You'l say the Emperor is young, and apt To take impression rather from his pleasures Then any constant worthynsse, it may be. But why do these, the people call his pleasures, Exceed the moderation of a man? Nay to say justly freind, why are they vices And such as shake our worthes with forraigne Nations? Æc. You search the soare too deep, and I must tel ye, In any other man this had been boldnesse, And so rewarded; pray depresse you spirit, For though I constantly beleeve ye honest, Ye were no freind for me else, and what now Ye freely spake, but good ye owe toth Empire, Yet take heed worthy Maximus, all eares Heare not with that distinction mine doe, few You'l find admonishers, but urgers of your actions, And to the heaviest (freind;) and pray consider We are but shadowes, motions others give us, And though our pitties may become the times, Iustly our powers cannot; make me worthy To be your ever freind in faire allegiance, But not in force: For durst mine own soule urge me (And by that soule, I speake my just affections) To turn my hand from truth, which is obedience, And give the helme my vertue holds, to Anger, Though I had both the blessings of the Brutij, And both their Instigations, though my cause Carried a face of Iustice beyond theirs, And as I am a servant to my fortunes, That daring soule, that first taught disobedience, Should feele the first example: Say the Prince, As I may well beleeve, seemes vitious, Who justly knowes tis not to try our honors? Or say he be an ill Prince, are we therefore Fit fires to purge him? No, my dearest freind The Elephant is never won with anger, Nor must that man that would reclaime a Lyon, Take him by'th teeth. Max. I pray mistake me not. Æci. Our honest actions, and the light that breakes Like morning from our service, chaste and blushing Is that, that pulls a Prince backe; then he sees, And not till then truly repents his errors, When subjects Chrystall soules are glasses to him. Max. My ever honored freind, Ile take your councel: The Emperor appeares, Ile leave ye to him, And as we both affect him, may be flourish. Exit Max. Enter the Emperor and Chilax. Empe. Is that the best newes? Chil. Yet the best we know Sir. Empe. Bid Maximus come to me, and be gone then: Mine own head be my helper, these are fooles; How now Æcius, are the Souldiers quiet? Æci. Better I hope Sir, then they were. Empe. They are pleas'd I heare, To censure me extremely for my pleasures, Shortly they'l fight against me. Æci. Gods defend Sir. And for their censures they are such shrew'd Iudgers; A donative of ten Sesterties Ile undertake shall make 'em ring your praises, More then they sang your pleasures. Empe. I beleeve thee. Art thou in love Æcius yet? Æci. O no Sir. I am too course for Ladies; my embraces That only am acquainted with Alarums, Would break their tender bodies. Empe. Never feare it, They are stronger then ye think, they'le hold the hammer My Empresse sweares thou art a lusty Souldier, A good one I beleeve thee. Æci. All that goodnesse Is but your Graces creature. Empe. Tell me truly, For thou darst tell me. Æci. Any thing concernes ye, That's fit for me to speake and you to pardon. Emp. What say the soldiers of me, and the same words, Mince 'em not good Æcius, but deliver The very forms and tongues they talke withall, Æci. Ile tell your Grace, but with this caution You be not stirr'd, for should the Gods live with us, Even those we certainly beleeve are righteous, Give 'em but drinke, they would censure them too. Empe. Forward. Æci. Then to begin, they say you sleep too much By which they judge your Majesty too sensuall, Apt to decline your strength to ease and pleasures, And when you do not sleepe, you drink too much, From which they feare suspitions first, then ruines; And when ye neither drinke nor sleepe, ye wench much, Which they affirm first breakes your understanding, Then takes the edge of honor, makes us seeme, That are the ribbes, and rampires of the Empire, Fencers, and beaten Fooles, and so regarded; But I beleive 'em not; for were these truths, Your vertue can correct them. Empe. They speake plainly. Æc. They say moreover (since your grace wil have it, For they will talke their freedoms, though the sword Were in their throat) that of late time, like Nero, And with the same forgetfullnes of glory, You have got a vaine of filing, so they terme it. Empe. Some drunken dreames Æcius. Æci. So I hope Sir. And that you rather study cruelty. And to be feared for blood, then lov'd for bounty. Which makes the Nations, as they say, despise ye, Telling your yeares and actions by their deathes, Whose truth, and strength of duty made you Cæsar. They say besides you nourish strange devourers, Fed with the fat o'th Empire, they call Bawdes, Lazie and lustfull creatures that abuse ye. A people as they terme 'em, made of paper, In which the secret sins of each mans monyes Are sealed and sent a working. Empe. What sin's next? For I perceive they have no mind to spare me. Æci. Nor hurt ye ô my soule Sir; but such people (Nor can the power of man restraine it) When they are full of meat and ease, must prattle. Empe. Forward. Æci. I have spoken too much Sir. Empe. Ile have all. Æci. It fits not Your eares should heare their vanities; no profit Can justly rise to you from their behaviour, Vnlesse ye were guilty of those crimes. Empe. It may be I am so, therefore forward. Æci. I have ever Learn'd to obey, nor shall my life resist it. Empe. No more Apologies. Æci. They greive besides Sir, To see the nations, whom our ancient vertue With many a weary march and hunger conquer'd, With losse of many a daring life subdude, Fall from their faire obedience, and even murmure To see the warlike Eagles mew their honors In obscure Townes, that wont to prey on Princes, They cry for enemies, and tel the Captaines The fruits of Italy are luscious, give us Ægypt, Or sandy Affrick to display our valours, There were our Swords may make us meat, and danger Digest our well got Vyands: here our weapons And bodyes that were made for shining brasse, Are both unedg'd and old with ease, and women; And then they cry agen, where are the Germaines, Linde with hot Spaine, or Gallia, bring 'em on, And let the son of war, steel'd Mithridutes, Lead up his winged Parthians like a storme, Hiding the face of Heaven with showres of arrowes; Yet we dare fight like Romanes; then as Souldiers Tyr'd with a weary march, they tell their wounds Even weeping ripe they were no more nor deeper, And glory in those scarrs that make 'em lovely, And sitting where a Campe was, like sad Pilgrims They reckon up the times, and living labours Of Julius or Germanicus, and wonder That Rome, whose turrets once were topt with honours, Can now forget the Custome of her conquests: And then they blame your Grace, and say who leads us, Shall we stand here like Statues? were our Fathers The Sonnes of lazie Moores, our Princes Persians, Nothing but silkes, and softnesse? curses on 'em That first taught Nero wantonnesse, and bloud, Tiberius doubts, Caligula all vices; For from the spring of these succeeding Princes Thus they talke Sir; Emp. Well, Why doe you heare these things? Aec. Why do you do 'em? I take the gods to witnesse, with more sorrow, And more vexation, doe I heare these taintures, Then were my life dropt from me through an hour-glasse Emp. Belike then you beleeve 'em, or at least Are glad they should be so; take heed, you were better Build your own Tomb, and runne into it living, Then dare a Princes anger. Aec. I am old Sir, And ten yeares more addition, is but nothing: Now if my life be pleasing to ye, take it, Vpon my knees, if ever any service, As let me brag, some have bin worthy notice, If ever any worth, or trust ye gave me, Deserv'd a faire respect, if all my actions, The hazards of my youth, colds, burnings, wants, For you and for the Empire, be not vices; By that stile ye have stampt upon me, Souldier, Let me not fall into the hands of wretches. Emp. I understand ye not. Aec. Let not this body. That has lookd bravely in his bloud for Cesar, And covetous of wounds, and for your safety, After the scape of Swords, Speares, Slings, and Arrows, Gainst which my beaten body was mine Armour, The Seas, and thirstie deserts, now be purchase For Slaves, and base Informers: I see anger, And death look through your eyes: I am markt for slaughter And know the telling of this truth has made me A man cleane lost to this world; I embrace it; Only my last Petition sacred Cesar, Is, I may dye a Roman. Emp. Rise my friend still, And worthy of my love; Reclaime the Souldier, Ile study to doe so upon my selfe too, Goe keep your command, and prosper. Aec. Life to Cesar— Exit Aecius—Enter Chilax. Chi. Lord Maximus attends your Grace. Emp. Goe tell him, Ile meete him in the gallery. The honesty of this Aecius Who is indeed the Bull-wark of the Empire, Has div'd so deep into me, that of all The sins I covet, but this womans beautie, With much repentance, now I could be quit of: But she is such a pleasure, being good, That though I were a god, she would fire my bloud. Exit.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Actus Secundus. Scæna prima. Enter the Emperour, Maximus, Lycinius, Proculus, Chilax, as at Dice. Emp. Nay ye shall set my hand out, tis not just I should neglect my fortune, now tis prosperous. Lyc. If I have any thing to set your Grace, But Clothes or good conditions, let me perish, You have all my mony Sir; Pro. And mine, Chi. And mine too. Max. Vnlesse your Grace will credit us, Emp. No bare boord, Lyc. Then at my Garden-House; Emp. The Orchard too. Lyc. And 't please your Grace, Emp. Have at 'em, Pro. They are lost; Lyc. Why farewell Fig-trees, Emp. Who sets more? Chil. At my Horse Sir, Emp. The dapl'd Spaniard? Chil. He. Emp. He's mine, Chil. He is so; Max. Your shorthorse is soone curried: Chil. So it seemes Sir, So may your Mare be too, if luck serve. Max. Ha? Ch. Nothing my Lord but grieving at my fortune, Emp. Come Maximus, you were not wont to flinch thus Max. By Heaven Sir, I have lost all. Emp. Ther's a ring yet, Max. This was not made to loose Sir, Emp. Some love token; Set it I say; Max. I doe beseech your Grace, Rather name any house I have. Emp. How strange, And curious you are growne of toyes? redeem't If so I win it, when you please, to morrow, Or next day as ye will, I care not, But only for my luck sake: Tis not Rings Can make me richer. Max. Will you throw Sir? there 'tis: Emp. Why then have at it fairely: myne. Max. Your Grace Is only ever fortunate: to morrow, An't be your pleasure Sir, Ile pay the price on't; Emp. To morrow you shall have it without price Sir, But this day 'tis my victory: good Maximus, Now I bethink my selfe, goe to Æcius, And bid him muster all the Cohorts presently; They mutiny for pay I heare, and be you Assistant to him; when you know their numbers, Ye shall have monyes for 'em, and above Something to stop their tongues withall. Max. I will Sir, And gods preserve you in this mind still. Emp. Shortly Ile see 'em march my selfe. Max. Gods ever keep ye.— Exit Max. Emp. To what end doe you think this ring shall serve now? For you are fellowes only know by roate, As birds record their lessons. Chil. For the Lady, Emp. But how for her? Chil. That I confesse I know not, Emp. Then pray for him that do's: fetch me an Eunuch That never saw her yet: and you two see Exit. Chil. The Court made like a Paradise. Lyc. We will Sir. Emp. Full of faire shewes and Musiques; all your arts (As I shall give instructions) screw to 'th highest, For my maine peece is now a doing: and for feare You should not take, Ile have an other engine, Such as if vertue be not only in her, She shall not choose but leane to, let the women Put on a graver shew of welcome. Pro. Well Sir. Emp. They are a thought too eager.— Enter Chilax and Lycias the Eunuch. Chil. Here's the Eunuch, Eun. Long life to Cesar. Emp. I must use you Lycias: Come let's walk in, and then Ile shew ye all: If women may be fraile, this wench shall fall. Exeunt. Scæne 2. Enter Claudia, and Marcellina. Claudia. Sirrha, what ayles my Lady, that of late She never cares for company? Mar. I know not, Vnlesse it be that company causes Cuckolds. Clau. That were a childish feare; Mar. What were those Ladyes, Came to her lately, From the Court? Clau. The same wench. Some grave Instructors on my life, they look For all the world like old hactht hilts. Mar. Tis true wench. For here and there, and yet they painted well too, One might discover where the gold was worne Their Iron ages. Clau. If my judgment faile not, They have been sheathed like rotten ships, Mar. It may be. Clau. For if ye mark their rudders, they hang weakly. Mar. They have past the line belike: wouldst live Clau. Till thou wert such as they are? Clau. Chimney pieces. Now heaven have mercy on me, and young men, I had rather make a drallery till thirty, While I were able to endure a tempest, And beare my fights out bravely, till my tackle Whistled i'th wind, and held against all weathers, While I were able to beare with my tyres And so discharg 'em, I would willingly Live Marcellina, not till barnacles Bred in my sides. Mar. Thou art i'th right wench. For who would live, whom pleasures had forsaken, To stand at marke, and cry a bow short signeur? Were there not men came hither too? Clau. Brave fellowes. I feare me Bawdes of five i'th' pound. Mar. How know you? Clau. They gave me great lights to it. Mar. Take heed Claudia. Clau. Let them take heed, the spring comes on. Mar. To me now, They seem'd as noble visitants. Clau. To me now Nothing lesse Marcellina, for I marke 'em, And by this honest light, for yet tis morning, Saving the reverence of their guilded doublets And Millan skins. Mar. Thou art a strange wench Claudia. Clau. Ye are deceived, they shew'd to me directly Court crabbs that creepe a side way for their living I know 'em by the breeches that they beg'd last, Mar. Peace, my Lady comes; what may that be? Clau. A Sumner Enter Lucina, and Lycias the Eunuch. That cites her to appeare. Mar. No more of that wench. Eun. Madam, what answer to your Lord? Luci. Pray tell him, I am subject to his will, Eun. Why weepe you Madam? Excellent Lady, there are none will hurt you. Luci. I do beseech you tell me Sir. Eun. What Lady? Luci. Serve ye the Emperor? Eun. I do. Luci. In what place? Eun. In's chamber Madam. Luci. Do ye serve his will too? Eun. In faire and just commands. Luci. Are ye a Romane? Eun. Yes noble Lady, and a Mantuan. Luci. What office bore your parents? Eun. One was Pretor. Luci. Take heed then how you staine his reputation, Eun. Why worthy Lady? Luci. If ye know, I charge ye, Ought in this Message, but what honesty, The trust and faire obedience of a servant, May well deliver, yet take heed, and help me. Eun. Madam, I am no Broker; Claud. Ile be hangd then. Eun. Nor base procurer of mens lusts; Your husband, Praid me to doe this office, I have done it, It rests in you to come, or no: Luc. I will Sir; Eun. If ye mistrust me, doe not, Luc. Ye appeare so worthy, And to all my sence so honest, And this is such a certain signe ye have brought me, That I believe. Eun. Why should I couzen you? Or were I brib'd to doe this villany, Can mony prosper, or the foole that takes it, When such a vertue falls? Luc. Ye speake well Sir; Would all the rest that serve the Emperour, Had but your way. Claud. And so they have ad unguem: Luc. Pray tell my Lord, I have receivd his Token, And will not faile to meete him; yet good Sir, thus much Before you goe, I doe beseech ye too, As little notice as ye can, deliver Of my appearance there, Eun. It shall be Madam, And so I wish you happinesse. Luc. I thank you.— Exeunt. Scæn. 2. Enter Æcius pursuing Pontius the Captaine, and Maximus following. Tumult &amp; noise within. Max. Temper your selfe Æcius, Pon. Hold my Lord. I am a Roman, and a Souldier, Max. Pray Sir; Æci. Thou art a lying Villaine, and a Traytor; Give me my selfe, or by the Gods my friend You'l make me dangerous; how dar'st thou pluck The Souldiers to sedition, and I living, And so Rebellion in 'em, and even then When I am drawing out to action? Pon. Heare me, Max. Are yee a man? Æci. I am a true hearted Maximus, And if the Villaine live, we are dishonourd. Max. But heare him what he can say. Æci. That's the way, To pardon him; I am so easie naturd, That if he speak but humbly I forgive him. Pon. I doe beseech yee Noble Generall, Æci. Has found the was already, give me rome, One stroake, and if he scape me then ha's mercy; Pon. I doe not call yee Noble, that I feare ye, I never care'd for death; if ye will kill me, Consider first for what, not what you can doe; Tis true, I know ye for my Generall, And by that great Prerogative may kill: But doe it justly then. Æci. He argues with me. By Heaven a made up Rebell. Max. Pray consider, What certaine grounds ye have for this. Æci. What grounds? Did I not take him preaching to the Souldiers How lazily they liv'd, and what dishonours It was to serve a Prince so full of woman. Those were his very words, friend; Max. These, Æcius, Though they were rashly spoke, which was an errour (A great one Pontius) yet from him that hungers For warres, and brave imployment, might be pardond. The heart, and harbourd thoughts of ill, make Traytors, Not spleeny speeches. Æci. Why should you protect him? Goe too, it shewes not honest; Max. Taynt me not, For that shewes worse Æcius: All your friendship And that pretended love ye lay upon me, Hold back my honesty, is like a favour You doe your slave to day, to morrow hang him, Was I your bosome peece for this? Æci. Forgive me. The nature of my zeale, and for my Country, Makes me sometimes forgive my selfe; for know, Though I most strive to be without my passions, I am no God: For you Sir, whose infection Ha's spread it selfe like poyson through the Army, And cast a killing fogge on faire Allegiance, First thank this Noble Gentleman, y'e had dy'de else. Next from your place, and honour of a Souldier, I here seclude you. Pon. May I speak yet? Max. Heare him: Æci. And while Æcius holds a reputation, At least command, ye beare no Armes for Rome Sir. Pon. Against her I shall never: The condemnd man, Ha's yet that priviledge to speak my Lord; Law were not equall else. Max. Pray heare Aecius, For happily the fault he has committed, Though I believe it mighty, yet considered, If mercy may be thought upon, will prove Rather a hastie sin, then heynous. Aec. Speake. Pon. Tis true my Lord, ye took me tir'de with peace, My words, almost as ragged as my fortunes. Tis true I told the Souldier, whom we serv'd, And then bewaild, we had an Emperour Led from us by the flourishes of Fencers; I blam'd him too for women. Aec. To the rest Sir; Pon. And like enough I blest him then as Souldiers Will doe sometimes: Tis true I told 'em too, We lay at home, to show our Country We durst goe naked, durst want meate, and mony, And when the Slave drinkes Wine, we durst be thirstie: I told 'em this too, that the Trees and Roots Were our best pay-masters; the Charity Of longing women, that had bought our bodies, Our beds, fires, Taylers, Nurses, Nay I told 'em, (For you shall heare the greatest sin, I said Sir) By that time there be wars agen, our bodies Laden with scarres, and aches, and ill lodgings, Heates, and perpetuall wants, were fitter praires, And certaine graves, then cope the foe on crutches: Tis likely too, I counselld 'em to turne Their Warlike pikes to plough-shares, their sure Targets And Swords hatcht with the bloud of many Nations, To Spades, and pruning Knives, for those get mony, Their warlike Eagles, into Dawes, or Starlings, To give an Ave Cesar as he passes, And be rewarded with a thousand dragma's For thus we get but yeares and beets. Æci. What think you, Were these words to be spoken by a Captain, One that should give example? Max. 'Twas too much; Pon. My Lord, I did not wooe 'em from the Empire, Nor bid 'em turne their daring steele gainst Cæsar, The Gods for ever hate me, if that motion Were part of me: Give me but imployment, Sir; And way to live, and where you hold me vicious, Bred up in mutiny, my Sword shall tell ye, And if you please, that place I held, maintaine it, Gainst the most daring foes of Rome, I am honest, A lover of my Country, one that holds His life no longer his, then kept for Cæsar. Weigh not (I thus low on my knee beseech you) What my rude tongue discovered, t'was my want, No other part of Pontius: you have seen me, And you my Lord, doe something for my Country, And both beheld the wounds I gave and took, Not like a backward Traytor. Æci. All this language, Makes but against you Pontius, you are cast, And by mine honor, and my love to Cæsar, By me shall never be restord; In my Campe I will not have a tongue, though to himselfe Dare talke but neere sedition; as I governe, All shall obey, and when they want, their duty And ready service shall redresse their needs, Not prating what they would be. Pon. Thus I leave ye, Yet shall my praires still, although my fortunes Must follow you no more, be still about ye, Gods give ye where ye fight the Victory, Ye cannot cast my wishes. Æci. Come my Lord, Now to the Field agen: Max. Alas poore Pontius.— Exeunt. Scæn. 4. Enter Chilax at one dore, Lycinius, and Balbus at another. Lyc. How now? Chi. Shee's come, Bal. Then Ile to'th Emperor.— Exit Balbus. Chi. Doe; Is the Musick placed well? Lyc. Excellent. Chil. Lycinius, you and Proclus receive her, In the great Chamber at her, entrance, Let me alone; and doe you heare Lycinius, Pray let the Ladies ply her further off, And with much more discretion: one word more, Lyc. Well; Chil. Are the Iewells, and those ropes of Pearle, Layd in the way she passes? Lyc. Take no care man— Exeunt Lyc. —Enter Emperor, Balbus and Proclus. Emp. What is she come? Chil. She is Sir; but t'wer best; Your Grace were seen last to her, Emp. So I mean; Keep the Court emptie Proculus, Pro. Tis done Sir. Emp. Be not too sudaine to hir. Chil. Good your Grace, Retire and man your selfe; let us alone, We are no children this way: doe you heare Sir? Tis necessary that her waiting women Be cut off in the Lobby, by some Ladies, The'd break the businesse else. Emp. Tis true, they shall. Chil. Remember your place Proculus, Pro. I warrant ye.— Exeunt Emperor, Balbus and Pro. Enter Lucina, Claudia, and Marcellina. Chi. She enters: who are waytors there? the Emperor Calls for his Horse to ayre himselfe. Luci. I am glad, I come so happily to take him absent, This takes away a little feare; I know him, Now I begin to feare agen: Oh honour, If ever thou hadst temple in weak woman. And sacrifice of modesty burnt to thee, Hold me fast now, and help me; Chil. Noble Madam, Ye are welcome to the Court, most nobly welcome, Ye are a stranger Lady, Luc. I desire so; Chil. A wondrous stranger here, Nothing so strange: And therefore need a guide I think. Luc. I doe Sir, And that a good one too. Chil. My service Lady. Shall be your guard in this place; But pray ye tell me, Are ye resolv'd a Courtier? Luc. No I hope Sir; Clau. You are Sir. Chil. Yes my faire one, Clau. So it seemes, You are so ready to bestow your selfe, Pray what might cost those Breeches? Chil. Would you weare 'em, Madam ye have a witty woman. Mar. Two Sir, Or else yee underbuy us. Luc. Leave your talking: But is my Lord here, I beseech ye Sir? Chil. He is sweet Lady, and must take this kindly, Exceeding kindly of ye, wondrous kindly Ye come so farre to visit him: Ile guide ye, Luc. Whether? Chil. Why to your Lord, Luc. Is it so hard Sir, To find him in this place without a Guide? For I would willingly not trouble you. Chil. It will be so for you that are a stranger; Nor can it be a trouble to doe service To such a worthy beauty, and besides— Mar. I see he will goe with us. Clau. Let him amble. Chil. It fits not that a Lady of your reckoning, Should passe without attendants. Luc. I have two Sir. Chil. I mean without a man; You'l see the Emperor? Luc. Alas I am not fit Sir, Chil. You are well enough. Hee'l take it wondrous kindly: Harke, Luc. ye flatter, Good Sir, no more of that. Chil. Well, I but tell ye; Luc. Will ye goe forward, since I must be mand, Pray take your place. Claud. Cannot ye man us too Sir? Chil. Give me but time. Mar. And you'l try all things: Chil. No? Hmake ye no such promise, Claud. If ye doe Sir; Take heed ye stand to't. Chil. Wondrous merry Ladies. —Enter Lycinius, and Proculus, Balbus. Luc. The wenches are dispos'd, pray keep your way Sir. Exit Lyc. She is comming up the staires; Now the Musick; And as that stirs her, let's set on: perfumes there. Pro. Discover all the Iewells: Lyc. Peace, Musicke. SONGS. Now the lusty Spring is seene, Golden yellow, gaudy Blew, Daintily invite the view. Every where, on every Greene, Roses blushing as they blow, And inticing men to pull, Lillies whiter then the snow Woodbines of sweet hony full. All loves Emblems and all cry, Ladyes, if not pluck't we dye. Yet the lusty Spring hath stayd, Blushing red and purest white, Daintily to love invite, Every Woman, every Mayd, Cherries kissing as they grow; And inviting men to taste, Apples even ripe below, Winding gently to the waste, All loves emblems and all cry, Ladies, if not pluckt we dye. SECOND. Heare ye Ladies that despise, What the mighty love has done, Feare examples, and be wise, Faire Calisto was a Nun, Læda sayling on the streame, To deceive the hopes of man, Love accounting but a dream, Doted on a silver Swan, Danae in a Brazen Tower, Where no love was, lov'd a Flowre. Heare yee Ladyes that are coy, What the mighty love can doe, Feare the fiercenesse of the Boy, The chaste Moon he makes to woe: Vesta kindling holy fires, Circled round about with spies, Never dreaming loose desires, Doting at the Altar dies. Ilion in a short Tower higher, He can build, and once more fire. Enter Chilax, Lucina, Claudia, and Marcellina. Luc. Pray Heaven my Lord be here, for now I feare it. Well Ring, if thou bee'st counterfeit, or stolne, As by this preparation I suspect it, Thou hast betraid thy Mistris: pray Sir forward, I would faine see my Lord. Chil. But tell me Madam, How doe ye like the Song? Luc. I like the ayre well, But for the words, they are lascivious, And over-light for Ladies. Chil. All ours love 'em. Luc. Tis like enough, for yours are loving Ladies Lyc. Madam, ye are welcome to the Court. Who waits? Attendants for this Lady; Luc. Ye mistake Sir; I bring no triumph with me, Lyc. But much honour. Pro. Why this was nobly done; and like a neighbour, So freely of your selfe to be a visitant, The Emperour shall give ye thanks for this. Luc. O no Sir; Ther's nothing to deserve 'em, Pro. Yes, your presence; Luc. Good Gentlemen be patient, and believe I come to see my husband, on command too, I were no Courtier else. Lyc. That's all one Lady, Now ye are here, y'are welcome, and the Emperor Who loves ye, but too well: Luc. No more of that Sir. I came not to be Catechizd, Pro. Ah Sirah; And have we got you here, faith Noble Lady, Wee'l keep you one month Courtier. Luc. Gods defend Sir, I never likd a trade worse, Pro. Harke ye: Luc. No Sir; Pro. Ye are grown the strangest Lady, Luc. How? Pro. By Heaven, Tis true I tell ye, and you'l find it. Luc. I? Ile rather find my grave, and so informe him. Pro. Is it not pity Gentlemen, this Lady, (Nay Ile deale roughly with ye, yet not hurt ye) Should live alone, and give such heavenly beauty, Only to walls, and hangings? Luc. Good Sir, patience: I am no wonder, neither come to that end, Ye doe my Lord an injury to stay me, Who though ye are the Princes, yet dare tell ye He keeps no wife for your wayes. Bal. Well, well Lady; How ever you are pleasd to think of us, Ye are welcome, and ye shall be welcome; Luc. Shew it In that I come for then, in leading me Where my lov'd Lord is, not in flattery:— Jewells shewd. Nay ye may draw the Curtain, I have seen 'em But none worth halfe my honesty. Claud. Are these Sir, Layd here to take? Pro. Yes, for your Ladys Gentlewoman; Mar. We had been doing else, Bal. Meaner Iewels Would fit your worths; Claud. And meaner clothes your bodies. Luc. The Gods shall kill me first. Lyc. Ther's better dying; I'th Emperors arms goe too, but be not angry— These are but talkes sweet Lady, Enter Phorba, and Ardelia. Phor. Where is this stranger? rushes, Ladyes, rushes, Rushes as greene as Summer for this stranger; Pro. Heer's Ladies come to see you. Luc. You are gone then? I take it tis your Que, Pro. Or rather manners, You are better fitted Madam, we but tire ye, Therefore wee'l leave you for an houre, and bring Your much lov'd Lord unto you— Exeunt. Luc. Then Ile thanke ye, I am betraid for certaine; well Lucina, If thou do'st fall from vertue, may the earth That after death should shout up gardens of thee, Spreading thy living goodnesse into branches, Fly from thee, and the hot Sun find thy vices. Phor. You are a welcom woman; Ard. Blesse me heaven, How did you find the way to Court? Luc. I know not. Would I had never trod it. Phor. Pre-thee tell me, Good Noble Lady, and good sweet heart love us, For we love thee extreamly; is not this place A Paradice to live in? Luc. To those people That know no other Paradice but pleasure, That little I enjoy contents me better. Ard. What heard ye any Musick yet? Luc. Too much. Phor. You must not be thus froward; what, this gown Is one o'th prettiest by my troth Ardelia, I ever saw yet; t'was not to frowne in Lady, Ye put this gowne on when ye came. Ard. How doe ye? Alas poore wretch how cold it is! Luc. Content ye; I am as well as may be, and as temperate, If ye will let me be so: wher's my Lord? For ther's the businesse that I came for Ladies: Phor. Wee'l lead ye to him, hee's i'th Gallery, Ard. Wee'l shew ye all the Court too. Luc. Shew me him, And ye have shewd me all I come to look on, Phor. Come on, wee'l be your guides, and as ye goe, We have some pretty tales to tell ye Lady, Shall make ye merry too; ye come not here, To be a sad Lucina. Luc. Would I might not.— Exeunt.— Enter Chilax and Balbus. Chil. Now the soft Musick; Balbus run— Bal. I flye Boy— Exit Balbus. Chil. The women by this time are worming of her,— If she can hold out them, the Emperour Musicke. Takes her to taske: he h'as her; hark the Musick: Luc. Good your Grace, Where are my women Sir? Emp. They are wise, beholding What you thinke scorne to looke on, the Courts bravery: Would you have run away so slily Lady, And not have seen me? Luc. I beseech your Majestie, Consider what I am, and whose, Emp. I doe so; Luc. Believe me, I shall never make a Whore Sir, Emp. A friend ye may, and to that man that loves ye, More then you love your vertue. Luc. Sacred Cesar, Emp. You shall not kneel to me Sweet, Luc. Look upon me, And if ye be so cruell to abuse me, Think how the Gods will take it; do's this beauty Aflict your soule? Ile hide it from you ever, Nay more, I will become so leprous, That ye shall curse me from ye: My deer Lord, H'as serv'd ye ever truly, fought your Battailes, As if he daily longd to dye for Cesar, Was never Traytor Sir; nor never tainted In all the actions of his life. Emp. I know it. Luc. His fame and family have growne together, And spred together like to sayling Cedars, Over the Roman Diadem; ô let not, As ye have any flesh that's humane in you, The having of a modest wife decline him, Let not my vertue be the wedge to break him, I doe not think ye are lascivious, These wanton men belye ye, you are Cesar, Which is the Father of the Empires honour, Ye are too neere the nature of the Gods, To wrong the weakest of all creatures: Women. Emp. I dare not do it here, rise faire Lucina, I did but try your temper, ye are honest, And with the commendations waite on that Ile lead ye to your Lord, and ye to him: Wipe your faire eyes: he that endeavours ill, May well delay, but never quench his hell.— Exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Actus Tertius. Scæna prima. Enter Chilax, Lycinius, Proculus, and Balbus. Chil. Tis done Lycinius: Lyc. Ho? Chil. I shame to tell it, If there be any justice, we are Villaines, And must be so rewarded. Bal. If it be done, I take it tis no time now to repent it, Let's make the best o'th trade. Pro. Now veng'ance take it. Why should not he have setled on a beauty, Whose honesty stuck in a peece of tissue, Or one a Ring might rule, or such a one That had an itching husband to be honourable, And ground to get it: if he must have women, And no allay without 'em, why not those That know the misery, and are best able To play againe with judgment? such as she is, Grant they be won with long seidge, endlesse travell, And brought to opportunity with millions, Yet when they come to motion, their cold vertue Keeps 'em like cakes of yce; Ile melt a Christall, And make a dead flint fire himselfe, ere they Give greater heate, then now departing embers Gives to old men that watch 'em. Lyc. A good Whore Had sav'd all this, and happily as wholsome, I, and the thing once done too, as well thought of, But this same chastity forsooth, Pro. A Pox on't, Why should not women be as free as we are? They are, but not in open, and far freer, And the more bold ye beare your selfe, more welcome, And there is nothing you dare say, but truth, But they dare heare. Enter Emperor and Lucina. Chi. The Emperour! away, And if we can repent, let's home and pray. Exeunt. Emp. Your only vertue now is patience, Take heede, and save your honour; if you talke, Luc. As long as there is motion in my body, And life to give me words, Ile cry for justice. Emp. Iustice shall never heare ye, I am justice, Luc. Wilt thou not kill me, Monster, Ravisher, Thou bitter bane o'th Empires look upon me, And if thy guilty eyes dare see these ruines, Thy wild lust hath layd levell with dishonour, The sacrilegious razing of this Temple, The mother of thy black sins would have blushed at, Behold and curse thy selfe; the Gods will find thee, That's all my refuge now, for they are righteous, Vengeance and horror circle thee; the Empire, In which thou liv'st a strong continued surfeit, Like poyson will disgorge thee, good men raze thee For ever being read again,—but vicious Women, and fearefull Maids, make vows against thee: Thy own Slaves, if they heare of this, shall hate thee; And those thou hast corrupted first fall from thee; And if thou let'st me live, the Souldier, Tyrde with thy Tyrannies, break through obedience, And shake his strong Steele at thee. Emp. This prevailes not; Nor any Agony ye utter Lady, If I have done a sin, curse her that drew me, Curse the first cause, the witchcraft that abusd me, Curse those faire eyes, and curse that heavenly beauty, And curse your being good too. Luci. Glorious theife, What restitution canst thou make to save me? Emp. Ile ever love, and honour you. Luci. Thou canst not, For that which was mine honour, thou hast murdred, And can there be a love in violence? Emp. You shall be only mine. Luci. Yet I like better Thy villany, then flattery, that's thine owne, The other basely counterfeit; flye from me, Or for thy safety sake and wisdome kill me, For I am worse then thou art; thou mayst pray, And so recover grace; I am lost for ever, And if thou lets't me live, th'art lost thy selfe too Emp. I feare no losse but love, I stand above it. Luci. Call in your Lady Bawdes, and guilded Pander's And let them triumph too, and sing to Cesar, Lucina's falne, the chast Lucnia's conquerd; Gods, what a wretched thing has this man made me? For I am now no wife for Maximus, No company for women that are vertuous, No familie I now can claime, nor Country, Nor name, but Cesars Whore; O sacred Cesar, (For that should be your title) was your Empire, Your Rods, and Axes, that are types of Iustice, Those fires that ever burne, to beg you blessings, The peoples adoration, feare of Nations, What victory can bring ye home, what else The usefull Elements can make your servants, Even light it selfe, and suns of light, truth, justice, Mercy, and starlike pietie sent to you, And from the gods themselves to ravish women? The curses that I owe to Enemies, Even those the Sabines sent, when Romulus, (As thou hast me) ravishd their noble Maydes, Made more, and heavier, light on thee. Emp. This helps not. Luci. The sins of Tarquin be rememberd in thee, And where there has a chast wife been abusde, Let it be thine, the shame thine, thine the slaughter, And last for ever, thine, the feard example. Where shall poore vertue live, now I am falne? What can your honours now, and Empire make me, But a more glorious Whore? Emp. A better woman, But if ye will be blind, and scorne it, who can help it? Come leave these lamentations, they doe nothing, But make a noyse, I am the same man still, Were it to doe again; therefore be wiser, By all this holy light, I should attempt it, Ye are so excellent, and made to ravish, There were no pleasure in ye else. Luci. Oh villaine. Emp. So bred for mans amazement, that my reason And every help to hold me right has lost me; The God of love himselfe had been before me, Had he but power to see ye; tell me justly, How can I choose but erre then? if ye dare, Be mine, and only mine, for ye are so pretious, I envie any other should enjoy ye, Almost look on ye; and your daring husband Shall know h'as kept an Offring from the Empire, Too holy for his Altars; be the mightiest, More then my selfe Ile make it: if ye will not, Sit down with this, and silence, for which wisdom, Ye shall have use of me, and much honour ever, And be the same you were; if ye divulge it, Know I am far above the faults I doe, And those I doe I am able to forgive too; And where your credit in the knowldge of it, May be with glosse enough suspected, mine Is as mine owne command shall make it: Princes though they be somtime subject to loose whispers, Yet weare they two edged swords for open censures: Your husband cannot help ye, nor the Souldier, Your husband is my creature, they my weapons, And only where I bid 'em, strike; I feed 'em, Nor can the Gods be angry at this action, For as they make me most, they meane me happiest, Which I had never bin without this pleasure: Consider, and farewell: you'l find your women At home before ye, they have had some sport too, But are more thankfull for it— Exit Emperor. Luci. Destruction finde thee. Now which way must I goe? my honest house Will shake to shelter me, my husband flye me, My Family, because they are honest, and desire to be so, Must not endure me, not a neighbour know me: What woman now dare see me without blushes, And pointing as I passe, there, there, behold her, Look on her little Children, that is she, That hansome Lady, mark; O my sad fortunes, Is this the end of goodnesse, this the price Of all my early praiers to protect me, Why then I see there is no God but power, Nor vertue now alive that cares for us, But what is either lame or sensuall, How had I bin thus wretched else? Enter Maximus and Æcius Æci. Let Tituis Command the company that Pontius lost, And see the Fosses deeper. Max. How now sweet heart, What make you here, and thus? Æci: Lucina weeping? This must be much offence, Max. Look up and tell me, Why are you thus? My Ring? ô friend, I have found it, Ye were at Court, Sweet, Luc. Yes, this brought me thither. Max. Rise, and goe home: I have my feares Æcius: Oh my best friend, I am ruind; goe Lucina, Already in thy teares, I have read thy wrongs, Already found a Cesar; go thou Lilly, Thou sweetly drooping floure: go silver Swan, And sing thine owne sad requiem: goe Lucina, And if thou dar'st, out live this wrong. Luc. I dare not. Æc. Is that the Ring ye lost? Max. That, that, Æcius, That cursed Ring, my selfe, and all my fortunes: T'has pleasd the Emperor, my Noble master, For all my services, and dangers for him, To make me mine owne Pandar, was this justice? Oh my Æcius, have I liv'd to beare this? Luc. Farewell for ever Sir. Max. That's a sad saying, But such a one becomes ye well Lucina: And yet me thinkes we should not part so lightly, Our loves have been of longer growth, more rooted Then the sharp word of one farewell can scatter. Kisse me: I find no Cæsar here; these lips Taste not of Ravisher in my opinion. Was it not so? Luc. O Yes, Max. I dare believe thee, For thou wert ever truth it selfe, and sweetnesse: Indeed she was Æcius. Æc. So she is still. Max. Once more: O my Lucina; ô my comfort, The blessing of my youth, the life of my life. Æc. I have seene enough to stagger my obedience: Hold me ye equall Gods, this is too sinfull. Max. Why wert thou chosen out to make a whore of? To me thou wert too chast: fall Christall fountaines, And ever feed your streames you rising sorrowes, Till you have dropt your mistris into marble. Now goe for ever from me. Luc. Long farewell Sir. And as I have been loyall, Gods think on me. Max. Stay, let me once more bid farewell Lucina, Farewell thou excellent example of us, Thou starry vertue, farethee-well, seeke heaven, And there by Cassiopeia shine in glory, We are too base and dirty to preserve thee. Æc. Nay, I must kisse too: such a kisse againe, And from a woman of so ripe a vertue, Æcius must not take: Farewell thou Phenix, If thou wilt dye Lucina; which well weighd If you can cease a while from these strange thoughts, I wish were rather alterd. Luc. No. Æc. Mistake not. I would not staine your honour for the Empire, Nor any way decline you to discredit, Tis not my faire profession, but a Villaines: I find and feele your losse as deep as you doe, And am the same Æcius, still as honest, The same life I have still for Maximus, The same sword weare for you, where justice wills mee, And tis no dull one: therefore misconceave not: Only I would have you live a little longer, But a short yeare. Max. She must not. Luc. Why so long Sir, Am I not grey enough with griefe already? Æc. To draw from that wild man a sweet repentance, and goodnesse in his daies to come. Max. They are so, And will be ever comming my Æcius. Æc. For who knowes but the sight of you, presenting His swolne sins at the full, and your faire vertues, May like a fearefull vision fright his follies, And once more bend him right again, which blessing (If your dark wrongs would give you leave to read) Is more then death, and the reward more glorious: Death, only eases you; this, the whole Empire: Besides compeld, and forcd with violence, To what ye have done, the deed is none of yours, No nor the justice neither; ye may live, And still a worthier woman, still more honoured: For are those trees the worse we teare the fruits from? Or should the eternall Gods desire to perish, Because we daily violate their truths, Which is the chastitie of heaven? No Lady, If ye dare live, ye may: and as our sins Makes them more full of equitie and justice, So this compulsive wrong, makes you more perfect: The Empire too will blesse ye. Max. Noble Sir; If she were any thing to me but honour, And that that's wedded to me too, layd in Not to be worne away without my being: Or could the wrong be hers alone, or mine, Or both our wrongs, not tide to alter issues, Not borne a new in all our names and kindreds, I would desire her live, nay more, compell her: But since it was not youth, but malice did it, And not her own, nor mine, but both our losses, Nor staies it there, but that our names must find it, Even those to come; and when they read, she livd, Must they not aske how often she was ravishd, And make a doubt she lov'd that more then Wedlock? Therefore she must not live. Æc. Therefore she must live, To teach the world such deaths are superstitious. Luc. The tongues of Angels cannot alter me; For could the world again restore my credit, As faire and absolute as first I bred it, That world I should not trust agen, The Empire By my life can get nothing but my story, Which whilst I breath must be but his abuses: And where ye councell me to live, that Cesar May see his errors, and repent, Ile tell ye, His penitence is but encrease of pleasures, His prayers never said but to deceave us, And when he weeps, as you think for his vices, Tis but as killing drops from balefull Ewgh trees That rot their honest neighbour: If he can grieve, As one that yet desires his free conversion, And almost glories in his penitence, Ile leave him robes to mourn in, my sad ashes. Aec. The farewells then of happy soules be with thee, And to thy memory be ever sung The praises of a just and constant Lady, This sad day whilst I live, a Souldiers teares Ile offer on thy Monument, and bring Full of thy noble selfe with teares untold yet, Many a worthy wife, to weep thy ruine, Max. All that is chast, upon thy Tomb shal flourish, All living Epitaphs be thine, Time, Story; And what is left behind to peice our lives, Shall be no more abus'd with tales and trifles, But full of thee, stand to eternitie. Æci. Once more farewell, go find Elysium, There where the happy soules are crownd with blessings, There where tis ever spring, and ever summer. Max. There where no bedrid justice comes; truth, honor, are keepers of that blessed place; go thither, For here thou livest chaste fire in rotten timber. Aeci. And so our last farewells. Max. Gods give the justice.— Exit Lucina. Aeci. His thoughts begin to worke; I feare him, yet He ever was a noble Romane, but I know not what to thinke on't, he hath suffered Beyond a man, if he stand this. Max. Aecius, Am I a live, or has a dead sleepe seized me? It was my wife the Emperor abus'd thus; And I must say, I am glad I had her for him; Must I not my Aecius? Aeci. I am stricken With such a stiffe amazement, that no answer Can readily come from me, nor no comfort: Will ye go home, or go to my house? Max. Neither: I have no home, and you are mad Aecius To keepe me company, I am a fellow My own Sword would forsake, not tyed unto me: A Pandar is a Prince, to what I am falne; By heaven I dare do nothing. Aeci. Ye do better. Max. I am made a branded slave Aecius, And yet I blesse the maker; Death ô my soule, must I endure this tamely? Must Maximus be mention'd for his tales? I am a child too; what should I do rayling? I cannot mend my selfe, tis Cæsar did it, And what am I to him? Aeci. Tis well consider'd; How ever you are tainted, be no Traitor. Time may out-weare the first, the last lives ever. Max. O that thou wert not living, and my freind. Aeci. Ile beare a wary eye upon your actions, I feare ye Maximus, nor can I blame thee If thou breakest out, for by the Gods thy wrong Deserves a generall ruine: do ye love me? Max. That's all I have to live on. Aeci. Then go with me, Ye shall not to your own house. Max. Nor to any, My greifs are greater far, then walls can compasse, And yet I wonder how it happens with me, I am not dangerous, and ô my conscience Should I now see the Emperor i'th hear on't, I should not chide him for't, an awe runs through me, I feele it sensibly that bindes me to it, Tis at my heart now, there it sits and rules, And me thinkes tis a pleasure to obey it. Aeci. This is a maske to cozen me; I know ye, And how far ye dare do; no Romane farther, Nor with more fearlesse valour; and ile watch ye: Keepe that obedience still. Max. Is a wives losse (For her abuse much good may do his grace, Ile make as bold with his wife, if I can) More then the fading of a few fresh colours, More then a lusty spring lost? Aeci. No more Maximus, To one that truly lives. Max. Why then I care not, I can live wel enough Aecius. For looke you freind, for vertue, and those triffles, They may be bought they say. Aeci. He's craz's a little. His greife has made him talke things from his nature. Max. But chastitie is not a thing I take it To get in Rome, unlesse it be bespoken A hundred yeare before; is it Aecius? by'r lady, and well handled too i'th breeding. Aeci. Will ye go any way? Max. Ile tell thee freind. If my wife for all this should be a whore now, A kind of kicker out of sheetes, t'would vex me, For I am not angry yet; the Emperor Is young and hansome, and the woman flesh, And may not these two couple without scratching? Aeci. Alasse my noble freind. Max. Alasse not me, I am not wretched, for ther's no man miserable But he that makes himselfe so: Aeci. Will ye walke yet? Max. Come, come, she dare not dye freind, that's the truth on't, She knowes the inticing sweets and delicacies Of a young Princes pleasures, and I thanke her She has made a way for Maximus to rise by? Wilt not become me bravely? why do you think She wept, and said she was ravish'd? keep it here And Ile discover to you. Aeci. Well. Max. She knowes I love no bitten flesh, and out of that hope She might be from me, she contriv'd this knavery; Was it not monstrous freind? Aeci. Do's he but seeme so, Or is he made indeed? Max. Oh Gods, my heart! Aeci. Would it would fairly breake. Max. Me thinks I am somewhat wilder then I was, And yet I thanke the gods I know my duty.— Enter Claudia. Claud. Nay ye may spare your tears; she's dead. She is so. Max. Why so it should be: how? Clau. When first she enter'd Into her house, after a world of weeping, And blushing like the Sun-set, as we see her; Dare I said she defile this house with whore, In which his noble family has flourish'd? At which she fel, and stird no more; we rubd her. Exit Clau. Max. No more of that: be gon: now my Aecius, If thou wilt do me pleasure, weepe a little, I am so parch'd I cannot: Your example Has brought the raine down now: now lead me freind, And as we walke together let's pray together truly I may not fall from faith. Aeci. That's nobly spoken. Max. Was I not wilde, Aecius? Aeci. Somewhat troubled. Max. I felt no sorrow then: Now ile goe with ye, But do not name the woman: fye what foole Am I to weepe thus? God's Lucina take thee, For thou wert even the best, and worthiest Lady. Aeci. Good Sir no more, I shall be melted with it. Max. I have done, and good Sir comfort me Would there were wars now. Aeci. Settle your thoughts, come. Max. So I have now friend, Of my deep lamentations here's an end.— Exeunt. Enter Pontius, Phidias, and Aretus. Phidias. By my faith Captain Pontius, besides pitie Of your falne fortunes, what to say I know not, For tis too true the Emperor desires not But my best Master, any Souldier neere him: Are. And when he understands, he cast your fortunes For disobedience, how can we incline him, (That are but under persons to his favours) To any faire opinion? Can ye sing? Pontius. Not to please him Aretius, for my Songs Goe not to'th Lute, or Violl, but to'th Trumpet, My tune kept on a Target, and my subject The well struck wounds of men, not love, or women. Phi. And those he understands not. Pont. He should Phidias, Are. Could you not leave this killing way a little? You must if here you would plant your selfe, and rather Learne as we doe, to like what those affect That are above us: weare their actions, And thinks they keep us warme too: what they say, Though oftentimes they speake a little foolishly, Not stay to construe, but prepare to execute, And think how ever the end falls, the businesse Cannot run empty handed. Phid. Can yee flatter, And if it were put to you, lye a little? Pont. Yes, if it be a living. Are. That's well said then: Pon. But must these lyes and flatteries be beleev'd then? Phi. Oh yes by any meanes. Pon. By any meanes then, I cannot lye, nor flatter. Are. Ye must sweare too, If ye be there. Pon. I can sweare, if they move me. Phi. Cannot ye forsweare too. Pont. The Court for ever, If it be growne so wicked. Are. You should procure a little too, Pont. What's that? Mens honest sayings for my truth? Are. Oh no Sir: But womens honest actions for your triall. Pon. Doe you doe all these things? Phi. Doe you not like 'em? Pon. Do ye aske me seriously, or trifle with me? I am not so low yet, to be your mirth: Are. You do mistake us Captain, for sincerely, We aske you how you like 'em. Pon. Then sincerely I tell ye I abhor 'em: they are ill wayes, And I will starve before I fall into 'em. The doers of 'em wretches, their base hungers Cares not whose bread they eate, nor how they get it: Are. What then Sir? Pon. If you professe this wickednesse: Because ye have bin Souldiers, and borne Armes, The servants of the brave Æcius, And by him put to'th Emperor, give me leave, Or I must take it else, to say ye are villaines, For all your Golden Coates, deboshd, base villaines, Yet I doe weare a sword to tell ye so, Is this the way you mark out for a Souldier, A man that has commanded for the Empire, And borne the reputation of a man? Are there not lazie things enough cald fooles, and cowards, And poore enough to be preferr'd for Banders, But wanting Souldiers must be knave too? ha: This the trim course of life: were not ye born Bawdes, And so inherit but your rights? I am poore And may expect a worse; yet digging, pruning, Mending of broken wayes, carrying of water, Planting of Worts, and Onyons, any thing That's honest, and a mans, Ile rather choose, I and live better on it, which is juster, Drink my well gotten water, with more pleasure, When my endeavours done, and wages payd me, Then you doe wine, eate my course bread not curst, And mend upon't, your diets are diseases, And sleep as soundly, when my labour bids me, As any forward Pander of ye all, And rise a great deale honester; my Garments, Though not as yours, the soft sins of the Empire, Yet may be warme, and keep the biting wind out, When every single breath of poore opinion Finds you through all your Velvets. Are. You have hit it, Nor are we those we seeme, the Lord Aecius Put us good men to'th Emperor, so we have serv'd him, Though much neglected for it: So dare be still: Your curses are not ours: we have seen your fortune, But yet know no way to redeem it: Meanes, Such as we have, ye shall not want brave Pontius, But pray be temperate, if we can wipe out The way of your offences, we are yours Sir; And you shall live at Court an honest man too. Phi. That little meat and means we have, wee'l share it, Feare not to be as we are; what we told ye, Were but meere tryalls of your truth: y'are worthie, And so wee'l ever hold ye; suffer better, And then ye are a right man Pontius, If my good Master be not ever angry, Ye shall command againe. Pont. I have found two good men: use my life, For it is yours, and all I have to thank ye— Exeunt. Scæn. 3. Enter Maximus. Max. Ther's no way else to doe it, he must die, This friend must die, this soule of Maximus, Without whom I am nothing but my shame, This perfectnesse that keeps me from opinion, Must dye, or I must live thus branded ever: A hard choice, and a fatall; God's ye have given me A way to credit, but the ground to goe on, Ye have levelld with that pretious life I love most, Yet I must on, and through; for if I offer To take my way without him, like a Sea He bares his high command, twix me and vengeance, And in my owne road sinkes me, he is honest Of a most constant loyaltie to Cesar, And when he shall but doubt, I dare attempt him, But make a question of his ill, but say What is a Cesar, that he dare doe this, Dead sure he cuts me off: Aecius dies, Or I have lost my selfe? why should I kill him? Why should I kill my selfe, for tis my killing, Aecius is my roote, and whither him, Like a decaying branch, I fall to nothing. Is he not more to me, then wife, then Cesar? Though I had now my safe revenge upon him, Is he not more then rumour, and his freindship Sweeter then the love of women? What is honor We all so strangly are bewitch'd withall? Can it relieve me if I want? he has; Can honor, twixt the incensed Prince, and Envy, Beare up the lives of worthy men? he has; Can honor pull the wings of fearefull cowards And make 'em turne againe like Tigers? he has, And I have liv'd to see this, and preserv'd so; Why should this empty word incite me then To what is ill, and cruel? let her perish. A freind is more then all the world, then honor; She is a woman and her losse the lesse, And with her go my greifs: but hark ye Maximus, Was she not yours? Did she not dye to tell ye She was a ravish'd woman? did not justice Nobly begin with her, that not deserv'd it, And shall ye live that did it? Stay a little, Can this abuse dye here? Shall not mens tongues Dispute it afterward, and say I gave (Affecting dul obedience, and tame duty, And led away with fondnes of a freindship) The only vertue of the world to slander? Is not this certaine, was not she a chaste one, And such a one, that no compare dwelt with her, One of so sweete a vertue, that Aecius, Even he himselfe, this freind that holds me from it, Out of his worthy love to me, and justice, Had it not been on Cæsar, h'ad reveng'd her? By heaven he told me so; what shall I do then?— Enter a Servant. Can other men affect it, and I cold? I feare he must not live. Serv. My Lord, the Generall Is come to seeke ye. Max. Go, intreate him to enter: O brave Aecius, I could wish thee now As far from freindship to me, as from feares, That I might cut thee off, like that I weigh'd not, Is there no way without him, to come neare it? For out of honesty he must destroy me If I attempt it, he must dye as others, And I must loose him; tis necessity, Only the time, and meanes is all the difference; But yet I would not make a murther of him, Take him directly for my doubts; he shall dye, I have found a way to do it, and a safe one, It shall be honor to him too: I know not What to determine certaine, I am so troubled, And such a deale of conscience presses me;— Enter Aecius. Would I were dead my selfe. Aeci. You run a way well; How got you from me freind? Max. That that leads mad men, A strong Imagination made me wander. Aeci. I thought ye had been more setled. Max. I am well, But you must give me leave a little sometimes To have a buzzing in my brains. Aeci. Ye are dangerous, But Ile prevent it if I can; ye told me You would go to'th Army. Max. Why, to have my throat cut, Must he not be the bravest man Aecius That strikes me first? Aeci. You promised me a freedom From all these thoughts, and why should any strike you? Max. I am an Enemy, a wicked one, Worse then the foes of Rome, I am a Coward, A Cuckold, and a Coward, that's two causes Why every one should beat me. Aeci. Ye are neither; And durst another tell me so, he dyde for't, For thus far on mine honor, Ile assure you No man more lov'd then you, and for your valour, And what ye may be, faire; no man more follow'd. Max. A doughty man indeed: but that's all one, The Emperor, nor all the Princes living Shall find a flaw in my coat; I have sufferd, And can yet; let them find inflictions, Ile find a body for 'em, or Ile break it. Tis not a wife can thrust me out, some lookt for't? But let 'em looke till they are blind with looking, They are but fooles, yet there is anger in me, That I would faine disperse, and now I think on't, You told me freind the Provinces are stirring, We shall have sport I hope then, and what's dangerous, A Battle shall beat from me. Aeci. Why do ye eye me With such a setled looke? Max. Pray tell me this, Do we not love extremely? I love you so. Aeci. If I should say I lov'd not you as truly, I should do that I never durst do, lye. Max. If I should dye, would it not greive you much? Aeci. Without all doubt. Max. And could you live without me? Aeci. It would much trouble me to live without ye. Our loves, and loving soules have been so us'd But to one houshold in us: But to dye Because I could not make you live, were woman Far much too weake, were it to save your worth, Or to redeeme your name from rooting out, To quit you bravely fighting from the foe, Or fetch ye off, where honor had ingag'd ye, I ought, and would dye for ye. Max. Truly spoken. What beast but I, that must, could hurt this man now? Would he had ravish'd me, I would have payd him, I would have taught him such a trick, his Eunuches Nor all his black-eyd boyes dreamt of yet; By all the Gods I am mad now; Now were Cæsar Within my reach, and on his glorious top The pile of all the world, he went to nothing; The destinies, nor all the dames of hell, Were I once grappl'd with him, should relieve him, No not the hope of mankind more; all perished; But this is words, and weaknesse. Aeci. Ye looke strangely. Max. I looke but as I am, I am a stranger. Aeci. To me. Max. To every one, I am no Romane; Nor what I am do I know. Aeci. Then Ile leave ye. Max. I find I am best so, if ye meet with Maximus Pray bid him be an honest man for my sake, You may do much upon him; for his shadow, Let me alone. Aeci. Ye were not wont to talke thus, And to your freind; ye have some danger in you, That willingly would run to action. Take heed, by all our love take heed. Max. I danger? I, willing to do any thing, I dig. Has not my wife been dead two dayes already? Are not my mournings by this time moath-eaten? Are not her sins dispers'd to other women, And many one ravish'd to relieve her? Have I shed teares these twelve houres? Aeci. Now ye weepe. Max. Some lazie drops that staid behind. Aeci. Ile tell ye And I must tell ye truth, were it not hazard, And almost certaine losse of all the Empire, I would wyne with ye: were it any mans But his life, that is life of us, he lost it For doing of this mischeife: I would take it, And to your rest give ye a brave revenge: But as the rule now stands, and as he rules, And as the Nations hold in disobedience, One pillar failing, all must fall; I dare not: Nor is it just you should be suffer'd in it, Therefore againe take heed: On forraigne foes We are our own revengers, but at home On Princes that are eminent and ours, Tis fit the Gods should judge us: Be not rash, Nor let your angry steele cut those ye know not, For by this fatall blow, if ye dare strike it, As I see great aymes in ye, those unborne yet, And those to come of them and these succeeding Shall bleed the wrath of Maximus: For me As ye now beare your selfe, I am your freind still, If ye fall off I will not flatter ye, And in my hands, were ye my soule, you perish'd: Once more be carefull, stand, and still be worthy, Ile leave ye for this howre.— Exit. Max. Pray do, tis done: And freindship, since thou canst not hold in dangers, Give me a certaine ruin, I must through it. Exit.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Actus Quartus. Scæna prima. Enter Emperor, Lycinius, Chilax, and Balbus. Empe. Dead? Chil. So tis thought Sir. Empe. How? Lyci. Greife, and disgrace, As people say. Empe. No more, I have too much on't, Too much by you, you whetters of my follies, Ye Angell formers of my sins, but devills; Where is your cunning now? you would worke wonders, There was no chastity above your practise, You would undertake to make her love her wrongs, And doate upon her rape: mark what I tell ye, If she be dead— Chil. Alas Sir. Empe. Hang ye rascalls, Ye blasters of my youth, if she be gon, T'wer better ye had been your fathers Camells, Ground under dayly waights of wood and water: Am I not Cæsar? Lyci. Mighty and our maker. Empe. Then thus have given my pleasures to destruction. Looke she be living slaves. Empe. We are no Gods Sir, If she be dead, to make her new againe. Empe. She cannot dye, she must not dye; are those I plant my love upon but common livers? Their howres as others, told 'em? can they be ashes? Why do ye flatter a beliefe into me That I am all that'is, the world's my creature, The Trees bring forth their fruits when I say Summer, The Wind, that kdowes no limit but his wildnesse, At my command moves not a leafe; The sea With his proud mountaine waters envying heaven, When I say still, run into christall mirrors, Can I do this and she dye? Why ye bubbles That with my least breath break, no more remembred; Ye moaths that fly about my flame and perish. Ye golden cancker-wormes, that eate my honors, Living no longer then my spring of favour: Why do ye make me God that can do nothing? Is she not dead? Chil. All women are not with her. Empe. A common whore serves you, and far above ye, The pleasures of a body lam'd with lewdnesse; A meare perpetuall motion makes ye happy: Am I a man to traffique with diseases? Can any but a chastity serve Cæsar? And such a one the Gods would kneele to purchase? You think because you have breed me up to pleasures, And almost run me over all the rare ones, Your wives will serve the turne: I care not for 'em, Your wives are Fencers whores, and shall be Footmens, Though sometimes my nyce will, or rather anger Have made ye Cuckolds for variety; I would not have ye hope, nor dreame ye poore ones Alwaies so great a blessing from me; go Get your own infamy hereafter rascalls, I have done too nobly for ye, ye enjoy Each one an heire, the royall seed of Cæsar, And I may curse ye for't; your wanton Gennets That are so proud, the wind get's 'em with fillies, Taught me this soule intemperance: Thou Lycinius Hast such a Messalina, such a Lais, The backs of bulls cannot content, nor Stallions, The sweate of fifty men a night do's nothing. Lyci. Your Grace but jests I hope. Empe. Tis Oracle. The sins of other women put by hers Shew off like sanctities: Thin's a foole Chilax, Yet she can tell to twenty, and all lovers. And all lien with her too, and all as she is, Rotten, and ready for an hospitall. Yours is a holy whore freind Balbus. Bal. Well Sir. Empe. One that can pray away the sins she suffers, But not the punishments: She has had ten bastards, Five of 'em now are lictors, yet she praies; She has been the song of Rome, and common Pasquill; Since I durst see a wench, she was Campe mistris, And musterd all the cohorts, paid 'em too, They have it yet to shew, and yet she prayes; She is now to enter old men that are children, And have forgot their rudiments: am I Left for these withëred vices? and but one, But one of all the world that could content me, And snatch'd away in shewing? If your wives Be not yet witches, or your selves, now be so And save your lives, raise me this noble beauty As when I forc'd her, full of constancy, Or by the Gods— Lyci. Most sacred Cæsar. Empe. Slaves. Lycias. Good Proculus: Pro. By heaven you shall not see it, It may concerne the Empire. Empr. Ha: what said'st thou? Is she not dead? Pro. Not any one I know Sir; I come to bring your Grace a letter, here Scatterd belike i'th Court: Tis sent to Maximus, And bearing danger in it. Emp. Danger? where? Double our Guard. Pro. Nay no where, but i'th letter. Emp. What an afflicted conscience doe I live with, And what a beast I am growne? I had forgotten To aske heaven mercy for my fault, and was now Even ravishing againe her memory, I find there must be danger in this deed: Why doe I stand disputing, then and whining? For what is not the gods? to give they cannot Though they would linck their powers in one do mischiefe. This Letter may betray me, get ye gon —Exeunt. And waite me in the Garden, guard the house well, And keep this from the Empresse; The name Maximus Runnes through me like a feavour, this may be Some private Letter upon private businesse, Nothing concerning me: why should I open't? I have done him wrong enough already; yet It may concerne me too, the time so tells me; The wicked deed I have done, assures me tis so. Be what it will, ile see it, if that be not Part of my feares, among my other sins, Ile purge it out in prayers: How? what's this? Letter red. Lord Maximus, you love Aecius, And are his noble friend too; bid him be lesse, I meane lesse with the people, times are dangerous: The Army's his, the Emperor in doubts; And as some will not stick to say, declining, You stand a constant man in either fortunes; Perswade him, he is lost else: Though ambition Be the last sin he touches at, or never; Yet what the people made with loving him, And as they willingly desire another May tempt him too, or rather force his goodnesse, Is to be doubted mainly: he is all, (As he stands now) but the meer name of Cesar, And should the Emperor inforce him lesser, Not comming from himselfe, it were more dangerous: He is honest, and will heare you: doubts are scatterd, And almost come to growth in every houshold: Yet in my foolish judgment, were this masterd; The people that are now but rage, and his, Might be againe obedience: you shall know me, When Rome is faire againe; till when I love you. No name! this may be cunning, yet it seemes not; For there is nothing in it but is certain, Besides my safety. Had not good Germanicus, That was as loyall, and as straight as he is, If not prevented by Tiberius, Bin by the Souldiers forcd their Emperor? He had, and tis my wisdom to remember it. And was not Corbulo, even that Corbulo, That ever fortunate and living Roman, That broake the heart strings of the Parthians, And brought Arsases line upon their knees, Chaind to the awe of Rome, because he was thought (And but in wine once) fit to make a Cesar, Cut off by Nero? I must seeke my safety: For tis the same againe, if not beyond it: I know the Souldier loves him more then heaven, And will adventure all his gods to raise him; Me he hates more then peace: what this may breed, If dull security and confidence Let him grow up, a foole may find, and laught at. But why Lord Maximus I injurd so, Should be the man to councell him, I know not; More then he has been friend, and lov'd allegeance: What now he is I feare, for his abuses Without the people dare draw bloud; who waits there? Servant. Your Grace. —Enter a Servant. Emp. Call Phidias and Aretus hither: Ile finde a day for him too; times are dangerous, The Army his, the Emperor in doubts: I find it is too true; did he not tell me 1. As if he had intent to make me odious, 2. And to my face; and by a way of terror, What vices I was grounded in, and almost proclaimd the Souldiers hate against me? is not The sacred name and dignity of Cesar (Were this Aecius more then man) sufficient To shake off all his honesty? Hee's dangerous Though he be good, and though a friend, a feard one, And such I must not sleep by: are they come yet? I doe beleeve this fellow, and I thank him; T'was time to look about, if I must perish, Yet shall my feares goes foremost. —Enter Phidias, and Aretus. Phi. Life to Cesar: Emp. Is Lord Æciuss waiting? Phi. Not this morning, I rather think hee's with the Army, Emp. Army? I doe not like that Army: goe unto him, And bid him straight attend me, and doe ye heare, Come private without any; I have businesse Only for him. Phi. Your Graces pleasure— Exit Phidias. Emp. Goe; What Souldier is the same, I have seene him often, That keepes you company Aretus? Are. Me Sir? Emp. I you Sir. Are. One they call Pontius, And 't please your Grace. Emp. A Captaine? Are. Yes, he was so; But speaking somthing roughly in his want, Especially of warres, the noble Generall Out of a strict allegiance cast his fortunes: Emp. Ha's been a valiant fellow. Are. So hee's still. Emp. Alas, the Generall might have pardond follies, Souldiers will talke sometimes. Are. I am glad of this. Emp. He wants preferment as I take it: Are. Yes Sir; And for that noble Grace his life shall serve. Emp. I have a service for him: I shame a Souldier should become a Begger: I like the man Aretus. Are. Gods protect ye: Emp. Bid him repaire to Proculus, and there He shall receive the businesse, and reward for't: Ile see him setled too, and as a Souldier, We shall want such. The sweets of Heaven still crowne yee, I have a fearefull darknesse in my soule, And till I be deliverd, still am dying.— Exeunt. Scæn. 2. Enter Maximus alone. Max. My way has taken: all the Court's in guard, And businesse every where, and every corner Full of strange whispers: I am least in rumour, —Enter Aecius and Phidias. And so Ile keep my selfe, Here comes Aecius I see the bait is swallow'd: If he be lost He is my Martyr, and my way stands open, And honour on thy head, his bloud is reckond. Aec. Why how now friend, what make ye here unarmd: Are ye turnd Merchant? Max. By your faire perswasions, And such a Marchant trafficks without danger; I have forgotten all Æcius, And which is more, forgiven. Aec. Now I love ye, Truly I doe, ye are a worthy Roman. Max. The faire repentance of my Prince to me Is more then sacrifice of bloud and vengeance, No eyes shall weep her ruins, but mine owne. Aec. Still ye take more love from me: vertuous friend The gods make poore Æcius worthy of thee: Max. Only in me y'are poore Sir: and I worthy Only in being yours: But why your arme thus, Have ye bin hurt Æcius? Aec. Bruisd a little: My horse fell with me friend: which till this morning I never knew him doe. Max. Pray gods it boade well; And now I think on't better, ye shall back, Let my perswasions rule ye. Aec. Back, why Maximus? The Emperor commands me come. Max. I like not At this time his command. Aec. I doe at all times, And all times will obey it, why not now then? Max. Ile tell ye why, and as I have bin governd, Be you so noble Friend: The Courts in Guard, Armd strongly, for what purpose, let me feare; I doe not like your going. Aec. Were it fire; And that fire certain to consume this body, If Cesar sent, I would goe; never feare man, If he take me, he takes his armes away. I am too plaine and true to be suspected. Max. Then I have dealt unwisely, Aec. If the Emperor, Because he meerely may, will have my life, That's all he has to worke on, and all shall have: Let him, 'a loves me better: here I wither, And happily may live, till ignorantly I run into a fault worth death: nay more, dishonour. Now all my sinnes, I dare say those of duty Are printed here, and if I fall so happy, I blesse the grave, I lye in, and the gods Equall, as dying on the Enemy, Must take me up a Sacrifice. Max. Goe on then, And Ile goe with ye. Æc. No, ye may not friend. Max. He cannot be a friend, bars me Æcius, Shall I forsake ye in my doubts? Æc. Ye must. Max. I must not, nor I will not; have I liv'd Only to be a Carpet friend for pleasure? I can endure a death as well as Cato. Æc. There is no death nor danger in my going, Nor none must goe along. Max. I have a sword too, And once I could have usd it for my friend. Æc. I need no sword, nor friend in this, pray leave me; And as ye love me, do not overlove me; I am commanded none shall come: At supper Ile meet ye, and weele drink a cup or two, Ye need good Wine, ye have bin sad: Farwell. Max. Farwell my noble Friend, let me embrace ye Ere ye depart; it may be one of us Shall never doe the like agen. Æc. Yes often: Max. Farwell good deer Æcius. Æc. Farwell Maximus Till night: indeed you doubt too much.— Exit. Max. I doe not: Goe worthy innocent, and make the number Of Cesars sinnes so great, heaven may want mercy: Ile hover hereabout to know what passes: And if he be so divelish to destroy thee, In thy bloud shall begin his Tragedy. —Exit. Scæn. 3. Enter Proculus, and Pontius. Pro. Besides this, if you do it, you enjoy The noble name Patrician: more than that too, The Friend of Cesar ye are stild: ther's nothing Within the hopes of Rome, or present being But you may safely say is yours. Pon. Pray stay Sir; What has Æcius done to be destroyd? At least I would have a colour. Pro. Ye have more, Nay all that may be given, he is a Traitor, One, any man would strike that were a subject, Pon. Is he so fowle? Pro. Yes, a most fearefull Traytor. Pon. A fearefull plague upon thee, for thou lyest; I ever thought the Souldier would undoe him With his too much affection. Pro. Ye have hit it, They have brought him to ambition. Pon. Then he is gone: Pro. The Emperor out of a foolish pittie. Would save him yet. Pon. Is he so mad? Pro. He's madder! Would goe to'th Army to him. Pon. Would'a so? Pro. Yes Pontius; but we consider— Pon. Wisely; Pro. How else man, that the state lies in it, Pon. And your lives too: Pro. And every mans. Pon. He did me All the disgrace he could Pro. And scurvily, Pon. Out of a mischiefe meerly: did you mark it? Yes well enough. Pro. Now ye have meanes to quit it, The deed done, take his place. Pon. Pray let me thinke on't, Tis ten to one I doe it. Pro. Doe and be happy.— Exit Pro. Pon. This Emperor is made of naught but mischiefe, Sure, Murther was his Mother: none to lop, But the maine linck he had? upon my conscience The man is truly honest, and that kills him; For to live here, and study to be true, Is all one to be Traitors: why should he die? Have they not Slaves and Rascalls for their Offrings In full abundance; Bawds more then beasts for slaughter? Have they not singing whores enough, and knaves too, And millions of such Martyrs to sink Charon, But the best sons of Rome must saile too? I wil shew him (since he must dye) a way to doe it truly: And though he beares me hard, yet shall he know, I am born to make him blesse me for a blow.— Exit. Scæn. 2. Enter Phidias, Aretus, and Æcius. Phi. Yet ye may scape to'th Camp, wee'l hazard with ye, Aretus. Loose not your life so basely Sir: ye are armd, And many when they see your sword out, and know why Must follow your adventure. Aec. Get ye from me: Is not the doom of Cesar on this body, Doe not I beare my last houre here, now sent me? Am I not old Aecius, ever dying? You think this tendernesse and love you bring me, Tis treason, and the strength of disobedience, And if ye tempt me further, ye shall feele it: I seek the Camp for safety, when my death Ten times more glorious then my life, and lasting Bids me be happie: Let the foole feare dying, Or he that weds a woman for his honour. Dreaming no other life to come but kisses; Æcius is not now to learne to suffer: If ye dare shew a just affection, kill me, I stay but those that must: why do ye weep? Am I so wretched to deserve mens pities? Goe give your teares to those that lose their worths, Bewaile their miseries, for me wear Garlands. Drink wine, and much; sing Peans to my praise, I am to triumph friends, and more then Cesar, For Cesar feares to die, I love to die. Phi. O my deare Lord! Aec. No more, goe, goe I say; Shew me not signes of sorrow, I deserve none: Dare any man lament, I should die nobly; Am I grown old to have such enemies? When I am dead, speake honourably of me, That is, preserve my memory from dying; There if you needs must weep your ruind Master, A teare or two will seem well: this I charge ye, (because ye say you yet love old Aecius) See my poore body burnt, and some to sing About my Pile, and what I have done and sufferd, If Cesar kill not that too: at your banquets When I am gone, if any chance to number The times that have been sad and dangerous, Say how I fell, and tis sufficient: No more I say, he that laments my end By all the gods dishonours me; be gone And sodainly, and wisely from my dangers, My death is catching else. Phi. We feare not dying: Aec. Yet feare a wilfull death, the just Gods hate it, I need no company to that that children Dare doe alone, and Slaves are proud to purchase; Live till your honesties, as mine has done, Make this corrupted age sicke of your vertues, Then dye a sacrifice, and then ye know The noble use of dying well, and Roman. Are. And must we leave ye Sir? Aec. We must all die All leave our selves, it matters not, where, when, Nor how, so we die well: and can that man that does so Need lamentation for him? Children weep Because they have offended, or for feare, Women for want of will, and anger; is there In noble man, that truly feeles both poyses Of life and death, so much of this wet weaknesse. To drown a glorious death in child and woman? I am a shamd to see ye; yet ye move me, And were it not my manhood would accuse me, For covetous to live, I should weep with ye. Phi. O we shall never see you more: Aec. Tis true; Nor I the miseries that Rome shall suffer, Which is a benefit life cannot reckon: But what I have been, which is just, and faithfull; One that grew old for Rome, when Rome forgot him, And for he was an honest man durst die, Ye shall have daily with ye: could that dye too, And I returne no trafficke of my travells, No pay to have bin Souldier, but this silver, No Annalls of Æcius, but he liv'd, My friends ye had cause to weep, and bitterly; The common overflowes of tender women, And children new borne crying, were too little To shew me then most wretched: if teares must be, I should in justice weep 'em, and for you, You are to live, and yet behold those shughters The drie, and witherd bones of death would bleed at: But sooner, then I have time to thinke what must bee, I feare you'l find what shall be; If ye love me, Let that word serve for all; be gone and leave me; I have some little practise with my foule, And then the sharpest sword is welcom'st; goe, Pray be gon, ye have obeyd me living, Be not for shame now stubborn; so I thank ye, And faryewell, a better fortune guide yee— Exeunt Phi. and Aretius. I am a little thirstie, not for feare, And yet it is a kind of feare, I say so; Is it to be a just man now againe, And leave my flesh unthought of, tis departed: I heare 'em come, who strikes first? I stay for ye: —Enter Balbus, Chilax, Lycinius. Yet I will dye a Souldier, my sword drawne, But against none: Why doe ye feare? come forward. Bal. You were a Souldier Chilax, Chil. Yes, I musterd But never saw the Enemy. Lyc. Hee's drawne, By heaven I dare not doe it. Aec. Why doe ye tremble? I am to die, come ye not now from Cesar, To that end, speake? Bal. We doe, and we must kill ye, Tis Cesars will. Chil. I charge you put your sword up, That we may doe it hansomly. Aec. Ha, ha, ha, My sword up, hansomly where were ye bred? Ye are the merriest murderers my masters I ever met withall; Come forward fooles, Why doe ye stare? upon mine honour Bawds, I will not strike ye. Lyc. Ile not be first, Bal. Nor I; Chil. You had best die quietly: the Emperour Sees how you beare your selfe, Aec. I would die Rascalls, If you would kill me quietly, Bal. —of Proculus, He promisd us to bring a Captaine hither, That has been used to kill. Aec. Ile call the Guard, Vnlesse you will kill me quickly, and proclaim What beastly, base, and cowardly companions, The Emperor has trusted with his safetie: Nay Ile give out, ye fell of my side, villaines. Strike home ye bawdy slave. Chil. By heaven he will kill us, I markd his hand, he waits but time to reach us, Now doe you offer. Aec. If ye doe mangle me, And kill me not at two blowes, or at three, Or not so stagger me, my sences faile me, Look to your selves. Chil. I told ye, Aec. Strike me manly, And take a thousand strokes.— Enter Pontius. Bal. Heer's Pontius. Pon. Not kild him yet? Is this the love ye beare the Emperor? Lyc. runs away Nay then I see yee are Traitors all, have at yee— Chil. Oh I am hurt, Balb. And I am killd— Exeunt Chil. and Bal. Pon. Dye Bawdes; As ye have liv'd and flourish'd. Aec. Wretched fellow, What hast thou done? Pon. Killd them that durst not kill, And you are next. Aec. Art thou not Pontius? Pon. I am the same you cast Æcius, And in the face of all the Camp disgracd. Æc. Then so much nobler, as thou wert a Souldier, Shall my death be: is it revenge provoked thee, Or art thou hir'd to kill me? Pon. Both, Aec. Then doe it. Pon. Is that all? Aec. Yes, Pon. Would you not live? Aec. Why should I, To thanke thee for my life? Pon. Yes, if I spare it, Aec. Be not deceiv'd, I was not made to thank For any curtesie, but killing me, A fellow of thy fortune; doe thy duty. Pon. Doe not you feare me? Aec. No. Pon. Nor love me for it? Aec. That's as thou dost thy businesse, Pon. When you are dead, Your place is mine Aecius. Aec. Now I feare thee, And not alone thee Pontius, but the Empire, Pon. Why, I can governe Sir; Aec. I would thou couldst, And first thy selfe: Thou canst fights well, and bravely, Thou canst endure all dangers, Keates, colds, hungers; Heavens angry flashes are not sodainer, Then I have seene thee execute; nor more mortall; The winged feete of flying enemies I have stood and viewd thee mow away like rushes, And still kill the killer: were thy minde, But halfe so sweet in peace, as rough in dangers, I died to leave a happy heire behind me; Come strike, and be a Generall. Pon. Prepare then: And for I see your honour cannot lessen, And 'twere a shame for me to strike a dead man, Fight your short span out. Aec. No thou knowst I must not, I dare not give thee so much vantage of me, As disobedience; Pon. Dare ye not defend ye, Against your enemy? Aec. Not sent from Cesar, I have no power to make such enemies; For as I am condemn'd, my naked sword Stands but a hatchment by me; only held To shew I was a Souldier; had not Cesar Chaind all defence in this doom, let him die, Old as I am, and quenchd with scarres, and sorrowes, Yet would I make this witherd Arme do wonders, And open in an enemy such wounds Mercy would weep to look on. Pon. Then have at ye, And look upon me, and be sure ye feare not: Remember who you are, and why you live, And what I have been to you: cry not hold, Nor think it base injustice I should kill ye. Aec. I am prepard for all, Pon. For now Aecius, Thou shalt behold and find I was no traitor, And as I doe it, blesse me; die as I doe.— Pontius kills himselfe Aec. Thou hast deceiv'd me Pontius, and I thank thee; By all my hopes in heaven, thou art a Roman. Pon. To shew you what you ought to doe, this is not; For slanders selfe would shame to find you coward, Or willing to out-live your honestie: But noble Sir, ye have been jealous of me, And held me in the rancks of dangerous persons, And I must dying say it was but justice, Ye cast me from my credit; yet believe me, For there is nothing now but truth to save me, And your forgivenesse, though ye held me hainous, And of a troubled spirit, that like fire Turnes all to flames it meets with, ye mistook me; If I were foe to any thing, t'was ease, Want of the Souldiers due, the Enemy, The nakednesse we found at home, and scorne, Children of peace, and pleasures, no regard Nor comfort for our scarres, but how we got 'em, To rusty time, that eate our bodies up, And even began to prey upon our honours, To wants at home, and more then wants, abuses To them, that when the Enemy invaded Made us their Saints, but now the sores of Rome; To silken flattery, and pride plaind over, Forgetting with what wind their feathers saile, And under whose protection their soft pleasures Grow full and numberlesse: to this I am foe, Not to the state, or any point of duty: And let me speake but what a Souldier may, Truly I ought to be so; yet I errd, Because a far more noble sufferer Shewd me the way to patience, and I lost it: This is the end I die Sir; to live basely, And not the follower of him that bred me, In full account and vertue Pontius dare not, Much lesse to out live what is good, and flatter. Aec. I want a name to give thy vertue Souldier, For only good is farre below thee Pontius, The gods shall find thee one; thou hast fashiond death, In such an excellent, and beauteous manner, I wonder men can live: Canst thou speake once more, For thy words are such harmony, a soule Would choose to flye to heaven in Pon. A farewell: Good noble Generall your hand, forgive me, And think what ever was displeasing you, Was none of mine: ye cannot live. Aec. I will not: Yet one word more. Pon. Dye nobly: Rome farewell: And Ualentinian fall, thou hast broke thy bases, In joy ye have given me a quiet death, I would strike more wounds, if I had more breath— he dyes. Aec. Is there an houre of goodnesse beyond this? Or any man would out-live such a dying Would Cesar double all my honours on me, And stick me ore with favours, like a Mistris; Yet would I grow to this man: I have loved, But never doated on a face till now: O death thou art more than beautie, and thy pleasure Beyond posterity: Come friends and kill me; Cesar be kind, and send a thousand swords, The more, the greater is my fall: why stay ye? Come, and Ile kisse your weapons: feare me not, By all the gods Ile honour ye for killing: Appeare, or through the Court, and world, Ile search ye: My sword is gone; ye are Traitors if ye spare me, And Cesar must consume ye, all base cowards? Ile follow ye, and ere I dye proclaime ye, The weeds of Italy; the drosse of nature— Exit. Where are ye, villaines, traytors, slaves.— Enter Proculus, and 3. others running over the Stage. Pro. I knew H'ad killd the Captain, 1. Here's his sword. Pro. Let it alone, 'twill fight it selfe else; friends, An hundred men are not enough to doe it, Ile to the Emperor, and get more ayd. Aec. None strike a poore condemnd man. Pro. He is mad: Shift for your selves my masters.— Exeunt. Aec. Then Æcius, —Enter Aecius. See what thou darst thy selfe; hold my good sword, Thou hast been kept from bloud too long, Ile kisse thee, For thou art more then friend now, my preserver, Shew me the way to happinesse, I seeke it: And all you great ones, that have falne as I do, To keep your memories, and honours living, Be present in your vertues, and assist me, That like strong Cato, I may put away All promises, but what shall crown my ashes; Rome, farthee well: stand long, and know to conquer Whilst there is people, and ambition: Now for a stroak shall turne me to a Star: I come ye blessed spirits, make me room To live for ever in Elizium: Doe men feare this? O that posterity Could learne from him but this, that loves his wound, There is no paine at all in dying well, Nor none are lost, but those that make their hell— kills himselfe. —Enter Proculus and two others, 1. Within. Hee's dead, draw in the Guard againe, Pro. Hee's dead indeed, And I am glad hee's gone; he was a devill: His body, if his Eunuches come, is theirs; The Emperor out of his love to vertue, Has given 'em that: Let no man stop their entrance.— Exit. —Enter Phidias and Aretus. Phi. O my most Noble Lord, look here Aretus, Heer's a sad sight. Are. O cruelty! O Cesar, O times that bring forth nothing but destruction, And overflowes of bloud: why wa'st thou kild? Is it to be a just man now againe, As when Tiberius and wild Nero raignd, Only assurance of his over-throw? Phil. It is Aretus: he that would live now, Must like the Toad, feed only on corruptions, And grow with those to greatnesse: honest vertue, And the true Roman honour, faith and valour That have been all the riches of the Empire, Now like the fearefull tokens of the Plague, Are meer fore-runners of their ends that owe'em. Are. Never enough lamented Lord: deer master— Enter Maximus. Of whom now shal we learn to live like men? From whom draw out our actions just, and worthy: Oh thou art gone, and gone with thee all goodnesse, The great example of all equitie, O thou alone a Roman, thou art perishd, Faith, fortitude, and constant noblenesse, Weep Rome, weep Italy, weep all that knew him, And you that feard him as a noble Foe, (If Enemies have honourable teares) Weep this decayd Aecius falne, and scatterd— By foule, and base suggestion. Pho. O Lord Maximus, This was your worthy friend. Max. The gods forgive me: Think not the worse my friends, I shed not teares, Great griefes lament within; yet now I have found 'em: Would I had never knowne the world, nor women, Nor what that cursed name of honour was, So this were once againe Æcius: But I am destin'd to a mighty action, And begge my pardon friend, my vengeance taken, I will not be long from thee: ye have a great losse, But beare it patiently, yet to say truth In justice tis not sufferable: I am next, And were it now, I would be glad on't: friends, Who shall preserve you now? Are. Nay we are lost too. Max. I feare ye are, for likely such as love The man that's falne, and have been nourishd by him, Doe not stay long behind: Tis held no wisdom, I know what I must doe ô my Æcius, Canst thou thus perish, pluckt up by the rootes, And no man feele thy worthinesse? From boyes He bred you both I think. Phi. And from the poorest, Max. And lov'd ye as his owne, Are. We found it Sir. Max. Is not this a losse then? Phi. O, a losse of losses; Our lives, and ruines of our families, The utter being nothing of our names, Were nothing neere it. Max. As I take it too, He put ye to the Emperor. Are. He did so, Max. And kept ye still in credit. Phi. Tis most true Sir; Max. He fed your Fathers too, and made them meanes, Your Sisters he preferd to Noble Wedlocks, Did he not friends? Are. Oh yes Sir: Max. As I take it This worthy man would not be now forgotten, I tell ye to my griefe, he was basely murdred; And something would be done, by those that lov'd him: And something may be: pray stand off a little. Let me bewaile him private: ô my dearest. Phi. Aretus, if we be not sodaine, he out does us, I know he points at vengance; we are cold, And base ungratefull wretches, if we shun it: Are we to hope for more rewards, or greatnesse, Or any thing but death, now he is dead? Dar'st thou resolve? Are. I am perfect. Phi. Then like flowers That grew together all wee'l fall together, And with us that that bore us: when tis done The world shall stile us two deserving servants: I fear he will be before us. Are. This night Phidias: Phi. No more. Max. Now worthy friends I have done my mournings Let's burn this Noble body: Sweetes as many As sun-burnt: Neroe breeds, Ile make a flame of Shall reach his soule in heaven: he that shall live Ten ages hence, but to reherse this story, Shall with the sad discourse on't, darken Heaven, And force the painefull burdens from the wombs Conceivd a new with sorrow: even the Grave Where mighty Sylla sleeps shall rend asunder And give her shadow up, to come and groane About our piles, which will be more, and greater Then greene Olimpus, Jda, or old Latmus Can feed with Cedar, or the East with Gums, Greece with her wines, or Thessalie with flowers, Or willing heaven can weep for in her showres. Exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Actus Quintus. Scæna prima. Enter Phidias with his dagger in him, and Aretius poysond. Are. He h'as his last. Phi. Then come the worst of danger, Aecius to thy soule we give a Cesar, How long is't since ye gave it him? Are. An houre, Mine owne two houres before him: how it boyles mee! Phi. It was not to be cur'd I hope. Are. No Phidias, I delt above his Antidotes: Physicians May finde the cause, but where the cure? Phi. Done bravely, We are got before his Tyranny Aretus. Are. We had lost our worthiest end els Phidias: Phi. Canst thou hold out a while? Are. To torture him Anger would give me leave, to live an age yet; That man is poorely spirited, whose life Runs in his bloud alone, and not in's wishes. And yet I swell, and burne like flaming A'etna, A thousand new found fires are kindled in me, But yet I must not die this foure houres Phidias. Phi. Remember who dies with thee, and despise death. Are. I need no exhortation, the joy in me Of what I have done, and why, makes poyson pleasure, And my most killing torments mistresses. For how can he have time to dye, or pleasure That falls as fooles unsatisfied, and simple? Phi. This that consumes my life, yet keeps it in me, Nor doe I feele the danger of a dying, And if I but endure to heare the curses Of this fell Tyrant dead, I have halfe my heaven. Are. Hold thy soule fast but foure houres Phidias, And thou shalt see to wishes beyond ours, Nay more beyond our meanings. Phi. Thou hast steeld me: Farwell Aretus, and the soules of good men, That as ours doe, have left their Roman bodies In brave revenge for vertue, guide our shadowes. I would not faint yet. Are. Farwell Phidias And as we have done nobly, gods look on us.— Exeunt severally. Scæn. 2. Enter Lycias, and Proculus. Lycias. Sicker, and sicker Proculus? Pro. Oh Lycias, What shall become of us? would we had dide With happy Chilax, or with Balbus, bedrid— Enter Lycinius. And made too lame for justice. Lycinius. The soft Musick; And let one sing to fasten sleep upon him: Oh friends, the Emperor. Pro. What say the Doctors? Lycin. For us a most sad saying, he is poysond, Beyond all cure too. Lyc. Who? Lycin. The wretch Aretus, That most unhappy villaine. Lyc. How doe you know it? Lyci. He gave him drink last: let's disperse and find him; And since he has opend misery to all, Let it begin with him first: Softly he slumbers. —Enter Emperor sicke in a Chaire, with Eudoxia, the Empresse, and Physitians, and Attendants. Musick and Song. Care charming sleep, thou easer of all woes, Brother to death, sweetly thy life dispose On this afflicted Prince, fall like a Cloud In gentle showres, give nothing that is lowd, Or painfull to her slumbers; easie, sweet, And as a purling stream, thou son of night, Passe by his troubled senses; sings his paine Like hollow murmuring winde, or silver Rayne? Jnto this gently, Oh gently slide, And kiss him into slumbers like a Bride. Emp. Oh gods, gods: drink, drink, colder, colder Then snow on Scythian Mountaines: ô my heart strings. Eudox. How do's your Grace. Phis. The Empresse speakes Sir; Emp. Dying, Dying Eudoxa, dying. Phys. Good Sir patience; Eudox. What have ye given him? Phys. Pretious things deere Lady We hope shall comfort him. Emp. O flattered foole, See what thy god-heads come to: Oh Eudoxa. Eudox. O patience, patience Sir. —Enter Proculus, Licinius with Aretus. Emp. Danubius, Ile have brought through my body. Eudox. Gods give comfort. Em. And Volga, on whose face the North freezes, I and an hundred hells, an hundred Piles Already to my Funeralls are flaming, Shall I not drink? Phys. You must not Sir. Emp. By heaven Ile let my breath out that shall burne ye all If ye deny me longer: tempests blow me, And inundations that have drunk up kingdomes Flow over me, and quench me: wher's the Villaine? Am I immortall now ye slaves? by Numa If he doe scape: Oh, oh, Eudox. Deere Sir; Emp. Like Nero, But farre more terrible, and full of slaughter, I'th midst of all my flames ile fire the Empire: A thousand fans, a thousand fans to coole me: Invite the gentle windes Eudoxa. Eudox. Sir; Emp. Oh doe not flatter me, I am but flesh, A man, a mortall man: drink, drink, ye dunces; What can your doses now doe, and your scrapings, Your oyles, and Mithridates? if I doe die, You only words of health, and names of sicknesse Finding no true disease in man but mony, That talke your selves into Revenues, oh And ere ye kill your patients, begger 'em, Ile have ye flead, and dride. Pro: The Villaine Sir; The most accursed wretch. Emp. Be gon my Queene, This is no sight for thee: goe to the Vestalls, Cast holy incense in the fire, and offer One powerfull sacrifice to free thy Cæsar. Pro. Goe Goe and be happy. —Exit Eudoxa. Aretus. Goe, but give no ease, The Gods have set thy last houre Valentinian, Thou art but man, a bad man too, a beast, And like a sensual bloudy thing thou diest. Pro. Oh—Traitor. Are. Curse your selves ye flatterers, And howle your miseries to come ye wretches, You taught him to be poysond, Emp. Yet no comfort? Aret. Be not abusd with Priests, nor Pothecaries, They cannot help thee: Thou hast now to live A short halfe houre, no more, and I ten minutes: I gave thee poyson for Aecius sake, Such a destroying poyson would kill nature; And for thou shalt not die alone, I took it. If mankind had bin in thee at this murder, No more to people earth again, the wings Of old time clipt for ever, reason lost, In what I had attempted, yet ô Cæsar To purchase faire revenge, I had poysond them too. Emp. Oh villaine: I grow hotter, hotter, Are. Yes; But not neere my heate yet; what thou feel'st now, Marke me with horror Cæsar, are but Embers Of lust and leachery thou hast committed: But there be flames of murder. Emp. Fetch out tortures. Are. Doe, and ile flatter thee, nay more ile love thee: Thy tortures to what now I suffer Cæsar, At which thou must arrive too, ere thou dy'est, Are lighter, and more full of mirth then laughter. Emp. Let 'em alone: I must drink. Are. Now be mad. But not neere me yet. Emp. Hold me, hold me, hold me, Hold me; or I shall burst else. Are. See me Cesar, And see to what thou must come for thy murder; Millions of womens labours, all diseases. Emp. Oh my afflicted soule too, Are. Womens feares, horrors, Despaires, and all the Plagues the hot Sunne breeds.— Emp. Æcius, ô Æcius: ô Lucyna, Are. Are but my torments shadowes. Emp. Hide me mountaines; The gods have found my sinnes: Now breake. Are. Not yet Sir; Thou hast a pull beyond all these. Emp. Oh hell, Oh villaine, cursed villaine: Are. O brave villaine, My poyson dances in me at this deed: Now Cesar, now behold me, this is torment, And this is thine before thou diest, I am wildfire: The brazen Bull of Phalaris was feignd, The miseries of soules despising Heaven, But Emblems of my torments. Emp. Oh quench me, quench me, quench me. Are. Fire a flattery; And all the Poets tales of sad Avernus, To my paines lesse then fictions: Yet to shew thee What constant love I bore my murdred mastere; Like a Southwind, I have sung through all these tempests My heart, my witherd heart, feare, feare thou Monster, Feare the just gods, I have my peace.— He dies. Emp. More drinke, A thousand Aprill showres fall in my bosom: How dare ye let me be tormented thus? Away with that prodigious body, gods, Gods, let me aske ye what I am, ye lay All your inflictions on me, heare me, heare me; I doe confesse I am a ravisher,, A murderer, a hated Cesar; oh, Are there not vowes enough, and flaming Altars, The fat of all the world for sacrifice, And where that failes, the blood of thousand captives To purge those sins? but I must make the incense: I do despise ye all, ye have no mercy, And wanting that, ye are no Gods, your paroale Is only preach'd abroad to make Fooles fearfull, And women made of awe, beleeve your heaven: Oh torments, torments, torments, paines above paines, If ye be any thing but dreames, and ghests, and truly hold the guidance of things mortall; Have in your selves times past, to come, and present, Fashion the soules of men, and make flesh for 'em, Waighing our fates, and fortunes beyond reason, Be more then all the Gods, great in forgivenesse, Breake not the goodly frame ye build in anger; For you are things men teach us, without passions, Give me an howre to know ye in: Oh save me But so much perfect time ye make a soule in, Take this destruction from me; no ye cannot, The more I would beleeve ye, more I suffer, My braines are ashes, now my heart, my eyes freinds; I go, I goe, more aire, more aire; I am mortall.— He dyes. Pro. Take in the body: oh Lycinius, The misery that we are left to suffer; No pitty shall find us, Licini. Our lives deserve none: Would I were chain'd againe to slavery, With any hope of life. Pro. A quiet grave, Or a consumption now Lycinius, That we might be too poore to kill, were something. Lycini. Let's make our best use, we have mony Proculus, And if that cannot save us, we have swords. Pro. Yes, but we dare not dye. Lyc. I had forgot that: There's other countries then. Pro. But the same hate still, Of what we are. Lyci. Think any thing, Ile follow— Enter a Messenger. Pro. How now what newes? Mess. Shift for your selves, ye are lost else: The Souldier is in armes for great Æcius, And their Lievtenant generall that stopt 'em, Cut in a thousand peeces: they march hither: Beside, the women of the Towne have murderd Phorba, and loose Ardelia, Cæsars she-Bawdes. Lyci. Then here's no staying Proculus? Pro. O Cæsar, That we had never known thy lusts: Lets fly, And where we find no womans man lets dye.— Exeunt Scæn. 3. Enter Maximus. Max. Gods, what a sluce of blood have I let open! My happy ends are come to birth, he's dead, And I reveng'd; the Empires all a fire, And desolation everywhere inhabits: And shall I live that am the author of it, To know Rome from the awe o'th world, the pitty? My freinds are gone before too of my sending, And shall I stay? is ought else to be liv'd for? Is there an other freind, an other wife, Or any third holds halfe their worthynesse, To linger here alive for? Is not vertue In their two everlasting soules departed, And in their bodies first flame fled to heaven? Can any man discover this, and love me? For though my justice were as white as truth, My way was crooked to it, that condemnes me: And now Æclus, and my honored Lady, That were prepares to my rest and quiet, The lines to lead me to Elizium: You that but stept before me, on assurance I would not leave your freindship unrewarded, First smile upon the sacrifice I have sent ye, Then see me commingly bodly: stay, I am foolish, Somewhat too suddaine to mine own destruction, This great end of my vengance may grow greater: Why may not I be Cæsar? Yet no dying; Why should not I catch at it? fooles and children Have had that strength before me, and obtaind it, And as the danger stands, my reason bids me, I will, I dare; my deare friends pardon me, I am not fit to dye yet if not Cæsar; I am sure the Souldier loves me, and the people, And I will forward, and as goodly Cedars Rent from Oeta by a sweeping tempest Winted againe and made tall masses, defie Those angry winds that split 'em, so will I new peece againe, above the fate of women, And made more perfect far, then growing privat, Stand and defie bad fortunes: If I rise, My wife was ravish'd well; If then I fall, My great attempt honors my Funerall.— Exit. Scæn. 4. Enter 3 Senators, and Affranius. 1. Guard all the posternes to the Camp Affranius, And see 'em fast, we shall be rifled else, Thou art an honest, and a worthy Captaine. 2. Promise the Souldier any thing, 3. Speake gently, And tell 'em we are now in councell for 'em. Labouring to choose a Cæsar fit for them, A Souldier, and a giver. 1. Tell 'em further, Their free and liberall voices shall go with us. 2. Nay more, a negative say we allow 'em. 3. And if our choice displease 'em, they shall name him. 1. Promise three donatives, and large, Affranius. 2. And Cæsar once elected, present foes, With distribution of all necessaries, Corne, Wine, and Oyle. 3. New garments, and new Armes, And equall portions of the Provinces To them, and to their families for ever. 1. And see the City strengthned. Affra. I shall do it, —Exit Affranius. 2. Sempronius, these are wofull times. 3. O Brutus, We want thy honesty againe; these Cæsars, What noble Consuls got with blood, in blood Consume againe, and scatter. 1. Which way shall we? 2. Not any way of safety I can thinke on. 3. Now go our Wives to ruin, and our daughters, And wee beholders Fulvius. 1. Everything Is every mans that will. 2. The vestalls now Must only feed the Souldiers fire of lust, And sensuall Gods be glutted with those Offerings, Age like the hidden bowels of the earth Open'd with swords for Treasure. Gods defend us, We are chaffe before their fury else. 2. Away, Let's to the Temples. 1. To the Capitoll, 'Tis not a time to pray now, let's be strengthend— Enter Affranius. 3. How now Affranius: what good news, Affr. A Cesar: 1. Oh who? Affr. Lord Maximus is with the Souldier, And all the Camp rings, Cesar, Cesar, Cesar: He forcd the Empresse with him for more honour. 2. A happy choice: let's meet him. 3. Blessed fortune; 1. Away, away, make room there, room there, room. —Exeunt Senators, Flourish. Within. Lord Maximus is Cesar, Cesar, Cesar; Haile Cesar Maximus. Affr. Oh turning people! Oh people excellent in war, and governd, In peace more raging then the furious North, When he ploughes up the Sea, and makes him brine: Or the lowd falls of Nile; I must give way, Although I neither love nor hope this. Cesar flourish. Or like a rotten bridge that dares a current, When he is sweld and high crackt, and farwell. Enter Maximus, Eudoxa, Senat. and Souldiers. Sen. Roome for the Emperor. Sold. Long life to Cesar: Affr. Haile Cesar Maximus. Emp., Max. Your hand Affranius. Lead to the Pallace, there my thanks in generall, Ile showre among ye all: gods give me life, First to defend the Empire, then you Fathers, And valiant friends, the heires of strength and vertue, The rampires of old Rome, of us the refuge; To you I open this day all I have, Even all the hazard that my youth hath purchasd, Ye are my children, family, and friends And ever so respected shall be, forward. Ther's a Prescription grave Sempronius, Gainst all the flatterers, and lazie Bawdes Led loose-liv'd Valentinian to his vices, See it effected; —Flourish. Sen. Honour wait on Cesar. Sold. Make room for Cesar there— Exeunt all but Affr. Affr. Thou hast my feares, But Valentinian keeps my vowes: oh gods, Why doe we like to feed the greedy Raven Of these blowne men, that must before they stand, And fixt in eminence, cast life on life, And trench their safeties in with wounds, and bodies? Wel froward Rome, thou wilt grow weak with changing And die without an Heire, that lov'st to breed Sonnes for the killing hate of sons: for me, I only live to find an enemy. —Exit. Scæn. 5. Enter Paulus (a Poet) and Lycippus, (a Gent.) Pau. When is the Inauguration? Lyc. Why to morrow. Paul. T'will be short time. Lyc. Any devise that's hansom, A Cupid, or the God o'th place will doe it, Where he must take the Fasces. Pau. Or a Grace. Lyc. A good Grace ha's no fellow. Pau. Let me see, Wil not his name yeeld somthing? Maximus By'th way of Anagram? I have found out Axis, You know he beares the Empire. Lyc. Get him wheeles too, T'will be a cruell carriage else. Pau. Some songs too. Lyc. By any meanes some songs: but very short ones, And honest language Paulus, without bursting, The ayre will fall the sweeter. Pau. A Grace must doe it. Lyc. Why let a Grace then. Pau. Yes it must be so; And in a robe of blew too, as I take it. Lyc. This poet is a little kin to'th Painter That could paint nothing but a ramping Lion, So all his learned fancies are blew Graces, Pau. What think ye of a Sea-nymph, and a heaven? Lyc. Why what shold she do there man? ther's no water. Pau. By'th masse that's true, it must be a grace, and yet Me thinkes a Rain-bow. Luy. And in blew, Pau. Oh yes; Hanging in arch above him, and i'th midle Lyc. A showre of raine. Pau. No, no, it must bee a Grace, Lyc. Why prethee Grace him then. Pau. Or Orpheus, Comming from hell. Lyc. In blew too. Pau. Tis the better; And as he rises, full of fires. Lyc. Now blesse us. Will not that spoile his Lute strings Paulus? Pau. Singing, And crossing of his armes. Lyc. How can he play then? Pau. It shall be a Grace, ile doe it: Lyc. Prethee doe, And with as good a grace as thou canst possible; Good fury Paulus, be i'th morning with me, And pray take measure of his mouth that speaks it. Exeunt Scæn. 6. Enter Maximus and Eudoxa. Max. Come my best lov'd Eudoxa: Let the Souldier Want neither Wine nor any thing he calls for, And when the Senat's ready, give us notice; In the meane time leave us, Oh my deere sweet. Eud. Is't possible your Grace Should undertake such dangers for my beauty, If it were excellent? Max. By heaven tis all The world has left to bragge of. Eud. Can a face Long since bequeath'd to wrinkles with my sorrowes, Long since razd out o'th book of youth and pleasure, Have power to make the strongest man o'th Empire, Nay the most staid, and knowing what is woman: The greatest aym of perfectnesse men liv'd by, The most true constant lover of his wedlock, Such a still blowing beauty, earth was proud of, Loose such a noble wise, and wilfully; Himselfe prepare the way, nay make the rape. Did ye not tell me so? Max. Tis true Eudoxa. Eud. Lay desolate his docrest peece of friendship, Break his strong helme he steerd by, sinke that vertue; That valour, that even all the gods can give us, Without whom he was nothing, with whom worthiest, Nay more arive at Cesar, and kill him too, And for my sake? either ye love too deerly, Or deeply ye dissemble Sir? Max. I doe so; And till I am more strengthend, so I must doe; Yet would my joy, and wine had fashiond out Some safer lye: Can these things be Eudoxa, And I dissemble? Can there be but goodnesse And onely thine deer Lady, any end, Any imagination but a lost one, Why I should run this hazard? O thou vertue! Were it to doe againe, and Valentinian Once more to hold thee sinfull Valentinian, In whom thou wert set, as pearles are in salt Oysters, As Roses are in ranck weeds, I would find, Yet to thy sacred selfe a deerer danger, The God's know how I honour thee. Eud. What love Sir? Can I returne for this, but my obedience; My life, if so you please, and tis too little. Max. Tis too much to redeem the world. Eud. From this houre, The sorrowes for my dead Lord, faryewell, My living Lord has dride ye; And in token, As Emperor this day I honor ye, And the great caster new of all my wishes, The wreath of living Lawrell, that must compasse That sacred head, Eudoxa makes for Cesar: I am me thinkes too much in love with fortune; But with you ever Royall Sir my maker, The once more Summer of me, meere in love, Is poore expression of my doting. Max. Sweetest, Eud. Now of my troth ye have bought me deere Sir; Max. No, Had I at losse of mankinde —Enter a Messenger. Eud. Now ye flatter. Mess. The Senat waites your Grace, Max. Let'em come on, And in a full forme bring the ceremony: This day I am your servant (deere) and proudly, Ile weare your honoured favour. Eud. May it prove so. —Exeunt. Scæn. 7. Enter Paulus, and Lycippus. Lyc. Is your Grace done? Pau. Tis done. Lyc. Who speakes? Pau. A Boy: Lyc. A dainty blew Boy Paulus? Pau. Yes; Lyc. Have ye viewed The worke above? Pau. Yes, and all up, and ready: Lyc. The Empresse does you simple honour Paulus, The wreath your blew Grace must present, she made. But harke ye, for the Souldiers? Pau. That's done too: Ile bring'em in I warrant ye. Lyc. A Grace too? Pau. The same Grace serves for both. Lyc. About it then: I must to'th Cupbord; and bee sure good Paulus Your Grace be fasting, that he may hang cleanly: If there should need an other voice, what then? Paul. Ile hang an other Grace in, Lyc. Grace be with ye.— Exeunt. Scæn. 2. Enter in state Maximus, Eudoxa, with Souldiers and Gentlemen of Rome, the Senators, and Rods and Axes borne before them. A Synnet with Trumpets. With a Banket prepard, with Hoboies, Musicke, Song, wreath. Sen., Semp. 3. Haile to thy imperiall honour sacred Cesar, And from the old Rome take these wishes; You holy gods, that hitherto have held As justice holds her Ballance equall poysd, This glory of our Nation, this full Roman, And made him fit for what he is, confirme him: Looke on this Son ô Iupiter our helper, And Romulus, thou Father of our honour, Preserve him like thy selfe, just, valiant, noble, A lover, and increaser of his people, Let him begin with Numa, stand with Cato, The first five yeares of Nero be his wishes, Give him the age and fortune of Emelius, And his whole raigne, renew a great Augustus. SONG. Honour that is ever living, Honour that is ever giving, Honour that sees all and knowes, Both the ebbs of man and flowes, Honour that rewards the best, Sends thee thy rich labours rest; Thou hast studied still to please her, Therefore now she calls thee Cesar: Chorus. Hayle, hayle, Cæsar, hayle and stand, And thy name out live the Land, Noble fathers to his browes, Bind this wreath with thousand vows. All. Stand to eternity: Max. I thank ye fathers, And as I rule, may it stil grow or wither: Now to the bancker, ye are all my guests, This day be liberall friends, to wine we give it; And smiling pleasures: Sit my Queen of beauty; Fathers your places: These are faire Wars Souldiers, And thus I give the first charge to ye all; You are my second (sweet) to every cup, I adde unto the Senat, a new honour, And to the sonnes of Mars a donative. SONG. God Lizus ever young, Ever honourd ever sung; Staind with bloud of lusty Grapes, In a thousand lusty shapes; Dance upon the Mazers brim, In the Crimson liquor Swim From thy plenteous hand divine, Let a River runne with Wine; God of youth, let this day here, Enter neither care nor feare. Boy. Bellonia's seed, the glory of old Rome, Envie of conquerd Nations, nobly come And to the fulnesse of your warlike noyce, Let your feete move, make up this houre of joyes; Come, come I say, range your faire Troop, at large, And your hy measure turne into a charge. Semp. The Emperor's growne heavie with his wine, Affr. The Senat staies Sir for your thanks, Semp. Great Cesar. Eud. I have my wish: Affr. Wilt please your Grace speake to him. Eud. Yes, but he will not heare Lords. Semp. Stir him Lucius; the Senat must have thankes. 2. Sen., Luc. Your Grace, Sir Cesar; Eud. Did I not tell you he was well: he's dead, Semp. Dead? treason, guard the Court, let no man passe, Souldiers, your Cesars murdred. Eud. Make no tumult, Nor arme the Court, ye have his killer with ye; And the just cause, if ye can stay the hearing: I was his death; That wreath that made him Cesar, Has made him earth. Sold. Cut her in thousand peeces. Eud. Wise men would know the reason first: to die, Is that I wish for Romans, and your swords, The heaviest way of death: yet Souldiers grant me That was your Empresse once, and honour by ye; But so much time to tell ye why I killd him, And waigh my reasons well, if man be in you; Then if ye dare doe cruelly condemne me. Affr. Heare her ye noble Romans, Tis a woman, A subject not for swords, but pitty: Heaven If she be guilty of malitious murder, H'as given us lawes to make example of her, If only of revenge, and bloud hid from us, Let us consider first, then execute. Semp. Speake bloudy woman. Eud. Yes; This Maximus, That was your Cesar, Lords, and noble Souldiers; (And if I wrong the dead, heaven perish me; Or speake to wyn your favours but the truth) Was to his Country, to his friends, and Cesar A most malitious Traytor. Semp. Take heed woman. Eud. I speake not for compassion. Brave Æcius (Whose blessed soule if I lye shall afflict me,) The man that all the world lov'd, you adoard, That was the master peece of Armes, and bounty; Mine own griefe shal come last: this friend of his, This Souldier, this your right Arme noble Romans: By a base letter to the Emperor; Stufft full of feares, and poore suggestions, And by himselfe, unto himselfe directed; Was cut off basely, basely, cruelly; Oh losse, ô innocent, can ye now kill me? And the poore stale my Noble Lord, that knew not More of this villaine, then his forcd feares; Like one foreseene to satisfie, dy'd for it: There was a murder too, Rome would have blush at; Was this worth being Cesar? or my patience? nay his wife By heaven he told it me in wine, and joy; And swore it deeply, he himselfe prepard To be abusd, how? let me grieve not tell ye; And weep the sins that did yet: and his end Was only me, and Cesar: But me he lyd in; These are my reasons Romans, and my soule Tells me sufficient; and my deed is justice: Now as I have done well, or ill, look on me. Affr. What lesse could nature doe, what lesse had we done, Had we knowne this before? Romans, she is righteous; And such a peece of justice, heaven must smile on: Bend all your swords on me, if this displease ye, For I must kneele, and on this vertuous hand; Seale my new joy and thankes, thou hast done truly. Semp. Vp with your arms, ye strike a Saint els Romans, May'st thou live ever spoken our protector: Rome yet has many noble heires: Let's in And pray before we choose, then plant a Cesar Above the reach of envie, blood, and murder. Affr. Take up the body, nobly to his urne, And may our sinnes, and his together burne.— Exeunt. A dead March.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">EPILOGVE. We would faine please yee, and as faine be pleasd; Tis but a little liking, both are easd: Wee have your money, and you have our ware, And to our understanding good and faire: For your owne wisdomes sake, be not so mad, To acknowledge ye have bought things deere and bad: Let not a brack 'th stuffe, or here and there, The fading glosse, a generall losse appeare: We know yee take up worse Commodities, And deerer pay, yet thinke your bargains wise; Wee know in Meate and Wine, yee fling away More time and wealth, which is but deerer pay, And with the Reckoning all the pleasure lost. We bid yee not unto repenting cost: The price is easie, and so light the Play, That ye may new digest it everyday. Then noble friends, as yee would choose a Mistris, Only to please the eye a while and kisse, Till a good wife be got: So let this Play Hold yee a while, untill a better may.</field>
   </doc>
</add>