<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Soane, George, 1790-1860</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Soane, George, 1790-1860</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">soane george 1790 1860</field>
      <field name="author_text">Soane, George, 1790-1860</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1820's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V3.0232.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1820</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460636</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Hebrew ; A Drama, In Five Acts</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Hebrew ; A Drama, In Five Acts</field>
      <field name="title_facet">hebrew</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">hebrew</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Hebrew ; A Drama, In Five Acts</field>
      <field name="year_display">1820</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1820</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1820</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460636&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460636&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Soane, George, 1790-1860&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;soane george 1790 1860&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Hebrew ; A Drama, In Five Acts&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;hebrew&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1820&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1820&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Soane, George&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1790&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1860&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Hebrew&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Drama, In Five Acts&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed For John Lowndes [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1820&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872995-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv30232&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Hebrew&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Drama, In Five Acts&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 162 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: The Hebrew.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Drama.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1820.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 2 Mar 1820.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE HEBREW. A DRAMA, IN FIVE ACTS</field>
      <field name="fulltext">To JOHN SOANE, Esq.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DRAMATIS PERSONÆ. NORMANS. Prince John of Anjou Mr. Foote. Prior Aymer Mr. Pope. Grand Master of the Templars Mr. Powel. Brian de Bois Guilbert Knight Templar, Mr. Hamblin. Maurice De Bracy Knight Templar, Mr. Mordaunt. SAXONS. Cedric the Saxon, a powerful Baron, Mr. Holland. Ivanhoe, his Son Mr. Penley. Robin Hood Mr. Cooke. Friar Tuck Mr. Oxberry. Scarlet, Robin Hood's Lieutenant Mr. Elliot. Oswald, Cedric's Steward Mr. Meredith. Gurth, a Swineherd Mr. Thompson. Wamba, Cedric's Fool Mr. Harley. Isaac, the Jew of York Mr. Kean. Rebecca, his Daughter Mrs. West. Miriam, his Niece Miss Carew.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PROLOGUE, BY R. BARLOW, ESQ. In these blest days, the horrid din of arms No longer wakes us with its dread alarms;— Our warriors seek no more the field or flood, And men have leisure to be wise and good. Yet we, alas! have scarcely dried the tear, Which flow'd to consecrate a monarch's bier;— Who, for those laurels watch'd through years of gloom, Which only rose to decorate his tomb.— Whate'er the factions of our giddy throng, Whatever ills from public woes have sprung; The veriest wretch that owns a Briton's name, Had prov'd his shield—the bulwark of his fame. —No more!—forgive the bard these mournful strains, Our “Hebrew” of to-night attention claims:— No longer scoff'd, in peaceful compact blend Christian and Jew, by turns each other's friend. —The days of yore are past,—the advent'rous times, When men were great in virtues as in crimes; —Such days have left us, yet one master hand, Hath borne the spell,—they rise at his command; Triumphant genius bids the past appear, To wake our terrors or command the tear;— Unlike the bards of old who hapless pin'd In want and solitude, your voice combin'd, Pours the rich bounty of your just applause, —The Novelist's, your own, and virtue's cause. —'Tis at this shrine our bard to-night hath lit His torch obscure—yet he, alas! unfit, The scenes of “Ivanhoe” to copy here, Hath sought for safety in a humbler sphere. If from compiler's dull mechanic ways, He fearless turns, will you withhold your praise? Ah, no! who boldly dares will ever find, A British audience, even in censure, kind;— If not presumptuous, yet with hope impress'd, Say will you crush this nursling of his breast? Think how unlike all other's is the cause Of our dramatic bards,—no courts—no laws— No hope—no suffrage, but in your applause;— Since then your favour's sought, your censure fear'd, Be just,—be generous,—judge not till you've heard.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">EPILOGUE, BY J. R. PLANCHE, ESQ. May I come in? your pleasure, let me know it; I'm sent to sound a parley by the Poet. When for that service first he fix'd to choose me, I answered, with a curtsey, “Sir, excuse me.” Why what dost fear, he cried, thou silly goose, Dost think they'll fire upon a flag of truce? Go, trumpet-tongued, this peaceful message bear To the besiegers in the outworks there; Tell them our garrison can't stand their shot, If they intend to fire it hissing hot; Vain all defence, the fort must fall for certain, Adieu to horn-work, covered way, and curtain; They, therefore, e'er they're all made “food for worms,” Surrender upon honorable terms. Away, he added, be an humble pleader, Or they'll attack our band, and kill the leader. His fears thus hastily the author told me, Then ope'd the sally-port, and here behold me. What force you're in, one charge, and you must rout us; What batteries on all the heights about us. Critics, your heavy troops; and Beaux, your light ones, Have you got serjeants?—O yes, plenty, white ones. Of conquest sure, their very looks are killing, And all hearts must confess their skill at drilling. First, then, I'll ask the officers' compassion; Next rank and file, I should say, rank and fashion, Let me crave your's; express your satisfaction, You half-price corps, who last came into action. And you of the artillery brigade, Whose greatest glory is a cannonade. The word has been attention, grant our prayer, And let to-morrow's word be—as you were. Let not our hope be a forlorn one made, But as a feu-de-joi, each fire a hand grenade: So shall our Hebrew glad his wandering nation, And gain “the promised land”—your approbation.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. SCENE I. —Cedric's Hall: Cedric and the Palmer. Cedric. Tell me not, Palmer; I must curse these Normans; 'Tis all I can; we bear the name and form Of Saxons, not the heart—else—to your tale; You spoke of good King Richard—Though a Norman, He loves his Saxons—to thy story—Oh! That noble Richard! While he pines in chains Of Austria's forging, here his brother, John, Ambitious of his throne, makes factious part With Templars, tatter'd soldiers, and a crew Of honorable beggars, such as live Conjecture says not how—But to your tale. Palmer. My story is of Ivanhoe— Cedric (interrupting him). My son! A father's curse,— Palmer. Curse not thy son. Cedric. I do. Palmer. Curse not thy son, old man;—he loves thee well. Cedric. It has not seem'd so; I will tell thee, Palmer; Thou art a Saxon, and wilt understand me. He lov'd a Jewess—that was sin enough; He did deny to leave her at my bidding; That was a sin a father could not pardon; I banish'd him my house, my blood, the land. Palmer. My life the pledge, Her soul is spotless as the vestal beam That falls in summer midnights from the moon Upon the brooks of earth. Horn without: Oswald enters. Oswald. My Lord, the Prior Aymer, and the Knight Brian de Bois Guilbert, request, for them And for their train, your shelter. Cedric. Normans both! Palmer. But yet thy door should not be bolted 'gainst them; For hospitality is as the sun, That shines on all, on weeds as on the flow'rs, Or else on nothing shines. Cedric. You chide me well. Go, bring them in. Oswald goes out, and re-enters, conducting the Prior Aymer, Brian, and their train. Cedric. To hearth and table welcome. Prior. Right noble Cedric, we do thank thee well. All seat themselves at the great table, except the Palmer, who places himself in a corner by the fire. Our way was to the tourney, which the Prince To morrow holds at Ashby, but the night Clos'd in upon us. Our noble host, you join The tournament? Cedric. Such is my purpose, father. Brian. 'Twill be a day for after times to talk of; The valours of our island will be there, No carpet warriors,—men,—whose hands and hearts Are temper'd as their swords—'Twill be a day Of blows, and blood, and death. Oswald enters. Oswald. The wealthy Jew, Isaac of York, craves shelter. Cedric. Bring him in. Brian. A Jew sit with a Templar! Prior. Or with me, A Father of the Church? Palmer. And hath he then No feeling of the tempest? Will the rains Spare him, that drench the Christian? Or these winds,— Will they pass over him as o'er the oak That bends, yet feels them not. Prior. Noble host, 'Tis he, whose daughter did bewitch your son. Palmer. His love is not their crime—their mis'ry rather. I pity the old man. Brian. By Paul! He comes! How the dog crouches! Oh! he'd play the part Of kind humility. But dæmon Pride Burns in that dark wild eye, and mocks the show His habit would put on. Enter Isaac. Isaac. Your pardon, pray: The storm is cold and wet, and growing night Made the few miles that lie 'twixt me and home A weary way—I mean my brother's home; For there I would abide to-morrow's tourney, Which being done, I shall return to York, To mine own dwelling. Ced. Well; be seated, Jew. Prior. Not here. Brian. Nor here. Isaac. O ye, twelve tribes! What evil is in me, Poor way-worn man, that I'm cast forth of all As dead flesh from the living bone? Palmer. Old man, My vest is dry; my hunger full; thou art Both wet and fasting. Sit. Isaac. And is it so? I did not think to weep—O, noble youth, I thank thee with my tears. Brian. A pilgrim thou! Shame of thy habit—Dost touch hands with Jews? Isaac. Thou hast done worse, for thou hast touch'd the earth In combat with young Ivanhoe.—So fame Reports from Palestine. Palmer. And truly. Brian. Slave! Cedric. Blood must not stain my hospitable board. Brian speaks aside to his Saracens. Prior. Let the Jew go; his presence is a stone To whet the knife of discord. Cedric. Say not so. Isaac. Kind Saxon, yes; 'tis fitting I should go; Better the old man die, if death indeed Be in the storm, than so much blood of youth Should flow in riot. Palmer. Templar, I have mark'd thee; The Jew goes not alone. Brian (contemptuously.) And who art thou? Palmer. I am—the Palmer; one who, in the lack Of thy philosophy, thinks man is man, Whate'er his faith, his habit, or his speech. Come, Jew, I'll be thy safety. Isaac. Noble youth! How shall I thank thee? Hate, and scorn, and blows, Are our sad portion—thou—men say I love My gold too well—it may be so; I'm old, And age will freeze the heart as winter locks The bounty of the brook: yet shine the sun, Twill melt the ice; thy kindness is a sun— I feel it at my heart. Brian. Base renegade! Prior. Vile infidel! Brian. Forth! Forth! Isaac. I pity thee; The poor old Jew—the dog—worse if worse be, Whom thy scorn spits upon, thy hatred loathes, Doth pity thee! think, Christian, what thou art, When one so poor, so beaten, so forlorn, Can say, I pity thee. Brian. Die, villain! Cedric. Hold! Cedric keeps back Brian, who had drawn upon Isaac. Isaac. Oh, valour nobly shown, and wise as noble! For is it not a valour most discreet, That knows to safely choose its foe, and makes Its secure war on hands that lack the sword, Or swords that lack the hand? Brian. Unloose me, sirs. Isaac. Hark how the lion roars! Palmer. No more, old man. Prior. Go forth, I say. Isaac. But this, and I am gone. Prior. Be wise, and fear. Isaac. What should I fear? I've broke The bread of Cedric;—drank his wine—I'm safe In hospitality. Cedric. 'Tis true;—He stays. Brian. Thou money-bag—thou thing, whose Midas-touch Turns all to gold,— Isaac. And what art thou?—A cypher,— That swells the social number though itself Is merely nothing.—What seed hast thou sown? What harvest reap'd?—What things of profit made? What merchandize exchang'd?—Thou hast set up A false god, Honour, at whose shrine man's blood Is pour'd in sacrifice by night and day; Thy worship is a murder;—and thy life Is nothing but that worship. Cedric. Jew, no more. Isaac. I was too rash—Say 'twas the fault of age, And pardon it; the dryest wood is still The quickest to the spark. Cedric. No more of strife. Oswald, conduct the Jew to his repose. Isaac. O noble Cedric! you have waken'd here A feeling that I thought was not; so long, So dully it had slumber'd.—Well, I see Impatience kindles in your eye—Good night! Thou'lt not sleep harder that an old man's pray'r Invokes a blessing on thee—and my heart, My very soul, breathes forth an orison For thy felicity. Blest be thy night, And oh, thy day more blessed. Fare thee well. (Exit Isaac. Prior. Let us to bed; the night is growing old, And we must forth with early morn to Ashby, To Prince John's tournament. (Aside to Brian. Brian, be calm. Brian. (to him) Yes; for I mind me of an after game— I'll pull the bravest feather from the wing Of this same infidel. Prior. The parting cup, And then to rest, good host. Cedric. Be't as you say. Prior. The toast be mine—the fairest of the fair! Although a Jewess, to her health—Rebecca— All. Rebecca! Prior. Now, good night. Cedric. Lights, knaves—Myself Will be your servant. All go out except the Palmer—Gurth enters. Palmer. How to save the Jew! For sav'd he must be at what ever price— Ha! honest Gurth— The Jew and I must forth. Undo the postern gate. Gurth. Ay, marry! when— At your good bidding? Palmer. Ay, at mine. The Palmer draws back his cowl. Gurth. How! Palmer. Silence; walls have ears. Gurth. But yet no tongues To tell what they do hear. Palmer. Where sleeps the Jew? Gurth. In the north tower. Palmer. And I? Gurth. I' the room below. Palmer. I know it well—the light—when all's still, come. Gurth and the Palmer go out on different sides. SCENE II. —A Gallery in Cedric's Castle: Cedric and Servants enter conducting the Prior, Brian, Saracens, &amp;c. Cedric. This way, my noble guests. Prior. We entertain Your kindness as 'tis offer'd, frankly, freely. Brian. A moment, with your leave—Melek—a trifle 'tis, yet proper to the moment. Cedric. Take your time. Brian. (aside to Melek) There is a pilgrim in the Prior's train; Melek. Francis, my Lord. (Wamba steals in.) Brian. Get me his pilgrim's garb, And bring it to my chamber. (Exit, Melek.) Our kind host!— All go out except Wamba, who comes to the front. Wamba. What should he want now with a pilgrim's frock? Some notable intrigue! your soldier, troth, Is ever nibbling at the wenches, as Your mouse at cheese, or fishes at the hook, When as the wind blows southerly. Good faith, Here is strange fellowship; Jew, Norman, Saxon; Here's Noah's ark; your Saxon is a horse; An ass the Jew, who bears his load for others; A wolf, your Norman—Well an if a man Should choose to prophecy, horse, ass, and wolf, Will be by th' ears ere morning. Gurth. (stealing in) Wamba!—Fool! Wamba. That's I; yet now I think on it again, It is not I, for he 's a wise man who Doth know himself; and if I know myself, Why then, no fool. Gurth. There's mischief stirring. Wamba. True; You're not abed. Gurth. Truce with thy mocks, good fool: Are all at rest? Wamba. At rest?—I'll not say that; But all are in their beds:—O, Gurth! Gurth! Gurth! Your taper burning in the chimney nook Shall see more merry sights, than e'er the sun Can hope to look upon. Gurth. Hark! Wamba. Wherefore? Gurth. Hush! Wamba. Your pitcher, I; two goodly ears and a wide mouth, but no tongue. Gurth. (striking him) Wilt not be silent? Wamba. What's that for? Gurth. For thee. Wamba. Thank ye; but, good troth, you're welcome to it again, an you'll take it at my hands. Gurth. No anger, fool. Wamba. Fool, quotha! Better be a fool in word, —as I am,—than a fool in deeds,—as thou art. I never get drunk with ale,—as thou dost,—and that is folly, for it makes the head ache: I am not married, —as thou art,—and that is folly, for it makes the heart ache—nay, and the head too beyond the cure of physic—no getting rid of the horn of cuckoldom; it grows, like your corn, the more you cut it. Gurth. Go to; my wife is faithful to me. Wamba. Neither am I valiant; for valour is quarrelsome: quarrels bring blows, blows bring pain; and he who is a voluntary to pain, shall have any praise under Heaven but that of wisdom. Now I think on't, I will tell thee a tale which thou shalt like marvellously, for thou shalt not understand its least syllable. Cedric. (without) Wamba! Wamba. Nuncle cuts short my tale. Gurth. Thou'lt be the more like a man:—but, Wamba, when Cedric is at rest, let me know—here— or in my chamber. Wamba. Some petticoat business. Knave thou hast been, knave thou art—may, can, will, and shall be, through all moods and tenses—past, present, and to come. An thou art not damned; the devil must be horn-mad. Wamba and Gurth go out on different sides. SCENE III. —A rude Bed-chamber. The Jew asleep on a Pallet. Brian enters in a Palmer's habit. Brian. The dull brute sleeps. Now, could I make him fear An instant danger, and so lead him forth To mine own castle, I'd wring heaps of gold From his close avarice. This guise will hide My real seeming. What should he with gold, But as the mule to bear't for others' use? Mule, I will ease thee of thy burthen. Isaac. (asleep) Mercy! Brian. His slumber speaks: Now for my holy part, A part I scarce shall prosper in—Awake! Isaac. Murd'rer! Hold back thy hand! A hundred marks— A thousand—for my life, my precious life. Brian. Nay, know me better; am I not your friend? Isaac. Thou art a Christian;—yet have mercy on me! Brian. I am thy friend, and come with friendly purpose. The Templar's avarice would wring the gold From thy hard gripe. Isaac. And thou will save me? Brian. Yes. Isaac. O noble youth! a hapless race are we! And thou wilt guide me forth. The mountain top Is not more open to the winds of Heaven Than we to persecution. Gen'rous youth! Wrong is not wrong when it is done to us;— We're held a game for service of the rich, Who fence us from the gripe of meaner hands To hunt us down themselves. Brian. Well; follow me; I'll be thy safety from the Templar. Isaac. Who Will safe me from thyself? Brian. Stay in thy doubt, And perish. Isaac. Hold! I do not doubt—And yet— Such was the figure, such the voice of him My dream show'd to me. Brian. How! a dream!— Isaac. E'en so. Laugh if you will—But has not heav'n ere now Through the thin shade of dreams discours'd to man, Divulging murder when hid fathoms deep? Are not the dreams of sleep like shadows seen In doubtful moonlight? Brian. Tush. Isaac. But hearken, youth, I follow'd you through night, when, on the sudden, A dreadful earthquake shook our lower world; The bosom of the earth was torn; the graves Yawn'd wide with cold and famish'd maw, As if, too leanly fed by death, their hunger gap'd For living food to gorge their appetite. Brian. Would'st teach me, like thyself, to shake at shadows. Isaac. Strange cries, such as no mortal tongue e'er breath'd, No mortal ear e'er heard till that sad hour, Fill'd up the list'ning pauses of the storm. The light'nings hissed, and flash'd upon the dead, Who had for ages slumber'd in their darkness: In the strong blaze I saw their livid cheeks, The quiv'rings of their blue and writhed lips— Yea, their op'd eyes glar'd strangely on the living With fire not of life.—I call'd on thee; But, while I spoke, the human form drop'd from thee; And thou a serpent, stood erect before me, With glaring eyes, and scales made bright with anger. I heard thy hiss, and the next moment felt Thy coil ring round me with an iron grasp, Bruising and crushing; and thy fiery tongue Shot, like a burning arrow, in mine eyes— Horror!—the very memory is madness! I will not follow thee. Brian. Thou must—thou shalt. Isaac. How say you? Brian. Follow me. Isaac. Thy wrath betrays thee. Thou art not the Palmer. Brian. Hence then with disguise. Isaac. The dream was truth. Brian. This avails thee not. If by denial, slow consent, or cries, You check my purpose, in that instant is My dagger at your heart. Now follow, Jew. Isaac. Have pity on mine age. Brian. Jew, wilt thou follow? Isaac. I can not—dare not. Brian. Dog, die like a dog. As Brian attempts to stab Isaac, the Palmer suddenly enters and arrests his hand. Palmer. Hold—noble Templar. Brian. Slave. Palmer. Strike if you dare, Cold midnight murderer; but yet beware; We're Cedric's guests, who wants nor will, nor means, T'avenge his broken hospitality. Brian. The present hour is thine; but triumph not; A time will come, when you shall both well wish This had not been; I will pursue revenge In earth, and air, and water, aye in fire. Isaac. Oh, Christian—no—hence with ye, pride and hate; My heart's a humble dwelling, and you love To throne in more ambitious habitations. Your pardon, Christian; let the past be past: Accept my hand. Brian. Accept my vow of hate. Where now I would have taken grains of gold, I will have tons; Look to it, Jew. Palmer. Indeed! Violent storm. Isaac. Hark! how the tempest roars! Does not its voice Chide thy vain savage boasting? Dost not feel Another world is clipping thee about? The howling wind makes faint thy loudest cries! The thunder shows thee as a sickly babe Screaming weak anger!—Hark! how it shakes these walls! While thy poor breath will scarcely move a rush. A violent burst of wind beats open the window, and shows the blighted arm of an oak. Isaac. Ha! see yon blasted oak that flings its arm Across the window—Once that arm was stout— Ay, stouter than thine own—Proud earthworm, look! Behold!—as that once was, so hast thou been;— As that is now, so shalt thou be— To the Palmer. Come! Come! The Palmer and Isaac go out. Brian remains as if stupified. END OF ACT I.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. SCENE I. Enter Isaac and Miriam. Isaac. O Jacob! what a losing venture's this! Miriam. But, uncle,— Isaac. O, my gold, my food! my fire! My light! my raiment! Miriam. Yet you gave the coin To Prince John freely. Isaac. My gold! Is't not my child? Child of my toil? My comfort in adversity, my joy In prosperous hours,—pillow of my rest, Companion of my day? Shall I not weep? Miriam. Take comfort to thee yet; The loss is not so great. Isaac. The loss not great? Fifty zecchins!—not great! By Jacob's staff, I'd rather they should suck so many drops Of blood from these old veins, that ill can spare them, Than e'en the tenth division of that sum. Miriam. Think of this, uncle, as the merchant does, Who flings his precious venture to the waves To save his bark from sinking. Isaac. Talk not, child; Talk not to me, my spirit is too sad. Miriam. Shall I sing to you? you were wont to love the melody of song. Isaac. Do what you list, But offer me no comfort—I am sad— Sad even to weeping. Isaac sits down. BALLAD—Miriam. A Knight went forth to Palestine; Ave Maria! But first he knelt at the marriage shrine, And said to his virgin bride, “Thou'rt mine,” Fairest Maria! His arm was strong, his voice was sweet, Ave Maria! And sang to the tramp of horses' feet, As man to man the bright squadrons meet, “Fame and Maria.” He fell, and to his squire he said, Ave Maria! “Cut the dark locks from my dying head, Say, as you give them to her I've wed, In death Maria's.” He brought them to the virgin bride; Ave Maria! She wept as the locks to her harp she tied, Which still, as the wind blew o'er them, sigh'd, “Fairest Maria.” Isaac. I do bethink me now, There is another loss; the goodly steed And the rich armour, lent to that young knight Who did protect me in the Saxon's hall, Who can he be? and wherefore thus disguis'd In Palmer's gear? But what is that to me? My lendings—the brave horse—the armour too— 'Tis they that I should think of. Miriam. Do not doubt. He was an honest youth; his voice was truth. Isaac. It may be so; I think it is; and yet 'Tis a large venture; one that makes me poor E'en to suppose its loss. Miriam. 'Twill not be lost. Isaac. But if it should—A bad race are these Christians; Gold in their hands is snow; it melts away In their hot grasp to water;—Well; well; well; 'Tis a good youth; he us'd the poor old Jew With gentle words, and gentler action;—yet I would my lendings were safe home again. The Palmer enters in armour. Palmer. My friend! Isaac. The Palmer. Palmer. Nay, the Palmer Knight, Since I have put on armour. Isaac. Miriam!—Go— (Exit Miriam. Well; and how art thou?—Is mine armour safe? My good horse too?—O, 'twas a cruel fight! Heav'ns! what a crash!—Mine ears ring with it still! Good youth—for my sake do not put thy life Unto such fearful peril—pray you now. Palmer. I thank thy kindness, and now list my speech. I was the victor. Isaac. Ay, you were!—You were— You dash'd them to the earth as ocean flings The sea-weed on the rock. Palmer. I've sold the spoils, As is our use. Isaac. You come to pay the loan Of the good steed and armour. Palmer. Even so. Isaac. Gold—pure, bright gold—and yet—no— Palmer. Why is this? Isaac. Take it again; in my hands 'twould be lead, And weigh me to the earth—You need its use; I have enough—What did I say?—I'm poor— Believe it, youth, most miserably poor— But keep it—keep it—you did peril life To save this worthless body!—Oh, my heart Warms to thee, and—and—when the old man dies, Perhaps you'll drop a tear upon his grave. Enter Rebecca. Rebecca. Tubal would speak with you; his bus'ness craves An instant answer. Isaac. Tarry thou awhile Till my return. (Exit Isaac. Palmer. Fair lady, lend your ear; I am the friend of Ivanhoe. Rebecca. Indeed— Does he still love. (Aside) Forbid it maiden pride— Does he still love his country? Palmer. How! so cold! Rebecca. You anwer not—or is he still unchang'd? Palmer. No, lady. Rebecca. No! Palmer. No, lady; care with him Has done the work of time. His youth is old. Rebecca. I spoke not of the outward form. Palmer. Alas! When unripe blossoms lose their outward show, Is't not because the worm within is busy, Working like change. Rebecca. Be freer of thy speech. Palmer. Lady—lady, his heart is well nigh broke: The blood is seething in his veins, more hot Than the hot sands the desert flings in scorn Against his face. Rebecca. Oh, alas! This sorrow is too great! My tears will flow. Palmer. Sorrow! you know it not: a few salt tears That fall and are forgotten are not sorrow. It is not thus he grieves; with hollow eyes, With famished cheeks, with nightly groans, he lifts The voice of his despair to Heaven—tears! The desert has no tears; and, where grief is, There is a desert. Rebecca. Palmer, you speak this Too well, and yet too ill. Palmer. My jealous doubt— I do conjure you, answer that I ask: Or if that maiden modesty deny The lips' confession, to a stranger ear— Then give that scarf, and it shall be a sign Thy love is still to Ivanhoe. Rebecca. (aside) There is A soft seduction in his speech that steals With magic influence to the heart, As odours on the senses. Palmer. Wilt thou not Wilt thou not give the scarf? Rebecca. Stranger! 'tis thine. Palmer. And Ivanhoe is thine;—I know his heart. Rebecca. Stranger, who art thou?—Oh, I do suspect— Palmer. I've sworn an oath, and on the holy cross, Not to divulge me unless force compel, 'Till he, who bound, unloose the oath. Rebecca. Thy hand. Palmer. Thou hast it, maid. Rebecca. The ring—you are,— Palmer. Thine,—ever thine. Rebecca. Is't real?—Is it not a dream?—No, no— I feel my heart is throbbing 'gainst thy hand— I have thee,—hold thee—ne'er to part again. Miriam, Enters. Miriam. Mine uncle calls. Trumpet. Palmer. And hark, the trumpet calls me to the Tourney. Rebecca. Yet stay, If still thy father's wrath pursue us. Palmer. I will appeal unto a father's heart. Rebecca. But if it fail— Palmer. To heaven and my sword. Miriam. You know this stranger? Rebecca. I. Miriam. It seems so. Rebecca. Come. Miriam. Your cheek is pale— Rebecca. 'Tis nothing, 'twill away The breath of morn grows warm and sickly here, I scarce respire—O let me drink the air. (Exit. SCENE II. —A Forest. Robin Hood, Scarlet, and Foresters, seated round a fire. GLEE. Others, like the sickly rose, Bloom but in the day's broad light; But our blood more warmly glows, In the darkness of the night. Night it is whose magic pow'r, Tints the cheek, and melts the soul; Night, that bids the wine's red show'r Drop more sparkling from the bowl. Scarlet. How swift the time has fled: the length of night Has seem'd but as an hour—nay, scarce so much. What thinks our Captain, noble Robin Hood? Robin Hood. I think, friend Scarlet, 'tis good time we chang'd The goblet for the bow—I'faith the morn Is blushing at our pranks. Scarlet. Good sooth now, Her worship is too modest— Robin Hood. You forget; You must be quick, an you have any will To this day's tournament.—Your bows, my friends. (Exeunt all but Robin Hood and Scarlet. Robin Hood. May our brother Saxons gain, As they did yesterday, the prize of valor. Scarlet. And most the Palmer Knight! He shew'd himself a right one. Robin Hood. Aye: an he strike to-day as he did yesterday— St. George! The Normans dropt before his blows, Like mellow fruit before the winds of autumn. Didst see how Prince John writh'd his nether lip? St. Withold's curse upon him!— Scarlet. 'Tis a churl! Robin Hood. Would that our Richard were safe home again! He, though a Norman, is a king for Saxons— Poor Isaac, too— Scarlet. Why yes, the Prince drank deep Of Isaac's purse—but that is little matter; The Jew is but a Jew Robin Hood. He's an open heart, Though somewhat a close hand. When I lay ill, Fest'ring with wounds, a price upon my head, He wasted gold on my necessities; While his fair daughter, kind Rebecca, was The surgeon to my sickness. Scarlet. People say, Her skill is borrow'd of the devil— Robin Hood. Tush. Scarlet. Laugh as you will; I'm partly of their faith Who say she is a witch. Robin Hood. More fool art thou; The Jew's a kind old soul, who loves his coin Perhaps too much, yet works withal more good Than those of better name. I say again, He nurs'd my sickness, fed my need with gold— How many Christians, think you, had done so? Scarlet. Not one of my acquaintance—Well; I've heard The Jews were skilful doctors—tis, indeed, Their quality of fame—but this—in faith, You must allow my wonder. Wamba enters hastily. Robin Hood. Whither so fast, good fool? Wamba. Out of the way of nuncle Cedric—Such news— First the Jew turn'd out to be Ivanhoe— No—Ivanhoe turn'd out to be the Jew— No, I don't mean that— Robin Hood. Gramercy, fool; thou tell'st thy story well— Wamba. First, Prince John took Isaac's purse from him, as he did yesterday, Whereat the Jew march'd off from the tourney. Robin Hood. But your Palmer Knight— Wamba. The Palmer Knight proves to be Ivanhoe, and his kind papa, Cedric, no sooner finds him to be his son, than off he flies, growling and cursing by all the Saints in the Calendar. Oh, 'tis rare sport. And now young Ivanhoe is fighting for the tourney's prize with Brian; and, I'faith, yonder is nuncle Cedric —I am off. (Wamba hurries out. Robin Hood. Come, Scarlet, to the fray. A curse upon these Normans. (Exit. END OF THE SECOND ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. SCENE I. —The garden belonging to Miriam's house— Ivanhoe and Rebecca seated. Ivanhoe. Oh! would this hour were long as it is sweet! Then would it never end. Rebecca. But why, my friend, This brow of sadness? Trust me now, it seems To chide my happier thought—Is't sickness clouds Thy better self? Ivanhoe. Thanks to thy loving care, My wounds are whole—I would not make thee blush With thine own praise, yet sooth thy healing skill Exceeds the surgeon's art no marvel, fame Taxes thee, Love, with witchcraft—true indeed There's witchcraft in thine eye. Rebecca. This flatt'ring strain Shows more like mirth, and therefore I'll not chide it. But how could I do less, when love for me Had clos'd against thy need a father's door? Ivanhoe. Talk not of him—Rebecca. I must leave thee. Rebecca. You go with us to York—This very hour We leave mine uncle on our journey home. Ivanhoe. Thou shalt know all—King Richard is return'd, At whose command I came to try the land, For fame told many stories of dark plots Laid by his brother 'gainst his life and throne. His will now bids me join him—Therefore list: Sev'n years I've lov'd you—lov'd as few have lov'd— Nor frown of friends, nor time, nor distance, nor The thousand forms of beauty, e'er have made My love forgetful of its first-born vow. Now, then, reward that love—let marriage join Our hands, whose hearts have been so long but one. Rebecca. Oh! not for worlds would I bring on thy head A father's curse. Enter Cedric—Ivanhoe kneels. Ivanhoe. To see thee here is joy Beyond my hope. Rebecca. (aside) Why do I tremble? I Have done no wrong. Cedric. What skills thy bended knee? Bend thy proud stubborn heart—Arise, young man. Arise, I say—I would not ought but Heav'n Should witness Cedric's race upon the knee. Ivanhoe. Your pardon first. Cedric. Arise, I say, and list. I wish'd to hate thee; but this foolish heart Plays false with reason, and I come to sue, To beg of mine own son—Fly from this witch— Rebecca. (aside). Be still, proud heart. Ivanhoe. She sav'd my life. Cedric. 'Twere better you had died, than so been sav'd. But I'll not waste more speech—My hand is rais'd— Speak—shall it bless or curse thee? Rebecca. Let me speak— I've lov'd your son—have dearly, truly lov'd him— And oh, must love him still; but from this hour Mine eye shall be a stranger to his sight. Ivanhoe. Rebecca! Rebecca. Thou'lt forgive him? Cedric. Hypocrite! Thou wilt not leave him—'tis the gloss of cunning. Rebecca. Believe the humble duty of my love, That bows to earth to do thee fitting homage— Believe my adjuration of yon Heaven, That now I call in witness of my truth— Believe—my tears. Cedric. Arise—I trust thee not. And yet so like to truth—but no—arise. Rebecca. Then, Ivanhoe—thy hand—Is it not mine? Ivanhoe. Thine—ever thine—and bless'd that it is thine. Rebecca. Then thus I give it where it most belongs. Will you not take it—'Tis a proud rich gift From one so poor. Cedric. I am all wonder— Rebecca. Ay! Thy wonder makes me wonder—Let it go— I am a willing sacrifice; and when Sorrow grows wild beyond my strength to suffer, I'll think upon this hour, and then my heart Will not quite break—will not quite break. (Exit Rebecca Cedric. My son— I do not chide thy grief—the maid is worth An honourable sorrow—Pity 'tis She comes of Jewish race. Ivanhoe (half aside.) She shall be mine. I will not yield her for the price of worlds. Cedric. Wake not a father's wrath—its fire wil scathe thee; Blight thy youth's freshness as the lightning drinks The verdure of the oak. Wilt leave the maid? Ivanhoe. Shall I be false to gratitude—to love— To mine own vows? Cedric. Wilt not obey me? Ivanhoe. My father! Cedric. Wilt leave the maiden? Ivanhoe. Never. Cedric. Henceforth be A stranger to my home, my heart, my race. I banish thee for ever—Mark—for ever. (Exit Cedric. Ivanhoe. My father—Stay—He's gone, and will not hear me— But yet there is good hope—ay, more than hope— My royal master, Richard—He has pow'r, And to that pow'r the will to do me service— A word from him will force my father yield. No doubts—no fears—I'll join the King, E'en as he bids me—Fortune, I defy thee. (Exit Ivanhoe. SCENE II. —Prince John's Tent: Prince John and Brian enter. Brian. Talk on; I love Rebecca. Prince John. Faith, your heart Must be the merest touchwood!—as I think, You saw her for the first time at the tourney. Brian. 'Tis even so. Prior. Were she of any other race—But she— An infidel! Brian. By this blest light, He is an infidel, who would not yield Faith, honour, country, life, for those rich lips, Those eyes where pleasure languishes, that breast Where love might feed, and appetite increase E'en by indulgence. Prince John. Well, but your Templar's vow Forbids all thought of marriage. Brian. Marriage! I only talk'd of love—and I will have her, Despite her father. Prince John. Were that all, there's none Would blame the deed; but Ivanhoe, our friend;— He loves the maid. Brian. Hell's curse upon the stripling. In love, in arms, in ev'ry thing, her foils me— But come what will, the maiden shall be mine; Ay, and this Jewish dog shall find my hand Can reach him, spite of Ivanhoe.—The fool— I meant no ill, but to his purse—but now— Baffled and mock'd—a day will come— 'Tis not far off. Prince John. Well—well—e'en as you will. The Jew is not within the pale of law; And as for Ivanhoe—King Richard's minion— I should not grieve if he were dead—but mind, I neither sanction nor deny your act. (Exit Prince John. Brian. Because you dare do neither. De Bracy enters. De Bracy. News, my friend. Fortune is kinder than thy utmost hope Could fashion her. Brian. But how? De Bracy. Ay, marry, how? The Jew and fair Rebecca travel on For York to night—Your castle's near, My followers prepar'd. Beauty and gold Are your's, if you dare seize them. Brian. If I dare; What is it I dare not? You mock me, friend.— But, speed our back! Occasion's wind blows fair, And must be us'd, or its inconstant breath Will fall again, and leave our vessel drifting. (Brian and De Bracy go out. SCENE III. —The outside of Copmanhurst Hermitage.— Ivanhoe enters. Ivanhoe. Farewell my noble steed! the kites and crows Will be thy monument. I needs must rest; My fresh scars ache with weariness. And yet King Richard's mandate was most urgent. Well, To-morrow I may join him. Ho—within. He knocks at the door. Clerk (within.) Pass on; disturb not in his prayers St. Dunstan's servant. Ivanhoe. Holy father mine, St. Dunstan is a kind good-natur'd saint, And I'll be sworn can better lack your prayers Than I your hospitality. Clerk (within.) Pass on. Ivanhoe. Pray you point out the road. The Clerk of Copmanhurst opens the window and looks out. Clerk. Pray you pass on. One pater and two credos you have marr'd Already. Ivanhoe. I am weary. Clerk. Rest thee then; 'Tis a soft bed, the green sward. Ivanhoe. Yes, indeed, Rather too soft; 'tis soak'd with rain; besides, The night-wind's bleak: I pray thee let me in. Clerk. An thou art weary, as thou say'st thou art, Thou wilt sleep soundly; he who soundly sleeps Feels neither wind nor rain. Ivanhoe. Good rhetoric! Yet 'twill not coax me to rest under Heaven While you sleep under shelter. Clerk. Aye, in troth! How wilt then help thyself? Ivanhoe. By breaking down Thy churlish door. Clerk. Well said! but wilt thou do it? Ivanhoe. Ay, by St. Julian will I. Clerk. Have thy will then. But an I like thee not the better; mark— I warn thee now—thou'lt find some little cause To rue my courtesy. Now, then, walk in. Ivanhoe enters the Hermitage. SCENE IV. —Interior of Copmanhurst Hermitage.—The Clerk and Ivanhoe enter. Ivanhoe. Shelter at least. Now for my bed and supper. What says your holiness? Clerk. Your bed is there, In yonder nook: for supper—'tis before you. Ivanhoe. A bed of straw, and supper of dry peas! What splendid fare! and wholesome too, or you Had never grown so stout on it. For drink? Clerk. There's plenty in St. Dunstan's well; his name Be blessed for it. Ivanhoe. Umph! you call yourself— Clerk. The Clerk of Copmanhurst; the holy clerk, As some do add; but I stand not on that, As being little worthy of the honour. Ivanhoe. Exceeding modest! But the cupboard there? 'Twas built for something. Clerk. I keep relics in it. Ivanhoe. The relics of cold ven'son it may be. Clerk. Now I think on't, the keeper of the forest Did leave a ven'son pasty. He goes to the cupboard and brings out a pasty. Ivanhoe. So I thought. 'Tis excellent! he left some wine too?—Yes. Clerk. I cannot recollect it. Ivanhoe. 'Tis indeed A trifle most unworthy to hold place In your most holy brain; but search that crypt; It may be you will find my guess is right. The Clerk goes to the cupboard and brings out a bottle of wine. Clerk. Ay, by St. Dunstan is it!—Mighty strange. Ivanhoe. Oh! very strange! Drink hael—But, holy clerk, Had I thy legs and such a brawny arm, I'd walk by moonlight, pattering my pray'rs, And ever and anon let fly a shaft Among the deer—What think you of it now? Were't not a pretty pastime? Clerk. You see the trinkets here? He opens a little armoury, of bows, cross-bows, &amp;c. Ivanhoe. I thank thee well, And make no farther question. Clerk. Heaven's faith! I do suspect thy valour as thy wit: But you're my guest; sing, if you cannot fight,— Do something to amuse me. Ivanhoe. I've no voice. Clerk. Nor fight, nor sing! and call yourself a Knight! Thou dost not know thy craft, man. Knocking without. Ivanhoe. More guests. Clerk. Help! Help! Sir Knight! I would not for my cowl they found me thus; The knaves might term this hospitable feast Debauchery, a vice I most abhor. Ivanhoe. Vile slanderers of virtue! Robin Hood. (without) Open quick: Open to Robin Hood! Ivanhoe. Mort de ma vie! The King of Sherwood forest and mad Tuck! Now by my holy dame, a braver king And more anointed priest, my travel ne'er Has met withal. Robin Hood and Foresters enter. Robin Hood. How! Ivanhoe! Tuck. St. Dunstan! You know him then? Robin Hood. 'Tis little strange, I know The gallant Knight who won the tourney's prize; But quick, mad clerk; do off thy frock of grey, And don thy Lincoln green; we've work in hand. Brave Knight, we need your aid. Ivanhoe. I grieve my hours Are number'd to a purpose that admits Of no delay. Tuck. I'm ready for your work. Robin Hood. Attend: your father, Cedric; the rich Jew, His daughter, fair Rebecca,— Ivanhoe. What of her? She should be now at York. Robin Hood. Their way, indeed, Was thither, when Sir Brian bore them off; Chance made me witness of the deed. Ivanhoe. My arms!— Robin Hood. Ay, now you speak it in a soldier's note. Ivanhoe. Come on, brave friends! No pity—no remorse, Till vict'ry, new launch'd, float on a sea Of crimson water mid the shouts of triumph. Robin Hood. Nay, while we talk, the time for deed grows cold. Ivanhoe. To Brian's castle! Wrap the walls in fire! Nought's for the coward!—all is for the brave! (Exeunt omnes. SCENE IV. —A Prison in the Turret of Brian's Castle; in one Corner is a wide Fire-place, fronted with rusty Bars of Iron. Isaac lies in the corner on a Bundle of Straw. Isaac. When will it come? the last strong fearful wrench, That tears the struggling spirit from the flesh? Sick! Sick! And life had still such hoarded sweets For time to reap,—the kiss of infant love— The smiles of social joy—the thousand hopes That fourscore years had twin'd about my heart:— And I must die—must rot in the cold grave; And stranger feet will rest them in my home! And stranger joys will laugh around my hearth. Enter Brian and Saracens. Brian. Up, Jewish dog! Up, infidel! Isaac. Good Knight, Be merciful! Brian. Thou art my pris'ner, Jew; If freedom be a jewel of high carat, Thou'lt not deny its purchase at my price,— A thousand silver marks. Isaac. There never was,— There never will be, such a sum; a hill,— A mountain 'tis, of silver. Brian. Is it? Well; I will be gentle, and if silver's scant,— Isaac. It is, it is. Brian. Then I'll take gold. Isaac. Gold! gold! Where shall I find it? In the earth or sea? The coffers of my tribe hold not the sum. Brian. The fire flame roars,—What think you of your bed? For your's it will be, if you yield not soon To that I ask. Isaac. You do not mean it?—No; The father of all good ne'er made a heart Of so much cruelty, and yet he made The serpent and the wolf. Brian. Be wise, old man; That fire will bite more sharply than the wolf; That flame will grasp thee in its burning coil, More fiercely than the serpent. Take thy choice. Isaac. I have no choice; I lack the money. Brian. False, and vain as false. I'll have thy gold; first, as I need its use; Next, to thy grief, and in it my revenge, For that thou sought'st a friend in him I hate. Isaac. Look on my pains! Send forth thy angel, death! Return me to the dust, that earth may feel No more than earth. Brian. Nay, come; thy answer, Jew; Hark! how the flames are roaring for their prey. Isaac. Would I were dead! Brian. Hast ever felt the pain Of fire but in thy finger? Think of that, And tremble. Isaac. Flesh cannot bear the pang! I'll give—I've not the gold—have mercy—mercy— Brian. Dost think thy cries can move me? I have seen The sack of cities, when a thousand flames, As hot as these, have gone forth to devour Men, women, children—aye, bed-ridden age And puling infancy—and deem'st thou then The screaming of a single, wretched Jew, Can shake my purpose? Hope it not, old man; Wilt give the money? Isaac. I will; you'll set My daughter free; she'll borrow of our tribe That dwell in York, and thou shall have the coin Weigh'd to thee on this floor. Brian. No, Isaac, no. Isaac. How else shall I provide it? Brian. That's your care; But for your black-eye'd daughter, she shall be My handmaid in the fashion of the tribes Of Israel—a good example, Jew, If wisely followed, Isaac. Art indeed a man? Oh take what you've ask'd; Take ten times more—take all—make me a beggar, Let me feed in the highway with the dogs— But spare my child, my sweet, my guiltless child. Brian. Hope it not, Isaac; mine she is, and shall be. Isaac. The horse leech, Sorrow, fix upon thy heart, And gripe it 'till 'tis bloodless—Oh the maw Of dogs be tomb for thee. Brian. (coolly) Thy curses wound not— But has thy flesh a charm 'gainst steel and flames? Isaac. My child! my child!—I do defy thee, else. Tear me with pincers; let fire gnaw the flesh From off these bones, with tooth that wounds but kills not, That life may look upon its own decay,— Still I defy thee. Brian. To the trial then! Shouts are heard without: clash of swords. Yet hold! what sound is that? He leaps upon the table and looks out of the grated loop hole. Besieg'd! besieg'd! The arrows fly in showers!—Ha! I'm struck. De Bracy. (without) What, Brian ho! the castle is beset. Brian plucks the Arrow from his breast, and falls into the arms of the Saracens: while they are busy in staunching the wound, &amp;c. Isaac speaks. Isaac. Triumph!—he falls!—How,—do my curses wound? Dost thou not feel them griping at thy heart? Christian, dost thou hear me? Thine was the eagle's flight,—high,—high in air! Thou look'st upon the sun, and in thy pride Made it no shame to tear with rav'nous beak, The birds of humbler quarry!—What! thy wing Is broken, flapping bloodily in dust— May it ne'er heal again to bear thee up, Where thou may'st souse upon the weaker things That fly beneath thee—no—shame, Isaac—shame List to his groans—list to the bubbling blood— How his limbs quiver—Christian—I forgive thee. END OF THE THIRD ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT IV. SCENE I. —An open space before the burning ruins of Brian's castle; The trees and hills are covered with snow; Robin Hood, Ivanhoe, and a party of Foresters, are sitting on the ground. Robin Hood. Well, sirs, what think ye? Did e'er monarch feast Upon so wide a table, or beneath A canopy so rich, or 'fore a hearth That burns with such a fire? Ivanhoe. In faith, 'twould warm Poor old December with his locks of snow, And comfort his blue nose.—A boon, my friend! Robin Hood. 'Tis thine ere ask'd. Ivanhoe. When first flames wrapt yon walls, They lit me to Rebecca. To be brief, I bore her to a cottage from the aim And blank of danger, leaving her in guard Of faithful Gurth; and back return'd, to save A father's life! Robin Hood. But to your boon. Ivanhoe. 'Tis this; See her safe hence to York;—the task were mine, But that a bus'ness of no common poise Calls me another way. Robin Hood. It shall be done E'en to your wish. Ivanhoe. Her father, I much fear, Has perish'd in the tumult. If he live, Call him my friend, and let him find that name His safety. Robin Hood. Though he stood in my worst hate, No harm should touch a hair upon his head. Ivanhoe. Your hand,—my father comes; you know your part. Cedric enters with Foresters. Cedric. I thank you for my safety. Robin Hood. Thank this Knight; But for his skill that led our hands, yon walls Had burnt no jubilee for your release. Cedric. I thank him well; yet wordy thanks are poor— An unseal'd bond, if deeds stamp not thereon The sign of value: ask then what thou wilt— 'Tis thine if it be Cedric's. Robin Hood. Fairly said. Ivanhoe. I take thee at thy word—Forgive thy son! Cedric. Were that you ask the purchase of my life, I'd die ere yield it; but my word is past; I pardon Ivanhoe. Ivanhoe. He's at thy feet. Cedric. How? Dost thou dare? Robin Hood. Saxon! your plighted word. Cedric. 'Tis true; and yet— Ivanhoe. Father! Cedric. Thou hast o'ercome! Rise—to my heart. Ivanhoe. This magic hour makes sweet The bitterness of years; yet even now, While joy smiles on me as a new-trimm'd bride, And would be clipt, I must perforce away, Her virgin sweets untasted—'Tis honour calls! Cedric. Then go, my son. Were I now dying, none So near to close mine eyes, thou shouldst not stay 'Gainst honour's call—My blessing with thee—Go! (Exit Ivanhoe. Cedric. And now to York! (Exeunt omnes. SCENE II. —Another part of the Forest. Foresters (without). Nay, no resistance, Jew! Come on, mad wags! Robin Hood, Wamba, and Ivanhoe, enter. Robin Hood. It is his voice—and Scarlet with his band. Tuck entering with Isaac, followed by Scarlet and Foresters. Tuck. Room for your holy Clerk, my merry men! I come, like to an eagle, with my prey Clutched in my talons. Shout, merry men! Isaac. The Christian shepherds these! Robin Hood. What, Isaac! thou art safe—I think, mad Clerk, The wine speaks out of thee, Tuck. St. Dunstan, now! But wine's your only orator; he deals Such tropes, such flourishes, and aye, speaks truth, While this same sneaking, false, cold-blooded knave, This soberness, will lie you by the hour, And sixty to the hour. Robin Hood. But why is this? I mean this holy war against poor Isaac. Tuck. He is a captive to my spear and shield—Stand forth; Rehearse to them my valor. Isaac. Oh! alas! I am confounded; this old brain doth totter. Robin Hood. Where didst thou find him? Tuck. In the cellar, where They found me quite exhausted: quite. Speak ye, my friends; now was not I exhausted. Scarlet. Aye; and the wine-but too. Tuck. Ye lie, ye pagans; Ye worse than pagans! But what recks this? The Jew Is a converted Jew, and knows his creed, His ave and his pater as well—no— Nearly as well as I do. Robin Hood. Is it so? Say, Jew, hast thou renounced thy unbelief? Isaac. Renounce the faith of my forefathers! Horror! Scorn would hiss at me living, and, when dead, My bones would rest with strangers. Tuck. Dost recant? I'll jerk thee, infidel. He attempts to strike the Jew, when Wamba interposes his wand. Robin Hood. Nay, No quarrels, bully Clerk; do on your frock, For here's a brother. Tuck. I do kiss thy hand; But for the Jew, I scorn him with my heels. He puts on his Friar's frock, as a party of Foresters lead on the Prior Aymer. Tuck. Ha! brother mine; St. Andrew's day with us; we're taking tythes. Gurth rushes in. Gurth. To rescue, or she's lost. Robin Hood. Who's lost? Gurth. Rebecca. Isaac. My daughter!—When?—Where? Speak!—Speak! Gurth. De Bracy, flying with the wounded Brian, Pass'd by the cot, and tore her from my arms; Too feeble 'gainst the number that fled with them. Isaac. And do I feel no more? Where are the sighs The groans, the tears! that sorrow's winter pours On frozen hearts? Oh, then our earth is sick, When seasons from their wonted liv'ry change, And winter frowns most gloomy in its stillness. During the Jew's speech, Robin Hood has listened to Gurth. Robin Hood. An half hour since they fled? How could'st thou waste The tenth part of that time in coming here? Gurth. They bound me, and 'twas long or ere I broke Those bonds. Tuck. My cowl then to a beggar's cap, They're gone to Templestowe. Isaac. At Templestowe—A hapless place for me And for my race—Near those proud walls, Her buried mother sleeps the sleep of death. When shall thy servant rest his weary head Upon death's pillow? Oh, my day has been A long, a weary one! I fain would sleep. Robin Hood. I have it—Prior— The Prior is brought forward. Write thou to thy friend; If in three hours he does not yield the maid, Her honor, too, unscath'd, I'll hang thee up On yonder oak. Tuck. Promotion, brother, mine. Prior. You mean it not. Robin Hood. I swear it, by yon Sun! Prior. Well, then, it must be so. The Prior writes in his Tablets. Robin Hood. You'll bear the scroll to Templestowe; 'tis scarce Two miles from hence; shalt have the Prior's mule To help thy speed. Isaac. God bless thee, Christian! Robin Hood. Up, old man;—beshrew thy woman's heart!— Prior gives the Letter to Robin Hood. Robin Hood. Here; take the scroll; the mule's by yonder elms. Isaac. We soon shall meet again, and then I'll thank thee. (Exit Isaac. Robin Hood. Look to the Prior, Tuck. Tuck. I'll keep him fast: Come, brother, mine. Robin Hood. And bear a sober brain. Tuck. St. Dunstan now! you talk of what I drink, But, never speak of this same wicked thirst That still torments me. Robin Hood. Hie thee hence, mad clerk. Tuck and Foresters go out with the Prior. Robin Hood turns to Gurth, who, during this, has stood with his face in his Cloak. Why, Gurth,—art deaf, or dumb? Gurth. Would I were nothing Or any thing but that I am. I ne'er Can face my master. Robin Hood. All will yet be well; Come, man—a cup makes all things even—come, (Exit Robin Hood, leading out Gurth. SCENE III. —Templestowe—Brian enters, forcing in Rebecca. Brian. I have you in my grasp—no fooling, girl— Curse on these wounds—wither'd the hand that struck me— Your voice is feeble as your cries to help you; We're now in Templestowe, whence all the might Of all your friends, twice doubled, could not force you. Rebecca. Will not a woman's pray'rs, a woman's tears, Persuade thee from thy purpose? Brian. Nay, 'tis thus That I would have thee—dew-drops in thine eyes, Pale fear and blushing anger in thy cheeks, Mingling their colours—'tis the hunter's joy That the prey flies him. Rebecca. Hast thou then no fear Of earth or heaven? Brian. Tush! an idle dream; Thou must be mine. Rebecca. Oh! by thy father's bones! Thy mother's grave!—By thine own dying hour!— Perchance it now is striking!—in his name Who sits above us, seeing though unseen, Renounce thy dreadful purpose—let me go. Brian. I reck not of the future—for the present, 'Tis mine, and I'll enjoy it—foolish girl! My castle burns—I've fought—have bled for thee— A heavy price to pay so light a toy— Therefore, be wise; there's none can rescue you. Rebecca. Yes, one. Brian. Indeed! I would well see that friend. Rebecca. That friend is death. She flies up the Stairs and appears upon the Parapet. Approach not, stir not. Brian. Hold! Rebecca. Stir not—or from these walls that beard the clouds, I'll fling me headlong to the rocks below. Brian. It cannot be such spirit dwells in one So soft! so timid! Rebecca. Trust not thou to that; Despair is bolder than thy boldest thoughts;— And oh! he is with me—he lends me strength To look upon this depth that mocks the eyes; He lends me wings for the dark flight, and thus— Brian. Hold!—Hold!—Rebecca—By the cross I swear No harm shall touch you—look, behold!—I've sworn it. Rebecca. Well, I will trust thee, but if once deceiv'd— Brian. Have I not sworn it? Rebecca. I'd not be the mock Of my too easy faith—but I will trust thee. Brian. Girl! thou hast done what man could never do— Thou'st blench'd this cheek with fear. De Bracy enters. Now? De Bracy. All is lost. Brian. What? De Bracy. The Grand Master comes,—your deadly foe. Brian. This cannot be—He's ill in France. De Bracy. Deceit! A forg'd report, that he might come, as now, Unlook'd for—You well know his bigot zeal, His hatred to the Jews—Rest well assur'd He'll take advantage of our Templar law, That makes it death for any woman, who Shall come within our walls—And 'tis too late To think of her concealment. Rebecca. Now you see The evil of your passion; to yourself It brings defeat—to me, dishonour. The Grand Master enters, with Knights Templars. Grand Master. As I expected—Oh, in happy time I've come amongst you—Templars we in name, But not in deed—Woman, who are thou?—Speak. Rebecca. Rebecca—Daughter to the Jew of York. Grand Master. The witch, the sorc'ress—whose unholy cures Are famous through the land—thy very name Is a foul scandal to a Christian ear. Yet speak thou for thyself. Rebecca. What should I say? You cannot understand me—that I feel— My faith, my sex, my nation, all to you Are witnesses against me: yet be just: If Brian love me, call it not my crime, My mis'ry rather—If I've given health To aching sickness, was't an evil gift? Grand Master. No, but the means were evil. Rebecca. The good end Is oft corrupted by the means that gain it, As death of one may be the life of many; I've not dealt so; the good I've work'd has brought Evil to no one but myself. Grand Master. You hear; She doth confess her cures were at the price Of her immortal soul. Rebecca. I said not so; You know my meaning. Grand Master. Sorc'ress, thou shalt die: Thy witch'ries have condemn'd thee to the stake— But more than this; our Templar law declares, Whatever woman enters any house Devote to Templars, she shall die the death. Rebecca. Not mine own will; force brought me in these walls. Brian. The maid speaks truth; 'twas I compell'd her here. Grand Master. For which good deed thy life should pay the forfeit, But that I think thy heart would mock such pain; Thy punishment shall be this maiden's death; So shall one blow strike both offenders. Rebecca. Hold— Since now the evils of thy cruel law Are bruising to me, let me share the good That law may offer. Grand Master. Aye; indeed! What good Can Christian laws afford thy loathed tribe. Rebecca. I do deny thy charge, and will appear In trial by my champion. Grand Master. Who will be Thy champion? Rebecca. Who that bears The name of man, and doth deserve that name, Will to a woman's innocence deny The peril of his life? There lies my gage. She throws down her glove. Grand Master. De Bracy, give it into Brian's hand; This most concerns him; therefore let him be Our Temple's champion. Brian. I—I lift my hand Against Rebecca. Grand Master. What! dost fear the fight? Wilt have thy honor stain'd—thy spurs pluck'd from thee, Thy good spear broken? Brian. Give, give me the pledge. Rebecca. Where, Ivanhoe—Where art thou now? Will none, None of these numbers champion woman's cause? No—not one. On the wreck alone I stand in infinite despair; no land Is near to hope. Yet while mine eye looks out Upon the endless waste of night, one star, One little star, unfolds its friendly light, And I'm not all alone. The dark clouds rise— Yet the star shines, the only spark of light In nature's darkness—Faith is that star— Clasping her hands and looking to Heaven. Isaac rushes in through the crowd. Isaac. I have thee—hold thee to my heart again! But let me look at thee; art safe? art well? Has no harm touched thee? Is my flouret whole? Unhurt?—Unsoil'd?—Pale, pale, but that is little. Come to my bosom! Sweet e'en to weeping! Oh, my child! my child!— Grand Master. Wonder has held me dumb! What can it be, A Jew should dare so much? Isaac. I had forgot The letter—I do crave your mercy here. He takes off his cap and presents the letter. Grand Master. From thy hand, infidel?—De Bracy Give it to us. Isaac. Bless thee, my Rebecca! A daughter be to thee, as thou hast been Unto thy father! Rebecca. Oh! my father, Oh! Take thy poor travell'd dove unto thy ark; She has been forth upon the wat'ry waste And found no resting place. Grand Master. I've read the scroll; It changes not our judgment; she must die, Unless her champion prove that judgement false. Isaac. Die! wherefore? Heaven! what wrong hath she done To thee, or to thy people? Grand Master. How! dost dare To bandy words with us? Hence! hence! vile Jew! Wake not our wrath. Isaac. Thy wrath! the savage bear Will turn upon the huntsman, when her young Stand in his danger: think ye then the Jew Less hearted than the bear?—Your pardon Knights, My age is weak; take ransom for my child; I was too rash; let money buy her free. Grand Master. Not all the money of thy tribe shall do it. Rebecca. Tarry not, father: fear thee for thy life. Grand Master. Will no one force him hence? Isaac. My life! What is't? Oh, if your thirst must drink up blood, drink mine. Swill, swill to bursting! Dash against the stones This crack'd and aged vessel! When I'm gone I leave no mourner but my daughter here, And it is fit the young should mourn the old; So did I mourn my father; so, her child Should one day mourn for her. Grand Master. I tell thee, Jew, Thy pray'r is fruitless. Rebecca. Stay not my father—Oh, thine aged hand Is all too weak to turn the winged bolt That, wreath'd in fire, bursts thy feeble guard; And, smashing thy young plant, bears to the earth Its bruis'd and broken fragments. Isaac. Be merciful! be just! make not mine age A stranger in the land. I am a poor Infirm, heart-broken, man; although a Jew, No less a man;—your faith denies not that— Take pity on mine age; blow after blow Has rain'd upon this head; sometimes I fear My brain is shaken. Let that pass. Look down— Behold me in the dust! my tears are few; But like these few thin hairs, thus show the more The body's desolation. Youth may weep Its grief away; but age's sorrow burns:— Burns—burns, till that which fed it is consum'd. Rebecca. Stoop not, my father, to these cruel men. Grand Master. Vile jew! thy daughter dies. Isaac. She shall not die. Brian. By Heaven! De Bracy. (aside to him) You are lost If once you speak. Rebecca. My father, tarry not. Isaac. Hear, Heaven! hear—No children have these fiends— I cannot curse them in their children—else, Shed madness on them Moon! And thou, O earth, Let all thy fruits be ashes in their mouths! Thy cooling waters, fire!—wolves—wolves they are; Then let them, like wolves, feed upon each other, The brother on the brother; till, from lack Of living food, they burst their father's tombs And prey upon the bodies that begot them! Grand Master. Shall I be bearded in my place of pow'r? Isaac holding his daughter to his breast, and stretching forth his right hand to Heaven. Isaac. Ye powers of air! Come to my breast—and now send forth your storms; Crush, crush us all to dust! one common tomb! Wind! lightning! thunder! blow! blaze! and strike! END OF ACT IV.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT V. SCENE I. —The Jews' Burying Ground.—Violent Storm.— Isaac discovered sitting on the Grave of his Wife. Isaac. —Awake! awake!— Will nor this wind, nor rain, nor thunder, wake thee? Thou must sleep soundly! would I slept as sound! What light breaks through the clouds? not morn—not morn— 'Twas but the storm-fire—morn is yet far off! Eternity freeze up the stream of time! This moment be the ever! Perish time! Or slumber but a week—a day—an hour— A Clock strikes Four. He will not—no he will not—morn will come! My child will die—I do not think I'm mad— No—no—not mad—But yet my brain's on fire!— 'Tis but the heat of night. (Storm) Does it not rain? I hear the plash upon the leaves! and yet It falls not on my head: the trees too sob, And shudder in the wind, and yet no wind Blows on this burning body. Violent Storm. Enter Miriam. Miriam. Oh! through night I've sought you, uncle: pray you now remove From out the storm: fire, water, thunder, wind, Contend as if for mastery; the earth Is reeling, rocking to its strong foundation; And were in flames, but that the clouds shoot down River on river on its smoking breast. Isaac. I am not mad—no—no—I am not mad. Miriam. I pray you now— Isaac. What—Miriam?—is it you? Go home—go home. Miriam. I only wait for you. Isaac. Sings: “Then Jeptha wept o'er his child, “Oh must my daughter die “For Gileads victory? “My daughter—oh my child— Wherefore should men be fathers? they are curs'd In children's love as in their hate. Storm. Miriam. Come in. Isaac. Sings:— “In the lone wood let me die! “In the lone wood let me lie! “Winter shall my sexton be; “He will shake from some oak tree “Dry leaves, 'stead of dust, on me. Miriam. My dearest uncle! pr'ythee now come in. Isaac. (Pointing to Heaven.) He has not call'd me yet; But he soon will—look!—look!—dost see?—dost see Yon eyeless fellow digging up the earth? 'Tis the bald sexton Death—he works for me: Ha! ha! hark how his dry bones rattle in the toil! He stops.—Art tir'd? or is it deep enough? To it again—He shakes at me his glass; The sands are few—they run like mill- streams—look, He comes—most horrible—so near! Keep off— Stretch not thy bony gripe to me—I'll fly— Fly to earth's centre! open—open—open earth— Tis thy son calls thee—open—let me in— Save me from death—he clutches me! too late! Darkness and winter— He shudders and falls. Miriam. Dearest uncle!—Help! Help or he dies—Is no one near? help!—help! What can I do to aid him? Help—oh help. The sun breaks partially through the clouds.—Robin Hood, Tuck, Scarlet, and Foresters, enter. Miriam. He opes his eyes—dear uncle! joy! Isaac. Who is it calls me? Daughter is it you? The sun peeps through my curtains. Is it late? What, Miriam, strangers—there was something here— Some heavy cause of grief my child!—'tis gone! Gone! gone!—all's blank. Robin Hood. The wrath of heaven sure Is on the Jew: or else there could not be Such misery to man. Isaac. Still not a word. Anon, I shall remember. Miriam. Dear Sir. Isaac. Hush! I shall remember. Oh! these waters roar So fiercely in mine ear—King Jeptha—aye— I stood before his throne—The Templar Knights— I cannot—no, I cannot. Robin Hood. Poor old man, I need must pity thee. Miriam. Alas—alas! The bell tolls for Rebecca. Isaac. That bell—stay—stay—my brain! The bell tolls again—Isaac Shrieks. I know all now! Too well—too well, my daughter! Oh, my child! Miriam. He weeps, and sense returns. Robin Hood. Come, look up man! Here's good hope yet. Isaac. Hope! lead me to the place Where, where my daughter—dies. Robin Hood. 'Twere best, my girl, You did to his desire; I shall be there. Miriam. Come, dearest uncle, lean on me. Isaac. Thou'rt kind— I love thee well; but thou art not my child! I'll walk alone. (Exit Isaac. Robin Hood. How's this? Miriam. His daughter dies— Lest some brave Knight against the Templar prove Her innocence in arms. Robin Hood. Fine faith is theirs! A holy crew, these Templars! By St. George! Speed, Scarlet, to young Ivanhoe! Declare What you have heard. (Exit Scarlet. Miriam, 'twere best you look'd To the old man; his grief is wild, And may offend his life. Miriam. Ye kind pow'rs above, Support my weakness in this trying hour. (Exit Miriam. Robin Hood. And now as Richard bid For Templestowe, that if these Templars dare To beard our royal lion, our near aid May swell his scanty numbers. Tuck. He'll need all: The time was short for gathering, Robin Hood. Spy thou The vantage of the time; see all—say nought. Keep the door lockt, but throw the windows up, Tuck. Go to,—I'll shoe my tongue with list; go to— I will be silent as a mill on Sunday, An unwound clock, an organ lacking wind, Or as a woman's tongue. Robin Hood. A woman's tongue? Tuck. Aye, marry—when she's fast asleep. (Exit Tuck. Robin Hood. Now, then; tough hearts, tough bow, and limber strings. (Exeunt Robin Hood and Foresters. SCENE II. —A Room in Templestowe; a few closing chords of the Harp are heard from an inner Chamber as Brian enters. Brian. How sadly sweet! it drops like odours! 'tis Passion's own tongue, and speaks not to the ear, But to the heart. She must—she shall be mine! Rebecca, thou sad maid, come forth! She comes— Her eyes weigh'd down by tears—as morning dews Sit heavy on the tulip's golden round, And stoop its burthen'd tenderness to earth. Rebecca enters. Rebecca. Thou here? Brian. Thy friend is here. Rebecca. Friends! they, alas! Are birds that sing but to the summer. Brian. Tush! Tush! take me in my meaning. Rebecca. Well. Brian. Be mine And I will save thee—save thee from a death, Worse than the worst of thoughts. Rebecca. To live a life Worse than the worst of deaths. Brian. Be wise in time; You'll hardly find a champion. Say you do; My arm is strong—the chance uncertain; pause,— I ask thy heart—will buy it at the price Of fame and name, so dearly do I love thee. Rebecca. Aye, as bees love the violets of the spring. To rifle their best fragrance and desert them. Brian. Be wise, I say; Death, in his fairest fom, When sleep hangs on his temples, and his hand Flings round him poppies, yet's a thing of fear. But when he comes, as he will come to thee, With burning fingers plucking out thine eyes. Oh! bethink thee well; can'st thou bear this? Rebecca. He who lays on the load, Will lend me strength for its endurance. Brian. Fond And peevish girl, I do but ask thy love; Which, given to thy lover, makes him rich And leaves not thee the poorer. Rebecca. Aye! indeed! Is not a maiden poorer in the loss Of maiden fame? I thought, that honor was To woman what sun is to the day; Without which, all its beauties are unseen,— Its roses looking nettles:—gone her fame, Woman is poorer than a beggars' alms. Brian. Fame, 'tis a dream! Oh leave this wintry land, And hearts as wintry; fly to the rich east; The quick-wing'd hours shall be our handmaids, each With a young pleasure, partner of his dance, Shall beat the greensward with her silver feet, Like moon-beams dancing on a summer brook; Odours shall gem their locks, which each quick step Shall shake on us in showers, as morning's breath Shakes dew drops from the myrtle. Rebecca is going; he takes her hand. Brian. How, would you leave me? Rebecca. Sir, this speech! but no, Let me be still myself, though his rude tongue Is drunk with license. Brian. Is't not better thus, Than doing as our sober grey beards do, To sleep upon the sunny bank of life, And dream of happiness. Rebecca. Look down—look down! Upon thy servant. Brian. Oh! deceives not me, I know your sex; ice freezes in your looks, But the warm current flows beneath that ice, As quick as when the bright unfetter'd stream Is sparkling to the Sun. Bell. Rebecca. Hark! hark! the bell! Brian thou art a murderer—Again! Hark! air and earth and water catch the sound, And now by day or night, on flood or land, Whenever time repeats this hour of death, A voice from all the elements at once, Shall shriek it in thine ear as I do now, Brian, thou art a murderer! (Exit. Brian. Hear me;—she is gone! Now by St. Paul—Revenge! I'll be reveng'd! Proud girl—Rebecca! wilt thou not return? But for a moment—Still deaf to my pray'r! So deaf will I be when thy screams affright The vulture wheeling o'er thy head in watch For his burnt offering.—Revenge—Revenge! (Exit. SCENE LAST. A level plain, surrounded on all sides by hills, so as to form an amphitheatre. In the back is a rivulet, over which is a low bridge; on either side of the scene are rude seats, rising one above the other: in the middle is a stake, with chains, surrounded with faggots; near it is a black chair; six Saracen slaves stand about it, four of which bear lighted torches: a crowd assembled below; Tuck in front, watching the people: Gurth enters. Gurth. What! Friar Tuck. Tuck. I answer not to that. Gurth. I cry you mercy; you possess, I know, A wardrobe of good names; and which suits now Will't please you wear? Tuck. Call me Clerk Anselm. Gurth. Good! But what's your bus'ness here? Tuck. My curious friend, That's no part of your bus'ness to inquire. Howbeit, I care not much an if you know; I keep a running reck'ning with St. Dunstan, He scores me up my sins; I score to him, Per contra, all my virtues: now it haps, The balance runs most horribly against me; A round score of wenches kiss'd, as many deer Kill'd in the moonlight, twice so many cups, In twice so many days, beyond full measure. These stand on his page, mine's all white; at best Some lean-gut virtues written there; whereon I deem it wise to join this holy work; The burning of a witch will make all even. A bell tolls: a Knight enters, bearing the great Standard of the Temple, on which is inscribed, “Le Beau Seant.” Six trumpeters precede, sounding a mournful march; Knights preceptors, two and two, pass over to their seats. The Grand Master follows, carrying in his hand the Abacus, and takes an exalted place among them; the Banner, Le Beau Seant, is fixed behind him, and waves over his head. After him Brian de Bois Guilbert enters, De Bracy at his side, followed immediately by a Herald; these three take their places in the lists below; when all the above-mentioned are on the stage, the trumpets cease, and a Hymn with its Chorus is sung by the Neophites, who enter two by two in black vestments; a guard of Warders follow, in the midst of which Rebecca walks, habited in coarse white garments: She is led to the chair by the stake. Tuck and Gurth mix with the crowd. [Neophites.] Chorus. Jubilate Deo! Raise To high heav'n the voice of praise. Jubilate Deo! Hymn. To the altar fire we bring, No sweets of th' Arabian spring, No blood of bulls, nor fruit of trees, But a richer gift than these— Chorus. Jubilate Deo! Hymn. With the heart of love we bring, As a sin burnt-offering, Virgin youth that else would die, Lost to thee eternally. Chorus. Jubilate Deo!—Raise To high heav'n the voice of praise! Jubilate Deo! Grand Master. Our Temple's champion! Brian. Ready to thy hest. Grand Master. Ask then the maid if yet she yield her guilty. Brian goes to Rebecca: Isaac enters, followed by Miriam. Isaac. Mir—Miriam. Miriam. I am here. Isaac. Lend me thine arm. Look thou, and tell me. He pauses, unable to speak. Miriam. What, dear uncle? Isaac. Look:— How does she bear this trial? Does not fear Shake her young limbs? a horrid ghastly fear? Miriam. I dare not look. Isaac. I will—her father will. Brian returns to his place: De Bracy steps forward, and lays Rebecca's glove at the feet of the Grand Master. Grand Master. She doth deny—sound, Herald, for our champion. Herald sounds the trumpet. Grand Master. Again. Herald sounds a second time. Grand Master. Again. Herald sounds a third time. Isaac. Hush, hush! 'tis but the echo's voice, No trumpet answers for the Hebrew—none! All that is human leaves us!—All!—all!—all! Hear me, kind heaven! Hear an old man's pray'r, Who bites the dust in agony—let these grey locks be death, And each an agony! I'll die them all To save my child—or in atonement take These tears—this broken heart, this bloody sweat, Which cold, cold anguish wringeth from by brow, And save my child! Grand Master. No champion comes; but yet My mercy gives thee limit 'till yon clouds Shall dark the sun; Go, to thy father go; Bid farewell to the earth, and all of earth. Rebecca. Thy blessing be upon me. Isaac. Thou image of thy mother!—can it be That ought so sweet should perish—look down, heav'n, See how she lies on this cold wither'd heart, A snow drop on the breast of winter!—Spare My bud of spring, and let these white snows melt, If such thy pleasure, into earth again. Rebecca. A bitter hour it is! but it will pass, As others oft have pass'd, of no less woe; Time will moss o'er my memory, dear father, And the quick hours, trampling o'er my tomb, With constant feet wear out my epitaph. Isaac. Thy calmness ghasts me? Oh, so look the dead! So marble calm! So horribly repos'd. Rebecca. Grief, like the waters of some chilling fount, Whose coldness numbs the light woven flower to stone, Has wrought mysteriously about my heart, And frozen it to ice. Grand Master. No champion comes. Isaac. The dark clouds roll—roll—roll— Be hush'd, ye winds! their edge is on the sun! Burst, fall in show'rs—look, they pause!—Ah! no— They shut out light, and with it shut out life! Why should I live? break, break thou stubborn heart. The Grand Master gives a sign to the Saracens to seize Rebecca. Rebecca. Off, off, tis but a dream! pass—pass away; What strange and ghastly forms—can I not wake, Can I not shut thee out? I'll close mine eyes They'll pass away. Isaac. Rebecca! Grand Master. To the stake! Rebecca. Tis real! oh, forbear! but for a moment. She clasps her Father's arm. Hold me dear father! in thine arms I'll die, Murder me here—I will not shriek, off—off— Father! They'll slay me—save, oh save thy child! Isaac. Stay, hark, a champion comes! I hear the tramp Of horses on the earth! it nears—and hark— A trumpet sounds! De Bracy. The Jew speaks truth— Isaac. Again! Earth, air, and heaven—hark! He comes—he's here. Ivanhoe. A champion to Rebecca, Am I too late? Grand Master. How! Brian. Ivanhoe! Rebecca. Thank heaven. Isaac. The noble youth! a Sampson to our cause! Ivanhoe. Dost license me thy champion?—Speak. Rebecca. I do: Yet no, thy wounds are fresh, thy strength is weak; Better to die than peril thee. Isaac. Behold Thy father's agony—Rebecca!—child! See you this furrow'd brow? Rebecca. I do—I do Accept thee for my champion. Ivanhoe. You have heard She takes me for her champion. Brian. I'll not fight, With one thus half himself; go, get thee heal'd; In fitting time, it may be I will scourge Thy boyish pride. Ivanhoe. Twice beaten, and thus brave! Do battle to thy pledge; or recreant yield. Brian. Dog of a Saxon! arm thee to thy death. Isaac. Most merciful! most mighty one!—Be not His father's sins remember'd in this hour! The Herald retires from the Lists: The Grand Master flings down Rebecca's glove—Brian and Ivanhoe advance. Ivanhoe. Why dost thou droop thy sword? Brian. What light was that Which shot across my face—I am withered—blasted; I've sin'd against earth and heaven—I die— Brian reels: his Squire catches him in his arms and unclasps his Helmet. Isaac. Lo! heaven's wrath, The strong one is struck down! though helm and mail Tremble proud dust! your arms avail ye not, Pow'r clips ye as the air, felt though unseen. The Templars lay down their arms.) Grand Master. Give freedom to the Jewess. Take, old man, Thy daughter at our hands. Isaac. Where is she? An unkind mist is gathering between us; Speak to me let me hear thee. Rebecca. Art thou ill, Dear father? Isaac. Give me thy hand! Rebecca. 'Tis here. Isaac. Where?—Where? Rebecca. You hold it now. Ivanhoe. Fear not my love: 'Tis but the first gush of exceeding joy. Isaac starts from the arms of those who hold him, and gazes for a moment at his Daughter. Isaac. My child, wilt not, wilt not, to these old arms? Rebecca. Oh my dear father! (Falls into his arms.) Isaac. Earth recedes—ah now I feel the presence of another world; The heaven's unclasp their gates of burning light, The seat of immortality's unveil'd Where the great mover beams mid'st angel hosts; A sun 'midst untold stars—'Tis sweet to die. Isaac sinks into the arms of Ivanhoe: Rebecca kneels grasping her father's hand: the Curtain slowly falls to a plaintive melody. THE END.</field>
   </doc>
</add>