<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Hoole, John, 1727-1803</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Hoole, John, 1727-1803</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">hoole john 1727 1803</field>
      <field name="author_text">Hoole, John, 1727-1803</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1800's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V2.0510.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1800</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460181</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Olympiad</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Olympiad</field>
      <field name="title_facet">olympiad</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">olympiad</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Olympiad</field>
      <field name="year_display">1800</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1800</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1800</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460181&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460181&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Hoole, John, 1727-1803&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;hoole john 1727 1803&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Olympiad&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;olympiad&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1800&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1800&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Hoole, John&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1727&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1803&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Olympiad&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for Otridge and Son ; R. Faulder [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1800&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872754-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv20510&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Olympiad&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 143 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted&lt;lb/&gt;Poetry omitted&lt;lb/&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: The olympiad.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Opera.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1767.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Unknown.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE OLYMPIAD.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PERSONS OF THE DRAMA. Clisthenes, King of Sicyon, Father of Aristea. Aristea, in love with Megacles. Argene, a Cretan virgin, in the dress of a shepherdess, under the name of Lycoris, in love with Lycidas. Lycidas, in love with Aristea, and Friend of Megacles. Megacles, in love with Aristea, and Friend of Lycidas. Amyntas, the Governor of Lycidas. Alcander, the Confident of Clisthenes.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Scene lies in the fields of Elis, near the city of Olympia, on the banks of the river Alpheus.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. SCENE I. The woody part of a deep valley, with high trees that grow upon the opposite hills, the branches of the trees meeting overshade the valley that lies between them. Lycidas, Amyntas. Lyc. Amyntas, I am resolv'd—forbear to urge Thy fruitless counsels— Amyn. Hear me, Lycidas; Calm yet a little this tempestuous passion. Lyc. In whom again shall Lycidas confide, If Megacles deceive him? Megacles, Even in the greatest need, deserts his friend. Most wretched he who trusts his future bliss On friendship's doubtful faith! Amyn. Be not too rash In censuring his delay: no little space Divides fair Elis from the Cretan shore Where Megacles resides: must your impatience Give wings to him? Perchance your messenger Might linger on his way: the sea that rolls His tides between, may stay your friend: be calm, He still may come in time. The Olympic games Begin not till the sun has pass'd the noon, And scarce Aurora yet proclaims the dawn. Lyc. Thou know'st that all who hope the victor's prize, Should with the morn appear within the temple, To tell their rank, their country, and their name; And swear at Jove's high altar, not to employ Or fraud or circumvention in the field. Amyn. I know it well. Lyc. Thou know'st that he who comes Too late to execute this solemn rite, Must stand excluded from the glorious trial. See'st thou not how the combatants already Throng to the temple? Hear the rural shouts Of eager multitudes; then say, Amyntas, What have I more to expect? What hopes remain? Amyn. But what is your design? Lyc. Among the train To appear before the altar. Amyn. What besides? Lyc. Prove with the rest my fortune in the field. Amyn. Thou, Lycidas! Lyc. And dost thou think my courage Unequal to the attempt? Amyn. Alas! my prince, Here nought avails the skill in sanguine fields To wield the gleaming falchion; other arms, Far other forms of war must here be tried; Far other arts, the names to us unknown; The dreadful cestus and the ponderous disk; These to your rivals are familiar grown, By frequent exercise; but you, untaught, In the first ardor of unthinking youth, Too late may mourn with them the unequal conflict. Lyc. Had Megacles, expert in arts like these, Arriv'd in time, his valour had supplied The place of Lycidas: but since he's absent, What else remains for me? This day, Amyntas, The Olympic combatants contend not only For olive wreaths, the victor's wonted meed; But Aristea is the bright reward; The royal heir of mighty Clisthenes; The first and loveliest of our Grecian dames, Whose charms have kindled in my breast a flame, That blazes forth even in its infancy. Amyn. What then of Argene? Lyc. These eyes no more Must hope to see her: love no longer lives When hope expires. Amyn. And yet you oft have sworn— Lyc. I know thy purpose, thou would'st here detain me In fruitless converse till the hour is past. Farewell. Amyn. Yet hear me. Lyc. No. Amyn. Behold where comes— Lyc. Who comes, Amyntas? Amyn. Megacles. Lyc. Ha! where? Amyn. Between those trees—no—'tis not Megacles. Lyc. Thou dost but mock me; and indeed, Amyntas, I well deserve it, who could blindly place My hope in Megacles. [going. SCENE II. Enter Megacles. Amyn. Behold him here— Lyc. Ye righteous powers! Mega. My prince! Lyc. My friend! O come, Come to my breast: my hopes again revive. Mega. And is it true that Heaven affords me once The means to show the gratitude I owe you? Lyc. Yes, thou canst give me happiness and life. Mega. Say, how? Lyc. By entering on the Olympic games Beneath my name, and combating for me. Mega. Are you in Elis yet unknown? Lyc. I am. Mega. By this device what would you seek? Lyc. My peace. O Heaven! let us not waste the time—this hour The rival combatants must give their names. Fly to the temple; say thou art Lycidas; If thou delay'st, thy coming here is vain; Go—I will tell thee all at thy return. Mega. With secret pride, my friend, I go The name of Lycidas to wear; That all the much-lov'd name may know, Which ever in my heart I bear. Observing Greece henceforth shall say, Our thoughts, or actions are the same; Our hearts the like affections sway, Nor have we differ'd even in name. [Exit. SCENE III. Lycidas, Amyntas. Lyc. O generous friend! O faithful Megacles! Amyn. It was not thus you spoke of him but now. Lyc. View me at length possess'd of Aristea: Go, dear Amyntas, see that all's prepar'd; I, with my spouse, will ere the close of day Depart from Elis. Amyn. Prince, be not so ready To fancy happiness: you yet have much To fear; your artifice may be discover'd; Or in the trial Megacles may fail. I know he ever has been found victorious; Yet well I know an unforeseen event Sometimes confounds the coward and the brave: Nor virtue always meets the same success. Lyc. Why would'st thou seek to trouble me in vain With thy perpetual doubts? So near the port Would'st thou persuade me still to dread a storm! The man who blindly listens to thy fears, Will doubt of morning light, or evening shade. The steed, approaching to the goal, His eager course impatient speeds; No more obeys the rein's control, The chiding voice no longer heeds. Thus, fill'd with hopes, the exulting breast No dread can know, no counsel hear; But seems of present joy possest, To think that happiness is near. [Exeunt. SCENE IV. A spacious country at the foot of a hill, covered over with pastoral cottages. A bridge across the river Alpheus, composed of trunks of trees. Between the trees, that grow upon the plain, is a prospect of the city of Olympia at a distance. Argene in the dress of a shepherdess, weaving garlands. Chorus of nymphs and shepherds, all busied in pastoral employments. Chorus. Hail! peaceful shades, dear pleasing seat! Hail happy freedom's sure retreat! Arg. No fraud here lurks with foul design Our pleasures to destroy; But constancy and love combine To heighten every joy. Chorus. Hail! peaceful shades, dear pleasing seat! Hail happy freedom's sure retreat! Arg. Here each of little store possest, Content with little lives; Rich in himself, his tranquil breast No poverty perceives. Chorus. Hail! peaceful shades, dear pleasing seat! Hail happy freedom's sure retreat! Arg. Without or guards or strong-built hold, Our peace is here secure; No treasur'd heaps of tempting gold The midnight thief allure. Chorus. Hail! peaceful shades, dear pleasing seat! Hail happy freedom's sure retreat! Arg. Here undisguis'd the simple loves Of nymphs— No more—for Aristea comes [rising, the nymphs and shepherds go out. SCENE V. Enter Aristea attended. Aris. Lycoris, Pursue your harmless pastime. Arg. Dost thou, princess, Return to bless again my poor abode? Aris. O that I could as well avoid myself As I can fly from others! Ah! my friend, Thou little think'st how fatal is this day To Aristea. Arg. Rather say this day Is glorious to you! Of your matchless beauty What ampler proofs can future times receive? To win you all the flower of Greece this day Meet in th' Olympic lists. Aris. He whom alone I wish to find, alas! he is not there. But let us change to some more pleasing theme; Again resume your interrupted tasks. Lycoris sit, and let me hear thee speak: Thou didst begin to tell me all thy fortunes; Pursue the story now; with thy lov'd converse, Assuage awhile my pains; and if thou canst, By telling thy afflictions, soften mine. [they sit. Arg. If aught from me has power to charm your grief, Then are my sufferings not without reward. Already have I told you that my name Is Argene, that Crete beheld me born Of noble blood, that my affections soar'd A higher flight than even my birth could claim. Aris. Thus far I have learn'd. Arg. Hear whence my woes began. On Lycidas, the princely heir of Crete, I fix'd my love, and was again belov'd. Awhile with prudence we conceal'd our flames: Till passion strengthening, as it oft befalls, And prudence growing weak, some watchful eye Perceiv'd at length, and read our mutual glances: The tale to others flew; from tongue to tongue The rumour spreading reach'd the royal ear. The king with anger heard, rebuk'd his son, And sternly bade him never see me more; And thus by opposition but increas'd His wish to see me; so the fanning wind Adds strength to fire; so rivers higher swell, In straiten'd bounds. Impatient with his love The frantic Lycidas resolv'd to fly And bear me thence by force; his whole design To me he sent, the messenger betray'd His trust, and gave the letters to the king. My hapless lover then was close confin'd, And I commanded to a foreign husband To give my hand, which I refus'd to obey. Against me all declar'd; the monarch threaten'd, My friends condemn'd me, and my father oft Urg'd me to accept the nuptials: nothing now Could save me but determin'd flight or death, Of these I chose the first, which prudence seemd'd To point, and nature least recoil'd to follow. Unknown I came to Elis: in these woods I purpos'd to reside, 'midst shepherds here A rural nymph, I now am call'd Lycoris. But in the faithful bosom of Lycoris, I cherish still the heart of Argene. Aris. Indeed I pity thee; but cannot yet Approve thy flight; a virgin and alone To seek a distant country—to forsake— Arg. And should I then have yielded up my hand To Megacles? Aris. To Megacles!—O Heaven! Declare what Megacles was this? Arg. The husband For whom the king design'd me: ought I then To have forgotten— Aris. Know'st thou not his country? Arg. Athens. Aris. What cause had brought him into Crete? Arg. The cause was love; for so himself declar'd. A band of robbers, at his first arrival, Attack'd, and had depriv'd him of his life, But Lycidas by chance came by and sav'd him. Since which they still have liv'd in strictest friendship: This friend of Lycidas, known to the king, Was, as a stranger, by the royal mandate Decreed for me. Aris. But dost thou yet remember His aspect? Arg. Yes, methinks I see him present. Fair were his shining locks, his eyebrows dark, His lips of ruddiest hue, and gently swelling; His looks sedate, and full of tenderness; A frequent smile, a pleasing speech—but princess, Your colour changes—say—what can this mean? Aris. O Heaven! that Megacles whom you describe, Is him I love. Arg. What say'st thou? Aris. O! 'tis true: In secret long he lov'd me; but my father Refus'd my hand to one in Athens born: Nay would not hear or even vouchsafe to see him. He left me in despair, and never since Have I beheld him; but from thee I learn What has befallen him since. Arg. Our fortunes both Are surely wondrous. Aris. Could he now be told That here I am made the prize of victory. Arg. Dispatch some trusty messenger to Crete, To give him notice: thou meantime, procure The games to be delay'd. Aris. Say how, my friend? Arg. Great Clisthenes is Aristea's father; 'Tis he presides, th' elected judge, to rule The solemn rites; he if he will can change— Aris. But, ah! he will not. Arg. Yet, what harm, my princess, Springs from the trial? Aris. Haste then, let us go And find out Clisthenes. [both rising. Arg. Forbear—He's here. SCENE VI. Enter Clisthenes attended. Clis. My daughter, every thing is now prepar'd; The names are gather'd, and the victims slain, The hour of combat fix'd; nor can we longer Defer the games without offending Heaven, The faith of nations, and thy father's honour. Aris. Fond hopes, farewell! [aside. Clis. O! I should give thee cause For pride indeed, did I disclose the rivals That seek to combat for thy sake. Megara Olinthus sends; Clearchus comes from Sparta; From Thebes her Atys; Erylus from Corinth; From Crete's fam'd isle the youthful Lycidas. Arg. Who? Clis. Lycidas, the Cretan monarch's son. Aris. Does he too seek me? Clis. Yes; he comes to prove His fate with others. Arg. Has he then so soon Forgot his once-lov'd Argene? [aside. Clis. My daughter, Let us be gone. Aris. Grant my request, my father, Delay the combat for awhile. Clis. Impossible! But wherefore should'st thou ask it? What can urge This strange desire? Aris. 'Tis ever time enough To barter freedom: marriage to our sex Is but a galling yoke; and sure we suffer Enough of evil in our servile state, Without the nuptial tie. Clis. Such is the language Of womankind; but falsely they complain. No longer murmur that your fate Ungently dooms you to obey; Since even in your subjected state, You rule o'er us with sovereign sway. While we in fortitude transcend, You boast resistless beauty's arms: In vain would feeble man contend; For courage yields to female charms. [Exit. SCENE VII. Argene, Aristea. Arg. And didst thou, princess, hear? Aris. My friend, farewell! I must attend my father: thou who know'st Of my dear Megacles, O if thy heart Be gentle as thy looks, in kind compassion Procure me tidings of the man I love. Ah! seek to know what land detains The object of my care: If still his breast unchang'd remains, If I his converse share. Enquire if e'er he gently sighs At mention of my name; If e'er, when tender passions rise, His lips his thoughts proclaim. [Exit. SCENE VIII. Argene alone. Has then ungrateful Lycidas so soon Forgot his vows? Unhappy Argene! To what have thy offended stars reserv'd thee! Learn, unexperienc'd virgins, learn from me: Behold the practice of deceitful men! Each calls you still his life, his soul, his treasure; Each swears the dear remembrance of your charms Beguiles the day, and wastes the midnight hours: All arts are theirs: they can turn pale and weep, Before your sight seem ready to expire: But heed them not—they are dissemblers all. Amidst a thousand hope not e'er One heart sincere to find; Though each, in presence of the fair, May boast a constant mind. By custom now is grown despis'd The faithful lover's name; And constancy, that once was priz'd, Is made the lover's shame. [Exit. SCENE IX. Lycidas, Megacles meeting. Mega. My Lycidas! Lyc. My friend! Mega. Behold me here— Lyc. Hast thou completed— Mega. Every thing is done. I, in thy stead, have visited the temple, And, in thy place, shall soon begin the trial; Then, ere the signal for the strife is given, Thou may'st disclose the bent of thy design. Lyc. O! should'st thou conquer, all the realm of Love Has not a lover happier than myself. Mega. What mean'st thou? Lyc. To reward the victor's toils A maid is promis'd of transcendent charms, And royal birth: these eyes had scarce beheld her When my heart glow'd, and panted to possess her: But little vers'd in these athletic games— Mega. I understand you—I for you must win her. Lyc. Even so, my friend—demand my life, my kingdom, Whate'er I have, my Megacles, is thine, And all too little to return thy friendship. Mega. There need not, prince, such motives to incite A grateful vassal, and a faithful friend: To thee I owe my life; then hope the best; I trust thou shalt possess thy wish'd-for bride. I come no stranger to the field; ere this My labours have bedew'd the sands of Elis: Nor is the sylvan olive to these brows An unaccustom'd wreath; and never yet This breast was more secure of victory: The thirst of honour, and the warmth of friendship, Add strength to every nerve: I pant with ardor, And seem already in the glorious trial. Methinks I see each rival combatant, Methinks I conquer! From the trampled plain My locks and face with dust are cover'd o'er, And shouts of pleas'd spectators fill my ears. Lyc. O my lov'd friend! O dearest Aristea! Mega. What say'st thou, ha! Lyc. I call by name on her My soul adores. Mega. And nam'st thou Aristea? Lyc. I do. Mega. What Aristea? Lyc. Aristea, Born on Asopus' banks, the only off-spring Of royal Clisthenes. Mega. O Heaven! 'tis she, 'Tis she I love! [aside.]—And must we fight for her? Lyc. For her. Mega. Is this the virgin I must gain you, By conquering here? Lyc. The same. Mega. Is Aristea Your hope, your comfort? Lyc. O! she's all to me. Mega. I feel the stroke of death! [aside. Lyc. Be not surpris'd: When thou shalt see the beauties of that face, Thou wilt perhaps excuse me: Gods themselves, Without a blush, might own a passion there. Mega. Too well I know it. [aside. Lyc. Should'st thou prove victorious, Can there be found one happier than myself? Even Megacles shall triumph in my joy: Wilt thou not sympathize in my delight? Mega. Doubtless. Lyc. And wilt thou not, my friend, esteem The moment blest that gives me Aristea? Mega. Most blest—O Gods! [aside. Lyc. And will not Megacles Grace with his presence these auspicious nuptials? Mega. Distraction! [aside. Lyc. Speak. Mega. I have no will but yours. What unknown misery, what hell is this! [aside. Lyc. How tedious seems the day! Alas! thou know'st not, Or canst not sure believe, that expectation Is death to one who loves, and loves like me. Mega. I know it well. Lyc. Yes, Megacles, even now My thoughts call up futurity: already In fancy I possess my beauteous bride. Mega. This is too much. [aside. Lyc. Methinks I seem— Mega. No more— You've said enough; I own the name of friend, And know the duties which that name imports; Yet think not therefore— Lyc. Why are you displeas'd? In what have I offended? Mega. Inconsiderate! What have I done!—[aside.] This transport springs from zeal To do you service: hither am I come Tir'd with a length of way, the fight draws near, But little time remains for my repose, And of that little you would now deprive me. Lyc. What hinder'd thee before to speak thy thoughts? Mega. Respect restrain'd my tongue. Lyc. Then would'st thou rest? Mega. I would. Lyc. Shall we from hence retire together? Mega. No, Lycidas. Lyc. Then wilt thou still remain Beneath these shades? Mega. I will. Lyc. Shall not thy friend Attend thee here? Mega. O no. [impatiently. Lyc. What can this mean! [aside. Farewell, and may'st thou find thy wish'd repose! Still while you sleep, with pleasing themes May Love inspire your peaceful dreams, And whisper how I'm blest! May yonder stream more silent flow, And every zephyr gentler blow, To sooth my friend to rest. [Exit. SCENE X. Megacles. alone. Ye gracious powers! What tidings have I heard? What unexpected stroke is fallen upon me! Shall she I love become another's right, And I resign her to my rival's arms? But, O! that rival is my dearest friend! How strangely for my torment fate unites Two names so opposite! Yet sure the laws Of friendship never can exact so much; Forgive me, prince, I am a lover too. To ask me to resign my Aristea, Is but to ask my life—And does not then This life belong to Lycidas who sav'd it? Do I not breathe through him? and canst thou doubt, Ungrateful Megacles! Should Aristea E'er know thee thus forgetful of thy friendship, Even she might justly hate thee. Never, never Shall she be witness to this change—the laws Of faith and amity alone I'll hear, Of gratitude and honour. All I dread Is to behold her; let me shun th' encounter; How shall I meet her sight! To think of it, My heart beats quick, cold sweats bedew my face, I tremble,—I am lost!—I cannot bear it. SCENE XI. Enter Aristea. Aris. Stranger. [without seeing his face. Mega. Ha! who is this that breaks upon me? [turning. Aris. O Heaven! [sees Megacles. Mega. O Gods! [sees Aristea. Aris. My Megacles! My life! And is it thee, do I again behold thee! Ye powers! I faint with joy, my tender breast Can scarce support this mighty tide of pleasure. Thou dearest object of my constant wishes, So long bewail'd, so long invok'd in vain! At length thou hear'st thy faithful Aristea; Thou art return'd in a propitious hour; O happy sufferings! O indulgent love! My sighs and tears are amply now repaid. Mega. How cruel is my fate! [aside. Aris. Thou answer'st not, My much lov'd Megacles! Still art thou silent! Why does thy colour change? What mean those looks Confus'd? Why seem thy eyes to shun me thus? Whence is that starting tear? Perhaps, alas! No longer I possess thy love—perhaps— Mega. What say'st thou!—Ever still—know then, I am— I cannot speak—What wretchedness is mine! [aside. Aris. Thou chill'st me to the soul: and know'st thou not That here for me the combatants contend? Mega. I know it well. Aris. And com'st not thou to enter The lists for Aristea's sake? Mega. I do. Aris. Why are you then so sad? Mega. Because—O Gods! What torment equals mine! Aris. I understand thee: Some envious tongue has made thee doubt my truth: If this afflict thee, thou art indeed unjust; For never, Megacles, since last we parted, Have I even sinn'd in thought against my love. Thy voice has seem'd for ever in my ears; My lips have dwelt for ever on thy name; My heart retain'd thy image: never yet I've felt a second flame: thy Aristea— Mega. Enough—I know it well— Aris. Thy Aristea, Shall sooner die than for a single moment Forego her plighted faith. Mega. Distracting thought! [aside. Aris. But look upon me—speak— Mega. What can I say? SCENE XII. Enter Alcander in haste. Alc. My lord, dispatch, if here you come to fight; The signal's given, that to the glorious trial Invites the combatants. [Exit. SCENE XIII. Megacles, Aristea. Mega. Assist me Gods! Farewell, my love! Aris. And wilt thou leave me thus? Yet go—return my husband; I forgive thee. Mega. Such happiness is not reserv'd for me. [going. Aris. Hear me, dost thou still love me? Mega. More than life. Aris. Dost thou believe me true? Mega. Thy truth I think Unsullied as thy beauty. Aris. Go'st thou not To conquer, and to win me? Mega. I would hope it. Aris. And dost thou still possess thy wonted valour? Mega. I trust, I do. Aris. And thou wilt gain the prize? Mega. I hope for victory. Aris. Then am not I, Dear Megacles, thy spouse? Mega. My life, adieu. In thy future happy days, Think on him who lov'd so well. Aris. Tell me what thy grief can raise, Tell me, love, thy consort tell. Mega. Cease, cease, thou idol of my heart. Aris. Speak, Megacles, thy thoughts disclose. [Mega.] Alas! by speaking you impart [Aris.] Alas! by silence you impart Both. New troubles that increase my woes. Aris. While thus I see my lover mourn, In vain the cause I seek. Mega. With jealousy, I rage, I burn, Yet, ah! I dare not speak. Both. What hearts could e'er before sustain Such fatal grief, such cruel pain! [Exeunt severally. END OF THE FIRST ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. SCENE I. Aristea, Argene. Arg. No tidings of the combat yet arriv'd? Aris. No, beauteous Argene: the law is hard That suffers not our sex to be spectators. Arg. Alas! 'twere greater pain, perhaps, to see The man we love expos'd in such a conflict, Nor have it in our power to give him succour, Yet to be present— Aris. I methinks am present Though absent far: even now my labouring mind Forms things that are not. Could'st thou see this heart; The combat's here, my friend, here, here it rages More than in yonder field: before my eyes I see the lists, I see my Megacles, The judges and contending combatants! Imagination paints his rivals stronger, His judges partial: doubly in my soul I feel whate'er he feels: the cruel blows, The threats, the insulting shouts—O! were I present, I should but fear the truth; while thus in absence, My anxious thoughts create a thousand dangers, And what is not, and is, alike I fear. Arg. No messenger as yet appears— [looking out. Aris. None yet— O Heaven! Arg. What can this mean? Aris. Alas! I doubt! How my heart trembles! Arg. Whence this mighty tumult? Aris. My fate's decided—See, Alcander comes. Arg. O! haste Alcander, haste to give us comfort; What news? SCENE II. Enter Alcander. Alc. Most fortunate! The king, O princess! Sends me to you the harbinger of joy. And I— Aris. Are the games finish'd? Alc. Yes; they are. Arg. Declare the victor. Alc. I'll relate the whole: Already now the impatient gazing crowd— Aris. All this I ask not. Alc. Let me yet relate— Aris. Say, who has conquer'd? Alc. Lycidas has conquer'd. Aris. Ha! Lycidas! Alc. The same. Arg. The prince of Crete? Alc. Yes, he who lately landed on these shores. Aris. Ill fated Aristea! [aside. Arg. Wretched Argene! [aside. Alc. Most happy princess! What a noble consort Has fate allotted thee! Aris. Alcander, leave us. Alc. The king expects you. Aris. Leave us—I will follow. Alc. He waits your coming in the sacred temple, Where now assembled— Aris. Wherefore go'st thou not? Alc. Is this the recompense my tidings find! [aside.] [Exit. SCENE III. Aristea, Argene. Arg. Ah! tell me, princess, is there under Heaven One, O ye powers! more hopeless than myself? Aris. Yes, Argene, that wretch am I! Arg. O never May love on thee inflict the pangs I feel! Thou know'st not what I've lost; how dear that heart Had cost me, which thou now hast ravish'd from me. Aris. Nor canst thou judge the torments I endure. I grant the sufferings great you prove, You lose the object of your love; But yet may freely vent your grief, And seek from pity some relief: While I, by ruthless Fortune crost, Behold myself and lover lost; Yet cannot, midst my woes, retain The wretched freedom to complain. [Exit. SCENE IV. Enter Amyntas. Arg. [to herself.] And must I neither pity find nor succour? Amyn. Almighty powers! Sure Argene appears In yonder form! Arg. At least revenge, revenge May be procur'd. [going. Amyn. Thou, Argene, in Elis! Why here, and here alone in homely weeds? Arg. Art thou too come to assist the black designs Of thy perfidious prince? The Cretan king Has doubtless to a sage conductor given The care of Lycidas! Behold the fruit Of thy instructions! Glory then, Amyntas, To see thy pains succeed: who seeks at full To know the tiller's care, must mark the soil. Amyn. Already has she heard—[aside.] Not my advice— Arg. Enough—no more—In Heaven there still is justice For all, and may sometimes be found on earth: I will implore it both from men and Gods; My rage shall, like his falsehood, keep no bounds. To Clisthenes, to Greece, to all the world I'll publish he's a traitor: infamy Shall still pursue his steps, that every one May hate, may shun him, and with just abhorrence May point him out to all that know him not. Amyn. These thoughts are sure unworthy Argene. Anger, though just, is yet a treacherous guide. Were I as thee I'd prove more gentle methods. Contrive that he may see thee, speak to him, Recall his promises to his remembrance; 'Tis ever better to regain a lover, Than to subdue a foe. Arg. And dost thou think That e'er Amyntas he'll return to me? Amyn. I hope at least—thou wert his only joy, For thee he languish'd, died for thee; remember, Has he not vow'd a thousand times— Arg. Remember! I for my sorrow recollect it all. What said he not one fatal day? What God did not attest? And can he then, ye powers, betray The faith he once profess'd? For him I every blessing spurn, Yet now he flies my sight; And wilt thou, love, with this return, A constant heart requite? [Exit. SCENE V. Amyntas alone. Unthinking state of youth! when I behold thee Expos'd to every giddy change of love, I find new comfort in the calm of years. 'Tis ever grateful from the shore to view The distant wreck; not that we take delight In other's woe, but that the mind with pleasure Contemplates ills from which ourselves are free. Yet hold—and has not hoary age its storms? Alas! too many; nor is even exempt From dread of others: though the name may change, Folly is folly still; each age is rul'd By love or hate, by anger or desire. We're vessels left to wander wide Amidst a rough and stormy tide; Our furious passions that prevail, Are dangerous winds that swell the sail; Our life's the sea on which we steer, And pleasure is the rock we fear. Though like a wary pilot now Her watchful station Reason keeps; Yet soon the waves may stronger grow, And whirl us headlong o'er the deeps. [Exit. SCENE VI. Clisthenes preceded by Lycidas, Alcander, and Megacles wearing an olive crown. Chorus of wrestlers, Guards and People. Chorus. Than Lycidas a nobler name For fortitude renown'd, Did ne'er along his winding stream Alpheus' shores resound. Chorus. Part I. No hero e'er more bravely stood, In combat hand to hand; No mightier labours e'er bedew'd The fam'd Olympic sand. Chorus. Part II. Minerva's arts are his in fight, The wings of Love in speed; Not Phœbus' or Alcides' might Can Lycidas exceed. Chorus. Such worth, such valorous deeds display'd, For ages shall endure: No time with dark oblivion's shade Such honours shall obscure. Clis. Brave youth! who 'midst thy glory still retain'st Thy graceful modesty; permit me now To press thee thus with fondness to my bosom. O happy king of Crete! who could give birth To such a son as thee! O had I still Preserv'd my son Philinthus, he perhaps Had been like this—[to Alcander.] Alcander thou remember'st With what affliction I consign'd him to thee; But yet— Alc. It now avails not to revive Misfortunes past. Clis. 'Tis true—My Aristea [to Megacles. Shall recompense thy worth: if Clisthenes Has aught besides to give, demand it freely: Thou canst not ask what I'd refuse to grant. Mega. Be firm, my heart!—[aside.] My lord, I am a son, And have a tender father; every pleasure I share not with him loses half its value: I would be first to bear the tidings to him Of all that has befallen me; I would ask The sanction of his will for my espousals; And in his presence give my hand in Crete To Aristea. Clis. Thy desire is just. Mega. With your permission I will now depart: But, in my stead, I leave this friend behind The guardian and conductor of my bride. [presenting Lycidas. Clis. What can those features mean? While I behold them. A strange emotion runs through every vein! [aside. Declare, what youth is this. Mega. His name's Egysthus; His country Crete; he to the royal blood Is near allied; but friendship more than blood Unites our souls; so equal are our thoughts, In every grief or joy alike we share, And naming Lycidas you name Egysthus. Lyc. Ingenious friendship! [aside. Clis. Let Egysthus then Conduct thy spouse: but surely Lycidas Will not depart without one interview. Mega. O no—this meeting must be dreadful to me, For parting would be death: I feel already The pangs of suffering— Clis. Aristea's here. Mega. Unhappy me! [aside. SCENE VII. Enter Aristea. Aris. To these detested nuptials I come, even as a victim to the altar. [aside. Lyc. Those heavenly charms will soon be mine for ever! [aside. Clis. Draw near, my daughter: look, behold thy husband. [presenting Megacles. Mega. Ah! were it so! [aside. Aris. My husband! [sees Megacles. Clis. Yes; confess A fairer tie was never form'd by Heaven. Aris. If Lycidas has conquer'd, can my love— My father's sure deceiv'd. [aside. Lyc. She thinks her husband Is Lycidas, and hence her trouble springs. [aside. Aris. Is this the victor, father? Clis. Canst thou ask it? Dost thou not know him by his looks? His face Besmear'd with dust, bedew'd with honour'd toils? That leafy wreath, the glorious ornament Of him who triumphs? Aris. Said'st thou not, Alcander— Alc. I said the truth, O princess! Clis. Doubt no longer: Behold the spouse to whom thou art join'd by Heav'n; And never could a father's love obtain A nobler from the indulgent Gods. Aris. O transport! [aside. Mega. O torture! [aside. Lyc. Happy day! [aside. Clis. What! neither speak! Whence is this silence? Mega. Heavens!—What shall I say! Aris. Fain would I speak but— Clis. Well I understand thee, My presence is ungrateful: majesty, The stern demeanour of the king and father, Accords but ill with love. I know how irksome To me were such restraints: remain together, I praise the modesty that keeps you thus In mutual silence. Mega. Still my fate's more wretched! [aside. Clis. I know that Love's a boy, and flies The converse of the grave and wise; Delights in gamesome toys, but fears The rigid frown of hoary years: For distant awe can ne'er agree With frolick mirth and liberty. [Exit. SCENE VIII. Aristea, Megacles, Lycidas. Mega. O whither shall I turn, divided thus Between my friend and love! [aside. Lyc. 'Tis time I now Reveal myself to Aristea. [to Megacles. Mega. Stay— [to him. O Heaven! [aside. Aris. My lord, my husband, from thy wife Conceal thy grief no longer. Mega. Cruel fate! [aside. Lyc. My friend, my love admits no more delay. [to Megacles aside. Aris. Thy silence, dearest Megacles, distracts me. Mega. Yet hold, my heart; complete thy sacrifice: [aside. Vouchsafe, O prince! one moment to retire. [to Lycidas. Lyc. Retire! Say, wherefore— Mega. Go: confide in me. I must disclose the whole to Aristea. Lyc. But may not I be present? Mega. No: this converse Imports far more than thou may'st think— Lyc. 'Tis well; Thou bid'st and I obey: I'll not be far, An instant may recall me—Think, my friend, For what, for whom thou speak'st: if Lycidas Has e'er deserv'd thy gratitude and love, Now prove it; to thy faithful aid I trust My peace, my life. [Exit. SCENE IX. Megacles, Aristea. Mega. O cruel recollection! Aris. At length we are alone, and I may now, Without constraint, give vent to joy; may call thee My hope, my treasure, my delight— Mega. No, princess; Those rapturous names are not for me: reserve them To grace some happier lover. Aris. And is this A time for such discourse? this happy day— But thoughtless as I am thou dost but mock me; I am to blame to be alarm'd. Mega. Alas! Thou hast but too much cause— Aris. Explain thyself. Mega. Hear then; but rouze thy courage, Aristea: Prepare thy soul to give th' extremest proof Of dauntless virtue. Aris. Speak, what would'st thou say? How my heart trembles! Mega. Hast thou not declar'd A thousand times, 'twas not my form that won thee, But that sincerity, that grateful mind, That soul of honour which inspir'd my thoughts? Aris. Most true indeed: such didst thou seem to me; As such I know thee yet, as such adore thee. Mega. Should Megacles e'er change from what thou knew'st him, Be false to friendship, perjur'd to the Gods, Forget the benefits conferr'd upon him, And give him death to whom he owes his life; Say, couldst thou love him still? permit him still To woo thee, or receive him for thy husband? Aris. And dost thou think that I can e'er suppose My Megacles so lost to every virtue? Mega. Know then, by fate's decree, that Megacles Must be this wretch if e'er he prove thy husband. Aris. What hast thou said? Mega. Now hear the fatal secret. The prince of Crete, who languish'd for thy charms, Implor'd my pity; 'twas to him I ow'd My life preserv'd: ah! princess, judge thyself, Could I refuse— Aris. And thou hast fought— Mega. For him. Aris. And wilt thou lose me thus? Mega. Yes, to maintain Myself still worthy of thee. Aris. Must I then— Mega. Thou must complete my work: O Aristea! Confirm the dictates of a grateful heart. Yes, generous maid, let Lycidas henceforth Be what till now thy Megacles has been; To him transfer thy love: my friend deserves This happiness: I live within his breast; Nor can I deem thee lost, if he has gain'd thee. Aris. Distracting change! I fall from highest Heaven To deepest Hell—A passion, pure as mine, Deserves a better fate—Alas! without thee Life is not life! Mega. O beauteous Aristea! Do not thou too conspire against my virtue. Already has it cost me dear to form This dreadful resolution: one soft moment Destroys the glorious work. Aris. To leave me thus— Mega. I have resolv'd— Aris. Hast thou resolv'd? And when? Mega. This is the last—How shall I live to speak it? This is the last farewell. Aris. The last!—Ingrate! Assist me, Heaven! my feet begin to fail; Cold damps bedew my face; methinks I feel The freezing hand of death upon my heart. [leans against a tree. Mega. My boasted fortitude decays apace; The longer I remain, the less I find The power to part—Rouze, rouze, my soul!—I go— O! Aristea, live in peace. Aris. What say'st thou? Wilt thou then leave me? Mega. Fate, my Aristea, Demands this separation. Aris. And thou go'st— Mega. Yes, never to return. [going. Aris. Hear me—Ah no!— Say, whither go'st thou? Mega. Far from thee, my love, To breathe in other climes— [going, he stops at the entrance. Aris. O help!—I faint— [falls in a swoon upon a rock. Mega. Unhappy Megacles! what do I see? Her spirits sink with grief; my only joy, [returning. My Aristea, droop not thus: behold Thy Megacles is here—I will not go— Thou shalt be yet—What have I said? Alas! She hears me not: and have ye, cruel stars, More misery for me? No; there rests but this, This only to sustain! Where shall I find A friend to counsel? What must I resolve? To leave her thus were cruel tyranny! But what avails my stay? Shall I espouse her, Deceive the king, betray my friend? O! never: Honour and friendship both forbid the thought: Yet may I not at least defer this parting? Alas! my resolution then must meet A second separation. Cruelty Is mercy now—Farewell, my life! Farewell, My dear lost hope! On thee may Heaven bestow The peace denied to me—[kisses her hand.]—Almighty powers! Preserve your beauteous work, and add to her's The days that I may lose!—What Lycidas! Where art thou, Lycidas? [looking out. SCENE X. Enter Lycidas. Lyc. Has Aristea Been told of all? Mega. She has—Make haste, O prince! Assist thy spouse. [going. Lyc. Ye powers! What do I see? What can this mean! [to Megacles. Mega. Some unforeseen disorder Has overcome her senses. [going. Lyc. Dost thou leave me? Mega. I go—but O! remember Aristea! [to Lycidas. What will she say on her returning sense! Methinks I know it all!—[aside.] Hear, Lycidas! O! should she seek, or ask thee where Thy hapless friend is fled; Return this answer to the fair: My hapless friend is dead. Yet, ah! let not such grief torment The tender mourner's breast: Reply but this: that hence he went, With anguish sore opprest. What deep abyss of woe is mine, From her I love to part! And thus for ever to resign The treasure of my heart! [Exit. SCENE XI. Lycidas, Aristea. Lyc. What labyrinth is this in which I am lost! See Aristea senseless! Megacles Departs afflicted— Aris. O ye powers! [coming to herself. Lyc. But look! Her gentle soul resumes its wonted functions: My love, my princess! once again unclose Those beauteous eyes. Aris. Ah! faithless, faithless husband! [not seeing him. Lyc. Call me not thus; but here receive my hand, A pledge of constancy. [takes her hand. Aris. At least—O Heavens! [sees Lyc. Where, where is Megacles? Lyc. He's gone! Aris. Ingrate! Is he then gone! Had he the heart to leave me In such a cruel state? Lyc. Thy husband's here. Aris. Is then humanity, faith, love, compassion, [rising in a rage. Banish'd from every breast! If swift-wing'd justice Consume not such offenders, why, ye powers! Why are there bolts in Heaven? Lyc. I am all amazement! Say, who has wrong'd thee? Dost thou seek revenge? Speak, speak, my love! Behold thy husband present, Behold thy Lycidas! Aris. O Gods! art thou, Art thou that Lycidas? Fly hence, be gone! Avoid my sight! It is through thee, perfidious, I suffer all this wretchedness! Lyc. What crime Have I, unknown, committed!—I am distracted! Aris. Barbarian! 'tis by thee I'm slain; By thee I from myself am torn: Through thee this anguish I sustain, Through thee forsaken and forlorn! Ne'er hope from me thy peace to find; That treacherous bosom I despise: Thy soul is hateful to my mind; Thy looks are poison to my eyes! [Exit. SCENE XII. Lycidas, enter to him Argene. Lyc. [to himself] And am I this barbarian, this perfidious! Ye powers!—I'll follow her, and know the cause Of this mysterious chiding. Arg. Traitor, stay! Lyc. Ha! do I dream or wake! [sees Argene. Arg. Thou dost not dream; O no! thou seest forsaken Argene; Ungrateful man! behold these features, once Thy sole delight, if midst my past misfortunes A trace remains of what they once have been. Lyc. Whence could she come? In what a luckless hour Am I surpris'd? If still I loiter here I lose my Aristea. [aside.]—[to her.] Beauteous maid! I understand not what thy words import; Some other time thou may'st at better leisure Explain thy meaning. [going. Arg. Hear me, cruel man! [holding him. Lyc. Unhappy me! [aside. Arg. Dost thou not understand me? But well I understand thy perfidy, Thy new affection! All thy frauds I know; And Clisthenes from me shall know them all, To thy confusion. [going. Lyc. O forbear! Yet hear me; [holding her. Be not offended, Argene: forgive This seeming coldness: I remember now My former love, and if thou wilt conceal me, Perhaps—who knows th' event? Arg. And can I suffer A baser insult? Say'st thou then, perhaps— Who knows th' event? Yes, yes, 'tis I am guilty: The motives thou hast urg'd to plead thy pardon, Are doubtless mighty proofs of thy affection. Lyc. Yet hear what I would say. [offers to take her hand. Arg. Leave me, ingrate! I'll hear no more! Lyc. O! Gods! I'm all distraction! Arg. No; the flatterer Hope in vain Essays his soothing power: Revenge alone I seek to gain, And love expect no more. Let peace be banish'd from thy breast, Where treason holds her seat; I'll call myself no more distress'd, But all my pains forget. [Exit. SCENE XIII. Lycidas alone. Was ever fate so cruelly perplex'd? If Argene betrays me, I am lost. I must pursue her yet, and calm her rage; But who, meanwhile, shall pacify the princess? My friend alone—but whither is he gone? I'll seek him; Megacles at least will give me Advice and comfort. [going. SCENE XIV. Enter Amyntas. Amyn. Megacles is dead. Lyc. Say'st thou, Amyntas! Amyn. 'Tis, alas! too true. Lyc. Ha! wherefore!—Say, what impious hand has dar'd Cut short a life so precious? Let me find him, He shall be made a monument of vengeance To all mankind. Amyn. Forbear thy search, and know 'Twas Lycidas that kill'd him. Lyc. Me?—Thou rav'st! Amyn. O would to Heaven I did! wandering but now In search of thee, amid these trees I heard A sudden groan, and hastening tow'rds the sound, Beheld a man who turn'd his sword unsheath'd Against his breast, and stood prepar'd to fall Upon the fatal point: I ran to save him, Held him from death, and snatch'd the weapon from him: But when I saw the face of Megacles, Think how we both remain'd; recovering soon, What madness urges thee to seek thy death? I would have said, but ere I could begin, “Amyntas, I have liv'd enough—” (he cried, And sigh'd full deeply from his inmost heart) “I cannot, will not longer bear the light, “Depriv'd of Aristea; ten long years “I've liv'd for her! 'Tis Lycidas, alas! “Unknowing kills me: yet he wrongs me not; “This life was once his gift, and he resumes it.” Lyc. Alas! my friend—Go on— Amyn. This said he vanish'd Swift as a Parthian shaft. Thou see'st yon' rock, Whose lowering front o'ershades Alpheus' stream: Like lightning thither speeding, from the summit He leap'd, and headlong plung'd amid the flood. In vain I cried for help, the waves receiv'd him, And opening, swift in circling eddies whirl'd, Then sudden clos'd again; the echoing banks Return'd the sound, and he was seen no more. Lyc. What dreadful image rises to my sight! Amyn. O let us seek at least those dear remains That once contain'd such treasure of a soul: 'Tis the last office that afflicted friendship Can pay his memory! [Exit. SCENE XV. Lycidas alone. Alas! Where am I! What has befallen! Must then offended Heaven Shower all its wrath on my devoted head? O Megacles! Where art thou, Megacles! What is this world without thee? Cruel Gods! [raving. Restore to me my friend! 'Twas you who snatch'd him From my embrace, from you I now demand him; If you refuse to give him to my vows, Where'er he is, by force I'll wrest him from you; I fear not all your bolts—I have a soul Can urge my steps to tread the path below, Which Hercules and Theseus trod before. SCENE XVI. Enter Alcander. Alc. What, Lycidas! Lyc. Even from the lowest depth— [not hearing Alcander. Alc. Hear, Lycidas! Lyc. Ha! what art thou whose rashness Breaks in upon my frenzy? Alc. From the king I come a messenger. Lyc. What would the king? Alc. He wills that thou be banish'd far from hence, A shameful exile: should the setting sun Leave thee in Elis, thou'rt condemn'd to die. Lyc. And sends he thus to me? Alc. Learn hence to assume A borrow'd name, to break the bonds of faith, And dally with the majesty of kings. Lyc. Dar'st thou, rash man!— Alc. No more—thus far, O prince! My duty bids me, which I have fulfill'd; The rest remains with thee. [Exit. SCENE XVII. Lycidas alone. Presumptuous man! [draws. This sword shall through thy breast—What have I said? Whom would my rage chastise? 'Tis I am guilty: I am the offender—Let me rather plunge My weapon here—Die, wretched Lycidas! Ha! wherefore dost thou tremble, coward hand, What is't withholds thee?—This indeed is misery: I hate my life, and yet my death affrights me. My heart is torn in pieces! Rage, revenge, Repentance, friendship, tenderness, compassion, Love, shame, all, all distract me: never breast Was rent before with such contending passions! What can this mean? I tremble 'midst my threats! I burn and freeze; I weep even while I rave; I wish for death, yet know not how to die. Methinks the shades of night arise, And blot the lustre of the skies! Around what horrid forms appear! I feel a thousand furies here! Meægras' sanguine torch inspires My bosom with terrific fires! Alecto all her venom drains, And sheds the poison through my veins. [Exit. END OF THE SECOND ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. SCENE I. A double path formed by the ruins of an ancient Hippodrome, in a great part overgrown with ivy, brambles, and other wild plants. Megacles, held by Amyntas, on one side, and on the other, Aristea, held by Argene, unseen of each other. Mega. Leave me, thou seek'st in vain to oppose my purpose. Amyn. O! think my friend! think yet again: believe me Thou may'st not find once more the fisher's hand Whose aid but now preserv'd thee from the stream. Reflect that Heaven is tir'd of succouring them Who tempt too far its goodness. Mega. Impious succour! Inhuman pity! to refuse him death Who lives a dying life! O Heaven!—Amyntas, Leave me. Amyn. O never! Aris. Leave me, Argene. Arg. No, hope it not. Mega. Depriv'd of Aristea, I cannot, ought not longer to survive. Aris. Yes, I will die where Megacles was lost! Amyn. Yet stay. Arg. Yet hear me. Mega. Wherefore should I stay? Aris. What must I hear? Mega. There is no comfort now Remains for me. Aris. I have no hope on earth. Mega. Yet to prolong my life thou striv'st in vain. Aris. To keep me here from means of death, in vain Thou would'st attempt. Amyn. Yet stay. Arg. Yet hear. Aris. O Heaven! Mega. O Gods! [meeting each other in the middle of the stage. Aris. And art thou Megacles! Mega. Ah! princess! Aris. Ungrateful! dost thou hate me, fly me thus, That when I seek for death to unite me to thee, Thou tread'st again the paths of life. Mega. Behold, My dearest Aristea, how I am curs'd! All, all the ways that lead to wish'd-for death, Are barr'd against me. Aris. Say, what pitying hand— SCENE II. Enter Alcander. Alc. O! sacrilegious madness! Impious fury! Aris. What new disasters are there yet in store? Alcander, speak. Alc. This instant has thy father Receiv'd new life. Aris. What dost thou mean? Alc. What mourning, What ruin might have cover'd all the land, Had Heaven preserv'd him not. Aris. Say, how? Alc. Thou know'st By ancient custom that the solemn pomp Of sacrifice concludes this festive day. While Clisthenes, encompass'd by his guards, Drew near the hallow'd temple to complete The sacred rites, whate'er the cause we knew not, Or whence he came, but Lycidas impetuous Oppos'd our way: such dreadful looks till then I ne'er beheld: his right hand grasp'd a sword: His head was bare, and all his garments torn; His locks dishevell'd; from his fiery eyes Darted malignant beams; fierce indignation Flush'd on his cheek still moist with recent tears. Amid the astonish'd guards he forc'd his way, And rushing tow'rds the king—Here end thy life, Furious he cried, and rais'd his impious steel. Aris. O Gods! Alc. The king, with countenance unchang'd, Stood still to wait th' event, fix'd on the youth A look severe, and thus majestic spoke: Rash man, what mean'st thou?—Mark how Heaven protects The lives of kings!—These words at once stopt short The insensate youth; a sudden chillness seiz'd him; His lifted arm refus'd the fatal blow; With awe he own'd offended majesty, Grew pale and trembled, dropt his threatening sword, And from his eyes that glar'd so late with rage, The copious tears gush'd forth. Aris. I breathe again. Arg. O fatal rashness! Amyn. O unthinking youth! Aris. What of my father now? Alc. He has before him The criminal in chains. Amyn. Ah! let us try What means may save him yet. [Exit. SCENE III. Megacles, Aristea, Argene, Alcander. Mega. Tell me, what says Unhappy Lycidas? Alc. To all they ask He nought replies; though doom'd to death, he seems To know it not, or heeds not what befalls him. He weeps, he calls on Megacles, for him Enquires of all, on that dear name his lips Still dwell, as if they knew no other sound. Mega. I can no longer hold: for pity's sake Lead, lead me to my friend. Aris. O unadvis'd! Where would thy rashness tempt thee! Hast thou not Deceiv'd my father? Know'st thou not that thou Art Megacles? To appear before the king, Would ruin thee, and cannot save thy friend. Mega. Yet let me die at least with Lycidas. [going. Aris. Hear me. Believ'st thou not 'tis better far That I should fly to appease my angry father? Mega. I durst not hope so much. Aris. Yes, for thy sake At least I'll try. Mega. O generous Aristea! Grant Heaven that virtuous soul may long reside In thy dear form: I said, when first I saw thee, Thou wert not mortal—go, my love! Aris. Enough; This needs not, one persuasive look from thee Binds me to all that Megacles can ask. In thee I bear so dear a part, By love so firm am thine; That each affection of thy heart, By sympathy is mine. When thou art griev'd, I grieve no less, My joys by thine are known; And every good thou would'st possess, Becomes in wish my own. [Exit. SCENE IV. Megacles, Argene. Mega. Assist, ye mighty Powers! the pitying goodness Of Aristea!—Will her father then Forego his indignation! Justice sure Too strongly claims the offender's punishment: And yet paternal love may conquer all. But should it fail—O Heaven! might I at least Be witness to their converse—Argene At distance I will follow. Arg. No, forbear: Why should thy care for him distress thee thus? Thou see'st the Gods themselves are wearied grown, Then leave him to his fate. Mega. Ha! leave my friend! O no, such baseness never shall be mine! When Heaven assum'd a pleasing face, I follow'd him in smiling skies: Then let me still his footsteps trace, Though round us gathering storms arise. As in the furnace gold refin'd, Casts every dross impure away: So in adversity the mind Of constant friends will faith display. [Exit. SCENE V. Argene alone. Spite of myself I feel compassion for him: Fain would I show my rage; I know full well I have ample cause, but midst my anger still My threatning lips belie my trembling heart. And wilt thou Argene confess this weakness! It shall not be—ungrateful! perjur'd man! I here detest my pity, never more Will I behold that treacherous face! 'tis now The object of my scorn; I would exult To see him punish'd: should he fall before me Wounded to death, I would not shed a tear. SCENE VI. Enter Amyntas. Amyn. Where shall Amyntas fly? Ill-fated day! O Lycidas! Arg. Is then the traitor dead! Amyn. No, but he soon must die. Arg. Believe it not, Amyntas: many with the wicked join, And hence they never fail of help at need. Amyn. Thou art deceiv'd: there is no more to hope. The laws pronounce his death; the people murmur; The priests exclaim: offended majesty Demands his blood: the criminal is nam'd A victim to complete the sacrifice He had profan'd: the public have already Confirm'd his sentence: he must be slain On Jove's high altar; there the offended king Will to the priest present the sacred axe. Arg. Can nought reverse his doom? Amyn. What can reverse it? The youth already is enrob'd with white: I saw him crown'd with flowers—O Heaven!—I saw him Move to the temple: now, perhaps even now, He is arriv'd, and now, O Argene, The consecrated steel may drink his blood! Arg. Alas! unhappy prince! [weeps. Amyn. Why shouldst thou weep When tears are vain? Arg. And comes not Aristea? Amyn. She comes, but nothing has obtain'd; the king Or will not hear, or cannot grant her suit. Arg. And what of Megacles? Amyn. Hapless he's fallen Upon the guards that sought his track: but now I heard him midst his chains demand to die To save his friend; and were himself not guilty He had obtain'd his wish; but never here One criminal can for another bleed. Arg. At least he has procur'd another victim That may and will redeem him: Generous goodness! O glorious fortitude! Can I hear this Without a blush! Are then the bonds of friendship More strong than those of love?—My soul is warm'd To emulate such virtue! let us gain Our share of honour; while the world endures, Let my misfortunes be admir'd and pitied, And none with tearless eyes repeat my name. My bosom glows with unknown fire, I feel the God my soul inspire; No mortal bounds his power restrain. Methinks I see, unmov'd with fear, Cords, axes, wheels, and swords appear, And dreary shades of victims slain! [Exit. SCENE VII. Amyntas alone. Fly! save thyself, Amyntas! on these shores All, all is death and horror—yet, O Heaven! Where shall I go, depriv'd of Lycidas? I who have nurs'd him from his infant years, Bred him from birth obscure to regal honours, Shall I forsake him thus, depart without him? No, to the temple I'll again return; There meet the fury of the offended king: Let Lycidas involve me in his fate, There let me die with grief, but die beside him. Like the poor wretch by tempests thrown To suffer wreck on seas unknown, When 'midst the waves he pants for breath, And struggles with surrounding death: The wreck that bore him, bears no more, The stars are lost he view'd before; Even Hope her seat no longer keeps, But leaves him helpless to the deeps. [Exit. SCENE VIII. An outside view of the temple of Jupiter Olympus, the descent from which is by a magnificent flight of steps. An open place before the temple, with an altar burning in the middle: around is a wood of sacred olive-trees, from which the crowns are made for the victors in the games. Clisthenes descends from the temple preceded by a crowd of people and his guards: Lycidas in white vestments crowned with flowers: Alcander, Chorus of priests, some of whom carry the instruments of sacrifice. Chorus. Eternal Power! in Heaven rever'd, Great Sire of Gods attend! Thy vengeful bolts, by mortals fear'd, Great God of kings suspend! Part Chorus. See mighty Jove! thy wrath to assuage, His blood thy altar stain, Who in a king, with impious rage Thy image durst profane. Chorus. Eternal Power! in Heaven rever'd, Great Sire of Gods attend! Thy vengeful bolts, by mortals fear'd, Great God of kings suspend. Part Chorus. The wretch shall pass the dreary tide From Lethe's silent shore: With him shall all our fears subside; His guilt be heard no more. Chorus. Eternal Power! in Heaven rever'd, Great Sire of Gods attend! Thy vengeful bolts, by mortals fear'd, Great God of kings suspend! Clis. Ill-fated youth! behold thy hapless days Draw to their wretched period: yet may Jove Punish me, if I feel not such compassion, I dare not look on thee: and would to Heaven I could conceal thy crime: but this, my son, This must not be. I am guardian of the throne, To me the dignity unstain'd descends; And I must render it unstain'd to him Who shall succeed me, or must vindicate The rights infring'd. It is the painful duty Of those who reign, sometimes to curb their pity. But if thou wishest aught, except thy life, Speak freely thy desire; and here I swear To see it duly answer'd: yes, my son, Ask what thou wilt, and close thine eyes in peace. Lyc. My father, for these words are from a father And not a king and judge, I hope not, ask not, Desire not pardon; nor would even receive it. Fate with afflictions has so heap'd my days, That life not death I fear. My only wish, Since he still lives, is to behold my friend Before I die: this final grace I beg, Let me embrace him once and die contented. Clis. Thy suit is granted. Guards! let Megacles Be brought before our sight. Alc. You weep, my lord: What new compassion has so far depress'd Your troubled soul? Clis. Alcander, I confess it. I wonder at myself; his looks, his voice Have rais'd a strange convulsion in my frame, That vibrates through my nerves. Midst all my thoughts I seek, but seek in vain to find the cause; Ye righteous Gods what can this tumult mean? Whence can these tender passions rise? This warmth that through my bosom flies, This new, but pleasing pain? Sure pity never could impart Such strong emotions to the heart, That thrill through every vein. SCENE IX. Enter Megacles, guarded. Lyc. Come, great example of unsullied friendship, Come, most belov'd, and dearest Megacles! Mega. Alas! my prince, and do I find thee thus? Lyc. To see thee living makes me bless'd in death. Mega. And what is life to me if I'm denied To pay it for thy safety? Yet thou shalt not Be long before me; no, my Lycidas, Together shall our friendly manes cross The dismal stream. Lyc. O! thou, while fate permitted, The dear companion of my joys and sorrows! Yes, we must part: since then we've reach'd at length This fatal hour, give me thy faithful hand And hear me; 'tis my prayer, my last command. Still live, I charge thee live; and O! my friend, Close with thy pitying hand my dying eyes: Sometimes remember me: return to Crete: There to my father—most unhappy father! All unprepar'd for such a cruel stroke, There soften, while thou tell'st the bitter tale: Comfort, assist his age oppress'd with grief, I recommend him to thee—if he weep, Dry up his tears, and if he ask a son; Thou, in thyself, to him a son restore. Mega. Ah; hold—thy words distract me! Clis. No, Alcander, I can resist no longer: mark those looks, Observe that strict embrace, each tender sigh, Those last adieus confus'd with frequent tears! Unhappy state of frail mortality! Alc. My lord, the hour for sacrifice is past. Clis. 'Tis true—Ye sacred ministers, receive The victim to your charge, and you, ye guards, Divide him from his hapless friend. [the priests and guards part them. Mega. Barbarians! O! from my breast, you rend my bleeding heart. Lyc. Alas! my friend! Mega. My dearest prince! Both. Farewell! [looking on each other at a distance. Chorus. Eternal Power! in Heaven rever'd, Great Sire of Gods attend! Thy vengeful bolts, by mortals fear'd, Great God of kings suspend! [While the Chorus is sung, Lycidas kneels at the altar by the side of the priest. The king receives the consecrated axe from one of the ministers of the temple; and as he is preparing to deliver it to the priest, the foregoing chorus is sung accompanied with solemn music.] Clis. O Sire of Gods and men! Almighty Jove! At whose dread nod, earth, sea and Heaven are mov'd! Thou, with whose power the universe is fill'd, Thou, from whose hand depends the wondrous chain Of causes and events! accept this victim Now sacrific'd to thee; and may it wrest The threatning thunder from thy awful hand! [As Clisthenes is about to deliver the axe to the priest, he is interrupted by the sudden appearance of Argene.] SCENE X. Enter Argene. Arg. Forbear, O king! Forbear ye holy priests! Clis. O rashness unadvis'd! Thou know'st not, nymph, What rites thou hast disturb'd. Arg. I rather come To make them more acceptable to Jove; I bring a guiltless voluntary victim, One who has fortitude enough, and seeks To die for this offender. Clis. Where's the victim? Arg. In me behold it. Mega. Wondrous proof of love! [aside. Lyc. O my confusion! [aside. Clis. Know our law permits not The weaker sex to suffer for the strong. Arg. Yet sure the wife may suffer for her husband: For thus I've heard Alceste in Thessalia Preserv'd Admetus' life; and well I know That her example is become our law. Clis. What art thou then the wife of Lycidas? Arg. He gave his hand, and plighted me his faith. Clis. Lycoris, hearing thee, I've more than caught Thy frenzy: can a kingdom's heir espouse A low-born shepherdess? Arg. I'm not Lycoris, Nor am I lowly born—my name is Argene. The ancient glory of my noble blood Is known in Crete; and Lycidas can tell If e'er he vow'd me love. Clis. Speak, Lycidas. Lyc. 'Tis surely now compassion to be false. [aside. Believe her not. [to Clisthenes. Arg. Ha! canst thou then deny it? Turn thee, ingrate! if me thou wilt not own, Yet see thy gifts; behold this golden chain, Which I from thee receiv'd that hapless day, When thou didst swear to take me for thy bride. Lyc. O 'tis too true! [aside. Arg. Behold him, mighty king. Clis. Guards! take her from our presence. Arg. Hear, my friends! Ye sacred ministers! Eternal Gods! If any Gods are present at these rites, This sacrifice unjust, before ye all I here protest, I swear that I am wife To Lycidas, and I will die for him; Nor shall a power—O princess! haste, assist me, Thy father hears me not. [sees Aristea. SCENE XI. Enter Aristea. Aris. Believe me, sir, She well deserves your pity. [to Clis. Clis. Would you then Reduce me to distraction like yourselves? Speak, but be brief. [to Argene. Arg. Then let these jewels speak While I am silent; do the nymphs of Elis Wear ornaments like these? [gives the chain to Clisthenes. Clis. What do I see! [disturbed. Tell me, Alcander, know'st thou not this chain? Alc. Know it! 'Tis what adorn'd thy helpless son, When to the waves an infant I expos'd him. Clis. Lycidas!—Heavens! through all my frame I tremble! Rise, Lycidas—look here—say, is it true? Had she this gift from thee?— Lyc. And yet for that She must not die—our promise was a secret— It never had effect—the marriage rites Were never solemniz'd. Clis. I ask but this, Was this thy gift? Lyc. It was. Clis. Say, from what hand Didst thou receive it? Lyc. From Amyntas' hand. Clis. And who is that Amyntas? Lyc. One to whom My father gave the charge to form my youth. Clis. Where is he now? Lyc. With me he came from Crete, With me arriv'd at Elis. Clis. Instant seek For that Amyntas. Arg. He himself is here. SCENE XII. Enter Amyntas. Amyn. O Lycidas! [offers to embrace him. Clis. Forbear awhile, and answer, But truly answer, whence thou hadst this chain. Amyn. My lord, 'twas given me by a hand unknown; Since which have twenty-five long years elaps'd. Clis. But where was this? Amyn. Where turbulent Asopus Near Corinth pours his current to the sea. Alc. Sure in that visage I confess the trace Of features seen before: I am not deceiv'd, 'Tis he himself! [aside.]—O mighty king! I am guilty, [kneels. And own my former crime: yet grant me pardon, And I'll disclose the whole. Clis. Rise then, and speak. Alc. I did not, as thou gav'st to me in charge, Expose the infant; vanquish'd by my pity, I gave him to this stranger, who by chance Appear'd before me, hoping he might bear The hapless child to some far distant shore. Clis. Where is that child, Amyntas? What befell him? Amyn. I—Heaven! What mystery must I now reveal! Clis. Ha! art thou pale? Speak, wretch, what didst thou with him? Add not by silence to thy former guilt. Amyn. Thou hast him present—Lycidas is he. Clis. How! Is not Lycidas the prince of Crete? Amyn. That prince an infant died. When I to Crete Again return'd, I gave the afflicted king This child; and to supply the son he lost, By my advice he bred him for his heir. Clis. Gods! 'tis Philinthus, 'tis my son, my son! [embracing him. Aris. Ye powers! Lyc. Am I your son! Clis. Yes; thou wert born A twin with Aristea: Delphos bade me Expose thee, when an infant, to the sea, Threatning in thee the crime of parricide. Lyc. Now I perceive what caus'd my secret horror, When late this hand was rais'd against your life. Clis. Now well I understand the strange emotion I felt before thy presence. Amyn. Happy father! Alc. 'Tis yours this day to render many blest. Clis. Nor do I purpose less. My son shall be The spouse of Argene, and Megacles Of Aristea—but my son Philinthus Is criminal, and stands condemn'd to die. Mega. No more he's guilty since he's found your son. Clis. Has then my blood the mighty privilege Of doing wrong unpunish'd? All come here To shew their fortitude; shall I alone Give proofs of weakness? Never shall the world Thus witness to my shame. Ye ministers! The sacred fire rekindle on the altar; Go, die my son!—I shall not long survive thee. Amyn. O cruel justice! Alc. O inhuman virtue! Mega. My lord, forbear, thou canst not now condemn him; In Sicyon, not Olympia, art thou king: The day is past in which thou didst preside, The criminal must wait the public sentence. Clis. Then hear the public voice; let that decide, I neither ask his life, nor seek to save him. Chorus of Priests and People. The son, though guilty, shall survive Nor by his punishment deprive Of peace a guiltless sire: Let not such horror stain the day, Or unpropitious grief allay The joys our rites require. END OF THE THIRD ACT.</field>
   </doc>
</add>