<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Horne, R. H., (Richard H.), 1802-1884</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Horne, R. H., (Richard H.), 1802-1884</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">horne r h richard h 1802 1884</field>
      <field name="author_text">Horne, R. H., (Richard H.), 1802-1884</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1880's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V3.0085.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">[1881]</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460522</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">John The Baptist, Or, The Valour of The Soul ; In Two Acts</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">John The Baptist, Or, The Valour of The Soul ; In Two Acts</field>
      <field name="title_facet">john the baptist or the valour of the soul</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">john the baptist or the valour of the soul</field>
      <field name="title_text">John The Baptist, Or, The Valour of The Soul ; In Two Acts</field>
      <field name="year_display">[1881]</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1881</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1881</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460522&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460522&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Horne, R. H., (Richard H.), 1802-1884&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;horne r h richard h 1802 1884&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;John The Baptist, Or, The Valour of The Soul ; In Two Acts&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;john the baptist, or the valour of the soul&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;[1881]&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1881&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Horne, R. H., (Richard H.)&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1802&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1884&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;John The Baptist, Or, The Valour of The Soul&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;In Two Acts&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Newman and Co.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;[1881]&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872863-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv30085&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;John The Baptist, Or, The Valour of The Soul&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;In Two Acts&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 66 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted&lt;lb/&gt;Only verse drama included&lt;lb/&gt;Play reproduced elsewhere in English Verse Drama omitted&lt;lb/&gt;The following play has been taken from this source:&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: John the Baptist.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1881.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Unknown.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">JOHN THE BAPTIST; OR, THE VALOUR OF THE SOUL. In Two Acts.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">NOTE. “The early Christian Apologists anathematised the Greek mysteries, but no sooner did Christianity become the faith of the civilised world than—as Mr. Maccoll has pointed out— attempts were made to vivify the faith of the early converts, and enlist new proselytes by means of dramatic representations. Hence sprung up the Mystery and Miracle Plays, and the ‘Moralities,’ which for ages nurtured the piety and instructed the minds of the rude people to whom books could not speak, and in whose ears the sermons of the Churchmen were but the windy ethics of the Schools. Wyckliffe and his followers launched fulminations against them. But Martin Luther, whose robust mind saw in them an effective aid to his propaganda, gave them his sanction, on the ground that ‘such spectacles often do more good and produce more impression than sermons.’ Hence, throughout Sweden and Denmark they were long popular; and even up to the close of the sixteenth and the beginning of the seventeenth centuries, when Elizabeth, James I., and Charles I. often witnessed them, they flourished in England. To this day their influence may be seen in the Cornish acting of ‘St. George and the Dragon’ and ‘Beelzebub.’” Standard, (on the “Ober-Ammergau Play,”) April 15th, 1880.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">“Verily I say unto you, among them that are born of women there hath not risen a greater than John the Baptist.” Matthew xi. 11.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. SCENE I. The Clouds of Heaven. Angels descend upon the earth on a broad green plain of Judæa. Time, night. Chorus of Angels. A new Star of the Night is born— The Night of human grief and gloom— A Star to shine With beams divine Upon man's cradle, course, and tomb. Semi-Chorus the First. He shall baptize with dews of Morn, And streams from rocks and flowering meads; And fill the land with golden corn Where grew gigantic thorns and weeds! A Voice. When old Idolatries become man's scorn, With Vengeful Wrath of early creeds! Semi-Chorus the Second. But soon shall rise another Star, Half-brother of the same rare growth— Each, Leader of the Soul's first war— The Holy Ghost begat them both. Luke i. 13, 15, 18, 19, 24, 25, 26, 41. A Voice. The Peace and Love For which they strove, Mankind shall find in ages far. Chorus. Now sing of John, The earliest one, Wakening the earth To a new birth, For many a hard fight, lost and won! Though his bleeding head For a girl's dance paid;— Sing we a high triumphal song To the Valiant Soul as pure as strong! The bearer of the mighty rod! The first-begotten Son of God! Luke i. 13, 15, 18, 19, 24, 25, 26, 41. SCENE II. The Wilderness, between Bethany and Jericho. A Voice (crying in the Wilderness). “Prepare ye the way of the Lord! Make His paths straight! Every valley shall be filled, And every mountain and hill Shall be brought low; And the crooked made straight, And the rough ways smooth; And all flesh shall see The salvation of God!” Enter John, clothed in ragged skins. John. The dry dust, bare boughs, and the fruitless thorn— The scorching sun, sharp rains and howling winds— Companion this my body; as the wolf, The stork, the pelican, the lonely owl, And silent fox, are cherished savagely. From the same pool or gushing rock we drink, But differing in our food; they eat whate'er Of life they can subdue—oft-times each other— While I in bitter roots find nourishment, And berries, sweet or bitter. But my soul Hath other nutriment in noblest dreams, Visions, and hopes, and inward prophecies, For I walk here companion'd by my God! (John seateth himself upon a ledge of rock.) My father, Zacharias, said of me— “Thou child—the child of my old age, and hers, Thy mother, yea my wife Elizabeth— To whom the Angel Gabriel was sent To make her know and instantly believe The Holy Ghost would fructify her womb, And also glorify her coming child; Thou,” said my father, “art that holy son. Thou shalt be fillèd with the Holy Ghost! Thou shalt be called the Prophet of the Highest; For thou shalt go before the face of God, His ways preparing! Knowledge shalt thou give Unto His people of their sure salvation, By sins remitted through God's tender mercy, Whereby the day-spring from on high hath visited Us in our tears and yearnings—to give light To them that sit in darkness and the shadow Of Death, and guide to ways of peace our feet.” Luke i. 76, etc. Thus spake my aged father unto me, Yea, thus spake Zacharias. I am ready. (John riseth, and taketh his staff.) The day is come— After severe probation and seclusion Of my whole life—when I to Israel Must show myself—the herald of these things! [Exit. SCENE III. Portico of the Palace of Herod, Tetrarch of Galilee. Herod and his queen, Herodias— (richly and immodestly attired)—are now seated at chess. Herodias. And in three moves I win! Herod. If I play ill. Herodias. Play how thou mayest, Lord Tetrarch, I must win. Herod. I do not see it. Herodias. Therefore art thou lost. (The Queen moves.) Herod. Not so! (Herodias laugheth.) Not yet! Ho, slaves! bring wine! (Voice of John the Baptist without.) “Bring judgment!” Enter John. Herodias. This is the wild man from the wilderness! Herod. I have heard much of thee. There have been men Who in thy savage haunts have thronged to hear Thy raving prophecies; but get thee hence, And to thy woods return. Herodias. While yet you may. Herod. Why comest thou here? John. To warn thee of the doom, That, like a beetling cliff, hangs o'er thy head! Herod. What doom? And wherefore? Herodias. Give the wolf some meat; For this he comes; or have him beaten hence. John. One of the Tetrad art thou. Herod. Hence a King. John. Of Galilee: thy brother Philip also— Tetrarch of— Herodias (half rising). Let him speak no more! John. I will Speak more. Thy brother Philip's wife— Herodias. Away! John. Sits at thy side—thy sister and thy wife!— Herodias, thy stone-eyed concubine, Who now would look me dead! But I am sent Thee to admonish of thy sinful life— Thy ruthlessness to the poor—thy lack of justice— Thy many evil deeds! Herod. Thou sent!—Who sent thee? John (pointing upwards). The Most High! He, to whom Tiberius Cæsar Is but a nodding tree-top, and his armies The motley autumn leaves which fall around! [Exit John. Herodias. Thou heard'st!—he did blaspheme Tiberius Cæsar! Bid thy guards follow him!—pluck out his heart— Or slay him with the back ridge of their swords, So shall he have more time to call his God! Herod. Thy passion prompts, and reasonably prompts In thee; but I were best restrain my hand, For many people gather tow'rds this man, Calling him “holy,” one possessed of gifts From preternatural sources. This may be. Herodias (darkly). So. To our game! Herod (pointing to the chess-board). Let all stand still awhile! (Aside.) A Prophet risen from the dead, some say; While others think he never died at all, But was borne upward in a fiery chariot! I'm very ill at ease touching that man. [Exit Herod, followed by guards, slaves, etc. Herodias (rising slowly). The beast-clad savage called me “concubine!” “Stoney-eyed wife and sister!”—he shall find Such stones have secret fires, and secret sight. Go thy ways, “Prophet of the Wilderness!” I will watch over thee with sleepless eyes! End of Act I.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. SCENE I. The Valley of the Jordan. Chorus of People. Behold, he comes!—he whose voice cried For years within the Wilderness, Unquelled by hunger, cold, distress!— Prepare God's way, both straight and wide! Each valley He shall fill— Each mount and hill Shall be brought low; The crooked shall be straight in growth; Rough ridge and row Shall be made smooth; And all flesh shall salvation see In God's Paternity. Enter John. John. I do baptize men only for repentance, Whence comes remission for your previous sins. O, viperous generation! a Voice hath warn'd you To flee from wickedness, which dragon-like Pursues to rend you? Bring forth, therefore, fruits Worthy of true repentance, nor fall back On Abraham and the mist-clad patriarch times— Whose sacred clouds and thunders none may scan— For God is able of these stones to raise Fresh children unto Abraham. Now, behold The axe is laid unto the root; each tree That bringeth not good fruit shall be cut down And cast into the fire. Luke iii. 7, 8, 9, etc. Chorus of People. What shall we do? John. He that two garments hath, let him give one To those who need: he that hath food, do likewise. Chorus of Publicans. We, also, at thy hand Would be baptized with holy dew, In this our hopeful land: Master! what should we do? John. Exact no more than justice doth appoint. Chorus of Soldiers. Master! what shall we do? John. Do violence to no man!—cease your trade In bloody fields: seek ye the loom or plough: Be false to none: content ye with your wage. Full Chorus. Who art thou?—say! For we expect thy promised day, When to all barren fields and sorrowing homes Messiah comes! And art thou he? John. With water I baptize; a mightier one— Albeit my brother, younger by six months Luke i. 36.— Cometh, the dusty latchet of whose shoes I am not worthy to unloose; and He, With fire of life, and with the Holy Ghost, Shall baptize all who are His chosen grain— Casting the chaff away, to burn till lost In ashes and the highway's common dust. SCENE II. The River Jordan. A Grove on one side; a Roman Temple on the other. Enter Herodias from the Temple. Herodias. I have besought the Gods of Rome For aid and vengeance,—and a sign That every towering Form of stone Approved of my design. No smile—and no oracular word— But from the walls there fell a sword! The omen was divine. (Voices from the Grove—Herodias retires within the Temple.) Enter John from the Grove, followed by his Disciples. John. Do honestly; love God, but fear no man. Herod, with all his guards, is of less weight Than one true soul. Fear God, but love Him more; For he whose love is only through his fear, Owns a low piety, worse than a dog Who hath no higher knowledge. Come, my brothers! Enter many People to be Baptized. (John now steps into the waters. Many come to him, in succession.) Chorus of Disciples. Destroying Wrath of ancient days— The terrible God of Moses— Is changing to a pitying love, Surrounded by divine soft rays; While from dark clouds we now can see, Descending slow, a sun-lit dove Whose breast hath tints of roses, That glance and sparkle tremulously! John (baptizing). Pass on your way, my brothers!— Fix not your hopes for ever on this world, But on a higher Kingdom, which is Heaven! The Talmud.— Go on your way rejoicing in the Lord:— Who is a pitying Father to us all:— Do unto others as you would that they Should do unto you: Idem.—in the wilderness Aid those who are lost, and in a shipwreck those Who sink where ye can swim;—but who now cometh? This young man whose divine humility Maketh my rough knees tremble! “One,” he saith, “From Nazareth.” I know who he must be,— Though since our childhood we have never met. Behold, a white bird softly now descendeth, And hovereth over him! This—this is he, My younger brother, grown to man's estate Since we were parted in our infant years, Whom I have seen in visions!—this is he Whose winnowing-fan shall separate the chaff From the sound corn; shall make the poor rejoice, The rich ones sorrow; give his pure heart's blood For sinful men, and teach the trampled people— Earth's slavish lap-dogs for successive kings— Herodias appears in the porch of the Temple, and retires.) The worshippers of gew-gaws in a row— Of necklaces, crowns, bracelets that excite Mad follies—seeing not reality— Of chains and charms, all framed and forged in Hell— Shall teach, I say unto ye, that the shade That followeth on one godly ploughman's heel, Homeward returning from his honest work, Is nobler than the shining devilishness Of all the Cæsars and their Tetrarch mimes! Roman Guards issue from the Temple, and seize John, who is borne away to prison. Several of his Disciples, striving to rescue John, are slain. SCENE III. Bed-chamber of Salome—daughter of Herodias by Philip, Tetrarch of Ituræa, and brother of Herod. (Herodias caressing Salome.) Herodias. Thou hast a Mænad shape, and in the dance 'Twill best be seen. SALOME. But not as for the bath! Herodias. No; for these garments I will substitute This rich transparent veil, and wide-mesh'd nets Enwrought with gold threads and keen-flashing gems. Come—fold thee—thus—or thus? Salome. I fear this dress Will discompose all modesty. Herodias. Think only Of that wherein thou dost surpass all others. Salome. The dance? Herodias. Thou hast, besides, a dazzling beauty— Stinging, withal! Salome. I hope thou dost but jest? I would not sting. Herodias. Thou dost not understand. The music and the lamps will I arrange, So to diffuse rare fancies through the brain Where wine and incense, subtilly devised, Hath bred voluptuous delirium. Salome. But nought of this— Herodias. How say'st thou? Salome. Shall I feel. Herodias. The better will thine innocence and art Make others feel it. Be not led astray By scruples, thoughts, hopes, fears, or vanities— Though, for the last, thy secret tinglings Were not mistimed; but give free scope to grace; Cast back thy beaming hair—thine arms on high Wave, and fling back, and bend thy serpent shape On all sides, thus—t' the music. I shall call thee “Dipsas!” Salome. A burning serpent!—do not so! Herodias (laughing). Or “Seminuda!”—vestal of the Sun! Salome. I do not like these names. Herodias. Well, 'tis no matter. Lord Herod's birthday must we celebrate, As each best can. Salome. But, mother, hast thou not Some further purpose in this dance? Thy face Is wrought with changeful lines and lights? Herodias. I have— But no design that's clear. 'Twere vain romance, Save that the hot breath and the whispering Of a red-crested basilisk charms mine ear With something that may chance—causing great joy and fear! End of Act II.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. SCENE I. Festal Hall in the Palace of King Herod. Herod, Herodias, Lords, Ladies, High Captains, and Chief Estates of Galilee seated at supper. Roman Music. Herodias. Fill the King's cup again! Herod. 'Tis not yet empty! (The King laughs.) Thy joy is like a new and prodigal summer That giveth not due time from flower to fruit, But forceth consummation. Herodias. Then, fill all— To the King's birthday! Herod. Nay, 'twas drank before! Herodias. His future birthdays! Herod. (Laughing) Still, in life's advance! [All drink to the King. Trumpets. Herodias brims Herod's goblet. Music of the psaltery, sackbut, harps, and cymbals. Herodias. Listen!—'tis for a wondrous dancing-girl! Herod. I guess her name—I have heard much of her, As matchless in the dance. It is thy daughter. Herodias. 'Tis Seminuda!—vestal of the sun! Herod (with delight). Let Phœbus part with her a little while! Where is she?—wherefore comes she not? Send for her! Herodias (rising hastily). I—I will go for her! (aside) 'Twere best she came Without me, and my promptings be not seen. [Exit Herodias. Herod. My birthday should be rich as autumn's lap With flowers and fruit. Bring more—bring heaps— And bring, besides, the wine of my first youth! Slaves bring in additional vases with flowers; golden chargers heaped up with fruits; and urns of incense. Dance-music as before. The King falls into a delirium, as the colours of the incense are varied with the movements of the dance-music. Herod. I see a dazzling platform in the sun, Whereon a virgin of the temple dances! Ha! 'tis a vision!—wherefore comes she not? My blood's on fire! where is reality? SCENE II. Bed-chamber of Salome, in a wing of the Palace, as before. Herodias, undressing Salome. Herodias (wildly). Now! now! my shrinking girl! Salome. What would you do? Herodias. Make you a true Terpsichore! Salome. But not Like Greek or Roman statuary? Herodias. No—no! Leave all to me. I understand the King. Salome. But I am now quite naked! Herodias. Take this veil! This flying cloud! Hold out your wrists!—these bracelets! The jewelled anklets now! That's well. Now fold thee I' the lustrous serpent volumes of this scarf. The King is mad for thee!—begone! and dance! (Thrusts Salome out.) Herodias (gasping for breath). Stoney-eyed wife and sister, how is it with thee? And ‘concubine,’ he called me! Very soon Herod will shower rich gifts—he will grant anything To the enchantress. (Dance music heard from the hall.) Ha! the harp and flute! Sackbut and cymbals!—now the tambourine Beats at the heart and spins around the brain! Now I behold my glorious naked one! Yet not all naked—I'm too wise for that— How the witch dances! Ha! ha! Seminuda! She was well named, I know; for madness breeds On expectation—pants for the next moment! That's well! I love the changes of the dance! Oh, it is wondrous beautiful, my girl! My grace—my limbs—my glancing mysteries— My jewelled anklets—rich breasts—showers of hair! Oh, I will kiss my beautiful one all over, And with fond bites of transport cover her! SCENE III. The Festal Hall, as before. Salome dancing, with a tambourine in one hand, and amidst clouds of incense of changeful colours. Herod (in a wild rapture). The priestess of Sol's Temple now hath sent A goddess clad in nought but odorous clouds To madden each delight! No more! no more! Yet cease not—cease not—my brain whirls!—no more! Her flying locks were golden! now they change To gilded black, shot with a lightning blue! Now, all of silver!—tossing flames! and now— Her limbs are roseate, and a sparkling dew Besprays her symmetry, as from the sea Her feet came plashing thro' the bright-edged foam! I say, no more! Oh, I do swear to give thee Whatever thou shalt ask, thou wondrous sprite! Yea, to my kingdom's half—hear it, ye Gods! Ye great Lords, Captains all—all hear the King! [Salome retires amidst clouds of incense, and the clash of cymbals.] First Lord. She could not answer—'tis too high a gift. (Aside) What emeralds!—pearls! Second Lord. (Aside) The King hath lost his wits! Herod. Now breathe soft Lydian flutes with sweet accord Of voice and dulcimer! I'll drink no more, But let the fumes of wine give music shapes. And visions of such forms as now we saw Multiplied, passion-varied, intervolvent limbs! SCENE IV. Marble bath-room, in the Palace. Enter Salome half-fainting. Salome. Why was the King so wrought upon? what spell Can a girl's dance enkindle, thus to madden Into such promises? [She walks up to a mirror, and prepares for the bath.] And swear—methought— Unto the half of's kingdom, he would give me . . . . Herod did swear! What shall I ask of him? Enter Herodias, (with a triumphant air). Herodias. Witch! larks-heel! now will I kiss thy feet, thou wonder! Salome. Have I done so very well? Herodias. Oh, matchless well! Salome. You heard King Herod's promise? Herodias. Yes—yes—yes! Salome. What shall I ask? Herodias (fiercely.) The head of John the Baptist! Salome (in dismay). The head of—Oh, my mother! What, the head Of John!— Herodias. I say his head—brought in a charger! Salome (shuddering). But what to do—with that fast-bleeding gift? Herodias. To roll before the dogs of Galilee! Or toss into the Jordan—for self-baptism! Salome. Oh mother!—Oh, I cannot! Herodias (with passion). But you must! We are not safe while that head holds its place. Think of the insults, barb'd—and poison'd too; Think of his daring threats against King Herod— My husband—thy step-father—of the danger To his rule here in Galilee—his life— My life—nay, all our lives;—and think besides, Of this great moment for a perfect vengeance, Which ne'er may fall again! My will is fix'd. Ask nothing else, but that forthright they bring thee The head of John the Baptist in a charger! Salome (in dismay). How—how shall I find words for this? My mouth Will open without speech! Herodias (furiously). Look in my face! And gather words, like lightning on the wall Whereon a dazzling scrawl writes—‘half a kingdom!’ Salome. But this is of Death's kingdom! Herodias. And life's safety For all of us. Jewels in heaps—but first That mortal ruby! Salome (starting). Oh, you strip all off! I am again unclothed! Herodias. No, no, this veil! Fold thee within its lustrous serpent-volumes! And now return!—begone, I say!—and ask! [Exit Salome.] Herodias (gasping for breath). I, too, lose speech! O, burning tears of joy! Speak for me, scalding fountains of the grove Where Vengeance stalks in hopes to meet the ghost Of him she hath destroyed. [Voices from the hall] Ha! she has asked! [Storm without. Hurricane, followed by heavy hail and rain.] Enter Herod (in great trouble). Herod. What hath thy daughter asked? why hast thou caused her To crave this thing? I do repent mine oath. The fumes of wine are driven o'er towers and fields By sudden gusts of thought. Curs'd be that dance! Jephtha was wrong in keeping his rash vow: 'Twere good he had considered which was worse— To keep it, or to break it;—and 'twas worse To keep it. Many do believe and follow This Prophet John. I have observ'd him well— As a just man, and holy—and have heard Much of his teaching, and have thought it good— Heeding, in some sort, his reproof of us:— Albeit, I would not have that known. Thy mænad Should ask for something else. Herodias (rising solemnly). She shall do so. Herod. What would she have? Herodias. I care not—but I know Thou wilt repent the change. Herod. What should I fear? Herodias. The Gods, by whom you swore. Herod. I will consult the priests. Herodias. And fear besides Great Cæsar's anger. Heard not thine own guards What this man said of all the race of Cæsars!— Of all the Cæsars, and their tetrarch apes— Those were his words. Bethink thee of thy crown— Not half thy kingdom, but the whole of it!— Thy life—and of thy royal oath before Those who sat with thee at thy birthday feast, Who should not deem thy sceptre and thyself A trembling shadow and a mockery! Herod. All this is true. Herodias. Come back with me to the Hall. (Aside) The King turns pale: Check—check—and I shall win. Herod. I am exceeding sorry for mine oath. Mark vi. 17, &amp;c. Herodias (dolefully). And I—and I;—but the Gods heard you swear! And all the lords and captains of the court! [Exeunt. SCENE IV. Dungeon in the Castle of Machærus (west of the Dead Sea), with iron grating for window. John seated on a stone slab. John. Nights creep on nights, and here they hold my life Pending the pleasure of the wicked queen— The incestuous spouse of Herod! Yet do I hear, Through these black walls, of gracious miracles done By my exalted brother. As for me, No miracles I wrought, for I was only A Voice from Heaven, that cried to evil doers Repent!—repent! But he who crieth now Will long be heard, when John hath passed away. I was appointed to a certain work, And some of it is done. Much—much remains, But not for me: a greater hand must do it. Last night there came an incoherent storm Of bursting clouds: a more enduring tempest Will shake the earth and all its palaces, When he whose footway I have heralded Shall be enthronèd on the hearts of men! John's Disciples appear outside the iron grating. First Disciple. Master, they come to kill thee! Second Disciple. Full of wine, On his last birthday feast—and for a dance— The King unto Herodias' daughter swore To give what e'er she asked. Third Disciple. She ask'd thy head! John. From day to day have I consider'd death, And should have done so thro' the solemn night But that I slept too well, and that, moreover, I dreamt of him who cometh after me, To carry on my work, and do his own— Far more expanding. He is of sweet discourse, And winning gentleness, and hath indeed A wary wisdom that shall serve more ends Than my too rugged nature. Mark ye, how By haste and rashness I have wasted power, Which else had lasted longer for more good. I glory in my martyrdom, but lament It comes thus prematurely by my fault. I pray your pardon. Follow Jesus, then, When I am dead, I charge ye all, my sons— My friends—my brothers—and God's blessing 'tend ye! [Sound of iron bolts withdrawn, and outer doors opening.] Chorus of Disciples. The Son of God—yet son of man— Fulfils the mission of his span, First Martyr of salvation's plan, The Valiant Soul who led the way O'er old Idolatries and Hebrew Wrath, Into the true Paternal path, Where shines the loving day. O, coming day! O men of future years! Give John your heart's exalting tears Through which the Light of Lights will smile in every ray! Enter Executioner with an axe, attended by a Captain of the Guard, and four guards with bull's-hide thongs. [A black Slave stands in the doorway with a large silver charger, in which a momentary reflection of the face of Herodias appears.] Executioner. King Herod sends me to take off thine head! John. Enough: thine axe doth speak for thee; but wherefore These men with thongs? Executioner. To bind thee. John. 'Tis not needful. Executioner. Had I not brought them, would'st thou as a lamb Submit to death? John. Perhaps thou hast done wisely. The end being sure, thou savest me a low contest. The strength of the great wilderness is in me— These bones, thews, inward spirit—and I doubt not, If that I would resist, this earth would groan With several trunks beside me. 'Tis the forest That speaks within me. Heed it not. Executioner. Would'st send A message to the King? John. He is more weak Than cruel. 'Twere of no avail. Executioner. Would'st pray? Short time hast thou for prayers. John. I want no time: My life has been one constant prayer. I am ready. [At a sign from the Captain of the Guard, two guards thrust aside a barrier, showing an opening into a smaller and darker dungeon.] Captain of the Guard. (pointing). Behold the block that waits you! John (calmly). I salute it As a new friend, but will not bow to it. [John enters the inner dungeon. The Executioner and two guards enter; followed by the Slave bearing the silver charger.] The Voices of John and the Executioner are heard from within. Voice of the Executioner. Kneel! bow thine head! Voice of John. No. That will I not do; But thus arm-folded die. Now, draw thy sword! Voice of Executioner. This axe were speedier. Voice of John. Think not John will feel Thy blows. His soul is too completely armed, Fill'd, and uplifted! Why dost thou so slowly Draw forth thy sword? Voice of Executioner. Behold, 'tis drawn—but pray thee! Turn from me those bright pitying eyes—or else— Voice of John. I will look upward, then! I thank thee, friend. Mine eyes the Kingdom seek whereto my spirit Now beats her pinions for a sudden flight! Uplift thy blade!—higher—more steadily— Voice of Executioner. 'Tis high enough—but bend thy body forward! Voice of John. Strike!—strike again! My feet are still on earth— Now—now I spring and poise! O, God of Israel! [At the third blow John's head is heard to fall.] Re-enter Executioner and guards, from the inner dungeon, and then the Slave bearing John's head in the charger. They pass through the first dungeon, and Exeunt. SCENE V. Exterior of the Castle of Machærus. Morning twilight breaking upon the outer bars of the dungeon wall. The Disciples of John are standing in front of the dungeon bars. Chorus. O, Master! whom we first did seek Amidst the forests and the streams, The desert sands, the stony peak— A Prophet fed by heavenly dreams, And clothed by faith in future beams!— We follow'd thee, like moons that turn Around a planet, and receive The orbit course wherein they live,— Pure fire in each transparent urn, That glorifies yet doth not burn. Sub-Chorus, the 1st. Erewhile men saw a naked sprite— A sepulchre's phantasmal gleam— A dancing meteor of the night— Make a King's brain with fancies teem, 'Midst drunken passions of delight. Sub-Chorus the 2nd. And see! in yonder feasting hall— O see! a streaming charger borne! Upon it, a divine man's head, A tyrant's conscience to appal, And haunt with pale smile his incestuous bed! Mark vi. 14, 15, 16. Sub-Chorus, the 3rd. The prickly-pear's bush clumps the shore; Rich carmine movements fill its breast;— The mastic, cypress, sycamore, Have inward currents without rest: The shell-fish close-lock'd, graved in sand, Beneath the wave knows sea from land, While in deep darkness tremulous;— But nothing moves in John's dark house! Sub-Chorus, the 2nd. Ah, now unto the tomb Bear the dear headless form! Cover it with earth—with tears— With tears that feel like blood; With thoughtful prayers, and dreams— Which should be joyful dreams Wherein we are not parted From him, our martyr'd saint full-hearted. Sub-Chorus, the 3rd. O hour of blissful woe! O, Death! O, Life beyond! Chorus. Brothers! our Master's last command obey! Seek we the holy man from Nazareth, Who must depart—make sail from Galilee. Him let us follow now through life and death! Brothers, away! Hark to a mournful voice as from the sea! The morning twilight gleams— The night-shades flee! [The Chorus dies away into distant echoes and whisperings.]</field>
   </doc>
</add>