<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Oxford University Press</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Oxford University Press</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">oxford university press</field>
      <field name="author_text">Oxford University Press</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1970's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V1.0924.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1974</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:459554</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Temptation ; the Woman Taken in Adultery ; -the Butchers [Chester</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Temptation ; the Woman Taken in Adultery ; -the Butchers [Chester</field>
      <field name="title_facet">temptation the woman taken in adultery</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">temptation the woman taken in adultery</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Temptation ; the Woman Taken in Adultery ; -the Butchers [Chester</field>
      <field name="year_display">1974</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1974</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1974</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459554&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459554&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Temptation ; the Woman Taken in Adultery ; -the Butchers [Chester&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;temptation the woman taken in adultery&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1974&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1974&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Temptation ; the Woman Taken in Adultery&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;-the Butchers [Chester]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;New York, Toronto&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Oxford University Press&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1974&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3873703-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv10924&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 20th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;20th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Temptation ; the Woman Taken in Adultery&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;-the Butchers [Chester]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 24 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Medieval verse drama.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries, introductory and editorial matter omitted&lt;lb/&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Copyright (c) 1974 Early English Text Society. This text may not be reproduced, except for fair dealing purposes, without the express permission of Chadwyck-Healey and the copyright holder.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: The temptation (Chester).</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: English mystery and miracle plays.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1475 ?</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 1377–1382 ?&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Square brackets represent sections of text which have been deleted or added at different stages in the evolution of the manuscript.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE BOWCHERS PLAYE Incipit Pagina Duodecima qualiter Jhesus ductus est in desertum a Spiritu. Incipiat Diabolus.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DIABOLUS Nowe by my soverayntie I sweare and principallitye that I beare in hell-pine, when I am theare, a gamon I will assaye. There is a doseberd I would deare that walkes abroad wydewhere. Who is his father I wott neare, the sooth if I should saye. What maister mon ever be this that nowe in world commen is? His mother I wott did never amisse, and that now mervayles mee. His [father] cannot I find iwys, for all my crafte and my couintise. Hit seemes that heaven all should be his, so stowte a syre is hee. He is man from foote to crowne, and gotten without corruption; so cleane of conversation knewe I non before. All men of him mervayle mone, for as man hee goeth up and downe; but as God with devotion [he has bene honoured yore]. Sythen the world first begane knewe I never such a man borne of a deadlych woman, and hee yet wembles. Amonge sinfull synne dose hee none, and cleaner then ever was anyone; blotles eke of blood and bonne, and wiser then ever man was. Avarice nor any envye in him could I never espie. He hase no gould in tresorye, ne tempted ys by no syght. Pryde hasse he none, ne gluttonye, ne no likinge of lecherye. His mouth hard I never lye neather by day nor night. My heighnes he puttes aye behynd, for in him faulte non can I fynd. If hee be God in mans kinde, my crafte then fully fayles. And more then man I wott hee is, elles somethinge he did amys; save only [hongarye he is], iwis, elles wott I not what him ayles. And this thinge dare I soothly saye: if that hee be God verey honger should greeve him by no waye; that weare agaynst reasoun. Therfore nowe I would assaye with speach of bread him to betraye, for he hasse fast nowe manye a daye; therfore bread were in seasoun. Diabolus dicit: Thou, man, abyde and speake with mee. Goddes Sonne yf that thou be, make of these stones—nowe lett see— bread through thy blessinge. DEUS Sathan, I tell thee sycerly bread man lives not only bye, but through Goddes word verelye of his mouth [cominge]. Therfore thou pynes thee, Sathanas, to suplant mee of my place by meate, as sometyme Adam was, of blys when hee was brought. Disceaved hee was that tyme through thee, but nowe must fayle thy postee; therfore to meeve that thinge to mee yt shall serve thee of nought. Sathan, through thine inticement honger shall nought torne myne intent, for Goddes will omnypotent is my meat withouten fayle, and his word perfect sustenance to mee alwayes without distance; for thou shalt finde no varyance in mee that shall thee avayle. DIABOLUS Owt, alas! What is this? This matter fares all amysse; hongree I see well hee is, as man should kindlye. But through no craft ne no coyntyse I cannot torne his will, iwys; that neede of any bodely blys in him nothinge hasse hee. For hee may suffer all maner of noye as man should, well and stifflye; but aye hee winneth the victorye as godhead in him weare. Some other sleight I mott espye this disobedient for to destroye; for of mee hee hasse the maistrie unhappingely nowe here. Adam, that God himselfe wrought, through my discent in bale I brought; but this syre that I have sought, borne of on woman, for no neede that himselfe hasse, with no counsell in this case to greeve him I may have no grace, for no craft that I can. Yett will I seeke some sutteltie. Come forth, thou Jhesu, come with me to this holy cittie; I have an errande to saye. Verey God if that thou bee nowe I shall full well see, for I shall shape honour for thee or that thou wend awaye. Tunc statuat Jesus super pinnaculum templi, et dicat Diabolus: Say thou nowe that syttes so high: if thou be Goddes Sonne, by sleight come downe, and I will saye in sight thou diddest a fayre maistrye. Thine owne angells mon keepe to thee that thou hurt no foote ne knee. Shewe thy power; now lett see that thou may have maistrye therbye. Jesus dicit ad Diabolum. JESUS Sathan, securlye I thee saye hit is written that thou ne maye tempt God, thy lord, by no waye, what matter soever be ment. Discendens de pinnaculo dicat Diabolus: Alas, that me is woe todaye! This have I fayled of my praye. Was I never rent in such araye ne halfe so foule reprived. Tunc Sathan adducet Jhesum super montem, et dicat Diabolus: Yett, fellowe, if it be thy will, goe we playe us to a hill; another poynte I must fulfill for ought that may befall. Looke abowte thee nowe and see of all this realme the royaltie; for to kneele downe and honour me thou shall be lord of all. JESUS Goe forth, Sathanas, goe forth, goe! It is written and shalbe soe: ‘Thy lord God thou shalt honoure oo and serve him though thee nye.’ DIABOLUS Owt, alas! That me is woe for found I never so great a foe. Though I to threepe be never soe throe, I am overcommen thrye. Alas, my slight nowe am I qwyt. Adam I founded with a fytt, and him in comberans soonne I knyt through contyse of my crafte. Nowe soone of sorrowe he mone be shitt and I punished in hell-pitt. Knewe I never man of such wytt as him that I have [lafte]. Alas, for shame I am shent. With hell-houndes when I am hent I must be ragged and all torent and dryven to the fyre. In sorrowe and woe nowe am I brought, and all my cunninge is sett at nought; endles payne must I have unsought to my reward and hyre. But I am nowe of good intent to hould a court ful diligent, and call my servants verament shortly for to appeare; then to reward with dignitie that all their life have served mee. In burninge blys there shall they bee and sytt with Luciferre. DOCTOUR Loe, lordinges, Godes righteousnes, as Gregorye makes mynd expresse: syns our forfather overcommen was by three thinges to doe evill— gluttonye, vaynglorye, there bine too, covetous of highnes alsoe— by these three poyntes, bowt moe, Christ hasse overcommen the devill. That Adam was tempted in gluttonye I may well prove appertly, when of that fruite falsly the devyll made him to eate. And tempted hee was in vayneglorye when hee height him great maistrie, and have godhead unworthelye through eatinge of that meat. Alsoe hee was tempted in avarice when he height him to be wise, knowe good and evill at his devise more then he was worthye. For covetousnes, Gregorye sayth expresse, sinnes nought greatly in riches but in willinge of highnes and state unskylfullye. Alsoe Christe in these sinnes three was tempted, as yee might well see; for in gluttonye—leeve yee mee— hee moved him sleightely here when he entysed him through his read to torne the stones into bread, and soe to move his godhead which hee was in a weare. In vayneglorye he tempted him alsoe, when hee bade him down to goe the pinnacle of the temple froe an unskilfull gate. And in covetousnes he tempted was when hee shewed him such ryches and height him londes more and lesse, and that through great estate. This overcome thrise in this case the devill, as playd was in this place, of the three sinnes that Adam was of wayle into woe weaved. But Adam fell through his trespas, and Jhesu withstoode him through his grace; for of his godhead soothnes that tyme was cleane disceived. Tunc venient duo Pharasei adducentes mulierem in adulterio deprehensam. Dicat PRIMUS PHARASEUS Maister, I read by God almight that we lead this wretched wight, that was taken thus tonight in fowle advowtrye, before Jhesu in his sight; for so to tempt him I have tyght to wyt whether hee will deeme the right or elles unlawfullye. SECUNDUS PHARASEUS That is good read, fellowe, by my faye. Soe mone we catch him by some waye; for if hee doe hir grace todaye, he dose agaynst the lawe. And if hee byd punish her sore, hee dose agaynst his owne lore that hee hasse preached here before: to mercye mon should drawe. Tunc adducent mulierem inter se coram Jesu, et dicat PRIMUS PHARASEUS Mayster, this woman that is here was wedded lawfully to yeare; but with another then her feare we found her doe amisse. And Moyses lawe byddes us stone all such as binne uncleane. Therfore to thee we can us meane to give a dome of this. Jesus scribens in terra dicat: Nowe which of you everychon is bowt synne, buske him anon and cast at her the first stonne belyve or that ye blynne. PRIMUS PHARASEUS Speake on, maister, and somewhat saye: shall shee be stoned or elles naye; or do her mercye as thou maye, to forgive her this synne? SECUNDUS PHARISEUS Mayster, why art thou so styll? What writest thou, if it be thy will? Whether shall we spare or spill this woman found in blame? What writest thou, maister? Now lett me see. Owt, alas that woe is mee! For no longer dare I here bee, for dread of worldly shame. Et fugiet, et postea dicat Primus Pharaseus: Why fleest thou, fellowe, be thy faye? I will see soone and assaye. Alas, that I weare awaye farre beyonde France! Stond you, Sybble, him besyde. No longer here dare I abyde agayst thee for to chyde, as have I good chance. Et fugiet, et dicat Jesus ad mulierem: Woman, where binne these men eychon that putten this gilt thee upon? To dampne thee nowe there is none of tho that were before. MULIER ADULTERIA Lord, to dampne mee there is non, for all they binne awaye gonne. JESUS Nowe I dampne thee not, woman. Goe forth and synne noe more. MULIER A, lord, blessed most thou be, that of mischeiffe hasse holpen mee. Hethenforth filth I will flee and serve thee in good faye. For godhead full in thee I see that knowes worke that doe wee. I honour thee, kneelinge one my knee, and so will I doe aye. DOCTOR Nowe, lordes, I pray you marke here the great goodness of Godes deede. I will declare, as hit is neede, these thinges that playd were, as Augustine speaketh expressely of hit in his homely upon St. Johns Evangelye; this hee sayes in that case: two wayes the casten him to anoye syns he had preached mych of mercye, and the lawe commandeth expressely sych women for to stone that trespassen in advowtrye. Therfore they hoped witterlye varyans in him to espye— or blenquyshe the lawe cleane. That wyst Jesu full well their thought, and all theire wyttes hee sett at nought— but bade which synne had not wrought cast first at her a stonne; and wrote in claye—leeve yee mee— their owne synnes that they might see, that ichone fayne was to flee, and they lefte hir alonne. For eychon of them had grace to see theire sinnes in that place; yett non of them wiser was, but his synnes eych man knewe. And fayne the were to take the waye lest they had dampned binne that daye. Thus helpe that woman in good faye, our sweete lord Jesu. Finis</field>
   </doc>
</add>