<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Fletcher, John, 1579-1625</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Fletcher, John, 1579-1625</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">fletcher john 1579 1625</field>
      <field name="author_text">Fletcher, John, 1579-1625</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">17th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V1.0162.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1679</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:458921</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Faithful Shepherdess</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 17th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 17th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Faithful Shepherdess</field>
      <field name="title_facet">faithful shepherdess</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">faithful shepherdess</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Faithful Shepherdess</field>
      <field name="year_display">1679</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1679</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1679</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:458921&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:458921&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Fletcher, John, 1579-1625&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;fletcher john 1579 1625&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Faithful Shepherdess&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;faithful shepherdess&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1679&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1679&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Fletcher, John&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1579&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1625&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Faithful Shepherdess&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed by J. Macock, for John Martyn, Henry Herringman, Richard Marriot&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1679&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3871582-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv10162&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 17th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;17th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Faithful Shepherdess&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 200 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted&lt;lb/&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;lb/&gt;Epigraph and commendatory poems included with The Maids Tragedy&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: The faithful shepherdess.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Pastoral.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1609 ?</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 1608–1609.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE Faithful Shepherdess.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Actus primus. Scena prima. Enter Clorin a Shepherdess, having buried her Love in an Arbour. Hail, holy Earth, whose cold Arms do imbrace The truest man that ever fed his flocks By the fat plains of fruitful Thessaly, Thus I salute thy Grave, thus do I pay My early vows, and tribute of mine eyes To thy still loved ashes; thus I free My self from all insuing heats and fires Of love: all sports, delights and jolly games That Shepherds hold full dear, thus put I off. Now no more shall these smooth brows be begirt With youthful Coronals, and lead the Dance; No more the company of fresh fair Maids And wanton Shepherds be to me delightful, Nor the shrill pleasing sound of merry pipes Under some shady dell, when the cool wind Plays on the leaves: all be far away, Since thou art far away; by whose dear side How often have I sat Crown'd with fresh flowers For summers Queen, whil'st every Shepherds Boy Puts on his lusty green, with gaudy hook, And hanging scrip of finest Cordevan. But thou art gone, and these are gone with thee, And all are dead but thy dear memorie; That shall out-live thee, and shall ever spring Whilest there are pipes, or jolly Shepherds sing. And here will I in honour of thy love, Dwell by thy Grave, forgeting all those joys, That former times made precious to mine eyes, Only remembring what my youth did gain In the dark, hidden vertuous use of Herbs: That will I practise, and as freely give All my endeavours, as I gain'd them free. Of all green wounds I know the remedies In Men or Cattel, be they stung with Snakes, Or charm'd with powerful words of wicked Art, Or be they Love-sick, or through too much heat Grown wild or Lunatick, their eyes or ears Thickned with misty filme of dulling Rheum, These I can Cure, such secret vertue lies In Herbs applyed by a Virgins hand: My meat shall be what these wild woods afford, Berries, and Chesnuts, Plantanes, on whose Cheeks, The Sun sits smiling, and the lofty fruit Pull'd from the fair head of the straight grown Pine; On these I'le feed with free content and rest; When night shall blind the world, by thy side blest. Enter a Satyr. Satyr. Through yon same bending plain That flings his arms down to the main, And through these thick woods have I run, Whose bottom never kist the Sun Since the lusty Spring began, All to please my master Pan, Have I trotted without rest To get him Fruit; for at a Feast He entertains this coming night His Paramour, the Syrinx bright: But behold a fairer sight! [He stands amazed. By that Heavenly form of thine, Brightest fair thou art divine, Sprung from great immortal race Of the gods, for in thy face Shines more awful Majesty, Than dull weak mortalitie Dare with misty eyes behold, And live: therefore on this mold Lowly do I bend my knee, In worship of thy Deitie; Deign it Goddess from my hand, To receive what e're this land From her fertil Womb doth send Of her choice Fruits: and but lend Belief to that the Satyre tells, Fairer by the famous wells, To this present day ne're grew, Never better nor more true. Here be Grapes whose lusty bloud Is the learned Poets good, Sweeter yet did never crown The head of Bacchus, Nuts more brown Than the Squirrels Teeth that crack them; Deign O fairest fair to take them. For these black ey'd Driope Hath oftentimes commanded me, With my clasped knee to clime; See how well the lusty time Hath deckt their rising cheeks in red, Such as on your lips is spred, Here be Berries for a Queen, Some be red, some be green, These are of that luscious meat, The great God Pan himself doth eat: All these, and what the woods can yield, The hanging mountain or the field, I freely offer, and ere long Will bring you more, more sweet and strong, Till when humbly leave I take, Lest the great Pan do awake, That sleeping lies in a deep glade, Under a broad Beeches shade, I must go, I must run Swifter than the fiery Sun. [Exit. Clo. And all my fears go with thee. What greatness or what private hidden power, Is there in me to draw submission From this rude man, and beast? sure I am mortal: The Daughter of a Shepherd, he was mortal: And she that bore me mortal: prick my hand And it will bleed: a Feaver shakes me, And the self same wind that makes the young Lambs shrink, Makes me a cold: my fear says I am mortal: Yet I have heard (my Mother told it me). And now I do believe it, if I keep My Virgin Flower uncropt, pure, chaste, and fair, No Goblin, Wood-god, Fairy, Elfe, or Fiend, Satyr or other power that haunts the Groves, Shall hurt my body, or by vain illusion Draw me to wander after idle fires; Or voyces calling me in dead of night, To make me follow, and so tole me on Through mire and standing pools, to find my ruine: Else why should this rough thing, who never knew Manners, nor smooth humanity, whose heats Are rougher than himself, and more mishapen, Thus mildly kneel to me? sure there is a power In that great name of Virgin, that binds fast All rude uncivil bloods, all appetites That break their confines: then strong Chastity, Be thou my strongest guard, for here I'le dwell In opposition against Fate and Hell. Enter an old Shepherd, with him four couple of Shepherds and Shepherdesses. Old Shep. Now we have done this holy Festival In honour of our great God, and his rites Perform'd, prepare your selves for chaste And uncorrupted fires: that as the Priest, With powerful hand shall sprinkle on yours Brows His pure and holy water, ye may be From all hot flames of lust, and loose thoughts free. Kneel Shepherds, kneel, here comes the Priest of Pan. Enter Priest. Priest. Shepherds, thus I purge away, Whatsoever this great day, Or the past hours gave not good, To corrupt your Maiden blood: From the high rebellious heat Of the Grapes, and strength of meat; From the wanton quick desires, They do kindle by their fires, I do wash you with this water, Be you pure and fair hereafter. From your Liver and your Veins, Thus I take away the stains. All your thoughts be smooth and fair, Be ye fresh and free as Air. Never more let lustful heat Through your purged conduits beat, Or a plighted troth be broken, Or a wanton verse be spoken In a Shepherdesses ear; Go your wayes, ye are all clear. [They rise and sing in praise of Pan. [Shepherds.] The SONG. Sing his praises that doth keep Our Flocks from harm, Pan the Father of our Sheep, And arm in arm Tread we softly in a round, Whilest the hollow neighbouring ground Fills the Musick with her sound. Pan, O great God Pan, to thee Thus do we sing. Thou that keep'st us chaste and free As the young spring, Ever be thy honour spoke, From that place the morn is broke, To that place Day doth unyoke. [Exeunt omnes but Perigot and Amoret. Peri. Stay gentle Amoret, thou fair brow'd Maid, Thy Shepherd prays thee stay, that holds thee dear, Equal with his souls good. Amo. Speak; I give Thee freedom Shepherd, and thy tongue be still The same it ever was; as free from ill, As he whose conversation never knew The Court or City be thou ever true. Peri. When I fall off from my affection, Or mingle my clean thoughts with foul desires, First let our great God cease to keep my flocks. That being left alone without a guard, The Wolf, or Winters rage, Summers great heat, And want of Water, Rots; or what to us Of ill is yet unknown, full speedily, And in their general ruine let me feel. Amo. I pray thee gentle Shepherd wish not so, I do believe thee: 'tis as hard for me To think thee false, and harder than for thee To hold me foul. Peri. O you are fairer far Than the chaste blushing morn, or that fair star That guides the wandring Sea men through the deep, Straighter than straightest Pine upon the steep Head of an aged mountain, and more white Than the new Milk we strip before day light From the full fraighted bags of our fair flocks: Your hair more beauteous than those hanging looks Of young Apollo. Amo. Shepherd be not lost, Y'are sail'd too far already from the Coast Of our discourse. Peri. Did you not tell me once I should not love alone, I should not lose Those many passions, vows, and holy Oaths, I've sent to Heaven? did you not give your hand, Even that fair hand in hostage? Do not then Give back again those sweets to other men, You your self vow'd were mine. Amo. Shepherd, so far as Maidens modesty May give assurance, I am once more thine, Once more I give my hand; be ever free From that great foe to faith, foul jealousie. Peri. I take it as my best good, and desire For stronger confirmation of our love, To meet this happy night in that fair Grove, Where all true Shepherds have rewarded been For their long service: say sweet, shall it hold? Amo. Dear friend, you must not blame me if I make A doubt of what the silent night may do, Coupled with this dayes heat to move your bloud: Maids must be fearful; sure you have not been Wash'd white enough; for yet I see a stain Stick in your Liver, go and purge again. Peri. O do not wrong my honest simple truth, My self and my affections are as pure As those chaste flames that burn before the shrine Of the great Dian: only my intent To draw you thither, was to plight our troths, With enterchange of mutual chaste embraces, And ceremonious tying of our selves: For to that holy wood is consecrate A vertuous well, about whose flowry banks, The nimble-footed Fairies dance their rounds, By the pale moon-shine, dipping oftentimes Their stolen Children, so to make them free From dying flesh, and dull mortalitie; By this fair Fount hath many a Shepherd sworn, And given away his freedom, many a troth Been plight, which neither envy, nor old time Could ever break, with many a chaste kiss given, In hope of coming happiness; by this Fresh Fountain many a blushing Maid Hath crown'd the head of her long loved Shepherd With gaudy flowers, whilest he happy sung Layes of his love and dear Captivitie; There grows all Herbs fit to cool looser flames Our sensual parts provoke, chiding our bloods, And quenching by their power those hidden sparks That else would break out, and provoke our sense To open fires, so vertuous is that place: Then gentle Shepherdess, believe and grant, In troth it fits not with that face to scant Your faithful Shepherd of those chaste desires He ever aim'd at, and— Amo. Thou hast prevail'd, farewel, this coming night Shall crown thy chast hopes with long wish'd delight. Peri. Our great god Pan reward thee for that good Thou hast given thy poor Shepherd: fairest Bud Of Maiden Vertues, when I leave to be The true Admirer of thy Chastitie, Let me deserve the hot polluted Name Of the wild Woodman, or affect some Dame, Whose often Prostitution hath begot More foul Diseases, than ever yet the hot Sun bred through his burnings, whilst the Dog Pursues the raging Lion, throwing Fog, And deadly Vapour from his angry Breath, Filling the lower World with Plague and Death. [Ex. Am. Enter Amaryllis. Ama. Shepherd, may I desire to be believ'd, What I shall blushing tell? Peri. Fair Maid, you may. Am. Then softly thus, I love thee, Perigot, And would be gladder to be lov'd again, Than the cold Earth is in his frozen arms To clip the wanton Spring: nay do not start, Nor wonder that I woo thee, thou that art The prime of our young Grooms, even the top Of all our lusty Shepherds! what dull eye That never was acquainted with desire, Hath seen thee wrastle, run, or cast the Stone With nimble strength and fair delivery, And hath not sparkled fire, and speedily Sent secret heat to all the neighbouring Veins? Who ever heard thee sing, that brought again That freedom back, was lent unto thy Voice; Then do not blame me (Shepherd) if I be One to be numbred in this Companie, Since none that ever saw thee yet, were free. Peri. Fair Shepherdess, much pity I can lend To your Complaints: but sure I shall not love: All that is mine, my self, and my best hopes Are given already; do not love him then That cannot love again: on other men Bestow those heats more free, that may return You fire for fire, and in one flame equal burn. Ama. Shall I rewarded be so slenderly For my affection, most unkind of men! If I were old, or had agreed with Art To give another Nature to my Cheeks, Or were I common Mistress to the love Of every Swain, or could I with such ease Call back my Love, as many a Wanton doth; Thou might'st refuse me, Shepherd; but to thee I am only fixt and set, let it not be A Sport, thou gentle Shepherd to abuse The love of silly Maid. Peri. Fair Soul, ye use These words to little end: for know, I may Better call back that time was Yesterday, Or stay the coming Night, than bring my Love Home to my self again, or recreant prove. I will no longer hold you with delays, This present night I have appointed been To meet that chaste Fair (that enjoys my Soul) In yonder Grove, there to make up our Loves. Be not deceiv'd no longer, chuse again, These neighbouring Plains have many a comely Swain, Fresher, and freer far than I e'r was, Bestow that love on them, and let me pass. Farewel, be happy in a better Choice. [Exit. Ama. Cruel, thou hast struck me deader with thy Voice Than if the angry Heavens with their quick flames Had shot me through: I must not leave to love, I cannot, no I must enjoy thee, Boy, Though the great dangers 'twixt my hopes and that Be infinite: there is a Shepherd dwells Down by the Moor, whose life hath ever shown More sullen Discontent than Saturns Brow, When he sits frowning on the Births of Men: One that doth wear himself away in loneness; And never joys unless it be in breaking The holy plighted troths of mutual Souls: One that lusts after ever several Beauty, But never yet was known to love or like, Were the face fairer, or more full of truth, Than Phœbe in her fulness, or the youth Of smooth Lyæus; whose nigh starved flocks Are always scabby, and infect all Sheep They feed withal; whose Lambs are ever last, And dye before their waining, and whose Dog Looks like his Master, lean, and full of scurf, Not caring for the Pipe or Whistle: this man may (If he be well wrought) do a deed of wonder, Forcing me passage to my long desires: And here he comes, as fitly to my purpose, As my quick thoughts could wish for. Enter Shepherd. Shep. Fresh Beauty, let me not be thought uncivil, Thus to be Partner of your loneness: 'twas My Love (that ever working passion) drew Me to this place to seek some remedy For my sick Soul: be not unkind and fair, For such the mighty Cupid in his doom Hath sworn to be aveng'd on then give room To my consuming Fires, that so I may Enjoy my long Desires, and so allay Those flames that else would burn my life away. Ama. Shepherd, were I but sure thy heart were sound As thy words seem to be, means might be found To cure thee of thy long pains; for to me That heavy youth-consuming Miserie The love-sick Soul endures, never was pleasing; I could be well content with the quick easing Of thee, and thy hot fires, might it procure Thy faith and farther service to be sure. Shep. Name but that great work, danger, or what can Be compass'd by the Wit or Art of Man, And if I fail in my performance, may I never more kneel to the rising Day. Ama. Then thus I try thee, Shepherd, this same night, That now comes stealing on, a gentle pair Have promis'd equal Love, and do appoint To make yon Wood the place where hands and hearts Are to be ty'd for ever: break their meeting And their strong Faith, and I am ever thine. Shep. Tell me their Names, and if I do not move (By my great power) the Centre of their Love From his fixt being, let me never more Warm me by those fair Eyes I thus adore. Ama. Come, as we go, I'll tell thee what they are, And give thee fit directions for thy work. [Exeunt. Enter Cloe. Cloe. How have I wrong'd the times, or men, that thus After this holy Feast I pass unknown And unsaluted? 'twas not wont to be Thus frozen with the younger companie Of jolly Shepherds; 'twas not then held good, For lusty Grooms to mix their quicker blood With that dull humour, most unfit to be The friend of man, cold and dull Chastitie. Sure I am held not fair, or am too old, Or else not free enough, or from my fold Drive not a flock sufficient, great to gain The greedy eyes of wealth-alluring Swain: Yet if I may believe what others say, My face has soil enough; nor can they lay Justly too strict a Coyness to my Charge; My Flocks are many, and the Downs as large They feed upon: then let it ever be Their Coldness, not my Virgin Modestie Makes me complain. Enter Thenot. The. Was ever Man but I Thus truly taken with uncertainty? Where shall that Man be found that loves a mind Made up in Constancy, and dare not find His Love rewarded? here let all men know A Wretch that lives to love his Mistress so. Clo. Shepherd, I pray thee slay, where hast thou been? Or whither go'st thou? here be Woods as green As any, air likewise as fresh and sweet, As where smooth Zephyrus plays on the fleet Face of the curled Streams, with Flowers as many As the young Spring gives, and as choise as any; Here be all new Delights, cool Streams and Wells, Arbors o'rgrown with Woodbinds, Caves, and Dells, Chuse where thou wilt, whilst I sit by, and sing, Or gather Rushes to make many a Ring For thy long fingers; tell thee tales of Love, How the pale Phœbe hunting in a Grove, First saw the Boy Endymion, from whose Eyes She took eternal fire that never dyes; How she convey'd him softly in a sleep, Has temples bound with poppy to the steep Head of old Latmus, where she stoops each night, Gilding the Mountain with her Brothers light, To kiss her sweetest. The. Far from me are these Hot flashes, bred from wanton heat and ease; I have forgot what love and loving meant: Rhimes, Songs, and merry Rounds, that oft are sent To the soft Ears of Maids, are strange to me; Only I live t'admire a Chastitie, That neither pleasing Age, smooth tongue, or Gold, Could ever break upon, so pure a Mold Is that her Mind was cast in; 'tis to her I only am reserv'd; she is my form I stir By, breath and move, 'tis she and only she Can make me happy, or give miserie. Clo. Good Shepherd, may a Stranger crave to know To whom this dear observance you do ow? The. You may, and by her Vertue learn to square And level out your Life; for to be fair And nothing vertuous, only fits the Eye Of gaudy Youth, and swelling Vanitie. Then know, she's call'd the Virgin of the Grove, She that hath long since bury'd her chaste Love, And now lives by his Grave, for whose dear Soul She hath vow'd her self into the holy Roll Of strict Virginity; 'tis her I so admire, Not any looser Blood, or new desire. Clo. Farewel poor Swain, thou art not for my bend, I must have quicker Souls, whose works may tend To some free action: give me him dare love At first encounter, and as soon dare prove. The SONG. Come Shepherds, come, Come away without delay Whilst the gentle time dost stay. Green Woods are dumb, And will never tell to any Those dear Kisses, and those many Sweet Embraces that are given Dainty Pleasures that would even Raise in coldest Age a fire, And give Virgin Blood desire, Then if ever, Now or never, Come and have it, Think not I, Dare deny, If you crave it. Enter Daphnis. Here comes another: better be my speed, Thou god of Blood: but certain, if I read Not false, this is that modest Shepherd, he That only dare salute, but ne'r could be Brought to kiss any, hold discourse, or sing, Whisper, or boldly ask that wished thing We all are born for; one that makes loving Faces, And could be well content to covet Graces, Were they not got by boldness; in this thing My hopes are frozen; and but Fate doth bring Him hither, I would sooner chuse A Man made out of Snow, and freer use An Eunuch to my ends: but since he's here, Thus I attempt him. Thou of men most dear, Welcome to her, that only for thy sake, Hath been content to live: here boldly take My hand in pledg, this hand, that never yet Was given away to any: and but sit Down on this rushy Bank, whilst I go pull Fresh Blossoms from the Boughs, or quickly cull The choicest delicates from yonder Mead, To make thee Chains, or Chaplets, or to spread Under our fainting Bodies, when delight Shall lock up all our senses. How the sight Of those smooth rising Cheeks renew the story Of young Adonis, when in Pride and Glory He lay infolded 'twixt the beating arms Of willing Venus: methinks stronger Charms Dwell in those speaking eyes, and on that brow More sweetness than the Painters can allow To their best pieces: not Narcissus, he That wept himself away in memorie Of his own Beauty, nor Silvanus Boy, Nor the twice ravish'd Maid, for whom old Troy Fell by the hand of Pirrhus, may to thee Be otherwise compar'd, than some dead Tree To a young fruitful Olive. Daph. I can love, But I am loth to say so, lest I prove Too soon unhappy. Clo. Happy thou would'st say, My dearest Daphnis, blush not, if thy day To thee and thy soft heats be enemie, Then take the coming Night, fair youth 'tis free To all the World, Shepherd, I'll meet thee then When darkness hath shut up the eyes of men, In yonder Grove: speak, shall our Meeting hold? Indeed you are too bashful, be more bold, And tell me I. Daph. I'm content to say so, And would be glad to meet, might I but pray so Much from your Fairness, that you would be true. Clo. Shepherd, thou hast thy Wish. Daph. Fresh Maid, adieu: Yet one word more, since you have drawn me on To come this Night, fear not to meet alone That man that will not offer to be ill, Though your bright self would ask it, for his fill Of this Worlds goodness: do not fear him then, But keep your 'pointed time; let other men Set up their Bloods to sale, mine shall be ever Fair as the Soul it carries, and unchast never. [Exit. Clo. Yet am I poorer than I was before. Is it not strange, among so many a score Of lusty Bloods, I should pick out these things Whose Veins like a dull River far from Springs, Is still the same, slow, heavy, and unfit For stream or motion, though the strong winds hit With their continual power upon his sides? O happy be your names that have been brides, And tasted those rare sweets for which I pine: And far more heavy be thy grief and time, Thou lazie swain, that maist relieve my needs, Than his, upon whose liver alwayes feeds A hungry vultur. Enter Alexis. Ale. Can such beauty be Safe in his own guard, and not draw the eye Of him that passeth on, to greedy gaze, Or covetous desire, whilst in a maze The better part contemplates, giving rein And wished freedom to the labouring vein? Fairest and whitest, may I crave to know The cause of your retirement, why ye goe Thus all alone? methinks the downs are sweeter, And the young company of swains far meeter, Than those forsaken and untroden places. Give not your self to loneness, and those graces Hid from the eyes of men, that were intended To live amongst us swains. Cloe. Thou art befriended, Shepherd, in all my life I have not seen A man in whom greater contents have been Than thou thy self art: I could tell thee more, Were there but any hope left to restore My freedom lost. O lend me all thy red, Thou shamefast morning, when from Tithons bed Thou risest ever maiden. Alex. If for me, Thou sweetest of all sweets, these flashes be, Speak and be satisfied. O guide her tongue, My better angel; force my name among Her modest thoughts, that the first word may be— Cloe. Alexis, when the sun shall kiss the Sea, Taking his rest by the white Thetis side, Meet in the holy wood, where I'le abide Thy coming, Shepherd. Alex. If I stay behind, An everlasting dulness, and the wind, That as he passeth by shuts up the stream Of Rhine or Volga, whilst the suns hot beam Beats back again, seise me, and let me turn To coldness more than ice: oh how I burn And rise in youth and fire! I dare not stay. Cloe. My name shall be your word. Alex. Fly, fly thou day. [Exit. Cloe. My grief is great if both these boyes should fail: He that will use all winds must shift his sail. [Exit.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Actus Secundus. Scena Prima. Enter an old Shepherd, with a bell ringing, and the Priest of Pan following. Priest. Shepherds all, and maidens fair, Fold your flocks up, for the Air 'Gins to thicken, and the sun Already his great course hath run. Soe the dew-drops how they kiss Every little flower that is: Hanging on their velvet heads, Like a rope of crystal beads. See the heavy clouds low falling, And bright Hesperus down calling The dead night from under ground, At whose rising mists unsound, Damps, and vapours fly apace, Hovering o're the wanton face Of these pastures, where they come, Striking dead both bud and bloom; Therefore from such danger lock Every one his loved flock, And let your Dogs lye loose without, Lest the Wolf come as a scout From the mountain, and e're day Bear a Lamb or kid away, Or the crafty theevish Fox, Break upon your simple flocks: To secure your selves from these, Be not too secure in case; Let one eye his watches keep, Whilst the t'other eye doth sleep; So you shall good Shepherds prove, And for ever hold the love Of our great god. Sweetest slumbers And soft silence fall in numbers On your eye-lids: so farewel, Thus I end my evenings knel. [Exeunt. Enter Clorin, the Shepherdess, sorting of herbs, and telling the natures of them. Clor. Now let me know what my best Art hath done, Helpt by the great power of the vertuous moon In her full light; O you sons of Earth, You only brood, unto whose happy birth Vertue was given, holding more of nature Than man her first born and most perfect creature, Let me adore you; you that only can Help or kill nature, drawing out that span Of life and breath even to the end of time; You that these hands did crop, long before prime Of day; give me your names, and next your hidden power. This is the Clote bearing a yellow flower, And this black Horehound, both are very good For sheep or Shepherd, bitten by a wood Dogs venom'd tooth; these Ramuns branches are, Which stuck in entries, or about the bar That holds the door fast, kill all inchantments, charms, Were they Medeas verses that doe harms To men or cattel; these for frenzy be A speedy and a soveraign remedie, The bitter Wormwood, Sage, and Marigold, Such sympathy with mans good they do hold; This Tormentil, whose vertue is to part All deadly killing poyson from the heart; And here Narcissus roots for swellings best, Yellow Lysimacus, to give sweet rest To the faint Shepherd, killing where it comes All busie gnats, and every fly that hums: For leprosie, Darnel, and Sellondine, With Calamint, whose vertues do refine The blood of man, making it free and fair As the first hour it breath'd, or the best air. Here other two, but your rebellious use Is not for me, whose goodness is abuse; Therefore foul Standergrass, from me and mine I banish thee, with lustful Turpentine, You that intice the veins and stir the heat To civil mutiny, scaling the seat Our reason moves in, and deluding it With dreams and wanton fancies, till the sit Of burning lust be quencht; by appetite, Robbing the soul of blessedness and light: And thou light Varvin too, thou must go after, Provoking easie souls to mirth and laughter; No more shall I dip thee in water now, And sprinkle every post, and every bough With thy well pleasing juyce, to make the grooms Swell with high mirth, as with joy all the rooms. Enter Thenot. The. This is the Cabin where the best of all Her Sex, that ever breath'd, or ever shall Give heat or happiness to the Shepherds side, Doth only to her worthy self abide. Thou blessed star, I thank thee for thy light, Thou by whose power the darkness of sad night Is banisht from the Earth, in whose dull place Thy chaster beams play on the heavy face Of all the world, making the blue Sea smile, To see how cunningly thou dost beguile Thy Brother of his brightness, giving day Again from Chaos. Whiter than that way That leads to Joves high Court, and chaster far Than chastity it self, yon blessed star That nightly shines: Thou, all the constancie That in all women was, or e're shall be, From whose fair eye-balls flyes that holy fire, That Poets stile the Mother of desire, Infusing into every gentle brest A soul of greater price, and far more blest Than that quick power, which gives a difference, 'Twixt man and creatures of a lower sense. Clor. Shepherd, how cam'st thou hither to this place? No way is troden, all the verdant grass The spring shot up, stands yet unbruised here Of any foot, only the dapled Deer Far from the feared sound of crooked horn Dwels in this fastness. Th. Chaster than the morn, I have not wandred, or by strong illusion Into this vertuous place have made intrusion: But hither am I come (believe me fair) To seek you out, of whose great good the air Is full, and strongly labours, whilst the sound Breaks against Heaven, and drives into a stound The amazed Shepherd, that such vertue can Be resident in lesser than a man. Clor. If any art I have, or hidden skill May cure thee of disease or festred ill, Whose grief or greenness to anothers eye May seem unpossible of remedy, I dare yet undertake it. The. 'Tis no pain I suffer through disease, no beating vein Conveyes infection dangerous to the heart, No part impostum'd to be cur'd by Art, This body holds, and yet a feller grief Than ever skilfull hand did give relief Dwells on my soul, and may be heal'd by you, Fair beauteous Virgin. Clor. Then Shepherd, let me sue To know thy grief; that man yet never knew The way to health, that durst not shew his sore. Then. Then fairest, know, I love you. Chor. Swain, no more, Thou hast abus'd the strictness of this place, And offred Sacrilegious soul disgrace To the sweet rest of these interred bones, For fear of whose ascending, fly at once, Thou and thy idle passions, that the sight Of death and speedy vengeance may not fright Thy very soul with horror. Then. Let me not (Thou all perfection) merit such a blot For my true zealous faith. Clor. Dar'st thou abide To see this holy Earth at once divide And give her body up? for sure it will, If thou pursu'st with wanton flames to fill This hallowed place; therefore repent and goe, Whilst I with praise appease his Ghost below, That else would tell thee what it were to be A rival in that vertuous love that he Imbraces yet. Then. 'Tis not the white or red Inhabits in your cheek that thus can wed My mind to adoration; nor your eye, Though it be full and fair, your forehead high, And smooth as Pelops shoulder; not the smile Lies watching in those dimples to beguile The easie soul, your hands and fingers long With veins inamel'd richly, nor your tongue, Though it spoke sweeter than Arions Harp, Your hair wove into many a curious warp, Able in endless errour to infold The wandring soul, nor the true perfect mould Of all your body, which as pure doth show In Maiden whiteness as the Alpsian snow. All these, were but your constancie away, Would please me less than a black stormy day The wretched Seaman toyling through the deep. But whilst this honour'd strictness you dare keep, Though all the plagues that e're begotten were In the great womb of air, were setled here, In opposition, I would, like the tree, Shake off those drops of weakness, and be free Even in the arm of danger. Clor. Wouldst thou have Me raise again (fond man) from silent grave, Those sparks that long agoe were buried here, With my dead friends cold ashes? Then. Dearest dear, I dare not ask it, nor you must not grant; Stand strongly to your vow, and do not faint: Remember how he lov'd ye, and be still The same Opinion speaks ye; let not will, And that great god of women, appetite, Set up your blood again; do not invite Desire and fancie from their long exile, To set them once more in a pleasing smile: Be like a rock made firmly up 'gainst all The power of angry Heaven, or the strong fall Of Neptunes battery; if ye yield, I die To all affection; 'tis that loyaltie Ye tie unto this grave I so admire; And yet there's something else I would desire, If you would hear me, but withall deny. O Pan, what an uncertain destiny Hangs over all my hopes! I will retire, For if I longer stay, this double fire Will lick my life up. Clor. Doe, let time wear out What Art and Nature cannot bring about. Then. Farewel thou soul of vertue, and be blest For ever, whilst that here I wretched rest Thus to my self; yet grant me leave to dwell In kenning of this Arbor; yon same dell O'retopt with morning Cypress and sad Yew Shall be my Cabin, where I'le early rew, Before the Sun hath kist this dew away, The hard uncertain chance which Fate doth lay Upon this head. Clor. The gods give quick release And happy cure unto thy hard disease. [Exeunt. Enter Sullen Shepherd. Sullen. I do not love this wench that I should meet, For ne'r did my unconstant eye yet greet That beauty, were it sweeter or more fair, Than the new blossoms, when the morning air Blows gently on them or the breaking light, When many maiden blushes to our sight Shoot from his early face: were all these set In some neat form before me, 'twould not get The least love from me; some desire it might, Or present burning: all to me in sight Are equal, be they fair, or black, or brown, Virgin, or careless wanton, I can crown My appetite with any; swear as oft And weep, as any, melt my words as soft Into a maiden ears, and tell how long My heart has been her servant, and how strong My passions are: call her unkind and cruel, Offer her all I have to gain the Jewel Maidens so highly prize: then loath, and fly: This do I hold a blessed destiny. Enter Amaryllis. Amar. Hail Shepherd, Pan bless both thy flock and thee, For being mindful of thy word to me. Sul. Welcom fair Shepherdess, thy loving swain Gives thee the self same wishes back again, Who till this present hour ne're knew that eye, Could make me cross mine arms, or daily dye With fresh consumings: boldly tell me then, How shall we part their faithful loves, and when? Shall I bely him to her, shall I swear His faith is false, and he loves every where? I'le say he mockt her th'other day to you, Which will by your confirming shew as true, For he is of so pure an honesty, To think (because he will not) none will lye: Or else to him I'le slander Amoret, And say, she but seems chaste; I'le swear she met Me 'mongst the shady Sycamores last night And loosely offred up her flame and spright Into my bosom, made a wanton bed Of leaves and many flowers, where she spread Her willing body to be prest by me; There have I carv'd her name on many a tree, Together with mine own; to make this show More full of seeming, Hobinall you know, Son to the aged Shepherd of the glen, Him I have sorted out of many men, To say he found us at our private sport, And rouz'd us 'fore our time by his resort: This to confirm, I have promis'd to the boy May a pretty knack, and many a toy, As gins to catch him birds, with bow and bolt, To shoot at nimble Squirrels in the holt; A pair of painted Buskins, and a Lamb, Soft as his own locks, or the down of swan; This I have done to win ye, which doth give Me double pleasure. Discord makes me live. Amar. Lov'd swain, I thank ye, these tricks might prevail With other rustick Shepherds, but will fail Even once to stir, much more to overthrow His fixed love from judgement, who doth know Your nature, my end, and his chosens merit; Therefore some stranger way must force his spirit, Which I have found: give second, and my love Is everlasting thine. Sul. Try me and prove. Amar. These happy pair of lovers meet straightway, Soon as they fold their flocks up with the day, In the thick grove bordering upon yon Hill, In whose hard side Nature hath carv'd a well, And but that matchless spring which Poets know, Was ne're the like to this: by it doth grow About the sides, all herbs which Witches use, All simples good for Medicine or abuse, All sweets that crown the happy Nuptial day, With all their colours, there the month of May Is ever dwelling, all is young and green, There's not a grass on which was ever seen The falling Autumn, or cold Winters hand, So full of heat and vertue is the land, About this fountain, which doth slowly break Below yon Mountains foot, into a Creek That waters all the vally, giving Fish Of many sorts, to fill the Shepherds dish. This holy well, my grandam that is dead, Right wise in charms, hath often to me said, Hath power to change the form of any creature, Being thrice dipt o're the head, into what feature, Or shape 'twould please the letter down to crave, Who must pronounce this charm too, which she gave Me on her death-bed; told me what, and how, I should apply unto the Patients brow, That would be chang'd, casting them thrice asleep, Before I trusted them into this deep. All this she shew'd me, and did charge me prove This secret of her Art, if crost in love. I'le this attempt; now Shepherd, I have here All her prescriptions, and I will not fear To be my self dipt: come, my temples bind With these sad herbs, and when I sleep you find, As you do speak your charm, thrice down me let, And bid the water raise me Amoret; Which being done, leave me to my affair, And e're the day shall quite it self out-wear, I will return unto my Shepherds arm, Dip me again, and then repeat this charm, And pluck me up my self, whom freely take, And the hotst fire of thine affection slake. Sul. And if I fit thee not, then fit not me: I long the truth of this wells power to see. [Exeunt. Enter Daphnis. Daph. Here will I stay, for this the covert is Where I appointed Cloe; do not miss, Thou bright-ey'd virgin, come, O come my fair, Be not abus'd with fear, nor let cold care Of honour stay thee from the Shepherds arm, Who would as hard be won to offer harm To thy chast thoughts, as whiteness from the day, Or yon great round to move another way. My language shall be honest, full of truth, My flames as smooth and spotless as my youth: I will not entertain that wandring thought, Whose easie current may at length be brought To a loose vastness. Alexis within. Cloe! Daph. 'Tis her voyce, And I must answer, Cloe! Oh the choice Of dear embraces, chast and holy strains Our hands shall give! I charge you all my veins Through which the blood and spirit take their way, Lock up your disobedient heats, and stay Those mutinous desires that else would grow To strong rebellion: do not wilder show Than blushing modesty may entertain, Alexis within. Cloe! Daph. There sounds that blesseds name again, Enter Alexis. And I will meet it: let me not mistake, This is some Shepherd! sure I am awake; What may this riddle mean? I will retire, To give my self more knowledg. Alex. Oh my fire, How thou consum'st me? Cloe, answer me, Alexis, strong Alexis, high and free, Calls upon Cloe. See mine arms are full Of entertainment, ready for to pull That golden fruit which too too long hath hung Tempting the greedy eye: thou stayest too long, I am impatient of these mad delayes; I must not leave unsought these many ways That lead into this center, till I find Quench for my burning lust. I come, unkind. [Exit Alexis. Daph. Can my imagination work me so much ill, That I may credit this for truth, and still Believe mine eyes? or shall I firmly hold Her yet untainted, and these sights but bold Illusion? Sure such fancies oft have been Sent to abuse true love, and yet are seen, Daring to blind the vertuous thought with errour. But be they far from me with their fond terrour: I am resolv'd my Cloe yet is true. [Cloe within. Cloe, hark, Cloe: Sure this voyce is new, Whose shrilness like the sounding of a Bell, Tells me it is a Woman: Cloe, tell Thy blessed name again. Cloe. [within] Here. Oh what a grief is this to be so near, And not incounter? Enter Cloe. Clo. Shepherd, we are met, Draw close into the covert, lest the wet Which falls like lazy mists upon the ground Soke through your Startups. Daph. Fairest are you found? How have we wandred, that the better part Of this good night is perisht? Oh my heart! How have I long'd to meet ye, how to kiss Those lilly hands, how to receive the bliss That charming tongue gives to the happy ear Of him that drinks your language! but I fear I am too much unmanner'd, far too rude, And almost grown lascivious to intrude These hot behaviours; where regard of fame, Honour, and modesty, a vertuous name, And such discourse as one fair Sister may Without offence unto the Brother say, Should rather have been tendred: but believe, Here dwells a better temper; do not grieve Then, ever kindest, that my first salute Seasons so much of fancy, I am mute Henceforth to all discourses, but shall be Suiting to your sweet thoughts and modestie. Indeed I will not ask a kiss of you, No not to wring your fingers, nor to sue To those blest pair of fixed stars for smiles, All a young lovers cunning, all his wiles, And pretty wanton dyings, shall to me Be strangers; only to your chastitie I am devoted ever. Clo. Honest Swain, First let me thank you, then return again As much of my love: no thou art too cold, Unhappy Boy, not tempred to my mold, Thy blood falls heavy downward, 'tis not fear To offend in boldness wins, they never wear Deserved favours that deny to take When they are offered freely: Do I wake To see a man of his youth, years and feature, And such a one as we call goodly creature, Thus backward? What a world of precious Art Were meerly lost, to make him do his part? But I will shake him off, that dares not hold, Let men that hope to be belov'd be bold. Daphnis, I do desire, since we are met So happily, our lives and fortunes set Upon one stake, to give assurance now, By interchange of hands and holy vow, Never to break again: walk you that way Whilest I in zealous meditation stray A little this way: when we both have ended These rites and duties, by the woods befriended, And secresie of night, retire and find An aged Oak, whose hollowness may bind Us both within his body, thither go, It stands within yon bottom. Daph. Be it so. [Ex. Daph. Clo. And I will meet there never more with thee, Thou idle shamefastness. Alex. [within] Cloe! Clo. 'Tis he That dare I hope be bolder. Alex. Cloe! Clo. Now Great Pan for Syrinx sake bid speed our Plow. [Exit Cloe.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Actus Tertius. Scena Prima. Enter Sullen Shepherd with Amaryllis in a sleep. Sull. From thy forehead thus I take These herbs, and charge thee not awake Till in yonder holy Well, Thrice with powerful Magick spell, Fill'd with many a baleful word, Thou hast been dipt; thus with my cord Of blasted Hemp, by Moon-light twin'd, I do thy sleepy body bind; I turn thy head into the East, And thy feet into the West, Thy left arm to the South put forth, And thy right unto the North: I take thy body from the ground, In this deep and deadly swound, And into this holy spring I let thee slide down by my string. Take this Maid thou holy pit, To thy bottom, nearer yet, In thy water pure and sweet, By thy leave I dip her feet; Thus I let her lower yet, That her ankles may be wet; Yet down lower, let her knee In thy waters washed be; There stop: Fly away Every thing that loves the day. Truth that hath but one face, Thus I charm thee from this place. Snakes that cast your coats for new, Camelions that alter hue, Hares that yearly Sexes change, Proteus alt'ring oft and strange, Hecate with shapes three, Let this Maiden changed be, With this holy water wet, To the shape of Amoret: Cynthia work thou with my charm, Thus I draw thee free from harm Up out of this blessed Lake, Rise both like her and awake. [She awakes. Amar. Speak Shepherd, am I Amoret to fight? Or hast thou mist in any Magick rite; For want of which any defect in me, May make our practices discovered be. Sul. By yonder Moon, but that I here do stand, Whose breath hath thus transform'd thee, and whose hand Let thee down dry, and pluckt thee up thus wet, I should my self take thee for Amoret; Thou art in cloths, in feature, voice and hew So like, that sense cannot distinguish you. Amar. Then this deceit which cannot crossed be, At once shall lose her him, and gain thee me. Hither she needs must come by promise made, And sure his nature never was so bad, To bid a Virgin meet him in the wood, When night and fear are up, but understood, 'Twas his part to come first: being come, I'le say, My constant love made me come first and stay, Then will I lead him further to the grove, But stay you here, and if his own true love Shall seek him here, set her in some wrong path, Which say, her lover lately troden hath; I'le not be far from hence, if need there be, Here is another charm, whose power will free The dazeled sense, read by the Moons beams clear, And in my own true map make me appear. Enter Perigot. Sull. Stand close, here's Perigot, whose constant heart Songs to behold her in whose shape thou art. Per. This is the place (fair Amoret) the hour Is yet scarce come: Here every Sylvan power Delights to be about yon sacred Well, Which they have blest with many a powerful Spell; For never Traveller in dead of Night, Nor strayed Beasts have faln in, but when sight Hath fail'd them, then their right way they have sound By help of them, so holy is the ground: But I will farther seek, lest Amoret Should be first come, and so stray long unmet. My Amoret, Amoret. [Ex. Amaryllis, Perigot. Per. My Love. Amar. I come my Love. Sull. Now she has got Her own desires, and I shall gainer be Of my long lookt for hopes as well as she. How bright the moon shines here, as if she strove To show her Glory in this little Grove, Enter Amoret. To some new loved Shepherd. Yonder is Another Amoret. Where differs this From that? but that she Perigot hath met, I should have ta'n this for the counterfeit: Herbs, Woods, and Springs, the power that in you lies, If mortal men could know your Properties! Amo. Methinks it is not Night, I have no fear, Walking this Wood, of Lions, or the Bear, Whose Names at other times have made me quake, When any Shepherdess in her tale spake Of some of them, that underneath a Wood Have torn true Lovers that together stood. Methinks there are no Goblins, and mens talk, That in these Woods the nimble Fairies walk, Are fables; such a strong heart I have got, Because I come to meet with Perigot. My Perigot! who's that, my Perigot? Sull. Fair maid. Amo. Ay me, thou art not Perigot. Sull. But I can tell ye news of Perigot: An hour together under yonder tree He sate with wreathed arms and call'd on thee, And said, why Amoret stayest thou so long? Then starting up, down yonder path he flung, Lest thou hadst miss'd thy way: were it day light, He could not yet have born him out of sight. Amor. Thanks, gentle Shepherd, and beshrew my stay, That made me fearful I had lost my way: As fast as my weak Legs (that cannot be Weary with seeking him) will carry me, I'll seek him out; and for thy Courtesie Pray Pan thy Love may ever follow thee. [Exit. Sull. How bright she was, how lovely did she show! Was it not pity to deceive her so? She pluckt her Garments up, and tript away, And with her Virgin-innocence did pray For me that perjur'd her. Whilst she was here, Methought the Beams of Light that did appear Were shot from her; methought the Moon gave none, But what it had from her: she was alone With me, if then her presence did so move, Why did not I essay to win her Love? She would not sure have yielded unto me; Women love only Opportunitie, And not the Man; or if she had deny'd, Alone, I might have forc'd her to have try'd Who had been stronger: O vain Fool, to let Such blest Occasion pass; I'll follow yet, My Blood is up, I cannot now forbear. Enter Alex. and Cloe. I come sweet Amoret: Soft who is here? A pair of Lovers? He shall yield her me; Now Lust is up, alike all Women be. Alex. Where shall we rest? but for the love of me, Cloe, I know ere this would weary be. Clo. Alexis, let us rest here, if the place Be private, and out of the common trace Of every Shepherd: for I understood This Night a number are about the Wood: Then let us chuse some place, where out of sight We freely may enjoy our stoln delight. Alex. Then boldly here, where we shall ne're be sound, No Shepherds way lies here, 'tis hallow'd ground: No Maid seeks here her strayed Cow, or Sheep, Fairies, and Fawns, and Satyrs do it keep: Then carelesly rest here, and clip and kiss, And let no fear make us our pleasures miss. Clo. Then lye by me, the sooner we begin, The longer ere the day descry our sin. Sull. Forbear to touch my Love, or by yon flame, The greatest power that Shepherds dare to name, Here where thou sit'st under this holy tree Her to dishonour, thou shalt buried be. Alex. If Pan himself, should come out of the lawns, With all his Troops of Satyrs and of Fawns, And bid me leave, I swear by her two eyes, A greater Oath than thine, I would not rise. Sull. Then from the cold Earth never shalt thou move, But lose at one stroke both thy Life and Love. Clo. Hold gentle Shepherd. Sull. Fairest Shepherdess, Come you with me, I do not love you less Than that fond man, that would have kept you there From me of more desert. Alex. O yet forbear To take her from me; give me leave to dye By her. [The Satyr enters, he runs one way, and she another. Sat. Now whilst the Moon doth rule the Skie, And the Stars, whose feeble light Give a pale Shadow to the night, Are up, great Pan commanded me To walk this Grove about, whilst he In a corner of the Wood, Where never mortal foot hath stood, Keeps dancing, musick, and a feast To entertain a lovely Guest, Where he gives her many a Rose, Sweeter than the breath that blows The leaves; Grapes, Berries of the best, I never saw so great a feast. But to my Charge: here must I stay, To see what mortals lose their way, And by a false fire seeming bright, Train them in and leave them right. Then must I watch if any be Forcing of a Chastitie: If I find it, then in haste Give my wreathed horn a Blast, And the Fairies all will run, Wildly dancing by the Moon, And will pinch him to the bone, Till his lustful thoughts be gone. Alex. O Death! Sat. Back again about this ground, Sure I hear a mortal sound; I bind thee by this powerful Spell, By the Waters of this Well, By the glimmering Moon beams bright, Speak again, thou mortal wight. Alex. Oh! Sat. Here the foolish mortal lies, Sleeping on the ground: arise. The poor wight is almost dead, On the ground his wounds have bled, And his cloaths foul'd with his blood: To my Goddess in the Wood Will I lead him, whose hands pure, Will help this mortal wight to cure. Enter Cloe again. Clo. Since I beheld yon shaggy man, my Breast Doth pant, each bush, methinks, should hide a Beast: Yet my desire keeps still above my fear, I would fain meet some Shepherd, knew I where: For from one cause of fear I am most free, It is impossible to ravish me, I am so willing. Here upon this ground I left my Love all bloody with his wound; Yet till that fearful shape made me be gone, Though he were hurt, I furnisht was of one, But now both lost. Alexis, speak or move, If thou hast any life, thou art yet my Love. He's dead, or else is with his little might Crept from the Bank for fear of that ill Spright. Then where art thou that struck'st my love? O stay, Bring me thy self in change, and then I'll say Thou hast some justice, I will make thee trim With Flowers and Garlands that were meant for him; I'll clip thee round with both mine arms, as fast As I did mean he should have been embrac'd: But thou art fled. What hope is left for me? I'll run to Daphnis in the hollow tree, Whom I did mean to mock, though hope be small, To make him bold; rather than none at all, I'll try him; his heart, and my behaviour too Perhaps may teach him what he ought to do. [Exit. Enter Sullen Shepherd. Sul. This was the place, 'twas but my feeble sight, Mixt with the horrour of my deed, and night, That shap't these fears, and made me run away, And lose my beauteous hardly gotten prey. Speak gentle Shepherdess, I am alone, And tender love for love: but she is gone From me, that having struck her Lover dead, For silly fear left her alone and fled. And see the wounded body is remov'd By her of whom it was so well belov'd. Enter Perigot and Amaryllis in the shape of Amoret. But these fancies must be quite forgot, I must lye close. Here comes young Perigot With subtile Amaryllis in the shape Of Amoret. Pray Love he may not 'scape. Amar. Beloved Perigot, shew me some place, Where I may rest my limbs, weak with the Chace Of thee, an hour before thou cam'st at least. Per. Beshrew my tardy steps: here shalt thou rest Upon this holy bank, no deadly Snake Upon this turf her self in folds doth make. Here is no poyson for the Toad to feed; Here boldly spead thy hands, no venom'd Weed Dares blister them, no slimy Snail dare creep Over thy face when thou art fast asleep Here never durst the babling Cuckow spit, No slough of falling Star did ever hit Upon this bank: let this thy Cabin be, This other set with Violets for me. Ama. Thou dost not love me Perigot. Per. Fair maid, You only love to hear it often said; You do not doubt. Amar. Believe me but I do. Per. What shall we now begin again to woo? 'Tis the best way to make your Lover last, To play with him, when you have caught him fast. Amar. By Pan I swear, I loved Perigot, And by yon Moon, I think thou lov'st me not. Per. By Pan I swear, and if I falsely swear, Let him not guard my flocks, let Foxes tear My earliest Lambs, and Wolves whilst I do sleep Fall on the rest, a Rot among my Sheep. I love thee better than the careful Ewe The new-yean'd Lamb that is of her own hew; I dote upon thee more than the young-Lamb Doth on the bag that feeds him from his Dam. Were there a sort of Wolves got in my Fold, And one ran after thee, both young and old Should be devour'd, and it should be my strife To save thee, whom I love above my life. Ama. How shall I trust thee when I see thee chuse. Another Bed, and dost my side refuse? Per. 'Twas only that the chast thoughts might be shewn 'Twixt thee and me, although we were alone, Ama. Come, Perigot will shew his power, that he Can make his Amoret, though she weary be, Rise nimbly from her Couch, and come to his. Here take thy Amoret, embrace and kiss. Per. What means my Love? Ama. To do as lovers shou'd That are to be enjoy'd, not to be woo'd. There's ne'r a Shepherdess in all the plain Can kiss thee with more Art, there's none can feign More wanton tricks. Per. Forbear, dear Soul, to trie Whether my Heart be pure; I'll rather die Than nourish one thought to dishonour thee. Amar. Still think'st thou such a thing as Chastitie Is amongst Women? Perigot there's none, That with her Love is in a Wood alone, And would come home a maid; be not abus'd With thy fond first Belief, let time be us'd: Why dost thou rise? Per. My true heart thou hast slaine. Ama. Faith Perigot, I'll pluck thee down again. Per. Let go, thou Serpent, that into my brest Hast with thy cunning div'd; art not in Jest? Ama. Sweet love, lye down. Per. Since this I live to see Some bitter North-wind blast my flocks and me. Ama. You swore you lov'd, yet will not do my will. Per. O be as thou wert once, I'll love thee still. Ama. I am, as still I was, and all my kind, Though other shows we have poor men to blind. Per. Then here I end all Love, and lest my vain Belief should ever draw me in again, Before thy face that hast my Youth misled, I end my life, my blood be on thy head. Ama. O hold thy hands, thy Amoret doth cry. Per. Thou counsel'st well, first Amoret shall dye, That is the cause of my eternal smart. [He runs after he. Ama. O hold. Per. This steel shall pierce thy lustful heart. [The Sullen Shepherd steps out and uncharms her. Sull. Up and down every where, I strew the herbs to purge the air: Let your Odour drive hence All mists that dazel sence. Herbs and Springs whose hidden might Alters Shapes, and mocks the sight, Thus I charge you to undo All before I brought ye to: Let her flye, let her 'scape, Give again her own shape. Enter Amaryllis in her own shape. Amar. Forbear thou gentle Swain, thou dost mistake, She whom thou follow'dst fled into the brake, And as I crost thy way, I met thy wrath, The only fear of which near slain me hath. Per. Pardon fair Shepherdess, my rage and night Were both upon me, and beguil'd my sight; But far be it from me to spill the blood Of harmless Maids that wander in the Wood. Ex. Amar. Enter Amoret. Amor. Many a weary step in yonder path Poor hopeless Amoret twice trodden hath To seek her Perigot, yet cannot hear His Voice; my Perigot, she loves thee dear, That calls. Per. See yonder where she is, how fair She shows, and yet her breath infects the air. Amo. My Perigot. Per. Here. Amo. Happy. Per. Hapless first: It lights on thee, the next blow is the worst. Amo. Stay Perigot, my love, thou art unjust. Peri. Death is the best reward that's due to lust. [Exit Perigot. Sul. Now shall their love be crost, for being struck, Ile throw her in the Fount, lest being took By some night-travaller, whose honest care May help to cure her. Shepherdess prepare Your self to die. Amo. No Mercy I do crave, Thou canst not give a worse blow than I have; Tell him that gave me this, who lov'd him too, He struck my soul, and not my body through, Tell him when I am dead, my soul shall be At peace, if he but think he injur'd me. Sul. In this Fount be thy grave, thou wert not meant Sure for a woman, thou art so innocent. She cannot scape, for underneath the ground, flings her into the well. In a long hollow the clear spring is bound, Till on yon side where the Morns Sun doth look, The strugling water breaks out in a Brook. [Exit. [The God of the River riseth with Amoret in his arms. God. What powerfull charms my streams do bring Back again unto their spring, With such force, that I their god, Three times striking with my Rod, Could not keep them in their ranks: My Fishes shoot into the banks, There's not one that stayes and feeds, All have hid them in the weeds. Here's a mortal almost dead, Faln into my River head, Hallowed so with many a spell, That till now none ever fell. Tis a Female young and clear, Cast in by some Ravisher. See upon her breast a wound, On which there is no plaister bound. Yet she's warm, her pulses beat, Tis a sign of life and heat. If thou be'st a Virgin pure, I can give a present cure: Take a drop into thy wound From my watry locks more round Than Orient Pearl, and far more pure Than unchast flesh may endure. See she pants, and from her flesh The warm blood gusheth out afresh. She is an unpolluted maid; I must have this bleeding staid. From my banks I pluck this flower With holy hand, whose vertuous power Is at once to heal and draw. The blood returns. I never saw A fairer Mortal. Now doth break Her deadly slumber: Virgin, speak. Amo. Who hath restor'd my sense, given me new breath, And brought me back out of the arms of death? God. I have heal'd thy wounds. Amo. Ay me! God. Fear not him that succour'd thee: I am this Fountains god; below, My waters to a River grow, And 'twixt two banks with Osiers set, That only prosper in the wet, Through the Meadows do they glide, Wheeling still on every side, Sometimes winding round about, To find the evenest channel out. And if thou wilt go with me, Leaving mortal companie, In the cool streams shalt thou lye, Free from harm as well as I: I will give thee for thy food, No Fish that useth in the mud, But Trout and Pike that love to swim Where the gravel from the brim Through the pure streams may be seen: Orient Pearl fit for a Queen, Will I give thy love to win, And a shell to keep them in: Not a Fish in all my Brook That shall disobey thy look, But when thou wilt, come sliding by, And from thy white hand take a fly. And to make thee understand, How I can my waves command, They shall bubble whilst I sing Sweeter than the silver spring. The SONG. Do not fear to put thy feet Naked in the River sweet; Think not Leach, or Newt or Toad Will bite thy foot, when thou hast troad; Nor let the water rising high, As thou wad'st in, make thee crie And sob, but ever live with me, And not a wave shall trouble thee. Amo. Immortal power, that rul'st this holy flood, I know my self unworthy to be woo'd By thee a god: for e're this, but for thee I should have shown my weak Mortalitie: Besides, by holy Oath betwixt us twain, I am betroath'd unto a Shepherd swain, Whose comely face, I know the gods above May make me leave to see, but not to love. God. May he prove to thee as true. Fairest Virgin, now adieu, I must make my waters fly, Lest they leave their Channels dry, And beasts that come unto the spring Miss their mornings watering, Which I would not; for of late All the neighbour people sate On my banks, and from the fold, Two white Lambs of three weeks old Offered to my Deitie: For which this year they shall be free From raging floods, that as they pass Leave their gravel in the grass: Nor shall their Meads be overflown, When their grass is newly mown. Amo. For thy kindness to me shown, Never from thy banks be blown Any tree, with windy force, Cross thy streams, to stop thy course: May no beast that comes to drink, With his horns cast down thy brink; May none that for thy fish do look, Cut thy banks to damm thy Brook; Bare-foot may no Neighbour wade In thy cool streams, wife nor maid, When the spawns on stones do lye, To wash their Hemp, and spoil the Fry. God. Thanks Virgin, I must down again, Thy wound will put thee to no pain: Wonder not so soon 'tis gone: A holy hand was laid upon. [Exit. Amo. And I unhappy born to be, Must follow him that flies from me.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Actus Quartus. Scena Prima. Enter Perigot. Per. She is untrue, unconstant, and unkind, She's gone, she's gone, blow high thou North-west wind, And raise the Sea to Mountains, let the Trees That dare oppose thy raging fury, leefe Their firm foundation, creep into the Earth, And shake the world, as at the monstrous birth Of some new Prodigy, whilst I constant stand, Holding this trustie Boar-spear in my hand, And falling thus upon it. Enter Amaryllis, running. Amar. Stay thy dead doing hand, thou art too hot Against thy self, believe me comely Swain, If that thou dyest, not all the showers of Rain The heavy clods send down can wash away That foul unmanly guilt, the world will lay Upon thee. Yet thy love untainted stands: Believe me, she is constant, not the sands Can be so hardly numbred as she won: I do not trifle, Shepherd, by the Moon, And all those lesser lights our eyes do view, All that I told thee Perigot, is true: Then be a free man, put away despair, And will to dye, smooth gently up that fair Dejected forehead: be as when those eyes Took the first heat. Per. Alas he double dyes, That would believe, but cannot; 'tis not well Ye keep me thus from dying, here to dwell With many worse companions: but oh death, I am not yet inamour'd of this breath So much, but I dare leave it, 'tis not pain In forcing of a wound, nor after gain Of many dayes, can hold me from my will: 'Tis not my self, but Amoret, bids kill. Ama. Stay but a little, little, but one hour, And if I do not show thee through the power Of herbs and words I have, as dark as night, My self turn'd to thy Amoret, in sight, Her very figure, and the Robe she wears, With tawny Buskins, and the hook she bears. Of thine own Carving, where your names are set, Wrought underneath with many a curious fret, The Prim-Rose Chaplet, taudry lace and Ring, Thou gavest her for her singing, with each thing Else that she wears about her, let me feel The first fell stroke of that Revenging steel. Per. I am contented, if there be a hope To give it entertainment, for the scope Of one poor hour; go; you shall find me next Under yon shady Beech, even thus perplext, And thus believing. Ama. Bind before I goe, Thy soul by Pan unto me, not to doe Harm or outragious wrong upon thy life, Till my return. Per. By Pan, and by the strife He had with Phœbus for the Mastery, When Golden Midas judg'd their Minstreloy, I will not. [Exeunt. Enter Satyr, with Alexis, hurt. Satyr. Softly gliding as I goe, With this burthen full of woe, Through still silence of the night, Guided by the Gloe-worms light, Hither am I come at last, Many a Thicket have I past Not a twig that durst deny me, Not a bush that durst descry me, To the little Bird that sleeps On the tender spray: nor creeps That hardy worm with pointed tail, But if I be under sail, Flying faster than the wind, Leaving all the clouds behind, But doth hide her tender head In some hollow tree or bed Of seeded Nettles: not a Hare Can be started from his fare, By my footing, nor a wish Is more sudden, nor a fish Can be found with greater ease, Cut the vast unbounded seas, Leaving neither print nor sound, Than I, when nimbly on the ground, I measure many a league an hour: But behold the happy power; That must ease me of my charge, And by holy hand enlarge The soul of this sad man, that yet Lyes fast bound in deadly fit; Heaven and great Pan succour it! Hail thou beauty of the bower, Whiter than the Paramour Of my Master, let me crave Thy vertuous help to keep from Grave This poor Mortal that here lyes, Waiting when the destinies Will cut off his thred of life: View the wound by cruel knife Trencht into him. Clor. What art thou call'st me from my holy rites, And with thy feared name of death affrights My tender Ears? speak me thy name and will. Satyr. I am the Satyr that did fill Your lap with early fruit, and will, When I hap to gather more, Bring ye better and more store: Yet I come not empty now, See a blossom from the bow, But beshrew his heart that pull'd it, And his perfect sight that cull'd it From the other springing blooms; For a sweeter youth the Grooms Cannot show me, nor the downs, Nor the many neighbouring towns; Low in yonder glade I found him, Softly in mine Arms I bound him, Hither have I brought him sleeping In a trance, his wounds fresh weeping, In remembrance such youth may Spring and perish in a day. Clor. Satyr, they wrong thee, that do term thee rude, Though thou beest outward rough and tawny hu'd, Thy manners are as gentle and as fair As his, who brags himself, born only heir To all Humanity: let me see the wound: This Herb will stay the current being bound Fast to the Orifice, and this restrain Ulcers, and swellings, and such inward pain, As the cold air hath forc'd into the sore: This to draw out such putrifying gore As inward falls. Satyr. Heaven grant it may doe good. Clor. Fairly wipe a way the blood: Hold him gently till I fling Water of a vertuous spring On his temples; turn him twice To the Moon beams, pinch him thrice, That the labouring soul may draw From his great eclipse. Satyr. I saw His eye-lids moving. Clo. Give him breath, All the danger of cold death Now is vanisht; with this Plaster, And this unction, do I master All the festred ill that may Give him grief another day. Satyr. See he gathers up his spright And begins to hunt for light; Now he gapes and breaths again: How the blood runs to the vein, That erst was empty! Alex. O my heart, My dearest, dearest Cloe, O the smart Runs through my side: I feel some pointed thing Pass through my Bowels, sharper than the sting Of Scorpion. Pan preserve me, what are you? Do not hurt me, I am true To my Cloe, though she flye, And leave me to thy destiny. There she stands, and will not lend Her smooth white hand to help her friend: But I am much mistaken, for that face Bears more Austerity and modest grace, More reproving and more awe Than these eyes yet ever saw In my Cloe. Oh my pain Eagerly renews again. Give me your help for his sake you love best. Clor. Shepherd, thou canst not possibly take rest, Till thou hast laid aside all hearts desires Provoking thought that stir up lusty fires, Commerce with wanton eyes, strong blood, and will To execute, these must be purg'd, untill The vein grow whiter; then repent, and pray Great Pan to keep you from the like decay, And shall undertake your cure with ease. Till when this vertuous Plaster will displease Your tender sides; give me your hand and rise: Help him a little Satyr, for his thighs Yet are feeble. Alex. Sure I have lost much blood. Satyr. 'Tis no matter, 'twas not good. Mortal you must leave your wooing, Though there be a joy in doing, Yet it brings much grief behind it, They best feel it, that do find it. Clor. Come bring him in, I will attend his sore When you are well, take heed you lust no more. Satyr. Shepherd, see what comes of kissing, By my head 'twere better missing. Brightest, if there be remaining Any service, without feigning I will do it; were I set To catch the nimble wind, or get Shadows gliding on the green, Or to steal from the great Queen Of Fayries, all her beauty, I would do it, so much duty Do I owe those precious Eyes. Cor. I thank thee honest Satyr, if the cryes Of any other that be hurt or ill, Draw thee unto them, prithee do thy will To bring them hither. Satyr. I will, and when the weather Serves to Angle in the brook, I will bring a silver hook, With a line of finest silk, And a rod as white as milk, To deceive the little fish: So I take my leave, and wish, On this Bower may ever dwell Spring, and Summer. Clor. Friend farewel. [Exit. Enter Amoret, seeking her Love. Amor. This place is Ominous, for here I lost My Love and almost life, and since have crost All these Woods over, never a Nook or Dell, Where any little Bird, or Beast doth dwell, But I have sought him, never a bending brow Of any Hill or Glade, the wind sings through, Nor a green bank, nor shade where Shepherds use To sit and Riddle, sweetly pipe, or chuse Their Valentines, that I have mist, to find My love in. Perigot, Oh too unkind, Why hast thou fled me? whither art thou gone? How have I wrong'd thee? was my love alone To thee worthy this scorn'd recompence? 'tis well, I am content to feel it: but I tell Thee Shepherd, and these lusty woods shall hear, Forsaken Amoret is yet as clear Of any stranger fire, as Heaven is From foul corruption, or the deep Abysse From light and happiness; and thou mayst know All this for truth, and how that fatal blow Thou gav'st me, never from desert of mine, Fell on my life, but from suspect of thine, Or fury more than madness; therefore, here, Since I have lost my life, my love, my dear, Upon this cursed place, and on this green, That first divorc'd us, shortly shall be seen A sight of so great pity, that each eye Shall dayly spend his spring in memory Of my untimely fall. Enter Amaryllis. Amar. I am not blind, Nor is it through the working of my mind, That this shows Amoret; forsake me all That dwell upon the soul, but what men call Wonder, or more than wonder, miracle, For sure so strange as this the Oracle Never gave answer of, it passeth dreams, Or mad-mens fancy, when the many streams Of new imaginations rise and fall: 'Tis but an hour since these Ears heard her call For pity to young Perigot; whilest he, Directed by his fury bloodily Lanc't up her brest, which bloodless fell and cold; And if belief may credit what was told, After all this, the Melancholy Swain Took her into his arms being almost slain, And to the bottom of the holy well Flung her, for ever with the waves to dwell. 'Tis she, the very same, 'tis Amoret, And living yet, the great powers will not let Their vertuous love be crost. Maid, wipe away Those heavy drops of sorrow, and allay The storm that yet goes high, which not deprest, Breaks heart and life, and all before it rest: Thy Perigot— Amor. Where, which is Perigot? Amar. Sits there below, lamenting much, god wot, Thee thy and fortune, go and comfort him, And thou shalt find him underneath a brim Of failing Pines that edge yon Mountain in. Amo. I go, I run, Heaven grant me I may win His soul again. [Exit Amoret. Enter Sullen. Sull. Stay Amaryllis, stay, Ye are too fleet, 'tis two hours yet to day. I have perform'd my promise, let us sit And warm our bloods together till the fit Come lively on us. Amar. Friend you are too keen, The morning riseth and we shall be seen, Forbear a little. Sull. I can stay no longer. Amar. Hold Shepherd hold, learn not to be a wronger Of your word, was not your promise laid, To break their loves first? Sull. I have done it Maid. Amar. No, they are yet unbroken, met again, And are as hard to part yet as the stain Is from the finest Lawn. Sull. I say they are Now at this present parted, and so far, That they shall never meet. Amar. Swain 'tis not so, For do but to yon hanging Mountain go, And there believe your eyes. Sull. You do but hold Off with delayes and trifles; farewell cold And frozen bashfulness, unfit for men; Thus I salute thee Virgin. Amar. And thus then, I bid you follow, catch me if you can. [Exit. Sull. And if I stay behind I am no man. [Exit running after her. Enter Perigot. Per. Night do not steal away: I woo thee yet To hold a hard hand o're the rusty bit That guides the lazy Team: go back again, Bootes, thou that driv'st thy frozen Wain Round as a Ring, and bring a second Night To hide my sorrows from the coming light; Let not the eyes of men stare on my face, And read my falling, give me some black place Where never Sun-beam shot his wholesome light, That I may sit and pour out my sad spright Like running water, never to be known After the forced fall and sound is gone. Enter Amoret looking for Perigot. Amo. This is the bottom: speak if thou be here, My Perigot, thy Amoret; thy dear Calls on thy loved Name. Per. What art thou darest Tread these forbidden paths, where death and care Dwell on the face of darkness? Amo. 'Tis thy friend, Thy Amoret, come hither to give end To these consumings; look up gentle Boy, I have forgot those Pains and dear annoy I suffer'd for thy sake, and am content To be thy love again, why hast thou rent Those curled locks, where I have often hung Riband and Damask-roses, and have flung Waters distil'd to make thee fresh and gay, Sweeter than the Nosegayes on a Bridal day? Why dost thou cross thine Arms, and hang thy face Down to thy bosom, letting fall apace From those two little Heavens upon the ground Showers of more price, more Orient, and more round Than those that hang upon the Moons pale brow? Cease these complainings, Shepherd, I am now The same I ever was, as kind and free, And can forgive before you ask of me. Indeed I can and will. Per. So spoke my fair. O you great working powers of Earth and Air, Water and forming fire, why have you lent Your hidden vertues of so ill intent? Even such a face, so fair, so bright of hue Had Amoret, such words so smooth and new, Came flying from her tongue; such was her eye, And such the pointed sparkle that did flye Forth like a bleeding shaft; all is the same, The Robe and Buskins, painted Hook, and frame, Of all her Body. O me, Amoret! Amo. Shepherd, what means this Riddle? who hath set So strong a difference 'twixt my self and me That I am grown another? look and see The Ring thou gav'st me, and about my wrist That curious Bracelet thou thy self didst twist From those fair Tresses: knowst thou Amoret? Hath not some newer love forc'd thee forget Thy Ancient faith? Per. Still nearer to my love; These be the very words she oft did prove Upon my temper, so she still would take Wonder into her face, and silent make Signs with her head and hand, as who would say, Shepherd remember this another day. Amo. Am I not Amoret? where was I lost? Can there be Heaven, and time, and men, and most Of these unconstant? Faith where art thou fled? Are all the vows and protestations dead, The hands help up, the wishes, and the heart, Is there not one remaining, not a part Of all these to be found? why then I see Men never knew that vertue Constancie. Per. Men ever were most blessed, till crass fate Brought Love and Women forth, unfortunate To all that ever tasted of their smiles, Whose actions are all double, full of wiles: Like to the subtil Hare, that 'fore the Hounds Makes many turnings, leaps and many rounds, This way and that way, to deceive the scent Of her pursuers. Amo. 'Tis but to prevent Their speedy coming on that seek her fall, The hands of cruel men, more Bestial, And of a nature more refusing good Than Beasts themselves, or Fishes of the Flood. Per. Thou art all these, and more than nature meant, When she created all, frowns, joys, content; Extream fire for an hour, and presently Colder than sleepy poyson, or the Sea, Upon whose face sits a continual frost: Your actions ever driven to the most, Then down again as low, that none can find The rise or falling of a Womans mind. Amo. Can there be any Age, or dayes, or time, Or tongues of men, guilty so great a crime As wronging simple Maid? O Perigot, Thou that wast yesterday without a blot, That men call blessed; thou that wast the spring From whence our looser grooms drew all their best; Thou that wast alwayes just, and alwayes blest In faith and promise; thou that hadst the name Of Vertuous given thee, and made good the same Ev'en from thy Cradle; thou that wast that all That men delighted in; Oh what a fall Is this, to have been so, and now to be The only best in wrong and infamie, And I to live to know this! and by me That lov'd thee dearer than mine eyes, or that Which we esteem'd our honour, Virgin state; Dearer than Swallows love the early morn, Or Dogs of Chace the sound of merry Horn; Dearer than thou canst love thy new Love, if thou hast Another, and far dearer than the last; Dearer than thou canst love thy self, though all The self love were within thee that did fall With that coy Swain that now is made a flower, For whose dear sake, Echo weeps many a shower. And am I thus rewarded for my flame? Lov'd worthily to get a wantons name? Come thou forsaken Willow, wind my head, And noise it to the world my Love is dead: I am forsaken, I am cast away, And left for every lazy Groom to say, I was unconstant, light, and sooner lost Than the quick Clouds we see, or the chill Frost When the hot Sun beats on it. Tell me yet, Canst thou not love again thy Amoret? Per. Thou art not worthy of that blessed name, I must not know thee, fling thy wanton flame Upon some lighter blood, that may be hot With words and feigned passions: Perigot Was ever yet unstain'd, and shall not now Stoop to the meltings of a borrowed brow. Amo. Then hear me heaven, to whom I call for right, And you fair twinkling stars that crown the night; And hear me woods, and silence of this place, And ye sad hours that move a sullen pace; Hear me ye shadows that delight to dwell In horrid darkness, and ye powers of Hell, Whilst I breath out my last; I am that maid, That yet untainted Amoret, that plaid The careless prodigal, and gave away My soul to this young man, that now dares say I am a stranger, not the same, more wild; And thus with much belief I was beguil'd. I am that maid, that have delaid, deny'd, And almost scorn'd the loves of all that try'd To win me, but this swain, and yet confess I have been woo'd by many with no less Soul of affection, and have often had Rings, Belts, and Cracknels sent me from the lad That feeds his flocks down westward; Lambs and Doves By young Alexis; Daphnis sent me gloves, All which I gave to thee: nor these, nor they That sent them did I smile on, or e're lay Up to my after-memory. But why Do I resolve to grieve, and not to dye? Happy had been the stroke thou gav'st, if home; By this time had I found a quiet room Where every slave is free, and every brest That living breeds new care, now lies at rest, And thither will poor Amoret. Per. Thou must. Was ever any man so loth to trust His eyes as I? or was there ever yet Any so like as this to Amoret? For whose dear sake, I promise if there be A living soul within thee, thus to free Thy body from it. [He hurts her again. Amo. So, this work hath end: Farewel and live, be constant to thy friend That loves thee next. Enter Satyr, Perigot runs off. Satyr. See the day begins to break, And the light shoots like a streak Of subtil fire, the wind blows cold, Whilst the morning doth unfold; Now the Birds begin to rouse, And the Squirril from the boughs Leaps to get him Nuts and fruit; The early Lark that erst was mute, Carrols to the rising day Many a note and many a lay: Therefore here I end my watch, Lest the wandring swain should catch Harm, or lose himself. Amo. Ah me! Satyr. Speak again what e're thou be, I am ready, speak I say: By the dawning of the day, By the power of night and Pan, I inforce thee speak again. Amo. O I am most unhappy. Satyr. Yet more blood! Sure these wanton Swains are wode. Can there be a hand or heart Dare commit so vile a part As this Murther? By the Moon That hid her self when this was done, Never was a sweeter face: I will bear her to the place Where my Goddess keeps; and crave Her to give her life, or grave. [Exeunt. Enter Clorin. Clor. Here whilst one patient takes his rest secure I steal abroad to doe another Cure. Pardon thou buryed body of my love, That from thy side I dare so soon remove, I will not prove unconstant, nor will leave Thee for an hour alone. When I deceive My first made vow, the wildest of the wood Tear me, and o're thy Grave let out my blood; I goe by wit to cure a lovers pain Which no herb can; being done, I'le come again. [Exit. Enter Thenot. The. Poor Shepherd in this shade for ever lye, And seeing thy fair Clorins Cabin, dye: O hapless love, which being answer'd, ends; And as a little infant cryes and bends His tender Brows, when rowling of his eye He hath espy'd some thing that glisters nigh Which he would have, yet give it him, away He throws it straight, and cryes afresh to play With something else: such my affection, set On that which I should loath, if I could get. Enter Clorin. Clor. See where he lyes; did ever man but he Love any woman for her Constancie To her dead lover, which she needs must end Before she can allow him for her friend, And he himself must needs the cause destroy, For which he loves, before he can enjoy? Poor Shepherd, Heaven grant I at once may free Thee from thy pain, and keep my loyaltie: Shepherd, look up. The. Thy brightness doth amaze! So Phœbus may at noon bid mortals gaze, Thy glorious constancie appears so bright, I dare not meet the Beams with my weak sight. Clor. Why dost thou pine away thy self for me? The. Why dost thou keep such spotless constancie? Clor. Thou holy Shepherd, see what for thy sake Clorin, thy Clorin, now dare under take. [He starts up. The. Stay there, thou constant Clorin, if there be Yet any part of woman left in thee, To make thee light: think yet before thou speak Clor. See what a holy vow for thee I break. I that already have my fame far spread For being constant to my lover dead. The. Think yet, dear Clorin, of your love, how true, If you had dyed, he would have been to you. Clor. Yet all I'le lose for thee. The. Think but how blest A constant woman is above the rest. Clor. And offer up my self, here on this ground, To be dispos'd by thee. The. Why dost thou wound His heart with malice, against woman more, That hated all the Sex, but thee before? How much more pleasant had it been to me To dye, than to behold this change in thee? Yet, yet, return, let not the woman sway. Clor. Insult not on her now, nor use delay, Who for thy sake hath ventur'd all her fame. The. Thou hast not ventur'd, but bought certain shame, Your Sexes curse, foul falshood must and shall, I see, once in your lives, light on you all. I hate thee now: yet turn. Clor. Be just to me: Shall I at once both lose my fame and thee? The. Thou hadst no fame, that which thou didst like good, Was but thy appetite that sway'd thy blood. For that time to the best: for as a blast That through a house comes, usually doth cast Things out of order, yet by chance may come, And blow some one thing to his proper room; So did thy appetite, and not thy zeal, Sway thee be chance to doe some one thing well. Yet turn. Clor. Thou dost but try me if I would Forsake thy dear imbraces, for my old Love's, though he were alive: but do not fear. The. I do contemn thee now, and dare come near, And gaze upon thee; for me thinks that grace, Austeritie, which sate upon that face Is gone, and thou like others: false maid see, This is the gain of soul inconstancie. [Exit. Clor. 'Tis done, great Pan I give thee thanks for it, What art could not have heal'd, is cur'd by wit. Enter Thenot, again. The. Will ye be constant yet? will ye remove Into the Cabin to your buried Love? Clor. No let me die, but by thy side remain. The. There's none shall know that thou didst ever stain Thy worthy strictness, but shall honour'd be, And I will lye again under this tree, And pine and dye for thee with more delight, Than I have sorrow now to know the light. Clor. Let me have thee, and I'le be where thou wilt. The. Thou art of womens race, and full of guilt. Farewel all hope of that Sex, whilst I thought There was one good, I fear'd to find one naught: But since their minds I all alike espie, Henceforth I'le choose as others, by mine eye. Clor. Blest be ye powers that give such quick redress, And for my labours sent so good success. I rather choose, though I a woman be, He should speak ill of all, than die for me.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Actus Quintus. Scena Prima. Enter Priest, and old Shepherd. Priest. Shepherds, rise and shake off sleep, See the blushing Morn doth peep Through the window, whilst the Sun To the mountain tops is run, Gilding all the Vales below With his rising flames, which grow Greater by his climbing still. Up ye lazie grooms, and fill Bagg and Bottle for the field; Clasp your cloaks fast, lest they yield To the bitter North-east wind. Call the Maidens up, and find Who lay longest, that she may Goe without a friend all day; Then reward your Dogs, and pray Pan to keep you from decay: So unfold and then away. What not a Shepherd stirring? sure the grooms Have found their beds too easie, or the rooms Fill'd with such new delight, and heat, that they Have both forgot their hungry sheep, and day; Knock, that they may remember what a shame Sloath and neglect layes on a Shepherds name. Old Shep. It is to little purpose, not a swain This night hath known his lodging here, or lain Within these cotes: the woods, or some near town, That is a neighbour to the bordering Down, Hath drawn them thither, 'bout some lustie sport, Or spiced Wassel-Boul, to which resort All the young men and maids of many a cote, Whilst the trim Minstrel strikes his merry note. Priest. God pardon sin, show me the way that leads To any of their haunts. Old Shep. This to the meads, And that down to the woods. Priest. Then this for me; Come Shepherd let me crave your companie. [Exeunt. Enter Clorin, in her Cabin, Alexis, with her. Clor. Now your thoughts are almost pure, And your wound begins to cure: Strive to banish all that's vain, Lest it should break out again. Alex. Eternal thanks to thee, thou holy maid: I find my former wandring thoughts well staid Through thy wise precepts, and my outward pain By thy choice herbs is almost gone again: Thy sexes vice and vertue are reveal'd At once, for what one hurt, another heal'd. Clor. May thy grief more appease, Relapses are the worst disease: Take heed how you in thought offend, So mind and body both will mend. Enter Satyr, with Amoret. Amo. Beest thou the wildest creature of the wood, That bearst me thus away, drown'd in my blood, And dying, know I cannot injur'd be, I am a maid, let that name fight for me. Satyr. Fairest Virgin do not fear Me, that do thy body bear, Not to hurt, but heal'd to be; Men are ruder far than we. See fair Goddess in the wood, They have let out yet more blood. Some savage man hath struck her breast So soft and white, that no wild beast Durst ha' toucht asleep, or wake: So sweet, that Adder, Newte, or Snake, Would have lain from arm to arm, On her bosom to be warm All a night, and being hot, Gone away and stung her not. Quickly clap herbs to her breast; A man sure is a kind of beast. Clor. With spotless hand, on spotless brest I put these herbs to give thee rest: Which till it heal thee, will abide, If both be pure, if not, off slide. See it falls off from the wound, Shepherdess thou art not found, Full of lust. Satyr. Who would have thought it, So fair a face? Clor. Why that hath brought it. Amo. For ought I know or think, these words, my last: Yet Pan so help me as my thoughts are chast. Clor. And so may Pan bless this my cure, As all my thoughts are just and pure; Some uncleanness nigh doth lurk, That will not let my Medicines work. Satyr search if thou canst find it. Stayr. Here away me thinks I wind it, Stronger yet: Oh here they be, Here, here, in a hollow tree, Two fond mortals have I found. Clor. Bring them out, they are unsound. Enter Cloe, and Daphnis. Satyr. By the fingers thus I wring ye, To my Goddess thus I bring ye; Strife is vain, come gently in, I scented them, they're full of sin. Clor. Hold Satyr, take this Glass, Sprinkle over all the place, Purge the Air from lustfull breath, To save this Shepherdess from death, And stand you still whilst I do dress Her wound for fear the pain encrease. Sat. From this glass I throw a drop Of Crystal water on the top Of every grass, on flowers a pair: Send a fume and keep the air. Pure and wholsom, sweet and blest, Till this Virgins wound be drest. Clor. Satyr, help to bring her in. Sat. By Pan, I think she hath no sin, She is so light: lye on these leaves. Sleep that mortal sense deceives, Crown thine Eyes, and ease thy pain, Maist thou soon be well again. Clor. Satyr, bring the Shepherd near, Try him if his mind be clear. Sat. Shepherd come. Daph. My thoughts are pure. Sat. The better trial to endure. Clor. In this flame his finger thrust, Which will burn him if he lust; But if not, away will turn, As loth unspotted flesh to burn: See, it gives back, let him go, Farewel mortal, keep thee so. Sat. Stay fair Nymph, flye not so fast, We must try if you be chaste: Here's a hand that quakes for fear, Sure she will not prove so clear. Clor. Hold her finger to the flame, That will yield her praise or shame. Sat. To her doom she dares not stand, But plucks away her tender hand, And the Taper darting sends His hot beams at her fingers ends: O thou art foul within, and hast A mind, if nothing else, unchaste. Alex. Is not that Cloe? 'tis my Love, 'tis she! Cloe, fair Cloe. Clo. My Alexis. Alex. He. Clo. Let me embrace thee. Clor. Take her hence, Lest her sight disturb his sence. Alex. Take not her, take my life first. Clor. See, his wound again is burst: Keep her near, here in the Wood, Till ha' stopt these Streams of Blood. Soon again he ease shall find, If I can but still his mind: This Curtain thus I do display, To keep the piercing air away. Enter old Shepherd, and Priest. Priest. Sure they are lost for ever; 'tis in vain To find 'em out with trouble and much pain, That have a ripe desire, and forward will To flye the Company of all but ill, What shall be counsel'd now? shall we retire? Or constant follow still that first desire We had to find them? Old. Stay a little while; For if the Morning mist do not beguile My sight with shadows, sure I see a Swain; One of this jolly Troop's come back again. Enter Thenot. Pri. Dost thou not blush young Shepherd to be known, Thus without care, leaving thy flocks alone, And following what desire and present blood Shapes out before thy burning sense, for good, Having forgot what tongue hereafter may Tell to the World thy falling off, and say Thou art regardless both of good and shame, Spurning at Vertue, and a vertuous Name, And like a glorious, desperate man that buys A poyson of much price, by which he dies, Dost thou lay out for Lust, whose only gain Is foul disease, with present age and pain, And then a Grave? These be the fruits that grow In such hot Veins that only beat to know Where they may take most ease, and grow ambitious Through their own wanton fire, and pride delicious. The. Right holy Sir, I have not known this night, What the smooth face of Mirth was, or the sight Of any looseness; musick, joy, and ease, Have been to me as bitter drugs to please A Stomach lost with weakness, not a game That I am skill'd at throughly; nor a Dame, Went her tongue smoother than the feet of Time, Her beauty ever living like the Rime Our blessed Tityrus did sing of yore, No, were she more enticing than the store Of fruitful Summer, when the loaden Tree Bids the faint Traveller be bold and free, 'Twere but to me like thunder 'gainst the bay, Whose lightning may enclose but never stay Upon his charmed branches; such am I Against the catching flames of Womans eye. Priest. Then wherefore hast thou wandred? The. 'Twas a Vow. That drew me out last night, which I have now Strictly perform'd, and homewards go to give Fresh pasture to my Sheep, that they may live. Pri. 'Tis good to hear ye, Shepherd, if the heart In this well sounding Musick bear his part. Where have you left the rest? The. I have not seen, Since yesternight we met upon this green To fold our Flocks up, any of that train; Yet have I walkt these Woods round, and have lain All this same night under an aged Tree, Yet neither wandring Shepherd did I see, Or Shepherdess, or drew into mine ear The sound of living thing, unless it were The Nightingale among the thick leav'd spring That sits alone in sorrow, and doth sing Whole nights away in mourning, or the Owl, Or our great enemy that still doth howl Against the Moons cold beams. Priest. Go and beware Of after falling. The. Father 'tis my care. [Exit Thenot. Enter Daphnis. Old. Here comes another Stragler, sure I see A Shame in this young Shepherd. Daphnis! Daph. He. Pri. Where hast thou left the rest, that should have been Long before this, grazing upon the green Their yet imprison'd flocks? Daph. Thou holy man, Give me a little breathing till I can Be able to unfold what I have seen; Such horrour that the like hath never been Known to the ear of Shepherd: Oh my heart Labours a double motion to impart So heavy tidings! You all know the Bower Where the chast Clorin lives, by whose great power Sick men and Cattel have been often cur'd, There lovely Amoret that was assur'd To lusty Perigot, bleeds out her life, Forc'd by some Iron hand and fatal knife; And by her young Alexis. Enter Amaryllis running from her Sullen Shepherd. Amar. If there be Ever a Neighbour Brook, or hollow tree, Receive my Body, close me up from lust That follows at my heels; be ever just, Thou god of Shepherds, Pan, for her dear sake That loves the Riversbrinks, and still doth shake In cold remembrance of thy quick pursuit: Let me be made a reed, and ever mute, Nod to the waters fall, whilst every blast Sings through my slender leaves that I was chast. Pri. This is a night of wonder, Amaryll Be comforted, the holy gods are still Revengers of these wrongs. Amar. Thou blessed man, Honour'd upon these plains, and lov'd of Pan, Hear me, and save from endless infamie My yet unblasted Flower, Virginitie: By all the Garlands that have crown'd that head, By the chaste office, and the Marriage bed That still is blest by thee, by all the rights Due to our gods; and by those Virgin lights That burn before his Altar, let me not Fall from my former state to gain the blot That never shall be purg'd: I am not now That wanton Amaryllis: here I vow To Heaven, and thee grave Father, if I may 'Scape this unhappy Night, to know the Day, To live a Virgin, never to endure The tongues, or Company of men impure. I hear him come, save me. Pri. Retire a while Behind this Bush, till we have known that vile Abuser of young Maidens. Enter Sullen. Sul. Stay thy pace, Most loved Amaryllis, let the Chase Grow calm and milder, flye me not so fast, I fear the pointed Brambles have unlac'd Thy golden Buskins; turn again and see Thy Shepherd follow, that is strong and free, Able to give thee all content and ease. I am not bashful, Virgin, I can please At first encounter, hug thee in mine arm, And give thee many Kisses, soft and warm As those the Sun prints on the smiling Cheek Of Plums, or mellow Peaches; I am sleek And smooth as Neptune, when stern Eolus Locks up his surly Winds, and nimbly thus Can shew my active Youth; why dost thou flye? Remember Amaryllis, it was I That kill'd Alexis for thy sake, and set An everlasting hate 'twixt Amoret And her beloved Perigot: 'twas I That drown'd her in the Well, where she must lye Till Time shall leave to be; then turn again, Turn with thy open arms, and clip the Swain That hath perform'd all this, turn, turn I say: I must not be deluded. Pri. Monster stay, Thou that art like a Canker to the State Thou liv'st and breath'st in, eating with debate Through every honest bosome, forcing still The Veins of any that may serve thy Will, Thou that hast offer'd with a sinful hand To seize upon this Virgin that doth stand Yet trembling here. Sull. Good holiness declare, What had the danger been, if being hare I had embrac'd her, tell me by your Art, What coming wonders would that sight impart? Pri. Lust, and a branded Soul. Sull. Yet tell me more, Hath not our Mother Nature for her store And great encrease, said it is good and just, And wills that every living Creature must Beget his like? Pri. Ye are better read than I, I must confess, in blood and Lechery. Now to the Bower, and bring this Beast along, Where he may suffer Penance for his wrong. [Exeunt. Enter Perigot with his hands bloody. Per. Here will I wash it in this mornings dew, Which she on every little grass doth strew In silver drops against the Sun's appear: 'Tis holy water, and will make me clear. My hands will not be cleans'd. My wronged Love, If thy chaste spirit in the air yet move, Look mildly down on him that yet doth stand All full of guilt, thy blood upon his hand, And though I struck thee undeservedly, Let my revenge on her that injur'd thee Make less a fault which I intended not, And let these dew drops wash away my spot. It will not cleanse. O to what sacred Flood Shall I resort to wash away this blood? Amid'st these Trees the holy Clorin dwells In a low Cabin of cut Boughs, and heals All Wounds; to her I will my self address, And my rash faults repentantly confess; Perhaps she'll find a means by Art or Prayer, To make my hand with chaste blood stained, fair: That done, not far hence underneath some Tree, I'll have a little Cabin built, since she Whom I ador'd is dead, there will I give My self to strictness, and like Clorin live. [Exit. The Curtain is drawn, Clorin appears sitting in the Cabin, Amoret sitting on the one side of her, Alexis and Cloe on the other, the Satyr standing by. Clo. Shepherd, once more your blood is staid, Take example by this Maid, Who is heal'd ere you be pure, So hard it is lewd lust to cure. Take heed then how you turn your eye On each other lustfully: And Shepherdess take heed lest you Move his willing eye thereto; Let no wring, nor pinch, nor smile Of yours his weaker sense beguile. Is your Love yet true and chaste, And for ever so to last? Alex. I have forgot all vain desires, All looser thoughts, ill tempred fires, True Love I find a pleasant fume, Whose moderate heat can ne'r consume. Clo. And I a new fire feel in me, Whose chaste flame is not quencht to be. Clor. Join your hands with modest touch, And for ever keep you such. Enter Perigot. Per. Yon is her Cabin, thus far off I'll stand, And call her forth; for my unhallowed hand I dare not bring so near yon sacred place. Clorin come forth, and do a timely grace To a poor Swain. Clo. What art thou that dost call? Clorin is ready to do good to all: Come near. Peri. I dare not. Clor. Satyr, see Who it is that calls on me. Sat. There at hand, some Swain doth stand, Stretching out a bloudy hand. Peri. Come Clorin, bring thy holy waters clear, To wash my hand. Clo. What wonders have been here. To night? stretch forth thy hand young Swain, Wash and rub it whilest I rain Holy water. Peri. Still you pour, But my hand will never scower. Clor. Satyr, bring him to the Bower, We will try the Soveraign power Of other waters. Satyr. Mortal, sure 'Tis the Blood of Maiden pure That stains thee so. [The Satyr leadeth him to the Bower, where he spieth Amoret, and kneeling down, she knoweth him. Peri. What e're thou be, Be'st thou her spright, or some divinitie, That in her shape thinks good to walk this grove, Pardon poor Perigot. Amor. I am thy love, Thy Amoret, for evermore thy love: Strike once more on my naked breast, I'le prove As constant still. O couldst thou love me yet; How soon should I my former griefs forget! Peri. So over-great with joy, that you live, now I am, that no desire of knowing how Doth seize me; hast thou still power to forgive? Amo. Whilest thou hast power to love, or I to live; More welcome now than hadst thou never gone Astray from me. Peri. And when thou lov'st alone And not I, death, or some lingring pain That's worse, light on me. Clor. Now your stain This perhaps will cleanse again; See the blood that erst did stay, With the water drops away. All the powers again are pleas'd, And with this new knot appeas'd. Joyn your hands, and rise together, Pan be blest that brought you hither. Enter Priest, and Old Shephered. Clor. Go back again what ere thou art, unless Smooth Maiden thoughts possess thee, do not press This hallowed ground. Go Satyr, take his hand, And give him present trial. Satyr. Mortal stand, Till by fire I have made known Whether thou be such a one, That mayst freely tread this place. Hold thy hand up; never was More untainted flesh than this. Fairest, he is full of bliss. Clor. Then boldly speak, why dost thou seek this place? Priest. First, honour'd Virgin, to behold thy face Where all good dwells that is: Next for to try The truth of late report was given to me: Those Shepherds that have met with foul mischance, Through much neglect, and more ill governance, Whether the wounds they have may yet endure The open Air, or stay a longer cure. And lastly, what the doom may be shall light Upon those guilty wretches, through whose spight All this confusion fell: For to this place, Thou holy Maiden, have I brought the race Of these offenders, who have freely told, Both why, and by what means they gave this bold Attempt upon their lives. Clor. Fume all the ground, And sprinkle holy water, for unsound And foul infection 'gins to fill the Air: It gathers yet more strongly; take a pair Of Censors fill'd with Frankincense and Mirrh, Together with cold Camphyre: quickly stir Thee, gentle Satyr, for the place begins To sweat and labour with the abhorred sins Of those offenders,; let them not come nigh, For full of itching slame and leprosie Their very souls are, that the ground goes back, And shrinks to feel the sullen weight of black And so unheard of venome; hie thee fast Thou holy man, and banish from the chast These manlike monsters, let them never more Be known upon these downs, but long before The next Suns rising, put them from the sight And memory of every honest wight: Be quick in expedition, lest the sores Of these weak Patients break into new gores. [Ex. Priest. Per. My dear, dear Amoret, how happy are Those blessed pairs, in whom a little jar Hath bred an everlasting love, too strong For time, or steel, or envy to do wrong? How do you feel your hurts? Alas poor heart, How much I was abus'd; give me the smart For it is justly mine. Amo. I do believe. It is enough dear friend, leave off to grieve, And let us once more in despight of ill Give hands and hearts again. Per. With better will Than e're I went to find in hottest day Cool Crystal of the Fountain, to allay My eager thirst: may this band never break. Hear us O Heaven, Amo. Be constant. Per. Else Pan wreak, With bouble vengeance, my disloyalty; Let me not dare to know the company Of men, or any more behold those eyes. Amo. Thus Shepherd with a kiss all envy dyes. Enter Priest. Priest. Bright Maid, I have perform'd your will, the Swain In whom such heat and black rebellions raign Hath undergone your sentence, and disgrace: Only the Maid I have reserv'd, whose face Shews much amendment, many a tear doth fall In sorrow of her fault, great fair recal Your heavy doom, in hope of better daies, Which I dare promise; once again upraise Her heavy Spirit that near drowned lyes In self consuming care that never dyes, Clor. I am content to pardon, call her in; The Air grows cool again, and doth begin To purge it self, how bright the day doth show After this stormy Cloud? go Satyr, go, And with this Taper boldly try her hand, If she be pure and good, and firmly stand To be so still, we have perform'd a work Worthy the Gods themselves. [Satyr brings Amaryllis in. Satyr. Come forward Maiden, do not lurk Nor hide your face with grief and shame, Now or never get a name That may raise thee, and recure All thy life that was impure: Hold your hand unto the flame, If thou beest a perfect dame, Or hast truely vow'd to mend, This pale fire will be thy friend. See the Taper hurts her not. Go thy wayes, let never spot Henceforth seize upon thy blood. Thank the Gods and still be good. Clor. Young Shepherdess now ye are brought again To Virgin state, be so, and so remain To thy last day, unless the faithful love Of some good Shepherd force thee to remove; Than labour to be true to him, and live As such a one, that ever strives to give A blessed memory to after time. Be famous for your good, not for your crime. Now holy man, I offer up again These patients full of health, and free from pain: Keep them from after ills, be ever near Unto their actions, teach them how to clear The tedious way they pass through, from suspect, Keep them from wronging others, or neglect Of duty in themselves, correct the bloud With thrifty bits and labour, let the floud, Or the next neighbouring spring give remedy To greedy thirst, and travel not the tree That hangs with wanton clusters, let let not wine, Unless in sacrifice, or rites divine, Be ever known of Shepherd, have a care Thou man of holy life. Now do not spare Their faults through much remissness, nor forget To cherish him, whose many pains and swet Hath giv'n increase, and added to the downs. Sort all your Shepherds from the lazy clowns That feed their Heifers in the budded Brooms: Teach the young Maidens strictness, that the grooms May ever fear to tempt their blowing youth; Banish all complements, but single truth From every tongue, and every Shepherds heart, Let them still use perswading, but no Art: Thus holy Priest, I wish to thee and these, All the best goods and comforts that may please. Alex. And all those blessings Heaven did ever give, We pray upon this Bower may ever live. Priest. Kneel every Shepherd, whilest with powerful hand I bless your after labours, and the Land You feed your flocks upon. Great Pan defend you From misfortune, and amend you, Keep you from those dangers still, That are followed by your will, Give ye means to know at length All your riches, all your strength, Cannot keep your foot from falling To lewd lust, that still is calling At your Cottage, till his power Bring again that golden hour Of peace and rest to every soul. May his care of you controul All diseases, sores or pain That in after time may raign Either in your flocks or you, Give ye all affections new, New desires, and tempers new, That ye may be ever true. Now rise and go, and as ye pass away Sing to the God of Sheep, that happy lay, That honest Dorus taught ye, Dorus, he That was the soul and god of melodie. [Shepherds] The SONG. [They all Sing. All ye woods, and trees and bowers, All you vertues and ye powers That inhabit in the lakes, In the pleasant springs or brakes, Move your feet To our sound, Whilest we greet All this ground, With his honour and his name That defends our flocks from blame. He is great, and he is just, He is ever good, and must Thus be honour'd: Daffadillies, Roses, Pinks, and loved Lillies, Let us fling, Whilest we sing, Ever holy, Ever holy, Ever honour'd ever young, This great Pan is ever sung. [Exeunt. Satyr. Thou divinest, fairest, brightest, Thou must powerful Maid, and whitest, Thou most vertuous and most blessed, Eyes of stars, and golden tressed Like Apollo, tell me sweetest What new service now is meetest For the Satyr? shall I stray In the middle Air, and stay The sayling Rack, or nimbly take Hold by the Moon, and gently make Sute to the pale Queen of night For a beam to give thee light? Shall I dive into the Sea, And bring thee Coral, making way Through the rising waves that fall In snowie fleeces; dearest, shall I catch the wanton Fawns, or Flyes, Whose woven wings the Summer dyes Of many colours? get thee fruit? Or steal from Heaven old Orpheus Lute? All these I'le venture for, and more, To do her service all these woods adore. Clor. No other service, Satyr, but thy watch About these thickets, lest harmless people catch Mischief or sad mischance. Satyr. Holy Virgin, I will dance Round about these woods as quick As the breaking light, and prick Down the Lawns, and down the vails Faster than the Wind-mill sails. So I take my leave, and pray All the comforts of the day, Such as Phœbus heat doth send On the earth, may still befriend Thee, and this arbour. Cle. And to thee, All thy Masters love be free. [Exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">To my Friend Master John Fletcher upon his Faithfull Shepherdess. I know too well, that, no more than the man That travels through the burning Desarts, can When he is beaten with the raging Sun, Half smother'd in the dust, have power to run From a cool River, which himself doth find, E're he be slack'd; no more can he whose mind Joyes in the Muses, hold from that delight, When nature, and his full thoughts bid him write: Yet wish I those whom I for friends have known, To sing their thoughts to no ears but their own. Why should the man, whose wit ne'r had a stain, Upon the publick Stage present his vain, And make a thousand men in judgment sit, To call in question his undoubted wit, Scarce two of which can understand the laws Which they should judge by, nor the parties cause? Among the rout there is not one that hath In his own censure an explicite faith; One company knowing they judgement lack, Ground their belief on the next man in black: Others, on him that makes signs, and is mute, Some like as he does in the fairest sute, He at his Mistress doth, and she by chance: Nor want there those, who as the Boy doth dance Between the Acts, will censure the whole Play; Some if the Wax-lights be not new that day; But multitudes there are whose judgement goes Headlong according to the Actors cloathes. For this, these publick things and I, agree So ill, that but to do a right for thee, I had not been perswaded to have hurl'd These few, ill spoken lines, into the world, Both to be read, and censur'd of, by those, Whose very reading makes Verse senseless Prose: Such as must spend above an hour, to spell A Challenge on a Post, to know it well: But since it was thy hap to throw away Much wit, for which the people did not pay, Because they saw it not, I not dislike This second publication, which may strike Their consciences, to see the thing they scorn'd, To be with so much wit and Art adorn'd. Besides one vantage more in this I see, Your censurers now must have the qualitie Of reading, which I am afraid is more Than half your shrewdest Judges had before. Fr. Beaumont.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">To the worthy Author Mr. Jo. Fletcher. The wise, and many headed Bench, that sits Upon the Life, and Death of Playes, and Wits, (Compos'd of Gamester, Captain, Knight, Knight's man, Lady, or Pusill, that wears mask or fan, Velvet, or Taffata cap, rank'd in the dark With the shops Foreman, or some such brave spark, That may judge for his six-pence) had, before They saw it half, damn'd thy whole Play, and more; Their motives were, since it had not to doe With vices, which they look'd for, and came to. I, that am glad, thy Innocence was thy Guilt, And wish that all the Muses blood were spilt In such a Martyrdome, to vex their eyes, Do crown thy murdred Poeme: which shall rise A glorified work to Time, when Fire, Or mothes shall eat, what all these Fools admire. BEN. JONSON.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">This Dialogue newly added, was spoken by way of Prologue to both their Majesties, at the first acting of this Pastoral at Somersethouse on Twelfth-night, 1633. Priest. A broiling Lamb on Pans chief Altar lies, My Wreath, my Censor, Virge, and Incense by: But I delay'd the pretious Sacrifice, To shew thee here, a Gentle Deity. Nymph. Nor was I to thy sacred Summons slow, Hither I came as swift as th'Eagles wing, Or threatning shaft from vext Dianaes bow, To see this Islands God; the worlds best King. Priest. Bless then that Queen, that doth his eyes invite And ears, t'obey her Scepter, half this night. Nymph. Let's sing such welcomes, as shall make Her sway Seem easie to Him, though it last till day. Welcom as Peace t'unwalled Cities, when Famine and Sword leave them more graves than men. As Spring to Birds, or Noon-dayes Sun to th'old Poor mountain Muscovite congeal'd with cold. As Shore toth' Pilot in a safe known Coast When's Card is broken and his Rudder lost.</field>
   </doc>
</add>