<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Jones, Ernest Charles, 1819-1868</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Jones, Ernest Charles, 1819-1868</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">jones ernest charles 1819 1868</field>
      <field name="author_text">Jones, Ernest Charles, 1819-1868</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1830's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V3.0349.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1836</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460721</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Student of Padua ; A Domestic Tragedy. In Five Acts</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Student of Padua ; A Domestic Tragedy. In Five Acts</field>
      <field name="title_facet">student of padua</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">student of padua</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Student of Padua ; A Domestic Tragedy. In Five Acts</field>
      <field name="year_display">1836</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1836</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1836</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460721&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460721&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Jones, Ernest Charles, 1819-1868&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;jones ernest charles 1819 1868&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Student of Padua ; A Domestic Tragedy. In Five Acts&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;student of padua&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1836&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1836&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Jones, Ernest Charles&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1819&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1868&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Student of Padua&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Domestic Tragedy. In Five Acts&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed by William Henry Cox&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1836&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3873059-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv30349&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Student of Padua&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Domestic Tragedy. In Five Acts&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 243 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: The student of Padua.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1836.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Unknown.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE STUDENT OF PADUA. A DOMESTIC TRAGEDY. In Five Acts.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DRAMATIS PERSONÆ. Lorenzo, a Venetian Merchant. Julian, his Son, a Student of Padua. Lodoro, a Venetian Merchant. Augustus, his Son. Frederick St. Cyr, a dissipated Poet. Angelo, a Painter. Antonio, a Venetian Gentleman. Barbarigo, a Venetian Nobleman. Galeno, a Physician. Giacomo, Servant to Lorenzo. Peter Servant to Lodoro. Beppo Servant to Lodoro. Officer, Guards, Waiters, Serenaders, Gondoliers, &amp;c. Lorenzo's Wife. Bianca, Daughter to Lodoro. Her Mother, and Wife to Lodoro. Maria, her Attendant.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE, during the first three Acts, in Venice; during part of fourth Act, a forest on the Euganean Hills; and during fifth Act, the Isle of Ledo, near Venice.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PREFACE. Venice. As all readers most unreasonably expect from all writers the reasons why anything is written, the Author of the following drama considers himself bound to explain, that the work was composed during an autumnal residence here, to beguile the tedium of convalescence; and that a few copies of it are now printed and circulated among his friends, to gratify his pleasure— which he is heterodox enough to believe, every man has a right, in a lawful extent, to do. As, therefore, he confesses the book to be a creation of his own humour, and in his own “vein;” as it violates the acknowledged proprieties of the drama, in not always displaying virtue rewarded, and iniquity hanged; as, scorning to pamper to the delicate sensibilities of hypocrites and slaves—it ventures to expose the truth, and develope such scenes as are but too faithful to the highly civilized and, consequently, highly vitiated conditions of the human race; and, as its Author holds in perfect contempt and absolute ridicule, all critical axioms and regulations for the drama, which was designed to pourtray the most irregular, and not the most ordinary passions and actions of men—of course, he neither anticipates the support of the periodical literature of England nor fears its abuse. However, in saying this, he begs not to be mistaken, for “Some fellow, Who, having been praised for bluntness, doth affect A saucy roughness; and constrains the garb, Quite from his nature; he cannot flatter, he! An honest mind and plain, he must speak truth, An' they will take it, so; if not he's plain.” To be plain, he professes to be neither more honest nor straight-forward than his neighbours, neither less of an egotist nor more of a fool; neither less desirous of the admiration of the good, nor more covetous of the adulation of the bad, than are all the rest of his race. He is neither so young as to be deceived by the chimeras of a heated and sufficiently luxurient imagination, into fancying his pen the open sesame to the gates of immortality; nor so old as to despair of being rewarded according to his deserts. He is neither so wise as to underrate the preciousness of worldly honor, nor so insane as to build the castle of his happiness on the “baseless fabric” of such a dream. He is neither so rich as to wish to print his own effusions for the sake of seeing them adorn his library shelves in the dignity of morocco and gold; nor so poor as to be unable to defray the expense of publishing what a bookseller would, very probably, indignantly shelve. He is neither anxious for the romantic notoriety of a “great unknown;” nor desirous to remain in anonymous obscurity. He is neither greatly given to hunger after fame; nor is he wholly divested of an honorable appetite for such a bon bouche. He is neither so coxcombical as to believe that his few readers will be very inquisitive after his identity; nor so infra. dig. as not to assure himself that some would like to know his “local habitation and his name.” He is neither so bilious and melancholy as to be entirely adapted to the inditing of sonnets “to his mistress' eyebrow;” nor so light-haired and sanguine, as to love beef-steaks and port wine before all things on earth. He is neither so much on the west of the Alps, as to bother himself vastly about the fussy observations of the press; nor so located among savages as not to feast his gratified senses on the many valuable papers that exalt the journals of Great Britain above all others in the world. He does not wish to be regarded as a foreigner; and yet cares little if not called English. In fact, he is just a proper man of the world with, perhaps, more of the insolence of the Britain than the politeness of the Gaul. He is femininely capricious—inasmuch as he is not resolved whether this work shall end his Apollonic aspirations, or herald in a series of consecutive dramas! And he is masculinely animal, inasmuch as he may feel himself so self-satisfied and comfortable on the ottoman of the East, as altogether to neglect the nobler energies becoming a native of the “Isles of the West.” That he will have his share of praise, and his modicum of detraction, whether merited or not, he is as perfectly assured as he is that there are Whig and Tory newspapers, clever and silly gentlemen, good natured patrons, and yellow visaged critics—and that, according to the kneading of the gold, silver, brass, and clay, in the Baal-god of English adoration—the Press—so will be the proportions of excellent material, or horrible trash, dragged out from the obscurity of this Drama, and held forth for the gape of admiration or the finger of scorn. Being no cynic, the Author would like to please all; but being no idiot, he knows he cannot do it. Being a lover of the drama, and an admirer of its moral excellence, he naturally endeavours to induce the world to worship at his shrine! but knowing the world to consist of antagonist elements curiously admixed, he is perfectly aware that he can never achieve his end. He, himself, pretending to be a poet, advances poetry to the very summit of the intellectual pyramid reared up through many ages by the mind of man; but being persuaded that the comprehension and judgment of mankind differ as materially as their physical senses of sight, smell, and taste vary in remote portions of the globe—he is not surprised to perceive that a multitude of revilers will consider him madly worshipping an insignificant devil, instead of a mighty god. The Magnus Apollo of one person's veneration being the golden beetle of another's praise, he does not “fool himself to the bent” of presuming that the reader will fall down at the Author's shrine; whilst at the same time, he consoles himself with the reflection, that, as every faith has its followers, so converts may be made, even to his creed. He does not flatter himself that this play will ever be performed; yet he cannot deny that he considers it worthy of a trial. He conscientiously believes that the present managerial system is very bad, yet he honestly confesses that he does not know a better. He had no actors in view when he drew his characters from nature, yet he is mightily mistaken if Mr. Macready could not impersonate the impassioned hero, and much deceived if many of our performers could not nobly support the play. He does not say this out of flattery to any person, yet he does not withhold that many deserve the compliment. Thus then, Gentle Reader, being, like yourself, an anomily of contradictions, and having made as honest, if not as polite an obeisance, as other Authors, he begs to present the following pages to your admiration, or abjuration—not questioning your judgment any more than he does your right to judge.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. SCENE I. A Hall in Lorenzo's House. Enter Frederick St. Cyr and Giacomo, meeting. Gia. —Good morrow, Signor Frederick St. Cyr. Fred. —Ah ha! good Giacomo! How goes the world? Gia. —Roundwards. Fred. No, backwards. Come, is Julian home? Gia. —Yes, unexpectedly— Fred. I expected it. Gia. —You expected him? Why no one knew his coming; He only knew't himself some hour ago. Fred. —Still, I expected it. Gia. Expected what? Fred. —That Julian, like a gust of wind, would come And ruffle up your feathers ere you knew't. Gia. —Ay, signor, but his father scolds most terribly. Fred. —So does a housewife, when, on washing day, It rains; but can she stay the elements? Anger's the steam of petty minds, and must Escape, or else there's danger that they burst. Look you, my friend, your worthy master wishes To thrust on Julian the profession of A learned doctor. Now this youth is warn'd Of nature to recoil from such a calling, Just as the skin shrinks up from cold. How think you, Having attain'd an age to judge and reason, That he will 'bide the rebuke of his own conscience Without demurring?—pooh, pooh! Does his father Wish that his son were such an arrant fool? Gia. —In sooth, I am no reasoner on these things; But Julian surely will not be a doctor. Fred. —Why should he? we're not fashion'd all alike To fit the customs of society. Lorenzo is a worthy goldbeater— His mind contracted as a grain of metal: His son's imagination as expansive As the rich leaf spread o'er its widest surface. One grows out of the other, differing as The ocean from the river. Come—I'm preaching, Julian was born a poet, and his father May strangle, but he cannot change his nature. Enter Lorenzo suddenly. Lor. —Good morrow, sir! You speak your feelings freely. Fred. —I am a kind of forager upon Society, and make my manners fit Me like my gloves and jerkin—easily. Lor. (Bowing.) —And what procures my humble roof this honor? Fred. —(Aside. What an icicle politeness is!) Why, sir, Hem! How is Julian, sir? Lor. O very well. Fred. —He makes some stay? Lor. Some six or seven hours. My pleasure doth command him hence to-night. Fred. —So soon? Lor. Why not? I'll see no son of mine Squandering another hour in idleness. He's spent too many precious ones in Venice With those, whose company hath profited His purse, and time, and reputation, little. Fred. —(Aside. Thus ever strikes the coward with a hint.) Lor. I much regret that business calls me from The etiquette of entertaining you. Fred. —Good morning, signor! Lor. —(Aside. Curse his insolence!) Good morrow, sir. (Aside. He'll surely now be gone.) Fred. —Good morrow, sir, and pleasant calculations Over the counter. (Appears intensely looking at some pictures.) Lor. (Aside. Heavens! he'll drive me mad!) Good morning, signor! Fred. Why, signor, I thought you gone. Not on 'Change yet? (Looking at a clock), Past the hour! How's stock? Consols? What news from India? Lor. (Aside. Cursed puppy!) Fred. —The war with Tunis, people say, hath raised The gold dust. But such news is Greek to me. Lor. —So long as you have gold to spend. Fred. True! Clever! Lor. —(Aside. Why the young monkey laughs at me.) Fred. Ha! ha! Yes witty! Were I doge, I'd melt the crown To coin dubloons. There's nothing, sir, like gold. Lor. —Young gentleman, I do not understand you! Exit. Fred. —Oh yes, you do! ha! Giacomo! Why, fool! What ghost hath crossed your wonder? Gia. Master Frederick, He's foaming at the mouth with passion! Fred. Well— Have you not seen the Adriatic foam And calm again? An old man's anger is Not quite so terrible. Bell rings violently. Gia. Oh! coming, sir! Coming, sir! coming, sir! (Going.) Fred. Giacomo! Gia. Sir, coming! Exit. Fred. —By Jove! he lords it most magnanimously Over his subject slaves, this worthy goldbeater! Gad! if his wife, and son, and two domestics, Can find such occupation for his wrath— What would the nation do an' he were Doge? Well, heav'n compassionate a passionate man! But where does Julian bury all his cares?— I'll hunt the young recluse out. Julian, hey! I'd rather range the desert than inhabit This garnished solitude. Hey! Julian! Julian! SCENE II. —A Room in Lorenzo's House. Lorenzo and Julian. Lor. —Enough! Now, mark me, Julian! you remember I brook no opposition from my children: By heaven, I will not! I have rear'd you as A chosen vessel to contain my hopes; But if you thus leak out my good advice, And waste my dear and cherish'd expectations, You cease to be a child of mine for ever. Jul. —Your pardon, sir! I am unfitted for This single occupation which your love Provides me; but in all things else, I am Your most obedient son. Pray hear my reason! Lor. —Reason! What reason is there in deriding And tampering with a parent's wish, incurring Thus censure and rebuke from all our neighbours? Jul. —The censure of the busy, who decide On things they cannot comprehend, by me Is estimated lighter than the air. I cannot mould my fortunes to receive The impress of each idle fool's opinion. Lor. —Young man, this arrogance that thus outbraves The world's opinion, is an earnest of An evil inclination. Jul. Nay! I know Good men's approval is a great reward: And, richly merited and fairly won, Outshines the stars of all nobility! To this I have aspired, and therefore scorn All intermedlers, as I spurn the dirt. Lor. —You must submit to many things perforce, Like all the world, against your vagrant taste. Would you lie down i'the sun, and idly wait 'Till fortune come to you? Behold your old Companions all! how they're dispersed to bring The produce of their labours home at night To Venice, here, their great and native hive! Why would you be the only drone? Jul. The drone! You do not, or you will not, understand me. Lor. —I know I've chosen you a rich profession. D'you weigh its honors rightly? Jul. Ay, its crown Of laurels would be weeds and thorns to me! Worse—poison, that would eat into my brain And launch me down a maniac to my tomb! Lor. —Have you no rev'rence for your teacher's words Of promise if you persevere?—For, mark, sir! Lacking that, genius and good luck must fail To grasp the topmost plumes of eminence— These promise and predict success to you! Jul. —They judge like people who esteem the moon And stars no bigger than they seem at distance. Is't likely, they, who cannot plumb the source From whence springs up the tide of what we do, Can prophecy how high, how far, or wide The stream of capability may flow? O, sir! if we were speaking of a thing Tangible, open, visible—my purse, My dress, my manner—I should bow to years And riper judgments; but of what pertains To th'secret workings of another's mind, Presumption's self should not pretend to speak. Lor. —Command then must assume the right to act! Jul. —No! do yourself not such a foul injustice; Obey your reason, not your passion! O! My father! If you knew how I revere You with a child's affection, you would pause E'er thus you snap the ties of my young love. I must speak freely. I can brave your anger, But not for all the wealth of Crœsus, will I forge my honor to a paltry lie. Lor. —You're most grandiloquent in advocacy Of this romantic beggary. It seems A poet's rags have some peculiar charm. You cannot both be idle and be rich. Jul. —Poverty is an evil of the mind— A terror of imagination only. The poor in circumstance, are frequently The wealthiest in the blessings of content— And oh! content's a treasure of such price, That only he can count its value, who Possesses this inestimable gem. Lor. —You choose your destiny then, beggary, And th'applause of empty-headed fashion! You deem it wiser than t'accompany me On the Rialto, where Lorenzo's son Would see a thousand bonnets doff'd to him, And ev'ry bonnet lin'd with gold and gems. Jul. —Yet, each is happy in his own degree, The Arab and the senator of Venice. There's many a heart beneath th'imperial star Of empire, born to perish miserably; While many a savage roams the wilderness, With thoughts and feelings that would grace a throne! The poet's worldly sacrifice is great, His sorrows many, but his joys surpass Their gloominess, eclipsing with the light Of immortality the storms of life: And th' recompense of self-approval is A gorgeous sun-set for the eve of life! Lor. —Look at your dissipated, worthless friends, Angelo, and St. Cyr.—what has the painting Or poetry of one or other won For them, but poverty, neglect, and scorn? Jul. —With which, perchance, they're happier than arrayed In all that wealth the meanest mind acquires. But, let us grant these men unmeritorious. The crime of one renders not others guilty. Have we no wicked and dishonest senators? Unthrifty merchants? lying lawyers? quacks? And hypocritical, blaspheming priests? There's imposition every where on earth! Except against a calling for its followers; And we must throw off all things old, and find New occupations out for honest men. Lor. —Enough! such argument is useless, when The resolution's taken. Well you know I'll brook no opposition in my children. You must obey, or be no son of mine! Jul. —But hear me, sir! I only ask your ear For my most urgent argument. Lor. (Going.) Peace, peace! To night adjourn to Padua! There reflect Whether obedience and a father's friendship, Or disobedience and his enmity, Be wiser choice. Jul. (Aside. A father's enmity!) For God's sake listen, sir! Lor. I will not listen! A parent's duty is command—a child Implicitly obeys, or from that hour It disobeys, it is no child of mine. Exit. Jul. (Following.) But father! sir! Nay, sir! (Returning.) O God of heav'n! What most fantastic tricks are these for nature To play upon us? Why, his anger hangs A lie upon the affection of his blessing! I used to think, that, with the very beast, The bonds of blood were something more than cobwebs, To perish at the touch of interest! O shame upon humanity! that gold, Opinion, selfishness, a gross desire, Usurps the throne of our affections, and Cancels the law heav'n wrote upon our hearts. O, Venice, Venice! flaunting in thy robes Of splendour and untold magnificence! Look at thy image in this old man's avarice, And blush to think thou hast exchang'd the impulse Of virgin nature for a painted cheek, And hollow breast of harlotry! O shame! Shame on us all that cannot elevate Our souls above the dust we tenant!—Shame! Enter Giacomo. Gia. —Sir, sir, sir! Signor Julian, Jul. What mystery? Gia. —O, sir, here's Signor St. Cyr here i'the garden. He has been waiting these two hours, and, God knows, they were two hours too long for him; but all, as he says, out of pure affection for you. But he's talked such nonsense to the parrots, that one would suppose he hadn't a care. Jul. —Out, garrulous old fool; what know you of his cares? Gia. —Oh, know, sir—of course I know nothing—only— Jul. —Speak to the point, and stand not mouthing there Your borrowed wit. Gia. You stop my mouth— Jul. Peace, peace! We must attend on our own exegencies, Or leave our urgent wants untended—hence! Exit. Gia. —Hoity toity! Why how choleric be all these college squibs! Well, well, when their blood runs as slowly as mine—some of 'em though will never live to to try it, or they'd find their words would not slip off the tongue-end quite so merrily. Old servants now o'days are old fools. All old things are old humbugs, and a basket bottom stuck on four bulrushes, is a better seat than our grandfather's chair. Ah! we shall see these changes of all the old coinage turn out some brass farthings. But Julian's a good boy. As for that St. Cyr, master says he's a bad soil to sow good precepts on. I'm sure he's a moist climate, and yet as little acquainted with water as a Venetian might be. Julian calls me ass, when I tell him this. Well, there's many an ass' head between short ears. Bell rings violently. Ay, that's my master's ring. The very bells get a benefit when he's in a passion. I could tell him, if I dare, that he'll drive dear Julian to desperation, and then what will become of us? Why the very cats and dogs seem better pleas'd when Julian's at home. I never heard a tongue that didn't wag in his praise, except master's, and he thinks the best education for a child is, to abuse and scold him from morning till night. Bell rings violently again. Coming, sir!—Well, such passions as these bring their own punishments, or I'm much mistaken. Exit. SCENE III. —A garden behind Lorenzo's house. Julian and Frederick. Fred. —Come, come, you manufacture and invent your cares, And fancied griefs are worse than actual woes; What is opinion man, to you or me? Jul. —We all pretend to bid defiance to The world's opinion, with patrician scorn— Yet, Frederick, there's not one of us but would Demean himself a prouder man, upborne Upon the shoulders of its approbation. Fred. —Pshaw, man! opinion is the breath of fools! If man must crouch beneath the yoke of man, The creatures whom we should despise, become Our tyrants—nay, our very gods, and bind Us slaves to Superstition's chariot wheel. Opinion, pooh! it is the veriest trick Of juggling knavery to over-reach His neighbour's purse. For he, who dares be great, Must smash this looking-glass of conscience, or Be outstared by the ghosts of his own fears. Jul. —You estimate too lightly what we should Revere— Fred. You fear what fortitude should spurn. When Julias Cæsar bursts his marble shroud, And thunders forth that Cæsar fear'd a world's Opinion, more than as a slave's rebuke, Then I'll fall down and worship—not 'till then! Jul. —Alas! my father will not hear me reason. Fred. —Sdeath! if a parent have the privilege To stifle reason in his child, your mother Might just as usefully bring idiots forth, As creatures to be made such monsters of. Jul. —I might reproach, but should forgive a father. Fred. —Forgiveness for the gods! Men built of clay, And modell'd strangely weak and helpless, with A thousand passions, lawless as the winds, May preach, but do they practise this forgiveness? Jul. —It is not what we do, but what we should do, Men think of, when they judge us. Fred. O, the devil Take all such thinkers! There was a time when I Could thwart desire, repress my passions, wring The blood-drops from my very heart, with striving T'appease this Cerberus, opinion. But, Julian, there is a period in our fortunes, Beyond which we cannot strain our energies To catch the smile of the still sneering world. After that we exchange our love for hate, Our suffering for revenge—our sympathy For utter scorn of all abuse or praise. Love fits a maiden's lips, as doth a glove Her lily hand; but, on the armed breast, Sheath'd in the mail, experience gives us, link By link, from batt'ling with the world, it sits As lightly as a feather on the helm. Jul. —Then we outlive the feelings which, like rainbows Arch'd o'er the skies, redeem life's cloudy way? Fred. —No, there's ambition's light'ning glory left; The thunder of revenge; the storm of hate; A thousand godlike passions after all Our worldly dreams have perish'd! Jul. Meteors to Mislead us to our ruin. Fred. Who nobly dares Is next to him who wins a glorious fame. The carrion cannot fancy heavenly splendours He has not courage to aspire to; but The eagle, stricken from his lofty height, Falls to the lowly earth an eagle still! Jul. —But, Frederick, they who soar, should plume their wings With buoyant approbation, and not load Their struggling pinions with a people's curse. Fred. —A curse upon the people! Well, well, come, Truce to such cares as blanch the cheek of youth. Who gives his spring-time to the fears of autumn, Deserves an early winter on his head. You sup with us to-night? I'll seat you with Some weather-beaten spirits that will laugh Through the barr'd dungeon windows of their hopes, As merrily as in the open day Of fortune's sunshine. Jul. I am not of these. The world's disapprobation withers up The laughter on my lip, as tempests sear The drooping leaf. Fred. O, we can spunge these schoolboy Apprehensions from your slumbers. Come, You sup with us to-night? Jul. In truth, I cannot. Fred. —That cannot be a truth. Pray, give't the lie. Jul. —I lie to-night upon the road to Padua. Fred. —Do so. Declare you go, and stay away. Jul. —Ay, but my going is a certainty. Fred. —Then certainly I would not go to night. Jul. —Sadly I must depart for Padua. Fred. —You shall depart in sadness when you go; As sad as sorrow—but remain to-night. Jul. —It will not be. Fred. It may be if you will. Jul. —I am most willing it should be so, if— Enter Giacomo suddenly. Gia. —My mistress, sir, your mother, bids me say, She has induc'd my master to consent, That you postpone your travel till to-morrow, And, as the Senator Lodoro holds A masquerade to-night, she doth entreat Your company— Jul. Enough! these varlets grow Loquacious in their duties now-a-days, The world is fashion'd to such vanity. Fred. —Julian, we number you our servant? Jul. No! These revels please me not: my soul is strung To such a pitch of fever'd hope and fear, That every cup lights frenzy in my eye. Excuse me, Frederick, I will not drink. Fred. —Drink!—You shall drink, and crown your cups with myrtle! Jul. —Why? Fred. Why, your fortune being desperate, Your state is happiest. Jul. Prove it— Fred. Thus, I hold Men's fortunes are the best, when grown so bad They suffer by no earthly chance, but may Be mended by whatever change betides. Jul. —God send him succour who is fallen so low! Fred. —What god? Dan Cupid, sir? Jul. You trifle. Fred. Ay! So do we all, only our vanity Invests our favourite trifle with importance. Well, well, I fret the magnanimity Of thy yet virgin love—Adieu! To-night We sup together in the tavern, where The doors are open to all guests but care. Exit. Jul. —What wretched creatures are we thus to waste Existence in an abject slavery To lust and passion, though we gild them with The fashionable epithet of pleasure! Ambition, gold, fanaticism, wine, All visions of distemper'd minds, or longings Of the diseas'd and heated body—yet, We go, like martyrs, smiling to our doom! Gods! Ye have made us wonderful, strange beings! I half deride, and yet a destiny Seems to impel me to the poet's lot— Albeit, it is stamp'd with ignominy; Instead of, as it should be, honourable And manly daring for an honor'd rank. Enter Giacomo. Gia. —My mistress waits for you. Jul. I come directly. Exeunt. SCENE IV. —A Chamber in Lorenzo's House, the casement opening out on the grand canal. Bianca and Maria. Mar. —Well then, my lady, since I may not talk Of Signor Julian, as your lover, tell me, How will you dress to-night? In spotless white? Your heart's unspotted with the taint of love? In green, perhaps? I think it should be green— Green's jealousy—and you'll be jealous when You see him gaily flirting with another, Though you cry “pshaw; don't mention him, I pray!” In yellow? did you say, in yellow? No, That is forsaken, and I dare be sworn, You never need wear that for him—no, no! If nature can be true, he'll not be false. Bia. —Ah me! Mar. Why how you sigh, my lady! Pray How will you dress? Bia. Did you speak me, Maria? Mar. —La! now, my lady! I've been talking here This half hour, and you have not heard a word! And sighing when you ought to practise smiles Before your glass. Ah! now you are in love! Bia. —Maria, peace! you do assume too much— It is not maidenly to speak of love. Mar. —But love will not be silenc'd like a child. Bia. —Yes, prudence ought to seal our lips, for love Confess'd is love controlless. Mar. But a sigh Convicts us, does it not? You said so once. If so, you are in love, for now you sigh'd. Bia. Did I, Maria? Mar. Ay, my lady, heavily— Oh, heavily! I wish you'd heard't—'twas shocking. Bia. —How, girl? Mar. Most sad and sorrowful, as if Your heart were burning with some secret fire— Just such a warmth as you might feel in love, And that love for a troubadour like Julian, Who sang the song praising Bianca's beauty. Bia. —Out, foolish girl! Come, I'll no more of this. I waste the moments due to company. Prepare my toilet. Let me have some flowers— D'you mind, Maria? fresh, not gaudy flowers. Mar. —Heartsease, my lady? Bia. Get away, mad girl! You will offend me. Mar. (Aside. You will more offend Yourself, by thus deceiving your ownself. Good heav'n! if love, now, were the deadliest crime In nature, it could not be fear'd and shunn'd More than by those, whom nature formed for love. Well—this may be the fashion, but the form And favour do not please me, for all that.) Bia. —Maria! Mar. Yes, my lady—I am gone. Exit. Bianca goes to the casement, and opens it. Bia. —How tranquilly that sister moon looks down, Nun-like, upon this wilderness of care— This struggling, heartless, soulless world! Pale orb!— That, in thy icy stillness, I have dream'd To be the convent of those broken hearts That die of love, upon this barren earth— How gladly, though so young, could I lie down Within thy arms, and whisper what I dare Not tell th' unsympathizing crowd—I love! I love? ay, and this lonely love is far Too heavy for my solitary breast. This very love, that, shared with him I love, Would sit no heavier on the gladden'd heart Than dew on flow'rs—than sunbeams on the skies. Music heard from the canal. Alas! Hark, there is music on the waters, Breathing its melancholy to the air! Perhaps the tones of lovers wafting high To heav'n their earliest vows of constant love. Why should I lack the privilege music hath? Because this custom stamps me—Ah! I dare Not think on't! if a woman asks for love! Enter Mother. Mo. —Bianca, child!—did you not hear me call? Bia. —No, mother. Mo. Why, you have forgot our guests. St. Mark hath chim'd the hour of invitation— What make you here, by moonlight, in your chamber, Loit'ring away the moments? Girl, of late Your father and myself both notice how You'r altered in demeanour—What means this? Bia. —Nothing. Mo. Nothing! nothing, Bianca?—shame! I know there's something in it. Girls, like you, Seldom forego their pastimes, and forget The toilet and saloon for nothing. Now, I hope you do not think yourself in love? Bia. —In love, my lady mother? In love with whom? Mo. —I seek to know with whom—for, look, Bianca, Your father and myself, attentive to Our interest, but having most at heart Your welfare in the scheme, invite to-night The Signor Barbarigo—who's a noble Of condescending grace and lofty rank. Bianca, the Lodoros have too long Looked on, while poor pretenders, round about Have ta'en patrician honors—'tis our turn To loll upon the purple—you may be The first called lady of our rising house. Bia. —I pray you, mother, tell me how you mean? Mo. —Barbarigo, girl, may fall in love with you! Bia. —I never saw him, and perhaps could not Return his love— Mo. Return his love? pooh! pooh! This is the squeamishness of your romance And youth. Bianca, let these things, with you, Be what they were with me, girl—toys, toys, toys! Your father's state was lifted much o'er mine By nature, yet I lifted myself up To share his bed—I love him, as a lady Of prudent virtue should esteem her lord: What more? Bia. O, mother, I believe you do. You are my mother—but, I'll ask you, if You'd loved another, ere you saw my father, Or fancied of another kind of love Than his might prove, what would you then have done? Mo. —Strangled such peevish feelings, and secur'd Myself respect and fortune, as I've done. Bia. —But is not self-respect before the world's Esteem? O! I could never love myself, If I should love one man and wed another. Mo. —O, ay! you're young and sickly, and, just now, Would stake a cottage and a beggar's love Against a palace and a coronet. Come! leave these follies for each baby face, And learn to be a woman. Start not, mind, At ought you hear to-night; perhaps it dates The rising of our star. Bia. (Aside. Perhaps its fall!) Mo. Bianca! Bia. Madam? Mo. Why, girl, how you sigh! You heard me, did you not? Bia. Yes. Mo. Recollect, Your Mother's temper brooks no contradiction. Come, do not be so timid. Ere yon moon Re-fills the heavens with splendour, it shall gild Thy palace walls, and light a score of maids To tire thee as a princess for the feast. Exit. Bia. —No, it shall silver o'er the marble tomb, Where I would rather end my woes, and let Death wed the roses on my cheek, than live A life of blazon'd misery, and feel Myself a harlot, even in riches' arms! O God! how blind, how strangely, wilfully, Insanely blind, are they whose duty 'tis To guard the tenderness they madly crush! Have they ne'er heard, or read of woman's love? A timid thing that shrinks, if but the sun Of rudeness gaze upon it, 'till arous'd By cruelty and insult to new life— And then you'd better stir the Syrian tiger To leap upon your heart, than dare a woman To bid defiance to your savage laws. Ah me! I could have died, as dies a flow'r For lack of rain, parched up, and gently bow'd Into a timeless grave, beneath the heat Of my own burning passions! But to be, Besides, the creature of another's lust, The implement of others' avarice— The word of gain upon a father's lip— The show-thing of a mother's vanity— O God, forgive me! I will sooner fall With every curse of earth upon my head! Exit.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. SCENE I. —Lodoro's servants, beppo and others, arranging the room. Enter Lodoro. Lod. —Come, bustle, sirrahs! Zounds! d'ye think We pay our servants to be idle? Bep. (Aside. By Saint Mark! I'd rather earn a penny civilly, Than dollars given with curses and with kicks.) 2d. Ser. —Beshrew me, but a crabbed master's curse Enough for any servant's sins! Lod. Come, sirrahs! Bep. —Signor, the company arrives. Lor. Well, bustle, sir! Zounds! you're asleep. Enter Lorenzo. Lorenzo, welcome met! A very, very hearty welcome, sir, As I'd extend to any man in Venice. (Aside. I thought the vulgar fool would be the first.) Lor. —Thanks, signor, I esteem you as you speak. We've been much less acquainted these late years, Than when, i'the freakish days of friendly boyhood, We robb'd the Doge's orchard, and, to school Went, hand-in-hand, a munching o'the spoil. Lod. —Well, signor, come, dwell not on these remembrances, They do recall— Lor. Things that I'm proud of, sir! My lowly origin, my— Lod. Ay, 'tis true! 'Tis over true, Lorenzo. Hear me, sir. I estimate you higher than you wot of. No merchant here hath track'd the devious steps Of commerce, thro' her dirty shifts, and borne A more untainted character than yours. Your word, sir—nay be patient, sir!—your word Is money on exchange. Your honor's ne'er Been pawn'd for interest. Now—mark the sequel!— The senators, at my solicitation, Intend conferring on your shoulders all The honors of their robes. For this, I only Entreat a very trivial return. Lor. —Name it. Lod. Report hath whisper'd, you retain, Within the law's unyielding grasp, the lands And palaces of the Lord Barbarigo? Lor. —Sir, I make no disguise of, thro' my agent, Lending much money on that noble's 'states. Lod. —He's riotous in dissipation. Lor. So 'Tis rumour'd; and, for this, I have withheld All further means to feed his follies. Lod. (Aside. I Remov'd that difficulty.) Will you speak Aside with me? Julian and Augustus enter from different sides. Ha, Julian! welcome here! In good time, too, a youth of mine—Augustus, This gentleman's the Signor Julian, boy, A Paduan student—son of my old friend. I pray you make his friendship. Exeunt Lodoro and Lorenzo. Jul. I enjoy An honor I have long solicited. Aug. —O, sir, the very enviable repute, All Venice trumpets of your growing fame, Doth make me feel a prouder man henceforth. The walk of genius through this merchant world, Is something we should follow with delight. Jul. —Your scholar'd tongue hath learn'd the courtier trick Of flattery betimes— Aug. You know, you feel, You must confess, I only speak the truth! Jul. —Well, well! I long to be what thy too hasty And generous temper makes me out already; But, sir, I also know the long neglect, Indifference, doubt, suspicion, slow applause, Envy and opposition I must brave, For years, e'er I can be the man you think me— The man that for himself is lov'd of men. But, come! we mock our youth with aged cares. I beg you entertain me with your guests— Who's this? Enter the wife of Lodoro, a young Lady, an Officer and other Company. Aug. This lady is my mother, and She curtsies to a damsel—oh! a maid Who picks the flowers about Parnassus' foot, And culls them into dainty bouquets. There, Behold that soldier—martial in his cloak And coward in his eye. Look, note him well! D'you observe disorder in him any where? A single hair curl'd out of tune? Oh no! For therein lie his lands, his tenements. His teeth are Indian pearls, and any dame Who'll wear them near her lips, must give her hand And fifty thousand ducats for the bargain. Enter one fantastically dressed. Oh! look you, too, a traveller! Mark his coat— His Joseph's coat—his many colour'd coat! See how he swaggers like a galliot with Her painted banners hung to catch the breeze! List, how he prates, of pyramids and pearls— Jabbers in French and curses in Hebraic— Quotes Sanscrit, mentions Allah, shows his shoes, And swears he bought them in a Turk's bazaar. During this, Bianca has entered and joined the company: Julian remains with his eyes fixed on her. But, Lord! you do not mark me! How is this? Jul. —I do, I do—go on! Aug. The devil take it! Who talks without a list'ner? If there's aught On earth upsets our vanity, it is Being eloquent without an audience. Ha! A poet in his dreams! What is't you see? Jul. —A lovely vision! Hist! Augustus, tell me Who owns yon fairy foot-fall on the earth So spiritually light, it scarcely bends the flowers? Aug. —That spirit, of your conjuring fancy, calls Me brother. I have kissed her as my sister, And swear she's only delicate flesh and blood. Jul. —Time, since we met, hath been her playmate Then She was but young, as is a May-day rose: Yet, modell'd so enchantingly, that I Have never dreamed of fairer form than hers. Aug. —You speak this out of compliment to me! Jul. —Blister my tongue then, if my heart respond Not to the pulse of passion on my lip! Augustus, you're my junior—and you hope, With ripening years, as you are told, to see Abroad more beauty than you find at home. I know the world—I've peeped behind its mask: And, tell you, when we have a virtuous flow'r, In likeness of a sister, wife, or love, The skies allow no more—earth's granted all Its treasures in a moment, and we fool Ourselves to madness if we hunt for others. Aug. —You love my sister, sir? Jul. To say, I love, Is to give common utterance to a passion That lords my every other sense, and bids Me look to her as to the source of life. Aug. —Julian, my sister's honor'd in the love And admiration of a man like you. Nay, walk with me. I will prefer your suit, And second your entreaties with my own. Come, let us talk. Jul. For ever! 'tis so sweet To talk with those who'll hear of those we love! Exeunt. Enter Lodoro. Lod. —This fool Lorenzo, now, refuses me His aid to tangle Barbarigo in A legal mesh, and bag him for my daughter. And yet, I do detect the undercurrent Of his manœuverings! He thinks to win The girl for Julian—apes the prick o'conscience; And clothes his speech in th' hypocrite's assumptions About injustice, irreligion—out! The driv'ller! Does he ween, I cannot see His specious plotting through this paltry mask? By heaven! I think we're all devising ill— The secret is, the greatest villain thrives. At least I rest not in obscurity Because the shoe of greatness pinches here— Here i'the conscience. Enter Barbarigo. (Aside. Ha! I must be cautious!) How very condescending now this is! Bar. —Indeed, Lodoro, I apologize, I fear my visit's late. Lod. Nay, name it not! Oh! late? ha! ha! my lord, we do not hold These low observances of punctuality. In your ear now, here is a scrub—a scrub! The dirtiest merchant in all Venice, sir! A very trickster to each filthy turn! One, by-the-bye, whom you have little cause To greatly love—Lorenzo, he is call'd. I was constrain'd, through interest, to invite His meanness to this comp'ny, and he comes 'Sieging my doors for supper, e'er I'd wip'd The dinner from my beard—oh, late? ha, ha! These are your early men! Not late, my lord. Bar. —(Aside. The beggar, how familiar he is! No matter, he's my tool, and they who work With iron, must at times be singed.) O, sir, I know this us'rer well—he has a son, Curse him! he has a son, a puppy, sir! Lod. —A most assuming puppy, and given to vice Of many kinds. Bar. I am his debtor, for A rascal's trick he play'd me, and would fain Take payment from his skin, but that I'd soil My fingers with the hound. Lod. The saucy dog! Bar. —He fac'd me out of my undoubted right To the first prizes at the Paduan schools. I do assure you, it was all a trick. Lod. —A trick, my lord! I do believe a trick! But come, my lord—I have an only daughter— Nay, of her wealth and beauty I speak not; But will you condescend to dance with her? Bar. —With all my heart—come on! Lodoro, mind, To-morrow raise me some ten thousand ducats— This was the bond on which I patronize Your ball. Lod. Ten thousand ducats! Barbarigo, Will nothing less bestead th' immediate want? Bar. —I cannot bate a dollar. Lod. Strange, my lord! A month ago, you drew a larger sum. Bar. —No marvel in the matter—yesterday I stak'd and lost it on a cast o'the die. Lod. (Aside. Unthinking prodigal!) My lord, I fear, If thus runs on the current of your fortunes, 'Twill timeless reach its leap, and dash into Th'abyss of ruin! Love of gaming is A falling stone that gains velocity At ev'ry bound, until the fearful power's Acquir'd to shiver all its strength to atoms. Bar. —Lorenzo, do you fancy he, who flings His wasted frame upon the gamester's bed, Sees not his ruin painted in his dreams? Peace! you would ask impertinently, why Not pause upon the precipice? You're sober, But gambling is a drunkenness, and youth A fever—some it wears away, and others Outlive the trial—which shall conquer, I Care little! come, your daughter, come, come, come! Exeunt. Enter Julian. Jul. —How marvellous slowly crawls the weary pace Of the snail-blooded world, contrasted with Th'impetuous eagerness of our desires, Our hopes and fears! Enter Augustus. Augustus! speak to me! What tidings? Is her answer affable? You urg'd my proffers timidly? You lack'd My ardour to enforce them? But she's young— She's very young and fearful. She will think on't. Nay, speak! Is this your friendship, that would trifle A moment with the feelings of your friend? For shame, young man!—for shame! Aug. No, listen, Julian! I smile, but only at the impatient blood O'erboiling in you, and usurping all Your judgment. I have never, since we parted, Found moments to prefer your suit. My sister Dances with one Lord Barbarigo. Jul. Ha! Aug. —What is he? Jul. Noble. Aug. Is he much esteem'd? Jul. —He much esteems himself. Aug. How hold you him? Jul. —Where he holds me—at arm's length. Aug. How is this? Short answers—exclamations!—these are not The satisfaction candour owes to justice. The Barbarigo is distinguish'd for His rank and riches. Do you fancy, since You love my sister, all are treasonable Who interchange a courtesy with her? Jul. —Your grace, Augustus! I am ill! Adieu! Exit. Aug. —What mystery is gathering round us now? Julian is honourable. Barbarigo Acknowledg'd noble, courteous, and rich— And yet the other winces at his mention, As at the hearing of some villain's name. I'll follow Julian—something may be heard Of moment to Bianca's destinies. Exit. Enter Bianca and Maria. Bia. —Maria! did I not behold Augustus Bespeak the Signor Julian? Mar. Love is blind. Bia. —Blind to the world, when more than worlds within The cloister of the bosom lie. Mar. A riddle? Bia. —Bear with me, I am very sad, Maria! Mar. —Sad in such company? Bia. The laughing lip Often belies the heavy heart. Mar. Alas! Sadness and youth make sorry company. Bia. —They do Maria! But the laughter from The hollow chest of insincerity— The affability of the contemptuous eye— The compliment of the insidious tongue— The pressure of the sycophant's warm hand— The bow, the cringe, the slander of detraction, Mingling like weeds upon a hot-bed, here To night, have sicken'd me of gaiety. Mar. —This is the very mood of your disease. Bia. —Disease? Mar. Yes! love at first, is a disease, That, from the object of its passion, turns On all things with disgust and loathing. Bia. Love? Mar. —Yes! and I dare be sworn you are in love. Bia. —What matter—call it what you will, to me 'Tis misery—I feel no happiness. Why did they christen Love a laughing god? Alas! his herald is a stifled sigh, His sojourn sorrow, and his bed the grave! They never felt the wound, who deem'd the arrow Tip't with a smile—it should have been a tear! Mar. —Your morning and your evening words belie Each other. Bia. Ay, my heart hath prov'd me false! Maria!—words are poor interpreters Of feelings—when a woman speaks of love, Hang your opinion on a blush, or draw Conclusions from a look; but never trust Your judgment to the weakness of her tongue. Come with me, I'll to bed. I wish, Maria, We could disrobe our minds, as easily As we cast off the garments of our pride. Exeunt. SCENE II. —A hall in Lorenzo's house. Giacomo. Well, here's a comfortable uproar for a neutral party! what a pleasant thing to see every body fighting, and nothing to do with the quarrel ourselves. Master curses Julian—Julian curses his destinies, and mistress blames them both. Now, I wonder who's right, and who's wrong. Perhaps both, perhaps all. All right—all wrong? Well, that's curious—but still it may be true. Let me discuss the matter. I'm fond of discussion. Master insists upon Julian not being a poet. Now, if God made Julian a poet, master may make him a cobler, but can't unmake him a poet—therefore master's wrong, to insist upon what he can't do. Bell rings. Coming sir! that's Julian's bell. Stop till I discuss the subject, whether Julian's right or wrong. Well, Julian won't obey his father—there, then, Julian's wrong. Ay, but Julian can't obey his father—there Julian's right. Bell rings again. Coming, sir, directly, just let me discuss this! Well Julian's wrong, and Julian's right—and—let me see— master's wrong, and master ayn't right. Why, then, Julian's more right than master, so Julian's most right— Enter Frederick St. Cyr. Fred. —And most right means very right—and very right is quite right—ergo, Julian is quite right. Now, you old dotard! why didn't you answer the bell, and not detain a gentleman at the door, while you were philosophising in the hall? Gia. —I fancied it was Julian's bell, sir, and intended going, as soon as I had settled which I should serve— father or son. Fred. —Why, the one that's right, to be sure. Gia. —That's very right, sir—but suppose he cannot afford a servant, sir, and the other can—then, if I serve this one, I'm all wrong. Fred. —Giacomo, thou art more correct than thy correctness imagines. Every man adapts his philosophy to his interest, and, so, each is the best philosopher after all. We are all right, and we are all wrong. Gia. —Upon my word, Master Frederick, I half believe what you say is true. Fred. —Truly, I thank you for your half belief, inasmuch as, if you go and retail my philosophy at the corner of the next street, it's chance but you get your head broke for a knave, and certain that you will be wholly disbelieved for a liar and a fool. Gia. —But how is that, sir? Fred. —Because, you arrant blockhead! you must take the world as it is, and not attempt to make it what it should be—unless you wish to be stuck in the pillory of every man's ridicule, and pelted with the dirt of his abuse. Lorenzo. (Within. Giacomo! Giacomo! Giacomo!) Gia. —Here's my master coming, sir. Fred. —Ay, so I hear. Gia. —O, sir, he's in a fury! Fred. —So am I. Gia. O, for God's sake, sir, begone! Fred. —For Peace's sake, you mean—she was a goddess. Enter Lorenzo. Ha! Lorenzo! pleasant day. Lor. —Sir, I'm not accustomed to this gross Familiarity. Fred. True. Giacomo! a chair! Giacomo places chairs. Pray, sir, be seated. Lor. (Aside. This in my own house!) Fred. —Be seated, signor. Nay, an you prefer Standing, excuse me (sits down), I am rather weary. We idlers seldom ruffle our sensations By walking—streets are really horrible! Lor. —May I, sir, ask permission in this house, Lately my own, to hear your business! Fred. —Lately your own!—you have parted with it then? Lor. —It seems so. But your business. Fred. O ay! Julian— Julian your son, sir, he's a clever youth. Lor. —Indeed! Fred. Indeed, he is a promising youth. Lor. —Upon my word! Fred. Upon my word and honor! But to the business. Pray, now, what d'you mean To make of Julian? Lor. Make of Julian? sir! Is this your special business, or mine? Fred. (Rising.) 'Tis yours Lorenzo! and to be more serious— For I can set aside this levity And reason like a man when necessary— I here have forc'd myself on your attention, To blame your unparental harshness with My friend—my noble, generous, gifted friend! You will not so belie your natural love As punish an opinion with your anger? Lor. —And, may I ask, who constituted you An umpire of your senior's conduct? Fred. Age, That should lean on experience, like a crutch, At times, too trusting in its strength, will tumble— Eepecially in things that touch our happiness. There, each by heaven is constituted judge, And man may marr, but cannot mend the precepts Ingrafted in our hearts from infancy. Listen, sir! though you will not profit by My warning, you shall hear it. Try your power! Immure your son in pestilential cities. Invent, contrive, adapt his energies To purposes of base aggrandisement. Torture his body, dispossess his mind Of its affections, appetites, desires, And natural love—and lead him in the chains Of splendid slavery. Yet, after all, O'er his disfranchised heart triumphant Nature, Will vindicate her proud supremacy— And, like an uncag'd eagle, to the clouds And solitudes of poetry, his soul Will rise victoriously, despite your wrath And the denunciations of your curse! Exit. Enter Lorenzo's Wife. Wife. —What ails you, husband? Lor. Leave me! Wife. Are you ill? Lor. Begone! Wife. How have I merited this anger? Lor. —You've all colleag'd against my happiness. You, and your disobedient son—and then His worthless, heartless, good-for-nothing friend, Dares to insult me to my very face. Begone! I tell you! Wife. But, for mercy's sake! Compel not Julian to this harsh adventure! Recall your sentence—you will drive him mad. Lor. —I care not! not a straw! I'd rather see Him perish at my feet, than disobey My inclinations! Do you think I'll have My children turn my masters? Wife. Ah! Lorenzo! How we forget, in censuring our children, The fooleries of our own younger days! Lor. —You advocate his disobedience? Wife. No! But recollect we might as wisely order The summer flowers to bloom, the trees to blossom, As dictate to the nature of our hearts. Lor. —I care not! you may tell your hopeful son To post to Padua, and fulfill my bidding— Or leave my roof for ever! Exit. Wife. Gracious God! How passion can usurp our reason! Surely, Surely, this is but momentary anger. Affection, duty, honor, sense, and shame All, all cry out upon such foul injustice! Enter Julian. O Julian! Julian! Jul. Mother! why these tears? Wife. —I wept for joy at thy nativity, But little thought to weep for sorrow, now, That ever thou wert born. Jul. Your blessing, mother! I will remove this rheum from your eyes, And cut the ulcer from my father's heart. The world hath room enough for me— Wife. To starve in! Jul. —Starvation—death itself, in conscientious Performance of the destiny assign'd us, Is nobler than a splendid slavery To the dominion of another's whims. Wife. —You little know the fearful obstacles Life hath to combat. Jul. To the noble mind Obstacles are, what fences, bars, and gates Are to the generous temper'd hunter—trifles To overleap—the trials of our power. Wife. —Youth's sanguine. In the morning of the heart's Affections, hope is natural as sunshine In the clear skies; but age is calculating— Especially against our chance of fame, And honor in the adventures of our skill. Jul. —I've friends. Wife. By name! Jul. You wrong them! I have given My purse, my hand, my confidence to them. Drunk, smiled, and laugh'd in comp'ny—shar'd their thoughts— What fear, then, with such honourable men? Wife. —Honourable! Jul. Do you doubt them? Wife. Julian! I would not dash a youth's affection with The poison of suspicion; that will come, With other passions that disgrace us—scorn, Contempt, misanthropy—too soon!—alas! Ere age hath blanched your brow, your heart will be Old enough, God knows, in its hate of men. Jul. —These are the fears of your declining age. Wife. —No, Julian, it is our misfortune never To have our foresight credited, until The evils prophesied have been fulfill'd. I cannot hope, that you, intoxicated With the good fortune of your fancy, will Regard my caution. Disappointment must Effect more miracles in one short year, To alter your opinion of the world, Than would a lifetime spent in list'ning to Another's counsel. Julian, take this purse— Nay, sir, refuse it not! you cannot stir A footstep in the world without it—No! While you have money, you command mankind— When you have spent it, you become their slave. Be rich, and you are honor'd every where— Be poor, and you lose every man's good word. Jul. —Your blessing. Wife. Yet a word—be honorable. A ruin'd honor is a broken glass, That artfulness may patch together, but, Once broken, men will never more entrust Aught precious to its leaky custody. Jul. —Mother! Wife. Be patient, Julian! when you rest Within the world's embraces, you'll forget Your mother— Jul. Never! Wife. Yes, we soon forget In pleasure's arms, the arms that cherished us. The heart is like a running brook, where each Succeeding current wipes the last away. Jul. —Come, mother! Wife. Well, I'll try to live, if but To pray for you! Jul. You are too serious. Wife. Julian! Believe me, that your mother's farewell words Will oft recur in other years, when she Who utters them hath pass'd away for ever! If you despise these marks of her affection, Regret will haunt your memory to the grave. Jul. —Here, on my knees, I swear to venerate Your love, and to fulfill your maxims, mother! Wife. —Then, whatsoever destiny be thine— Brilliant, or blackened—honor'd, or revil'd— The memory of a virtuous life shall hallow The bitterness and agony of death. Men may revile 't—but on their mockery tread With scorn, as you would trample on an adder! For, to the spirit, virtue is what silver Is to the mirror, robb'd of which, the glass Reflects no more the presence of one charm. I weary you. Jul. Who wearies of such counsel Is undeserving of its benefits. Wife. —Then, fare thee well! I cannot, cannot say For ever—but it will be so. Jul. Nay, nay! Wife. —My boy! my boy! O Julian! you will never, In all that world of gaiety you seek, Find one whose prayers ascend to heaven for thee So fervently and truly as a mother's. Exit. Jul. —Her kindness shakes the resolutions from My heart, like blighted blossoms from a tree. How strange! that gentleness should overcome Determinations proof to violence! But, when I think upon my sullen father— The marble-hearted stoic, on the pedestal Of his own pride, who'd rather see his child A victim at the altar, than descend To study aught beneath his own opinions— I feel a destiny invokes me hence! Surely, if thieves, and rogues, and murderers Can live and flourish, honesty can't starve. And, yet, where villany so prospers, virtue Hath little chance but to be rooted up. If baseness, ignorance, hypocrisy So thrive on earth, methinks it is no soil For meritorious works to blossom in! Enter Augustus. Who enters here? Aug. Your patience! I have dar'd To snap the pack-threads of good manners thus, For weightier arguments must bind us here A moment. To be very plain, you love My sister—so some hours ago you pledg'd Your honor—you solicited from me A brother's influence—then, may I ask What meant your most uncerimonious parting? Jul. —Love came to me, sir, most uncourteously— And, when the mind is anxious, we forget Our proper carriage to society. Reflecting men forgive such errors. Aug. Julian, I understand your love, but not your fears. Jul. —D'you know your father? Aug. Why this idle question? Jul. —Augustus, do you know your father properly? Aug. —Another man—and I should cut the string Of bantering like this with sharper answer. Jul. —You have mistaken me. D'you know this man, Your father, as you saw him in a glass? He loves you—but he loves his interest more— More, than that lily of his garden flowers, Which he would madly pluck to plant upon A noble's bonnet, where the gorgeous thing Would droop and die—it is a tender flow'r! Aug. —I comprehend you—Barbarigo? Jul. Who Will elevate the sister to his bed— The father to his treasury—the son To be the upper servant to his palace. Aug. You madden me! I see it all!—fool! fool! Fools that we are, to talk of honor, while Such villany surrounds us! Julian, now I know my father, he shall deeply feel The folly of adventuring his gains Upon the prospect of his children's slavery. Ha! ha! it will be excellent to laugh Over the wreck of such a miser's dreams! Come on! nay, stand not musing there, when all My soul burns, like a war-horse for the fight. Jul. —Stop! you're enthusiastic—you are young! Enthusiasm's the offspring of our youth— Suspicion is the fruit of disappointment. Be not surprised, then, that the bursts of sunshine, In th' April skies of thy young fortunes, only Affect me with incredulous disdain. Aug. —What has disturb'd you so? Jul. A trifle! only My blood relations—on whose hearts, I deem'd Heav'n grafted an eternal sympathy— Have spurn'd my love, and proved my bitterest foes. My father casts me on a world, that yawns To eat our reputation up—and properly, That charitable world, hath flung me back Upon the poverty of my own self! And now, with all my aspirations scorn'd, My honor doubted, and my worth despised, You smile, sir, do you? that I cannot dance For joy, at every trifle of good luck? Aug. —O curse the tyrants! Jul. Ponder, sir! for all The immortality of Cæsar would not Hallow the damning crime of paricide! Aug. —But recollect the glories of their names, Who, like the everlasting spheres, are doom'd To shine eternally. Jul. I do, and think how many, With unsung aspirations have gone down, Unepitaph'd, into a beggar's grave! Aug. —Nor stirred by glory, nor by love? Jul. Love is A holy word—if you have never felt How much of heav'n it lends to all of earth, Profane it not! Aug. What are your purposes? Jul. —I know not! ask the gods my destiny! I think upon Bianca, and I cannot Wed her fair blossoms to my wither'd fortunes! I love her, but 'tis with a love so holy, That I would not profane her happiness. Aug. —Then Barbarigo weds Bianca, and— Jul. —O agony! why visit misery With your reflections on its wretchedness? Aug. —Enough, sir, I have done!—I court you not To wed my sister—Nobles seek her hand, And you— Jul. I know it all! and I, a beggar— A beggar living on the world's opinion!— Should not be over dainty.—Sir, you wrong The scruples of an honorable man. Aug. —I only taunted you—your pardon, Julian. Jul. —The guiltless need no pardon. Aug. Will you see My sister? Jul. I believe I must; but if Aught evil from this night betide her years, Eternity will never expiate My deep remorse! I fear, I madly seek A destiny, that wisely I should shun. Exeunt. SCENE III. —A Tavern, with table and glasses. Frederick St. Cyr, Angelo, Antonio, and other Venetian Gentlemen. Fred. —A curse! a curse upon your melancholy! Why should a man be overcome by bile T'expose his folly in the public ways, A sign for scorn; and make our sad humanity A thing so odious and intolerable, That on the very beasts we look with envy? Ang. —You argue right, an' we could save ourselves. Fred. —Zounds! but if I should say you could not help Being cheerful, you would laugh at me. Then why Not rule our melancholy as our mirth? Ang. —But Julian's fortune's are adrift—the tide Of destiny sets in upon his duty, Threat'ning to deluge it, and yet he clings Nobly, though sadly, to obedience. Fred. Bah! Noble? Ha! ha! a slave's nobility! Ang. —To live, we must live in the world's opinion. Fred. —Life's a strange riddle, that some men do guess, But most relinquish—never understanding. Few, very few do guess it. These are call'd Men of the world. The many give it up— Are laugh'd at, cheated, cozen'd, and so die. Or living, live in vain attempts to solve Its mysteries—mistaking right for wrong— Cavilling, carping, toiling, cursing, sinning A thousand ways against observances; And waging universal war, to hold An inch—a hair breadth of existence here. Enter Waiter. What, ho! my Ganymede! some nectar, boy! Waiter. —More Rum? Fred. Oh! Rum for such as we? ye Gods! Bacchus, Silenus! thou immortal ass, That bore the immortal weight! is't come to this, Men cannot judge our humours by our faces? You are from England, and have serv'd in Grub-street, Where poverty is still the poet's bride. Begone, you varlet! bring me wine, with sparkles, Shall lift my fancy to ambrosial bowers, Where dance the Houris in Mahomet's heaven. Nothing like wine! nought like the generous grape! Ang. —You seem to think so. You are drinking deep. Fred. —Well, so is all the world—of love or war, Or avarice, stupidity, or something— What matter, what, so long as worldly cares Die with the sparkles from our goblet's glory! Ang. —You make the aim of living then to revel? Fred. —I do!—and 'till I find a sober man, Why not! Ant. I'm sober. Fred. Nay, now, you are drunk! Drunk with your vanity, drunk with your griefs— Drunk with a passion for your mistress—drunk— Ant. —Enough, enough! Angelo, art thou drunk? Fred. —Ay, with his paints, his hopes of fame or gain. The latter, if he take a friend's advice. Ant. —Nay, with the fame, an' he would be a man. Fred. —Back feather'd fame to heavy gold? you're drunk! Angelo, heed not what the fellow says. He's drunk, mad drunk!—paint, sir, for gold, gold, gold! Paint portraits—flattering, false, fair faces paint! Make ugliness angelic—tip the lie To nature—you will starve upon the truth! Ant. —Then what will Julian do with poetry? Fred. —Write his own epitaph, and die a beggar! Ang. —He speaks of writing plays. Fred. He'll play the fool, then! Sdeath! worse and worse! who listens to the play In Venice now? Our senses, drunk with folly, Reel through the streets to gape at monstrous things, Spurned by our father's sober faculties! Ang. —A sermon from a sinner—how appropriate! Fred. Who oft'nest fall, best know the tripping place. I own I'm drunk, but I can waken sober, And with the morrow be a man again. Whereas this huge intoxicated city— Besotted with some stupid mummery, Until its wise men and its counsellors, Distort their gravity with vile grimaces, And all our grey beards wag in approbation At th' antics of some foreign mountebank— Will wallow in its ignominy, till Some prophet voice rolls o'er its slumbering senses, And stirs them to their former majesty. Ang. —I wonder how your fellow citizens Would hear this sweeping judgment of their virtues? Fred. —Like men who honor truth wherever spoken! Let Julian make a drama of his life. It may want kings and queens, daggers and swords, Battles and bugles, and machinery— Ay, that's the word—machinery, for show: But, if calamity in her rough garb— Grief as she is, naked, and every day Walking our mighty city—suffering— If truth, if nature, if unpainted scenes Of human life, in human words, have power To wet the eye or warm the soul of man, By heaven! then let him write but what he's seen, Heard, played a part in, on this busy world, And, if it fail, I have not rightly read The human heart—and that's my only book! But where's this Jule? This traitor Jule! Ah! Julian! Thou'rt no philosopher to feed thy cares On water! Enter waiter. Ho! some wine!— Get drunk, say I! Get merrily drunk, my boys! the head ache o'er, The conscience settled with a few potations, You're a freemason in philosophy, And know the panacea for all ills! But where's my Jule? ay, I'll admonish him! Ang. He has a sweeter teacher far to-night. Fred. Sweeter? but not a truer. Ang. Yes, it is Nature: and the preceptress a sweet girl. Fred. Bianca? Ang. Ay, and much I fear that villain, The Barbarigo, thwarts his love. Fred. What's that? Repeat it, friend, I'm rather elevated— Rather above my understanding—a little! Ang. I say, I have been told that Barbarigo Is Julian's rival. Fred. Where is Julian now? Not present, is he? Jule, my boy! art here? Ang. Here? good luck! He's serenading, man! Fred. He's serenading woman, I should think. Which of you will bestead me to the spot? Ant. Shame, man, to break a lover's sanctity! Fred. Sanctity! friend, I comprehend you not. I fancy Jule's in danger—that's enough— A friend's a friend, sir, be he drunk or sober! Ho, there! a gondola! a gondola! Ang. —You cannot stir, you're hardly steady. Fred. Steady? Its very likely—but a drunken friend Is better than a sober enemy. Ang. —I doubt it. Fred. O, for shame, sir! Would you pause To doubt when danger's near your friend—to the devil. Go to the devil with such friendship! go! What, ho! a gondola! a gondola! Come, keep thy foot as steady as thy heart! Thy hand as firm and strong as is thy friendship, And, Master Barbarigo—ha! ha! ha! Exit. Ant. —Unconscionably drunk, upon my conscience! Aug. —I wish his conscience stood him better friend Than does his foolery. Come! we must look to't! Exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. SCENE I. —Chamber in Lodoro's palace, the casement opening on to the grand canal. moonlight, music heard in the distance. Bianca, Maria. Bia. —What most unseasonable mirth is this? Is there no sanctity for grief? Alas! Methinks, we should respect each other's woe When misery is so common to us all! Mar. —Your melancholy makes you feel this mirth Discordant. 'Tis a brilliant serenade The courteous Barbarigo gives his love. Bia. —Poor man! If he must waste his love on one, Whose soul reflects not his, as those bright waters Mirror that moonlight, he had better die! If I should love, 'twould be as suns look down To feed the flowers up-gazing to their light. Mar. —I knew you'd love! Bia. Because you trusted nature, Whose precepts told you that we all must love. No matter what the object be, love is As natural—as much a part of woman, As is the light to heaven, the green to earth, Or anything that is most natural. Mar. —I fear, my lady— Bia. What, Maria? Mar. How Your father will receive this news. Bia. Maria! Obedience, duty, country, kindred, all Are only names, to those whose bosoms once Have given birth to passions, that you may Despise, but can no more control, than tear The rooted mountains from the steadfast earth! Enter Augustus. Who enters? Aug. Fear not! Bia. O, my brother! how You have alarm'd me! Aug. Pardon me! Ill news Is seldom usher'd in with ceremony. Bia. —Speak out! Aug. Come, do not tremble! But tomorrow Our father pledges you a noble's bride. Mar. —My lady! Bia. I am well! what would you with me? Say on, Augustus. Aug. I am still your brother, Although the unwelcome messenger of this. You'll wed the Barbarigo? Bia. By heaven! I will not! Aug. —A convent then awaits you, and a life— Bia. —Of ignominious solitude!—I know it. Augustus, I have loved you! Tell me, have you Not read in antique Roman story, how Lucretia gave her stainless Latin blood An offering to the daughters of her land? Aug. —What mean you? Bia. That her spirit is not dead! But lives in woman's heart as long as tyranny Usurps the natural honor of mankind! Aug. —Your words are wild, Bianca. Bia. And the current Of my o'erboiling blood—outraged and scorn'd By savage selfishness—is ten times fiercer! Aug. —What answer do I bear your father? Bia. Go! Bid him essay to curb the storm's career! Bridle the tempestuous ocean! chain the winds! And then reflect how easy 'tis to bow And bend the passions of the bursting heart! Aug. —Bianca, these are idle words! ere long You'll beg your freedom from a convent— Bia. Never! Freedom unto the body, when the soul Is fetter'd by its giant handed passions, Is no more freedom than a larger cell, A longer link, a wider, broader hell, Unto the chain'd and damn'd are liberty! O, my dear brother! I forget my sex! Bear with me! I am but a woman! weak By nature—weaker by designing man. Have pity! Let me weep upon your bosom! Aug. —Companion of my earliest, best affections! Look in my face! It smiles when yours is cheerful, And weeps when you are sorrowful! I only Essayed the virtue of your heart, and find A woman's love dies but with woman's life. What, never blush, girl! nature hath too many Infirmities to drop the eyelash o'er— We need not be asham'd of truth.—This Julian— Enter Julian. You tremble! Bia. O Augustus, I have given My love too lightly! Swear to Julian, that My heart is true to him, though false to me! Jul. —I do believe it! and I'd rather trust To nature's undisguised simplicity, Than all the worthless oaths in honor's code! Exeunt, unperceived, Augustus and Maria. I do offend you with my earnestness. Forgive me, lady, that I have presum'd To level you to hopes so poor as mine! Bia. —Julian, I will not contradict my heart, Belie my nature, and disgrace my sex By pandering to the custom—for I love you! Perhaps you hate me for this bold confession; But I would sooner hunt the faded light Of yesterday, than hope to feel again My maiden prudence! If hypocrisy Be woman's virtue, I have sadly sinn'd. Jul. —Bianca, there are villains—so they say— I fear 'tis true!—would pin a woman's virtue Upon her words—I am not one of these! I love you for yourself. I love you for The spirit that can spurn duplicity— Convention gives another designation To such dishonesty, but I forget it. My dictionary is my heart—and quarrelling O'er words is wretched when we mean the same. Bia. —Augustus! Gone? Jul. You do not fear to trust Your honor with your lover? Bia. No, I never Fear what I love, or love what I should fear. Jul. —Come, then! I have a gondola at hand. We will go forth upon the sleeping waters; And, in the interchange of holy vows And starry dreams of future happiness, Forget the pain and sorrow of the past. Why do you sigh, dear lady? Bia. I know not. Sometimes I have presentiments of evil, As if the soul foredream'd of danger, as The ocean's depths are troubled long before The tempest wakens in its cavern'd bosom. Jul. —O never fear! Bia. I cannot help it, Julian! Fear seems as much a part of me as hope; And, like a silly girl, at times I weep That I am far too happy, when I think How very short our happiness may be. Jul. —A lover's eyes should only see the rainbow, And disbelieve the clouds and storms of life. We know they shadow every sky; but, while It can, imagination should create A sunshine in the gloom, a glory in The storm, and love and beauty all around! Enter Augustus. Aug. —Julian! Jul. What now? Aug. You cannot linger here With safety! Jul. Safety? where's the danger? speak! Aug. —Bianca! Jul. I submit then! Oh, the agony! That those who meet to love should part to grieve! What says my lady? Bia. I have tears to weep Away the heavy hours, until thy smile, Like sunshine, comes to dry the waters up. Jul. —Is this the end of every happiness? I've heard, but never credited 'till now, How short—how fearfully short is human joy! Bianca, love! I leave my soul with you, And drag my body to a sleepless couch. O! think how very lonely I shall be! Bia. —Alas! you rob me of the power of thought, Save to brood o'er the misery of your absence. Aug. —Come, sir, the moments hasten. Time respects No more the lover in his mistress' arms, Than sickness hurrying to the awful grave. Come! kiss me girl! Good night, and pleasant slumbers! Come, Julian! Heaven defend the man who drives A love sick gentleman! come, Julian! come! Jul. —Farewell, Bianca! they, who never loved, But little know the horror of that word. We, who thus gaze our farewell from the eye, Can feel how terrible it is to die! Exeunt Julian and Augustus. Bia. —Maria! are you there? Enter Maria. Come here Maria! Give me your arm, girl! Mar. How you tremble, lady. Bia. —Do I? What creatures are we of our passions! Strong in design—in action imbecile. Great to ourselves—ignoble unto others. Assuming wisdom—laughed at for our folly. O love! O melancholy, mournful love! Source of all joy! All joy destroying passion! Soul of our souls! without whose influence The heavens, the earth, and all created things Would fall to pieces like a broken billow! O wherefore are thy joys so dash'd with sorrows— Thy sorrows intermingled so with joys— That with, or without thee, we're wretched still! O Julian! Julian! I could die for joy That I possess thee, as I could have died For agony without thee! Fare thee well! Exeunt. SCENE II. —A narrow and dark street in front of Lodoro's Palace. Enter Barbarigo and Serenaders. Bar. —A serenade! and yet her casement closed As firmly as her lips. Friend, Barbarigo! What, an' she love another? Whisper says The stripling Julian. Cunning then must match Th' advantage of his luck! come hither, friends! My honest lads, I hired you to essay A lady's heart with music—could you find Her lover's with a dagger? You're brave boys! 1st. Ser. —Why not retain that pleasure for yourself? We share our love, but should reserve revenge, It is such pleasure, for our own enjoyment. Bar. —Right! But Venetian nobleness of late Is so notorious, I should hang for what Would pass away unnoticed, done by you. 1st. Ser. —(Aside. The coward's shift! I know his courage well, And will not damn myself to save another!) Bar. —Why do you hesitate? A dagger, man, The ocean, secrecy, and gold. Come, come! 1st. Ser. —No, signor, keep your gold! The poor man's character Is all his fortune, and he's bound to guard That ten times closer than his richer neighbour. Bar. —Ha! ha! a conscientious villain! Enter Frederick, followed by Angelo, Antonio, and others. Ha! Whose here? Fred. Stand fast! Who art thou?—friend or foe? Bar. —A friend to Bacchus, and a foe to all Who say their prayers, and sober creep to bed. Fred. —Friend, thou art sober, for I know thee well, And thy intentions, Barbarigo, here. I'm drunk—but I am honorably drunk, And thou art most dishonorably sober! Bar. —What mean you, braggart? Fred. Braggart to thyself! 'Twill make a sword knot for your useless steel. You seek to thwart, in love, a nobler man Than ever trod in Barbarigo's shoes. Bar. —You're quarrelsome! Fred. You're villanous! Bar. Draw! Fred. Draw! Bar. —Prepare to die! Fred. I'll send thee first to hell, Thou licensed bully of society! Now make thy boasted greatness proof! Come! show The world thou art a better man than I! They Fight, Frederick falls mortally wounded. Barbarigo and Serenaders escape. Fred. —The devil seize his cool sobriety! This comes of fighting drunk. Ang. Art hurt, St. Cyr? Fred. My valour is not fumy: but, methinks, I could not, on cold water, slay my man. Enter Julian, Augustus, and Attendants, with torches. Aug. —Where are these brawlers at my father's door? Jul. —Frederick! by the mass! account for this! Frederick thou art not surely hurt? Fred. A little! Jul. —Speak, I implore you! Fred. Oh! nothing! only, Jule, You have been drinking love—I drinking wine— And Barbarigo drinking blood—that's all! Jul. (to Angelo) —Speak, sir! Ang. We tracked our friend, who followed here The Barbarigo—Frederick heard him bargain With hired assassins for your life— Fred. Ay, ay! Less elocution!—I've but little life To spare, and death needs not your hiperboles To herald him! Jul. You're wounded— Fred. Murdered, sir! Say honourably slain, we will not quarrel About the epithet. Jul. O God of heaven! And must he perish in a cause like this! Fred. —The cause is good enough, when thousands die For ribbons, gold, and stars! A brawl's a brawl, And kings and nations fight for nothing more, Begild their motives with what names you will! No matter, Jule, my child! we all must die! And when we have drained the gilded cup of life— Weighed good and evil—chosen which is which— And come upon the dregs of disappointment— It little matters when or how we go! Jul. —O Frederick! this is poor philosophy To soothe a dying man! Fred. Philosophy? Philosophy is but another word For madness, that aids neither life nor death! Jul. —I would not argue now on such absurdity. But Frederick— Fred. Julian! come, I know your meaning. You wonder that I do not weep at leaving A world, whose happiness hath long left me. The sorest heart in deepest silence breaks! We come and go, the creatures of our fate, Mourned for a moment—then forgot for ever! We judge each other by our smiles or tears— And yet the veriest jester of mankind Oft wears his smile upon an aching heart! The fool reproves the wise man, in his folly— For in the drunkard and the blasphemer, The best of us are emblem'd; making scorn Of his almighty love who made us all. Ha, ha! you look most eloquent amazement! Coupling my wise words with my foolish deeds, You know not which to call me, knave or fool. Regard your neighbour—merchant, lord, or slave— Is not his nature such a contradiction To all the sense of reasoning man, that laughter Curls up the lip of every thing that is! Jul. —Alas! this creed is little consolation! Fred. —I do not weep—it is because I've known The inutility of life— Jul. Except To teach us how to die. Fred. True! But my days Were squandered in a fever to outrun My cares—I could not do it, Julian, no! But, courage! let me die, sirs! Tell the world I care not for its epitaph, I could Not read its praise, and shall not hear its curse! Dies. Jul. —Let me look steadfastly upon that face! There! cover it! Its marble stillness gives No answer to the question I have asked. I wished to gather from its silence whether Our sorrows end with our existence here— If so, I'd like to die! Ang. Julian! come, man, This is no blame of yours. Jul. No, it said nought! Death's silent and mysterious hand hath sealed The secret in eternity; and sent Him, with his countless follies on his shoulders, Without a single grace of preparation, Into the presence of his God and Judge. Ang. —What think you on? Jul. Terrible things! Aug. Come, man, The world will hold you innocent, no fear! Jul. —The world? The world, no fear, will hold us guilty, If they but find a shadow of suspicion, A spot of doubt, a breath of ill report On which to hang the curse of their damnation! Aug. —You make the danger over fearful. Jul. Fear? A heart that hath outlived, like mine, the trial Of earth's sad disappointment, grows too callous To tremble. Let the happy tremble! Wretches, Like me, have nothing left to fear! Enter Barbarigo and followers. Bar. Ha! Julian! Renounce for ever her, whose name you sully! This sword shall win Bianca from your hopes! Jul. —I will not fight with you, assassin!—Slave! You seek to polish up your tarnished honor By wiping out its blemishes on me. Get thee away! if this be honor, I Am most dishonorably ashamed of it! Bar. —Coward! you shall not thus escape me! Jul. Coward? I am so little coward, Barbarigo, That I have courage to deride a slander, And pass the hired assassin by with scorn. Bar. —Coward! come back! turn on me, if you be A man! A true Venetian—Turn, I say! For Venice, for Bianca, turn, you coward! Jul. —That I am true Venetian, let this prove; That, true unto my country's dignity, I brave the slanderer of Venice, whilst I scorn'd him as the lib'ler of myself. But for the lady's name, your blasphemy Profanes, I will wipe out your impious speech In your own venomous blood! no parly, come! They fight, Barbarigo is disarmed. There! take your life! Nay, thank me not! you'll find Life, shorn of honor, such a bitter curse, That death would seem a blessing. Powers above! Have ye designed us for no better ends Than warring on each other, like the beasts! I wonder that your lightenings do not blast The uplifted arm against its fellow creature! What, to its fallen victim (pointing to Frederick) is that honor For which he perished? By the mass! 'tis strange The dead rise not in judgement on our deeds! Methinks my sense will abdicate its throne To these usurping passions, for I cannot Reason myself out of a tyrannous hate Of men—if men are nothing more than these! Enter Officer and Guards. Off. —What, ho! there! stand or fall! we do attach You traitors to the peace—seize every one! Your swords! Jul. Mine hath disgraced its master's courage! It owed the state that murderer's blood, yet would not Strike to his heart—hence! disobedient steel! What an egregious innocent am I To look with pity on mankind, whose hearts Are harder than the everlasting rocks! Sunk in their guilt as fathomless as hell! And only fit to wreak our vengeance on! Off. —Your pardon, but my duty thrusts on me What I regret. Jul. Regret it not, I pray you! Weep, if you will, that human villainy Requires a human scourge! You must, perforce, Think men are wondrous savage; all you see Are spotted with some damnable black sin. Off. —I strive to think more favourably of men Than those I see induce me. There are beings Deserve our praise, if we will seek them out. Jul. —So people say—experience contradicts it. Truth, justice, virtue, honor are the words, That, imp-like, play upon our tongues; but black Hypocrisy reigns in the hearts of all! The world is but a strumpet, and, I tell you, There is not in her arms one honest man! Exeunt Julian, Officer, and Guards. Ant. —We'll seek his father, for events like these Blot out all difference, and bring together, In friendliness, the most determined foes. Ang. —Such should be, but is not the course of things— What ought to be's so different from what is. Ant. —Misfortune heals our anger with her rough But salutary physic. Julian's father Must sympathise with his son's sufferings, Albeit he may reprobate his errors. Ang. —If anger were the mere result of will Opposed, submission would restore our love. But man's displeasure's often an enigma— Solved by his temper, avarice, conceit, Pride, vanity, moroseness, natural bile, And artificial follies. Julian's sire Will live to rue the bitter day he flung A child, however faulty, from his heart! Exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT IV. SCENE I. —Hall in Lodoro's palace. Peter, Beppo, and other Servants' arranging the Room. Peter. —By the holy keys of St. Peter! but this is the most cruel catastrophe to such a day that ever was degendered on a house! Beppo. —Marry! Master Peter, but you're too learned for a servant—you talk finer than your master. What now may be the meaning of these corkscrew words? Peter. —Demonstrate the word. Beppo. —Ay, rumonstrate—you're a rum un to get out such expressions—you remind me of a beef-eater at a show. Peter. —Beppo, thy vulgarity will for ever keep thee and good luck on the wrong side of the hedge. Look you, let me see your man that talks big, and all the world shall look up to his great words—but let me see your fool that speaks low, and all the world shall walk over his imbecility: I tell you, Beppo, your modest man is but the rug on which every gentleman wipes his shoes. Beppo. —Well, Master Peter, you won't suffer under the defects of modesty. I never saw a servant who carried his head more fearlessly in the face of his master. Peter. —Why, friend Beppo, an' we will be civil to the insolent world, we must take the consequence, which is—the world's contempt. But an' a man carry his head with becoming hauteur, he at least keeps his nose above all unpleasant odours. Beppo. —Hortur—what a word for a Christian to swallow! Peter. —It is an elegant extract from our neighbours the French. And, let me tell you, Beppo, to season your conversation with a spice of French, now-a-days, is the criterion whereby a person of breeding is judged. Beppo. —But you cannot speak French. Peter. —N'importe, violà donc. Beppo. —Holy mother! Peter. —There again, Beppo, in that indigenous oath you manifest the coarseness of your extraction. Now a lady's lips may pout out Sa'cristi, which, being interpreted, is much worse than yours—but as the one is foreign, it comes within the pale of fashion, whereas the other is totally excommunicated from ears polite. Beppo. —Well, it must be a grand thing to travel! Peter. —Truly, Beppo, it is the sign whereby, in these times, you shall know the gentleman from the boor. Look you! not to be able to speak of the Pyramids and Les Modes de Paris, Parnassus and Le Palais Royal, Timbuctoo and the Holy Land, argueth an insignificance, not only very lamentable in itself, but militating much against the advancement of our great toe into the drawing-room of the recherché. Beppo. —By Saint Peter!— Peter. —Ah! swear not by such a vulgar oath! unfortunately I am called Peter, but my parents were very religious, and consequently very silly old people. Beppo. —Master Peter, mayhap I'm somewhat older, though less learned than you—but let me tell you, I am too old ever to learn that true religion makes a fool of a man. Peter. —Upon my honor! The boor is insolent! Beppo. —I'm honest, Master Peter. Peter. —Ruffian! would you insult a gentleman? Villain, and knave! Beppo. —Hard words for an honest man to stomach! Peter. —Dirty and detestable varlet! Beppo. —Varlet to yourself! Peter. —Zounds! are you saucy! sir, I wear a steel! Beppo. —And I, Master Peter, carry about with me the only defence that an honest man needs—a bold heart and a willing arm! Come! an' we try a tussel in the good old fashion, I will acquaint that mountebank jacket with the nature of the canal. I don't know, and I don't much respect your modes abroad—but, an' you wish to be friend or foe after the good old custom of my country, and my fathers, I'm your man, and am ready for what you will! Peter. —Gracious Lady! what a Russian bear! Enter Maria. Mar. —How! quarrelling in the hall among yourselves, instead of holding together to study your master's wants? It seems those who are paid for their service are ever the last to render it. Beppo. —Indeed, Mistress Maria— Maria. —Beppo, this disturbance was not yours. Peter. —Ineffably divine creature! Maria. —Sir, if there be one thing more than another, that turns me sick, it is the intrusion of a fool! Peter. —Ah! my adorable and perfectly exquisite angel! Maria. —How long must silenced patience bear such insults! Shame upon ye all, rioting now in such absurdities, when you should mourn behind our buried pastimes! Augustus will be dispatched to Cyprus, to cut his way back to his father's favours through the ranks of war. My poor lady is dying of grief! Julian may be hung for taking justice out of the hands of the law—and my lord and lady will break their hearts for spite, that all the world won't go at the bidding of their wish—and here are you knaves quarrelling over a straw while the house is tumbling to pieces about your ears! Get away, with you, each man to his work! and, Beppo, you shall go with me to inquire the news of Julian's fortunes. Exeunt. SCENE II. —A street in Venice. Enter Giacomo, meeting Maria. Gia. —Heigho! Maria! what terrible times these be! Mar. —The times are good enough—we blame the age For errors that we should amend ourselves. The world is never over old for us T' improve our manners in it. Tell me, doth Not Julian stand acquitted? Gia. By the law. But by the lawless passion of his father, Condemned to any misery that ill-luck Can lead him to, and she is seldom slow To help us down the precipice of ruin. How did my lady bear the tidings? Mar. As The tender sapling bears the light'ning's flash— She fell a shivered victim to the earth! And now you might as well expect fresh leaves To blossom on the blasted tree, as hope To see her ever smile again! Gia. Alas! And yet they dare to question woman's love! God bless her! life indeed were but a desert, Unless the flower of woman's loveliness Bloomed o'er the waste and beautified the scene! Mar. —Thank heav'n, time hath not hardened all our natures! Some still are living who deserve to live, And thou art one of these, good Giacomo? How can you find the Signor Julian? Gia. Ah! I know no more than you, Maria. Report Rumours his having fled to hide his sorrow And broken fortunes in the solitudes Of the Euganean hills—he cannot brook The heartless gaze of public scrutiny. The Barbarigo, too, hath bought his freedom, And Julian's boiling wrath would prompt his arm To blot the memory of his injury out With blood, if he remained in Venice. Mar. Ah! They will compel my lady to espouse The Barbarigo: for, in Venice, titles, Wealth, and a palace, laugh to scorn the poor Pretensions of an honorable heart, Like Julian's, that is rich in honor only, And his too fatal passion for my mistress! Gia. —Would Julian knew her constancy! Mar. He could not— Dared not doubt it for a single instant! Gia. —Maria! I, an old man, may be pardon'd To say the best of us forget each other, As fortune gives or takes away her favours. Mar. —Oh! not Bianca! while her sense remains Unwarped by these disasters, she will cling, Like ivy, to her faith—by heaven she will! Enter Lorenzo's Wife. Wife. —Giacomo! where, O! where is my poor boy? What bosom must that be to tear asunder The fibres of its old affections thus, And thrust its offspring on the cruel world! The infant that clung sleeping to his heart! The child that from his knee looked up and smiled Hope, peace, and joy into a father's face! The boy that grew beside him in his sports, Free as the breeze and graceful as the fawn! The man that proudly honored him, and stood The ornament of his declining years! And then to hurl this jewel from his heart Like an infectious and abhorr'd disease, And trample him i' the dust of beggary— He hath much need to ask of heaven forgiveness! Mar. —My lady, if good Giacomo would seek The Signor Julian with some present aid, Time may assist our exigencies. Wife. True! If his indignant bosom hath not burst Already, and let forth the groaning life. Such souls as his are crushed, but never bowed. Go, Giacomo! search every where. This purse Will speed his fortunes for a period. Come, Maria! come with me, and tell me how Your poor unhappy lady bears this news. Exeunt. SCENE III. —A Forest among the euganean hills. Julian. Jul. —How wearily time lingers with the wretch! The hours that pass so swiftly o'er our joys, Yet eke their moments out to mock our woes. Where now are all those gorgeous images With which our youthful fancy peopled life? The thoughts, the dreams, the hopes, the aspirations, That in our minds were as the stars in heaven— The flowers on earth—the blossoms of the tree! How years and disappointment's hand restore Them to their pristine elements, and leave The empty heart a miserable ruin! A ruin round whose early walls there clung How many—oh! how many lovely things— All faded, withered, fallen, past away! O God! that all our smiles must turn to tears! That all our happiness must change to sorrow! And the great soul, that spurns adversity, Must bend in slavery to the body's yoke! Lo! I am grown right lean and hungry on Philosophy! All things in nature feed One on another, or they die and perish, Even as these sinless leaves and flowers! Ay, hunger Still links us to the most detested shifts! Hunger! the body hungers—and the soul Is hungry too—all things in nature hunger One for another! Autumn hungers after The dying glories of the spectral boughs— Beast prowls for beast—man laps the blood of man— While, death, triumphantly, with hideous jaws, Hungers to swallow all into the tomb! Accursed life! and thrice accursed death! SCENE IV. —A street in Venice. Angelo and Antonio. Ant. —Welcome, my friend! What news of Julian? Ang. Bad! True to her custom, Fortune seems to heap Calamities upon th' unfortunate. Julian's mishaps have so divorced his actions From all allegiance to his better reason, That even now he's counted for a madman. Ant. —Thanks to our stars! we know that, once mistaken, The world's swift censure overtakes our steps And hunts us through each persecuted change. Where shelters Julian his condemned head? Ang. —Under the weeping skies! God turn their anger, And o'er the houseless lull their storms to sleep! Shall we go seek him? I have not a heart So cased by artifice as to reflect Good fortune's smiles and sicken at her frowns. Those I write in the tablets of my love, The hand of death alone shall wipe away! Ant. —I serve you in a cause so righteous. Ang. Come! Exeunt. SCENE V. —Another street in Venice. Julian. Jul. —Life is a fearful struggle—right to wrong— When all the odds are in a bad man's favour! And yet 'tis more dishonorably base To die, and give our names to ignominy, Than to persist in battling with ill-luck And conquering the agony of want. Enter Senator. So! I will ask this senator of Venice To find me labour, in his way of duty. Good morrow! Are you not a senator? Sen. —A senator, to whom you are unknown. Jul. —I'm of the multitude the titled know not. But of that multitude whence, daily springs Some one who makes his name familiar with The latest record of his country's language. Sen. —What does this lead to? Jul. I entreat you not Utterly to despise me as our custom Warrants, because I am a nameless stranger! I am a scholar; and, to th' eternal shame Of my dishonorable land, I swear I crave the food denied me here in Venice! Sen. —Impossible! Jul. There's nought impossible! Genius and beggary—wealth and despair— Virtue disgraced, and vice exalted!—oh! There is no crying sin so foul and hideous— No passion so deformed, unnatural, And monstrous to belief, that is not cherished, Fostered, and worshipped in your halls of grandeur!— And will you tell a starving man it is Impossible to hunger? Would you felt Want's awful and hyæna-like desire To leap upon the heart's blood of such monsters As scorn and riches make us! By the heavens!— Even senators would dread the indignant poor! Sen. —What mean you, rebel? Jul. Rebel!—you are right! Nature rebels against all art's refinements To starve the spirit tamely from the body! Sen. —Molest me, and I will alarm the guard. Jul. —Molest you? Senator! you are at liberty To pass along in the enjoyment of The enviable consciousness of good Witheld, with the ability to give. Sen. —There's money! Jul. Curse and ruin seize your money! The ruin its accursed acquisition, Time out of mind, hath wrought the noble heart! Sen. —What would you? Money you refuse— Jul. Hath nature Prompted you to no other sympathy With suffering, than ostentatious charity? What would I?—Physic for my bleeding heart! Balm for my wounded honor! Something that Would heal this lacerated, groaning spirit, Stabbed by the dagger of unkindness! Something Approaching to humanity—if such A virtue now exist among mankind! Sen. —I am a stranger—are there none whose aid You should demand? Jul. None! If there were ten thousand, Linked to me by the bonds of flesh and blood, I would not sue my brother for a gift, Because my brother. 'Tis the heart I seek, That glories in its goodness, and would beat As warmly for a stranger and a slave, As for its own and nearest, dearest blood! Sen. —You speak well—but such imposition's practised— Jul. —I know it! But hath nature written honesty On no man's forehead? Look upon this face And tell me if you think I am a villain! Sen. —I must repeat— Jul. You hesitate?—O God! 'Tis hopeless!—Virtue never hesitates Between the wish to do, and doing good! I'll word your benediction—“Rascal, hence! I feel your clutches on my purse, away!”— May the God of heav'n commiserate your sins! I would not curse aught so ignobly vile! Exit Senator, and enter Gondolier. Another of my kind!—Your occupation? Gond. —A rudish one—a gondolier of Venice. Much labour, more abuse, some pence, my bread, And shelter in my sea-rock'd bark by night, Are all I know of life and life's enjoyments. Jul. —'Tis but a shabby picture, yet I lack So good a bed or board—I'll serve you, friend. Gond. —You're jesting—it were likelier I served you. Jul. —No, I am little like a jesting man. My means are run ashore—I ask but work, However rude, to gain a livelihood. Gond. —Still you but jest. Some noble, I presume, Returned from revels— Jul. Every word is true! Gond. —Then, friend, you're sailing from your course. Hard work Would master you—Seek something better, man!— Try beggary—you have not strength for me. Jul. —Dastard! I have enough to chastise yet Your incivility! Driving him off. So! even these, The refuse in the siftings of ill-luck, Have learned no sympathy from hardships, that Should make misfortune seem their common friend. What use are all thy lessons, earth, that teach The heart to grow no better, age by age? Enter Giacomo. Here is a most aristrocratic varlet! He who hath fed on other's bounty should Be generous—I ask your charity! Gia. —My master begging! gracious heav'n, he's mad! Jul. —Ah, Signor Giacomo! once my good servant— You see, now, what a curious world this is, Where fortunes shift, as cards change hands, and those Who served become the servers—pray relieve me! Gia. —O, Master Julian! O, my dear young master! Jul. —I am a beggar—and our poverty Is a sharp medicine, that purges out The delicacy of our former pride. Gia. —You trifle with me—all I have is yours. Jul. —Thou liest! Ay, to gain excuse and time, Thou dost prevaricate—get hence, thou worm! I cannot injure what I once have loved!— Another, and I would have smote him down, To teach the purse-proud savage in his pride, That want is still more terrible than wealth! Exit. Gia. —O heaven! my poor, poor master's brain is turned! I've seen men wear their evil fortunes like A rusty garment—but, alas! this change Will murder him! My kind, good Master Julian! Enter Maria. Alas! Maria! my poor unhappy master! Mar. —Is?— Gia. Mad with his griefs! Mar. And my unhappy lady— Gia. —Good heavens! not?— Mar. Mad? Not in the common meaning And acceptation of that frightful word. Hers is a suffering too deep for passion To give tempestuous utterance to—'tis silent As the disease that eats into the heart, And steals the blossoms from her cheek away!— Mysterious as the approach of death! She never, Never will smile again, my poor, poor mistress! Ah, me! this sad, sad life, that, ere we die, Makes us lament that ever we were born! Gia. —God speed my lady! Such a heart as hers Was over righteous for this wicked world: And the compassionate angels will remove The treasure to its home in some far heaven. Mar. —Surely the all just skies have not afflicted Our sense with these calamities in vain! If stubbornness melt not with such reproof, The chastisement and will of God are nothing! Gia. —I would now Julian's father could foresee The consequence of his unnatural pride, Ere some unthought of, horrible disaster Place reparation past his reach for ever! Enter Lorenzo's Wife. Wife. —What news of Julian? Gia. Such as should destroy A parent's sense of other news for ever. Madness and poverty are his companions, To smooth the pillow of disease and ruin. Wife. —Spare me, old man! have mercy on a mother! Madness and poverty? One is enough To render life a curse most horrible! The two might warrant some such desperation As blots our claim out to be counted human. Gia. —I parted with him even now, but previously Had gathered from the whisperings of report, That, on the Isle of Ledo, he conceals His wretchedness.— Wife. I'll seek him instantly— A mother's blessing may ameliorate Somewhat the cruel pangs of injury! Enter Lorenzo. Lor. —Still weeping for this disobedient boy? Wife. —'Tis not an easy task to pluck up all Our old affections by the roots, and fling Our hopes away, like common things of earth. Lor. —Hang him! The disobedient reprobate! Wife. —He is indeed most disobedient now! Would he obeyed his mother's wild commands!— And I would bid him stay—but death hath called My gentle boy away for ever! Lor. Death? Wife. —Giacomo, lead me forth unto his grave! If tears availed me, I'd bedew the ground Till flowers of sweet remembrance, in the perfume Of immortality, sprung up to blossom Over my boy, more beautiful than they! Shame on them now triumphantly to bloom O'er his pale corpse, that living shamed them all! Lor. —Speak, I implore you! Giacomo, what's this? Julian and death? my son!—my boy!—my Julian! Dead? Dead? Forgive me, God! for I am dying! Falls on the Earth. Wife. —Woes me! my grief outstrips my judgment, and Mourning too much one loss, I make another. Look up, look up! make me not in one breath Widow and childless—one is agony Enough for one unhappy breast to suffer! Lor. —Where have they buried him? Wife. He is not dead! Lor. —I'll not believe it! Wife. There is hope, I swear it! Lor. —Hope for a wretch like me?—I'll not believe it! Wife. —Put not away in this unmanly fashion, The assurance reason gives us.—Julian lives— And injuries redressed are swiftly cured. Lor. —I do reject the phantasy of hope As a most worthless dream, and to my heart Will hug remorse, as with a lover's eagerness! Wife. —For shame! are these extremes of passion fit To find their utterance from a man like you? Lor. —Lost, lost, and shipwreck'd in the tempests of My own conceits!—the deadliest fate of all! The victim of my own most monstrous follies!— Burnt in a self created hell! Ah, Julian! My poor unhappy boy! Pardon me! pardon! Exit. Wife. —What are we made of, to be shattered thus, By the least turn of fortune's tide and wind? I thought to melt him, by a stratagem, From th' frozen sternness of his anger, back Into the current of parental love; And, like a long-pent stream, the sluices broken, Over all intermediate things he dashes Frightfully to his ruin. Where's the use Of age and life's experience, if they teach No moderation in our natural passions? SCENE VI. —A room in Lodoro's house. Bianca discovered musing beside a harp—Enter Maria. Mar. —Ah, me! the misery of a hopeless sorrow! O youth! what is thy strength? O beauty! where Is all thy glory, when an angry breath Of fortune withers up both power and pride? Go to! you are but fancies of the brain! This eye, that yesterday so brilliant was!— This cheek, that in a flower-like beauty blossomed!— How meaningless, how faded, how decayed! This heart, that bounded with a million hopes, Countless and gay, as waves on summer seas, Young as the morning, lovely as the spring— To day is old and withered up with care! Go to, I say! all things below deceive us! And there is nothing under the vast skies, Robed in whatever colours it may be, But is a gross deception and a fraud!— But ah! how is my poor unhappy lady? Bianca, coming forward. Bia. —Julian, why regret our wicked union? It is no crime, on earth to wed those hearts That, from the earliest ages of creation, Nature had married in the halls of heaven. Nay, do not frown so! It is worse than hell, When they who once adored, turn round with hate Upon the idol of their former love! Mar. —Alas! my lady! Bia. Is it tender hearted T' upbraid the lovely weakness that was once The diadem of all your happiness? O fy! for shame! out on ungrateful man! To pluck the spring-flower of our beauty thus, And fling it on the winter blasts, to perish! Mar. —My lady! Bia. Monstrous! monstrous wickedness! There's no depravity so boundless, but Within man's breast, capacious for all evil, Hath lodgment!—Oh! the very beasts have more Than he, of nature's bounteous gratitude! Who shares your sorrows, doubles all your joys?— Woman! whose sole reward is your contempt!— I tell you, hell holds nought so vile as man! Mar. —Oh! have you no religion? Bia. Yes, religion Once, with a rainbow sympathy, could bind My aspirations to eternity. Then I was innocent—I had not loved! Since I have dared the crime of loving—Julian! The Eden of thy eyes is all the heaven, The hope, the happiness left with this heart! Thou art my girl Maria? Mar. Ay, my lady. Bia. —I bade you once bring flowers—you told me then, There grew a pansie, called heart's-ease—Go, now, I do beseech you! cull me some of these! Mar. —How feels my lady? Better now? Bia.- Ay, faith! The flowers—and I shall soon be well again! We'll hold a merry marriage feast to night! Are my lord's wedding garments all arranged? Go, bid him hasten—or I sadly fear His rival, Death, will kiss the bride to night. How strange that a presentiment of death At times should haunt us in the midst of life! Enter Mother. Mar. —Here comes your lady mother. Mo. Girl! how feel you? Bia. —At midnight, in the marble vault, we meet! Mo. —Bianca, have you then forgot your mother? Bia. —Do we forget the cold amidst the snow? The heat i' the tropics, or the tempest in The storm and whirlwind? Do we ever, ever, Ever forget those who have injured us? Mo! —Maria, I observe she still upbraids Her father and myself, yet constantly Is kind and amiable to you who serve her. This speaks more of deception than insanity. Mar. —Indeed, my lady, I must boldly say You do her feelings such a violence, By thrusting in her ear your arguments In favour of the Barbarigo's suit— I marvel not, her anger still pursues you. Mo. —I am rebuked! We must be temperate, And not o'erstrain the duty of our children, Or we may snap affection's strongest chords. I have withstood her love for Julian, who, Is but, in circumstance, a very beggar. Yet, if we lose our darling child, how more— How ten times more than beggars we should be! Come, and consult with me of this, Maria. Where lodges Julian? Mar. On the Isle of Ledo, And half as mad as my poor lady. Mo. Come! Exeunt Mother and Maria. Bia. —Upon the Isle of Ledo—half as mad! Ye stars, that rule, or seem to rule our destinies! I grow so mad of hopeless grief, that any Uunnatural thing I did would show more wisdom Than perishing so miserably slow! I've loved, and lived, and suffered—and what more Hath life, that I should not exchange for death?— Except that the worst evil of our life May mend—with death the evil is eternal! What kind of woman have I grown, to argue These awful mysteries in such cold blood? I, who once gloried in the noonday sunshine Of every joy, now plunge i'the darkest night Of misery and despair!—Such is the lesson, Bitter and cruel, that we learn of life! Julian! If I must die, it shall be where This heart may perish worthily—within Thy arms!—Ye adverse fortunes! now I dare ye, And laugh your most malignant powers to scorn! Exit. SCENE VII. —A room in Barbarigo's Palace. Barbarigo, Galeno. Bar. —Thou art acquainted, being a physician, With many subtle remedies—Is there No poison that can rid us of our foes? The haunting phantom of detection scares you? Gal. —I know a chemical so deadly strong, That 'ministered unto the doge, he'd fall, Amidst th' assembled senate, dead to earth. Bar. —(Aside. We never want our tools, however bad, But we may hunt them out among mankind!) You're poor? Gal. Our poverty bespeaks itself, And, not like merit, needs be pointed out. Bar. —(Offering a purse.) You understand this argument? 'tis heavy. Gal. —So is a murderer's conscience! Bar. Conscience? pooh! When fortune so unconscionably leaves us, Methinks, without great conscientious scruple, We might shake hands with any accident To mend our means. Come, I presume we have Each others cue—except, like all the world, You make a virtue of your villainy— While mine is but my virtue—to the matter! Why do you hesitate? Detection? Speak! Or, by San Marco! if you dare my anger, I'll bray your shaking bones in your own mortars, And roast them in your own crucibles! Gal. My lord! Remember you have placed your reputation Somewhat incautiously within my power! Bar. —Dastard! Gal. Another word, and I alarm The night guard! Bar. You escape me not, you villain! Gal. —Peace, or I give the alarm! Bar. Ha, ha! Galeno! I did but test the metal of thy courage, And find thee trusty—but, suppose I mention To th' Inquisition somewhat of the chemical That in th' assembled senate, would, without Suspicion, slay the doge? Ha! have I caught you? Come, sirrah! there was never yet a scoundrel But might be mated in his villainy. What? speak! Gal. My lord, I was not serious— Bar. —I am! and bent on Julian's life or yours. Which do you estimate the dearest? Gal. How Has he deserved this treachery? Bar. By vilely Stealing upon the slumber of my fortunes, In his too happy favour with a lady; And rousing me to the dread consciousness, That one, or both of us must surely die! Gal. —In such a way? Bar. Who yields his foe one inch Of vantage, that he wisely might maintain— May live with honor, but would die a fool. We grow too wordy on this business.—See! Your best reward (showing the purse) and let it be enough, Besides, that 'tis my pleasure Julian dies— And, like each pleasure, I must pay for it. Ha! you assent? That is, your poverty Rebels against pride's nice considerations, And thus we fall the victims of ourselves! Go instantly—go in this very tune! Speak to him from his father—feel his pulse— Pronounce him feverish—prescribe a draught— An anodyne—a strong potation, doctor! One that requires no second dose—come, come! When Julian sleeps, you slumber on a pillow, So gilded that e'en conscience will not wake you. Gal. —You bind me by a double chain—and both The links are strong ones—poverty and fear. Bar. —Ay, ay, and hope is stronger far than both! Away then! and, remember, sir, the chemical! The doge, the Inquisition! (Exit Galeno) Fear is still Our heaviest power upon the human mind, From Rome to Iceland, over land and sea! Exit.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT V. SCENE I. —Interior of a Peasant's Hut on the Isle of Ledo. Julian. Jul. —Thank God! I have fulfill'd man's destiny! That is, to be beloved, believed, bepraised— And then to be betrayed, belied, bescorned! To hear, in infancy, affection's blessings— And feel, in manhood, hatred's bitter curse! To harbour hopes as gorgeous as the heavens, One after one for disappointments changed! To win a heart as pure as virgin snow, And see its passion melt and die away! To honor—as the heritors and lords Of countless excellences—our superiors— And find them out impostors, knaves, and fools! Pursuing shadows—entertaining dreams! Believing every one—believed of none! Defamed by those we benefit—abused By those we trusted—ridiculed by all!— And elbowed through a clamorous, senseless crowd!— Their wonder, or their mockery and scorn— Such is our life—and mine, thank God! is ending! Justice and honor, ye have fled this earth, And left us to our natural destitution! Enter Galeno. Gal. —Pardon me! a physician from your father, Sent to consult with you about your health. How feel you? Jul. Like a flower without the rain, Beneath a parching sun! my brain is hot, And lacks the dew of sympathy to cool Its troubled pulse. Gal. This draught will lull to sleep Your sorrows, and, to-morrow, you will cease To recollect your cares. Jul. I do believe it! How lovely is the night! how fairly pace The marshall'd stars along the heavens! They say These all shall perish, even as ourselves. Dost thou believe it, friend? That ruin's hand Shall quench these glorious lights, and dash these spheres All into darkness, night, and anarchy, While things like us shall rise to other life? Gal. —Such thoughts are impious—We're forbid to argue On many things we think on. Jul. But to wrangle, And wrestle with our doubts, is all our chance To rectify our errors. Silently The earth reclaims the earthly part of us! But, when the curtain of another scene Draws up, we all must argue for ourselves. What recks it then, you told me this, or that Is right, or wrong—as I have judged, so shall I then be judg'd—it is an awful thought! Gal. —He's surely mad! Jul. Ha! mad? didst thou say mad? Merciful God! I thought 't would come to this! Mad! you said mad? Ay, that's the word! the shift Of villainy, assassin like, to stab us, And cut the throat of honest reputation! Methinks there's far more madness living here Than dying for a better place than this! Go! get you gone! And, when I'm dead, be sure You bury with me all my virtuous deeds, And hawk my vices thro' the slanderous crowd! Oh! what a bad, censorious world this is! Doctor, the good, the brave, the young, must die! Yet never died that mortal, o'er whose grave Detraction did not, like a viper, crawl! Gal. —(Aside. I have not courage for this sinful business!) Jul. —Each man, who would not have his purpose doubted, Should chalk it up, or we'll belie his worth! It is a monstrous and incongruous state, Where truth and falsehood seem so like each other, That no man living knoweth which is which! Gal. —(Aside. Poor fellow! all the wisdom and the folly Of his wreck'd nature, for the mastery strive. I cannot pawn my soul to such a purpose, Though Ruin's phantom goad me to the task! I cannot, cannot do it!—Barbarigo Is, in his vengeance, most unnatural, And, what he wills in wrath, fulfils in blood! Guide me, ye powers! I have no strength to stand! Takes out a phial. To think that such an instrument as this, Creation's purposes can so defeat, And change this stirring life so stirless death! Jul. —(Seizing the phial.) What have we here? Gal. A sleep-inviting draught. Jul. —How nobly art helps limping nature on! I will assay your cordial! Gal. No! for God's sake! Jul. —Like all the world, thou art a contradiction— Witholding what is for our benefit, And bountifully giving all that's bad! Get thee to bed, and think of growing better! Out! I will take this potion, and redream The long lost pleasures of my happier days. Hence! hence I say! I see you have a lie Blistering upon your pandering lips—get hence! Drives him off, and returns and Swallows the draught. Enter Angelo. Angelo! ha! how goes the chamelion world? Cast off another colour? Thou art come To see how pride can struggle with misfortune? Ang. —No, heaven forbid! Jul. Methinks heaven hath forbid All good to dwell in such a bad abode, As is this earth, where we but come to die! Ang. —We are not all so bad— Jul. As to put out Of pain the victims of our cruelty! We love to see the misery we make! Oh! we're kind hearted scoundrels, all of us! Ang. —What means this? Jul. Nothing, but a fragment of Philosophy, I learn'd just now. Ang. From whom? Jul. —A doctor—who informed me I am mad. What think you? will you try my pulse, sir? Ang. Julian? Jul. —Ha! ha! I find our senses all alike, And ignorance is monarch every where! Ang. —Julian? Jul. No pity! Ang. There's my purse, adieu! Jul. Come hither! Let me gaze upon thee, man! Before I quit this world, I fain would read The lineaments that mark an honest face. Ang. —Take this, good fortune may again be yours. Jul. —Good fortune, to the miserable man, Is but a foil to set his misery off. Ang. But take the purse! Jul. It can no longer turn The hinge of my sad destinies. No! keep it! Therein you have a talismanic charm To ope the steel-lock'd lips of adulation, And, god-like, rule the worship of mankind. My hopes—the worse for me!—were never sunk In gold.—How I'd have used it, were it mine, The Oracle of Time alone could tell. I have not worshipp'd it—therein hath been My worldly folly—It was still to me But as a shadow on a running stream. If I have erred—the atonement is my death! Ang. —Then, Julian, thou'rt resolved to die against The awful judgment of both earth and heaven? Jul. —In heaven there's mercy, but on earth there's none!— And I am done with all whose condemnation, Praise, smiles, or tears, can ever more affect me! Ang. —With all? Your poor old father now repents. Jul. —Pride ne'er repents! He would not ask forgiveness, And could not look me in the face, and say He has not injured me. O Angelo! Language hath not the power to tell how much I loved that father! How I would have given My soul to study and my hand to labour, But for a single smile of approbation! A smile that I did value more than all The praise, the honor of all other men! For years I wooed his love, as sedulously As the sun shines in heaven. I lived for him, And him alone; I thought, in honorable Emulation of the bards of old, To shed reflected glory on his house, And weave a halo round his aged brow. For this, I broke companionship with pleasures Proper to youth-time, and made solitude My soul preceptress. Hours and hours I spent In the dim woods, beneath the aged pine; And, for each hour I gave to learning's search, I spent another, thinking on my father!— Visioning a father's happiness and pride, In the fair reputation of his son! Ang. —Well, well! But he regrets his harsh demeanour— None can do more than mourn and mend the past! Jul. —I do forgive each individual wrong, And every injury he ever did me! For I am journeying to a home, where all The storms of earth die on th' eternal shore Of peace and joy!—I do forgive my father! Ang. —Nay, you will soon be better! Jul. Soon? yes, soon! Ang. —There's hope enough to build an Eden on! Jul. —I raised my paradise on hopes as fair, And honorable—I may say it now— As ever arch'd the skies of promise.—See! Here's the fulfilment of a poet's dream! Ang. —But think upon Bianca! Jul. Oh! I do! And pray that she be happier, far more happy Than ever I could make her! If there be A blessing for the virtuous, it is hers! Ang. —Will you not see her? Jul. To unman my purpose? Ang. —Your purpose? Jul. My unchanging resolution Never again to mingle with my kind! No, Angelo! the lightning-blasted oak Puts forth no more its blossoms to the storm. The flowers of human sympathies are perished, Like dead leaves, on my wither'd heart; and nothing Remains with me but hatred of my race! Loathing and detestation! hate and scorn! All of ye! every one! you're all alike! Ang. —(Aside. Poor fellow! but I will not leave him thus. Misfortune has unhinged his natural feelings, And substituted these unholy passions.) Julian sinks on a seat, overcome with the effects of the Opiate. You're sadly fever'd! will you sleep awhile? I'll watch you. Jul. Well, I care not if I do. I have not slumbered peacefully of late— Moons have roll'd by, while millions slept, and still These burning eyes have watched the stars, and told, Upon their march, the hours of misery! When grief hath made the weary day too long, What an exceeding blessing slumber is! Ang. —How is it, Julian? Thou art ghastly pale! Jul. —My troubled breath comes short and painfully! The warm blood seems to stagnate in my heart!— Angelo!—I am poison'd! Ang. Poison'd? Help! Help, there, without! Jul. Hush! you invoke the winds! I am alone—our misery needs no train To follow its sad funeral to the grave! Ang. —Who tend upon you? Jul. Solitude and want! Harsh ministers to smooth our death-bed pillow! But habit soon familiarizes us To love what once we loathed and trembled at. Ang. —I must bring succour! Jul. Stir not, if you love me! I soon shall be beyond their aid, as now I am beyond the injuries of men! Ang. —What shall I do? Jul. Obey my dying words— Silence! I have a thousand things to say; Yet ere this feeble pulse half numbers that, With all my countless sins—we all are sinners Alike!—I shall be with the things that were! But when the multitude point out the grave Of the—the suicide—give them the lie! I am not mad!—I am no murderer!— Will you believe me? Ang. 'On my soul I will! Jul. —Thanks! thanks! ye gods! at last I've found a friend! Angelo, I am dying!—you inquire If desperation raised Want's bony hand Against the tyranny of life? You think I am a suicide—the word will choke me! Ang. —What am I to believe, then? Jul. What you see, Not what you should believe your friend to be! Ang. —Appearances— Jul. Are such poor evidence To try and judge those thou whom we value by, That we deserve our eyes pluck'd out, who would Permit them to see aught against our reason. Oh! how my throat is parching! burning!—ah! Some water! blessings on you! may they fall In shower-like plenteousness upon your heart! Angelo! I am poison'd by the malice Of some one.—Oh! it could not be my father! He hath abandon'd me most cruelly! But then he loved his gold—his pride—his power— Better than he could love his child.—He loved me Next to his avarice! he would not slay me! Ang. —Divest yourself of such unnatural thoughts— He could not, would not lift his hand against you! Ha! I suspect that coward, Barbarigo! Jul. —Then may the gods forgive, as I forgive him! I would not change that grave, to which I'm hurrying, With all its horrors, for a thousand years Of life, strength, glory, and a guilty heart! O! what strange shadows glide before my vision! Ang. —He sinks! he dies! Julian! Ha! Thou art better? Jul. —Angelo! It may be I have not lived To day, as I would live to-morrow—none— None do so! for still we err, and age, As well as youth, deplores its yesterday! Much we could rectify, if life were leased A little longer—so we say—yet all Would sin again—and, therefore, it is better, Better to die, when young in our enjoyments— Than when the heart's grown old in sin and sorrow! No epitaph, except a sigh, for me! A tear from thee, my beautiful Bianca!— Bianca's dead? Ang. No, surely not! (Aside. Poor fellow! His dying fancy wanders to the past!) Jul. —O, my dear girl!—And so they buried her Under the flowerless earth, because she lov'd— Loved me! Ah! woe, woe, woe is me! All things that love me die! Well, I will die! And we will meet in far and happier lands! In the lone stars, love, which we gazed upon Full many an evening by the ocean shore! Art thou Bianca's spirit? Ang. Look upon me! Jul. —I cannot see—my sight grows very dim! Is that old man my father? Ang. Where? Jul. Look! there! He's weeping o'er a new made grave—alas! How very old and sad my father's grown! Look, look! They're strewing flowers upon a corpse! It is my mother's!—Mother! Barbarigo! Unhand me! Take your grasp from off my throat! Let me but breathe!—you choke me!—let me breathe! I feel I've yet a giant's strength to tear Your murderous heart out by the gory fibres! Villain! you strangle me!—Ha! murder! Ha! You choke—cho—choke me! Ah! help! oh! Dies. Lorenzo rushes in, followed by Antonio and Giacomo. Lor. —What do I see? What voice is that I hear! Words words ye have no power to utter this! Ang. —Where lingers Julian's mother? Ant. With his spirit! Ang. —Dead? Lor. Yes, I murder'd her! I broke her heart! Broke hers!—broke his! and cannot break my own! Ang. —God pity our disasters, and forgive us! Lor. —God makes, and man unmakes, deforms, defiles, Abuses all the bounteous gifts of nature, And, to worst curses, heaven's best blessings turns! Ang. —Lorenzo!— Lor. Do not curse me! O, my God! The very criminal, with blood-stained hands Clasp'd, on the scaffold, o'er his weeping child, Would show more pity than I did to mine! Ang. —I would— Lor. I know it! curse and blast my heart, Ten thousand times more black than it is cursed! I do deserve it all! That all mankind, All human nature, yea the stones o'the street, Rise up in judgment, and, with tongues of fire, Pursue me down to hell for ever! Ang. Sir, Your passion doth forget all proper reverence! Lor. —Rev'rence! what thing upon the wide, wide world Reveres Lorenzo! poverty, starvation, Famine, disease, death—all, all things are better, Happier—yea nothing—to be nothing were To be more envied than to be Lorenzo! I, on whom Providence bestowed so much— Wealth, marriage, offspring, and ten thousand blessings Denied to twice ten thousand wretched creatures!— Years link'd unto years, for ever and ever, Cannot make guilt return to innocence! To curse what blest me!—Hate what loved me so!— Pride, avarice!—O ye damned, damned demons! What loosed ye out of hell to scourge us so! O death! My boy so doubly blest in death! The guilty never, never, never die! Rushes out. Enter suddenly, from one side Bianca, and from the opposite, her Mother, Lodoro, Barbarigo, Maria, and Attendants. Bia. —Where is he? Julian! Julian! dead and cold! Throws herself on the body. Ang. —Confusion on confusion, grief on grief! Antonio, follow, or that desperate man, Lorenzo, may take vengeance on himself. Exit Antonio. Lod. —Unhappy girl! come hence! what sight is this? Bia. —(Rising.) You do not know it? No, no! It is death! Death! murder! death! gaze on its ghastly face Until you know the aspect of its horror, It soon shall be the tenant of thy halls! Lod. —We must remove her! Bia. Angelo, they call you? Ang. —Yes, lady. Bia. Thou wert friend of my poor Julian's? Ang. —I watched him to the last! Bia. O happy you! The very bed on which he died was happier To be beside my Julian, than Bianca! Oh! how I envy you that last sad blessing, To close the dying eyes of one you loved! Ang. —His last breath murmur'd forth Bianca's name. Bia. —There! there! I knew—I told you how he loved! I felt it! swore it! yes I swore he loved Me worthily! O Julian! to thy spirit I pledge this vow of an eternal love! Withstand me not! I will pour o'er the dead The offering that ye would not give the living! O Julian! They have sealed thy coral lips In endless silence! they have closed thine eyes In everlasting darkness! never more Can eye or lip assure me of thy love! But even death thy spirit could not slay! No, no! it smiles upon me even now! Look you, it smiles! smiles as it smiled in life— Making a sunshine of my sorrow! there! It goes! I follow! Julian! gentle Julian! Smile love! thy lady follows thee! My boy! They can't pursue us now! come, sit thee down, Under the shadow of these leafy trees, And sing me songs of olden chivalry! Lod. —We must remove her from the body! Bia. Hush! It is the murmur of the little brook! Fear not! they cannot persecute us now! Come, gentle Julian! Come, my poet boy! Sing me some wild old song, that shall recall The pleasant times gone by, when, side by side, We wandered on the Adriatic shore! Well, never mind! we will not mourn the past! It is a memory on which to dwell, That ocean, with the sun-light on its bosom, Like lovers sleeping in each others arms! But we'll forget these things, and hope shall roam, Like angels, through the future's azure skies! We will not think on fathers or on mothers, But all in all will be unto ourselves! My love is weary! we have travelled far! Far, far away from earth and all its cares! Sleep, love! the sound of sorrow never more Shall travel from the distant world of woe! Sleep, my beloved, on this mossy bank! While I will strew with violets thy head, And pleasant dreams attend thee in thy slumbers! Enter Officer and Galeno, attended by Guards. Off. —Barbarigo, thou'rt attach'd upon the charge Of this physician, with the death of Julian. Bia. —'Tis false! He is not dead, my gentle Julian! Lo! he but slumbers! hush! you will awake him! How came you to this distant land? we're spirits! You cannot harm us now! we're sinless spirits, And god hath told us we may love each other! Off. —Alas! this is indeed a mournful scene! Bia. —The little birds have sung my boy to rest! The music of the forest leaves hath lull'd His heart to sleep beside the running stream! How cold he is! poor child, how cold he is! But never mind, his love is warm as ever! Mo. —This is thy doing, Barbarigo! Off. Justice Demands its victim—off with him to prison! Lod. —Have you no sorrow? no remorse? Hard hearted, Unnatural, monstrous, bloody murderer? Off. —Lord Barbarigo!— Bia. Barbarigo! ha! Up Julian! Julian! Barbarigo's here! Protect me, love! O waken, waken, Julian! Fly! fly! up, Julian! Julian, let us fly! O'er plains and mountains, valleys, rivers, seas— Through the unfooted desert! let us brave Cold, hunger, thirst, fatigue—Oh! death itself!— Anything but to meet that murderer! Up, Julian! Oh! my love, he will not hear me! He cannot! God of heaven! they have murdered him! Falls on the Body. Off. —The state commands the evidence of these! Ang. —Now retribution falls upon you all! Vengeance may slumber, but she never dies! Time brings our deepest hidden sins to light, And justice one day overtakes us all! Long, long, throughout the startled land, shall ring, The sad recital of this Tragedy— And may the moral not be cast away! THE END.</field>
   </doc>
</add>