<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">, , Beckingham, (Charles), Mr, 1699-1731</field>
      <field name="author_facet">, , Beckingham, (Charles), Mr, 1699-1731</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">  beckingham charles mr 1699 1731</field>
      <field name="author_text">, , Beckingham, (Charles), Mr, 1699-1731</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">18th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1710's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V2.0218.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240355</field>
      <field name="date_text">1718</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:459939</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Scipio Africanus ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Scipio Africanus ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="title_facet">scipio africanus</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">scipio africanus</field>
      <field name="title_text">Scipio Africanus ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="year_display">1718</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1718</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1718</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459939&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459939&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;, , Beckingham, (Charles), Mr, 1699-1731&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt; beckingham charles mr 1699 1731&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Scipio Africanus ; A Tragedy&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;scipio africanus&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1718&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1718&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;, , Beckingham, (Charles), Mr&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1699&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1731&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Scipio Africanus&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for W. Mears, J. Browne, and F. Clay [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1718&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872277-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv20218&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 18th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;18th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Scipio Africanus&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 138 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Scipio Africanus.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1718.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 18 Feb 1718.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Scipio Africanus: A TRAGEDY;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Fortior est qui se, quam qui fortissima vincit Mænia—</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE PROLOGUE. Spoken by Mr. Quin. Oft as the Muse, the Register of Fame, Calls from the awful Tomb some glorious Name, Oft as she shews what Virtues Cato knew, Or draws the Scipio's Glories out to View; New Transport on each Feature stands confest, And Expectation burns in ev'ry Breast; Conscious how little Worth these Times behold, We're pleas'd to learn what Heroes were of Old: And when the Poet writes with happy Fire, Ev'n where we cannot Weep, we must Admire. Our Author, who ne'er yet has trod the Stage, Or taught his Muse to swell with Tragick Rage, Boasts, he his Scenes does with a Roman grace, Whose Virtues Britons need not blush to trace. What Youth that's zealous in his Country's Cause, Who wears a Sword to guard her sacred Laws, But may from Scipio learn the Patriot's Name, And from his Maxims emulate his Fame? What laurell'd Chief, who in the doubtful Field, Has forc'd reluctant Victory to yield, But may from Scipio learn, 'tis greater far Himself to conquer than o'ercome in War? Such is the Hero we display to Night, With Conquest deck'd, but more in Honour bright: A Victor, who a Victor's Pride foregoes, And counts it base t'insult his conquer'd Foes; A Lover too, but One that dares controul The guilty Passion, and reform his Soul: Silent attend; and let his Actions raise A gen'rous Ardor to deserve his Praise; If you approve the noble Pattern shewn, Think, in his Virtues you'll applaud your Own.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE EPILOGUE, Spoken by Mrs. Bullock. Well, now you've seen a Youthful Bard's Essay, His first Attempt in the Dramatic Way; Let's know your frank Opinions—I confess, I can't but wonder whence he hopes Success. Thinks he, his blunt victorious Man of War, Has Charms sufficient to engage the Fair? One who his Mistress calmly could resign To each brisk Spark that swears—Oons, Sir, she's mine? No— Give me the Man who owns a Passion warm, That dares be bold—and take the Fort by Storm; Not, like his cold debating Scipio, stand, But urg'd by Love—takes us with Sword in Hand. Old Roman Worth moves not our Sex's Hearts, We Modern Dames love more prevailing Parts. One who in Raptures does his Flame discover, The bold, the daring—ah!—the pushing Lover. But hold— I had forgot, somewhat I ought to say To move your Pity to befriend our Play: I told the Youth he must not hope Success, A Tragedy to take without Distress! He thinks Semanthe's Wrongs will move you—No, You're satisfy'd a Rape's no mighty Woe; Besides, can that with any Grace appear, While pert and noisy Sparks stand peeping here. [Pointing to the Scenes. Our private Scenes are grac'd with powder'd Beaus, Who, judging wrong, laugh at our Tragic Woes, And prove their Want of Sense to shew their Cloaths. Alas! poor, weak, insipid, talking Elves, Whom Nature form'd only to please themselves; They'll damn that Part, turn round to shew their Shapes For Beaus were ne'er found capable of Rapes; A Set of Rakes and Wit-wou'ds are the rest, The Ladies Pity, and their Footmens Jest. Our Author mostly fears that noisy Band, Who censure what they cannot understand: But to true Judges of Dramatic Wit, By me he humbly does his Cause submit. Then for Semanthe's sake a Plaudit give, Indulge the Boy, and let his Scipio live.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Dramatis Personæ. MEN. Scipio, General of the Roman Army, in Love with Almeyda, Mr. Quin. Lelius his Lieutenant and Friend, Mr. Corey. Alucius, a Spanish Prince, betroth'd to Almeyda, Mr. Smith. Trebellius, Roman Officer, Rival for Semanthe, Mr. Leigh. Lucilius, Roman Officer, Rival for Semanthe, Mr. Ogden. WOMEN. Almeyda, a Spanish Captive Princess, betroth'd to Alucius, Mrs. Thurmond. Axarte, an Old Spanish Captive Princess, Mrs. Kent. Semanthe, her Daughter, in Love with Trebellius, Mrs. Bullock. Phænissa, Confident to Almeyda, Mrs. Spiller. Guards, Officers, and Attendants. SCENE, a Camp, near the City of Carthage in Spain.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. SCENE, a Tent before the City Carthage. Enter Scipio and Lelius. Scipio. The Town is ours, those lofty Walls that seem'd To emulate the Skies, and brave our Force, No longer can maintain their haughty Pride, But yield to our Assault—This happy Day Such Fortune waits on our Triumphant Arms, The Ruling Gods, in Justice to our Cause, Have crown'd our Toils with so compleat a Vict'ry, Glorious and Great, (e'en to Amazement Great) That Rome no more with Anguish shall reflect On past Misfortunes, and successless Battles, But think them doubly recompenc'd in this. Lel. This is a Conquest worthy Scipio's Sword; A Glorious Conquest, by the Gods reserv'd For you their Fav'rite Chief, to plant its Laurels On your Victorious Brow, and shew the World, That Heav'n and Godlike Scipio fight for Rome. Scip. Lelius, I think thou art my faithful Friend; If so, Sincerity becomes thee best. Dress me not up with Praises undeserv'd, Nor attribute to me the sole Applause, When ev'ry one acquir'd an equal Share. It has the Tincture of a flatt'ring Art, Therefore a thing most odious to the Man, Who prizes Caius Lelius as his Friend. As I'm a Roman, so my Blood's unstain'd With the ambitious Thirst of noisy Fame. If I'm ambitious, 'tis to serve my Country, To hunt her Foes through ev'ry Hostile Clime, Though at th'Expence o'th'dearest Drop of Blood That swells my Veins, and animates this Frame. But are not you as anxious as my self, As much concern'd to do your Country good? Have you not all been equally engag'd, Expos'd to frequent Hardships, and the same Dangers with equal Resolution met? And shall I rob you of your just Deserts, The due Applause of Brav'ry?—No, my Friend, Learn this from me, that Gen'ral who conquers, (Tho' ne'er so valiant) if he once denies The Praise his Fellow-Soldiers duly merit, And arrogates the Glory to himself, By that ambitious Act he sullies sullies all. Lel. I can but wonder at thy gen'rous Soul, Illustrious Honour to the Roman Name, Pattern of Goodness to succeeding Times! Thus to preserve thy Virtues undefil'd, Thy Temp'rance free from the polluting Charms Of Greatness, e'en amidst the flowing Tide And ecchoing Shouts of Vict'ry,—by my Soul, I'm lost in Admiration. Scip. Lelius, enough; As we profess a Friendship, let's observe Its sacred Rules inviolably just. We must not too profusely lavish it In empty Words, but cherish it as dearly As Women Beauty, or as Niggards Gold: Be this our Maxim, 'tis a Thing that's rare, And therefore ought with Care to be preserv'd. [Sound of Trumpets. These Trumpets speak some Message from the Town, Trebellius and Lucilius are return'd From Carthage. Enter Trebellius and Lucilius. Speak, Sirs, what Tydings from the Town? Tre. Heav'n, that first favour'd the Attempts of Rome, By Scipio's Conduct crown'd them with Success; With such Success as only Heav'n could grant, And only Scipio's Virtue could obtain; So speedy and so great, continues still To smile with Kindness on us: As our Toils Were great, so likewise great are our Rewards, The Strength, the Pow'r of Spain in Carthage fell; The Captive Crowd (all bury'd in their Fears,) Now curse their Fate, now in dissembling Terms Cringe to that Mercy they disdain'd before; The num'rous Spoils in gaudy Triumph born, Compleat their Horror, and the Victor's Joys. Luc. Yes, Sir, what Victor can refrain from Joy At such a Conquest, which disdains Applause From those inferior Triumphs of the Day, Where Beauties own the far superior Force Of Mars, and in their silent Tears confess Captivity; Maids of the noblest Blood, The blooming Pride of Spain, proceed in Form To hear their Doom from you? Who would not brave Each glorious Danger in the Field of War, The hissing Arrow, and the pointed Steel, What Coward would not bid adieu to Fear, When such strong Motives, such delicious Charms Provoke him to be brave? Scip. 'Tis well, Lucilius; But let's not triumph in a Woman's Tears, It is beneath a Roman; for we fight Only to right our Country: And, my Friends, Let me commend you all; for you have fought Like Patriots zealous for the Publick Good, And bravely conquer'd in your Country's Cause; I must embrace you all. You Trebellius, And you Lucilius, reconcile your Strife; Both wear the Mural Crown your Acts deserve, Both dear to Scipio, worthy of Applause. Luc. What! shall Trebellius wear the Mural Crown In equal Honour with my self?—But hold, I'll smother my Resentments for a while. [Aside. Scip. Was it not you, Lucilius, who inform'd us, The Captive Ladies were in mournful Pomp Approaching to our Camp? Luc. It was, my Lord, And lo, they come—Some distance from yon' Mount, Perceive you not a thronging Crowd that press This Way? They are the Captives, whose Beauties Attract the dazzled Eyes and wishing Hearts Of the rough Soldier, and disarm his Rage. Scip. Trebellius and Lucilius, both away, Conduct the beauteous Captives safely hither. [Exeunt Treb. and Lucil. They are distress'd, and they shall have Relief, Such a Relief as Scipio can bestow. We're not alloted Conquests to indulge, To pamper up, and satisfie the Hopes Of vain Ambition, proudly to insult And Lord it o'er the Wretched; (when to them, Unhappy Subjects of the Victor's Triumph, It is sufficient Curse to undergo What Victory imposes)—No, we are injoin'd By the soft Ties of sympathizing Nature, By that immortal Pow'r who conquer'd for us, To imitate his Goodness, and extend Compassion e'en to those we have subdu'd. Nay, 'tis a greater Glory, it bespeaks A greater Conduct in the Victor's Breast To use it right, than Courage to obtain it. But see, the Royal Captives now appear In such Majestick melancholy Pomp, That even Victory itself grows dull, And sickens at its Triumphs. Enter Trebellius conducting in Semanthe and her Mother Axarte; Lucilius, Almeyda and her Confident Phænissa. Scip. By Heav'n 'tis mournful, wondrous mournful all; When Innocence, and Beauty so Divine Stand thus expos'd to the destructive Hand Of War, and suffer for their Country's Crimes: A Sight like this would strike the Savage Hearts Of the most fierce Barbarians with Remorse, And soften 'em to Pity. Axa. Oh General! [Kneeling. Oh Scipio! fam'd for thy Success in War, Thou Scourge to all the Enemies of Rome, Divest thy Bosom of a Soldier s Roughness, Look down with Pity on this Captive Train, Who thus unfortunately mourn the Fall Of their dear Country. Oh my Semanthe! Oh my poor Daughter! 'tis not for myself, But for thy Sake thy tender Mother kneels, Fearing the rude oppressive Force of War Should mingle in an undistinguish'd Heap Of bloody Slaughter thy weak Innocence; Or, that the barb'rous Violence of Soldiers Flush'd with Success, insulting in the Field Of Devastation, Massacre and Blood, Should seize thy Person as a common Spoil, And violate thy Beauties, unless He, This Victor, will compassionate thy Fate. Scip. Rise, Madam, and dispel these anxious Fears, Your beauteous lov'd Semanthe and your self Shall both be safe, 'tis Scipio that assures it: The Warriour only rages in my Breast, When th'enlivening Trumpet calls me forth, T'exert my Courage in the glorious Field Of Honour, and dispute my Country's Cause: But when the Fury of the Battle ends, Destruction ceases, and my Rage is past, Returning Pity sways within my Breast, And mourns the Havock which my Sword had made. Axa. Believe me, Royal Sir, I scarcely thought Such Goodness, such Humanity was lodg'd Within a Roman Breast; but I'm convinc'd, I find, and I am pleas'd to find it now: Nor do I wonder that my Husband fell, That Carthage yielded to the Roman Arms, When Scipio's Virtues, so divinely bright, Were leagu'd against it; for approving Heav'n Smiles on the Honest, and asserts their Quarrel. And oh! I wish that my Mandonius liv'd To see th'exalted Worth of injur'd Rome! He would no longer guide his hardy Troops, Brandish a Spear against the Roman Cause: Vain empty Wish! Mandonius is no more; Lost to his Widow and defenceless Child, Who in this Depth of Sorrow are compell'd To crave Assistance at a Victor's Hand. [Weeping. Scip. To pay our last Affections in our Tears To the cold Ashes of a buried Friend, A Husband, or a Parent, is a Debt, A Tribute due to Nature and to them; I (tho' the Instrument of Death) bemoan Th'unhappy Warrior, and forget the Foe. For by the awful Gods of Rome I swear, That I had rather all the busie World Was reconcil'd in peaceful Amity, Than envious Wars and Tumults should confound And fill the Earth with Ruin, tho' my self Might heap a thousand Laurels on my Head, By mixing in the Broils;—and curs'd be he, That Foe to Nature, who will keep alive The Flames of Discord for a private End. Yet, since 'tis done, th'unalterable Will Of Fate, accomplish'd by your Husband's Fall; Tho' thus forlorn and destitute, depriv'd You of a Husband, of a Parent She; Banish not Comfort, but expect from me The Help of both; repine not at your Fate, Captivity shall soon grow easie to you; You shall again obtain your Liberty, Soon as this busie Scene of War is o'er. Trebellius, guard the Ladies to your Tent; Attend them there with Honour and Respect. [Exeunt Trebellius, Semanthe, Axarte. [Scipio turning sees Almeyda. How could my faulty Eyes escape so long, So beautiful an Object? Alm. No wonder, Sir. A Slave, a Captive Woman must attend, And wait the Leisure of a Conqueror. Scip. Pierce not my Heart with such unwelcome Sounds, With those severe Expressions, Slave and Captive. Can they reflect on me? Can you suppose That Scipio glories in a Woman's Bonds? Think on those Charms which so profusely reign In ev'ry Feature; think how fair you are, And thence conclude you are no more a Slave. Alm. What Share of Beauty can Almeyda boast, She thus forsaken, and o'erwhelm'd with Ills? Or what avails it, when prevailing Mars Views its Distress, and joys in its Captivity? Oh Love! Oh my Alucius! [Aside. Scip. Why those Sighs, As if some weighty Sorrow had o'er-press'd Your Soul, and that Way work'd its furious Vent? Alm. Yes, Sorrows upon Sorrows, that demand The largest Tribute that my Soul can pay. Scip. If from your Bondage you derive these Woes, Let me relieve you there, and with your Bonds Dismiss these weighty and pernicious Cares; Explain the Means, and Scipio will obey. Alm. Thanks, Noble Scipio, for these gracious Terms: But you inquire what means this pensive State, This cloudy Aspect, and these flowing Tears; 'Tis that Misfortunes rush so fast upon me, They almost hurry me to wild Despair, And make me wish a thousand thousand Times That I was laid intomb'd within my Grave, Beyond the future Malice of my Stars; I cannot,—dare not farther to proceed. Scip. Gods! 'tis a Pity; if I must not learn The Reason of your Griefs; yet give me leave (As I'm the General of Rome) to shew The Duty of a Roman, and afford All the Assistance your Afflictions claim. Alm. Great Sir, I only can repeat my Thanks. Scip. Madam, I ask them not; you may command This Tent, and ought which may the least avail To ease the sad Remembrance of your Bonds. Madam, we leave you to your self and Friend. [Exeunt Scipio, Lelius, Lucilius. [Manent Almeyda, Phænissa. Alm. Oh! my Phænissa, Partner of my Woes, Thou only Remnant of my Shipwreck'd Fortunes; If that my Soul can know one glimm'ring Hope, One dawning Joy, 'tis at the Sight of thee: Ha, said I, Joy! What Joy can I receive To see my Friend unhappy? Cruel Thought! Phæ. Condemn it not, but stile it the Effects Of purest Friendship rather, here 'tis prov'd. Alm. Severely too. Phæ. But wherefore should you thus Lament, and rend your Bosom with Complaints, And make your self more wretched than you are? This Victor is as kind as he is great; He gently begs you to forget your Cares, And treats you with the Promise of your Freedom; Still, still you may be happy; oh revive, Chear up your gloomy Soul, and welcome Light! Alm. Think not Almeyda's Soul can be reviv'd With fancy'd Pleasures, she must still despond, Her Love is lost, Alucius is no more; At least no more for me, that gallant Prince, That Godlike Heroe, that most charming Youth, To whom my Vows were plighted; but alas, This rude, this barb'rous wide Destroyer, War, Has made a Separation; he perhaps Lies stretch'd upon the Ground a breathless Coarse; Or, if alive, my bleeding Heart forbodes That we shall never, never meet again. Phæ. Why do you thus anticipate your Fate, And double your Misfortunes? 't must not be; Methinks, if divining Thoughts prove true, And my exulting Mind portends aright, I see Alucius, the good anxious Prince, Consulting for his lov'd Almeyda's Safety, Contriving Means to rescue her he loves From all the Hardships of a Victor's Chain. Alm. I know, Phænissa, thou art ever kind, To sooth my Heart with Promises and Hopes; But yet I am unwilling to deceive, Or blind my Sense with weak fictitious Joys: Nay, tho' I wish it (witness, oh ye Gods, How much I wish it!) yet my Heart denies To hear of Comfort 'till th'Event is sure. Come, my Phænissa, let us now retire To calm Distress, and chase away Despair. Mean while, if Pity shou'd some Goddess move To succour my afflicted hapless Love; Dispel these Clouds that o'er my Fortune wait, And ease the hard Condition of my Fate; At past Misfortunes I'd no more repine, Forget them all, was but Alucius mine. The End of the First ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. SCENE the First. Scipio solus. The Toils of Battle past, new Toils succeed, My Breast is now the Theatre of War: Methinks my Blood forgets its proper Course, Seems all Congeal'd and Curdled in my Veins; Something within me whispers, it is Love, The raging Force of secret, growing Love: Gods! did I 'scape Mars and Bellona's Rage In Battle, to be subject to a Boy, And fall a Victim to the Snares of Beauty? This Captive, lovely through the Veil of Grief, Makes deep Impression in my ravish'd Heart, And crowds in every Thought.—But see, she comes, Sweet as Aurora, when from Eastern Clouds She darts, to give the World a New-Born Day. Enter Almeyda. Alm. Is there a Day, a Night, within the Date Of Humane Life, untainted with an Ill? If now we form a Scheme of mighty Pleasure, Boast in the Prospect of approaching Bliss, Anon we lose the Momentary Joy, As with an Airy Phantome of a Dream, Rich in the Night, but empty in the Morn, We find our selves deceiv'd, the envious Pow'rs Repent their Favours, and retract their Gifts. Scip. Still, Beauteous Maid, must that Angelick Form [Scipio turning to her. Be cover'd o'er with the pale sickly Hue Of Discontent? And doth the barb'rous Sense Of thy unhappy Fortune still continue To press so hard upon thy tender Bosom? Still must those Watry Pearls descend so fast From their bright Orbs, like Evening Dews, that fall T'improve the Beauties of the Morning Flow'rs? Declare, if Scipio hath neglected ought Which might conduce to mitigate these Woes. Alm. No, Sir, my grateful Heart must ever own That you have us'd me nobly, and been kind (E'en to excess of Kindness,) but alas! What is that Kindness to a Wretch like me? Plung'd in this Gulph, what Joys can I expect? How be Reliev'd, when I am all Despair? Oh my lost Love! [Aside. Scip. But why do you resolve To Feast on Sorrows, and indulge your Griefs? Why thus reserv'd, thus Cruel to your self, Concealing Ills, which, when deny'd a vent, And lab'ring inward, but disturb you more? Tell me, Almeyda, I conjure you, tell me The fatal Cause, and Scipio will redress. Alm. Ask me not what I dare not to reveal; Or when reveal'd, Heav'n only can reverse. Scip. And sure the Gods will never be unkind, Deaf, and relentless to the tender Pray'rs Of supplicating Beauty—Hark! what Noise, As if some Tumult from the distant Camp. [Shout of Souldiers. Madam, a Gen'rals Duty calls me forth At present, to discharge th'important Trust, To quell Disorders in their Birth, and then Almeyda claims my quick Return. (Exit. Scip. Enter Phænissa. Alm. So, my Phænissa, in thy Hast appears Important News; thy better Looks declare, In outward shew some great uncommon Joy. Phæ. It is a Joy Phænissa brings, a Joy, Which will restore the Springs of sinking Nature; Alucius is alive— Unmangled by the Bloody Strokes of War, And only wretched in his sever'd Love. Alm. Such Transports rush upon me from thy Words, That I can scarce endure the rapid Pain; My Mind's dissolv'd in unexpected Bliss, The Gloomy Clouds of Horror are dispers'd, And everlasting Day now dawns around me. Speak, speak, my best Phænissa, oh speak on! Repeat the balmy Comfort to my Ears; Assure me I shall see him once again. Phæ. Within this Hour, a Private Messenger Found means to gain Admittance to this Tent, Enquiring for Almeyda— At first I was surpriz'd; ask'd him from whom, From whence he came? he said from one unknown To all but her; I told him, that my self Was Friend and Partner of Almeyda's Fate, Nor unacquainted with her Love; he then Freely reveal'd the most Delightful News; Told me Alucius sent him to inform Almeyda that he liv'd; liv'd (if the Gods permit) To rescue his Almeyda from her Bonds. Alm. Phænissa, 'tis too much, the swelling Joys, The big encreasing Extasies are too Too violent for Woman to sustain; Yet prithee tell me, will Alucius come To free Almeyda? Yes, thou saidst he would. But why, Almeyda, if thou lov'st the Prince, Why shouldst thou urge his Ruin? But 'tis Love That prompts him to so hazardous an Act; 'Tis the same Love that forces my Consent, And thus extorts my Wishes. Phæ. As your Loves Are thus unsullied, constant and sincere, So trust me, you will soon be happy both, And reap the Blessings of a Faithful Flame; Soon as the Sun shall in the West decline, In Roman Habit thy Alucius comes. Alm. Then Sun drive on, drive on in full Career, And let thy fiery Coursers, fleet as Winds, Guide the immortal Chariot round the Sphere, With more than Common, with a Lover's Speed. For that blest Hour shall both our Joys compleat, Make mine as Happy, as thy own, as Great, When you retiring to your Thetis' Charms, Revel on Love, and wanton in her Arms; Then blest Almeyda shall behold her Lord, Whom she so long hath Lov'd, so long Ador'd. [Exeunt. SCENE the Second. Trebellius, Semanthe. Sem. Alas! Semanthe dares not to attend, Or listen to th'alluring Sound of Love; Besides, she is a Spaniard, and a Slave, Enslav'd by the Superiour Arms of Rome; How can she yield to Love, to Love that Man Who fought against her Country, and eras'd The Stately Carthage? No, her Father's Ghost, The Dead Mandonius will resent her Crime, And haunt his Daughter for her faulty Love, To match with one who was a Foe to Spain, A Roman, to whose Proud Victorious Arms The Glorious Warriour fell a Sacrifice. Tre. True Madam, Carthage is subdu'd, and Spain Already bows submissively to Rome: Your Father shar'd the Common Fate of War, Expiring in the Field, but yet my Sword Drank not his Blood; Trebellius stands excus'd, And blameless of his Death; nor could his Arm, For any Private Malice, seek his Life. The Publick Contest made us Publick Foes: But you on ev'ry side Protection claim, The Vanquish'd, and the Haughty Victors, both Are Vassals to the Fair: If you have lost A kind indulging Father, you have found A Lover far more kind; one who admires, Makes you the Idol of his Doating Soul, Pays equal Rev'rence to your Awful Virtue, As to his Gods, and lives but in your Smiles. Sem. I fear, Trebellius, you're but too well skill'd In all those Arts, so common to your Sex, To praise our Beauties, and pretend such Love, Such vehemence of Love confirm'd by Oaths, The Artful Practice basely to delude, And undermine a weak believing Woman: Ought we not then to guard against your Wiles? Tre. And should you therefore judge Trebellius so, Condemn the Guiltless Man by others Crimes? No, if there is a Majesty Supreme, Who overlooks the Actions of Mankind, And punishes Deceit; let him, that God, Dart all his Thunder on this guilty Head, When e'er my Tongue belies my Honest Heart. Sem. These Imprecations needless are, and vain; Think you Semanthe can consent to Love? Or if she should, would not yourself condemn, Accuse her Artless Folly, to believe The Treachery of Man, to bury all Her Griefs, Resentments for her Father's Death, In the soft Transports of a guilty Love? Tre. Could I refuse the Mansion of the Blest; Yon' Starry Kingdoms, and Eternal Glories? But then, and not till then, could I reject Semanthe's Love, or blame her for the Gift, The Rich, the Glorious, the Immortal Gift: Oh! doubt not of my Truth, Celestial Fair, Grant me that Heav'n, and I'll (if possible) Repay its sweet Possession with my Love. Sem. Where am I? Sure my Soul is ravish'd from me; My Eyes grow dim, and glimmer at the Light; A Thousand Phantoms thwart my dazzled View, And leave me in a Maze; my Heart beats high, And now again it throbs, then droops within me. [Aside. Tre. May I presume to flatter my fond Hopes? Think that the Fair Semanthe yet will deign To bless me with her Love? Sem. No more; forbear To tempt me farther, and betray my Weakness. Tre. No, rather let me me push the small Success, Improve the lucky Moment, whilst Semanthe Yet doubts, yet seems unwilling to decline My Love. Sem. Cruel, insulting Man, to force A Virgin thus, to struggle through the Bounds Of Modest Niceness, and confess her Frailty; Where is that boasted Quickness feign'd to dwell In Lover's Eyes? Can'st thou not yet discern? Tre. I do, my Life, my Soul; these Eyes presage Those Strugglings are the Symptoms of thy Love; The certain Symptoms of the yielding Maid: Is it not so? Or are my Eyes in fault, That fancy what I wish? Sem. Yes, to suppose The Looks must speak the Language of the Heart, And tell thee, that I Love. Tre. Deluded Man! To raise Imagination up so high, And be beguil'd at last. Oh Godlike Maid! Excuse this Fault, or rather call it none: Yet grant me some Support, (tho' but the least,) To keep alive my Hopes, and check Despair. Sem. Yes, thou may'st Hope, and that's the greatest Gift A Virgin can bestow. Tre. It is enough; 'Tis all I ask, and more than I deserve: Oh! I could listen an Eternity To those delightful Accents; I could dwell For ever on those Lips, that bad me Hope: Oh my Soul's Goddess! you have giv'n your Slave An endless Series of unbounded Bliss, Beyond the vain Delusions of the Brooks, And shady Grottos in th'Elysian Country: Mine is a solid Blessing; from this Time, From this propitious Minute, will I date My Smiling Æra of indulgent Fate. Mars and Bellona now to Cupid yield, To gentler Love resign the warlike Field: The Little God, pleas'd with his am'rous Trust, Is to the Soldier in the Lover Just; Safe, and secure from War's destructive Frowns, With Love's succeeding Joys the Fav'rite Warriour Crowns. [Exeunt. SCENE the Third. Lucilius solus. Luci. Trebellius and the Fair Semanthe there? Walk they not Hand in Hand? By Heav'n they do: Damnation, I am Thunderstruck; can He, That worthless Animal presume so high? It is impossible; he dares not do't: But yet my Jealous Soul forbodes he does; Which, if he should, Perdition sieze my Soul If ever I forgive him; if my Sword Haunts not his Life with all the restless Malice, The Fury of an angry, injur'd Foe; If that I use not ev'ry Art, and Fraud, To blast his Wishes, and supplant his Love, And low'r his high, ambitious, growing Pride: He rivals me in Glory, and in Love: When I my self, first mounted on the Breach, And scal'd the dang'rous Wall; Trebellius, then My Evil Genius was my Rival there; But now he wounds me in a dearer Part, And robs me of Semanthe, of my Love: But shall he bear her off an easy Prize, And Riot on those Charms which should be mine? His Blood shall answer for the bold Attempt. Our Gen'ral comes, and him I would avoid. [Exit. Lucilius SCENE the Fourth. Enter Scipio, Lelius. Scip. The Tumult is appeas'd; the Murm'ring Troops That mutiny'd for Plunder, all are hush'd, And silenc'd at our Sight, the Camp's at Peace. Lel. Sedition ever treads upon the Heels Of Victory; the Soldiers when no more Their Foreign Foes invite them to the Field, Taught to Dispute, raise new Intestine Jars; But quickly to returning Duty aw'd, The senseless Slaves relent, and cringe with Fear. Scip. Yes, Lelius, they submit; but yet a Tumult, A greater far than that, disturbs my Breast: War is the Province of the Great and Brave; But an inchanting slavish Love is Scipio's. True, I have Fought, and Conquer'd in the Field, Chas'd hostile Squadrons o'er the trembling Plain, And crush'd my Foe beneath my reeking Sword: This have I done; but now my Triumph's o'er; Now Scipio in his turn must learn to Bow Spite of the Roman, own th'ungrateful Bonds Of an ignoble, but prevailing Passion: Almeyda, she, that Gift of Victory, Returns her Chains upon her Conqueror, And with resistless Beauty bears me down. Oh Lelius, I am lost! Lel. Is't possible? Is Scipio fetter'd in a Woman's Chains? He, who hath fac'd the dreadful Front of War, Extended his Victorious Arms o'er half Th'affrighted Western World; is he enslav'd? Exert the former Warriour in your Soul; Recall your well-taught Reason to your Aid: You, have subdu'd your Enemies, improve Th'Heroick Glory, and subdue your Self. Scip. Doth Caius Lelius, doth my Friend advise These useless Means to heal a Lover's Pain? The Arguments you urge distract me more, Augment my Griefs, to think what I have been; How Great? How Glorious once? And now how Weak? Lel. I counsell'd with an honest good Intent, Prescrib'd a Cure most proper for your Wound; But with Concern, I find, your Tortur'd Breast Cannot admit the Means. Scip. Alas! my Friend, Nought but a kind Return of Love can yield A fainting Lover Ease. Lel. Then, mighty Sir, Befriend your self, you have it in your Pow'r; Almeyda is your Pris'ner, in your Tent; Declare your Love, she dares not but comply. Scip. No; Scipio's Soul disdains th'ungen'rous Thought; Scipio had rather be for ever wretched, Languish an Age in Misery himself, Than in Oppression triumph, or demand That by Compulsion, which the Will denies. It is Inhuman, and unworthy Us, Who only Conquer to Reform the World. Lel. Divinely spoke, and worthy him that speaks it Thou wondrous Man! thou Prodigy of Virtue! Then try some gentler, some more humane Way; Intreat, perswade the Fair One to be kind. Scip. Yes Lelius, I'll pursue thy Counsel, try To change the Soldier's to the Lover's Stile; Use all the strongest Eloquence that Art, Or the sharp Anguish of my Soul can frame, To plead my Passion, and promote my Love. The Heroe shakes in vain the whizzing Spear, Boasts the rich Trophies, and the Pomp of War: Though Captive Princes sweat beneath his Chains, A greater Foe unconquer'd yet remains; Love feels with rival Pride, and envious Shame, His growing Honours, and aspiring Fame; Then his big Schemes are in a Moment crost, Beauty unnerves him, and the World is lost. [Exeunt The End of the Second ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. SCENE the First. Scipio, Almeyda. Scip. To tell you that I love you, that my Soul Allows your high Dominion, and with Joy Accepts its Chains, wou'd be a needless Tale; Your self are conscious of the Pow'r you bear. These Eyes have seen Maids of the noblest Bloom, The foremost both in Beauty and in Blood; Them with a cool Indiff'rence have I view'd, No Love, no Philtre trickling through my Veins; Dauntless, and unacquainted with the Force Of Beauty; Battles were my sole Delight; War was the darling Mistress of my Heart; There did it range at large, 'till you o'ertook, And by superior Charms confin'd it here. Alm. Forbear to mention that which I must doubt, Or granting true, I never can return. Scip. What never, Madam? Alm. No, I never can. But why should Scipio thus demean his Soul, Ignobly stoop to her who is his Slave? Or can Almeyda dare believe that Man, Who conquer'd, and retains her in his Bonds? For you 'tis too inglorious, and for me Too great. Scip. These Obstacles are soon remov'd; True Love is never limited, confin'd To trifling Customs, or the senseless Rules Of Birth, or dull Distinction, the Debates Of cool deliberating Lovers, that As much the fiercer, is the nobler Flame: But where is this inglorious Meanness? Where That mighty jarring Difference, when I bow A Suiter for the fair Almeyda's Love? Are you not equal to my self in Blood? And tho' distress'd, as much to be esteem'd, And worshipp'd as if circled with a Crown? 'Tis a base Passion that admires a Form, When tempting Wealth unites its dazzling Lustre To add new Beauties, and improve the Fair; But when those guilded Trifles are no more, Soon vanishes away. Alm. Be cautious, Scipio, nor Too heedless tempt your Ruin. Scip. Cautious, say you? Can Scipio from himself fear ought? If he must fall, It will be only by Almeyda's Charms. Alm. Why there's the Danger, there's the fatal Rock Which I advise you timely to beware: Be not profuse, or lavish in the Praise Of Beauties which you never can enjoy: Do not too rashly thus indulge your Love To a resistless and unbounded Height, When all the Prospect of Success is lost. Scip. And can there, cruel Charmer, can the same Fierce Tyranny prevail within thy Heart, As Triumphs in thy Eyes, to name Despair To one that's gasping in the Pangs of Death? Look on him gently, and reverse his Doom, Afford one Promise, one kind Gleam of Hope. Alm. Instruct me, Gracious Heaven! inspire my Tongue In this disorder'd Tumult of my Soul: If I reveal our Loves, Alucius dies, By Silence I provoke a Victor's Wrath. [Aside. Scipio. Why will you rack me thus with doubtful Fear? Reflect but on the Tortures I endure, The dreadful Anguish of my lab'ring Breast; You cannot but compassionate my Pains. Alm. Compassionate! I do; observe my Heart, See how it pants, and can you then upbraid me? Scip. If rising Pity pleads in my behalf, Obey, obey that Pity, and consent. Alm. It is not in my Pow'r, indeed it is not. Scip. But wherefore not? What mighty secret Bar Forbids my Joys, and envies my Repose? Alm. A thousand Reasons start into my Mind, And warn me to be cautious; which to speak Is only to inhance our Miseries, And plunge us in a deeper Flood of Woes. Scip. Disastrous State of Love for ever puzzled, Plagu'd with Objections, and chain'd down to Hardships! To say that you compassionate, yet give No Cure, distracts the wretched Lover most, It aggravates the Pains he felt before. Alm. To bid you hope in this unhappy State, Whilst I am thus bewildred and forlorn, Is to be impious both to Heav'n and you: Those Pow'rs indeed may more propitious smile, And bless Almeyda with an happier Hour; 'Till then her Confidence is plac'd above, Her Wishes all to their Decrees resign'd. Scip. Then Scipio hope, Almeyda bids thee hope, Hope, and expect that white propitious Hour, When Heav'n shall bless thee with Almeyda's Love; For in a Lover's Hopes dwell coming Joys, As budding Flow'rs fore-run the blooming Year: Let me retire, indulge my promis'd Bliss; Remember, Madam, that you bad me hope. [Exit Scipio. Alm. Yes, I remember my own wretched State, That I'm belov'd, where 'tis not in my Pow'r To love again; Alucius I am thine: But hush my Cares, a Beam of Joy breaks in Upon my Soul, and whispers he'll be here; He will! What to receive his fatal Doom? To die? No, Heav'n forefend! Ye sacred Pow'rs Protect his Person, ward each threatning Blow! On him my diff'rent Fates Dependant move, My Life, my Death, my Liberty, and Love. [Exit Almeyda. SCENE the Second. Enter Trebellius and Lucilius different Ways. Luc. Hah! That Trebellius,—at the Sight of him My Blood beats high within my angry Veins; But I'll dissemble, and explore his Soul. [Aside. Well met, Trebellius, Fellow Soldier, why Hovers this Cloud of Sadness on your Brow? What! over-cloy'd with Happiness, my Friend? Trebellius you have fought a glorious Battle, And you are well rewarded for your Toils, Semanthe, and the Mural Crown. Tre. Lucilius, Why Envy you thus your Fellow Soldier's Praise, That thirsty Avarice of Martial Men? Which rightly weigh'd is but an empty Toy, Vain as are Infant's Bubbles swell'd with Wind, Which quickly lose their splended Gaiety, And vanish into nought: But hath not Mars Enlarg'd his Honours, the Rewards of War, With equal Kindness on your self? But Love, In that I own the Favour of my Stars; To Morrow's Night shall bless me with a Bride, With all that's exquisite, and worthy Hope, Where Nature's utmost Beauties are compleat. Luc. But I'll prevent it. [Aside.] Trebellius be advis'd, There is a certain Bar between your Loves Which may endanger both; observe me well, Take this my friendly Caution, and desist. Tre. Prithee unfold the dark mysterious Sense Thy Words contain, explain the secret Cause. Luc. I tell thee there is Danger in thy Love; Ruin attends it, that's enough at once; Another time I may inform thee farther. Tre. Lucilius, No; my Hopes are so confirm'd, So strengthned in th'Expectance of my Joys, That no light Terrors can alarm my Mind, Or scatter through my Breast th'infectious Fear. Luc. Then you'll persist, and, obstinately rash, Provoke your Ruin. Tre. Yes, I will on In Spite of all the Dangers that impend; And extasy'd in Love, I'll brave 'em all. Luc. Come, come, you must not, nay, you shall not, Sir. Tre. Farewel, Lucilius, when we next shall meet, I hope this Fit of Madness will be cur'd. [Exit Trebellius. Luc. Madness indeed! It makes Lucilius rave; The fell Distraction glides through ev'ry Part: Was it for him, this empty grov'ling Wretch, My Honour slighted, and my Love refus'd? But shall I patiently endure the Scoffs, The Insults of a vaunting happy Rival? Surely my Roman Spirit cannot brook The foul Indignity: I must invent Some Means for my Redress, and quickly too. [Exit Lucilius. SCENE the Third. Almeyda Sola. Alm. Thus Expectation still foreruns our Bliss, And gives us Pleasure, e'er the Pleasure come; Imagination builds a thousand Hopes, And ev'ry Hope contains a thousand Joys. Heav'n! who comes here? Alucius! my swoln Heart Assures me it is he; I know that Face, Those Royal Graces spite of their Disguise: Fears, Pleasures, Jealousies at once arise, And in a mix'd Confusion crowd into my Soul. Enter Alucius, Running and Embracing Almeyda. Alm. Welcome Almeyda to my longing Arms! Welcome! thrice welcome to the glad Alucius! Nor were the few Remains of Man more pleas'd, After the Deluge of th'unpeopled Earth, To see the Mountains, and the Hills appear, The burthen'd Plains shake off th'oppressive Waves, Than is Alucius to behold his Love, His Dear, his lov'd Almeyda once again. Alm. Believe me, I am lost; my fleeting Soul Is hurried hence by this Excess of Joy; Alucius, is it thee? Do I behold, And touch thee once again? Is Heav'n so kind To bless me with Alucius? Let me now Be wrapt in the eternal Shades of Night, That I may end thus with a Taste of Bliss, Thus, thus embracing thee. [Embracing him. Alu. No, let us live; Live to enjoy one mutual happy State, When the Alarms of War shall all be hush'd, And Love display its Banners o'er the World, Triumphant Love. Alm. Oh! when may we expect That glorious Time, too fortunate for us? We, my Alucius, from our Infant Years Were doom'd a poor unhappy abject Pair, To bear the Frowns, and the continual Darts, Of arbitrary Fortune. Alu. Oh forbear With rash Complaints to kindle dying Rage; Heav'n is all Pity, and at length relents; Do not deny its Favours when receiv'd: We have, 'tis true, we have been wretched long, By Fortune cross'd, e'en in the Hour of Bliss; But now her Blessings in their Turn succeed, With this kind Meeting she compensates all. Alm. This Meeting is a favourable Gift, A Blessing I confess; but yet my Fears Foretel some fatal Ruin will ensue. How could'st thou be so cruel, and so kind, So kind to me, so cruel to thy self? Alm. For thee, Almeyda, what could I refuse? Is there a Joy within the utmost Limits, The fairest Part of this Terrestrial Globe; Nay, seated in those blissful Bow'rs above, I could prefer to thee, thou worthy Maid? Earth would grow dull, and Heav'nly Pleasures cloy, Alucius still would sicken for Almeyda. Alm. But yet your Danger, thus beset with Foes, Encompass'd round with Enemies of Spain, What Safety can you find? Alu. This Roman Garb Conceals me from Discov'ry; but were Ten thousand Dangers planted round this Tent, As many Daggers pointed at my Life, And only love my Friend, I'd brave my Fate. Thus, when the big impending Clouds appear, And struggling Winds proclaim some Tempest near, The trembling Birds the coming Danger fly, And seek for Shelter from the low'ring Sky, In wild Confusion, and Affright divide, The mournful Mate is sever'd from his Bride: But when the Gloom is clear'd, the Storm o'er past, Each seek his Consort with impatient Haste; Grieves 'till she's found, when found the joyful Pair, With warbling Transports charm the list'ning Air. [Exeunt End of the Third ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT IV. SCENE the First. Alucius, Almeyda. Alu. Must we be parted by these envious Hours, That glide in swiftest Motion from our Wishes, As if with Fortune they conspir'd against us? Must we be forc'd to be again unhappy, And quit this sweet Endearment of our Loves? Alm. Yes, my Alucius, we must part, indeed We must, and lose this transitory Joy. Thy Stay is dang'rous, Scipio may suspect, And with a Lover's Eyes detect the Fraud, And then inevitable Death ensues. Alu. Confusion! how it racks me! Shall I leave My Mistress to my Rival and my Foe? Shame and Dishonour to the Spanish Name! Fly, that the Roman may address thy Beauties? Th'Imagination stings me to the Soul. Alm. Be calm, Alucius, what Dishonour is't Timely to flie, when Death is in thy Stay? Or, what's the Prowess of a single Arm, Oppos'd and press'd by Multitudes of Foes? 'Tis rash, 'tis blind, 'tis impotent and vain. Be guided, my Alucius, be advis'd By her, who may without a Blush confess She loves thee dearer, better than herself. Alu. Shall I prophane that Love, thou beauteous Maid? Desert thy helpless Innocence so basely, And leave thee all abandon'd to thy Woes, Defenceless and alone, amidst a Host Of Enemies? Alm. Almeyda can be safe Without your Danger, safer if alone; This Scipio, this Victor is a Man Mild by his Nature, milder by his Love; Aw'd by that Passion, he forgets the Style, The usual Sternness of a Victor's Pride; Nay, if perchance he but observes me weep, He sighs himself, and begs me to forbear, To lay aside my Cares, and bids me hope For better Days. Alu. Did he? for better Days? What, for himself? 'Tis that Alucius dreads. This forc'd Respect, and seeming great Observance, Are only Baits to win you to his Love; Be on thy Guard, Almeyda; oh! beware. Alm. I thought, Alucius, you yourself could witness How much I priz'd, how dear I ever held My Virgin Honour, and untainted Mind, As bravely good, and anxious for their Safety, As hardy Patriots for the Publick Weal; And for Alucius to suspect me now, That only Man I to the World preferr'd, For Him to cast this Scandal on my Fame, Ungrateful Prince! severe Return of Love! Alu. Is not this Roman swell'd with youthful Blood? Has he not Eyes to view? A Heart to feel The strong Impression of thy Heav'nly Charms? Has he not too (all Hell is in that Thought!) A Victor's Pow'r to satiate his Desires? Alm. And have not I (weak as my Sex is deem'd) Courage and Virtue to prevent his Will, And guide a friendly Dagger to my Heart, Which shall at once secure my trembling Soul, Both from his Insults and thy groundless Fears? Alu. Call them not groundless, but a Lover's Fears; For, if I love thee, can I see thee his? Methinks e'en now I see him (curs'd Idea!) Gaze on thy Charms with languishing Deceit, Press those rich Worlds, and swear he'll have thee all: Thee too, (damn'd frightful Image of Despair!) Mov'd by his Glories, yield to his Embrace, Pant in his Arms, whilst thy Alucius dies. Alm. Is this, base Man, the Language of thy Love? These vile Suspicions, and abusive Terms? But from my Thoughts; and know, my Honour yet Can find Revenge for those who dare traduce it. Alu. My Jealousies have carry'd me too far, I fear I've injur'd the dear virtuous Maid, And dare not hope Forgiveness, yet I will Implore it, for she was all Goodness once. [Aside. Is there, Almeyda, is there yet a Pardon Left in thy Stores of Pity, for a Wretch By Jealousie transported from himself; Who, conscious of his Crime, at length repents, And humbled thus, kneels till his Pardon's sign'd? [Kneeling. Alm. Rise, rise, Alucius, for thou know'st my Soul, How prone to Love, how willing to forgive: Yet if that Love prevail'd not o'er my Wrongs, And pleaded strongly for thee in my Heart, Ought I not then for ever to resent This barb'rous Usage, and forget thee quite? But thou art my Alucius, and I can, I must forgive thee, for I love thee still. [Sinking into his Arms. Alu. And will thy injur'd Goodness then forgive? Alm. It will, it does; and to confirm thee more, And cure thy jealous Doubts, again I swear, My Virgin Breast's a Stranger to his Love, Nor ever felt an Influence but from thee. Alu. No more, Almeyda; may my Soul ne'er reach The happy Mansions of th'Elysian Shades, Ne'er taste those promis'd Beauties it adores, But lose them both, if it distrusts thee more. And when Alucius shall forget to love, To meet thy Virtues, and requite thy Truth, May all the Plagues that ever injur'd Heav'n Pour'd down to execute his sacred Wrath On humane Crimes, be doubly heap'd on him. Alm. Now let us part, nor farther tempt our Fate. Hah! ev'ry Minute I'm alarm'd with Fears Lest Scipio should approach, and see thee here, And then I tremble at the sad Event. Haste, haste, Alucius, instantly away, Our All depends upon thy wing'd Escape, Fly for thy self and me. Alu. Since we must part, Then let us part at least as Lovers ought, And seal that Faith we've sworn with an Embrace, A Parting Kiss—Farewel, my Life, my Soul! A short Farewel, for shortly I'll return, And with thy Ransom bring thee Liberty— Farewel once more—Oh, how my tortur'd Soul Shakes in its Frame when I pronounce Farewel! But 'tmust be so. Remember my last Words, Or Death for me, or Freedom for my Love. Alm. Farewel— [Exit Alucius. May ev'ry God vouchsafe to be thy Guard. [Exit Almeyda. SCENE the Second. Scipio, Lelius. Lel. Methinks, my Lord, this Lethargy of Love Has crept through all the Camp, th'Infection sits On ev'ry Brow; the Warriour minds no more The grateful Clangor of the Martial Trumpet; Glories no longer in his well-try'd Arms, Or burnish'd Helmet; but in wanton Mood Sits down, and revels on the Eyes of Women: [A Sound of Musical Instruments. Hark, their loud Mirth. Scip. Severe, upbraiding Sound! Alas! 'tis Scipio! Scipio is the Cause, He is the faulty Pattern to his Soldiers! Yet charge not him my Friend, but blame his Stars. Oh, had the pitying Gods, who gave me Life, Improv'd the Gift, and freed it but from Love! Then had they made me worthy of my self, The Title of a Roman, and the Name Which I derive from my great Ancestors Th'Immortal Scipios; but this Scipio wears The Laurels of a Warriour on his Brow, Yet he degenerates from a Soldier's Greatness, Deeply enamour'd throws aside his Glories, Forgets the Roman, and forgets himself. Heav'ns! is it just, that we who are engag'd In the Pursuit of Honour, should retreat, And for a Woman quit the glorious Chace? Enter Trebellius, with Alucius Prisoner. Hah! Trebellius with a Guard? A Pris'ner too Loaded with Chains? Trebellius, say the Cause Of this Disturbance. Tre. This rash Spaniard thus Disguis'd in Roman Habit, with Design T'attempt some dang'rous Enterprize, found means Of Entrance to our Camp; but as returning, Examin'd by Chrysantus Captain of the Guard, And being stopp'd his Passage, he refus'd An Answer, but that Instant drew his Sword, And offer'd at Chrysantus, who when stabb'd Alarm'd the Soldiers with his dying Groans, By whom this Pris'ner was pursu'd and ta'en. Scip. What urg'd thee, Spaniard, to so rash a Deed, So base to us, so dang'rous to thy self? Speak, by Confession mitigate thy Crime. Alu. 'Twas Rashness, I confess; but where's the Guilt, The Baseness, to commit an hostile Act Upon a Foe, and such is Rome to Spain? 'Tis true, you are successful, and your Arms Fam'd for a Conquest purchas'd by Surprize: Yet, would our Country but again assume Its pristine Valour, and inspire her Sons With the Immortal Sound of Liberty, List the firm Patriots in the Godlike Cause, Your now victorious Bands in Death should feel How much we dare, and can to set her free. Scip. So haughty and so proud, so brave in Bonds? Alu. A gen'rous Soul can never be subdu'd, You may confine the Body in a Dungeon, With Iron Fetters manacle each Limb, But yet his Soul dares, is, and will be free, And scorn his Victor, though he feel his Chains. Scip. Presumptuous Youth, cease thy ill-manner'd Boasts, This Carriage suits not with thy present State; If thou can'st hope for Mercy, plainly tell What Motive brought thee here, and who thou art. Alu. Make thy Demands elsewhere, my busie Soul, In weightier Tasks employ'd, disdains to hold A Parley. Scip. Fond Youth, spite of my Nature, Thou wilt draw down my Anger on thy Head: Speak, I adjure thee, on the Pain of Death, Speak to the Purpose. Alu. Me wouldst thou frighten With the harsh Sound of Death? 'Tis what I court, The greatest Mercy that my Foe can grant. Yet to acquit my Honour, not comply With thy severe Commands, I ll boldly tell What mov'd a Prince t'assume a mean Disguise; 'Twas Love—Love, that transform'd the Thund'rer himself, And chang'd him to a Mortal from a God. Scip. Love, Sir! for whom? What Mistress canst thou find Within our Camp, whose Beauty can deserve This Peril of thy Life? Alu. Yes, there is one For whom I'd hazard Life a thousand times, A thousand more, if 'twas as oft renew'd. Scip. Sure she's some wond'rous, more than common Fair, That pushes on, and animates thy Soul To this extravagant unbounded Daring. Her Name? Alu. Hold, thou imperious Roman! Insulting Conqueror! think not these Chains, These shameful Bonds deprive me of the Sense That's deeply grafted in the gen'rous Minds Of Princes, such am I, great as thy self, Sprung from the purest Blood that Spain can boast. Damnation! I've already been too mean, Too lavish in my Tongue to own my Love; But may it rot, or be for ever dumb, If I inform thee further—Come wreck your Malice, Doom me to Tortures, Dungeons, and Despair, There let me give a Loose to all my Rage, Curse my Ill Stars, my Fortune, and my self, My Conq'rors and the World, then like a Man And like a Prince expire. Scip. Trebellius, bear him hence, Confine him strictly, but with a Respect Suiting the Greatness of his Character. [Exeunt Treb. and Alu. guarded. Scip. A Spanish Prince (for so he stiles himself) Siez'd in our Camp for Murder?—And in Love? In Love! with whom? Nay, that's a Myst'ry still. It cannot be Almeyda that he loves— Why not? Almeyda is endu'd with Charms To wound the Noblest Breast—A Spaniard too? Nay then the Doubt is clear'd, it must be she; Yet let not Jealousie prevail too far, Examine ev'ry Point, be well inform'd, Urge not the hov'ring Tempest down too soon, Which, whensoe'er it falls, will crush us all. [Exeunt Scip. Lel. SCENE the Third. Lucilius solus. It must be so, since Scipio has refus'd Semanthe to my Arms, and she herself Hath with the proud Trebellius plighted Faith; My injur'd Honour and my Love require A speedy Remedy and just Revenge. Well, thus it is resolv'd, I'll try once more What soft and mild Persuasions can avail; But if she still persists, Force then must be My next and surest Refuge—See, she comes. Enter Semanthe starting back. Why, Madam, should you shun me with Disdain, As if my Aspect spoke some ill Intent, Some purpos'd Mischief brooding in my Heart, That drives you from my Sight? Why are your Looks Chang'd to that Frown? Your Brow thus sternly bent, The Marks of Indignation aim'd to me? Nor aim'd in vain, they pierce through ev'ry Part. Would you but prove propitious to my Love? Sem. Urge not a thing so hateful to my Thoughts, A Subject which I dare not understand. Can you suppose my Female Mind so weak? My Resolution wavering so soon, So easily, since last you were refus'd? Luc. Since last I was refus'd? Can I suppose Or term th'Effect of Modesty a Proof, A binding, certain Resolution?—No. Why should your Beauties, like the blooming Rose, Decay unpluck'd, and wither on the Stalk? Sem. 'Tis needless to employ these idle Words, To tempt a Virgin fix'd in her Resolves. Perhaps, from my Captivity you claim A Priviledge and Title to my Love— I grant I am a Captive to your Arms; But must my Love be guided by the Fate Of War, a Bribe for a precarious Life? My Person is your Pris'ner, but my Heart Is free, and wo' not be constrain'd . Luc. Nor need. What Force have I exerted yet, to cause This Accusation? Sem. I accuse you not, But beg you to desist from naming Love, So odious in its Sound. Luc. From me it may, But from Trebellius 'tis as soft and sweet, As welcome as the Lark's delightful Tune At the bright Dawn of Day. Sem. Trebellius, Sir? Luc. Yes he, your lov'd Trebellius is the Man; But long he shall not glory in his Prize, Or yield to Love, or by yon' Heaven I swear— Sem. What, to destroy thy Friend, and vilely wrong A Woman's Weakness? Could'st thou so debase Thy Soul with such a foul ungen'rous Act? Luc. Perdition seize that Friend, rather that Foe, Who drives me thus by Force to right my self! But you by your Consent may yet restrain My purpos'd Vengeance. Sem. Oh impossible! Shall I prove faithless to Trebellius? No. Luc. Then you're resolv'd— Sem. Yes, to be bravely true, And just to him I love— Luc. Yet think again. Sem. What would you, Sir? your fiery Eye-balls shoot Forth Lightning with your Words: Alas— Luc. I mean To make my Rival and your self repent The Injuries you've offered to a Roman, Unus'd to brook the slightest of Affronts Without Revenge; and thus like angry Jove I'll seize my Prey— [Seizes her, she cries out. These Outcries are in vain, Your Lover absent and the Guards secur'd. [Carries her off by Violence. SCENE the Fourth. Almeyda, Phænissa. Alm. Phænissa, speak no more; this fatal News Deprives my Soul of ev'ry Thought but Horror. Scarce two short Hours since we were wrapt in Joys, And nought but Praises to the bounteous Gods Were issued from our Lips, in Gratitude For their past Favours: But this last Relapse Of Fate, this Renovation of Distress— Phæ. Tho' I can scarcely answer for my Tears, (The Sympathy of Sorrow catch'd from you) Yet would I save Almeyda from Despair, And tune my Words with comfortable Hope. Alm. Canst thou be touch'd thus sensibly with Grief? Weep and bewail Afflictions not thy own? Judge from that Grief Almeyda's greater Cause. Phæ. Yet hope— Alm. Propose that Hope to those who never knew The Pangs of Love thus sever'd and distress'd. Perhaps this Instant my Alucius dies, Is basely murder'd—Can Almeyda hope? Or, if she must, 'tis only for a Grave, A Dagger, or some Poison to dispatch A hateful, tiresome Life Phæ. Have Patience, Madam; Let not this Phrenzy Rage to such Extreams. Alm. Preach Patience to the loud and whistling Winds, Bid Ocean, when his swelling Surges rise, Forego his Rage, and in a Moment calm. Patience! Oh ye Powers! can I be patient Under such Tortures?—Oh release me, Death! Phæ. For Heav'n's Sake! Alm. Heav'n (alas!) has cast me off, And turn'd me out a Wand'rer and forlorn: Destitute of Help both Humane and Divine, A Prostitute to Mis'ry and Despair: What Hopes, or what Dependance can I place On Heav'n? Oh Alucius! Oh Almeyda! Methinks I hear the Raven's croaking Note, Alucius' Death is sounded in that Voice: He shall not die alone, my self will haste And fold his dying Body, till one Fate Shall ease us both, both share the dreadful Blow, And to the Gloom of Death together go. [Exit disorder'd. The End of the Fourth ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT V. SCENE the First. Trebellius, Semanthe. Tre. Semanthe mourn, and I refus'd to share Her swelling Griefs, and bear a Lover's Part! Tell me, oh! tell me the unhappy Cause! Then put my Love, my Truth upon the Trial. Sem. No, I conjure thee fly Semanthe's Fate; Nor seek to know, what known thou wilt repent; If timely cautious, thou may'st yet be happy. Tre. How art thou chang'd, Semanthe? How are those Once radiant Orbs, in whose illustrious Beams So many little Loves and Graces smil'd, And thy attractive Beauties thus o'ercast With the dark Clouds of Grief? But stranger still How could Semanthe's Lips, which once pronounc'd The lov'd Trebellius, bid him fly thee now? Sem. There was a Time, 'tis true, we deem'd our selves The Fav'rites both of Fortune, and of Heav'n; We fed, we flatter'd our deluded Souls With the fond Hopes of mighty Joys to come; But now Experience shews us our Mistake, That all our Wishes, like th'uncertain Sky, Are now serene and gay, anon obscur'd. Tre. Still am I lost, still wandring in a Maze, Without a Clue t'unravel this Discourse, This intricate dark Labyrinth of Wonder. Tell me, thou beauteous mournful Maid, what Turn Of giddy Chance, what Change of angry Fate Thus palls our Pleasures, and obstructs our Hopes? Sem. To speak it, to reflect on it, is Death; Alas, the Thought is impious as the Cause; It is a Tale befitting only Hell, Or the inhumane Villain to unfold. Tre. Stand fast, my Soul, collect thy utmost Courage, Summon thy firmest Resolution now, To bear the Shock of this approaching Horror; I'm lost within my self, I doubt, I fear, I dread to know, yet long to be inform'd. Sem. Now be inform'd, behold the Ravisher, See the infernal Monster, he who acts And boasts in Crimes, which Hell would blush to own; 'Tis he hath plunder'd, basely stole away My treasur'd Love, my Honour, and my Peace. Enter Lucilius. Tre. A Roman and Lucilius! Damn'd, damn'd Villain! Drag him ye Furies to Eternal Flames, Plunge him in hottest Sulphur, there to howl, Curse his sharp Tortures, and repent in vain, And all too little for a Crime so horrid. Luc. Do rail, and vent thy Spleen, I'll not disown The Triumphs of my Love to Heav'n, or thee; 'Twas a luxurious Banquet, Jove himself Could not but envy me th'Enjoyment of it. Tre. And can'st thou, Monster, Do'st thou, dar'st thou hope, Because th'avenging Bolts of Thunder slept T'escape my Vengeance? Know, tho' Heav'n withheld Its Arm of Justice, yet Trebellius wo'not. Luc. Brav'd by this Talker? Draw then if thou dar'st, And prove thy boasted Courage, or my Foot Shall spurn thee from me for a Coward. Tre. Yes, [Semanthe faints. With Honour, Justice, Vengeance on my Side, I'll draw, and give thee thy due Chastisement, Base Ravisher.— [Fight, Lucilius falls. Luc. Dishonourable Death! Slain by a Rival's Hand! Is this my base inglorious Close of Life? My Lawrels blasted by this Stroke of Fate? But I've enjoy'd thy Mistress, dash'd those Pleasures Which thou did'st centre there, and that one Act Attones my forfeit Life, and sweetens Death. [Dies. Tre. Lie there, thou Victim to my injur'd Love. Rise, my Semanthe, view the Hand of Justice, [Turning to Semanthe. The Vengeance for thy violated Honour. Alas, she droops, the poor weak tender Plant Shakes with the Storms, and bows beneath the Tempest: Let me conduct thee hence, perhaps repose May calm thy ruffled Spirits, and dispel The baneful Thoughts of all these Horrors past. [Exeunt. Scipio, Lelius Guards. Scip. Hah! who lies there? Lucilius by his Garb. How ghastly, and how pale! All steep'd in Blood, In his own flowing Gore! Haste, haste our Guards, And seek the Author of this Bloody Act, Be he the nearest Friend to Scipio's Breast, His Crime shall meet the Punishment it merits. Remove the Body hence—Uncertain Fate! That we whom Yester's rising Sun beheld Masters of half the World, should now become Intestine Foes, and by each other fall! Fall by our selves, for Scipio by himself Is ruin'd and undone; but shall he still Be this dull, whining, am'rous Slave, when she, She that enchants him, answers with Disdain? Lelius, this Spaniard, has engag'd her Heart. Lel. Now, Scipio! now thy Greatness must be prov'd, This Instant all th'assembled Gods attend, And listen from the Skies with anxious Care, To know the Resolution of a Man, The Conduct of a Roman thus distress'd. Scip. I am a Man, a Roman, and distress'd; But what can I resolve, or which way steer, Without the Guidance of some greater Pow'r? Should I renounce this Love—why then I should Be what I ought to be, Great Scipio's Son, But can I? that's the Point; can I shake off This Love, and be the Man I was? Lel. Yes, greater. (Pardon the Boldness of a Friend) unite Virtue, Resolution, Courage, and be free: Wake your great Soul from this Lethargick Slumber, Forget this idle Dream, and re-assume The Judge, the Roman, and the General. Scip. I would, but cannot. Lel. You may. Scip. I have strove, Resisted all in vain, Love still maintains Its high Preheminence, whilst I, like Sisyphus Rolling a weighty Stone up an Ascent, Which soon, with Violence and rapid Speed, Comes hurrying downward, only can begin A Second endless Labour—Well, 'tis my Lot, And what I cannot conquer, I'll endure. [Exeunt. SCENE the Second. Almeyda upon a Couch, Phænissa by her. Alm. Why cou'd not I indulge this gentle Slumber, This short Reprieve from Sadness, where such Dreams So full of Extasy, and seeming Bliss, Danc'd in my Brain, and gather'd in my Thoughts; Where my Alucius (for I'll call him mine) Mine, was here presented in this Dream, With eager Transport seiz'd my yielding Hand, And led me to the sacred Temple? There, Oh, how our Hearts, which were before united, Rejoyc'd at the uniting of our Hearts! But 'twas a Dream, a faint, a fading Joy. Phæ. 'Twas an auspicious Omen of Success; These Dreams presage a Tide of coming Joys For you, and your Alucius. Alm. Phænissa, No; Fortune and we have ever been at Variance, Ne'er did she smile, but she design'd us ill, She shew'd us Heav'n, then with a spiteful Frown She bid us die: This Dream is her Device; She hath reduc'd me to the lowest Ebb Of Mis'ry; now with a triumphant Envy Sh'insinuates smiling Pleasures in my Sleep, Which when I wake, I find Delusion all. Phæ. Madam, the Gen'ral comes, dry up these Tears, They may produce Suspicion at this time. Enter Scipio. Scip. When Beauty weeps, 'tis like the Sun eclips'd, It spreads a Cloud of Terror all around, And stamps in ev'ry Heart the dismal Woe. Alm. Let not my Looks, or Griefs infectious prove; I wou'd alone be wretched, and alone In private Sorrow vent these gushing Tears. Scip. But yet these Tears are ominous to Love, And bode me no Success; must Scipio droop, Be still a Slave, and languish unredress'd, For an inexorable, cruel Fair? Alm. If cruel, that impute to Heav'n, not me; Blame those alone who never pair'd our Hearts, Nor destin'd mutual Love—Can I be blam'd? Can I reverse immutable Decrees? Scip. They are your own, not Heav'n's; 'tis you ordain, And cherish this Aversion to my Love, Or else I should not weary the long Days With craving Blessings at a Hand so fair, And so unkind; yet think, oh, timely think! Our mutual Welfare rests on you alone. Alm. You are my Conqu'rour, and my Patron both; And they demand my Rev'rence and Esteem; But when you talk of Love, the Lover's Name Is grating, and unwelcome to my Thoughts. Scip. Now you profess that Hate, disdainful Woman; These Arts, and weak Evasions are in vain: If I'm a Conqu'rour, I am curs'd enough; And if a Friend, my Curse is greater still. But say no more, you have reveal'd too much, Madness ensues, then dread the dire Effects. [Exit Scipio. Alm. What hath my Folly done? Provok'd the Man, The only Man, who had the Pow'r t'undo me? Did he not threaten in his Looks, his Words, Instant Revenge for his Repulse in Love? And all determin'd in Alucius's Death: And who but his Almeyda the curs'd Cause! Had I consented, feign'd, or own'd our Loves, The Event, tho' later, still had been the same: Yet shall I follow, stop the harsh Decree, And tell him all the melancholy Story, How much Alucius and my self have lov'd, How true, and how unhappy we have been; Perhaps he may be kind, and pity us: But shall I trust that Secret from my Lips, On which our Loves, our every Thing depends, Inflame him more, and aggravate his Rage? Oh miserable Fate! Should Hell ope wide Its horrid Caverns, where the howling Damn'd Moan their past Crimes, could there a Wretch be found More wretched than my self? The Torments there Are mild in Competition with my own. If there grim Minos shakes his aweful Nod, And spreads black Terrour o'er the sentenc'd Crowd; They own the Justice of th'Infernal Gloom, And that Reflection moderates their Doom: But I, tho' guiltless, all their Tortures feel, The rolling Stone, the Vulture, and the Wheel. They who would prove at once the worst Despair, Let 'em but Love, like me, they'll find it there. [Exeunt. SCENE the Third. Semanthe Sola. What is this Thing call'd Life? Tis better far To be no more, than be the Wretch I am, So young, and so unhappy, thus depriv'd Of both my Parents; one in Battle slain, The other (oh most fatal Loss to me!) Expiring here, prest with the triple Weight Of Years, of my Misfortunes, and her own. Oh my destructive Beauty! Oh Semanthe! Hast thou not Cause eternal to complain, T'accuse th'unconstant Guardians of thy Fate, And brand them with their cruel base Neglect? How have I glory'd in my Virgin State, My Love unsoil'd, my Honour undefil'd, Chast as my Thoughts, and white as falling Snow? But now that spotless Whiteness is no more, Polution, black as Hell, hath stain'd my Lustre. Trebellius too, that dear, that much-lov'd Man, Chief in my Heart, and first in all my Wishes, Falls like the injur'd Dove, an harmless Prey To the pursuing Vultures, for my sake: Then whither, whither shall Semanthe fly? A friendless Orphan, and unhappy Slave, Subject to ev'ry scornful Victor's Pow'r: No, I'll resolve and be in Death secure. [Exit. SCENE the Fourth opening and discovering Alucius in Prison on the Ground; an Officer speaks to Almeyda entring. Offi. This Act is at the Peril of my Life, And if discover'd, certain Death's my Doom; But see the Prince, there prostrate on the Ground. [Exit Officer. Manet Almeyda. Alm. Thus low reduc'd by thy inclement Stars! Lower thou' can'st not lie, but in the Grave, Where we shall both be soon, the best Retreat For Miseries like ours: Oh Alucius! Oh! my poor mournful Lord! Look up on her Who was thy dearest, lov'd Almeyda, once! Alu. Almeyda? Where? What kind Auspicious Voice, Eccho'd Almeyda to my dying Soul? Alm. Almeyda's self. Alu. And is it, is it she? By all my Hopes of Happiness it is: [Rising. Thus let me bound with Rapture to thy Arms; With equal Joy, as when a trembling Wretch, Wakes from a frightful Dream, and views the Day. Alm. Talk not of Joy, for nought but Horror's here. Alu. Horror in what? Thus in beholding thee? In folding my Almeyda in these Arms? Oh 'tis all Heav'n! Alm. But soon will be no more; This Meeting is our last: Alu. And is it so? Is Fate so merciless? Alm. Inevitably sure; Alucius and Almeyda both must dye. Alu. Alucius dye? Then welcome, welcome Death; Welcome as Freedom to the groaning Slave, Or to a harrass'd Country smiling Peace. Scipio enters unperceiv'd. Scip. Almeyda and the Pris'ner! How got she Admittance to this Tent? Surprising Sight! Now Scipio; now my Heart resolve, support This fatal, killing, unexpected Stroke, And that will be an Action worthy Scipio. [Aside. Alm. But 'tis for me, for me, that thou must die; For me, thou hast relinquish'd Regal Pomp; Depriv'd thy Country of its chiefest Hopes Alucius; let me not ungrateful prove To this vast Miracle of Kindness, Death Shall be Almeyda's Doom; e'en then our Souls, Which were so closely link'd when here below, Would in those Realms of Bliss be still the same, And still retain their Faculty of Love. Say, say, shall I accompany thy Death? Shall I intreat the Gen'ral on my Knees, Unus'd to bend in suppliant Posture? turn A Suiter for our Lives? Alu. For mine? Alm. For both, He may be merciful at last. Alu. That Mercy Beg for your self; Alucius cannot stoop To buy a despicable Life with such Disgrace; sue to a Conqueror; Oh Honour! Would it not Blush? Alm. But your Almeyda, Love Oppose this Ill-tim'd Principle of Honour. Scip. Nor Art, nor Reason, nor my best Resolves, Nor all the Roman muster'd in my Soul, Can more sustain this Tumult of Distress. [Scipio moves forward. Scip. Madam, 'tis well, we see how much you prize The Freedom, that we grant; 'tis wond'rous well. Alm. Oh Scipio! do not look thus sternly on me; Menace not Death, when you behold me, thus Strip'd of the Pride of Royalty, reduc'd To deprecate the Sentence of thy Fury: [Kneeling. Assume your wonted Goodness and Redress— Scip. In what? Alm. Look there and know. Scip. That Pris'ner? Alm. Yes, that Royal Pris'ner is my— Scip. What? Alm. My plighted Husband: Now the deadly Secret, Which lay so long pent in my fearful Breast, And labour'd for its Birth, at last is out. Scip. How Madam? He, that Pris'ner? Alm. Yes, my more Than Husband, if there is a stricter Tie, Our Loves are wove in that; Oh Pardon him! For I will still, still Kneel, till thou shalt say, I Pardon thee, Almeyda hath prevail'd. Scip. Yes, he shall live; but let him first recode From Love, and give me thee. Alu. Mercenary Roman; Propose thy Terms to such as shrink at Death; To Children, Misers, or luxurious Priests; But treat not thus with one who is a Man, And scorns to Barter for a servile Life. What, to foregoe my Love? Alm. That cannot be; Can Soul and Body parted, each remain Alive in that unnatural Separation? When one Twin-Plant is blasted by the Winds, Will not the other sicken at its Loss, And in its Partner's Absence soon decay? Scip. And what is Scipio? What is he to suffer? Should he resign the Mistress of his Heart; Her, that relentless Fair, for whom his Soul Hath languish'd, pin'd so long, hath felt such Pangs, Such Agonies, such Tortures, and Despair, Now tamely give her up; Hah! shun the Thought, It shall not, cannot, is not to be done: Surrender up the Woman that I Love! Gods! how it shocks me. Alm. Yet, yet feel Remorse, Give us some Hopes, e'er all the Means be lost In Death. Scip. I would, (bear witness for me Heav'n) I would, thou barb'rous, charming, cruel Woman, Assent to thy Desires; but there's a War, A Combat in my Breast; my wav'ring Thoughts, Are sway'd each Moment by th'alternate Force Of diff'rent Passions; Hah! what would Scipio? What wouldst thou yield thy Mistress to the Arms Of one who hates thee on a double Score, Rival in Love, and in thy Conquests too? Alm. His Love preceded thine. Scip. Grant that it did, I challenge him to Love thee more than I, To boast a Flame more pure, or Heart sincere. Alm. Yet— Scip. Yet I must Love thee; how can I forbear? Wherefore did Nature form thee so Divine, On those bright Features lavish all her Skill, But to be Lov'd, be Worship'd and Ador'd? Heav'n's! How she looks? What infinite variety Of undiscover'd Beauties still conspire To dart new dawning Glories! On my Soul, This Posture serves but to enhance her Charms. Is she so fair, and shall she not be mine? Alm. Nay, now you are Tyrannical. Scip. Your self That Tyrant are, which you would throw on me, Was I not humbled as the lowest Slave, Imploring what I might by Pow'r command? But for your Minion you disdain'd my Suit: Who is the Tyrant then? Alm. You are a Roman, Now prove the boasted Virtue of that Name, And act like Scipio. Scip. She brings to my Remembrance My sullied Glory, and my conscious Shame. [Aside [He pause Alm. See, see, he melts, his Resolution shakes, I read it in his Looks; he will relent. Scip. It shall be so, spite of these stubborn Pangs, These strong opposing Passions, yet it shall: [Aside. Yes, ye deserving Lovers, I consent, And thus decree your Happiness: Live free: My Love no longer shall molest your Joys, But by your Freedom I'll regain my own, Or else my faithful Sword shall do an Act Of Justice on its Coward Master's Breast. Almeyda, rise—Here, Spaniard, I resign, [Raising her. Receive her Hand from Scipio and thy Foe. Alu. Curs'd be that Villain, who maintains the Name Of Foe against such Goodness! then shall I Be guilty of Ingratitude so base? How, how shall I repay thee for this Gift, So exquisite, more welcome than my Life, The Gift of Heaven? Scip. Far be't from Scipio's Thoughts To make Advantage of thy private Friendship, But for the Publick, be a Friend to Rome, I ask no more. Alu. Excellent, Godlike Roman! In ev'ry Virtue, as in War, Supreme! My Sword, and all the Country I possess, Shall be employ'd as Scipio shall command. Alm. Your Pardon, Gen'rous Conqu'ror, that my Tongue 'Midst these fierce Transports lost, forgets to speak The Gratitude that rises in my Heart. Enter Trebellius. Treb. Thus far, my Gen'ral, have I trac'd your Steps, Thus do I press to importune a Favour, So great, that Death must follow its Denial; Freed by my Judges, still I am in Bonds, Instant Release from which depends alone On Scipio's Clemency. Scip. I know thy Wish, But 'tis not Scipio can confirm it to thee; The injur'd fair Semanthe is no more, This Night th'unhappy Beauty breath'd her last. Treb. Sharp, stabbing Sentence! my Semanthe dead? What farther Bus'ness hath Trebellius then For Life, to breath in this unwholsome Air, Depriv'd of his Semanthe? Scip. Chear, my Soldier, And imitate the Pattern of thy Gen'ral: Scipio hath lov'd like thee, like thee endur'd Its bitter Wounds, and its heart-breaking Pangs, But is at length the Master of himself. Come, come, my Warriour, rouze thee up to Arms Shake off th'inglorious Flame, and follow Scipio. Now we're our selves, and will again to War, Again our Eagles shall adorn the Air. With dire Alarms we'll chase the shatter'd Foe, Pursue the Terror, and conclude the Blow. But learn, ye Laurel'd Chiefs, whatever Spoils Crown your vast Actions, and reward your Toils, Your Fame's precarious, your Atchievements vain, Till o'er your selves you can a Conquest gain. [Exeunt omnes. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>