<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">University Press</field>
      <field name="author_facet">University Press</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">university press</field>
      <field name="author_text">University Press</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1940's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V1.0404.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240355</field>
      <field name="date_text">1944</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:459145</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Ghismonda ; A Seventeenth-Century Tragedy</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Ghismonda ; A Seventeenth-Century Tragedy</field>
      <field name="title_facet">ghismonda</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">ghismonda</field>
      <field name="title_text">Ghismonda ; A Seventeenth-Century Tragedy</field>
      <field name="year_display">1944</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1944</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1944</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459145&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459145&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Ghismonda ; A Seventeenth-Century Tragedy&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;ghismonda&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1944&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1944&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Ghismonda&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Seventeenth-Century Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Manchester&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University Press&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1944&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3873421-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv10404&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 20th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;20th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Ghismonda&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Seventeenth-Century Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 183 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Jacobean and Caroline verse drama.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries, introductory and editorial matter omitted&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Copyright (c) 1944, Manchester University Press. This text may not be reproduced, except for fair dealing purposes, without the express permission of Chadwyck-Healey and the copyright holder.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Ghismonda.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1933.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 1623–1624.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">GHISMONDA A SEVENTEENTH-CENTURY TRAGEDY</field>
      <field name="fulltext">To My old Colleague and Fellow-Student of the Drama H. B. CHARLTON</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE ACTORS' NAMES Tancred, King of Salern. Ghismonda the Princes, daughter to the King, and widdow to the Duke of Capua's son. Guiscardo, a gentleman appoynted by the King to attend her, and of his Councell. Gabriello a courtier. Pasquino a courtier. Glausamond, a chronomasticall courtier. Mistris Minks, the Princes' wayting-woman. Embassadour from the Duke of Capua. An executioner.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE PROLOGUE If't be a fault to shew you how a story May be preseru'd longer in memory Then if one tong alone had tould a tale, Our expectation's crost, and we shall fayle Of haueing courteous censure. Yet ne'rtheles All that haue cleare-ei'd iudgmentes will confesse Hee merits more that shewes accutely how Ghismonda di'd for Guiscard, to keepe the vowe Which she soo brauely made, then to heare this Absurdly tould. But 't may be, you will hisse At our kind of expression. Take heede! They that doe soe, will cause his head to bleede That's Priscian to them. Yet if a man, Able and well-discerning, please to scan Our lines like verses, foote by foote, we will To such an artist gladly submitt our skill And prostrate all our labours at his feete, Whose patience shewes himselfe to be discreete.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I Enter Gabriello and Pasquino. Gab. It cannot sincke into my head, a lady So fresh, so fasting, plumpe and prurient As our great widow Princes is, should leaue All those quick-risinge comforts this world yeeldes, Because she hath lost one husband. If some I know Weare in her case, perhaps they'd mourne a while, Or, if you will, deiect a verge's face Till the next sunshine day, but then, the winde Being still, the weather calme, and a new sutor Fitted with complementes for their accostment, The fault would be if expedition were not Obuious to appetite. 'Tis a receau'd decree Among the spirited ladies, a man that's slow And lumpish often dreames out all the day, While a braue sparke doth gett the prize away. Pasq. I graunt it. But there liues a noblenes In chast Ghismonda's breast that scornes to heare A motion of a second mariage-bed; And as her birth doth far surpas those dames Whose qualities you make relation of, So doth her worth excell there dignity; Her thoughtes and actions are all chastity. Gab. Herein I ioyne with you, and no disparagment Comes neare herselfe or [her] reputation, Though 'twere diuulg'd throughout all Italy That she mourn'd for a husband—not a dead one, But for a stirring prince whose agitation Can rise high capers for her recreation. Pasq. This theme is most vnfitt for our discourse. Nor can our duty giue vs priuiledge To parse vpon her thus. Gab. Is she of flesh? Pasq. Yes. Gab. Then she's made of earth, And vessels of this mettle are apt to cracke. Now if that Nature haue dispos'd her soe That she will make her weaknes weaker only, Because her stronger part hath left ye world, She wronges her sex and doth bely the custome Ta'n vp among our female votaries. Pasq. Lett my aduice be thus far followed, Rather to talke of what concernes ye meanest And of what moues in our owne hemisphere Then to assay to take the altitude Of the empyreum, far aboue our reach. Gab. It hath bene sayd, the safest way's the lowest, And from an high ascent a fall is dangerous. I'le take thy counsell once and prayse the pathe Where we may walke without a banke t'o'rethrow vs. Yet if thou beest not false or too officious, What need these wordes haue further life or memory? That we relate or speake of onely should Fitt the time that we speake it in, and not Make all society odious, for feare Of some false brother with a list'ning eare. Pasq. I am no statist. Gab. I dare sweare thou art not. Pasq. And yet I'd be loath to be a traytor too, For he that should but ope his mouth and say— Gab. What? Pasq. Nothing. Gab. Nay, then thou'rt monstrous wittye. Yet I'le make thee wiser, if thou'lt be rul'd by me; Drowne danger in greate glasses; old Canary Will make our braynes grow solid, our wites wary. Let's therefore to the tauerne; he that drinks worst With Bachus' execration is accurst; He that is lofty and comes at the head Shall haue the greatest part o'th'bisket bread. If thou beest able but to pay the shott, I'le drinke the sacke all vp when thou canst not, And if thou then wilt talke of thinges aboue thee, Farewell, fond foole, I neuer more will loue thee. Come, your only catholique drink is sack. [Exit Gab. Enter Tancred, Guiscardo and Glausamond. Tanc. Whether so fast, Pasquino? Haue you giu'n order I may haue notice, when the embassadour From the good Duke of Capua is ariu'd? Pray, haue a care of that. Pasq. Great King, I haue; And as it is my charge, 't shall be my greatest care. Tanc. You may goe on then; you haue done discreetly. [Exit Pasquino. Had but our kingdome, or the streingth therof, Ability to drye those salt teares vp Which plough rough furrowes in my daughter's face, Or weare the prime restoratiues, which are drawne By curious extraction out of goold Or pearle, as deare agayne, and the application Of theese vnto the bottome of her feete Of power enough to make her wrinkles smooth, I would confine my selfe vnto one dish, Make a vacuity in my diademe Of any thing but holes and aire; that ruby, Which by my father was so highly valued Well-skill'd Vesheti offer'd for it to barter A ship full-ballanc'd with refined goold, If it might but recure and comfort her, Should lie i'th'durt to be her stepping-ston. Glaus. Such stones will neuer cure her, may't please your Grace, But to invite her to some recreation, As playes or maskes, to take the aire abroad, Se a deare kill'd with bow; and perhaps this May in an emblem shew her how that Cupid, When he hath will, can shoote as sharp an arrow And make it smart as much (only he hath None that are fork'd to shoote), or, if he will, He can plucke forth an heauy-laden shaft And make all those of whome it doth draw blood Become both hateres of them selues and others. And when this hierogliphick thus informes her, Her nature being participate with yours, I know shee wilbe like you pliable, And both in mercy to her selfe and feare Of being obnoxious to the blinde god's rage, Shee'l kisse your aged councell and soone feele, A panting hart surpasseth one of steele. Tanc. She doth allege that she hath strongly vowed Neuer with kind amplexure to embrace Any man in those armes where that braue lord, Her husband, once was vs'd to be infoulded. Glaus. Venus forbid soe firme a resolucion: Did she not, by your Grace's fauor, say “I will not—vnlesse”, or “I will, if I Finde another to my mynd”, or “as my heart Now standes”? But peremptorily to say “No”, Except it be a double negatiue, Which I doe loue to heare a woman say, It is a pittifull case for the present And worthy memory for the future, For, vpon my life, noe woman liueing Will take a pride to be her successor. Tanc. Doest thou thinke they'r soe fickle? Glaus. All but shee. And if your Maiestie will say my boldnes Is but the freenes of my duty to you, I cannot be perswaded but that shee, Who knowes the whole world is so at her dispose That she may choose whome she please out of it, Canot so vnderprize her selfe as keepe That ring within a close-lock't cabinett Which may beseeme the greatest monarches wearing. With the permission of your soueraigne power, Did she conclude without a limitation? Tanc. To my remembranc, she did; Guiscardo, you Sometimes attending in her presence might Heare her let fall her mynd in ampler termes. Her good concernes vs all, and if you can Giue any light by that which you haue seene Or heard, vnfould it. Guisc. Your greatnes being pleas'd Thus far to grace the weaknes of your servant, With a submissiue heart and bow'd obedience I doe present you this advertismente. After it pleas'd your gracious Maiesty To appoynt me in that place of happines, Where 'twas my duty howrely to lay downe At her feete prostrate what my service was, Or the best power I had, had strength to make it, With a sigh, yet I hope not such a one As each time makes a drop of blood to follow, She bad me giue this doubt a resolucion— Whether I did thinke that the violacion Of a vow firmly made was not a sinn, And if it weare, whether it weare pardonable. Tanc. What might she meane by this? Glaus. I warrant you That followes, sir. There's ne're a lady in Europe, That vseth to aske young men questions, But knowes why she doth it and what she meanes By't too. Tanc. And what was thy answere, prythee? Glaus. Oh, sir, he's not yet come to the state of the question. Guisc. You'r i'th'right. Tanc. On, then. Guisc. My leige, I tould her she must iudg of that, Being shee knew the nature of the offence, If't weare one, better then I could, vnles I vnderstood the reasons why she vowed And how circumstances did one succeed another. Tanc. 'Twas well, Guiscard; and how did she reply? Guisc. A little while aposiopesically She stopt, and, as it weare a saynt that thought The aire was too corrupt to entertayne The breath her voice expel'd, forthwith she sayd: “Heauen shall resolue this scruple, and repentance Make this spott white by dayly excercise”; And silenc gaue her leaue to say noe more. Then, feareing least my presence had diseas'd her, Knowing my selfe vnworthy to partake Of any meditation she conceau'd, I made thus bold to say: “Doth't please you, Madam, I shall avoyd the roome or call your woman”? She answered “No”, and then she sayd agayne: “Thy readines doth manifest thy care; Therefore I'le aske my question out”; and then With as great state as if Apollo's preist Had gone t'interrogate the oracle About some high designe, she ask'd her selfe, Not me, for then the simile could not Hould; yet I stood by, and by her leaue And fayre command sometimes sayd “I” or “No”. Tanc. What did she aske? Guisc. The asking was soe gracefull, I had almost let that passe; but thus she askt— Whether 't were not a capital offence T'infringe a vow which did strictly tie her Neuer agayne to know another husband. I answer'd: “Madam, 'tis far aboue me to iudge, Yet without question 'tis an offending crime To breake a vow which in effect's an oath. But peraduenture you made it conditionall, And if the condicion be perform'd fully, Then th'obligacion is voyd certaynly; Therefore your Ladyship shall not doe amisse To thinke of that.” At which that she smil'd And sayd: “Can't be”? I answer'd: “Greater iudgmentes Are able to decide it, and, of theese None better then your owne”; for should I hazard This moment of my life, which is mayntayn'd But by the aire that passeth to and fro Through these ventiges vpon humane discretion, I'd chose her for my iudge, yea, my director, In what mortality is able to dispose of, Rather then all the senators of Roome, Liu'd they agayne; for she's a greater stay To vs then they were to the seauen-hil'd citty; And, being so wise, and able to consider What good is wanting to the comonwealth, And what felicity likely to ensue By her sterility or her frutefulnes, She'l turne the best side out, which is her mynd, And shew her thoughtes which yet lye hid in stillnes. Tanc. You did no fuller vnderstand them, then? Guisc. Not I, dread sir, and yet me thought her smile Came from a tree, whose frute was worth ye plucking, And did meane somethinge. Glaus. Sir, when there is stirring, There's hope of life, and she can hardly Smile but her lips will moue; and I hope The noble Princes is not so far gone as to Giue one smile and dye, as swans singe Once and last. No, no! Doe your best to gett her A braue cob; great I meane not—her owne Greatnes is bigg enough allready—but one That is sinowie and able, who may be wholly at Her service and soly at her will. This the way To cure her; and tak't o' my word, shee'l bringe You euery yeare a land-bird and yet haue a Nest-egg for a come-agayne. Tanc. I would I could once heare her in thy vayne! Glaus. You heare, she smiles, and that's no signe of death. I would you would giue me leaue to singe But one song to her! I warrant you, I'le make Her heart goe pant, pant, and shee'l pricke vp her Eares like a hare at a muset. You canot Wrong her more then giue a weake medicine To a strong disease; she wantes heate, and you Giue her almond-milke. Tanc. Let it be so. But se your tune be civill And your ditty modest; els you'l beknaue Your selfe and displease your master. Guisc. She aprehendes So sodaynly and doth discerne so clearely That you disgrace your selfe with her for euer, If you but vent one word of ribaldrye. Glaus. Sha! that is as 'tis tempered and as the season Fits. Sing “Willow” to a conquerer, or crowne A bridegroome with cipres, and misapplication Will make them both seeme as vnseasonable As a slasht dublet at Christmas. But they That will deale with ladies must goe to't, First, sembreefe time; then, if this hould out Well and you can hang vpon the pricke, three To one is a good cord; and soe you may rise From prick minum to prick crochet, from Prick crochet to prick quauer, and so on From prick to pricke, till you come to Double, treble, quadruple, or as many as You will semiquauers. This is strange Now to the non-intelligent; yet I'le lay My head on't, I'le make the solemst lady In Christendome, soe she be willing, vnderstand all this in a mounth without much Compultion and laugh at those that cannot, When she hath done. The wordes of art Are very harsh to the vncapable. Tanc. Is thy song compos'd? Glaus. It cannot, sir. Yet 'twill not be long in makeing; 'tis but Putting in her for her by him instead Of him, and 'twill be well. Tanc. So then. Say, Guiscardo, cannott You beare a part? Guisc. I should be sory, if in her deare service I could not shew as strong a breast as any. Tanc. All this is good; so far 'tis well gone on. The castle's strong which you doe set vpon; Breake downe the walles, but with a pleasing touch, You glad the King and all his subiectes much, For in her sweet-dispos'd alacritie Restes this great kingdom's cheefe felicity. Glaus. I warrant you, sir, I'le make her sing. Tanc. On that condicion Either of you shall haue a liuery Prepared of my cost—suit, cloke and all— And the worst trimming shalbe pearles inbroydrede. The very tagges o'th'poyntes shalbe the colletes That shal containe thousand pound diamondes in them, And yet be payd for too. Glaus. Wee'l deserue them, If such a seruice merit so high a prize. Enter Pasquino. Pasq. According to your powerfull commaund I come to giue you notice, euen now The Duke of Capua's embassadour is ariu'd. Tanc. Glausamond and Guiscardo, to your charge, And as the affaire is great, perform't discreetly. Rayse but her spirites so vp that she may grace Our presence, when the embasadour hath audience, And 'tis enough. Come, follow me, Pasquino. [Exeunt Tancred and Pasquino. Guisc. All that our endeauors can bring forth Is but the doeing of the Kinges command. Shee'l be no more mou'd with this triuiall course Then a strong tower, when a key-gun goes of. Glaus. That matters not; if we but please the King, It is enough; nor is it worth inquirye Whether the successe be good or ill. The way For vs and all courtiers to thriue by Is to please the King and neuer more thinke What will next follow. He whose heart relentes For doeing the wrong way, when the Kinges potentes Say “Thus 't shall be”, in simple honesty Meanes well, but his precise modesty Will keepe him bare enough and in disgrace; None can thriue now without a brazen face. [Exeunt Guiscardo and Glausamond. Finit Actus Primus.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACTUS SECUNDUS Enter Ghismonda, her wayting-woman, and Guiscardo. Guisc. Not vnles that it shall please your Highnes, Without a too much troublesome incrochment Vpon your gentle patience, will I take part In offering that which may breed your vnrest. Ghism. Doe you say it is the Kinges pleasure, I Should heare him? Guisc. Yes, Madam, and I inioyn'd To beare a part. But I respect not that, Though I confesse at first it pleas'd the King To destine me and all my best abilities Only to be imploy'd in your attendance; Yet, being so imploy'd, the whole dispose And power of me consistes in your command. Ghism. Nay, if it be so, I'le not gaynesay his will. Guisc. Trust my true service. Glausamond is directed With the best ordring of his voice and fingers His skill affordes to offer you a songe; And in so strict wordes the King gaue him charge That I dare thus far paune my reputation (Which lost with you, I wish my life may follow In the next moment) that he will offer you Nothing but what a chaste and modest eare May without blushing be partaker of. Your censure shall conclude myne good or bad, Before he come, if it so please your goodnes. Ghism. No, since it must be soe, I'le heare it all together, And so it will be either much better or much worse. One knocks. See who's there. Glaus. Pray, is her Grace at leasure? [At the dore. Wait. If you'l but stay a while, I'le know her pleasure. The King hath sent Glausamond to se your Highnes. Ghism. Call him in. Enter Glausamond. He that relates a message from the Kinge Deserues to be nam'd welcome. Glausamond, your Welcome, and I hope your newes deserues no lesse. Glaus. First your father's loue I here deliuer; secondly, his desire You would be merry i'th'day and sleepe i'th'night. Ghism. I am so, and my weake mortality Is not refin'd to make me so durable As hould this life so long without that nutriment. Glaus. The cause he feares you want it, lady, 's thus: He oft is witnes of your solemnesse In the daytime him selfe, but if you rest Or sleepe or wake or dreame or seigh, or what You doe, when the darke shade incloseth Your sacred selfe in—you say, widow-curtayns, But he desires the should be sportfull ones— He's ignorant of. Yet he doth feare much The cause by the effect and therefore bad me First craue your patient, lending eare and then Offer a song vnto you, onely made, If't may be, to giue you some recreation. Ghism. I haue heard some songes haue bene compos'd for mirth, And, being presented to the persons which They should haue wrought vpon, by what disaster I know not, the effect hath bene cleane contrary, And hop'd-for mirth hath prou'd deepe malancholy. Glaus. In ill-disposed bodies 't may proue soe. Ghism. Therefore lett this song be contrary, And it will worke mirth out of melancholy. Glaus. If your licence will admit the heareing, Assure your selfe, a good euent will follow. Ghism. Discretion ne're could be call'd obstinat; Therefore I'le yeald. He that's preiudicate May goe the wrong way and repent too late. The Songe. Glaus. The vertuous Queene, whose spottles chastitie Doth farr exceed Diana's modestie, Would faine dissolue her selfe with weeping still, Making her beauty subiect to her will. Guisc. The time will come, and wee shall ioy to see That she, who now's ingaged, shall liue free And shake those fetters of which greefe hath ti'd Her in, and then become a glorious bride. Both Heau'n grant this change and send this alteration, Turning her greefe to sportfull recreation. Glaus. The noble Queene, whose true nobilitie Hath the first place in Juno's pedegre, Is now perplext with greefe, and therefore wee Do stand partakers of her miserye. Guisc. The time will come, when euery blast yt blowes Vnrest to her, shall whisk it to her foes, And heau'n, auspitious being, shall wipe those teares Which shew her anguish and procure our feares. Both Heau'n grant this etct. Turning her greefe etct. Glaus. The beauteous Queen, whose lookes the Queen of loue Fear'd should be seene, because they weare aboue Hers, both in lustre and in dignitie, As now grown pale with looking solemnly. Guisc. The time will come agayne, if Heau'n so please, When euery accident shall giue her ease; And where the clouds are thick, the sun will show, And roses bud, where thorny brambles grow. Both Heau'n grant this chang and send this alteration, Turning her greefe to sportfull recreation. Ghism. Haue you not a second part? Glaus. A short one. Guisc. But 'tis not apted as we wish it weare. Only the wordes are as our hartes to you, And, where an accent wantes, or breath of time Says 'tis vnworthy of your heareing, Let your so oft-experienc'd noblenes Conclude the faultes not great, and we are crown'd. The song sung by Both togeither. The hower we look't for now begins to come, Our ioyes now speake which long before were dumbe. Heau'n heard our prayrs and then tooke pitty on vs, Because before it layd a cross vpon vs. Long let ye Princes liue, and we to pray Her comfort may grow greater euery day. Glaus. If it shall please your honoured Ladyship To haue a liuelyer tune, your word commandes it, For this is he that ne're gaynesayd a lady. Ghism. I am satisfied, and I hope that you Cannot but say the Kinges comandes fulfil'd. I doe desire you will from me present him With filial thankes and with a due obseruance. Enter Pasquino. Pasq. Your royall father and our soueraigne Hath set this day apart to entertayne The embassadour which lately is ariu'd From the great Duke of Capua, and intreates You would be pleas'd to grace the affayre so much As yeald your presence to the audience. Ghism. First the King knowes, and then the embassadour, If he doe come from Capua, my greefe As well as I can name it, and the occation. Therefore first with an offering of my duty, Then with a request of pardon, pray intreat him, My absence may be borne with. Pasq. He put of, And wil'd me let you knowe soe, this dayes busines Longer then he intended, onely because Your selfe should vnderstand the intelligence At the first hand, without another's telling. Ghism. Is it needfull I must heare't my selfe? Pasq. The King is of that mynd and therefore sent me. Ghism. Rather then haue a second or third relation To be disturb'd with, I'le endure the first. Guiscardo, lead the way. [Ex. Ghismonda: Guiscardo before her, the waiting-woman and Pasquino. Glaus. What, noe more manners Then to leaue me alone? Well, breeding es all. Had good old Tancred heard me but sing so long, He would haue cri'd “Oh, my best boy, but seldome Comes a better”! Blesse the old one, for the young One's mad, els she would ne're be Niobe So young! Yet the metamorphosis Is only in the hart; the other partes Are able yet to bend with supple flexure, If they were put to't, I dare lay my life on't. Enter Gabriello, chafinge. Gabri. A pox o' this rogue! I thought I had had a Young whelp to enter, and he hath caught The old woodcocke. Glaus. Who's that, Gabriello? Gab. He and I, I and he— What a question's that! Who dost think't should be? Glaus. O, now I know the foole o'th'one side, But whoe is the caulfes-head his brother? Gab. Ether thou or the great oxe Pasquino. Glaus. For my owne part, I thanke you and am Satisfied. But, prithe, tell me, What hath Pasquino done? Gab. Just as the fox did, when he intreated The crow to singe—eate the cheese and sent The crow to seeke her breakefast. Glaus. It is not in the compas of his cerebrum To cheate thee of thy victualls. Gab. I thought soe too, But he cheated me of meate, drink and cloth, Eu'n pure sacke. Glaus. What, did he so? Pore foole, alacke! Gab. I protest, I'le cut your fiddle-stringes. Glaus. 'Tis but steeping a shorte on in thy sacke, And it will serue agayne. Gab. The more wrong'd, the worse abus'd. Glaus. What's the difference betwene them? Gab. My learning scornes to acquaint you With my distinctions. Glaus. So, sir. Then in amity, frendship, loue, kindnes, Curtesie and good-fellowship, without thinking Of past mischances and hope of new reueng, How did he o'rereach thee in thy drinke? Gab. 'Twas thus. One serious day among the rest, When I had nought to doe but talke with him, Some matters of state this grene goose needes Would speake of, Which being made no greater thinges betwixt vs Then shittlecockes betwene a pare of battledores, Flirting as nimbly from him to me as did The old woman's brawne out of her mouth To her neighbor's trencher, I told the best Way to keep vs both from quarrelling and Hanging was to drowne great wordes in Deepe cups. Soe to the tauerne we went, Cal'd for and drunke alike; at last satiety Growing vpon vs, I asked for the reckoning. “That was a pore trick”, sayd Pasquino, “to goe And not drinke our galloundes a pece”. Now, thinking my head could beare as much As any elder brother's in Italy, I cry'd “Your good will be done, sir”. Then sayd he: “Prithe, let me but goe se one quart drawne Out of a butt of rich wine which I knowe By a priuie marke”. “Agreed”, sayd I, “and I'le stay Here the while”. Whi[ch] sayd Pasquino left Gabriello alone eight shillinges to pay, and I Had but a noble in my purse. Glaus. 'Twas an elder brother's trick, but a younger's Witt. And prithe, how didst come of? Gab. Eu'n as gentlemen doe that take vp Vpon nouerints. I was fayne to promise and Forc't to pay. Glaus. Prithee, tell me; hast thou had a sight Of the Duke of Capua's embassador? Gab. Yesternight I saw him, and he inquired Of the condicions of Lord Glausamond. Glaus. Well lorded, I assure you! Thou couldst shew Him the way to my Lordship's chamber. Gab. And did. Glaus. You shew'd your duty in it, and for requitall I'le doe as much to any courtesan That lookes for thee. But tell me in good earnest; Hast thou not heard the intent of his comming? Gab. A woord or too I did. Glaus. From whome? Gab. The Kinge. Glaus. Then thy intelligence must needes be good. Gab. I take it so. When he first came to court, I heard it whispered, the old Duke, father-in-law To the Princes, was so pleas'd with her carriage And sweetnes of her disposition that He tooke such care t'inquire her out a sutor Worthy of her that he hath sent this messenger, His trusty seruant, first to intreate the Kinge And then her Highnes that a braue prince, his neighbor, May come to offer his best seruice to her. Glaus. What, to owe in person? Gab. Soe I vnderstand it. Glaus. Great head and smale braynes! thou'rt out, For the fashion's now 'mongst great ones To owe by pictures, get children by atturney; One's the fashion, the other's the custome; yet The custome will outweare the fashion, and Making loue to a painted cloth or low conges To a little modicum of a card in an ebonie box Wilbe out of fashion, before the vse wilbe left Of gentlemen rideing in noblemen's sadles. Gab. Thou dost much ioy in being satiricall. Glaus. I may be so and sometimes am permitted To shew that by way of fooleing which A statesman would be cal'd in question for, If he durst speake it at the councell-table. Why, now you may abuse your father, and do't but witily, And some kind old foole will say “Who would thinke My sonne were so far read or had attayn'd In so few yeares to such a large proportion Of witt or grace”? The dayes we liue in Are now preposterous grown, the time come agayne, When 'twas a grace to lie, sin to speake playne. Tell a man of his faultes, because you loue him, You lose him quite, therby so moue him To anger and impatience that hee'le greeue To se you in his sight and not beleeue What your good wishes told him. Comend a gull, Whose father di'd but lately, leaueing him full Of that which drawes attendanc, and 'tis great odds Hee'le prize you as the heathens did there gods, Call you his genius, thanke your kind wordes to him, Although by these faire speaches you vndoe him. If you'r toe conscientious to lie, You must goe liue alone, for company You'r like to haue but little. Pray stand by, Vntill one come of your society, For two there are not liueing. Goe from Rome, If when a lie is told, you doe stand dumb And feare to applaud it, 'cause it is a crime; To sware a lie is true's the garb o'th'time. Will not your stomake stand to cheat your brother, You are not fitt to liue, for now a mother Will cosin her daughter of her soule for pay; I know an old iade did so yesterday. If thou wilt haue a further information, Giue but another qu; I'le make relation Of twice as much as this. Gab. Nay, I think 'tis better To goe in now, for perchanc the King Will be displeas'd, if ether of vs be wanting, Especially at this time of ceremony. Glaus. It may be soe. Therefore let's goe and see. [Exeunt. Finit Actus Secundus.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACTUS TERTIUS Enter Tancred, Ghismonda, Embassador, Glausamond and Guiscardo; ye King sits. Tanc. Sit downe, my deare Ghismonda; ye Duke of Capua Salutes you by this gentleman, his seruant, And in a letter with his owne hand subscrib'd Desires he may haue audience when you are present. Ghism. It is a smale request from one soe greate And a great favor done to one so low As I am now become with care and greefe. Tanc. He doth endeuor to regaine your losse. Ghism. 'Tis not within the boundes of possibility. Tanc. Harbour not such a thought. The embasie Which now's to be deliuered will informe you How by an easy way this may be done. Ghism. I should be glad to se it and apt to giue All the warme drops of blood that might be spar'd, Onely my life reseru'd, one day to gaze Vpon him, whom Heauen pleas'd to take from me. Tanc. This not the way. Are you willing to heare What the good Duke desires should be deliuer'd To you and me? Ghism. If that your Maiesty Comaund it soe. Tanc. Come then, sit downe by me. Our expectation now intreates your message. Embass. Since that the strength and safty of all kingdomes Is much aduanc'd by good confederates, And wise men loue most to conuerse with those Whose trust hath giuen them best experience, My master bad me let your Maiesty And yours and his deare daughter, the Princes, know, There cannot come so great a comfort to him, Nor more aduancment to your state and his, As he conceiues, then to double your aliance Which, though't be strong already, may be greater, If you'l be pleas'd to admit of this proposall Which by me thus he doth exhibite to you. The aged king, whose land Vulturnus' streame Dissectes from ours, is lately dead and left One only son to heire his crowne behind him, Who's named Felix, and all those that know him Say, wise Apollo was his godfather, Because the name is so significant. But he is not him selfe yet of that mynd, Wanting a lady, whose fayre company May make him thinke him selfe completly happy. This prince, so well-esteem'd, his dieing father Committed to my master's tutelage; Not that he thought his weaknes did disable Him to direct him selfe, but that he knew His councell would grow as the prince in yeares, And his loue cause him to bestow't vpon him. My master, being so much indear'd vnto The prince as his old father thought he would be, Sayd thus vnto him: “Son Felix”, for the old king Desir'd he so would call the prince, “your father's dead, Your realme so too, vntill you haue a wife. Receaue a motion which is fatherly, And tak't as kindly as I offer't freely. The faire Ghismonda and the good, for soe My conscienc bides me say, or els I lye, (Yet this assertion is but voluntary And not constrayn'd) lately the powers aboue Made widow; and you desire to place your loue On a deseruing subiect, striue to be High in her fauor, for if mortality Afford a faultles moueable, this is she”. Then with a gratefull conge which became him And pleas'd the Duke, my master (now his father, Yet but in name and care) the Prince reply'd: “'T had bene vnciuill both and disobedient 'T haue vndertak'n so great a thing without Asking your graue advice, and 'tis as ill Not to accept with broad-spreaded armes What you haue pleas'd to propose so nobly. Therefore, as your still-continued fauor Makes me obliged and names you my father, Put on this wisht designe, and let me goe To offer incense to the named goddes”. But this my Duke denied and did obiect Some inconueniences which did hinder A prince's trayne to goe soe sodaynely, And told the earnest Prince yt I should goe, A seruant to them both, to know the pleasure Of you, great King and Princes. If your admition Will grant him soe much freedom of accesse, Thought cannot fly more swift then his desire To lay his seruice at the Princes' feete; If, on the other side, you will not graunt Him thus far fauor, my master doth entreat Silenc may shutt vp what my tongue hath open'd And giue't no other place in memory Then this—'twas meerely done in curtesy. Tanc. We doe accept it soe. The Dukes fidelity To us, so often tri'd, doth well assure vs, His loue first made this motion; but since this is A great affaire of state, we must take time With our wise councell to haue consultation; And, this being done, I'le send him my resolue. Yet take this comforte with you and deliuer This message to my brother and the Prince: So earnestly I wish this may goe on That he hath much to ground his hope vpon. Farewell. Take order that two men-of-warr May be prepar'd to giue him safe-conduct. [Exit Tancred. Glaus. I shall, sir. Ghism. Let my duty to my father Be offered vp, for he hath much ingag'd me. Yet tell him I'm resolu'd to liue free And hope he will not take't discorteously. [Exit Ghismonda, and Guiscardo before her. Embass. I'le tender him your Highnes' salutation Which hee'le receaue as kindly as you send it. Glaus. That's kindly enough, for I can assure you, She dayly mournes for a dead lim of him, And if she did not honor much the father That got the son, she would not be so violent. Embass. Douth she mourne still? Glaus. As Cloris for Amintas. Embass. How was that? Glaus. Will you know in verse or prose? Embass. Ether, so it be breefe. Glaus. Then you shall heare it two wayes— Musically and wittily, and yet both at once. Cloris sate and sitting slept, Sleeping sight and sighing wept, And slept and sight and wept agayne For Amint[a]s that was slayne. “Oh, had you seene his face”, quoth she, “So sweet, so full of maiestye”— And then she stopt and then she cries “Amint[a]s, Amint[a]s”, and so she dies. White is not liker argent, nor black sable Then this sad story to what the Princes dayly Practiseth, but that yet she is not come To that height of extrematy as to dye. Embas. Then my iorney was vndertak'n in vayne, And message told so, if her extasie Be so imoderate, without limitation, And she hath so invr'd her resolucion Only to thinke on him that's dead and cureles. Glaus. That followes not. The goodnes of her nature Makes her doe this, and those being wrought vpon Yeeld soonest, if they see a peircing reason. Therefore take my aduice; when yt prince comes That meanes to bord this lofty pinnes, let him With a broadside come on, short, thicke and strong, Be sure to hitt where the last leake was stopt, For there's the weakest part. Embas. Come, your directions are too obscure. Glaus. I'le make a comment then so learnedly, When please the Prince to exercise my seruice, That he shall vnderstand and se distinctly What euery accent meanes. But to others Pray giue me leaue to write in charecters. Embass. Your power's your owne which I must yeeld vnto, Nor will I striue what you conceale to know. My buisnes bids me hast; I had not stay'd So long, but that I thought intelligence Would haue come from you which might haue regayn'd The losse of time I spent in this cunctation. [Exit Embassador. Enter Pasquino to Glausamond. Pasq. His Maiestie hath inioyned me to tell you, Your absence may not rob him of your service, For presently him selfe and all his councell Are to consult about affayres of state. Glaus. I'le hasten my attendance. [Exit Glausamond. Pasq. I now must looke the chaire be set in order, The table couered, and pen and inke vpon it, And all thinges els, whereby the roome may be Fitt for the thing in hand. Enter Gabriello. Gab. Neuer better mett; if I liue, I'le hau't out on you. Pasq. Forbare, I beseche you. Doe you know Who you speake to? Gab. Dost thou think 'tis square To drinke halfe and pay nothing? Pasq. I'le pay thee now. [Offers to strike him. Gab. I would you durst. Hang me, an't serue your turne, la! Pasq. Why, what came the wine to? Gab. Eight shillinges. Pasq. And how much didst thou pay? Gab. A noble, and promis'd the rest. Pasq. Then there's but sixteenpence To pay. Here 'tis. Gab. I'le haue four shillinges or bring An action o'th'case against you. Pasq. Rather then doe soe, I'le giue thee Security for thy money. Gab. Marry, with all my hart. I haue a blanke band, And 'tis but filling vp the place with thy name And the other place withe summe and vse-money, And it will fitt. Pasq. But dost thou say there must be vse-money? Gab. Some euer, for he that in these dayes Lendes or layes out money and takes no vse For it, forfetes the principall ipso facto. Pasq. This is soe among vsurers. Gab. Well, and why may not another man damne His soule for a shilling as well as one of Them doth daly for a groate? I know one Of them tooke brocage for lending a siluer Spoone of his owne to one of his neighbors To go to my Lord Maior's feast with. Such men as keepe the diuell's shop by the Great church will do these thinges often. Her's pen and inke all ready. [Fitts the blanke in ye band. Pasq. But brought for another purpose, for the King comaunded, each man's advise, as he Did pronounce it, herewith should be recorded. Gab. Come, 'tis well now. Pasq. Read it. Gab. Nouerint vniuersi per etc. Pasq. The condicion? Gab. The condicion is, that if you pay to Gabriello foure shillinges vpon the day apoynted, That then this bond of eight shillinges is voyd. Pasq. How? Eight? Gab. The bond is alwayse duble the debt. Pasq. Why soe? Gab. For feare the bond should be forfeited. Pasq. Why, what if it be? Gab. Then you are to pay the whole. Pasq. Two wordes to a bargayne; yet no[w] I think on 't, I will enter into this bond, soe that thou Wilt giue me the other foure shillinges In hand, and then thou hast this advantage, That it is all due, and thou mayst sue For it all at once. Gab. This is a tricke, indeed! Pasq. 'Tis so, but yet I learn'd it lately of the Old gentleman that bought muscadine of The fatt hostes. You know both parties. But, prithee, let it stay till we haue More lesure and lesse busines. Enter Tancred, Glausamond and Guiscardo to them. Tanc. You two, Glausamond and Guiscardo, are Acquainted with the buisines now in hand, For the embassador did particularize Each poynt, when you weare by. But Gabriello And Pasquino were not at the heareing, As I remember. Both No, an't like your Grace. Tanc. Yet you haue heard in generall the Effect of what he cam for. Gab. Yes, your Grace did open it the other night. Pasq. When you weare in the parke, and we attended you. Tanc. Right. My mynd since then hath thought of many doubtes, And you, the advisers of my comonweale, Are fitt to take them of, or make them greater. Therefore I inioyn each man, in order, What Heauen hath bid him say, discreetly vtter. Begin, Guiscardo, I apoynt it soe. Guisc. Since you are pleas'd, great King, thus far to make Me partner of your secrete, suffer me, sir, To vtter my advise, which yet, I know, Your wisdome needes not; and though it may seeme Boldnes not to be pardoned that my weakenes Doth goe about t'instruct your vndertakinges, Yet, much obliged to you and the Princes, In loyalty to you, in zeale to her, I shall presume, if you will giue me leaue, To speake my weake conceite. Tanc. With as free leaue I doe permitt the speach as euer kinge Did to his councell eare or patienc lend. Speake out. I heare thee gladly, good Guiscardo. Guisc. Lett not the rough expression of my mynd Blemish the duty my allegeance owes you, Nor let my tongue that stammers as it moues, Weaken the strength of zeale my hart owes her; Duty and zeale, zeale and duty both Makes a tongue speake which, till it had leaue, was loth And fearefull to presse on your greatnes thus. Me thinkes, if it might like your Maiesty, You might receaue more comfort in a son, Whose country's boundes do border vpon yours, Or, if there be none such whose pedegree In greatnes can match yours, nor whose worth In all poynts parralell your daughter's state, 'Twere not amisse in my conceit, if you And my admired Princes so thinke fitt, T'elect one of the noblest of these peeres Your owne realme can afford, so you may haue A subiect, frend, a servant and a son, All in a man, and the most honoured Princes i'th'world, your most indeared daughter Inioy a husband, whose obseruanc may Be all his life as on his wedding-day. Tanc. Indeed, I must confes, and ioy to doe soe, This kingdome is not so curst with sterility But it hath blest it selfe with propagation Of men of worth. Yet I must say agayne, Noe starr shines bright, when that the sun is by, Nor is he noble, whose nobility Is my power's subiect, in respect of her, For she's there Queen, yea, there sole gouernes, My leaue alowing. No, there must be state And princly blood in him that is her mate. Guisc. You need not care for that. In her sweet veines Streames royall blood enough to make him great Shalbe your son-in-law, and howsoeuer Your Maiesty doth think it may disparage Such a great lady as the Princes is To cast a fauoring looke from her quick eies By way of loue on any man within The compas of your larg dominion's limmites, Yet you perhaps more true content may take In a man, whome your fauours doe make great, Then in a prince, whose too sublimed mynd May happly make him swell so high that he Will scorne his wife, you, and your dignity. Moreouer, he will rob you of your ioy, Take your best comfort from you and transport Her into kingdomes you perhaps ne're heard of; Yea, peraduenture into foggy clymates, Whose poysonous vapors, health-forbiding mistes, May be iniurious to her constitution; And who can tell, when she's so far from you, Whether the eies of all your subiectes which Doe looke on her as Indians on the sun, Shall e're be blest with seeing her agayne? Weigh your owne good and there's, and you shall finde A word is weighty from a troubled mynd. Tanc. We shall hereafter therefore more imploy you In any thing that shall concerne vs much, For he that's troubled, for feare ye kingdome should Run into inconuenience, truely deserues Of his King and the state good estimation, Though honest men be now cleane out of fashion. You next, Gabriello. Doe you set downe, Pasquino, Breefe notes, that we may scan them ouer after. Pasq. As you inioyn'd, I doe. Tanc. Speake, Gabriello. Gab. For my part, truely, I am fully resolu'd To say as you say, and so I shall not err, For in your chaire of state, you'r more infallible Then any pope that e're was called holy. Tanc. Now thou shewest thy selfe a complet courtier, Because thou canst disemble, se how ye cry goes, And where the side is heaviest, say “omne bene”. Thus thou'lt apeare perfect in thy profession; Yet thou dost not hereby proue that honesty Must necessaryly competere huic gradui. Goe on, Pasquino and Glausamond. Pasq. Both at once? Glaus. No, no. You'r puny and therefore to speake first. Pasq. Puny, how? Glaus. Not so old in court. Pasq. What then? Glaus. What then, why, thus then. If thou Knowest not what to say, say “as my Learned brethren sayd before and the rest Thinke fit”, and it shalbe recorded—Pasquino, accord. Tanc. And what can your graue head say, Glausamond? Glaus. Who? I, sir? Euen as my brother-courtiers Sayd before. The oath that my foremann hath Taken for his gaine and behoofe I will well And truely obserue for my gayne and Behoofe, as art guided me to the subiect I worke vpon. Tanc. This is impertenent. Glaus. It may be, 'tis now, sir, but it hath sometimes Beene very much to the matter. Tanc. What answer's fitt, or rather, what advise, From whence we may deduce an answere To the kind, noble message the Duke of Capua Did send vs lately by his embassador About the treaty of a marriage Between my daughter and the Prince, his neighbor? Glaus. Doth the Princes like the motion? Tanc. She nether doth nor doth not, but I gather That saying nothing, she doth not gaynsay. Guisc. Your leaue being giuen so freely at the first, And an iniunction made by your command Each man should speake what Heauen put in his mynd, I think I shall make no great aberration, If I repeate what the best saint below it, The Princes, sayd, after you were goone. Tanc. When? And to whome? Guisc. To the embassador, when you left him. Glausamond heard it to, or els his mynd Was of another matter and worse imploy'd. Tanc. Doe you remember her wordes? Glaus. Some of them, for when your Maiestie Left vs together, the Princes did intreate The embassador to deliuer to the Duke, His master, her duty and thankes that he Would thinke of one so full of mysery. Tanc. This was rather an acceptation of the Offer then a deniall of the motion. Guisc. Thus far it was. But something els did follow. Tanc. What els? Guisc. Good memories carry most away; He can tell you. Tanc. The rest, Glausamond. Come, all concealmentes Are begg'd already and as much gotten by Them as may be; therefore, out with the treuth! That proues best in the end. Glaus. As I am a virgin, sir, I remember nothing Els. It may be, she seight or stopt twice, Before she came to the end of the period. Guisc. Sight or stopt! Sometimes your memorie's better. Euery three wordes a sigh was comma to, And for a colon alwaise she gaue two; But when she cam to make an end o'th'period, A single, solemn teare dropt downe alone Like a periodus and so full-poynted it. Tanc. It seemes then, she spake only by signes, Seighes and teares, but sayd nothing, or very little. Guisc. Yet she sayd thus: “Let my duty to my father Be offered vp, for he hath much ingag'd me; Yet tell him, I am resolued to liue fre And hope he will not tak't discurtiously”. Tanc. Resolued to liue free? Glaus. Indeed, I doe remember, she sayd soe, But what freedom she meant, I doe not know. Tanc. I'le leaue her to explayne her selfe. I cal'd you all together, because I would not in temerity Goe on my selfe without your best advise, Nor did I meane fully to conclude Of any thing without your free assent. But now I se, I must do't, or leaue't vndone, My selfe, for all of you, except Guiscardo, Smother your thoughtes. I know not what you meane by't, But none of you but he will speake freely. Heere is a letter which I pen'd my selfe Vnto the Duke, my brother, and it imports Thus much—that if it please the Prince to come, His welcome shalbe what my power can giue him. Glaus. This is an inuitation which will make A mettled lad not thinke a iorney tedious. Tanc. Thus, Guiscardo, all the wordes I heard you speak About this buisnes yet haue bene so weighty That they were ponder'd well, before you spake them, And so deserue the more to be esteem'd By me, who thinke it very necessary, Since you'r soe worthy to be trusted with The secretes of the state, to haue you carry This letter. Without any opposition, It must be you. What thinke you? Though you will not Shew your selues other then concealed statesmen, Yet your closse breasts may suffer you to say 'Tis well or ill. Glaus. You haue dispatcht as fitt a messenger As if great Joue had sent swift Mercury. Gab. I thinke so too. Pasq. Yes, without doubt. Guisc. I beseech you, choose another. I am Far vnfit to be an embassador. Tanc. You wrong your selfe and me to contradict it. I did make choice of you, onely because, Being about so great a buisines, I thought I could not choose a fitter man T'imploy then you. Kinges that desire to be Happy in what they vndertake, must striue To send such as you are, of embassies. The hapines and wellfare of a state Is propagated much, when trusty men Doe most comaund and mannag busines, And he that desires to doe his King best seruice, Is fittest to be sent of royall errandes. The premises your selfe hath prou'd vnto me, And I can henc deduce a good conclution. The loftiest ship I haue, is fully rigg'd And furnished with expert mariners; Both it and they shalbe thy seruitors, And when I know that thou art safe-return'd, The peeces in that ship shall ring a peale To honour thee and please the commonweale. Goe, and the fates that doe protect good men, Keep thee still safe and bring the backe againe. [Exeunt omnes: manet Guiscardo. Guisc. I had as lieue bene sent to Cerberus, To bid him ope the gates of Hell, that I Might fetch Proserpina out of Pluto's lapp; And 'tis as possible for me to doe as that, For I haue such a powerfull negatiue, Though not in playne wordes, yet infer'd vnto me, That though the charge be greate, yet I receau'd One farr aboue it from the gracious Princes. For whether by some sacred reuelation Or how I know not, she could tell me this, Before I had the least suspicion of it; For the other night, when I cam to attend Her Excellency in the presence chamber, Beck'ning, she called me to her and sayd: “Guiscardo, Doth thy hart stand to goe this taedious iorney”? Then, bowing my knees and hart to her at once, “I heare of none, deare Princes”, I repli'd. Then answered she: “I wish thou neuer maist, But if thou dost, I shall be very sory, The seruice that thou so oft hast shew'd Both to the King and me, shalbe rewarded With a longe, tedious iorney—little better, If I may terme it soe, then a sad exile. Were I the King, I'd send some men yt weare Good for no other purpose, whose gray heades By there graue councell know how to ordayne What may be done in all occurences. Such tough old lades can better far indure The boisterous tempestes on the troubled seas Then thy soft limmes, fitter for other vses. Yet, if thou goest, I wish some busnes may Cause thy returne, ere thou hast gone half-way.” Then she apoynted me, whensoeuer the King Apoynted me to goe, that I should stay One quick-pas'd hower, to take my leaue of her; And though I be not superstitious, Yet such wordes, me thought, were ominous, And I'le be pul'd in peces, 'fore I'le violate A word of her decree. She spake with such a smile And yet a solemn looke as might become Virtue herselfe, if she liu'd on earth. Well-temper'd greatnes and alacrity, Mixt both together, made the lookers-on Sware she was free from any passion. But I, the man whose earnest, burning hart Sought satisfaction what her meaneing was, Contayn'd my selfe as much as flesh could doe. I will put of my iorney for a while By feigned sicknes or some other guile, And by all meanes I can, I'le seke the loue Of my deare Princes which I prize aboue The fauor of the King. If she say “stay”, I will not goe, although the King next day Desteine my execution. Her wordes shall Make me a fre man or for euer thrall. [Ex. Finit Actus Tertius.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACTUS QUARTUS Enter Guiscardo, Ghismonda and her waiting-woman. Ghism. Doe you thinke it is expiable? Guisc. No question. Ghism. And they that doe soe, not subiect To payne of Purgatory? Wait. Venture that clog! On my soule, Waiting-women's trade were worth nothing, If they might not say: “By my maidenhead, 'tis Thus”, or “vpon my modesty, 'tis so”, and yet for All this, often breake what they say. Ghism. An oth's past saying. Wait. 'Tis as that was of worth you swore by. Ghism. I swore by Saint Charyty. Wait. Oh, happy you! She loues and likes and neuer is displeas'd With any but those that liue single or Lie alone, and yet those that doe so, if they Repent in time, she forgiues And calls her conuertes. Ghism. I did not binde my selfe so desperately As sware without some power of reuocation. Yet I resolu'd thus—till I found another As good in my conceipt as was the first I lost, I would be bound to liue a widow. Wait. 'Twas pretyly well-limited, indeed! Yet a leetle too strict, Madam. I doe thus— One comes to-day and giues me a ring; Supose it fitt this ioynt, or this, or any; Straight comes another and bringes a siluer thimble; Next day a bodkin's brought, of a good size And length, and he euer that hath a good bodkin, Pusheth out both the other for the time. Then the two first wilbe ready to hang themselues; Yet thinking first requestes are not alwaise granted, They'l come agayne, furnished with new trinketes, And by this time the bodkin wilbe bended, And when it is so and out of fashion, what Should one doe with it but throw it away Or sell it to them that cry endes of gold or siluer? But I besech your good Grace, what meane You by one as good as he you lost? Ghism. As worthy and as well-deserueing. Guisc. Deserueing your selfe? Ghism. I mean't so. Guisc. He that you will make so, is so, Madam. Ghism. Can you proue that without logick? I am Scholer enough to ask the question. Guisc. I can demonstrate it to you easily. Ghism. I pray, doe soe. Guisc. Your Grace's husband died, and then you vowed; Yet with so well-considered a restrainte You vowed, because you would haue power to breake it, Or els confin'd your selfe within a cage, The dores of which were made to shut and open At your dispose, for with a letter-locke They were so fastned that till you spake ye word, The skilful'st picklock knew not how to open't; But lock and key and all are at your will, To knock in peeces, or to be of vse. Or, if you'l haue a smoth-skin'd simile, Your vow doth bind you but as your gloue Stickes closse vnto [your hand], only to keep it warme, Or els to saue it from sun-scorching heate, Which, when you please, the other hand can plucke of. Ghism. Guiscardo, thou shalt be my confessor. Yet I will choose the time and place of shrifte, Because wordes spoken canot be recall'd, And being once vented in the open aire, Doe presently become so deffusiue That they that spake them, are not masters of them. Say, Guiscardo, will you beleeue an old Prophecie hereafter that sayd, a proper Man in court canot doe as he would, Because a greater then he hath apoynted Him a iorney which he must ether Vndertake or suffer for? Guisc. Yes, Madam, it is too infallible. Ghism. I would say something to you, but I feare My tongue is not so quick as one man's eare Which I suspect. Therefore, I'le leaue you now. But stir not, till I come agayne. I know A subtill way how thou shalt vnderstand My mynd, yet others at a gaze shall stand And wonder how't could be. So you stay Till I returne, 't may proue a happy day. [Exit Ghismonda, and waytinge-woman. Guisc. Deare Princes, you haue plac'd me in a station, Where I'le remayne more fixt and vnremou'd Then if the sterne, death-threatening god of war Had bid me lie perdue before his armye. Enter Pasquino. Pasq. The King comanded me, I should with speed Goe to the hauen, where your ship doth ride That is bound for your viage, and if I found you not, I should forthwith repare vnto your lodging, There to make knowne his royall plesure to you, Which is this. He thinkes you are too slow And sluggish in performing his edict. Enter Ghismonda and waiting-woman, with a cane in her hand. Guisc. I shalbe slower then he imagins, too. Ghism. What, Guiscardo, I thought by this time you Had bene ten leagues from land! your nimble ship, They say, sayles faster then any boat i'th'harbour. Guisc. I, Madam, when she hath lading To goe in her. Ghism. Trust me, she's richly fraught, when you are in her. Guisc. I would you thought so, Madam. I'd stay at home. Ghism. Dost thou feare drowning, man? Guisc. No, Madam, but yet I shalbe sea-sicke. Ghism. Alas, weake stomake! I pitty thy disease. Take this rod in thy hand [Giues him the cane and walke to th'riuer That runs by the hill, whereon the castle standes, And if this choice-made bait do catch a fish, Send it to me; it shalbe my prime dish. The reason why I bid thee doe thus much Is but to haue thee try how thou canst beare The vapours of the water; and no question, If thou canst but go thither with this rod, Fish there an houre or two, and then returne, And not be mou'd at all, thou'rt strong enough To goe to sea. Farewell, if that there be Any fish like thy selfe caught, bring it me. [Exit Ghismonda, and waiting-woman. Guisc. 'Tis short and pithy. Would I might haue such a pilot To steere the ship that I desire to sayle in. Pasq. You doe not tell me what answere I shall returne the King. Guisc. You se I had other buisines. Such a voice Comandes from me a far more strict attendanc Then thy hoarse vlulating. But, in short, Beare back this answere and informe the King, I doe desire him giue me leaue to stay Vntill the spring grow on and longer dayes Afford more time for me to doe his buisines, For yet I cannot goe. Pasq. Is this all? Guisc. Yes. Pasq. 'Tis a slight answere to returne the Kinge. Guisc. And thou as slight as it. If thou wilt deliuer't, Do; if not, choose—say nothing, if thou wilt. Pasq. You stand too much vpon your will, Guiscardo. [Exit Pasquino. Guisc. You shall not teach me how to stand or remoue. I haue direction from one that cannot err, For what I doe, although my guilty duty Sayth, I haue done ill to send ye King such word. Who would haue thought a foole with his totoligies Could haue detain'd me from a meditation Which I so inly long for? Vnmatched Queene, Whose vertue and whose prizeles eminence, Weare my weake tongue but able to expresse, Would playnly seeme to go as far beyond All other women's in extreamity Of true perfection as e're Diana did Exceed the chastnes of a common whore; Were all the female powers plac'd in order, And all the admiring seruantes that desire To haue there heauen on earth with looking on them In that pompe which the seruantes wish to bee, The mistres in that scorne which they doe vse, And my saynt stood i'th'midle and I by, My hart full of a deuout sacrifice, Ready to be hers, when her acceptation Should giue it grace, Venus would be her selfe, And pure sinceritie take away her crowne By merit, not by stealth or vsurpation (Distrust of right doth so), and then this goddes, Wanting a shape on earth to represent her Except the Princes, would earnestly intreate The Princes would voutshafe to be her seate. Yet I, the ground the foote o'th'chaire should stand on, Thinke the day makes the glorious stars pink-ey'd, A vestall flame obscures a dieing sparke, Thinke then agayne Ghismonda doth exceed The starrs that light the court, as these doe these. Could but thy worth admitt comparisons And not be therewith darkned! Darkned? How? Can a dimme vapour blinde the light o'th'sun, Or can an earthly simile disparage That forme that's all celestiall? Henc, black Disgrace, I kick thee and thy spight; if thou attempt To wrong my Princes, her indeared name Spurnes at salt enuy, and bides it for shame Go excercise it selfe vpon a subiect That may be like it selfe, for these together Will best agree, like birdes all of a feather. O thou, the wounder of my fainting heart, I flie to the for succor, and if there bee A peece of that sword left that wounded me, Send it me of a token. If it be sharp, There is no doubt but it will lance the sore And make corruption vanish, or by the touch Cure like Achilles' sword. Surely, in this I may find something that may giue me ease; It needes must ease me, since it was her guift. He pulleth a peece out of the cane. This peece is like her selfe, straight and vpright. Pardon, dread Princes, that my presumption did Compare thy person to a brittle cane. I'le doe thee right hereafter, noble dame, But in the meanetime I hope Heuen and you Will make my faultes, like thinges far of, seeme little. What's this, that's ti'd so fast with blue and siluer? He finds a letter. On my life, 'tis constancy and inocence. I'le open it; 'twas not put here for nothing. He opens and reades the letter thus: “My deare Guiscardo, since opportunity I could by no means get, wherby I might Disclose the affection which my hart bares you Without aduentureing that inconuenience Which I haue often giuen you warning of, I thought good to send this dumb messenger T'intreate your person this night in my chamber, And onely do intreat—loue ne'ere commanded, Except it were by sweet and mild perswasions. The passage which I thinke the most conuenient Is through the ventloope, directly vnderneath The window of my chamber which is oppos'd Just to the morning sun; yet there are some Briers layd o're the loope-hole t'auoyd suspicion Which, though they scratch a little, wil not hurt thee. This is the way, whereby I promised That thou shouldst know my mynd, yet none perceaue Besides thy selfe. Come, and, take my woord, Thou shalt confesse thy labor is not lost. And though thine owne eies did se me deliuer This to thy selfe, yet, least that any scruple Might haply arise by misconstruction, I haue subscrib'd my name with myne owne hand, Which is a fauor, if't be truely scand; And this I did, because I know that thou Art noble and esteem'st a ladie's vow. Be confident. I wilbe euer thine, So thou wilt promise to be solely myne. Wittnes thy Princes and thy loue, Ghismonda.” I come, deare lady, with a swifter course Then ships do sayle, blowne with a prosperous winde. He's dull that stayes, when such an angell calls And doth inuite him with so faire a summons. Lett me be cal'd Pigritia's son and heire, If I be slow in following this affaire! [Exit Guiscardo. Interim enter Pasquino at an other dore. Pasq. Well, noe more to the Kinge? Enter Tancred, Glausamond and Gabriello. But now gone out, an't please your Maiesty. Tanc. I wonder at it; his care vsed to be greater. Glaus. Times and seasons alter much, Wind and weather alter much, Loue and likeing alter much, Men and women alter much, And one word from one doth as much As two from the other. Tanc. What then? Glaus. What you please, but I can assure you, I haue found it soe. Tanc. What answere did Guiscard giue the, Pasquino? Pasq. Vpon my reputation, a very peremptory one! He tould me, he did desire your Maiesty Would giue him leaue to stay, vntill the Spring grew on and longer dayes Afford more time for him to doe your Busines, for yet he could not goe. Tanc. Could not goe? He knew all doubtes weare cast beforhand and What I did, a studied consideracion Did giue me warrant for. I like not this. He that is wise, will feare to doe amisse, And till now I thought Guiscardo so, But his neclect hath altered my opinion. Gab. I heard he went to take his leaue o'th'Princes And know her pleasure into Capua. Glaus. This was done with a reuerend respect. Tanc. Who told you so, Gabriello? Gab. Her waiting-woman. Tanc. Goe call her hither! [Exit Gabriello. It may be she mistooke. Glaus. No, 'tis a plaugy ape; she knowes all the Trickes of the chamber, inlettes, outlettes, And the double keis, better then an Older body, for when your Maiesty sent me To sing to the Princes, this youth was the Porter and cried “Who's there”? as shrilly and Cherpingly as the hen-sparrow Cries “Yet, yet, yet, yet”. Tanc. Thou didst not tell me how yt song wrought. Glaus. Rough and smooth for the time, but shee'l Relaps agayne, if she haue not A good phisitiann. Enter Gabriello and wayting-woman. Tanc. Now, Mistris Minks, how doth your lady? Wait. An't please your Grace, she lookes but pale And seemes but somwhat dumpish. Tanc. What company hath bene with her of late? Wait. None that I know of but Guiscardo, Who came to take his leaue and know her Pleasure, before he went his iorney. Tanc. Leaue vs, but tell your lady, my selfe Will shortly come to visit her; i'th'meane Time lett her send for my owne phisitian, And I'le giue order to him to make that Confection which is so soueraigne Aganist melancholie. [Exit waiting-woman. Glaus. Your Maiestie is far out, for phisicke will not Worke vpon those diseases young ladies Are trobled with, except they choose Theire owne phisitian. Tanc. This that tormentes her is noe naturall Disease, but onely greife, and that Troubles her intollerably. Glaus. Alas! we se that women of her age, Especially great ladies, do oft times greeue, Yet will not shew the causes of there woe, Except in priuat and but to one at once. Women's diseases still are better cured, When they haue but one surgeon, then if Many phisitians should administer. Those maladies which breed, when none are by, Ought to haue medcines layd to priuately. Gab. Doth not your Maiesty remember, the little Gentlewoman sayd, the Princes lookt pale. Tanc. Yes, and she must needes doe soe, for Shee hath scarce eaten, slept or done Any thing but greeue, euer since She lost her husband. Gab. Doe you think that's the reason? What Will you say, if I can giue you a better? Tanc. I'le applaud thee and count thee Wiser then my selfe. Glaus. Nay, I'le sweare, he's more learned And knowes a woman's constitution Better then the little doctor that Came from Padua to be A man-midwife. Tanc. Speake, Gabriello, and if thine vnderstanding Be more descerning then thy iudgment is, And if thy witt can any way informe Me of the secret which as yet lies hid, Vnfould it, and I will so recompence This open-harted explication That thou herafter shalt haue poure to aske What thy selfe pleaseth and haue it granted frely. Gab. Why then, if your Maiesty will needes haue it, I'le answere you with a question—“and that's Much for a foole to doe”, you'l say—I beseech You, is Guiscardo about the court? Tanc. It may be he is, though I am sure he Should not be. But what's this To the thing in hand? Gab. Nay, nothing. But if he be, I wish you Weare as young as he is, and he were As old as you are, and that you had a Wife as succulent as the Princes, Then you might get boyes as big as I am, And that the Princes had a husband, and That Guiscardo, if that he weare as old As you are, were married to Mr s Tattle, The midwife; then, according to the old Proverbe, he would be fitted with age And wedlock. And if theese Would doe noe good of him, you Should be sure that the next greate Frost he would be tamed, for age, Winter and wedlock, especially all Put together, tame man and beast. Tanc. If thy morall be as good as the fable, Esop's an asse to thee. Come, The meaning of thy riddle. Gab. Your Maiesty must pardone me. Satyristes Neuer make comentaries of there Owne workes. I know Glausamond can Gesse at any thing very vnhappily. Pray, put him to it. Tanc. Come, Glausamond, interpret. Glaus. None so fit as the oracle that standes by you, And I know he would send the length Of his weapon to any man that durst But say, he tould you he knew not what. Gab. You doe not say I did? Glaus. Oh, sir, not for a kingdome! My vayne lies another way. Tanc. Then without more concealing what you know Or mincing of the truth, you must deliuer; Playnly expresse what your meaning was, When you did speak of Guiscardo and the Princes, All in a line, as 'tweare. Gab. Why, nothing, I, But that I sayd, Guiscardo did want a wife And she a husband, and that, if you were young And had a young wife, and he old and had an Old wife, and the Princes married to a young Husband, you might get boyes, the Princes, If she would, might be pleas'd, and Guiscardo So toughly provided, the ladies of the court Might goe in quiett by him. Tanc. I neuer heard him tax'd with such a fault. Gab. You may doe. Tanc. Nor doe I thinke him guilty of that crime. His mayden-lookes cannot seeme innocent, His hart being foule within. Glaus. O, your Maiesty is deceau'd in that; smooth lookes Make the roughest woorke, if the come to't With an appetite and haue bene Kept long fasting. Tanc. Gabriello, what's the cause you doe suspect him? Gab. Will you know in breefe or at large? In publique or priuate? Tanc. The court should be a sanctuary to the King, And his seruantes' ears theire soueraigne's cabinet T'inclose his secretes in, vntill he please To haue them brought to light and obiected Vnto the worldes wide view and open censure. Therefore, with a well-established conceite That what you speake shall not by repetition Of theese your felloues further be dilated Then may conduce to our conueniencie; I bid you speake, and what you speake, speake freely. Gab. Then, as I loue you, thus it was, my leige. The other night, as Guiscardo went by Through the presenc and did his honour make To our fayre Princes, she ask'd him if he were Willing to goe this iorney. He repli'd: “Yes, Madam, if it please you and the King”. “Alas”, sayd she, “'tis pitty only thou Shouldst be pick'd out to vndergoe the paines And hazard which a traveller endures. Thy daynty limbes should rather be imploy'd In seeking of thy selfe a beautious brid; Yet if thou goe, I wish some busines may Cause thy returne, ere thou hast gone half-way”. These were her wordes, as I doe honour you. Tanc. Directly these? Gab. Just these. I think I doe not misse an accent. Glaus. I'd be sory to make my body guilty, When thou stood'st by! [Exit. Tanc. These wordes giue great cause of suspition, Yet proue nothing directly; care must be had To mark his footsteps strictly, and discretion Vs'd, to find out whether my daughter be Ingag'd so much as in conceit. Ther's remedy For one, but not the other. If he assaye To stepp aboue him selfe, one dismall day Will cut his proud hopes of; if her high spirit That calls me daughter, make her forgoe her merit, And vnderrate her selfe, we are ouerthrowne, And all our kingdom's hope extinct and gone. If Heauen for my offences haue contriu'd This way t'afflict me, Guiscardo is short-liu'd And I vnhappy. If sterne destinie So highly be displeas'd, let's goe and see What may be done in this extreamyty. [Ex. omnes. Finit Actus Quartus.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACTUS QUINTUS Enter Pasquino, Gabriello and Glausamond. Pasq. I tell the, I'le giue thee Very honorable satisfaction. Gab. I prethe now, I haue great occation for it. Glaus. Come, vntrusse; I know by my selfe, Courtiers had neuer more need of mony, Nor lesse conscience how they cam by it. Yet honorable satisfaction is noble satisfaction. Gab. I, but I haue bene so often cheated by it Already that I am resolued, I will trust it no more. Glaus. Will and resolucion be two braue Thinges in man, if they be well-grounded. Pasq. I'le refer my selfe to him. Gab. To Glausamond? Glaus. Mum, you may; I warrant you, I will not meddle. Pasq. Prithe, be vmpire. Glaus. I? away, away! Gab. If Glausamond will make a conscionable End, that I shall haue what I layd out, I'le put it to him. Pasq. Let's stand to his gentlenes, howsoeuer. Gab. I care not greatly. Glaus. My constitution is not giuen to be Judiciall. But, vpon both your intreaties, I shall strayne to doe much. Both Pray, make an end betweene vs. Glaus. Doe you agree to stand to my order? Both Very willingly. Glaus. Then thus. He that by lusty wordes and Great bragges would haue shew'd him selfe To haue bene the brauer fellow and after- ward did flintch and break company, Which, I take, was Pasquino— Gab. Most discerningly conceiued! Glaus. Shall pay the whole eight shillinges, viz., Foure for his owne part and Foure for Gabriello's. Gab. O, most iudicially decree'd! Pasq. O, most vnconscionably! Glaus. Say I doe vniustly, if I doe not render You both a very satisfieing reason. 'Tis fitt that Pasquino should pay the Whole—one halfe for being vnsociable And the other for Gabriello's patience. But your last censure is to come yet. Pasq. Lett it come, when it will come. I'le Neuer stay to heare it. [Offers to be gone. Gab. Nay, hang me, an you goe! Glaus. Come, come. Hearken to the verdict, As the court recordes it. Pasquino for his offence must giue to Gabriello for his patience the money Before named, or it shalbe at Pasquino's Choice, whether he will doe soe or finde Gabriello with muscadine after braune, And sack and clarret after egges and old Conies (which is the meate, you know, he Hath protest to loue so well, and the Better he likes the meate, The lesse drinke will serue him) From this day to this day— Gab. This day twelue mounth! Glaus. O, no! till this day senighte. The cap of iustice must be set on Equally, iust with the corner before, Bending or inclineing to nether side, And hereby shew the wearer of it to be Impartiall. Therefore, from this day To this day senight is a fitt time. And so shall you goe from the place where You are, to the place from whence you Came, when this quarrell was first begun, And soe let drinke settle what drinke Did first provoke. Pasq. A iudge? A hangman! I'le neuer stand to this end. Glaus. This or none. 'Tis a direct contempt of The court, and you incurr the danger of Commitment, an you doe not. Gab. Nay, you are gone in the courtes aboue. Now an you can but bring it downe Into the country and get a pac't iury There, much may bee. Glaus. Ne Hercules contra duos, nec peccans contra Judicem. Patience in extreamity bringes a man to the Three Cranes in the Vintree. Enter waiting-woman, chafinge. Goe thither, and I warrant you, no more controuersy. [Exit Gabriello, and Pasquino. I must needes speake with this gentlewoman That comes so i'th'nicke. Wait. Theese bodkins and siluer thimbles are vnlucky. I thought I had had, for euery day in the Weeke, one, and by being a little too coy, I haue driuen them all away and am Not now so fortunate as a country Wench that hath her sweetheart come To her on Sondayes in the afternoones. Glaus. Shall I salue your sore? I'le doe your worke as well as any. Wait. Cannot one greeue a little in private, But you must come ruffling in thus? Glaus. I thought you had loued ruffleing. But if you doe not, I'le handle you As tenderly as an egg, gingerly, gingerly. Wait. I pray, lett me alone and be gone. Vpon My modesty, my lady wilbe heere presently. Glaus. Nay, if the wind be in that dore, I am gone! I loue company at all sportes but this, But I would haue none by at this But my selfe and one more. [Exit Glausamond. Wait. I am fortunately ridd of him. Trust me, he's very vnhappy. Enter Tancred. Tanc. Good time o'th'euen, minion, Good time o'th'euen. Is your lady within? Wait. An your Maiesty please, I'le call her. Tanc. Where is she? Wait. In the garden, at her priuate meditation. Tanc. What company? Wait. None but her owne thoughtes, and they are holy. Tanc. I doe not question whether they be or no. Therefore, thy reply is vnnecessary in the Last part. Tell her, I came to se her, But will not depriue her of so sweete An euening as this is. You'l tell her, my good gerle? Wait. I'm going, an't please your Maiesty. [Exitura. Your Grace will not stay, till I come agayne? Tanc. O, no. 'Tis now too late. [Exit waiting-woman. Is she gone? Then This may perhaps be a good stale, especially If the wench be, as most chamber-maydes are Commonly, the prologue to the play, for if They that come by way of sutors, doe not First take say of theese, 'tis ten to one But they shall goe without a bit of venison. Pauseth a while. All time, as 'tis time in respect of howers Or dayes, we se alike; onely the weather Or season alters, as moueing accedentes Or happ'ning mutations make it change. Nor doth one day deserue denomination More then annother, as it is a day Composed of succession of instantes Or articles of time. But we that are The masters of this time, by Heauen's permission, Doe giue an epithite to this or that, Call this day sacred or the other curst, As the thing pleaseth which we se done in it. Grant now, you curtious fates, yt giue vs cause T'exclame of time or blesse its gliding minnits, That what I heard in parte and wholly feare, This night may proue the voyce of fame, not treuth. No time's more fit then this for me to know Whether I shalbe fortunate or no. Sit downe and rest, you aged limbs, and if Sits downe, as hideing him selfe. My feigned absence make this place be thought More sure then yet it is, I shall perceaue Whate're the night is guilty of; and if So great an oportunity as this Be slighted with neglect, I will conclude Ghismonda's holy still and mark this night With such an orient-rosie-colour'd letter, It shall surpas all in the calender. In hope of good successe I'le take my ease; Feares may be turn'd to ioyes, if Heauen please. Dormit. Enter Ghismonda and waiting-woman. Ghism. The nights seeme long, the howers sloely goe, To one that is opressed with grefe and woe; And such a one I thought my selfe to be, Vntill I was reuiu'd, thinking on thee. Stops. The nightes seeme short, ye howers go on apace, To one that rarely sees his mistris' face; Therefore, me thinkes, thou shouldst make hast to se Thy Princes which so highly vallues thee, And like a gemm esteeme that part of time, Wherin thou maist to such aduancment clime As haue thy Queene thy consort; thou dost not know Whether thou e're shalt do't agayne or no. One knockes. Se who's there. That is a hopefull knock. Enter Guiscardo. Wait. Euen the man that expectation cal'd for. Ghism. What, Guiscardo? Is not that a thorny way? Guisc. Deare Madam, it did scratch a little, but The blod I lost, was spent as martirs' liues And poured out, because they should be canoniz'd. Ghism. Thou seldom mak'st comparisons, but when thou dost Make such as these, thou think'st them pertenent. You may go se what a clock 'tis now. Wait. May I not play one game at laugh And lie downe, before I come agayne? Ghism. Yes, two or three. Wait. I humbly thanke your Excellency. [Exit waiting-woman. Ghism. Now priuacy hath giu'n vs leaue to know As much as may be, keping our honour safe, My hart explaynes it selfe thus far to thee, That neuer seruant with a more pleasing comfort Beheld his mistris then my loueing eies Doe now looke on thy best-beloued face. Thus nam'd and thought, thou'rt welcome. If epithite There be that more can please thee, speak't but to me; I'le not be daynty to bestow't on thee. Thou'rt welcome to this place, my deare Guiscardo. Guiscardo kneeles and kisseth her hand. Nay, goe a little higher, if you like. Guisc. It is a most presumptuous crime to be More bold then with royall maiesty. Ghism. 'Tis fit to be bold, when the Princes bids. A lady once desir'd to kisse her loue And told him so, whereat the man shrunk back. Guisc. Pardon me, Madam, if I be so bold As to come forward, and, by your permission, Doe that which he, it seem'd, did leaue vndoone. He kisseth her. Ghism. That was but a story that I tould you. Guisc. And I shew'd your Grace the meaneing. Ghism. Doe you begin to apprehend? Guisc. I doe, And with so greate a zeale of heart do tender My homage first and then my loue to you That did your person lay aside your greatnes, And I could think that you were not ye Princes, I durst presume to tell you I were hee You haue great interest in, or he in you. Ghism. The greater prize, the glory is the more To him that gaines it, and thou'lt be more renoun'd, If thou be grac'd by me then by a meaner. Come, sit downe heere, and, if thou dost remember That song which once did please me, let me heare. The stilnes of the night doth bannish feare; Yet sing but softly, lest some list'ning eare Should chance to spoyle our musick. The song, sung by Guiscardo. Vertue, Beautie, Goodnes stroue How to teach a man to loue. Vertue, teaching wisely, sayd: “Loue thou a well-disposed mayd”. Beauty sayd: “Loue one that's faire, And then thou canst not want an heire”. But Goodnes sayd: “I wish thee loue [King stirrs. Such a one as I approue: Such a body, such a mynd With the Princes you may finde”. The Princes falls asleepe. Guisc. She falles aslepe, to heare her worth commended. Vertue did euer so. O blest Guiscardo! If thou darst be so bold, steale one kis more From these soft lips which, euen with a touch, Will make thee liue aboue the yeares of Nestor. [He kisseth her. Tanc. You powers of patience, afford me but one dramm. Guisc. Such a kisse as this doth far exceede In relish all the nectar Joue e're tasted. [He kisses her agayne. Tanc. My buttons breake; I can conteine no longer. Ghism. I could sleep euermore, or feigne to sleepe, If I might haue such reall dreames to please me. Did they, whose flinty hartes haue none bene hit With the smart touches of blind Cupid's quiuer, But once conceaue or feele what hapines It is to be in loue, they'd mourne and weepe, And sob and sigh, to thinke those dayes are past In which they might haue seru'd there prentice age In Venus' schole, and by this time haue knowne How to do thus. She embraceth Guiscardo. Tanc. Patienc hath held too long. Die, both together! King shoots at them with a pistoll. Are you impenitrable? Then this shall do it. As he runs at them with a sword, he stumbles and falls. My chance hath kept me inocent, and Heauen Detein'd my hand from being soyl'd with blood And gaue me so much fauor, 'cause I should not Be hangman to so high-offending sinners. Yet it doth prompt me thus far as to see A iust reueng be taken on this slaue. Ghism. Be not offended, sir; what was done here, Inocence it selfe could not find fault with. Tanc. I scorne to call thee daughter, or the subiect; He is a traytor, and thou art a whore. Goe worship folly, for she is the power That most commaunds o're brittle womanhood. Guisc. Humbly I beg, sir, that your will may bee Perform'd on me, yea, with the vtmost rigor, So my deare Princes' honor may be safe. Ghism. Let your iust censure be vpon our merit And not a wrong end set, for then you make it Be capable of being cal'd erronious. As I haue hope of Heauen, no other thing Was done worse then you se! Tanc. 'Tis probable That you two, burning in hot desire, And, as it seemes (which breakes my hart to think on't), Inflam'd with other's lust, should be together And not act wickednes! You may as well affirme Goates are not hot, nor monkies' lust incontenent, As to perswade me thinke that this is true. Glausamond, Gabriello, Pasquino, where are you? Enter Glausamond, Gabriello and Pasquino. Ghism. 'Tis hard to alter your imagination; But, honoured father, let me neuer haue A looke of fauor from you, if there weare Any thing done, but only Guiscardo Did sing a song. If you doubt of this, Put him and me, both, to fire-ordeall. Glaus. There's no hurt in this. A good song Is worth much to a young lady, when She hath need on't, and, no question, Will doe her more good then hurt, If it be well sunge. Tanc. Hold thy tonge! Now thy iestes are out of season. I'm in another moode and now begin To doubt thy mother's treuth, whether thou wert Truly begott or no, for if thou hadst But any drop of blood in thee of myne, Thou'dst scorne to goe soe far below thy selfe As make thy seruant master of thine honour. Couldst thou feigne such obedience and such loue, And then proue false, both to thy selfe and father? O, rash young man, that run'st vnto thine end, Feareing to come too late! Couldst thou not stay, Vntill the apoynted time had cal'd the to it, But thou must make soe swift precipitation? Now I begin to call into my mynd, This was the cause that made thee so vnwilling To goe thy iorney. But thou wilt wish th'adst gone, Before this sentence had commaunded the, Guiscardo, go to execucion. Ghism. Sure, sir, So smale a slip, yea, such a little one That I doe doubt whether't be one or no, Without a far-extended indignation Weare meriting the name of cruelty, Canot deserue so sharp a condemnation. Tanc. 'Tis iustice and not cruelty condemns him; Nor can your busy tongue be worse imploy'd Then in excusing such a haynous crime. I haue decreed his fate, but doubt of yours. Ghism. Haue you decreed, this inocent shall die? Tanc. His inocence is dead already, but his guilt Shall be so punnished as I haue told you. Ghism. Is your decre irreuocable? Tanc. As that last word irreuocable. Ghism. Then let me make one suit vnto you, sir— That you will not torment your selfe with thinking What shall become of me, but suffer me To spend those solemne dayes I yet haue left, All alone by my selfe, sometimes my closet Being the cell which I shall make partaker Of those sad wordes my sighes shall dayly vtter, Sometimes that you'l permit me come and se This rome, wherin it pleas'd your Maiesty To take offence—not giuen, but receaued. Nor will I burden long this place or that, If your decre stand firme and alter not, For though I haue a body feminine, I'le shew a spirit that is masculine. And if Guiscardo's act deserue to be Cal'd an offence, thy soule shal not be fre [Speaking to Guiscardo. From being immur'd in flesh one hower, but I Wilbe an actor in thy tragedy. But if you'l shew your selfe compassionat, Let vs die both together, for 'tis too late To alter my decree, if yours do hould. I'm but a woman, yet made of the mould That Cesar was. Tanc. Thou dost resolue— At least, talke like an emperor, and while This wicked roote, whence thine ill-setled thoughtes First tooke infection, doth stand so neare thee, Thy will will make thy resolucion seeme Stronger this present then in futuryty, When wise repentance shall infeeble it. You, Gabriello and Pasquino, take Guiscardo As your prisoner and keep him closely and Safely, till you vnderstand our further plesure. Ghism. One word, before he goe, pray, suffer me To grace him with—at least to please my selfe. Neuer was man so well-belou'd of any As I intirely loue thy company. Glaus. As I'm vertuous, sir, 'tis pitty to part 'hem! Tanc. What now, sir? Haue him away! Ghism. Not one word more? Tanc. You haue had too many already. Do as I bid you. Gab. and Pasq. You heare the King, whome we must nedes obey. Guisc. Giue me leaue, great King, once to speak to you, Before I breath my last. Did not white inocence Liue in my breast, I'd blush and so be silent; Were my soule clog'd with guilt of this offence, I'd hang my heade and not implore your mercy; But since I'm free, yet you will haue me dye, I tell you, murder fits not maiesty. Gab. and Pasq. Come, you must stay no longer. Guisc. I'm satisfied, goe on. [Ex. Gabriello, Guiscardo and Pasquino. Ghism. I'le take my leaue too, and if you heare Ghismonda's deade, before Guiscardo die, Thinke, 'twas because she lou'd soe constantly. [Exit Ghismonda. Glaus. This an heroick wench; but Heauens defend, So sweet a peece should haue so sower an end, Vntill age produce it. Tanc. Feare not; she That could so soone shake of her husband's losse Which she sem'd so to greeue for, will make this cros A recreation to her. Glaus. O, good sir, let your hart be more waxie, For o' my conscience, shee's chaste! Tanc. O rogue! Glaus. Do not condemne, before you know cause. Tanc. I know too much. Glaus. By your fauor, what? Tanc. She kissed him twice or thrice in my sight. Glaus. That was but a weake and dry expression. Tanc. What wouldst thou haue? Glaus. Nothing, I, sir; but they that would be naught, As my fond, foolish, blushing face would neuer Suffer me to be, had rather haue other thinges. Tanc. Goe call Gabriello and Pasquino hither. [Exit Glausamond. She did but onely kisse him that I saw, But the earnestnes of it was a shrewd suspicion. If they did more, the sleep that seiz'd on me Became there baud; els I should haue preuented it. The pistol mist them, the sword mist them, And I fell downe, iust as I made at them. But chance did this to saue my reputation, Because I should not foule my sword i'th'gore Of so adulterate and corrupted blood. Or it may be that Justice, knowing them inocent, Did lay some rub i'th'way to make me fall And kepe my handes from sin and them from death. It canot be! Well, first I will doe this— Put out the heate, whereby Ghismonda's fire Tooke inflamation, and so cure her distemper; And when the part, wherin the gangren growes, Is amputated, the head is in no danger, Because it grew so low as in the foote. And for Ghismonda, her blood, being parte of mine At least in reputation, I'le not shed, But leaue for offence to Heauen's discretion. Yet I will dayly make experiment Enter Gabriello, Glausamond and Pasquino. Whether 'tweare like she did offend or not. Guiscardo's safe? Pasq. Yes, sure enough, I warrant you. Tanc. Did you bring him in at the iron gate? Gab. Yes, an't please your Maiesty. Tanc. And he shall haue theire fate that goe in there. With all the speed you can, let him be executed. Yet not in that base sort that felons die; Because my fauor made him a peare o'th'realme, I'le giue him leaue to haue a nobler end. Vpon the scaffold, where the traytorous lordes Do vse to die, there let his amorous head Be taken of, and so hee'le soone be dead. And when the executioner hath done His office thus far, let him forthwith Rip vp his breast and take the panting hart Which anguish will make swell, then put it in A cup of gold prepared purposely, And you, Pasquino, straight carry it to Ghismonda. This will make her ether b[l]ush or weepe. If she be guilty, she will hide her face, And then wee'l scorne her. But if her soule be fre From this foule sin, her teares will presently Declare so much, and then wee'l rayse her ioy By curteous vsage. Goe! This way will shew Whether we haue ben too seuere or no. [Exit Pasquino and Gabriello. Glaus. It could haue done no hurt, if you had stay'd The execution a little longer. Tanc. O yes, we should not then so sodainely Haue vnderstood whether Ghismonda be Guilty or no. This way we shall soone Perceaue the treuth of all. But howsoeuer You will conclude, Guiscardo merites death; His boldnes made his faulte a haynous one. Glaus. I doe not thinke soe, for boldnes nowadayes Is cal'd a vertue and gaynes both prick and prayse; And if you haue no more condemning reason Then this, most courtiers must be hang'd for treason. Tanc. If I should haue winck'd at this presumption In proud Guiscardo, it might haue drawne him on To thinke on stranger thinges and to assay What wisdome this way will be sure to stay. That which I haue decreed, I'le not recall; Better the subiect then the Kinge should fall. [Exeunt. Enter at another dore Pasquino and an executioner. Pasq. The scaffold ready? Ex. Yes. Pasq. And all other instrumentes of death? Ex. As may bee. Pasq. Set forth the scaffold; anger is impatient. Yet if it be not ready when he comes, I thinke he wilbe contented to stay for it! Executioner brings the scaffold. Soe. I'le goe fetch him. Doe you attend ye while. [Exit Pasquino. Ex. Had Guiscardo kist Peg or Dol now, There had bene no danger in it, but many Times, when a man leaps high at the First leape, commonly he breakes his neck In the fall. Enter Pasquino, Guiscardo and Gabriello. Pasq. Here's the place you'r like to leaue your head at. Guisc. I'm sory for it, since I haue not deseru'd it. If I had merited this kind of death, Which, I protest, I haue not, I should die As willingly as euer man expired. Yet to be destin'd to this end, which none But traytors vse to suffer, when my soule Knowes it selfe guiltles as a new-borne babe, Grat'th against weake nature and is a weight Too heauy far for innocence to beare. Pasq. Each of our liues is in our soueraigne's hand, Nor will it profit thee to blame his will. That which the King hath sayd, we must performe; Therefore, beleeue me, we dare not shew thee fauor And so aduenture to get his displeasure. Guisc. 'Tis easy to triumph on mysery. A mouse's strength throwes downe a falling tree, Though't be a cedar; yea, the meanest creature, Eu'n the mole, whose grou'ling path's confin'd To goe in earth so deepe that shee's deni'd To se the light o'th'sun vpon the surface, With her swine's snout will quicly ruinate A castle wall that is before declineing. Thou art this mole and now dar'st tread vpon My faleing fortunes and there ill disaster. I doe forgiue thee, since I know right well I'm goeing to Heauen, where malice doth not dwel. Strike, dismall sword! Neuer did any die That was thought faulty, with lesse guilt then I. Executioner cuts of his head. Pasq. Carry the body hence and open it. When you haue done, take out the hart which yet Doth pant within it, and, as the King directed, Put it i'th'golden cup that he comanded, And bring it hether. Sure, 'twill be sad newes, When I shall giue the Princes such a token. Exit Executioner cum cadauere. Gab. I'm glad the King apoynted thee to deliuer't. Pasq. 'Tis no great thing to doe. Gab. Surely, noe. To carry a cup with no more liquor in it Then riseth from the fume a dieing heart Is able to steame out, is no great matter Of labor or of bodyly toyle; yet 'tis A thing my stomake would not stand to doe, Vnles it weare to carry a cruell foe The heart of his dead frend, t'augment his woe— This were a deede of merit. Enter Ghismonda and her wayting-woman. Ghism. What, Pasquino! And Gabriello too! How doth your charge? Pasq. I hope, well. Ghism. How doth the Kinge? Pasq. Very well. Long may he be soe! Ghism. And you se, I am well too. Both We hope so, honour'd lady. Ghism. Then you hope I am as Guiscardo is, And that's well. I'm sure, your loyall heartes Will not desire me in another state. Pasq. I sayd, I hoped he was well. Ghism. How doe you hope? Pasq. Pray, pardon me. Ghism. Come, my resolution is so firmely fixt, I will not start at any thing. Out with it! Pasq. I hope his soule is well, but his bodie's dead. Ghism. And doe you se me stir'd? I told my father I was made of the mold that Cesar was, For he was made of earth, and soe am I, And I will shew a Roman constancie. You'l thinke much that I should haue the patience now To tell you how your wordes belie your knowledg. First you sayd, you hop'd Guiscardo was well; Then you sayd, the King is well, as if you knew it; And lastly you hop'd I was, and you saw it. O, you base-minded, hollow-harted slaues! Your wordes belye your thoughtes; your deedes, your consciences, All your faire shewes are but forsworne pretences. You hop'd nor this, nor that, that I or hee, Your Princes or Guiscardo, did do well. You hop'd Guiscardo and my selfe were well, And yet you striue to kill vs; him in act Vniustly you haue murder'd, me in effect. And lastly, that you sayd the King was well Of your owne knowledg thus I contradict— He hath an ouer-loding clogg within him, That he can neuer breath without vexation. And now you'l witnes that I haue some patience. Enter Executioner with the cup. What, sirrah! Tell me, haue you brought a cup That one may drinke of once and, drinking, die? Pasq. Madam, he hath brought that which I must giue To your owne handes, although you checke me for it. Within this golden cup remaines the hart Of dead Guiscardo which the King, your father, Hath sent you for a present, to comfort you With that which you so dearely did affect. Ghism. Neuer did Tancred, the great King of Salern, Declare his wisdome more, for 'tis but right And iustice that so noble a hart as this Should [not] be layd in a meaner graue then gold. Returne the latest thankes that I can giue Vnto my father, now grown mercifull In sending me so honourable a present, And tell him that my onely suit is to him, One common graue may hold Guiscardo and me, So that spectators may no difference see 'Twixt his and mine. Thus may we in death inioy What he in life deni'd so cruelly. Pasq. I'le let him know your pleasure. [Exeunt Pasquino and Gabriello. Ghism. I pray you, doe. Sweete entertayner of all my deare delightes! Accursed be his cruelty that causeth Me thus to se thee with my corporal eies! I thought, and so it was sufficient, That I had ioy enough, when I beheld thee With the sight of my soule. Minks, reach my cabinet. I'le drinke one draught to thee; thou art so worthy. Waiting-woman reacheth the cabinet, which the Princes openeth, findes a letter and reads the superscription thus: “To the faire handes of my indeared Princes Your honourer and true seruant Guiscardo. Humbly presentes his service.” Thy hand wrote virgin lines, and thy tongue spake Just as thy hand wrote, and all thy life Was but a iorney in a virtuous path. Were I so good as thou wert, I would wish To liue on earth still, there to imitate Thy rare perfections, and thus I should giue cause To the most vpright liuers to die for shame Or greeffe, despareing of thy imitation. Findes a bottell in the cabinet. Come, thou dissoluer of all cares and troubles, Enter that breast which so much longs to feele thee; Please her that hath displeased all but him Whose inocence did make him loose his life. Send me but quickly to him, and thou wilt be A learn'd phisitian, cureing misery. Emptieth the bottle into the cup. Here's a draught to the memory of Guiscardo. Drinks. The cup's too shallow and my wind too short To drinke to thee in such a gratefull sort As thy large merit cals for and enioynes me. But what is wanting in the humid quantity, The vertue o'th'confection will supply. Thou little part of euer-lou'd Guiscardo, Yet great in my esteeme, do not blush To looke thy loue i'th'face, but come to me And ease my greefe by thy sweete company. Though the King pleas'd to take thy life and blood, For no fault els but 'cause thou wert too good, Yet 'tis a hard and most vnequall thinge That inocence should die to please the King, And though on earth thou hadst so sharp a doome, Yet patience allwaise gaines by marterdome, And thou wert such a martir. My hart, come forth. I'le lay thee in a softer sepulcher, and though't be not So rich, yet 'tis more warme. Come of from me, I'le haue thee cloath a far more noble body. Takes of a black vaile, lined with white. I wrap thee in this cloth, because its whitenes Is like thy master, cleare without a stayne; Then next in this sad blacke, whose sable hue Doth shew a mourning hand did put it o're thee; And now goe to thy center. Puts the hart in her breast. Neuer woman was With a liue man and all his lineamentes So truely pleas'd as this pore, cold, dead hart Doth comfort me by its soe neare abideing. Lie closse to me; thou art a welcom guest. I will go to thy master and there rest; Though't be a solemne meeting, yet 'twill be Honour to him and ease of mynd to me. She struggles; waiting-woman cries. Wait. Madam, mistris, Princes, lady! Ghism. Doe not disturb my pleasing passage to him. She cries still. Enter Tancred, Pasquino and Glausamond. Pasq. I am afraid your Maiestie's come too late. Tanc. My deare Ghismonda, looke vpon thy father, And if thou hast a sence of what I speake Or apprehention of the teares I sheed, Speake to him that is greeueing, aged, weeping. Ghism. Death comes too slowly, yet suffers me to tell you, Those teares do not befitt you, nor please me. Who but your selfe did euer mourne for that Which your owne will was the sole causer of? Yet, if you haue a iott of that loue in you Which you haue made so great profession of, Afford this fauor which I humbly craue, That Guiscardo and I may haue one graue; And since he shew'd him selfe a constant louer, Good sir, giue leaue, one vrn vs both may couer. By takeing so much pitty, you will be Cal'd mercifull. She struggles. Guiscardo, I come to thee. Tanc. O, my deare hart, how little do I deserue To be the father of such a noble child! Sweete, do not leaue me so; my teares shall wash Those foule sins of my cruelty, committed 'Gainst thee and thy so well-belou'd Guiscardo. At this name she opens her eies. O, holy saint, thine inocence and his were Cossin germans, Or rather twins, so that thou canst not heare His name repeated, but thou lift'st vp thine eies, As if to him thou offeredst sacrifice. She grones and dies. O, now shee's gone. Glaus. Past all hope; stiffe allready. Tanc. I'le trye her thus. As at the repetition Of thy Guiscardo's name thou didst looke vp, So doe againe. No tongue can speake, when death Bereaues it of ability to moue. If his name thou so lou'dst, haue not the power To draw one word more from thee, let Tancred's name Be grac'd so far as haue thee call him father. I merit les then hee, and so my name Is not so vertuous. Shee's dead and cannot. This is a day, wherein mishap's a victor, And cruelty, the beastliest thing in man, Hath died my regall name so deepe in blood That he that cals me tirant, fauors me. I was a king vntill this darke-lookt hower, But now I'm slaue to hellish misery. 'Tis fit I should be, since I haue deseru'd it. Had I giu'n leaue that youthfull appetite Might haue inioy'd its wish in such a sort As did agree with noble decencie, I had bene blest, and those two dead, aliue, For they did wish no more; theire moderacion Was so reseru'd and fearefull of ill-doeing That they chose rather to vndergoe that taske Which to weake nature's harsh and terrible, Eu'n death it selfe, then any way t'assay To gather pleasures from a sinfull tree. Take in my daughter's body, and let it haue A fitt obseruance for so great a Princes Vntill I come, which shalbe presently, And then I'le se the rightes perform'd my selfe. Could I make them reuiue, whose death I caus'd, I'd kis the ground and creep vpon my knees And licke the dust, as if it were the spirit Of some most precious cordiall. But in vayne I wish for that which will not come agayne. Go, thou deiected man, and provide store Of blackes. Such martirs neuer were before; No story doth record where such a paire Did die so good, so inocent, so faire. [Exit Tanc.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">EPILOGUE Our play is ended, and your expectation, Tak'n vp with that which some men's approbation Scornes to be giu'n to—we doe scorne soe much To vnderprize our selues as thinke on such. But you, whose goodnes names you noble frendes, I come to let you know, our author sendes You store of thankes, and greeues, his tragedie Hath not deseru'd the gracefull courtesie You did him, lookinge on it. Yet he protests, You are more welcome then to greater feastes, And you will please him much, if your handes say, You are delighted with his tragick play. [Exit. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>