<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Heywood, Jasper, 1535-1598</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Heywood, Jasper, 1535-1598</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">heywood jasper 1535 1598</field>
      <field name="author_text">Heywood, Jasper, 1535-1598</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">16th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V1.0953.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1581</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:459583</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Sixte Tragedie of the most Grave and prude[n]t Author Lvcivs Annaevs Seneca, entituled Troas</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- Early modern and Elizabethan, 1500-1600</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- Early modern and Elizabethan, 1500-1600</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Sixte Tragedie of the most Grave and prude[n]t Author Lvcivs Annaevs Seneca, entituled Troas</field>
      <field name="title_facet">sixte tragedie of the most grave and prudent author lvcivs annaevs seneca entituled troas</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">sixte tragedie of the most grave and prudent author lvcivs annaevs seneca entituled troas</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Sixte Tragedie of the most Grave and prude[n]t Author Lvcivs Annaevs Seneca, entituled Troas</field>
      <field name="year_display">1581</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1581</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1581</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459583&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459583&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Heywood, Jasper, 1535-1598&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;heywood jasper 1535 1598&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Sixte Tragedie of the most Grave and prude[n]t Author Lvcivs Annaevs Seneca, entituled Troas&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;sixte tragedie of the most grave and prudent author lvcivs annaevs seneca, entituled troas&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1581&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1581&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Heywood, Jasper&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1535&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1598&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Sixte Tragedie of the most Grave and prude[n]t Author Lvcivs Annaevs Seneca, entituled Troas&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Imprinted ... by Thomas Marshe&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1581&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872059-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv10953&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- Early modern and Elizabethan, 1500-1600&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;Early modern and Elizabethan, 1500-1600&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Sixte Tragedie of the most Grave and prude[n]t Author Lvcivs Annaevs Seneca, entituled Troas&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 135 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Only verse drama included&lt;lb/&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;lb/&gt;Epigraph and dedication included with Hercules Furens&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Troas.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1559.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 1559.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE SIXTE TRAGEDIE OF THE MOST GRAVE &amp; prud?t Author LVCIVS ANNÆVS SENECA, entituled TROAS, vvith diuers and sundrye Additions to the same, by IASPER HEYVVOOD.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Argument. The ten yeares siege of Troy, who list to heare, And of thaffayres that there befell in fight: Reade ye the workes that long since written were, Of all Thassaultes, and of that latest night, When Turrets toppes in Troy they blased bright Good Clerkes they were that haue it written well As for this worke, no word therof doth tell. But Dares Phrygian, well can all report, With Dictis eke of Crete in Greekish toung And Homer telles, to Troye the Greekes resort In scanned verse, and Maro hath it song Ech one in writ hath pend a stoary long, Who doubtes of ought, and casteth care to knowe These antique Authors, shal the story showe, The ruines twayne of Troy, the cause of each, The glittering helmes, in fieldes the Banners spread, Achilles yres, and Hectors fightes they teach. There may the iestes of many a Knight be read: Patroclus, Pyrrhus, Aiax, Diomed, With Troylus, Parys, many other more, That day by day, there fought in field full sore. And how the Grekes at end an engine made: A hugie horse where many a warlike Knight Enclosed was: the Troians to inuade With Sinons craft, when Greekes had fayned flight, While close they lay at Tenedos from sight, Or hovv Eneas els as other say, And false Antenor did the tovvne betray. But as for me I naught therof endight, Myne Author hath not all that story pend: My pen his wordes in English must resight, Of latest woes that fell on Troy at end, What finall fates the cruell God could send. And how the Greekes when Troy was burnt gan wreake Their ire on Troians, therof shall I speake. Not I with spere who pearced was in fielde, Whose throate there cutte, or head ycorued was Ne bloudshed blowes, that rent both targe and shield Shal I resight, all that I ouerpasse. The worke I wryght more woeful is alas, For I the mothers teares must here complayne, And bloud of babes, that giltles haue bene slayne. And such as yet could neuer weapon wreast, But on the lap are wont to dandled bee, Ne yet forgotten had the mothers breast, How Greekes them slew (alas) here shal ye see To make report therof ay woe is mee, My song is mischife, murder, misery, And hereof speakes this doleful tragedy. Thou fury fel that from the deepest den Couldst cause this wrath of hell on Troy to light, That worckest woe guyde thou my hand and pen, In weeping verse of sobbes and sighes to wryght, As doth myne author them bewayle aright: Helpe woefull muse for mee besemeth wel Of others teares, with weeping eye to tell. When battered were to ground the towres of Troy In writ as auncient authors do resight, And Greekes agayne repayrde to Seas with ioy, Vp riseth here from hel Achilles Spright, Vengeance he craues vvith bloud his death to quight. Whom Paris had in Phœbus temple slayne, With guile betrapt for loue of Polyxeine. And wrath of hel there is none other pryce That may asswage: but bloud of her alone Polyxena he craues for sacrifyce, With threatninges on the Grecians many one Except they shed her bloud before they gone. The Sprightes the hell, and depest pittes beneath, O Virgin dere, (alas) do thrust thy death. And Hectors sonne, Astyanax (alas) Pore seely foole his Mothers onely ioy, Is iudgd to die by sentence of Calchas Alas the whyle, to death is led the boy, And tumbled downe from Turrets tops in Troy. What ruthful teares may serue to wayle the woe Of Hectors wyfe that doth her child forgoe. Her pinching pange of hart who may expresse, But such as of like woes, haue borne a part? Or who bewayle her ruthful heauines That neuer yet hath felt therof the smart? Ful well they wot the woes of heauy hart. What is to leese a babe from mothers breast, They know that are in such a case distrest. First how the Queene lamentes the fall of Troy, As hath mine author done, I shall it wryght Next how from Hectors wyfe they led the boy To die, and her complayntes I shall resight, The maydens death then I must last endight. Now who that liste the Queenes complaint to here. In following verse it shall forthwith appeare.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Speakers names. HECVBA Queene of Troy. A company of women. TALTHYBIVS a Grecian. AGAMEMNON King of Greeks. ASTYANAX. NVNCIVS. CALCHAS. PYRRHVS. CHORVS. ANDROMACHA An old man TROIAN. VLYSSES. HELENA. The Sprihgt of Achilles.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE FIRST ACTE. Hecuba. Who so in pompe of prowde estate, or Kingdome sets delight: Or who that ioyes in Princes courte to beare the sway of might. Ne dreads the fates which from aboue the wauering Gods downe flinges: But fast affiance fixed hath, in frayle and fickle thinges: Let him in me both se the Face, of Fortunes flattering ioy: And eke respect the ruthful end of thee (O ruinous Troy) For neuer gaue shee playner proofe, then this ye present see: How frayle and britle is the state of pride and high degree, The flowre of flowring Asia, loe whose fame the heauens resound, The Worthy worke of Gods aboue, is batered downe to ground. And whose assaultes they sought afar, from West wt Banners spred Where Tanais cold her braunches seuen, abroad the world doth shed. With hugie host and from the East, where springes the newest dea, Where Lukewarme Tygris channell runnes, and meetes the ruddy sea. And which fr? wandring land of Seythe, the band of widowes sought: With fire and sworde thus battered be her Turrets downe to nought. The walles but late of high renowne lo here their ruinous fall: The buildinges burne, and flashing flame, swepes through the pallas al. Thus euery house ful hie it smoakes, of old Assarackes lande: Ne yet the flames withholdes from spoyle, the greedy Victors hand. The surging smoake, the asure skye, and light hath hid away: And (as with cloude beset) Troyes Ashes staynes the dusky day. Through pearst with ire and greedy of hart, the victor from a farre. Doth view the long assaulted Troy, the gaine of ten yeares warre, And eke the miseryes therof abhorres to looke vppon, And though he se it yet scant himselfe, belieues might be wonne, The spoyles thereof with greedy hand, they snatch and beare awaye: A thousand shippes would not receiue aboorde so huge a pray The yreful might I do protest of Gods aduerse to mee, My countryes dust, and Troyan King I call to witnes thee, Whom Troy now hydes, and vnderneath the stones art ouertrode: With al the Gods that guides the Ghost, and Troy that lately stoode. And you also you flocking Ghostes of al my children dere: Ye lesser Sprightes what euer ill, hath hapned to vs here. What euer Phœbus watrish face, in fury hath foresayde: At raging rise from seas when earst, the monsters had him frayde. In childbed bandes I saw it yore, and wist it should be so: And I in vayne before Cassandra told it long agoe. Not false Vlysses kindled hath these fires, nor none of his: Nor yet deceyptful Sinons craft, that hath bene cause of this. My fyre it is wherwith ye burne, and Parys is the brand That smoaketh in thy towres (O Troy) the flowre of Phrygian land. But ay (alas) vnhappy age, why dost thou yet so sore, Bewayle thy Countries fatall fall, thou knewest it long before: Behold thy last calamityes, and them bewayle with teares: Account as old Troys ouerturne, and past by many yeares, I saw the slaughter of the King, and how he lost his life: By Th'aulter sloe (more mischiefe was) with stroake of Pyrrhus knife. When in his hand he wound his lockes, and drew the King to ground, And hid to hiltes his wicked sword, in deepe and deadly wound. Which when the gored King had tooke, as willing to bee slayne, Out of the old mans throate he drew his bloudy blade agayne. Not pitty of his yeares (alas) in mans extreamest age: From slaughter might his hand withhold, ne yet his yre asswage: The Gods are witnes of the same, and eake the sacrifyes, That in his kingdome holden was, that flat on ground now lies. The father of so many Kings Pryam of aunient name, Untombed lieth and wants in blase of Troy: his funerall flame. Ne yet the Gods are wreakt, but loe his Sonnes and daughters all, Such Lordes they serue as doth by chance of lot to them befall. Whom shall I follow now for pray? or where shall I be led There is perhaps amonge the Greekes that Hectors wyfe will wed. Some man desyres Helenus spouse some would Antenors haue, And in the Greekes their wantes not some, that would Cassandra craue But I (alas) most woeful wight whom no man seekes to chuse, I am the only refuge left, and me they cleane refuse Ye careful captiue company, why stints your woful crye? Beate on your breastes and piteously complayne with voyce so hye, As meete may be for Troyes estate, let your complayntes rebound In toppes of Trees: and cause the hills to ring with terible sounde. THE SECOND SCENE. The VVoman, Hecuba. Not folke vnapt, nor nevv to vveepe (O Queene) Thou vvilst to vvayle by practise are vvee taught, For all these yeares in such case haue vve bene, Since first the Troyan guest, Amiclas soughte And saild the Seas, that led him on his vvay With sacred ship, to Cibell dedicate From vvhence he brought his vnrepyning pray, The cause (alas) of all this dire debate, Ten tymes novv hydde the hilles of Idey bee, With snovve of Syluer hevv all ouer layd. And bared is, for Troyan rages each tree, Ten tymes in field, the haruest man afrayde, The spikes of Corne hath reapt, since neuer day His waylyng wantes new cause renewes our woe Lift vp thy hand, (O Queene) crie well away: We follow thee, we are wel taught thereto. HEC. Ye faythful fellowes of your casualty, Vntie thattyre, that on your heads ye weare, And as behoueth state of misery, Let fall aboute your woeful neckes your hayre. In dust of Troy rub all your armes about, In slacker weede and let your breastes be tyed Downe to your bellies let your limmes lye out, For what wedlocke should you your bosomes hyde? Your garmentes loose, and haue in readines Your furious handes vppon your breast to knocke This habite well beseemeth our distresse, It pleaseth me, I know the Troyan flocke Renew agayne your longe accustomde cryes, And more then earst lament your miseryes. We bewayle Hector. WO. Our hayre we haue vntide, now euerychone, All rent for sorrow of our cursed cace, Our lockes out spreads, the knottes we haue vndone And in these ashes stayned is our face. HEC. Fill vp your handes and make therof no spare, For this yet lawful is from Troy to take Let dovvne your garmentes from your shoulders bare. And suffer not your clamour so to slake. Your naked breastes wayte for your handes to smight Now dolor deepe now sorrow shevv thy might: Make all the coastes that compas Troy about Witnes the souude of all your careful crye Cause from the Caues the eccho to cast out: Rebounding voyce of all your misery: Not as she wontes, the latter word to sound But all your woe from farre let it rebound Let al the Seas it heare, and eke the land Spare not your breastes vvith heauy stroake to strike Beate ye your selues, ech one vvith cruell hand For yet your vvonted crie doth me not like VVe bevvayle Hector. VVO. Our naked armes, thus here vve rent for thee, And bloudy shoulders, (Hector) thus vve teare: Thus vvith our fistes, our heades lo beaten bee And all for thee, behold vve hale our heare. Our dugges alas, vvith mothers hands be torne And vvhere the flesh is vvounded round about VVhich for thy sake, vve rent thy death to morne The flovving streames of bloud, they spring thereout. Thy countres shore, and destinies delay. And thou to vvearied Troians vvast an ayde, A vvall thou vvast, and on thy shoulders Troy Ten yeres it stode, on thee alone it staide, VVith thee it fell: and fatall day alas Of Hector both, and Troy but one there vvas. HEC. Enough hath Hector: turne your plaint and mone And shed your teares for Pryame euery chone. VVO. Receiue our plaintes, O lord of Phrigian land And old tvvise captiue king, receiue our feare, VVhile thou vvert king. Troy hurtles then could stand Though shaken tvvise, with Grecian sword it weare, And twise did shot of Hercles quiuer beare, At latter losse of Hecubes sonnes all And roges for kings, that hgih on piles we reare: Thou father shutst our latest funerall. And beaten downe, to Ioue for sacrifies. Like liueles blocke, in Troy thy carkas lies. HEC. Yet turne ye once your teares, another way, My pryams death, should not lamented be. O Troyans all, ful happy is Pryame say, For free from bondage, downe descended hee, To the lowest Ghoste: and neuer shall sustayne His Captiue necke with Greekes to yoked bee. Hee neuer shal behold the Atrids twayne Nor false Vlisses euer shal he see, Not hee a pray for Greekes to triumph at His necke shall subiect to their conquestes beare Ne geue his handes to tye behynde his backe, That to the rule of Scepters wonted weare, Nor following Agamemnons chare, in bande Shall he bee pompe, to proude Mycenas land. WO. Ful happy Pryame is, each one wee say That toke vvith him his Kingdome then that stoode Now safe in shade, he seekes the wandring way, And treads the pathes of all Elizius wood, And in the blessed Sprightes, ful happy hee, Agayne there seekes to meete with Hectors Ghost. Happy Pryam, happy who so may see, His Kingdome all, at once with him be lost. Chorus added to the Tragedy by the Translator. O ye to whom the Lord of Lande and Seas, Of Life and Death hath graunted here the powre Lay dovvne your lofty lookes, your pride appeas The crovvned King fleeth not his fatall howre. Who so thou be that leadst thy land alone, Thy life vvas limite from thy mothers vvombe, Not purple robe, not Glorious glittering throne, Ne crovvne of Gold redeemes thee from the tombe: A King he was that wayting for the vayle, Of him that slew the Minotaure in fight: Begilde with blacknes of the wonted saile In seas him sonke, and of his name they hight. So he that wild, to vvin the golden spoyle And first vvith ship, by seas to seeke renovvne, In lesser vvaue, at length to death gan boyle, And thus the daughters, brought their father dovvne: Whose songes, the vvoodes hath dravven, and riuers held, And birdes to heare his notes, did theirs forsake, In peece meale throvvne, amid the Thracian field, Without returne hath sought the Stigian lake. They sit aboue, that holde our life in line, And vvhat vve suffer dovvne they fling from hie, No carke, no care, that euer may vntwine The thrids, that vvouen are aboue the skie, As vvitnes he that sometyme King of Greece, Had Iason thought, in drenching seas to drovvne Who scapt both death and gaind the Golden fleece, Whom fates aduaunce, there may no povvre plucke dovvne The highest God sometyme that Saturne hight His fall him taught to credite their decrees The rule of heauens: he lost it by their might, And Ioue his sonne novv turnes the rolling Skies. Who vveneth here to vvin eternall vvelth, Let him behold this present perfite proofe. And learne the secrete stoppe of chaunces stelth, Most nere alas, vvhen most it seemes aloofe. In slipper ioy let no man put his trust: Let none dispayre that heauy haps hath past The svvete vvith sovvre she mingleth as she lust Whose doubtful web pretendeth nought to last. Frailtie is the thride, that Clothoes rocke hath sponne, Novv from the Distaffe dravvne novv knapt in tvvaine With all the world at length his end he wonne, Whose works haue wrought, his name should great remaine And he whose trauels twelue, his name display, That feared nought the force of worldly hurt, In fine (alas) hath found his fatall daye, And died with smart of Dianyraes shurt, If prowes might eternity procure, Then Priam yet should liue in lyking lust, Ay portly pompe of pryde thou art vnsure, Lo learne by him O Kinges yee are but dust. And Hecuba that wayleth now in care, That was so late of high estate a Queene, A mirrour is to teach you what you are Your wauering wealth, O Princes here is seene. Whom dawne of day hath seene in high estate Before Sunnes set, (alas) hath had his fall The Cradels rocke, appoyntes the life his date From setled ioy, to sodayne funerall.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE SECOND ACTE. The first Scene. The Spright of Achilles added to the tragedy by the Translator. Forsaking now the places tenebrouse, And deepe dennes of thinfernall region From all the shadowes of illusious That w?der there the pathes ful many one Lo, here am I returned al alone, The same Achil whose fierce and heauy hande Of al the world no wight might yet withstand. What man so stout of al the Grecians host, That hath not sometyme crau'd Achilles aide, And in the Troyans, who of prowes most That hath not feard to see my Banner splaide Achilles lo, hath made them all affrayde. And in the Greekes hath bene a piller post, That stvrdy stode agaynst their Troyan host. Where I haue lackt the Grecians went to wracke, Troy proued hath what Achills sword could doe Where I haue come the Troyans fled a backe, Retyring fast from field their walles vnto, No man that might Achilles stroke fordoe I dealt such stripes amid the Troian route, That with their bloud I staynd the fieldes aboute. Mighty Memnon that with his Persian band, Would Pryams part with all might mayntayne, Lo now he lyeth and knoweth Achilles hand Amid the field is Troylus also slayne. Ye Hector great, whom Troy accompted playne The flowre of chiualry that might be found, All of Achilles had theyr mortall wound. But Paris lo, such was his false deceipt, Pretending maryage of Polixeine, Behynd the aulter lay for me in wayte Where I vnwares haue falne into the trayne And in Appolloes church he hath me slayne Wherof the Hel will now iust vengeance haue, And here agayne, I come my right to craue. The deepe Auerne my rage may not sustayne, Nor beare the angers of Achilles spright From Acheront I rent the spoyle in twayne, And though the ground I grate agayne to sight: Hell could not hide Achilles from the light, Vengeance and bloud doth Orcus pit require, To quench the furies of Achilles yre. The hatefull land, that worse then Tartare is And burning thrust excedes of Tantalus, I here beholde againe, and Troy is this O, trauell worse, then stone of Sisyphus And paines that passe the panges of Tityus To light more lothsome furie hath me sent Then hooked wheele, that Ixions flesh doth rent. Remembred is alowe where sprites do dwell The wicked slaughter wrought by wyly way. Not yet reuenged hath the deepest hell, Achilles bloud on them that did him slay But now of vengeance come the yrefull day And darkest dennes of Tartare from beneath Conspire the fautes, of them that wrought my death. Now mischiefe, murder, wrath of hell draweth nere And dyre Phlegethon floud doth bloud require Achilles death shall he reuenged here VVith slaughter such as Stygian lakes desyre Her daughters bloud shal slake the spirites yre, VVhose sonne we slew, whereof doth yet remayne, The wrath beneath, and hell shalbe their payne. From burning lakes the furies wrath I threate, And fire that nought but streames of bloud may slake The rage of winde and seas their shippes shall beate, And Ditis deepe on you shall vengeance take, The sprites crie out, the earth and seas do quake The poole of Styx, vngratefull Greekes it seath, VVith slaughtred bloud reuenge Achilles death. The soyle doth shake to beare my heauy foote And fearth agayne the sceptors of my hand, The pooles with stroake of thunderclap ring out, The doubtful starres amid their course do stand, The fearfull Phœbus hides his blasing brande The trembling lakes agaynst their course do flite, For dread and terrour of Achilles spright. Great is the raunsome ought of due to mee, Wherwith ye must the sprightes and hell appease, Polyxena shal sacrifysed be, Vpon my tombe, their yreful wrath to please, And with her bloud ye shall asswage the seas Your ships may not returne to Greece agayne Til on my tombe Polyxena be slayne. And for that she should then haue bene my wyfe, I wil that Pyrrhus render her to mee, And in such solemne sort bereaue her life, As ye are wont the weddinges for to see, So shal the wrath of Hel appeased bee, Nought els but this may satisfy our yre, Her wil I haue and her I you require. THE SECOND SCENE. Talthibius, Chorus. Alas how long the lingring Greekes in hauen do make delay, When eyther warre by seas they seeke or home to passe theyr way. Ch. Why, shew what cause doth hold your ships? and Grecian nauy stayes, Declare if any of the Gods haue stopt your homeward wayes. Tal. My mynd is mas'd, my trembling sinnewes quake and are affeard, For straunger newes of truth then these I thinke were neuer heard. Lo I my selfe haue playnly seene in dawning of the day, When Phœbus first gan to approch and driue the starres away, The earth all shaken sodaynly and from the hollow grownde: My thought I hard with roaryng crye a deepe and dreadful sound: That shoke the woods, and al the trees rong out with thunder stroke, From Ida hils downe fel the stones, the mountayne toppes were broke. And not the earth hath onely quakt, but all the Sea likewyse, Achilles presence felt and knew, and high the surges ryse. The clouen ground Erebus pittes then shewd and deepest dennes, That downe to Gods that guyde beneath, the way appeard from hence. Then shoke the tombe from whence anone in flame of fiery light, Appeareth from the hollow caues Achilles noble spright. As wonted he his Thracian armes and bannars to disploy And weild his weighty weapons wel agaynst thassaultes of Troy, The same Achilles seemde he than that he was wont to bee Amid the hostes and easly could I know that this was hee. With carkasse slayne in furious fight, that stopt and fild each floude. And who with slaughter of his hand made Xanthus runne with bloud. As when in Chariot high he sate with lofty stomacke stoute. Whyle Hector both and Troy at once he drew the walles aboute. Alowd he cride, and euery coast rang with Achilles sound, And thus with hollow voyce he spake, from bottom of the ground. The Greekes shal not with litle pryce redeeme Achilles yre, A princely raunsome must they geue, for so the fates require Unto my ashes Polyxene spoused shal here be slayne By Pyrrhus hand, and al my tombe her bloud shal ouerstayne. This sayd, he strayght sanke downe agayne to Plutoes deepe region, The earth then cloasd, the hollow caues were vanished and gon Therwith the wether waxed clere, the raging wyndes did slake, The tombling seas began to rest and al the tempest brake. THE THIRD SCENE. Pyrrhus, Agamemnon, Calchas. What tyme our sayles we should haue spread, vppon Sygeon Seas, With swift returne from long delay, to seeke our homeward wayes. Achilles rose whose onely hand, hath geuen Greekes the spoyle. Of Troia sore annoyde by him, and leueld with the soyle, With speede requiting his abode and former long delay, At Scyros yle, and Lesbos both amid the Ægæon sea. Til he came here in doubt it stoode of fall or sure estate, Then though ye hast to graunt his wil ye shall it geue to late. Now haue the other captaynes all the pryce of their manhood, What els reward for his prowesse then her al onely blood? Are his desertes thinke you but light, that when he might haue fled, And passing Pelyus yeares in peace, a quiet life haue led, Detected yet his mothers craftes, forsooke his womans weede, And with his weapons prou'd himselfe a manly man indeede: The King of Mysya, Telephus that woulde the Greekes withstand, Comming, to Troy, forbidding vs the passage of his land: To late repenting to haue felt. Achilles heauy stroke Was glad to craue his health agayne where he his hurt had tooke For when his sore might not be salu'd as told Appollo playne, Except the speare that gaue the hurte, restoared help agayne. Achilles plasters cur'd his cuttes, and sau'd the King aliue: His hand both might and mercy knew to slay and then reuyne. When Thebes fel: Eetion saw it and might it not withstand, The captiue King could nought redresse the ruin of his land. Lyrnesus litle likewyse felt his hand and downe it fill, With ruine ouerturned like from top of haughty hil. And taken Bryseys land it is and prisoner is she caught The cause of strife betwene the Kinges is Chryses come to naught. Tenedos yle wel knowne by fame and fertile soyle he tooke That fostreth fat the Thracian flockes and sacred Cilla shooke What bootes to blase the brute of him whom trumpe of fame doth show, Through all the coastes where Caicus floud with swelling stream doth flow? The ruthful ruine of these realmes so many townes bet downe, Another man would glory count and worthy great renowne. But thus my father made his way and these his iourneyes are, And battayles many one he fought whyle warre he doth prepare. As wisht I may his merits more shall yet not this remayne. Wel knowne and counted prayse enough that he hath Hector slayne Duryng whose life the Grecians al might neuer take the towne, My father onely vanquist Troy, and you haue pluct it downe. Reioyce I may your parentes prayse and brute abroade his actes, It seemeth the sonne to follow well his noble fathers factts, In sight of Priam Hector slayne, and. Memnon both they lay. With heauy theere his parentes wayld to mourne his dying day. Himselfe abhord his handy worke in fight that had them slayne, The Sonnes of Goddes Achilles knew were borne to die agayne The woman queene of Amazons that greu'd the Greekes ful sore. Is turnd to flight then ceast our feare wee dread their bowes no more. If ye wel waigh his worthynes Achilles ought to haue Though he from Argos or Mycenas would a Uirgin craue, Doubt ye herein? allow ye not that straight his wil be done. And count ye cruel Pryams bloud to geue to Peleus sonne? For Helen sake your owne childes bloud appeasd Dianas yre A wonted thing and done ere this it is that I require. Ag. The onely fault of youth it is not to refraine his rage The Fathers bloud already sturres in Pryams wanton age: Somtime Achilles grieuous checkes I bare with pacient hart, The more thou mayst, the more thou oughtst to suffer in good part Wherto would yee with slaughtred bloud a noble spirit stayne? Thinke what is meete the Greekes to do, and Troyans to sustayne. The proude estate of tyranny may neuer long endure. The King that rules with modest meane of safety may be sure. The higher step of princely state that fortune hath vs signd The more behou'th a happy man humility of mynd And dread the chaunge that cha?ce may bring, whose gifts so sone be lost And chiefly then to feare the Gods, whyle they the fauour most. In beating downe that warre hath wonne, by proofe I haue ben taught, What pompe and pride in twinke of eye, may fall and come to naught. Troy made me fierce &amp; proude of mynde, Troy makes me frayd withal: The Grekes now stand wher Troy late fel, ech thing may haue his fal, Sometyme I graunt I did my selfe, and Sceptors proudly beare, The thing that might aduaunce my hart makes me the more to feare Thou Priam perfit proofe presentst thou art to mee eftsones: A cause of pride, a glasse of feare a mirrour for the nones, Should I accoumpt the sceptors ought, but glorious vanity Much like the borowed brayded hayre, the face to beautify. One sodayne chaunce may turne to naught, and mayme the might of men With fewer then a thousand shippes, and yeares in lesse then ten. Not she that guydes the slipper wheele of fate, doth so delay: That she to al possession grauntes, of ten yeares setled stay. With leaue of Greece I wil confesse, I would haue wonne the towne But not with ruine thus extreme to see it beaten downe. But loe the battel made by night and rage of feruent mynd, Could not abyde the brydling bitte that reason had assignd. The happy sword once staind with blood vnsatiable is, And in the darke the feruent rage doth strike thee more amis. Now are we wreakt on Troy so much let all that may remayne. A Uirgin borne of Princes bloud for offring to be slayne And geuen be to slayne the tombe and ashes of the ded, And vnder name of wedlocke see the guiltles bloud be shed, I wil not graunt for myne should bee thereof both fault and blame. Who when he may, forbiddeth not offence: doth wil the same. Pyr. And shall his sprights haue no reward their angers to appeyse? Aga. Yes very great, for all the world shall celebrate his prayse, And landes vnknowen that neuer saw. the man so preysd by fame, Shall heate and kepe for many yeares the glory of his name. If bloudshed vayle his ashes ought strike of an Oxes hed, And let no bloud that may be cause of mothers teares, be shed. What furious fransy may this be that doth your will so leade, This earnest carefull sutte to make in trauayle for the dead? Let not such enuy towarde your father in your heart remayne, That for his sacrifice yee would procure an others payne, Pyr. Proude tirant, while prosperity thy stomacke doth aduaunce, And cowardly wretch that shrinks for feare in case of fearefull chaunce. Is yet agayne thy breast enflamde, with brand of Venus might? Wilt thou alone so oft depriue Achilles of his right? This hand shall giue the sacrifice, the which if thou withstand. A greater slaughter shall I make, and worthy Pyrrhus hand. And now to long from Princes slaughter doth my hand abide, And meete it were that Polyxene were layde by Priams side. Aga. I not deny, but Pyrrhus chiefe renowne, in warre is this, That Pryam slaine with cruell sworde, to your father humbled is. Pyr. My fathers foes we haue them known, submit themselues humbly, And Pryam presently yee wot, was glad to craue mercy. But thou for feare not stout to rule, liest close from foes vp shit: While thou to Aiax, and Vlysses, dost thy will commit. Aga. But needes I must, and will confesse, your father did not feare: When burnt our fleete with Hectors brands, &amp; Greeks they slaughtred weare. While loytring then a loofe he lay, vnmindfull of the fight. In steede of armes with scratch of quill, his sounding harp to smight. Pyr. Great Hector then despising thee, Achilles songes did feare: And Thessale ships in greatest dread, in quiet peace yet weare. Aga. For why aloofe the Thessale fleete, they lay from Troyans handes, And well your father might haue rest, he felt not Hectors brandes. Pir. Well seemes a noble king to giue an other king reliefe. Aga. Why hast thou then a worthy king berieued of his life? Pyr. A poinct of mercy sometime is, what liues in care to kill. Aga. But now your mercy mooueth you a virgins death to will. Pyr. Account yee cruell now her death whose sacrifice I craue. Your own deere daughter once yee knowe, your selfe to th'aulters gaue. Aga. Naught els could saue the Greekes fr? seas, but th'only bloud of her: A king before his children ought, his countrey to prefer. Pyr. The law doth spare no captiues bloud nor wil'th their death to stay Aga. That which the law doth not forbid, yet shame doth oft say nay. Pyr. The conquerour what thing he list, may lawfully fulfill. Aga. So much the lesse he ought to list, that may do what he will. PYR. Thus boast ye these as though in all ye onely bare the stroke: When Pyrrhus loosed hath the greekes, from bond of ten yeres yoke. A. Hath Scyros yle such stomaks bred? P. No bretherns wrath it knoes. AG. Beset about it is with waue. PYR. The seas it do enclose. Thyestes noble stocke I know and Atreus eke full well, And of the bretherns dire debate, perpetuall fame doth tell. AG. And thou a bastard of a mayde, defloured priuely. Whom (then a boy) Achilles gat, in filthy lechery. Pyr. The same Achill that doth possesse, the raigne of Gods aboue, With Thetys seas: with Æacus sprights, the starred heauen with Ioue Aga. The same Achilles that was slaine, by stroke of Paris hande. Pyr. The same Achilles, whom no god, durst euer yet withstand. Aga. The stoutest man I rather would his checkes he should refraine I could them tame but all your bragges, I can full well sustaine. For euen the captiues spares my sword: let Calchas called be. If destynies require her bloud, I will thereto agree Calchas whose counsel rulde our ships, and nauy hither brought, Unlookst the poale and hast by arte the secretes thereof sought, To whome the bowelles of the beast, to whom the thunder clap, And blasyng starre with flaming traine, betokeneth what shall hap. Whose words with dearest price I bought, now tell vs by what meane The will of Gods agreeth that we returne to Greece againe. Cal. The fates apoint the Grekes to buy their waies with wonted price. And with what cost ye came to Troy, ye shal repayre to Greece With bloud ye came, with bloud ye must from hence returne againe, And where Achilles ashes lieth, the virgin shal be slaine, In seemely sort of habite, such as maydens wont ye see, Of Thessalie, or Mycenas els, what time they wedded be. With Pyrrhus hand she shal be slaine, of right it shalbe so And meete it is that he the sonne, his fathers right should do. But not this onely stayeth our shippes, our sayles may not be spred, Before a worthier bloud then thine, (Polixena) be shed, Which thirst thirst the fates, for Priames nephew, Hectors litle boy: The Grekes shal tumble hedlonge down, from highest towre in Troy. Let him there die, this onely way ye shal the gods appeas, Then spread your thousand sayles with ioy ye neede not feare the seas. Chorus. May this be true, or doth the Fable fayne, When corps is deade the Sprite to liue as yet? When Death our eies with heauy hand doth strain, And fatall day our leames of light hath shet, And in the Tombe our ashes once be set, Hath not the soule likewyse his funerall, But stil (alas) do wretches liue in thrall? Or els doth all at once togeather die? And may no part his fatal howre delay. But with the breath the soule from hence doth flie? And eke the Cloudes to vanish quite awaye, As danky shade fleeth from the poale by day? And may no iote escape from desteny, When once the brand hath burned the body? What euer then the ryse of Sunne may see, And what the West that sets the Sunne doth know. In all Neptunus raygne what euer bee, That restles Seas do wash and ouerflow, With purple waues stil tombling to and fro. Age shal consume: each thing that liuth shal die, With swifter race then Pegasus doth flie. And with what whirle, the twyse sixe signes do flie, With course as svvift as rector of the Spheares, Doth guide those glistering Globes eternally. And Hecate her chaunged hornes repeares, So drauth on death, and life of each thing vveares, And neuer may the man, returne to sight, That once hath felt the stroke of Parcas might. For as the fume that from the fyre doth passe, With tourne of hand doth vanish out of sight And swifter then the Northren Boreas With whirling blaste and storme of raging might, Driuth farre away and puttes the cloudes to flight, So fleeth the sprighte that rules our life away, And nothing taryeth after dying day. Swift is the race we ronne, at hand the marke Lay downe your hope, that wayte here ought to win, And who dreads ought, cast of thy carefull carke: Wilt thou it wot what state thou shalt be in, When dead thou art as thou hadst neuer bin. For greedy tyme it doth deuoure vs all, The world it swayes to Chaos heape to fall. Death hurtes the Corpes and spareth not the spright, And as for all the dennes of Tænare deeepe. With Cerberus kingdome darke that knowes no light, And streightest gates, that he there sittes to keepe, They Fancies are that follow folke by sleepe Such rumors vayne, but fayned lies they are, And fables like the dreames in heauy care. These three staues following are added by the translatour. O dreadful day, alas, the sory time. Is come of al the mothers ruthful woe, Astianax (alas) thy fatal line Of life is worne, to death strayght shalt thou goe, The sisters haue decreed it should be so, There may no force (alas) escape there hand, There mighty Ioue their will may not withstand, To se the mother, her tender child forsake, What gentle hart that may from teares refrayne Or whoso fierce that would no pity take, To see (alas) this guiltles infant slayne, For sory hart the teares myne eyes do stayne To thinke what sorrow shall her hart oppresse, Her litle child to leese remedilesse, The double cares of Hectors wife to wayle, Good Ladies haue your teares in readines. And you with whom should pity most preuayle. Rue on her griefe: bewayle her heauines. With sobbing hart, lament her deepe distresse, When she with teares shall take leaue of her son, And now (good Ladies) heare what shall be done.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE THIRD ACTE. Andromacha. Senex. Vlisses. Alas ye careful company, why hale ye thus your hayres? Why beate you so your boyling breasts and stayne your eyes with tears? The fall of Troy is new to you but vnto me not so, I haue foreseene this careful case ere this tyme long agoe When fierce Achilles Hector slew and drew the Corpes aboute Then then me thought I wist it well, that Troy should come to naught In sorrowes sonke I senceles am and wrapt (alas) in woe, But sone except this babe me held, to Hector would I goe This seely foole my stomacke tames amid my misery, And in the howre of heauiest happes permittes me not to die, This onely cause constraynes me yet the gods for him to pray With tract of tyme prolonges my payne, delayes my dying day: He takes from me the lacke of feare the onely fruit of ill. For while he liues yet haue I left wherof to feare me still. No place is left for better chaunce with worst wee are opprest To feare (alas) and see no hope is worst of all the rest. Sen. What sodayne feare thus moues your mynd, &amp; vexeth you so sore? And. Stil stil (alas) of one mishap there ryseth more and more, Nor yet the doleful destenies of Troy be come to end. Sen. And what more grieuous chaunces yet prepare the Gods to send? Andr. The caues and dennes of hel be rent for Troyans greater feare And from the bottoms of their tombes the hidden sprightes appeare. May none but Greekes alone from hel returne to life agayne? Would God the fates would finish soone the sorrowes I sustayne. Death thankful were, a common care the Troyans all oppresse, But me (alas) amaseth most the feareful heauines. That all astonied am for dreade, and horrour of the sight: That in my sleepe appeard to mee by dreame this latter night. Sen. Declare what sightes your dream hath shewd, &amp; tell what doth you feare And. Two parts of al the silent night almost then passed were. And then the cleare seuen clustered beams of starres: were fallen to rest And first the sleepe so long vnknowne my wearyed eyes opprest. If this be sleepe the astonied mase of mynd in heauy moode, When sodaynly before myne eyes the spright of Hector stoode. Not like as he the Greekes was wont to battail to require: Or when amid the Grecians shippes, he threw the brandes of fyre. Nor such as raging on the Grees, with slaughtring stroake had slayne And bare indeede the spoyles of him that did Achilles fayne. His countenaunce not now so bright, nor of so liuely cheere, But sad and heauy like to owres and clad with vgly hayre It did me good to see him though when shaking then his head: Shake of thy sleepe in hast he sayd, and quickly leaue thy bed: Conuay into some secrete place our sonne (O faythful wife) This onely hope there is to helpe find meane to saue his life. Leaue of thy piteous tears he sayd, dost thou yet wayle for Troy? Would God it lay on Ground ful flat so ye might saue the boy. Up stirre he sayd thy selfe in hast conuay him priuily. Saue if ye may the tender bloud of Hectors progeny Then strayght in trembling feare I wakt and rold myne eyes aboute Forgettyng long my child pore wretch, and after Hector sought. But strayght (alas) I wist not how the Spright away did passe, And mee forsooke before I could my husband once embrasse. O childe, O noble fathers broode and Troians only ioy, O worthy seede of thauncient bloud, and beaten house of Troy. O ymage of thy father loe, thou liuely bearst his face, This countnaunce to my Hector had, and euen such was his pace. The pitch of all his body such, his handes thus would he beare. His shoulders high his threatning browes, euen such as thine they were O sonne: begot to late for Troy, but borne to soone for mee, Shal euer tyme yet come agayne, and happy daye may be, That thou mayst once reuenge and build agayne the towres of Troy, And to the towne and Troyans both restore their name with ioy? But why do I (forgettyng state of present destenye), So great thinges wish? enough for captiues is to liue only: Alas what priuy place is left my litle childe to hide? What seate so secret may be found where thou maist safely bide? The towre that with the walles of gods so valiaunt was of might, Through all the world so notable, so flourishing to sight, Is turnde to dust: and fire hath al consumd'e that was in Troy, Of all the towne not so much now is left to hide the boy. What place were best to choose for guile, the holy tombe is heere, That thenemies sword will spare to spoile wher sythe my husband deere. Which costly worke his father builte, king Pryame liberall: And it vp raisde with charges great, fo Hectors funerall. Herein the bones and ashes both of Hector (loe) they lie, Best is that I commit the sonne to his fathers custodie. A colde and fearefull sweat doth runne, through out my members all, Alas I carefull wretch do feare, what chaunce may thee befall, Sen. Hide him away: this onely way hath saued many more, To make the enmies to beleue, that they were dead before. He wil be sought: scant any hope remaineth of safenes, The paise of his nobility doth him so sore oppres: Andr. What way wer best to worke: that none our doings might bewray Sen. Let none beare witnes what ye do remoue them all away. Andr. What if the enmies aske me: where Astianax doth remaine? Sen. Then shall ye boldelie answere make that he in Troy was slaine. Andr. What shal it helpe to haue him hid? at length they will him finde. Sen At first the enmies rage is fierce, delay doth slake his minde. Andr. But what preuailes, since free from feare we may him neuer hide? Sen. Let yet the wretch take his defence, me carelesse there to bide. And. What land vnknowne out of the way what vnfrequented place May keepe thee safe? who ayds our feare? who shall defend our case? Hector, Hector that euermore thy friendes didst wel defend Now chiefly ayde thy wyfe and child and vs some succour send. Take charge to keepe and couer close the treasures of thy wyfe, And in thy Ashes hyde thy sonne preserue in tombe his life. Draw neare my Childe vnto the Tombe, why fliest thou backward so? Thou takst great scorne to lurke in dens thy noble hart I know. I see thou art asham'd to feare shake of thy princely mynd, And beare thy breast as thee behoues as chaunce hath thee assynd. Behold our case: and se what flocke remayneth now of Troy The tombe: I woeful captiue wretch and thou a seely boy, But yeeld we must to sory fates thy chaunce must breake thy breast, Go to, creepe vnderneath thy fathers holy seats to rest. If ought the fates may wretches helpe thou hast thy sauegard there. If not: already then pore foole thou hast thy sepulchere. Sen. The tombe him closely hides: but least your feare should him betray Let him here lie and farre from hence goe ye some other way. Andr. The lesse he feares that feares at hand, and yet if neede be so, If ye thinke meete a litle hence for safety let vs goe. Sen. A litle whyle keepe silence now refrayne your plaint and crie, His cursed foote now hether moues the Lord of Cephalie. And, Now open earth, and thou my spouse fr? Stix rend vp ye ground, Deepe in thy bosome hyde thy sonne that he may not be found. Vlysses comes with doubtful pace and chaunged countenaunce He knittes in hart deceiptful craft for some more grieuous chaunce. Vl. Though I be made the messenger of heauy newes to you, This one thing first I shal desyre that ye take this for true. That though the wordes come from my mouth, and I my messuage tell Of truth yet are they none of myne ye may beleue me wel. It is the word of al the Greekes, and they the authors be, Whom Hectors bloud doth yet forbid their countries for to see. Our careful trust of peace vnsure doth stil the Greekes detayne, And euermore our doubtful feare yet drawth vs backe agayne. And suffreth not our wearyed handes, our weapons to forsake, In child yet of Andromacha, while Troyans comfort take. An. And sayth your Augure Calchas so? Vli. Though Calchas nothing sayde Yet Hector telles it vs himselfe, of whose seede are we frayde. The worthy bloud of noble men oft tymes we se it playne, Doth after in their heires succede and quickly springes agayne. For so the hornles youngling yet, of high and sturdy brste, With lofty necke and braunched brow, doth shortly rule the rest. The tender twig that of the lopped stocke doth yet remayne, To match the tree that bare the bough, in time startes vp again With equall top to former wood the roume it doth supply, And spreads on soyle alow the shade, to heauen his braunches hye. Thus of one sparke by chaunce yet left it hapneth so ful oft. The fyre hath quickly caught his force and flamth agayn aloft. So feare we yet least Hectors bloud might rise er it be long, Feare castes in all thextremity and oft interprets wrong. If ye respect our case ye may not blame these old soldiars Though after years and monthes twice fiue, they feare again the wars. And other trauails dreadyng Troy, not yet to be wel wonne, A great thing doth the Grecyans moue, the feare of Hectors son. Rid vs of feare, this slayeth our fleete, and pluckes vs backe agayne, And in the hauen our nauy stickes, til Hectors bloud be slayne. Count me not feerce for that by fates I Hectors sonne require, For I as wel if chaunce it would Orestes should desyre. But since that needes it must be so, beare it with pacient hart: And Suffer that which Agamemnon suffred in good part. And. Alas my child would God thou wert yet in thy mothers hand. And that I knew what destenies thee held or in what land. For neuer should the mothers fayth her tender child forsake: Though through my breast the enmies al, their cruell weapons strake. Nor though the Greekes with pinching bandes of yron my handes had bound, Or els in feruent flame of fyre beset my body rounde. But now my litle Child (pore wretch alas) where might he bee? Alas, what cruel desteny what chaunce hath hapt to thee? Art thou yet ranging in the fieldes and wandrest ther abroad? Or smothred else in dusty smoake of Troy: or ouertroad? Or haue the Greekes thee slayne (alas) and saught to see thy bloud? Or torne art thou with iawes of beastes? or cast to foules for foode? Vl. Dissemble not, hard is for thee Vlisses to deceaue, I can ful wel the mothers craftes and subtilty perceaue. The pollecy of Goddesses Vlisses hath vndone, Set al these fayned wordes assyde, tel mee where is thy sonne? An. Wher is Hector? where al the rest that had with Troy their fall Where Priamus? you aske for one but I require of all. Vl. Thou shalt constrayned be to tell the thing thou dost deny. And. A happy chaunce were Death to her that doth desyre to dye. Vli. Who most desires to die, would faynest liue when death drawth on, These noble wordes with present feare of death woulde soone be gone. And. Vlisses if ye wil constrayne Andromacha with feare, Threaten my life for now to dye my cheefe desyre it were. Vl. With stripes with fyre tormenting death we wil the truth out wrest And dolour shal thee force to tel the secrets of thy brest. And what thy hart hath depest hid for payne thou shalt expresse, Oft tymes thextremity preuayles much more then gentlenesse, And. Set me in midst of burning flame with woundes my body rent, Use al the meanes of cruelty that ye may al inuent. Proue me with thirst and hunger both, and euery torment trye, Pearce through my sides with burning yrons in prison let me lie. Spare not the worst ye can deuyse (if ought be worse then this) Yet neuer get ye more of me. I wot not where he is. Vli. It is but vayne to hyde the thinge that strayght ye wil deteckt No feares may moue the mothers hart, she doth them al neglect. This tender loue ye beare your child, wherin ye stand so stoute, So much more circumspectly warnth, the Greekes to looke about. Least after ten yeares tract of tyme and battell borne so farre, Some one should liue that on our children might renew the warre, As for my selfe, what Calchas sayth, I would not feare at all But on Telemachus I dread, the smart of warres would fall And. Now will I make Vlisses glad and all the Greekes also, Needes must thou woeful wretch confesse declare thy hidden woe. Reioyce ye sonnes of Atreus there is no cause of dread. Be glad Vlisses tell the Greekes that Hectors sonne is dead. Vl. By what assurance proues thou that? how shal we credite thee: And. What euer thing the enmies hand may threaten hap to me Let speedy fates me slay forthwith, and earth me hyde at ones And after death from tombe agayne, remoue yet Hectors bones, Except my sonne already now, do rest among the dead. And that except Astianax into his tomb be led. Vliss. Then fully are the fates fulfild with Hectors childes disceace. Now shal I beare the Grecians word, of sure and certayne peace. Vlisses why what dost thou now: the Greekes wil euery chone, Beleeue thy wordes, whom creditst thou? the mothers tale alone. Thinkst thou for sauegard of her child the mother wil not lye? And dread the more the worse mischaunce to geue her sonne to die? Her fayth she byndes with bond of oth, the truth to verify, What thing is more of weight to feare, then so to sweare and lye? Now call thy craftes togeather al, bestirre thy wittes and mynd, And shew thy selfe Vlisses now, the truth herein to find. Search wel thy mothers mynd: behold shee weepes and wayleth out, And here and ther with doubtful pace, she raungeth al aboute, Her careful ears she doth apply to harken what I say, More frayd shee seemes then sorrowful. Now worke some wily way. For now most neede of wit there is and crafty pollecy, Yet once agayne by other meanes I wil the mother trye. Thou wretched woman maist reioyce, that dead he is: (alas) More doleful death by destenie for him decreed ther was. From Turrets top to haue bene cast and cruelly bene slayne. Which onely towre of all the rest doth yet in Troy remayne. And. My spright failth me, my limmes do quake, fear doth my wits c?founde And as the Ise congeals with frost, my bloud with could is bound. Vl. She tr?bleth loe: this way, this way I wil the truth out wreaste, The mothers fear detecteth all the secrets of her breast: I wil renew her feare goe sirs bestir ye spedely To seeke this enmye of the Greekes where euer that he lie. Wel done he wil be found at length, goe to stil seke him out, Now shal he dye. what dost thou feare why dost thou looke about? And Would God that any cause there were yet left that might me fray, My hart at last now all is lost hath layd all feare away. Vliss. Sins that your child now hath ye say already suffred death, And with his bloud we may not purge the hostes as Calchas sayth. Our fleete passe not (as wel inspired doth Calchas prophecy) Till Hectors ashes cast abroad the waues may pacify, And tombe be rent now sins the boy hath skapt his desteny. Needes must we breake this holy tombe wher Hectors ashes lie. An. What shal I do? my mynd distracted is with double feare. On thone my sonne, on thother syde my husbandes ashes deare, Alas which part should moue me most, the cruel Goddes I call To witnes with me in the truth, and Ghostes that guide thee all Hector that nothing in my sonne is else that pleaseth me. But thou alone God graunt him life he might resemble thee: Shal Hectors ashes drowned bee? hide I such cruelty, To see his bones cast in the Seas? yet let Astyanax die, And canst thou wretched mother bide, thyne owne childes death to see? And suffer from the hie towres top that headlong throwne he be? I can and wil take in goad part, his death and cruel payne, So that my Hector after death be not remou'd agayne. The boy that life and sences hath may feele his payne and dye, But Hector lo his death hath plast at rest in tombe to lie What dost thou stay? determine which thou wilt preserue of twayne. Art thou in doubt? saue this: loe here thy Hector doth remayne, Both Hectors be, thone quicke of spright &amp; drawing toward his str?gth And one that may perhaps reuenge his fathers death at length. Alas I cannot saue them both: I thinke that best it were, That of the twayne I saued him that doth the Grecians feare. Vl. It shalbe done that Calchas words to vs doth prophecye, And now shal all the sumptuous worke be throwne downe vtterly An That once ye sold? Vl. I wil it all from toppe to bottome rend. An. The fayth of Goddes I call vppon Achilles vs defend, And Pyrrhus ayd thy fathers right. Vl. This tombe abroad shall lye: An. O mischiefe, neuer durst the Greekes show yet such cruelty. Ye straine the temples and the Gods that most haue fauourd you, The dead ye spare not, on their tombes your fury rageth now. I wil their weapons all resist my selfe with naked hand, Theyre of hart shal geue me strength their armour to withstand. As fierce as did the Amazones beate down the Greekes in fight, And Menas once enspierd with God, in sacrifyce doth smyght, With speare in hand, and while with furyous pace she treads the gro?d And wood as one in rage she strykes, and feeleth not the wound: So wil I runne on midst of them and on theyr weapons dye, And in defence of Hectors tombe among his ashes lie. Vl. Cease ye: doth rage and fury vayne of women moue ye ought? Dispatch with speede what I commaund, &amp; plucke downe al to naught. An. O slay me rather here with sword rid me out the way, Breake vp the deepe Auern, and rid my destenies delay. Rise Hector and beset thy foes, breake thou Vlisses yre, A spright art good enough for him, behold he casteth fire, And weapon shakes with mighty hand do ye not Greekes him see? Or els doth Hectors spright appear but onely vnto me Vl. Downe quight with al. An. What wilt thou suffer both thy sonnes be slayne, And after death thy husbandes bones to be remou'd agayne? Perhaps thou mayst with prayer yet appease the Grecians all. Els downe to ground the holy tombe of Hector, streight shall fal. Let rather die the childe pore wretch and let the Greekes him kil, Then father and the sonne should cause the tone the others yll. Ulisses, at thy knees I fal, and hmmbly aske mercie, These handes that no mans feete els knew, first at thy feete they lye. Take pitty on the mothers case and sorrowes of my breast, Uouchsafe my prayers to receiue and graunt me my request. And by how much the more the Goddes haue thee aduaunced hie, More easely stryke the pore estate of wretched misery. God graunt the chast bed of thy godly wyfe Penelope, May thee receiue and so agayne Laerta may thee see, And that thy sonne Telemachus may meete thee ioyfully, His graundsires yeares, and fathers witte, to passe ful happely. Take pity on the mothers teares, her litle child to saue, He is my onely comfort left, and th'onely ioy I haue. Vl. Bryng forth thy sonne and aske. THE SECOND SCENE. Andromacha, Come hither child out of the dennes to mee, Thy wretched mothers lamentable store, This Babe Vlisses (loe) this Babe is hee, That stayeth your ships and feareth you so sore. Submit thy selfe my sonne with humble hand, And worship flat on ground thy maysters feete, Thinke it no shame as now the case doth stand: The thing that Fortune wilth a wretche is meete, Forget thy worthy stocke of Kingly kynd, Thinke not on Priams great nobility, And put thy father Hector from thy mynde, Such as thy Fortune let thy stomacke bee, Behaue thy selfe as captiue bend thy Knee, And though thy griefe pearce not thy tender yeares, Yet learne to wayle thy wretched state by mee, And take ensample at thy mothers teares. Once Troy hath seene the weeping of a child, When litle Priam turnde Alcides threats, And he to whom all beastes in strength did yelde, That made his way from hel, and brake their gates His litle enmies teares yet ouercame, Priam he sayd receiue thy liberty, In seat of honor kepe thy Kingly name, But yet thy Sceptors rule more faythfully. Lo such the conquest was of Hercules. Of him yet learne your hartes to mollify, Do onely Hercles cruel weapons please, And may no end be of your cruelty? No lesse then Pryam, kneeles to thee this boy, That lieth and asketh onely life of thee. As for the rule and gouernaunce of Troy Where euer Fortune wil ther let it bee. Take mercy on the mothers ruthful teares That with their streames my cheekes do ouerflow, And spare this guiltles infantes tender yeares That humbly falleth at thy feete so lowe. THE THIRD SCENE. Vlisses, Andromacha, Astianax, Of truth the mothers greate sorow, doth moue my hart full sore. But yet the mothers of the Greekes, of neede must moue me more, To whom this boy may cause in time a great calamtie. Andr. May euer he the burnt ruines of Troy reedifie? And shall these handes in time to come, ereckt the towne againe? If this be th onely helpe we haue, there doth no hope remain For Troy, we stand not now in case to cause your feare of mynde, Doth ought auayle his fathers force, or stocke of noble kinde? His fathers heart abated was, he drawen the walles abought. Thus euil haps, the haughtiest heart at lengh they bring to nought, If ye wil needes oppresse a wretch what thing more grieuous were Then on his noble neck he should the yoke of bondage bere? To serue in life doth any man this to a King denye? Vl. Not Vlisses with his death, but Calchas prophecy. An. O false inuentor of deceipt and hainous cruelty, By manhode of whose hand in warre no man did euer dye. But by disceipt and crafty trayne of mynd that mischiefe seekes, Before this tyme ful many one dead is, yea of the Greekes, The Prophets wordes and guiltles Gods saist thou my sonne require, Nay: mischiefe of thy breast it is, thou dost his death desyre. Thou night souldier, and stout of hart a litle child to slay. This enterprise thou takste alone and that by open day. Vl. Vlisses manhood wel to Greekes to much to you is knowne, I may not spend the tyme in wordes, our Nauy wil be gone And. A little stay, while I my last farewel geue to my child, And haue with oft embracing him my greedy sorrowes fild. Vli. Thy grieuous sorrowes to redresse, would God it lay in mee, But at thy wil to take delay of tyme I graunt it thee. Now take thy last leaue of thy Sonne, and fil thy selfe with teares. Oft tymes the weeping of the eyes, the inward griefe out weares. An. O deere, O sweete, thy mothers pledge, farewel my onely ioy, Farewel the flowre of honor left of beaten howse of Troy. O Troyans last calamity and feare to Grecians part Farewel thy mothers onely hope, and vayne comfort of hart. Oft wisht I thee thy fathers strength and halfe thy graundsires yeares But all for naught the Gods haue all dispoynted our desires. Thou neuer shalt in regal court thy sceptors take in hand, Nor to thy people geue decrees nor leade with law thy land. Nor yet thine enmies ouercome by might of handy stroke, Nor sende the conquerde nations all vnder thy seruile yoke. Thou neuer shalt beat downe in fight, and Greekes with sword pursew, Nor at thy Charyot Pyrrhus plucke, as Achill Hector drew And neuer shal these tender handes thy weapons weild and wrest, Thou neuer shalt in woods pursue the wyld and mighty beast. Nor as accustom'd is by guyse and sacrifice in Troy, With measure swift: betweene the aulters shalt thou daunce with ioy. O grieuous kind of cruel death that doth remayne for thee, More woeful thinges then Hectors death the walles of Troy shall see. Vliss Now breake of al thy mothers tears I may no more tyme spende. The grieuous sorrowes of thy hart wil neuer make an end. An. Vlisses spare as yet my teares and graunt awhyle delay, To close his eyes yet with my handes er he depart away. Thou diest but young: yet feard thou art thy Troy doth wayte for thee, Goe noble hart thou shalt agayne the noble Troyans see. Asti. Helpe me mother? An. Alas my child why tak'st thou holde by me? In vayne thou calst where helpe none is I can not succour thee. As when the litle tender beast that heares the Lyon crye, Straight for defence he seekes his damme, &amp; crouching downe doth lye, The cruel beast when once remoued is the damme away, In greedy iaw with rauening bit doth snatch the tender pray So strayght the enmies wil thee take, and from my side thee beare. Receiue my kisse and teares pore childe, receiue my rented hayre. Depart thou hence now ful of mee, and to thy father goe, Salute my Hector in my name and tel him of my woe Complayne thy mothers griefe to him if former cares may moue, The sprightes: and that in funerall flame they leese not all their loue. O cruel Hector suffrest thou thy wyfe to be opprest? With bond of Grecians heauy yoke and liest thou still at rest? Achilles rose: take here agayne my teares and rented heare, And (al that I haue left to send) this kisse thy father beare. Thy coat yet for my comfort leaue, the tomb hath touched it If of his ashes ought here lye Ile seeke it euery whit. Vl. There is no measure of thy teares I may no lenger stay, Deferre no further our returne breake of our shippes delay. Chorus altered by the translatour. O Ioue that leadst the lampes of fire, and deckst vvith flaming starres the skye, VVhy is it euer thy desyre to care their course so orderly? That novve the frost the leaues hath vvorne &amp; novv the spr?g doth close the tree. Novv fiery Leo rypes the corne, and stil the soyle should chaunged be? But vvhy art thou that all dost guide, betvvene vvhose hands the poale doth svvay, And at vvhose vvil the Orbs do slyde, careles of mans estate alvvay? Regarding not the goodmans case, nor caryng hovv to hurt the yll. Chaunce beareth rule in euery place and turneth mans estate at vvill. She geues the vvronge the vpper hand the better part she doth oppresse, She makes the highest lovv to stand, her Kingdome all is orderlesse. O parfite profe of her frailty, the princely tovvres of Troybeat dovvne, The flovvre of Asia here ye see vvith turne of hand quight ouerthrovvne. The ruthful ende of Hectors son, vvh? to his death the Greekes haue led, His fatall hovvre is come and gone, and by this tyme the Child is ded: Yet still (alas) more cares encrease, O Troyans doleful destenie, Fast doth approach the maydes decease, and novv Polixena shall die.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE FOVRTH ACTE. Helena, Andromacha, Hecuba What euer woeful wedding yet, were cause of funerall, Of wayling, teares, bloud, slaughter els or other mischiefes all, A worthy match for Helena, and meete for me it ware, My wedding torch hath bene the cause of al The Troyans care. I am constraynd to hurt them yet, after their ouerthrow, The false and fayned mariages of Pyrrhus must I showe. And geue the mayde the Greekes attyre and by my pollecy: Shal Paris sister be betrayd and by disceypt shal die. But let her be beguiled thus, the lesse should be her payne If that vnware without the feare of death: she might be slayne. What ceasest thou the wil of Greekes, and messuage to fulfill? Of hurt constraynd the fault returnth to th'auter of the ill. O noble Uirgin of the famous house and stocke of Troy, To thee the Grecians haue me sent I bring thee newes of ioy, The Gods rue on thy afflicted state more merciful they bee, A greate and happy maryage loe, they haue prepard for thee. Thou neuer should if Troy had stoode, so nobly wedded be, Nor Priam neuer could prefer thee to so hie degree. Whom flowre of all the Grecians name the prince of honour hie, That beares the Scepters ouer all, the lande of Thessaly Doth in the law of wedlocke chose, and for his wyse require. To sacred rightes of lawful bed, doth Pyrrhus thee desyre: Loe Thetis great with al the rest, of Gods that guide by sea. Each one shall thee accompt as theirs and ioy by wedding day. And Peleus shal thee daughter call when thou art Pirrhus wyfe, And Nereus shall accompt thee his the space of all thy life. Put of thy monrning garment now, this regall vesture weare Fogret henceforth thy captiue state and seemly broyd thy hayre. Thy fall hath lift thee higher vp, and doth thee more aduaunce Oft to be taken in the warre doth bring the better chaunce An. This ill the Troyans neuer knew in all their griefs and payne Before this tyme ye neuer made vs to reioyce in vayne. Troy towres geue light, O seemely tyme for mariage to be made, Who would refuse the wedding day that Helayne doth perswade? The Plague and ruine of each parte behold dost thou not see, These tombes of noble men, and how their bones here scattered bee? Thy brydebed hath bene cause of this for thee all these be ded For thee the bloud of Asia both and Europe hath bene shed. When thou in ioy and pleasure both the fighting folke from farre, Hast viewde: in doubt to whom to wish the glory of the warre. Goe to, prepare the mariages, what neede the Torches light? Behold the Towres of Troy do shine with brands that blase ful bright. O Troyans all set to your handes, this wedlocke celebrate: Lament this day with woeful cry and teares in seemly rate. Hel. Though care do cause the want of wit, and reasons rule denye, And heauy hap doth ofttymes hate his mates in misery Yet I before most hateful iudge dare wel defend my part, That I of all your greuous cares sustayne the greatest smart. Andromacha for Hector weepes, for Priam Hecuba, For onely Paris priuily bewayleth Helena. A hard and grieuous thing it is captiuity to beare, In Troy that yoke I suffred long a prisoner whole ten yeare. Turnd are the fates, Troy beaten downe, to Greece I must repeare, The natiue countrey to haue lost is ill, but worse to feare. For dread therof you neede not care your euilles all be past, On me both partes wil vengeance take al lightes to me at last. Whom each man prisoner takes God wot shee standes in slipper stay, And me not captiue made by lot yet Paris led away, I haue bene cause of all these wars, and then your woes were wrought, When first your shippes the Spartayn Seas &amp; land of Grecia sought. But if the Goddesse wild it so that I their pray should be, And for reward to her beautyes iudge shee had appoynted me, Then pardon Paris: thinke this thing in wrathful iudge doth lie, The sentence Monelaus geues, and he this case shall trye. Now turne thy playntes Andromacha, and weepe for Polyxeyne Mine eyes for sorrowes of my hart theyr teares may not refrayne. An. Alas, what care makes Heleyn weepe? what griefe doth she lament? Declare what craftes Vlisses castes, what mischiefe hath he sent? Shall shee from height of Idey hil be hedlong tombled downe? Or else out of the turrets toppe in Troy shal she be throwne? Or wil they cast her from the clieues into Sygeon seas? In bottom of the surging waues to end her ruthful days? Show what thy countnaunce hides and tell the secrets of thy breast: Some woes in Pyrhus wedding are farre worse then all the rest. Go to, geue sentence on the mayd, pronounce her desteny: Delude no longer our mishappes, we are prepard to die. H. Would God the'xpo?der of the Gods would geue his dome so right That I also on poynt of sword might leese the lothsome light, Or at Achilles tombe with stroake of Pyrrhus hand be slayne: And beare a part of al thy fates O wretched Polixeyne. Whom yet Achilles woeth to wed, and where his ashes lie, Requireth that thy bloud be shed, and at his tombe to die. An. Behold loe how her noble mynd of Death doth gladly heare, She deckes her selfe: her regal weede in seemely wyse to weare, And to her head she settes her hand the broyded hayre to lay, To wed she thought it Death, to die she thinkes a wedding day But help? (alas) my mother sounds to heare her daughters death, Aryse plucke vp your heart and take agayne the panting breath. Alacke good mother how slender stay, that doth thy life sustayne? A little thinge shall happy thee thou art almost past payne. Her breath returnes: she doth reuyue, her lims their life do take. So see when wretches fayne would die, how death doth them forsake. Hec. Doth yet Achilles liue (alas) to work the Troyans spight? Doth he rebell agaynst vs yet? O hand of Paris light. The very tombe and ashes loe, yet thirsteth for our bloud, A happy heape of children late on euery syde mee stoode. It wearied me to deale the mothers kisse among them al, The rest are lost, and this alone now doth me mother call. Thou onely child of Hecuba, a comfort left to me. A slayer of my sory state and shall I now leese thee? Depart O wretched soule, and from this carefull carcas flie, And ease me of such ruthfull fates, to see my daughter die. My weepyng wets (alas) my eyes, and staines them ouer al, And downe my cheekes the sodeine streames and showres of teares do fal. But thou deare daughter maist be glad, Cassandra would reioyse, Or Hectors wife thus wed to be if they might haue their choyse. And. We are the wretches Hecuba in cursed case we stande. Whom straight the shippe shal tosse by seas into a forraine land. But as for Heleyns grieues be gone and turned to the best, She shall againe her natyue countrey se and liue at rest. Hele. Ye would the more enuy my state if ye might know your owne, Andr. And grouth there yet more griefe to me that erst I haue not known? Hele. Such masters must ye serue as doth by chaunce of lots befal. Andr. Whose seruaunt am I then become whom shall I maister call? Hele. By lot ye fall to Pyrhus hands you are his prisoner. Andr Cassandra is happy, fury saues perhaps and Phœbus her. Hele. Chiefe kinge of Greekes Cassandra keepes and his captiue is shee. Hec. Is any one amonge them all that prysoner would haue me? Hele You chaunsed to Ulysses are his pray ye are become. Hec. Alas what cruell, dyre and yrefull dealer of the dome. What god vniust doth so deuide, the captiues to their lordes? What grieuous arbiter is he? that to such choyce accordes, What cruel hand to wretched folke, so euil fates hath caste? Who hath amonge Achilles armour, Hectors mothers plaste? Now am I captiue, and beset with all calamitie. My bondage grieues me not, but him to serue it shameth mee. He that Achilles spoyles hath won, shall Hectors also haue: Shall barraine lande enclosde with seas receiue my boanes in graue? Leade me Ulysses where thou wylt, leade me. I make no stay, My master I, and me my fates, shall follow euery way. Let neuer calme come to the seas, but let them rage with winde, Come fire and sword, mine owne mischaunce and Priams let me finde. In meane time haps this deepe distres my cares can know no calme: I ran the race with Priamus, but he hath won the Palme, But Pyrrhus comes with swiftned pace &amp; thretning browes doth wrest. What stayste thou Pyrrhus? strike thy sword now through this woful brest. And both at ones the parents of thy fathers wife now slay, Murderer of age, likes thee her bloud? he draw my daughter away Defile the gods and staine the sprights, of hel with slaughtred bloud, To aske your mercy what auayles? our prayers do no good. The vengeance aske I on your ships, that it the gods may pleas, According to this sacrifice, to guide you on the seas. This wishe I to your thousand sayles, Gods wrath light on them all, Euen to the ship that beareth me, what euer may befall. Chorus. A comfort is to mans calamity A dolefull flocke of felowes in distres. And sweete to him that mournes in miserie To here them wayle whom sorowes like oppres In deepest care his griefe him bites the les, That his estate bewayles not all alone, But seeth with him the teares of many one. For still it is the chiefe delight in woe, And ioy of them that sonke in sorrowes are, To see like fates by fall to many moe, That may take part of all their wofull fare, And not alone to be opprest with care. There is no wight of woe that doth complayne, When all the rest do like mischaunce sustayne. In all this world if happy man were none, None (though he were) would thinke himselfe a wretch. Let once the ritch with heapes of Gold be gone, Whose hundred head his pastours ouerretch, Then would the poore mans hart begin to stretch. There is no wretch whose life him doth displease, But in respect of those that liue at ease. Sweete is to him that standes in deepe distresse, To see no man in ioyful plight to bee, Whose onely vessel wind and waue oppresse, Ful sore his chaunce bewayles and weepeth hee, That with his owne none others wracke doth see When he alone makes shipwracke one the sand, And naked falles to long desyred land. A thousande sayle who seeth to drench in Seas, With better will the storme hath ouerpast His heauy hap doth him the lesse displease When broaken boardes abroade be many cast, And shipwrackt shippes to shore they flit ful fast, With doubled waues when stopped is the floud, With heaps of them that there haue lost theyr good. Ful sore did Pirrhus Helens losse complayne, What time the leader of his flocke of shepe, Vppon his backe alone he bare them twayne, And wet his Golden lockes amid the deepe, In piteous playnt (alas) he gan to weepe. The death of her it did him deepe displease, That shipwracke made amid the drenching seas. And piteous was the playnt and heauy moode Of woful Pyrrha and eke Deucalion That nought beheld aboute them but the flould, When they of all mankynd were left alone Amid the seas ful sore they made their mone To see themselues thus left aliue in woe When neyther land they saw, nor fellowes moe. Anone these playnts and Troyans teares shall quaile, And here and there the ship them tosse by seas: When trompets sound shal warne to hoyse vp sayle, And through the waues with wind to seeke their waies Then shall these captiues goe to ende their dayes In land vnknowne: when once with hasty ore The drenching deepe they take and shunne the shore. What state of mynd shal then in wretches bee? When shore shall sinke from sight and seas aryse? When Idey hill to lurke aloofe they see? Then poynt with hand from farre wher Troia lies, Shall child and mother: talking in this wyse: Loe yonder Troy, where smoke it fumeth hie, By this the Troyans shal their countrey spie.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE FIFTH ACTE. Nuncius, Andromacha. Hecuba. O dyre, fierce, wretched, horrible, O cruell fates accurste, Of Mars his ten yeares bloudshed blows the wofulst and the worst. Alas which should I first bewayle? thy cares Andromacha? Or els lament the wretched age of woful Hecuba? Hec. What euer mans calamityes ye wayle for myne it is. I beare the smart of al their woes each other feeles but his Who euer he, I am the wretch all happes to me at last. Nun Slayne is the mayd, and from the walles of Troy the child is cast. But both (as them became) they toke their death with stomacke stout. And Declare the double slaughters then, &amp; tell the whole throughout. Nun. One towre of all the rest ye know doth yet in Troy remayne, Where Pryam wonted was to sit, and view the armies twayne. His litle Nephew eke with him to lead, and from a farre, His fathers fightes with fire and sword to show on feats of war. This towre, sometyme wel knowne by fame, and Troyans honor most. Is now with captaynes of the Greeekes, beset on euery coast. With swift recourse and from the shippes, in clustred heaps anone. Both tagge and ragge they runne to gase what thing should ther be done Some clime the hilles to seeke a place where they might see it best, Some one the rockes a tiptoe stande to ouerloke the rest. Some on their t?ples weare the pine, some beech, some crownes of bay, For garlandes torne is euery tree, that standeth in they'r way, Some from the highest mountaynes top aloofe beholdeth all. Some scale the buildinges halfe thurnt, and some the ruinous wall. Yea some there were (O mischief loe) that for the more despyghte. The tombe of Hector sits vppon beholders of the sight. With princely pace Vlisses then past through the preased band Of Greekes, King Priams litle nephew leading by the hand. The Child with vnrepyning gate past through his enmies handes, Up toward the walles, and as anone in turrets top he standes, From thence adowne his lofty lookes he cast on euery part, The neerer death more free from care he seemd, and feare of hart. Amid his foes his stomacke swelles, and fierce he was to sight, Like Tygers whelpe, that thrais in vayne wt tothles chap to bight. Alas, for pitty then each one, rew on his tender yeares, And al the route that present were, for him they shed their teares, Yea not Vlisses them restraynd, but trickling downe they fal, And onely he, wept not (poore foole) whom they bewayled al. But whyle on Gods Vlisses cald, and Calchas wordes expound, In midst of Pryams land (alas) the child leapt downe to ground. And. What cruel Calchas could or scith such slaughter take in hand? Or by the shore of Caspyan Sea, what barbarous lawles land. Busyridis to th'aulters yet no infantes bloud hath shed Nor neuer yet were children slayne fortrast of Diomed. Who shal alas in tombe thee lay, or hyde thy limmes agayne? Nu. What limmes from such a headlong fall could in a child remayne, His bodies payse throwne downe to ground, hath batred al his bones. His face, his noble fathers markes are spoyld agaynst the stones. His necke vnioynted is: his head so dasht with flint stoane stroake, That scattered is the brayne about, the scul is al to breake. Thus lieth he now dismembred corpes, deformd and all to rent. An. Loe herein doth he yet likewyse, his father represent. Nun What time the Child hath headlong falne thus from the walls of Troy, And al the Greekes th?selues bewaild ye slaughter of the Boy, Yet strayght returne they backe, and at Achilles tombe agayne The second mischiefe goe to worke the death of Polixeine. This tombe the waues of surging seas, beset the vtter side, The other part the fields encloase aboute, and pastors wyde. In vale enuyroned with hils, that round aboute do ryse, A sloape on height erected are the bankes in Theatre wyse. By al the shore then swarme the Greekes, &amp; thicke on heaps they prease Some hope that by her death they shall theyr shippes delay release. Some other ioy their enmies stocke thus beaten downe to bee: A greate part of the people, both the slaughter hate, and see. The Troyans eke no lesse frequent their owne calamityes And all affrayd, beheld the last of all their miseryes. When first proceeded torches bright as guise of wedlocke is. And author therof led the way the Lady Tindaris. Such wedlocke pray the Troyans then, God send Hermiona And would God to her husband so, restoard were Helena. Feare masd each part, but Polixeine her bashful looke downe cast: And more then earst her glittring eyes and beauty shyn'd at last. As sweetest seems then Phœbus light, when downe his beams do sway, When starres agayne with night at hand opprest the doubtful day. Astonnied much the people were, and all they her commende, And now much more then euer earst, they prays'd her at her end. Some with her beauty moued were, some with her tender yeares: Some to behold the turnes of chaunce, and how each thing thus wears. But most them moues her valiant minde, and lofty stomacke hie, So strong, so stout, so ready of hart and wel prepard to dye. Thus passe they forth and bold before King Pirrhus goeth the mayde, They pitty her, they maruel her, their hartes were all affrayde. As sone as then the hard hil top (where die she should) they trode, And hie vppon his fathers tombe the youthful Pyrrhus stoode. The manly mayd she neuer shronke one foote, nor backward drew, But boldely turnes to meete the stroke, with stoute vnchanged hew, Her corage moues eche one, and loe a strange thing monstrous like. That Pyrhus euen himselfe stoode stil, or dread and durst not strike. But as he had, his glittring sword in her to hilts vp doon, The purple bloud, at mortall wound, then gushing out spoon. Ne yet her corage her forsooke, when dieng in that stounde, She fell as the'rth should her reuenge with ireful rage to gro?d. Each people wept the Troyans first with priuy fearful crye, The Grecians eake, each one bewayld her death apparantly. This order had the sacrifyce, her bloud the tombe vp dronke, No drop remaynth aboue the ground, but downe forthwith it sonke. Hec. Now go, now goe ye Greekes, and now repayre ye safely home. With careles shippes and hoised sailes now cut the salt sea fome. The Child and Uirgin both be slaine, your battels finisht are. Alas where shal I end my age? or whether beare my care? Shal I my daughter, or my nephew, or my husband mone? My countrey els, or all at once? or else my selfe alone? My wish is death that children both and virgins fiercely takes Where euer cruel death doth hast to strike, it me forsakes, Amid the enmies weapons all, amid both sword and fyre, All night sought for, thou fleest from me, that do thee most desyre. Not flame of fyre, not fall of towre, not cruel enmies hand Hath rid my life, how neere (alas) could death to Priam stand? Nun. Now captiues all with swift recourse repayre ye to the saies, Now spread the ships their sayls abroad, &amp; forth they seeke theyr waies. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>