<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">MacCarthy, Denis Florence, 1817-1882</field>
      <field name="author_facet">MacCarthy, Denis Florence, 1817-1882</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">maccarthy denis florence 1817 1882</field>
      <field name="author_text">MacCarthy, Denis Florence, 1817-1882</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1850's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V3.0770.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1853</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:461060</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Scarf and the Flower ; A Comedy</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Scarf and the Flower ; A Comedy</field>
      <field name="title_facet">scarf and the flower</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">scarf and the flower</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Scarf and the Flower ; A Comedy</field>
      <field name="year_display">1853</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1853</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1853</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:461060&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:461060&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;MacCarthy, Denis Florence, 1817-1882&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;maccarthy denis florence 1817 1882&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Scarf and the Flower ; A Comedy&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;scarf and the flower&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1853&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1853&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;MacCarthy, Denis Florence&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1817&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1882&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Scarf and the Flower&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Comedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Charles Dolman [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1853&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3873398-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv30770&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Scarf and the Flower&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Comedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 230 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted.&lt;lb/&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: The scarf and the flower.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Comedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1853.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Unknown.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE SCARF AND THE FLOWER. A Comedy.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PERSONS REPRESENTED. THE DUKE OF FLORENCE. ENRICO, Gentleman in the Duke's service. OCTAVIO, Gentleman in the Duke's service. FABIO. PONLEVI, Servant to Enrico. LISIDA, Daughter of Fabio. CHLORIS, Daughter of Fabio. NISE, their Cousin. CELIA, a Waiting Maid. MUSICIANS, &amp;c.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE—FLORENCE.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. SCENE I. A PUBLIC PARK. Enter ENRICO and PONLEVI in travelling dresses. PONLEVI. What a joyful thing it is, After travel, to draw nigh To one's native country! ENRICO. I Ne'er have felt so great a bliss. PONLEVI. No, nor I so great a pain, Since in sight of Florence, here, After wandering far and near, At this distance we remain; Without going there to know All the news that it hath got. ENRICO. 'Tis that I may know it not That I linger here. PONLEVI. If so, I'm in doubt to praise or blame, As there may be much to fear That 'twere better not to hear, Since that most loquacious dame, Lady Absence, tattles so!— But as you, in things of weight Trust me, speak, I know your state. ENRICO. Listen then to what you know,— I saw Lisida the fair, Chloris' sister,—it is true:— PONLEVI. Yes, I know it, and that you Have no wish but lives in her. ENRICO. Since as sisters, side by side, Darts of love and of disdain, Ever joined were seen the twain In the walks, or windows wide, Which of them, in truth, I wooed, Which of them I sighed to serve, I, the secret did preserve, Thus, thy rigour, I subdued, Chloris, it of course should be Chloris, whom my service moved, Were it Chloris that I loved, Chloris would have hated me:— I loved Lisida, and she, Therefore, love for me did lose; Love doth ever thus confuse Fortunes: Chloris (woe is me!) Favoured me: there's not of course Time to tell how Fabio (Sire to both) opposed—and so I return to my discourse: She such favour thus did show Towards me, that it closed the way To my love, which hidden lay, Buried in my breast below. For I thus could neither be With one gentle lady rude, Chloris thinking that I wooed Her the first, much less that she Whom I loved, my suit should gain, Since unto her trembling breast Was her sister's love confess'd— Thus divided, hope is vain,— Coward thus of courtesy, Blind, unthanked, and full of sadness, Loving Lisida to madness, Chloris vainly loving me, One I see, the other sigh for, Worship one, and one seem wooing, Loving one, and one pursuing, One I seek, and one I die for,— Thus doth joy, divided prove, Grief remaining still entire, Lisida I still desire, Chloris still I cannot love. PONLEVI. Little trouble, if you knew, This, by Jove, would give me. ENRICO. Why, What would you have done?— PONLEVI. What, I?— I would simply love the two; And if Lisida adored me, I, for Lisida, would die, Chloris, I would bid good-bye, If I thought that she abhorred me: For beyond the fame that moves him, Or the worth a man is showing, With a woman is the knowing That another woman loves him. Enter LISIDA, CHLORIS, NISE, and CELIA, veiled. CHLORIS. Oh! how pleasant is this plain, Palace home of plants and flowers! LISIDA. In the bright, green, fresh-leaved bowers, In the sunny drops of rain, May proclaims its happy reign! ENRICO, to Ponlevi. Stay, behold who wander here! CHLORIS. No, 'tis false, this verdant sphere Can a lovelier scene display At the dawning of the day, As when the sunbeams disappear. NISE. Can the changing moments make Scenes so fair, still fairer seem? CHLORIS. Yes, Aurora's magic gleam Brighter charms than these can wake. NISE. 'Tis an error—a mistake, Thus to give the crown of light To the morn,—the starry night Is the only queen. ENRICO. Señora, Wrong not thus the fair Aurora, Like yourself, a lady bright— Being so, 'twere wrong to think Aught but grateful love and duty To that fair benignant beauty,— In whose every breath we drink The orange, jasmine and the pink, To whose brightness Nature yields The sovereign splendour of the day, Whose fleeting sceptre hath more sway Than that the prouder noontide wields; It bringeth gladness to the fields, And colour to the flowers and groves, It is the season of the loves, Harmonious hour of wakening birds— How wrong to use disdainful words To her whose perfectness reproves. CHLORIS, aside. Ah! me, what form doth meet mine eye! LISIDA, aside. Eyes! who is this that now you see? Enrico! But if you must spy Things scarcely possible, say why 'Tis thine to kill me? let me die By the blind god's hands alone. CHLORIS, to NISE. Speak thou, that we may not be known Unto these two, and so pass by:— NISE, aside. Yes, the attempt at least I'll try:— Don Quixote of Aurora bright, Say what imports it, that at dawn Each dewy flower o'er earth's wide lawn May drink the tears it wept at night? Say, what imports the golden light That tips the hills with roseate flame— The drops of dew that put to shame The tinted sea-shell's treasures pearly? A lady, that must rise so early, Can be no very noble dame! ENRICO. To rise 'mid interlacéd bars Of summer woods and natural bowers— To change for countless troops of flowers The myriad armies of the stars— This 'gainst no proper feeling jars: If, where the green-boughs meet above, She wanders, 'tis but to discover The footsteps of her shepherd lover,— 'Twere less the lady if she strove To sleep, when she should watch with love. NISE. Well, let her rise and roam the plain, And woodlands wild, 'mid morning's dews, Seeking her loves,—for me I choose, With greater pleasure and less pain, In evening's calm and tranquil reign, Mine to enjoy, without a yawn Or envy of the spangled lawn; For to my mind 'tis clear display'd But for the common herd, was made This idle fancy for the dawn. [A noise within. But what noise is this I hear? CELIA. It is the carriage driving near, Of the duke. ENRICO. The duke? CELIA. 'Tis so. CHLORIS. Better then that we should go To our own. Remain thou here, And pardon us, Señor. ENRICO. But say, Why such haste? CHLORIS. Because this way He cometh after me, and I Desire, unknown to pass him by. ENRICO. Perhaps this casualty may, Without the breach of custom's laws, Permit my wish to serve appear, Which is to take away the fear His coming here to you doth cause; Here where the winding path withdraws Into the highway, I shall go, And then, by meeting him, shall so Divert him, till you have time to gain Your carriage, and depart again. CHLORIS. The thanks that for this act I owe, At present with this scarf I pay, Small gift with grateful feelings rife— It is the ransom of my life. [Gives him an azure scarf. ENRICO. Happy I am to serve you, may I know to whom I owe....? CHLORIS. To-day It cannot be. [Exeunt CHLORIS and NISE. LISIDA, aside. And now begin Once more, O heavens! the mental din— The heart's wild fears, the soul's eclipse— Too small the prison of my lips To chain the jealous fiend within, But since I can beneath this veil Avenge the burning pang I feel, And with the shaft of jealousy Strike dead the heart that makes mine die, Let me the subtle poison deal:— Sir, since we both so deeply owe Our thanks to you, alike we glow The debt of gratitude to pay— Hers, let the azure scarf display, Mine, by this flower I wish to show. [Gives him a flower. ENRICO. But stay. LISIDA. Unless you wish to appear Discourteous, do not follow me. [Exit. ENRICO. My doubt and wonder seem to be Greater, the more your words are clear. PONLEVI, to CELIA. You, at the least, won't stir from here. ENRICO, to PONLEVI. While, to detain the duke, I go, Do thou attempt their names to know. [Exit. PONLEVI. If this veiled dame, that hath delayed, Is in one sense, a waiting maid— She is a woman still, and so Perforce must tell me all she knows. CELIA. Do not, my good gallant, suppose That any maid or woman can Give lessons to a married man, What to permit and not disclose. PONLEVI. A good conceit, though rather low! But since Saint Secret's day we know, Is a feast day that's never kept, Help me to work, thou dear adept, Say, who are those that late did go? And take.... CELIA. It is a great temptation! PONLEVI. For every word your sweet mouth saith.... CELIA. What am I then to take? PONLEVI. Take breath, That you may make the whole narration:— CELIA. A great reward! PONLEVI. This compensation, Though high, I offer for thy sake. CELIA. Well then, I say, that if I take Breath, it is only but for one Reason— PONLEVI. And that? CELIA. Is just to run. [Exit. PONLEVI. What a Carthusian she would make! Quick as the lightning off she flies, And I will say, since I'm alone, My heart she carries with her own:— But by a lackey's wit and eyes, And by my horse's life, as wise In this adventure still am I; My master and the duke are here, This damsel I must still keep near,— A waiting-maid and secresy Some contradiction must imply. [Exit. Enter the DUKE, ENRICO, OCTAVIO, and attendants. ENRICO. Once again you must permit me Kiss your hand. DUKE. Again Enrico I rejoice to bid you welcome. ENRICO. He who comes with so much added Honour, Lord, to kneel before you, He who at thy feet doth see him, They the sphere from which are shining Greater light—a clearer sun He indeed, must truly well come. Enter FABIO. FABIO. Hither have I come to seek you, That I may, before departing, Kiss your hand, my lord. DUKE. 'Tis lucky, That Enrico hither comes, Just in time by his arrival To atone for your departure. FABIO, aside. Ah! not so, 'tis most unlucky, Since he staying here in Florence, I, in Naples will not be Free from manifold suspicions: But still Chloris is my daughter, And will prove how false they are. [Exit. DUKE. How didst thou feel in Spain, Enrico? ENRICO. Even as one whose life's employment Was to serve thee, gracious lord! Though I went there at a moment, Even if I were not thy servant, Well my absence had been spent. DUKE. How? ENRICO. My lord, I found the country Full of festivals and plaudits— Noble proof of loyal feelings, Noble evidence of love. DUKE. Even before thy tongue has spoken, Well my longing hath declared, That the cause of all those plaudits Was the great act of the nobles Swearing homage to Balthasar, Prince Infante, he who is Offspring of the sun and morning— Beam of mingled light and beauty— And since this is not a fitting Time to speak about the business Of your mission; and since I Now have lost the hope of seeing Her, who drew me to these groves, I desire that you, Enrico, Will divert my disappointment For not meeting with that lady. ENRICO. Listen to me then, your highness,— That thrice happy day on which Keeps the Roman Church the memory Of our Lord's Transfiguration, And God's homage celebrateth, Joining heaven itself therein, Was a faint and distant shadow Of the homage to Balthasar, Since if in our estimation Human deities are kings, No less mystery is figured By the day on which the earth Paid the homage to Balthasar, This ceremony took place on the 7th of March, 1632. Than whereon to God, the heavens. Well, upon this happy day, With thick shadows covered over, Rose the dawn, and the aurora, Veiled in clouds of densest darkness, Neither let the sun shine forth, Nor allowed the stars of morning To be heralds of its beauty; And though I, at other periods, Would perhaps to chance attribute This blank absence of the sun, It was not on this occasion Accident, but strict obedience, (Let the cause of this be hid in A parenthesis at present, For before my tale is over The parenthesis I'll fill). In the rich and royal temple Of the Church's holy doctor, The convent of San Jeronimo in Madrid. He whose charity, whose fervour, Reached to every living thing, Was the greatest scene enacted That the sun sees in his orbit— From his rising in the ocean To his setting in the sea. At the foot of the great altar Was a mighty stage erected, Well adapted for the homage, And upon the left hand swelling Swung the curtain of the kings; Ah! I speak not right, 'twas rather One rich cloud of gold and nacre; For, when brightly were unfolded The three dazzling plaits of purple, Light and majesty they threw, Giving, like the bright gold, glitter, Giving, like the nacre, pearls. From his palace came the king, At his side the queen, and followed By the prince, to whom the homage Would be sworn, his hands supported By his uncles, the Infantes: Never have I seen the spring-tide Crowned with more abundant flowers, Or the moon with brighter stars, Than the beautiful French lily Followed by the lovely train Of her ladies, who still brighter Shone, from shining in her presence. Then they all their places took, First, the king upon the right-hand Of the queen, and the Infantes Farther back, and on a little Seat, before them, sat the prince; Then alike in due gradation Were the seats upon the left hand Filled by prelates of the Church; Three ambassadors then followed— One from France, and Rome, and Venice, And the magistrates in order:— In the front were proudly stationed The grandees and lesser nobles, And the deputies of kingdoms After these: I name not any, Flattery here were but offensive; Confirmation's sacred rite Was the worthy ceremonial Which commenced the day's first act; Then to this, the oath of homage Followed soon. With gallant bearing, Modest and majestic both, Lively, and in all things lovely, Making reverence to all Unto whom 'twas due, Don Carlos The Infante, brother of Philip IV. Came the first to swear obedience; He was followed by Fernando, The Infante, brother of Philip IV. And as Spain doth take such glory, Being Catholic, at seeing These the oath of homage swearing,— One the shining steel engirding,— One the sacred diadem,— The Infante Don Fernando was a Cardinal. It appeared to me as if She with one loud tongue did utter Happy! happy be the kingdom, Happy without end or limit She whose first and proudest triumph Is achieved in arms and letters!— Let us leave the ceremonials At this point, for all the rest Were akin to this ensample, And go forth where fair Madrid Waiteth for an heavenly Iris— Where the crowded streets, so covered With a beautiful confusion— With confused and wondrous beauty Into fields and seas are turning Gilded robes and floating plumes; Now the military music Of the clarions and the trumpets Give the welcome proclamation Of the cavalcade's return. In the order they were seated Passed the chiefs of the procession One by one, until approaching Came the carriage of the queen; In advance of it a little, The Infantes came on horseback, And beside her at the coach-door Rode the king;—But let my tongue Here be mute, and that late spoken Marked parenthesis be filled; When I said, if you remember, That no sun appeared that morning, That no dawn was seen, nor tidings Gave the morning-star of day; That not even the night permitted Any stars to shine instead,— The parenthesis now opened, Let this sight be its completion, And thou'lt see it was not chance, But design, that hid the sunrise; Since in Carlos and Fernando Were two stars of morning shown— They the great sun's beauteous brothers, Whose bright beams his splendour feed. In the place of the aurora Rose a dawn of rarest beauty— Isabel in golden carriage, Which a thousand cupids guard; If it be aurora's office To give flowers, they were created By her loveliness, for flowers Are the fair French lily's escort;— If it be the dazzling duty Of the planet fourth in number To illuminate the circle Of its orbit—the fourth Philip Was the planet of this heaven: Child of sunlight and the morning Passed along the purest star— Round about enshrined in crystal, Sheltered by transparent glass,— If beside these stars of morning Those of heaven are put to shame,— If by her, who with aurora Sweetly staketh flower with flower— If by one whose radiant beaming Doth the great sun's rays diminish— If, in fine, by such a star, Unto whom the sun pays homage,— If to these, the stars of heaven Were but dim and misty shadows, Silent pomps—expiring lights— Not, through accident, did Nature Their bright rivalry refuse— But design, for they were absent Through the shame of being outdone. But all allegory being Laid aside, permit me further To describe unto you Philip— How with skill and noble bearing Firmly he his proud steed managed— And as this description springeth Not from flattery, but truth— It imports not if it seems so. Of a bright-brown burning sorrel— Of a fierce, ungoverned nature Seemed to me the kingly brute— In whose colour was depicted The apologetic anger Of the sun, that burned his skin, That upon its shining surface, In the noble beast's wild beauty He might contemplate his own! With such mettled pride he bounded, That a single bound proclaimed He could bear up a whole heaven: Among brutes a living mountain— Atlas turned to life 'mong beasts. How can I find words to tell thee Of the strong, proud disregard With which he, unmindful of it, Ground to dust the stony highway— But by saying this alone, That I only then discovered What a fire was 'neath Madrid?— For, where'er his hoof descended, At the touch there seemed to ope An abyss of fiery sparkles: And as he, who touches fire, Suddenly his hand withdraweth, So the noble steed drew back, With the same instinctive quickness, His proud hoof from out the fire That his hoof itself had kindled— Making fear itself so graceful, That his feet no more upheld him, Cunningly upraised in air With his boundings and curvettings. As with man, so in the brute-world Must a firm hand guide and rule it— Thus the king controlled the monster By the light rule of the reins:— Shall I say, that when afar Rang the clarions and the trumpets, He compelled him dance in time, With the foam-creating bridle?— No, for this has oft been said: Shall I say of horse and rider That they were indeed but one? No, for that were here unseemly: Shall I say they formed a map, Foam the sea, and earth the body— Wind the soul, and fire the foot? No, the thought were too conceited:— Shall I say the gallant horseman Lightly using boot and spur— Ever at the coach door bending— Firmly footed in the stirrups— Using gracefully the arm— Lowering now the hand, adjusting Now the rein—his cloak divided— With his body nicely balanced, And with courteous face and bearing Passed he thus along the highway By the coach-door of the queen? Yes, because the simple statement Gives the most exact description. Do not think that 'tis to flatter That I thus describe the skilful Horsemanship of Philip: no:— For there was not an achievement Which activity might reach to In a cavalier, that he Did not wondrously exhibit:— And the simple school wherein All his knighthood's lore was taught him Was on horseback in the saddle. If, my lord, his arms he practised, He with sharp sword could apportion Lessons learned from the foil; If he went unto the chase— Lively portraiture of warfare— He with arquebuse could cover Every thing that flew or ran; With the pencil he appeareth Wondrous Nature's new creator— And in melody, his skill Music's inmost soul hath reach'd to: In a word, of all the arts, There are none of which he knows not, And supreme perfection reaches, Without lengthened toil or effort. Oh! that fortune then would be— Oh! that heaven would be propitious— Since they have allowed his seeing This great act of homage offered With such loyal demonstrations Of true faith and strong affection To the fair prince of Asturias— That they will a god of battle Show him to the tented field, Trampling down the routed rebels Under his heroic feet,— And the Church's banners rearing, So that every thing may turn To his honour and our glory. DUKE. I would have been more delighted, Henry, by this tale of thine— If I could have disunited From this troubled heart of mine A deep trouble that doth blight it; But though sorrow be increased By proclaiming it—still I Feel, my friend, that I, at least, Owe your statement a reply,— Hear the pain with which I die, In requital of a feast:— How, I know not, (woe is me!) To begin it, but to be Pitied to the extent I'm smitten, I, a sonnet that I've written On the affair will read to thee: A frozen mountain on my bosom lay, Round which time twined a coronal of snow, While the warm heart fed fondly far below The ashes of a fire that burned alway. A beauteous beam—the wonder of the day— Down to that time with kindling torch did go, The snow encircled by the fire did glow, The fire by snow congealed to ice straightway. Etna at once of love and anguish deep— The ashes of my heart ascending higher, Burning my heart, compelled my eyes to weep, O living mountain! blind volcanic pyre! If thou art flame—how canst thou water keep? Alas! the tears of love themselves are fire! ENRICO. If, my lord, I may presume— This golden verse doth nothing prove, It merely paints the common doom Of human kind—that thou'rt in love, But it does not tell with whom. This bashful secrecy despise— Tell me the cause of all your sighs. DUKE. I think that when the name you hear, A well-known name it will appear, One whom unknown you still should prize. ENRICO. I? DUKE. Even so: I have the bliss To love a maid, whose like is not On earth. ENRICO. Your meaning still I miss. DUKE. Two daughters hath not Fabio got? PONLEVI, aside. My master's troubled much at this. ENRICO, aside. Merciful Heaven! what's this I hear? Can it be Lisida he means, Or Chloris? Ah! with jealous fear Once more I die!—[aloud] A doubt still screens The mistress that to thee is dear— For yet I do not know but she Chloris or Lisida may be, Or which thy tender love doth wake. DUKE. The very doubt is thy mistake; For who could doubt, whose eyes can see The difference 'twixt a flower and rose— Or rose compared with some bright star, Which in a nobler empire glows, And scattering lustrous light afar, Round it the beams of beauty throws? Lisida is.... ENRICO, aside. Ah! DUKE. The bud before it blows; But Chloris is the perfect rose. ENRICO. 'Tis so. [aside] Now who would e'er believe That I so gladly could receive Dispraise of her I peerless deem? DUKE. Chloris, in fine, my heart doth move, And sighs, tears, sorrows makes me prove. ENRICO. To weep, to suffer, and to sigh, Is not to love,—it is to die. DUKE. Is it then more to die than love? OCTAVIO. Though in silence I have heard Your complaints, through consolation, Still I think you have preferr'd Charges, without much foundation, Against Chloris, and so err'd; If to all your amorous wooing She, more candid than severe, Doth permit of your pursuing— If when evening draweth near Oft thy letters she is viewing— If, my lord, attentive ever To thy wish, when night's stars gleam, She, with condescending favour, Makes her room an academe, Where love's light lore supplies the graver:— Vain, my lord, must be your sorrow, Hills turn plains when love is thorough; For myself at least I'll say, She who lists to you to-day Will reply to you to-morrow. DUKE. Ah! how little thou dost know About love, Octavio!— He who wisely loves would rather Any scorn or favour gather Than without these love-gifts go; For the heart can never prove Deeper pain, than feel a love Of whose scornings we complain not, And whose favourings enchain not— Nought to praise or to reprove. Since without them we must be Joy or sorrow fancy free,— Saddest sight the earth is seeing Is the lover, pleased with being Loved as 'twere through courtesy. [Exit. ENRICO. What a tyrant Love doth reign! OCTAVIO. Well, I do not feel the chain; 'Tis to me a flowery noose— Though a pain to have or lose, I could live without the pain. ENRICO. Do you also mean to say That thou art enamoured? OCTAVIO. He Who beholds another play At his side doth often be Grieved when fortune flies away From the side that he is on,— Thus I saw the duke at play, Saw him play till hope was gone, Then I likewise lost, by one Self-same beauteous planet's ray Burned. ENRICO. Doth one house possess Your love and the duke's, then? OCTAVIO. Yes. PONLEVI, aside. When our hands a knot undo, Fate presenteth one anew,— Now he feels the deep distress Of friendship struggling with his love. ENRICO, aside. Whom doth Fate more strictly prove?— If thy dazzled heart from thee [Aloud. Sunlike Chloris' shade hath won, Lisida, who late could be But thy star, must be thy sun. OCTAVIO. Ah! my friend, it is not she. ENRICO, aside. God! how grateful I do feel! PONLEVI, aside. What, not she? This wheel on wheel, This whirling puzzle ne'er will end? OCTAVIO. As thou art my trusted friend, I from thee can nought conceal. ENRICO. Thou my friendship knowest well. OCTAVIO. With the sisters there doth dwell A fair cousin, a bright creature, Whom from head to foot, each feature Stamps a living miracle Of rare beauty. This loved woman, Whose divine perfections are More angelical than human, Is the beauteous beam—the star— Is the heaven my heart consuming:— But I do not wish to be her Praiser, since we go to see her, When my friendship hopes, that you May advise me not to woo, But worship as in heaven's own sphere. [Exit. ENRICO. And from this, I say it now:— Tell me, Ponlevi, didst thou Witness my two terrors? PONLEVI. Master, I beheld your whole disaster, Saw, 'twixt love and friendship, how— 'Twixt your friend and lord likewise, You did so soliloquise, That for numberless pretences, Every moment your seven senses Were at work. ENRICO. My fears and sighs Have been wholly turned to gladness. PONLEVI. It will not restore your sadness Very poignantly, or greatly, To be told that those whom lately You addressed so in your madness, Were the ladies above stated. ENRICO. Who to thee has this related? PONLEVI. Soon repenting her moroseness, And her unofficial closeness, This to me their maid narrated. ENRICO. Oh! then from this doubt relieve me, Which of them this scarf did give me? Which did give this beauteous flower? PONLEVI. This is quite beyond my power, Difficult to tell, believe me. ENRICO. Late the happiest of men, I am wretched once again: For I know not which to prize Of these gifts, or which despise. PONLEVI. I yet hope to tell thee then; If to-day again I meet them I on thy account will greet them With an air of courtly fashion, For when surge the waves of passion, Even the lightest winds that beat them Mark the surface; thus the breast In the face is oft confess'd. ENRICO. Go, explore that troubled wave, Find that Lisida but gave Either gift, and I am blest:— If one is like a poison'd breath, The other comes with healing rife— Safe whatever Fortune saith,— By my death securing life,— By my life securing death. [Exeunt. SCENE II. —THE GARDEN OF FABIO'S HOUSE. Enter NISE and CHLORIS. NISE. Here where, tenderly complaining, The murmuring fountain crystal tears is raining, Trust, dear cousin mine, Unto my love this secret love of thine. CHLORIS. Enrico is in sooth (Here let us linger, Nise) the most courteous youth, The bravest and most wise Throughout all Florence, or Dame Rumour lies. I do not say I loved, Or that I wished his heart should e'er be moved To love me; all I know Is, that it would not grieve me if 'twere so. Thus on life went, I neither loving, nor indifferent, When the god that wakes desire Breathed on the ashes and lit up the fire:— I need not say with what a grateful pride My heart replied, Repaying love's sweet favours with my yielding soul, For when thou know'st my grief, thou know'st the whole; This sweet compulsion, this soft strife, Was by his absence swiftly brought to life, Since it allowed the duke To visit me and plead his passion in his look: And I—so high his loyal soul I deem,— Fear that his love may reach the other extreme. Enter LISIDA. LISIDA. Let not this darksome night Envy the morning's beauteous pomp of light, Since even that glory is outshone By a more bright Aurora, and new dawn. Enter PONLEVI. PONLEVI. If perchance a new arrival Who has little shame to spare, May presume to take the freedom Just to enter where he likes, Give to me your twice three slippers, That I may this instant kiss The three gold-embroidered bases Of three columns of pure snow. NISE, to CHLORIS. Who is this buffoon, fair cousin? Chloris, aside. Servant unto one away. NISE, aside. Ah! I understand. LISIDA, aside. Dissemble Now my heart, since 'tis thy fate:— Ponlevi, how dost thou feel? [Aloud. PONLEVI. He, Señora, feels quite well, Full of gladness and contentment. LISIDA. Who? PONLEVI. My master, for of him Do you wish to know: 'tis little Matter how I feel: but you Need not soar to such a distance Like a Norway falcon. LISIDA. Thou Comest back as sharp as ever. PONLEVI. Virtue never can be lost. LISIDA. Say, is Spain a noble country? PONLEVI. Beyond doubt, most excellent. LISIDA. Lovely women? PONLEVI. He did never Speak with one the whole year through. LISIDA. Whom do you speak of? PONLEVI. Why, my master, Whom thou seekest to find out:— Do not take so many turnings When the race-course is so short. NISE. Then his taste must be imperfect. PONLEVI. No, it is extremely good, Shown by loving you. NISE. Me also? PONLEVI. Yes? NISE. But how could love arise Without his seeing me? PONLEVI. Quite easy; If he saw you, 'twere no wonder That he loved you; I am certain Were he even born blind, He would love you without seeing. CHLORIS. But one fickle heart 'mongst three, Say, how can it be divided? PONLEVI. 'Tis my master's sole command, That I no one must dispirit, For his case is so extreme Lest, perchance, one love miscarry, Always to have two in hand; So to show my strict obedience, I but say, Deum de deo, Or he loves from day to day. Enter CELIA. CELIA. At the gate the duke is waiting. CHLORIS. What vexation! CELIA. With him come Both Octavio and Enrico. CHLORIS, aside. Thanks to love! that even the duke Sometimes can a welcome visit Pay to me:—Admit his Grace. Enter the DUKE, OCTAVIO, and ENRICO; lights are introduced. CHLORIS. Here your Highness, 'neath this tree, 'Mid the cool air may rejoice. DUKE. Love doth neither give a choice Nor doth sadness leave me free; If 'tis given to me to see But thy beauty, 'tis all one Where my careless steps are gone, Be it garden, grove, or room, Heaven it must be, I presume, Where doth shine so bright a sun. The DUKE sits down upon a garden-seat, and CHLORIS on another; the ladies also on either side. OCTAVIO, to ENRICO. Does she not, this mistress mine, All my praise surpass by far? ENRICO. She deserves to be a star, Since to her such charms divine Must thy dazzled heart incline. OCTAVIO. Time and place are both propitious Now to speak to her my wishes. ENRICO. As a stranger, they, I fear Will avail me little here. LISIDA. Who could have been so malicious, As, Enrico, to bestow On thee this, since they must know It may make some bosom swell Jealously? ENRICO. And so, do well. LISIDA. Not that I am jealous, no, 'Tis but fancy. ENRICO. I confess I your meaning cannot guess. LISIDA. Jealousy you let one wreak, Not revenge: this scarf can speak. ENRICO. And this beauteous flower no less. LISIDA. Whose colour tells your hopes must be Turned to jealousy's green hue. CHLORIS, aside. Heavens! what sight is this I view? It is my sister's flower, ah, me! They kill me both, with jealousy. DUKE. What is it that disturbs thee so? CHLORIS. Naught. DUKE. And there thy glances throw? CHLORIS, aside. A potent grief! a powerful pain!— Enrico's coming home again, [Aloud. This passing interest made me show:— ENRICO. I an occasion hoped to gain, Se?ora, thy fair hand to kiss. LISIDA, aside. Heart! and must thou suffer this? CHLORIS. That you left the court of Spain But recently, is very plain, From the gifts with which you come. ENRICO. You see them quickly. CHLORIS. I have some Experiences, which ne'er betray, Nor do they now. ENRICO. And what are they? CHLORIS. This scarf and flower on breast and plume Love's favours seem, unless I err. ENRICO. What is mere chance should not appear A proof of favour. CHLORIS. If it were, Which of the two would you prefer? ENRICO, aside. How shall I fitly answer her As well as Lisida? CHLORIS. Without An answer, are you? ENRICO. Not through doubt Of what to say my thought I mask, But simple wonder love should ask; I would prefer, with lips devout Kissing it o'er and o'er again, That which a lady veiled to-day Gave me. CHLORIS, aside. He knows me, why delay?— But if there had been two, what then? [Aloud. ENRICO, aside. Who was e'er pressed in this close way?— With me, the foremost place should boast [Aloud. The gift of her I loved the most. CHLORIS. Which of the two is that? declare. ENRICO. That which the fairest hue doth bear, Better than words will tell almost. NISE. As questions of disdain and love— Fond problems of the troubled breast— Ever divert the duke the best, Let us this casual doubt remove, And find what colour best doth prove. ENRICO. This is not now the time or place For private favours, as his Grace Has his own loves to think of. DUKE. No, I shall be pleased: ENRICO, aside. And I, not so. CHLORIS. If from two colours we can trace The yet all phantom form of her Enrico loves, methinks the blue Must be the pure and peerless hue Which before all he doth prefer. LISIDA. I, if from colour we infer The soul's dear choice, must state my creed Is in the green. ENRICO. 'Tis mine to heed The argument, and learn from it The excellency of your wit:— Prithee proceed. LISIDA. I thus proceed: Green is the colour God doth fling First on the naked world, a dress Which doth increase its loveliness— It is the colour of the spring. The fairest sight the seasons bring Is that green ornament that sees, Voiceless and breathless 'neath the trees, The many-tinted flowers take birth On the green cradle of the earth— The trembling stars of every breeze. CHLORIS. Earthly that colour and must die And fading quickly ne'er be seen— But when the ground is clothed with green Transparent azure lights the sky, Spring hangs her azure veil on high Where myriad living lights are thrown Over the sky like flowers full blown,— Say which, more richly Nature dowers, An earthly heaven o'erhung with flowers Or heaven's bright field with stars o'erstrown? LISIDA. This seeming colour mocks our eyes, As if its bright cerulean glow Indeed were real: but we know There is no colour in the skies: Heaven with this brilliant falsehood lies— This azure fiction of the blue:— If we no other reason heard But this, the green should be preferr'd— One boasts a fair fictitious hue And one whose lovelier shade is true. CHLORIS. Not real colour I confess Is the sky's azure: but I know 'Tis better for not being so. Were it indeed its actual dress It would require but little stress To prove its greater beauty. This Must be, I hold, the cause of his Election, if he choose the blue, Since even though feigned it hath a hue Fairer than that, how true it is. LISIDA. The green speaks hope, which always we As love's most precious offering prize, At least so she may say, whose eyes That figured freshness ne'er will see, The azure speaks of jealousy, And fickle change—two fiends that well Know how to blight where'er they dwell, What matters, then, if love is given To wear perchance the hue of heaven, If it must feel the pains of hell? CHLORIS. He who on hope doth live alone, For that but slightly praised must be, But he who loves with jealousy Inscribes his love on bronze or stone, 'Tis thus its steadfastness is known, Not weakly lost when hope is o'er, He who, though jealous, doth adore Shows what a faithful heart hath he, Since in the hell of jealousy He can not hope for favour more. LISIDA. To hope is then the happier lot. CHLORIS. But to be jealous more discreet. LISIDA. Green is the flower so fresh and sweet. CHLORIS. The scarf is azure, is it not? LISIDA. Well, and what matters that? CHLORIS. And what Matters the other? LISIDA. But in fine Think not the flower is mine. CHLORIS. Nor mine The scarf. [They both arise. LISIDA. But if 'twere so...... CHLORIS. How would you act? LISIDA. I do not know. DUKE. Now in God's name the strife resign, No bitter words will sour the sweets Of this rare feast of wit I trust, Go not away. LISIDA. Indeed I must, Not to hear more such vain conceits. [Exit. CHLORIS. 'Tis not the winner that retreats. Neither would I hear more: and so Flying from hence I wish to go, If I have got your Grace's leave. [Exit. DUKE. That beauty ever doth receive. ENRICO. What has just passed I scarcely know. DUKE. Thou art, Enrico, amongst men The happiest lover now alive, For some, to thee love favours give, And others quarrel 'bout them then. ENRICO. This hath their colour done, 'tis plain, And not my fortune. DUKE. O strong power Of fate! [Exit. OCTAVIO. What grief! [Exit. NISE. 'Tis envy's hour, Who walks about in love's own hue! [Exit. ENRICO. Heavens! for a scarf, what dire distress! Heavens! what distress about a flower! [Exit.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. SCENE I. —A GARDEN. Enter PONLEVI and ENRICO. PONLEVI. You appear extremely happy. ENRICO. Yes, I am extremely so: And the spirit of contentment Ever wears the hues of joy. PONLEVI. Does it cost so much, a lady's Saying, I would speak with thee: Go, Enrico, to the garden? ENRICO. Lisida will speak, I fear, Angrily, for my addresses, But since that rare argument When the Scarf and Flower contended— Jealousy and love opposed— I have been declared her lover, Angry glances I can meet. Enter LISIDA and CELIA. LISIDA. Ah! Enrico! ENRICO. Not in vain, Seeing, ere his own Aurora, One hath risen, waits the sun— Saying, doubtless, day hath wandered From his pathway in the east:— Since without his light—'tis morning. LISIDA. Let not flatteries, Enrico, Cloak the feelings of your heart, Imitating honest silence, Simple truth should naked live: And as it is my intention Now at length to put an end To our mutual misconception, Listen to me: you retire: [To Ponlevi and Celia, who withdraw. Thou, Enrico, ere your journey Into Spain (and if I thus Recollect, 'tis for this reason That the breast is bronze to keep Ever fixed the soul's offences), Chloris' lover seemed to be...... ENRICO. Stay, for I am not desirous If by silence, we confess, To confess then by my silence What is ruin to myself, No, not Chloris was the day-star Lucent load-stone of mine eyes, No, they ever drank unsated Ray by ray a brighter sun— Flame by flame, a fairer fire-world. LISIDA. But how can you then deny What my very eyes were seeing? ENRICO. By denying what they saw. LISIDA. Were you not the very shadow Of her dwelling in the street? ENRICO. Yes. LISIDA. A statue on her terrace, Did the dawn not find you still? ENRICO. It is true. LISIDA. Have you not written To her? ENRICO. I do not deny Having written. LISIDA. And the night-time Was it not the dusky cloak Of your stolen loves? ENRICO. That sometimes I did speak to her at night, I confess. LISIDA. This scarf you carry, Is it not hers? ENRICO. I think that hers Once it was. LISIDA. What contradiction!— If to see, to speak, to write, If to wear her scarf around you, If to follow, and to watch, Be not love, I ask, Enrico, That you tell me what it is; Leave me ignorant no longer Of a thing so simply told. ENRICO. Let an illustration answer: The skill'd sportsman, who would make Of a seeming speck of plumage, Borne along in rapid flight, The swift mark at which he aimeth— Aims not at the bird itself, But beside it; understanding That to gain the wind's sure aid, He must cheat the wind a little: The experienced mariner, Who, the sea, that fierce and foaming Prodigy of nature, rules, Doth not turn his prow directly To the port he seeks to gain, But by tacking through the billows Wiles their wrath and comes to shore. The commander, who, a fortress Means to gain, doth first pretend That his call to arms is sounded 'Gainst another fort, and thus, By all sounds of martial clamour, So deceives the place, that he Hopes to find it unprotected 'Gainst the true attack: and thus Wins it less by force than cunning. The deep mine, that in the entrails Of the earth, begins far off, Like an artificial Etna— A volcano formed by skill— Does not, where its pregnant caverns Hold concealed a dread abyss Of immense and hidden horrors, Take effect, but then deceives Even the very fire that lights it— Here 'tis lightning—thunder there— Here conceives, and there travaileth. If, then, in the fields of air, Is my love that wily hunter; If it be the mariner On the inconstant sea of fortune; If in the wars of jealousy It appears the victor leader; If in the bosom's mine it proves The fire so hard to be resisted, Is it a wonder then that I Have kept disguised my heart's true feelings? But let this scarf my witness be, That I, as mariner and hunter, Commander and volcano wild, On land, in air, in fire and water, Would win, would come, would strike, would reach to Victory, ruin, aim, and port. [Gives her the scarf. LISIDA. You conceive that my resentments, Weakly flattered in this way— Will remit for your injustice The atonement of my wrong. No, Enrico, I'm a woman Proud enough to scorn the love That is only felt through vengeance Of another's slighting scorn: He who loves me, he must love me For my own deserts alone, He must love me for no object But the guerdon of my love: If, indeed, when Chloris thought you Her devoted lover, when Thou wert soul unto her body, You declared herself to me; Then, I think, perchance, Enrico, That with not ungrateful trust, That with heart but gently cruel, That with slightly scornful eyes, I might have esteemed...... No further Will I say—I've said enough— This alone I will acknowledge Briefly, that if thou hadst been Her received and favoured suitor, I suspect I had heard thee then, Not as now when thou'rt rejected:— For to love one whom we know Is the accepted of another Is the glory of our grief, But when rejected, is dishonour: So, Enrico, I advise That you neither seek nor ask for Remedy, because I think That the remedy will kill thee Soon as the disease: what gain By the remedy to perish When the disease will kill as sure? ENRICO. Oh! but stay! delay thee! hear me! LISIDA. What do you say? ENRICO. That I, please Heaven!...... Enter CELIA and PONLEVI. PONLEVI. Chloris comes, postpone your swearing, And so please Heaven a better way. ENRICO. While she passes, these close jasmines Will conceal me. LISIDA. How is this? Why so dread that she will see you Here with me? ENRICO. Ah! no, I fear It may trouble you: this only Is the cause why I should hide; But if it doth not concern you, Neither doth it matter me; Here I stay, I may see Chloris, Since 'tis you that I adore. LISIDA. This you do to make her jealous:— No, you stay not here with me. ENRICO. If I hide me, I offend you, If I do not, 'tis the same,— What then must I do? LISIDA. What? Neither Hide thee, nor yet stay with me. ENRICO. What then? LISIDA. Go. ENRICO, retiring hastily. Yes, I will do so. LISIDA. Stay! you go not in this way, But quite slowly, for my object...... ENRICO. Say it. LISIDA. Is that you should go And not fly, Enrico, frightened. ENRICO. In this manner you will see That I go, and thus obey thee. [In taking off his hat, the flower falls out unperceived. PONLEVI, aside. Were there stakes or palisadings, This would lead to a tournament. Enter CHLORIS and NISE; ENRICO goes before them bowing formally, and exits with PONLEVI at one side of the stage, as LISIDA and CELIA do at the other. CHLORIS. Nise, what a sight is this? What is this my vision sees? NISE. Troubles, pains, and jealousies— All thy shattered hopes of bliss:— If I tell thee a device Still to keep their loves apart, And thus tranquillize thy heart By a simple artifice, Tell me, Chloris, what thou'lt say If this stroke their love arrests?— CHLORIS. That you would with sportive jests Wile my serious griefs away. NISE. The sweet beauteous pink, which we Feel the garden's pomp doth make, Yieldeth poison to the snake, Even as honey to the bee, [She perceives the flower and takes it up. And this verdant flower, that here Timely fell, for illustration, From the hat's strict salutation Of some courteous cavalier, Yields the same results to thee— To the bee of love, its hue Honey gives, and poison too To the snake of jealousy;— Take and place it in thy hair. CHLORIS. This was Lisida's—the root And fertile source of our dispute. NISE. To this flower and to my care Trust thy remedy: the way Is to do what I tell thee. CHLORIS. Since I hope no remedy, I am willing to obey. NISE. Let thy earliest lesson be This, that howsoe'er love's sting Jealously thy bosom wring, There is no necessity That it be at all confest, But dissembling thy true sorrow, Thou the mask of laughter borrow. CHLORIS. Strange expedients you suggest. NISE. Even to bid her love him, though You to Lisida should say. CHLORIS. I? NISE. Yes, you, and in a way That...... but presently thou'lt know: Here Enrico comes. CHLORIS. Ah, me! NISE. Now begins thy simulation: Let thy look and conversation: Be as if it were not he. Enter ENRICO. ENRICO, aside. Quickly back, the flower that fell Here I hasten to regain. CHLORIS to NISE. Ah! how can I learn to feign? NISE to her. Feign you must, or not be well. CHLORIS. Why return so expeditious, Don Enrico, to these bowers? ENRICO. Who would care to seek for flowers When the Spring forestalls his wishes?— All who to a garden come Bring not flowers, but bear them thence; I alone with this dispense, Having brought this orange bloom. CHLORIS. What you mean, I cannot say, But I think some other passion In a very cautious fashion You attempt to serve this way, By this flower. Adieu! ENRICO. She goes! Beauteous Chloris, think...... Enter LISIDA. LISIDA, aside. That she May behold this scarf on me I return here now..... my rose Chloris wears! ENRICO, not perceiving LISIDA. This crimson glow— Speck upon a sun, so bright— Which presumes to blend its light With thy forehead's gold and snow, Is not in its proper place,— Guardian thorns did once enclose With their fence this beauteous rose, Still from out their strict embrace It was taken: wouldst thou then— With thy bright eyes' glances try To replace them, so that I Ne'er could get it back again? For though traitor thorns we meet— Your bright looks would ne'er betray it, Let my hand approach and lay it As a trophy at thy feet. LISIDA, aside. Can my sight or hearing err? NISE to CHLORIS. Lisida has seen thee. CHLORIS to her. True; Tell me, then, what I must do. NISE. You must leave him here with her. CHLORIS. Leave him here with her? NISE. Rely On this feigning for thy cure. CHLORIS. Be it so. NISE. But mind be sure, Show the flower in passing by. CHLORIS. That I'll do with little sighing, Since I wish she see me bear it: But, my scarf, she still will wear it. NISE. Go retiring, but not flying. CHLORIS. Love! obedience thus I show. NISE. My experienced skill obey. CHLORIS. With the scarf that she should stay! LISIDA, aside. With the flower that she should go! CHLORIS and NISE slowly retire; CHLORIS pointing triumphantly to the flower, and LISIDA to the scarf. ENRICO, aside. Who before did ever prove Such misfortune? LISIDA. Knighthood's stain, Base, inconstant, treacherous, vain, Fickle, faithless, without love, Canst thou an excuse prefer For thy love's hypocrisy, Since you gave the scarf to me, But to give the flower to her? ENRICO. Hear me!...... LISIDA. Wherefore hear thee, pray? ENRICO. See!...... LISIDA. Perchance some new deceit,— Said you not, that at her feet You would lay it? ENRICO. 'Twas to say Though from her I would receive it, 'Twas not for her head designed. LISIDA. Canst thou think me then so blind As, this falsehood, to believe it?— ENRICO. I the truth have told to thee. LISIDA. Would to God that it were so! ENRICO. If my love doth die or no, Hangs now on thy cruelty. LISIDA. Then 'twill die, if heaven above Works no miracle for thee. ENRICO. O unfounded jealousy! LISIDA. O too ill-requited love! [Exeunt. SCENE II. —A ROOM IN THE DUKE'S PALACE. Enter the DUKE with a letter in his hand, and OCTAVIO. DUKE. But only this denial Needed my love for its extremest trial. OCTAVIO. And do no sparks of hope appear? DUKE. Octavio, none: since Heaven doth interfere, It every hope prohibits. OCTAVIO. To-day dread Love his vengeful power exhibits, Making us proudly understand How like Heaven's bolts can fall the arrows from his hand, Since like the lightnings dashing wildly by— The proud they humble and make low the high. DUKE. Rather, Octavio, in coward mood His rage o'erwhelms the prostrate and subdued, The tower, the proudest front that rears, Must feel at length the heavy weight of years; If it declines or falls, 'Tis not a building then, but ruined walls— A mark unworthy of that flame august Which crumbles mightiest pinnacles to dust. OCTAVIO. Think not, my lord, a building so decayed, Although no more its mouldering walls are made A place where slowly preys The venom'd fang, the poisonous tooth of days, Time, to allow thy griefs to pass, Makes of thy years a basilisk of brass. DUKE. I hope not now for their duration. OCTAVIO. Would I could give thee joy or consolation! DUKE. Who has just entered? Hast thou been observant? OCTAVIO. It is Enrico. DUKE. And who else? OCTAVIO. His servant; Who the licence that you gave, doth use To enter here at times. DUKE. 'Tis true, he doth amuse My sorrows; but now leave me, I desire To speak here with Enrico. Enter ENRICO and PONLEVI. OCTAVIO, aside. On the wings of fire Speed, heart, to Nise, seize the luck befalls thee,— Fly! it is Love—the wingéd god that calls thee! [Exit. DUKE. How many thoughts doth musing sorrow trace! PONLEVI. Let me kiss, this instant, please your Grace, Sovereign ruler of this land, Your royal foot, which I would take by the hand. DUKE. To-day my heart is so oppressed with evil It cannot jest. PONLEVI. Then I may go to the devil! Forced laughter now is treason,— Women and jests please only when in season. [Exit. DUKE. Until now, to speak to Chloris fair, Made my love rest, my star bright promise wear, Dividing with the day The sweet delusions she at night would say; But since, at length, no more appears this gleam Of comfort, anguish reaches the extreme Of grief, despair, and discontent:— Hear this letter which to me she has sent:— [Reads. “My lord, The continual visits of your Highness have awakened more than one malicious suspicion: and my father being absent, that which, at one time would have been to him an honour, will now be the cause of double calumny. I expect him soon, and so I beseech your Highness to excuse my requesting that you will not come to see me”— I read no more: this sentence which she sends, This wrong, at length, my long-tried patience ends; Yes I avow it unto thee, This scorn does more than all her cruelty, More than her frowns, which once could prove Sweet prison chains that bound my captive love: And so, Enrico, I desire That for this evil, this consuming fire, You will this day a remedy procure me, And so thus swiftly kill me, or thus cure me; You must find out for me without delay What Chloris really thinks: behold a way To reach the ungrateful fair one's bosom, for Love hath its stratagems as well as war:— Thou knowest Nise, her fair cousin, who Is, as it were, the soul of her I woo; If then on her attentive you would wait And publicly her favours celebrate— I do not doubt that you will soon be loved: Your gallantry, Enrico, has been proved; Besides, a maiden, when she feels you mean Marriage, allows her inmost thoughts be seen; Thus having gained unto your aid With love the cousin, and with gifts the maid Who waits upon her, you will be possess'd Of the approach to the snowy mine of her breast, Which by a counter-mine of snow, Soon thou wilt make to burst with fiery glow:— And thus between the flames and snows My love the truth shall gain, and I, repose. ENRICO. My lord, although to-day had sought My hope, some way of serving you in aught— Octavio will from Nise sooner learn The secrets that your love would thus discern. DUKE. If to Octavio I had meant to unfold My secret, I Octavio would have told; And since I have confided it to thee, From thee I wish my cure of jealousy:— And not Octavio. ENRICO. I may first inquire Of Lisida, my lord. DUKE. Neither do I desire That Lisida should be aware of it, Since in continual rivalry of wit And beauty, the two sisters ever live, And this being known to one, would therefore give Her the advantage, and would make her be The suspicious witness of my jealousy. ENRICO. Since you will listen unto no excuse, Think of the inconvenience 'twill produce;— Octavio wooeth Nise, it will be A wrong to him. DUKE. I have more claims than he. ENRICO. 'Tis true, my lord, but I too woo a dame To be my wife, of noble name and fame, From whom I must forego my suit sincere: Grant me then leave...... DUKE. It is an idle fear, And wrong to me, as equal things to blend The displeasure of a mistress and a friend,— From whom, this slight fraud o'er, thou'lt be receiving Thanks, for effecting thus his undeceiving,— But if it more concerns thee, I resign My claim: 'twere wrong to force your wish to mine. ENRICO. My lord...... DUKE. No more address me. ENRICO. Will you refuse my service? DUKE. Do not press me. ENRICO. It was to warn thee...... DUKE. Do not speak a word. ENRICO. I feel you doubt my loyalty, my lord. DUKE. And with good reason, since you thwart my will. O vain, vain love! and friendship vainer still! [Exit. ENRICO. Can the world show in all its scenes of wrong A maze more subtle, or a knot more strong, Than that which friendship, loyalty, and love— Friend, mistress, lord, have round about me wove? If I refuse to woo fair Nise, then I leave the duke complaining; if again I woo her, 'tis Octavio that doth mourn— If I watch Chloris, she is wronged in turn; If I proclaim the truth, it will appear I break my trust; and if I persevere, I run the risk in Lisida's dear eyes Of seeming Nise's favours but to prize; Her too I wrong, and all the others so,— Lisida, Chloris, and Octavio:— Ah, me! then whither shall I go? How thus divided meet each separate woe? Serving the duke, Octavio not offending,— Wronging not Nise, Chloris none intending— Nor causing Lisida one jealous fear— Heavens! there's enough of complication here! [Exit. SCENE III. —THE GARDEN OF FABIO'S HOUSE. Enter LISIDA and CELIA. LISIDA. You're sure you saw him, then? CELIA. Unless Sure sight could err. LISIDA. And that the favour Which Chloris wore, 'twas Nise gave her, After Enrico lost it? CELIA. Yes; For in the garden as I loitered, Listening to many an idle sally Spoken by Pónlevi his valet, The whole affair I reconnoitred: Had I an opportunity As now, I would have sooner said it. LISIDA, aside. Since I must die else, shall I credit This doubtful witness, Jealousy?— Yes, for through design, nor chance, Nor sly collusion, could it be That his excuse could so agree With this, in every circumstance; Ah, me! how soon, when weak with woe, [Aloud. Whate'er we wish we seem to view— It does not need a thing be true,— It is enough it may be so:— Alas! unhappy undeceiving! Too late you come the wound to heal, For now, my Celia, now I feel, How harsh I was in not believing: God! how his generous heart must swell To think we parted severed friends,— But I will make him full amends. Await me here. CELIA. Consider well What you ought now to do. LISIDA. To write A letter free from every sting, Which, my dear Celia, you must bring Unto his hand, as swift as light:— Whose gentle influence stealing o'er His heart, will all its joys renew— Love and the sun when breaking through Quarrels and clouds shine out the more. [Exit. Enter PONLEVI. PONLEVI. Scarcely have I, in the palace, Left my lord, ungrateful Celia, When you see me here returning— The lightning of the cloak and sword— To embrace you, like the lightning. CELIA. Without speaking, would'st embrace me? PONLEVI. Yes; I better know the practice Than the theory of wooing. CELIA. And of wit, neither:—but, misfortune! Woe is me! here cometh Chloris, Walking thither through the garden; If she sees thee, 'tis my death-stroke. PONLEVI. Therefore, you enjoy the pleasure First of seeing me: but tell me What am I to do? CELIA. To hide thee Underneath these boughs. PONLEVI. Through terror I my feet am scarce uplifting, Like as in a comic drama, In the dwelling of his lady Is the king found by her father, Tottering-footed and large-bearded. [Conceals himself. Enter CHLORIS and NISE. CHLORIS. What has brought thee hither, Celia? CELIA. I am waiting till my lady Lisida would leave her chamber And come hither. CHLORIS. It is better That within the house you wait her. [Exit Celia. Nise, ah! my friend, my cousin, Little can you feel my anguish, Since for such a time you leave me! NISE. Speaking through the trellised windows Of these gardens, with Octavio Have I been. CHLORIS. A proper reason Hast thou given for thy detention, If you truly love each other. NISE. Neither loving nor forgetting, Thus at times his hopes I humour;— But with thee, how art thou speeding With the lesson? CHLORIS. I have studied It so well, that I need only An occasion to employ it. Enter LISIDA with a letter in her hand; on seeing them she conceals it. LISIDA. Was not Celia here this moment? CHLORIS. Here but now was Celia waiting; I have just desired her enter There within. NISE. I go to call her. 'Tis an excellent occasion [Aside to CHLORIS. Now to open the campaign— Jealousy to blind and baffle. [Exit. CHLORIS to LISIDA, who is retiring. Lisida, awhile detain thee, For I have many things to say. LISIDA. Then the consequence is certain That I have many things to hear: Begin. PONLEVI, peeping. Now comes a mighty battle. CHLORIS. Lisida, we are now together,— Thou art my sworn friend and sister, As to a friend's and sister's bosom Will I lay bare my secret soul, Two years have flown, thou must remember Since in my gardens, seemed Enrico A living statue—so alive— That all the plants were more indebted Unto his eyes for tearful dew-drops Than to the sighs that morning breathes:— Then came his absence, and as Heaven Varies so often our condition, That the bright day of love forerunneth Often the fickle eve of change, Easily thus, the scattered ashes Died in the fire but just enkindled, And in the chilling air of absence Vanished the flame of love itself. Shortly the duke became my suitor, And though my honour and good fame Offered resistance, I acknowledge Not with complete success; for some Gentle impression such uncommon Proofs of affection must have caused: On his returning home, Enrico, Jealous to see the duke's attachment, Or having now become enamoured Once again through jealousy's cause, Striveth now to wreak his vengeance Vainly through thee for my disdain: Let this garden be a witness— Whither in spite of all his anguish— Lest I should be in plaintive mood For having given the scarf thou'rt wearing, He back returned to give this flower— Type of the hope he still doth nourish. If you are then my friend and sister, As I have said; if thou wouldst share Part of my joy as all my sorrow, Do then this single act for me:— Love thou Enrico much—repaying With a firm faith and true affection His faith and love which are so false, Do not in any way exhibit Your knowledge that he feigns and hides Through thee his vengeance: to awaken Love, 'tis enough to think he loves:— Thus will the duke have lesser reason For being jealous, thus Enrico Feel full security in love, And in his lord's recovered favour,— I will gain quiet—you a spouse, And all more joy and less disquiet. LISIDA, aside. She thinks that me she is deceiving, When 'tis herself that is deceived:— Certainly, Chloris, when I saw thee Making such prefaces and prologues, I thought the affair was very arduous That should be done by me for thee:— Do you not ask me more, my sister, Than to deceive a man? Was never Anything easier? Insufficient Is it to know that I'm a woman? Needed it then to urge me so?— But notwithstanding all, to serve thee This I will say, that though I thought Never to speak to thee more, obedient Will I be now to thy commands; From this day thou'lt see me with him— Ever from dusky night till dawn— Ever from dawn till night descendeth— And ere upon that starry pyre The sun renews his life, consuming His golden plumes in silver fires— I will despatch to him a letter, Filled with a thousand fond entreaties, Telling him come to see me, so Worded, that you will be persuaded Even yourself that it is true:— Or at the least, no clear distinction Will you be able to discover Betwixt these feigned and false endearments: Do you wish more? CHLORIS. Not even so much. PONLEVI, aside. Did ever I hear a trick more artful Than this they have planned to fool Enrico?— Never in all my days: I'll slip Out of this place, while they are speaking;— I burst—I burn to tell him all: [While they converse together, PONLEVI slips out unperceived. LISIDA. Lose all anxiety, and trust me All shall be right. CHLORIS. Adieu then: [aside] cursed Be the revenge that turns to love, As well as the love that turns to vengeance! [Exit. LISIDA. If Chloris bids me for Enrico feign Love that the sooner he might her forget— Then with her sorrows would my eyes be wet, While I should feel my own love's sharp disdain: But if she thus my fondness would restrain, Snaring my love within this subtle net— Oh! it were doubly wrong in me to let Action and thought attempt a risk so plain: And since the mark at which her arrows fly Is pictured in this green-girt rose's hue— Gathered by stealth and speedily to die— Heedless I may, her jealous efforts, view— For he who once is guilty of a lie, Is always doubted though he speaketh true. Enter ENRICO and PONLEVI; they converse apart. ENRICO. You are lying. PONLEVI. No; I lie not. ENRICO. That this happened? PONLEVI. As I told you. ENRICO. What, that Chloris doth forget me, And that Lisida deceives me? PONLEVI. Yes, my lord, for both the ladies Are two super-cunning sly ones. ENRICO. I will prove this. PONLEVI. In what manner? ENRICO. Lisida herself will prove it; When we parted, she was angry,— If I find, upon our meeting All her jealous wrath abated, Ere I've made her satisfaction, It is true. PONLEVI. Then wait a little For a letter she will write you, ENRICO. Who could ever have such patience? LISIDA, advancing. Welcome mayest thou be, Enrico, For it seems my soul advanceth Ere my tardy words to call thee, Falsifying thus the slowness Of thy absence. ENRICO. Why wait longer? [Aside. Stay, thou false ungrateful siren, [Aloud. Cunning crocodile, delay thee, If you weep, your tears destroy me, If you sing, your songs are fatal, Proved too well by all your changes: Since to-day your jealous weeping Gave me mortal anguish, tyrant, And the strains that speak forgiveness Also give me death; Oh! leave me, Since of thee I am not certain, Whether tears or songs you give me. LISIDA. Neither to-day was feigned my weeping, Nor is my laughter false, Enrico, Opposite though they be, the twain Born of the soul are twin affections, If I, to day, wept jealousy's sorrows, I, to-day, sing praises to love; Joyously thanking all his unravellings, Since from Celia, secretly listening, Full explanation I have received!— Then it is not a siren that calls thee, Feigning tenderness, to her arms, Nor a crocodile is it that wrongs thee With the show of false flowing tears;— It is Love alone that among these branches Singeth or weepeth equally true, When he weepeth and when he singeth. ENRICO. Dost thou think, that I am ignorant All the words that now thou art speaking Are but feigned? LISIDA. And can this letter Be also feigned I was going to send? [Gives him the letter. ENRICO. Peace! peace! for even this letter Is a witness stronger than all The other grounds of my unhappiness, Since you promised Chloris your sister That you would write a letter like this: This is not love; it is a stratagem Planned by you two. LISIDA. And who so speedily......? PONLEVI, aside. Now I enter into the dance. LISIDA. Could have told you that we were speaking Lately together? PONLEVI, aside. Oh! what matter? Leave me under the cloud, I pray. ENRICO. Pónlevi here, who was carefully listening, Secretly hidden under the boughs, Heard what you and Chloris were planning, Cruelly planning against my peace. PONLEVI. I, my lady, said nothing about it; My master, begging his pardon, lies; Not a word of all he has uttered Has he ever been told my me. [PONLEVI seems disposed to retire through fear of LISIDA. LISIDA. Do not fear: say where was I speaking When you o'erheard me? PONLEVI. If I must speak, Since it was you yourself that ordered me, It was here. LISIDA. How long is it since? PONLEVI. But an instant. LISIDA. That is sufficient, Since if I did not go away Out of this spot, nor here was it written, It is clear, the cause of it is, My being undeceived in my jealousy, Not what Chloris has said to me. PONLEVI. Cleverly is the problem proven. ENRICO. So that it seems I am bound to believe You spoke falsely then to your sister, Now you are speaking the truth to me. LISIDA. Saw you never, Enrico, a table, Which when placed in one light presents A perfect form of exquisite beauty, And in another a monster feigns? For the figure is so indebted Unto the pencil's magical art, Opposite things it represents:— So is my love: in the light of Chloris It a monster of terror seems, But in that of Enrico, perfect Beauty becomes; and this alone In the soul is the only difference 'Twixt true love and one that is feigned. ENRICO. I know not how thy words are so potent, Notwithstanding my being deceived, That they make me credit you: let me At thy feet my gratitude show, Kissing the flower that their touch produces, Not to say, upon which they tread. LISIDA. Are not, think you, my arms more near thee? ENRICO. No, for they are a sphere too high. Enter CHLORIS and NISE. CHLORIS, aside to NISE. We have come at an evil moment. LISIDA to ENRICO. Lest this tiresome couple delay, And weary us waiting, take thy departure But for a little while, 'till they pass, And then return. ENRICO. Yes: I will do so. [Exit. LISIDA. Truly you owe me much, my sister, What would you more? I have embraced him, Merely to do what you command. [Exit. CHLORIS. Ah! you have given me death, my cousin, You from my hands have ta'en my arms, And given my weapons, even the weapons With which she strikes the deadly blow. NISE. It is quite true; yes, this deception Has turned out badly; but let us see If we may not strike out another. Have you some paper in your sleeve? CHLORIS. None but this, which is some trifling Bill or other. [Gives her a paper. NISE. 'Twill do quite well; Leave me now for awhile: the issue You, concealed, can easily see. [Exit Chloris. Ponlevi! PONLEVI. Your will, Señora? NISE. Listen to me. PONLEVI. What do you command? NISE. This. [She strikes him. PONLEVI. Good Heavens! you're going to strangle me! NISE. Caitiff vile! is it thus you dare To wrong my sense of honour? PONLEVI. What honour? NISE. Thus with blushless face of assurance So to dare? PONLEVI. But what have I dared? NISE. Wretch, be silent! [Strikes him again. PONLEVI. You are stabbing me With ten tapering daggers of crystal Bearing ten mother-of-pearl points. NISE. Thou to me? [She tears the paper. Enter LISIDA. LISIDA. What meaneth this outcry? What has happened, cousin? NISE. 'Tis nought:— Hence, thou scoundrel, infamous pander, Ere from a window out you fly; Thus I scatter the torn pieces, Numerous as spotted butterflies here, Of the letter you dared to bring me. PONLEVI. I? NISE. Presume not to answer a word. Hence! PONLEVI. Please Heaven..... NISE. Come, no replying. PONLEVI. That..... NISE. What, still dost thou dare to talk? Off with you! PONLEVI. Yes, I will do so.—Masters, [Aside. This lady has taken a drop too much. [Exit. LISIDA. Will you not tell me what has happened? NISE. Why, this fellow, before my face, Had the insolence to inform me That his master..... LISIDA. Speak! NISE. Desired Him to offer to me this letter; As he saw that he could not give Jealousy through thy means to Chloris, Now his hopes had turned to me. LISIDA, aside. This is another stroke of cunning; She must not carry her point in this. [Lifts up the pieces of torn paper. NISE. What are you doing, Lisida? LISIDA. Raising Merely the paper which you have torn. NISE. To what purpose? LISIDA. To this purpose, Nise, that as you once upraised A certain flower, which was Enrico's, Even from this very ground, to give It to Chloris, as if from Enrico, So do I, for a similar cause, Raise these pieces of torn paper. NISE, aside. Bless me! what unfortunate days Have been these for my efforts at lying. [LISIDA reads the fragments which she has collected. LISIDA. This says here, some lavender water— Here, a fresh egg—and here again, Powder of sublimate. This is sufficient— It showeth more concern than love; Since Enrico takes such precautions That you should wash your face so well, You must not have appeared to him thoroughly Neat, my Nise. NISE. Who can prevent The air from playing with pieces of paper? One it wafts, and another brings back; This, of course, cannot be the letter That I tore. LISIDA. It may be so: think How unhappy has been the issue Of all thy stratagems, all thy wiles. NISE. What are the wiles, and what the stratagems? LISIDA. These:— NISE. But do not compel me to say The many days that with passionate eagerness Unto me has Enrico paid court:— How he wooed me and wrote to me often, Tiring me out with his ceaseless suit. You yourself may hear him addressing To me the language of love, if you Hide for a little. LISIDA. I do not desire To take upon thee a greater vengeance, Than to convict thee of this lie; And since he will return, protected By these jessamines, I shall see If he writes to you, if he speaks to you. NISE. Heavens! Lisida dear, how quickly Thus you are taking me at my word! Do you not see I was only jesting? LISIDA. No, your object was to deceive. NISE. I but meant a little to rally thee; That was the object,—nothing more. LISIDA. Whether or no, I soon shall see it. [Conceals herself. NISE. Who e'er saw a more difficult pass? With the falsehood, Lisida holds me As within the jaws of a trap,— For in all his life, Enrico Scarcely a word to me has said. Enter ENRICO and PONLEVI. PONLEVI. Why like a bee around a hive, Do you circle this garden? ENRICO. 'Tis my centre; If now and then I did not enter, It were impossible to live. CHLORIS enters at the side scene, where she remains listening. CHLORIS, from her place of concealment. Here my attention I can give. LISIDA, from hers. From this spot the whole can be heard. ENRICO. Lisida promised not to have stirred Out of that spot. PONLEVI. She is not there, But in her place is Nise the fair. NISE, aside. Ah! he departs without saying a word. ENRICO, aside. Good God! here is Nise alone,— No one sees me, no one is near, If I could only conquer my fear, Opening the mine as the duke hath shown, I could serve his love and secure my own:— For a love that is secret and occult Should always a secret hour consult: I am alone and invisible here To Lisida, so I need not fear To make the attempt with a good result; Fair seraph of this sweet Paradise, [To NISE. This beautiful garden, love's bright bower, Since thou art both the guard and the flower, At once the protectress and the prize, Sheath the flashing sword of thine eyes, Hear the delicious sounds divine— Hear the trembling wishes that pine In the lover's bosom like prisoned doves, Accept this spoken homage as love's— And not, fair Nise, as if it were mine. NISE, aside. What is this that I hear? CHLORIS, aside. Ah, me! LISIDA, aside. Death my confidence doth reward. PONLEVI. Recollect this is Nise, my lord, And not Lisida. ENRICO. I saw thee, Therefore I love thee: so it should be: From that moment dazzled and blind, Heart and soul to thee I resign'd,— Motes that no other sunbeam know,— For thy form of beautiful snow Lives in a sphere of fire confined. Ever since then, my love to tell Day after day, an occasion I seek. PONLEVI. Think, my lord, 'tis to Nise you speak. ENRICO. I am not blind,—I know it well. LISIDA, aside. As love lives! it was truth that fell From Nise but now, whom he doth adore! CHLORIS, aside. Heavens! can there be a miracle more? It is for Nise that now he sighs! PONLEVI, aside. All in a moment for Nise he dies! NISE, aside. It must be love that but now he swore:— Who ever saw such a strange confusion! What was spoken in jest but now Turns out true one knows not how: Let me favour the new illusion. ENRICO. Though I have lived so long in delusion, Now undeceiving, at least, I die. NISE, aside. Never in all my life have I Seen a man more in love:—[aloud] But you Paid court to Chloris a time? ENRICO. 'Tis true, My will a slave at her feet did lie. CHLORIS, aside. Ah! the traitor, how soon it fled. NISE. Then it seems your affection is turn'd To Lisida, and for her you burn'd? ENRICO. My spirit was chain'd where her feet would tread:— This is the only true word I have said! [Aside. LISIDA, aside. Ah! how cruel! NISE. And now to me You offer your heart, the last of the three. ENRICO. In you my glory is all complete. NISE. Never in all my life did I meet A Florentine more Portuguese-like. ENRICO. To be Attached to two others will not be deem'd Any loss to the third, if you'll recollect. NISE. Why, can there be a greater defect? ENRICO. Rather a merit. No one has dream'd That anything should be less esteem'd, A book or a painting, a statue or blade, Because the artist perchance hath made Some others before it: no, it is thought Better fashion'd, more skilfully wrought, From his greater experience in art or trade. Thus I infer, in my love for you, It doth redound to its credit more, My having loved two others before; Not through election now I woo, Force, as God knows, I yield me to. For but living to-day in you, All that my love, my fortune can do— All the experience over me gone— Is to make a perfect work in one Of what I but learn'd in the other two. CHLORIS. This must I hear? LISIDA. This must I see? [NISE goes and takes LISIDA by the hand, and leads her where CHLORIS is standing. NISE. To back a palpable sophistry, You must reply, dear cousin mine, See if thou wilt thy claim resign. LISIDA, to ENRICO. Tell me again to trust to thee. PONLEVI. What could hither our steps allure? ENRICO. Help me, Heaven! NISE, to CHLORIS. You are now secure. CHLORIS. Not altogether:— NISE. What can it be That you now require? CHLORIS. To be sure of thee, Who will secure me?—so that the cure Worse than the old disease may prove. NISE. I have brought a doubt on his love, That was all I wish'd to produce. [Exeunt NISE and CHLORIS. LISIDA, to ENRICO. What have you now to say in excuse? Have you no tongue? ENRICO. It cannot move. LISIDA. Defend thy contract. ENRICO. 'Twere vain to try. LISIDA. Explain the cause. ENRICO. No power have I. LISIDA. Deceive me again. ENRICO. 'Twere little use. LISIDA. Speak. ENRICO. 'Tis fear that my words repress. LISIDA. Whose is the falsehood? ENRICO. Mine, I know. LISIDA. Whose is the truth? ENRICO. 'Tis mine also. LISIDA. Then what you said was a falsehood? ENRICO. Yes. LISIDA. This is not an evasion? ENRICO. No. LISIDA. No new deception has enter'd thy brain? ENRICO. Sincerity never has need to feign. PONLEVI. Did I not tell you over and over, That this was not the place for a lover? You wouldn't believe me, now all is vain. LISIDA. Such a false deceiving lover may die. ENRICO. Firm in his faith he means to live. LISIDA. What proofs of your firmness do you give? ENRICO. My silence, and my constancy. LISIDA. You are easy to melt. ENRICO. A diamond, I, LISIDA. Jealousy, anger, cloud my sense. ENRICO. Ah! upon what a slight pretence, Can the little sly god with wiles Turn into frowns the sunniest smiles, And make of love itself an offence.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. SCENE I. —THE STREET BEFORE FABIO'S HOUSE—NIGHT. Enter the DUKE, ENRICO, PONLEVI, and a MUSICIAN. DUKE. There is no power to which love will submit. ENRICO. One thing alone can make love do it. DUKE. And what is that? ENRICO. The will to subdue it; So Garcilaso, my lord, hath writ. DUKE. Then 'twas a false conceit of wit; For that can have but the same effect As forgetfulness, which men select As a cure for ills that are past recall, And which for love is no cure at all; Some other remedy recollect. ENRICO. This, notwithstanding, the way must be Of him who would save his heart from ruin. Yes, the beginning of love's subduing Is the desire of victory,— For how is it possible that he Can love the thing that he would forget? Thus the first obstacle is met;— That being conquer'd, the difficulty Is not in getting the victory, But in the earnest wish to get. DUKE. Well, it may be so; let me know How you have sped with Nise, though. ENRICO. Badly she heard my proffer'd love, (Ah! it is true, my death she'll prove!) [Aside. And since the return of Fabio, Such strictness reigns in the house, that no Chance is there now of getting nigh her. DUKE. Still persevere, until the fire Is totally quench'd that burns me so,— For if my suspicion could only know The truth it aims at, I would be Sure of obtaining the victory Over love, as in that case I would wish to subdue him. ENRICO. Your grace It is an affair of difficulty. DUKE. Fabio I know is most austere. ENRICO. Hush! For now methinks I hear In the balcony yonder some low voices. DUKE. And here again are some other noises; Let us, Enrico, draw more near. [CHLORIS and NISE appear at one window, LISIDA and CELIA at another. ENRICO. How, my lord, shall it clearly appear Which of the windows doth Chloris prefer, That you may try to speak to her? DUKE. Let us divide, and take separate stations, Thus we can make our observations, And on the results with each other confer. ENRICO. 'Tis an excellent plan, and so I take My position here. DUKE. And I shall pay The closest attention from this:—But stay, For hark! through the night's dark stillness break Sweet sounds, that tell us they mean to awake The notes of a harp. CHLORIS, to NISE. Dear Nise, thou'lt be The wish'd for syren of love's wild sea, If my pain thou'lt alleviate. LISIDA, to CELIA. Sing, Celia, and mitigate The fatal disease that killeth me. ENRICO, to the DUKE. Lest, perchance, your grace should express A wish to embark on this mimic sea, I have brought this musician with me: If they sing, shall he sing too? DUKE. Yes. PONLEVI. I, too, won't have power to repress My voice from responding to thy pain. ENRICO. Sing then, and perchance thy strain To a milder mood the heavens may move. DUKE, to the MUSICIAN. Sing to me the praises of love. LISIDA, to CELIA. Sing to me of jealousy's pain. CHLORIS, to NISE. Sing to me the praises of sadness. ENRICO, to PONLEVI. Sing to me the praises of joy; That the sun may know he cannot destroy, Even by his absence, beauty and gladness. THE MUSICIAN sings. Love, Love, then rulest above Kingdoms and laws and powerfullest things; Weak to thine is the sceptre of kings,— The only potent monarch is Love! CELIA sings. Jealousy, why to thee is given This name reproachfully! since the jealous But for one letter would be the zealous— And only the zealous reach to Heaven! PONLEVI sings. Who, O Fortune, with longing sighs Will at thy heedless altar kneel? Oh! paint with wings thy fickle wheel, Since swifter far than it rolls, it flies. NISE sings. Reason, Reason, tell me, I pray, How long shall conquering love be thy master? If pleasure, in coming, will not travel faster, Why shouldst thou fly so swiftly away? DUKE, to the MUSICIAN. Let no interruption come near thee. LISIDA, to CELIA. Cease not from the melody, no,— ENRICO, to PONLEVI. Oh! continue and speak my woe. CHLORIS, to NISE. Sing more; 'tis a joy to hear thee. MUSICIAN sings. Has fate some favour still concealed? CELIA sings. Has hope some blessing rich and strange? PONLEVI sings. Can thus my sorrows have some change? NISE sings. Can love's deep heart-wounds then be healed? DUKE. Sing, although their songs excel. LISIDA. Be not silent, although they sing. ENRICO. Sing,—your words some solace bring. CHLORIS. Do not cease, since you sing well. ALL sing. Reason, fortune, jealousy, love, Are passions that vary, Reason faileth through time And fortune grows weary,— Love is a fire which jealousy kindles, Pleasure groweth fatigued, And passion dwindles. DUKE coming to the window, in which are CHLORIS and NISE. Now that on the silent zephyr Gently dies your voice, fair Nise, Let it take thee, for my hope's sake, On my part an humble message. CHLORIS, aside to NISE. 'Tis the duke, say not I'm with thee, That he may not now address me. NISE. No, my lord, let not your highness Trust your hopes to such a medium, For within a fond heart's centre Is enshrined your worshipped image. DUKE. If the lady who is with thee Would say this, beyond expression Were my happiness. NISE. I doubt it, As the person who deceives you Is but one of my attendants. DUKE. Is it so?—then bid her say so. NISE. She is dumb and speaks no language. DUKE. 'Tis love's language that she knows not. LISIDA, to ENRICO. Badly do these fond expressions Harmonize with fickle actions. ENRICO. Rightly do these words' warm accents Come to aid as true devotion. LISIDA. What my eyes behold, they credit. ENRICO. Glasses dim the vision sometimes? LISIDA. No, it is impossible, If the crystals are but perfect. ENRICO. The most perfect oft deceive. DUKE. I shall come again, await me, I must see who this is yonder:— [He comes and speaks aside to ENRICO. Hark! Enrico. ENRICO. Please your highness:— DUKE. Firm is Chloris in her rigour, Since she will not even acknowledge That she is with Nise. ENRICO. Well, What do you wish, my lord? DUKE. That you Pass unto the other window; And as equal objects brought us Two together here this night, (You perchance to speak with Nise, Or with Chloris I,) and now One of these has been frustrated, Let us not be balked in both;— There she is; advance, thou knowest That on this my life depends. ENRICO. Such an incident to happen! CHLORIS comes to LISIDA'S window. CHLORIS. Lisida! LISIDA. Your pleasure, sister? CHLORIS. Yonder is the duke, attempting Every means to recognise me; He beheld two forms, to hinder Him from knowing I was one,— I entreat you to go thither. LISIDA. If you hither come to know Who is with me, I am happy To afford that satisfaction; 'Tis Enrico, and I go That you may speak with him. CHLORIS. No. LISIDA. I shall go: [aside] But 'tis that I Thus can make new observations; Let us see now which deceive me— Natural eyes, or crystal glasses. PONLEVI. In this night of roundelays, Sighs and songs and amorous speeches, I have none to speak to: so, While the rest converse in couples, I shall ask Don Monsieur Morpheus For his company awhile. [Stretches himself to sleep. OCTAVIO enters, and remains where PONLEVI had been standing. OCTAVIO, aside. If the man who feeleth one jealousy Cannot possibly be at rest, He who nourisheth two, how can he Be secure a moment of time? DUKE, to ENRICO. Come then. ENRICO, aside. That to this should compel me, One whose power doth equal his love. DUKE. Why do you wait? ENRICO. A man is yonder. DUKE. That, by no means, need give you alarm,— It is Ponlevi: he has been waiting There all along in secret. ENRICO, aside. Heavens! Grant me now some words of dissembling, That I may a goddess deceive. CHLORIS. Thanks be to Heaven! that now I am free from The pain of hearing the duke's complaints. DUKE. No, you must hear them; still will he seek you Wherever you are. CHLORIS, aside. What a singular chance! Heavens! from his suit I wish'd to withdraw me, And lo! I have fallen into his hands. Now, of necessity, I must speak to him. ENRICO, aside. I am here a little assured, Seeing that Lisida cannot possibly Hear my words, as she with the duke Now doth speak at the other window:— Most beautiful Nise...... [Aloud. OCTAVIO, aside. Does he say Nise? ENRICO. Since your voice of ravishment Seemeth the loadstone of all that lives, Drawing hither unto this threshold Wondering wild beasts out of the rocks, Beautiful birds from amid the flowers, Give occasion still for the thought That your dulcet singing allures one Here to die of its poisoned sweets, Which the cup of the night-air holds. LISIDA, aside. What is this, O Heavens! that I hear? Ah! has he hither come to seek me, That thus he might lose me once for all? OCTAVIO, aside. O faithless friend! and O thou lover, So lost to gratitude! As Heaven lives, Nought but his life can this atone for. [Exit. ENRICO. If you wish to know if my sufferings Are really felt, quite easy the proof. LISIDA. Not so easy, because I am certain That no hour of your life, Enrico, Is with the others perfectly true,— See if the crystals now mislead me. ENRICO. Lisida!...... LISIDA. Say not another word. ENRICO. As the Heavens live!...... LISIDA. Attempt no vain effort At giving me satisfaction again; Do not see me, do not speak to me. [LISIDA and NISE leave the window. ENRICO. Hear! listen!..... but what do I see? The gate of the garden some one opens:— My lord! DUKE. What now? ENRICO. I see a man Coming here from the house of Fabio. CHLORIS. It is my father; go, my lord, Out of the street before he sees you. [CHLORIS and CELIA also retire. DUKE. It is Fabio, let us go; Conceal thy face in thy cloak, Enrico; Me he will know not. ENRICO. What avails All concealments and dark disguises, When the day will bring to light What the treacherous night concealeth? [Exeunt. Enter FABIO. FABIO. Home! how badly you receive me! On the very day I come To your threshold, must I meet with, First of all, my griefs and cares?— A suspicion of Enrico's Aim on Chloris, that I had Ere he went to Spain, has brought me Swiftly hither from Milan, To be certain, if he causes Public scandals such as these; They have seen me and departed Those who so disturbed the street; Who they are I must discover. [Stumbles over PONLEVI. PONLEVI. Who's that? FABIO. Who's this? PONLEVI. 'Tis now very late, And so I beg of you, my good master, To cut short your nonsensical talk With Mesdames Lisida, Nise, and Chloris, And let us go. FABIO. That I may have first An opportunity to despatch you. PONLEVI. Oh! Heavens! what a grandfather's beard! What sudden terror in half a moment Has bearded you thus to such a length? FABIO. Say, to whom dost thou act as a servant? PONLEVI. 'Tis an easy thing to tell his name: To Enrico. FABIO. And this Enrico, Which of those three ladies doth love? PONLEVI. He loves them all. FABIO. This man is a simpleton; Which does he court? PONLEVI. He courts them all. FABIO. Tell me of which he is the suitor? PONLEVI. Of all, and it tires him not in the least. Not one of them all can he resign; Being, as it were, a triple-faced lover, Past, present, and the future, in one. FABIO. That I do not kill thee, is owing To your being beneath my wrath; It were a wrong to my sword to stain it With the pollution of such base blood. PONLEVI. Base blood is a lucky distinction Now and then. FABIO. Hence! fellow, away— Quick! PONLEVI. Yes, with the greatest pleasure. [Exit. FABIO. Enrico, building upon the favour Of the duke, thus ventures to bring These public scandals upon mine honour, Unworthily:—and since the thought That before his departure was only Mere suspicion has now become A matter certain beyond all question, Let me devise some remedy. Two methods are there in such a serious Conjunction of grief: prudence is one, And valour the other: upon the former Let me in the first instance rely:— I shall go to the duke, to complain me Of this outrage; if that doth fail, Then I must appeal to my valour. [Exit. SCENE II. —A ROOM IN THE PALACE. Enter OCTAVIO and ENRICO. OCTAVIO. Here, Enrico, I have sought thee. ENRICO. Well, my friend, your wishes say:— OCTAVIO. Give me not that name, I pray, Since thou'rt not what once I thought thee; 'Tis no friend who courts and kills And wounds you most when most confiding, Like the ungrateful serpent gliding Into the breast, where it distils Its poison, beyond all prevention:— To thee no more this name hath clung, Since you flatter with the tongue, And you kill with the intention. ENRICO. My truth I deign not to defend, Heaven be the witness! Earth the judge! Besides, you know we must not grudge The first suspicion to a friend:— Methought my friendship might have reckon'd On this indulgence, that it durst Answer you thus: we've pass'd the first— Let us not go to seek the second. OCTAVIO. Yes, we must do so: since, unmoved By all my heart to thee outpoured, Telling you how I Nise adored, Telling you how I Nise loved;— You, perfidious, your love durst break to her, You, ungrateful, your homage pay, You to her send letters by day, And at night, you dare to speak to her! ENRICO. Octavio, I cannot deny What you say and what you discerned, What you heard or what you have learned, Still I cannot give a reply Which an apology might appear, Or the faintest wish to excuse; But I cannot permit you use Reasons which only are too clear; Thus with justice I come to be Offended in turn, since if you know The reasons why you address me so, I know those that influence me:— My friendship this replies, since we Speak in the palace of his grace. OCTAVIO. Then name, Enrico, name the place Where our dispute may be more free. ENRICO. Then be it..... Enter the DUKE and PONLEVI. DUKE. What is this? ENRICO. 'Tis nought, My lord. DUKE, aside. The two with troubled air Appear confused; their looks of care Show that my love this strife hath wrought: I must prevent the consequence. Octavio! OCTAVIO. Can I serve your grace? DUKE. Be good enough the desk to place, And bring the writing implements:— You can retire until we call! OCTAVIO, aside to ENRICO. Where shall we end our affair, we two? ENRICO. Where, I shall let thee know. OCTAVIO. Adieu. [Exit. ENRICO, to PONLEVI. You can await me in the hall. [Exit PONLEVI. DUKE. Enrico, what is this about? ENRICO. A loss, my gracious lord, which has been The greater from its being foreseen To be inevitable. DUKE. Has he found out The affair so quickly? But my mission Must be to make you friends again. ENRICO. Ah! no, my lord, in honour's pain Nor power nor rank is the best physician. Enter FABIO. FABIO, aside. Enrico with him, so much the better!— Can you allow me an audience, sire? DUKE. Yes: Enrico, do thou retire. ENRICO, aside. Now to write Octavio's letter. [Exit. FABIO. Since my griefs I cannot control, But calmly and sadly the thoughts arise, Would that the tears that flow from my eyes Were the tongues of my very soul! DUKE, aside. My troubles I see are not all past:— What is the matter, Fabio? FABIO. Why, Anguish, my lord, and honour have I, And I weep because of the last: A cruel burden beareth about it The soul to which Fortune honour gives; He cannot live happily he who lives Either with honour, or yet without it.— I have two daughters, my lord. DUKE, aside. No doubt Can now remain; good heavens! that he Cometh here to complain of me Even to myself, having found out My love for Chloris:—Yes, I know [Aloud. That honour the brightest and most pure In either beauty may be secure, And your confidence speaketh so. FABIO. Not so much, but some power may leave A shade on this boasted brightness yet. DUKE, aside. He speaks more plainly:—[aloud] Do not let, Fabio, your generous heart believe Too easily what may doubtful appear. FABIO. I am not, my lord, so indiscreet As to approach your grace's feet Badly informed, as you shall hear:— Enrico, using the friendly relations He is on with you, as wings to near A brighter and more ambitious sphere, Insults with foolish manifestations Of love my house. DUKE, aside. I breathe more free: Although the blame that to him is given Does not prove that I am forgiven;— Since I am in fault as well as he. FABIO. And so I ask your grace, that you Diminish this evil. DUKE. Passion-warmed, You hither come, and badly informed, For I myself am certain you do Enrico wrong, being aware, The lady to whom he doth pretend Cannot injure you, nor offend. FABIO. Again, my lord, I have to declare, Not blindly in this matter I grope, Since I know, ere he went to Spain, Chloris was the cause of his pain— The beautiful sky that bound his hope:— Since I know, from his embassy Having returned, he still doth pay His obstinate suit—for by night and day The Argus of my house is he; Can any misconception follow from thence? Is not, my lord, the evidence clear? Does my honour no outrage fear On such undoubted evidence? DUKE. What did you say? FABIO. That he pays court To Chloris. DUKE, aside. Ah! my heart, what woe!— And before he went to Spain? FABIO. 'Tis so. DUKE, aside. What do I hear? O heavens! FABIO. In short, As he, my lord, I have little doubt, With Chloris holds a higher place, From his great favour with your grace, You must his marriage bring about:— Or having, at so great a cost, Thus tried my anger to allay, I must attempt some other way To find my honour that is lost. DUKE, aside. Oh! what poison these replies— Oh! what darkness this eclipse— Make me drink without my lips? Makes me see without my eyes? Let me recall the day aright Of his return—my drive, and where— Yes, 'twas the park—I found him there— And how she avoided me that night; Then came the question, light and gay, Of the scarf and flower, which rank'd above The other? Oh! what memory, love, Dost thou possess? Thou need'st not say That since then she wrote to be Excused receiving my respects— The cause is proven by the effects, That his coming banish'd me. FABIO. Does justice then so little owe Unto my wrong, my bitter pain— That one word you do not deign To give me in reply? DUKE. Oh! no— No, Fabio, it is because Words cannot answer your appeal— And I can yet do naught but feel. FABIO. Then to my birthright—valour's laws— Must I appeal in my distress:— Enter ENRICO and PONLEVI; they converse apart. ENRICO. You are to seek Octavio, And to give him this letter; go. PONLEVI. Octavio did you say, sir? ENRICO. Yes. DUKE, aside. Enrico, here!—I scarce can smother My wrath, or trust myself to stay, This is no place to do or say— Pass then from one extreme to the other, My grief. ENRICO. Your grace seems somewhat heated, And full of anger—what is the reason? DUKE. I shall tell you in good season. [Exit. PONLEVI. This is a pretty way we are treated. ENRICO. Fabio, can you explain this? FABIO. No, I understand it not—if I could Explain it to myself I would; But as it is, I do not know. [Exit. PONLEVI. I told you that you should not love Chloris, in that desperate way, And that it would some future day To you a source of sorrow prove; But Octavio passes yonder, I shall make no more delays. [Exit with the letter. ENRICO. Ah! through what a cruel maze Of entanglement I wander! Enter CELIA, veiled. CELIA. Till I found him, have I enter'd Treading soft with leaden footsteps, Not to say that they are woollen,— Hist! ENRICO. Is it I? CELIA. Yes. ENRICO. Then I hear you. CELIA. My Señora...... ENRICO. O my Celia! CELIA. Sends you this. [Hands him a letter. ENRICO. I feel most happy, Though, perchance, in it should come Anger, anguish, and resentment, For the person who remembers, Even to chide, cannot forget us; [Reads. “One revenge must my wrongs obtain, and that is an opportunity of telling them. Repair immediately to the public walk; I shall meet you at the country-seat of the duke, where you may hear them, and I can speak them.” [Resumes aside. The very hour and situation, That I have mentioned to Octavio, Has Lisida for me appointed; Since I wrote to him to meet me In the grove beside the villa:— I am once again bewildered. Shall I send her an excuse? No, it would but add another New suspicion. It is better That I may not be the hindrance Of my fortune, there to meet her, And however ends the matter, Whether good or ill, I reckon On a full, free exculpation;— Say to Lisida, my Celia, [Aloud. I am eager to obey her. Enter PONLEVI. PONLEVI, aside. As an answer to the letter Which but now I brought Octavio, I bring this, which at my entrance Here, was given me by a stranger;— But who's here?—Is not this damsel Beauteous Celia, whom I worship? CELIA to ENRICO. I shall tell her so. [Going. ENRICO. Hark! Celia. CELIA. What are your wishes? ENRICO. Wait a little: The duke, 'tis plain, is disappointed [Aside. With me, or has grown suspicious, That I have not yet discover'd The hidden love-designs of Chloris— Now perhaps the secret casket I with golden key may open, Since the occasion is propitious. Celia of my eyes, my Celia, [Aloud. In thy hand my life is lying— My enjoyment, my heart's quiet— All I have and all I value At thy feet to-day I offer. CELIA. Why with such exaggeration Thus address me? PONLEVI, aside. Am I dreaming?— Flattering speeches too to Celia!— This the only thing was wanting To his being now in love with All the family of Fabio. CELIA. I am ignorant what you aim at. ENRICO. Take this diamond—sparkling offspring Of the sun—Apollo's radiance, Though a stone. CELIA. I only take it, Not to seem, Señor, uncivil. PONLEVI, aside. Uncivil! O ungrateful Celia! Why you're more so than a monkey; You should not take it then. ENRICO. Thou Celia, To end the matter, art the mistress Of my life. CELIA. Then be it known to you I am thine. PONLEVI, aside. And I am furious! Thine she says—that I should see this!— Thine she says—that I should hear this!— I shall kill him—ah! but no— For he is my lord,—how doubtful Do I stand 'twixt love and honour— Here a fool, and there a madman. ENRICO. Tell me, Celia, since the house-thief Prieth everywhere, 'tis needful Nothing can from you be hidden That is in it...... PONLEVI. Nor you either. ENRICO. Who is speaking there? PONLEVI. Your servant. ENRICO. Wait then farther off. PONLEVI. How pleasant! [They speak in a low tone of voice, PONLEVI standing apart. ENRICO. Who pays court to Chloris, tell me, Who is he the happy lover That doth merit her, for whom She disdains the duke? And, Celia, If through thee I reach this knowledge...... CELIA. Say no more,—to all I answer Only this, that I am handmaid Unto Lisida—and sorry Am I, that from her I brought you On her part, that amorous letter; That for jealousies some other Consolation you should look for:— What a fair atonement! [Exit. ENRICO. Hear me! What ridiculous punctilio! Even a waiting-maid I'm destined To make jealous! PONLEVI. Ay, and me too, Ay, and every man, I'm thinking, On the earth. Great king of the Romans, Tarquin. Treacherous and unrighteous master— False, promiscuous, and pursuing High and low, tag-rag and bobtail— Is it thus to a loyal valet That you break the faith and duty That you owe him? Was it, tell me, With this object (Heavens! I'm choking!) That I told you, I loved Celia? That I said I Celia worshipped? ENRICO. As I live, by heavens! you rascal From the sharp point to the pummel Of this sword...... PONLEVI. Now do not swear so,— For the affair is too transparent; With my very ears I've heard it— With my very eyes I've seen it. ENRICO. I shall make thy heart's blood bathe thee In a false bright red enamel, If you cease not. PONLEVI. Can the jealous Then be silent, how? why? wherefore? ENRICO. Human patience ne'er was tempted In this manner! PONLEVI. In this manner Were our women ever tempted? ENRICO. Leave my presence, idiot, madman. PONLEVI. Yes, when I relate my mission. I thy letter gave Octavio, Which he took; on coming hither, In the hall a servant gave me This, to you to be delivered. [Gives a letter and exit. ENRICO. [Reads] “I did not say when I spoke to you, that my determination was taken to refuse hearing your explanations; and because in the field they cannot be given, I await you behind the pleasure-house of the duke. I desire to speak with you beside the rivulet that divides it from the wood. God guard thee!—Fabio.” Oh! that Fortune thus should conjure Up against one wretched being Such a concourse of misfortunes! Let me just enumerate them. Where I'm bound to meet Octavio Is the thicket of the duke; Lisida appoints the villa, Fabio the rapid streamlet Which in this place separateth The same building from some elms.— Now 'tis plain I must be deaf to Lisida's dear letter—Love Must descend his throne, for Honour There to rule with sovereign sway— I Octavio cite, and Fabio Citeth me, both one and the other At one time and for one quarrel. If the one doth bravely wait me, I as bravely wait the other— Which dilemma is the stronger, To meet him whom I have challenged Or who challenged me? The two Have their force—for in all questions Of this nice and delicate nature, Honour has its paradoxes, Which the duel, skilled in settling Differences, must reconcile: Since an equal right it giveth, That which is for me occasion'd— And that which I myself occasion:— To meet him whom I have summon'd, Is to satisfy my own wrong— Him who summons me, another's:— But this is a false deduction; For another's wrong that summons Me to answer, is my own:— In the one case, the same reason Which I have, because the duel Is by me originated, Is against me in the other:— To fail him whom I have challenged, Is to leave a grave suspicion That I could my promise break:— For he'll seek the place of meeting On the faith of that. As little Can I fail to meet the other, Since, relying on my honour, He awaits me; so that neither One nor the other can I turn from, Since if I cannot attend to Even the challenge of two pleasures, Tell me, Fortune, can I listen Unto the call of two such griefs? How can it be, that terror doeth, Every hindrance falsifying, What even pleasure fails to do? In the eye of reason, doubtless, Both complain without a cause, They of Nise and of Chloris Mutually complain, while I Neither worship lovely Chloris Nor fair Nise do I love;— Who will e'er believe, O Heavens! That 'twere possible, that I, So enamour'd, so devoted, Can two other men make jealous About ladies that I love not, And not one, 'bout her I love?— Well, to have at least this solace! And for this one gleam of rapture I, my evil fortune pardon All its other forms of woe, Though I notice at one moment, Fabio's anger undeceives me, That Octavio speaks revilings, That the duke, grown discontented, Doubts my faith and flies my presence,— That fair Chloris now is weeping Tears that flow from old illusions— That poor Nise feels indignant At the mockery of my wooing— That my Lisida herself, Mourning needlessly, intrusteth Her belief to seeming truth— That reproachfully speaks Celia— And that even a fool, a madman Must be jealous even of her!— All of which, I tell thee, Fortune, Without anger I forgive, And still more, that these my musings, Even by sifting, find a way, By which, full of cheerful daring, I both challenges may meet:— This indeed is much to promise, But I feel it may be done;— Would, O gracious Heaven! to-day It were done, for then were over Anger, vengeances, vexations, Insults, injuries, distractions, Rage, revilings, and offences, Complaints, resentments, and confusions, Shadows, dreamings, and surmises, Strange illusions and caprices, And jealousy which means all these. [Exit. SCENE III. —A WOOD. Enter FABIO. FABIO. Let this shady thicket be The appropriate theatre of my destiny. The duke shall know, it doth belong To Fabio's self, to satisfy his wrong Without him. Here Enrico I shall fight, Armed not with steel, but with my sense of right: A rustling sound from yonder point comes near, Yes 'tis two women who are walking here, About this seat, where Nature doth display April's young charms and all the sweets of May. Enter ENRICO. ENRICO. Pardon, if I have delayed. FABIO. Death ne'er delays, Not even from him who looks with longing gaze For his approach; yes, here, some time beneath This tree, I have waited, to...... ENRICO. Your sword still sheath; This place is far too public here, and so Let us go deeper into the thicket. FABIO. Let us go. [They enter. SCENE IV. —ANOTHER PART OF THE WOOD. Enter OCTAVIO. OCTAVIO. Let no one say that any act can show More courage or more valour, than the slow Approach of an antagonist, to wait, I do not say to fight, that hath a double fate, But to await him, this doth bring to light More certain steady valour than to fight:— People approach; Enrico 'tis—and Fabio Is with him. Enter ENRICO and FABIO. FABIO, aside. As I live, it is Octavio! Enrico's friend; why this must be An ambuscade,—O traitor! OCTAVIO, aside. O false enemy! I, here alone, Enrico had expected [Aloud. To meet you...... FABIO. Here alone, and unprotected. OCTAVIO. And not with Fabio at thy side. FABIO. And not by Octavio accompanied. OCTAVIO. Well, even to meet you two I am not loth. FABIO. Well, should you wish it, even to meet you both, Courage enough have I. OCTAVIO. And I the same! ENRICO. Hear me, and you shall learn that here alone I came. I wrote to you that in this place, Octavio, I would expect you; at the same time, Fabio Wrote to me to the same effect. In this Extreme perplexity and dark abyss, Bewilder'd at my double character, At once the challenged and the challenger, Confused and sadden'd thus, I durst Not be the judge to which to turn to first, And so, together I have brought you,— See now, if accompanied, I sought you, Arrange the point of precedence; that being known, You are two, you are men of honour, I am alone. Enter the DUKE. DUKE. Is Enrico here? ENRICO. Yes, here I stray. DUKE. I am rejoiced that I did persevere, In seeking you, until I met you here: Were not my orders not to leave to-day The palace? ENRICO. I can only say By way of excuse, my lord...... DUKE. 'Tis well,— All now is understood that late befell— With your whole conduct I am hurt; I say That I will punish another way Him who has made my heart with sorrow swell. ENRICO. My lord...... DUKE. Enough. ENRICO. If I may be...... DUKE. No more. ENRICO. Allowed...... DUKE. Still more offences, you Are adding to your first. Remain, you two; Do thou, Enrico, come along with me. [Exit. ENRICO. Even as thy shadow shall I follow thee. [Exit. OCTAVIO. That his favour should occasion this! FABIO. That this should happen from a power like his! OCTAVIO. O evil fate! FABIO. O luckless destiny! OCTAVIO. No vengeance is there for my jealousy! FABIO. Vengeance to-day, my honour you must miss. [Exeunt. SCENE V. —A ROOM IN THE DUKE'S COUNTRY PALACE. Enter LISIDA and CELIA. LISIDA. To the most remote apartment Of the duke's house have I entered, And even here, to me it seemeth, We are not in perfect safety From my father; but the gardener Who has left us here, and went Out to see what is occurring, (For with women, I have noticed, Ever is a swain obliging Ever is a rustic courteous)— Does he not delay? CELIA. Not greatly, For I hear a key now turning In the gallery-door, and some one Enters by that way. LISIDA. Who is it? CELIA. Enrico and the duke. LISIDA. Alas! What shall he say, if he finds me Thus concealed within his dwelling, And in this disguise? I know not Why, against my cruel fortune, Heaven unites such torturing foes. CELIA. What shall we do? LISIDA. There is a closet Here, and luckily it is open; Let us, Celia, hide therein; They may pass without perceiving We are there. I thus may gain More than lose by this adventure, Since I must, to some remoter Time, adjourn my present doubts. [They enter the closet, which looks out in the garden; the door is closed. Enter the DUKE and ENRICO. ENRICO. What, my lord, have you discovered That so much doth irritate you, Seeking thus the most secluded Chamber here for explanation? DUKE. First I'll see if yonder closet Door is locked, before I speak:— Yes, we are alone, Enrico, And the fitting time is now, To acquaint me with the substance Of what you have learned for me Of the feelings of fair Chloris— Who is then her lover? Who? ENRICO. Though, complying with your orders, I paid seeming court to Nise, Nothing certain could I learn. DUKE. There we differ, for I have! ENRICO. Chloris then has got a lover? DUKE. Yes, Enrico. ENRICO. Do you know him? DUKE. As a traitor—a deceiver. ENRICO. If I knew him, I would give him Death this moment by this sword. DUKE. No; for I myself must do so; Since in Honour's grave diseases, Power is but a bad physician, And since valour is more skilful, I prefer to trust to it. Villain! draw thy sword, defend thee— Here we're equal man to man— You and I, and none to see us. [The DUKE draws his sword. ENRICO. Oh! my lord, my lord, restrain thee! Whilst submissive at thy feet, I implore that, ere you slay me, You at least will tell me why. DUKE. This it is, that you, though loving Chloris ere you went to Spain, When my heart to you intrusted All the secret of its love, You, I say, concealed your passion Underneath your broken faith. ENRICO. Oh! withhold your sword, your highness. Oh! withhold your arm, withhold These reproaches, which afflict me More than all, and hear the truth. DUKE. Speak then. ENRICO. I loved Lisida From the moment I first saw her: Chloris may, my lord, in mocking Mood, perhaps her scorn have lessened, Which with common courtesy I acknowledge, since, believe me, Chloris I have never loved. DUKE. What! you never loved her? ENRICO. No. DUKE. Then a new offence you offer To my lady and myself:— If you loved her, you offended Me in that, and if you loved not, You offended her as well. [Advancing. ENRICO, retiring to the door. Heaven, my lord, I call to witness That I cannot now recede One step further. DUKE. It were useless. ENRICO. Loyalty be now my judge, That if this were a balcony, I would fling myself from it. DUKE. I would leap too, and pursue thee. ENRICO. Everything respect suggested I have done—retired before thee Till the very wall I've reached to;— By the cross upon this sword-hilt Do I swear to thee I draw it, But on this account—this only— That I can retire no further. DUKE. And for this alone I have waited, But to see thy sword unsheathed, That I then might thus attack thee. [ENRICO draws his sword, placing his back against the door by which LISIDA and CELIA had entered; they open it, ENRICO passes through, and it is immediately closed. ENRICO. Heaven, no doubt, my life preserveth For some reason known to it. [Door closes. DUKE. Heavens! within this room were hiding Strangers,—I shall break the door, Splintering it in thousand pieces With my hands and with my feet. [He strikes with his dagger at the door. LISIDA, within. Gardeners of this country palace, Help! come quickly, break the door, For the duke in sudden anger Slays Enrico. DUKE. 'Tis the voice Of fair Lisida.—The Heavens Give to thee both life and fortune. FABIO, within. Break the door, now let us enter Every one. DUKE. Well, since no more Valour now can give me vengeance, Wit must do it; yes, I think I have found a means. Enter FABIO, CHLORIS, OCTAVIO, NISE, and PONLEVI. FABIO. 'Tis opened:— What is this? DUKE. What could it be? But for anger, satisfaction, And for jealousy, the same, It delights me, lovely Chloris, To behold you here and now. CHLORIS. Walking hither with my sister Some hours since, she wished to stay Until fell the shades of evening, And I have returned for her. DUKE. Then in time for gratulations, Have you come, for she is wed. FABIO. Wed! my lord, and say with whom? DUKE. With Enrico: 'twas an error, Fabio, when you thought that he Was in love with lovely Chloris, Since it seems 'twas Lisida;— I heard all about the challenge From this servant. PONLEVI. I should be Speaker of your house, your highness. DUKE. I, the happy end foreseeing, Matters so arranged, that they Stay within this garden waiting Till your anger is appeased; Let it not disturb a rapture That thy sanction only needs. CHLORIS, aside. Enrico I have lost! ah, me! NISE, aside. Naught with us to-day has prospered. DUKE. Come, Enrico, hither come; Come, fair Lisida, and kneeling Kiss your sire's forgiving hand. Enter LISIDA and ENRICO. ENRICO. First I kiss thy feet, your highness. LISIDA. May the green eternal laurel Bind thy brows, my gracious prince. FABIO, aside. Though I don't believe a tittle Of all this, I must affect it, Since 'twill give a contradiction To the rumours of the vulgar, When my daughter is his wife:— All is owing to your favour. [Aloud to the DUKE. DUKE. Make this peace secure, Octavio, And to Nise give thy hand, Since, alas! the lovely Chloris Is so fair, that no one here Doth deserve her.—Ah! fair tyrant, [Aside. Well I now revenge thy scorn. CHLORIS. Let this explanation bring Unto all a sure conviction, That to do a wrong to Love, Can but prosper for a short time; Being a god, he needs must triumph Over every other foe. FABIO, to the audience. May your favour grant us pardon For the faults that we have shown. END OF THE SCARF AND THE FLOWER.</field>
   </doc>
</add>