<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Shadwell, Charles</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Shadwell, Charles</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">shadwell charles</field>
      <field name="author_text">Shadwell, Charles</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">18th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1720's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V2.0331.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240355</field>
      <field name="date_text">1720</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460037</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Rotherick O'Connor, King of Connaught</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Rotherick O'Connor, King of Connaught</field>
      <field name="title_facet">rotherick oconnor king of connaught</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">rotherick oconnor king of connaught</field>
      <field name="title_text">Rotherick O'Connor, King of Connaught</field>
      <field name="year_display">1720</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1720</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1720</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460037&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460037&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Shadwell, Charles&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;shadwell charles&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Rotherick O'Connor, King of Connaught&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;rotherick oconnor, king of connaught&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1720&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1720&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Shadwell, Charles&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Rotherick O'Connor, King of Connaught&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Dublin&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for George Risk and Joseph Leathley ... and Patrick Dugan [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1720&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872373-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv20331&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 18th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;18th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Rotherick O'Connor, King of Connaught&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 172 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Only verse drama included&lt;lb/&gt;The following play has been taken from this source:&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Rotherick O'Connor.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1720.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Unknown.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ROTHERICK O' CONNOR, King of Connaught, . OR THE Distress'd Princess A TRAGEDY.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PROLOGUE By Colonel Allen. Design'd to have been spoke, but came too late Your Clemency has rais'd our Author's Heart, On Buskins now he struts, assumes a Part, Far diff'ring from his former groveling Way, In tragick Strains, he undertakes to day; For all his Confidence, I let him know, A Tragedy was more than he could do. I told him what he enterpriz'd was hard, Presumptions in a Greek or Irish Bard, A Sophocles was only fit to tell, How Oedipus, and injur'd Ajax fell; Th'Exploits, of mighty Men and fighting Kings, Were Sounds too big for humble trembling Strings. What need you for a Tale so high to go, Said I, have you not Robinson Crusoe, There Incidents in full Perfection flow. Such a Dramatick is the fam'd De-Foe. Can't you the trusty Friday imitate; There's an accomplish'd Minister of State. Then for a Hero, without Sense or Fear, There's William Atkins, fits you to a Hair, For he the silly Rogue repents at last, Marry's the Blouze, after six Children past; And then an Episode of Salvages, Who sing and dance, and love all under Trees; Diverting Cannibals, men-eating Men, Who fight to eat, and eat to fight again, Five plump black Girls, trust, ready to be roasted, Were Whip—unty'd, and presently were toasted, Brave lucky Jades, Things then were finely carry'd, Half dead with Fear of spitting, they were marry'd These friendly Hints I gave, but 'twould not do, Full of him self, he would his own pursue, Resolves to show a Monarch of your own, Who holds alone from Jupiter his Throne, His Rule of Life does from his Passions draw, Not aw'd by Priests, nor terrify'd by Law; A Popish Priest he ventures to expose, Who sticks at nothing to distress his Foes, Thanks Revolution, we have none of those, For such outragious Plagues we're not in Pain, They're to be found in Moscovy or Spain.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PROLOGUE Spoke by Mr. Giffard. Written by Mr. Shadwell. From distant Climes, each scribling Author brings, A Race of Heroes, and a Race of Kings; And in soft Numbers humbly does implore, To Act his Murders, on this boarded Floor; His Rebels, Virgins, Heroes, all must Dye, To grace some Conqueror in his Tragedy. Be he a Roman, Greek, or Persian Born, Thus Forreign Stories, do our Stage Adorn. Our Author tries, by Different Ways to please, And shews you Kings, That never cross'd the Seas. He brings to View, five hundred Years ago, Heroes nurs'd up in Slaughter, Blood and Woe: Kings, that Govern'd with an Arbitrary Sway, And slavish Subjects, born but to Obey. When Brehon Laws cou'd reach the Subjects Life, And none but great Ones, dare support the Strife. Then Nature show'd 'em in their strongest Passions, When each King Govern'd by his Inclinations. When Church and Clergy, were the Monarchs Tools; And who oppos'd their King were reckon'd Fools: Learn then from those unhappy Days of Yore, To scorn and hate an Arbitrary Power. To Praise and Love those Laws that make you Free, And are the Great Bullworks of your Liberty Adore the Prince who rules by milder Sway, And like good Subjects, Lawfully Obey: All Tragedies this Moral shou'd Observe, The best of Kings does surely best Deserve.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">EPILOGUE Spoke by Mr. Griffith. Written by Mr. Shadwell. So thank my Stars, the Buskin Tale is past And all the Dead, are come to Life at last; Just now I heard the Kings and Princess say, They hoped to Live, to Die, another Day, Provided you Resolve to like the Play. Our Poet swears, by all that's Great and Good; No more he'll dip his Hands in Humane blood, It is his first Effort in Tragick Strains, And knows not how it came within his Brains, It is a vile Ill-natured Thing, to keep, Such Things in Plays, as make the Ladies weep. For when a Female puts on sower Faces; She looses fifty of her Airs and Graces. But give her something that will make her Smile, Oh! how she Conquers, how she does beguile: Now, 'tis observ'd, our Friends two story High, Do always Laugh, when other People cry, And murdering Scenes, to them are Comedy. The Middle Region, seldom mind the Plot, But with a Vizard chat, of you know what, And are not better'd by the Play one Jot. But you great Judges of the Pit, who come; In Order to be sent with Pleasure home. Are like the Water-Man that looks two Ways, You first observe the Ladies, then our Plays. With them you please your Eye, with us your Ear, And could we always keep those Fair Ones here, Whole Shoals of pritty: Fellows would appear. To you bright Nymphs, who in that Circle sit, Who with a look can Govern all the Pit: Bid 'em be to our Author's Writings kind, Bid 'em be to his Faults a little Blind; Do but say something in the Man's behalf, And Faith when next he writes he'll make you Laugh.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">EPILOGUE By Hercules Davis Esq; Design'd to have been spoke by Mr. Griffith, if all the Persons in the Play had been kill'd. What, are they all destoy'd, pray look around, Can none to speak the Epilogue be found. Not one by Jove! Hey day—Then I must try, How far will reach my Stock of Poetry. So then, let's think—No! I shall want no Time; For such a Scene as this, will teach to Rythme. And thus I do proceed. The Poet has to please you, done his best; But to keep one alive, had been a Jest, For if he had done that, both He and I, Conceiv'd you'd call the Play, a Comedy. That is not all the Thing, that brings me here, But that poor Charles is lying in Despair, And will be soon as dead as any there. Unless bright Nymphs, who in the Circle sit, Command some Mercy from Th'adoring Pit. For well we know, to you they Homage pay, And none but you their biteing Tongues can sway: Love is the thing, will hardest Hearts subdue; Which makes us thus, apply our selves to you. To you bright Charmers of the blooming Age, Who ev'ry Creature round you can engage To you, who in your riper Years can move, And thaw an Icy Stoick into Love. To you we humbly sue and thus complain; Be you our Friends, the Pit we're sure to gain, They are just what you make 'em still we find; They never can be, when you smile unkind. Going off he returns and says. Provided you will be here on Monday Night, they will come all alive again for the Benefit of the Author.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Dramatis Personæ. Rotherick O'Connor King of Connaught. Mr. Rogers. Dermond, Mac Morough King of Leinster. Mr. Dummut. Strongbow, Earl of Chepstow. Mr. Layfield. Cothurnus Son to Dermond. Mr. Elrington. Auliffe O'Kinaude a Faithful Friend of Dermond's. Mr. Watson. Maurice Regan. Dermond's Friend and Favourite. Mr. Gillford. Catholicus Arch-Bishop of Tuam. Mr. Vanderbank. Mortagh, Forsterer to Eva. Mr. Dogherty. I Guard.—Mr. Dogherty. II Guard.—Mr. Watson. III Guard.—Mr. Ralph Elrington. Women. Eva. Daughter to Dermond. Mrs. Gifford. Avelina. Daughter to Rotherick. Mrs. Moreau.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Act I. Scene the First. Enter Maurice Regan. Reg. Thus far my Royal Master's Orders, are Obey'd, all his Subjects; groaning under Rotherick's Tyranny, are Yerning for Their Lawful Prince, and wish with longing Hearts, To Prostrate themselves, and fall before him: I have nothing more to do in State Affairs, But will unbend my Mind, and give it up To Love; and see the Object of my Heart's Desire, appears, full of her Native, and Her heavenly Charms. Enter. Eva, Dress'd like a Shepherdess. Eva. Welcome; my Father's Faithful Friend and Mine. I have perused the Letters that you sent, And with a Heart o'rewhelm'd with joy, am glad, To find great Henry, that Godlike Man, So good as to espouse, our Monarch's Cause. Reg. Your Virtue would engage the Gods, to be The King of Leinster's Friend, your Prayers are heard. Eva. In your most tedious Absence, I have been A constant Guest, to this poor homely Cottage, And with my Tears, and Prayers, spun out my Time. Rotherick, the Cruel King of Connaught; Hated by Gods, and Men, offer'd Rewards; To those who found me out, and brought me to him; But by Repeated Miracles, good Heaven, Saved me from his Tyranny, my Forsterer, The faithful Man, oft with his aged Hands, Has drove the Savage Kerns from off his Land, And guarded me with wakeing, watchful Eyes, Many a long cold and blustering Winter's Night. Reg. The poor Man's faithful Care, shall be rewarded: Oh my Charming Eva, what Thoughts had I; Who not only loved you as my Princess, But as my Angel, and the Saint to whom I pray'd, When your cruel Father, only so to me, Lay'd his Commands upon me, to attend Him to great Henry's Court, the gaudy Sight Could not divert me from the Thoughts of you, Amidst the Gold and sparkling Diamonds The well burnish'd Helmet, Barbered Horses; Glittering Equipage, and fawning Courtiers, Nay; amongst a Multitude of English, Welsh, and Norman Beauties, I could pass along: And neither lend an Ear, nor cast an Eye; Indulging all my Senses and my Thoughts, On you, the Object of my Soul's Desire. Eva. Sure then, there is a sympathy in Love, For when I've try'd to drive you from my Thoughts, And listen'd to the Shepherds awkard Tale: My Attention stole from him by Degrees; And ne're would leave, till center'd all on you: But tell me pray now, what these Strangers are? My Father has engag'd to fight his Foes. Reg. A Warlike Race of Men, they Britains call, Mix'd with some English Archers most Expert, Who gain upon your Father's Enemys; Like stormy Floods, upon a level Sand, They like a Torrent came, and drove down all, And Wexford, soon surrender'd to their Mercy, Your Father, to Reward their Warlike Care; At once gave Fitzstephens and Fitzgerald: Two of their Chiefs, as by Agreement made; That City, and two Cantreds adjoyning. And to oblige the noble Earl of Chepstow, Your Royal Father as King of Leinster, Has bestow'd on Henry of Mount Maurice. Two Cantreds, Situate between those Towns; Of Waterford, and Wexford near the Sea: The Earl with all his gallant followers, Are with Impatience soon expected here. Eva. But when they have conquered all our Enemy's, Perhaps they'll then attack my Father's Friends, And so in Time, make Slaves of all this Island. Reg. The Men are gallant Men, and make some Show Of Virtue, and compassionate, good Nature; Their Country seems, more civiliz'd than ours; With Arts and Sciences, they polish all The rude, the wild, ungovernable Crew. No petty Princes there, dare take up Arms, Or by a lawless Force, pretend to Right: One mighty Monarch Governs through the Land, He takes Advice indeed of all those Men, Who are by long Experience made most Wise His constant study is his Peoples care, They are his Servants, Children and his Friends. Eva. Regan, Your Zeal for Strangers knows no Bounds; You have forgot you were in Ireland born, Where pure Religion by St. Patrick taught: Is still kept up, with a becoming Zeal. Here we are govern'd by Nature's Dictates, Not by dissembling Art, which teaches Men To Act, quite opposite to what they think; Wisdom makes Hypocrites, Nature makes none. Perhaps with artful Engines made for War: These Strangers may strike Terror through the Field; And so afright my Father's Rebel Subjects: Who Conscious of the Injuries they have done, No doubt in dread of him, will fly before them; But when the Hibernian Spirit's rous'd, These Strangers, will not be such mighty Men. Reg. Your Pardon fairest Princess. I ne're meant, By praising of these Strangers, to take off Any Glory from the Heroes of my Country, I know at once, we act what Men dare do; And always justifie, what we think Right: But our mistaken Zeal is led away, Without our Wisely weighing of the Cause, Or why shou'd the Tyrant Rotherick, thus pursue; And drive your Father from his Native Throne, Force him to sue to Strangers for their Aid; To Hire them with his Lands, to shed the Blood Of those, he once did call his Faithful Subjects. Eva. Rotherick is revengeful, and ambitious, Tho' he pretends, my Father was the Aggressor, And much I fear they have been both to blame, What Murders does a Tyrant's Will invent, How insolently do they Lord it or'e. The greatest part of the Creation; And yet a Feavour shakes them, and they dye, And crumble into Dust, and Ashes, like The poorest, and the meanest of their Subjects. Reg. These are too melancholy Reflections For us, whose business shou'd be Love. My long and faithful Services to your Father, Will Embolden me, to ask you of him. Before your Exile, you have of't confest, A loving and a tender Passion for me. Eva. And you as of't, have triumph'd or'e my Weakness, And with such strange aluring Ways so wone, My tender, weak, ungarded Heart. It heaves and throbs, and trembles at your Name, And makes my Mind, subservient to it's Laws, And will not let me think of ought but you. Reg. You Gods, how exquisitely blest am I! I envy no Monarch, fear no Rival; Nor would I quit my Interest in your Love. To be the greatest Thing I ever saw, That's the British King in all his Glory. Enter Mortagh her Forsterer. Mor. Oh doleful News! I doubt you are betray'd, My Cabin is beset with fifty Horse, They say King Dermond did Command them here, To fetch away his Royal Daughter Eva. But too much I fear, they come from Rotherick. Regan. Oh, curst Fate! the Tyrant has betray'd us; Death is not half so Terrible as he. Eva. I despise your Fears, neither he nor Death, Can once be dreadful, to a noble Soul. Remember Regan, you're an Irish Man; And whether Life, or Death, behave as such. This Dagger is the Guardian of my Virtue, When that's Attackt, my Life's not worth my Care: To Dye in such a Cause, is Nobly brave, Death is Freedom, whilst Life is for a Slave. Enter Auliffe O'Kinaude. Speaks as he Enters Kin. Guard well the Doors, I'll search the Cabin Through. Reg. You'll not search far, before you find your Prize; But you must call more Help, before you gain her, This Sword, will make you buy your Conquest dear. Mor. The Pincess shan't be your's, till we are Dead. Kin. The Princess! oh you Gods! then is she Here? Reg. Pleasing Surprize! my dearest best of Friends, Most noble Princess Auliffe O' Kinaude, Your Father's faithful Friend, and Counsellour. Eva. I hope you left my Royal Father Well. Kin. In a good State of Health, and full of Friends, Strongbow, Earl of Chepstow, with two Hundred Knights, And a numerous band of gallant Soldiers, Were met near Waterford, by Leinster's King, The English furiously attack'd that City, Enter'd the Breach, ransack'd the Place, and slew All those they found in Arms, except Reginald, And one Ophelim, Prince of Decies, whom They have imprison'd, this Pacquet fairest Princess, was from your Royal Father sent. I have obey'd his orders hitherto, But now, oh Joy! must wait for your Commands. Eva. (Reads) “It is our Will and Pleasure, under the “Care of our faithful Counselour Auliffe O' “Kinaude, that you strait repair to our “Royal Court at Furness, where you will “Not only meet your loveing Father, but the “Earl of Chepstow, to whom I have betroth'd you, (She Speaks) I've read enough to drown my Peace Of Mind for ever. Reg. How strangly is her Countenance perplext! Something in that Letter, much displeases her, I fear to guess, what Horror it contains. Kin. And if your Royal Highness, so thinks fit, The sooner we set out upon our Journey, The safer it will be; a hundred Horse, From the Mountains, this Morning we espy'd, And the Country People has inform'd us, Two hundred more, are scouring of the Roads, The Tyrant Rotherick, now begins to fear The English Power, which he once dispis'd, Is drawing all his Forces to the Field; And does design, as he has given out, To give your Father and the English Battle. Eva. Death! Horror! and Destruction! seize us all. I curse the Hour, since first these Stangers came. They will enslave us soon, at least those Fools, Who are in Love, with the simple thing call'd Life. I'm ready for your Journey when you please, Those Monarchs still are Tyrants to me, Who would command my Will, and force me to A Deed, which shocks and stabs my very Nature. Obey our Parents, 'tis a harsh Command, My Faiths already given, well what then, How will these Contradictions both agree, Death ends the Argument, and sets me free. Mor. Will not my fairest charge, give leave for me To attend you to your Royal Father. Then when your safely lodg'd, under his Roof, I may contentedly come home and Dye. Eva. My Father will I hope take care of you, Heaven is my witness honest Mortagh, With what reluctancy I leave this Cabbin, When I go from hence, I go from happiness, To be Wretched, Great, and Miserable. Mor. Say not so, my Royal Mistress, Heaven Has in store for you a thousand Blessings. Which Day by Day, it will pour down upon you. Reg. I hope the Letter from your Father, does Not contain ought that can disturb your Breast. Eva. It does contain enough to shock us both, Upon the Road perhaps I'll tell you more. Reg. Too well I guess the Trouble it must give us. Eva. Come Sir, lead on to Death, or to my Father. Kin. If the Enemy attack us, it is Death, For none of us will Live, and part with you. (Exeunt. SCENE draws and discovers Rotherick Catholicus, and Guards. Rothe. What have we no Intelligence to Day? No Strangers, nor no Leinster Men brought in? Catho. Several Parties of your Horse, and Foot, Whose Orders were to cross the Shannon, Are Hourly expected back my Leige. Retho. 'Tis well, but if they bring not Prisoners with them, Those who command those Men, shall surely die. I Rotherick O' Connor, King of Connaught, Will make the Nation tremble at my Sway, And force each native Slave, to drive away These Vagabonds, these Strangers, from our Land. Well my good Catholicus, have you perus'd. The Copy of that Grant? sent to be sign'd, By that most mighty Lord, of all our Church, Infallible and never erring Pope Adrian the fourth, and since that confirm'd, By Allexander's Bull, to give my Land Away to Henry the English King. Now by St. Patrick, who was a greater Man, Then ever fill'd your jugling, Papal Chair, I swear revenge on all the Romish Tribe. Would thou have done so, hadst thou been a Pope? No! I know thou durst not Who gives the Priest The Power, he pretends to have on Earth? Is it not your King; and pray now, who am I? Your Spiritualities of Tuam, Are not worth much, without my Subjects Gold. You talk of Heaven, but you covet Earth. Catho. Far be it from my thoughts; to disobey My Royal Master's Will; we know our Church, Our Lives, and all we have, center in you. And we of Ireland, have never own'd The Pope's Supremacy, or Power here; For from St. Patrick, to this present time, Our Church has always, strenuously opposed him. Rothe. Or there should be no Churches, through my Realm. What use have I for Priests? except their talk Can keep the wild, unruly Mob in awe, And give a Sanction to my Kingly Actions. Catho. I and my Clergy are at your Devotion. Rothe. Or they would live but slavish, wretched Lives. Catholicus, full well I know thy Worth; And what I think a mighty Vertue in thee; Thou never contradicts, in ought, my Will; Thy Zeal has never been impertinent, Nor push'd it self between me and my Pleasures: Thy Knowledge is too great, to think that Kings, Are tyed to Rules, like other Mortal Men. Oh! how I would crush a Fellow that should cry, His Liberty, or talk of self defence, Property, or scan the Actions of his Prince: Thou should Excommunicate the saucy Slave; And doubting that thy Curse would not take Place, This Javelin should push his Soul to Hell. A Noise without. Catholicus, go learn from whence that Noise. Catholicus goes to the Door and returns. Catho. My Leige, the Guards are leading Dermonds Son to Death, according to your late Commands. Rothe. Call back the Wretch, I'll see him e'er he Dyes. (Catholicus goes out and returns with Cothurnus) Catho. Bring him near the King. Rothe. Bring him nearer yet. Cothur. Barbarous Tyrant, when my Thoughts were fixt On future pleasing Joys, and things above; Why wouldst thou make me think of Hell and thee? Rothe. So you'r prepar'd to die, your Mind is calm, and you forgive your greatest Enemies. Cothur. Mankind I can forgive, but thou'rt a Devil. Rothe. Am I so? that Devil shall torment thee then. Catho. For shame, you talk not like a dying Man, Nor know not the Respect to Majesty. Cothur. Call'st thou that Pageant Wretch a King? He is a Rebell with a Tyrant's Power; And has usurp'd my Father's lawfull Right. His Life has been, one Scene of Wickedness, Rapine, Lewdness, Murder Paricide; And thou his fawning, pious, cringing Priest, With your exalted Hands, and turn'd up Eyes, Can first confess and then absolve him for it. Catho. So please your Majesty, 'tis time he dies. Rothe. Let him talk his Glass, 'twill soon be run: Catho. He rails against the Church, no Priest of mine Shall give the Wretch a Christian Burial. Cothur. I shall go to Bliss, without thy Pasport. Thou Wolf, crouded into a sheepish Cloathing. Catho. The people, are with Impatience waiting For the Execution, so please my Leige, The Guards may now conduct the Heretick there. Rothe. Hold, let me talk and reason with the Youth, Thy Father it is true, was King of Leinster, And had he govern'd well, might still have reigned; But you forget, he ravished O Rourk's Wife, Who was the Daughter of the King of Meath; Know you, that he plunder'd all the Country round, And forc'd O Neale. O Carroll and Mc Loughlin, To give him Hostages, which he destroy'd; Whilst O Borne and Daniel Prince of Ossory, Amazed at all his horrid Villanies, As all good Men should do, deserned him; At which the abandon'd Wretch to England flies, And humbly sues, to Vagabonds and Strangers, Bringing the lawless Rout to murder us, And for their Reward, gives them whole Cities, Notwithstanding which, he sues to me for Peace; And I, as good Catholicus can tell, Took his Homage, but on these Conditions; That he shou'd dismiss the English Strangers, You his Son was sent to me as an Hostage, And had he but perform'd, you should have had My Daughter Avelina for your Bride; But he you know, has broke through all his Oaths, And let the British Stranger you call Strongbow, With his Rebell Rout, invade and plunder Meath. I did upbraid him for his Breach of Oaths, And threatned, if he kept not well the Peace, That you his favourite Son, shou'd lose your Head, His surly Answer was; He would proceed To conquer Connought, which the Villain claim'd As if it once had been his ancient Right, For which base Act of his, you suffer Death. Enter Avelina. Ave. Oh! dread Sir, recall your horrid Sentence, And let nor that brave Youth, be punish'd so; By your Commands, I gave him up my Heart, And you declared I was to be his Wife. Rothe. Go too; my Mind is altered, that's enough for you. Take back your foolish Bauble of a Heart, And carry it with you to a Nunnery. Ave. To Death most willingly, I can't survive him. Rothe. Ha! what says't thou? Death! die, and if you dare, I'll make you live, and live in Torture too, That rebell against your King, your Father. Catho. It is a crying, roaring heavy Sin. Perhaps a Nunnery and Penitence, With Store of Fasting, may wash off the Crime. Cothur. Rotherick, forbear to use your Daughter ill Pour all your haughty Vengeance down on me; It is a double Death to see her Tears. Cothur. Oh! have I found a way to Torture you, And bring your haughty Soul within its Bounds, I have a Pleasure yet to come; your Death Had been a petty Vengeance to my mind. But you are deep in Love, and with my Daughter: Now by the Gods She straight shall suffer Death before your Face And whilst her trickling Blood is reeking Hot, I'le open all your Veins, to mix amongst it. Ave. Thou best of Fathers, dearest best of Kings, That Sentence is the Thing I wish'd for most; My tender Heart, can never bear to see His mangl'd Carcass, thrown about the Streets; But whilst I am dying, I may fix my Eyes With eager Wishes, give a parting Sigh, And hope to mingle with his Righteous Soul; Above the unbounded Regions of the Air. Catho. She's raving Sir, and has not mention'd yet, One word of Paradise, and Purgatory; I dare pronounce, he's taught her how to Raile Against the Mother-Church, and Pious Church-men; 'Twere fit we purge her of her Sins before She suffers Death, mean while if he were Dead, She might be brought to own, her horrid Sin, Be penitent, and so be made a Saint. Rothe. Well, it shall be so, haste and see him die: And Avelina too shall see him die, Cothurnus, 'tis your Father's sins have drawn This heavy Death upon your youthful Soul, He sold his Country to a forreign Yoke: Be satisfy'd in this, I'll seek him out, And soon his groveling Corps, shal overtake thee: Ave. In pity to my tender Youth, forbear To blast his Soul, whilst mine is blossoming. Cothur. How tender does she plead, and would prevail, With any thing that's humane, but a Tyrant. Farewell my softest, fairest Avelina, Death I can bear, but not the Sight of you. Catho. Make way there, and let the Prisoner pass. Cothur. Farewell proud Priest, we two shall meet no more; I shall mount up, whilst you must sink below. Enter a Souldier. 1 Guard. My Leige, a Messenger from Leinster's King, Is with a Trumpet come and brought this Letter. The King opens the Letter. Catho. The King is taken up with State Affairs, You have your Orders, lead the Prisoner off. Ave. Oh cruel Man, 'tis from my Fathers mouth You must receive the Orders for his Death. Rothe. Cothurnus, for a Day or two your Life's Prolong'd, your Father writes me Word, he'll send Donagh, Abbot of Furnes to this Place, To treat with me about the safest Way; Of driving back these Welsh, and English Men; Perhaps it is a Stratagem of his To gain some Time, or may be to Surprize Some Fortress, or some Castle in the Frontiers, Be it so, we can Revenge it soon enough: Catholicus, my Daughter is your Care; If Dermond sends us Peace, she may Love on, If not 'tis fit she bid the World Adieu: Guards, lead back Cothurnus to his Prison. Cothur. I thank you not, since Death's my Lot; Happen when it will, it shall be welcome. Exit. Catho. Perhaps my Leige, he is prepar'd to die: Rothe. If so Catholicus, where's my Revenge? To take him from a State of noise and Strife, And give him Happiness beyond my own; So from an Enemy become a Friend: A Monarch's made to Rule each petty Slave, To bid him Live, or send him to his Grave. Mercy, is for a vile Mechanick Soul, No humane Passion, should a King controul: 'Tis Justice is the Rule, that Guides his way; And all is Just and Good that Monarchs say. Exeunt. End of the first ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. Enter Dermond King of Leinster Strongbow Earl of Chepstow. Strong. My Informations are good I'me sure, and you Have Dealings under Hand with Rotherick. Der. Will you not hear me speak, I'll tell the Fact: Cothurnus is my Darling only Son, The day was fixt for him to suffer Death; I thought my Letter might prolong his Life, Till we were able to o'rethrow the Tyrant. Strong. Why was not I consulted all this while? Come 'tis unfair, it is deceitful, base; And I, nor mine, have not deserv'd this Usage: Did I from England come, with Gallant Troops, To serve a Prince, who would betray us all; Now by St. George, and his bright Sword I swear; It were a Deed, that would be Justify'd: To give you up a Victim to your Foes, And leave your Land, a Heap of Desolation. But why this mighty Care to save your Son? Is it consistent with the Agreement made? How can you fulfill your Sacred contract? 'Tis like you have forgot, that when you die Your Kingdom must descend to me, and that Your Daughter Eva was to be my Wife; You put me off from Day to Day, Perhaps You do repent you of the Bargain made? I do not die for Love of her, nor all The paultry beauties of your barren Land. Der. Believe the Word and Honor of a King: Each Tittle I'll most Sacredly perform, My daughter Eva is expected soon; The Moment that she comes, the Priest shal tye The holy Knot, and so unite your Hearts. Strong. Till when 'tis fit a Guard be set on you, My Souldiers murmur, and my Friends give out, Your cut-throat Subjects, have contrived a Plot To Murder all of us, at Dead of Night. Der. Oh horrible! Rotherick has surely sent, Some Traytor, to disperse the Seeds of Discord: Between your Troops and mine. Strong. It can not be— You only are to blame, and gave us Cause To be uneasy, and mistrust you all: Deceitfulness, is very deeply Rooted. In each Corner of this wretched Isle, Instead of Friendship, Charity, and Love; You plunder, burn, and sacrifice each other: And strive and fight, and gape for Revenge. Der. A horrid War, long Time has Plagu'd this Isle And Right and Wrong, are to Confusion brought: Their lawless Passions thirsting after Blood, Have even Depopulated all the Land. Nobility is no where to be found: The base Plebean, Lords it over all. Strong. Such is the horrid fate of civil War, Shame and Destruction, always Fall on those; Who by their Factions are the Cause of Strife. Enter Auliffe O Kinaude. Wounded, Leaning on his Sword. Der. What means this Dreadful Sight! my Heart misgives me! Kinaude! What makes you Bleed! Where's my Daughter? Kin. Death is not half so Terrible, as what (If I have Life;) I have to tell you: As we were guarding onwards to this Place, By your dread Commands, Her Royal Highness; A Party of two hundred Horse, attackt Us in the Rear, some Miles we did retreat, Tho' a Pace, not much faster than our Foes; My royal Mistress, bid us face about: And force the Enemy with Souldier's Hearts, Much asham'd to see her Courage more than ours, Our Souls push'd forward to the War: At first we gain'd some Ground, and kill'd our Share. But being over power'd, they cut us down On the Field of Battle, all were left for Dead, Except the Princess, whom they carry'd off. Regan was wounded in our first Attack, But when I search'd the Field, I found him not: My woeful Story makes my Wounds gush out, I'm Faint, I can no more. (Dies.) Strong. Dermond, thy Crimes have been of horrid Hue: Or Heaven sure, would never punish so. Der. Since it's Heavens Will, I'le try to bear it; To loose my faithful Friend and Counsellor: Death with his Iron Claws has done the Deed, And no doubt, has robbed me too of Regan. But then my Daughter, that goes through my Heart; And pierces to my very Soul, Revenge, Revenge is all my Cry, and all my Thoughts. Strong. Now whilst you're Warm, let's execute the Deed; And march with all our Forces to this Tyrant; Rescue the Princess, from his Hellish Arms; Or sacrifice our Lives in the Attempt. Robert Fitz-stephens, Henry of Mount Maurice, And Fitzgerald, wait impatiently for Orders On the Shanon's brink; give 'em but the Word: And Connaught soon shall find it self o'rewhelm'd, With blood and Slaughter, be honest to your Friends, Intirely rely on them, be Firm And stedfastly adhere to what we say; No Danger can alarm our noble Breasts; It is true Courage leads us calmly on: We're Heroes if we conquer, if we die, We'll die like Men. Der. Thy generous noble Soul Raises and animates my drooping Spirits Be witness all that's Sacred, here I swear. Just, and inviolably to perform; Each circumstance of what I promised you; And at my Death, you reign sole King of Leinster. Could we but relieve my darling Daughter, The joy and Transport it would give my Soul, Would make me quite forget all other Grief; But oh, I fear the cruel Tyrant's Will, May lead him on to Butcher all my Race; My only Daughter, and my only Son. Strong. These are but Words, lead on to Blows; Leave Words to Women, if you'd crush your Foes, Draw to the Head, with Zeal, the pointed Arrow, Raise the Javelin, bring forth the keenest Sword; And all the destroying Instruments of War: Let Skrieks and Groans, the Musick of the Field, In one continued Clamour, fill the Skies, And cover o'er the Ground so high with Blood, That Shoals of gasping, dying Enemies, May float, and swim about, upon the Surface. Der. Thou Great, thou God-like! more than Man, thou Britain! When once my Soul knows Fear, or shrinks from thee, May I become the abjects, Wretch on Earth. Oh could my Sword, but pierce the Tyrant's Heart, The Dog, the Villain, Monster, Rotherick; Oh! how I'de feed, and please my just Revenge, And eagerly push on the Fiend to Hell. Strong. Lead on, let Fortune bring him to our View, and leave the rest to us. We'll Crown our Heads with one eternal Fame, And blast his Laurels, with perpetual Shame. Exeunt. SCENE a Prison. Enter Avelina. Ave. This dark, this dismal dead of Night, so fills My soft, my tender Mind with fear and horror: I start and tremble, at each gush of Wind. Catholicus at last is gone to Sleep; May he Sleep for ever, dreadful Goaler, Most cruel Persecutor of my Love. Oh my Cothurnus! how my tender Heart Does beat, and throb, and bleed in your Behalf: Guard me you Saints, since Virtue is your care, Reward my Love, and Constancy; give me, Oh give me, to the Arms of that dear Youth, Who when he dies, will joyn your Pious Quire, And add a Lustre to your Heavenly Glories. Why name I Death, I fear 'tis ominous: My Nerves begin to tremble, and my Legs Refuse to move, and lead me to the Prison. Assist my Soul, shake off this Female weakness. Give me a Hero's Heart, a Hero's Hand, And all the barbarous cruelty of War. Let me rush on, and beat down all his Guards; Fly to his Arms, then be again a Woman. (Exit. Enter Cothurnus with his Sword drawn. Cothur. Take this Sword, and fight for Love and Liberty: Those were his Words. The Slave was surely sent By Avelina; this scroll of Paper, Is the Pening of her lovely Fingers. Reads, ‘Force through, I'll meet you at the Prison Gate, ‘The silent time of Night, 'twixt Twelve and One. Then be it so, the Guards are all asleep; But my retreat will never be secure, Without I murther all that are my Watch. Rotherick is a Tyrant, how can that Justify the murder of these Wretches; Tyred out with Labour, and with Duty: They are Innocent, and sleeping calmly, Scarcely Dream of Wounds and Horror, Blood and me. There's self Defence, 'tis all I have to plead; Oh no! my Avelina's waiting for me. You Guardian Angels, who ore Men preside, Take care, and waft the Righteous Souls of those, Whom my poor Hands are forc'd to push from Life: Conduct them to that place of Harmony, Where Bliss and Happiness; fill up the space Of great Hereafter, and Eternity. The time draws nigh, then hardned be my Heart, That I may act the murthering, killing part. (Exit. (A Noise without, clashing of Swords and crying out.) 1 Guard. Treason, Murder, Cothurnus is broke loose Has forc'd the Doors, and will escape. (Groans are heard) Hard hearted, cruel Monster, Oh! SCENE the Fields. Enter Avelina. Ave. Oh my weak Heart, the Noise points towards me, And methoughts I heard them name Cothurnus. Murder! what will this horrid Night bring forth. Enter Cothurnus, his Sword bloody. Cothur. Who comes there? Ave. 'Tis I, 'tis Avelina. Cothur. That's well. I've waded through a World of Blood: Pray Heaven that we pay not for it all. Come to my Arms my Love. Ave. With joy, I would partake of all your Fate, Can drag the load of Life, or go to Death. Guard without crys 1 Guard. Treason, Murder, Cothurnus is escap'd. Ave. Oh Heaven's, we're betray'd, whither shall we fly? Cothur. To Death my dear, 'tis all we have for it now. That Fellow narrowly escap'd my Sword, He knows I did design to take his Life, 'Tis therefore fair in him to push at mine. Without 1 Guard. This Way, I track him by his bloody Feet. Cothur. Go hence my dear, it is not fit that you Should see me butcher'd by this Band of Soldiers. Ave. 'Tis Death to part: Oh no! I'll stay and dye Before I'll run, and leave you here alone. I wish that you would go away with me, A League from hence, I have a faithful Maid, Whose Mother will protect me for some time; Perhaps we'll meet an opportunity Of joyning Forces, from your Father's Camp. Cothur. To save your Life, I'd venture any thing. Ave. For Heavens's sake, avoid this Place, let's fly. Cothur. For your sake, I will prolong my Destiny. (Exeunt. Enter Catholicus and Guards. Catho. Slaves, Villains, Cowards, fly and overtake 'em. 1 Guard. The Day begins to break, I saw a glimpse Of two in haste, who that way bent their Course. Catho. Fly then; who Kills them both, shall dye a Saint. (Exeunt Guards I'll follow after, as my Legs will let me. By this, his Majesty's alarm'd; I dye If they are not, secured, a woeful Night T'will be for me; I'm almost out of Breath. Exit. Enter in haste Cothurnus and Avelina. Cothur. It is vain to Fly, the Camp's alarm'd, And yonders Light foretels the coming Day. Ave. The Morn comes on apace, and I grow Faint, Cothurnus, since you must dye, take me with you; Or say you'll let me run upon your Sword; How sweet were Death, if you would give the Blow. Cothur. Forbear, you know not how you wound my Soul. Be happy still, and never think of me. Your Father may have Bowels, and forgive, So sweet, so soft, so kind a Thing as you. I know my Doom, and I can die but once. Enter Guards. 1 Guard, We'll save the Princess, but the Villain dies. Cothur. Take back the Villain, I'll sell my Life full dear. 1 Guard. Fall on, a horrid Death is his deserts. Ave. You Slaves, through me you come to touch his Life. 1 Guard. So be it then; we're bid to kill you both. Cothur. Hold your murdering Hands, and save her precious Life. 1 Guard. We'll spare her Life, if you give up your Sword. If your so Cruel to deny her that; Her Death will lie directly at your Door. Cothur. Promise me upon a Soldiers solemn Word, You safely will conduct her to her Father; And I will leave my Body to your Mercy. Ave. Trust not their Cruelty; with Sword in Hand You'll make your Terms, and may spin out your Doom. 1 Guard. Believe her not, you can't escape us now. Enter Catholicus. Catho. Give me a Javelin, I'll kill the Body, And after put up Prayers to save his Soul. Cothur. Keep off, thou sack of Sin, my Sword is sharp. I hate the World, and would not ease 'em of you Ave. Barbarous Catholicus, no Bowels left, No drops of human Nature round thy Soul, To save two tender Lovers from the Grave: Thus on my Knees, with watry Eyes I sue. Cothur. Avelina rise, disdain to sue for Peace, From one who is your mortal Foe and mine. You Coward Guards come on, I live too long. Ave. Cruel Cothurnus, could you say too long, When Avelina was so near your side. Enter Rotherick and Guards. Rothe. Where is my Rebel Daughter, where's my Foe, Who has so bravely broke the Prison Doors; And whilst my Souldiers slept, with bloody Hands, Has calmly made his Way, through Death and Wounds. I am a Tyrant, cruel and revengeful; Because I love my Country, and oppose The Man, who gives up all his Land to Strangers. Guards, Hue him, Cut him, Mangle him to pieces: Hold, stay, his Father once I own'd a King, And he his Son, might have some Princely sparks of Majesty and Kingly Power about him. Rash Youth, I will forgive your late Offence; Put up your Sword: Oh, were your Father honest. How could I hug, and take you to my Bosom. Come hither Avelina, is it true That you have such a Passion for this Youth? Ave. At first, in just obedience to your Will, I strove with all my might to like and love him; Since which, each Day my Love is grown much stronger. Rothe. Why then it is a folly in your Father; To oppose a Love that is so strongly fixt: Come here brave Youth, and take her from my Hands (Rotherick takes Cothurnus and Avelina's Hands) Guards seize them both, I'll make them know my Power: Go, let him lose his Head immediately: No Words, Catholicus go see it done. Catho. I fly to execute my Master's Will: Cothur. Farewel thou Monster, Devil, Villain, Tyrant. (Exeunt all but Rotherick.) Enter Eva and Regan, his Arm in a Scarf, and Guards. Rothe. Whom have we here? 1 Guard, My Leige Dermond's Daughter is taken Prisoner. Of all the gallant Troops, that did attend her, This is the only one was left alive. Rothe. You've done your Duty, and shall be rewarded. 'Tis plain I am a Favorite of the God's, The only thing on Earth, I wish'd to have, Was all vile Dermond's Race within my Power. By Heaven she's Beautiful! her Eyes strike Fire. And sets my Soul, in a continued Flame. Lady, you are not half so much my Prisoner, As I am your's, my Troops have conquer'd you, That I may fall a Victim, at your Feet, Cothurnu's Life is now within his Sister's Power, He shall not Die, till she gives Orders for't. What gloomy Thing art thou, with down cast Look? Reg. Let it suffice, I'm Dermond's faithful Friend; An Enemy to thee, and all thy Race. Rothe. Most courteous Slave! civil, and obliging, Assure your self, I shall reward you for't, Some Days I'll study how I shall torment you: Till when, you Guards, let him be loaded well With Chains of Iron, till his haughty Soul, Is humbled so, that he Speaks well of me. Eva. Know proud Tyrant, you and my Father have A long Account, and you must pay for all. Rothe. Would I could meet him once, that we might Ballance. I'd cut and mangle, all his foreign Slaves; And justly give him, what he most deserves, A cruel ignominious shameful Death. By Heavens! I'd strip him of his Kingly Robes, And like a Felon, hang him on a Tree. Eva. Go meet him in the Field, as if you were A noble, brave, courageous Enemy; Push forward, through the thickest of the Ranks, And dye if possible, upon the Ground, Your noble Heroes call the bed of Honour; And so avert these Judgments, that must fall Upon the vilest, basest, worst of Tyrants. Rothe. So! Reg. No such Blessings er'e can fall upon thee; Thou art Nature's violent Convulsion, Made by Heaven's command, to show the World, What Ways it has of punishing Mankind, When Wickedness doth call a Vengeance down. Rothe. Guards, lead that Wretch unto the Verge of Life. Show Death, but give him Sustenance enough To make him breath in spite of all his Threats. Catholicus, that Female is your Care. Preach off her Pride, and learn her to obey, And relish well my arbitrary Sway. Women like Coin, can never current be, Without their stamp't with Glorious Majesty. Exeunt. End of the Second ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. Enter Eva, and Avelina. Eva. Could I have wish'd a better Fate then this, To meet so kind a Partner in my Sorrow; A Friend, a Prisoner, and a Sister too. Ave. Heaven began to pitty our Distress, And to our broken Hearts o'rewhelm'd with Grief, Hurryed down this Gleam of Joy upon us; But oh! my Tyrant Father is revengful, And whilst that we are laying Schemes for Life, Perhaps has sign'd the Warrant for their Deaths, Whose Lives, can only make us wish to Live. Eva. My faithful Lover must be lost for ever; My Father's Palace would be Woe to me. So far, is your's a different Case to mine, In losing of my Brother: what you lose, By Time, and other thoughts, may be forgot. When I'm torn from my Regan, I must joyn My Hands with one, who is a Stranger born. To lose the thing we Love, is Grief enough; But horror to my Soul! what Grief is that? To wed the Creature, whom my Country hates. Ave. It is indeed a dismal Heap of Woe. But Prayers and Tears, perhaps may set us free, And Crown us both with Love and Happiness. Eva. Hope is the sickly folly of the Mind; Flatters, stupifies, and lulls our Thoughts to Sleep, And when the Danger comes, makes Cowards of us. The noble Soul disdains to wish and hope; But ruminates upon the worst Events; Draw up fierce Resolution to their Aid, And dares defy, what wordly Woes can bring. Ave. Your brave Heroick Soul, enlivens mine, And Fear and Trembling, Handmaids to our Sex, Are Strangers to me now, I've thrown them off; And since I must dye once, I care not when. Eva. Wipe off those Tears, and let our Goaler see, How much we do despise his haughty Threats: Laugh and redicule his Wracks and Tortures, Till Gall and vile Revenge, choak up his Throat. Ave. Catholicus, the vilest Wretch alive, Blows up my Fathers Anger to that pitch, That in his Passion, Right and Wrong are drown'd. See where the Holy, Pious Outside comes, Which is a Covering to the worst of Men. Enter Catholicus. Catho. It is not safe to let them be together, When Malice takes Possession of a Female: It strongly works, and brings forth dire Effects, I'le wheedle out the Secrets of their Hearts: And then, as bound, betray them to the King. (Aside) (To them) Peace wait on you both, if you are not at Prayers, I fain would hold some short Discourses with you, Have you Avelina, weighed the good Advice I cordially, and like a Friend, this Morn Repeated to you? Are you sensible How much you have offended Heaven, and The King your Father? in the Love of one, That is to the Church and him, an Enemy. Eva. Know proud Prelate, when your Lives are opposite To what you preach and Pray, no one gives Ear To what you utter: Example leads the Way, And makes your Proselytes, zealous and Sincere: But we abhor the Wretch, who in his Heart Has base Revenge; with Goodness at his Lips, Hypocrisie and Cant, is rooted in you. Catho. From you, my Meekness can bear more than this; I think I am in Duty bound, to hear All the Scurrility you have to say: When you have said your worst, I can revenge My self, upon your Brother, and your Friend. Ave. Have you no bowels of Compassion then? No tender Spark, about your flinty Heart? Catho. Yes, perhaps I have; if I was right attackt: But do you think that Flesh and Blood can bear, To hear you talk, and rail, and be your Friend; I own the Zeal I have to serve your Father, Has often push'd me on, to do such Deeds, As I have wept and pray'd and fasted for; And executed Pennances, that would Have made your tender Eyes shed tears of Blood. Ave. You once I know did say, you were a Friend To poor Cothurnus, and his mournful Cause; But you of Late, have pushed him on to Death, And show'd a horrid aggravating Spirit. Catho. I grant you, when he charg'd me of a Crime, My tender righteous pious Soul abhorr'd, My Saint-like-ship would sink into a Man, And think too much of Earth, and so Resent. Eva. Is that the Rule of Faith which guides a Prelate? You for your self can humane Nature plead, And won't you then allow it to a Soul. With grief opprest, upon the verge of Life, Condemn'd to Die, for what they think unjust? Then Nature makes her Sallys and resents, Beyond the common Course of base Revenge. Catho. I grant you, Life is sweet, and worth our Care To those who tremble at the Sight of Death, It is a good and comfortable Cordial: But we the Clergy, have our Wills resign'd; And hate so much the Vanities of Life, That we are wishing, panting after Death, In hopes to shake of soon this mortal body. Ave. Father, methinks in you, it is a sin to die When here on Earth you may do so much good, A God-like, meritorious Act 'twould be: To soften so my Fathers wrathful mind, That poor Cothurnus and my Eva's Friend: Might yet have hopes of Life in Spite of Chains, Oh! how they'd bless, and praise, and thank you for't. Eva. Why are the Clergy by our holy Church, So set apart from other Men, but that Their Study should be Acts of Charity; Their Lives a Course of one continued Good. To make the Laity in love with Joys, Above their sordid humane Apprehensions; That when they shall shake off this mortal clay, They may arrive amongst those solid Joys; Which all that own our Faith, are panting after. Catho. 'Tis now you've found the way to touch my Heart, I weep, and let me tell you 'tis a Sign Of tender Love, when e're a Prelate weeps. But see the King appears. Enter Rotherick. Rothe. I'm come Catholicus, to see how well You use these fair Ones, take heed I've no Complaint. Catho. I'm naturally compassionate my Leige: And much more so, to Beauty in Distress. Rothe. Your Ministers of State, who execute Their Royal Masters will, should be like them: And I thou knowst, have tender thoughts about me, And punish but where Injuries are great; Revenge is then my best Prerogative: Say Avelina, have you taught the Princess, To have a better Notion of me now, Then when we last unhappily did meet? Ave. The Princess Sir is sweet, is kind and good; And sensible of all the power you have; At first, Captivity she could not Brook, Which made her vent some Words that you thought harsh; But well I know— Eva. (aside) Take heed my Fair one, least you say too much. Ave. (aside) His Temper now seems calm, and we perhaps; May gain some Respite for your Brothers Life: And if you cannot joyn in all I say; Let him suppose your Silence gives Consent; Least he should reassume again the Tyrant. Rothe. There is a certain Haughtiness, sits round Her killing, dreadful, sparkling, pleasing Eye: A Sort of Majesty, which does foretell That all who look and gaze, must be her Slaves; May I believe my Daughter fairest Eva? When she declares, that your Resentment is So soften'd, as to think your Rotherick, Your abject Slave, is not so much a Tyrant As you in your Anger, have proclaimed him. Ave. (aside) Now dearest Eva, put on all the Woman; And you and I shall gain his Heart for ever. Eva. Rotherick you know, it has been my Fate Even from my Infancy, to've been Taught That you were cruel, lawless, and revengfull; The terrible, and most unhappy War: Which has continued for so many Years, Between my Father and yourself, perhaps Has been a Motive to your Enemies; To paint you so, as you have not deserved. But as my Mind's possess'd, you can't remove The Prepossession, but by acting so, As may convince me you are good and Just. The King of Leinster, may have been a Foe So base, and so ungenerous; as you Have had a Cause, which would provoke a Saint: And made your Blood and Slaughter, just and right, But say my Father, he has been to blame; Why must the innocence of my Brother, Be made a Sacrifice, to your Revenge? I would fain believe, that your Humanity Should you calmly think would save his Life, That would be a King-like, God-like Action. Rothe. How her words inchant me! I grow Enamour'd, Am shaking off, that haughty manly Spirit, That should attend the Heart of Majesty. Ave. Cothurnus, once 'twas thought, had gained your Heart, We know King Dermond, by his Breach of Treaties Has plainly shown, he does disown his Son; Or sure the Care of him, might have restrain'd His Troops from further Acts of hostile War: Be you to him a Father Sir, and show by Your Mildness, the King of Leinster's Cruelty. Eva. And give the World a handle to believe, That you have acted on a Principle of Good, A View of Happiness to all Mankind. Then you are truly Heavens Vicegerent here, When your Subjects are your Care; each neighbouring King Your Friend, and ev'ry Action of your Life A publick Blessing, and a publick Good. Rothe. Catholicus, with Speed go free Cothurnus. Catho. I shall my Leige, that's from his Chains you mean; Not give him Liberty to go abroad. Rothe. Prelate, how dare you thus explain my Will, And handle it as if it were a Text? Giving it your vile Interpretation; Fly dull Priest with Speed, free him, fetch him here; If you expostulate, put on his Chains, Prepare to Die, and wait my Orders for't. Catho. I fly my Leige, (aside) curse on their female Tongues, The Storm at last, is like to fall on me. (Exit) Eva. You now appear, what Majesty should be; Great and Noble, yet kind and merciful Whilst this Divinity is hovering round you; It Emboldens me, to be asking still. Rothe. The more you ask, the more you still will please me. Eva. There was a faithful Servant taken with me, Who shares Cothurnus Fate, and lyes in Chains: If it so please your Majesty, I beg Regan may be released, and share your Favour. Rothe. Fly Avelina, overtake the Priest: Tell him 'tis my Will, that he brings Regan too; So I think my Royal Princess call'd him. Ave. With hasty Wings of Love and Joy I go. (Exit. Rothe. You see fair Angel, I am not that thing: Your Father and his Ministers, have painted me; I love my Country, and scorn that Prince, Whom small Revenge for Injuries received, Can draw to act a Deed, which all good Men Abhor. The selling of his Country To the vilest Vagabonds and Strangers, Forgive me Charmer, when my Zeal displays The horrid traiterous Folly of your Father. Eva. I can't defend my poor unhappy Sire For that Act of his, for which I've oft shed Tears: I have a Soul, that would not sell The barren part of all my Land, to be Revenged of Millions of my Enemies: Bring in Strangers, to cut the Throats of those Who are my Friends, my Children and my Subjects: Oh! you Saints, you Martyrs, and you holy Tribe, Who watch our Actions, and set down our Sins: Blot off this horrid Fault from out your Books, And give my Father a repenting Heart. Rothe. Thus in my Arms, let me for ever hold thee; Thou Excellent, thou best, thou more than Woman: Oh! how the Touch of her inflames my Soul, Boils up my Blood, and sets my Heart a trembling. Eva. Hold Sir let me go, you now grow troublesome. Rothe. To my self I'm sure, perphaps I'm so to you; She pants, she heaves her Breast, ay now's the Time; The critical the happy Moment's come: We're all alone, and I must now enjoy her, May all her Sexes frailty's possess her, And all my Sexes strength and Charms attend me: Eva. For Heaven's sake let go my Hand, what mean you? Oh how I tremble! would I were gone from hence, My sinking Spirits, bodes no good to me. Rothe. Know Eva, I admire and adore you: And must enjoy, or die in the Attempt. Eva. Ha, what says the Monster? am I left alone With such a wretch as would attempt my Honour? Rothe. Take care of what you say; you've raised Me to a pitch of Love, and Madness—Madness may So get the better of my Love, that you May 'curse the Day, on which you did refuse me. Eva. Refuse thee what! thou horrid Monster? Oh Saints! into what wretch'd Hands I'm fall'n. Rothe. Come be not Coy, I want no Stratagem To heighten up my Love, I'm all Extasie, Therefore struggle not; but give up thy self To an amorous Monarch who adores thee. Eva. Unhappy Virgin, where will my Sorrow end? Let go my hands, thou base detested Villain, Help help, is no one near to give me help. Rothe. Forbear my dear, do not exalt your Voice; There's none that hear you, dare approach my Presence, I am the Mighty Lord o're all my Slaves: When I command, no one must disobey; Be not foolish then, push not on thy Ruin, But live the favourite Mistress of a King, Who would do any thing, to gain thy Love. Eva. The Powers above, affist and witness for me; That I detest, abhor, and hate thee so: That all the punishment thou canst inflict, And such a Tyrant; does not want Invention, Would be Charms and extasie, compared to thee, And I can love, and hug, and worship Hell E're I could design, to have one thought of thee: So thus I quit thee; and will seek out Death. (She struggles and gets from him.) Rothe. And when thou'rt dying, then I will enjoy thee; As you're expiring, make you wish to live. Eva. Thou Fiend of Hell, thou Tyrant; I believe thee, I tremble not, for what thy Tongue can utter: Go vent thy Malice on my sordid Clay, My innocent and Righteous Soul, flys up Above, beyond the reach of thee, and Hell. Rothe. Curse on my Folly, how I loyter here; About the silly trifling Thing a Woman, I will rush on, and take thee to my Arms, In spite of all the World, hell and Seas. He runs towards her, she pulls out a Dagger and wounds him, he struggles with her and gets the Dagger from her. Eva. Villian have at thy Heart, thou hast it there. Rothe. Thanks to my Arm, no doubt you meant it well: Thou stumblest at the petty sin of Love; But yet with lifted Eyes, can murther Kings, A meek, and innocent, and harmless Maid. Curse on thy haughty insolence and Pride, To humble thee, I'll send and Contradict The Orders that I gave Catholicus: Will study Cruel new invented Deaths, To give Cothurnus, and the slave his Friend. Eva. No good Angel sure, could guard thee from the blow; My zealous pious Hand design'd to give thee, It would have been a meritorious Deed: Lasting honour's, would have Crown'd my Memory, I won't repine at what the Fates decree, Perhaps a Thunderbolt, a flash of Lightning, Or a trembling Earth, are kept in store for thee. Rothe. Rail on, provoke me till I hate thee so, That I may take a pleasure in your Death; If I can't raise your blood, I'll let it out. Catches hold of her and points the Dagger at her. Eva. Strike home, my panting Heart is waiting for thee; Do not miss the Blow, I'll point thee to it. Rothe. Thus I'd revenge my self on all thy Race. Take thy Deaths wound, your Gods I cannot do it! Yet she must die, but I'll enjoy her first; See yonder is a Couch, I'll drag her thither. (She struggles with him.) Eva. Kill me, hack me, tear me, and destroy me, But do not seek to wrong my Innocence; What have you no Remorse, no thoughts of Heaven? Rothe. Thou art the Heaven which I think of now, Come on, or I will tear thee Limb from Limb: Ha, I faint, my Blood gushes out apace; Perhaps the wound you gave, will be my Death, But I will be reveng'd; Gaurds, Treason; Murder: Enter Guards Fly you, call my Chirurgeons and Physitians; Seize me that Traitoress, force her to yon Chamber, And lead me to her, where if Life is left; I will in Spite of all her Cries and Tears, Rush into her Arms, surfeit in Delight, And die away with Extasie. But oh! I faint, a Dizziness o'rewhelms my Eyes; Make haste, and lay me gently on my Couch. (they carry him off. Eva. Help Murder, oh ye Saints and Angels, try To save my Innocence, or let me die. (they hurry her off opposite to him End of the third ACT</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT IV. SCENE a Prison. Cothurnus and Regan in Chains. Cothur. I grant you, our Religion teaches us To bear the Ills of Life, without repining. Regan. To part with Ills we have, we hurry on Perhaps to worse; Cowards may wish to die, Because they fear to live, but noble Souls Can with undaunted Courage, meet the Shocks Of Life, and still appear Philosophers. Cothur. There is in Life, no Blessing worth our Care. But to be free from Slavery and Chains. But see the vile Catholicus appears: Enter Catholicus. That ominous, Ill croaking Raven, bodes no Good To you nor me, except he brings us Death. Reg. Bring what he will, let us resolve to show That we can meet it, tho' we do not seek it. Catho. Cothurnus, did you know what Pains I took. To bring the News, the happy joyful News, You'd say I was indeed your best of Friends; The King my royal Master, sent me here, To free you from these horrid dismal Chains. And fly with Speed to bring you to his Presence, And by his cheerful Look I do foresee, With Life and Happiness, he'll crown your Days; Away with Speed, Cothur. Not till you've released my Friend. Catho. My Orders reach not him, I'm sorry for't. Cothur. Put on my Chains again, I will not leave him. Reg. Forbear my Prince, to use Expostulations; Comply with the Commands from Rotherick sent; The Powers above have work'd a Miracle, And soften'd so his flinty harden'd Heart, That he may have repented of his Crimes; Your Father, should he hear you were destroy'd Disconsolate, 'twould sink him down to Death; Your Kingdom and your Name, would then be lost And all your Subjects ruin'd and destroy'd, For one weak and generous Act, to serve your Friend, You would bring all this Misery upon you. Therefore with Speed be gone, ne're think of me. Cotur. Regan I will go, but with a heavy Heart: My Fathers faithful Friend and mine farewell. Reg. Farewell, my Royal Prince, farewell for ever; Should the Gods so pour a Blessing on you, As to bring you to your Father once again, Tell him Regan liv'd and dy'd his faithful Slave. (As they are going out) Enter Avelina. Ave. Oh my Cothurnus, do I hold thee fast? And once again Embrace thee in these Arms: Catholicus, it is my Fathers Will: That with Cothurnus, Regan be released. With floods of Joy, your Sister and my self Have felt his mild, his kind, his tender Usage; Lead Catholicus, lead us to my Father, Where we shall meet the solid Joy we wish, And neither fear, nor hope to change our Fate. Cothur. Oh! let Rotherick give you to my Arms; And sign a Solemn everlasting Peace, Then prostrate at his Feet I'll throw me down, And think him worthy of a Sovereign Crown: Forget he was a Tyrant, I his Slave; Will call him Father, and his blessing Crave. (Exeunt. Scene draws to Rotherick's Tent. Enter Rotherick, Chirurgeons and Guards: Rothe. Ay, as you say, the Blood might make me Faint, But now you have bound it up, I'm well again. Exeunt Chirurgeons Guards call forth that Tyrannick cruel Beauty, For Love and for Revenge my Soul is thirsting. Enter Guards with Eva. See how the haughty Goddess stalks along. And with her Eyes, shootsdarts of Scorn upon me. Go, Guards be gone, and leave us to our Selves, I'll conquer her proud Heart, or dye a Slave. Exeunt Guards. Eva. Then all my Prayers could not preval I find. Heaven has for some horrid Sins of mine, Continued you alive. to be my Torment. Rothe. To be your loving Lord, my Sweetest Eva. One Way, tho' Death insue, I will enjoy thee, Chuse then, the soft, the kind, the tender Heart. O'reflowing with the Amorous Fire of Love. Rather then the Stern, the cruel Countenance, Crowded full of anger, Horror and Rrevenge. Eva. Suppose I tell you, I've Consider'd on't And find my Resolution wavering. And when you talk of Love. can listen to it, And often steal a wishfull Look a Sigh. Perhaps in time, it may grow up a Passion. Rothe. Encourage it, no doubt it will be Love, And I my self, will raise the Passion for you. Eva. Stand off, I now begin again to hate you. Rothe. The quick Inconstancy of your wavering Sex. Love, or Hate, my Flame so fast consumes me, I can wait no longer, but will push my Doom. And thus! and thus! I seize upon my Prey. (Takes her in his Arms she Skrieks, as he is going out, he meets Catholicus, Regan, Cothurnus, Avelina and Guards; seeing them he quits his Hold, She runs to Cothurnus. Catho. My Leige, according to your Orders, I Have brought the Prisoners hither. What more Commands? Rothe. Curse on thy Officiosuness, go send them back, And bid my Guards drag thee away to Death. Eva. Save me Cothurnus, Save me Avelina, Give me death, but guard me from the Ravisher. Cothur. The Ravisher!— Are these the joys, our flattering Hopes foretold? Is this the Parent that I was to meet? Is this the great the awfull Godlike Monarch? Is this the tender Parent of his People? Is this— Rotherick takes a Javelin from one of the Guards, and Stabs Cothurnus. Rothe. Go thou to Death, I long design'd it for thee. Cothur. Tyrant I thank thee, thou hast done the Deed, And I must leave my Sister to your Mercy, For my charming Avelina's Sake, I cou'd suffer more, much more; but Oh! (Dies. Ave. He's gone, he's cold, he's dead, Oh cruel King! I must make Haste, I shall not overtake him. (Stabs her self with a Dagger.) So, I aim'd full well, my Heart has felt it. Reg. What a Bloody Scene of Death and Horror's here! Rothe. Thou disobedient Wretch, who bid thee die? Ave. Your rash and bloody Hand, first gave the Blow, For when you pierc'd, and stab'd Cothurnus's Flesh, You push'd the Javelin, quite through my Soul, Who could design to Live, when that brave Youth was gone? Repent you Sir, of all your horrid Crimes, By Prayer and Fasting, try to make your Peace, With that most Just avenging Deity, Whom you have so dreadfully offended, Hard-hearted Father! poor unhappy Eva! (Dies. Rothe. Silly foolish Girl, no doubt she meant it well: But I can shed no Tears, Eva you see What bloody Havock, your Disdain has made here; Sure you are sorry, for your Obstinacy, And cannot long persist against my Will. Eva. I did expect your Daughters dying words, Would rouze up something of the Man within you: Shew a relenting Heart, and thoughts of Heaven, Shed Tears of Blood, and put on just Resolves, Confess thy Sins, and make some Expiation. Enter Guard. 1 Guard: Arm, arm my Leige! Dermond and his Strangers Have seiz'd and kill'd the Out-guards to our Camp; And now with mighty Force, are Marching down, Burning and destroying all before them. Rothe. Let them come on, the hand that kill'd the Son, If Fate looks on, perhaps shall kill the Father; So I shall quench my Thirst, in just Revenge. Enter Catholicus. Catho. To Horse my Leige! they'll seize you in your Tent; They've made the Camp a horrid Field of Blood, And I am told your Foot are giving Way. Rothe. Ha! what sayst thou— Dare they be Cowards, and belong to me? Eva you see, we've Business on our Hands, And therefore must put off our dear Enjoyment Prelate, I've a long Account to make with you Another time; go take her to your Care, And let the Guards go see that Fellow die; If once you shou'd suspect the Enemy Of gaining Ground, or rushing to the Tent, Take this Dagger here, push it through her Heart, And send her to Cothurnus, and my Daughter: Now my keen Sword, do thou but stand my Friend, My Arm shall lead thee, to such Blood and Slaughter, That wert thou thirsting like the barren Sands, Thou should'st have Floods to drink, and quench thy Thirst. Exit. Noise without of Drums and Trumpets. Eva. As thou deservest, so Heaven help thy Cause. Catho. You heard my Royal Master's Orders Sir, I do suppose, you are prepar'd to Die. Reg. Catholicus, at present I am not, for Methinks I wish to help my Royal Master, And be revenged, for my Cothurnus's Death. Catho. If you are ruminating on Revenge, And so should die, you may go to Purgatory. Enter Guard. 1 Guard. The King in a most gallant Manner, pushed The Enemy with all his Might, and Strengh, At first he bravely forc'd them to retreat, And would have gain'd a certain Victory: But that his Horse, was by an Arrow shot, Which so confused the Troops, they all gave way. 'Tis feared our Foes will gain the Camp: 'Tis highly fit, that you remove from hence, Or you, too soon will fall into their Hands. (Exit. Catho. (aside) Should I now destroy Regan, and the Princess, And be taken afterwards, by Dermond, My Life will be a Sacrifice for all; These English are well Disciplin'd to War, Henry the second is a gallant Prince. The Church does flourish much within his Realm, And what is our Delight, Church-Men bear some Sway; The Pope has sure enough, bestow'd him Ireland. I begin to think, he had A most Religious Right, to give away; I ought to pay Obedience to the Chair. (To them) Regan you know your Life is in my Power, And fairest Eva, has nor long to Live, Without that I compassionate her Cause. Say should I set you free, would you protect Me, from the Insolence of Dermonds Troops? Recommend me to the Earl of Chepstow, And should there be a Peace, include me in it. Reg. We'll grant what ever Terms you can demand. Eva. How meritorious will your Actions be, To all good Men, especially my Father If you give up his Daughter and his Friend, When you had Rothericks orders, to Destroy: No Pious Saint, that e're was Canonized, Could plead so good a right to Heaven as you. Catho. It does appear to me you love the Pope, And all that love the Pope, should be protected, Within the Tent there are some weapons lodg'd. (He goes to the Door and brings a Sword.) Regan take your Life, and swear by this bright Sword, To fight the Papal, and your Country's cause, And let us both protect the fairest Eva. Reg. Thus on my knees, let me return you Thanks, When next I loose this Sword, Life go thou with it. Eva. Catholicus, you have so gain'd my Heart, That here I make a solemn sacred Vow, When solid, settled Peace shall bless this Land: In Memory of you, I'll build a Church, And near adjoyning to it, a Monastry; A Day for ever shall be set apart, To sing the glorious Actions of thy Life, That after Ages, may adore, and wonder. Reg. Catholicus, 'twere fit we sally out; Your Presence may prevail, and win the Day, The Awe is much, the Soldiers bear you: And when they hear so good, so great a Man, Exclaim against vile Rotherick's Tyranny, It may perhaps take off, the Edge of War. Eva. And make them all submit to Dermond's Power: And so you'll be the blessed Means of Peace, And hinder Christian Blood from being shed. Catho. When we who love the Pope, would do a Thing, We want not Arguments to justifie us, And when we stubborn it, and sullen grow, It is but crying Conscience to the Crowd, And they will follow us in Multitudes. Enter Guard. 1 Guard. My Royal Master has done more than Man! He rally'd thrice his Troops, each time repuls'd: Despairing of Success, he's march'd away With all his Horse, to try to gain a Pass, By which he'll streighten much the Enemy: Our Foot surrounded by their Foes, are now Capitulating for their Lives; 'tis Time That you surrender to the Conqueror, For fear the raging Soldiers use you ill. Reg. Know you ought, about the King of Leinster? 1 Guard. 'Twas rumour'd in our Camp, that he was Kill'd, And by the Hand of Rotherick him self. Eva. Revengful Tyrant! most unhappy Eva! Catholicus, 'tis now I wish to die. 1 Guard. Madam that News as yet, is not confirm'd, And might be politickly given out, To Animate our Troops, and make them Fight. Catho. It may be so, suspend your Grief a while, And take not up this Sorrow so at Interest; Should it be true, your Will must be resign'd: Reg. Any Tidings of the Earl of Chepstow? 1 Guard. That's he I do suppose they Strongbow call. Reg. The same. 1 Guard. He and his gallant Archers, push'd our Troops. The Strangers fought like Devils not like Men; They gave no Quarter, nor they ask'd for none, But up and down the Field, they strow'd the Limbs Of all King Rotherick's gallant Soldiers. Catho. Learn where the Enemies Head-Quarters are, And straitways bring us Notice who commands, That we may send to him, and make our Terms. Exit Guard. Reg. Give your self no Pain, the Princess is your Friend, And she will gain you Terms as for herself, If Royal Dermond is alive, no doubt you'll find He is your Friend, and will support the Roman Church: If Heaven has thought fit to plague the Land So much, as to translate him from this Life; The Earl of Chepstow is a gallant Man, Fill'd with Humanity, a noble Soul, Bred up by Honour, and a Soldier's Heart Commands his Body, full of Life and Fire, He pushes on to gain immortal Glory, He is a Man— Eva. He is so, but know Regan, he's no more: You have a mind to lavish in his Praise, And say those things, that Irish Men deserve; But I shall curse the Day he landed here, And you your self e're long, will wish him Dead. Reg. I think him more compassionate and just, Than to oppose our long, long settled Love; At present, he accepts your Father's Offer, Supposing that your Heart is undispos'd, Eva. Oh Regan! flatter not your self and me, With Hopes, or Joys, or Peace, or Length of Days, Mine, has been a long continued Scene of Woe. Catho. This Discovery may do me Service, And at the King of Leinster's Court, make Peace For all the Clerks within my Diocess, Nothing delights a States-man like a Secret. Reg. Catholicus, 'twere time we sally'd out, Our Lives have long subsisted by your Mercy, And thus your generous Goodness we'll reward: I will protect you with this Sword and Arm, And through King Dermond's Camp, I will proclaim Catholicus, a Friend to him and England. Catho. Regan, your Zeal to me, and to the Roman Church. Will one Day make your Lusture shine fourth bright, And from a Man, you will become a Saint. Eva. In horrid Life no Pleasure I can find, To a Wretch like me, none ever was design'd. A Glympse of Happyness, I oft am shown, Then to my Misery again I'm thrown. Am hurl'd about, the Tennis-Ball of Fate, To be most Wretched, is to be most Great. Exeunt. End of the fourth ACT</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT V. Enter Eva, Regan, and Catholicus. Reg. It is with Joy, I tell my dearest Eva, King Dermond lives, and with immortal Fame, This glorious Day, has Crown'd him with a Laurel, Flourishing and Green, points out the Heroe; And after Ages will repeat his Name. Enter Strongbow, Dermond and Guards. Der. With weary'd Arms I have pursu'd my Foes. And look'd for Rotherick, in the thickest Crowd, That most inhuman Murderer of my Son: Come to my Arms my dearest, dearest Daughter, The Comfort, and the Blessing of my Life; With Tears I've heard your mournful Tragedy: Cathliocus I thank you for her Life; Regan, my faithful Councellour and Friend, With open Arms and Joy, I do receive you. The noble Earl of Chepstow next, deserves My lowly humble Thanks, and loudest Praise, To reward his Courage, I'm too Poor, To shew my Gratitude, I'll give him all I hold most dear, my sweetest darling Daughter; Eva come here and let me joyn your Hands, Where I'm sure with Joy you'll joyn your Heart; Take her my faithful Friend and Allie, And with her, take my Crown, and take my Kingdom. Strong. Dermond, your Crown and Scepter I despise, But your Daughter, is a Jewel I adore. Eva. My Lord, my Father, sure will give me leave To think, on what I am going to do; 'Twere fit I spend some Time in Church Affairs, And give my Thanks for Blessings I have received, And make my Peace with good Catholicus, And so perform the solemn Vows I made Through all my Sorrow and Adversity. Der. 'Twere fit a decent Time were given you To make you worthy of so great a Prize. Strong. Her shining Beauty, captivates my Heart, And 'tis with eager Love, I wish her mine. Der. Regan, how willingly I would reward you, My Heart alone can tell, I doat upon you, And would give you all, a Monarch has to give. Reg. My faithfull Services 'tis time to plead; No, curse my Fate! I pleaded them too late; You were profuse and lavish of your Store, And gave away to Strongbow all you had; And for your favourite Friends, left nought but Words. Der. What says my Regan! have I nothing left? Then is my sacred Friendship reckon'd Nothing, My regal Power, nor all my Titles, My Grants of Rebell Lands, nor all my Places Reckon'd Nothing! To hear the Man say this Who may command them all, 'tis wondrous strange. Eva. Your Majesty must pardon Regan's Talk, Rotherick's Tyranny has turn'd our Senses; The barbarous Murder of my Brother, His unheard of Cruelties to us all, And most inhuman Usage of his Daughter; Might pierce the soundest Brain, and cause Distraction. (Aside) Regan for Shame, command your Temper better, Your warm Discourses may bring Ruin to us, But cannot change our Doom; rely on me. Strong. Dermond, the Number of the Prisoners taken Are numerous, and should proud Rotherick Rally, And bring his Forces to another Charge; We shall repent us that we let them live; 'Tis my Advice, they all be put to Death. Eva. (Aside) Cruel, barbarous, inhumane Monster! (to him) And would you have them all, to suffer Death? In cool Blood, must they be butcher'd thus? Strong. The Discipline of War, has so decree'd; This may seem Cruel, to the tender Eva, But Souldiers are inur'd to War and Blood; We only shew Compassion to our selves, And to prolong our Lives, take theirs away. Catho. (Aside) I as a Prisoner must suffer Death; Heaven forbid! I am not fit to die. (to them) If Dermond gives a Prisoner leave to Speak, The Resolution of the Earl of Chepstow, May be a present Plea for your Security, But may prove fatal to your future Peace; The Country are inrag'd, and would throw off The Yoke, the heavy Yoke, of Rotherick's Sway, And are inclin'd, as we the Clergy know, To choose the King of Leinster for their Prince, And one and all would cry, long live King Dermond. But should you put to Death their Fathers, Sons, Their Brothers and their Kins-Folks, it must not be, It will inrage, and bring Destruction on, Whilst calmer Means, may win them all to Peace. Der. Catholicus, you've spoke my Sentiments; But if the Earl of Chepstow will agree To call a Council, I'll propose it there, And what is Reason must be all our Guides. Strong. My own Opinion is to me strong Reason; Notwithstanding which, I will give Ear to you. Der. Mean Time, 'twere fit our Daughter take some Rest The Nuptials we'll defer a Day or two; And follow now the Business of the State' Settle that, and then let us give way to Joy; Regan attend my Daughter to my Tent, And let soft Slumbers, calm her heavy Mind. Strong. A Day or two, to me in love's an Age; Dermond, I cannot brook so long Delay. Der. Be it to Morrow then, will that Suffice? Strong. Suppose it were to Night, what hinders it? Eva. What may hinder it an Age, my Consent; Know you not? that it is necessary. Strong. I know fair Princess, that you should be consulted. But I am rough, plain Speech'd, and made for War, No fawning, cringing, bowing ogling Lover, That can swear, and lie, and call you Goddess; I am honest, and your Father knows full well, When all his Friends and Subjects did forsake him; I joyn'd him; with a warlike Troop of Men; Who, swift as Lightning, sent his Foes to Death, And through the thickest Battle I rush'd on, To save your Father, when oppress'd by Numbers, When sprawling on the Ground his Horse lay dead: I rais'd him on my Steed, and fought on Foot, Nay, to animate my Troops, I sacrificed My only Son, a Youth who run away With Cowardice opprest, I show'd my Men, What punishment a Fault like that deserved; For with my Sword, I cut him through the Waste: I could say more then this— Der. Indeed you could— And I for ever; must acknowledge you My Friend, my great Supporter, and my Father. Strong. What say you fairest Lady, will this do, Can you think, I've worth enough to merit you? Eva. I am a poor Forlorn, and abject Creature, Far unworthy, of your great Heroick Soul; My heavy Heart, oppress'd with Woe, Can give no Entrance to a Lover yet: Perhaps, when I've consulted all your Charms, And study'd o're, your great and wondrous Acts: Then may be, the proper Season we should Wed, Till when, I beg to call the Time my own. Reg. 'Twere fit I lead the Princess to your Tent. Der. Her Eyes look heavy, lead her to Repose. Eva. Lead me to my Grave, there lyes my true Repose. Exeunt Eva and Regan. Strong. Dermond, me thought her Air was Insolent, With scorn she look'd, as if she did despise me, Take heed, she plays not False, my passions strong; If she is so ungreatfull to her Father, As to deny, to give her self away To one, who is so much her Fathers Friend. Now by my Soul, I did not think of this! Curse on her Female pride, why who am I? No doating Fool, that sues and whines for Love: I call her to my Arms, as by Agreement made, We have sign'd and seal'd and you gave her to me. All Articles by Generals made, are Sacred; And were the petty Girl, a-kin to me, She should not dare, to put it off one Moment. Dermond go follow her, and let her know How dangerous it is, to disoblige me: Should I draw off my Forces from your Camp, Rotherick has Men enough, to crush you all, Go tell her this, and tell her I'm Enraged, Say 'tis Love, or what you else can think on. Der. Far be it from me, or my Daughter either; To disoblige, so kind so good a Friend: It shan't be long before she doth Consent. Exit. Catho. (Aside) 'Twere fit I pay Obeysance to this Earl, I find he has a Soul, and will command. (To him) Most Noble General, perhaps I could Declare the cause of all the Princess's Coolness; And tell you such a Secret, would surprize you. Strong. Whoever does, a generous Deed to me, Shall find his friendly Actions well rewarded: Prelate speak out, and tell me what you know, About this Female Toy, that has inraged me. Catho. My Noble Earl she is a Toy indeed, And such a one as you may well despise; And give a most convincing Reason for't, She has ingag'd, and gave her Heart away, To that Ill-looking Man, you Regan call. Strong. Ha! what say'st thou, gave her Heart away to him? And give to him, what she denied to me: My Tide of Passion swells, and rages high, Such an affront, no mortal Man can bear. Know's she my Birth, knows she my glorious Acts? And will she, does she, dares she, thus despise me. Catho. I over heard them both, confess their Passions; They love express'd, in a Romantick Manner, They sigh'd and said they'd die for one another. Strong. They did so! and by Heavens so they shall: I'm thirsting for Revenge, I'll drink the Draught, And Dermond shall not live, or Regan dies. Catho. I beg my Lord, you will not let them know, You got the mighty Secret out of me. Strong. Of whom are you afraid, if I protect you? Catho. My Lord, you know they say, I am their Prisoner. Strong. Go too, I know that what they say is False, I as the Victor, do command the Field, The Tents the Spoils, the Prisoners, all are mine, And when I design to speak the word, you're free; Besides, I would not prosecute the Church. My War is not to People of your Cloth, I do expect you all, should Pray for me; And in return, I will protect your Lives, Your Fortunes, Livings, and your Sacred Houses: I come not to destroy, but give you Liberty, And bring this barbarous Nation, to such Laws As will draw Peace and plenty to your Country. Catho. The blessing of the Roman Church protect you for't; I'll send to my Cathedral, and we'll sing Te Deum for your glorious Victory: The Clergy in their Pulpits, shall declare That you have all the Right you would have; We'll found it, on what Principle you please. Strong. The right of Conquest, is the Right I own. Catho. Then they shall preach up that, and in such Terms That were you Beaten, they should say you conquer'd; 'Tis good to have the Roman Churchmen on your Side, We can Preach up Peace, or raise Rebellion. Observe that Prince, sits easiest on his Throne, Who strives to make the Clergy all his one. Strong. Prelate, 'tis true, your Maxims are most Wise, And when my raging Breast, sinks down to Calm, I will make them all my constant Practice; Till when, 'twere fit I do exert my Power, About this foolish Girl, that gives me Pain, That is, she raises Scorn; and galls Ambition, Catho. Before you go about to use Revenge, 'Twere well, you shou'd o'rehear the Lovers talk, Which will convince you, what I say is true; When if you were at once to charge them with it, They would deny, and lay the Fault on me. Srong. You reason well, I'll follow your Advice, And should this Regan once declare his Love, 'Twere fit he dies; or my Resentment sinks; My strong ambitious Passion, flies above, And Scorns within a middle Sphere to move. And it shall be a true recorded Story, No Rival in my Love, nor in my Glory. Exeunt. Enter Regan, and Eva. Eva. It is impossible to stem the Tide, Or think, or hope to take a Flight from hence. Reg. I have a faithful Friend, who would conceal us. Eva. They'd search the Country round, and bring us here, And you for serving me, might suffer Death; For Stongbow then, would come to know your Love. Reg. And do you think that I would keep it Secret? No, were he posted at his Armies Head, I'd tell him I deserved you more than he. Eva. This Violence, might prove fatal to our Love, But mine's a Chain of Woe, which I must bear. Reg. And yet I would consult your Peace of Mind, Nay give you up, and die to make you Happy. Enter Dermond. Der. Eva, from the Earl of Chepstow, I am sent, To tell you, he demands you as his Wife, You know what obligations I have to him, And how my future Peace depends upon him, Comply with me, and give to him your Heart. Eva. Cruel Father! could you sell my Happiness? Sacrifice your Daughter to the Thing on Earth, The vilest Thing, she most could Scorn and Hate: It must not, may not be: I cant comply To mingle Soul's with one who is a Stranger; Command me Sir to Death, I'll go with Joy. But cannot live to wed the Man I hate. Der. Will not my Happyness, my Subject's Peace, My Kingdom's Welfare, and your Country's good, Weigh nothing with your harden'd Heart? go too, Thou disobedient Girl no more my Child: I thought to have bless'd thee, prais'd thee, lov'd thee, But instead of this, I now must curse thee. Reg. The Gods forbid, my Royal Master should do so, On me, 'tis all your Curses you must pour, On me; you must call Heaven's vengeance down; I am the Cause of all your Tears and Woe. The Princess in her young and tender Years, Gave leave for me, to talk to her of Love, And I presuming on my Services, Doubted not, of your Consent, when time should serve, I often did resolve, to tell you this, But you were still involv'd in heavy Troubles, And not prepar'd to hear an amorous Story. Der. Perdition seize us all! then you are Wed; Thou Friend, thou Villain! I can hear no more. Exit. Eva. Regan, go call him back and undeceive him, Reg. Undeceive him! how is it possible? Then are you not by solemn Contract mine? Eva. The Contract is, I'm not to wed another, But am not therefore, strictly tyed to you: I'll end my Days in a Religious House, And then my Father's Blessing will remain, And I protected from the Earl of Chepstow, May silently fit down; and die in Peace. Reg. Then is your Love so wavering, so inconstant? That you can leave me, give me up with Ease. Eva. Regan, when we part I dread the Agonies, I fear my Love, outweighs my Resolution. Reg. Come to my Arms, and then I'm sure it will. Enter Catholicus Speaking to Strongbow. Catho. You see their Intimacy, wait a while, That by their Words, you may discover more. Strong. Curse on their circling Joys, I'll kill them both. Catho. No blood-shed good my Lord, keep back I pray. (Strongbow goes back.) Peace attend you both, you happy happy Pair: I pleaded with the Earl of Chepstow for you, Knowing that your Love has long been growing; But he Impatient as the Wind, resolves To make you his, or die in the Attempt. Reg. Then let him die, thinks he, I'll quit my Right; Is there an inequality in Birth? Or does his wondrous Merit darken mine? That makes him thus pretend, to Lord it o're us, My Royal Master, willing to Recover; Rebellious Subjects to their true Allegiance, Hired this Noisey Lord, and all his Knights, To serve him in the War, and they assume A Power, a Command, as if they conquer'd, And we, and all the Country were their Slaves. Enter Strongbow and Guards. Strong. Curse on his Tongue, I'll hear no more, Guards seize him. Catho. Mercy on us! I fear we are betrayed. (The Guards goes to seize Regan, he draws and opposes them) Reg. Stand off you Wretches, send your gallant Earl, To meet the greatest Foe he has on Earth. 2 Guard. Deliver up your Sword, or you must Die. Reg. Thy Life shall answer, I will keep my Sword. 2 Guard. Why then have at thy Heart, thou hast it there. Eva. Help, Traytors! Treason, they will murder Regan. Reg. Eva, it is done, and now you are releas'd From all the Vows and Contracts you have made. Strong. You Sir, how came you to exceed my Orders? 2 Guard. He oppos'd, I did it in my own defence. Reg. You did your Duty, and I thank you for it: Eva be happy, think of me no more. (Dies. Eva. Talk not of happiness to me, I go Where both of us shall never fear, nor meet with Trouble. (She offers to stab her self, Strongbow takes the Dagger from her.) Strong. Heavens forbid, my Princess you must Live. Enter 3d Guard. 3 Guard. The King of Leinster, sent me with all speed, To let you know, that Rotherick is joyn'd With fresh Supplys, and has engag'd the Van: He begs you'd march the Archers, and the Horse. Strong. Give Orders for their March, I'll head them soon; (Exit Guard. Dry up those watry Eyes, my dearest Princess, I fight your Father's cause to set you free; Whilst I remain a Slave, a Woman's slave: Catholicus, to your Care I do commit, This best, this sweetest Treasure of my Soul. Catho. Hard by adjoyning, is a Monastry; The Lady Abbess of it is my Sister: I'll leave her to her Care, whilst I go pray, The Saints, to Guard you through the Battle. Strong. Your Prayers and Care shall be rewarded, Take up the Body, give it Funeral Rites. Catho. I'll take Care to lodge it in the Monastry. Strong. Do so, if I had Time I'd shed a Tear, In hopes 'twould please my Princess; fare you well. (The Guards take off the Body.) (Exit. Eva. Lead me to this pious Sanctuary, And let my Soul shake off all worldly Cares; Except the hearing of my Father's Safety. Catho. We'll go, where you shall meet no more misfortunes. (Exeunt. (Noise of Warlike Instruments.) Enter Rotherick with his Sword Drawn. Rothe. Curse on my Coward Troops, they all give Way; These hellish Strangers, drive down all before them: Could I meet Dermond, or this Earl of Chepstow, At the full Value I would sell my Life, And dying, drag their Souls to follow me. Enter Catholicus and Eva. Catho. The troops Crow'd this way, there's no Safety there. Rothe. (Espyes them.) Ha! my Darling Eva, thou'rt a prize indeed; Two Battles I would lose, to gain this Foe, My good Catholicus come here my Friend. Catho. With Tears of Joy my Leige. Rothe. —Villian thou lyest. (kills him. And with those words, I'll send thy Soul to Hell. Catho. Quite through, you've pierced my Heart and I must die, There's all my worldly Glory thrown away; I've lost a Cardinal's Cap, so fare you well. (Dies. Rothe. So perish all those Ministers of State; Who are unfaithful to their Sovereigns: Now my dearest Eva, thou'rt all my own, My Love and my Revenge, I'll quench on thee: (He halls her.) Nay struggle not, for 'tis all in vain, I'm resolved. Eva. Help, Murder, Tyrant, Ravisher, help, help! Enter Dermond. The Gods have sent my Father to my Aid; Protect me Sir, and take me from the Tyrant, Rotherick, the Hellish Rotherick is here. Der. Monster, turn thy cursed Face, and meet thy Doom; I have been seeking thee through all the Field, I will repeat thy Crimes, and punish thee. Rothe. I know them all, I'll make thee use few Words, My Sword shall speak for me, and I'll revenge: (They fight Dermond falls.) It was in just that part, I kill'd your Son. Eva. Help help, he hath kill'd my Father, Dermonds kill'd! Rothe. Cease your Clamour, you Fly to be Pursued; You see the Fates have now decreed you mine: How often must I win you as my Prize? Der. Rotherick, perhaps the Earl of Chepstow Will revenge my Death, spare my Daughters Virtue, Farewell thou most unhappy Child, Death comes! (Dies. Eva. Oh! my Father, can you hear those dying words, And not relent, and suffer me to die? Rothe. You were the cause of all this Devastation, You with your haughty Pride, refus'd my Love; And so your Brother, and your Father died: But now I think I've conquer'd all your Race, And without interruption, shall enjoy you. Enter Strongbow and Guards. Eva. The Earl of Chepstow comes to set me free, And he is now the only Friend I've left; Turn this way Sir, and see a wretch'd Maid, See here, the Cruel Tyrant Rotherick: Behold the bloody Executioner, Of my Brother, Father, and Catholicus. Strong. My charming Princess! I'll revenge your Cause, I've saved your Country, and would gain your Love, Yeild Tyrant quickly, to my Mercy yieild; I've vanquish'd all thy Troops; throw up thy Sword. Roth. If thou art Valiant, as thou has given out, Come here, and meet me with a single Arm; I know thy Troops can overpower me. And such their number is that I must fall; But if you're Noble, let us meet in Death, And let me fell my Life, and Kingdom well. Strong. Guards, secure the Princess, and if I should die, Proclaim her Queen of Leinster, and obey her: It is with Joy my fairest I proceed, To Vindicate your Right, and so revenge The Death of all those Souls, this Wretch has murder'd. As he's a King, this Honour he shall have, The Earl of Chepstow, push'd him to his Grave. (Rotherick and Strongbow Fight.) Eva. My Heart grows pityfull, and I must Pray The Saints, to favour Strongbow's Cause and mine. Strong. Well have you Fought, but Death at Last's your Fate; None ever conquer'd yet, the Earl of Chepstow. Rothe. Thou hast o're power'd me, and I must Die; Grant me but one Request, I'll die in Peace: Fetch hither to my Hand, that foolish Girl, That I may Squeeze, and crush her in my Arms, To Death, I hate her, and I hate my self, And you, and all the World where am I going? (Dies. Eva. Lead me, from his Loathsome hatefull Body: For tho I know he's dead, I tremble still, You are the protector of my Honour, In what, or how, am I to reward you? Strong. Much more then this, I'd do to gain my Eva; Comply with my Request, and Crown my Love, Be a Parent to your sinking People. Obey your Father, own your self my Wife; And let us to this Isle, give lasting Peace. Eva. My heart is swell'd, and so opprest with Grief, 'Tis pain and Anguish when I utter Words; I beg you would command my Fathers Army, Rule and govern well his Kingdom curb his Foes, And give his poor, and wretched Subjects ease; Whilst I, in one continued Life of Prayer, Send up my Pious thoughts, to Heaven for you. Strong. (Aside) Her grief may waste away, 'Tis time to mind the business of the Field Take up the Bodies, whilst I lead the Princess, To the pious Abbess of yon Monastry, Where she may, in silent Grief, her losses mourn, And shed a Tear, on each deserving Urn: 'Till time, wear off the gloomy Face of Woe, And brings to mind, I kill'd her greatest Foe: With Love you Gods, possess the charming Fair, That she may raise her Lover, from Despair. End of the Fifth ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">EPILOGUE For Mr. Elrington, to be Spoke in Mourning, The last Time the Dutchess of Bolton comes to the Play House before she leaves Ireland. If Love or Anger, by the Poet wrote, Can take possession of the Player's Thought, That their sham Grief, can touch the Passions so, To make your Eyes with tender Pity flow; How much, when real Grief does move the Heart, Can every Player, truely act his Part. A Melancholy Theme, is coming on, A doleful Scene, and yet the Play is done. Bolton, the great supporter of our Stage, Born to do Good, and to adorn the Age. Must England bless, with her bright shining Rays, And totally Eclipse, our happy Days; Then like Antipodes, we shall appear, When their Sun rises, oh, 'tis setting here. These mournful Weeds, true Sorrow, doth Express 'Tis loss of Bolton, loss of Happiness. The Orthodox, and holy Fathers say, With laying Hands, the Spirit they convey, Oh! could your Grace as easily transfer, To some good Angel, all your Character, How happy would this Stage, this Nation be, And truly blest that happy fairest She: Ladies, exert your selves, and try what you, With all your native generous Charms can do: Be good, be great, and to your Players kind, And may you each enjoy a Bolton's Mind, This drooping Theatre, with Zeal support, And in her Absence, make this Stage your Court: With heavy Looks, observe her cross the Main, And wish and pray, and hope, for her again. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>