<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Cumberland, Richard, 1732-1811</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Cumberland, Richard, 1732-1811</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">cumberland richard 1732 1811</field>
      <field name="author_text">Cumberland, Richard, 1732-1811</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1810's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V2.0414.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1813</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460115</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Sybil or the Elder Brutus ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Sybil or the Elder Brutus ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="title_facet">sybil or the elder brutus</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">sybil or the elder brutus</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Sybil or the Elder Brutus ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="year_display">1813</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1813</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1813</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460115&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460115&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Cumberland, Richard, 1732-1811&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;cumberland richard 1732 1811&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Sybil or the Elder Brutus ; A Tragedy&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;sybil or the elder brutus&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1813&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1813&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Cumberland, Richard&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1732&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1811&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Sybil or the Elder Brutus&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for G. and W. Nicol by W Bulmer and Co. [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1813&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872445-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv20414&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Sybil or the Elder Brutus&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 150 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Only verse drama included&lt;lb/&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: The sybil.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Drama.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1813.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 3 Dec 1818.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE SYBIL, OR THE ELDER BRUTUS. A TRAGEDY.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Crudelis ubique Luctus, ubique pavor et plurima mortis imago.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DRAMATIS PERSONÆ. Sextus Tarquinius. Lucius Junius Brutus. Titus, his son. Collatinus. Valerius Poplicola. Vitellius. Centurion. Præfect of the Guard. Roman Soldier attending on Tullia. Lucretius. Tullia, wife of Tarquin. Tarquinia, his daughter. Priestess of Rhæa. The Cumæan Sybil. First Temple Virgin of Rhæa. Roman People, Soldiers, Virgins of Rhæa, Servants of Collatinus, Senators, and Ghost of Servius Tullus, late King of Rome.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE, Rome.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. A Square before the Palace of Tarquin. A number of common people collected together are discovered upon the drawing up of the curtain. First Roman. Will any body say to me that he has seen this thing? 2 Rom. What thing, neighbour, are you speaking of? 1 Rom. Marry, sir, a thing to puzzle those that be wiser than either you or me—A woman— if indeed that can be a woman, which every body talks of and nobody hath seen; whose prophecies are in every man's mouth, yet no man is bold enough to say he has heard them, or aver that he believes in them. 2 Rom. If it is the Sybil you are speaking of— 1 Rom. It is the Sybil we are speaking of; who speaks of any other thing? 2 Rom. Then I am he that hath seen her, and these are the ears that have heard her prophecy. 1 Rom. May we believe you? 2 Rom. As you list for that; but I will rehearse to you the manner of it, then judge ye for yourselves. Certain idle fellows of the city, to the number of a score or upwards, had collected themselves in the square of the Capitol for the purpose of making mockery of a poor witless ideot, whom you all know, Lucius Junius by name. For this unmanly pastime of theirs, I was reproving them somewhat angrily, when lo! in a moment there stood before my eyes a female figure, tall and comely in person, wild in her attire, and of an aspect such as awed me to behold. The scoffers fled; I kept my post and silently awaited the event, perceiving she address'd herself to speak—“Thou hast well done,” she cried, “honouring a fool, for, mark my words —A fool shall set Rome free.”—This said, she vanish'd from my sight. 1 Rom. I'll mock no more at Junius for one. 3 Rom. Nor I, but reverently accost his worship as oft as I encounter him. 4 Rom. This will bring fools in credit with the people. 1 Rom. And humble those that in their self-esteem are oracles of wisdom. 3 Rom. Look, look! what comes? 2 Rom. It is the Sybil; it is she herself!— Run, run, and save yourselves. How her eyes glare! she's terrible to look at. 1 Rom. Oh! that I were fool enough to be in her favour, and not so over-wise as to run away from her! [Exeunt omnes. The Sybil. Awake, ye torturers of the human heart! Start from your iron beds and come on earth, Ye furies, that with scorpions sting the soul! I, the Cumæan prophetess, the Sybil, Fate's awful harbinger, invoke your presence. The winds, which in my native caves are pent, Blow me from the Æolian shores to Rome O'er the curl'd waves, which my light feet ne'er touch'd. This is thy palace, Tarquin! hither late I brought the mystic volume, which thou, wretch, Three times repuls'd and scorn'd the friendly fates. The last sun rises on thy bloody house. Come night, and this proud palace shall be ashes. Did not my warning voice cry out—A fool, A fool shall set Rome free? Behold, he comes! Brutus, the fool predicted—He shall seize The dagger reeking from Lucretia's wound, And with that violated matron's blood Cement the fabric of immortal Rome. [Exit. Scene changes. A state Apartment in the Palace of Tarquin. Tullia, and Sextus Tarquinius. Tul. Away! thou'rt mad. Sex. I've privilege for that; I am in love. Tul. Yes, with thy kinsman's wife: Out on thee, wanton! Sex. With the wife of Jove, So she'll put by her cloud and take the form Of my Lucretia. Tul. Thy Lucretia! thine! Is Collatinus dead? Thus would'st thou sport With a chaste matron's fame? Sex. Is't nothing, then, To be the son of Tarquin, and a prince? To have powers, opportunities and means, With strong desires to push them on? Ye Gods, Give reason to mechanics! I'll be mad, Mad as my mother Tullia. Tul. Peace, reviler! When was I mad? Sex. When was you mad, good mother? When with ambition's phrenzy in your soul, And all Rome's empire in your view, you drove Your chariot wheels o'er your dead father's body Up to the shouting Forum. Tul. 'Twas the cause, The cause, my Sextus; and for this base clay, How differs it from the dull earth we tread on, When the life's gone? Sex. Nay, if you talk of cause, Mine is a cause to bring the Gods amongst us: Why, Jove, the king of Gods, hath left Olympus, And turn'd himself into a grazing beast For one not half so fair as my Lucretia. Tul. Into what beast, what reptile art thou chang'd? Why art thou not at Ardea? Why not foremost To mount the breach, and shew these sullen nobles, Who murmur at our greatness, that the race Of Tarquins reigns by valor as by might. [Trumpet. Hark! 'tis thy father's trumpet—welcome, soldier! Enter Vitellius. What tidings from our royal lord and husband? Vit. Health and a happy greeting—Your brave sons, Titus and Aruns, are return'd from Delphi. Tul. Where are the princes? Vit. In the camp at Ardea. The king determines with tomorrow's sun To mount the breach. You are expected, Sextus. Sex. Love hath his duties, sir, as well as war. Have our wise brothers brought their fool from Delphi? Vit. I left him with the pages in the court Hustling for drachmas. Tul. Whom? What fool? Vit. A man, Who, when he had a name, was Lucius Junius: A braver citizen Rome never boasted, And wise and learn'd withal; now chang'd, alas! A spectacle which humbles me to look on. Sex. Now, by the Gods! I much desire to see him. I want a fool, a ready antick thing, To run on errands, and to make me sport. Tul. What pleasure can such spectacles afford? Sex. Oh, there is much good moral in a fool; Besides, I dreamt of such a thing last night, And I will see him. Tul. If thou wilt, thou must. But is he harmless in his moody humours? Sex. Tame as my horse, which, tho' devoid of reason, Shall turn, shall stop, and at my angry bidding Shall kneel till I am throned on his back; And this shall Junius; the like instinct stirs Him and my horse—no more. Tul. Set him before us. [Exit Vitellius. He turn'd to folly on his brother's death: That brother Tarquin kill'd. If there's on earth A thing I dread, it is a fool. The Sybil, Whose mystic book at such a price we bought, Augur'd the race of Tarquins should be kings, Till a fool drove us hence, and set Rome free. Sex. A very foolish augury, good mother, For Sabine superstition only fit. But these are not good Numa's nursing days; The world is grown from infancy to manhood. Stand but our power till Junius pull it down, And it shall be immortal—Lo! he comes: This dread prediction of the frantic Sybil, This scourge of kings, this terror of the Tarquins, Rome's great deliverer. Vitellius brings in Lucius Junius Tul. Gods, is this the man, This Lucius Junius? 'Tis a goodly prison For beggary to dwell in; a rich tomb To harbour nought but emptiness. O Nature, That thou should'st be thus prodigal in matter, And yet forget a mind! Will he speak to us If we do question him? Vit. I think he will: Yet sometimes, when the moody fit doth take him, He will not speak for days; yea, rather starve Than utter nature's cravings: then anon He'll prattle shrewdly, with such witty folly As almost betters reason. Tul. Hark thee, fellow! How art thou call'd? L. Jun. A fool. Tul. Fool, for thy nature; Thou answer'st well, but I demand thy name. L. Jun. Nothing but fool. Tul. His faculties are brutish;— Brutus shall be thy name. L. Jun. Thanks to your grace! Sex. Dost like thy new name, gentle Brute? L. Jun. So well, Who will may take the fool: I care not who— Your Highness, an it like you. Sex. I the fool! Sirrah, good words, or I will have thee beaten. L. Jun. A fool thou wilt not beat—a brute thou dar'st not, For the dull ass will kick against his striker, If struck too harshly. Tul. Let me hear no more; There's mischief in his folly. Send him hence. Sex. Nay, let us hear him, for the fool's sententious. I'll search him with more questions. Hark thee, Brutus, Thou wast at Delphi with our princely brothers— Stand the brave pair in health? L. Jun. Praise to the Gods! They stood where others fell. Sex. What dost thou mean? Explain thyself. L. Jun. They bore away the prize From fourteen Grecian cities. Sex. Hah! what prize? L. Jun. The prize for drinking. Sex. Is it truth he speaks? Vit. I am his witness. 'Twas at Bacchus' feast Giv'n by Hipparchus the Athenian tyrant— Two Thericlean cups of mighty girth, That would have puzzled Bitias. Oh! the Greeks Drink deep, and dance more than our Salian priests. I saw their comic scoffers mount the car, With lees of wine besmear'd, in antick sport Mocking the crowd—T'was a rare mummery. Sex. Why then we might have kept our fool at home, For Greece is stock'd already. Tell us now What said the Pythia to our prodigy, The snake i'th' Capitol? L. Jun. An ugly reptile; She will'd us not to speak of it—The Gods Endure it not; Hercules was scar'd i'th' cradle, And young Apollo, since he fought the Python, Cannot abide to look upon a snake. Tul. Put you none other questions to Apollo? [To Vitellius. Vit. Your sons did ask who should be chief in Rome. Tul. Hah! what replied the oracle to that? Vit. With pains and strugglings the prophetic dame This destiny reported from her God: “Great and most glorious shall that Roman be, Who shall first greet his mother with a kiss!” Sex. Hail, mother! [Salutes the Queen. L. Jun. Woe for me, I have no mother— And yet I kiss'd her first. Tul. Thou kiss'd her? thou—? L. Jun. Yea, madam, for just then my foot did slip In the fresh blood of a new-slaughter'd victim, And falling I did kiss my mother—Earth. Tul. Oh, that the earth had swallow'd thee outright Till thou had'st kiss'd the center! I perceive The Gods are leagu'd with folly to destroy us. My very blood chills at my heart—Away! [Exit. Sex. Hark thee, thou Brutus, I in part suspect Thou ap'st this folly; if I find thee trifling, Or juggling with the Pythia for predictions, By all the Gods, I'll have thee flay'd, thy skin Strip'd into thongs to strangle thee withal, Dissembling varlet! [Seizes him. L. Jun. Take away your hands; They come too near my throat. [They struggle. Vit. My lord, forbear! Threat'ning a fool you do but wrong yourself. Sex. But that I love his son, the noble Titus, My dagger should have pierc'd his throat ere now, And sent him to his mother Earth for ever. He shall be watch'd.—Vitellius, follow me. [Exit. Vit. The Gods restore thee, Brutus, to thyself, And us to thee! Farewell! [Exit. L. Jun. A little longer, A little longer yet support me, patience! The day draws on: it presses to the birth— I see it in the forming womb of time— The embryo liberty. Hah! 'tis my son— Down, rebel nature, down! Titus enters. Tit. Welcome to Rome! Would I might welcome thee to reason too! Ah, woe is me, that ever I was born To call thee father; rather would I cross My direst foe on earth than meet this ruin. Yes, thou hast lips that utter, limbs that move, An outward form and fashion of a man, But where's the light o' the building, where's the soul, Which should inform those lips, direct those limbs, And lead thee back to the lost road of glory? L. Jun. Give me thy hand—nay, give it me— Tit. What would'st thou? Speak to thy son. L. Jun. I had a thing to say, But I have lost it. Let it pass—no matter. Tit. Look not upon me with those eyes, but speak; Utter thy cravings—Art at ease, poor creature? Who injures, who annoys thee? Tell thy friend. How can I serve thee? What dost lack? L. Jun. Preferment. Thou can'st do much at court. Tit. Ah! this is nothing. L. Jun. So much the fitter for a fool's petition, And a court promise. Tit. Oh, this trifling racks me. L. Jun. Lend me thine ear: I'll tell a secret to thee Worth a whole city's ransom. This it is; Nay ponder it and lock it in thy heart— There are more fools, my son, in this wise world Than the gods ever made. Tit. Say'st thou, my father? Expound this riddle. If thy mind doth harbour Aught that imports a son like me to know, Or knowing to atchieve; if there be aught Of grace or comfort to be done to thee, Or to thy weeping country, so it stand Within the order of things possible, How hard soe'er, declare it. L. Jun. Now, my son, Should the great Gods, who made me what thou seest, Repent, and in their vengeance cast upon me The burden of my senses back again— What would'st thou say? Tit. Oh, my lamented father, Would the kind Gods restore to thee thy reason— L. Jun. Then, Titus, then I should be mad with reason. Had I the sense to know myself a Roman, This hand should tear this heart from out my ribs, Ere it should own allegiance to a tyrant. If, therefore, thou dost love me, pray the Gods To keep me what I am—Where all are slaves, None but the fool is happy. Tit. We are Romans, Not slaves. L. Jun. Indeed! why, who art thou? Tit. Thy son. Dost thou not know me? L. Jun. You abuse my folly. I know thee not—Wert thou my son, ye Gods! Thou would'st tear off this sycophantic robe, Tuck up thy tunic, trim these curled locks To the short warrior cut, vault on thy steed; Then, scampering thro' the city, call to arms And shout for liberty— Tit. Defend me, Gods! [Starts. L. Jun. Hah! does it stagger thee? Tit. For liberty? Said'st thou for liberty?—It cannot be. L. Jun. Indeed! 'tis well—No more. Tit. What would my father? L. Jun. Begone, you trouble me. Tit. Nay, do not scorn me. L. Jun. Said I for liberty? I said it not: The awful word breath'd in a coward's ear Were sacrilege to utter. Hence, begone! Said I you were my son? 'Tis false: I'm foolish; My brain is weak and wanders; you abuse it. Tit. Ah, do not leave me; not in anger leave me! L. Jun. Anger? what's that? I am content with folly; Anger is madness, and above my aim. [Music. Hark! here is music for thee, food for love, And beauty to serve in the rich repast. Tarquinia comes. Go, worship the bright sun, And let poor Brutus wither in the shade. [Exit. Tit. Oh, truly said! bright as the golden sun Tarquinia's beauty beams, and I adore. Soft music. Tarquinia enters, preceded by Damsels bearing a Crown of gold, some with Censers, &amp;c. proper for the Ceremonials of a dedication to Fortune. What dedication or what holy service Doth the fair client of the Gods provide, Decking their shrines, and with these dulcet sounds Making the fane harmonious? Mighty Jove, Is there in thy celestial synod one, Who will not listen to Tarquinia's prayer? Tar. I go to Fortune's temple, there to kneel Before the blazing altar, and suspend Upon the votive shrine this golden crown. While incense fills the fane, and holy hymns Are chanted for my brothers' safe return, When the consenting Goddess smiles upon me, What shall I ask for Titus? Tit. Though the Goddess, In her blind bounty, should unthrone the world, To make me one vast empire, my ambition, If by thy love unblest, would slight the gift: Therefore of Fortune I have nought to ask, She hath no interest in Tarquinia's heart; Nature, not Fortune, must befriend me there. Tar. Well hast thou said: Chance rules not my affections; And, as I think thy heart like mine is true, Truth with its own reflection must agree, Honour to honour, love accord to love, And I to Titus. Tit. Oh, support me, Gods! Am I so blest above all human kind? Pitied, approv'd, belov'd? And may this heart, So long the victim of conflicting passions, At length repose in hope? Tar. Now hear and mark me— Impressions, which low minds are taught to hide, My soul, superior to reserve, avows; Fearing no insult I affect no art: Thy gentle manners, Titus, have endear'd thee, Although a subject Roman, to Tarquinia: My brother Sextus wears thee next his heart; The queen herself of all our courtly youth First in her favour holds the noble Titus: And though my royal father well may keep A jealous eye upon thy Junian race, A race unfriendly to the name of King, Yet thee he cherishes, with generous joy The monarch sees thy early virtue shoot, And with a parent's fondness rears its growth. Tit. Sweet fruits are sometimes couch'd in bitter rinds, So is my love within a hostile name; But neither name, nor nature, nor the voice Of my lost father, could he wake to reason, Not all the wrongs that tyranny could pile On my afflicted head, not all the praise That patriot gratitude could shower upon me, Can shake the faithful purpose of my heart, To sever it from love and my Tarquinia. Tar. Tis well! but ere you bind my faith, reflect! You say your father, should he wake to reason, Could not divide you from me; have you set His awful form in a prospective view? Can you resist the terrors of his voice, If in a tone oracular he warn you To shake off this soft passion? Who can say When this new inspiration may arouse him? Tit. The time I know not, but myself I know: This life may be extinguish'd, and the heart Must cease to beat, when death will have it so; But whilst I live, I live to thee alone. Tar. Approve that firmness in the shock of trials, And if my love can recompense thy virtue, Nor tortures, nor temptations, nor the wreck Of Rome and empire shall divide me from thee. To this I pledge my hand. Now to the temple. [Exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. The Capitol. The Equestrian Statue of Tarquin. Night. The Sybil. Now, in this dead and secret hour of night, Tarquin, on hellish violation bent, With silent tread steals to the innocent couch Of chaste Lucretia—Think not, ravisher, Indignant virtue shall survive pollution; By her own hand a Roman wife can fall. Now, Brutus, throw thy mask of folly off; Father of freedom, Rome's deliverer, rise; Put fire into the languid souls of men, Let loose your ministers of wrath amongst them, And mark this hideous night with ruin, Gods! Launch forth thy thunders, Capitolian Jove, Nor let that vaunting tyrant proudly ride In presence of thy temple. Strike him down, Ye lightnings! lay his trophies in the dust, And vindicate the majesty of justice. Hark! 'tis begun! flash, ye blue, forked fires! Loud-bursting thunders, roar! and tremble, Earth! [Exit. [Thunder and Lightning—during which the Statue of Tarquin is struck down to the Earth. Sextus Tarquinius and Vitellius. Vit. Was ever night so dreadful? Sex. None so blest: A proud reluctant beauty I have master'd, And the kind Gods—I thank them for the favour— With their own music crown my triumphs—Hark! [Thunder. Vit. What do I see? your father's statue fallen, Unhors'd and headless—Gods, avert the omen! The Capitol's great founder laid thus low By Jove's own thunder at the basest foot Of the proud pile he rear'd. Sex. Oh, father Tarquin, Put from all use religion amongst men; Down with the shrines of the unthankful Gods, Who, whilst we rear immortal fanes to them, Strike at our brittle trophies, nor allow us The frail memorial of a few short years. Vit. The elements are out of course, the heavens, As if in anger at the impenitent earth, On the Tarquinian mount rain'd blood. Sex. Away! Haunt me no more with omens—I'm secure: The proud, the virtuous, the untam'd Lucretia Is—let these conscious lightnings tell you what— The torches of accommodating night, That usher'd Jove to Semele—The moon, She too amidst the tumult, she at times Her maid'nish mantle put aside and gaz'd, Wishfully gaz'd—loud thunders roll'd the whilst, And echo'd heavenly plaudits to my joys. Vit. What hast thou done? declare! Sex. What have I done? What the sun does, that amorous reveller, When through the barrier of the frozen north Flaming he bursts: Spring and the laughing Hours Look on, and scatter roses in the lap Of marriageable Earth: he all the whilst, With glowing cheeks and kisses kindling fire, Rifles her sweets; the winter in her veins, The snows that on her unsmircht bosom lie, Melt at the quick'ning touch—So came the son Of Tarquin, burning fierce with hot desires, To chaste Lucretia's chamber— Vit. Oh, no more! Imagination cannot feign an act So horrible as this. I tell thee, Prince, If thou hast wrong'd this matron— Sex. If I've wrong'd her— If—be accurst henceforth all peevish scruples, All honourable folly!—Still I press'd, Still she refus'd, and ran through all the maze Of womanish evasion: Fir'd at length I threaten'd force; she rail'd, and in a tone Of high declamatory virtue call'd On heav'n and earth—I seiz'd her—frantic then, And louder than the Pythian priestess grown, She shriek'd out—Collatinus! Husband, help! A slave rush'd in—I sprung upon the caitiff, And drove my dagger through his clam'rous throat; Then turning to Lucretia, now half dead With terror, swore by all the gods at once, If she resisted, to the heart I'd stab her, Yoke her fair body to the dying slave, And then, with dreadful imprecations, after Rivet pollution to her name for ever. Vit. Oh deed, that whelms in ruin all your hopes, And gives your name to general execration Till time shall be no more: Take leave of peace, Bid honour, empire, Rome farewell for ever. —Hark, they are up! That yell of female slaves Bursts from Lucretia's house—She dies, she dies! And see the frantic husband!— Sex. Mad as Nessus. A single arm cannot oppose a host; Courage must yield to numbers—Give him way! [Exeunt. Collatinus, followed by Valerius and sundry others. Col. Friends, citizens of Rome, avenge my cause! Shake off inglorious sleep and seize your arms— Lucretia dies—she bleeds for Rome and you. Revenge, revenge! Val. My noble friend and kinsman, To you and to your cause Valerius vows Faith and affiance, till this direful act Shall be aton'd with judgment on th' offender; But let me counsel you to calm this passion; Loud cries avail us nothing. Col. Call my slaves, Provide me lights, and on a funeral bier Place her pale corpse, and so let all go forth. It cannot be but dead Lucretia's wound Shall plead most eloquently. Val. Be it so! Retire we for that purpose. Brutus appears. Col. Hah! what's that? L. Jun. A thing not worth a name. Val. 'Tis Lucius Junius: Pass on and stay him not—The hour is precious. [Exeunt Col. Val. and Servants. L. Jun. [contemplating the fallen Statue.] Fall'n idol, art thou laid thus low? Tis well. For this I thank you, Gods, that when you point Your shafts at human pride, it is not chance, 'Tis wisdom levels the commission'd blow. But I, a thing of no account, a slave— I to your forked lightnings bare my bosom In vain—for what's a slave, a dastard slave, A fool, a Brutus?—Hark! the storm rides on, The scolding winds drive through the clattering rain, And loudly screams the haggard witch of night. Why should this Collatinus quit his pillow And breast the thunder, when his soft-arm'd wife Might wrap him in Elysium? As I pass'd His doors but now, the south indeed blew high, And yet methought I heard a screaming yell Louder than all the storm. My thoughts grow wild, Engender with the scene, and pant for action. With your leave, Majesty, I'll sit beside you [Sits on the fallen Statue. And ruminate awhile—Oh! for a cause, A cause, just Gods!—Soft you, what stir is this? Valerius enters with Attendants. Val. By Numa's altar on the Cælian mount Dwells Caius Quintius the pontifical: Bear him this writing—Be not put aside With the stale shifts of lazy servitors, But do thine errand boldly—This to Tatius! This to my son-in-law Fabricius!—This, And above all, to the plebeian Decius; You'll find him at the house of Servius Cotta. In the old square west of Diana's grove By Rhea's fountain—Haste and tell my friends With Collatinus I expect their coming. Pray them to use their earliest speed. Away! [Exeunt attendants severally. L. Jun. Valerius—Hoa! Val. Who calls me? L. Jun. Brutus. Val. Go! Get thee to sleep. [Val. is departing. L. Jun. Valerius!— Val. Peace! I say, Thou foolish thing. Why dost thou call so loud? L. Jun. Because I would be heard. The time may come When thou shalt want a fool. Val. Prithee, begone! I have no time to hear thy prattle now. L. Jun. By Hercules, but you must hear. [Rises and advances. Val. You'll anger me. L. Jun. Waste not your noble anger on a fool. 'Twere a brave passion in a better cause. Val. Thy folly's cause enough. L. Jun. Rail not at folly. 'Tis a convenient cloak to hide a slave: Cast off this idle trick of anger from you; Dance to the music of your chains, as I do, A merry measure, laugh aloud and live, Not by your wits, that were to starve in Rome, Where the whole mass and congregation breathes Exquisite folly; each sense savours of it, Sight, taste, touch—all is fool—There's but one wise, And him the Gods have kill'd. Val. Kill'd whom? L. Jun. Behold! Oh! sight of pity—Majesty in ruins— Down on your knees; down to your kingly idol! Val. Let slaves and sycophants do that; not I. L. Jun. Wilt thou not kneel? Val. Begone; you trouble me. Valerius kneels not to the living Tarquin. L. Jun. Indeed! belike you wish him laid as low. Val. What if I do? L. Jun. Jove tells thee what to do— Strike!—Oh! the difference 'twixt Jove's wrath and thine! He at the crowned tyrant aims his shaft, Thou, mighty man, would'st frown a fool to silence, And spurn poor Brutus from thee. Val. What is this? Let me look nearer at thee. Is thy mind, That long lost jewel, found, and Lucius Junius Dear to my heart restor'd? or art thou Brutus, The scoff and jest of Rome, and this a fit Of intermittent reason? L. Jun. I am Brutus. Folly, be thou my Goddess! I am Brutus. If thou wilt use me, so! If not, farewell. Why dost thou pause? Look on me! I have limbs, Parts and proportions, shoulders strong to bear, And hands not slow to strike. What more than Brutus Could Lucius Junius do? Val. A cause like ours Asks both the strength of Brutus and the wisdom Of Lucius Junius. L. Jun. Tell not me of wisdom; If there be no part that a fool can act, A very foolish cause you have, good cousin. Hah! what slow-moving train of fiery shapes Visits the sleeping night? Is mine eye faithful, Or was it but the error of the time? And hark! a groan. Who and what are they? Val. Romans; Sad, mournful men, a family of woe; Thy friends and kinsmen once. Oh! Brutus, Brutus, Wert thou not soul-enslav'd, to all sense lost, More dull and sordid than the trodden earth, They have a tale to tell— [The Body of Lucretia is brought in upon a bier, attended by a numerous train bearing torches. Collatinus and other Romans. L. Jun. Stand, hoa! there; stand! Your burden of mortality set down, And answer yield me what dead thing you carry; Why at this hour come ye like spectres rather From fiery Phlegethon, than men and Romans? Speak; Brutus questions. Col. Noisy fool, avaunt! Thrust him aside, and pass. Val. Do him no wrong; But if thy griefs will let thee, pause awhile, And as thy friends and neighbours stand around thee, Kind-hearted Romans, whom thy loud lamentings, Spite of Jove's thunder, have this night unhous'd, Speak thy full sorrows! Col. Set the body down— Hard task and heavy, Romans, you impose; But since it is your pleasure to demand Why we your peaceful slumbers have invaded With cries above the storm—Simply 'tis this— Lucretia's dead—Bear with me for a while— [Weeps. L. Jun. Lucretia dead!— Col. There on that bier she sleeps Never again to wake; a beauteous flower, An innocent sweet rose, by the rude hand Of violence pluckt up—Oh Gods, oh Gods! She was the mark and model of the time, The mould in which each female face was form'd To look like her; she was the very shrine And sacristy of virtue: every knee, Whilst the Gods went unworshipt, bent to her: You all can witness, when that she went forth It was a holiday in Rome; old age Forgot its crutch, labour its task, all ran, And mothers turning to their daughters cried— There, there's Lucretia! Give me, ye blest Powers, A daughter like Lucretia, other boon I ask not, great Disposers!— L. Jun. Under favour, You straggle from the point at which we stick. Speak of the manner of her death, so please you; Leave numb'ring her perfections, which we knew, And knew as numberless, as if you strove To sum up grain by grain the countless sand On the surf-beaten shore—These things to tell us Argues no thrift of words. 1 Rom. Hear the fool, neighbours, How gravely he declaims— 2. Rom. And wisely too. Since he hath been at Delphi he speaks oracles. 3 Rom. Can this be Lucius Junius? 1 Rom. List again!— L. Jun. If Nature's hand hath cropt this early flower, Why do we grieve? for it was Nature's giving; And these deep sobs wrung from your bleeding heart She, your stern creditor, exacts as usance For her imparted loan. In one plain word, If she came fairly by her death, declare it, And so dismiss us to our beds at once From the night air—If not, proceed! Col. Oh friends, This night, this fatal night, from Ardea's walls Wing'd with fond speed I came. I found her, Romans, Not deckt as she was wont with nuptial smiles, Love's proper greeting, but transform'd with woe, A spectacle to start from: On her cheek, In place of rosy health, a turbid spot Of livid purple burn'd, in her sunk eyes Despair sate deep-engulph'd; rous'd at my cries She rais'd her head, and in a voice once sweet And tunable as young Apollo's lyre, Now hoarse and crackt with horror, bade me fly, Fly her polluted arms, which damned lust And brutal violation had defil'd. L. Jun. Hah! violation—Do we dwell in dens, Caverns and rocks, or amongst men in Rome? Lives he who wrong'd Lucretia? Speak; declare! 1 Rom. How steadily he questions! 2 Rom. Mark his eye, What a new form he wears! Answer to Brutus. Col. He lives who did the wrong. L. Jun. Oh shame, shame, shame! Romans, your courage sleeps. 'Tis not for nothing The Thunderer keeps this coil above your heads. Rise, snatch your arms, and you, much injur'd Roman, Give us to know the wretch, who dar'd defile This lifeless innocent. Col. Sextus Tarquinius. L. Jun. To the moon, folly? Vengeance, I embrace thee! Col. Hah! 'tis the inspiration of the Gods Speaks with thy organs. Can'st thou pardon, Brutus, What in the phrenzy of my grief I utter'd? L. Jun. I heeded not your phrenzy, nor your grief; Your cause, your cause is all. How died Lucretia? Col. By her own hand she died— L. Jun. Heroic matron! Col. Here is the dagger! On its bloody point Her life's last drops yet hang— L. Jun. Give me the dagger! Come, let me grasp it—Hail, thou sacred weapon, Virtue's deliverer, hail!—With this sharp steel, Empurpled with the purest blood on earth I cut your chains of slavery asunder. Hear, Romans, hear! did not the Sybil tell you, A fool should set Rome free? I am that fool; Brutus bids Rome be free. Col. Oh glorious Brutus, Thus let me press thee to my aching heart; Thus weeping on thy neck adore the Gods, Who have restor'd thee to avenge my wrongs, And in my wrongs my country. L. Jun. Peace; be still. Think not to melt me by this woman's wailing. No; one perpetual, one relentless frown Shall sear up this fixt brow, nor shall my heart E'er beat a peaceful measure, these rude locks Feel the disposer's touch, till I have buried This dagger in the lewd adulterer's heart. 1 Rom. Live, Brutus, valiant Brutus! Down with Tarquin! 2 Rom. We'll have no Tarquins. We will have a Brutus. 3 Rom. Let's to the Capitol, and shout for Brutus. L. Jun. I your king! Brutus your king! no, fellow citizens, If mad ambition in this guilty frame Had strung one kingly fibre, yea but one, By all the Gods, this dagger which I hold Should rip it out, tho' it entwin'd my heart. Val. Then I am with thee, noble, noble Brutus! Brutus the new restor'd, Brutus by Sybil, By Pythian prophetess foretold, shall lead us. L. Jun. Now take the body up! Bear it before us To Tarquin's palace; there we'll light our torches, And in the blazing conflagration rear A pile for these chaste relics, that shall send Her soul amongst the stars. On! Brutus leads you.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. A Court belonging to Tarquin's Palace. In the front a grand entrance, with folding Gates closed. Tullia with a Soldier. Tul. Where is the prefect, who commands our guards? Why don't you sally and disperse these rioters? Sold. Madam, the insurgents have repuls'd your guard; The western gate is forc'd; Flavius Corunna, The captain of the watch, is kill'd amongst them. Tul. Go, tell the carrion slaves if they persist I'll have their heads upon the gates this night; But if they'll come like sober citizens At noon, the prætor shall redress their wrongs. [Exit Soldier. Sextus enters. Tul. You have done well, sir! was it not enough To have your range through all our willing dames, But you must stain an honourable bed, And force our noblest matron? Sex. What's my crime? What have I done but what Rome's founder did? Our Sabine mothers made not half this coil, When by their lusty ravishers compell'd They peopled Rome by rapes. Tul. Lucretia's dead. Sex. The more fool she to die for such a toy. Tul. I tell thee, madman, thou hast torn by the roots Thy father's empire up. Where are thy senses? Dost thou not see; canst thou not hear? All Rome Is up in arms and thundering at our gates For just revenge. Sex. Revenge!—Our slaves our masters? Imperial Deities, revenge for slaves? Give them the torture; send them to the Furies, And let them learn revenge of those who teach it. Roman Soldier returns. Sold. All's lost! The palace is in flames; nor threats, Nor supplications move; the frantic throng Madder than bacchanalians toss their brands And spread the blaze around; they thirst for blood, Prince, for thy blood. Sex. My blood! By father Mars, They shall not buy a drop from out these veins, But at a price shall make them rue the purchase. [Draws his sword and rushes out, followed by the soldier. Tul. Gods! whither shall a frantic mother fly? Accursed seige of Ardea! Oh, one cohort, That I had here one cohort!—Tarquin, Tarquin, Where art thou? save thy wife, thy son, thy city! Ah! if amidst my legions I might fall, Death were not then inglorious; but to perish By the vile scum of Rome, hunted by dogs, Baited to death by brawling base mechanics— Shame insupportable! Titus enters. Tit. What is this rage? Whence are these rioters that storm your palace? Tul. Rome as one man revolts. Heav'n guard our lives! Why come you thus alone? Where is Tarquinia? Tit. Lo, where she stands immovable, aghast, List'ning the shock. I do but fly for succour. Where is the prince; where's Sextus? Tul. Where? Oh heavens! His madness hath undone us. Where is Sextus? Perhaps ev'n now the barbarous ruffians hurl him Alive into the flames, or piecemeal drag Along the streets his mangled trunk— Tit. No more Let me go forth. Vitellius meets and stops him. Vit. Turn, noble Roman, turn; Set not your life upon a desperate stake. Fly, seize the moment, wretched queen, and fly! Hark, they are at your gates! [A shout. Tul. Is my son slain? Vit. Furious he sprang upon the rabble throng, And hew'd his desperate passage; but the time Admits no further question—Save yourself! Tul. I was not born to fly. Let the tide enter; Let the vile rabble look upon the eyes Of majesty, and tremble. Vit. They are mad; Nay, more than mad: 'Tis phrenzy multiplied, When a fool leads them on. Tul. Hah! say what fool? Vit. Your new-nam'd fool, your Brutus. Tit. Death! my father— Tul. Oh Sybil! Oh my fate! Farewell to greatness! I've heard my doom. 'Tis past. Tit. Earth, earth inclose me! Where shall I hide my shame? Tul. Haste to Tarquinia. If there be yet a spark of nature left In thy stern father's bosom, call it forth, And keep destruction off— Tit. Or die defending. [Exit. Tul. It comes, it bursts upon us—See! we fall, [The Gate is burst open, and a magnificent edifice is discovered in flames. We sink. Rome's glory moulders into ashes; Round her gilt domes the serpent flames ascend And hiss her to perdition. Open, earth, Yawn to the pit of Acheron, and gulph Me and mankind at once. Come, snaky Furies, Lash us with fire from Pluto's hottest forge, And desolation swallow all things up. [Brutus is seen amidst the ruins with followers. Hah! art thou come? Do I behold thee, Brutus? Horrid prediction! Fool, that art my fate; [He advances. Vulture of Caucasus, that gnaw'st my heart! Barbarian, stop! what seek'st thou? L Jun. Justice; vengeance. Tul. Vengeance on whom? L Jun. Thee and thy guilty race. Lucretia's murder'd spirit will have vengeance: A husband frantic with his wrongs, a father Broken with grief and bending to his grave, These and a suffering nation cry for justice. Tul. Is this your justice? Look upon these flames. Have I deserv'd this? Hath your absent king? L. Jun. Tarquins, we cast you from us. Where is Sextus? Yield up your son and live. Tul. Thou fool unnatural! Senseless of soul, dost think I am that monster To yield my son to thee? No, not for worlds; Not for a thousand lives, had I so many; Nor could I if I would: Thank'd be the Gods, There lives of my brave race to crush thy treason, Audacious rebel! L. Jun. Seize the parricide! [They advance and surround her. Tul. Avaunt! I am your queen. L. Jun. They have no queen. You reign no longer. In those fires you see The funeral pile of royalty. Tul. Away! Give me a sword, and let me fall like Tullia. L. Jun. No, we reserve our swords for nobler uses Than to make war with women: To the Tarquins, To your adulterous son we leave that shame. Tul. If then 'twill better sate thy cruelty, Precipitate me quick into those flames, And with the wreck of empire mix my ashes. L. Jun. Nor that, nor other death expect from us. Take her to Rhæa's temple, take her hence, And lodge her with her ancestors. Tul. Ye Gods, My father's sepulchre—I'll not approach it. L. Jun. 'Twill furnish wholesome recollection. Hence! Tul. Not to that fatal place—send me not thither. L. Jun. 'Tis fixt. Vit. Will Brutus hear an ancient friend? L. Jun. Brutus will hear; but Brutus owns no friend, That leagues not with him in the cause of justice. Tul. Choose the most loathsome dungeon—there confine me, Or give me death instead. My heart recoils Against that temple. L. Jun. There, and only there, By your dead father's tomb, you must abide The judgment of the state. Tul. Then by the Gods, Whom for the last time I invoke, whose shrines I've incens'd o'er and o'er, though now forsaken, Now at my utmost need—Nor earth, nor air, Nor the wide sea from its unbounded stores, Shall minister support; if no means else Of ready death present themselves, I'll starve; No particle of food shall pass these lips, Till, in the void of nature, hungry madness With blank oblivion ent'ring shall confound And cancel all perception—Now lead on! [Exeunt Tul. and Vit. with guards. Valerius to Brutus. L. Jun. Hail to my friend! smile not these ruins on thee? Val. Yes, Brutus; yet it is not in these fires, The yells of dying wretches, nor the crash Of falling palaces Valerius joys; It is the day-spring of reviving freedom, The dawn of brighter hopes that chears my bosom, And makes these terrors pass away like clouds Before the uprising sun. L. Jun. For me, Valerius, Come danger in what hideous shape it may, Come death, I reck not, so I may bequeath To my son's sons deliverance and redemption From the dire race of Tarquin. We have now Far overleapt discretion, and must swim To the glad shore, where beck'ning fortune stands, Or perish in the gulph wherein we've plung'd. Val. Then let us on together, noble Brutus, And breast the torrent. Our assembled friends With Tarquin's spoils have rear'd a mighty pile For dead Lucretia. They expect our coming. L. Jun. Proceed: I'll follow thee. [Exit Val. Titus meets Brutus as he is going off. Tit. Turn, Oh my father, And look upon thy son. L. Jun. What wouldst thou? speak! Tit. Yes, if amidst these horrors I can find Courage to give my agonies a voice. L. Jun. No more of this—be brief and to the point. Tit. If thou hast reason, oh, have mercy also! But if in madness thou hast done this deed— L. Jun. I am not mad but as the lion is, When he breaks down the toils, that tyrant craft Hath spread to catch him. Think not we will suffer These monsters to profane the air of heaven With their unholy breath. Is there a heart Within one Roman bosom does not pant With ardour to avenge Lucretia's death? Tit. Justice demands atonement for the deed; But is this justice? L. Jun. At the birth of freedom Frantic and wild are the first struggling throes, That cast the mighty embryo on the world: Cradled in blood the herculean infant lies, Till with maturer years he casts the slough And film of imperfection; Peace and justice And comely order welcome his approach, And loves and graces triumph in his train. Tit. What mighty project labours in thy bosom? Horror pervades my soul. L. Jun. The time is short, And other calls than nature's must be serv'd. There is some lurking passion at thy heart, Something which sets thy faculties at variance, And leaves but half a soul for Rome and me. Art thou my son? Tit. Be witness for me, nature, I am; but, till the Gods restor'd thy reason, I was an orphan with a living father— L. Jun. Go on; confess thy weakness and dismiss it. Tit. 'Twas in the sleep of my dear father's reason, When Tarquin's freedman in a saucy mood Vented vile jests at thy unhappy weakness, Stung to the quick, I snatch'd a weapon up And fell'd him to my foot. L. Jun. Why, 'twas well done. The knave was saucy and you slew him—On! Tit. 'Twas on this very spot Tarquinia stood, And when her wrathful father had denounc'd Immediate death on this my filial act, She, with the tongue of interceding pity, And tears that stream'd in concert with her suit, Implor'd, prevail'd, and gave me life—and love. L. Jun. 'Tis well! behold, I give her life for life: Rome may be free altho' Tarquinia lives. This I concede; but more if thou attemptest, If, in dishonour of my great design, Mine and thy fame thou damn'st at this great hour With any boyish weakness—if thou waverest— By all the Gods!—Nay, if thou dost not take Her image, tho' with smiling Cupids deck'd, And pluck it from thy heart, there to receive Rome and her glories in without a rival, Thou art no son of mine, thou art no Roman— Nay, mark me, Titus!—thou art lost—thou'rt dead. [Exit. Tit. Where is that power in nature, that can pluck Her image from my bosom? Can the voice Of a descended God command it from me? It cannot be: these horrors that surround me, This awful interdiction, the dread frown Of a stern father, now transform'd from less To more than man, all, all in vain conspire To tear away her chains; a look, a word, The gentlest breath, that whispers to my ear The music of her voice, enslaves my sense, And charms down all resistance. Hah! she comes, And sorrowing comes—Had I not love enough Without the aid of pity to augment it? Fatally sad she looks— Tarquinia enters. Tarquinia, speak! Speak, thou too beauteous mourner! Tar. I attend To know if this sad crisis will decide For truth or treason; if the son of Brutus Will take me to his pity and protection, Or stab with perfidy the heart that loves him. Tit. Cruel suspicion! Do my eyes inspire Thoughts of such horror? beam they not upon thee Unutterable fondness? Oh! thou dear one, I live but to preserve thee. Tar. To what end Am I preserv'd? I will not breathe the air That rank rebellion taints, nor live one hour Longer than Tarquin's daughter ought to live. Tit. Banish these gloomy thoughts: dear to my soul Your honour as your person. You are free: I have my father's sanction for your safety. Tar. Insolent sanction! Thou should'st not have ask'd My life of Brutus. Tit. Not have ask'd thy life? Say rather I should not have been his son: But 'twas the will of nature, and has made me So hateful to thee, thou would'st sooner die Than live in safety, at my suit preserv'd. Tar. I scorn a life that is preserv'd by Brutus; I scorn to outlive parents, brothers, friends, And stand like some lone column in a desart, Pointing where late a princely city rose. No; I'll not live a solitary relict, A walking pageant to swell out the train Of some proud demagogue, whom I must thank For charitable air; I'll die with those Whom this dire night hath murder'd. Tit. Who are murder'd? Whom hath the sword of Brutus slain? Not one Of all thy kindred— Tar. Say'st thou? Lives my mother? Tit. She lives—and Sextus, even he escapes The storm, which he has rais'd, and flies to Ardea. Tar. Speed him, ye winds, with eagle swiftness thither! And may those thunders, that now shake the walls Of tottering Ardea, like a whirlwind burst On this devoted city, whelm its towers, And crush the traitorous hive beneath their ruins. Now, Titus, where is now thy promis'd faith? Did'st thou not swear no dangers should divide us? Tit. I did; and, constant to my oath, behold me Thy faithful guardian in this night of terrors. Tar. Be still my guardian; snatch me from these terrors, Bear me to Ardea, be the friend of nature, And give the rescued daughter to the arms Of her protecting parent; thus you gain The praise of men, the blessing of the Gods, And all that honour, all that love can grant. Valerius enters. Val. Hah! art thou found? Hear me, thou son of Brutus! I come to thee at thy great father's bidding— Hear and obey! He wills thee to repair To Mars's fane, where Rome's chief citizens Assemble, to elect the public Guardians Of peace and justice. How shall I report? Tit. Say, when the son of Brutus hath obey'd The calls of mercy, he'll attend on those Of justice and his father. Val. Hah! no more? Tit. Valerius, I well know, would not exact From his own son other reply than this. Val. Beware! remember as a friend I've warn'd you. [Exit. Tit. Oh my distracted heart! where shall I turn me? Tar. By all the guardian deities, whose shrines I've incens'd daily for thy sake, my Titus; By all the demons, who prepare the heart To rush upon the self-destroying stroke, The same dire moment, which gives thee to Brutus, Gives me to death. Tit. Oh thought of horror! Gods, Can ye inflict distress deeper than mine? Tar. Why do you waver? Cast away this weakness; Be glorious in your cruelty, and leave me. Lo! I am arm'd—Farewell!—How I have lov'd you My death shall witness, how you have deceiv'd me Let your own conscience tell. Now to your father! Now go and mingle with those murderers; Go, teach those fiends what perjury can do, And shew your hands bath'd in Tarquinia's blood; The filial deed shall welcome you to Brutus, And fill his gloomy soul with savage joy. Tit. Take, take me hence for ever! Let me lose In these dear arms the very name of son, All claims of nature, every sense but love. Tar. The Gods that guard the majesty of Rome, And that sweet Power, whose influence turns thy heart To pity and compliance, shall reward And bless thee for the deed. Tit. Can he be blest On whom a father's direful curse shall fall?— Tar. A madman's imprecation is no curse. Tit. Can he have peaceful dreams, whose very blood Against the fountain of his life rebels? Oh! I have heard a voice, I have beheld A countenance so awfully severe, 'Twill never from my memory. Tar. Be a man! Tit. Yes, whilst thy love upholds me I can stand Against the world's contempt; remember only For whose dear sake I am undone; remember My heart was honour's once. Tar. And shall be ever. Come, I will shew thee where bright honour grows, Where thou shalt pluck it from the topmost branch, And wear it in its freshest fairest bloom. [Exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT IV. A Street in Rome with the Temple of Mars in view. The Sybil. Hail, Rome! arise, thou mistress of the world! From her Cumean cavern once again The Sybil hails thee with prophetic voice. Tarquin, the seventh and the last of kings, Pass off, begone! The fool, the fool expels thee. Thus, thus I cast a spell into the air— Lo! the charm works; the sun himself is sick, And dimly glimmers through a lurid cloud. The Fates will have more blood. Hide, hide thine eyes, Oh mother Nature; weep thyself to water, Ere the terrific vision bursts upon thee, And the stern father dooms his son to death— Oh justice, horrible to human feelings!— And now behold! the father falls—he dies— Brutus himself expires—Th' adulterous prince And the fierce consul meet, they fight, they fall— See where they lie! their broken arteries spout, And the parcht earth drinks up their mingling blood. And you, ye senators in Mars's fane, First-born of freedom, here assembled, hail! From farthest Ganges to the western isles Your's is the world. Prepare your necks, ye nations, Stoop to the yoke—The Sybil's word is fate. [Exit. Valerius with a Centurion—Lucretius meets him. Lucre. Hail, venerable Roman! are the people Still sitting in assembly? Val. They have chosen A senate of the prime nobility, And nominated Consuls for the year Great Brutus and thy injur'd son-in-law, With every office, form and ordination, That constitute a state for peace or war. Lucre. Prais'd be the Gods! sorrowing I have inurn'd Lucretia's chaste remains, and from her ashes Now see the phœnix liberty arise. What more hath life to give? Val. Live for thy country. Within this temple Rome's first senate meets: There, on the awful stage where wisdom acts, Reverend with years, Lucretius will complete And round the sacred circle. Lucre. Ah, Valerius, What can a sorrow-broken heart conceive Worthy of Rome and Brutus? Yet I'll enter. Wilt thou not lead the way? Val. Some business waits me, Which being dispatch'd I'll follow— [Exit Lucre. Now, Centurion, Are all things well? Cent. All things are well. Last night It was my fortune on the watch to encounter, And with some loss to take an armed band Of citizens, revolting to the army Of your dethroned tyrant. Val. Call forth Brutus, Call forth the Consul, Lictors! [Lictors enter the temple. 'Tis to Brutus, His Country's father, you must make report. Oh shame! that any should be found so lost To glory. Where have you bestow'd your prisoners? But hark! the Consul comes—To him your answer Will be address'd more fitly. Brutus comes forth preceded by his Lictors bearing the fasces. Health to Brutus! Shame and confusion to the foes of Rome! Now without preface, soldier, to your business. Cent. As I kept watch before the Latian gate, Ere break of day, an armed company Burst on a sudden through the barrier guard, Pushing their course for Ardea. Straight alarm'd I wheel'd my cohort round and charg'd them home: Sharp was the conflict for a time and doubtful, Till, on the seizure of Tarquinia's person, A young patrician— L. Jun. Hah! patrician? Cent. Such His dress bespoke him, though to me unknown. L. Jun. Proceed!—What more? Cent. The lady being taken, This youth, the life and leader of the band, His sword high waving in the act to strike, Dropt his uplifted weapon, and at once Yielded himself my pris'ner—Oh Valerius, What is amiss that thus the Consul changes? L. Jun. Why do you pause? Go on! Cent. Their leader seiz'd, The rest surrender'd. Him a settled gloom Possesses wholly, nor as I believe Hath a word pass'd his lips, to all my questions Still obstinately shut. L. Jun. Set him before me. [Exit Centurion. Val. Oh! my brave friend, horror invades my heart. L. Jun. Peace, peace! contain thyself. Val. I know thy soul A compound of all excellence, and pray The mighty Gods to put thee to no trial Beyond a mortal bearing. L. Jun. No, they will not— Nay, be secure they cannot. Prithee, friend, Look out, and if the worst that can befal me Be verified, turn back and give some sign What thou hast seen—Thou canst excuse this weakness, Being thyself a father. [Val. gives the sign. Hah! enough: I understand thee—Since it must be so, Do your great pleasure, Gods! Now, now it comes! [Titus and Tarquinia are brought in guarded. Tit. My father! Give me present death, ye Powers! Cent. What have I done? Art thou the son of Brutus? Tit. No, Brutus scorns to father such a son. Oh! venerable judge, wilt thou not speak? Turn not away; hither direct thine eyes, And look upon this sorrow-smitten form, Then to thine own great heart remit my plea, And doom as nature dictates. Val. Peace, you'll anger him— Be silent and await! Oh suffering mercy, Plead in a father's heart and speak for nature! Tar. Oh, earth, earth, earth! if in thy boundless stores, Parent of all things living, thou hast treasur'd One healing drop of mercy, on the heart Of this relentless father let it fall, And melt the rock within him. Turn him, Gods, Turn him to what yourselves delight in most, To pity, to forgiveness. Ye blest stars, Whom grateful mortals rais'd to the bright spheres In which ye shine, and gave you names in Heaven, Mildly benignant as ye are, ye will not Withhold your influence: And thou, changeful moon, Thou, that can'st sway our senses at thy will, Make wisdom foolish, and make folly wise, Oh, virgin Goddess, as thou hast restor'd The long-lost mind of Brutus, touch it now With mercy mild as thine own silver beams! [Brutus turns away from his son, waves his hand to the Centurion as a signal to remove him to a further distance, and then addresses himself to Valerius. L. Jun. Valerius!— Val. What would'st thou, noble Roman? L. Jun. 'Tis said thou hast pull'd down thine house, Valerius, The stately pile that with such cost was rear'd. Val. I have, but what doth Brutus thence infer? L. Jun. It was a goodly structure: I remember How fondly you survey'd its rising grandeur, With what a fatherly delight you summon'd Each grace and ornament, that might enrich The child of your creation, till it swell'd To an imperial size, and overpeer'd The petty citizens, that humbly dwelt Under its lofty walls in huts and hovels, Like emmets at the foot of tow'ring Ætna: Then, noble Roman, then with patriot zeal, Dear as it was and valued, you condemn'd, You levell'd the proud pile; and in return Was by your grateful countrymen sirnam'd. And shall to all posterity descend— Poplicola. Val. Yes, Brutus, I conceive The awful aim and drift of thy discourse, But I conjure thee to reflect— L. Jun. Away! Doth no one but Valerius love his country Dearer than house, or property, or children? Come to the Senate, there thou'lt see if Brutus Earn not a name as glorious as Poplicola. Soldier, meanwhile guard faithfully your pris'ner; The Senate will determine on his fate. [Going. Tar. Stop, turn and hear the daughter of your king! I speak for justice—mercy thou hast none. If it be treason in a night like this, When Tarquin's palace blazes to the skies, And you, the masters and the lords of Rome, Bid murder scour the streets—if then to fly, When you have fir'd the roof upon the heads Of undefended women, be a crime To your new state and self-created Senate, I am your criminal; single in guilt, Singly I claim your judgment— L. Jun. You have said: Here let your plea conclude. Tar. For him—your son— By tears, entreaties, by the threats of death, With dagger drawn and pointed at my heart, By the resistless energy of love, By gratitude's strong call, I drew him off From your stern summons to defend and save A helpless fugitive—And doth there live, Who calls himself a man, that had done less For a fond woman? I preserv'd his life, Who shall condemn him for protecting mine? L. Jun. We try the crime; the motive Heav'n will judge. My honour he hath stabb'd—I pardon that. He hath done more, he hath betray'd his country— That is a crime which every honest heart, That beats for freedom, every Roman feels, And the full stream of justice must have way. Tar. Because thy soul was never sway'd by love Can'st thou not credit what his bosom felt? L. Jun. I can believe that beauty such as thine May spread a thousand fascinating snares To lure the wavering and confound the weak; But what is honour, which a sigh can shake? What is his virtue, whom a tear can melt? Truth, valour, justice, constancy of soul— These are the attributes of manly natures: Be woman e'er so beauteous, man was made For nobler uses than to be her slave. Tar. A glorious cause no doubt you take in hand, And most auspiciously your freedom dawns, Hard, unrelenting man! Are these the fruits Of filial piety, and hath thy son Wearied the Gods with prayers, till they restor'd A mind, and gave thee reason? Would to Heaven, They'd giv'n thee mercy too! 'twould more become thee Than these new ensigns, Brutus; more than all Thy lictors, haughty Consul, or thy robes Dipt in the blood—oh horror!—of a son— L. Jun. No more—By all the Gods, I'll hear no more. Tit. A word for pity's sake—Before thy feet, Humbled in soul, thy son and prisoner kneels. Love is my plea; a father is my judge; Nature my advocate—I can no more: If these will not appease a parent's heart, Strike thro' them all, and lodge your vengeance here. L. Jun. Break off! I will not, cannot hear thee further. The affliction nature hath impos'd on Brutus, Brutus will suffer as he may—Enough That we enlarge Tarquinia. Go, be free! But go from Rome, go to your father's court; There your bright eyes may play their harmless fires Around the flattering circle, here your beauty With mortal anguish wrings the parent's heart, And death and ruin ambush in your smiles. Lictors, secure your prisoner; point your axes, And follow to the temple: For the lady, Be it your care, Centurion, to provide Safe conduct out of Rome.—Now to the Senate. [Exit. Val. Ill-fated youth, I have a father's heart Within this breast, that melts at your contrition, And fain would be your advocate with Brutus, Yet trembles at the rigour of his justice. Be patient, and in nature place your hope. [Exit. Cent. Come, lady, you must part. Tar. Part! must we part? You shall not tear him from me; I will die Embracing the sad ruin I have made. Cent. You've heard the Consul. Tar. Thou hast heard the King, Fought for him whilst he led you on to conquest. Thou art a soldier, and should'st spurn an office, Which malefactors, tho' condemn'd for murder, Would rather die by torture than perform. Tit. Hear, I conjure thee, hear! If thou dost wish That I should meet the peril of my fate With any manly firmness, or dost cherish A hope, how faint soe'er, that I should 'scape it, By that hope I conjure thee to accord To Brutus, and accept his promis'd safeguard. Your words, your looks, your beauty feeds his wrath; In that fair face he reads my guilty love, And pity flies his heart; let passion pause; Leave me to solitude, to silence leave me; Then nature's gentlest whispers may be heard. Tar. Say'st thou? Conduct me to the dreariest waste That ever melancholy madness trod, And let my swelling heart in silence burst; Plunge me in darkneis, shroud this fatal form In everlasting night, I am content. Lo! I obey—This is the test of love; This is the sacrifice—I part to save thee. Tit. See, I am warn'd—farewell, my life's last joy! When my eyes lose thy image, they may look On death without dismay. To those blest Powers, Who gave thee every virtue, every grace, That can ensure perfection, I commit thee. [Exit with Lictors. Tar. 'Tis past! Now, misery, I am all thine own. [Exit with Centurion. Scene changes. The Temple of Rhæa with the tomb of Servius Tullus, late King of Rome. Lamps burning. Priestess of Rhæa, Virgins of the Temple. Priest. Daughters of Rhæa; since the lords of Rome Have to your holy hands consign'd the charge Of their now captive queen, inform your priestess How your sad prisoner abides her durance. Is her great soul yet humbled, or indignant Doth it still breathe defiance and contempt? 1 Virg. Sullen and silent she resolves on death: She will not taste of nourishment. Priest. Alas!— I cannot doubt but you have urg'd her to it. 1 Virg. Much, but to none effect—Lo! here are viands— [Pointing to a table. All means have been attempted—See, she comes! Tullia enters. Tul. When the breath stops, the body shall have peace; But who can tell me where the soul shall go? Which of you, virgins, can resolve that question? Priest. I pray you, royal lady, be entreated To take some nourishment. Tul. I tell you no. The wants of nature are below my thoughts: I am myself a spirit; I live on air, And meditation is my proper diet. Priest. Think what a train of weary hours have pass'd Since you had taste of food. Tul. 'Tis well! so many Being gone by, the fewer are to come. Priest. If it were only in regard of us, Not of yourself, consent. Tul. Kind-hearted souls! Carry your trenchers to the hungry cells Of starving debtors, so your charity, Wasted on me, shall cheer a thankful heart. Priest. How can you live to meet your royal husband, To fold your children in your arms again, If you resist support? Tul. Hah! well remember'd— What news from Ardea? Will he march for Rome? Hark! do you hear his trumpet? Is he coming? Uncover!—This is hope, and worth the feeding— What have you done? Oh, this is luxury. Methinks you take me for a queen, when thus You tempt my palate. Who serv'd in these dainties? Priest. Your willing ministers, the sisterhood Of your own Goddess Rhæa. Tul. Why 'tis well. But doth your king know of this bounty, virgins? Priest. What king? We comprehend you not. Tul. What king? Brutus, the king of Rome. Knows he of this? Priest. What shall we say? Yes, Brutus knows of this. Tul. And would he I should eat? Priest. He would. Tul. Amazement! Doth he not wish my death? Priest. By these means never: He wills you to support life's fainting frame With all due nourishment. Tul. Merciful villain! Detested be the nourishment he gives! All food he touches turn to poison, Gods, Though it lay waste creation. Subtle traitor! Yes, he would have me live to page his triumphs: I know the utmost of his mercy—No; I will not live; I will not page his triumphs; I'll starve, I'll die the death—Bear off your viands; I will not taste, though immortality Were grafted to each atom—Take them hence! Priest. If such be your resolve, let the crime fall On your own head! We are free. Tul. Hark, what is that? Heard you that groan? Priest. It is your fancy's coinage; We heard no groan. Tul. Again!—'Tis deep and hollow: It issues from the vault—Set the door open! Unbar it, I command you. By the Gods, The voice is more than human which I hear— Open, I say! Priest. It is your father's tomb. Tul. My father! righteous Gods, I kill'd my father, And these deep groans are his. Daughters of Rhæa, Have you not heard the parricidal act? Was it not told you how I drove my steeds Spangled with blood across my father's trunk, Dragging his breathing carcass at my wheels? Yes, I did this—I was the wretch who did it; I did not think of heaven and heavenly justice, Ambition was my God—Now, now it comes— Horrible retribution! Priest. Wretched daughter, If thou hast done this deed, prepare thy spirit By wholesome meditation for atonement, And let no passion interrupt the task Of penitence and prayer. Tul. I'll pray no more. There is no mercy in the skies for murder, Therefore no praying, none; 'tis all in vain: I have a plea for my impenitence— Madness: I tell thee, woman, I am mad; These groans have made me mad; all the night through They howl'd distraction to my sleepless brain. You've shut me up with Furies to torment me, And starv'd me into madness. I am famish'd; Hunger hath made me furious—Oh, some food— For charity some food! Priest. Behold 'tis here! 'Tis at your lips, and courts you to receive it. Tul. 'Tis false! it is no food; 'tis all a cheat Invented to torment me; should I taste Or touch it only, instantly your spirits Would howl and hiss me into worse perdition Than hell hath yet a name for—I'll go forth— Ah no, I'm giddy—Sick to death and giddy— Sleep, sleep, relieve me! Lead me to the couch. [They lead her to a Couch on which she reclines. Priest. A sleep which is death's prelude falls upon her; Or is it death itself? She breathes. How awful Is that still pause the ling'ring spirit makes Before it wings its flight! Mark, virgins, mark! Now to the altar of your Goddess Rhæa, And there with expiatory hymns and prayers Invoke a requiem to her parting soul. [Exeunt Priestess and Virgins. Solemn Music at a distance. When it ceases, the Sybil appears. Syb. Sleep'st thou, detested parricide? Sleep on! Though wasted Nature slumbers, conscience wakes, And the grim Furies haunt thy soul with dreams, Worse than thy waking terrors. See, she shakes! Death's pangs convulse her heart. Yet, ere she die, By dread commission from the avenging Fates I must command this stony vault to open, And give its miserable relics up. Come forth, thou phantom of a murder'd king, And look upon thy daughter!—Hah! 'tis here! [Ghost of Servius Tullus comes forth. Wake, impious daughter, and behold thy father! [Tullia starts out of sleep. Tul. Strike me, great Gods, oh, strike me with your bolts! What do I see?—'Tis he; it is my Father! Do I yet live?—Am I awake?—Begone! Wilt thou not hence? Take off thine eyes; they kill me. Nay, then 'tis done—Earth, earth, receive and hide me. [She falls to the ground and expires. Syb. Hence, shadowy terror, hence! The fates dismiss thee. Death strikes his victim, and my task concludes. [Curtain falls.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT V. The interior of the temple of Mars. Brutus seated in the Consular chair. Titus is brought in by the Lictors with their axes turn'd edge-ways towards him: At a signal from Brutus they withdraw. Titus approaches his father. L. Jun. Prisoner, approach, we now forego the names Of son and father, sad exchange! to meet As criminal and judge. Nay, do not kneel! Man doth not owe to man such low submission. Tit. But guilt to virtue doth; repentance owes Prostration to the Gods, and thou, oh Brutus, Art like a God on earth. Not to Rome's Consul, But Rome's deliverer, bend I the knee. L. Jun. Stand up and hear me. 'Tis a dread commission I now must open—Traitors, who conspire Against mature societies, may urge Their acts as bold and daring; and, tho' villains, Yet are they manly villains—But to stab The cradled innocent as thou hast done, To strike thy country in the mother-pangs Of struggling child-birth, and direct thy dagger To freedom's infant throat, is deed so black, That my foil'd tongue refuses it a name. Tit. Let me supply it—Death. L. Jun. Oh Gods, oh Gods! Tit. Nay, do not shrink; I am not yet so far Apostate from my great original, As to survive disgrace. L. Jun. Thou hast pronounc'd The fatal word that Justice must decree— Hard word, and painful for a father's tongue— Thou art my son. Tit. No, I have lost the name. I was thy son, and had my father deem'd me Worthy to share his thoughts, had I but known The secret of his heart, I had devoted My soul to honour and escap'd this ruin. L. Jun. Ah, Titus, 'twas because I mark'd your weakness; You were a courtly, young, ambitious lover, The friend of Sextus, and I fear'd to trust you. Tit. Wisely you acted for the general good: Had I deceiv'd you Rome had lost a father, Now losing me she has little to lament. L. Jun. Justice demands that I should wield her sword With an impartial hand: whom can I strike, If I should spare my son? But when I make This sacrifice to justice, it is not That Brutus feels less than a father feels, But that he does all that a Roman should. And now 'tis past—Go— Tit. Whither? L. Jun. Must I add To public execution? Tit. Say not that: Shall thy son suffer like a common felon? L. Jun. How else do traitors suffer? Tit. Shameful fate! My head struck off, and my disjointed limbs— L. Jun. Stop!—What hast thou to urge? If thou hast aught, Rigour admits that I should hear the plea. Speak! Tit. I had once a hope— L. Jun. What was thy hope? Tit. That I might fall as noble Romans fall, By my own sword. L. Jun. Let me reflect!—Away! It is the trick and sophistry of mercy; It mocks at justice and defrauds the law. Tit. Nor law nor justice should have more than life, And with the body kill the spirit too. I have a weapon here, a bosom friend, That could have marshall'd me a secret road, Without a father's privilege, to death; But I resolv'd the wond'ring world should see The unshaken firmness of a patriot's soul: And, careful of thy fame, reserv'd the blow, Till at thy feet I might receive my doom, And, dying, float them with my filial blood. L. Jun. Stop thy rash hand! Give me some pause for thought! Put back thy weapon—Oh! that I could find Some course to satisfy my country's honour, And save thy forfeit life!—but 'twill not be. Yet I will grant thy pray'r—A shameful death Thou shalt not suffer. In the public square Before the people—Oh support me, Gods!— Give me a voice to speak!—Thou must ascend The scaffold there prepar'd; then in the view Of Rome's appeased citizens, then, Titus— Strike at thy heart. Tit. Upon my knees I thank thee! Thus let me press thy venerable hand, And print my life's last gratitude upon it! L. Jun. Arise, arise! You come too near my heart. Tit. What signal shall there be when I may strike? L. Jun. When I come forth, and from the temple porch Hold up my hand, then—need I add the rest? Remember! Tit. Righteously. L. Jun. Farewell for ever! Lictors, attend! conduct your prisoner forth; And, whilst you march with slow and solemn step, Let the funereal minstrels, as they are wont, Sound their sad prelude to the mournful act. [Titus is carried out by the Lictors; a dead march, which gradually dies away as it becomes more distant. Brutus remains seated in a melancholy posture on his tribunal. L. Jun. [rising.] How heavily these melancholy sounds Ring out the knell of death; and now they cease— Thy pilgrimage, poor youth, is at an end: A few sad steps have brought thee to the brink Of that tremendous precipice, whose depth No thought of man can fathom. Now thou stand'st Upon thy grave with sorrow-smitten eye, And dagger underneath thy mantle grasp'd, Watching my signal—Now vindictive justice Bids me go forth—This silence is my summons. Hard, hard condition mine! Limbs, bear me up Against this shock of nature, to support The dreadful office, which the Gods impose On me their trembling minister, whose heart They should have cas'd in marble; and made dead To human feelings, ere they bade me meet A spectacle, that harrows up the soul With terror and dismay—There lies the road That I must take—One effort, and 'tis past. [Exit. [Whilst Brutus is off the Stage, a deep and distant groan is heard, and he re-enters the temple in great agitation. Brutus re-enters. Oh agonizing sight!—The deed is done: Justice is satisfied; my son expires. Valerius to Brutus. Val. My friend, where art thou? Let my arms enfold And comfort thy brave heart; let me partake Thy manly sorrows: Brutus is not childless; Each grateful Roman henceforth is thy son. L. Jun. Come, gallant friend, it were not fit you knew What passes here; for you and I must act Like men in whom the common herd can spy No gust nor flaw of passion, to unstring The nerves that now should brace them to the pitch: This is no time for wailing and lamenting; Tarquin will march for Rome—for, do him right, The man is no mean soldier. Val. We must shape Our measures to like promptitude with his: Great enterprizes only are achiev'd By great and noble darings. We must face The peril of the attempt, as men resolv'd To conquer or to die. L. Jun. Ah my brave friend, Were life as stale and wearisome to all As 'tis to Brutus, we should entertain War as a mistress; where the battle burns There we should throng, there we should choak their ranks With piles of slain and torrents of our blood, And welcome victory in the arms of death. Collatinus the Consul, with Senators and others, who support Titus. Col. Consul, behold thy son! a few short moments Are left of life, and 'tis his last request, That at thy feet he may have leave to die. L. Jun. And have I no friend left to strike a sword For very charity into this heart? Why do you heap these agonies upon me, And call me Consul? Who will watch for Rome, When you have kill'd your centinel?—Approach, Thou bleeding ruin, thou last mangled wreck Of all my joys, that were embark'd with thee; And perish'd in the surge, that was thy grave. Can'st thou speak to me? Tit. Venerable judge, Father of Rome and freedom, may this blood, By thy commandment spilt, wash out my crime. And shall this heart, before its pulses stop, Be blest with thy forgiveness? L. Jun. All the peace That my forgiveness can bestow I grant; The Gods will give the rest: in this sad heart No record will remain of thy offence; Thy punishment hath cancell'd that, and now Nought but thy early virtues, the fair promise Of my fond hopes, all blasted in the bud, Shall dwell in my remembrance—Hah! he dies! Support him in your arms—The quivering lids Close on his sightless eyes: convulsion tears His laboring heart; it rises to his throat— He gasps, he writhes in anguish—he expires! [Titus falls into the arms of the people. Val. Bear him away! quench not the light of Rome, That yet survives in Brutus. Valiant Consul, Great above men in sorrows as in soul, Rouse from the meditation on this scene, And cheer thy drooping friends. L. Jun. Approach, my friends, Ye that are fathers, and be taught by me To reverence justice. Mark if I bestow One tear upon the dead. I'll not embalm His body with the brine which hirelings shed, To trick their funerals forth with purchas'd woe: If I make salt this earth, 'twill be with blood, The blood of Tarquins, hot libidinous blood, Not with weak women's tears; let grief stand off, Till nobler guests are serv'd. Centurion enters. Cent. Health to the Consul! The king draws down his powers upon your town. As with Tarquinia I was on my way, Our party by a cohort in the van Of the main army was constrain'd to halt, And question'd of our purpose: This explain'd, Sextus Tarquinius, arm'd from heel to head, Rode forth and bade me render up to him The lady under guard; I did—When he, Their greeting past, dismiss'd me with these words— This courtesy, said he, which I accept From your revolting masters as a pledge Of their return to duty, hath so far Unedg'd my sword, that I will come to Rome Prepar'd to treat of peace and composition, And, ere I strike, to hear— L. Jun. Arm, warriors, arm! Put not your faith in Tarquins; if they treat, 'Tis only when they tremble. Friends, go forth, Marshal our city's force without the walls, And let our trumpets answer to their tongues, When they would parley. Sound out an alarm! [Trumpets. Brutus, Collatinus, &amp;c. exeunt. Manent Valerius and Centurion. Cent. Noble Valerius, may I crave your ear To a few words apart? Val. Speak and be brief. Cent. If Brutus may be wrought to interchange A hostage with the king, I have the word Of Tarquin's daughter for a peaceful truce, With pardon and redress of all that's past. Val. What hostage would the king demand of Brutus? Cent. Titus his son, whom in a luckless hour I made my prisoner—Hah! you shake your head: Is there no hope he will be mov'd to staunch The blood, that else in torrents must be spilt? Val. Titus is dead. Cent. Then, Discord, to thy work! The sword is out—We conquer or we die. [Exeunt. Scene without the walls of Rome. Trumpet sounds a parley. Brutus, follow'd by Valerius and other armed Romans. L. Jun. Look out, and say what company is that Whose trumpet sounds a parley—By the Gods, I will not trust these Tarquins with the hearing. No other conference shall they hold with Brutus Than shield to shield and sword oppos'd to sword, Amid the din of battle. Good Valerius, Advance and stop these parleyers— Tarquinia with Vitellius and others. Tar. Where is Brutus; Where is the Consul?—Oh, redeem the time, Save your devoted town, your children, wives, Your altars from destruction! In my hand I hold the sacred instrument of peace, Stampt with the royal signet to assure The credit of the deed. If you have wrongs, Here's that will heal your wrongs; if doubts or fears, Here's evidence to make suspicion blush. Scorn not this embassy because I bear it, Who than a woman fitter to assuage The angry feuds of men, and into love Convert your hatred? L. Jun. Messenger more fair Your father could not send, I do admit; But holding no allegiance to the sender, And resolute to cast our tyrant off, We pray you to avoid so rude a brawl, As needs will follow, when our noisy trumpets Charge to the onset and bray out for battle. Tar. If you reject us in the fond belief That fear provokes this embassy, look out And scan your danger well, ere you defy it. Will you not hear me, Brutus? In one word The truce is seal'd. Give up your son a hostage, And I, the daughter of a king, commit My life into your keeping. L. Jun. That we gave you When both were living—Titus is no more. [Exeunt L. Jun. Val. &amp;c. Tar. Monster of cruelty! Unnatural father! Thou murderer, what hast thou to do with peace, Hated by Gods and men? Why do I live? Come to my heart, deliverer! [Offers to kill herself. Vit. Stop thy hand! Hence, hateful weapon! Why this desperate act? Will it revive the dead? Will Brutus feel The dagger that destroys thee? Will it seat Thy father on his throne? 'Twill tear his heart With agonies, and quench the glorious hope Of Victory, now hovering on the wing 'Twixt eitheir host. Behold how many heroes Assemble to revenge the death you mourn— And see! a warrior comes, whose glittering form Brings light and life to chase despair away. Sextus Tarquinius and Soldiers. Sex. How now, my sister! why thus plung'd in grief? Brave natures face misfortune, cowards fly it. Not in the round of habitable earth Was there a man I lov'd like Titus Junius. I know the fatal story—He is slain; Our Mother too, after strange sort is dead; I hate a preface to a tale of horror— So now thou hast it all. Tar. Immortal Powers, Who on your suffering creature cast this load Of misery, to your all-commanding will Submissive I bow down my vassal neck, Nor murmur at your providence—Behold A wretch, on whom the brightest hopes had dawn'd, Now whelm'd in dark despair; a heart, in which Affection glow'd, and every tender string Thrill'd with the touch of sympathy, now torn And rent with agony; a form, alas! Which flattery said you moulded with some care, Now scorn'd and cast without remorse away, Like sherds that shiver in the potter's hand: If still it be your pleasure to take hence All that makes life a blessing, and yet bid Your ling'ring victim live, I will obey, Till, soften'd by my patience, you relent, And mercifully end my woes in death. Sex. Haste thee, Vitellius, lead her to the fane Of Juno Sospita; there she may rest In safety till this storm of grief subsides. [Exit Vitellius with Tarquinia. What means the king that he delays his march? Go one of you, and from you rising ground Look out, and make report what you espy. [Exit Soldier. Hah! who art thou?— Brutus, Valerius, and other Romans. L. Jun. Brutus, the foe of tyrants. Yield, ravisher! behold thou art inclos'd. Let these disarm and pass: their lives we scorn; Thou, violator of the marriage bed, Thou must atone to justice. Sex. Sound to arms! Call up the king to action— L. Jun. Call the king? Where is your vigilance? Your king is fled; Your soldiers are dispers'd; they pile their arms, And shout for liberty. The Soldier returns. Sol. Oh fatal truth! All, all is flight, confusion, and revolt. Sex. Dastard, 'tis false: my Romans cannot fly— Hear me, thou Brutus! life to life I dare thee In equal combat, branding thee a traitor, The assassin of a son, whom, oh dire murderer— Thou didst deserve as much as thou dost heaven. L. Jun. Tho' thy base deed, defiler, well might warrant Contemptuous seizure, yet this bold encounter Shall to no other chastisement expose thee Save as this arm shall punish—I accept Thy challenge, ravisher, and wield a sword Edg'd with Lucretia's wrongs. Val. What is't you do? Consul, remember Rome. L. Jun. Remember Rome! It is for Rome I strike; it is your cause, Ye Gods, and to your justice I commit it. Valerius, by our friendship I conjure thee, Come not betwixt us—Romans, I command you, Stand all aloof; if I am here to fall, Give honourable passage and protection To this bold son of Tarquin—conquering me, He will deserve to live. Sex. 'Tis fairly said! Thus to the manes of thy murder'd son I make libation of thy blood— [They fight and Brutus is wounded. Break off! Thou'rt wounded—breathe awhile. L. Jun. Gods, can there be Such noble bearing in a cause so vile? Val. Brutus, you bleed apace. Sex. Go, stop your sluices, And come afresh. I scorn a fainting foe. L. Jun. Foil'd by a stripling! I disdain the thought. [They fight and Sextus falls. Val. Oh, nobly fought! He falls, he faints, he dies— Freedom and Rome survive. [Vitellius runs in and receives Sextus in his arms as he is falling. Vit. Peace, nor insult The brave, tho' vanquish'd—See, the hero dies! The mightiest of the race of Tarquin dies. [Sextus dies. Val. Short are the conqueror's triumphs—Help to save him; Friends, Romans, countrymen, your Consul falls, The pillar of your nation is o'erthrown. [Brutus sinks to the ground. L. Jun. Mourn not for me! The interposing Gods Have snatch'd a sorrow-wounded soul to rest. I've liv'd enough for fame, for Rome and freedom; And, when I'm dead, pluck forth this heart, my friends: You'll find in mournful colours pictur'd there The dear-lov'd image of a dying son— Farewell to all!—Lucretia is reveng'd— Valerius, reach thy hand—my friend—'tis past! Dies.</field>
   </doc>
</add>