<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Hogg, James, 1770-1835</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Hogg, James, 1770-1835</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">hogg james 1770 1835</field>
      <field name="author_text">Hogg, James, 1770-1835</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1810's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V3.0784.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1817</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:461069</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Haunted Glen</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Haunted Glen</field>
      <field name="title_facet">haunted glen</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">haunted glen</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Haunted Glen</field>
      <field name="year_display">1817</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1817</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1817</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:461069&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:461069&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Hogg, James, 1770-1835&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;hogg james 1770 1835&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Haunted Glen&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;haunted glen&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1817&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1817&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Hogg, James&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1770&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1835&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Haunted Glen&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Edinburgh&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed by James Ballantyne and Co. for Longman, Hurst, Rees, Orme, and Brown ... and John Ballantyne [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1817&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3873403-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv30784&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Haunted Glen&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 100 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted&lt;lb/&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;lb/&gt;Epigraph included with All-Hallows-Eve&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: The haunted glen.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Dramatic poem.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1817.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Unknown.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE HAUNTED GLEN.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DRAMATIS PERSONÆ. Lu, a Scottish Prince, carried off by the Fairies, and afterwards chosen their King. Philany, Fairy. Dew, Fairy. Snowflake, Fairy. Foambell, Fairy. Rue, Fairy. Mothe, Fairy. Spirit. Cairney, a rude Hind. Simon, his Son. Knight. Lula, a Princess living in concealment. Eps, Wife to Cairney.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT FIRST. SCENE I. A Dell, by moonlight; with a distant view behind.— Enter a Fairy, winding swiftly among the trees. Voice above. Voice. Fairy, fairy, whither away? Fairy. Come down and see; It fits not thee To hide in the bud of the chesnut tree, And scare with yelp and eldrich croon The spirits that pass by the light of the moon. Voice. I heard a sound come through the wood, I fear'd it came from flesh and blood; But I'll be with thee for evil or good. Enter Spirit. Now, fairy, tell me, whither away, For I have much to thee to say, And much to do ere the break of day? Fairy. I know thee not—I cannot tell Whether thou art from heaven or hell. In Scottish glen, since the days of old, I have watch'd the hamlet and the fold; Long have I sojourn'd by mountain and dale, I have sail'd on the moon-beam, and rode on the gale For a thousand years, and a thousand more; But, spirit, I never saw thee before. Spirit. Here am I sent for a while to dwell; Tell me thy nature, and mine I'll tell. Fairy. This form was made when the rose first grew, Of an odour dissolved in the falling dew, When first from the heaven it 'gan to distil Above the top of the highest hill. And if I may judge from the moment I came, There's a germ of the rainbow in my frame, For my being grew, I remember well, When first the bow on the rose-bud fell; And the very first scene that met my view Was its pale blossom, tinged anew With stripes of the green, the red, and the blue. But I am a spirit of joy and love, For the breath that form'd me was from above. Spirit. Then, gladsome spirit, list to me, For we may meet by tower and tree: When first the fires of vengeance and wrath Were kindled in a world beneath, They from their boundaries burst on high, And flash'd into the middle sky; From these, a thin blue vapour came, Something between a smoke and flame, And it journey'd on through the firmament, Till with a sun-beam it was blent: Of that I was framed, and in my mood, There is something evil and something good. But I have been busy since I came here, There's a comely corpse lies stretched near— Within yon wood, of alders gray, There was murder done at the close of day. O, I ne'er saw so lovely a sight, As a maiden's corpse in the pale moonlight! Fairy. Ah! spirit of stern and ill intent, The land may rue that thou wast sent. Spirit. 'Tis true, I love to seek and see The evils of humanity, And the woes and plagues of the human lot, But I cannot hurt where sin is not. Come, trifling fay, I'll consort you The relics of mortal beauty to view; The writhed limb you there may see, And the stripes of blood upon the lea; Half open is her still blue eye; Her face is turned unto the sky; The shadows sleep on her bosom bare, And the dew-weft on her raven hair, And never again shall spirit see Such picture of sorrow and sanctity! Fairy. Get thee away, Thou elfin gray, Thou art not fit with fairies to stay! For me I am sent by the still moon-light, Each flowret's bosom to bedight, For the fairies revel here o'er night. The time draws on when Lu of Kyle, Who in Fairy land hath sojourn'd a while, Must be crown'd by a virgin's hand, The king of the fairies of fair Scotland; And fairies have ridden, and fairies have run, From the evening set till the morning sun, The first of mortal maidens to find, Fairest of body, and purest of mind; For she must be chaste as the snow-drop at noon, Stately as cherubim, mild as the moon, Sweet as the rose-bud, and fresh as the dew, That sets the crown on the head of King Lu. Spirit. If right I judge, you will only miss Your aim in travelling far for this; For in this glen there dwells a dame, The fairest of human form and name; But if I get sway of this woodland scene, This matchless maid shall be, ere e'en, What many a maiden before has been. Fairy. Get thee away, thou elfin gray! Thou art not fit with fairies to stay! The fairies of Scotia are mild as the even, Jocund and blythe as the laverock in heaven; Tender to childhood, gentle to age, Pesterous to priest, and freakish with sage; But whatever they do, or wherever they go, They grieve aye for human failings and woe. Get thee away, over brake, over thorn, Woo thy dead corse till the break of the morn, For I hear the sound of the fairies' horn. (Exit Spirit.) Scene continues. Endless trains of Fairies, clothed in green, and riding on white steeds, are seen in the distance—Song within. Fairy Song. Sweet is the mountain breeze of night, To fairy troopers blithly riding, Over holt, and holm, and height, Through the links of greenwood gliding. Chorus. Are Lu! Ora Lu! Who shall man and fairy sever? Ara Lu! Ora Lu! They are knit, and knit for ever. Lu is prince of Fairyland, Vales of light and fairy fountains; Lu shall wield the regal wand Over Scotia's heathy mountains. Chorus. Ara Lu! Ora Lu! &amp;c. Enter Lu and Female Fairies. First Fairy. Our names, prince—Our new names. Lu. Come hither, beauteous trifle. Thy name be hence Philany, and thy charge The nestlings of the birds, that sing at eve And ere the morning sun.—And thou, pale blossom, Thy name is Snowflake; and thy envied charge The walks and couch of virgin purity. O guard that well!—If e'er thou mark'st the eye Beaming with more than earthly lustre,—then Thy sickening opiates use, to dim the ray Too bright for man to look on.—In the night By maiden's bosom watch; and if she dream, Lay thy cold hand upon her youthful breast; Hang on her waving locks by day, and watch Her sweet and mellow breath; and as it heaves And rocks thee to and fro, thou shalt discern The slightest workings of the soul within; The rest thy wisdom and thy care direct. Kiss me, thou little sweet and humid thing, Bright as the orient—thy name be Dew; Thy care the wild-flowers of the hill and dale, To pearl the rose and weave the heavenly bow. And thou, her sister, guard the rivulets, And silver pools, where little fishes dwell, And sport them in the sun—thou hast a flock Full wayward and exposed—so be thy care— Thy name is Foambell, brook thou well the name. And thine is Rue—thy charge, declining life. And thou, that hast a pathos in thy looks Bespeaking mould of tenderness and love, Be guardian thou of playful infancy; Watch o'er the imps, and when the comely boy Nears to the precipice, where blossoms wave, Or to the pool, where green inverted hills, And trees, and shrubs betray—then flutter thou Close by his foot like gilded butterfly To lure the rosy lubber from the snare Of adder's young, and from the sloe-worm's den. Thy name is Mothe, the joy of doing good Be thy reward. Thou downy dancing thing, Fond as the nestling, playful as the fawn, Thy dwelling be the mountain, and thy task To guard the young deer, and the leveret And tender lamb—thy name is Gossamer. Embrace me all, then bound you on your way, To sport and revel till the dawn of day. (He embraces them all.) Sweet gladsome beings! sweet you are, and kind, And well I love you. But my mortal frame Is not so subtilized and pure, but that I feel in your communion something short Of true felicity. In all your rounds, And wanderings wild, search for the mortal maid Of purity and beauty so refined That spirits may consort with; and no stain Of human love or longing intervene. Dew. Prince, here I met with a spirit stern, Who said that by this forest dern, There dwells the fairest loveliest dame, That ever wore the human frame; But wicked men and fiends below Have both combined to work her woe. Prince, watch this glen, and if you see A knight of comely courtesy Lead a fair maiden to the wood, Of lady mien and mournful mood, Be sure that knight's intent is ill, For the blood is on his corselet still! Lu. Hie you away, by valley and brae, Attend to your tasks, by night and by day, And each take a thousand fays along, To tend your behests for right or for wrong; And here will I watch till the rising sun, For fear more guilty deeds be done. The Fairies dance slowly round him in a circle, and sing. The baby's rest shall be sweet and sure, The maiden's slumber blest and pure; The grey-hair'd sire shall rejoice in mind, And look before and not behind; The flowers shall blow, and the rainbow beam, The fishes sport in the sunny stream; Young Love and Peace shall go hand in hand, And Sin and Sorrow flee the land; The lamb beside the fox shall stray, The kid and fawn round the marten play, And the child shall dance by the adder's den, Since spirits pure are conjoin'd with men. CHORUS. Then hie away, fairies, hie away, Light over flower and tender spray, Light over moonbeam and midnight dew, Our blithsome gambols to renew. SCENE II. A Cottage. Cairney, Eps, Simon. Sim. Mither, I'm gaun to dee now!—It's a' o'er wi' me now! Eps. And what's my dainty son gaun to dee for now? Sim. Oh, it's for that Lula!—Plague on your Lula, that I ever saw her face!—And wae be to you for twa auld doitit bodies that ever pat it in my head to seek her for a wife, and to fa' in love wi' her, and court her, and then to get baith the skaith and the scorn.—I'm gane!—I'm clean dead!—Oh, plague on a' paughty queans! wi' their clear wily e'en! and their curls flauffing about their dimpled cheeks and ee-brees! they hae put me by mysel! but I'll hae amends o' them and o' ye a'! dear amends! Eps. Sit still, Sim.—Sit still, my dear son Sim, and hae a wee patience.—What are ye gaun to do wi' that muckle knife? Sim. I'm gaun to cut aff my head—What wad ye hae me to do wi't?—I'm gane! clean gane! I wadna gi'e a bawbee for my life!—But ye hae nane to blame but yoursels!—It is weel wared! Ye lose your son, and ye may tak up the neist ye find. —Oh, thae women! thae women!—De'il that there had ne'er ane o' them been born, wi' their sma' waists, and their lang white necks, and their legs turned and polished like fiddlepins. Eps. Wow, Sim, man! What for do ye speak that gate?—Ye ken if women ne'er had been made, the warld couldna hae been uphadden.—And whar wad ye hae been yoursel, ye gowk? Sim. And then they'll smile and they'll smirk!— And they'll caper, and prim their bits o' gabs!— And fling back their locks o' hair, that fock may see their reid-an-white haffats—and they'll gloom ae while, and greet anither—and pace away frae ane on their tip-taes!—I wonder how e'er it cam into ony anes head to mak sic creatures as women!—Or if I had been gaun to mak them ava, I wad hae made them something farrant like. Eps. Gramercy! Cairney, did you ever hear sic a rave o' nonsense?—The poor lad's dementit. Cair. He's a thowless gull!—Just naething but a muck hott!—He maks nae ill hand at a paritch bicker or a haggies; but for a bonny lass, ye may as weel set my tike to court her.—I hae seen the day, but it's gane, that if I had had her a cooking— Sim. And wow ye hae muckle to brag o' that way! Let ony ane look at my mither, and see what ye hae achieved.—Ye certainly hae won the dandilly-tosh o' the parishen! Eps. Alak, Simon! ye shouldna lightify the banes that bare ye.—I dinna like to hear it—Sorrow and eild will runkle the fairest and the bonniest; and or ye come to my time o' day, ye'll no be sae bright o' the lire. Sim. O, that I had ne'er seen the face of a woman, or seen only sic as yours!—I hae tint mysel athegither!—I'm daft—horn mad wi' love!—But there will soon be an end o't!—I'll tell ye what I think, mither—I think the women are a set o' bad wicked creatures, and that the maist o' them will gang an ill gate.—Paintit naethings! Limbs o' Sautan they are!—I believe it was nae ither than him wha gae them that fine lily whiteness to their hands and necks, and made their cheeks sae rosy, and their skins sae feele and saft—and then the lips and the een!—O Lord! O Lord! I canna thole them, and I winna thole them, nae langer!—I'll tell ye, father, what I'll do w'ye—I'll gi'e ye a' my sheep ilka clute, skin and birn, if ye'll just chip my head aff wi' an axe.—Live langer I winna; for she has guided me like a dog, like a whalp, like a messan! Cair. Son, hear me speak—Woo her, and woo her like a man; and I say and swear it, that you shall have her—But if I hear mair o' your hanging, or drowning, ye sanna want a hand to gi'e ye a heeze—silly, hen-heartit, white-livered gouk!—Woo her, and woo her the way I bade ye; and if she dares ill-treat or mock my son, I'll let her ken whase house and hands she's in!—Yes, boy, ye sal hae her, though I should tie her twa arms to the bed-posts. Sim. I wad just do that, father—that's the only chance I hae now—I'll stand by you. Eps. O fie, my dear gudeman and son, dinna speak that way—she's a sweet gentle creature, far frae hame, and has nae body to own her—But poor woman! she's aye somebody's bairn!—It wad be a sin and a shame to guide her ill—Mind the auld sang— Win a maid and wear a maid, But never overbear a maid; For gin ye fret or fear a maid, Ye nouther win nor wear the maid. Ye ken, son, she is a leddy born and bred, and ye should speak to her in a gentle and respectable way. Cair. Leddy, wife!—We ken little what she is— For a' her lear and scholarship, and thrimble-thrumbling at the harp, she may be comed o' the gypsies, for aught we wot. Eps. O fie! To speak that gate o' Lula! The dearest creature that ever this land bred! But, son, ye ken she gaed to the courting wi'ye when I desired her.—Tell us a' that past atween ye. Sim. Weel, ye see, we gaed away to the wood thegither, but she was unco sweer drawn, and was aye gathering bits o' yerbs and chirms o' gerse, never minding me; at length we came to a bit green swaird, and sat down thegither, and I pat my plaid round us baith. Cair. Ay—weel—that wasna sae ill. Sim. And when I laid it round her neck, I wad fain hae lettin my arm lie still there, but she pat it away sae gently that I hadna the face to offer again. Cair. That was sachless and silly-like! Sim. Then I says, “My bonny Lula,” says I— Cair. My bonny Lula—that was good—right that. Sim. “My dear heart's life and blood!” says I— Cair. Heart's life and blood!—O that was nonsense! Sim. “Ye ken my mither likes ye unco weel, and canna think ever to part wi' ye.” Eps. Ye said true, Simmy; ye said true! and what did she say to that? Sim. She gae a bit siche, and pu'd some threads and poukins o' woo' out o' my plaid; and when I lookit earnestly in her face, she took a ewe-gowan and pluckit a' the fringe aff it, bit by bit.—I didna ken what to do, nor what to say, for I was just like to sink down through the grund wi' perfect love— and sae I took her hand in atween baith mine, and squeezed it and sleekit it down, as it had been a young kittlen—“Oh me! what will I do?” quo' I; and then I said something that wad hae been better unsaid, and was gaun to kiss her hand, but she wadna even suffer that, but pu'd it frae me, and turn'd her face half away, and I thought by the dimple o' her cheek that the jade was laughin' at me. Cair. Maist likely she was, I think. Sim. “Turn round your face to me, Lula,” quo' l—“Turn round that bit bonny face again, for I hae nae skeel o' speaking in at the hole o' ane's neck.” And what think you the contrarisome shrew said? Eps. Haud your tongue now, Sim, for I downa bide to hear ye say ony ill o' her.—Ye might deserve a' that she said, for ye ken that ye're no owre weel bred. Sim. Weel, weel, mither, haud ye wi' her; ye'll soon win quat o' poor Sim. Ye want nae better, I find. Eps. Be quiet now, dear son, and tell me some mair that past atween ye.—I ken she hasna the nature to be uncivil to a dog, if it be civil to her.—Did you never ask her to be your wife ava'? Sim. Ask her to be my wife!—I may as weel ask the Erne Craig to be my wife; or the Moon; or the Seven Sterns—I'll hae the same success—I hae just ae chance—O, father, wad ye but lay velant hands on her! Cair. Ay, that's the way to gang to wark wi' her. Eps. Shame on him that says it!—Shame to you baith!—But I dare ane o' ye to wrang her, or lay a foul finger on her in my house!—I'll gar the blood blind the een o' the first scurvy loun that attempts it. Cair. Fich! auld ettercap! wha cares for your brag?—And you, if you hadna been a fool and a booby, ye might hae had her lang syne for your wife. Sim. For my wife!—Ah, what a thought that is! That's a killing, murdering thought!—ane that nae man can brook. Cair. Ye never wad tak my advice. Sim. Your advice!—Haud your tongue about your advice—I wish I had never heard it, nor yet made use o't.—But I'm a ruined man!—Shamed!— Affrontit!—Scorned!—Despised!—I can never, and shall never, see her face again.—Welcome, death! (Crying.)—Welcome, welcome! give me your hands —Farewell, father and mother; farewell, sun and moon, and sterns and women—this is the last o' poor Sim! (He puts a rope round his neck—His father pulls him up in anger—He cries out and is let fall—Scene closes. SCENE III. A Wood. Enter Lu. Lu. Another day is past; and it has been To me a day of such delight, and pain, And new sensations mingled, as I never Deem'd consonant with being.—I have seen The peerless maid of this romantic glen; Have watch'd her every motion, word, and look, With lover, and alone.—Such beauty, truth, And purity of soul, I did not ween This sinful world contain'd! I love her so, That I would yield this uncorporeal frame, This state of mental energy, attain'd By seven years penance, and again assume My former state of gross humanity, Rather than lose that virgin's fellowship, Her confidence, and love.—I watch'd her steps, Led by that treacherous, that destroying fiend, That demon in the guise of man, and heard His smooth deceitful tale—I took the form Of redbreast, and I hopp'd upon the spray Close to her cheek, and sung my plaintive note; And she call'd me sweet Robin, and I saw A kindness in her looks. Sir Knight, said she, List to that Robin's note—Methinks he says, “Beware, young simple Lula.”—On my faith! The Knight replied, 'tis very like these words! I wish I were that Robin's mate, said she, To fly away with him o'er many lands, And live in innocence!—And then I sung, “Would that you were, sweet Lula.”—Her blue eyes Turn'd doubtfully up to the sky when this She heard sung by a bird; her lovely face Was stamp'd with sweet amazement and deep thought. Then I became a coney, and I stole From out the brake, and hitch'd around their seat, Mounching the herbs, then raised up my long ears As listening in dismay, and look'd full wise; Making my cloven lip and wiry beard Move with grimace.—Back to the thicket then Amain I scudded, and as quick return'd, And cower'd and mounch'd the grass—She laugh'd at me, And praised my antic tricks, but little ween'd I was a fairy lover, and far less A mortal prince rid of his mortal nature. I must retire, and take some other form, For here my loved and beauteous Lula comes, Led by the wretch that woos her to her fate. (Exit.) Enter Lula and Knight. Lula. Where do you lead me, Knight? I may not go Farther into the glen; have you not heard How it is haunted? Knight. Fear not, gentle Lula; No spirit may do harm to innocence And beauty such as thine.—Come, let us stray Deeper into this dell, and watch the rise Of the full moon. See how her radiant verge Streams through the broken cliffs of yon far hill, Like fragments of a moon. The Queen of Heaven Smiles from her lattice! Has it not a cast Of sweet sublimity that scene, my Lula? Lula. It has.—O, I could list and look for ever, And muse upon these goings on of nature! Knight. 'Tis a fit scene for love.—Will you not hear The man that loves you to distraction, breathe His vows of constancy, and endless truth? Lula. Nay, then I'm gone; I loathe the very name Of love, and every baneful consequence That follows in its train. Why talk to me Of love, when Emma's lost?—Emma, who loved you With fondness never equall'd! Tell me, Knight, Where think you Emma's gone? Knight. How can I know? Woes me! poor Emma! She is fled, I fear, With false deceiver, or some base-born hind;— Let us not think of her. Lula. Yet you grow pale At mention of her name—I honour you For this—'Tis true she loved you!—What is here? There's blood upon your basnet, Knight!—Your hilt And arm are stain'd with it.—What blood is this? Knight. It is the blood of my white steed, which I Slew in a rage, and which I sore repent. Lula. Your steed is whole, and standing in his stall; I saw him; ask your groom. Knight. It was my hound, My milk-white hound—Woes me, that she is slain! Lula. Your hound is well, and hunting through the wood. Knight. It was a deer that held the hound at bay, 'Twas that I meant. Lula. You have not slain a deer For months and days, nor is it hunting time; You rave! or do not think of that you say.— But here's our gentle Robin come again, To cheer us with his homely note.—O, Knight, Let us return.—Hear what the Robin sings. Knight. Come, let us dive into the dell, my Lula, And see the moon lie bathing in the stream, Deep in the centre of the wood; it is A scene will charm you.—Let us go, my love. Lula. I never farther leave my home at eve; That glen is dangerous, for spirits there Hold nightly rendezvous.—Poor Emma loved Thoughtful to stray in it;—now, where, alas! Is simple Emma? Knight, though I nought fear, Strange fancies crowd on me.—Ah, might it be As I now deem!—Do guardian spirits ever Take form of beast or bird? Knight. So sages say. But wherefore ask?—Come, let us go, my love, Down that sweet winding glen.—You cannot fear To walk that space with me—I know the scene Hath that in't will delight you. You shall see The moonbeam streaming o'er the shadowy hill, To kiss the winding wave, and deck the trees In golden foliage—You shall see the shades Of hills, and trees, and rocks, lie stretch'd afar, Bathing in liquid crystal, till you lose Sense which is the true world, the stars, and moon, And which the elemental imagery. O! I beseech you, let us go, sweet Lula. Lula. Well, I will go; for when I hear you talk Of nature I am charm'd—'tis so unlike The converse of these simple cottagers; But talk of that alone, and not of love, Else I'll not list, nor answer deign to you. Why am I plagued with language which I loathe? (Going, stops short.) Protect my senses, Heaven!—Can it be? Look at that bird, Sir Knight—Is it not changed In form and size since last we look'd at it. Knight. What is it? Lula. See! it grows and changes still; Waylays and threatens us—I will not go Farther upon that path for will of man. Knight. Then my resolve is fix'd—Dame, you shall go, Return home as you may. Lula. What do you mean? Knight. Only that you shall go into that glen Far as I list to lead you—if you prove As coy when you return, my well-earn'd skill In woman I give up. Nay, struggle not, Nor pule, nor cry, for neither shall avail. Enter Lu, who by a wave of his hand lays the Knight flat on his back. Lula. O, comely stranger, spare my helpless youth! Protect and guard me; here I throw myself Into your arms. Lu. And from all brutal force, And insult, shall these arms protect you, maid. Lula. Yes, I can trust you—there is in your look, And your embrace, that chasten'd dignity, That calm pure sympathy, which I have long'd And pined so much to look on—Whence are you? From what blest land, or kingdom, came you thus To my deliverance? Lu. These lands were mine, Far as the soaring eagle's eye can reach; But I resign'd them for a dynasty Wild and ætherial.—Could you love me, Lula? Lula. I know not—If your touch and looks were aye As pure as they are now—methinks I could. Lu. Then I'll be aught for thee—I'll be again The thing I was, that I may be caress'd And loved by you; though pain, and woe, and death, And spirits' vengeance on the issue wait. Come with me, gentle maid; and, while I lead you Home to your cot, I will a tale unfold Shall make your ears to tingle, and your thoughts Wander into delirious mystery. (Exeunt Lu and Lula. The Knight rises.) Knight. What can this mean?—How was I struck to earth, And chain'd as by some spell?—Curse on the stripling! Who can he be, or whither did he come To brave me in this guise?—'Tis like a dream. And yet I saw them go arm link'd in arm, While I not moved a finger or a limb. Might I believe that I some thing have seen Not of this world, that with one wave of's hand Could strike me motionless, then do I strive In vain for the possession of the maid. But here I swear above this craven sword, (That for the first time slept within its sheath Beneath the eye of insult,) not to brook Life without Lula.—Never shall I see Another filch that precious morsel, placed Thus in my reach!—Arm, thou wast never wont To lie in dull and nerveless apathy When will call'd, “Strike.” Ah! couldst thou do it now, When the most delicate and luscious cup That ever mock'd Desire's pale parching lip Was rudely dash'd away?—Blood and revenge Be hence thy meed, or scornful Lula mine!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT SECOND. SCENE I. The Glen.—Twilight. Lu and Fairy meeting. Lu. Welcome, my little Foambell, here. How fare thy flocks by frith and meer, By river, pool, and streamlet clear? Fairy. O, Prince, my charge I yield again! My little breast is rent with pain! No happy thing on earth may be, While ruthless man holds sov'reignty. I chose the sweetest stream that fell From mountain, glen, and moorland well, Where, happy, gay, and innocent, My sinny tribes were in thousands blent; And I rejoiced, and smiled to see Each awkward beck and courtesy, How downward turn'd each full set eye, As I their Queen went sailing bye. One day I spied, upon the strand, A carl that waved a sounding wand, Of marvellous length, whom I did deem Some earthly guardian of the stream; But coming nigh, I wept full sore To see my people dragg'd ashore, One after one, and two by two, And welcomed forth with murderous blow, While their dying throes rejoiced his sight, For his ugly face had the grin of delight. This scene my feelings could not bear, I tried to wile them from the snare; The form of a fisher-man I took, And I angled before him in the brook; But they wearied of my phantom fly, And the carl he thrash'd, and waded nigh; I could not scare them from his hook, For I cast no shadow on the brook; Though boardly my frame as man's might be, “The sun shone through my thin bodye.” I wist not what to do or say, For still the carl he plash'd away; And his rod, that stretch'd o'er half the flood, It sounded through the air so loud, That it made me start and pant for breath, For I knew the sough was the sound of death. No minute past but one or more Were dragg'd forth struggling to the shore; I saw them flutter in wild affright, And shiver and gasp in piteous plight; Their silvery sides, that in the flood Shone bright and pure, were striped with blood; Yet no remorse did the carl feel, But thrust them in his wicker creel. Then I bethought me of a plan, Of turning pike instead of man; And aye where his hook the angler threw I chased away my harmless crew; Oh, how astonish'd were the throng When I came gaping them among! Away they fled to ward the scath, Fast I pursued with threat of death. Most gleesome sport I had the while, But wondered at the carl's wile, For o'er the ripple he swum his fly, So sleek and so provokingly, That scarcely could I myself restrain From springing at that bait amain; For though by sage it be denied, Nature and form are still allied. Amazement mark'd the fisher's look, Another fish he could not hook; He changed his tackle, he changed his fly, And blamed the colour of the sky; But baulk'd for once, he went away, Cursing the fish and hateful day. Full six times twelve away he bore, I saw him count them on the shore, All rest of life, withouten law, To gorge a miscreant's ravenous maw. Then sooth, while man has sway below, My watery charge I must forego. Lu. But here comes slender Gossamer, Like shred of silver through the air.— What news, thou gentle pitying child, From mountain, glen, and forest wild? Gos. Ah, woful news! my heart's in pain! All would be joy in my domain, The kid and lamb would sport in peace, The young deer dwell in happiness; But man—remorseless, ravenous man! Kills and devours, and stay who can. The life-blood and the trembling limb Of parting life are joy to him; That rank devourer hence restrain, Or take from me my charge again. Lu. Woes me, that those we so much love, Such troublers should of nature prove: But here comes one whose placid face Speaks better things of the human race.— Welcome, fair Snowflake, back to me; How thrives sweet virgin purity? Snow. Ah, Prince, decline the woeful theme! Give it not thought!—Give it not name! Else first restrain or quench the blood Of man, the defacer of all good! The maiden is pure without a stain, And pure in mind would aye remain, But man—I sicken at the thought Of all the shame that he hath wrought! There is no art—there is no wile That may the maiden heart beguile, And cloud for aye the joyous smile, Which this destroyer scorns to prove, This recreant in the paths of love. Thousands to shame and ruin driven, Debased on earth—debarr'd from heaven— Of human forms and souls divine, Yearly at Love's unholy shrine; On bloated altar doom'd to lie, Unblest to bleed, unwept to die. Without regret, or wish t'atone, He boasts his feats and urges on; And when no other schemes remain To give the virtuous bosom pain, To Beauty's walks he wends his way, With shameless stare in open day, To check the step, abash the eye, And tint the cheek of modesty. O Prince, my charge I must disclaim, While man's rude nature is the same. And more, a baleful imp, I fear, Is lately come to sojourn here; A stranger spirit, bent on ill, Whom I have watch'd o'er vale and hill; His purposes we must gainsay, Else shame may be ere break of day. Yon cot I mark'd him prying round, But scared him thence, and there I found The loveliest maid of mortal race, In dangerous and in helpless case; A clown had crept her door within, And left it open to the gin; A dark knight stood her casement nigh, With burning cheek and greedy eye, While the unweeting simple maid Kneel'd on the floor and inly pray'd. Her light locks o'er her shoulder swung, Her night-robe round her waist was flung; Her eyes were raised—her breast of snow Heaved with devotion's grateful glow; The speaking lip, the brow erect, The movement on the polish'd neck; The blooming cheek, the fervent mien, Were all so comely, so serene, The breeze of earth did ne'er embrace Such pure angelic loveliness. The peasant's rugged form I took, And braved the blood-hound's surly look; At me he flew with horrid bay; I fled, provoked, and led the way Straight to the base and wicked clown; The ban-dog seized and pulled him down; Aloud he cried, and fought for life, And rough and bloody was the strife. Then in the maiden's form so light, Forthwith I glided by the knight, Who follow'd fast, and begg'd and pray'd, But still I flew along the glade; Just when his arms were stretch'd to press My waist with hellish eagerness, A quagmire deep I led him in, And left him struggling to the chin. Thus far, full deftly have I sped, Protecting maidhood's guiltless bed; But ah! if man, the lord below, Continue still as he is now, Alas! my Prince, my toils will prove Light balance in the scale of love. But who would strive?—Last night I spied The loveliest flower on Leven side In her bed-chamber laid to rest, A sweet babe cradled on her breast; Such fondness melted in her eye— Affection's holiest purity! When with her breast the elfin play'd, His round cheek to that bosom laid, That I was moved, and ween'd, if bliss Be found in life's imperfectness,— If pure affection's from above,— If “Love is Heaven, and Heaven is Love,” All love, all fondness is outdone By mother's o'er her only son; That glow is bright, its workings kind, Calm, chasten'd, ardent, yet refined. Then let me roam as heretofore, And think of guarding maids no more. Song by Lu. Never, gentle spirits, never Yield your cares of human kind! Can you leave the lonely river, From the moonlight valley sever, All your guardian love resign'd? Thrown aside, and scorn'd the giver? Never, gentle spirits, never! Chorus of Fairies. Never till the dawn of day, Dawn of truth that shine shall ever, Will we quit our polar way; Over green-wood, glen, and brae, Over tree, Over lea, Over fell and forest free, Over rock, and over river, Over cairn and cloud to quiver; Never, gentle spirits, never! Never!—Never! SCENE II. Inside of the Cottage. Simon holding down a great Dog. Sim. Murder! murder! holloa!—Blood, and fire, and desolation, ho!—Come a' here! Come a' here, for the sake o' man, and life, and death, and— Murder! murder! Ho! Enter Cairney. Cair. What's the matter wi' ye, callant? What ails ye? Sim. What ails me! That's sic a question to speer! Dinna ye see that I'm worried? Isna that aneugh to ail me?—Worried to death—a' torn to pieces, and chew'd to bird's-meat—and yet to come and speer what ails me.—Come directly, and help me to kill this devil! Cair. Let the dog gae, fool.—I'll command him off.—Burly, get off, thief—Hame to your hole, dragon! —Son, what were you seeking here? Sim. Hush! I may tell you—I was watching that witch, Lula—I had gotten ae door opened, and another unsneckit ere ever she heard a jerg; and I was just ready to seize on her the moment she lay down— Cair. And I was waiting to gi' ye help, provided ye needit it. Sim. War ye, my dear dad? O that dog!—that confoundit dog! we might hae had her bund hand and fit afore this time, and brunt afore day-light. Cair. Was it to kill her that you were watching her? Sim. I wad like to hae her bund at ony rate. I carena what come o' her, if I'm in hands wi' her ony way; I wad just do ought till her that I could get done.—But I'm gane now—There's no a hale inch in my bouk. Cair. How in the wide world did the dog come here to attact you, the very man he likes best? Sim. O, father, she's a witch—a rank witch—I saw by her look that she's a witch; and I'll swear till't; for her ee was set in her head, her lip was gaun, and the veins o' her neck war a' stirring and heaving, like wee moudieworts aneath the snaw. Cair. The behaviour of the dog is ayont my comprehension. Sim. O, father, she's a real witch!—if ye wad but haud her till I scored her aboon the breath, or gart her say the verse, ye wad see.—I'm a' rinnin' o' blood, and dirling wi' pain now; but I fand I was witched, and drawn to her by some invisible strength. And I'm sure naething short o' suppernatral power could hae gart the hound brik his chain, and come a' the gate here to worry me. Cair. It looks a little odd, I do confess. Enter Lula. Sim. O, ye witch! ye unfernal correspondent! Are ye there, wi' your angel face, and your wicked devices? Ye hae a weel-faur'd polished outside—Ye hae a brow, and a neck, and a breast, bonnier war never seen; but the heart within is blacker than the craw's wing. O, ye wild enchanter! ye hae power o'er men and dogs!—See what ye hae done!—See what ye hae brought me to. But ye shall never see the light of day, if green widdy will bind, or red lowe burn ye. Lula. Heaven shield thy wits!—Dear Simon, what is this? Sim. Dear Simon! Dear Simon!—Father, do ye hear that?—O what will come o' me?—It is here still!—Blood canna sloken't—Water canna drown't —The tooth o' the maskiss dog canna gnaw it out o' me! It is here still, lowing and scowdering me up like a moorburn!—Dear Simon, she says! Lula. Indeed I do call you dear Simon. You little know the regard I have for you, if you would but behave yourself. Tell me then, seriously, what brought you here? Sim. Gudefaith, that's a plumper!—Father, what shall I say now?—I think I be stupid!—What brought me here? Ye ken that o'er weel!—It was yoursel, wi' your witchery, and your enchantments, and your black art of Oxford. Confess your cantrips, ye witch o' Bethel, that ye pat a weed in my shoe, or drappit my doublet neist the heart wi' your luve-draps that wad gar deils follow ye—Yes, ye drew me here—ye draggit me here by a force ayont the power o' man to broostle wi'—and ye hae the 'frontery to speer “what brought me here!” Lula. I draw you here! What raving is this?— What does it mean? Sim. Ay, and wha was't brought the dog here— the mangrel blood-hound, wi' his teeth like brogue-elshins, to tear me, his master, to pieces? Was there aught o' nature there?—Can ye deny that too? Lula. (Aside.) Cairney, what does this mean? I fear he is gone mad. Cair. Whisht, lassie! dinna let him hear.—He's bitten. Enter Knight, covered with mire. Knight. I have you now, Dame Lightfoot.—You have sped Too well in your cursed plot. Was ever man Lured to such snare, and left in such a plight? O, I'll have sweet revenge on you for this! Lula. I'm all amazement! How am I to blame? How came you thus? Knight. So thou art mocking, art thou? Deceitful minx! I'll drag you to the gulf To which I was decoy'd, and treat you there As your deservance merits. Lula. (Aside.) O, Cairney, he is bitten too! Cair. I trow sae.—Did ye see aught o' my dog, sir—a muckle gollaring hallanshaker beast like yoursel, that whiles gangs snaiking about i' the night-time? Knight. Hence with you, old bell-weather.—Come, dame, I have to deal with you—You go with me. Sim. You! You tak away that lassie! Ye had better no try't, gin ye like.—Chewed as I am, I'll maybe gie ye twa-three prods whar ye canna weel thole it, ere that take place. Enter Spirit, who has been lingering near. Spirit. (Aside.) Now I'm invisible, I will Have my sport, and have my fill; With this elfin spear of mine, I will prick him to the spine— Take you that for curse and crime, We shall meet another time. (He wounds the Knight with a small lancet, who, turning round and seeing no one, knocks down Simon, and kicks him.) Sim. Holloa! Gie owre!—Deil's i' the carl!— What is't ails the clairty thief?—Ill-faurd, glaury-like tike, that ye are; whaten a gate's that to guide fock i' their ain house?—We're a' witched thegither —a' horn mad!—Ane lying thrawing his neck like a half-worried tod—anither a' draiggled, and bemired, and half-drowned—and yet hingin' owre her and canna get away, like laverocks owre an edder.—O, ye witch! ye vilde witch! was't no eneugh that I shoud be a' ae blister frae head to fit, that ye boude to bring that muckle, dirty, hangit-like whalp wi' your black airt, and eigg him up to fa' to and mell on me! Oh, may the deil tak a' witches an' worrying tikes, and nasty draiggle-tailed gentlemen! Muckle hing-luggit, croudy-looking thief! (Knight kicks Simon, who cries out.) Sim. Oh! Ugh! Cease! Gie owre, I tell ye! Damn the body! Ugh! Enter Eps. Eps. Master, hae ye nouther mense nor good manners? What's the matter, Cairney? Lula, my bonny bairn, tell me what maks a' the stir at this time o' night? Cair. Alas, Eps! the muckle mangrel maskiss has gaen mad, and bitten poor Sim, an' he's infected. Eps. O alack that ever I saw the day! What will I do for my dear bairn? Cut out the bit, my man; haste ye and cut out the bit. Sim. Hear till her now! Hear what she's saying! The mair ane hears o' women he'll think the less o' them! How can I cut out the bit when I'm a' bitten owre the hale body? Ye may cut me a' out, an' what kind of a son wad ye hae then? I might live wanting a wee piece flesh, but I think I could hardly do without the halewore o't. That's women's wit! That's like ane o' their grand cures!—(Leans forward wardon the floor in a desponding way.) —Aih wow! but it is an awsome thing this! It never strak me afore, but I see an' find it is a' owre true! Mad!—to gae mad!—(Weeps and cries out in despair.)—Oh dreadfu'! dreadfu'! to think o' ganging mad, and rinning yauffing, and youlling, and froaing at the weiks o' the mouth—to rin chacking and biting the dirty hint-legs o' the kye to pit them wud—and then to be bund and smoored atween twa tikabeds—or drink poison out of a lang laddle, an' a' the while biting pieces out o't wi' my teeth—Oh, oh!—(Cries.)—To think that in a day, or an hour, I maun be rinnin' setting up my reid een glentin like burning candles, and whan ought comes near me to nurr and gurr.— (Grins and howls like a dog.) Eps. O mercifu' heaven, it is coming on him already! —My poor bairn!—What shall we do? Sim. And then to set up my gab to the lift, and yauff, and bark, and bough-wough like a hund! (Growls and barks like a dog, and springs forward on all four to bite the Knight's legs—He escapes, and is seized by the mastiff without—a great tumult is heard.) Eps. Haste, Cairney, gie the man some help or he'll be killed. Sim. Keep fast the door, or ye're a' gane thegither —Let him tak it—time about's fair play—Deil that he rive him a' to collops—what's he seeking here?—Oh me! oh me! oh me! Eps. Hae patience, my poor man, Providence will maybe hae mercy on ye yet. Sim. Let us alane o' your patience and providence, mither—they're nae doctrines for a man gaun mad. Ye'll soon see me rinning i' the lone hinging by the kye wi' my teeth—ye may crack o' your providence then. Cair. Get up, get up, Simon, an' tak heart. Sim. Na, na, I downa get up; it's mair feasible-like to gang on four this way. Cair. Tell me how you feel, and what you feel inclined to do. Wad ye like to bark, an' bite, an' devour? Sim. I think I wad—I wad just like to flee on aboon Lula there, and worry her. Cair. You really feel inclined to do her a mischief? Sim. Ay, that I do!—I wad rather do good to her than ill, if I could get it done; but I wad rather be doing ill to her than naething ava'. Eps. I trow there's mair nature than madness in that, an' I hope a' will be weel yet.—Come and let us put you to bed, my poor luckless man. Lula. And I'll bathe your wounds, and dress them, and watch with you, Simon, for my heart is sore for you. Sim. Will you indeed, sweet Lula? Ah, ye are a bit dear lassie for a' that's come and gane! But it's a' ane to me—Shame, worrying, love, madness— ony ane o' them's eneugh—but a' put thegither! Oh dear! Oh dear! (Exeunt.) SCENE III. A deep Dell. Knight sitting disconsolate. Knight. Sure there's some power unseen, unmeet for man To cope with, watches o'er that witching thing. First by a stripling I was stunn'd, and laid Flat without motion; next to slough decoy'd, Bay'd by a madman—by a blood-hound torn. If I escape infection from the fangs Of that outraged monster, I shall never Strive for possession of that maiden more, Though my heart burn within me. Enter Spirit, who speaks and sings aside. Spirit. Then my sport will all be done; Knight, before the rising sun, Wet and weary, rack'd with pain, You shall seek that maid again. Sings. My love's blithe as the bird on the tree; My love's bonny as bonny can be; Though she loves another far better than me, Yet the dream wears kind in the morning. Then I will steal to my love's bed-side, And I will kiss my bonny bonny bride; And I'll whisper a vow whatever betide, To my little flower in the morning. Her breath is as sweet as the fragrant shower Of dew that is blown from the rown-tree flower; O never were the sweets of roseate bower Like my love's cheek in the morning! Her eye is the blue-bell of the spring, Her hair is the flue of the raven's wing, To her bonny breast O how I'll cling! While sleeping so sound in the morning. Knight. Holloa! who goes there? Spirit. (Aside, imitating.) Holloa! who goes there? (To him.) A true man, sir, or one that may soon be so—an honest blithe youth, and a lover to boot;— fa lal de ral all, &amp;c. (Sings and skips about.) Knight. You a man? You a lover? An elfin brat, by the soul of King Cowl! But if thou art a devil, thou art a merry one. Pray, master lover, what man, or youth, or boy, would thus run frisking and capering about in the woods, and singing by the light of the moon? Spirit sings. By the wan light o' the moon, By the wan light o' the moon, He staw into his love's window By a blink o' the dowy moon. But wae be to the fause grey cock, For he craw'd an hour owre soon; The lassie thought it day when she sent her love away, But it was but a blink o' the moon. [Spirit.] I am going a wooing, sweet sir, but, like the grey cock, I'm an hour o'er soon. O that the time were come, for my heart is like to flutter out of its little tenement! Knight. You going a wooing? Spirit. Ay, sir, I; and I'll come speed too.—I know my time—O that it were come!—Pray, sir, did you ever see this flower of all the world that has made its appearance at that white cottage in the glen? Knight. Ay, forsooth! Spirit. It is there I go—O my heart is all on flame when I think of her, and the joys that await me there! I have heard her sentiments of love and lovers, and I shall not use her as the silly Knight of Auchingaur has done. Goodbye, sir; farewell. Knight. Holloa!—Stop, sweet youth—Come near me, if you please, and let me look at you—Who the devil are you? Spirit. It is not material—fal lal, &amp;c.—O, sweet adorable Lady Lula! What a mean-spirited lifeless driveller he must be, your Knight of Auchingaur! Were I but loved and desired as he has been, I would not lose such blest opportunities, nor shall you ever complain of me, as you do to all the world of him! Knight. Do you know that knight, sir? Spirit. No, but it matters not; he must be a man of wood—a piece of cold clay soil baked up, without the leaven of life or animation. If he had heard what I have heard from her own lips! or seen what I have seen!—O were I but that knight!—But as it is, I'll have her myself—Goodbye, sweet sir. Pray, why do you sit watching and writhing here? —But it is all one—I care not. Sings. The poor shilly-shally knight, He's nae man ava; He's no worth a flee, to let The bonny lass awa'. An' will I clasp her slender waist, An' kiss her lips sae sweet? I'm downright dizzy wi' the thought! In troth I'm like to greet! An' the poor shilly-shally knight, &amp;c. (Exit singing.) Knight. A plague go with thee, atom of impertinence! What skip-jack is this? Well, go thy ways, jews-ear: if thou art not worried like a rabbit ere thou gainest the door, I bode wrong.—But what a piece of intelligence! I was sure the girl affected me—she could not hide that; but I never weened that I had baulk'd her expectations so much.—I now know my cue, and she shall not again complain of me.—But let me consider—Can I go home tonight, and another gone avowedly to steal on her rest, while she is perhaps dreaming of me? No; wet, weary, and torn as I am, I must go back the way I came; and should the mastiff worry yon ape, which I joyfully predict, then shall I take his place; but if I find him where his betters should be, I'll mince him! I will!—Oh me! (He halts away.) SCENE III. Inside of the Cottage. Cairney sitting drowsy by the fire—to him enter the Spirit. Spirit. Bid you good-morrow, honest carl. Cair. Hoh! avoid ye, in the name of Saint Aaron! Wha the foul thief are ye, callant? Keep your ain side o' the house, an' it be your will. Spirit. Hush, goodman! I am a wooer, an honest youth, and the son of an old friend. Cair. I little wot about ye, lad—ye hae an unco wan-yirdly like look—an' how gat ye in here? Spirit. I came by the casement. Cair. The deil o' there ye cam. Keep to the lee o' the low awee, and come nae within the breath o' auld Cairney—he's fortified—he has Black luggie, lammer-bead, Rowan-tree an' red thread, To pit the spirits to their speed. Ely away afore I bring them a' an' extinguish ye. Ye're either a brownie, a fairie, or a willie-an'-the-wisp —if ye ken o' a hidden pose, speak, but otherwise, ely. Spirit. I tell you, goodman, I am a wooer, and a friend, and I have gained young Lula's consent, provided you agree. I came here to ask her of you, and afterwards to see herself, but was benighted;— trust me, I am honest, and son to an old friend of your own. Cair. He has a daft-like son o'ye, man—but keep your ain side o' the ingle, and say what ye like—I hae help at hand, an' deil a feared I'm for ony sic wizzling. Spirit. Give me then your consent to wed Lula. Cair. Na, na, lad; Lula has other tow to teaze. Spirit. That is ungenerous—She has told me all her views in life, and transferred me to you. Cair. And pray, sweet young man, what are her views in life? When I hae learn'd these I may consent. Spirit. She said she had long loved your son, and on that account had lingered here; but that he had proved himself to be unworthy of a maiden's love— that he might long ago have had possession of her person, which, since he had declined, she disdained him, and would now yield herself up to me. Cair. The very words I aye said! Od, callant, ye hae some insight, however ye cam be it—But or the morn at e'en she sanna tell that tale—ay, or daylight, if I get my will. Silly dult! he'll gang creepin' and whinin' about, an' trying to pit down himsel, and fighting wi' dogs, but he'll never do as he should do. Gang about your bisiness, callant—it is a shame for the like o' you to be gaun snouking after the women at this time o' night—dirty, menseless, ill-bred thing! Spirit. Well, goodbye, old churl; I shall have her in spite of you, and that “ere twice the sun meet with the sea.” (Exit Spirit.) Cair. The deil ye will!—I'll turn your nose to green cheese or that come about—Whaten an ill-faurd weazel-blawn urf is that, bouting in on fock i'the night time like something that's no canny: I'll gang an' see how the twa are coming on, an' if Sim be really gaun mad, or only put a wee hair-brained wi' mishanters. SCENE IV. The Grove. Enter Lu and Fairies. Lu. Fairies, the night wears on apace; There's a paleness spread on the heaven's face, A silvery haze so mild to see, As lambent and as pure as we. Soon will we mount with blithsome sway Through these bright paths on our spiral way, On the locks of the morning star to swing, Or the veil of the sky for the dew to wring; To gallop the blue so lightsome and boon; Or braid the fair tresses of beauty so bright, That wanton and wave at the horns of the moon, They are half of them æther and half of them light. But ere we depart from the morning ray To follow the moonlight west away, O Spirits, advise what shall be done, This loveliest flower beneath the sun, From shame, from sin, and from sorrow to win? Dew. Bear her away 'Twixt the night and the day; We Spirits have might When we work for the right, And each of us as much weight can bear Of aught corporeal through the air, As the swallow can carry on wing opprest, Or the merle upbear to her downy nest. Then bear her away 'Twixt the night and the day, For she is too pure in this world to stay. Lu. That may not be—By rite divine, In holy church, and at holy shrine, She has been wash'd, with prayer and vow, And named by a name to which we bow. Or she must change with free good will, Or be as she is for good or for ill; Should I her gain, say shall she be The Queen of the Fairies, and queen to me? Dew. Treason and pain! Speak not again! Trial and penance must long remain! Bonny Philany, Snowflake, and Foam; Rainbow, Rainbow, blink and go home! Phil. (Aside.) Regard not, Prince, that freakish thing, From jealousy her ravings spring; One we must have, whatever befal, To-morrow is our great festival, And nought but mortal virgin's hand Must crown thee King of the Fairy land; And then thy fate is fix'd for ever, From us and ours no more to sever. Lu. Would that the time were not so soon! It is not yet the wane of the moon. Phil. Prince, I have a word to say to thee— Your troubled mind and eye I see; But if you dare to harbour a thought Of yielding a crown so dearly bought, With all the joys of the moonlight dell, And the fervent beings that love you so well, For the sake of a flower that will soon decay, A piece of fair well-moulded clay, We'll pick these bright eyes from your head, And there we'll fix two eyes of lead; We'll pull the heart from thy breast bone, And there we'll lodge a heart of stone; So take thou care, lest some espy The thoughts that in thy bosom lie. Lu. Sweet friendly fay, 'tis all too true; Nor thought nor wish I'll hide from you: Either that maiden here I must have, Or return to the world, to death, and the grave. O haste thee, Snowflake, haste and glide To yon little cot by the green-wood side, And watch yon maid till the break of day, For I hear the watch-dog's angry bay; Watch by her pillow, and look to her bed, For I fear that beauty is hard bested. Then hie you away, fairies, hie you away! Lean to the breeze, and ride in array Over the land and the sea so fleet, Over the rain, and the hail, and the sleet, Keep aye the sun far under your feet; The morning behind, and the stars by your side, The moon-beam your path, and her crescent your guide, For O her mild and humid flame Suits best with the fairies' airy frame! And meet we again to-morrow at even, When the first star peeps through the veil of heaven; And here such a palace of light shall be As the world ne'er saw and never will see: For there shall be lamps and glories in store, And a thousand stars, and a thousand more; And there shall the ruby and onyx be seen, The amethyst blue, and the emerald green, With millions of gems of varied flame, That have no likeness and have no name. And our columns shall reach to the middle sky, And the throne shall stand as the pine-tree high; Soft music shall flow of the spheres above, The songs of gladness, and songs of love; And our feast shall begin with glory and glee, But little we know what the end shall be! Song. O weel befa' the guileless heart In cottage, bught, or pen! An' weel befa' the bonny May That wons in yonder glen; Wha lo'es the good and true sae weel— Wha's aye sae kind, and aye sae leal, An' pure as blooming asphodel Amang sae mony men. O weel befa' the bonny thing That wons in yonder glen! There's beauty in the violet's vest, There's hinny in the haw, There's dew within the rose's breast, The sweetest o' them a'. The sun may rise and set again, An' lace wi' burning goud the main, The rainbow bend attour the plain Sae lovely to the ken; But there's naething like my bonny thing That wons in yonder glen. 'Tis sweet to hear the music float Alang the gloaming lea; 'Tis sweet to hear the blackbird's note Come pealing frae the tree; To see the lambkin's lightsome race; The speckled kid in wanton chace; The young deer cower in lonely place Deep in his flowery den; But what is like the bonny face That smiles in yonder glen! END OF THE SECOND ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The great length of this Pastoral rendered its full insertion here inconvenient. But as all the foregoing plays were originally written merely as exercises in dramatic composition, and as such are now presented to the public, the Author deemed that a part of any of them, and of this last in particular, was as sufficient for a specimen and as amusing as the whole. It will be observed, that it is founded on the old romance of Tam Lane, and from that the issue may be divined. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>