<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Galt, John, 1779-1839</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Galt, John, 1779-1839</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">galt john 1779 1839</field>
      <field name="author_text">Galt, John, 1779-1839</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1810's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V3.0382.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">[1812]</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460745</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Lady Macbeth ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Lady Macbeth ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="title_facet">lady macbeth</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">lady macbeth</field>
      <field name="title_text">Lady Macbeth ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="year_display">[1812]</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1812</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1812</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460745&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460745&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Galt, John, 1779-1839&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;galt john 1779 1839&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Lady Macbeth ; A Tragedy&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;lady macbeth&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;[1812]&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1812&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Galt, John&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1779&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1839&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Lady Macbeth&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed For Cadell And Davies&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;[1812]&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3873081-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv30382&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Lady Macbeth&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 70 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory omitted.&lt;lb/&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Lady Macbeth.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1812.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Unknown.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">LADY MACBETH, A TRAGEDY.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHARACTERS. MACBETH. BAUDRON. SEATON. LADY.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The stage represents an anti-chamber, in the castle of Dunsinane.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. SCENE I. Macbeth and Seaton. MACBETH. Methought last night, as I lay on my couch, I saw a silent-footed phantom pass, In the pale likeness of my faded wife. It look'd upon me sadly, and withdrew. Such sights, 'tis said, betoken change and death. Attends the spæing hermit on our leisure. SEATON. He does, an't please your highness. MACBETH. Send him in. Seaton, how fares the queen? SEATON. Still worse and worse. The drousy poppy-draught has shut perception, But ven'mous dreams creep underneath the sleep, And sting her spirit as it fetter'd lies. MACBETH. Seaton, alas!—But send the culdee here. SCENE II. MACBETH. I would a little learn to know aright, The dark precursors and ill-boding forms, That make so wild my fated path of life. SCENE III. Macbeth and Baudron. MACBETH. Nearer Baudron.—People say that Nature Hath gifted thee with perspicatious sight, To ken beyond our general human range, The viewless mechanism of the world; That thou hast held familiar colloquy, With beings to our sense impalpable; And learnt from them the index of events, Far in the future and unknown of time. I would discourse at large on this awhile, And feed my fancy with thy mystic wisdom. BAUDRON. Your majesty confers great honour on me, But age, dread sir, is all my faculty; And that strange skill which rumour so proclaims, Is but the art of noting, meeting things, Fruit of a long variegated life. There is in nature, sir, no accidents. The boundless providential enginry Still moves harmonious; and the augur-signs Are but remote accordant parts, discern'd Without the wedded wheels and linking chains. For all the motions, in the frame of time, Proceed combin'd, and rise from one great spring. MACBETH. What are those influential energies, In their own nature substanceless, that take Corporeal semblance;—Fate's dread oracles, Who by the heralding of things to be, Create the purposes that give them birth? BAUDRON. These, sir, elude the grasp of our gross wits: They are like that occult intelligence Which stirs between the ocean and the moon, Known to exist by its effects alone. MACBETH. My dearest love! but wherefore come you here? Go to thy couch again. Sweet, how is this That thou dost wrap thyself so in the sheet?— Let me take from thee that sepulchral omen. BAUDRON. Whom did your majesty just now address? MACBETH. Saw you it not? BAUDRON. Saw what, my gracious lord? MACBETH. A gliding apparition of the queen. This is the second time it hath appear'd: Last night it came dress'd in her chamber robes, And gazing mournful on me, pass'd away; But now it show'd the grim gaunt look of death, And vanish'd, mantled in a winding sheet. BAUDRON. God save her majesty— MACBETH. What moves thee, Baudron? Such metaphysical phenomenæ Are sights to which my eyes have grown accustom'd; And I would know what is't that they foretoken. BAUDRON. Alas! the visions that amaze your highness, Are the conceits of melancholy lymphs, Mingled by nature in the glowing brain. MACBETH. But what do they portend? Interpret this: Say wherefore twice hath the wan effigy Of my perturbed, care-afflicted queen, Risen to view a pale untimely ghost. BAUDRON. It was her wraith. The unknown minister Who gives presentiment of coming woe, Alas! forewarns that she is doom'd to die. If it come thrice, call holy men around, And let your wordly legacies be made; For then the warding angel of your life Resigns the keep to all subduing death. The same day's sun that sees the queen a corpse, O mighty king! shall never set to thee. SCENE IV. MACBETH. He cows my spirit, like the midnight owl, The fatal prophet of the battlements, That in his airy cloister overhears The cloud-carr'd angels, hailing, as they pass On dismal purposes of destiny.— Oh what avails all regal exhibition, While fest'ring in my bosom lies, the guilt Of Duncan's blood, and Banquo's feller doom. The priestly benediction, and the oil, Nor all the ritual of the stone at Scoone Can charm my eyes to innocent repose. SCENE V. Lady and Macbeth. LADY. Macbeth, Macbeth, rid me of misery.— All things in nature have become adverse And daunt me out of life. The glorious sun, That sheds to all delight and lumination, Is the remembrancer of that dread dawn Which show'd us Duncan, murder'd by our hands, All horrible with his upbraiding gashes; The beauteous moon that makes black night so fair, With her chaste splendour as she climbs the sky, Still wears, at rising, that deep blush of shame, With which she look'd on Banquo's bleeding corse. The steller gems, the wakeful eyes of heav'n, Show as they shine that they kept Argus watch When we were busy at our midnight crime; If one but glance at me an eager look, The time has been when admiration pleas'd, I shrink appall'd, and trembling shun the gaze; The soothing phials of the doctor's skill, Beget suspicion, for they bring to mind The drugged wassail that seduc'd the grooms To leave their royal charge in fenceless sleep, To the foul carve of our ambitious waste; Yea, my own hands, though costly scents perfume, Are hateful by the old man's tainting blood; And thou thyself, my former love and pride, Art made so terrible by my remorse, That I am madly urg'd by wicked fiends, To think thy death would calm the hell that's here. MACBETH. What potent sorcery transmutes thy nature, Changing its high imperial arrogance Into this weak and timid phantasy? Rouse thee, dear wife, with that intrepid mind Which when I shrunk appall'd in my intents, Was wont by its courageous inspiration, To nerve my soul with valour like its own. LADY. Oh! it hath perish'd with the pageant hope That marshal'd my ambition. O'er my thoughts Tremendous fancies fall like chilling shadows On lonely spots by untold crimes accurs'd, And a dread vista opening in the tomb, Has shewn me horrors that dismay Despair To cling to life.—I would but dare not die. MACBETH. And come the apparitions to thee too? LADY. As I, enchanted by the poppy's drouze, Lay on my couch, me-thought time had relaps'd Back to that night on which we Duncan slew; And as I would have wash'd my bolter'd hands, Deep anguish pierc'd me, and in thought I died. Exposed a space upon the regal bier, The same on which, we falsely, sad adorn'd That good man's corpse; me-thought I was convey'd With dues of heraldry into the vault, Where all the royalty of Scotland rest, And plac'd, dread punishment! by Duncan's side. The requium finish'd and the herald done, The mouldy yawn of the sepulchre's gloom Was clos'd, and I, left to resolve to dust. MACBETH. Terrible state. LADY. Then did I hear around, The churm and chirruping of busy reptiles, At hideous banquet on the royal dead. Full soon, me-thought, the loathsome epicures, Came thick on me, and underneath my shrowd, I felt the many-foot and beetle creep; And on my breast, the cold worm coil and crawl. When all that was corporeal had resumed Its elemental essence, I became Lost in vacuity and silent gloom; A strange oblivion of sense, space, and time. Anon I heard a trumpet from afar, Swell with a sweet melodious invitation; And saw ascend, millions of radiant forms: Joyous they rose, and with them Duncan pass'd More glorious than the Indian gem. His breast Was ruby-stain'd, Macbeth! MACBETH. Our guilty mark! LADY. Again the trumpet sounded; but so shrill, So wild, so dissonant, so dread a shriek, That I in terror started from the tomb, And saw around me, all the wretched throng That wrought on earth, catastrophes of sin. Thou too wast there, but so, in form, transnatur'd, That, fear to see thee, broke the spell of sleep. Why stand you dumb, entranced in moody thought? MACBETH. The mind hath other vision than the eyes; They are but windows in its tenement.— Baudron is right, and these prospective sights, Are but the distant coming-round of things. LADY. What is't you mean? Believ'st thou in this dream? Shall we in death, lie conscious of the rot? MACBETH. Calm thyself, love—I have a culdee priest, A wond'rous man, whose years exceed the round Of a full century; and in his frame, The faded energy of life renewing, Puts forth a-fresh, the redolence of youth. He hath deep insight of this complex world, And knows the springs and pivots of events; Th'invisible pervaders that controul The secret lymphs which bear into the brain, Those drifting fancies, that industrious Reason Converts to schemes and knowledge practical;— All these are known to him. He is a man, A sage, of rare peculiar faculty, And will unfold to us, the pith of dreams, And that imperishable consciousness, Which wakes in sleep, and may in death survive. LADY. Shall we confess to him we kill'd the king, And mew contrition like two silly urchins, Sick with the surfeit of the pantry's spoil? MACBETH. My dearest partner of unhappy greatness!— LADY. Alas! Macbeth—but let us be ourselves, And strongly master this enthusiasm Look at that table—see where ranged appears The esculapian pageantry of death, And then survey my blanch'd and haggard form, Which, more than sickness, canker'd thought corrodes. With these before me, and with this at heart, I will wear boldly what I've dearly won: What is done, is; and though my restless couch Be nightly hideous with phantastic gorgons, Whose silent transit freeze me into death, I wake to royalty, and will exact The dues and reverence of our high estate. SCENE VI. Seaton, Macbeth, and Lady. SEATON. My gracious lord,—thick-coming messengers Announce the Southrons o'er the Firth advanced, Led by Macduff, the fiery thane of Fyfe, And headed by young Malcom. MACBETH. Let them come; Here, by the bulwarks of our castle safe And destiny impregnable, we scorn The shock and larum of approaching war, Till Birnam forest come to Dunsinane. SCENE VII. Macbeth and Lady. MACBETH. The times grow murky, and our star, dear love, Hath reached the zenith. Fate's malignant orbs Show baleful aspect in our horoscope, And fortune, e'er it wanes, dims with eclipse. Oh! we have found that every phase of fortune, From the first faint edge, to the round bright full, Marks the progression and the rise of care. LADY. These pallid fancies, better would become My dreamy couch, than the bold circumstance With which thou art assailed. Take courage thane; Rouse thee to war. Have not the weirds told, That as in panoply divine incas'd, Thou art invulnerable to the steel Of all of woman born? Assert thy fate. MACBETH. But I have lost the relish of renown, And that which made the plaudits of the world Richer than Music's voice, is mine no more. O curs'd ambition; in pursuit of thee, Thou unsubstantial iris of the brain, I have so far into the desert run, That all around me seems one blasted heath, And still the phantom lures to wilder wastes. LADY. Come, come, forbear; this idle wonderment— The dismal crimson that so coarsely glares In the mind's painting of our secret deeds, Time, with the mellowing varnish of success, May yet appease, and the admiring good Confess the merits of our great designs. I was not form'd of sterner mould than thou, Nor yields my couch a calmer sleep than thine; Yet will not I, in this great game of life, Spurn at the board because these shiftings vex me. No, no, Macbeth; we cannot now return; But on we must go—on, nor look behind: And when a smoother brighter height we gain, There plant those purposes of public weal Which shall protect us; and within their shade, Repose in honour, and lamented die. MACBETH. Yes: I will go, for I am pledged to it; And like the homeless outcast prostitute, Still heap the cairn of happiness with sins. SCENE VIII. Macbeth, Lady, and Baudron. MACBETH. How now is this, if thou canst see afar The forecast shadows of events, that thus The pamper'd Southrons, with the fierce Macduff, Invade our borders, and not I inform'd? BAUDRON. My gracious lord; such things particular, In the vague range of your old slave's dim knowledge, Have no precursor but the vulgar cry, Which long and loud hath rumour'd preparation. LADY. His boding then is like the raven's croak; A dismal gibber that but daunts the heart, Without instructing where the danger lies.— Send him away—we are ourselves, old man, Deep-read in this lugubrious lore of fancy. BAUDRON. Fain would I shun these honour'd conf'rences, But still his majesty commands me back. If 'tis your highness' will, let me retire; And in my lonely hazel-curtain'd cell, Forget the court in charity to man. O! holy Nature, thee I do acquit Of all the foul that stains thy minion here: How fair and nobly hast thou done thy part! How bright and glorious shines the gen'rous sun! How rich and soft earth's carpeting of flowers! How fresh and joyous to the corp'ral sense, The all-embracing dalliance of the air, Contrasted with the base device of courts, The dire cabal and mid-night work of blood. MACBETH. Traitor! what would'st thou? Darest thou jibe at us? LADY. Tut, my good lord, you do mistake the man. He spoke but in a fit of calenture, Th'impassion'd poetry of fond desire.— Baudron, at night, I would converse with thee, And learn the names by which to know the stars, That, glittering, course the ocean of the sky; And whence that radient messenger hath come, Which, nightly, in our zenith vault, is seen With unknown splendour, firing half the heavens. Till then, adieu.—Oh! shame to be so stirr'd.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. SCENE I. BAUDRON. The night advances to that horal bourn, Where touch the wheels of yesterday and morrow, And all the castle in defenceless sleep, Fetter'd lies prostrate. 'Tis the chosen time, When Rapine girds himself for enterprize; Treason harangues his sworn conspirators In dismal vaults, by torches darkly shown; And Murder grasping firm the gleaming knife, Stalks, with perturbed pace and soundless tread, To the devoted couch.—Macbeth's a-foot!— 'Tis hallow-eve, and annual on this night, Our youthful villagers, with rites and charms, And old traditionary oracles, Explore their destin'd boons of love and fortune. Some say, that licensed from an antient date, Th'imprison'd mischiefs roam at large to-night; And in the gay unguarded heart of youth, By juggling omens, raise perplexing thoughts, That ravel all their future thread of life. SCENE II. Lady and Baudron. LADY. Set down the lamp and wait without the door, To give me notice when the king returns. Have you heard, Baudron, what this wizzard is, Whom they have brought again to vex his highness? BAUDRON. A solemn knave, that tampers with men's fears. It grieves me much, that thus his majesty Should lose the bent of his great character In a mysterious passion to unfold The seeds and secrets of the time unknown. LADY. This mournful lapse in my dear lord's brave nature, While 'round the encompassing and trait'rous foes, Deepen their files, awakes in me such fears, That I could die for ease. Though I have felt The pangs of birth, a mother's sleepless cares, And watch'd my infant's couch with throbbing heart; Sweet was that watching, and those cares were gentle, And slight the pains to these I suffer now. Thou art, I think, a good man; old and wise, And much hast noted in this mazy world. Oh! can'st thou not instruct me to redeem Thy royal master from his cheerless bias, And to untwine the gnawing serpent here? BAUDRON. In camp, and council, and the earnest strife, Lie the true med'cine for the king's disease: But solitude and sights of human woe, And shelterless probation of distress, Only, can minister to your relief. LADY. I have a tower lav'd by the salt-sea waves, In whose horizon, never sail is seen, Save the lone ferry-boat in summer calms, Or stranded vessel in a winter's morn, With her dead crew all frozen to the masts. For such a place, so desolate and dread, I would forsake these gorgeous rooms, and barter The pomp and servitude around my throne, If I might taste the Lethé of repose. BAUDRON. Alas! great lady. LADY. Wherefore so do you pause, And sighing, wear a look so full of woe? Why kneel you thus so pale? Rise, Baudron! speak! BAUDRON. To gain that sweet oblivious bliss of sleep, Th'incumber'd spirit must unrobe itself Of all the garniture of royal pride, And pray Heav'ns mercy, as an alm, to grant The nightly down that eases daily toil. For the proud throne, in ashes you must sit; Change the rich crimson for a sack-cloth wrap; Cast from your brow its unblest ornament, The golden round, and radient type of power; Yea, on the cold and parent earth degraded, Confess the dismal secrets of your breast. LADY. Begone, old man: intruding prater, hence! SCENE III. LADY. Oh! shall I never know a calm again; But like the sea, urged by the charter'd storms, Bursting embarkments, still o'er pass my will In billowy violence of troubled thought. The old man, skilful, by Experience taught, Discerns my soul's conceal'd and cureless sore. But the afflicting cancer of remorse, Makes scarcely half my sum of misery. Macbeth, enchanted by his fatal credence In the prognostics of bewild'ring lore, Foregoes the occupation of a king, For uncouth riddles and phantastic orgies, Nor, with his wonted prescience, provides For the dire shock of England's feudal streams, Which flood the lowlands, to the Granpian's base; And, swelling with the torrents of our clans, Impetuous roll to insulate us here. What, if by such fore-dooming negligence, Young Malcom seize us in this last retreat, And cage us for an ignominious show, Like savages that feed on human carn! SCENE IV. Lady and Seaton. LADY. Seaton, what now? SEATON. The watch upon the hill, See, by the moon-light, thick-defiling spears Flick'ring among the boughs of Birnam wood. LADY. Hie to the king, and with some hasty speech, Say, I entreat his special presence here. SEATON. His majesty approaches. LADY. Then, retire. SCENE V. Macbeth and Lady. MACBETH. Be jocund, heart, good things await us still. 'Tis hallow-eve, and I have cast my fortune, Which a brave seer hath shrewdly scann'd, and found, Bating the vexing present's brief ordeal, Nought but presumptives of prosperity. LADY. Fye; be a man, and leave such idle search To cred'lous girls and boys professionless. Or, if you will in signs and omens deal, Survey the visible portents around. MACBETH. He has explained them all. The fiery star Whose nightly apparition, o'er our heads, Hath shed, of late, such fear into our hearts, He has convinced me, by astrology, Is the celestial swift-moving index Of our hot-headed and far-follow'd foe. LADY. The dreadest prodigy of all the time, Is the delusion that invests thy mind; And like a spell, denies thee power to thwart The rising adversaries of thy throne. E'en while our castle and its mountain base, Shake by the multitud'nous tramp of war, No stir of preparation yet is heard. All those fierce thanes, that favour'd our bold cause, Who, roused in time, would still have faithful stood; By this remissness from allegiance slip, And make their peace with Malcom as he comes. MACBETH. There's not a man of them that shall be spared. I'll taint the air, of the perfidious towns, With traitors limbs for these desertions. LADY. When? MACBETH. Ere Birnam forest come to Dunsinane. Beneath our walls, the English epicures Shall leave these curs that want the canine faith, To crouch before us; but to crouch in vain. LADY. Infatuated hold! nor with the vaunt Of wild mythologies and false predictions, Think to repel our stern antagonists. Know you, the watch upon the southern hill Decerns th'advance of bright-defiling spears, Glimm'ring behind the dark of Birnam wood, Like the portentous streamers in the sky? Awake, my thane, and shake thy drouze away; Summon the council, and with manly charge, Inspirit all that with our fortunes rank, And boldly as you won, maintain the crown. But I grow faint, and must to bed return. The fervid malady, kindled by care, Parching, makes head, and withers me to death. Damsels, without!—Good night, my dearest lord; Rouse thee to action.—Here; support me hence.— Come Hope, to him, though thou hast fled from me. SCENE VI. MACBETH. Spirit of valour, more than masculine, Whom nor disease, nor circumstance can daunt, But still when heaviest prest springs into strength, And with its native royalty dilates Still mightier than before.—Had I but men Temper'd to half her pitch of energy, The heav'ns might glare with prodigies of fire, And hell's grim demons on the clouds appear, In hideous panoply for Malcom's cause, Nor change the pride of my collected soul.— Who waits?—Send to me here the culdee priest.— If all things be in one great frame conjoined, The old man should by nat'ral symptom know The issue of this crisis in my fate. SCENE VII. Macbeth and Baudron. MACBETH. Thy look is weary, Baudron, and thine eyes Seem as if grief had meddled with thy rest. BAUDRON. My feeble rag of life can ill endure The perturbation that besets me here. These lengthen'd vigils prey upon my strength, And I have used the charter of old age Too freely, with her majesty, I fear. MACBETH. She will forgive thee—I will speak to her; And when this traitorous investment's o'er, Which circumscribes us to the castle here, Thou shalt have 'tendance and the softest down, To breathe in peace thy latter days away.— But tell me, Baudron, by what marks to know The fall and ebbing fortune of a king? BAUDRON. Then I must speak what prudence would conceal, And things relate of harsh ungrateful note To the sooth'd ear of flatter'd majesty. MACBETH. Fear not—my hearing has accustom'd grown To tidings of adversity; and I Can listen, to the worst that may befall, Calm as the swain that hears the fading leaves Whisp'ring that Winter hastens to disperse. BAUDRON. Alas! your highness hath already learnt The dismal knowledge of your own estate. The deep low discontents, throughout the land, Have long been murmuring prelude to the clang Of foreign war, which now so loudly dins The dirge and knell of your departed power. MACBETH. But I am safe the weird sisters said, Till Birnam wood shall come to Dunsinane; And by their greeting upon Forres moor, Have I not found that they predict the truth? Nature hath turns that in the plainest course Perplex our wisdom: and may I not hope, Who hath received such proof of special fate, That those sad signals which are wont to show Disast'rous change to others, shall to me Prove but precursors to a passing care? As night is harbinger to the gay morn, And boist'rous Winter heralds forth the Spring. SCENE VIII. Macbeth, Seaton, and Baudron. MACBETH. Well! what new chance hath so amaz'd thy wits, That they seem ready in thy straining eyes To leap from some great jeopardy? SEATON. My lord, The tartan'd Celts that from the western isles, And the fierce Donalds from Benevis' side, Who lay upon the heath, have left their ground, And with th'outrageous insolence of pipes, Are seen by all the wardens on the walls, Precipitously hurrying to the foe. MACBETH. Well, let them run; I little priz'd their faith. These mountain aborigines have been The stubbornest to tame, of all beneath The antient scepter of the scottish kings. This waste in loyalty smites the great arm Of royal vengeance with paralysis, And makes the tasks that press upon our time, Of heavy labour and uncertain fruit.— Seaton, why stand you here?— SEATON. I have but half The errand of my coming-in reported. MACBETH. What hast thou more? Who else deserts from us? SEATON. By urgent summons from the queen herself, The chieftains lodged within the keep attend Your highness' presence in the council-hall. MACBETH. We shall be there anon—Seaton command The armourer to have my mail prepared. SCENE IX. Macbeth and Baudron. MACBETH. My soul is kindling, Baudron, for the fight, And they who dare disturb the lion's den, Shall rue the boyhood that provokes his rage. I was a famous soldier in my day, And my heart leaps for this impending strife, As when the trumpet call'd me up to arms, On the proud dawn of battle. But I feel That eighteen years of vexing monarchy, Have cool'd the martial ardour in my heart, And the entanglement of crafty care Has long destroy'd the frankness of my youth. BAUDRON. Alas! dread sir, so is the course of life. There have been men that nature meant for heroes, So overborn by fortune's accidents, That at their exit from the world's great stage, Instead of plaudits, and the full resound Of admiration irresistible, They have been followed by the damning hiss, So ill and slovenly they did perform. MACBETH. Would I had still but a free soldier liv'd, And been unstain'd by any other blood Than the red trophy of my country's foes. BAUDRON. Why starts your majesty? MACBETH. See you not these? BAUDRON. Where? What? MACBETH. It is the selfsame heraldry With which the gentle Duncan was convey'd To the last mansion of the scottish kings! BAUDRON. I see it not—Alas my gracious lord!— MACBETH. What can this dismal pageantry betide? Another and another! still they come Solemnly marshall'd—ha! the sable bier! It stops—and see the sheeted dead thereon Doth raise itself. My wife!—'tis all away.— Baudron— BAUDRON. What would your highness? MACBETH. Good old man, To live so long and fear no sights like these. BAUDRON. My royal lord— MACBETH. Baudron, didst thou not say, That if the spectral vision of the queen Rose thrice before me, her decided death Should mine foretoken, on the selfsame day? Now thrice the airy semblance has appear'd, And this time with such charnel exhibition, That none may question what the sign portends. BAUDRON. The lonely shepherds in the isles forlorn, And pale enthusiasts bred in silent glens, Have oft by metaphysical discernment, Seen these sad shows, and verified the bode. SCENE X. Lady, Macbeth and Baudron. LADY. Macbeth! Why start you so aghast, my thane? Why touch you thus, and look to the old man? Thy cheek is ashy, and thy restless eye Denotes strange fear and doubt mysterious. MACBETH. Alas! the constancy of my sad mind Is put to dreadful proof. Around me rise Such prodigies and omens of dismay, That were my spirit fram'd of temper'd steel, And to the stroke invulnerably firm, I need must quake to witness what I see. LADY. I left him hopeful—tell me how is this? Hast thou been with thy priestly exhortation, Cowing the hope that he so much requires? MACBETH. Oh! there are things in this mirac'lous world, Which time, nor learning, never can explain. LADY. Good, good, my lord—but to the council come; Malignant Fortune wins by our default. This fatal sadness, that unmans you so, Would better suit the weak of my disease.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. SCENE I. LADY. Where may I shun this omnipresent horror That scares my every sense, and fills my soul. My shadow turns the monitor of guilt, And, pointing with its unsubstantial hand, Seems the precursor of avenging justice; While the shrill ring of arms, distributing To all the servants, sounds as awfully As the deep-tolling of a passing bell. SCENE II. Lady and Seaton. LADY. What now, good Seaton; what new ill hath chanc'd? SEATON. The wood of Birnam has begun to move. LADY. What says the king? SEATON. He was disturb with ire, That men should say a thing so wry to nature; Anon his choler fell, and he appear'd Like some prime merchant, who receives the news Of all his fortune perish'd in the waves. LADY. Alas, alas,—go, bid my maids attend. The fiery fever thrills through all my frame, And darts delirium to my tingling head. SCENE III. Macbeth and Lady. MACBETH. The wood of Birnam comes to Dunsinane! LADY. Art thou Macbeth, and wear'st these looks of fear, E'en while the men of Malcom, from thine eye, Hide their pale faces with the forest boughs? For such must be this daunting miracle. MACBETH. But they that did forewarn me of the sign, Bade me to dread no danger till it came. Behold it doth arrive. LADY. They warn'd thee well: But the prediction has been read amiss. We should have stood expecting fortune's change, And been so ripe in all the means of war, That Birnam forest, moving from its site, Should e'en have found our full matur'd array, Prepared for chances supernatural. But my enfeebled limbs foregoe their office, And to my couch I must again return. Go to thy men, and with thy wonted fire, Inflame their bosoms to th'accustom'd zeal. SCENE IV. MACBETH. Why should I, thus, be still the toy of fortune, While my own hand contains the means of riddance? This is the key that may unlock the door, And show me all the secret things of fate. But wherefore is it, that I dread its use? I, who so oft in pride of youthful blood, Have all the tumults of the battle dared, As 'twere, to force, outrageously, to enter The undiscover'd labyrinth of death, Though then I knew not this pursuing fear; Nor had incited, thus to hunt me down, The hungry vengeance of vindictive men. Oh! while so chased, am I afraid to fly, Since tarrying here, ensures a certain woe; And using this, will bear me safe away. To be imprison'd in this mortal cell, And know the boundless liberty without! To be so manacled, and yet to shrink From the short tingle of the setting free! Oh! to what cowardice the dross of flesh Degrades the noble element of man. Seaton, without; who waits, Seaton, I say? SCENE V. Macbeth and Seaton. MACBETH. What mean these acclamations from our men? SEATON. The enemy have thrown the branches down, And round the castle, show us all their war; Light-kindled spears and crests of waving plumes, Which your bold lieges on the walls and towers, Welcome with gay defiance. MACBETH. Hearts of gold! Give them my thanks. In their courageous note, I heard the voice of other times resound.— I'll wear to-day, the armour I had on, When, for my carve at the Dane's carnage feast, I gain'd new honour from the good king Duncan. Ha! will my every thought still turn on him, And each slight motion of long unfelt joy, But stir the wounds of guilty agony! SCENE VI. Baudron, Lady, and Macbeth. BAUDRON. O spare me, spare, dreadful majestic dame; Tremendous lady, spare my feeble life. MACBETH. Hold, dearest, hold: what would'st thou with this dagger? BAUDRON. Thou shalt in sulphur burn for sorcery. He holds cabals and traffickings accurst, With the malignants that make murk the mind; And doth suborn them to beset my couch, With bosoms smear'd, and visages all grim; Like dead men rising from their mid-night beds. MACBETH. Hast thou then, Baudron, pow'r with imps of ill? BAUDRON. My lord, my gracious lord; her highness' brain Yields to the fervour of the fever's rage. LADY. I feel his devilish conjurations work, Constraining me by terrible conceits, To crawl dishevel'd, like the eastern king, Whose locks were matted by the rain of heav'n. MACBETH. If thou hast cunning to concoct the thoughts To these persuasions, old man, stay not here; Hie thee to Malcom's camp, and there employ Thy subtile metaphysics to dismay. LADY. Look there, Macbeth, where his black art hath brought That pale, thin, meek, old, hoary king asleep, So like my father when I saw him die. Anon, anon, the spell doth work apace, And the botch'd bosom shows all foul with blood. Whose are these gory sacrilegious hands? One holds a dagger, and the other gropes, As 'twere, to find the corpse.—They are my own! SCENE VII. Baudron and Macbeth. BAUDRON. It is, my liege, the fume of the disease, Clouding like vapour her serene of mind: The sun of reason fails amidst the gloom. MACBETH. She was not wont to see these spectacles; And since thou hast been here, free friend with us, We have, such air-embodied horrors seen Rising before us, in the cheerful wake, Like incantations of the wizard Sleep, That day has grown as hideous as the night; And baleful Memory, witching nurse of Fancy, Mingling the caldron of perturbed care, Gives aspectable form to dreadest things. Again, I say, if thou hast wrought this change, Depart our threshold. But if thou art man, Stay; for the genius of thy antique lore, Is touch'd with mystery, so finely wild, That I could listen, had I leisure ease, Far rather to thy high hypothesis, Than to the cadence of the minstrel's song. SCENE VIII. Seaton, Macbeth, and Baudron. SEATON. My lord, the enemy move to the walls, Th'impetuous thane of Fyfe before the van, Waves his claymore, and urges to the gate. I saw him turn impatient as he came, And drag with fierceness, which brook'd no delay, The batt'ring engines, lab'ring up the steep. MACBETH. Let them come on, and all of woman born. My soul is kindling, and from every tower, We will such hurl of furious vengeance hail, In barbed shafts and missiles, wing'd with flame, That they shall rue their trait'rous appetite, To break the fold where majesty lies pent. SCENE IX. BAUDRON. Poor miscompounded, miscommissioned man, Enrich'd with valour and the heart's best ore, But so mixt up with fellest cruelty, As still to have affinity for ill. While I rejoice that, thus, the ruthless king, Whose scepter, grimly clutch'd, has made the land Quake to its utmost ocean-beaten cape, Already feels the retribution close, My bosom yearns afflicted for the man; As when a father mourns the dismal end Of his o'er-fondled, long-unchidden son. Ill-starr'd Macbeth! had destiny withheld Thy high enthusiasm from the sway Of thy arch-human wife, who, sternly proud, Amidst the storms of fortune and disease, Stands like a rock, around whose clouded head, Gleam fires from heav'n, while billows dash the base; Perchance, O hapless, to thy trophied name, The long processions of posterity Might have, admiring, look'd and pass'd improv'd. Hark! 'tis the engines thund'ring at the gates. SCENE X. Lady and Baudron. LADY. I will not, damsels, have the doctor more. Ha! coreless stump of age, how is't that thou Appear'st unshaken, while the royal trees Feel the rude lopping of the tempest's force? Again, again; the house itself grows craz'd, And by this dreadful batt'ring trembles all. Ye jerking vaults have ye turn'd traitors too? Down, down at once, incairn me while a queen, That I may 'scape the ignominious pelt Of rabble execration. 'Tis ours that shout! SCENE XI. Seaton, Lady, and Baudron. SEATON. The foe retires, for havoc, eagle-fang'd, Pounces resistless where the king appears, And none withstand the rage. Wounds to our men, Become, as 'twere, new energies to life. Their valour burns with an intenser heat, By the quick stirring of their fomen's steel. The king shall yet be king. LADY. —Did'st thou think else? What! had'st thou con'd in previous cogitation, The phrase and suppliancy meet to earn The base prolongment of thy cringing life? SEATON. I have, dread madam, ever faithful prov'd; Nor aught, that duteous service might desire, Has been neglected in my willing tasks. LADY. Rise from thy knees.—Alas! my troubled brain, With vague and fearful rumours all perplext, Betrays me often to forget myself. SCENE XII. Lady and Baudron. LADY. Can'st thou, old man, to changeful life inured, Teach me the art to keep in even flow, The method of my thoughts. I feel myself, Like one forced far by currents from the shore, In some small bark, that the great billows toss, On the white curling of their mighty mains;— No will of mine availing. BAUDRON. Happy they, Who as they toil along the flat low sands, To pick their pittance from the tide's refuse, Can see, unwishing to partake the voyage, The cheer'd departure of the gaudy ships, Whose swelling sails advance to meet the sun. LADY. Thy pale morality would better suit The meek dejection of a pining fair, That mourns her high-born lover's faithlessness, Than the stern grief of a devoted queen. I pray thee, Baudron, vex my heart no more. My fancies thicken as the tumults rise, And whirl in frantic eddies to despair. SCENE XIII. Lady, Macbeth, and Baudron. LADY. How now, Macbeth, what dost thou from thy post? Forth to the men; nor in thy fury slack, 'Till thou hast swept with iron besoming, The impeded course of our regality. MACBETH. My fate is verified. No man of them Withstands the flash and tempest of my sword. Back from the gates they all recoiling roll, A bloody rubbish: wounded, dead and dying, Lie heap'd a hideous pile. LADY. My valiant king! Back to the revels of grim Mars again, And gorge thy valour. MACBETH. Ah! my dearest love, I have, alas, encountered there a foe, More terrible than all of woman born; And ere again I breast the battles surge, I would hold parley with the old man here. LADY. Fye, fye, Macbeth, thou dalliest with our fate. MACBETH. I oft in childhood roamed the haunted glens, And heard the rustle of the bard-sung ghosts; In bolder youth, all lonely, I have scaled The windy summits of our wildest hills, And heard the whisp'ring of contriving sprites: But, nor in childhood, nor in pensive youth, Nor when the sisters on the blasted heath, With supernatural prediction hail'd; Nor all the spectral visions I have seen, By night, or noon, or in the witches' cave, Ere struck such chill into my daunted heart, As the creations of my guilt to-day. LADY. By what new goblin hast thou been amaz'd? MACBETH. Each wound I gave, seem'd Duncan's gash renew'd; Each groan I heard, sounded like his expire. Whene'er I turn'd, to praise my valiant men, In their brave exhibition, I discern'd Th'accusing semblance of the murder'd Banquo, As when he fought with me against the Dane. All the encrimson'd secrets of my life, Glar'd in my sight; and though to madness driv'n, I rush'd to meet destruction every where, The bolts flew harmless o'er my charmed head, And pointed spears fell blunted from my mail. Oh! that which promis'd me a safe long life, Inflicts more anguish than a thousand deaths. LADY. There is no remedy for us, Macbeth. MACBETH. Help, help; she dies!—fly, help—the doctor; fly. LADY. He has no lenitives for my disease; Nostrum nor simple can remove my pain. SCENE XIV. Seaton, Macbeth, and Lady. SEATON. My lord! my lord! Macduff has storm'd the gate! The men cry for you; and the rushing foes Fill all the court. MACBETH. Well, well, go save thyself. LADY. Art thou a king, Macbeth?—Stay not for me; I do begin to freshen and revive. Away my thane, and with the joyous news Of thy success recruit me.—Thane, away. SCENE XV. Lady and Baudron. LADY. What see'st thou, damsel, to look at me so? Give me some drink, some strong restorative. A clay-cold chill is creeping to my heart— Where the parch'd devil of the fever sits, And craves the cooling freshness. Give, O give.— But all the welling fountains of the hills, Cannot allay the deadly thirst that's here. BAUDRON. This wat'ry bev'rage slightly tinged with wine— LADY. Ha! wretch—'tis blood!— BAUDRON. Alas! they all have fled, In panic horror at the howl she gave, And left her, dreadful doom! to die alone.— Hither ye pale appall'd. This mighty dame, Is now as harmless as the sludge, that's cast From the brief trenchment of a baby's grave. SCENE XVI. Macbeth, Baudron, Seaton &amp;c. MACBETH. Come, stand apart, and let me look on her. Tears ill would suit the stern magnificence That should attend thy bier: such drops as these Red trickling from my sword, should fall for thee. For thou wast made of such courageous stuff, That the heroic when compar'd with thine, Prov'd minor metal form'd for meaner use. Yes, noble lady, thou hast died a queen; Invidious Fortune would have bent thee down, But thy undaunted spirit aw'd the fiend, And with triumphant royalty has left Its frail corporeal mantle as it rose, To rouse me to great things. Baudron thou said'st, That the same sun that saw the queen a corse, Would ne'er on me bestow a setting beam. Lo! there she lies!—And hark, the storm without Thunders prelusive to the dread finale. Fate do thy worst, I dare thee to the beard; Nor life, nor crown, nor victory, nor fame, Inspire my great intent. For death I fight; And will the black tremendous trophy gain, Ere this last consummating day be done. Pull down the royal standard from the tower, And in its stead unfurl the funeral pall; The ensign of my cause. To all adieu. Dull guestless mansion of my love farewell; I go to meet her, though it be in Hell! END.</field>
   </doc>
</add>