<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Burges, James Bland, Sir, 1752-1824</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Burges, James Bland, Sir, 1752-1824</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">burges james bland sir 1752 1824</field>
      <field name="author_text">Burges, James Bland, Sir, 1752-1824</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1810's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V2.0633.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1817</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460271</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Knight of Rhodes ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Knight of Rhodes ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="title_facet">knight of rhodes</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">knight of rhodes</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Knight of Rhodes ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="year_display">1817</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1817</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1817</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460271&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460271&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Burges, James Bland, Sir, 1752-1824&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;burges james bland sir 1752 1824&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Knight of Rhodes ; A Tragedy&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;knight of rhodes&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1817&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1817&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Burges, James Bland, Sir&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1752&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1824&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Knight of Rhodes&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for Edward Kerby [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1817&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872589-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv20633&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Knight of Rhodes&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 144 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Only verse drama included&lt;lb/&gt;Play reproduced elsewhere in English Verse Drama omitted&lt;lb/&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;lb/&gt;Preface included with The Knight of Rhodes&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: The Knight of Rhodes.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1817.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Unknown.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE KNIGHT OF RHODES. A TRAGEDY.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Periculosæ plenum opus aleæ Tractas: et incedis per ignes Suppositos cineri doloso. HORACE.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">TO THE READER. Of the Dramas contained in these volumes, two, namely, Riches, and Tricks upon Travellers, have been acted, and only the former of these was published. The terms of Mr. Arnold's licence being restricted to the performance of Operas at the Lyceum Theatre, the author found himself under the necessity of introducing into his comedy of Tricks upon Travellers the prescribed number of songs; but as they did not please himself, he was apprehensive they might not, when stript of their musical accompaniments, prove more satisfactory to others: he therefore declined the immediate publication of the piece, and he now brings it forward as it was originally written. The six remaining Dramas are entirely new, and as such are submitted to the indulgence of the Public.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DRAMATIS PERSONÆ. Villiers, Grand-Master of Rhodes. Damaral, Knight. Almeida, Knight. Davila, Knight. Raymond, Knight. Garcias, Knight. Du Mesnil, Knight. Hali, A Turkish Captive. Omar, Envoy from the Turkish General. Ismena, A Turkish Captive.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Scene—Rhodes.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Time—During the Siege of Rhodes, by Mustapha, General of Soliman II, in the year 1521.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. SCENE I. A public Place in Rhodes. Enter a Mob, some crying “a Villiers,” others “a Damaral.” To them enter Garcias. GARCIAS. What mean these clamours? Wherefore throng ye thus, When proclamation has been made that all Should keep good order, and not bar the way Through which, when past th'election, our Grand-Master Must with his noble cavalcade proceed? Hence! and take heed to observe strict discipline. [Exit Mob. Enter Raymond. Raymond! What tidings? RAYMOND. All hath ended rightly. Though still beleaguer'd closely by the Turk, Our Order still though menac'd with destruction, We now may confidently 'wait the issue. Th'election falls on Villiers. GARCIAS. Heav'n be thank'd! He is a gallant and a courteous knight, Whose valour and experience yet may save us. But say, good Raymond, how did his opponent, The haughty Damaral, bear his disappointment? RAYMOND. As such a spirit, so untamable, So fill'd with high and arrogant pretensions, Might bear th'extinction of his cherish'd hope. Soon as the herald had announc'd the name Of Villiers as the sov'reign of our Order, He cast a look of stern disdain around, And, while our knights proceeded to enthrone And swear allegiance to our new Grand-Master, He proudly turn'd away, and left the temple. (A trumpet sounds. But hark! We must be gone—that trumpet's voice Warns us 'tis time to join the grand procession, Which to his palace must escort the prince. Let us away—we have no time to lose. [Exeunt. Enter Damaral and Almeida. DAMARAL. Talk not to me of patience! Try no more To sooth by argument my spirit wounded Past all endurance!—Am I thus repaid For all my services?—Ungrateful Rhodes! Have I, when others wanton'd in the lap Of idle peace, for thee, untir'd, sustain'd War's harsh aggression; have I, undismay'd, Dar'd the rude ocean when the tempest rag'd, And, reckless of my life, led on our host To fame and vict'ry, to be slighted thus? ALMEIDA. Well hast thou prov'd thyself a worthy knight: Yet, when the choice could fall on one alone— DAMARAL. And why not I that one?—Look to our archives, Say, if among our Order's bravest champions There stand a name than Damaral's more renown'd? Ask the proud Turks who e'er like him could face them? They will do justice to my high deserts, Which those who profit by them have forgotten. ALMEIDA. No, Damaral! no; they ne'er can be forgotten. We, who have witness'd all thy brave exploits, Do ample justice— DAMARAL. Yes! You pass me by, You treat me with neglect, degrade me lower Than him whom court intrigues, not warlike service, Have dragg'd to notice. Yet you talk of justice! ALMEIDA. Though upon Villiers th'election fall— DAMARAL. On Villiers!—him!—As well may'st thou attempt To tell me, that a weak and puling sea-boy Can steer our gallies through th'Ægean gulf, When the south wind tears up its foaming waves! ALMEIDA. Thou dost but wrong thyself and thy deserts, Thus to inveigh against another's worth. Think on the perils which encircle us: The Turks with toil incessant urge the siege, Each day they gain advantage over us, While Europe's princes fail to send us succour. DAMARAL. Think on our perils? Little boots reflection, When thus our means of safety are abandon'd. Let those provide against them, who presume In danger's hour our tott'ring state to guide. I rule not here in Rhodes: one, doubtless far More worthy of pre-eminence, is chosen, Who can employ those arts my stubborn nature Rejects with proud disdain. Let him see to it. ALMEIDA. This is no time for querulous complaint, For nursing idle jealousies and feuds, When danger presses and demands our swords. But hark! The echoing trumpet's note proclaims The installation of our chief is over, And that in state, attended by his knights, He this way comes. DAMARAL. Let him—I will not shun him— I'll meet him here. ALMEIDA. Nay, prithee stand aside. Leave him free passage. DAMARAL. Be it as thoud'st have it. Now mark—behold—the proud procession comes. (A martial symphony. Procession of Grand-Master and Knights, who file off on each side of the stage. Raymond and Davila advance. Damaral and Almeida stand aside.) VILLIERS. Thanks, brave companions! Since your favouring voices Have thus exalted me beyond my hopes, Far, far indeed beyond my wish!—For who, When adverse fortune low'rs, would court pre-eminence? My best ambition shall be to maintain Your fair opinion, and deserve your sanction. RAYMOND. Had we not known thy worth, had not experience Borne ample witness to thy zeal and honour, We had not fix'd on thee. Many are brave, Many are active, provident and wise; But one so deck'd with all the qualities Adapted to our present exigence, As him on whom our Order's choice has fall'n, We know not. DAVILA. Happy is indeed the choice, And most in this, that, by selecting thee, We 'scape the pride and tyranny of Damaral. VILLIERS. Good Davila, forbear! The knight you speak of Is a renown'd and gallant gentleman, In whom the virtues of our Order beam With more than common lustre. DAVILA. Aye—he's valiant; But rash, imperious, haughty— DAMARAL (advancing). Is it thus Thou dar'st traduce an absent warrior's name? VILLIERS. Illustrious Damaral! Do not let the day, Which our religion bids us reckon holy, Be tarnish'd by dissention. He did ill To derogate from thy establish'd fame. DAMARAL. For him, I heed but little what he says: The censure or approval of a boy Touch not my reputation—(to Davila)—murmur'st thou? VILLIERS. Cease—nor presume to urge this question farther. Retire, young knight!—You, noble Damaral! Heed not His hasty words. If, at the present moment, I could repine at my unsought-for honours, 'Twould be that partial suffrages have deck'd me With those distinctions which were more thy due. DAMARAL. That is a point we need not now discuss.— Thou'rt chosen. VILLIERS. Credit me, we do thee justice. We've all been witnesses of thy desert, And speak no more than truth, when we confess Our Order's safety, Rhodes's self, depend On thy experienc'd worth. I've known thee long, And would deserve thy friendship. DAMARAL. Friendship, say'st thou? VILLIERS. Did I respect thee less, I would not thus Solicit thy regard. And why in vain— DAMARAL. 'Twere better not to ask.—I cannot palter, And chaffer civil speeches.—'Tis enough— Enter Garcias (hastily). GARCIAS. Joy to our noble chieftain! May th'event I come t'announce be a propitious omen! Scarce had'st thou left the temple, when approaching We saw Du Mesnil's galley, follow'd close By a brave prize, from whose high topmast wav'd Our Order's ensign, while, beneath, the crescent, In token of subjection, humbly droop'd. She seems a carrack of no mean account. E'en now triumphantly they reach the port; (Shouts.) And hark! fresh shouts of exultation tell Th'arrival of the victor. Enter Du Mesnil, Hali, Ismena, and other Turkish Captives. VILLIERS. Brave Du Mesnil! Thrice welcome is thy presence. On the day, When the free voices of my brother knights Have call'd me to a station full of peril, To see thee thus victorious is a pledge Of future triumphs. DU MESNIL. May each enterprize, Which thou shalt plan, be crown'd with equal fortune, As that which by heav'n's guidance we achiev'd. VILLIERS. Thanks, gallant friend! Say, whence and what thy prize? DU MESNIL. As off the Samian coast I held my cruize, This vessel I espied. I gave her chase, O'ertook and captur'd her. Of those on board None seem of estimation, save this maiden, Who, if report speak truly of her charms, In grace and beauty far transcends her sex. I have respected her too much, to say If rumour do her justice; but behold her, Veil'd as she was when she became my captive. VILLIERS. Damsel! though chance hath thrown thee on our mercy, Here art thou safe. If our respectful service Can mitigate captivity, command it. ISMENA (unveiling). Heroic lords of this renowned isle, Whose valour still withstands the mighty pow'r Of our imperial Sultan, take my thanks! Your slave, to freedom, friends and country lost, Hath nothing else to offer. DAMARAL (aside). What rare beauty! (To Almeida) Didst thou e'er witness such perfection? ALMEIDA. Never— Whate'er of charms can dignify the sex Seem in her form assembled. VILLIERS. By my life, 'Twill put his knightly honour to the proof, Who takes the charge of beauty so alluring. I covet not the task. DAVILA. It were, in truth, A service of more peril, than to face Whole legions of her countrymen in arms. VILLIERS (to Damaral). How say you, noble sir! You are not apt To shrink from danger. DAMARAL. No! In flood or field I court the post of danger.—But why turn Your question upon me?—Am I a man Fit for this courtly function? VILLIERS. If the function Be that of honour, who so fit as Damaral?— Now tell me, thou, (to Hali) that stand'st beside the fair, What is thy name, thy station and degree? HALI. My name is Hali. I was sent in charge Of this fair damsel on my way tow'rds Cyprus, By the command of my imperial master, The Sultan Soliman, there to espouse her To the illustrious Selim, who now mourns The sad detention of his lovely bride, Ismena, now your captive. VILLIERS. Noble lady! We war not with the fair, and, though proscrib'd From marriage, venerate its sacred rights. I will intrust thee to a loyal knight, Whose high command thy safety shall insure, And in whose courtesy thou may'st confide. If noble Damaral would accept the charge— DAMARAL. What mean'st thou? I accept? VILLIERS. Nay, take me right. How can a soldier's mistress be more safe, Than in a soldier's care?—Give me thine ear. [Villiers and Damaral retire. HALI (aside to Ismena). Mark how good fortune meets us! This is happy Beyond our fondest hope. Now spread your snares, T'entrap the heart of that audacious Christian, That Damaral, our Sultan's direst foe. ISMENA. He seems a gallant gentleman. HALI. He's that, Which we must mould and model to our purpose— A headstrong, fev'rish fool. I know him well, And to my cost: so that he know not me, All shall be right. ISMENA. How dignified his mien! His air how noble! HALI. Why dost gaze upon him? Thou heed'st me not.—'Tis the eventful moment, Which must be seiz'd at once, or lost for ever. See—they advance.—Now give your lures their scope. VILLIERS. Beauteous Ismena! I have urg'd a suit, In which thy happy star has been propitious; And now into the hands of this brave knight, Than whom our Rhodian Order cannot boast One of more noble bearing, I commend thee. And now farewell awhile—my duty calls me. Du Mesnil! lead us to the port; we long To view the prize thy gallantry has won. [Exeunt Villiers and train. Manent Damaral, Hali, Almeida, and Ismena. DAMARAL (to himself). So young, so paramount in ev'ry beauty Which can adorn her sex? To me intrusted? And why to me? Why am I singled forth? This pref'rence seems suspicious.—Ho! Almeida!— See'st thou what mighty honours fall upon me? Is it not high command, and glorious service, To wait upon that beauteous piece of mischief, To minister as her caprice may dictate, And play th' obsequious keeper to a minion, Whose spells and witchcrafts might ensnare a hermit? Wilt not become me, think'st thou? ALMEIDA. I must wonder That passion should thy better judgment cloud. Had our new chief to thee preferr'd another, Then might'st thou have complain'd; but when he chose thee— DAMARAL. Doubtless he had his reasons—aye, and strong ones. He hath o'er-topt me. In the face of Rhodes, Nay of all Christendom, he tow'rs above me, And the first fruits of his ambitious growth Are pois'nous to mine honour. ALMEIDA. Nay, my lord! I pray you be more just.—Think not thus of him. DAMARAL. What other thoughts should occupy my soul, Than the subversion of my fondest hope, The ruin of my fame— ALMEIDA. No more of this. See where the damsel, whom thou hast in charge, With downcast eye thy courtesy awaits. Her patient suff'rance and unrivall'd charms— DAMARAL. I note them but too well. In ev'ry glance Temptation ambush'd lurks, each gesture teems With sorcery. In the fair field of war I heed not peril; 'tis familiar to me— Here I'm a coward.—Take her to my palace, Treat her with all thy wonted courtesy, But let me not behold her. HALI (aside to Ismena). Mark! he's going— ISMENA. My patron! my protector! will you leave me? I thought I was intrusted to your charge. Was I accepted only to be scorn'd, And thrown aside as one not worth a thought? DAMARAL. Detain me not, I pray.—I've giv'n full order For all that may befit thee. Ask—command— Thy pleasure shall be absolute in all. But I must hence; the pressure of the time Requires me.—Nay—I pray thee look not thus— Be of good cheer. ISMENA. I would thou couldst remain! I'm little us'd to supplicate for pity; 'Till now I never sued— DAMARAL (aside). I'm lost for ever, If she look so upon me!—(to Ismena)—speak not thus— My palace, wealth, and those who own my sway, Are thine—command them as thou wilt, but let me Not linger here.—Almeida, to thy charge! HALI (aside). Now's the decisive moment. Follow up Thy 'vantage, and the victory will be ours. ISMENA. What? Go'st thou? Then am I despis'd indeed! Is this the gallantry of Christian warriors? When I arrive in Cyprus, if they ask me How captive ladies are receiv'd in Rhodes, When Damaral, the noblest, bravest, best Of all his knightly Order treats me thus, What shall I say? DAMARAL. Tell them that Damaral, Who never fled from battle, fled from thee. ISMENA. What can you see in me that you should fly from? The conqu'ring crescent flames not on my brow. A harmless captive, what can I devise? What mischief can you apprehend from me? DAMARAL. Infinite mischief!—Thou art much too fair, And I too sensible of beauty's pow'r. I would possess myself; for I am thrown Far in the rear of fortune, and have need Of all my constancy. But that is lost, When I converse with thee. ISMENA. If you require it, I will be silent; nothing will I do, Nothing will meditate, that may disturb Or check your efforts in your country's cause. Go forth to combat; bathe your conqu'ring sword In Turkish blood: I'll call no curses down, I'll not invoke our Prophet to avenge The widows and the orphans you have made. DAMARAL. Why now it is you shew me all my danger. 'Tis the sweet flatt'ry of those 'witching lips, The love-inspiring lustre of those eyes, That give th' alarm to honour.—Be content— I trust thee to a friend of tried discretion. ISMENA. Alas! your kindness might have sooth'd the sorrows Of a sad captive cast upon your bounty. You're doubtless noble; but there is a virtue Of which you cannot boast, and that is pity. Hadst thou been brought a pris'ner to my country, And to my charge intrusted, I had not To delegated care abandon'd thee. DAMARAL. Say'st thou?—I see resistance is in vain— I am the captive—we exchange conditions— You have prevail'd—I serve, and you command. Almeida! let the guard conduct us on. Those who are here attending, and all others, Whose services Ismena may require, Must be allow'd admission to her presence. Come on, fair lady! I've no will but thine. [Exeunt. END OF ACT I.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. SCENE I. An Apartment in Damaral's Palace. Enter Hali and Almeida. HALI. Thy friend hath here a princely residence, Well decorated, as becomes his wealth. Those who, like him, are wont to plough the main, Reap noble harvests. ALMEIDA. Fortune hath in this Rewarded his exertions: had she prov'd Not less propitious to his other claims, His noted valour and unrivall'd fame Might have exalted him to sov'reign rule. But I must leave thee. Here, I pray, remain. My duties call me. [Exit Almeida. HALI. Fortune, I'm thy debtor! To be committed thus to Damaral's charge, In his own house receiv'd—and then that all Remembrance should be blotted from his mind Of me, whose once aspiring hopes he crush'd— It is most strange. But I forget not thus. No—deep engrav'd in my avenging soul The keen remembrance of my wrongs remains. Once, like himself, beneath the Rhodian banner I courted fortune; honour, wealth, and fame Invited my ambition, when this Damaral, Whose overbearing spirit ne'er could brook The breach of his injunction, in the face Of our assembled host degraded me, Blasted my rising hopes, and left me nought To sooth my pangs but hatred and revenge. They are become congenial to my soul: For them I sought the Turk, for them forsook The country and religion of my fathers. By him, whose faith I now profess to bear, I'll make him render a severe account. I have that with me, which, if rightly us'd, Shall hurl him from his height.—But soft—behold him. Enter Damaral and Ismena. DAMARAL. Within these walls, which own me as their master, Command, fair lady! ISMENA. Thanks, my gracious lord! Thou'rt far too bounteous.—Hali! join with me To pay that tribute, which beneficence Exacts from grateful hearts. HALI. On the behalf Of princely Soliman, I thank thee. DAMARAL. Hold— Thanks are superfluous. Let us have no more. Lady, I pray thee take me as I am, A plain, blunt soldier. While beneath this roof, Nought shall be wanting to thy fair reception. ISMENA. My wants are few, and those thy kind attentions Amply provide for. DAMARAL. Wouldst thou choose to have Thy guardian Hali still attendant on thee? ISMENA. If such thy pleasure. I have known him long, And ever found him worthy. He is now The only friend I have. DAMARAL. Not so, fair lady. Though rough, and all unus'd to courtly fashions, We can appreciate excellence like thine, And pay the homage which is most thy due. Retain thy charge, good Hali—(to Ismena)—nay, no thanks. I am thy debtor, lady, for th' occasion Of proving my obedience to thy wishes. But, if it please thee, let us to th' apartment Destin'd for thy reception. Come, good Hali, We shall require thine aid for such arrangements As may be fitting for thy lovely mistress. A soldier's followers are not us'd to wait On guests like her.—Permit me to conduct thee. [Exeunt. SCENE II. Grand-Master's Palace. Enter Villiers, Raymond, and Davila. VILLIERS. Have all our posts been duly visited? These are no times for ease and self-indulgence, When the proud Ottoman, beleagu'ring close, Threatens th'immediate downfal of our state. RAYMOND. All has been done that vigilance can do. Yet surely now unequal grows our contest— VILLIERS. That thought should urge us on to fresh exertions. As Christian knights, we should prepare to meet The will of heav'n. (Trumpet sounds. What means that loud appeal? Go forth, good Raymond, and demand the cause. [Exit Raymond. DAVILA. It sounded like a parley. What can move The Turk, who hitherto hath seem'd t'avoid All intercourse, save that of ruthless war, Thus to solicit audience? Enter Raymond. RAYMOND. From the foe An envoy seeks admission to thy presence. VILLIERS. Conduct him hither straight. [Exit Raymond. Whate'er his mission, Friendly or hostile, we're for both prepar'd. Enter Raymond and Omar. VILLIERS. Approach, and freely speak. OMAR. Illustrious chief! From Mustapha, the delegate of him, Who, drawing from the Prophet his descent, His sceptre wields, I greet thee. He hath learnt That in a bark of war, to Cyprus bound And captur'd by a galley of your Order, A damsel, to the governor betroth'd, Is made a pris'ner. As by knighthood's rules Both she and her attendants are exempt From war's stern stricture, so, our Gen'ral trusts, Thou wilt on just conditions yield them up. VILLIERS. Well hast thou said, that not with helpless females Our Order wages war. Thus far believe: While here the object of your suit sojourns, She shall with fitting courtesy be treated. Say, on what terms doth Mustapha propose We should accord the captive maid's release? OMAR. Either such ransom as thou may'st require, Or adequate exchange of such as chance Hath made his pris'ners. VILLIERS. Should we grant your suit, We shall disdain to barter her for gold: But for a knight—for such, alas! there are, Whom, in despite of valour, fate compels To bear his fetters—if he will to exchange her— OMAR. 'Tis not our usage, when a knight is captiv'd, On any terms his liberty to grant: Yet doth our chief so highly prize Ismena, He may for once dispense with rigid rules, And listen to your proffer. VILLIERS. That were well, And worthy of himself. But say, dost think, Were we to grant the boon he now demands, And, on this basis, for th'exchange to treat Of all whom war, on either side, hath thrown Into captivity—dost think, I say, He would concede a truce, 'till we might bring Our treaty to conclusion? 'Twere most worthy To soften thus th'asperities of war. OMAR. Send forth, and make your proffer; I, meanwhile, Will here remain, a hostage for the safety Of him whom ye employ. VILLIERS. 'Tis fairly said. Give us short space thy proffer to discuss, And thou shalt know our purpose. Here, meantime, Abide on our good faith. OMAR. There is one Hali, Who hath the charge of fair Ismena. Might I, By your permission, hold short parlance with him, I might impart to him some brief instructions, Which Mustapha, on knowledge of her fate, Fram'd for the better guidance of her conduct. VILLIERS. Thy boon is granted. Raymond! see thou giv'st him Such conduct as befits both him and us; And let the valiant Damaral have due notice, As it behoves, of what has now occurr'd. [Exeunt severally. SCENE III. Apartment in Damaral's Palace. Enter Ismena and Hali. HALI. So—our plot works. Thou'st bravely play'd thy part. ISMENA. Would it were one more worthy and becoming! There's something in this man, that pleads against The dark contrivance form'd for his undoing. He has a noble nature, richly stor'd With rare heroic qualities. 'Tis pity To turn them thus against him, and pervert Heav'n's choice endowments to a guilty purpose. HALI. 'Tis not for us, the slaves of Soliman, To scan the merits of our destin'd victim, To whom this isle, which long hath been esteem'd The bulwark of the Christian potentates, Now looks for safety 'gainst the pow'rful force Commission'd to reduce it. While he heads The practis'd militants who form his Order, Doubtful must prove the conflict: he remov'd, On yon proud ramparts shall our standard wave— ISMENA. Hush!—see, he comes— Enter Damaral. HALI. Welcome again, my lord. We spoke of thy exceeding bounty tow'rds us, So delicate, so dignified. Believe My mistress is most thankful. DAMARAL. Had it pleas'd My wayward fate to place me in the station, Which, without boasting, I might well have fill'd, I could have giv'n thee, lady, other greeting. As 'tis—but this is not a theme which suits Th'occasion. HALI. Pardon me—it is a theme Which suits thee but too well. DAMARAL. There was indeed A time, when I expected the fulfilment Of my long cherish'd hopes. But that is past. HALI. 'Tis ever so. From those, whom our exertions Have aided in the perilous hour of action, If we require return, ingratitude Mars expectation. Brave and gen'rous foes Appreciate best the worth by which they suffer. They nurse no jealousy, they have no motives— DAMARAL. How's this? Methinks thy boldness— ISMENA. Chide him not— He speaks but truth. Ere we Byzantium left, The rumour of Carette's decease was spread, And on the choice of a new Rhodian chief The thoughts of Soliman were turn'd. I've heard him Discuss the merits of the diff'rent knights, On whom he thought the Order's choice might fall. He did full justice to thy worth: but had he Known thee as I do, could he but have witness'd Thy gen'rous courtesy— DAMARAL. From other lips Such praise were hateful. I have nothing done To merit thy approval. Try me farther, Devise occasions to call forth my zeal— ISMENA. I know the fame thou hast acquir'd in arms, But little did I think to find thee thus, Combining knightly worth with courtly grace. DAMARAL. Fie! thou'rt a flatt'rer—I've no graces, I— Rude as the boist'rous element I roam, I cannot play the courtier. I can feel, And plainly speak the dictates of my heart. ISMENA. Ah! could but those, who seek to gain our favour, Know how superior to their flimsy arts Sincerity and manly candour shew, They'd speak and act like thee. I love plain dealing. DAMARAL. Thou art in all superior to thy sex. I have not been a stranger to their charms, But, on the faith and honour of a soldier Who scorns deception, never saw I yet Beauties like thine, which touch at once the sense, And with soft bondage captivate the soul. ISMENA. Oh speak not thus! Hast thou so soon forgotten With what design I bent my course to Cyprus? Hast thou? Alas! I had myself forgotten. DAMARAL. Forgotten, say'st thou? And didst thou forget it? To Cyprus?—Selim?—Aye, 'twas so—by heav'n! It cannot, must not be— ISMENA. Ah! cease, my lord— I must not hear thee. Had I been convey'd At once to Cyprus, had I never known thee, Ne'er felt thy kindness, my unpractis'd heart Had haply not rebell'd against its fate. As 'tis—I do beseech you pardon me. (Going. DAMARAL. Ah! go not thus away, nor coldly check The gen'rous dictates of thy feeling breast— ISMENA. I may not answer—cannot, dare not hear thee— I know not what I say—the heart will feel— The tongue will wander—stay me not I pray— Had I but known thee ere my fate was fix'd— What is't I've said?—Oh! think not harshly of me— Farewell—I go to be again myself. [Exit. DAMARAL. Am I myself? My better half seems gone When she departs. HALI. My gracious lord seems mov'd. DAMARAL. Who can unmov'd perfection's self behold? HALI. That she's most fair is true; yet her pure mind Transcends her outward charms. She has a heart, Gentle, affectionate; tumultuous passion As yet ne'er made it throb: he, who shall gain it, Shall gain a treasure richer than the crown Of Asia's sovereign. DAMARAL. I believe thee truly— So rare a creature were indeed a treasure Monarchs might envy. Would it were my lot! HALI. Whose could it be who would so well deserve it? Fam'd as thou art beyond all Christian knights, She of all peerless maids Byzantium boasts The sweetest paragon of loveliness— By heav'n! the union of such excellence Must in the book of fate have been predestin'd.— Nay, my good lord, I pray thee give me hearing. Hath not some secret guidance hither led her? Is she not here an inmate?—There is more In this than merely chance could have produc'd. DAMARAL. 'Tis, as thou sayst.—But would'st thou have me think— HALI. I know not what it is thou may'st not think. My thoughts are busy. 'Tis not in thy nature To prove insensible of charms like her's, And as for her, whose heart ne'er own'd the sway Of am'rous passion, how can she withstand Attractions such as thine? DAMARAL. As mine?—No, no! She ne'er would think of me—my bloom is past— I lack the courtly elegance that wins The favour of her sex! HALI. Thou may'st not be In life's first spring: unlike our pamper'd youth, The hour of action thou hast not consum'd In idle dalliance. What of that? Thy fame, Thy feats in war, the glorious scars thou bearest, Will often weigh in female bosoms more Than their trim graces. When you spoke, methought No common feelings mov'd her. Mark'd you not How came and went her colour? I ne'er saw her Affected thus. DAMARAL. I noted a confusion— But I had no concern— HALI. I know not that. She is a woman; women have quick eyes, And make a juster estimate of men, Than men do of themselves. I should not wonder If she were mov'd, when she convers'd with one, Whose signal worth she had so long been taught T'admire and venerate. DAMARAL. Knew she aught of me? HALI. Oft have we talk'd of thy illustrious deeds, And oft thy gallantry provok'd her praise. 'Twas, I remember, on the fatal day, When to Byzantium the report arriv'd Of the surpassing victory thou hadst gain'd Over the Turkish fleet on Cyprus' shore— DAMARAL. Yes! 'twas my doing—yet I'm now pass'd over, While Villiers—but it matters not—proceed. HALI. 'Tis strange—I crave thy pardon for my boldness— 'Tis surely strange that those, who might appreciate Thy services, should thus repay a deed— DAMARAL. Enough—I know not how we've wander'd thus. Thou spok'st of fair Ismena's partial judgment. HALI. 'Tis true. As of thy prowess we discours'd, She with uplifted eyes remain'd awhile As if in silent transport, then on the sudden She cried, “what godlike valour! Oh that Selim “Were but renown'd like him, then would Ismena “Fly to his conqu'ring arms and wed his glory!” DAMARAL. Did she say that?—It may—yet 'tis not likely She should so quickly feel a soft impression. HALI. 'Tis not unlikely for a maid like her. She is not one whom practice of the world Hath caution taught. Secluded from all converse, Like a poor bird, confin'd within its cage, She sigh'd for freedom; from whatever hand The boon might come, 'twould have been acceptable. Now, set at large, she finds she has a heart, She feels it glow, she hails its gen'rous impulse, And gives it to a corresponding spirit, Attun'd to love, and worthy of the blessing. DAMARAL. I would I might believe thee. HALI. Good my lord, My life for your's 'tis so. I've known her long, And cannot be deceiv'd. Her ev'ry look Betray'd her secret passion—speak to her— Judge for thyself— DAMARAL. Thou'st set my soul on fire— But was she not intrusted to my charge, A soldier's mistress to a soldier's care? 'Twas so—it may not be. HALI. It might not be, Were he her choice or worthy to possess her. But such is not her fate. She knows him not, Nor, did she know him, would her gentle heart Own him its master. By the Sultan's pow'r Consign'd to the stern sway of one, more fit To call her daughter than to hail her bride, Think what a fate is her's! Did she not weep When we discours'd of Cyprus? Own'd she not That when she look'd on thee she had forgotten— DAMARAL. She did—she did— HALI. Why disbelieve her then? Why hesitate at once to know thy bliss? The foeman's sword could never keep thee back: Let not the smiles of willing beauty daunt thee. Come, come, my lord—let's have no further parly; Fortune befriends the bold, and love rewards them! [Exeunt. END OF ACT II.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. SCENE I. Damaral's Palace. Enter Hali. HALI. The lark, when high in his aërial flight, Arrested by the practis'd fowler's voice, Will sink unconscious of the fatal net Spread for his ruin. Not a beast that ranges In licens'd freedom the wild wilderness But may be trammell'd by the hunter's art: And man, imperious man, who thus subdues All meaner natures, let a bait be offer'd Of pow'r to tempt his wayward appetite, Sinks from his fancied eminence, and falls The poor degraded victim of temptation. The haughty Damaral himself, that hero, That demi-god, he whose resistless sword Spread through the Turkish legions wide dismay, Caught by a wanton female's vain allurements, Bows to her sway, and supplicates for ruin. 'Tis ready for him—the deep mine is charg'd, And nought is wanting but the needful hand To apply the match.—Would Omar but arrive To second my bold effort— Enter Almeida. ALMEIDA. Hast thou heard One Omar, envoy from the Turkish Sultan, Hath reach'd our harbour? HALI. Omar, didst thou say? (Aside) By heav'n! he comes propitious to my purpose— (To Almeida) Omar!—I know him not.—Is it yet bruited What is his mission's object? ALMEIDA. If report Speak justly of his purpose, he's empower'd For the surrender of our guest to treat. But who are these? Enter Raymond and Omar. RAYMOND. I come from our Grand-Master, To impart to Damaral what has late occurr'd, And for this envoy from the Turkish camp To ask short parlance with the captive Hali. ALMEIDA. Damaral will give thee audience. For the rest, Behold the captive Hali. OMAR. Art thou he, To whom the fair Ismena was intrusted? HALI. I have that charge. OMAR. I would impart to thee— Your favour, gallant knights! I've that to say Which female delicacy renders sacred. RAYMOND. Take thy full license—say whate'er thou will'st— I will to Damaral straight, and then rejoin thee. ALMEIDA. This way, good Raymond— [Exeunt Raymond and Almeida. HALI. Doubly art thou welcome! Our harvest's ripe, and waited but thy hand To reap it fully. Precious are the moments Which fortune gives us. Let them not be lost. Com'st thou to treat for our release? OMAR. Such is The simulated purpose of my mission. As thou hast prosper'd, I must act. Instruct me— Shall I urge on my suit, or, to gain time— HALI. Give him no time—for, if he once reflect, Our project will be vain.—Give him no time— Press home thy suit, and leave the rest to me. But soft—his friend returns.—I've more to say, Which calls for privacy— Enter Almeida. HALI (to Omar). Thy words are sage, And shall be graven in thy servant's heart. (To Almeida) Save thee, good sir. ALMEIDA. I pray you rest within. While in our hospitality ye share, Ye may what yet remains at ease discuss. OMAR. We thank thee for thy kindness—pray lead on. [Exeunt. SCENE II. Another Apartment in Damaral's Palace. Damaral and Ismena. ISMENA. Ah cease, my lord! I may not hear thee more. In all thou say'st, there is a shew of truth, A glow of gen'rous sentiment so warm, That an unpractis'd heart like mine might melt To its undoing, were I to believe thee. DAMARAL. Trust me, my fair, mine is no flatt'ring tongue; Untutor'd in the eloquence of love, It fails to speak the dictates of my heart. Could'st thou read that, thou would'st not doubt my truth. ISMENA. I would not doubt it—pardon me, my lord— I know not what I say—I ought to doubt it. 'Tis dang'rous to believe. A lover's vows Are light as air, no sooner breath'd than gone. Who trusts to them is lost. DAMARAL. A lover's vows Are true as holy faith when honour breathes them. Credit me, fair, not love itself could tempt me To vouch an ardour which I did not feel: Nay, did I think thy heart avow'd a passion For him to whom thy Sultan hath assign'd thee, I'd not aspire to gain thee. If thou lov'st him, Confess it, and, howe'er severe the trial, Whate'er may prove the pang, I'll own his right, And bury my presumptuous love in silence. ISMENA. Love him? Love Selim? No! Whate'er my fate, No pow'r shall make me own him as my lord. Rather, secluded from the sight of men, Would I in solitude consume my youth, Or, doom'd to bondage, by incessant toil Procure a scanty sustenance, than wed him. DAMARAL. Then may I hope, then may my tow'ring wishes Aspire to thy perfections. Oh Ismena! 'Till now I never felt the pow'r of love: A rugged soldier, 'till I view'd thy charms I knew it but by name. Now, now I own it, And at thy feet breathe forth my raptur'd soul. ISMENA. Arise, my lord—nay, kneel not thus before me— How can I answer thee? DAMARAL. I ask not words: A look, a smile, can reach my heart, and tell What words can never speak—how now! who's that? Enter Almeida. Why thus intrude upon my privacy? ALMEIDA. Raymond awaits, and present audience craves. DAMARAL. What brings him now? Was there no other time But this to break upon me?—Bid him hence. ALMEIDA. There is an envoy from the Turk arriv'd, Who brings proposals— DAMARAL. Say'st thou from the Turk? That may not be dispens'd with. (To Ismena). For a moment I must receive him. Trust me, fair, I will not Be absent from thee long. (To Almeida). Bid him approach. [Exit Almeida. (To Ismena) Retire awhile, I pray; he'll soon depart, Then with impatience will I fly to thee. ISMENA. I shall expect thee—think me not too bold That thus I speak—let fair construction wait On my defect—my heart, alas! will feel— DAMARAL. Thou'rt all perfection! Heav'n is in thine eye, Thy glance is rapture, and thy touch is madness! Curse on the chance that interrupts my transport!— Hark!—He's at hand—away, away, away! He may not see thee—all my soul goes with thee. [Exit Ismena. Enter Raymond. So, sir! What please you to require of me? RAYMOND. By Villiers am I charg'd to give thee notice There is an envoy from the Turk arriv'd— DAMARAL. Well—what of him?—There is a certain matter Which calls for my attention—so be brief. RAYMOND. Thus then it is. He urges the release Of the fair maid— DAMARAL. Ismena? RAYMOND. Of Ismena. Either for ransom, which our chief disdains, Or by exchange for pris'ners of our own. DAMARAL. He hath refus'd her? RAYMOND. No—he deems it best To treat with him, perhaps obtain a truce, Which may give time for succours to arrive. Thou heed'st me not. Attend, I pray— DAMARAL. To what? To the crude fancies of an idle dreamer, Who, when the time demands our swords, expects By idle courtesies to win success? Let's hear no more on't! RAYMOND. I beseech your patience. If we can save the blood of our brave friends— DAMARAL. There was a time when in our swords we trusted, When Rhodian honour scorn'd to meet a foe Except in equal field. But that is over. Go—tell your courtly ruler I'm too old To learn new fashions. RAYMOND. Nay, reflect, I pray. DAMARAL. 'Tis beyond bearing he should thus presume Of his own will to give the damsel up— RAYMOND. Thou dost mistake him— DAMARAL. No—I know him well— But go, bear answer to your haughty chief, I have accepted her in charge, and will not To please his new caprice surrender her. RAYMOND. Since it is so, farewell! [Exit Raymond. DAMARAL. Surrender her! No! were whole hosts of Ottomans to claim her, I'd guard her with my life!—Surrender her! Just at the moment when she's mine to lose her! For what? To pleasure him?—'Tis beyond bearing— He master here in Rhodes! He to decide! He to command me! Heav'n and earth! My soul Labours within me, when I think upon His elevation and mine own defeat. A sycophantic courtier, one well read In diplomatic lore, cunning to treat Of embassies and such like scambling stuff, A carpet knight, who, while my limbs were cas'd In rugged steel, clad his in ermin'd robes, And wielded in his weak enervate hand, Unfit for nobler instrument, his pen, The while in mine the faulchion of our Order Spread wide destruction through the Turkish host— Enter Hali. HALI. Pardon, my lord, if I unbidden enter To pay my duty, and return my thanks For all thy courtesies. Since 'tis decreed We now must leave thee— DAMARAL. Hast thou heard it then? HALI. Though freedom be a boon we all would grasp at, Yet sometimes we are willing slaves. I fear There's one among us, who will not rejoice To quit a mild captivity for thraldom More irksome far— DAMARAL. What mean'st thou? HALI. Poor Ismena! Untoward is thy fate; thy tender heart Will hardly bear the shock which now awaits it. To be consign'd to hateful Selim's arms— DAMARAL. She shall not go—no pow'r on earth shall force her— Let Villiers, if he dare, come here to claim her— HALI. No, no, my lord—invested as he is With all the pow'r and influence of your Order, He has more certain means to work his ends. He's cool and politic; thou wert his rival; He knows thou'rt his superior in renown, And only waits occasion to evince That hatred, which a little soul will feel For those it fears. DAMARAL. I care not for his hatred. HALI. I look'd for such reply; it well becomes The hero, whom, of those who grace our age, Th'impartial voice of fame hath mostly deck'd With glory, and bespeaks the proud disdain Of a brave spirit, struggling 'gainst the tide Of adverse fortune. Yet it most concerns thee Not too contemptuously to underrate A foe who, like thy rival, holds a pow'r Which at a stroke may crush thee. Well are known Thy valour, and thy high repute in arms: But he is deck'd with such authority, That Damaral's self must bow— DAMARAL. Thou know'st me not. Let him take heed. If I am once provok'd, My arm can reach him, though he's plac'd so high. HALI. 'Tis bravely spoken. If my feeble aid— I crave forgiveness—I am but a captive, One of whose faith thou hast not had experience, Nor other testimony than the voice Of my fair mistress. DAMARAL. Can I ask for more? She, who is truth and purity itself, Assur'd me she had prov'd and found thee true. HALI. I have indeed been faithful to her service, And for the man on whom her pref'rence falls I would do much. I could, an I might speak— DAMARAL. Say what thou will'st. But what avails thy zeal, When ev'ry hope, which love or fair ambition Once fondly cherish'd, is for ever lost? HALI. When fortune seems most adverse, gen'rous minds Find in themselves fresh energies. 'Tis true A hated rival is preferr'd before thee— DAMARAL. Why waken thus remembrances so cruel? Couldst thou indeed teach me to sate my vengeance— HALI. I could. DAMARAL. 'Twere well thou didst. HALI. Thou art not one Whom danger can appal; thou wouldst not shrink At glory's call to meet impending fate. But canst thou face opinion? Canst thou brave The prejudices which enslave mankind? DAMARAL. Thy questions are mysterious. HALI. I'll be plainer: I will not doubt thy firmness, but will shew thee How in thy gen'rous nature I confide. There is a secret, which, if I disclose it, May touch my life.—Thy patience, I beseech thee— Most nearly it concerns thee: all thy hopes, Revenge, ambition, love, depend upon it. My bosom holds it: there's no human pow'r Can tear it from me. To none else but thee, Whose cause I make my own, would I impart it. DAMARAL. Whate'er it be, thou may'st disclose it safely. HALI. I doubt thee not; yet deem me not intrusive, If, ere I put my life into thy hands, I ask more strong assurance. Wilt thou pledge Thy knightly honour, that, whate'er I say, Thou wilt not take advantage of my frankness, Or make me suffer for my boundless zeal For thee and thy best int'rests? DAMARAL. Say no more. Damaral disdains to wrong the man who trusts him. Whate'er may be thy secret, on the honour Of a true knight, no mischief shall betide thee. HALI. I take thy pledge.—Now grant me thy attention. I am not what I seem. I am a man Long honour'd with the Sultan's confidence. I know his secret thoughts, and, 'mongst them, this: That, 'midst his Christian foes, there's not a knight Whose worth he so esteems, whose warlike fame So highly he appreciates, as thine own. 'Tis so, believe me. DAMARAL. He has had no cause To love or praise me. HALI. True—of all his foes He has had most cause to deprecate thy valour. But far beyond the scope of vulgar minds His spirit soars. Though in an enemy, He can distinguish merit and confess it. DAMARAL. Nay, though he threaten to subvert our Order, I scruple not to own his princely worth. HALI. 'Tis nobly said. Now come I to the point. As far beyond all Christian knights he rates thee, With that becoming candour, which adorns A gen'rous soul like his, he would evince His full conviction of thy high desert. DAMARAL. What mean'st thou? HALI. Thus it is. When I at Cyprus Should land my charge, he bad me find the means Of passing hither. By the chance of war, In this at least propitious to his hope, Have I thus soon accomplish'd his intent. DAMARAL. Dost thou commission bear from Soliman? Dar'st thou avow it? HALI. On thy solemn pledge Relying, I intrust thee with my life. 'Tis in thy pow'r; thou may'st imbrue thy sword In my heart's blood, or give me o'er to torture— But thou'rt too noble. DAMARAL. True—my word is pledg'd. Thou'rt safe—proceed— HALI. Behold this scroll—nay, start not— I had it from my royal master's self— DAMARAL. Keep it away—I may not look on it— HALI. It breathes no pestilence—thou may'st with safety Peruse its characters. Thou know'st already What is its end and purport. It contains The sentiments of one who feels thy worth. DAMARAL. I know not if I ought—already, saidst thou, Am I advis'd of its contents?—Here—give it—ha! (Reads) “From Soliman, the master of the world, “To valiant Damaral health”— HALI. I told thee so. Thou see'st the Sultan owns thy high desert, And would embrace thee as a friend. DAMARAL. I do— But on what terms? HALI. Read on. DAMARAL (reads). “Thou aim'st at pow'r; “But courtly artifice will thwart thy wishes; “Villiers will gain the government of Rhodes.”— How learnt he that? HALI. From him are not conceal'd The machinations of your Christian princes. Imperial Charles, who knew thou would'st not yield Implicit def'rence to his haughty will, Supported him against thee. DAMARAL. Was it so? By heav'n! I thought it—but I'm glad I know it. (Reads) “Should Rhodes by thy assistance ope her gates, “On thee its sov'reignty will I confer: “I will maintain thy throne, and from thy loins “Shall issue dynasties of future kings.”— Here—take it back again—it must not be— HALI. Not be? Forbid it fate! Shall great revenge, Shall regal dignity be slighted thus? Wouldst on thy rival's head avenge thy wrongs, Snatch from his feeble hand th'imperial sceptre, Be hail'd the Rhodian king? Or, if thou lov'st, Wilt thou stand tamely by, while from thine arms They tear Ismena, while her peerless beauties, Thine own, if thou assert them, are consign'd To him she most detests, when by a word Thou may'st proclaim to all the world thy love, And place a diadem upon her brow? DAMARAL. Give me some pause— HALI. Will Villiers, think'st thou, give it? Perhaps his orders are already issued To rob thee of thy love.—Give thee some pause! Would that my words were light'nings to inflame All that is man in thee! DAMARAL. I am a man. Thou'dst have me more. HALI. I would. I'd have thee rise To the true level of thy princely soul, I'd hail thee king, I'd give thee thine Ismena! Thou know'st my master's power; he can, he will Fulfil his promise. DAMARAL. 'Tis a tempting proffer— But it is rated at a price so high— HALI. Can it be rated at a price too high? DAMARAL. I do confess—but say, should I accept it, What surety is there that, if Rhodes were his, He would these ample promises fulfil? HALI. His honour. 'Tis a high and sacred pledge, Which ne'er was forfeited. I took thy word, And scrupled not t'intrust thee with my life— DAMARAL. Thou didst.—But still the plan's impracticable. We are beleagur'd round; none can go forth: And if one might, where could I find a friend, Whom I might trust with Mustapha to treat? HALI. Canst thou trust me? DAMARAL. I think I may. HALI. Thou may'st. DAMARAL. Nay, credit me, I think it. But thou canst not— HALI. There's nought more easy. Grant me thy attention. If Villiers shall persist in his design, Give semblance of consent: then, when his choice Of one to treat of it with Mustapha Is undecided, name me. DAMARAL. He'll not hear on't. HALI. Why not? I shall be only charg'd to bring The Turk's response. A captive may do that, And save your knights from a degrading function. Nay, they will have security enough For my fidelity and prompt return, When they reflect that on them must depend Th'enlargement of Ismena. Gain but this, And trust to my address for full success. DAMARAL. There's much in what thou say'st— Enter Almeida. ALMEIDA. Most noble sir, Thy presence is requested at the council, Where Villiers waits thy coming, to decide What answer shall be render'd to the Turk. DAMARAL. My instant presence at the council, say'st thou? (To Hali) 'Tis somewhat sudden. HALI. 'Tis a hint from fortune. Neglect it not. Thy fate rests on the moment. A throne—Ismena—vengeance— DAMARAL (to Almeida). I'll obey him. [Exit Almeida. DAMARAL. The die is cast—my fate is on the stake— I will rely upon the Sultan's faith. Expect my prompt return. Prepare thee straight. [Exeunt. END OF ACT III.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT IV. SCENE I. The Grand-Master's Palace. Villiers, Raymond, Davila, and other Knights discovered. RAYMOND. So ended my discourse with Damaral. In my relation I have much suppress'd Of what rude passion utter'd. VILLIERS. It is pity, That such a gallant gentleman as he is Should thus give way to moody discontent. DAVILA. He hath a spirit which disdains controul: The shadow of authority disturbs him. I never saw so proud a man, or one So little form'd to struggle with reverses. His recent disappointment taints his mind, And brooding envy works so strongly in him, That, did occasion suit— VILLIERS. Think better of him, Nor breathe suspicion 'gainst his high desert. Though rough, he's honest, and, though hasty, loyal. DAVILA. You judge him by yourself. A noble nature From the clear mirror of its own pure soul The characters of other men reflects, Sheds a resplendent ray of glory round them, Transforming all their frailties to perfection. VILLIERS. If to think well of others be a weakness, I am indeed most weak. We all have frailties, And that, of which we're conscious in ourselves, We should with charity excuse in others. The gallant Damaral has approv'd himself Our Order's best support: let us then weigh His merits 'gainst his faults, and we shall find How they prepond'rate.—But no more—He comes. Enter Damaral. DAMARAL. Here on thy summons I attend. VILLIERS. 'Tis well. Thou know'st the cause wherefore we thus assemble, But we are yet to learn why thou disdain'st Our mandate. DAMARAL. Noble sirs! Ye have known me long, My merits and defects. I need not tell you I am a man of plain, unvarnish'd manners, Unpractis'd in the modes of courtly life, Who never studied grace, or learn'd to mould My phrases to the fashion of the time. What passes in my heart my tongue will speak, And, when I'm mov'd by choler, I am apt To give free utt'rance to my sudden thought. This ye all know; and, if too strongly now Or hastily of what ye plann'd I spoke, Let your good favour pardon my defect. VILLIERS. 'Tis spoken like thyself.—Thou know'st the Turk Asks with strong instance the release of her Whom brave Du Mesnil took. Could our compliance Obtain from them a truce, the Christian pow'rs Might then have time to send their wish'd-for aid. DAMARAL. And thereto do your councils tend? VILLIERS. They do. DAMARAL. To treat with Mustapha?—We never yet Held parley with our unbelieving foe. 'Tis 'gainst our rule. Yet, as you sagely judge, Th'occasion seems to warrant it. Then why Reject what our necessities require? Whom send you forth? VILLIERS. That is a point, whereon Thy judgment may assist us. DAMARAL. 'Tis indeed A service which discretion will require, And yet 'tis such as will degrade the doer. When heard ye, since our Order had existence, That any knight so far forgot his station, As the forbearance of the foe to court? VILLIERS. So stand the rule and practice of our Order. Yet this, methinks, is an exception to it: For, after all, what is it but t'arrange Terms of exchange for those we captive hold? DAMARAL. True—'tis no more.—Yet that is all too much, And may have consequences—no!—'tis certain Ye cannot send a knight.—But then whom else?— Let me reflect.—A thought has just occurr'd,— How far 't may be expedient you must judge,— Why, when none else can fitly be employ'd— For so it is—should you not try the captive, Who hither with the damsel came? DAVILA. The captive? What know'st thou of the captive?—Trust to him! DAMARAL. In what respect, I pray, can he deceive us? What is the object of his purpos'd mission? The freedom of the damsel. What the terms On which that boon depends? A truce. Who then So fitly may be trusted with the charge, As he who feels most int'rest in her welfare? He seems well suited to the task, and trusty. VILLIERS. We know him not. If thou hast cause to trust him— DAMARAL. Cause, say'st thou?—No—I talk'd with him indeed— The lady much commends him.—For myself, I have no cause—but she must know him best.— (Aside) How ill I play the hypocrite! (To Villiers) 'Tis certain He has an int'rest, which none other has, To prompt him to exertion. VILLIERS. He hath so. Shall we commission one to bring him hither? DAMARAL. 'Twere sagely done.—(Aside) If I stay longer here, My feelings will betray me. (To Villiers) There's a matter, Which presses strongly, and requires my presence. I'll send him to thee. Judge of him thyself; And give him thine instructions.—I will send him. [Exit Damaral. DAVILA. What? So abruptly gone?—I marvel much He thus should change without apparent cause. To Raymond now all fury, venting threats 'Gainst any who should dare remove the maid; Now, first to send her back.—And then the captive— 'Till now a total stranger; yet he vouches He is deserving trust. He may be so; But I would have other security, Than that he gives us. VILLIERS. Be content, I pray. If he be such as Damaral has describ'd, It may be well to use him. DAVILA. I have done.— Raymond! a word.—Let's watch this trusty captive. I like not over confidence. RAYMOND. Agreed. VILLIERS. Come with me, friends! Let us th'instruction frame For our new messenger. Should our attempt Meet with success, our pains are well bestow'd; If not, upon our arms and oft-tried valour Let us depend, and look to heav'n for safety. [Exeunt. SCENE II. An Apartment in Damaral's Palace. Enter Hali. HALI. I would he were return'd! He went prepar'd To second all my views; but who can tell What mischief cool reflection may produce? They know not, who have never tried deceit, How perilous it is. When my blood's hot, And all my faculties are rous'd to action, I mock at danger: but suspense unmans me.— 'Tis strange he comes not!—If I can but lead him Into the snare devis'd for him, his ruin Follows immediate. Either Rhodes must fall, And all his flatt'ring hopes be buried with it, Or to the world his treasons shall be blazon'd. I care not which betide. Whatever chance, My vengeance will be full. Enter Ismena. ISMENA. I'm glad I've found thee. Know'st thou of Damaral aught? HALI. He is gone forth On what imports us mainly. Our design Is prosp'rous far beyond our warmest hope. All his wild passions, leagued against himself, Champion our purposes. I hold him fast— ISMENA. I'm sorry for it! HALI. How's that?—Sorry, say'st thou? ISMENA. I am a woman, and perhaps I feel A woman's weakness; but there's something tells me We are engag'd in an unworthy cause. Had he been otherwise than I have found him— HALI. I tell thee, had he been less prone to yield To the dominion of ungovern'd passion, Our project had been marr'd. If we succeed To warp him from his duty, all the glory Of this important conquest will be ours. ISMENA. Think of the princely qualities of him, Whom thus we doom to ruin. If he err, His very faults are the excess of virtue. HALI. Give o'er this idle talk!—Thou should'st have pleaded Thy nature's weakness ere we left Byzantium. ISMENA. Oh would that heav'n had sav'd me from a share In guilt, from which my feelings now recoil! How can I hear him pour forth vows of love, Read in his ev'ry glance ingenuous passion, And, like an adder foster'd in his bosom, Distil insidious poison?—Think me not So lost to ev'ry feeling, so devoid— HALI. I heed not what thou art, so thou be firm. Our triumph's sure; then comes our rich reward— ISMENA. Perish the thought! What? For a deed like this? The very beasts, that range the fields for prey, May be subdued by kindness. They can feel, But I—too horrible!—than they more cruel, Combine to ruin him who loves me best. And what a man! First among Europe's heroes, Brave, gen'rous— HALI. Cease—I'll hear no more—retire— And mark—when Damaral shall revisit thee, See thou receiv'st him as thou ought'st. Call forth All thy seducing charms, greet him with smiles, But, as thou lov'st thy life, give not a hint Which may instil suspicion in his soul. Begone! I have no time to lose with thee! ISMENA. Nay, force me not away!—I pray thee hear me! HALI. Away! [He forces her out.] So! this is well.—The shaft I aim'd 'Gainst Damaral will recoil upon myself, If I prevent it not. She must have feelings!— 'Tis mine own fault: I should have known her sex. But hold—he comes at last. Now must I dress My face in smiles. Enter Damaral. Welcome, my gracious lord! I waited with impatience thy return. How goes our enterprize? Thy looks are cheering— DAMARAL. Are they? I guess'd not that. In sooth, my mind Feels more than wonted trouble. I'm not us'd To wear a double face, or make my tongue The lying herald of my heart. HALI. 'Twere well, If we could always reach our purpos'd aim By the straight path. Yet wise men have affirm'd (What sage experience warrants) 'tis the end Which justifies the means. Would'st thou in war Disclose thy real purpose, that the foe Might praise thy candour, and defeat thy plan? That were stark folly. He, who best can veil The stroke he aims, is surest of success. DAMARAL. Yet could I wish, so hateful is it to me, We might dispense with that which so degrades A soldier's honour. There's a madd'ning whirl Of thought within me— HALI. Think of it no more. What tidings bring'st thou? DAMARAL. All—but my sharp reflections— All seem auspicious. They— HALI. Nay, my good lord— DAMARAL. I had forgotten.—Villiers hath consented To send thee forth to treat of the conditions, And wills thee to repair to him forthwith. HALI. Then let me not delay. Time now is precious. Look for my prompt return.—Farewell, my lord! [As he is going, he turns back. Yet hold—my zeal had nearly overrun My better judgment. How could I forget That which omitted might have foil'd our hopes? DAMARAL. Have foiled them? HALI. Aye, my lord. Though Mustapha, Who knows me, might not have refused me credence On things of less concern, yet, on a matter Like this, he might demur. He would demand, What proof hast thou of Damaral's confidence? And what am I to answer?—I have none. DAMARAL. What proof would he require? HALI. Suppose thou giv'st me— Under thy hand I mean—two lines of credence? 'Tis a mere trifle. DAMARAL. How?—a trifle, say'st thou? HALI. 'Tis of no farther use, than to convince Our Gen'ral of my truth. But that's essential. It matters not what evidence I have, If it do that. Perhaps we may devise Some other means.—Aye—that will do as well.— Thou bear'st a signet, whereon is engrav'd Thine Order's blazoning, the Christian Cross. Suppose thou giv'st me that? DAMARAL. I'll give thee nought! HALI. And why refuse it me?—Dost thou then doubt me? DAMARAL. Give me thy hand.—In very truth, good Hali! I do believe thee honest. HALI. Give me proof on't.— What do I ask?—The means of thy success. DAMARAL. I would do much; but this, which thou requir'st, Is of such moment— HALI. Thou dost doubt me then? If so, farewell! I find I knew thee not. Let thy successful rival keep his pow'r, Forego the crown which thy acceptance courts; Let fair Ismena from thine arms be torn, Let her be giv'n to Selim— DAMARAL. Say no more— I scorn to treat with him I would not trust— Here—take it (gives the signet). See thou guard'st it carefully. HALI. As mine own life. Thou may'st rely upon me. DAMARAL. Nay, I distrust not thee so much as fortune. HALI. Doubt nothing. Fare-thee-well! [Exit Hali. DAMARAL. Stay yet a moment!— He's gone!—That signet—'tis a trust— Enter Ismena. ISMENA. My lord! DAMARAL. My lov'd Ismena! They have kept me from thee— ISMENA. If thou com'st now in time for me to save thee, I shall be blest indeed. DAMARAL. What means my love? ISMENA. Hast thou seen Hali? DAMARAL. Even now he left me, As thou cam'st hither. ISMENA. Had ye much discourse? DAMARAL. We had.—Why look'st thou thus?—Thy colour changes! ISMENA. Pass'd any thing which may affect thee nearly? Forgive me, Damaral! for I have a cause, Grave as thy life, essential as thine honour. DAMARAL. What say'st thou?—Is then Hali a deceiver? What then—oh heav'nly pow'rs!—What then art thou? ISMENA. Oh! I'm a wretch, who have no other plea For thy forgiveness than too late repentance. I'm plung'd in guilt so black, thy noble nature Must fail to fathom it. Had I foreseen Thou wert but half so gen'rous and so kind As I have found thee, not the Sultan's pow'r Nor Hali's arts had made me an accomplice— DAMARAL. In what? ISMENA. Oh look not thus!—How can I tell thee The sum of my offence?—Thou'lt hate me—fly me— Here, in my guilty heart, thy weapon plant, Forget that I'm a woman, look upon me As one with demons leagued for thy destruction! DAMARAL. Almeida! Ho! Enter Almeida. Pursue—bring Hali back! ALMEIDA. Which was his course? DAMARAL. He's gone to the Grand-Master— Fly, and o'ertake him ere he reach the palace. If thou dost love me let him not escape. Away, away! [Exit Almeida. (To Ismena) Thou leagued for my destruction? ISMENA. Hear me, and, if it yet be not too late, Let me preserve thee.—I'm combin'd with those, Who, knowing thee impetuous, brave and honest, Form'd their infernal project to undo thee. Hali devis'd the plan; his was the task To work upon thy passions, and incite thee To join against thy country: me they chose, Detested pref'rence! to seduce thy heart— DAMARAL. No more!—I cannot speak to thee!—Could'st thou— ISMENA. I knew thee not, had never felt thy kindness; But now my heart acknowledges thy worth, And I would save thee if I can from ruin. DAMARAL. Thou know'st not half the dreadful guilt, in which Thy practice hath involv'd me. ISMENA. Hear me yet! Thus, on my knees, let me implore thy pity! If penitence can find forgiveness from thee, If tears can move thee!—I may save thee yet. DAMARAL. Leave me—nay, leave me—I can't speak to thee— Oh beauteous falsehood!—Hence, I would not harm thee, For I have lov'd thee—lov'd thee, while thou spread'st Snares for my life and fame.—I may be tempted, If thou stay'st longer—hence! ISMENA. Oh! for thine honour— DAMARAL. Honour!—mine honour!—To a treach'rous slave Have I surrendered that!—Oh fool, fool, fool!— But I shall reach him!—Bar not thus my way! ISMENA. Oh grant me hearing! DAMARAL. Vain are all your arts! They've work'd—they cannot ruin me again! [Exeunt. END OF ACT IV.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT V. SCENE I. An Apartment in Damaral's Palace. Enter Damaral. DAMARAL. Almeida come not yet!—I cannot bear This ling'ring torture.—To pursue the villain E'en now I tried, but shame and conscience struck me, And drove me back.—I'm fallen abject low, To skulk and tremble with a traitor's fear! Enter Almeida. How now?—Hast dragg'd him hither? ALMEIDA. No, my lord. DAMARAL. Then thou hast slain him? ALMEIDA. Slain him? Good my lord, You talk'd not of his death: you bad me seek him, And to our sov'reign's palace we pursued him. He had been there— DAMARAL. Had been?—Where is he now? ALMEIDA. After a brief and private conference With our new ruler, he again went forth, And hasten'd tow'rds the bastion of Auvergne. DAMARAL. Why cam'st thou back? Why did'st thou not pursue him? ALMEIDA. I sent some followers after him, instructed Without delay to bring him to thy presence, Whilst I return'd to tell thee what had pass'd: But, as he went in diligence, 'tis likely He may, ere they could reach him, have gone forth. DAMARAL. 'Tis well.—I would be private.— [Exit Almeida. Gone forth, said he? Why aye—it may be—nay, it must be so. What should prevent him, licens'd as he was, Bearing commission too from Villiers' self? Beyond all doubt he's gone, and all is safe.— Safe?—Oh no, no! What can be safe, when thus I have committed honour, fame, and conscience To a perfidious slave?—Say he were true, Secret as Erebus, that in the caves Of dark unfathom'd ocean my offence Were buried instantly, though from the world My shame may be conceal'd, can I—oh thought Destructive of my peace!—Can I e'er silence Th'upbraiding monitor, which to my soul Will speak the fatal truth?—Blush, Damaral, blush! Seek out some far sequester'd nook, where ne'er Can penetrate the eye or reach the voice Of mortal man; there shroud thy shame, there shrink From conscious guilt—Who's that?—What brings thee here? Enter Ismena. ISMENA. If to thy presence thus I come uncall'd, 'Tis as a penitent to ask forgiveness. Oh! could'st thou know the workings of my soul— DAMARAL. I am more calm than when I parted from thee, But dare not trust myself to look upon thee. Thy mask of candour is not now more fair, Than it was erst, when, false and treacherous, Thou stung'st the bosom that had shelter'd thee. ISMENA. I wear that mask no longer. No! for ever I cast away disguise, and dare be honest. Oh gracious Damaral! if thy noble heart Be open to sweet mercy, hear my story, And, though thou may'st not pardon, pity me! Torn from the guardians of my early youth, Within the walls of a seraglio rear'd, I learnt no arts but those which pleasure taught, And was enjoin'd no duty but obedience. My sov'reign's will became his servant's law: When he ordain'd to send me forth to prove thee, I deem'd myself distinguish'd by his choice; But, when I knew thee, when I found thee noble, And grac'd with each heroic quality, Which can exalt the man or deck the soldier, My soul revolted at the foul design; Virtue resum'd her empire o'er my heart, And urg'd me to confess my fault and save thee. DAMARAL. I lov'd thee once—I will not chide thee now: And he, whose peace thou'st ruin'd, thus forgives thee! The heart, which can resist thy pow'rful pleadings, Is more or less than human. ISMENA. Gen'rous man! Is my fault pardon'd?—Witness, righteous heav'n! And bless me as my penitence is true! Enter Almeida. ALMEIDA. The council is conven'd. On urgent matters Thy presence is requir'd. DAMARAL. Know'st thou if Hali Be yet come back? ALMEIDA. As he went forth to treat On business of grave import, 'tis unlikely He should return so quickly. DAMARAL. Thou hast reason. Report that instantly I will attend them. [Exit Almeida. Farewell, Ismena! let no recollection Of former errors pang thy feeling breast. I have forgotten them. ISMENA. My heart's too full To thank thee as I ought. May ev'ry blessing Light on thee and preserve thee!—But beware— Beware of Hali! [Exeunt severally. SCENE II. Council Chamber. Enter Du Mesnil and Garcias. DU MESNIL. Garcias! well met.—Know'st thou why thus we're summon'd? GARCIAS. Since last we here assembled, I've not heard That aught important has occurr'd. Perhaps The captive, whom our chief sent forth to treat With Mustapha, has brought an answer back. But see the noble Damaral. Enter Damaral. We discuss'd The cause why our Grand-Master hath conven'd us. We deem'd it might be, that the captive, charg'd To bear his answer to the Turkish camp— DAMARAL. Is he return'd? GARCIAS. Nay, if thou know'st it not, It surely cannot be. DU MESNIL. Whate'er the cause, We now shall learn it, for our chief approaches. Enter Villiers, Raymond, and Davila. Behold us here, obedient to thy pleasure: Vouchsafe to instruct us wherefore thus we meet. VILLIERS. The cause of meeting soon shall be detail'd. At this eventful period, ev'ry moment Teems with new circumstances, which demand Our vigilant attention. DU MESNIL. True—the times Are critical: we cannot be too cautious. We have to deal with those, who scruple not To use all means which may effect their ends. VILLIERS. We are aware of that, and therefore seek To counteract their plans. Yet 'tis not easy, Whate'er our caution be, to guard against Our foe's insidious projects. Proteus like, They can assume variety of shapes, And mould themselves to what may best conduce To work their purposes.—When I reflect On the important trust we gave that captive, Methinks we should have ponder'd more upon it. We acted hastily. Yet had we cause, (to Damaral) For thou wert satisfied he was trust-worthy. DAMARAL. I deem'd him so— VILLIERS. 'Twas a sufficient sanction. Had'st thou much converse with him? DAMARAL. Converse?—Yes, We talk'd—He was an inmate in my house, And so we had discourse.—He seem'd a man Of more than ordinary depth of thought, And well matur'd reflection. VILLIERS. May we ask, If thou intrusted'st him with aught beyond The limited instruction which we gave him? DAMARAL. I?—Good my lord! I have not seen him since. Went he not straightway forth?—Is he return'd? DAVILA. If yet thou hast not heard, I may perchance Impart some tidings of him. I and Raymond Were station'd at the bastion of Auvergne, When towards our post the trusty captive came. He seem'd in haste, yet could I not avoid With courteous salutation to accost him. As we convers'd, certain of thy dependents In haste came up. When they could find their speech, They told him thou had'st need of him; but he, Regardless of them, with more eagerness, Insisted on his passage through the gate. DAMARAL. Thou did'st accord it? DAVILA. I had nearly done so; But, on reflection thou might'st have strong cause To stop his progress, I oppos'd his wishes. DAMARAL. What right had'st thou— DAVILA. I pray thee give me hearing, My tale is nearly ended. He, indignant That thus I barr'd his way, pushed on. A contest rose. I know not what the issue might have been, For he is strong and pow'rful, had not chance By a propitious turn concluded it. As we stood grappling, from his bosom fell A signet— DAMARAL. How?—What say'st? DAVILA. Thine own—I knew it. The symbol of a trust. What trust it were, I guess'd our chieftain here might choose to know, And therefore deem'd it right to arrest the bearer, As I do thee. [He lays hold on Damaral. DAMARAL. Hold off thy hands! Release me! VILLIERS. Let not respect be wanting to the man, Whose services our Order has experienc'd. (To Damaral) —Prove as it may th'event, of this be sure, Before suspicion can affect thy fame, We must have weighty proof of thine offence. Thy judges are the partners of thy glory, They fought beneath thy banners, and partook Of thy well-earn'd renown: as their own honour They cherish thine; and, when they judge thy cause, The recollection of thy past deserts Will plead for thee more loudly in their hearts, Than if a venal host of bold declaimers Should advocate thine innocence.—Bring forth The captive whom ye have in charge! Enter Hali, guarded. Stand forward! Here, in this noble presence, art thou brought To answer for thyself. Suspicions strong Attach upon thee: yet, to save thyself, Dare not— HALI. Thou may'st thine exhortation spare; I know my life is forfeit to thy pow'r, And scorn to save it by a mean evasion. I stand prepar'd to answer, as becomes A man disdainful of his fate. VILLIERS. 'Tis well. Whose was the signet, that we found upon thee? HALI —(Pointing to Damaral). 'Twas his—intrusted to me by himself. VILLIERS. And with what motive? HALI. Give me leave awhile. Had I been one of those, whose tim'rous spirit Shrank from th' approach of danger, I had not, As I have done, affronted sure destruction. Ye may believe me, for I care not now Who knows my character. Let others pardon: In the recesses of my soul I lodge The wrongs I suffer; there I brood upon them, Foster their growth, wait for the fav'ring moment Which gives me 'vantage, while, meantime, with smiles And courteous bearing I amuse my victim, 'Till my avenging dagger drinks his blood. VILLIERS. Methinks thou paint'st a fiend, and not a man. HALI. It matters not what title it deserves: I speak it of myself. VILLIERS. Come to the point, Nor further waste our time in vain discourse. HALI. It was not vain discourse, to shew the springs Which mov'd my conduct.—Let me now proceed, And let the stern and haughty Damaral hear. Hopes of high retribution from your foes, And deeply-rankling hatred of himself, Led me, of risk disdainful, to devise The means of his and Rhodes's overthrow. DAMARAL. Hatred of me?—What means he?—Until now He knew me not. HALI. Thou knew'st not me, 'twas plain; But I knew thee, and had strong cause to know. Remember'st thou Velasquez, who once serv'd Beneath thy banner, whom thy harsh controul Compell'd to leave the service of the Order, And, robb'd of ev'ry hope of fair ambition, Elsewhere to seek his fortune? DAMARAL. Who?—Velasquez?— Such man I think there was— HALI. Such man there is— Behold him here before thee! DAMARAL. Heav'n and earth! Am I so caught? So basely, blindly caught? HALI. Thou art!—And yet my triumph is not full. Thyself, thy same, are prostrate at my feet: But, had I reach'd the Turkish camp, the fall Of Rhodes's self had dwindled thine to nothing. This fate denied me; but enough remains. I found thee deck'd with honour and renown; I wrought upon thy vanity and passion, I led thee to conspiracy and treason, And now I leave thee to contempt and shame! VILLIERS. Prevent his further speech! (The guards seize Hali. (To Damaral.) —Th' atrocious slanders Of this convicted traitor can't affect Our confidence in thy long-honour'd worth. I marvel not, that thus to be arraign'd By one, who has avow'd his hatred to thee, Should for a moment shake thy constancy. A soldier's choicest treasure is his fame; And who so well can estimate its value, As he whose fame all others has surpass'd? The short-liv'd triumph of malevolence Will but enhance thy glory. Speak, and meet His foul and daring charge with full reply. DAMARAL. Thrice noble prince! And ye, illustrious knights, Once my companions in the toils of war, Now here assembled to pronounce my doom, That from my soul I thank ye for your candour, That (to Villiers) had I known thy nobleness and worth, I had not wish'd to injure thee, believe. Ye bid me justify myself, and promise Such fair construction as my words deserve. There was a time, when gladly I had seiz'd Such fair occasion to release myself From charges, which, to honourable minds, Are worse than death. I had not waited then, But, with the promptitude of innocence, Boldly repell'd the voice of calumny. Such time is pass'd! VILLIERS. Is past?—Nay, noble Damaral! Forget not thus thyself. DAMARAL. Could I forget Myself, and the transactions of this day, I might obey thee.—Memory is too busy. My bold accuser spoke the truth. He wrought Upon my senseless vanity and passion, He led me to conspiracy and treason, Robb'd me of fame, and plung'd me in dishonour! Enter Ismena, struggling with the Guards. ISMENA. Stand off! prevent me not!—I will have passage! [She throws herself at the feet of Villiers. Oh noble sir! VILLIERS. What mean'st thou?—Lady, rise— This attitude becomes thee not. ISMENA. No, no! Here let me prostrate fall, here, at thy feet, Let me confess my shame, t'atone for crimes By blackest villainy devis'd, and plead For him, whose gen'rous, unsuspecting nature— VILLIERS. Retire—we have no time to hear thee now. ISMENA. In mercy send me not unheard away! I plead not for myself—I am unworthy. Oh! pour your vengeance on my guilty head, Rack, if you will, the fatal form which 'snar'd him— VILLIERS. I may not hear thee more.—Thou must retire— ISMENA. Oh never, never!—(runs to Damaral)—Dear, ill-fated Damaral! Canst thou forgive me? DAMARAL. This is not the moment, To give free utt'rance to my lab'ring thought. I have forgiven thee—nay more, believe, While this heart beats, or while this working brain Retains the mem'ry of what most I lov'd, Thou shalt be there.—But thou must now retire. Should we not meet again— ISMENA. Not meet again! (To Villiers) If ye have hearts, oh! send me not away— VILLIERS. We shew most pity, in preventing thee From torturing a mind, already loaded With more than human fortitude can bear. Du Mesnil! lead her hence. ISMENA. A moment yet— A little moment.—I have much to say, Ere this poor suff'ring heart with sorrow breaks! DAMARAL. Nay, nay, unman me not.—May angels guard thee! VILLIERS. Bear her away! [Exeunt Ismena and Du Mesnil. That an event, so novel in our Order, So dreadful in itself and consequences, Should strike you, noble comrades! with dismay, I cannot marvel. 'Mongst yourselves resolve What course we should adopt. But for this wretch, This trait'rous renegado from our faith, Whose foul contrivance has seduc'd a spirit Once our support and pride, what else for him Remains, but instant death? HALI. (Breaking from the guards) Unhand me, ruffians!— Give vengeance her free scope! I fear it not. Whate'er my life, whatever were my crimes, My death is glorious. Think ye I will plead For mercy or remission of my tortures? No! though Velasquez be your victim, still He triumphs in his fate, and scorns your pow'r. Draw forth your murd'rous instruments; devise New punishments my constancy to prove: I'm arm'd against them all. From ev'ry vein The life-blood may distil; the ling'ring rack May multiply the agonies of death: Amid them all, this cheering thought remains— Ye can't bereave me of accomplish'd vengeance! VILLIERS. Away with him! [Exit Hali, guarded. Now comes the painful task, By stern necessity impos'd upon us— DAVILA. Your pardon, noble sir! My heart is full, And feelings irresistible incite me To speak the honest dictates of my soul. While unacquainted with the gen'rous nature Of this brave knight, I censur'd his demeanour, And, with an earnestness I now regret, Pursued him to the ruin of his fame. I knew not then the sum of his desert: But, when I see him with sublime disdain Reject all subterfuge, when pow'rful truth Impels him to avow a secret crime Charg'd on him by the single testimony Of a malignant and revengeful foe, I feel and own his honour. Let me plead In his defence, whom lately I accus'd, And, trusting to the nobleness of those Who guide our Order's councils, hope for mercy. VILLIERS. We all must feel like thee. In ev'ry bosom Remembrance lives of his recorded worth, And justice shall by mercy be attemper'd. Meantime—(to Damaral)—while undecided is thy cause, Thou must to Raymond render up thy sword. DAMARAL. Were ye to judge me as I judge myself, Your course had been far other.—Ere I leave you, Take for your noble clemency my thanks. Wer't not for that which rankles in my heart, And turns to mortal poison the blest mercy, Which, when it shews me what I might have been, Doubles my shame and sorrow, I might prize A life, which now no more is worth my care. But I too long detain you. What remains Will soon be past. I must resign my sword. (Takes it off.) Yet, ere we part, let me again survey That blade (half draws it), whose edge with destination sure Oft bore destruction 'mid our Order's foes. Thou wert my trusty friend; thou ne'er deceiv'st me— I then was not unworthy to possess thee. What's that?—a tear?—and from thy master's eye? I will not wipe it off—it shall remain. Excuse me, sirs! ye've all been witnesses What this good sword has done (draws it). It serv'd me once To gain an ample harvest of renown, Nor now deserts me in adversity. [He stabs himself. VILLIERS. Prevent his rash attempt! DAMARAL. It is too late. [He falls. Farewell!—when my offences shall be told, Be it remember'd that I made atonement. (To Villiers) Give me thy hand—forget—forgive me—oh! [He dies. THE END.</field>
   </doc>
</add>