<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Hill, Aaron, 1685-1750</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Hill, Aaron, 1685-1750</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">hill aaron 1685 1750</field>
      <field name="author_text">Hill, Aaron, 1685-1750</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">18th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1760's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V2.0263.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1760</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:459979</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Merlin in Love</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Merlin in Love</field>
      <field name="title_facet">merlin in love</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">merlin in love</field>
      <field name="title_text">Merlin in Love</field>
      <field name="year_display">1760</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1760</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1760</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459979&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459979&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Hill, Aaron, 1685-1750&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;hill aaron 1685 1750&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Merlin in Love&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;merlin in love&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1760&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1760&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Hill, Aaron&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1685&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1750&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Merlin in Love&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for T. Lownds [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1760&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872316-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv20263&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 18th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;18th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Merlin in Love&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 54 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Only verse drama included&lt;lb/&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Merlin in love.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Pantomime.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1760.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Unknown.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">MERLIN in Love: OR, Youth against Magic. A PANTOMIME OPERA. In Five Acts.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. SCENE, an apartment in the Doctor's house: A table with a bottle, and two glasses.—Harlequin, in amorous grimace with Columbine, the Doctor's daughter. They represent, in silent action, the gradual advance of a courtship; in which she appears, first, coy and reserved; then softened and satisfied; and, at length, tender and passionate. They then break a piece of gold, and, exchanging the two halves, embrace, kiss; and plight a formal and solemn promise in dumb show. Here they are interrupted, by the entrance of the Doctor; who brings Merlin with him, dress'd like a conjurer, with his wand, long beard, and trailing robe. Mock-Recitativo. Doct. Call all things, here, your own, Most sage magician! Merl. Wou'd—you excepted none! O learn'd physician!— Doct. All—All—I freely grant. Merl. Since long I've sought her: Includes the Doctor's grant The Doctor's Daughter? Doct. How bless'd my Columbine, That you approve her! Come hither, Romp of mine; Receive this Lover. Harlequin, during this last Scene, appears surpriz'd, uneasy, jealous.—Merlin, amorous, joyful, courtly.—Columbine, averse, scornful, angry—making signs of dislike, to his beard, his age, and pretensions. Air I. Merl. Why do those killing eyes, No longer languish? Why, thro' my bosom, flies, This hopeless anguish? Air II. Col. mocking in the same tune and manner. Pray, let my eyes alone; Old men see double: Cou'd you, but clear your own, 'Twou'd ease all trouble. During the time that these two airs are singing, the Doctor follows Harlequin with action of contempt, to turn him out of the apartment; which he avoids by a mixture of respectful compliments, dexterous turns, shrugs, airs, and evasions. Air III. Merl. Vain my hope to move her pity! Sighing age can none create; Why are old men fools of fashion? Youth alone, in love has weight. Cupid! let my wand command thee: Come, and charm her heart to love. If the fair one dares withstand thee! Age, and Magic join'd, may move. At the end of the air, Cupid descends, singing; and being descended, continues the following song, in action of courtship, in favour of Merlin. Air IV. Cupid. See! fair disturber of a wise man's rest, Charm'd to his aid, see! from above, Descend, the powerful god of love! Let thy pityless breast Consent to be blest: Nor be blind to a truth that thy passion shou'd move. Age with wisdom do not shun, Youth and folly oft are one. Light consenting Brings repenting: Will you run To be undone? Ah! look back, and here, be won. Let not fancied ills affright you; Rule, and wealth, and fame invite you: Be but willing—and, 'tis done. Columbine, at the end of the song, turns away disdainfully, and rejects the addresses of Cupid. Recitativo. Merl. Try—since Love can plead, and moves not, Try, if Fortune she approves not: Fortune, pow'rful Empress! rise— And court her eyes. [Strikes the stage with his wand, and the figure of Fortune rises, and makes court, in dumb action, which Columbine rejects. Merl. In vain, even Fortune tries! Wisdom!—sometimes, woman loves thee, Wisdom, see! if she approves thee. [Calls up the figure of Wisdom, which she rejects, as before. Merl. No—no—no— Alas! what stubborn lengths the cruel go! Honour is their idol passion: Honour! stronger, ev'n than Fashion! Honour, rise, and force compassion. [Honour ascends, courts, and is also rejected. Merl. Still, still—it will not be! She slights, even thee. Last, then, rise Pow'r!—the sex's darling joy, Rise, rise, O Pow'r, and all thy arts employ; This scornful rigour to destroy. [Power rises, addresses, and is rejected. After having severally, in vain, pointed out Merlin to Columbine's choice, they join in a grand dance, keeping Cupid for the middle figure. During all this, Merlin's dumb action expresses hope, love, desire, respect.—The Doctor's, wonder; and delight, at Merlin's skill: but anger at his daughter's obstinacy.— Harlequin, terrified, despairing, hoping, appears lively, and dejected, by turns; with all the wanton variety of air, look, and action, adapted to his character. After the Dance. Air V. Col. In vain, deluded Pow'rs! in vain, You tempt the constant heart: True love is the same, both in pleasure, and pain; And proof, against reason, and art. Fickle Fortune!—I defy thee: Blind, and wanton, ever turning! [Fortune sinks. Honour! all, who press too nigh thee. Feel their restless bosoms burning. [Honour sinks. To our ruin, Power deceives us: [Power sinks. Wisdom, oft, of joy bereaves us: [Wisdom sinks. Love, alone, is worth our care, All is hope, and sunshine, there! Love, alone, is worth our care. During Columbine's song, Fortune, Honour, Power, and Wisdom, severally, vanish, as she rejects them, in singing, with a motion of her hand, and stamp of her foot;—and Fortune, when about to disappear, catching Cupid in her arms, carries him down, along with her. Air VI. Doct. And, why do you look like an ass? And, why do you sigh, like a ninny? Come, cast out your devil, the lass; And raise a new spirit within ye. [The bottle. What! tho' she's as cross, as her mother! Two glasses will wash her away. Then, cease to be making a pother: Here's that, will re-moisten your clay! Tho' it make us not young, like another, 'Twill make us as brisk, and as gay. Look!—it smiles, like the day! Send the girl to her play: And, like men of sound sense, let us drink her away. They sit down, at the table, and drink: Merlin continuing melancholy; sighing, folding his arms, looking down, and shaking his head: and the Doctor expressing, in dumb action, a discourse of comfort, and persuasion. Harlequin, in the interim, observing, that Merlin, when he sat down, to drink, had deposited his wand against the side of the scene, makes dumb intimation to Columbine, of his purpose to steal it. She catches the hint, with delight; and, to favour the attempt, by screening him from observation, pretends, officiously, to fill wine for her father. Merlin, at approach of his mistress, rises, complaisantly, to offer her his chair, which she declines; and her father pushes her away, in high indignation: during which bustle, Harlequin steals the wand, and returns, unobserv'd, to his station. The old gentlemen re-assume their chairs, and their glasses: and Harlequin, beckoning Columbine, takes hold of her hand; and, waving the wand, a triumphal chariot, drawn by two doves, whose reins are held by a Cupid, arises under their feet, and carries them up into the air.—As they ascend, it thunders, and lightens: at the noise of which Merlin starts up, frighted; misses his wand, and bursts into great agony. Recitativo. Merl. Alas! alas! I'm lost! Doct. starting up suddenly. Why?—What's the matter? Merl. Fool, that I was!—Ah!—Post! Doct. following Merl. who traverses the stage in a great heat. Why came you at her? However—since she's parted, Why, let her be forgotten: Be not thus broken-hearted; Love's hopes were always rotten. Merl. turning hastily upon him. Go,—go,—nor interpose, 'Twixt me, and anger. Is this the duty, that a daughter owes! Doct. Ah!—Gipsy!—hang her! Merl. Had I not lost my wand, All dangers over-ruling; Ere this, my powerful hand— Doct. Had spoil'd their fooling. Merl. Away—I'll, yet, recover A new one, to supply me: Then, woe to this bold lover, Who dar'd defy me. [Merlin, taking a book out of his pocket, describes a circle, with it, on the stage. Doct. You've business with the devil! I hate all intervening. My stay might be uncivil, Since that's your meaning. [Runs out. Merlin, mutters in his book, the following incantation, in Recitativo. Merl. Swinswang hopandthumpo lethale farcificando! Grande tastexalto, quadrill et ombretilmorno! Tossalong stradlingo, beautilosto masculinando! Air VII. Not sung, but spoken. Merl. 'Tis done the powerful charm is heard! Belov'd, by realms below: Hell's empire, at the sound, is chear'd! And joyful Furies glow! At the close of the air, there appears something, swelling, and leaping, out of the neck of the bottle, which Merlin takes hold of, and draws up a new wand; with which he walks, angry, about the stage, making flourishes, while he sings. Air VIII. Merl. Rise, from your frightful caverns, rise, Ye winds, that drive the deep! Roar, in your race, along the skies; And the seas in surges sweep. Trace the world from West to East; And again, from Pole to Pole; Let the waves in moving mountains, roll! Let meeting winds to winds impart Sound, fury, swiftness, dread; Then, whirling, every way, at once, depart, And o'er each region spread. Find him, bring him, sweep him back! Or, blow,—till the rooted mountains shake: And their iron intrails crack! Go—sweep him back. At the end of the air, Merlin striking the table, it falls together, in form of clouds, at the touch of the wand, and is turned into four Spirits, in figure of the four Winds, who first, forming a short, swift, and violent dance, separate, and rush out, four different ways.—Merlin, then, goes off, with revengeful and threatening action.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. SCENE, a wild, rocky, prospect, with an opening, in front, that descends to Merlin's cave;—an old hollow tree growing close by its entrance. Merlin comes up, out of the cave, and looks, every way, round, with action expressing melancholy, and impatience. Air IX. Merl. Ah!—fatal road of life! thro' vales of woe! Where pale despair Tho' at each stage of rest, gay roses blow, Feels the sharp thorn of care! Ah me!—what teaches knowledge? but to know The pains, which man is doom'd to undergo! Life's a light, and gaudy bubble, Gilt with hope, and broke by trouble: Every passion, spite of reason, Rules us, in—and out of, season. Man is only born, to know Variety, of never-ending woe. A Spirit [one of the four Winds] descends, and whispers Merlin: who seems brisker, upon the intelligence brought him; and, after seeming to give orders to the Spirit, puts him into the hollow tree: and returns, himself, into the cave. Music, in the air.—The chariot descends, with Harlequin and Columbine; and, after they are alighted, flys up again, and disappears. They embrace, in high rapture; as, for joy, at their escape; but look round, as wondering what place they are brought to. Air X. Harlequin trips time to her singing. Col. 'Tis over—'tis over— And I, and my lover, In freedom escaping, forget the past pain. Let us shake off our chain, And new pleasures obtain; For life, without loving, is living, in vain. In the midst of their transport, music is heard, under ground, and the place, upon which they are standing, begins to rise under them.—Harlequin, in a great fright, runs about, as in search of a place, wherein to hide Columbine; and at length, putting her into the hollow tree, stands behind it, himself; and peeps, expressively, at what passes. Then, arises, slowly, to the sound of the subterranean music, a huge mushroom, covering eight or nine feet of the stage; and, from under it, thro' a little arch'd door, that opens, in the stalk, come out two Fairies, (a lover, and his mistress,) follow'd by a Fairy blackamore page, carrying a scaling ladder, for his Lord and Lady to mount by. Air XI. Duetta. Sung by Children. [1.] He Fairy. Gentle Fay! Pip, the gay! See! the day She. Smiles, like thee; He. And, to me, Cries—kiss her, and play: She. Come—trip, trip, away; 'Tis pity to stay, All day, In the dusk of our shades, when, above ground, we may Both. Dance the sun-shine away. 2. He. Mushroom!—beneath whose gloom we dwell; Thou, roof, to our cell! Continue to swell;— She. Let our size Also rise, Ten inches nearer to the skies! He. That my Fay's enchanting eyes Alluring the ken Of giant men, May the ladies, that live here above-ground, disgrace, And shame all the race; Tho' my Pip cou'd scarce furnish a nose for their face. She. Hard case! Both. That the greatest, in charms, shou'd be smallest, in space! 3. He. How that smile Can beguile! To the page] Hop, come hither—mark your time; Set the ladder,—let us climb: I wou'd be rais'd, and look sublime! For, who shou'd more exalted be, She. Than he, Who, loving, thus, is, thus, belov'd by, thee! Than she, Who, loving, thus, &amp;c. He. Than he— She. Than she— Both. Who, loving &amp;c. [They strut, in state, round the mushroom, while Hop sets up the ladder, against it; then, climb up, and form a dance, on the top of it. Hop takes away the ladder, and returns, as he came, shutting the door in the stalk, after him. After the dance, Harlequin, who is advanc'd from behind the tree, with action, expressing a mixture of fear, pleasure, and curiosity, coming near the mushroom, the Fairies discern him, and vanish, thro' the center of the mushroom; the woman, first; and, then, the man-fairy.—The mushroom sinking down, as at first. Harlequin, after looking on the place, with signs of great wonder and delight, attempts to enter the hollow of the tree, in search of Columbine: but, starts back in great fright, at appearance of an overgrown bear, that fills up the trunk, like a centinel. After many fearful windings, twistings, and reverted looks, at distance, he bethinks himself of his wand; and, gathering courage to return, strikes the bear, on the nose. At touch of the wand, the bear falls down, in form of a path, from the hollow tree, cover'd neatly with a carpet: at the upper part of which, appears Columbine, in act of descending. Harlequin embraces her, in extasy; and, after mutual expression of rapture, discerning the mouth of the cave, points to it, as a place of safety, and repose. Air XII. Col. Let us go, with the man, that we love, Where-ever ill-fortune can carry: All the dangers on earth, she may venture to prove, Who dares be so bold as to marry. Step first: and I'll follow unfearing; When hopes are endearing, And fancy looks chearing, The worst stroke of Fortune, 'tis easy to parry: When the call is from love, none but cowards will tarry. [Harlequin leads her down into the cave: and the scene closes upon them.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Air XI. Duetta. Sung by Children. [1.] He Fairy. Gentle Fay! Pip, the gay! See! the day She. Smiles, like thee; He. And, to me, Cries—kiss her, and play: She. Come—trip, trip, away; 'Tis pity to stay, All day, In the dusk of our shades, when, above ground, we may Both. Dance the sun-shine away. 2. He. Mushroom!—beneath whose gloom we dwell; Thou, roof, to our cell! Continue to swell;— She. Let our size Also rise, Ten inches nearer to the skies! He. That my Fay's enchanting eyes Alluring the ken Of giant men, May the ladies, that live here above-ground, disgrace, And shame all the race; Tho' my Pip cou'd scarce furnish a nose for their face. She. Hard case! Both. That the greatest, in charms, shou'd be smallest, in space! 3. He. How that smile Can beguile! To the page] Hop, come hither—mark your time; Set the ladder,—let us climb: I wou'd be rais'd, and look sublime! For, who shou'd more exalted be, She. Than he, Who, loving, thus, is, thus, belov'd by, thee! Than she, Who, loving, thus, &amp;c. He. Than he— She. Than she— Both. Who, loving &amp;c.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. SCENE, the inside of Merlin's cave. A moss-bed—a table;—books: and, on one side, a large easy chair. Enter Harlequin, with Columbine weary, and inclinable to sleep.—Harlequin points out the moss-bed, as a proper scene of repose: she lies down, on it: and he offers to lie by her side; which occasions a whimsical dumb scene of entreaty, on his part, and refusal on hers. Air XIII. very slow measure. Col. No—no—don't expect it, Marry, first, and, then, 'twill do: Now—now—I must reject it; Wait the grace, and, then, fall to. You—men—early tasting, Spoil your stomach, ere 'tis noon; Then,—then—wou'd keep us fasting, 'Cause yourselves have eat, too soon! After the air, she directs him to the easy chair; into which he leaps, antickly, up, and reclines himself, in a lolling, extravagant posture. On a sudden, the head of the chair sneezes; and Harlequin beginning to move, as in surprize, is caught fast, by an arm of the chair, about his waist: at which, twisting his face round, with great agony and distortion, the other arm of the chair is rais'd above his head, which is grasp'd violently by the hand of it. Harlequin roars out, and struggles to get loose. Columbine, behind, starts up, and leans, trembling, against the side of the cave. At length, he breaks free; and, running to a little distance, looks back, in a posture of astonishment; trembling, in expression of horror; and drops his wand, in his escape. The easy chair rises, slowly, into figure of a man (the back part falling down, to form the tail of his robe) and appears to be Merlin; who taking up Harlequin's wand, surrounds him, with a magical circle.—He falls down, on one knee, and makes signs of prayer, humility, and submission. Air XIV. Merl. Demons! Furies! rise, and take him, From his dream of safety wake him; Let a whirlwind rise, and shake him, Seize him—break him; Nor, till lost in air, forsake him. Two Furies arise, and form a dance round the circle, to the tune of the incantation: to which Harlequin keeps time, with the trembling of his right knee, and left heel, upon the stage: introducing an apt and doleful groan in each close of the music. Columbine, at length, in pity, appears, and comes forward. Recitativo. Col. Ah!—be not too severe: Bid, bid, those devils forsake him. Consider,—I am here; And, let me take him. Merl. Ah! welcome, cruel fair! Let me but gain thee: I wou'd his fate forbear; Cou'd that obtain thee. Col. Where must he go?—Alas! Merl. Where-e'er he pleases. This wand shall be his pass: Col. My sorrow ceases. Go—fated lover!—go, Wait fairer weather. Better, to lose me, so! Than love, and life, together! Harlequin weeps, shrugs, sighs, shakes his head, makes signs that he will hang himself: but, after great tokens of reluctance, pulls out his half piece of the gold, that was broke, between him and Columbine, and restores it dloefully to her.—She gives it, as if unwilling, to Merlin; and, then, taking her own half, from her bosom, tallies, and exchanges the pieces. Recitativo. Col. This broken half is mine: Merl. To mine, I fit it. Col. As, now, both pieces join, Let both hearts hit it. Merl. Next, as both pieces, thus, Once more, become divided; Col. So, 'till death severs us, Rest truth, in truth, confided. At a signal of Merlin's wand, the Furies disappear. Air XV. Merl. Come hither, poor trembler, and have a good heart, The danger is over, for ever: Tho' one, thou hast lost, thou mayst gayly depart, And look out a second, as clever. Take with thee this wand, and go, try thy success, Whome'er thou shalt like, thou mayst take her: And, when thou no longer delight'st to possess; Turn round like a Lord, and forsake her. Merlin leads off Columbine: Harlequin, in sad, and dismal, airs, goes off, on the other side. They look back, step by step; and, at last, burst away, in agony, at the opposite doors; in mimic imitation of distress'd lovers in tragedy.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT IV. SCENE, a wheat field, the back unreap'd;—in the front some standing sheaves. A reaper, and woman binder, at the foot of one of the sheaves, at dinner. Bread, cheese, and a gallon cag, before them. Harlequin, in dumb courtship, appears suddenly fond of the woman, who expresses contempt, and throws cheese-parings at him. The man, at length, rises, angry. Air XVI. Clown [1.] What wou'd you have friend—What is't, you mean? You'd best gang your ways—and leave us, aloan: Sure! 'tis a proudness, not often seen, To hinder a poor man—from kissing his oan. 2. Dorcas, and I, here, meant you no harm— Your fine, 'broider'd coatd'ant make me afeard: Folks in the country, keep foot, and arm, Enow, to secure 'em from soon being scear'd. 3. Nay—tho'—by hap now, Dorcas had been Betray'd here, aloan—I'll tell you one thing: She had been able—shin Sung with a gesture of throwing out the foot, like a wrestler. against shin, To give you, at least, friend, as good as you bring. Harlequin cajoles the reaper, seems to beg pardon of the girl; and grows exceedingly civil: this, reconciling the Clown, he takes the cag, to drink to Harlequin; and they shake hands: but, while the reaper has the cag at his mouth, Harlequin strikes it, with his wand, and it rises over the countryman's head, falls down, about him, in shape of a great barrel; and sinks, with him, under the stage. —The girl, in grief for the loss of her lover, is addressed, with great airs of gallantry, by Harlequin, who, to entertain, and divert her melancholy, touches the wheat-sheaves with his wand: upon which, they move, divide, and fall into measure; forming a kind of hop, and thump, dance, in which they go off the stage, at different openings. Harlequin, persisting in his amorous airs, the girl, growing more and more angry, at length falls upon him, and beats him. After breaking out of her hands, he waves his wand, with great indignation, and seeming resentment. It thunders: at which, he looks frighted, and amazed, as expecting a different consequence. There arise, to him, instead of spirits, Merlin and Columbine. She reproaches him, in the following air. Air XVII. Col. Ah! false, inconstant man! was this your passion? You change, by nature, all; and love, for fashion! Your light, uncertain, hearts, are always roving: And, women, still, are lost, by truth in loving. Cou'd I have thought, so soon, to see you changing! Farewel, fond hope of faith!—Man lives, for ranging. Harlequin, in his surprize, having dropt his wand, Merlin kicks it away, and sets his foot upon it. Air XVIII. Merl. [1.] Tremble, at thy fate, deceiver! Hope no more, to 'scape the pain Thou, who, cou'dst so lightly, leave her, Ne'er deserv'st to please, again. 2. Go, prepare—the vengeance waits thee. Which thy fortune late out-ran: None will pity, now she hates thee; None befriend the perjur'd man. At the end of the songs, it thunders again; and the scene is changed, in a moment, into the prospect of a rolling sea, surrounded with cliffs, steep rocks, and precipices: at sight whereof, Harlequin runs off the stage. Furies rise out of the sea, with tridents in their hands: and are sent out by Merlin, in pursuit of Harlequin. They hunt him up and down, round the house, and behind the tops of the rocks, sometimes seen and sometimes not, while Merlin below, sings the following chace, to the sound of a French horn. Air XIX. Merl. Up, and down, o'er the hills, from the rock to the vale, Pursue him, affright him, o'ertake him—away: Let the sound of the horn wing your speed, as you scale, And drive you upon him, like tempests of hail! Hunt away, hunt away: See! the light of the day Seems to double its brightness, and points out the way! At the close of this song, one of the Furies enters in front, above the cliffs, with Harlequin sticking on the points of his trident; and plunges him into the sea, in face of the audience—The dashing of water, heard, at fall of the figure.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT V. SCENE, the sea, as before. Merlin and Columbine. Recitativo. Col. I'll not be satisfied: No— Merl. Why?—relentless fair! Sure!—when a perjur'd lover died, He claim'd not this despair! Col. No more—I die, to hear his name, Who, for my sake, has bled: Merl. Yet, while he liv'd, you join'd, to blame. Col. Alas!—But, now, he's dead! Merl. Wou'd you be pacified, my art Cou'd, yet, his life restore: But, let an oath convince my heart, You ne'er will see him, more. Col. I swear— Merl. Enough. Behold this wand, Whate'er he dares require, Who waves it, with commanding hand, It grants the bold desire. Neptune, beneath the stormy wreck, Shall hear its magic call: And give your perish'd wand'rer, back, From his sea-cover'd hall. Col. If such, its power, ah! let my hand That charity bestow! Let him, by aid of this dear wand, To me, redemption owe. To me, who, injur'd, can forgive; And will, from death, restore: Then, once, upbraid him—bid him live, And never see him more. Merlin intrusts her with the wand; and she sings the following incantation. Air XX. Col. Down, through the deep, down, far, far, far, below, Profoundly aweful, and serene! Where whisp'ring tempests are afraid to blow, And nothing mortal's seen! Hear!—from thy coral groves, great Neptune! hear! Descend, ye Pow'rs, that aid my waving rod! Descend in magic sounds—go, near; Strike thro' his storm-resisting ear: And wake the sleeping god! Tell him—love, that lives, to bless, Reclaims a wanderer, lost: O!—let him save me from distress; And free the fleeting ghost. During the invocation, there arises out of the sea, a huge whale, that covers the whole flat of the stage.—In the mouth of the whale, sits Harlequin, with a lanthorn in his hand, and sings, in his ascending. [Note, a singer placed behind him. Air XXI. Harl. Where am I? good people, where am I? It smells like a fish's belly! May I never more dive, If, dead, or alive, Is a point, that I know, how to tell ye! But whoever may ha' me, I am sure, I don't sham ye, When I swear, and declare, That I tremble, and stare; And am melting apace, to a jelly! The whale continues to rise, higher and higher, till at length it forms the roof to a marine palace, supported on for silvery pillars, glittering like the scales of fishes.—The sea re-appears below; and, from the midst of it, arises a coral rock, with Neptune seated on its top; surrounded by Tritons below, and Mermaids at more distance. Air XXII. To the sound of the Tritons' shells. Nept. Sound, sound, ye Tritons! sound your tuneful shells! Tell the mortal, that invokes us, Magic force, in vain, provokes us; But, when love its sorrow tells, Complaining beauty, heard through all our cells, Our aid compels; And adamantine hearts to pity swells! Tell the Fair One, we approve her; Send her back, her roving lover, More sincere, and grateful to her.— Let, him since his fancy chose her, Let him—now his life he owes her, With a faithful passion, woe her, Nor pursue her, Like a false one—to undoe her. Let him, &amp;c. During the song, a succession of rocks, arising from behind, form a winding ascent to the back part of the roof, whereby Neptune goes up out of sight, preceded in state by the Tritons; while the Mermaids sink into the surges. The clouds being drawn up from before, there appears, above the roof, a transparent arch; to the opening whereof advance the Tritons, from behind; followed by Neptune, leading Harlequin, and delivering him, at the opening of the arch, to the care of two Cupids: supported between whom, he is gently let down to the sound of soft music; and presented to Columbine. Air XXIII. Col. Turn, turn away your face, Lest this last favour, This final act of grace, This leave you gave her; Shou'd bring your mistress woe, By your repenting: And you shou'd jealous grow, And curse consenting. Air XXIV. Merl. Stretch, as you please, your grace, I will not heed it: See! see!—I shade my face; 'Twas Love decreed it. Merlin turning away his face, and shading himself behind his robe, Columbine, after winking upon Harlequin, strikes Merlin with the wand, and changes him into an ass, with a halter about his neck: after which, she dresses Harlequin in his rival's robe, and puts the wand into his hand; with which, he struts and dances about in exstacy: and, at length, mounting on the ass's back, is led off in triumph by Columbine, singing. Air XXV. Col. The wise may take warning, as well as they can, Still thus, will it come to pass! Let a young woman loose, at an old cunning man; The conjurer proves but an ass.</field>
   </doc>
</add>