<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Jonson, Ben, 1573-1637</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Jonson, Ben, 1573-1637</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">jonson ben 1573 1637</field>
      <field name="author_text">Jonson, Ben, 1573-1637</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">17th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V1.0756.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1616</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:459449</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Greek, Modern (1453- )</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Part of the Kings Entertainment in Passing to his Coronation</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 17th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 17th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Part of the Kings Entertainment in Passing to his Coronation</field>
      <field name="title_facet">part of the kings entertainment in passing to his coronation</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">part of the kings entertainment in passing to his coronation</field>
      <field name="title_text">Part of the Kings Entertainment in Passing to his Coronation</field>
      <field name="year_display">1616</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1616</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1616</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459449&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459449&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Jonson, Ben, 1573?-1637&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;jonson ben 1573 1637&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Part of the Kings Entertainment in Passing to his Coronation&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;part of the kings entertainment in passing to his coronation&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1616&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1616&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Jonson, Ben&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1573&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1637&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Part of the Kings Entertainment in Passing to his Coronation&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Imprinted ... by Will. Stansby&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1616&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3871488-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv10756&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;gre&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 17th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;17th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Part of the Kings Entertainment in Passing to his Coronation&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 84 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Only verse drama included&lt;lb/&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;lb/&gt;English commendatory poems and Latin epigraph included with Seianus his Fall. A Tragœdie&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Part of the Kings entertainment in passing to his coronation.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Entertainment.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1604.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 15 Mar 1604.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PART OF THE KINGS ENTERTAINMENT IN PASSING TO his Coronation.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Quando magis dignos licuit spectare triumphos! Mart.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">At Fen-Church. The Scene presented it selfe in a square and flat vpright, like to the side of a Citie: the top thereof, aboue the Vent, and Crest, adorn'd with houses, towres, and steeples, set off in prospectiue. Vpon the battlements in a great capitall letter was inscribed, Londinivm: According to Tacitvs: At Svetonivs Annal. l. 14. mirâ constantiâ, medios inter hosteis Londinium perrexit, cognomento quidem Coloniæ non insigne, sed copiâ Negotiatorum, &amp; commeatu maxime celebre. Beneath that, in a lesse, and different character, was written CAMERA REGIA, Which title immediately after the Norman conquest it began to haue; and Camd. Brit. 374. by the indulgence of succeeding Princes, hath beene hitherto continued. In the Freeze ouer the gate, it seemeth to speake this verse: PAR DOMVS HÆC COELO, SED MINOR EST DOMINO. Taken out of Martial, and implying, that though this citie (for the Lib. 8. Epig. 36. state, and magnificence) might (by Hyperbole) be said to touch the starres, and reach vp to heauen, yet was it farre inferior to the master thereof, who was his Maiestie; and in that respect vnworthy to receiue him. The highest person aduanc'd therein, was MONARCHIA BRITANNICA, and fitly: applying to the aboue mentioned title of the citie, The Kings Chamber, and therefore here placed as in the proper seate of the empire: for, so the glorie and light of our kingdome M. Camden, speaking of Brit. 367. London, saith, shee is, totius Britanniæ Epitome, Brittanic? Imperij sedes, Regum? Angliæ Camera, tantum inter omneis eminet, quantum (vt ait ille) inter viburna Cupressus. Shee was a woman, richly attyr'd, in cloth of gold and tissue; a rich mantle; ouer her state two crownes hanging, with pensile shields thorow them; the one lim'd with the particular coate of England, the other of Scotland: on either side also a crowne, with the like Scutchions, and peculiar coates of France, and Ireland. In her hand shee holds a scepter; on her head a fillet of gold, inter-wouen with palme and lawrell; her hayre bound into foure seuerall points, descending from her crownes; and in her lap a little globe, inscrib'd vpon ORBIS BRITANNICVS. And beneath, the word DIVISVS AB ORBE. To shew, that this empire is a world diuided from the world, and alluding to that of Clav. De mallij Theodor. cons. Panegyri. Eclog. 1. —Et nostro diducta Britannia mundo. And Virg. —Et penitus toto diuisos orbe Britannos. The wreathe denotes victorie and happinesse. The scepter and crownes soueraignetie. The shields the precedency of the countries, and their distinctions. At her feet was set THEOSOPHIA, or diuine Wisedome, all in white, a blue mantle seeded with starres, a crowne of starres on her head. Her garments figur'd truth, innocence, and cleerenesse. Shee was alwayes looking vp; in her one hand shee sustayned a doue, in the other a serpent: the last to shew her subtiltie, the first her simplicitie; alluding to that text of Scripture, Estote ergo prudentes sicut serpentes, Matth. 10. 16. &amp; simplices sicut columbæ. Her word, PER ME REGES REGNANT. Prou. 8. 15. Intimating, how by her, all kings doe gouerne, and that she is the foundation and strength of kingdomes, to which end, shee was here placed, vp on a cube, at the foot of the Monarchie, as her base and stay. Directly beneath her stood GENIVS VRBIS, Antiqui Genium omnium gignendarum rer? existimarunt Deum: &amp; tam vrbib. quam hominib. vel cæteris rebus natum, Lil. Gre. Gy. in Synt. deor. 15. &amp; Rosin. Antiq. Ro. l. 2. c. 14 A person attyr'd rich, reuerend, and antique: his haire long and white, crowned with a wreathe of Plane tree, which is said to be Arbor genialis; his mantle of purple, and buskins of that colour: He held in one hand a goblet, in the other a branch full of little twigs, to signifie increase and indulgence. His word HIS ARMIS: pointing to the two that supported him, whereof the one on the right hand, was BOVLEVTES. Figuring the councell of the citie, and was suted in blacke and purple; a wreathe of Ciuica corona fit è fronde querna, quoniam cibus, victus? antiquissimus querceus capi solitus sit, Ros. lib. 10. cap. 27. oke vpon his head; sustayning for his ensignes, on his left arme a scarlet robe, and his right hand the Fasciculi virgarum, intra quas obligata securis erat, sic, vt ferrum in summo fasce extaret, Ros. l. 7. c. 3. Vbi notandum est, non debere precipitem, &amp; solutam iram esse magistratus. Mora enim allata, &amp; cunctatio, dum sensim virgæ soluuntur, identidem consilium mutanit deplectendo. Quando autem vitia quadam sunt corrigibilia, deplorata alia; castigant virgæ, quod reuocari valet, immendabile secures præcidunt, Plut. Prob. Rom. 82. Fasces, as tokens of magistracie, with this inscription; SERVARE CIVES. the other on the left hand. POLEMIVS, The warlike force of the citie, in an antique coate, or armour, with a target and sword; his helme on, and crowned with lawrell, implying strength and conquest: in his hand he bore the standard of the citie, with this word, EXTINGVERE ET HOSTEIS. Expressing by those seuerall mots, connexed, that with those armes of councel and strength, the Genius was able to extinguish the kings enemies, and preserue his citizens, alluding to those verses in Seneca, Extinguere bostem, maxima est virtus Ducis. Octa. Act. 2. Seruare Ciues, maior est patriæ, patri. Vnder-neath these, in an Aback thrust out before the rest, lay TAMESIS. The riuer, as running along the side of the citie; in a skin-coate made like flesh, naked, and blue. His mantle of sea-greene or water colour, thin, and bolne out like a sayle; bracelets about his wrests, of willow and sedge, a crowne of sedge and reede vpon his head, mixt with water-lillies; alluding to Virgils description of Tyber; —Deus ipse loci, fluuio Tyberinus amœno, Æn. lib. 8. Populeas inter senior se attollere frondes Visus, eum tenuis glauco velabat amictu Carbusus, &amp; crineis vmbrosa tegebat Arundo. His beard, and hayre long, and ouer-growne. He leanes his arme vpon an earthen pot, out of which, water, with liue fishes, are seene to runne forth, and play about him. His word, FLVMINA SENSERVNT IPSA. A hemistich of Ovids: The rest of the verse being, Amor. l. 3 el. 5. —quid esset amor Affirming, that riuers themselues, and such inanimate creatures, haue heretofore beene made sensible of passions, and affections; and that hee now, no lesse pertooke the ioy of his maiesties gratefull approch to this citie, than any of those persons, to whom hee pointed, which were the daughters of the Genius, and sixe in number: who, in a spreading ascent, vpon seuerall grices, helpe to beautifie both the sides. The first, EVPHROSYNE, or Gladnesse: was suted in greene, a mantle of diuers colours, embroydred with all varietie of flowres: on her head a gyrland of myrtle, in her right hand a crystall cruze fill'd with wine, in the left a cup of gold: at her feet a tymbrell, harpe, and other instruments, all ensignes of gladnesse, Natis in vsum lætitiæ scyphis, &amp;c. And in another place, Hor. Car. 1. Ode 27. Nunc est bibendum, nunc pede libero Pulsanda Tellus, &amp;c. Et Ode. 37. Her word, HÆC ÆVI MIHI PRIMA DIES. As if this were the first houre of her life, and the minute wherein shee Stat Syl. 4. Epu. Domit. began to be; beholding so long coueted, and look'd for a presence. The second. SEBASIS. or Veneratio, was varied in an ash-colour'd sute, and darke mantle, a vayle ouer her head of ash colour: her hands crost before her, and her eyes halfe closde. Her word, MIHI SEMPER DEVS. Implying both her office of reuerence, and the dignitie of her obiect, Virg. Ecl. 1: who being as god on earth, should neuer be lesse in her thought. The third. PROTHYMIA, or Promptitude, was attyr'd in a short tuck't garment of flame-colour, wings at her backe; her haire bright, and bound vp with ribands; her brest open, virago-like; her buskins so ribanded: Shee was crowned with a chaplet of trifoly, to expresse readinesse, and opennesse euery way; in her right hand shee held a squirrell, as being the creature most full of life and quicknesse: in the left a close round censor, with the perfume sodainely to be vented forth at the sides. Her word, QVA DATA PORTA. Taken from an other place in Virgil, where Eolvs at the command Æne. 1. of Ivno, lets forth the winde; —ac venti velut agmine facto Æne. 1. Quâ data porta ruunt, &amp; terras turbine perflant. And shew'd that shee was no lesse prepar'd with promptitude, and alacritie, then the windes were, vpon the least gate that shall be opened to his high command. The fourth. AGRYPNIA, or Vigilance, in yellow, a sable mantle, seeded with waking eyes, and siluer fringe: her chaplet of Heliotropium, or turnesole; in her one hand a lampe, or cresset, in her other a bell. The lampe signified search and sight, the bell warning. The Heliotropium care; and respecting her obiect. Her word, SPECVLAMVR IN OMNEIS. Alluding to that of Ovid, where he describes the office of Argvs. —Ipse procul montis sublime cacumen Occupat, vnde sedens partes speculatur in omneis. Met. 1. and implying the like duety of care and vigilance in her selfe. The fifth, AGAPE, Or louing affection, in crimson fringed with golde, a mantle of flame-colour, her chaplet of red and white roses; in her hand a flaming heart: The flame expressed zeale, the red and white roses, a mixture of simplicity with loue: her robes freshnes and feruency. Her word, NON SIC EXCVBIÆ. Out of Clavdian, in following. De 4. Cons. Honor. Panegyri. —Neccircumstantia peila Quàm tutatur amor. Inferring, that though her sister before had protested watchfulnesse, and circumspection, yet no watch or guard could be so safe to the estate, or person of a Prince, as the loue and naturall affection of his subiects: which she in the cities behalfe promised. The sixt, OMOTHYMIA, Or vnanimity in blew, her roabe blew, and buskins. A chaplet of blew lillies, shewing one trueth and intirenesse of minde. In her lappe lies a sheafe of arrowes bound together, and she her selfe sittes weauing certaine small siluer twists. Her word, FIRMA CONSENSVS FACIT. Auxilia humilia firma, &amp;c. Pub. Syr. Mi. Intimating, that euen the smallest and weakest aydes, by consent, are made strong: herselfe personating the vnanimity, or consent of soule, in all inhabitants of the city to his seruice. These are all the personages, or liue figures, whereof only two were speakers (Genivs and Tamesis) the rest were mutes. Other dumbe complements there were, as the armes of the kingdome on the one side, with this inscription. HIS VIREAS. With these maist thou flourish. On the other side the armes of the citie, with HIS VINCAS. With these maist thou conquer. In the centre, or midst of the Pegme, there was an Aback, or Square, wherein this Elogie was written: Maximvs hic Rex est, et lvce serenior ipsa Principe qvae talem cernit in vrbe Dvcem; Cvivs Fortvnam svperat sic vnica Virtvs, Vnvs vt is reliqvos vincit vtraqve viros. Praeceptis alii popvlos, mvltaqve fatigant Lege; sed exemplo nos rapit ille svo. Cviqve frvi tota fas est vxore marito, Et sva fas simili pignora nosse patri. Ecce vbi pignoribvs circvmstipata corvscis It comes, et tanto vix minor ANNA viro. Havd metvs est, Regem posthac ne proximvs Haeres, Nev Svccessorem non amet ille svvm. This, and the whole frame, was couered with a curtaine of silke, painted like a thicke cloud, and at the approach of the K. was instantly to be drawne. The Allegorie being, that those clouds were gathered vpon the face of the Citie, through their long want of his most wished sight: but now, as at the rising of the Sunne, all mists were dispersed and fled. When sodainely, vpon silence made to the Musickes, a voyce was heard to vtter this verse; Totus adest oculis, aderat qui mentibus olim, Claud. de laud. Stil. lib. 3. Signifying, that he now was really obiected to their eyes, who before had beene onely, but still, present in their minds. Thus farre the complementall part of the first; wherein was not onely labored the expression of state and magnificence (as proper to a triumphall Arch) but the very site, fabricke, strength, policie, dignitie, and affections of the Citie were all laid downe to life: The nature and propertie of these Deuices being, to present alwaies some one entire bodie, or figure, consisting of distinct members, and each of those expressing it selfe, in the owne actiue spheare, yet all, with that generall harmonie so connexed, and disposed, as no one little part can be missing to the illustration of the whole: where also is to be noted, that the Symboles vsed, are not, neither ought to be, simply Hieroglyphickes, Emblemes, or Impreses, but a mixed character, partaking somewhat of all, and peculiarly apted to these more magnificent Inuentions: wherein, the garments and ensignes deliuer the nature of the person, and the word the present office. Neither was it becomming, or could it stand with the dignitie of these shewes (after the most miserable and desperate shift of the Puppits) to require a Truch-man, or (with the ignorant Painter) one to write, This is a Dog; or, This is a Hare: but so to be presented, as vpon the view, they might, without cloud, or obscuritie, declare themselues to the sharpe and learned: And for the multitude, no doubt but their grounded iudgements did gaze, said it was fine, and were satisfied. The speeches of Gratulation. GENIVS. Time, Fate, and Fortune haue at length conspir'd, To giue our Age the day so much desir'd. What all the minutes, houres, weekes, months, and yeares, That hang in file vpon these siluer haires, Could not produce, beneath the As being the first free and naturall gouernment of this Iland, after it came to ciuilitie. Britaine stroke, The Roman, Saxon, Dane, and Norman In respect they were all Conquests, and the obedience of the subiect more enforced. yoke, This point of Time hath done. Now London reare Thy forehead high, and on it striue to weare Thy choisest gems; teach thy steepe Towres to rise Higher with people: set with sparkling eyes Thy spacious windowes; and in euery street, Let thronging ioy, loue, and amazement meet. Cleaue all the ayre with showtes, and let the cry Strike through as long, and vniuersally, As thunder; for, thou now art blist to see That sight, for which thou didst begin to be. When Rather then the Citie should want a Founder, we choose to follow the receiued storie of Brute, whether fabulous, or true, and not altogether vnwarranted in Poetrie: since it is a fauor of Antiquitie to few Cities, to let them know their first Authors. Besides, a learned Poet of our time, in a most elegant worke of his Con. Tam. &amp; Isis, celebrating London, hath this verse of her: Æmula maternæ tollens sua lumina Troiæ. Here is also an ancient rite alluded to in the building of Cities, which was, to giue them their bounds with a plough, according to Virg. Æn. li. 10. Interea Aeneas vrbem designat Aratro. And Isidore, lib. 15. cap. 2. Vrbs vocata ab orbe, quod antiquæ ciuitates in orbem fiebant; vel ab vrbo parte aratri, quo muri designabantur, vnde est illud. Optauitque locum regno &amp; concludere sulco. Brvtvs plough first gaue thee infant bounds, And I, thy Genivs walk't auspicious rounds In euery Primigenius sulcus dicitur, qui in condenda noua vrbe, tauro &amp; vacca designationis causa imprimitur; Hitherto respects that of Camd. Erit. 368. speaking of this Citie, Quicunque autem condiderit, vitali genio, constructam fuisse ipsius fortune docuit. furrow; then did I forelooke, And saw this day For so all happie dayes were. Plin. cap. 40. lib. 7. Nat. Hist. To which Horace alludes, lib. 1. Ode 36. Cressâ ne careat pulchra dies notâ. And the other Plin. epist. 11. lib 6. O diem lætum, notandumque mihi candidissimo calculo. With many other in many places. Mart. lib. 8. epi. 45. lib. 9. epi. 53. lib. 10. 38. lib. 11. 37. Stat. lib. 4. Syl. 6. Pers. sat. 2. Catull. epig. 69. &amp;c. mark't white in The Parcæ, or Fates, Martianus calls them scribas ac librarias superûm; whereof Clotho is said to be the eldest, signifying in Latine Euocatio. Clotho's booke. The seuerall Those before mentioned of the Britaine, Roman, Saxon, &amp;c. and to this Register of the fates allude those verses of Ouid. Met. 15. —Cerues illic molimine vasto. Ex ære, &amp; solido rerum tabularia ferro: Que neque concussum cœli, neque fulminis Iram, Nec metuunt vllas tuta atque æterna ruinas. Inuenies illis incisa adamante perenni Fata &amp;c.— circles, both of change and sway, Within this Isle, there also figur'd lay: Of which the greatest, perfectest, and last Was this, whose present happinesse we tast. Why keepe you silence daughters? What dull peace Is this inhabites you? Shall office cease, Vpon th'aspect of him, to whom you owe More then you are, or can be? Shall Time know That article, wherein your flame stood still, And not aspi'rd? Now heauen auert an ill Of that blacke looke. Ere pause possesse your brests I wish you more of plagues: “Zeale when it rests, Leaues to be zeale. Vp thou tame River, wake; And from the liquid limbes this slumber shake: Thou drown'st thy selfe in inofficious sleepe; And these thy sluggish waters seeme to creepe, Rather than flow. Vp, rise, and swell with pride Aboue thy bankes. “Now is not euery tyde. TAMESIS. To what vaine end should I contend to show My weaker powers, when seas of pompe o'reflow The cities face: and couer all the shore With sands more rich than A riuer diuiding Spaine &amp; Portugal, and by the consent of Poets sti'ld aurifer. Tagvs wealthy ore? When in the flood of ioy, that comes with him, He drownes the world; yet makes it liue and swimme, And spring with gladnesse: not my fishes heere, Though they be dumbe, but doe expresse the cheere Of these bright streames. No lesse may Vnderstanding Euphrosyne, Sebasis, Prothumia, &amp;c. these, and I Boast our delights, albe't we silent lie. GENIVS. Indeede, true gladnesse doth not alwayes speake: “Ioy bred, and borne but in the tongue, is weake. Yet (lest the feruor of so pure a flame As this my citie beares, might lose the name, Without the apt euenting of her heate) Know greatest Iames (and no lesse good, than great.) In the behalfe of all my vertuous sonnes, Whereof my The lord Maior, who for his yeere, hath senior place of the rest, &amp; for the day was chiefe serieant to the king. eldest there, thy pompe forerunnes, (A man without my flattering, or his pride, As worthy, as he's Aboue the blessing of his present office, the word had some particular allusion to his Name, which is Benet, and hath (no doubt) in time bin the contraction of Benedict. blest to be thy guide) In his graue name, and all his brethrens right, (Who thirst to drinke the nectar of thy sight) The councell, commoners, and multitude; (Glad, that this day so long deny'd, is view'd) I tender thee the heartiest welcome, yet That euer king had to his The citie which title is toucht before. empires seate: Neuer came man, more long'd for, more desir'd: And being come, more reuerenc'd, lou'd, admir'd: Heare, and record it: “In a prince it is “No little vertue, to know who are his. To the prince. With like deuotions, doe I stoope t'embrace This springing glory of thy An attribute giuen to great persons, fitly aboue other, humanity, and in frequent vse with all the greeke Poets, especially Homer. Iliad. a—???? ????????. And in the same booke.—??? ????. ???? ?????????. godlike race; His countries wonder, hope, loue, ioy and pride: How well dooth he become the royall side Of this erected, and broade spreading Tree, Vnder whose shade, may Brittaine euer be. And from this branch, may thousand branches more Shoote o're the maine, and knit with euery shore In bonds of marriage, kinred, and increase; And stile this land, the As Luctatius calls Parnassus, Vmbillicum terra. nauill of their peace. This is your seruants wish, your cities vow, Which still shall propagate it selfe, with you; And free from spurres of hope, that slow minds moue: “He seekes no hire, that owes his life to loue. To the queene. And heere she comes that is no lesse a part In this dayes greatnesse, then in my glad heart. Glory of queenes, and An emphatical speech, &amp; well re-enforcing her greatnes; being by this match, more than either her brother, father, &amp;c. glory of your name, Whose graces doe as farre out-speake your fame, As fame doth silence, when her trumpet rings You Daughter to Frederick sec?d king of Denmarke, and Norway, sister to Christierne the fourth now there reigning, &amp; wife to Iames our Soueraigne. daughter, sister, wife of seuerall kings: Besides alliance, and the stile of mother, In which one title you drowne all your other. Instance, be The prince Henrie Frederike. that faire shoote, is gone before, Your eldest ioy, and top of all your store, With Charles duke of Rothsey, and the Lady Elizabeth. those, whose sight to vs is yet deni'd, But not our zeale to them, or ought beside This citie can to you: For whose estate Shee hopes you will be still good aduocate To her best lord. So, whilst you mortall are, No taste of sowre mortalitie once dare Approch your house; nor fortune greete your grace But comming on, and with a forward face.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The other at Temple-barre. Carried the frontispice of a temple, the walls of which and gates were brasse; the pillars siluer, their capitalls and bases gold: in the highest point of all was erected a Ianvs head, &amp; ouer it written, IANO QVADRIFRONTI SACRVM. Which title of Quadrifrons is said to be giuen him, as he respecteth all Bassus apud Macro. l. 1. Satur. cap. 9. climates, and fills all parts of the world with his maiestie: which Martial would seeme to allude vnto in that Hendicasillable, Et linguâ pariter locutus omni. Lib. 8. Epist. 20 Others haue thought it by reason of the foure elements, which brake out of him, being Chaos: for Ovid is not afraid to make Chaos and Ianvs the same, in those verses. Me Chaos antiqui (nam sum res prisca) vocabant Fast. lib. 1. Adspice, &amp;c. But we rather follow (and that more particularly) the opinion of the Lege Marlianum, l. 4. cap. 8. Alb. in deorum. ancients, who haue entitled him Quadrifrons, in regard of the yeere (which vnder his sway is diuided into foure seasons, spring, summer, autumne, winter, and ascribe vnto him the beginnings and ends of things. See M. Cic. De nat. deorum, lib. 2. Cum? in omnibus rebus vim haberent maximam prima &amp; extreme, principem in sacrificando Ianvm esse voluerunt, quod Quasi Eanus. ab cundo nomen est deductum: ex quo transitiones peruiæ Iani, fores? in liminibus profanarum ædium, Ianuæ nominatur, &amp;c. As also the charge and custodie of the whole world, by Ovid: Quicquid vbi? vides cœlum, mare, nubila, terras. Fast. Jbid. Omnia sunt nostra clausa patent? mana: Me penes est vnum vasti custodia mundi. Et ius vertendi cardinis omne meum est. About his foure heads he had a wreathe of gold, in which was grauen this verse, Tot vultvs mihi nec satis pvtavi. Mart. l. 8. Epist. 2. Signifying, that though he had foure faces, yet he thought them not enough, to behold the greatnesse and glorie of that day: beneath vnder the head was written, Et modo sacrifico clvsivs ore vocor. Ouid. Fast. 1. For being open he was stil'd Patvlcivs, but then vpon the comming of his maiestie, being to be shut, he was to be called Clvsivs. Vpon the outmost front of the building was placed the intire armes of the kingdom with the garter, crowne, and supporters, cut forth as faire and great as the life, with an Hexastich written vnder-neath, all expressing the dignitie, and power of him that should close that temple. Qvi dvdvm angvstis tantvm regnavit in oris Parvoqve Imperio se toti praebvit Orbi Esse regendo parem, tria Regna (vt nvlla deesset Virtvti fortvna) svo feliciter vni Ivncta simvl sensit: fas vt sit credere votis Non i am sangvinea frvitvros pace Britannos. In a great freeze, below, that ranne quite along the bredth of the building, were written these two verses out of Horace. Lib. 2. Epist. 1. ad Aug. Ivrandasqve svvm per nomen ponimvs aras, Nil oritvrvm alias, nil ortvm tale tatentes. The first and principall person in the temple, was IRENE, or Peace, shee was placed aloft in a Cant, her attyre white, semined with starres, her haire loose and large: a wreathe of oliue on her head, on her shoulder a siluer doue: in her left hand, shee held forth an oliue branch, with a handfull of ripe eares, in the other a crowne of lawrell, as notes of victorie and plentie. By her stood PLVTVS, or Wealth, a little boy, bare headed, his locks curled, and spangled with gold, So Cephisiodotus hath fained him. See Paus. in Bœoti. &amp; Phil. in Jmag. contrary to Aristop. Theogn. Lucian and others, that make him blind and deformed. of a fresh aspect, his body almost naked, sauing some rich robe cast ouer him; in his armes a heape of gold Ingots to expresse riches, whereof hee is the god. Beneath her feet lay ENYALIVS, or Mars, groueling, his armour scattered vpon him in seuerall pieces, and sundrie sorts of weapons broken about him, her word to all was Vna trivmphis innvmeris potior. pax optima rerum Sil. Ital. Quas homini nouisse datum est, pax vna Triumphis Innumeris potior. signifying that peace alone was better, and more to be coueted then innumerable triumphs, besides, vpon the right hand of her, but with some little descent; in a Hemicycle was seated ESYCHIA, or Quiet, the first hand-maid of peace; a woman of a graue and venerable aspect, attyred in black, vpon her head an artificiall nest, out of which appeared storkes heads to manifest a sweet repose. Her feete were placed vpon a cube, to shew stabilitie, and in her lap shee held a perpendicular or leuell, as the ensigne of euennesse and rest: on the top of it sate a Halcion or kings-fisher. Shee had lying at her feet TARACHE, or Tumult, in a garment of diuers, but darke colours, her haire wilde, and disordered, a foule and troubled face, about her lay staues, swords, ropes, chaines, hammers, stones, and such like to expresse Turmoile. The word was, Peragit Tranqvilla Potestas. De Malii. Theo. cons. Panegy. Claud. Quod violenta nequit: mandata? fortius vrget Imperiosa quies. To shew the benefits of a calme and facile power, being able to effect in a state that, which no violence can. On the other side the second hand-maide was ELEVTHERIA, or Libertie, her dressing white, and some-what antique, but loose and free: her haire flowing downe her backe, and shoulders: In her right hand shee bare a club, on her left a hat, the Characters of freedome, and power: At her feet a cat was placed, the creature most affecting, and expressing libertie. She trode on DOVLOSIS, or Seruitude, a woman in old and worne garments, leane and meager, bearing fetters on her feet, and hands, about her necke a yoake to insinuate bondage, and the word Nec Vnqvam Gratior. Alluding to that other of Claud. Nunquam libertas gratior extat, De laud. stil. li. 3. Quam sub Rege pio. And intimated, that libertie could neuer appeare more gracefull, and louely, then now vnder so good a prince. The third hand-maid was SOTERIA, or Safetie, a damsell in carnation, the colour signifying cheare, and life, shee sat high: vpon her head she wore an antique helme, and in her right hand a speare for defence, in her left a cup for Medicine: at her feet was set a pedestall vpon which a serpent rowld vp did lie. Beneath was PEIRA, or Danger, a woman dispoiled, and almost naked, the little garment shee hath left her, of seuerall colours, to note her various disposition. Besides her lies a torch out, and a sword broken (the instruments of her furie) with a net and wolues skinne (the ensignes of her malice) rent in pieces. The word, Terga Dedere Metvs. Borrowed from Mart. and implying that now all feares haue turnd their Lib. 12. Epist. 6. backes, and our safetie might become securitie, danger being so wholly deprest, and vnfurnisht of all meanes to hurt. The fourth attendant is, EVDAIMONIA, or Felicity, varied on the second hand, and apparelled richly; in an embroidered robe, and mantle: a faire golden tresse. In her right hand a Caduceus, the note of peacefull wisedome: in her left, a Cornucopia fill'd onely with flowers, as a signe of florishing blessednesse; and crownd with a garland of the same. At her feet, DYSPRAGIA, or Vnhappinesse, a woman bareheaded, her necke, armes, brest, and feete naked, her looke hollow and pale; she holds a Cornucopia turned downward with all the flowers falne out and scattered, vpon her sits a rauen, as the augury of ill fortune: and the soule was Redevnt Satvrnia Regna. Out of Virgil, to shew that now those golden times were returned againe, Eclog 4. wherein Peace was with vs so aduanced, Rest receiued, Libertie restored, Safetie assured, and all Blessednesse appearing in euery of these vertues her particular triumph ouer her opposite euill. This is the dumbe argument of the frame, and illustrated with this verse of Virgil, written in the vnder freeze. Nvlla Salvs Bello: Pacem Te Poscimvs Omnes. Æneid. lib. 11. The speaking part was performed, as within the temple where there was erected an altar, to which at the approch of the king appeares the Flamen One of the three Flamines that as some thinke Numa Pompilius first instituted, but we rather with Varro take him of Romulus instituti?, wherof there were only two, Hee, and Dialis: to whom he was next in dignitie. He was alwayes created out of the Nobility, and did performe the rites to Mars, who was thought the Father of Romulus.MARTIALIS. And to him, GENIVS VRBIS. The Genius we attired before: To the Flamen we appoint this habit. A long crimson robe to witnesse his nobilitie, his typpet and sleeues white, as reflecting on purity in his religion, a rich mantle of golde with a traine to expresse the dignitie of his function. Vpon his head a Scaliger in coniect. in Varr: saith Totus Pileus, vel potiùs velamenta, Flammeum dicebatur, vnde Flamines dicti. hat of delicate wooll, whose top ended in a cone, and was thence called Apex, according to that of Lucan. lib. 1. Attollens? Apicem generoso vertice Flamen. This Apex was couered with a To this lookes that other coniecture of Varro. lib. 4. de lingua Latina. Flamines, quod licio in capite velati erant semper, ac caput cinctum habebant filo, Flamines dicti. fine net of yearne which they named Apiculum, and was sustained with a Which in their attire was called Stroppus, in their wiues Inarculum. bowd twigge of Pomegranat tree, it was also in the hot time of Summer to be bound with ribands, and throwne behind them as Scal. Ibid. in con Ponè enim regerebant apicem, ne grauis esset summis æstatis caloribus. Amentis enim, qua offendises dicebantur sub mentum adductis, religabant; vt cum vellent, regererent, &amp; ponè pendere permitterens. Scaliger teacheth. In his hand he bore a golden censor with perfume, and censing about the altar (hauing first kindled his fire on the toppe) is interrupted by the Genius. GENIVS. Stay, what art thou, that in this strange attire, Dar'st kindle stranger, and vn-hallowed fire Vpon this altar? Fl. Rather what art thou That dar'st so rudely interrupt my vow? My habit speakes my name. Ge. A Flamin? Fl. Yes, And Of Mars whose rites (as we haue toucht before) this Flamin did specially celobrate. Martialis call'd. Ge. I so did ghesse By my short view, but whence didst thou ascend Hither? or how? or to what mistick end? Fl. The noise, and present tumult of this day, Rowsd me from sleepe, and silence, where I lay Obscur'd from light; which when I wakt to see, I wondring thought what this great pompe might bee. When (looking in my Kalender) I found The With vs the 15 of March, which was the present day of this triumph: and on which the great feast of Anna Perenna (among the Romans) was yeerely, and with such solemnitie remembred, Oui. Fast. 3. Idibus est Anna festum geniale Perennæ, Haud procul à ripis, &amp;c. Ides of March were entred, and I bound With these, to celebrate the geniall feast Of Who this Anna should be (with the Romans themselues) hath beene no trifeling controuersie. Some haue thought her fabulously the sister of Dido, some a Nymph of Numicius, some I?, some Themis. Others an old woman of Bouilla, that fed the seditious multitude, in Monte sacro, with wafers, and fine cakes, in time of their penurie: To whom, afterward (in memory of the benefit) their peace being made with the nobles, they ordaynd this feast. Yet, they that haue thought neerest, haue mist all these, and directly imagined her the Moone. And that shee was called ANNA, Quia mensibus impleat annum, Ouid ibid. To which, the vow that they vsed in her rites, somewhat confirmingly alludes, which was, vt Annare, &amp; Perrennare commodè liceret, Macr. Sat. lib. 1. cap. 12. Anna stil'd Perenna, So Ouid. ibid. Fast. makes Mars speaking to her, Mense meo coloris, iunxi mea tempora tecum. Mars his guest Who, in this moneth of his, is yeerely call'd To banquet at his altars; and instal'd Nuper erat dea facta, &amp;c. ibid Ouid. A goddesse with him, since shee fills the yeare, And Where is vnderstood the meeting of the Zodiack in March, the moneth wherein shee is celebrated. knits the oblique scarfe that girts the spheare. Whilest foure-fac't Ianvs turnes his That face wherewith he beholds the Spring. vernall looke Vpon their meeting houres, as if he tooke High pride and pleasure. Ge. Sure thou still dost dreame, And both thy tongue, and thought rides on the streame Of phantasie: Behold here hee nor shee, Haue any altar, fane, or deitie. Stoope: reade but this Written vpon the Altar, for which we referre you to the page 859. inscription: and then view To whom the place is consecrate. 'Tis true That this is Ianvs temple, and that now He turnes vpon the yeere his freshest brow: That this is Mars his moneth; and these the Ides, Wherein his Anne was honor'd; both the tides, Titles, and place, we know: but these dead rites Are long since buryed, and new power excites More high and heartie flames. Loe, there is hee, Who brings with him a The Queen: to answere which in our inscription we spake to the King MARTE MAIORI. greater Anne then shee: Whose strong and potent vertues haue The Temple of Janus we apprehend to be both the house of War, and Peace: of warre, when it is open, of peace when it is shut: And that there, each ouer the other is interchangeably placed, to the vicissitude of Times. defac'd Sterne Mars his statues, and vpon them plac'd His, Which are Peace, Rest, Libertie, Safetie, &amp;c. and were his actiuely, but the worlds passiuely. and the worlds blest blessings: This hath brought Sweet peace to sit in that bright state shee ought Vnbloudie, or vntroubled; hath forc'd hence All tumults, feares, or other darke portents That might inuade weake minds; hath made men see Once more the face of welcome libertie: And doth (in all his present acts) restore That first pure world, made of the better ore. Now innocence shall cease to be the spoyle Of rauenous greatnesse, or to steepe the soyle Of raysed pesantrie with teares, and bloud; No more shall rich men (for their little good) Suspect to be made guiltie; or vile spies Enioy the lust of their so murdring eyes: Men shall put off their yron minds, and hearts; The time forget his old malicious arts With this new minute; and no print remayne Of what was thought the former ages stayne. Back, Flamin, with thy superstitious fumes, And cense not here; Thy ignorance presumes Too much, in acting any Ethnick rite In this translated temple: here no wight, To sacrifice, saue my deuotion comes, That brings in stead of those thy Somewhat a strange Epithite, in our tongue, but proper to the thing: for they were only Masculine odors, which were offerd to the Altars, Vir. Ecl. 8. Verbenas? adole pingueis, &amp; mascula Tura. And Plin. Nat. Hist. lib. 12. cap. 14. speaking of these, hath Quod ex eo rotunditate guttæ pependit, Masculum vocamus, cum alias non fere mas vocetur, vbi non sit fœmina: religioni tributum ne sexus alter vsurparetur. Masculum aliqui putant à specie testium dictum. See him also, lib. 34. cap. 11. And, Arnob. lib. 7. aduers. Gent. Non si mille tu pondera masculi Turis incendas, &amp;c. masculine gums. My cities heart; which shall for euer burne Vpon this altar, and no time shall turne The same to ashes: here I fixe it fast, Flame bright, flame high, and may it euer last. Whilest I, before the figure of thy peace, Still tend the fire; and giue it quick increase With prayers, wishes, vowes; whereof be these The least, and weakest: that no age may leese The memorie of this so rich a day; But rather, that it henceforth yeerely may Begin our spring, and with our spring the prime, And According to Romulus his institution, who made March the first month, and consecrated it to his father, of whom it was called Martius, Varr. Fest. in Frag. Martius mensis initi? anni fuit, &amp; in Latio, &amp; post Romam conditam, &amp;c. And Ouid. Fast. 3. A te principium Romano dicimus anno: Primus de patrio nomine mensis erit. Vox rata fit, &amp;c. See Macr. lib. 1. Sat. cap. 12. and Solin. in Poly. hist. cap. 2. Quod hoc mense mercedes exeluerint magistris, quas completus annus deberi fec sset, &amp;c. first accompt of yeeres, of months, Some, to whom we haue read this, haue taken it for a Tautologie, thinking Time ynough express'd before in yeeres, and moneths. For whose ignorant sakes we must confesse to haue taken the better part of this trauaile in noting, a thing not vsuall, neither affected of vs, but where there is necessitie, as here, to auoid their dull censures: where in yeeres and moneths we alluded to that is obserued in our former note: but by Time we vnderstand the present, and that from this instant, we should begin to reckon, and make this the first, of our time. Which is also to be helpt by emphasis. of time: And may these Ides as fortunate appeare To thee, as they to In which he was slaine in the Senate. Caesar fatall were. Be all thy thoughts borne perfect, and thy hopes In their euents still crown'd beyond their scopes. Let not wide heauen that secret blessing know To giue, which shee on thee will not bestow. Blind Fortune be thy slaue; and may her store (The lesse thou seek'st it) follow thee the more. Much more I would: but see, these brazen gates Make haste to close, as vrged by thy fates; Here ends my cities office, here it breakes: Yet with my tongue, and this pure heart, shee speakes A short farewell; and lower then thy feet, With feruent thankes, thy royall paynes doth greet. Pardon, if my abruptnesse breed disease; “He merits not t'offend, that hastes to please. Ouer the Altar was written this Inscription: D. I. O. M. BRITANNIARVM. IMP. PACIS. VINDICI. MARTE. MAIORI. P. P. F. S. AVGVSTO. NOVO. GENTIVM. CONIVNCTARVM. NVMINI. TVTELARI. D. A. CONSERVATRICI. ANNÆ. IPSÆ. PERENNÆ. DEABVSQVE. VNIVERSIS. OPTATIORI. SVI FORTVNATISSIMI. THALAMI. SOCIÆ. ET CONSORTI. PVLCHERIMÆ. AVGVSTISSIMÆ. ET H. F. P. FILIO. SVO. NOBILISSIMO. OB. ADVENTVM. AD VRBEM. HANC. SVAM. EXPECTATISSIMVM. GRATISSIMVM. CELEBRATISSIMVM. CVIVS. NON. RADII. SED SOLES. POTIVS. FVNESSIMAM. NVPER. AERIS. INTEMPERIEM. SERENARVNT S. P. Q. L. VOTIS. X. VOTIS. XX. ARDENTISSIMIS. L. M. HANC. ARAM. P. And vpon the Gate, being shut, IMP. IACOBVS MAX. CÆSAR AVG. P.P. PACE POPVLO BRITANNICO TERRA MARIQVE PARTA IANVM CLVSIT, S.C.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">In the Strand. The Inuention was a Raine-bow, the Moone, Sunne, and those seuen starres, which antiquitie hath styl'd the Pleiades, or Vergiliæ, aduanced betweene two magnificent Pyramid's, of 70. foot in height, on which were drawne his Maiesties seuerall pedigrees Eng. and Scot. To which bodie (being fram'd before) we were to apt our soule. And finding that one of these seuen lights, Electra, is rarely or not at all to be seene, (as Ouid. lib. 4. Fast. affirmeth. Pleiades incipient humeros releuare paternos: Quæ septem dici, sex tamen esse solent. And by and by after, Siue quòd Electra Troiæ spectare ruinas Non tulit: antè oculos opposuit? manum. And Festus Auien. Paraph. in Arat. Phænom. Fama vetus septem memorat genitore creatas Longæuo: sex se rutila inter sidera tantùm Sustollunt, &amp;c. And beneath —cerni sex solas carmine Mynthes Asserit: Electram cœlo abscessisse profundo, &amp;c.) We ventred to follow this authoritie; and made her the speaker: presenting her hanging in the ayre, in figure of a Comet; according to Anonymus. Electra non sustinens videre casum pronepotum fugerit; vnde &amp; illam dissolutis crinibus propter luctum ire asserunt, &amp; propter comas quidam Cometen appellant. THE SPEECH. Electra. The long Fest. Aui. paraph. Pars ait Idææ deflentem incendia Troiæ, Et numerosa suæ lugentem funera gentis, Electram tetris mœstum dare nubibus orbem. Besides the reference to antiquitie, this speech might be vnderstood by Allegorie of the Towne here, that had beene so ruined with sicknesse, &amp;c. laments I spent for ruin'd Troy, Are dried; and now mine eyes run teares of ioy. No more shall men suppose Electra dead, Though from the consort of her sisters fled Vnto the Hyginus. Sed postquam Troiæ fuit capta, &amp; Progenies eius quæ à Dardano fuit euersa, dolore permotam ab his se remouisse, &amp; in circulo qui Arcticus dicitur constitisse, &amp;c. Arctick circle, here to grace, And gild this day with her Electra signifies Serenitie it selfe, and is compounded of ?????, which is the Sunne, and ???????, that signifies serene. She is mentioned to be Anima sphæræ solis, by Proclus, com. in Hesiod. serenest face: And see, my She is also faind to be the mother of the rainebow. Nascitur enim Iris ex aqua &amp; erenitate, è refractione radiorum scilicet. Arist. in Meteorol. daughter Iris hasts to throw Her roseat wings, in compasse of a bow, About our state, as Val. Flac. Argonaut. 1. makes the rainbow indicem serenitatis. Emicuit referata dies, cœlum? resoluit. Arcus, &amp; in summos redierunt nubila montes. signe of my approach: Attracting to her seate from A name of the sunne, Stat. The. lib. 1. tor quentem cornua Mithran: And Martian. Capel. lib. 3. de nup. Mer. &amp; Phil. Te Serapim Nilus, Memphis veneratur Osirin, Dissona sacra Mithran, &amp;c. Mithras coach, A thousand different, and particular hiewes, Which she throughout her body doth diffuse. The Sunne, as loth to part from this halfe spheare, Stands still; and Phœbe labors to appeare In all as bright (if not as rich) as he: And, for a note of more serenety, My fixe Alcyone, Celæno, Taygete, Asterope, Merope, Maia. which are also said to be the soules of the other sphæres, as Electra of the sunne. Proclus. ibi. in com. Alcyone Veneris. Celæno Saturni. Taygete Lunæ. Asterop. Iouis. Merope Martis. Maia Mercurij. faire sisters hither shift their lights; To do this hower the vtmost of her rites. Where lest the captions, or prophane might doubt, How these cleere heauenly bodies come about All to be seene at once; yet neithers light Eclips'd, or shadow'd by the others fight: Let ignorance know, great king, this day is thine, And doth admit no night; but all doe shine As well nocturnall, as diurnall fires, To adde vnto the flame of our desires. Which are (now thou hast closd vp Alluding backe to that of our temple. Ianvs gates. And giu'n so generall peace to all estates) That no offensiue mist, or cloudie staine May mixe with splendor of thy golden raigne; But, as th'ast free'd thy London. Chamber, from the noyse Of warre and tumult; thou wilt powre those ioyes Vpon His citie of Westminster, in whose name, and at whose charge, together with the duchie of Lancaster this arch was erected. this place, which claimes to be Since here, they not onely sate being crowned, but also first receiued their crownes. the seate Of all the kingly race: the cabinet To all thy counsels; and the iudging chayre To this thy speciall kingdome. Who so faire And wholsome lawes, in euery court, shall striue By Æquitie, and their first innocence to thriue; The base and guiltie bribes of guiltier men Shall be throwne backe, and iustice looke, as when She lou'd the earth, and feard not to be sold For that, Hor. Car. lib. 4. Ode. 9. Ducentis ad se cuncta pecunia. which worketh all things to it, gold. The dam of other euils auarice Shall here locke downe her iawes, and that rude vice Of ignorant, and pittied greatnesse, pride, Decline with shame; ambition now shall hide Her face in dust, as dedicate to sleepe, That in great portalls wont her watch to keepe. All ills shall flie the light: Thy court be free No lesse from enuie, then from flatterie; All tumult, faction, and harsh discord cease, That might perturbe the musique of thy peace: The querulous nature shall no longer find Roome for his thoughts: One pure consent of mind Shall flow in euery brest, and not the ayre, Sunne, moone, or starres shine more serenely faire. This from that loud, blest Oracle, I sing, Who here, and first, pronounc'd, thee Brittaines king Long maist thou liue, and see me thus appeare, As omenous For our more authoritie to induce her thus, See Fest. Auien. paraph. in Arat. speaking of Electra, Non nunquam Oceani tamen istam sargere ab vndis, In conuexa poli, sed sede carere sororum; Atque os discretum procul edere, detestatam. Germanos? choros sobolis lachrymare ruinas, Diffusam? comas cerni, crinisque soluti Monstrari effigie, &amp;c. a comet, from my spheare, Vnto thy raigne; as that All comets were not fatall, some were fortunately ominous, as this to which we allude; and wherefore we haue Plinies testimonie. Nat. Histo. lib. 2 cap. 25. Cometes in vno totius orbis loco colitur in templo Romæ, admodum faustus Diuo Augusto iudicatus ab ipso: qui incipiente eo, apparuit ludis quos faciebat Veneri Genetrici, non multò post obitum patris Cæsaris, in collegio ab eo instituto. Nam? his verbis id gaudium prodidit. Iisipsis ludorum meorum diebus, sydus crinitum per septem dies in regione Cœli, quæ sub septentrionibus est, conspectum. Id oriebatur circa vndecimam horam diei, clarumque &amp; omnibus terris conspicuum suit. Eo sydere significari vulgus credidit, Cæsaris animam inter Deorum immortalium numina receptam: quo nomine id insigne simulacro capitis eius, quod mox in foro consecranimus adiectum est. Hæc ille in publicum, interiore gaudio sibi illum natum se? in eo nasci interpretatus est. Et siverum fatemur, salutare id terris fuit. did auspicate So lasting glory to Avgvstvs state. THE END.</field>
   </doc>
</add>