<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Lillo, George, 1693-1739</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Lillo, George, 1693-1739</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">lillo george 1693 1739</field>
      <field name="author_text">Lillo, George, 1693-1739</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">18th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1740's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V2.0294.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1740</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460006</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Elmerick : or, Justice Triumphant ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Elmerick : or, Justice Triumphant ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="title_facet">elmerick or justice triumphant</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">elmerick or justice triumphant</field>
      <field name="title_text">Elmerick : or, Justice Triumphant ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="year_display">1740</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1740</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1740</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460006&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460006&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Lillo, George, 1693-1739&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;lillo george 1693 1739&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Elmerick : or, Justice Triumphant ; A Tragedy&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;elmerick or, justice triumphant&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1740&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1740&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Lillo, George&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1693&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1739&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Elmerick : or, Justice Triumphant&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for John Gray [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1740&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872342-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv20294&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 18th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;18th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Elmerick : or, Justice Triumphant&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 141 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Elmerick.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1740.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 23 Feb 1740.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ELMERICK: OR, Justice Triumphant. A TRAGEDY.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">TO HIS ROYAL HIGHNESS THE PRINCE OF WALES.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PROLOGUE. Spoken by Mr. Quin. No labour'd Scenes to Night adorn our Stage, Lillo's plain Sense wou'd here the Heart engage. He knew no Art, no Rule; but warmly thought From Passion's Force, and as he felt he wrote. His Barnwell once no Critick's Test cou'd bear, Yet from each Eye still draws the natural Tear. With generous Candour hear his latest Strains, And let kind Pity shelter his Remains. Deprest by Want, afflicted by Disease, Dying he wrote, and dying wish'd to please. Oh may that Wish be now humanely paid, And no harsh Critick vex his gentle Shade. 'Tis yours his unsupported Fame to save, And bid one Laurel grace his humble Grave.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Dramatis Personæ. MEN. Andrew II. King of Hungary: Commonly called Andrew of Jerusalem. Mr. Mills. Conrade, Prince of Moravia. Mr. Millward. Elmerick. Mr. Quin. Bathori, Father to Ismena. Mr. Wright. Belus, Secretary to Elmerick. Mr. Winstone. WOMEN. Matilda, Queen of Hungary. Mrs. Butler. Ismena, Wife to Elmerick. Mrs. Mills. Zenomira, Attendant on the Queen. Miss Bennet. Lords, Deputies, and Guards. SCENE the King's Palace at Buda.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. SCENE I. Scene Ismena's Apartment in Elmerick's House. Enter Ismena alone. When we are bless'd even to our utmost wish, Is it the nature of the restless mind To work its own disquiet, and extract Pain from delight? O Elmerick! my life, My lord, my husband! when I count with transport Thy amiable virtues, when I think How fair a treasure I possess in thee, I'm lost in scenes of soft, bewild'ring bliss; Yet fear, I know not why, some fatal change May rob me of my happiness. Enter Bathori. Bath. So melancholy, and alone, my daughter! Ism. My Lord is with some Nobles of the States. Bath. You shou'd remember 'tis the greatest honour To be so oft consulted, so rever'd By men who stand the foremost in their country. Ism. Remember too, how dear a sacrifice My Elmerick made, when he forsook retreat, And chang'd our solid peace for courts and senates. We knew no want, no avarice, no ambition: Intruding business and corroding cares, Though hid beneath the pomp of wealth and power, Must take from our felicity; who find, Each in the other, what the world besides Is much too poor to give. Bath. You must not weigh Your single quiet with the good of millions. Your noble husband's rank and high abilities Have destin'd him the servant of his country: For Elmerick has every gift of Heaven That renders publick care a debt to virtue, And soft retirement poor, unmanly baseness. Ism. Still you forget the graces that have made Your only child, your lov'd Ismena, happy. Bath. Thou dearest comfort of thy father's age! My heart is pleased that thou art mindful of them. Your well placed love, this tender gratitude, Are proofs you merit, what you justly boast of, To have the hand and heart, to be the wife Of Elmerick—I cannot praise thee higher. Ism. The highest praise my vainest wish aspires to, Is that my ardent love bears some proportion To its exalted object. Bath. Both are happy; And Heaven preserve you so!—I judge that now The States may be assembling in the Palace, As summon'd by the King. He has not met them Since they elected Elmerick their Palatine, Pursuant to the grant he gave his people. He means this morning to appoint a Regent, Then to set forth for Palestine. Ism. What dangers He generously meets! Bath. For me, I own, I ne'er approv'd this rash, romantick war, Begot by hot-brained bigots, and fomented By the intrigues of proud, designing priests. All ages have their madness, this is ours. The King is wise, benevolent and brave, But covetous of Glory to excess; And if he steer amiss, 'tis in a torrent That bears down all before it. Ism. His fair Queen, No doubt, will greatly mourn so long an absence. Bath. Perhaps she may.—Yet—I cou'd wish, Ismena, (I speak in confidence and with concern) The Queen were wise, and gentle like thy self. Ism. My place and near attendance on her person Have given me means to know her, and, 'tis sure, To Nature none owes more. Bath. Yes, I confess, Matilda wants not charms, sharp female wit, And dignity of form; but her warm passions, And the wild eagerness with which she follows Each gust of inclination, may, I fear, Prove dangerous to herself, the King and Realm. Ism. Detraction cannot say she e'er transgrest The strictest bounds of virtue. Bath. Suppose her chaste, 'tis pride, not virtue in her. Can she be virtuous, who beheld, unmoved, The treacherous arts of her licentious brother To tempt your virgin honour, while he stay'd To grace his sister's nuptials, and stained Buda With his Moravian riot? Ism. I reveal'd Her thoughtless conduct, which indeed amazed me, Only to you, my Father.—Let it die: Be all her errors mended and forgot, Her worth improv'd and honour'd. Bath. Nay, I wish it: Wou'd I cou'd add, with truth, I hop'd it too!— Thou dearest pleasure of my ebbing life, With thee conversing, I forgot the hours Were passing on—I go: The States demand me. [Exeunt separately. SCENE II. The Assembly of the States. 1st L. That the King means this day to join the army Is then no longer doubted? Elm. No, my Lord. 1st Ld. May health and safety wait upon his person! 2d Ld. May fortune never cross his generous labours, But victory and triumph bring him home! Elm. So please just Heaven! 'Tis the devoutest wish Of every honest heart in Hungary. To them enter King, Bathori, Attendants. King taking a Seat of State. K. You Nobles, and you Deputies of Hungary, And you confederate States that own our scepter, Know, I this day depart for Palestine: Where, like a mourning matron, by her sons Neglected or forgot in her distress, Lyes sacred Sion, captived and profaned. But ere I name the Regent of my Kingdoms, Which you shall witness, and, I trust, applaud; I greet, with heart-felt joy, your wise election Of Elmerick, first Palatine of Hungary: The Conservator of your laws and rights, Guardian of Liberty, and Judge of Power. His manly virtues answer my big thought, And give full vigour to the awful title: Wisdom consummate in the fire of youth, The hardiest valour join'd with soft compassion, And justice never to be brib'd or awed— Elm. My life's poor labours never can deserve My Country's favour, or my Sov'reign's praise. And O perpetual source of bounteous virtue, Who but a King, whose wide expanding heart Feels a whole people's bliss, humanely great, Wisely ambitious, e'er, benignant, plan'd, In his high soaring thought, so large a gift; Gave to a subject right to judge his acts, And say to sov'reign power—Here shalt Thou stay? K. What we have thought of Regal Government, Its bounds and end, I hope our reign has witness'd. To make a People wretched, to entail The curse of bondage on their drooping race, Can add no joy to sense, can sooth no passion That hath its seat in nature—May reproach Sound through the loathing world his guilty name Who dares attempt it.—What can be his motive, Whom long descent, or a free People's love, Has raised an earthly God, so to degrade Himself, and take the office of a Fiend!— Too foul mistake!—Let me aspire to glory By glorious means! To have my reign illustrious, The theme of loud-tongued fame and ecchoing Nations, May it give birth to an eternal Æra, And be the happy date when Publick Liberty Receiv'd its last perfection! Bath. Matchless King! How shall thy subjects pay this God-like gift! K. Defend it as your lives—Said I your lives? That's poor, and far unworthy its importance; Defend it as you wou'd your fame and virtue. And if, hereafter, some ill-judging Monarch Invade your rights with bold oppressive power; Under the conduct of your Palatine, Repel by Legal Force the known injustice, And place the sacred crown of holy Stephen, Thus forfeited and impiously prophaned, On some more worthy head. (Pauses)—All gracious Heaven! Affection melts their hearts—There's not an eye But swells with tears in all this great Assembly. The active warmth of youth, the cool experience Of venerable age, the statesman's wisdom, And hardy soldier's courage, overcome By obligation, melt to infant softness, And speechless tears. Bath. O gracious Monarch! 1st Ld. Father! Elm. Glory, and Guardian Angel of our country! K. Why, let the envious call this flattery, Unmanly art! to which unhappy slaves Are forced to form their lips—You need it not— My last, just care has made it useless to you. Elm. When gratitude o'erflows the swelling heart, And breaths in free and uncorrupted praise For benefits received; propitious Heaven Takes such acknowledgment as fragrant incense, And doubles all its blessings. K. 'Tis enough— The powerful theme had sway'd my glowing thought From the important business of this day, Which claims your high attention—I shall now Repose the Sov'reign Power in proper hands, During the war I wage in Palestine. Elm. May Heaven direct your choice! For what is law more than the breathless form Of some fall'n Hero, spiritless and cold, To be despis'd and trampled on at pleasure By every bold offender; unless steady And vig'rous execution give it life. K. 'Tis justly urged, my Lord, and you yourself Shall in my absence guard it from contempt By vigorous execution. Take the sword, And bear it not in vain.—Shou'd any dare, Presuming on their birth or place for safety, Disturb my subjects peace with bold injustice; Let no consideration hold your hand, As you shall answer it to me and Heaven: Think well how I would act, or ought to act, Were I in person here, and do it for me. Elm. An awful trust, my Liege, and strongly urged: And while I rule your realm, shou'd some bold crime Demand the righteous rigour you enjoin; May Heaven deal with me, as I shall discharge With faithfulness and courage, or neglect, Through treachery or fear, the painful duty. K. Unbless'd a King, whose self-reproaching heart Ne'er, calm, reposes on a subject's virtue! Thank Heaven, I am not such: I taste the safe, The generous joys of confidence well placed. With you, brave Elmerick, the States have lodg'd Their noblest right, and I dare trust my crown. But there is yet a dearer, tenderer charge, And let me recommend, ere I dismiss you, [Turning to the States. More than my crown, my Queen to your affections. I go, once more, to take my last adieu, Then lead my hallow'd banners to the East. [Exeunt. SCENE III. Queen and Zenomira. Q. To stoop beneath a constant weight of cares To purchase ease for others!—Poor and senseless! Injurious to himself, and base to me! Zen. The King is held by all most wise and just. Q. For me, I cannot think so—Then this start To Palestine, this warlike pilgrimage, This holy madness will bear no excuse. Need he regard whether the line of Baldwin, Or Saladin, be victors in a clime So far remote, who might enjoy repose And pleasure here? I tell thee, Zenomira, I'm not, by far, so happy as Ismena. For Elmerick, the theme of every tongue, Can love: And to our sex, love crowns all merit. Zen. Madam, the King— Q. He comes to take his leave. Ungrateful man! He merits not my heart, who vainly dares To rate his pride above it. [Exit Zenomira. Enter King. K. The urgent business of this day, Matilda, How has it robb'd me of thy dear society! Q. You will have constant business, Sir—The camp Detains you from me now, and now the senate; And when your court receives you, restless still, And fired with some bright phantom of ambition, You mix with hoary heads, and plan new glories. K. If, faithful to the trust imposed by Heaven, I oft have born with grief thy painful absence; O think me not less thine, my lov'd Matilda, But pity my sad duty. Q. Said you duty?— Your idol Honour rather—that you worship— That sends your banners to the distant East, To fruitless wars, and visionary triumphs. K. Honour's a duty, Madam, and the noblest; And ardent I pursue the powerful impulse. There are (with shame I speak it) those who loiter In this religious warfare. The Emperor Cannot unite his Germans; France delays: Grim death has forced the slaught'ring battle-axe From Cœur de Lion's strong unerring hand; And John of England, his unthrifty brother, Repell'd abroad, prepares his luckless sword To wound the liberties, rescind the laws, And sheath it in the bowels of his kingdom. Our troops are ready: Sion's mournful cries Call loud for instant succour—and I go. Q. Then I must learn to bear my King's neglect, And endless solitude. K. No, my Matilda; The time will come when wars rough labours ended Shall give me up devoted to thy beauties, And all our days to come shall blended flow In one pure stream of calm, unruffled love. Q. Our days to come Are dark uncertainties; and doating age, Shou'd we attain it, painful or insipid. K. Do not distract me, call back these reproaches. Urge not, my Queen, thy soft'ning power too far, But think thy husband's triumphs will be thine.— Mean-time, to soften my unwilling absence Thy brother comes, the partner of thy heart: Each day my Court expects him from Moravia. His sprightly temper, his engaging converse, Will steal all sorrow from thee. Q. In my brother I still have found a friend; and friendship now Is all the good my widow'd heart must hope for.— But in your absence, Sir, the Sovereign Power To whom intrust you? Whom must I obey? K. Lord Elmerick, as you know was my fix'd purpose, I have appointed Regent of my Kingdoms. Q. The world talks loud of Elmerick's fair merits, And I, unused to think on such grave subjects, Congratulate your choice.— K. You're just; and kind To crown with your auspicious praise the man Whom I so love and honour.—May I hope. That all those lips have dropt less gentle to me, Was but the tender fears of love alarm'd? Oh say but this! and I will think it kinder Than all th'endearments of affected fondness. Q. Think what will please you best, and that I said it,— And may the shining Fame you seek so far Pay your long labours! K. One embrace, Matilda! May Heaven on all thy days shed sweetest comfort, And peace with angel wings o'ershade thy slumbers! Eager for Fame, and zealous to chastize The foes of Heav'n, I thought I could resist This heart-invading softness—Fond mistake! Call'd to begin the task by leaving thee, I find my fancy'd heroism vain, And all the feeble tender man returns.— I must not give it way.—Once more, farewel. [Exeunt separately. The End of the First Act.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. SCENE I. Queen and Ismena. Q. Yes, I resent the King has left me thus!— Thus in the bloom of youth to be forsaken!— I'll have revenge. Ism. Forgive your servant, Madam; Grief and impatience interrupt your reason: You think not what you speak, or will not think it, When time shall give you leisure to reflect. The King, howe'er in this— Q. Excuse him not; I never lov'd him, and now never will.— You seem amaz'd! Is it so very strange, A lady should not love the man she weds? Ism. My happy fortune, Madam, makes me think so, Nor wou'd I lose that thought to be a Queen. Q. I wou'd I were no Queen!—at least not here! When in Moravia, at my father's court, The only daughter and the darling joy Of my fond Parents love; officious Fame Proclaim'd me as a miracle of beauty: Justly or not is now of small importance, 'Twas then thought true, and Princes came in crouds To love and be refus'd. The noblest triumphs Our sex can boast, charm'd my aspiring thoughts; And constant revels, feastings, mirth and musick Sooth'd every sense. No grave grimace, that's call'd Religion here; no visionary schemes To set the Rabble free, and fetter Kings; No anxious cares for what regards not us, Remote posterity; obscur'd the lustre, Or damp'd the joys of Olmutz' gallant court: Soft am'rous sighs were all the mournful sounds, And deep intrigues to gain some haughty Fair Were all the business of that happy place I left for this proud, solemn seat of dulness, This pompous grave of pleasure, hated Buda. Ism. What wit and charms has education marr'd (Aside.) Q. Then judge, Ismena, Who know'st this formal Court, and sober King, My hopeless, lost condition. Ism. May I hope Your Majesty's forgiveness, should I ask, The absence of your royal Lord excepted, What more cou'd kind, indulgent Heaven bestow? Power, wealth, and honour wait upon your will. Q. Power, wealth and honour feed man's high ambition; But for our humbler sex, we're true to nature, And rest content with pleasure. But to me Pleasure's impossible, whilst my grave Master More than forbids it by his wise example. And then this last injurious slight has mov'd me Beyond the power to pardon. Ism. Shou'd my Lord Have left me thus, I might, I must have griev'd— I think to death; but sure no angry thought Had ruffled my sad bosom. Q. You, Ismena, Are a rare instance of felicity, A happy, marry'd woman. Ism. 'Tis true, my Lord, Or I am partial, has not many equals: The manly beauty of his pleasing face, His perfect symmetry and noble mein, His tender language, and his soft address— Q. I am no stranger to them—Wou'd I were! (Aside.) Ism. But then the matchless beauty of his mind— Ne'er were the great and tender so united As in the soul of Elmerick. Q. Rash creature! (Aside.) Ism. How happy were our sex if more were like him! Q. Why was not I reserv'd for such a lover? My passions must have vent. (Aside.) Gentle Ismena! Wait for me near the fountain in the garden. (Exit Ismena. When murm'ring at my fate, to set before me, And in so full a light, those very graces That long have charm'd me! Vain, officious woman!— Why have you, Heaven, so form'd this heart for love, With no more reason, than you must foresee, Subservient to that love, will make me wretched? Enter Elmerick. Elm. Hail to the Queen! and may the news I bear, Prove a glad omen of my future service From this auspicious hour! Your royal brother, The valiant Conrade, is arriv'd at Buda. Q. Now by the joys my soul has long been lost to, This kind, this gen'rous haste to bring relief To a forsaken solitary Queen, Does justice to your character. My thanks— But that's a poor reward, current at courts For want of something better.—I wou'd find Some solid favour to engage your service, Worthy of me, and worthy your acceptance. Elm. Is there a man so venal or so vain, As not to think the happiness to serve So good and great a Queen, a full reward For all he can perform?—And then the honour Done to my wife!—Your favour to Ismena Exceeds all gratitude. Q. Gall, gall and poison. (Aside.) Elm. Madam, I take my leave. The Prince is ent'ring. Q. My Lord, when our first interview is over, We shall expect your presence. (Exit Elmerick. Enter Conrade. Conr. My Matilda! Long let me press thee to my joyful breast, I who have often mourn'd thy tedious absence, Thou dear, dear object, both by choice and nature, Of my fond love, my sister and my friend! Q. And was it tedious? Did you think it long? Why should I doubt it? When was you not kind? When did thy active genius let me want New pleasures to repel intruding thought, And lash the lazy minutes into swiftness? Our Parents— Conr. Are well. There is no sorrow in Moravia But from the want of thee. Q. I have not known, 'Till now, a joyful moment since I left it. Conr. We have been happy: And shou'd Fortune prove Once more propitious to me, those gay fires That shone so bright at Olmutz, may revive And blaze at Buda. Q. What, my dearest Conrade, Has Hungary to give worth thy desiring? Conr. Forgive, Matilda, while I own my Heart. Though I have ever lov'd and fondly love thee, I had, besides the joy of seeing thee, Another powerful hope that fired my soul, And wing'd my haste to Buda. Q. You surprize me! Conr. When first I led you here to warlike Buda, And gave you blooming to your royal husband, You must remember, during my short stay, I saw and lov'd the daughter of Bathori. Q. I know it well, and all her rigors to you; But thought your am'rous and inconstant heart (Lost often, and as many times retriev'd Since I beheld you last) had not retain'd The least impression of Ismena's charms. Conr. Not all the gaudy pleasures I once courted, Can cure the rooted passion, raging still, Invincible as ever. It has cost me, While distant from her charms I pin'd in absence, A sickness almost fatal to my life; Which though my youth recover'd, the soft poison Still preys upon thy brother's heart, Matilda, And makes me hate my being:—I will die, Or find relief. And therefore am I come, Determined, to attempt my fate once more: My state cannot be worse.—That she is wedded To Elmerick, I know: Yet he's a subject; And were he more, his greatness shou'd not awe me. Q. This favours my design on Elmerick's heart,— If he should gain Ismena, Elmerick's mine. (Aside.) Let me dissuade you from a wild attempt, Your rashness must defeat. Lord Elmerick, Who now resides, as Regent, in the Palace, Must soon perceive your love, and will find means To guard his honour, and secure Ismena From bold solicitation. Con. I'm convinc'd That course were wrong, do you direct me better, Or see me die the victim of despair. Q. How, Conrade! can you think I would assist In such a purpose?—But were virtue silent, A cloud of difficulties rise before me: Lord Elmerick is Palatine and Regent— Terms must be kept with him. And then Ismena, Fond of her Lord, and vain of such a choice, Will hear you with disdain. For happy Elmerick Fills all her tender wishes, all her heart.— Yet should some accident disturb their loves, There might be hope: For she who once has lov'd, May love again. The softness in our frame, That has dispos'd us first to the fond passion, Is ready to betray us ever after. Conr. This distant glimpse of hope, this poor reversion, To one that loves as I do, is despair— But 'tis from her alone, who rules my fate, That I can learn my doom. Where may I find her? Q. I gave her charge to wait me in the garden, And soon shall meet her there. Conr. Unkind Matilda, Cou'dst thou know this, and yet detain me here? I wou'd not lose the present, lucky moment For ages in reversion. (Exit Conrade. Q. Yes, my Conrade, Though you was ever dearly welcome to me, I now behold you with unusual transport. O! may your sighs, your vows, your importunities Subdue Ismena's heart; as Elmerick, Without their pleasing aid, has conquer'd mine: At least divide, break, and confound their peace: Raise storms of jealousy, and fill their souls With darkness and despair: 'Till in the tempest Love be for ever lost, and the wild wreck Compel abandon'd Elmerick to seek For shelter in some near and friendly port, And find the blest asylum in my arms. (Exit Queen. SCENE II. A Garden. Conrade and Ismena. Conr. Her charms are still the same, and at her sight Love burns with double fury: Yet I want My former resolution: I am aw'd, And scarce have courage left me to approach her. (Aside.) —Be not surpriz'd, adorable Ismena, To see me here, and see me still your slave: Yes, those all-powerful beauties, that subdu'd My ranging heart to constancy and truth, Still hold the binding charm: To love Ismena Is, as I feel too well, to love for ever. Ism. As you are brother to my royal mistress, I'm not surpriz'd to see you here, Prince Conrade; But as I'm wife to noble Elmerick, To hear you hold this language does surprize me. Conr. Nor time, nor absence, nor the last despair, For I have prov'd them all, can cure my passion, A mortal passion, that must soon consume me, Unless you bid me live. Ism. Live, and be wise; Live, and be noble: break your vassalage To passions that debase the name of Prince, While that of Man is forfeited and lost. Conr. This high disdain, this counsel urg'd in scorn, Is cruel and unjust.—Too haughty Fair! Wilt thou ne'er learn compassion? Never melt At my long tender sorrows? Let me hope— Ism. What have I done to raise your vanity To this presumptuous heigth? Conr. O call it love, And I'll confess it soars to all the heights Of fond, distracted passion. Ism. Impious trifles! Are these the arts by which false man betrays?— Unhappy women! do they yield to guilt Because a madman raves, a traitor flatters?— I thought, vain Prince, I had been better known; And that your rash attempt when here before, At least, had taught you wisdom. Conr. I confess My love was then to blame, so to expose Your virgin honour: You have now a husband— Ism. You sink beneath my scorn—I have a husband— And such an one as loose incontinence Would want the will to wrong. Sir, if I bear This insult unreveng'd, 'tis to my prudence, Not to your birth and name, you owe your safety. Conr. My safety!—Hell!—let the proud Palatine But dare to threaten thus— Ism. Take my advice, And dare not to provoke him. Thus far, Prince, I judge my scorn sufficient. Conr. Oh! 'tis too much, and all that I can fear:— I'll conquer it or perish. Ism. Since your reason Is wholly lost in this impetuous frenzy, To shun your madness shall be all my care. Conr. Fly where you will, honour, as well as love, Compels me now for ever to pursue you. Ism. The light, vain Libertine grows formidable!— His insolence may lay a scene of ruin, That chills my blood with horror but to think on. Conr. Her Cynick father!—There's another champion. What with her innate pride and high alliances She makes a strong resistance; and my passion, Enter Bathori. By opposition irritated, burns More fiercely to attempt the noble conquest. (Exit Conrade. Bath. Prince Conrade just now leaves you? Ism. Let him go. Bath. You seem disorder'd. Ism. Howe'er misplac'd by Fortune, Nature form'd me For the domestick joys of calm retreat: I'm sick of court already. Bath. For what cause? You know your Lord, by his high trust compell'd, Here must reside: It cannot be dispens'd with. Ism. 'Tis true, and all our happy days are past: For insolence and Conrade still pursue me. Then judge, when this shall reach my husband's ear, As soon it must, how will his soul endure This outrage on my virtue and his honour? Shall I not see his hands stain'd with the blood Of the Queen's brother, or the noble Elmerick (A thousand, thousand deaths are in the thought) Bleed by the rage of impious, desperate Conrade? Bath. Unheard-of insolence! He shall be taught The difference between the passive slaves Of loose Moravia, and our free Hungarians. Your Lord must never learn this daring insult: For know, my Child, I hold myself sufficient To shield a daughter from this princely Libertine, And awe him into silence and respect. Ism. You know him not: He is not to be aw'd: There is but one, one only way to shun him: Let me forsake the court, with you retire 'Till Conrade quits the kingdom. Bath. Rightly judg'd. Thy prudence is thy guard; safer in that From being made the theme of busy rumour, Ever injurious to a woman's fame, Than in an army rais'd for thy defense. My house and arms are ready to receive thee. Exeunt. End of the Second Act.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. SCENE I. Queen and Zenomira. Q. Be dumb, vain, busy wretch: Because thou'rt trusted, Dost thou presume to offer thy advice? Wou'd'st thou be hated too? Zen. Think, royal Madam, To whom I, undeserving, owe my fortune. My gratitude— Q. A servant's gratitude!— Consider well your interest and your safety. Remember I, who made you what you are, Can make you more, or speak you into nothing. If Elmerick return the love I proffer, I shall employ you often: Shou'd he not, (Do not my eyes dart ruin while I speak it) My first command in this shall be my last. Seek him now, And bring him hither.—No, I see my brother: Wait in the anti-chamber 'till he's gone, Then do as I directed. [Exit Zenomira. Enter Conrade. Conr. Curst be the hour, When, sated with delight, I quitted Olmutz, Where all my vows were heard with extasy, And beauty took its value from my breath, To meet contempt, despair and death at Buda. Ismena at this instant leaves the court: No hope is left, no patience—I'm distracted. The subtle tyrant Love, who led me long Through flow'ry paths, and spread elysium round me; Whose fires, 'till now, serv'd but to heighten pleasure, And quicken it to transport; has betray'd me To plagues and torments not to be supported. Ismena is essential to my being. O Matilda! Assist me with your counsel, or I'm lost. Q. Alas! he knows not it too much imports me. [Aside. Do not abandon hope, but leave despair To fools and cowards. Know, exalted souls Have passions in proportion violent, Resistless, and tormenting: They're a tax Imposed by nature on preheminence, And fortitude, and wisdom must support them. Conr. Who but Matilda e'er cou'd flatter misery, And prove superior merit from our weakness? At thy awak'ning voice my hope revives. Coud'st thou but stop Ismena's purpos'd flight (And nothing is too hard for wit like thine) I yet may triumph o'er her pride and virtue. Q. By stratagem to keep Ismena here Can serve no end: When she perceives the fraud, She'll fly more irritated than before. Conr. But I shall see her first. Q. What can you hope From such an interview? while Elmerick Continues kind, he'll prove too strong a rival. Her pride and virtue are meet accidents: She chanc'd to marry where she chanc'd to like; But should he, touch'd with some new flame, neglect her, As time is fruitful of more strange events, Her pride wou'd make her hate him.—You must wait. Conr. You talk of ease whole ages hence to one Stretch'd on the rack of violent desire. By Heav'n I will pursue to her retreat, And bear her thence in spite of Father, Husband, And every sword that dares oppose my purpose. She shall return to court, she shall behold And hear my raging love, she shall be mine. Q. Forbear such wild and unbecoming thoughts: The Palatine is Regent, you a stranger, And I, perhaps, have reasons of my own To keep his good opinion. If to see her Within this Palace, with the due respect You owe her birth and rank, may satisfy For once your present ardour, I'll assist you. Love may perhaps inspire your soothing tongue With eloquence to soften, and persuade The melting Fair to break her resolution, And hear at least, if not return your Love: The firmest purpose of a Woman's heart To well-tim'd, artful flattery may yield. Conr. And shall I see again my lov'd Ismena? Oh say what pow'r, what art can bring her hither? Q. Belus, chief secretary to the Regent, Shall be, unknowingly, a proper agent: He has been Zenomira's lover long— But see she comes, she must not see you now: Trust in a sister's love, and wait th'event. [Exit Conrade. Enter Zenomira. Zen. Madam, my Lord the Regent will attend you. Q. Is Belus still thy lover, Zenomira? Zen. So he professes, Madam. Q. Then shou'd you feign a message from his Lord, He'd not distrust you? Zen. His believing passion Ne'er yet has seem'd to doubt whate'er I utter'd. What must I say? Q. Say that her Lord intreats Ismena, some time hence, to meet him here. I think she has conceiv'd some slight disgust Which I wou'd fain remove. This artifice I shall so well account for when I see her, You and your lover shall incur no blame. Zen. What dangers wou'd I meet, cou'd I improve Your friendship for that Lady! May I hope Your thoughts of Elmerick are chang'd already? Q. The plague of confidents!—Do as directed. [Exit Zenomira. And yet this wretch, this little busy wretch, Whose love, whose care and counsel I despise, Is infinitely wiser than Matilda! I've sent for Elmerick—But let me think Ere yet my sliding feet forego the shore, That quitted once can never be recovered, In what a boundless ocean am I plunging, With only one uncertain light to guide me!— If that should fail, I sink o'erwhelm'd for ever.— But shou'd the grateful Elmerick stretch forth His saving hand, and snatch me from the billows, Love will return a thousand solid joys For every transient pain.—But O the hazard!— A woman and a Queen to offer love, And hear herself refus'd!—'Tis misery! 'Tis everlasting shame! 'Tis death and Hell! I will not think so poorly of my fate, My self, or Elmerick—My present lot Is cheerless and forlorn—Impetuous gusts Of stormy passions drive me through the gloom, Unsteady and uncertain. All before me Is the profound, unfathomable deep; And all behind a dark and boundless waste— But he appears, the star that must direct me To peace and joy—or light me to my ruin. Enter Elmerick. I fear, my Lord, this importunity May interrupt your labours for the Publick, I shall become your trouble. Elm. I serve the King, I serve the publick, Madam, serving you: My pride and joy is to attend your person. Q. And are you pleas'd, most noble Elmerick, To hear a woman's talk, and sooth my cares? But you are wond'rous good: And let me boast That I've a heart susceptible of kindness, In all its various forms, ev'n to a fault. Elm. How infinitely bountiful is Nature? Giving such softness to the pleasing sex, As well rewards the toils she lays on ours. If we excel, 'tis when the glorious hopes Of serving or delighting you inspire us; And to obtain your smiles is to be happy. Q. If happiness be in our pow'r to give, 'Tis hard to want the blessings we bestow: To love and to be lov'd is to be happy. Elm. Your sex by nature form'd to merit love, Can rarely want it. Q. Possibly the brave, Who hate ingratitude, wou'd not despise A lady who renounced her native pride, The painful'st proof our sex can give of love. Elm. A generous man must think it double grace, When love and virtue condescend to chuse him. Q. My Lord, shou'd fate reduce some hapless woman, Trembling and almost dying with confusion, To make an offer of her love to you; And such a love as instant death or madness Were certain to ensue, shou'd you refuse it; How wou'd you act? How treat a suppliant heart, Whose weakness you had caus'd? Elm. Your pardon, Madam; 'Tis what I can't suppose, and asks no answer. Q. Why not suppose? Is it impossible? Say—I—shou'd love; and trusting to your honour, Have laid this fair occasion in your way To break my fall, and spare me half my shame. Elm. What vanity Have I betray'd, what baseness, what presumption, To need so strange a trial? If you doubt My loyalty, and think I entertain Designs injurious to my Sov'reign's honour, And your fair virtue— Q. 'Tis too much, my Lord, This diffidence, this cold reserve—You urge me To what I wou'd avoid, beyond the bounds I had prescrib'd myself: Yes, I cou'd die Ere speak more plain; but must not have you think I wou'd betray you. Heavens! what feign a passion My soul ne'er knew! No, rather let me bear Your utmost cruelty, your scorn and hatred, For what I am, a lost unhappy Queen, Than once be thought so mean and so perfidious. Elm. Confounded and amaz'd, my fault'ring tongue Scarce does its office.—Whither wou'd you urge me? 'Tis too severe a proof!—As you are fair; As charms like yours, may warm the coldest heart, And shake the most resolv'd; what if my senses Should mutiny against my weaker reason, And tempt me to betray you,—horrid thought!— To sure and endless ruin! Q. What do you see That looks like ruin here? Elm. Guilt:—That is ruin. Q. Why be it so, your love shall make it glorious. Elm. No, shame and just remorse must still pursue Foul, trust-betraying love. And shou'd I say Ev'n that were in my power, I must deceive you. Shou'd wild desire, in an unguarded moment, Rifle your charms, and lay your virtue waste; The first return of thought wou'd bear me back To her, who claims me by the dearest ties Of virtuous, grateful love. Oh then return, With recollected powers o'ercome this weakness, And rise more glorious from this short decline. Q. This short decline!—No, let victorious love Here end a Queen's confusion, or your scorn Sink my despairing and indignant soul Where calm repose and hope shall never find it, And your repentance come too late to save me. Elm. I must assert your honour and my own. Remember who I am, my trust, and office— Almighty power! Shall I who bear the sword To punish bold offenders, break the laws Your providence has call'd me to defend? Doth the least subject look to me for justice, And shall my King, my ever-gracious master, In recompence for his unbounded favour, Receive the highest, most opprobrious wrong A King or man can suffer? Q. Shame and ruin! Elm. Not to deceive you, Madam, not to flatter Views so unworthy of yourself and me; I must avow the ample power I hold, Each thought, each toil, my life, devoted all To gratitude and justice. Q. Enough my Lord—your gratitude has charm'd me— Who shall oppose your justice? Here display it: Rise by my ruin to the height of glory, And let fame deaffen the astonish'd world With your triumphant virtue. Elm. I wou'd triumph But o'er your weakness, not your peace and fame: So may you triumph too.—Oh hear me, Queen— Q. I have heard too much, I've heard my love refused.—Death! horror!—shame And burning indignation!—Pierce my heart, Dispatch me, give me death. Is that too much?— Is pity to the wretched, is compassion Of every kind among the hateful crimes The gen'rous, valiant Elmerick abhors?— Then give me this, afford the means of death, And leave me to apply them. [Going to seize his sword. Elm. Heavens! what frenzy Possesses you!—Yet hear me— Q. Off, be gone, And let me die! Elm. Safe as my soul the secret Shall be preserv'd. Q. What! be oblig'd to you!— Owe my precarious honour to your silence!— But keep your sword, I shall not want even that— Elm. She is not to be trusted with her life— Royal, unhappy Fair, what can I say To calm this raging tempest in your bosom? For though I dare not be, what you must hate, False to my trust and Sov'reign; I wou'd die To save your life and honour, to restore Your peace of mind, and raise declining virtue— Enter Conrade. Shame and confusion!—Madam, see, the Prince— Conr. Well may'st thou start, proud Lord: The Queen's disorder, And your confusion, must import some rudeness. Q. Rudeness!—that word suggests an happy thought— Yes, let despair and shame give way to vengeance. [Aside. O brother! if I dare to call you brother After the vile indignity I've suffer'd; That wretch, presuming on his boundless power, Has talk'd to me of love. Elm. What can I answer? When accidents concur with calumny, Her pois'nous breath obscures the brightest fame, And conscious virtue only can support us. Conr. I saw and heard too much. The traitor's life Is a mean sacrifice. Elm. To plead my cause Before a judge like thee, were mean and vain; Yet be advis'd, young Prince, nor rashly draw A sword that can't avail you. Q. Will you hear him? Think on the affront done to our royal house:— Remember who he is, think on Ismena: Who, if he 'scapes your sword, is lost for ever. [To Conrade. Conr. Then love inspire me. [They fight. Q. Ah! my brother!— Elmerick has th'advantage. [Conrade disarm'd. Elm. Take your life, Young Prince. The false appearance that misled you, Withholds my hand from punishing your rashness; But as the King's authority lives in me, It may be fatal to repeat these insults, Which nor my spirit, nor my place will bear. Remember you are warn'd. For you, proud Queen, I pity and forgive your groundless hatred, And still have that attention to your happiness, To wish, even from my soul, you wou'd review, With an impartial eye, our different conduct. Wou'd you atone for error, make it short; Reproach yourself, and use this as a motive, That he, whom you have wrong'd, scorns to reproach you. [Exit Elmerick. Q. Most exquisite! Legions of plagues and curses! Has Heaven nor Hell no vengeance in reserve, No bolts to strike, no light'ning to consume This overbearing traitor; who has dar'd To talk of wrongs, reproach, and teach us fear! Conr. Vain of th'advantage fortune gave him o'er me, He us'd me with the last indignity, Gave me my life in scorn, check'd, rated, threaten'd.— But may my sword ne'er do me right in battle, May I be blasted with a coward's name, If I forget to pay him this foul outrage With double weight of vengeance. Enter Zenomira. Zen. Madam, Ismena— Q. Ha!—Ismena, say'st thou!— Say, Zenomira, that her Lord expects her. [Exit Zenomira. Conr. Ismena in my power! O Fortune, Fortune! From this blest hour I'll worship none but thee. I might have rack'd my thoughts in vain for ages, And ne'er have found the thousandth, thousandth part Of this complete, this most luxurious vengeance. Q. Revenge, thou com'st too sudden; And risest to my view in such a form, So shocking, so tremendous, that my soul Shrinks back with horror now I shou'd embrace thee.— I justify thy scorn, proud Elmerick, By this degenerate pity.—Let it be— The haughty Regent's heart shall know such anguish, That his complaints shall move ev'n Fiends to pity, And vengeance to repent.—Retire, my Conrade, And watch till I have sent Ismena hence. [Conrade retires. I am so lost, that only horror, ruin, Can cover my disgrace. Enter Ismena looking round. Ism. Lord Elmerick not here!— Have my unheeded steps mistook their way?— The Queen!—and deep in thought! Q. She has not wrong'd me— But misery is cruel and remorseless. Ism. Forgive me, gracious Queen, if I am rude, In vent'ring thus to press on your retirement; I was inform'd Lord Elmerick was here. Q. Yes,—no,—he was—Good Heavens! how shall I frame My tongue to this vile office. [Aside. Ism. Are you well?— Pray, Heaven preserve the Queen!—You're strangely alter'd —The blood forsakes your cheeks—you start, and tremble. Q. You'd see your Lord, seek him in those apartments. Ism. For that I came; but dare not leave you thus. Q. It was a short disorder, and 'tis past— Go, you're expected— [Exit Ismena. She is gone, and ruin, Inevitable ruin meets her there. The mean, perfidious, barb'rous task is done. My heart is adamant, or Heaven-born pity Had melted my resentments. Poor Ismena! To be so plac'd by fate, that love or vengeance Cou'd find no passage to the stubborn breast Of Elmerick, but through thy breaking heart. The End of the Third Act.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT IV. SCENE I. Belus and Zenomira. Belus. Then you confess that I've been made the tool Of some vile purpose, that my Lord ne'er sent The message you deliver'd?—Faithless woman! How shall I meet my Lord's just indignation, Or make my conduct clear? Zen. Prepare to curse, Prepare to kill me, Belus; or my fears Will quickly end me, and prevent your justice. Bel. False woman! you've betray'd me into ruin. Zen. O we are both betray'd, and both are ruin'd: Both made t'assist in such a villainy As Hell would blush to own, and Heav'n and Earth Must join to see reveng'd. O cruel Queen! Curst Conrade! lost Ismena! Bel. Conrade!—Queen! Zen. I say the Queen, and Conrade, and Ismena. I saw her pass to the Queen's own apartment, And cursed Conrade follow her soon after. The rooms were bar'd.—But O the dismal cries, The lamentations and the shrieks that followed!— Bel. O lost Ismena! O unhappy Lord!— Yes they become thee well, these gushing tears— Zen. But danger presses on us—What's our duty In this extreme? Bel. To be both just and cautious: Not rashly to proclaim what we have heard, But boldly dare to evidence the truth, And justify our selves, whenever call'd on.— But see, Ismena comes. Merciful Heav'ns! Who that beholds her now, can doubt her suff'rings! Zen. Heart-breaking spectacle! Bel. She thinks us guilty: We must avoid her sight. (Going) Her Father's here!— Enter at opposite doors Bathori and Ismena. O what a woful greeting! Now, by Heaven, I know not which demands compassion most. (Exeunt Belus and Zenomira, Bath. The Regent sent to see Ismena here?— Perhaps, then— Ism. Oh!— Bath. From whence that mournful sound! Ism. Since life is but a witness of my shame, Why do I longer bear it; Bath. Some sad child Of sorrow and despair, hiding her face, And bending t'wards the earth, seems to bewail. In bitterness of soul, some dire misfortune. Ism. Why is the grave, the hospitable grave, The silent seat of darkness, closed to me? Almighty power! (raising her face) My Father! ha!— (seeing Bathori) Bath. Impossible!— Art thou Ismena?—Let me doubt it still— To see thee thus, and know thee for my child, Must split my brain with horror. Ism. Since my woes Renounce all cure, and, told, must blast the hearer; O let me pour them out to wilds and deserts, Shun all mankind, but chiefly those I love! Bath. Come, my Ismena, to my sheltring bosom— Close, closer still—and while I thus weep o'er thee, Tell me, my child,—I know 'twill break my heart, But let it break—come, tell me all thy suff'rings. Ism. Think where I am, remember what I told you Of the detested rage of brutal Conrade. Bath. Then art thou ruin'd, past redemption ruin'd! Ism. Past, past redemption! every other ill May be reliev'd by hope, or born with patience; Here hope's impossible, and patience guilt. Bath. Then the last sacred business is revenge— Ism. Look down, all-pitying Heaven, on these my woes, Woes undeserv'd, and guiltless misery: They plead my cause, the cause of innocence, An injur'd, violated, matron's cause; And shall they plead in vain? Bath. Yes, my dear child, In whom thy Father's secret soul rejoiced; Whose goodness and whose happiness was such, He found old age delightfull; let thy foes, Those kindred-fiends, to this thy just appeal Plead their high rank, and try its weight with Heaven. Ism. Or Elmerick, whose wrath perhaps they fear Much more than Heaven's. Bath. And therefore may avoid. This asks some thought— For who can answer for thy husband's transport, Wise as he is, when he shall hear thy wrongs? Ism. O what a scene of horror have you rais'd! He'll rush, unarm'd, on our insidious foes, Fall in their toils, and perish. Yes, my woes, My miseries, enormous as they are, Admit of aggravation. Bath. His danger wou'd be great. Some hand less fear'd May make revenge more certain—Nay, 'twere kind To spare thy Lord such anguish and despair. Ism. O Heaven! and Earth! to whom shall I complain, Where pour my sorrows forth, if not to him? Bath. Think you expose his life. Ism. Death seal my lips! Bath. Retire, and trust our vengeance to my prudence. Compose thy self, and when thou seest thy Lord— Ism. Madness will seize me, Or raging grief disclose the horrid secret. (Exit. Bath. Suspence was ease to this confirm'd despair. Would thou wert dead, Ismena!—O my child! Thou art so lost beyond the reach of hope, That love itself compels thy wretched Father To wish thee dead; and in the bitterness Of anguish mourn that ever thou wert born. May one kind grave soon hide thy woes and mine. Ismena!—oh!—But while I weep thy wrongs, The spoiler lives.—Those are the Queen's apartments, And, doubtless, there her brutal brother lurks. Nor courts, nor shrines and altars shall protect him. What, ho! within! Prince of Moravia! Conrade! If thou'rt a man, stand forth, appear and answer. Enter Conrade. Conr. What insolence is this!—Ismena's Father!— Bath. Yes, impious Prince, the Father of Ismena. Conr. Forbear, rash man; this foul reproach I pardon. Somewhat, I grant, is due to thy first transports Of jealous honour, and much more from me To fair Ismena's father. Bath. Yes, thy blood. Conr. Yet hold; I've that to say may calm thy fury. Bath. Coward! Conr. I smile, old man, And will be heard. Your daughter has been wrong'd, But most by her ungrateful, faithless Lord; Whose rude attempt upon the Queen, my sister, Makes what I've done a just, though bold, reprisal. Let him atone his treasonous presumption, Which, be assur'd, he answers with his life; And let me perish, if I not restore The injur'd honour of your lov'd Ismena With vast increase, and seat her on a throne. Bath. I'd rather see her in the arms of death Than reigning o'er the universe with thee. Mark thy progression, From rape to subornation, thence to murther. Long-suffering Heaven, whose patience thou hast tir'd, Calls loud for vengeance on thee. (Draws.) Conr. Frantick man! Enter Queen, Lords and Guards, who interpose. Q. You Lords of Hungary, behold this sight, And vindicate your hospitality. Is this fit treatment for a royal guest? Will you endure this more than barb'rous outrage, And share the guilt of him and his confed'rates? Who twice this day, and for a cause too vile For me to name, have sought my brother's life. 1 Ld. How shall we reconcile what we have seen With your known wisdom, and consummate virtue? Bath. Believe me, friends, there is, there is a cause For what you saw, for what I fain wou'd hide, These eyes still swelling with unmanly tears; Which when you know, you'll join with me to curse The chance that brought you, to prevent my justice. 1 Ld. The great, good man! so long, so often prov'd The fearless advocate of injur'd innocence, Wou'd he shed tears, And call for justice when no wrong was done him? Judge others as they please, I will not think it. 2 Ld. Nor I. 3 Ld. Nor I. 4 Ld. Why is that wrong conceal'd? Bath. For most important reasons: Though I fear It will too soon be known. 4 Ld. 'Till then, my Lord, Excuse me, if I think our country's honour Must suffer by your conduct. 5 Ld. That's my judgment. Bath. If your long knowledge of me cannot gain Some credit to my word, at least suspend Your hasty censures. (Going.) 1 Ld. We accept your word, And vow to share your counsels, and your fortune. Bath. You're truly noble. And be well assur'd That 'tis an honest cause, and worth espousing. (Exeunt Bathori, 1, 2, 3 Lords. Q. Unmanner'd Traitors! From you, my Lords, who think and act more nobly, What may insulted Majesty expect? 4 Ld. All that becomes good subjects, who will guard The venerable rights of hospitality. 5 Ld. Bathori, whose rash conduct we condemn, At our joint charge, shall answer to the regent His bold attempt. Q. The Regent!— His daughter's husband! his confed'rate!— 5 Ld. No kindred, Madam, will prevail with Elmerick To stop the course of justice. Q. Left to him, Whose daring insolence has been the source Of these fierce discords! Lords, if you regard The publick safety, if you love the King, Or dare defend your Queen from foulest insult; Go find him now, attack him unprepar'd, Stand not on forms, the least delay is fatal. 4 Ld. Your pardon, Madam— 5 Ld. Our zeal shall never make assassins of us. Q. Nor men, tame Lords. You who have seen my brother Assaulted with a murderous intent, Is this your boasted loyalty and honour? 4 Ld. These bind us to respect the character, The dignity and person of the Regent. 5 Ld. If you, my Queen, or you, great Prince, are wrong'd, The King will do you justice. (Exeunt Lords. Conr. Canting traitors! They go to join our foe, and swell his power: This shrub of one day's growth, this idol Regent Attracts their ready worship. Q. Let them go. Now by the burning rage that drinks my blood The fools spoke true: The King shall do us justice. Conr. Elmerick, His Influence— Q. We will accuse him first. The King has not yet reach'd Alba-Regalis, You soon will overtake him. What you saw Of Elmerick's base purpose strongly urg'd, Join'd with the earnest letters I shall write, Will so alarm and prepossess the King; That all complaints of their Ismena's sufferings Will be regarded as an after feint, A mean device to screen her guilty lord. What are your thoughts? Conr. That thou wast born to triumph. This traitor, when unmask'd, shall fall unpitied By all mankind, and hated by Ismena. Q. Still your Ismena! Conr. O my best Matilda! The hopes that freed by death from her false husband, And of his crimes convinc'd, she then may deign To bless my vows, and share my future throne, Are more than safety, life or vengeance to me. My blind impetuous passion once desir'd Those charms alone which violence cou'd gain; But now the avarice of love aspires To mutual bliss, and more refin'd disdains Th'imperfect pleasures which her will denied. Q. She may be wholly and for ever yours. You mark'd with how much care the cautious Sire Preserv'd the secret of his daughter's wrongs. Conr. Oh may I live to make her reparation By gentlest love for wrongs which now my soul Detests, and sickens at the vile remembrance. Q. Live and be bless'd. I do not hate Ismena: Cut off, that source of both our wrongs, her husband, And my tormenting thirst of vengeance ceases. Conr. Prepare your letters. I'll be instant ready. (Exit Conrade. Q. Yes, I will humble that exalted mein, And teach this new made Regent's pride submission. He is secure, and let him be so still; 'Till my revenge, a slighted Queen's revenge, Burst forth, and blast him with unthought of ruin. (Exit Queen. SCENE II. Ismena's Apartment. Enter Elmerick running to embrace her. Elm. Thou hast too long been absent, my Ismena! A thousand anxious cares have fill'd my heart Since I beheld thee last. But thou art found, Who ne'er appear'd to my desiring eyes But peace and comfort and delight came with thee. O take me to thy arms, and quite extinguish The memory of pain. Ism. O misery! (refusing to embrace him.) Unequal'd misery! I am excluded For ever from those arms. Elm. All-gracious Heaven! What mean these broken thoughts, this lab'ring anguish, My soul, thou sum of all my joys, my wife! Ism. Thou hast no wife. Elm. Distraction! Ism. I'm a wretch Without a name, and fain would quit my being. Elm. Protect me, Heaven! Ismena! what dire thought Shakes thy sweet soul with such tempestuous agony? What ill so sudden, since we parted last, Preventing even my fears, has burst upon thee? Say, tell me— Ism. No, I cannot, dare not tell you:— You cannot bear it. Though I ne'er conceal'd A thought before, I must be silent now. Elm. What can this mean? And yet I dread to know— Perhaps the envious Queen has wrong'd my truth, Can you suspect my love? Ism. You love too well: O that 'twere in your power to love me less! Elm. Nay, then I'm lost indeed—Pronounce my doom; But let me hear it folded in thy arms. Ism. Avoid me, fly, and think of me no more. Elm. What! shun my arms, Ismena! Ism. There's my misery, I must for ever shun 'em—Now, my Father, Where is your prudence? Must I seem a monster, Ungrateful, false to Elmerick; or bring —Detested thought—pollution to his arms? Elm. Pollution! madness! Ism. I have been betray'd, Basely betray'd to infamy and ruin, Render'd unworthy of thy chaste embraces, That execrable fiend, that monster Conrade Has robb'd me of my honour. Elm. Hear me, Heaven! Let not this whirlwind of overwhelming passion Tear up my being—Let me live whole ages Though raging with despair, rather than die And leave her unreveng'd. Ism. Had not religion Withheld my hand, whose law forbids self-murder, (That short and easy cure for shame and anguish) These sorrows ne'er had reach'd you. Elm. Talk not thus, Talk not of dying; thou art innocent, Thy mind unstain'd; thy wrongs shall be reveng'd, And thou still bless my days. Ism. It cannot be: My power to bless is lost. I am the blot, The only blot of Elmerick's fair honour.— O! why was it committed to the charge Of one so heedless, so improvident, Guardian unworthy of a trust so noble. Elm. O my Ismena! Ism. O my dearest Lord! Alas you weep—I cannot bear your tears, They melt my firmest purpose—but Farewell— One last embrace, as on a dying friend, It will not stain your glory to bestow On your undone Ismena— Elm. To my bosom With tenderer fondness did I never press thee. Here rest, my love, a while, and lose thy woes. Ism. The greatness of my woes will make 'em short: I feel my vital powers decay apace. To part with thee, was all that e'er appear'd Dreadful to me in death—that's past already— And all to come is ease and soft repose. When I'm no more, remember, Elmerick, My reverend Father; comfort and support him The best you can: My loss will touch him nearly. I see you burn for vengeance, but beware; The cruel, treach'rous Queen conspir'd with Conrade. Elm. Alike remote from rashness and from fear, I'll trace this hellish mystery to its source, And deal to each, with an inflexible And equal hand, the portion they deserve: I'll weigh it as the action of my life That must give name and value to the whole; And raise a monument to thee and justice Shall strike exalted wickedness with terror, And freeze the boiling blood of future Conrades. Farewell, be patient, and expect th'event. (Exeunt. End of the Fourth Act.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT V. SCENE I. Queen alone. Queen. To recollect and judge our actions past, May yield instruction—I approve my caution, And bless the fortune that conceal'd my weakness For the proud Regent, even from my brother. My seeming innocence preserves respect, And gives him life and vigour to pursue My daring scheme to crush the man I hate. Shou'd it succeed, secure from all reproach, Life may be worth my care. Enter Zenomira. I had forgot— This woman knows too much—her lover too— They may be dangerous—that too shou'd be thought on, And shall be so hereafter—What's your business? Zen. Madam, the Regent asks to be admitted. Q. Why shou'd I be alarm'd?—No, 'tis not fear That gives this sudden sickness to my heart:— This tremor, these convulsive starts proceed From strong aversion only—I contemn him. [Apart. Yes, let him enter. [Exit Zenomira. I'll enjoy his anguish: Safe in my sex and dignity, I'll tell him, That 'tis my pride and glory to have made him The very wretch he is. Enter Elmerick and Zenomira. Zen. Madam, the Regent— Elm. I've orders, Madam, from your Lord and mine Fit only for your ear. Q. What gloomy grandeur he assumes! What insolent tranquillity he bears! You may withdraw. [Exit Zenomira. Elm. I hear, Conrade is fled. Q. You've bad intelligence, the state must suffer While you're no better serv'd: He scorns to fly, And will confront you soon. Elm. 'Till then, let guilt And fear attend, and keep the villain waking. Q. You come to rail: Begin, I stand collected, Nay, will assist you. You refus'd my love, And in my turn, I have undone Ismena. Elm. You do confess it then? Q. I glory in it. To wound you where I knew you most secure, To taint your Heaven, to curse you in Ismena, Was my contrivance: Conrade's desperate passion, Subservient to my vengeance, wrought her ruin. Elm. This I had charg'd you with; but, self-convicted, My pains are spar'd, and here your process ends. [A pause. Thou awful power, whose bright tremendous sword Rules Heaven and Earth, while Hell resists in vain, Inexorably firm, eternal Justice; Fearless I offer up this high delinquent To you and to Ismena: Deign t'accept No common sacrifice, and may it prove A solemn lesson and a dreadful warning, T'instruct and to alarm a guilty world. Q. Dost thou presume, the subject of our throne, To menace me with justice? Elm. You're no Sov'reign, Your King's authority resides in me. Q. Not to assassinate his Queen. Help. Treason. [Calls. Elm. Cease your vain clamour, and prepare to die; I've taken measures not to be prevented. Q. Traitor, think who I am, respect my rank. Elm. That you shou'd have respected. The blackest aggravation of your guilt Is from your rank, and other benefits Receiv'd from Heaven: Not to have done much good With your advantages, forfeits them all, And leaves you debtor to a vast account; But there abuse— Q. And who shall judge of that? Elm. All may, and must, who feel and suffer by it; But I've a double right to judge and punish. The ignominy of a bar and scaffold, Which our strict laws, and your high crimes demand; For the King's honour, here I take upon me At my own peril to remit, and make Myself your only judge, and this your scaffold. If you've not sin'd beyond the hopes of pardon, But wou'd in pray'r and penitential tears Employ a few short moments, they are yours— The utmost of my mercy. Q. So determin'd! The King's arrival yet wou'd change our fates. [Aside. Cruel man! Blame your own scorn for what I've rashly done, And let us now exchange mutual forgiveness. [Weeps. Elm. I have not gone thus far without consulting Reason and Justice, with the extent and end Of that great Power and Trust impos'd upon me: No, had the wrong you've basely done my wife, Been done the meanest peasant's wife in Hungary, Nor rank, nor vain intreaties shou'd protect you. Q. Conrade is gone t'accuse you to the King— You know how well the strong appearance won My brother's credit to th'imputed crime; My death wou'd be so full a confirmation Of all I charg'd you with, that certain ruin, And everlasting infamy, must follow. Elm. And do you thus atone for your offences? Is this the use you make of my indulgence, To boast new crimes? Q. To warn you of your danger. I tell you once again, you dare not kill me. Elm. I dare not let you live, for that's injustice,— The only thing I fear: And had you fear'd it, You had been safe and happy. Enter now Ye ministers of justice: Do your office. Enter the Executioners. While they prepare to strangle her, she speaks. Q. Is there no help then? Must I fall his victim?— Almighty power, who gav'st me my existence, And with it strong affections and aversions, Why hast thou dealt so very hardly with me? If you have mercy— [They pull her into the Recess in the back Scene, and strangle her. Elm. O let her life atone for all its errors!— Thus I supply the interrupted pray'r That death breaks off, and may it find acceptance! The fiercest anger in the human mind Shou'd reach but to the grave—Belus. Enter Belus. Bel. My Lord, What is your pleasure? Elm. We must seek the King. Bel. My Lady's father, and th'assembled Peers— Elm. 'Tis true, I had forgot. Behold within there. [Pointing to the Recess in the back Scene. Bel. Alas! my Lord!— [Seeing the Queen. Elm. At what are you surpriz'd? Bel. The Queen is dead! Elm. She is, and by my sentence. Have I done ought unjust? Bel. I dare not say it, Yet stand astonish'd at the rigorous deed. Elm. So do not I that wickedness abounds, When justice is a wonder. Seek the Peers, And bring 'em to behold what thou hast seen. Bel. You wou'd not have this known? Elm. Not have it known! The business of my life is to proclaim it. [Exit Belus. O thou impartial, universal power, Wise Nature's eldest law, wrote by herself Upon the heart of man, eternal Justice; Inspired by thee, with one determin'd blow, I have redrest my poor Ismena's wrongs, (As far as wrongs like hers can be redress'd) And wip'd dishonour from my house and name: And now if I am call'd to be thy martyr, My race will end with glory. Enter Bathori and Lords. Bath. I have declared To these right noble Lords, as you commanded, The Queen and Conrade's most inhuman guilt. Elm. Then judge, my Lords, whether this dreadful act Merits reproach or praise. [Pointing to the Queen. 1st Ld. Speak he that can. 2d Ld. Astonishingly bold— 3d Ld. But righteous vengeance: Unprecedented Justice! Ba. Yes, this transcends example. Gracious Heaven! May I but live to see her brother thus!— 1st Ld. Sir, your interest May make you partial: Not that we condemn Or justify the Regent: To the King We must refer his sentence. Elm. 'Tis but just. And so may Heaven deal with my soul hereafter, When I shall stand at that all-seeing bar; As I will render up a strict account, Urge to the King himself his Queen's misdoing, And seek my judge with his wife's blood upon me. 1st L. Heard you that trumpet? [Flourish of trumpets. 2d Ld. See, the King appears. Enter King, Conrade, and Attendants. K. Where is this Patriot who defies all law, And uses our authority for treason? I ask for Elmerick. Elm. Your loyal subject, The Palatine and Regent of your kingdom, Who bears that name, is here. K. Doth not the presence of thy King confound thee? Elm. I burnt with strong impatience 'till I saw him. K. Where is Matilda? Go and call the Queen: Let her appear, and strike the Traitor dumb. —What means this gloomy silence? Are you motionless? Why am I not obey'd? Elm. I pray, give back— Behold, unhappy King, to what my Justice Has brought thy guilty Queen. K. Heavenly powers! Matilda! Am I come, though on the wings Of love, too late to save thee? [Runs to the body in the recess Conr. O my sister! Are these our promis'd joys? Is this our triumph? Elm. Suspend the Husband, and exert the King. K. Inhuman wretch! I will exert the King, And give new majesty and double terror To that important name, for thy destruction. Elm. Sir, I resign my life without reluctance; Take, if you please, my head. But know, your fame Is in the balance, and your conduct now Must fix your character to all posterity; Must place you in the list of lawless tyrants, Or Kings, whose virtue dignify'd the office, And honour'd human nature. If you think The abject fear of death, not a regard To your yet spotless virtue and renown, Inspires my tongue, you've my compassion, Sir. Monarchs are men—I've said—and use your pleasure. K. I thought I knew thee well: hence my amazement Is equal to my grief and indignation. Had'st thou the tongue of Angels, cou'd'st thou hope To clear thyself of my Matilda's death? Elm. Nor was it e'er my purpose to attempt it; But I've a right to justify myself If innocent, and to be heard with patience. K. But if thro' passionate and blind prevention You do refuse to hear, I had rather die Than bear the unavailing name of Palatine, First guardian of the rights of freeborn Hungary, And live a witness to an innovation So fatal to my country Thou hast touch'd My inmost soul. I'd rather thou shou'dst 'scape, Than fix a precedent which may be urged Hereafter, to suppress the voice of truth; Lose the benignant character of King, And change my glories for a tyrant's shame.— You shall be heard: A seat—O my Matilda, Forgive this short delay. Let the rash man, Endeavouring to defend, convict himself, And fall the more abhorr'd. Elm. You may remember, Sir, When you appointed me your substitute, You did pronounce, in presence of your states, The worst abuse of law and all just power, Is when the great offend and pass unpunish'd. This you injoin'd me strongly not to suffer, Nor bear the sword in vain. You've been obey'd— The Queen transgress'd—and I have done my duty. K. Your duty, Sir! Dare you affirm the Queen— Elm. Deserv'd the death I gave her. Hear me out. If, with deep fore-thought and deliberate malice, To plot and to effect a matron's ruin, To give her up to a lewd spoiler's rage, By laws divine and human, be pronounc'd A crime deserving death, the guilty Queen Drew on herself the justice I inflicted. Her wicked agent Conrade, her vile brother, Who stain'd the purity of my Ismena, Is left to prove your justice. [King rises. K. Can it be! Thy lovely, chaste Ismena! Elm. She, my wife. Lovely she was, and chaste; and not less worthy That just regard the meanest may pretend to, I trust, for being mine. Conr. Evasive traitor! Say for what cause, with impious prophanation, You dar'd attempt your master's sacred bed; And I may deign to answer to your charge. K. Is this the court of Buda? This vile stage Of lewdness, death, and black recrimination? Of what a sudden growth is rank corruption! That, during my short absence, hath infected My house and throne, those I most loved and trusted. —But bring the clearest proof of this foul charge Against my Queen and brother, or expect The self same mercy thou hast shewn to her: Whom, if thy accusation be unjust, Thou'st basely murder'd twice. Elm. I have the strongest proofs, My wife's accusing tears, who cou'd not forge To her own ruin and to my dishonour A tale so full of shame. But more, the Queen, The Queen herself, triumphant in her malice, Confest it to my face, and gloried in it. K. And will Ismena vouch it?—I think highly Of your Wife's truth;—so did I of Matilda's— I'll not condemn her on a single witness: Ismena is but one, thy word is nothing. Elm. I have yet farther Proofs. Peruse this scroll, (Giving the King a Paper.) This full avowal of the hellish deed, Witness'd by these who both were actors in it, (Pointing to Belus and Zenomira.) Without designing ill, which I produce With strong reluctance, as it speaks a weakness Of the lost Queen, which I wou'd fain conceal. K. Why shou'd I tremble thus? Let truth appear, And shame light where it will. (Reads) Madness and death! Confess a guilty passion for the Regent!— Can these things be!—That dignity of spirit, That high demeanour stoop to such dishonour!— How shall I credit—what I can't reject? How root out fixt ideas from a heart Matilda fill'd, and bend it to conviction?— O Elmerick! I see the pois'nous source Of our united woes. Elm. Her will refus'd, She offer'd at her Life— Conr. This claims attention. (Aside.) Elm. Which while I strove to save, her brother enter'd; And, by her art deceiv'd, attempted mine: The rest that paper speaks. Conr. Too fatal truth! 'Twas gallant in him then not to accuse her. I see my fate, and am prepar'd to meet it. (Aside.) K. You do acknowledge, and confirm for truth All that is here contain'd? (To Bel. and Zen.) Both. So Heaven deal with us. K. 'Tis all too plain: Her lawless love, fierce malice, Conrade's foul rage, and poor Ismena's ruin— To find her guilty, is to find her hateful: And I wou'd hate—what once I dearly lov'd. No blood—but tears, and those too weakly shed, Must stream o'er thy dishonourable hearse, Unhappy, false Matilda!—But no more.— I will dismiss this weak unworthy softness. Let Elmerick go weep.—Ismena's wrongs May call forth tears that manhood may be proud of. To weep Ismena is to feel for virtue. How is it with her sorrows? From this hour My tenderest care shall be to give them comfort. Elm. I fear her sorrows ne'er will taste of comfort. But see, the messenger I sent returns. Enter Messenger. Mess. I come, my Lord— Elm. Be brief: how fares my wife? Mess. As Angels fare, With whom she now inhabits. When you sent me, I found her in the arms of her attendants— Fainting she seem'd—But when I told my message She rais'd her head, and lifting up her eyes, 'Till then just clos'd, propitious Heaven! she cried, Defend this noblest pattern of your justice, Nor let his matchless love go unrewarded. Then with an heavenly smile addrest me thus. Assure my Lord I die without reluctance. My soul, that melts with gratitude, presages Unequal'd blessings shall attend him here, While I enjoy—and then her speech forsook her, And she, without one painful sigh, expir'd. K. Too sure a testimony hast thou given Of thy foul wrongs, Ismena—Elmerick!— Quite speechless and o'erwhelm'd!—her father too!— Turn not away—I do not offer comfort— I mean but to mourn with you. Elm. So to die!— Her delicately chaste and heavenly soul Forsook its earthly temple when prophan'd Without the steel or poison's lawless aid— And lives the man who wrong'd me in Ismena? Hear then, O righteous King, my high appeal To thee, and to the law of warlike Hungary. Give me to meet this impious Prince in battle; There, in the crouded lists, dread scene of justice, There only can I sue for retribution, Wrong'd as I am, without a soldier's shame. And thou, Ismena, from thy sainted seat, Where high thou sit'st crown'd with the starry wreaths That angels weave for purity like thine, Look down propitious on me, and accept This high, this second sacrifice of vengeance. Conr. Then I have murder'd thee, ador'd Ismena. These mourn thy fate with tears, but what's the sorrow That streaming eyes can utter and relieve! Though thou disdain'st my grief, yet learn this truth (turning to Elmerick) From him thou most abhor'st:—The innocent Are not the fittest objects of compassion: O there's no pain, no misery like guilt— Nor do I fall thy sacrifice: For know, Had I been plac'd above the power of vengeance; Ismena's fate, th'effect of my rash love, Had been lamented thus, and thus reveng'd— (Stabs himself.) K. This is t'atone one error by another. Conr. Nothing but error: I was born to err: The willing slave of every youthful passion. 'Tis now too late to learn—my day is past— 'Tis night—Ismena—oh— (Dies.) Elm. Unerring power! whose deep and secret counsels No finite mind can fathom and explore; It must be just to leave your creatures free, And wise to suffer what you most abhor: Supreme and absolute of these your ways You render no account—We ask for none. For mercy, truth, and righteous retribution Attend at length your high and awful throne. Ismena is aveng'd—Let me be wretched! K. Our sorrows must be felt. Yet, O! brave Elmerick, Let not the Publick suffer! Thou'st done greatly. Still hold the Sov'reign Power till I return From Jordan's sacred stream and holy Sion; My Substitute till then, my Friend for ever. The face of justice as she shines in Heaven, In native purity, unclouded splendor, Alone can charm beyond thy virtuous daring. That be Thy praise—that I approve it mine. End of the Fifth Act.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">EPILOGUE. Spoken by Mr. Milward. You, who supreme o'er ev'ry work of Wit, In Judgment here unaw'd, unbiast sit, The Palatines and Guardians of the Pit; If to your minds this meerly-modern Play, No useful sense, no gen'rous warmth convey; If Fustian here, thro' each unnat'ral Scene, In strain'd conceits sound high, and nothing mean; If Lofty Dulness for your Vengeance call; Like Elmerick Judge, and let the Guilty Fall. But if Simplicity with Force and Fire, Unlabour'd thoughts and artless words inspire; If, like the Action which these Scenes relate, The whole appear irregularly Great; If master-strokes the nobler Passions move, Then, like the King, acquit us, and approve. The END.</field>
   </doc>
</add>