<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Talfourd, Thomas Noon, Sir, 1795-1854</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Talfourd, Thomas Noon, Sir, 1795-1854</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">talfourd thomas noon sir 1795 1854</field>
      <field name="author_text">Talfourd, Thomas Noon, Sir, 1795-1854</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1840's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V3.0076.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1840</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460514</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Glencoe</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Glencoe</field>
      <field name="title_facet">glencoe</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">glencoe</field>
      <field name="title_text">Glencoe</field>
      <field name="year_display">1840</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1840</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1840</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460514&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460514&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Talfourd, Thomas Noon, Sir, 1795-1854&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;talfourd thomas noon sir 1795 1854&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Glencoe&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;glencoe&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1840&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1840&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Talfourd, Thomas Noon, Sir&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1795&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1854&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Glencoe&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Eduard Moxon&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1840&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872858-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv30076&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Glencoe&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 176 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted&lt;lb/&gt;Only verse drama included&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Glencoe.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1839.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 23 May 1840.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">GLENCOE; OR, THE FATE OF THE MACDONALDS. A TRAGEDY, IN FIVE ACTS.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">FIRST REPRESENTED, 23D MAY, 1840.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. SCENE I. The Hall in the House of Mac Ian in Glencoe. Midnight.—A turf fire burning.—Storm heard without.— John Macdonald discovered sitting pensively at a table; Alaster pacing the room. JOHN. Let me entreat you, Alaster, to sleep; Three nights of feverish waking, at your age, May spoil you for a watchman; for your nerves, Undisciplined by care, throb many hours, While those of elder and sedater spirits, Ruled by the time, count one. Rest those slight limbs On yonder couch of heather;—I would pledge My word to rouse you at the first faint tread Which may announce your father; but 'twere needless; In deepest slumber it will stir your heart, And rouse you to his arms. ALASTER. How can I sleep? How can you wish that I should sleep, when night Succeeds to night, and still the unconquer'd wind, Laden with snow and hailstones, dashes round us, As if in scorn of Highlanders, content To yield the fastnesses in which it held Joint empire with our sires; and still the fear That it hath dealt its vengeance on the head We love increases,—with the time o'erpast For sad and shameful travel? JOHN. Alaster, I must not hear you blend those words with aught Our sire resolved. You did not guess the war Of fierce emotions that, within his frame Unshaken, raged, as time brought nigh the hour When he must plight his faith to England's King, Or to the power of unrelenting foes Yield up his clansmen. While the sky was clear, With wavering purpose he inclined to wait His doom at home; but when the snow-storm hurl'd Its icy arrows through the hills, the woes Of roofless desolation all would share Shriek'd at his heart, and peril lent a show Of honour to the journey, which had else Seem'd shameful;—so he girt him to the task As to a doom'd man's office. If we lose All else, we will preserve our household laws; Nor let the licence of these fickle times Subvert the holy shelter which command Of fathers, and undoubting faith of sons, Rear'd for our shivering virtues. You o'erstep The province of a Highland chieftain's son; You must not judge your father. ALASTER. It is true, And I submit me to your chiding: still 'Tis hard to own new tyranny; to shrink Before its threats; to feel the Highland heart Shrivel and die within its case, nor strike One blow for ancient sovereignty and honour. JOHN. I grant that it is hard; but if the blow Be without hope, 'tis nobler to forbear, Nor buy a glorious moment with the blood Of trusting clansmen. Would you know what virtue Endurance may possess, when action fails, Look at our cousin Halbert!—To your eye, Whose memory reaches not his fiery boyhood, He seems distinguish'd only by that charm Of courtesy which hearted kindness sheds Through simplest manners, and an aspect grave Which these huge rocks impress upon the port Of him who loves them. You have often seen Our father to his greeting make return Of gibe or withering silence, which he bears In gentlest mood;—yet once his soul was passion'd With wilder rage than even your ardent youth Can guess; but I err now; for I o'erstep An old injunction not to tell his story, Till manhood fitted you to hear it. ALASTER. Manhood! JOHN. I did not mean to ruffle you. Your years, Though few, have been instructed by distress, And I admit your title to the cares And knowledge happier fortunes had deferr'd. Sit, then, and listen. Halbert's father long With ours contested who might claim descent From eldest line of ancestry, and right To chieftainship and lands. Fierce conflicts held The claim in doubt, till old Macdonald fell Stricken for death;—then, conscious that his sons, Halbert, the eldest-born, about your age, And Henry, a slight stripling, scarcely twelve, Could ill sustain the quarrel, or protect Their mother in her sorrow, sent the priest Who shrived him, to entreat his rival's hand In peace,—with offer to resign his claims: So that the blacken'd tower in which he lay, Its ruin'd chapel, the small niche of rock In which they are embraced as in a chasm Rent 'neath our loftiest peak by ancient storm, And some scant pastures on Loch Leven's side, Were ratified as Halbert's. To this pact I was a witness, and the scene lives now Before me.—In a room where flickering light Strove through the narrow openings of huge walls, On a low couch, Macdonald's massive form Lay stretch'd;—with folded arms my father stood Awed by the weakness of the foe so late His equal; the expiring warrior raised His head, and catching from the eager looks Of the wan lady who had wiped the dew Of anguish from his forehead, argument To quell all scruple, solemnly rehearsed The terms, and, as his dying prayer, implored Halbert to keep them. ALASTER. So he yielded? JOHN. No; One flush of crimson from the hair which curl'd Crisply around his brows, suffused his face And throat outspread with rage;—he slowly raised His dirk; and, though the agony which swell'd His heaving breast prevented speech, we read In his dilated nostril, eyes that flash'd With fire that answer'd to the uplifted steel, And lips wide-parted for the sounds which strove In vain to reach their avenue, a vow Of never-resting warfare;—so he stood Rigid as marble, of his mother's face Turn'd on him from her knees—of the wild fear Which struck his gamesome brother sad,—of all Unconscious. While we waited for his words, Another voice, from the deep shade that gloom'd Beyond the death-bed, came;—and midst it, stood The squalid figure of a woman, wrought Beyond the natural stature as she stretch'd Her wither'd finger towards the youth, and spoke— “Halbert, obey! The hour which sees thee rule O'er the Macdonalds of Glencoe shall bring Terror and death.”—Then glided from the room. He did not start, but as his ears drank in The sounds, his colour vanish'd from his face; The light forsook his eyes; his nerveless hand Released the dirk; he sank on trembling knees, Beside the couch, and with a child's soft voice Said, “I obey”—and bow'd his head to take His father's blessing, who fell back and died When he had murmur'd it. The youth arose Sedate, and turning to his mother, said, “I live for you.” Since then he has remain'd What you have known him. ALASTER. What was she who wrought This awful change? JOHN. Have you not heard of Moina? Although she has not since that day been seen Within our vale, her awful figure glared On the remotest infancy of men Who now are reckon'd old. Her age alone Would make the obscurest thread of human life Drawn out, though many births and deaths of Hope, A thing to tremble at;—'tis said she gazed On that best piece of heavenly workmanship— Our Mary's beauty, when the shrivell'd Queen Of England foully shatter'd it; some crime Or mighty sorrow now forgotten drew Her steps into deep solitude. Preserved By her majestic bearing from the grasp Of law, she owns the power to pierce the veil Of mortal vision;—the sole tie she knows To this world is a kindred with our race, From which she sprung;—yet only giant griefs Borne or foreshadow'd have the power to stir Her dull affections, or to invite her steps From the rude hovel where she dwells alone Far on the mountain plain, within the round Of stones which point Death's ancient victories O'er nameless heroes. Whether earnest thought And long communion with the hills whose moan Foretells the tempest, taught her first to break The bondage of the Present, or worse aid Hath given her might, I cannot tell; pray Heaven That you may never cross her! ALASTER. Her strange words Fell lightly on the younger son, whose acts Of boyish prowess wrought in frolic mood I once admired;—has anything been heard Of that gay scapegrace? JOHN. No;—he could not brook The dulness of his home, though not uncheer'd By female grace; for there the lovely child Of brave Hugh Campbell, whom Macdonald loved, Spite of the hatred that he bore his clan, Has, from the opening of her youth's first blossom Found shelter;—and no fairer Scotland boasts Than Helen Campbell. If young Henry lives, Be sure you'll find him on the sunny side Of Fortune's favour.—Hark! The Cona's roar! It bursts the icy chains which long have held it, And riots in its freedom. ALASTER. 'Twill destroy The slender bridge below us. Should our Father Approach that way!—I will not linger thus. JOHN. He bade me wait him here. Ho! Kenneth! (calling.) Run Enter Kenneth. Swift to the bridge, it may be yours to save Your chief. [Exit Kenneth. His journey will not lie that way, Yet horrors thicken round us. 'Mid the roar Methinks I hear a step—it comes—alas! 'Tis not Mac Ian's. Enter Halbert Macdonald. Halbert, I have scarce The power to bid you welcome as I ought; We are sad watchers for our sire's return, And almost blame the footsteps of a friend Which might be his. HALBERT. I came to ask of him;— For having cross'd him on Loch Leven's shore Three nights ago, scarce two miles hence, I heard With wonder the report which found its way To our lone dwelling but to-night, that still He was abroad. ALASTER. Are you assured 'twas he? Did he address you? HALBERT. Alaster, you know How rarely he will grace me with a word; But this is not a season for a thought, Save of his peril. I had made my way, Breasting the hurricane, in hope to lead Our herd to shelter ere the night should add Dark terrors to the storm: in blackening mist I saw a mantle flicker; then the hairs Of a white head, which stream'd along the wave Of flying vapour; swift I ran to aid Some aged wanderer's steps, and cried aloud. He fled before me, till my fleeter limbs O'ertook him; then he faced me;—'twas your father! A look, in which strong anguish baffled scorn, He fix'd upon me; waved his arm aloft, In action that forbade pursuit, and took The pathway to Loch Etive. I believed He wish'd but to avoid me, and that done, He would turn homeward. ALASTER. If indeed 'twas he And not a dreadful shadow of his mould, He fears to meet the faces of his friends After his oath to William. HALBERT. If he lives, That oath is past; and being past, dear cousin, Let it not prompt a word which may add pangs To a brave spirit's shame. At earliest dawn I'll search each cavern'd nook within our glen, Nor leave a crevice which the smallest rill Has hollow'd, unexplored. I know them well: So haply I may find the reverend chief Crouch'd in some narrow cave,—his stately head In resignation bow'd upon his staff, And waiting, without struggle, the last chill Of slowly freezing death;—may lead him home, And win one cordial pressure of his hand, To speak he owns me true. JOHN. A footstep!—hush! Enter Angus. JOHN. Angus at such an hour! ANGUS. A fearful summons From a shrill voice, between the tempest's gusts, Call'd me to meet my chief. JOHN. Would he were here! He comes even now (listening). No. Enter Donald. JOHN. This is terrible! DONALD. Is not Mac Ian here? I came to meet him; Roused from my bed by such a piercing cry As rarely syllables a human name! JOHN. You hear! Other old Clansmen enter. JOHN. I ask not why you come: I know Some mortal tidings linger on the storm, And ye are here to share them. Let them come: We can but die! HALBERT. Heaven fit us to endure! JOHN. Another step; I know it well!—'tis his! Pray you withdraw awhile; but go not hence. [Halbert and the Clansmen retire to the end of the Room. Enter Mac Ian. MAC IAN. Still watching?—you too, Alaster? What care My absence must have brought you! My dear sons, Do not despise your father, who returns The subject of King William. JOHN. All you do Must have our reverence. Let me bring you wine. MAC IAN. No; it would choke me. I must drain no more The goblet to assuage the patriot glow Of love and pride; I may not drink to Him Whose ancestry my own revered; and wine Were poison to me now. ALASTER. Is all then past? MAC IAN. It is; and sad as was the task, the way Was worthy of its end. When through deep snow I reach'd Fort-William, nerved to take the oath Before the General,—I was told his office Did not allow him to record it: thence I was compell'd to struggle through the storm To Inverary, where the Sheriff deign'd, Although beyond the appointed time, to seal The degradation of our race. I pass'd Within two miles of this beloved home, And dared not turn to it. HALBERT —(speaking to Angus behind). 'Twas there I met him. MAC IAN. Who spoke? Is he who track'd me in the storm Come as a spy, upon my sad return, To gaze upon my sorrow? Let him face me! HALBERT —(coming forward). I came not to offend you. JOHN. No;—he came In terror for your safety. MAC IAN. Said he so? Nay, Halbert, look yourself; scant powers are left To grace the seat you wait for, yet my son Shall fill it after me. Declare your wish To rend it from us;—'twere a nobler course Than that you follow. HALBERT. Sir, you do me wrong; I boast no virtue when I claim content With that which you have left me;—would not change My naked turret, in its mountain hold, Reach'd by the path along whose rugged steeps Discord and envy climb not, for the fields Rich Inverary in its scornful groves Embosoms; and to me the mouldering walls Of its small chapel wear the glory yet Of consecration which they took from prayers Of the first teachers, though a thousand storms Have drench'd and shaken them. Forgive me, sir: I have a patrimony which forbids Envy of yours. MAC IAN. You hear—he taunts me now;— Do you believe that show of meekness cheats A soldier's eye?—that we esteem your thoughts Subdued to habits of a herdsman's life, And all the passion and the pride of youth In these o'ercome? HALBERT. I strive to conquer them, And not in vain. You think that strange. If day Illumed the glen, I'd show you, from your door, A shapeless rock, which, thence observed, presents No mark to give it preference o'er the mass Of mountain ruin;—yet from upward gaze Of the slow traveller, as he drags his steps Through yon dark pass, it shuts the mighty gorge, Above with all its buttresses; its lake, Black with huge shadows; and its jagged heights, Which tempt the arrowy lightning from its track To sport with kindred terrors. So, by grace Of Heaven, each common object we regard With steadiness, can veil the dark abodes Of terrible Remembrance at whose side Fierce Passions slumber, and supply to Hope The place of airiest pinnacles it shades. Thus, sir, it is with me. JOHN. Believe it, father; Indeed 'tis true. MAC IAN. Perhaps I do you wrong; We'll speak of this to-morrow, when I meet The eldest clansmen, and with shame, enforce Their new allegiance. JOHN. They await you now. MAC IAN. Here?—I must face them;—tell them to approach. [Mac Ian takes his seat;—John beckons the old Clansmen, who surround it. MAC IAN. I have cold welcome for you, friends; you come To share the wreck of the Macdonalds. I, The most unhappy of the race, have been To make the final sacrifice. I felt Resistance, with our deaths, would glut the hate Of Scottish minions bribed by England's gold; And I have sworn—relate it for me, John, I cannot tell it! JOHN. To secure your lives My father perill'd his;—and yesternight, At Inverary, pledged our faith to William. Enter Kenneth wildly. KENNETH. Too late! too late! HALBERT. What mean those awful words? Is all his anguish vain? KENNETH (seeing MAC IAN). No, he is safe! Why start ye?—though the bridge is swept away, Our chief's unharm'd. HALBERT. And thus you welcome him, With words which freeze the soul! You meant no ill; Yet death is in your words. KENNETH (kneeling to MAC IAN). Forgive me. MAC IAN. Rise; I'm arm'd for any ill, unless it fall On these, my life's last comforts. [Looking on John and Alaster. HALBERT. Sir, farewell! When peril comes—as come it will—regard The meanest clansman's life less cheap than his Whose loyalty you wrong. [Exit Halbert. MAC IAN (to the Clansmen). Good night, my friends. [Exeunt Kenneth and Clansmen. Come near me, children;—I can scarcely bear To look into your faces. You forgive me? JOHN. Forgive! We honour and revere you. Bless us! [John and Alaster kneel, one on each side of Mac Ian's chair. He lays his hands on their heads. MAC IAN. There;—we are knotted now to live or die. [The Drop Scene falls. END OF ACT I.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. SCENE I. The Hall of Halbert's Tower. Time—Daybreak. Enter Lady Macdonald with a Letter, followed by Drummond, in the uniform of the Earl of Argyle's Regiment. LADY MACDONALD. Thanks for your pains. Let me devour again The precious characters. (Reads.) “I come, dear mother, Raised to high favour and command, to take My quarters in your vale.” The morn's faint light Had scarce enabled eyes less glad than mine To read;—they are dazzled now. [To the Soldier.] Pray you go in: We have poor entertainment to bestow, But our best cheer is yours. DRUMMOND. I must return Upon the instant; shall I bear your answer? LADY MACDONALD. There is no need; he speeds; his eager wish, If I may judge it by my own, will add Wings to his swiftness. Yet a moment stay; Know you the writer of these lines, my son,— Is he of gallant port? SOLDIER. Our regiment's pride, And first in favour of Glenlyon. LADY MACDONALD. Take A happy mother's thanks. [Exit Soldier. I shall behold A hero whom I parted from a child; Trace in his lineaments the hints which gave Sweet promise of his manhood; shall enjoy In one rich hour the pleasures which are spread Through years to her who watches the degrees Of youth's expanding brightness. Where is Halbert? Where Helen? She will laugh with wildest glee To find her little playmate a plumed soldier, And share his mirth. No gaiety like his Has cheer'd her since he left us. She is here. Enter Helen Campbell. HELEN. So early raised to meet the morning's chill? LADY MACDONALD. I feel no chill; the ecstacy within me Clothes all without with summer; you shall share In joy which seldom visits these old walls. HELEN. O say not so;—there's not a day but bears Its blessing on its light. If Nature doles Her gifts with sparing hand, their rareness sheds Endearments her most bounteous mood withholds From greenest valleys. The pure rill which casts Its thread of snow-like lustre o'er the rock, Which seems to pierce the azure sky, connects The thoughts of earth with heaven, while mightier floods Roar of dark passions. The rare sunbeam wins For a most slight existence human care, While it invests some marble heap with gleams Of palaced visions. If the tufts of broom Whence Fancy weaves a chain of gold, appear, On nearer visitation, thinly strewn, Each looks a separate bower, and offers shade To its own group of fairies. The prized harebell Wastes not its dawning azure on a bank Rough and confused with loveliness, but wears The modest story of its gentle life On leaves that love has tended; nay, the heath, Which, slowly from a stinted root, unfolds Pale lilac blossoms,—image of a maid Rear'd in a solitude like this,—is bless'd, Instead of sharing with a million flowers One radiant flush,—in offering its faint bloom To fondest eyes. Say not again, dear lady, That joy but seldom visits these old walls. LADY MACDONALD. Not while they shelter you, my lovely child; But new joy waits us; you have not forgotten Our careless Henry? HELEN. No!—forgotten Henry! But he has long forgotten us; no message Has told us of his welfare, since he found us Too sad for his companions. LADY MACDONALD. Pardon in him, As I do, young ambition's upward gaze, Which, fix'd upon the future, cannot turn To glance upon the distant and the past. HELEN. Is it indeed so, madam? LADY MACDONALD. You are grave now— You who are joyous in our weariest days Be glad; for Henry will this day return To charm us with his merriment. HELEN. To-day? Henry return to-day! Speak once again That blessed news. LADY MACDONALD. He comes to-day, upraised In Argyle's regiment to command, and graced With favour of Glenlyon. HELEN. Of my uncle? I think of him unseen, as a stern soldier Who, living to obey and to command, Allows no impulses but these which guide Along the rocky, strait, untinted channel, That discipline has hewn. If Henry wins Favour from him, he'll win the hearts of all. Comes he alone? LADY MACDONALD. His troop is quarter'd with us, To taste in peace our simple Highland fare, And feel our Highland welcome. But I long For Halbert's presence; though he does not love The clansmen of Argyle, he must rejoice In Henry's fortune. HELEN. He has not return'd Since, yestere'en, he left us to inquire The issue of Mac Ian's journey. LADY MACDONALD. You Alarm me;—not return'd? HELEN. Fear not for Halbert; You know he loves to wander at all hours, And, ever present to himself, will rule His course in safety. Is that he? The step Is hurried; yet it should be his. Enter Halbert greatly agitated;—throws himself into a seat. LADY MACDONALD. My son, What ails you? Speak! HALBERT. I will—soon—presently; Ha! Mother! Helen! safe;—thank Heaven! Has nothing To-night appall'd you? LADY MACDONALD. Nothing. HALBERT. That is strange. LADY MACDONALD. What has befall'n us? Is Mac Ian dead? HALBERT. No; he survives; he has only lost the thing Which makes life precious!—Ruin yawns for all— Poor fated clansmen! I have heard again Old Moina's voice. LADY MACDONALD. Her voice who spake when death— HALBERT (laying his hand on her arm). Mother! LADY MACDONALD. He shivers as with ague. Speak, my son! HALBERT. Yes—it is over now.—I'll tell you all, As far as words can tell it. As I left Mac Ian's door, and walk'd in mist, which clung Around me like a shroud, that voice shriek'd forth Close at mine ear, “The Hour is nigh!”—Each cliff, Pillar, and cavern, echo'd back the words, Till they appear'd to fill the glen with sound, As floods from thousand streams might deluge it. 'Twas no delusion; surely as you hear My voice, I heard them. LADY MACDONALD. You have mused, my son, In dismal solitudes on our old tales Till each wild pass is haunted, and the wind, Struggling within a mountain gully, moans Or shrieks with prophecy. HALBERT. No!—It transfix'd me As with an arrow,—when it sunk, still night Held its breath, waiting terrors! 'Neath the moon Our three huge mountain bulwarks stood in light, Strange, solemn, spectral;—not as if they tower'd Majestic into heaven, but hoar and bow'd Beneath the weight of centuries; and each Sent forth a sound as of a giant's sigh: Then, from their feet the mists arising, grew To shapes resembling human, till I saw, Dimly reveal'd among the ghastly train, Familiar forms of living clansmen, dress'd In vestments of the tomb;—they glided on, While strains of martial music from afar Mock'd their sad flight.— [A distant band heard playing “The Campbells are coming.” I hear that music now,— The same—the same—Do you not hear it, Helen? Mother? HELEN. I hear a lively strain which speaks, Approaching soldiers, who'll make winter bright And fill our vale with gladness. HALBERT. There is death In those blithe sounds;—I know them now;—the tune Which wakes the shallow heart of false Argyle, Hollow and cruel ever. HELEN. Sure there's one Who owns that clan you would not spurn! HALBERT. Sweet girl! Your beauty, early sever'd from its stem, And planted in an honest soil, retains No vestige of its origin. [The music is heard approaching. Yet nearer! Look not on me with those beseeching eyes; [To Helen. I will enjoy it;—'tis a gallant strain: See, Helen, how you mould me;—I can smile now. HELEN. And you shall smile; while you have been enthrall'd By dismal fancies, we have heard sweet news Of our long-sigh'd-for Henry. HALBERT. Of my brother? Shall we embrace him soon? HELEN. We hope to-day. HALBERT. Then I will cast all sadness from my thoughts, And own these portents idle;—my fair brother, Who in staid manhood made me feel a child, While I instructed him with tiny arm To brave the torrent to its whirling pool O'er rocky ledge descending! I am a boy Again in thinking of it. [Enter Henry Macdonald in the dress of an officer of the Earl of Argyle's Regiment; Halbert starts and stands apart; Lady Macdonald eagerly embraces Henry. LADY MACDONALD. O, most welcome! HALBERT (apart). A soldier of Argyle! a purchased slave To his poor country's foes! Would he had lain, In all the glory of his youth, a corpse, Or I had died first! HELEN (laying her hand imploringly on Halbert's). Halbert, speak to him. HALBERT. Yes;—I'll not dash that bonnet from his brow; Right, right—I'll speak to him. My brother! [Henry embraces Halbert, who receives him coldly. HENRY. Stiff And melancholy grown! These rugged walls Have shed their sullen gloom into your nature, And made my welcome cold. HALBERT. These walls are sacred— Fit home for honest poverty; 'twere well If you had never left them. HENRY (approaching Helen). They contain One form of radiant loveliness;—is this My some-time playmate Helen? You are silent; You do not bid me welcome. HELEN. Welcome, Henry? It is because my heart's too full of welcome To vent its joy in words. HALBERT (apart). So fond! so free! This stripling will engage the care of all Within my little world;—for shame! the thought Is selfish and most base; I must suppress it.— [Aloud. You'll spend some time, I hope, in these poor walls, And teach us to be gay. HENRY. Our regiment mean To teach your clan the finest of all lessons— The art of spending life. We hope to raise Strange echoes of delight among your mountains. Let your old men prepare their choicest tales Of ancient chiefs; your lads their sinews brace For noontide games and midnight dances; bid Your maidens' hearts be stout, for we shall lay Fair siege to some of them. Your mansion, brother, Will not be colder, if you'll deign to share A soldier's purse. [Henry offers a purse to Halbert, who is about to dash it on the ground, but restrains his passion; pauses and returns it. They speak apart from Lady Macdonald and Helen. HALBERT. Remove it from my sight, Lest it provoke my curse upon the gold, Which, having tempted Scotland's peers to sell Their country, pass'd through treacherous hands to yours. HENRY. Through treacherous hands! I will not hear that said: Expend your spleen on me; but speak a word Disgraceful to the officers I serve, And though my brother, you shall answer it. HALBERT. You make me smile now. I will answer it. I must have speedy speech with you, where none Shall break upon us. HENRY. At my earliest leisure. [To Lady Macdonald. Mother, my duty calls me hence awhile, To hear my captain's orders. Helen, soon I shall reclaim old friendship. [Apart to Halbert.] In an hour, Upon Loch Leven's margin, 'neath the shade Of the first rock, expect me. HALBERT. Do not fail. [Exit Henry. LADY MACDONALD. Come, Helen, let us see the tower prepared To feast our noble soldier and his friends. Is he not all a mother's hope could image? HELEN. He is indeed;—at first he scarcely knew me; Changed as he is, I had not mistaken him Among a host of heroes! [Exeunt Helen and Lady Macdonald. HALBERT (alone). Down, wild rage! These rebel passions ought to fright me more Than night's grim phantoms. I had deem'd my temper Proof 'gainst all griefs, all injuries, all scorns; But this—my brother self-sold to our foes!— I must be conqueror still. (Looks out.) O, blessed star Of morning, do you wait upon that cone Whose whiteness mocks our marble, to renew The calm cerulean distance can impart To thoughts of earth's brief struggles? Linger yet! It sinks; 'tis gone; its peace is in my soul. [Exit Halbert. SCENE II. A Room in a Highland House. Sentinels seen pacing before the Windows.—Glenlyon, Lindsay, and other Officers of Argyle's Regiment. GLENLYON. These are rough quarters for the winter, friends; But let us make them jocund—find the huts Which yield the warmest shelter from the snow, And let our stores of wine and brandy pay The courtesies we win. 'Tis easy service. LINDSAY. Is nothing more intended here than feasting? GLENLYON. Lindsay, I fain would hope not; we shall wait For final orders. Now, our duty's plain— To win the favour of our hosts;—if more Should be commanded, 'twill be ours to do it. Enter Henry Macdonald. GLENLYON. You know this glen, Macdonald: to your charge I leave disposal of the soldiers; place them Where frankest entertainment will be given. HENRY. The entertainment may be coarse, but given With heartiest welcome. I shall grant a boon To every clansmen in whose hut I place One of my gallant comrades. GLENLYON. See all lodged, And then report to me. This hut be mine. HENRY. May I retire? I must redeem a pledge Within this hour. GLENLYON. An old acquaintance found? You have my leave, sir. [Exit Henry. Some one knocks; attend; Who waits? Enter Drummond. DRUMMOND. Mac Ian's sons are at the door, And ask to see you. GLENLYON. Ha!—of course admit them. [Exit Drummond. The children of the stubborn chief who dared Accuse our loftiest nobles that they filch'd The money sent to buy the peace of Scotland! I'd thank him for a brawl. Your pleasure with me? Enter John and Alaster. JOHN. We bear Mac Ian's greeting to Glenlyon; He trusts you come in friendship, now his oath To William is recorded. GLENLYON. How! recorded? ALASTER. Yes; by the Sheriff of Argyle. We tell The fact, not boast it. GLENLYON. You speak boldly, sir; A spirited young Highlander, i'faith: Let me enlist you in our troop; we teach Some manners that you lack. ALASTER. And let me lack them, Ere I endure your teaching. JOHN. Alaster! Forbear. GLENLYON. O, let him speak. The oath is taken? JOHN. It is: though the appointed day had pass'd, Yet, as mere error and the storm produced The slight delay, it was forgiven. GLENLYON. Well! Your father acted prudently at last: Within you'll taste some wine, and tell me how His journey prosper'd. JOHN. Sir, you have not made Reply to my sole question;—do you come To visit us in friendship? GLENLYON. Friendship? Surely— Fort-William's garrison, too small to hold Our regiment, sends us beggars to request Your hospitable greetings. JOHN. They are yours, And all our glen can offer shall attend them. GLENLYON. Your hand. [To Alaster] And yours;—you'll be a soldier yet. [Exeunt. SCENE III. The Banks of Loch Leven. Enter Henry. HENRY. First at the place!—the morning's chill;—I wish The quarrel were with other than the man I wait for; but of all the useless things Which form the business of the world, regret Is the most idle. Yet, I wish 'twere past.— He's here. Enter Halbert. HENRY. I have but little time to spend, And the air freezes. Let's to work at once. Select your ground, sir. HALBERT. Do you mock me, Henry, With this vain show of courage? HENRY. I came hither Upon your summons, as I thought, to end A soldier's quarrel with a soldier's sword; But if you can restrain the bitter speech To which I must not listen, I prefer To take your hand in kindness. As you will. HALBERT. Did I not feel that I have words to pierce Through that cold bravery to the heart within it, I might relieve you of some frolic blood Which makes the front of your rebellion proud. HENRY. Rebellion! HALBERT. Have you not rebell'd at once Against your clan, your country, and the tomb Of a brave father who embraced in you The darling of his age? Behold his sword You now defy,—your plaything while he talk'd Of noble daring, till you paused in sport To hear and weep. Its sight should wound you now More than its edge could. What would be his grief Could he behold you in that hated dress, Link'd to the foes of Scotland! O, my brother, Why did you this? HENRY. If you intend to ask What urged me to take service with Argyle, I answer you at once.—My eagle spirit, Which wanted air to soar in; frank disdain Of dull existence, which had faintly gleam'd, Like yonder Serpent-river, through dark rocks Which bury it; ambition for a lot Which places life and death upon a cast, And makes the loser glorious. Not for me The sullen pride of mouldering battlements, Or rites of tottering chapel. HALBERT. Is it so? Is ancient sanctity, which sheds its grace Upon the infant's sportiveness, and cleaves To the old warrior when he falls, a thing To mock at? But I wrong you there: I know Your heart then spoke not. I could cherish pride In your gay valour, if a generous cause Had won its aid;—nay, deeming Scotland lost, If you had sought your fortune at the court Of England, I had borne it;—but to join With these domestic traitors—men who know The rights they sell; who understand the ties Which, through the wastes of centuries, cement Our clans, and give the sacred cord one life Of reverential love; for whom these hills On the clear mirror of their childhood cast Great shadows; who have caught their martial rage From deeds of Wallace and of Bruce, and learn'd To temper and enrage it with the sense Of suffering beauty, which from Mary's fate Gleams through dim years; and who conspire to crush These memories in men's souls, and call the void They make there, freedom—is a deed to weep for! HENRY. I may not hear the comrades whom I love Thus slander'd. HALBERT. You shall hear me while I speak Of that which nearly touches you, as one Of a small—branded—poor—illustrious race; Who boast no fertile pastures; no broad lake Studded with island woods, which make the soul Effeminate with richness, like the scenes In which the baffled Campbells hid their shame, And scorn'd their distant foes. Our boasts are few, Yet great:—a stream which thunders from its throne, As when its roar was mingled with the voice Of eldest song, from age to age retain'd In human hearts;—wild myrtles which preserve Their hoard of perfume for the dying hour When rudeness crushes them;—rocks which no flowers Of earth adorn, but, in themselves austere, Receive The Beautiful direct from Heaven, Which forces them to wear it,—shows their tops Refined with air; compels their darkest steeps Reluctant to reflect the noontide sun In sheeted splendour—wreathes around them clouds In glorious retinue, which, while they float Slowly, or rest beneath the sable heights, In their brief fleecy loveliness grow proud To wait upon The Lasting.—And the right To walk this glen with head erect, you sold For bounties which Argyle could offer! HENRY. No— Not for base lucre!—for a soldier's life, Whose virtue's careless valour, unperplex'd With aught beyond the watchword. If your cause Were vital, I would freely draw my sword To serve it; but where lives it? HALBERT. In the soul Which, ruffled by no hope to see it tower Again in this world, cherishes it still In its own deathless and unsullied home;— That soul which, swelling from the mould of one Obscure as I, can grasp the stubborn forms Of this great vale, and bend them to its use, Until their stateliest attributes invest With pillar'd majesty the freeborn thoughts Which shall survive them. Even these rocks confess Change and decay; show where the ancient storm Rent their grey sides, and, from their iron hearts, Unriveted huge masses for its sport, And left their splinters to attest a power Greater than they;—but mighty truths like those On which our slighted cause was based, shall hold Their seat in the clear spirit which disdains To sully or resign them, undisturb'd By change or death:—they are eternal, Henry! HENRY. If we were now the lords of this domain You love so well, I might have own'd a tie To bind me to your wishes; you resign'd them; What can these mountains yield to one who owns Mac Ian as their lord? HALBERT. The power to bear That bitter taunt—which yet I feel!—O Henry! Was that well said? HENRY. You should not have provoked it By slanders on my officers and friends. HALBERT. Your friends! Poor youth! companionship in mirth, Ungraced by thought, makes shallow friends; and yours Are worse than shallow—they are false. HENRY. Nay, this I will not bear; draw, sir! [Henry draws his sword, and rushes on Halbert, who dashes it from his hand. HALBERT. Take up your sword; See how a bad cause makes a brave arm weak! Blush not; 'twas but in pastime. HENRY. Kill me now, And walk the hills in pride! HALBERT. Too plain I see Our paths diverge;—but let us not forget That we have trod life's early way together, Hand clasp'd in hand. How proud was I to watch Your youngest darings, when I saw you dive To the deep bottom of the lake beneath us, Nor draw one breath till in delight you rose To laugh above it; when I traced the crags By which with lightest footstep you approach'd The eaglets' bed; and when you slipp'd, yet knew No paleness, bore you in my trembling arms To yon black ridge, from which in the cold thaw The snow wreath melts, as infancy's pure thoughts Have vanish'd from your soul. HENRY. No—Halbert—no! Graceless I shook them from it, but they crowd Here at your voice. HALBERT. And you will not forget us? Go, then, where fortune calls you, loved and praised— Let not the ribald licence of a camp Insult the griefs of Scotland. 'Mid the brave Be bravest; and when honours wait your grasp, Allow a moment's absence to your heart While it recals one lonely tower, whose doors Would open to you were you beggar'd, shamed, Forsaken;—and beside whose once-loved hearth Your praises shall awaken joy more fervent Than nobler friends can guess at. Ah! you weep— My own true brother still! HENRY. I am! I am! [They embrace. Enter Helen. HELEN. Forgive me that I follow'd you. I saw Both ruffled at your parting; but my fears Never suggested an event so sad, As that two brothers, from whose swords alone We hope protection, should direct their points Against each other's lives. HENRY. You must not leave This spot with the belief that Halbert shares The blame of this encounter; mine the fault, Be mine the shame. HALBERT. I will not let you pour On Helen's ear one word of self-reproach; You'll not believe him shamed? HELEN. Indeed I will not; I feel that shame and Henry are disjoin'd As yonder summits. [To Henry. I must teach your steps The pleasant pathways which we used to tread In old sweet times. [Takes his hand. HALBERT (apart). It cannot be she means Other than sisterly regard in this; 'Tis but the frankness of a courteous heart. No more—no more. HELEN (to Halbert). Will you not walk with us? I have a hand for you too. HALBERT. Nothing else? HELEN. Yes; and a heart—a grateful one. So solemn! Nay, you must smile; this is a day of joy, And shall be cloudless. Hark! the music calls us. [Martial music at a distance. HALBERT. Those strains again! Forgive me. Let us home. [Exeunt. END OF ACT II.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. A Fortnight is supposed to elapse between the Second and Third Acts. SCENE I. The Quarters of Glenlyon. Enter Glenlyon and Lindsay. GLENLYON. Are you not weary of your quarters, Lindsay? LINDSAY. Not I;—I care but little where I lodge. GLENLYON. These fifteen days among the snows will nerve Our soldiers to encounter a campaign In coldest winter. Do they bear it bravely? LINDSAY. Bear it? The rogues exult in it! Rude plenty And loosen'd discipline make rich amends For rations duly meted, and warm shelter, The garrison affords. Our savage hosts Have open'd their rock-cellar'd stores of ale, And of the luscious juice from honey press'd, Which the wild bee from scanty heather wins To make us jocund; laughter and the dance Have shaken many a hovel. May I ask If we are destined long to dally thus? GLENLYON. I know not, Lindsay; what our mission was You heard:—I scarcely dare remember it; I, who have ever held my conduct true To orders, as my pistol to my touch, And feel these fastnesses are unsubdued While a fierce clan like this retains its show Of unity and ancient right, recoil From that which we may execute. But thus We must not loiter; every social cup— Each pressure of the hand, will make our work Harder and darker. I will send at once To Duncanson; perchance Mac Ian's oath Accepted by the Sheriff, though so late, May save him. There's a mournful courtesy In this old chief, crest-fall'n but self-sustain'd, Which softens me to wish it. LINDSAY. He is crafty, But yet most daring: never will the Highlands Know peace while he infests them. GLENLYON (writing). Wound not him With the sharp tongue on whom your sword may deal; I will despatch Macdonald: can you tell Where I may find him? LINDSAY. No: but I am sure He's pleasantly engaged; for I have met him Often, since we have lodged here, with a lady Gracing his arm, whom a slight glance approves Of rarest beauty. But he comes to make His own report. Enter Henry Macdonald. GLENLYON. 'Tis well, sir, you have come; You have but seldom sought my orders here; And but that I am told you have fair plea For such remissness, I might censure it. At present, I require to know the name And station of the damsel who has drawn So true an officer from duty. HENRY. Sir, My home was in this glen, and I live here Beneath my brother's roof. GLENLYON. Nay, no evasion; Tell me at once to whom I owe your absence, Or hope no favour. HENRY. If I had not fear'd The old estrangement which the father caused Might touch the daughter, I had long ere this Sought for her your protection. She is the child Of your slain brother, from your love so long Unhappily divided. GLENLYON. I knew not That he had left a daughter. HENRY. When he died, You were abroad; and she, an infant, found A sire in mine. GLENLYON. Poor girl, to find her here At such a moment!—but she shall be cared for. HENRY. Cared for! GLENLYON. Yes—cared for;—said I something strange? Is't strange that I should care for her? To business:— You are swift of foot, and know the jagged paths Among these hills. [Gives a letter. Bear this to Duncanson, And bring his answer with your best despatch: When you return, we'll talk of my fair niece, The partner of your rambles. I'll find means To honour and reward you. Lindsay, come. [Exeunt. SCENE II. A Room in Halbert's Tower. Enter Lady Macdonald and Helen. LADY MACDONALD. Helen, how grave you are! While winter stretch'd Its dull eventless length, your ready mirth Streak'd the dark hours with gaiety, which else Had been unvaried gloom. Now that our snows Glitter with dancing feathers and bright plaids, Our echoes learn to laugh, and our rough paths Are cheer'd by tales of love, you droop and sigh! Does any secret grief afflict my child? HELEN. Grief, madam! 'Tis the pensiveness of joy, Too deep for language, too serene for mirth, Makes me seem sad. To meet in manhood's bloom The gentle playmate of my childhood; propp'd On the same arm to tread the same wild paths; And in sweet fellowship of memories, feel Hour after hour of long-forgotten pleasure Start forth in sunny vividness to break The mist of heavy years,—is joy so hearted, That it can find no colour in the range Of gladness to express it;—so accepts A solemn hue from grief. LADY MACDONALD. Have you then felt Those years so heavy, you have help'd to make So light to me? Your lodging has been bleak, Your entertainment scanty; yet your youth Has been so furnish'd with rich thoughts, so raised To lofty contemplations, that my pride In the bright valour of my younger son Cannot prevent my wonder that the hours In which my Halbert with delighted care Has minister'd to your soul's noblest thirsts, Should be thus soon forgotten. HELEN. Not forgotten, Nor have the years been heavy: when I said so, I was most thankless. Pardon me, sweet lady, But when with Henry, I recal old times, I look across the intervening years As a low vale in which fair pastures lie Unseen, to gaze upon a sunlit bank On which my childhood sported, and which grows Near as I watch it. If his nature seems Unsoften'd by reflexion,—like a rock Which draws no nurture from the rains, nor drinks The sunbeam in that lights it, yet sustains A plume of heather,—it is crown'd with grace Which wins the heart it shelters. LADY MACDONALD. My dear Halbert, How will you bear this! HELEN. Can it be, you fear My joy in Henry's presence should afflict A soul so great as Halbert's? LADY MACDONALD. I do fear it;— I know it; shudder at it: can you doubt That Halbert loves you? HELEN. Do not think it, madam, For mercy's sake, if you intend by love Something beyond a brother's fondest care For a lone sister! You are silent; turn Your face away; your bosom throbs as grief Or terror shook it. Am I grown a curse To you—to him? O whither shall I fly? Where seek for counsel? Dearest lady, save me! [Helen throws herself on Lady Macdonald's neck. LADY MACDONALD. Rest there, beloved fair one; I will try To temper this to Halbert;—yet I fear— He's bending towards us. HELEN. Hide me from his sight, I cannot bear it now. LADY MACDONALD (leading Helen to the side). That way; I'll break This sorrow to him, if I can;—be calm. [Exit Helen. Enter Halbert from the opposite side. HALBERT. Was not that Helen? Wherefore should she fly Upon my coming? But her absence serves My purpose now. I came to talk of her. LADY MACDONALD. Of her? Sit down; you look fatigued and ill: I'll fetch a draught of wine. HALBERT. Fatigued and ill! My looks belie me, then; I scarce have felt So fresh in spirit since I was a boy, And the sweet theme I come to speak of needs No wine to make it joyous. It is marriage. LADY MACDONALD. My son! HALBERT. Why, you look pale; I thought my wish Was also yours. I know a common mother, Who, having lost her husband in her prime, Seeks from a grateful son some slight return For love that watch'd his infancy, may feel Her fortune cruel, when a new regard, With all the greediness of passion, fills The bosom where till then affection reign'd, Which answer'd, though it could not rival, hers: But we have lived so long as equal friends With love absorbing duty, that I thought, And I still think, increase of joy to me Must bring delight to you. I could have lived Content, as we have lived, and still prolong The lingering ecstacy of fearless hope, But that the licence of the time, which brings A band of loose companions to our glen, Requires that I should claim a husband's right To shield its lovely orphan. LADY MACDONALD. You mean—Helen? HALBERT. Whom else could I intend? If you have been Perplex'd by fear that I might mean to seek Another's hand, no wonder you grew pale. But still you tremble;—what is this? LADY MACDONALD. My son, Are you assured she loves you? HALBERT. As assured As of my love for her. In both, one wish, As she has glided into womanhood, Has grown with equal progress. LADY MACDONALD. Have you sought Of her, if she esteems it thus? HALBERT. By words? No; for I never doubted it: as soon Should I have ask'd you if a mother's love Watch'd o'er my nature's frailties. If sweet hopes Dawning at once on each; if gentle strifes To be the yielder of each little joy Which chance provided; if her looks upraised In tearful thankfulness for each small boon Which, nothing to the giver, seem'd excess To her; if poverty endured for years Together in this valley,—do not breathe Of mutual love, I have no stronger proofs To warrant my assurance. Mother, speak! Do you know anything which shows all this A baseless dream? LADY MACDONALD. My Halbert, you have quell'd Fierce passion by strong virtue; use your strength— Nay, do not start thus; I do not affirm With certainty you are deceived, but tremble Lest the expressions of a thankful heart And gracious disposition should assume A colour they possess not, to an eye Bent fondly over them. HALBERT. It cannot be; A thousand, and a thousand times, I've read Her inmost soul; and you that rack me thus With doubt have read it with me. Before Heaven, I summon you to witness! In the gloom Of winter's dismal evening, while I strove To melt the icy burthen of the hours By knightly stories, and rehearsed the fate Of some high maiden's passion, self-sustain'd Through years of solitary hope, or crown'd In death with triumph, have you not observed, As fading embers threw a sudden gleam Upon her beauty, that its gaze was fix'd On the rapt speaker, with a force that told How she could lavish such a love on him? LADY MACDONALD. I have; and then I fancied that she loved you. HALBERT. Fancied! Good mother, is that emptiest sound The comfort that you offer? Is my heart Fit sport for fancy? Fancied!—'twas as clear As it were written in the book of God By a celestial penman. Answer me, Once more! when hurricanes have rock'd these walls, And dash'd upon our wondering ears the roar Of the far sea, exulting that its wastes Were populous with agonies; with loves Strongest in death; with memories of long years Grey phantom of an instant;—as my arms Enfolding each, grew tighter with the sense Of feebleness to save;—have you not known Her looks, beyond the power of language, speak In resolute content, how sweet it were To die so link'd together? LADY MACDONALD. I have mark'd it. HALBERT. Then wherefore do you torture me with doubt? What can you know, what guess, that you can weigh Against these proofs? LADY MACDONALD. Be firm; she loves another. HALBERT. 'Tis false!—and yet, great Heaven! your quivering lips Attest it. And you knew this? You partook Her counsels—His?—Yes, His!—you know the name Which I must curse—of him I must pursue Through deserts and through cities till I search His bosom with my sword. Tell me the name— Now—now—delay not. LADY MACDONALD (laying her hand on his arm). Halbert, pause, and look Into your mother's face, and then reply To her:—does she deserve this of her son? HALBERT. I am a wretch indeed to use command Where I should humbly sue.—Sit, sit, dear mother, Assume your old authority. [Wildly places her in a chair and falls on his knees beside it. I kneel There—meekly as you taught me—when you raised For the first time my little hands to God; A child, obedient and infirm as then, I do implore you, tell your wretched son What he must suffer. LADY MACDONALD. Are you arm'd to bear it? HALBERT. For all things. LADY MACDONALD. Henry— HALBERT. [Starting up. My own brother! Now I see it clear;—remember how she gazed With fondness on him, when he came array'd In a slave's tinsel; how she seized his hand When I had dash'd the insulting weapon from it, Aim'd at my life. Would I had slain him there! LADY MACDONALD. What fearful vision crosses you? Slay Henry— Him whom you moulded! From unthinking youth Strike him to bloody senselessness, and bid Your twice-stabb'd mother gaze upon her sons— The murder'd and the guilty! HALBERT. Guilty?—yes! I am—I thought it—felt as if my arm Could act it;—utter'd it. Look not upon me! Earth hide me!—cover me! [Sinks into a seat and covers his face with his hands. LADY MACDONALD. I fear'd this outbreak Of fire subdued, not quench'd. My noble son, As you have wrestled with the fiends, and quell'd them, Be victor now! HALBERT (rising). Are you assured she loves him? It may be but a girlish dream,—her eye Enchanted for a moment by the grace Of youth—her fancy dazzled by the show Of military prowess,—while her soul In its serene and inmost temple waits Untouch'd and true. 'Tis so. LADY MACDONALD. Would that it were! HALBERT. I will awake her spirit from its trance; I'll meet her face to face, and soul to soul, And so be satisfied. LADY MACDONALD. You shall do so, If you will rule your passion. HALBERT. I am calm, Docile as infancy; I'll seek her now. LADY MACDONALD. No;—I will bring her on the instant. Think That she has not a refuge in the world Except in our protecting care, and feel How gently she should be entreated! Rage From you would kill her. HALBERT. Rage—to her? All weak In passion as I am, you need not fear it. LADY MACDONALD. I'll trust you. [Exit Lady Macdonald. HALBERT (alone). She will come with her sweet voice To charm away this mist. Alas! I'm rude And moody; he is gay, and quick of spirit, And light of heart. Why did I let them roam So often? Yet it cannot be; her heart Could not be caught by gauds;—so pure; so arm'd— So true! Enter Henry Macdonald. HENRY. What, musing! Let me not disturb Deep meditations. Is my mother near, Or Helen? HALBERT. Helen! HENRY. I have scarce a word To spend with either; though I would not pass Your tower unvisited, I'm bound to speed, For I am bearer of an urgent letter To Duncanson. HALBERT. To Duncanson? The foe Most bitter to our clan;—and you dare bring it Here;—to your father's hall—where you were train'd To clansman's duty;—which you left in scorn, And now revisit in a lackey's guise To boast a cursed mission; yield it to me, Traitor and slave! or I will tear it from you. HENRY. Stand off!—what frenzy rules you? Let me pass. HALBERT. There's treachery in it—and in you. Enter Lady Macdonald and Helen. LADY MACDONALD. Your word! [Halbert, at sight of Helen, pauses and shrinks back. HALBERT (to Henry). Forgive me; I am ill at ease, and scarce Know what I utter. HENRY. I shall think of this But as brain-sickness which your studies bring; Heaven keep me from them! I must not delay A moment more:—farewell;—I shall return This way to-morrow, and shall hope to find Your grave philosopher in reason's mood. [Exit Henry. LADY MACDONALD. I leave you; recollect your word. HALBERT. I will. [Exit Lady Macdonald. HALBERT. Be not alarm'd, sweet Helen; if your looks, Turn'd gently on me, had not power to still The tempest my frail nature has endured, The issue of this moment would command All passion to deep silence, while I ask— If my scathed life enrich'd by yours may spread Its branches in the sunshine, or shrink up In withering solitude, a sapless thing, Till welcome death shall break it? HELEN. Do not think Your noble nature can require a reed So weak as mine to prop it: virtue's power, Which shields it as a breastplate, will not yield To transient sorrow which a thankless girl Can hurl against it. HALBERT. Little do you guess The heart you praise: 'tis true, among the rocks I sought for constancy, and day by day It grew; but then within its hardening frame One exquisite affection took its root, And strengthen'd in its marble;—if you tear That living plant, with thousand fibres, thence, You break up all;—my struggles are in vain, And I am ruin! HELEN. What a lot of mine! I, who would rather perish than requite Long years of kindness with one throb of pain, Must make that soul a wreck! HALBERT. No, Helen, no— It is a dream; your heart is mine; mine only,— I'll read it here:—you have not pledged its faith To—any other? HELEN. No;—not yet. HALBERT. Thank God!— Then you are mine; we have been betrothed for years. HELEN. Would it had been so! HALBERT. You desire it? HELEN. Yes; I then had kept such watch upon my soul, As had not let the shadow of a thought Fall on your image there; but not a word Of courtship pass'd between us. HALBERT. Not a word. Words are for lighter loves, that spread their films Of glossy threads, which while the air's serene Hang gracefully, and sparkle in the sun Of fortune, or reflect the fainter beams Which moonlight fancy sheds; but ours—yes, OURS!— Was woven with the toughest yarn of life, For it was blended with the noblest things We lived for; with the majesties of old, The sable train of mighty griefs o'erarch'd By Time's deep shadows; with the fate of kings,— A glorious dynasty—for ever crush'd With the great sentiments which made them strong In the affections of mankind;—with grief For rock-enthronèd Scotland; with poor fortune Shared cheerfully; with high resolves; with thoughts Of death; and with the hopes that cannot die. HELEN. Hold! If you rend oblivion's slender veil Thus fearfully, and spectres of the past Glide o'er my startled spirit, it will fail In reason. HALBERT. No;—it shall cast off this cloud, And retain no impression save of things Which last for ever;—for to such our love Has been allied. How often have we stood, Clasp'd on yon terrace by columnar rocks, Upon whose jagged orifice the sky With its few stars seem'd pillar'd, and have felt Our earthly fortunes, bounded like the gorge That held us, had an avenue beyond, Like that we gazed on; and when summer eve Has tempted us to wander on the bank Of glory-tinged Loch-Leven, till the sea Open'd beyond the mountains, and the thoughts Of limitless expanse were render'd sweet By crowding memories of delicious hours Sooth'd by its murmur, we have own'd and bless'd The Presence of Eternity and Home! HELEN. What shall I do? HALBERT. Hear me while I invoke The spirit of one moment to attest, In the great eye of love-approving Heaven, We are each other's. When a fragile bark Convey'd our little household to partake The blessing that yet lingers o'er the shrine Of desolate Iona, the faint breath Of evening wafted us through cluster'd piles Of gently-moulded columns, which the sea— Softening from tenderest green to foam more white Than snow-wreaths on a marble ridge—illumed As 'twould dissolve and win them;—till a cave, The glorious work of angel architects Sent on commission to the sacred isle, From which, as from a fountain, God's own light Stream'd o'er dark Europe—in its fretted span Embraced us.—Pedestals of glistening black Rose, as if waiting for the airy tread Of some enraptured seraph who might pause To see blue Ocean through the sculptured ribs Of the tall arch-way's curve, delight to lend His vastness to the lovely. We were charm'd, Not awe-struck;—for The Beautiful was there Triumphant in its palace. As we gazed Rapt and enamour'd, our small vessel struck The cavern's side, and by a shock which seem'd The last that we should suffer, you were thrown Upon my neck—You clasp'd me then;—and shared One thought of love and heaven! HELEN. Am I indeed Faithless, yet knew it not? my soul's perplex'd;— Distracted. Whither shall it turn?—To you!— Be you its arbiter. Of you I ask, In your own clear simplicity of heart, Did you believe me yours? HALBERT. Yes; and you are. With this sweet token I assure you mine, [Places a ring on her finger. In sight of angels. Bless you! HELEN. It is done I dare not, cannot, tear this ring away. HALBERT. It but denotes what Heaven has register'd; We must not pause: when will you that this pledge Shall be redeem'd? To-morrow? HELEN. Give me time To speak with—to call in my scatter'd thoughts. HALBERT. The next day, then? HELEN. Direct it as you please; Would I were worthy!—pray you leave me now. HALBERT. I go to share my blessedness with her Whose love you share with me;—our mother, Helen. [Exit Halbert. HELEN. Where am I?—can I wake from this strange dream? [Observes the ring. No—'tis all real—the good and brave alone Have power upon the spirits of the guiltless To raise or mar them. O that I had met All evil things—oppression—slander—hate— How would I have defied them! Enter Lady Macdonald. LADY MACDONALD. Is it true You have consented to wed Halbert? HELEN. Yes. LADY MACDONALD. My child, come to my heart. How's this? You are pale And cold as marble. HELEN. You may well regard My purpose with distrust;—but when I take The noble Halbert's hand, I bid adieu To every recollection which might touch My duty to him. I shall never muse On childhood's pleasures, innocent no more For me;—shall never tread the shelter'd paths Which I have lately linger'd in; nor think Upon a soldier's glories; nor repeat One name—O never!—I am very weak, I did not know how weak. The Virgin aid me! LADY MACDONALD. She will, my lovely one. HELEN. I'll seek the chapel, If these poor limbs will bear me.—On your bosom I must seek strength first, mother. LADY MACDONALD. Weep there, child, And may Heaven's arms encircle you as mine! [Exeunt. END OF ACT III.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT IV. SCENE I. The Tower of Halbert. Time—Noon of the Sixteenth Day. Enter Henry Macdonald. HENRY. Will no one answer me?—I call in vain;— And must pass on without that glimpse of Helen I came to win. [Kenneth crosses the stage. Stay fellow; where's my mother? KENNETH. She is preparing for our master's wedding, Of which our notice has been short; 'twas yesterday Appointed for to-morrow. HENRY. Halbert's wedding!— That's pleasant news, though strange;—to think my brother, My solemn brother, all this time in love! He has not trusted me; so I must ask Of you, the fair one's name. KENNETH. Name!—surely, sir, It could be none but Helen Campbell. HENRY. Cease Your jesting with that name, or with my sword I'll try to teach you manners. KENNETH. Jesting, sir!— We have little jesting here;—although these walls Will ring for once, when our dear master gives them So kind a mistress. HENRY. Dare you mock me? No!— I will not vent my rage on you;—if this Is not a jest, tell your kind mistress,—here Henry Macdonald waits her!—bid her come And answer to him as she loves her life. KENNETH. I'll seek her, sir. HENRY. Begone. [Exit Kenneth. Can this be true? Yes; that poor knave would never dare invent A tale so monstrous;—but it passes all My lightest comrades tell of woman's falsehood. How will they scoff at me—duped and despised By this meek mountain damsel—cast aside For a dull dreamer of the rocks, who dared To school me with his wisdom! Wise, indeed, The lady has become, to leave my hopes Of wealth and glory for these crazy walls, And solemn disputations. 'Tis a jest, I'faith a merry one!—her uncle, too, My captain and my friend!—Most generous brother, I'll mar your triumph yet. Enter Helen. O you are here! HELEN. Yes; on a summons couch'd in terms more harsh Than needful: I had come on lightest word That spoke your wish to see me. HENRY. Do you talk To me of harshness! Look me in the face— Look steadily upon me, and reply To one brief question. [Henry seizes Helen's arm; she looks at him and turns away in tears. HENRY. No!—I need not ask it. Yet hold one moment; is the bridegroom here? I long to wish him joy. HELEN. Accuse him not: He's innocent of all. HENRY. O, doubtless! Still 'Twas churlish not to bid me to his bridal; What is the happy hour? HELEN. Sunrise. HENRY. Until That hour, farewell. HELEN. O leave me not in scorn! But as you are a brave man, to the weak Be merciful. Although no plighted faith Is broken with you, I will not allow A base self-flattery to conceal the truth That I have wrong'd you—stolen delightful hours, And cherish'd gentle vanities, with heart Too joyous to revert to holy ties Long woven, though unrecognised, which link'd My destiny to Halbert's. He has shown That, though I knew it not, my life is his, And I have own'd his title to the hand This ring enriches. HENRY. And for dreams like this You have repell'd a soldier's love, which you, And only you, could have secured—released him From the sole anchor of a giddy youth, (So you described it,) and yourself from share Of his young fortunes, and the ample dowry With which your uncle would have graced them! HELEN. Stain not The few sad moments we may spend with thought So little worthy. Had my lot been cast With yours, I should have cared for no success Save as it made you happier; sought no pleasures But the perennial gaiety your mirth Had shed around me;—deem'd no travel long If shared with—Hold!—Accept my last farewell;— May that undaunted courage which breathes in you Inspire you to attain the airiest heights Of glory, and upon them carve a name Resplendent to all soldiers;—yet your frankness Dispel all envy from it; may your feasts, Crown'd with delights, be shared by noblest friends; And from your towering fortunes, may the cloud Which a slight woman's wayward folly wreathed Around them, in soft sunshine melt at once, And, with her, be forgotten! So Heaven speed you! [Exit Helen. HENRY. Yes; it will speed me; for she loves me still! But I forget my duty;—this despatch Is waited for by him who shall avenge me! [Exit Henry Macdonald. SCENE II. The Quarters of Glenlyon. Glenlyon—Lindsay. GLENLYON. Surely 'tis time Macdonald had return'd, The readiest, boldest, and most constant officer I ever yet promoted;—some mischance Or treachery must delay him. Treachery—faugh! 'Tis an ill word, but may import no more Than a safe means of justice, which rash force Might frustrate. Would our messenger were here! LINDSAY. Indeed time presses; we shall bear the charge Of weakness for the doubt which has delay'd The course prescribed. GLENLYON. He was not wont to loiter. If the command be clear, my course is plain; And yet—he comes—could I suspect he knew The tidings that he bears, his face would tell them. Enter Henry Macdonald. GLENLYON. How's this? Your looks are wild; have you met aught Should shake a brave man's constancy? HENRY. I crave Your pardon; 'tis a private grief unnerves me; The lovely lady who has shared my walks, And, as I proudly thought, return'd the love She had inspired in me, at sunrise weds My elder brother. What of that? My duty Has been perform'd;—and Duncanson's reply Is here. [Henry delivers a letter to Glenlyon. GLENLYON. Thanks;—wait within;—refresh yourself;— I'll deal with your fair rebel. [Exit Henry Macdonald. My hand trembles As it has never trembled;—I shall mar The seal;—open and read the letter.— [Lindsay opens and reads the letter. Well? LINDSAY. It is as I expected and you fear'd; The order is to guard the avenues To-night; and ere the morning, put in force The royal ordinance on the lives of all Below the age of seventy. GLENLYON. Would that death Had met me first! LINDSAY. Yet you will not withhold Obedience? GLENLYON. Never;—I am shaken now, But you shall find me constant to obey The simple law of duty:—none shall live. LINDSAY. Think of these clansmen as of rebels snared In treason, whom a law, disdaining forms, Has sentenced: it is hard to make brave soldiers The executioners of civil judgment; Yet we must do our office. GLENLYON. Be it yours To show the men their duty. LINDSAY. I will do All you may order; but I cannot range The soldiers so as to prevent escape Through the wild passes of these mountains; none, Unless familiar with the glen, can do this. GLENLYON. Call in Macdonald. [Exit Lindsay. He shall plant the men: His present passion moulds him to our will. Re-enter Lindsay and Henry Macdonald. GLENLYON (to Henry). There is a service I would claim of you, Which, well achieved, shall humble to your feet The rival who presumes to cross your wish For my alliance, and reward your love With happiest fortune. HENRY. Let the service be So full of peril that the chance of life Bears but a thousandth portion of the hope That death is greedy with, and I embrace it. GLENLYON. It lacks the peril you desire. This clan, Though crouching now to William's power, retains Its lion fierceness. We must tame its chiefs By forcing them, in abject terms, to sue For pardon—yield their hidden stores of arms— And feel themselves subdued. At dawn to-morrow We'll awe them to submission, by array Of soldiers, planted in each track, whose arms Shall make the glen their prison. What I seek Is, that at midnight, you, who know the paths, Would so dispose the soldiers that no clansman Escape the vale—save by the eastern road, Which Duncanson will line;—that done, repose— And dream that at the sunrise you shall see Your daring rival suppliant, and my niece Your wealthy bride. Will you do this? HENRY. I will. Enter Drummond. DRUMMOND. I come to ask if I shall bid the band Attend you at the feast. GLENLYON. What feast? LINDSAY. The banquet Mac Ian gives to-day:—the hour is near. GLENLYON. A banquet! that is terrible. LINDSAY (apart to Glenlyon). Be wary; Eyes are upon us. (Aloud.) You will send the band; All we can do, should grace our visit. GLENLYON (to Drummond). Yes: You may retire. [Exit Drummond. GLENLYON (to Henry). At dawn I will attend Your bridal; 'twill be yours. At this night's feast Beware that by no word or look you hint The midnight duty or the morning's hope: Be calm—as I am. [Exeunt Glenlyon and Lindsay. HENRY (alone) How shall I subdue The mantling sense of victory which laughs And dances in my spirit? He who dash'd My good sword from my grasp shall feel he stands Before his master; chidden as I was, And, for a moment, silenced, I shall rain Pardon and life on him who would have stolen The mistress of my soul. She's mine! She's mine! [Exit. SCENE III. Terrace before Halbert's Tower. Enter Lady Macdonald and Halbert. HALBERT. Is she so pensive still! LADY MACDONALD. Alas! in vain I watch to see some gleam of pleasure light Her mournful eyes. Save that her fingers ply The needle constantly, as if they wrought From habit of sweet motion, you might doubt If in her statue-like and silent beauty The life of this world stirr'd. HALBERT. If Henry broke Upon her suddenly, his harsh demeanour Might drive the colour from her cheeks, and scare Her thoughts from their repose. LADY MACDONALD. I cannot hope it; She has been more serene since then. Before, She would pursue her work with restless hand; Leave it and pace the room; sit down and sigh, As if heart were breaking; wring her hands; And then—as finding strength to chase some image That madden'd her away,—toss back her head, And smiling, urge her needle with more speed Than at the first. But since she spoke with Henry She has been calm, though sad, as one beyond The reach of fear or hope; who saw her course And was resign'd to follow it. HALBERT. Resign'd! Is that my sum of happiness? To hold, As in a tyrant's grasp, a lovely form Subdued by its own gentleness, yet know That the celestial mind defies the power Of finest bonds,—and from the winning smile In which fond custom wreathes the face, escapes To scenes long past, or for a distant voice Waits listening! I have held the gaoler's lot Far heavier than his captive's;—yet how light His chains to those I must inflict and bear! LADY MACDONALD. You wrong my lovely daughter;—when she weds, Each wish, each hope, each fancy which might dim The brightness of her constancy, will fly For ever. Her affections have been toss'd, But not perverted; as the water keeps Its crystal beauty in its bed of rock, Though vex'd by winds which from a cloudless sky Sweep o'er high mountain tarns, her soul perplex'd By contrary emotions, caught no taint, Sunk or uplifted, but will settle, bright As not a breath had wreath'd it. She will prove With all her soul a true wife to you, Halbert, Though not a blithe one. HALBERT. Do you not believe She will be happy soon? LADY MACDONALD. She will be tranquil; But if you ask me if she will enjoy The happiness for which her nature's framed, I cannot veil my fears. HALBERT. What should I do? I have known fearful heart-struggles; but this Makes all seem nothing. LADY MACDONALD. There is in your soul A noble purpose. HALBERT. Must I give up all, And yet live on? No human hope remains For me if this be blasted. With the fall Of the great objects which my youth revered, I lost all power to mingle in the strifes Of this new-modell'd world. I cannot taste The sweet resources Heaven, in grace, provides For love-lorn manhood; thirst of fame in me Is quench'd; society's miscall'd delights Would fret me into madness; and bright war, The glorious refuge of despair, would seem A slaughterous and a mercenary trade To one who has no country. If I act The thought which fills your bosom, I must live Loveless and hopeless. Can you ask it, mother? LADY MACDONALD. I cannot ask it. But I saw in you High resolution gathering, while I spoke Of Helen's present state, and what I fear 'Twill be when— HALBERT (stopping her). Speak no more. It shall not be; I will make ready for the sacrifice. LADY MACDONALD. My noble son! Let me embrace you, proud As never Roman mother in the arms Of her crown'd hero. Shall I speak to Helen? HALBERT. No—not for worlds—I cannot utter yet The irrevocable word. It may be still That you misjudge her;—or that she mistakes Her heart's true feeling. I will wait the morn. Enter Alaster Macdonald. ALASTER. My father sends me with a gracious message Which I rejoice to bear, though it confess A fault in him; he offers you his hand, With frank confession he has done you wrong, And claims your presence at the feast he gives To-day to Argyle's officers. HALBERT. Dear cousin, I am most happy in Mac Ian's love, And will with earnest duty answer it; But I entreat him to excuse me now, For I am busy with sick thoughts; unfit For high festivity. ALASTER. I know you hate, As I do, this submission; but 'tis done; No courtesies can make it deeper. Hark! [Distant music heard. The guests assemble now. HALBERT. That music breathes As when I heard it first;—in lively strain It vibrates on the ear, but on my soul Falls like a dirge. Some awful doom awaits Our race, and thus through sounds of this world speaks To the mind's ear. I will avert or share it. Yes;—I attend you. Mother, you will watch Your precious charge as if on every glance A life depended? I am sure you will. [Exit Lady Macdonald. Now, Alaster, I am ready for your feast. [Exeunt Halbert and Alaster. SCENE IV. A Hall in Mac Ian's House. A Banquet. Mac Ian, Angus, Donald, John Macdonald, Glenlyon, Lindsay, Henry Macdonald, Officers of Argyle's Regiment, and Clansmen, seated. MAC IAN (rising). Once more I thank you for the grace you pay To a fallen chief, whose name and title live As shadows of the past; but who can taste A comfort in his downfall, while brave men Show, by their courteous action, they preserve Respect for what he has been. Let us drink A health to those you serve;—the Majesties Of England; whom to death I had withstood, Had hope for James's cause remain'd; but whom, That hope extinguish'd, I will frankly serve. Rise, clansmen! Drink to William and his Queen, To whom we owe our duty. GLENLYON. We esteem The pledge at its just value. MAC IAN. I perceive Your thoughts still wrong me. Stoutly have I fought Upon King James's side; but with Dundee His cause expired. I felt it when he fell, Lifting his arm to wave these clansmen on, To make his triumph sure. The menial slave, The household traitor, who, with felon hand, Stole then his noble life, destroy'd, in him, A line of monarchs. While the tangled woods Of Killikrankie rang with shrill delight Of our victorious Highlanders, I knew That we were conquer'd; and I sheathed my sword For ever. ANGUS (apart to Donald). Do you mark him! DONALD. Yes; his life Casts out its dying flash. He's doom'd. GLENLYON. You wrong Your gallant comrades; surely loss of one Might be supplied. MAC IAN. Not of a man like him. 'Tis not in multitudes of common minds That by contagious impulses are sway'd, Like rushes in the wind, a mighty cause Can live; but in the master mind of one Who sways them. Sooner would these glorious hills, If crush'd to powder, with their atoms guard Our glens, than million clansmen fill the place Of such a chief. Would I had died with him! No more of this; fill me some wine. [Drinks. Enter Alaster and Halbert. Your leave One moment. (Mac Ian comes to Halbert, and takes his hand.) MAC IAN. Halbert, I lack words to thank This kindness as I ought. HALBERT. It is a joy For me to know I am at peace with all, And, most of all, with you. MAC IAN. 'Tis very strange: I am amazed how I could doubt your faith; A film is passing from my soul, that leaves All clear within its vision. Take your place. [Halbert and Alaster sit on the opposite side of the hall to Glenlyon and Lindsay. MAC IAN (resuming his seat). Your pardon. Let us drain another cup To our chief guest, Glenlyon; frank in war, And generous in alliance. HALBERT (to Alaster). Watch him now; He changes; see—his very lips are pale;— I will unmask him. ALASTER. Pray forbear. GLENLYON. Accept A soldier's thanks. HALBERT (to Alaster). His voice is choked—look now— Do you not see him shiver? ALASTER. It is but fancy; How can he hope to see us fall more low Than he has sunk us? MAC IAN (to Glenlyon). You must pledge me now;— Wine to Glenlyon. [Glenlyon rises—takes the cup—puts it to his lips— and hastily returns it. HALBERT. He does not taste the wine, He dares not taste it. Hold me not. [Breaking from Alaster. Glenlyon! Why did you put aside the untasted cup? Why did you change and glare? Why is your heart— Your hollow heart, shivering and shrinking now? Look on him, friends! Mac Ian!—Angus!—Donald! John!—Alaster! Does some infernal charm Delude you, that you rise not? [To Glenlyon.] Answer me! What fiendish thought was yours when you withdrew That goblet from your lips? LINDSAY. Who's this that dares Insult Glenlyon? HALBERT. Parasite, I speak not To such as you! Behold him now! He's silent. LINDSAY. In scorn. [To Glenlyon.] You will not deign to make reply To this coarse brawler? Let us hence. GLENLYON (addressing Mac Ian). Farewell! You cannot curb the rudeness of your followers, Nor I endure it. [Glenlyon and Lindsay retiring. HALBERT. Let them not depart; Not for myself I speak,—for I shall find No time so fit to die; but for your wives— Your sires—your babes—your all. Glenlyon! turn, If you have so much nature as to look The thing you dare. GLENLYON (turning). Be brief in your demand. What is your pleasure? HALBERT. That you spend three minutes With me in the cold moonlight;—arm'd;—alone. GLENLYON. With you—a conquer'd rebel? MAC IAN (holding Halbert). He's a guest Beneath this roof's protection. HALBERT. Let him claim This shelter if he dare, and I will kneel, And he shall trample on me. LINDSAY (to Glenlyon). Come away! ALASTER. Dear Halbert, do not risk a life so dear As yours is to my father. HALBERT. Risk my life— Dost see him? There is that within his breast Would paralyse his arm, and make his knees Tremble, and bid the stubborn soldier fall Half slain without the steel;— [To Glenlyon. I charge on you Black treason—what I know not yet—but feel; Will you confess, or meet me? LINDSAY. Do not answer. GLENLYON. I meet you!—Talk to me of treason!—me Who bear the lawful orders of a king; To whom you are a traitor;—whom your race, With all the hatred of their savage thoughts, Abjure;—but he shall curb them—they shall feel His power is here. Your worthless life, rash fool, To-night I spare;—but if again we meet, It shall be as you wish, for death. [Exeunt Glenlyon, &amp;c. HALBERT. It shall. MAC IAN (to Halbert). I thank your generous courage, but I look With wonder on your passion. HALBERT. What! does nothing Whisper of peril to you? MAC IAN. No—my heart Is jocund;—stripp'd of glory, power, and name, We shall be all united and at peace. HALBERT. Heaven grant it! ALASTER. I would rather die to-morrow, If I might choose, than hold the sweetest home At England's mercy. HALBERT. My brave cousin! Blessings In life and death be with you. MAC IAN. Come away; This sadness will infect us. There's my hand And my heart with it. ALASTER. And mine too. JOHN. And mine. MAC IAN. Farewell;—no strife shall separate us more. [Exeunt Mac Ian, Alaster, and John. HALBERT. That's well!— [Sees Henry. My brother here?—he wakes my soul To its own sufferings. Yet we must not part thus. Brother! HENRY. What would you with me? HALBERT. I would know We part to-night as brothers should; you think That you have cause to blame me: wait awhile, And you may judge me better. HENRY. Blame you?—No— Not I—except that you forgot to bid Your brother to your bridal. He'll make bold To go unbidden. HALBERT. Fail not;—you may find A blessing there you will be grateful for. HENRY (aside). Can he suspect my purpose?—O, no doubt You have deserved all gratitude;—and there Will crown your favours. HALBERT. I will take your hand; It trembles. HENRY. No;—or if it shakes,—the night Chills bitterly. It will be firm to-morrow. [Exit Henry Macdonald. HALBERT. To-morrow!—that will settle all—I'll seek My mother now;—if she is still assured That Helen loves—I cannot bear the thought, Silence and darkness teach me to endure it! [Exit Halbert Macdonald. END OF ACT IV.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT V. Scene.—A Chapel adjoining Halbert's Tower, partly in ruins, in which is seen the Tomb of Halbert's father.—Morning just breaking. Enter Halbert Macdonald. HALBERT. The hour approaches when my life's last hope Will be extinguish'd;—it is quivering now Upon the verge of darkness;—yet I feel No pang—no throb. My spirit is serene, As if prepared to cleave celestial air To passionless delights—this calm within me Has something awful. Enter Lady Macdonald. HALBERT. Mother, wish me joy. LADY MACDONALD. Joy, Halbert?— HALBERT. Yes;—of victory achieved O'er the last passion which can ever rack My bosom. I can bear to ask you now, If any change in Helen raises doubt How she will answer, when—I am not so arm'd As I have boasted. LADY MACDONALD. No;—she scarcely raised Her head, until her work—a bridal robe— Hung dazzling on her arm; as then she sought Her chamber, I impress'd one solemn kiss Upon her icy brow: then as aroused From stupor by poor sympathy, she threw Her arms around my neck; and whispering low, But piercingly, conjured me to keep watch Upon her thinkings, lest one erring wish Should rise to mar her duty to her lord. HALBERT. I ask no more, till in this holy place Her soul shall answer mine; too well I know The issue; yet I shrink not, nor repine. LADY MACDONALD. Your calmness frightens me; you think of death. HALBERT. But as a thing to sigh for, not to seek; I never will forsake you for the grave, Till Heaven dismiss me thither. Has she slept? LADY MACDONALD. I know not; but her chamber has been still, Until, on notice of the priest arrived She sent to pray the guidance of his arm To lead her to this place. HALBERT. The priest arrived! O what a world of happiness these words Should indicate. It opens now to show Its glories melting into air. They come— Her step is heavy; may the heart that sways it Go lighter hence! Enter the Priest, leading Helen, in bridal attire. HALBERT (meeting them). Before a solemn change Shall pass on our condition, let me claim One kiss, in memory of the wintry paths Which we have walked with purity of heart And heaven-ward aspect;—should death take us now, It had no terrors. [Kisses Helen's forehead. PRIEST. Sir, your words are sad For such an hour. Shall we begin the service? HALBERT. We wait my brother's presence. HELEN. O not his! I am quite ready; let the rite proceed. Enter Henry Macdonald. HALBERT. You are most welcome;—we have waited for you. HENRY (looking eagerly round). Your pardon; all are not assembled yet. Where is Glenlyon? HALBERT. Who? HENRY. The lady's uncle; He has, no doubt, approved her choice, and means To grace the ceremonial. You will wait His coming? HALBERT. He resign'd this lovely one To those who knew her worth; he shall not now Infest the roof that shelters her. HENRY (aside). All lost! What can detain him? PRIEST. Shall the rite proceed? HALBERT. I have a few momentous words to speak Before the rites begin;—to you, fair Helen, I must address them; but I pray my brother, Whom they touch nearly, to attend. HENRY. I listen. HALBERT. How, through sad years, the consecrated joy Which seems to wait me at this hour, has dawn'd And brighten'd, from its first uncertain rays Along the rugged pathway of a life Else unadorn'd, my passion-fever'd speech Has shown;—nor less divine the vision glows Now it stands clear before me, and invites To mingle heaven with earth. You cannot doubt it. HELEN. Never;—I only wish I could dsserve A love like yours. HALBERT. Yet ere I grasp this dream, And make its phantoms real;—within these walls By both revered;—where side by side we knelt In infantine humility, and faith No question ruffled; where your spirit sought To cast from its pure mirror, each faint cloud Which jocund thoughts might breathe, or nicest fear Imagine to o'erspread it;—at the tomb Of him who watches o'er his trembling son, At this dread crisis of his fate;—I ask you— Explore your heart; and if you find a wish That glances at another fortune, speak it! HELEN. Have mercy on me! HALBERT. You have seen me chafed By passion worse than aimless in a soul Whose destinies are fashion'd by a Power Wise, bountiful, resistless;—and the words Such frenzy dashes with its foam might seem To urge that one unlike myself must prove Unfit for your affection. Hear me now, When calmer reason governs me! There stands One near to me in blood; a soldier, valiant, And raised above all baseness; in the bloom And gladness of his youth; who loves you—not Perchance as I do—but who loves you well;— You are a soldier's child;—your noble heart May from most natural impulse turn to one Endow'd and graced as he is;—if I read Your wish aright;—I'll join this hand with his,— As freely as I would relinquish life To succour yours. HELEN (sinking on her knee before Halbert). Heaven bless you! HALBERT (raising Helen). 'Tis enough; Now let me draw this ring away—'tis done— You'll let me wear it for a little time— A very little time? Come, Henry,—take This hand, with the deep blessing of a man Whose all is given with it. [Takes Henry's hand to join it to Helen's. Henry stands abstracted. HALBERT. You are cold— Your thoughts are far away;—a blackness spreads Across your face; speak to us! HELEN. He is stricken With wonder at your goodness. Henry; Love! Join me to bless your brother. HENRY. Will no bolt From heaven fall on this head! HELEN. His senses wander, Scared at this sudden happiness;—anon All will be well. [Grasps his arm. HENRY. O never!—do not gaze Upon me;—Helen, touch me not;—fly all. HALBERT. Wherefore? From whom? HENRY. O God! I cannot tell it. [A confused cry heard far in the Valley below. HALBERT. What cry is that? LADY MACDONALD. The shrieks of death arise. HENRY. Not death! Enter Angus. ANGUS. Fly for your lives; our cherish'd guests Have fall'n upon the clansmen wrapp'd in sleep With murderous swords; and burning hovels light Their slaughterous way. HENRY. 'Tis false. ANGUS. False! Hark! Behold! [Another cry heard more distinctly from the Valley, and the glare of distant fire seen. HENRY. O misery! I meant not this. HALBERT. You! Enter Alaster Macdonald, wounded. ALASTER. Cousin— Halbert—I've struggled through the ranks of death Dying to cry for justice. A few moments— And my poor life expended, you will bear The Chieftain's sword. HALBERT. Where is your Father? ALASTER. Slain. HALBERT. And John? ALASTER. Both murder'd in their sleep. I cry For justice on the head of him who ranged The assassins. Hear me! I would kneel indeed But my joints stiffen. HALBERT. Where's the traitor? Alaster (looking round, sees Henry and exclaims). There! [Falls lifeless into the arms of the Priest, who bears him out. HALBERT. My most unhappy brother! PRIEST (returning). He has pass'd. HALBERT. And I am Chief! This is the fatal hour That Moina saw. [Angus and Attendants kneel to Halbert. Ancestral shades, I see You beckon in yon flame. Let me sit here; The grave will serve. Where does the doom'd man stand? HENRY. Here! Chief of the Macdonalds, let my blood Atone my crime—it was not this—I meant But your disgrace. How little did I know The heart I meant to grieve! Strike! vindicate The ancient power, which perishes while thus I pray to be its victim. Do you hear? [Renewed cries from the Valley. Release me from those cries; give me one look Of love, and end me. HALBERT. Will none plead for him? HELEN. It was for me. [To Lady Macdonald. Plead for your son. LADY MACDONALD. I plead For him who, plotting infamy, has brought Death on our race! All things around me plead Against him; and that wail is fraught with shrieks Of mothers, who, with death's convulsions, strive In vain to shield their infants—such as he Was once—as innocent, as blithe, as fair. O Henry! Henry! could I die for you! [Lady Macdonald falls on his neck. Another cry heard. She starts away. Helen sinks on her knees beside the Tomb. HENRY. I'm ready. HALBERT. There!—without. HENRY. I'll wait you there. HALBERT. Will Heaven vouchsafe no refuge? [As he raises his arms in supplication, a shot strikes him; he falls. That is well. Mercy, Most Merciful!—I am absolved. Enter Glenlyon. GLENLYON. Am I too late? My niece— HELEN. Away! away! HENRY (rushing on Glenlyon). Die, murderer! LADY MACDONALD (stops his arm). Let him live. Glenlyon, I pray you may have life stretch'd out beyond The common span of mortals, to endure The curse of Glencoe cleaving to your soul. HELEN. Amen! GLENLYON. It is upon me, yet I will preserve you. HALBERT. Leave us to die. Enter Drummond. DRUMMOND. I seek Glenlyon here. The eastern pass is open; Duncanson Has not arrived: that way the clansmen fly. GLENLYON. Heaven speed them! [Exit Glenlyon. HENRY. Then will I oppose this breast To the pursuing demons, till I win The death I thirst for. [Exit Henry. HELEN. Henry! [Sinks on the ground. HALBERT. There is comfort; Raise me to clasp my mother. You will pray For Henry;—and will find a child in her Whom mercy spares this moment. [To the Priest. To your charge I leave the gathering of my scanty fortune, Which will provide a refuge for these sad ones In some small convent, where they'll weep out life. Will you do this? PRIEST. I will. HALBERT. Bless you! I mark The face which gazed in pity on my rage Beside my father's death-bed:—'tis subdued— Hush'd—conquer'd—pardon'd—and I die in peace. [Dies. END OF THE PLAY.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">NOTES. “Frank disdain Of dull existence which had faintly gleam'd Like yonder Serpent river, through dark rocks Which bury it.” —p. 32. The Serpent River is a rapid mountain stream on the north side of Loch Leven, which after a fall of about twenty feet, rushes through a series of overhanging rocks, like natural arches, through which the rapid water below can be scarcely discerned. “No broad lake Studded with island woods, which make the soul Effeminate with richness, like the scenes In which the baffled Campbells hid their shame, And scorn'd their distant foes.” —p. 33. These lines refer to the charge which the enemies of the Campbells used to urge against them, that when beaten from the borders of Loch Finne, they found shelter on the shores and in the islands of Loch Awe, and defied their foes to follow them, by the proverb, “It is a far cry to Loch Awe.” Perhaps Loch Awe embraces or borders on the most lovely scenery in the Highlands, and Glencoe is embedded in that which is the most sublime. “We were charm'd, Not awe-struck;—for The Beautiful was there Triumphant in its palace.” —p. 57. In seeking to embody in this passage, the author's impression of the Cave of Fingal, in Staffa, he is aware that it differs from that which all the descriptions he has read of the same scene convey. All suggest far greater dimensions—a hollow far more vast and awful, but less exquisite in beauty, than to his eye the reality justifies. “Compared to this (it has been said) what are the cathedrals or the palaces built by men?—mere models or playthings;—imitative or diminutive as his works will always be when compared with those of nature.” According to the author's recollection, the cave would be more fitly compared to a narrow aisle of a great cathedral, fashioned with nicest art, and embellished with the most florid sculpture, than represented as something immeasurably greater than the cathedral itself; and the actual admeasurement of the cave will rather accord with this impression, than with that which is more popular. The height of the top of the arch above the water at mean tide is sixty-six feet; the breadth at the entrance forty-two feet; whence it contracts during its length of two hundred and twenty-seven feet, until at the extremity it is only twenty-two feet in width; and the roof descends in nearly the same proportion. When it is further recollected that even this width is narrowed to the eye by the row of exquisite columns which continue on the northern side, and along which the adventurer may step, and that a slight bend about half way breaks its uniformity, perhaps he will be pardoned for thinking that there has been much exaggeration in attributing the grandeur which arises from space and gloom to this wonderful cavern. On the other hand, justice has not been done—indeed, never can be done by words—to the fairy loveliness of the scene,—the delicate colour of the water,—the grace of the columns,—the elegance of the arched roof, and the blue serenity of the distant sea, as seen from beneath it. “The order is to guard the avenues To-night, and ere the morning, put in force The Royal ordinance on the lives of all Below the age of seventy.” —p. 66. The following is the despatch which Duncanson sent, and on which Glenlyon acted. It was addressed, “For their Majesties' Service, to Captain Robert Campbell, of Glenlyon. “You are hereby ordered to fall upon the rebels, and put all to the sword under 70;—you are to have special care that the old fox and his cubs do on no account escape your hands;—you are to secure all the avenues, that no man escape. This you are to put in execution at four in the morning precisely, and by that time, or very shortly after, I will strive to be at you with a stronger party; but if I do not come to you at four, you are not to tarry for me, but fall on. This is by the king's special command, for the good and safety of the country, that these miscreants be cut off root and branch. See that this is put in execution without either fear or favour, else you may expect to be treated as not true to the king or government, nor a fit man to carry a commission in the king's service. Expecting that you will not fail in the fulfilling hereof, as you love yourself, I subscribe these with my hand. “Robert Duncanson.” “Stoutly have I fought Upon King James's side; but with Dundee His cause expired.” —p. 74. “Dundee himself,” says Sir Walter Scott, “contrary to the advice of the Highland chiefs, was in the front of the battle, and fatally conspicuous. Observing the stand made by two English regiments, he galloped towards the clan of Macdonald, and was in the act of bringing them to the charge, with his right arm elevated, as if pointing the way to victory, when he was struck by a bullet beneath the armpit, where he was unprotected by the cuirass. He tried to ride on, but being unable to keep the saddle, fell mortally wounded, and died in the course of that night. Such was the general opinion of his talents and courage, and the general sense of the peculiar crisis at which his death took place, that the common people of the low country cannot even now be persuaded that he died an ordinary death. They say that a servant of his own, shocked at the severities which, if triumphant, his master was likely to accomplish against the Presbyterians, and giving way to the popular prejudice of his having a charm against the effect of leaden balls, shot him in the tumult of the battle with a silver button taken from his livery coat. The Jacobites and Episcopalian party, on the other hand, lamented the deceased victor as the last of the Scots, the last of the Grahams, and the last of all that was great in his native country.”— Tales of a Grandfather, chap. 56. Sir Walter Scott says,—“Claverhouse's sword, a straight cut-and-thrust blade, is [1802] in the possession of Lord Woodhouselee; and the buff coat which he wore at the battle of Killicrankie, having the fatal shot-hole under the armpit of it, is preserved in Pennycuick-house, the seat of Sir George Clerk, Baronet.”—Border Minstrelsy, vol. ii. p. 45; Note to Tales of a Grandfather, vol. ii. 114. THE END.</field>
   </doc>
</add>