<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Brooke, Henry, 1703-1783</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Brooke, Henry, 1703-1783</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">brooke henry 1703 1783</field>
      <field name="author_text">Brooke, Henry, 1703-1783</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">18th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1780's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V2.0601.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1789</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460254</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Earl of Westmorland ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Earl of Westmorland ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="title_facet">earl of westmorland</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">earl of westmorland</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Earl of Westmorland ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="year_display">1789</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1789</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1789</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460254&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460254&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Brooke, Henry, 1703?-1783&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;brooke henry 1703 1783&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Earl of Westmorland ; A Tragedy&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;earl of westmorland&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1789&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1789&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Brooke, Henry&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1703&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1783&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Earl of Westmorland&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for John Sewell [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1789&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872797-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv20601&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 18th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;18th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Earl of Westmorland&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 140 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter, including The Life Of The Author, omitted&lt;lb/&gt;Only verse drama included&lt;lb/&gt;Plays reproduced elsewhere in English Verse Drama not included&lt;lb/&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: The Earl of Westmorland.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1778.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 1742.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE Earl of WESTMORLAND: A TRAGEDY.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PERSONS. OSBERT, King of Northumberland. BRUERN, Earl of Westmorland. OSRIC, Earl of Manchester, and Friend of Bruern. EDWIN, Son of Bruern and Rowena. IVAR, King of Denmark. HUBBA, his Brother. ROWENA, Wife of Bruern. Lords of the Council, Officers, Soldiers, Messengers, Nuns, Attendants.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE, the Suburbs of York.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. SCENE I. The Suburbs of York. Enter Osric and Edwin. Edwin. Where would you lead, sir—whither do we travel? Osric. Hold, we are near the appointment of our journey. Where do we travel, say'st thou?—O, my son! To save a treasure, more than mines can boast; To seize, to snatch her from impending war, And give a mother to the arms of Edwin. Edwin. A mother, sir!—My mother, say you? Osric. Yes. Edwin. O yet beware, how you excite desires In a fond heart; a sense of new delights, To pine with eager and with empty longings! A mother!—Are you not my father, then? Osric. No, Edwin, no—far other than thy sire, I claim thee as the child of my adoption, Heir of my heart, and of my soul begotten. Edwin. O, sir, the creature of your goodness ever! But then my parents—will you not inform me? Osric. Search not too deep; behind their honour'd names, Lurk deadly dangers.—O, thou noble youth! There is a secret—and, for thy dear safety, I wish it ever so—for my sad heart Misgives me in the issue.—This same Osbert, The king, who long hath fill'd Northumbria's throne, Did wrong thy valiant sire: thy sire, provoked Beyond the bearings of a saint-like sufferance, Wrench'd the avenging thunder from Heaven's hand, Levied fierce war, and rent his country's peace. I was his friend, the inmost of his soul; And ere his daring purpose was avow'd, In secret he consigned thyself and mother, Her to my care, and thee to my adoption— For well he knew, tho' loyalty withheld My hand from his rebellion, yet my heart Rank'd on his side, and bled amid the battle. Edwin. A cause, you say, there was—and O, I hope, A worthy cause. Osric. A cause there was, my Edwin! But not the varying circumstance of things, Not nature can afford a worthy cause, For warring on our country—Think of that— And if—as haply thou shalt hear a tale Too soon for thy repose—then, Edwin, then, Suppress the vengeance rising in thy bosom; And, to the judgments of vindictive Heaven, Permit the crimes of man. Edwin. O, tell me all— Osric. I fear I have reveal'd too much already. Edwin. What can you fear from me?—Fear not your Edwin! Am I not as the creature of your goodness, Form'd by your hand, and charm'd to your direction? Osric. The best of mortals have their hour of frailty— Fear, Edwin, fear yourself!—I do remember, When yet thou had'st not breathed five hours of life, A servant bore thee in thy swathed attire To the great hall, wherein thy father sate With many noble friends—An aged pilgrim Stood at the gate: all piercing was his eye, But calm his aspect; and his staff appear'd A prop for piety, and years well spent, And wisdom, to repose on—He approach'd; And having eyed thee with a look, that seem'd To penetrate and sound the depths of time, He laid thy fingers on his palm—he paused, And then to these prophetic words gave utterance: Little, feeble, mighty hand! Thou shalt save a sinking land; On the salt and circling flood, Build thy country's wall with wood; Build the wall of wide renown— And give one head to Britain's crown! Yet, 'ere this or that be done, The Raven must obscure the sun, Filling nations with affright, Covering Britain broad as night! Thou shalt pierce him as he flies— On his fall shall Britain rise! Yet, O yet, 'ere this be done, Thou, the subject, and the son, Shalt lift thy fell and fatal dart, To pierce thy king and father's heart! Edwin. Ha! what a sudden terror shakes my limbs, And freezes to my heart!—Father, and king!— Murder my father!—lightnings strike me first. Prevent this parricide—lop off these hands; Tear my heart forth; nor leave a power to act, Or think such horrors! Osric. Peace to thy heart—thy father is no more! Edwin. He fell not then by my misdeed—thank Heaven! Osric. No. But thy mother now demands our care. This way, my son. [Exeunt. SCENE II. The Inside of the Abbey. Rowena, and Nuns ranged on each side, with Tapers. Anthem. Here, in every sacred aisle, Solemn walk, and silent cell, Truth and Peace serenely smile, Hope and warm Devotion dwell. Safely landed, here we mourn Foundering mortals, left behind; Wretches, on the deep forlorn, Tost and wreck'd with every wind. What has Grandeur to supply, What has Pleasure to impart?— Mere illusion to the eye, Real anguish to the heart! Here, from time and transience won, Beauty has her charms resign'd; Heaven already is begun, Opening in an humble mind. Fount of Truth, Seraphic bowl, Pour the nectar from above! O, descend into the soul, Thirsting after life and love! Death is conquer'd, time is past, Heaven is present to our view— Welcome, welcome, joys that last! Short seducing world, adieu! [The Nuns retire. Rowena advances slowly, and speaks. All hail Devotion, hail thou wing'd for Heaven, Divine ambassadress! Here let me dwell With Solitude, thy sister, and the train That wait on thy uprising—Patience, Peace, And Resignation calm, and Charity Whose love enfolds a world. A Nun enters. Nun. Madam, an antient man, His look importing haste and earnest suit, Entreats admittance. Row. Whence? Nun. From Osric, as he says, late Earl of Manchester. Row. Say'st thou, from Manchester? Quick, give him entrance. [Exit Nun. SCENE III. Osric enters. Row. What would'st thou, stranger? Osric. O, all-beauteous saint! Time cuts each lingering preface from my tongue— Ruin has spread her baleful wings around, And I from far have hasten'd to preserve thee. Row. Do I not hear a voice, that used to make The widow's music—tuneful as the fall Of waters on a burnt and thirsty land? If thou art Osric, say—at once inform me; Or if his angel, I will kneel to thee. Osric. Hold thee, Rowena!—Yes, I am that Osric, Nor yet immortal. Row. Wherefore, then, these weeds, Thrown o'er thy virtues, like a miser's chest Rusting on treasure? Some mishap has found thee; Why else an absence of twelve tedious years? Where hast thou been, what distance has withheld thee? And why now here, why thus, and at this hour, When Apprehension, fearful centinel, Stands all alarm'd upon the gloom of night, And startles at events? Osric. The tale is long—time serves not now for utterance— Even, while we speak, destruction rushes onward! Danes, Dacians, Goths, collecting all their powers, From Weser to the cold Septentrion star, The sons of winter, pour such legions forth, As, number'd, never yet have met in arms, To speed perdition! Swift, O haste thee hence!— Friendship attends to guide thy sacred steps To some asylum; and, to guard thee forth, Waits a young champion, valiant as his sire, And gentle as thy self. Row. What champion?—Ah! I will not hope it—no, I will not, Osric! Yet thy looks speak—and lives my Edwin, then— My child?—O, call him, give him to my tears, To my heart's yearnings!—Yet, do not call him; No, rather keep him from my arms for ever! Perhaps he knows, knows all the piteous tale Of his unhappy parents—how the ravisher, This king of satyrs, stole upon the hour Of faith, and holy hospitality— My husband absent, every power away, That should have guarded innocence and virtue From brutal force, from horrid violation— And stain'd the chastest, whitest page of life, With foul dishonour! Osric. No, he knows it not. Row. Why, where has he escaped the shafts of slander? Is there a tongue that speaks Rowena's name, But aptly tacks pollution to the sound, And taints the passing breeze?—Who knows nought else, Is learn'd in my misfortune; and the shame, That sits between the low abased brows Of his sad mother, shall attaint my child, And blast his filial virtue. Osric. Think not so. For thou art all one excellence, too pure For grosser imputation!— These many years, the busy, meddling world, Has talked itself to silence; and thy son, Hath ever lived, till this important hour, A stranger to thy name.— Soon as thy mighty husband fell in battle, Upon that bloody day, wherein he made His last dread effort to revenge thy wrongs, Driven from my country, from my native honours, I fled, thy little son within my arms; And in the court of royal Ethelred, Till now have sojourn'd—Edwin, gentle youth! Approach, my Edwin!—draw with reverence here, And bend thee as to Heaven! SCENE IV. Edwin advances with slow reverence. Row. What loveliness!— Fond, fond resemblance! gesture, form, and grace, Like my lost lord!—ideas, once so loved, Nor yet forgotten!—Parent nature, how, How dost thou stir me! how awaken all The tender, dear distractions! O, my child! [Embraces. Edwin. Your pardon, madam—I am much unskill'd, And new to all the duties of a son; But in your face, as in the front of Heaven, There is a language that bespeaks my soul, And dictates more than outward forms can reach! Here, at my heart, you pull the vital cords; Within I know and feel from whence I am, Part of your being—But—O mother!— Row. What says my child? Edwin. Had Heaven so will'd, how doubly blest were Edwin! My father—what of him? Row. Thy father?—ah, that I can only say, Thou had'st a father!—His paternal lips Have held fond talk with thy unthinking days, For he did love thee with a mother's feeling; And that strong arm on which the nations hung, With thee hath toy'd away the smiling hours, And grew around thy slumbers—Me, even me, He loved—too fatally he loved thy mother!— The nobler passions of humanity, Bore his bold vessel with too strong a wind— We were his ruin—O, my child, my child! Thy father loved too well—and we have lost him. Osric. Bright saint, let other hours indulge the scenes Of fond remembrance—now, the times are urgent! Haste, haste, Rowena, 'ere the speedier foe This night, perhaps, shall rush around these walls, And intercept our journey. Row. Ah, my lord, Fly thou—and with thee be my Edwin's safety! But take no thought for one so lost as I am.— I cannot, must not fly. Osric. Say you, Rowena?— We have mistook your meaning. Row. No, good Osric— My rest is fix'd even here; and Heaven, I trust, Is the next mansion that receives Rowena. Osric. It must not be—Already, I behold The powers of hell unbound; They rush to earth, and with them bring along Hair starting horror, fear, and hate, and rage, And wild ey'd famine, and wide-reaching waste, And lust and rape—by whom thy wrongs, Rowena, Are multiplied on thousands. Row. Not so, I hope—around this hallow'd pile, Oft hath the rage of battle felt rebuke; While each licentious soldier stood abash'd, Or bow'd at distance—From the pensive shrines, The twilight arches, and the shadowy domes, Religion throws a far-forbidding awe On all beholders. Edwin. Alas! my mother, have I found you then, To part with you so soon? like chearing light, But for a moment sent to blind-born eyes— Just come, to shew the blessedness of sight, And bid them close for ever! Osric. Soft!—some lights approach,— This way they move—Thy chamber, haste, Rowena! An hour shall send us to thy last resolves. [Exit Rowena. Back Scene closes. 'Tis Osbert—that is he—This way, my son; I would observe him. [They retire. SCENE V. Enter Osbert attended. Osbert. Haste, Wolford!—gather up our scatter'd soldiers, Call the militia in—alarm the country— Line the wall round—and bar the massy gates— Confusion! to be thus surprised! No word, no warning of the coming danger!— Our scouts, are they gone forth? Officer. They are, my liege. Osbert. Throw open all our magazines of arms; We want new levies—and proclaim rewards To old and young, to every trade and rank, Whose arm shall lift a sword in our defence. Where's Anulph, Adelfrid? Officer. They are fled, my lord. Osbert. O recreant slaves! they've eat our honey up, And now forsake the hive—Quick, what's the news? Enter an Officer. Officer. Retire, my liege, retire—'ere morning dawns, The foe is on us. Osbert. Let them come, my friends. Short is the conning of a soldier's lesson— If not to live, why then, to fall with honour. Retire, and leave me to my thoughts a while— [Exeunt Attendants. 'Tis finish'd—Thou hast found me, Heaven!—Where now, O, where's Northumbria's guardian, where is Westmorland, Whose arm launch'd forth the thunder of the war And crush'd invasion?—where my guilt hath sent him, By my foul rape of his most chaste Rowena, Dishonoured to his grave!—Where too is Manchester, My throne's best prop, the wisdom of my council? Him too I have cast off; and given, in place, Riches to knaves, to cowardice commission, Office to ignorance, and trust to traitors. SCENE VI. Osric and Edwin come forward. Osbert. Who art thou? Osric. A Briton. Osbert. Subject to whom? Osric. My country, and the law. Osbert. Hath not thy king a name? Osric. Yes, I remember now—his name was Osbert, Till lost to fame, and of himself forgotten. Osbert. Ha! know'st thou not, that chastisement attends The voice of insolence? Osric. The voice of truth! Osbert. O, it is A voice, to which I have been long a stranger!— Pride, stand aloof! ye visionary forms Of titled majesty, away! while thus, Thus to my arms I take one honest man, More worth to kings than empire! [Embraces Osric. Osric. Saints of Heaven! Is this Northumbria's monarch, this our Osbert, Whose heart so long was shut from all access Of alienated worth?—Rowena!—Westmorland! Osbert. I understand thee— O, severely true! Heaven pardon and redress! Osric. Then pardon thou—my liege, my still loved lord! [Kneels. Pardon a rash and most licentious tongue, That thus, with unexampled boldness, durst Defame thy virtues, and traduce my master. Osbert. Ha! Manchester! Osric. The same—Why turns my prince From his old man? Osbert. Ungrateful to mine eye, Is the cold visage of the friend I have injured. Osric. No more!—I swear, Thus to have found thee, to thyself restored, Is every loss retrieved—'tis more than empire! It is thy better birth-day, hail'd and hymn'd By angel forms, and heavenly winged saints, That guard a British throne! Osbert. My father!—Come, Come to my heart, and plant thy virtues there. [Embrace. And O! thou sage of years, thou son of wisdom, If there is aught in art or arms to friend us, One cast of helpful council—stretch thy hand, And save a sinking realm! Osric. One yet remains, One last expedient, one of mightiest proof— But strange to power, and still to kings ungrateful. Osbert. O name it! Osric. Wherefore do I see thee thus, With luke-warm soldiers, thinly sown around thee? Where are thy sons, thou father of a people! That now should combat for their own inheritance? O! to the souls of unpossessing slaves No loss can come, and every lord is equal. Osbert. What's to be done? Osric. Yet, ere the morning dawn, Summon thy subjects, yield them their dear rights, The rights of men free-born—the sons of Heaven, Who hold, in common with the proudest kings, The gifts of nature, and the claims of reason! Would'st thou have soldiers faithful, daring, dauntless; Give them a stake to fight for—Is it gold, Office, or honour, or the brighter prize Of animating glory?—No—'tis more! 'Tis Liberty, my prince, assured by law, And circled from encroachment!—Never fell Army, or empire, 'ere the fatal day, In which they fell from Freedom! Osbert. O, enough—all, all shall be amended, As thou, my friend and father, shalt appoint. But say— What youth is that whose form attracts our eye, And bids it note him? Osric. Mine, my gracious sovereign. Osbert. Is he thy son? Osric. I have no other child. Osbert. Son, worthy of the sire!—Approach, brave youth! And say how best a monarch may prevail, Who means to woo and win thee to his friendship? Edwin. My gracious lord, the little worth I boast, Will save the seeking. Osbert. O! we trust not thee, To speak thine own deservings; well we know, Honour ne'er rises in its own report. But if we yet survive to-morrow's sun; If, by thy wise and warlike father's councils; If, by thy arm, thou offspring of the brave! It lie in valour, or in art to save; Thence, every joy and every equal care, From both I gather, and with both I share— With him my scepter, and my heart with thee; Thou my loved brother, and my father he! [Exeunt. END OF THE FIRST ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. SCENE I. Osbert and Osric. Osbert. Still living—and so near me?—O, the rapture!— The dear distress'd!—Will you then plead my pardon? Will you not tell her—nay, enforce it, Osric; Pour all the abundance of my soul before her— Tell her, her safety lies within these walls; My crown is hers, my life her best protection. Osric. Mean you to wed her, then? Osbert. Would'st thou not, my friend, Aspire at Heaven, if distance did not bar thee? Wed her!—yes, Osric—for a single day, An hour of bliss in her society, I'd barter every year of life to come— But, O my crime—that outrage on her honour!— Her peace, her beauty, and her spotless innocence, Rent and polluted by my brutal passion!— What shall I plead?—Pardon she never can— Tell her, in that, we are already wedded; For Osbert hates himself. Osric. I will, my lord. Osbert. Nay, but this night—this very night, my Osric!— Fate may dispose the morrow to another. Tell her this instant hour stands singly up 'Twixt life and death, time and eternity, Connubial honour and the blot of ages! Away—my peace attends on thy return!— Some angel sit upon thy charmed tongue, And teach thy breath persuasion. [Exit Osbert. Osric. Rowena married, and a queen!—'tis well— The foe expell'd, my prince return'd to virtue, Her honour rescued, and his fault forgotten!— But, Edwin!—there's the gulph—this dread prediction! For Osbert wedded, then becomes at once His king, and father; so may fate be answer'd!— 'Tis but in man, throughout the maze of life, To mark the clue of his peculiar duty— 'Tis Heaven's to wind and guide the thread at pleasure. [Exit. SCENE II. Enter Westmorland and Ethelwald. Ethel. I swear it is too much—Again permit me To gaze, to feast my sight—again fall prostrate— [Kneels. To kiss the steps of my reviving lord— My lord, my long lost lord—to touch, to clasp him, That every sense may swear—'tis he, indeed; And not some phantom of illusive joy, That would abuse his servant! West. To my arms— To your returning master, rise, my friend, My long tried Ethelwald! Ethel. Dead! wept! entomb'd!— Your solemn trophy rais'd!—all the sad rites, Of dirge, and mournful obsequy!—yet thus, To see, to feel, that things impossible Appeal to demonstration! West. List, my friend, And lose thy wonder.— Fame says, that, on the eve of holy-cross, Cover'd with wounds, along the blood-stain'd bank Of southern Tyne, thy hapless master fell. He fell, indeed!—confusion followed straight, And rout, and darkness, that dispers'd alike Victor, and vanquish'd. Yet, not so retired One faithful soldier—he, o'er heaps of dead, Sat mournful, till the moon should lift her lamp, To light him to his lord, whom soon he found— From my pale head he loos'd the mangled casque; And, bending o'er me, thro' the silent night Pour'd forth his loud affliction. To his plaint, And the cool fresh, I rais'd my ponderous lids, Then sunk again—Transported, all in haste He stript my arms, and on a headless trunk Bestow'd the rich endowment; bound my wounds, And, with a sinewy, and a dear embrace, Upborn, convey'd me from the field of death, To a near hamlet. Ethel. Pay him, bounteous Heaven!— Let me not taste of death, till I become A servant to that servant! West. Sense, and health, With time, return'd; till when, I held my secret. Then did I give my fortune to the winds, That threw me on the Dane—him long I serv'd, Led forth his battles, and enlarged his bounds; And, in return, he comes, my soldier now, To free my country, and to right my quarrel. Ethel. Alas! my master, is it in thy leading, That such a host of foes comes banded onward, To lay fair Albion waste? West. No, Ethelwald— My soldiers step as though on holy ground, Smooth as a mist that moves upon the morning, Dropping kind dew on every head, save one— For there our vengeance levels—he, your king!— Your precious Osbert!—lives he? Ethel. He does. West. Thank Heaven for that—O, snatch him not, ye fiends! Set him but first within my reach of sight, And if he scape this arm—live, Osbert, live!— Bow, world, before thy lord—for he's immortal!— SCENE III. Enter Hubba. Hub. I have traced and found thee, Westmorland!—O friend, Does this beseem the general of our armies— Thus to forsake his camp, alone, unguarded; And cast his valued person on the edge Of danger, and of darkness? West. O, my Hubba, There is, there is a cause!— Hub. Wherefore that sigh, When fame, when friendship, and when Denmark wait, But till the morrow's sun shall light the world, To give Northumbria's scepter to your hand, And crown your arms with conquest? West. O friend, friend! My steps have long been strangers to ambition— I seek not fame, nor royalty. Hub. How, Westmorland! What else is worthy of a warrior's notice? West. Vengeance. Hub. Vengeance? West. Vengeance, my royal friend!—O, generous Hubba, Oft was I on the point to tell thee all, To pour my anguish in thy friendly bosom— But shame withheld the tale. Hub. Long have I mark'd The labours of thy soul, the big emotion; But fear'd to ask, although I wish'd to ease thee. West. The hour is come that must reveal my wrongs, Loud as their cry for justice—List, my friend, It is a grievous tale—I once was held, Fair, brave, and young, the hope of my loved country, Her first in arms, and honour'd as her king. Upon a time, I saw a noble maid, Daughter and heiress to the earl of Devon; I saw, I loved, and woo'd, and won her to me— But, O, to say how blest—new-budding youth Would run to age, in numbering o'er her beauties, And never feel decay!— Where'er she moved, the gladsome east went with her, And rose in morning-comfort on my sight. At length, this angel, placed on earth, brought forth A son, a little cherub to the world, Cloath'd in the brightness of his mother's beauty. So, all was full, rhe social, the humane, And every cordial amity!—Two years Pass'd blissful on, and smiled.—But then!— Hub. What then? West. Ay, then arrived that hour, that fatal hour, Which hell caught out, and mark'd for my undoing— When, in a visit, as from friend to friend, King Osbert sought my castle, I was absent— But my too charming bride!—dark envy saw, And sigh'd—his crown seem'd poor—high passions rose, That swept faith, friendship, Heaven, and earth before 'em. To sue, was vain—he knew it vain—what else? Force, guilty, ruffian force—and I was ruin'd!— Hub. O, honour, virtue!—what, Northumbria's Osbert? West. Even he—the scepter'd ravisher, the robber— The lustful, lawless ruler!—Go, my friend, We have a business here of private claim, But dear import—return thou to the camp, Prepare our destined embassy to York, And challenge forth whoe'er, in single fight, Shall stand his country's hope—he shall be met, And these the high conditions—if we conquer, Then, Osbert cedes, and fair Northumbria's crown Is left at our dispose; but, if we fall, We swear to abdicate his throne for ever, And leave the land in peace. Hub. It shall be done. West. Osbert, I think, will not confide his crown To any second arm: for he is bold; Though guilty, warlike as the sons of earth, Ere nature knew decline—my vengeance then, With sudden transport shall spring forth, confess'd, And gripe its quarry. Hub. 'Tis most likely—O, May all the powers that war on perfidy Succeed your hope!—Adieu. [Exit Hubba. West. My Ethelwald, Are we not near the place that holds my treasure— The blest abode, where my Rowena dwells, And consecrates the shrine?— Ethel. We are, my lord— Yon pile, yon happy pile, contains the saint, And lifts our earth to Heaven. West. Your arm, my Ethelwald, For I am sudden faint with doubt and joy, And trembling expectation— Now walls, kind walls, be faithful to your trust; Give but these eyes to see her once again, And I will case your spires with beaten gold!— Lend me thy cloak—Attend a-while without— Yon gate invites my entrance— [Exeunt. SCENE IV. An Apartment in the Abbey. Rowena and Osric seated. They rise and come forward. Osric. Yet, give me leave— Row. No more—I pray, no more!— Honour!—shame to it, for it sticks on guilt, And leaves reproach to virtue! I will none on't— My lord, my lord, I am married to my grave, And will no other husband. Osric. Wondrous creature, All sainted excellence!—I did but wish My country wedded to her peace in thee; To see thy bright example, as a glass, Rais'd to the public eye, where every soul Must shame to look, or dress itself to virtue. Row. Alas! good Osric, I have no skill to queen it; And if the little virtue Heaven has lent, Will serve to pilot on one humble bark To its last port, it is a task sufficient— So much for royalty!—And, for the rest, I had rather mix me with the loathsome dead, And yield my living body to corruption, Than turn my soul into the bed of sense Still more detested. Osric. Yet, Rowena, yet, There is a claim, your country has a claim— Row. A claim! Osric. Yes, lady, Of retribution—that you seal her peace; A kind reverse of blest prosperity, In recompence of all the mighty ills, You brought upon her. Row. I, Osric, I? Osric. Not the famed Helen, whose destructive charms Laid Asia waste, and made all Greece a widow, Caused equal desolation—Still, methinks, I see thy husband in his vengeance rise Loud as the thunder, furious as the whirlwind, O'erturning armies, and our tower-fenced towns, In undistinguished ruin! Row. No, Manchester—He warr'd on guilt alone, The friends of violence, the foes of virtue! Osric. Against his country, and her lawful king— Row. His country's lawless tyrant! Osric. He is penitent— As pilgrims sworn to wander thro' the world, Their bare feet weeping blood on every flint, For one false step. Row. O name him, name him not! Osric. How!—cannot piety, like thine, so rais'd O'er all we deem of angels—fast, and prayer, And vigils, that already hold in Heaven Their nightly converse—cannot these afford One drop of mercy to repentent frailty, That kneels and prostrate falls beneath thy feet For blest forgiveness? Row. O, Osric!— My friend, my father!—well, I will confess it— To thee I will confess—days, nights, and years, I have strove, and combated, and pray'd for help, And waked, and watch'd, and wept, and wish'd to pardon, To quell the swelling hate, the big resentment— In vain—still faithful to the dread remembrance, The giant wrong returns too mighty for me— His name, his dire idea!—'tis my curse, The spectre of my thoughts, my detestation, My daily, nightly horror!— Heaven, pardon thou!—But where?—O! where's the power, Shall wash my stain away? Osric. Thy stain, thou mirror of divine perfection!— Thy stain? Row. Indelible, It sticks—'tis rooted in my name, my memory, Deep as existence—O, the ruthless ravager, Who kills for ages!—Seest thou, Manchester, These organs, once so pleasing to the eye, Now to the soul they hold abhorr'd, and loathsome? This body of pollution, 'tis my burden, A load irreconcileable—till death Shall mix and crumble it with kindred dust, That no discerning finger may point out Where lie the ruins of the lost Rowena. Osric. Fairest, my suit, I doubt, was over earnest, But did not mean offence—Repose attend thee! Heaven's happiest visions open in each thought, And furnish out thy slumbers! [Exit. SCENE V. Westmorland enters, and bends on one Knee. Row. O! once, indeed, I had a husband—his all-placid face Was as a little Heaven, new planeted With twin bright stars; and beauty from each limb, As through a summer casement, look'd abroad, And found no rival.— Ha! what art thou— [Seeing Westmorland. That thus obtrudest thy irreverend step Upon the sacred vigils of the night?— Com'st thou in friendship? [West. kneels. West. From that sacred breast, Heaven's choicest seat, far, far be dread and danger! In friendship? yes—with awe—with adoration. Row. Whence? West. Peace be to your gentle heart!— I bring a token, and from one, who once Was honour'd with the highest, dearest claim, That ever did enrich a mortal—one, Who once did boast Rowena for his blessing— Her long lost, her life-wedded Westmorland. Row. If, O if— Celestial messenger! thou dost descend, To tell my hour's at hand—I hail thy summons! My soul is on the wing to meet my lord, Where all cares end, and love alone's immortal. West. He lives—thy happy husband!— He lives, he comes!—Already has he past A length of distant lands—already reach'd The beach that beetles o'er that envious sea, Which roll'd between you!— Row. Living!—landed!— Did'st thou say, landed? West. Yes, within this hour— This, this exalted hour, this hour of blessedness! Prepare to hear, to see, to hold— [Westmorland rises—the cloak drops, Row. Ah, Heaven! O'erwhelm me not with hopes of happiness, That mock a mortal's reach!—Am I awake? In life, or death, that form should be remember'd— It breaks upon me—O the gracious figure!— 'Tis he, my lord, my husband!— Shield me, give me room!— His presence fills the place—but leaves our air— Too thin for breath—I cannot—oh— [Faints. West. Here end me, nature!—I have lived my length, [Catches her. Have climb'd the zenith of my Heaven—and hence 'Tis declination all—Wake, O wake, my love, Star of sweet influence! Ye silver lids, That chamber up the morning, open straight, Open your gates, that I may see my day. Row. This crown is hot—it sears me to the brain! Yon is a brighter, for 'tis gem'd with stars!— Away—unhand me, ruffian—thou a king! Have I not sworn it? I will not be wedded. [Breaks from him. West. Alas, she raves— Row. Indeed—eyes mock me not! If it is he, I'll have him!— [Runs into his arms. West. Rowena, dearest!— Why wilt thou pluck up sorrow by the roots, With such deep heaves? Why drown me with thy tears?— This passion quite o'erbears my growth of joys, Which else had reach'd the stars—Ah, those dove eyes, How they do speak!— Wilt thou not know me? Row. Art thou not my lord, My wedded lord, fair Albion's arm of war? And am not I thy true and humble wife, Sworn servant of thy will? I think, even so. But whether so it be, in life or death— Awake, or over-watch'd—in sooth, I know not. West. O, thou fair creature, Whom nature form'd so exquisitely apt To fill the deep desirings of my soul, Made up of love, and peace-born blessedness! Do I then hold thee?—painful, painful rapture! Row. Lord of my life, hast thou alone the power To pass the bourn of pale mortality, Whence none return beside? or has the grave, Cold and insensible till now, relented, Warm'd by my sighs, and quickening to my wishes— And given thee back, thus lovely, to the light, Thus, thus, to my embraces? [Embrace. West. My heart's blessing!— The season serves not now—we shall have time, We shall have time for all the wond'rous tale— To talk, to listen, mingling sweet regards, And looks, and smiles, and questions, from that tongue, Tuned, as the harp of David, to expel All anguish from the soul! Row. Delightful intercourse, Foretaste of Heaven!—But then— West. Why that look averted? Then!—What of then, thou dearest? Row. Then, my Westmorland, How shall I dare to lift a face of shame To that majestic brow?—And yet, I trust, 'Tis not the transience of external beauty, A form alone that won thee to my wishes— No, thou didst wed a more essential wife, The heart, the immortal soul of thy Rowena, Still thine, and unpolluted. West. Ha!—yes, thou shalt have vengeance!—Say'st thou, dearest? O, no, thou art all, from violence, from Osbert, From mortal touch, all pure and unpolluted, As snow new sifted through a northern sky, And kist by the cold breeze—thy chaster breath Would serve to light the vestal fire anew, And consecrate its flame. Row. Our Edwin lives— West. For that I bow to Heaven— There undivided, clasp'd within our offspring, The fondest wish my soul ere form'd is answer'd. Enter Ethelwald. Ethel. My lord, beware!—Just issuing from the town, By distant torch-light I discern some troops, That this way bend their motions. West. Then, Rowena, We part for some few hours—To morrow's sun Shall light me to my love; and I will lift her To such a height, so near divinity, The bending world shall look with wonder upward, And worship while they gaze! Row. O, my life's lord— Grandeur and I have vow'd a wide divorce— I can't support the stedfast searching brow, The world's broad look—I sink to death beneath it! Ah, might I wooe thee to the kindly vale, The sweet descents of life!—there Peace keeps home, Nor ever visits at a lordly mansion; But with the loves and joys, and downy hours, Bounds o'er the green, and laughs within the cottage. West. Then, be it so— Soon as one urgent debt is paid to honour, Adieu the cares, and coils, that worldlings dress In rainbow robes, and falsify with titles! Far from the scenes of frenzy, let us fly To some fair Eden of primeval innocence, Where my Rowena's presence shall bereave The fox of fraud, the tyger of his fierceness; Shall tune all passions of the soul to peace, The waves, the winds, and war-worn elements, To their first order—Thou, like sinless Eve, New from the hand of Heaven, returning bliss To that fond bosom whence she drew her being; My vital consort, my far dearer part, Warm at my side, and panting at my heart! [Exeunt END OF THE SECOND ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. SCENE I. The Council Chamber. Osbert, Osric, Edwin, and Lords, rising from Table. Osbert. The dawn has almost stolen upon our councils. Here break we up; and let a short repose Fit us for weightier toils. [Exeunt all but Osbert and Osric. No ray of hope, thou sayest— No glimpse, however distant, that may serve To light me to my wishes? Osric. None, my lord. Cold as a marble emblem of the dead, By some chill vault incircled from the world, Rowena's every sense is shut, alike, To love as to ambition—Yet the turns, The strange events that lodge within the womb Of wide futurity, alike forbid Despondence, as presumption. Osbert. There I cast One little grain, where hope may yet take root In possibility—For, O my friend, My father! who hast given me, by thy councils, My better birth—a birth, wherein alone Existence can have worth, my birth in virtue!— Already does my soul attempt for freedom; And, from the fetters and the gloom of guilt, Gets all aloft, and soars within my bosom. I feel new being, joyous, calm, humane, The kindly offices of man to man, How sweet the intercourse!—of kings to all, Thrice blest prerogative! Osric. True, my loved liege— When monarchs stoop to act, and feel like men, They rise a flight o'er angels. Osbert. Yes, my Osric, The foe who meets the ardour of to-morrow, I think was born when luckless planets ruled. I pant for day—I pant, to shew my people, What deeds their king shall dare in their defence, The first in danger, as the first in office. But I detain thy age from needful rest; Thy couch expects thee—this one warm embrace Shall yield thee till the morning. Osric. First of kings, Thrice valiant Osbert,—may thy future reign Rise, like the coming sun, upon the world, Chearful to man, dispensing light and life! And after a long course of wide beneficence, Retire, when late, to Heaven, and set in glory! [Exit Osric. Enter an Officer. Officer. My liege, as westward we held on our rounds Near the York Minster, we espied a man, Of port majestic, and of shining arms, Dazzling the night. He would have pass'd our guard; And Anulf, Ethelbald, and valiant Oswald, Fell by his arm—At length, by numbers quell'd, He waits your pleasure— Osbert. Give him entrance. Ha!— SCENE II. Enter Westmorland in Chains. A majesty indeed!—though some lorn cloud Appears to have informed his manly brow With well acquainted sorrow!—Say, brave stranger, Who, and whence art thou? Silent!—then, perhaps, Some dear and sacred grief sits heavy on thee, That should not be prophaned by vulgar ears. Leave us together. [Exeunt Guards. Now, declare thyself— And if thou bearest up but to thy seeming, Noble and virtuous, though thou should'st be found My foe profess'd, know Osbert for thy friend. West. Thy foe profess'd!— Osbert. Of Denmark, art thou? West. Yes. Osbert. What—of the powers now banded against Britain? West. A leader. Osbert. Speak thy purpose. West. Thus says the Dane; and what my tongue declares, His scepter ratifies—Not lust of fame, Or empire, bears us to Albion's shore; But justice on a single head—Grant that, And Denmark is your friend. Osbert. Have ye, for this, o'erspread our seas with fleets, Our land with arms? West. We have. Osbert. Name the offender. West. Nay more— We ask, but what by law of arms we warrant— The guilty and the injured, man to man!— The rest let fate decide. Osbert. 'Tis granted, chearfully. West. And surely—is it? Osbert. Yes, if there's truth or honour in the land; In Heaven, or earth, aught binding. West. You will not shrink— Osbert. No—though ourself should answer thy bold summons. Thou hast our faith—I swear it, by my head. West. 'Tis there our vengeance levels! Osbert. Insolent!— And who is he, that dares impeach a monarch? And more presumptuous still, that singly dares, In equal field, to meet the arm of Osbert? West. He stands before you— Osbert. Ha!—thy name? West. 'Tis Westmorland!— A long pause. Now do you know me? Osbert. Westmorland!— Had yawning hell Cast all his fiends upon me—neither depth, Nor height—the universe could not afford A spectre, like thyself, to shake the nerve, And blanch the cheek of Osbert! West. O thou fell tyger, hungry as the grave, Gorged with the lives of innocence and honour!— What can'st thou answer, thou imperial spoiler, To me, thy subject?—now thy slave—in chains— Alone—unarm'd—yet, by thy proper guilt, Exalted as thy judge—an awful judge, To sink thee to perdition! Osbert. I had made— I hoped, I trusted, I had made—my peace On earth, in Heaven!—but, like a baneful blast, A sudden pest, thou art come to wither up All the wide harvest of my ripen'd hopes— Thou plague, thou hell of Osbert! West. Yes— Beyond this life—while there's a place for being— War, hateful, deadly, and determined war, Must be the lot of Westmorland and Osbert! Heaven can't contain us; nor the suffering earth, And keep her elements at peace— The seat of memory is curs'd that holds thee— O I would chase thee to the verge of thought, There push thee off, and blot thee from creation— Though I leapt after! Osbert. Rebel, I thank thee—thou dost well expunge My single fault by thy superior wickedness! To thousands—to thy country false, thou traitor— Who never wrong'd thee!— West. Ha!—yes—it may—it may be so— Devil!—'tis thou hast damn'd me then—Yet, wherefore? The very wren would rouze at such a wrong; Would guard his little nest from violation, And plume himself against the princely eagle! In such a cause, all ways, all means, are lawful— Truth does avouch it—vengeance! it is my food, My thirst—High Heaven, who gave a world to man, Gave it in common—trash not worth contention!— But chastly paled the bridal bed around, With sanctities and honours, whose offence Is deeper than damnation! Osbert. O, thou hast, Thou hast, indeed, been injured—past repeal, Or the world's recompence!—What's to be done? West. The duty of a king— One act of justice—let it mark thy reign— Let not a nation sink for thy transgression!— For once give answer to the call of honour; And as thou hast been ever bold in ill, Be bold for once in honesty! Osbert. O! no— Yes—any other arm but thine—or thine, Though doubled, so thou drop thy dread ally That combats for thee HERE!—O no, I cannot— I will not fight thee!— West. Then, perish Britain, Or cast the tyrant out!—War, pass thy bounds! Range vengeance, wide as air! crush, crush the world, So thou but wrap him in the general ruin!— Art thou, art thou a man—a king—a warrior— A champion, chosen to breast thee to the breach?— And dost thou quail, and skulk behind thy people? Dost thrust the sucking babe, and fear-frozen mother, Betwixt thyself and danger? Osbert. Oh!— West. Thy oath is past, thou must abide the venture. Take arms of vantage, case thee round in steel Of proof impenetrable—give me, but, Naked, defenceless, but to have one stroke, One grapple for the bleeding cause of honour, And I acquit thee—from the first of time, Through all eternity, I seal thy pardon! Osbert. Well—when?—it shall be done!—Thou hast me short, A little short of recollection now— Time soon shall serve—I swear it—arm to arm, Great, injured man!—thou shalt be satisfied. West. Wilt thou?—And I will thank thee in the grave. Osbert. I will— West. Well—hold thee to thy pledge—thy faith—thy manhood— I may expect thee, then— Osbert. Yes—else, may Heaven Stand in thy place for vengeance! An Officer enters. Officer. My liege, the foe approaches, and is now In sight of York— Osbert. Most noble stranger!—for an hour or two, You must consort with patience—Guards, conduct him; And see that he be treated with attention, Becoming princely dignity and honour. [Exeunt Westmorland and Guards. SCENE III. Enter Osric and Edwin, with Citizens. Osric. My lord, they come apace, the storm bends this way! Mine be the walls, mine and the citizens— But haste with Edwin, haste to horse, my liege! Array your soldiers in the square, and hold them Ready to sally on the first advantage. Haste, valiant Osbert! [Exeunt severally. SCENE IV. The Fields before York. A Danish March and Music. Ivar, Hubba, and Soldiers, enter with the Great Raven-Standard of Denmark. Hub. How fair to sight, how chearing to the sense, These fields throw fragrance to the vernal breeze, And greet our soldiers with a sweet salute! Ivar. It is a tempting invitation, Hubba— This favourite isle, this daughter of the gods, Retires with conscious beauty from the world; Like sea-born Venus, rises from the waves, And chastly courts the soldier's arm to clasp her. Hub. Ivar, thus far, the voice of honour calls; And friendship answers to the glorious summons, To pluck oppression from the seat of power, And substitute the injured: 'tis an office, Worthy the delegates of Heaven. Ivar. True, brother. Nor do I grudge Northumbria to her Westmorland, Our brave, unhappy friend—But then, my Hubba, In Britain's heavenly sphere, there are more stars Than gem the crown that Westmorland must wear; Nor can we want a cause, while great ambition, That made a god of Grecian Philip's son, Inspires with equal ardour. Hub. O, beware!— If these your counsels, let your breast conceal them, Nor trust them to the ear of Westmorland. I know how dear he holds his country's health; Nor would I wish his valour for our foe. Think how his arm might sway the scale of Britain! A name is light, yet his outweighs a legion. There's not a Dane throughout your numerous hosts, But looks to him, as to the god of battles; And wears some favour, letter'd with his name, To charm misfortune from them. Soldier enters in haste. Ivar. How now? thy looks speak haste— What tidings, soldier? Sold. O, my sovereign lord! 'Tis rumour'd, that our leader, in the night, Adventuring near the city, was beset, And, all unseconded, is either slain, Or captive now in York. Ivar. The sword of Denmark Shall richly pay his ransom— Now loose the war, impetuous as a flood, And thou hot sun be quench'd, and set in blood. (Sound Trumpets) [Exeunt. SCENE V. The Inside of the Abbey. Rowena and Nuns. Row. Pass but a little time, and all shall be, To every purpose of this present world, As though they had never been!—Build on, projection! Pile, avarice! ambition, scale the clouds!— It is but as a dream of varying fancy; A breath—and all is vanished! Hear me, my children!—List, ye hallow'd virgins, O list, and take my last instructions with ye!— Ha!—did ye mark that groan? 1st Nun. No one is near— Row. Methought it came attended by a voice, That echoed—“Take her last instructions with ye.” 1st Nun. Hark—hark! [Charge, drums and trumpets at a distance. Row. Defend us, Heaven!—the noise of battle!— [They look out. The form of coming war, how dreadful is it!— Wide on the right, no opening spot can shew What ground they tread.—Alas, alas, for York! She cannot stand the shock—her ancient towers Already seem to shake at their approach, And bow to her foundations. [Sound, beat, and clash. 1st Nun. Look!—O look!— Row. Ha!—Yes—the town too issues to the battle— On either part, the kings ride foremost—Now, Now they have mark'd each other for destruction— He's down—the Dane is down!— Now Osbert is unhorsed— O bravely rescued!— And such a fair deliverer! Ha!—'tis my Edwin!—Turn, thou infant warrior, Nor tempt the random blow— Ah, rash, rash boy!— See how he throws himself amid the battle, And makes a mock of danger— O, save him, save him, Heaven!—They gird him in— A child against an army!— He's down, he's down, and I will look no more— What dreadful sounds are these?— [An approaching tumult. See, Edith, see. [A Nun goes out, and instantly returns. 2d Nun. They come—they are at our doors, A band of ruffians!—Save us, madam, save us! Row. Quick, to the gate, fly some one!—make it sure, But for a few short moments—For myself, Blow tempest!—nature, wreck!—it matters not— 'Tis finish'd—I am secure—But, O for these, Thine own devoted—O, or never, now Inspire, thou Living Strength! a wondrous deed, A courage not their own—Say, my sisters, What would ye do, from lust and violation, What dare, from such a lost estate to escape? 1st Nun. Put us to proof. 2d Nun. We dare the last extremes. 3d Nun. Tortures, or death, or worse. Row. One dear embrace— For now we part no more!—and thus, and thus— [Embrace. We bind us to each other, in a knot, More firm than that which winds the world together, For ours is tied in virtue. O, if they yet survive—my child, my husband! In whom my soul lives, feelingly transferr'd Through all their faculties—protect them, Heaven! Quit, quit all care of me, and take the dear ones To your peculiar guardianship! Hark!—for now [The noise approaches nearer. Our trial is at hand—Are ye prepared? [Draws a knife. Nuns. We follow you to death! [The Nuns do the same. Row. And such a death, As should preserve the very life of virtue, [A shout at the door. Were scarce a sin—They come!—Sisters, away!— 'Tis triumph all above, when Virtue wins the day. [Exeunt. END OF THE THIRD ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT IV. SCENE I. Osbert enters. Osbert. What art thou, Time? Thy many ages past, were once to come; And now, are—nothing!—What thou art at present, We cannot, if we would, retain—The morrow! Ah, who would wait the coming of the morrow, But that Hope bears him to some promised bliss, That yesterday ne'er knew!—The morrow comes; And, like its predecessors, merely serves To count our cares—Where's he, who would recall The happiest term of time once past, or wish To plant it in the days of life to come? But what is life to come, where hope comes not?— Rowena, injured sanctity! in thee The world is bankrupt; and for aught that's now Contained beneath yon star-set canopy, I reck not—For the rest—the dread hereafter!— A life of guilt were haply best atoned, So Heaven in mercy warrant, by a death Of justice, and of honour!—Who attends? Enter Officer. Take this seal, soldier—go, and bow thee down Before our noble captive; give him freedom, Arms, and safe conduct to Saint Cyprian's Grove— Say, we have business for a sword like his, And wait him there. [Exeunt severally. SCENE II. Osric and Edwin. Osric. But to be loosed to such ungovern'd sorrow— 'Tis desperation!—'tis the anarchy Of minds o'erthrown, where passions ride aloft, And the fair fields of ripening virtue lie Defaced beneath the tempest! Edwin. Pardon, sir!— I would—I will obey you—are you not My only parent, now?—O, happy father! You lived not to behold this day—the loss Of your child's mother—of your loved Rowena— Of all that earth could boast of Heaven—of all That life could give of joy, or death take from us!— But the cold grave, with its unfeeling shrowd, Now shuts you from the sense.— Osric. Yet, Edwin, yet, She may be safe: they would not, could not perpetrate A deed, of such reproach to manhood—no! Your eyes shall yet behold her. Edwin. Never, never!— O sir, till I beheld her angel-face, I knew not what it was to have a mother. I had laid up, within my fond conception, A thousand promised scenes of joys to come, Delights of filial sweetness; days, and years, Spent in the glad officiousness of duty, Made happy by her smiles—O, mother fair! Why died I not in thy defence? For O, this weak unexecuting arm Was impotent to save thee! Osric. 'Twas Heaven's will— What lay in man to do, thou didst, my Edwin! The king hath summon'd us to council, here— If thou dost prize my safety, dry thy tears, And keep their source a secret. Retire awhile, To calm this storm of overbearing passions. [Exeunt. SCENE III. A Grove. Osbert enters, and walks some time disturb'd. Osbert. My hand, my heart, be firm!—It is a period Of infinite import—a mighty summons!— The voice of equity, the sense of honour, Rouze up the man, the soldier, and the king, To fill the hour with deeds of answering greatness. Heaven take the issue to thine own direction! SCENE IV. Westmorland enters with the Officer. Osbert. My noble friend, most welcome!—You withdraw. [Exit Officer. West. And is it come, the thirsted hour?—O transport! Art thou mine, vengeance?—what! the sacrifice Within the grasp of honour?—Haste, call forth Thy guards— Thy champions chosen to answer to the fire That rages in my heart, thou yet art mine!— Tho' the swift bolt should shoot between us, Osbert! Thou art mine for ever!— Osbert. Be it!—Thou seest I have ta'en no vantage, Westmorland, Of aid, arms, time, or place—fair, equal, all, And secret—Silent, art thou?—then, come on; [Draws. And let us prove the prowess of an arm So far renown'd—if mine betray me not, Thou shalt be well encount'red—What impedes?— For injured honour—for revenge—come on!— West. Amazement holds me—Is it possible!— No vantage, dost thou say—and this right hand Arm'd by thyself against thy proper bosom? 'Tis contradiction to eternal order— Could aught so guilty, be so noble?—No— I wage no war with thee—thou art not Osbert. Osbert. I am—Come on— And rouze thee, like the lion, with the lash Of wrongs, long treasured for the hour of wrath And vengeance due. West. Osbert! Osbert. Say. West. What art thou? Osbert. One, who for a guilty deed, Would make a gallant restitution. West. Yes, yes, you must—O glorious man!—you must— The world impels—fame—honour rolling down Through late posterity, demands it of thee.— O, woe, that present virtue now must bleed, For past transgression!— Osbert. Fall, whate'er may fall, If my nerves tell me right, thou now art summon'd To thy best guardianship—Art thou prepared? West. Not yet—not yet—This greatness, goodness, nobleness, This bounteous satisfaction to your servant, Does it not claim my praise?—it does, it does!— O generous, gallant Osbert, cruel justice Will wring his debt, though pity weep for it! But not till I have paid, thus paid my thanks, My homage, to my lord, my bounteous master! [Kneels, and kisses his hand, then rises and draws. Come on. [They fight. Rest you, my liege!— Osbert. No—fate is busy— And we will know the issue—Now beware— [Osbert is wounded—Westmorland steps back concerned, and Osbert leans upon his sword. West. Alas!— How is it? Osbert. Westmorland!— West. What says my king? Osbert. Thy debt is paid! West. Forbid it, Heaven!—I wish'd not to exact So close a reckoning. Osbert. Thine aspect tells me, I have thy pity—If I have thy pardon, To seal a bless'd oblivion of all injuries, One last embrace! West. O, truly, to my arms, My heart—my king, my gracious master! [Embrace. Osbert. Pardon—full pardon, is it? West. Heaven shower on both a pardon free and full, Like that I grant to Osbert! Osbert. Once, most loved, And ever held in honour—noblest Westmorland! O, had not passions hurried me to deeds, Detested by the doer—what a race Of kindred glory had we run together! West. Alas! the steps that press the paths of error, Are not all thine. Osbert. My brother!—hast thou too had thy faults?— Then lend thine arm to frailty—Let me lean On that forgiving bosom—O, those tears, Those tears, my Westmorland, they fall upon me, Like Heaven's indulgent dew—each drop, of power To wash a stain away!—This signet—take it— Thy passport hence—I had to tell thee much— Of love—of nobleness—o'ercome—yet struggling— A moment—life's no more—It answers not— Sad tidings, too— They had unman'd thee!—thy Rowena is—Oh— [Dies. West. Gone!—art thou gone forever?—Osbert, Osbert!— To kill thee once, I would have given a world; And now would give, thou noblest, first of men! A thousand worlds to have thee back again. [Exit. SCENE V. A Pavilion in the Danish Camp. Ivar, Hubba, and Danish Officers. Hub. O stain to manhood!—'tis a blot, my brother, That covers Denmark!—yes, it is a deed That ties the worth and freshness of our fame To detestation!—What, to wrong a sex, Sacred to arms, and guarded by their weakness— The murder of defenceless women!—Gods, Of virgins too, devoted to your altars! It is a war with Heaven and earth! Ivar. Advise, How may we cast the unworthy imputation From our own honours. Hub. Will you, to your servant, Permit this dear concern? Ivar. Most willingly. Hub. Arnold, be thine the care to seize on all The perpetrators of this deed—to York Convey them—Kenulph, be it thine, From the sad ashes of yon pile to cull The sacred reliques—see them closed in gold, Fit emblem of the purity that pass'd Thro' such a fire!— [Shouts. Ivar. What new alarm?—See, soldier, whence those shouts, That echo through our camp? Enter Officer. Officer. My royal lord! 'Tis said our general approaches, free, And safe, from York. Ivar. How, say'st thou—is it possible? By mighty Thor, he comes!—'tis he— SCENE VI. To them Westmorland enters. Ivar. My friend! Hub. Great father of the war, [Embrace. Most welcome! Free, arm'd, unhurt? West. It is a story, Full of strange accident. Ivar. Come you from York? West. I do—where Osbert fell beneath my hand, In equal combat slain. Ivar. Proclaim it to the Heavens! Sound, sound it, every instrument of triumph! Hail him ye hosts—our general is a king, Northumbria's monarch! Thus let me salute him, With earliest gratulation.— Hub. O, my friend— Soul of all honour!—may thy empire spread Wide as thy worth and glories! West. Thanks to both, And grateful retribution—Ha!— Eyes see amiss—or hence be dark for ever!— Those ruins!—Speak, who burnt the hallow'd pile? Hub. Trust me, my noble friend, we both are guiltless— Both were in battle fallen, when this dire act Of outrage and dishonour was committed. West. O, if Arabia's spicy nest be desolate, Where is my bird, the Phænix of its odours?— Who can inform me?— Ethelwald enters. Ethelwald! Where is thy precious charge, thy mistress?—Silent!— Alas, there's desolation in thine eye!— Speak, I conjure thee—yet, while I have power To ask, or sense to hear thee. Ethel. O, prepare— Prepare to pardon, then, this tongue accurs'd 'Bove all that e'er were doom'd to speak of woe!— Rowena—your Rowena is— West. What?— Ethel. Dead! [Westmorland falls. Ivar. He stirs not.—General! Hub. Most noble Westmorland!— Nor hears.—The tempest-brooding calm is on him; And it may break in violence, self urged Against his precious life. Ivar. Remove his sword. Hub. Down, art thou down?—amid the world's wide forest The stateliest pine o'erthrown!—O conquering grief! Before thee falls, who stood the force of thousands. He moves.—Friend! Ethel. Master! Ivar. Royal Westmorland! [They raise, and seat him on a sopha. West. Alas—the lot of man is frailty! I murmur not, that I was born to suffer— But this was such a stroke!—my heart, to this, Lay quite disarm'd and unprovided!—Ethelwald! Speak, say what envious cruel fiends have brought This sudden night upon us? Ethel. O, my loved lord!—the day was scarce disclosed, When, in contempt of all the powers of Denmark, Bold Osbert sallied forth. Never was field So fought—until, on either part, the chiefs Sore toil'd, or fallen, were carried from the battle! Then, round yon pile, were gather'd, as from hell, The insatiate furies, Cruelty and Lust!— What could Rowena do?—the thunder slept, Nor Heaven descended on the wing to save her.— West. Proceed, proceed—my soul is in thy tidings; And every listening pulse suspends to hear thee! Ethel. When she perceived no help was near, she call'd Her virgin train around her. Straight she drew A knife, now sacred to the cause of virtue, And bade them mark her—Yet, while they beheld That face, whereon, like first created nature, Beauty divine was visibly imprest, At once 'twas chaos all!—her cheeks, her lips, She gash'd, she mangled!—and, to knowledge, now Rowena was no more!— West. Powers immortal!— Ethel. Then rose the daughters of her bright example High o'er their sex, o'er all that e'er was famed In story!—each was a Rowena, now! In rush'd the ruffians—but, when they beheld Beauty to horror turn'd, their boiling lusts Froze inward—back they slunk—but soon return'd, Laden with stubble, and with kindling brands, That caught the pile around—As incense breathed In morning sacrifice direct to Heaven, Rowena, and her train of maiden-saints, Ascended wrapt in flames!—and I but scarce Escaped to bring the tidings. West. Mighty being! Parent of good! for my Rowena, thanks!— You thought I should be troubled—not the least— I never knew an hour of peace like this!— All, all, within, is still, amid the tempest, The wreck of human nature! Ivar. Your looks are much disturb'd—Retire, my friend. West. Is the king come?—are all our friends invited? Sit, sit!— Sound trumpets, bear the triumph of my joys Upon the chariot of the air, to Heaven, And tell them, 'tis the bridal day of Westmorland! Mark ye, the king looks sad—I cannot blame him— What, what is empire, to a bride like mine!— See where she sits, the queen of health and beauty Dealing out joys, as plenteous as the spring Throws odours to the breeze!—Approach not, friends, Lest you be lost, like me, beneath her charms— Her sweets oppress! they grow too mighty for me! Joys insupportable!— Ivar. Help, bear him forward. How strong this passion shakes him! West. Osbert, thy hand—ruin hath reconciled us— What a dark journey do we go together!— Ha, who are these?—their hands are weighty on me! O, treacherous Danes!— I have lost my powers—they bind me to a rock— See, see the Magic Raven, how he plumes!— How he prepares his beak!—Ungrateful bird!— I, who have fed him with the spoil of nations, Am now become his prey— Loose me—he searches to my inmost bosom— He tears my heart—he gorges up my vitals! [Faints. Hub. Alas! and is our Denmark so accurs'd, There to bring ruin where she meant to rescue? Ivar. Soft, he revives; his eye is more composed.— How fares our friend? West. O, ye have kindly brought the dawn about me— Reason's returning beam, to guide our passage; The sun, that lights this little world of man.— Patience, good Heaven!—I will abide your pleasure. Hub. Unhappy, honoured, injured Westmorland! What shall your afflicted suppliants plead, In mitigation of your just displeasure? Here are our swords—and, if thou canst not pardon, At least revenge!— West. No—take them back—Alas! I am, myself, the frail one of my kind, The very child of error—There is, yet, One suit wherein I'd move ye. Hub. Say on, and think your will but told again In our obedience. West. Thus it is—Since things, By some o'erruling hand, have turn'd averse To my soul's purpose; and that I, once deem'd My country's guardian, shall in story now Be held a traitor to her peace—I would Hence forward spare the expence of blood—To York Dispatch your herald— And challenge forth whoe'er, in single fight, Shall stand his country's hope. Ourself will meet him, And these the high conditions—If we conquer, The gift of fair Northumbria's scepter, then, Is left at our dispose—but if, and who Shall bar Almighty Pleasure?—if I fall, You swear to abdicate her throne for ever, And leave the land in peace. Ivar. It shall be done. Say, is there aught beside? West. Not now. I feel A drowsy weight steal o'er my travel'd soul. Ivar. Adieu! Hub. May all The peace that rests with virtue, aid your slumbers! [Exeunt all but Westmorland. West. False Danes! I know ye now—those ruins!—Soft, That runs again to madness—O, these fields, These fields of blood, whence are they?—is it Westmorland That brought such carnage on his country?—How, How does that feel!— This host of fiends I have conjured up—but how To quell them—there's the task!—to lay the hurricane That wrecks thy peace, fair Albion! My country, fear no more from my hostility— Send but a toilet-champion to the field, And to his stainless sword this breast shall be As passable as air! [Reposes on the sopha, and the scene closes. SCENE VII. Funeral Procession, and Dirge. I. Wretched mortals, doom'd to go Through the vale of death and woe! Let us travel sad and slow. II. Care and Sickness, Toil and Pain, Here their restless vigils keep: Sighs are all the winds that blow, Tears are all the streams that flow! Virtue hopes reward in vain— The gentlest lot she can obtain, Is but to sit and weep! III. Ye dreary mansions of enduring sleep, Where pale mortality lies dark and deep! Thou silent, though insatiate Grave, Gorged with the beauteous and the brave, Close, close thy maw—thy feast is o'er, Time and death can give no more! IV. In Rowena thou hast Thy consummate repast! All that earth could boast divine, All we held of Heaven is thine! Time and death no more can gain— They have all perfection slain! O Grave, thy festival is o'er; The beggar'd world can give no more! Song of Consolation. I. Ye desolate mortals who stray, Dark, devious, and wilfully blind; O turn, and distinguish the way That leads to the bliss of mankind! The titles ye falsely assign, With their symbols are ever at strife; And death by appointment divine, Is our birth and our portal to life. II. The Framer of Nature from chaos and night, Who drew yon fair system of order and light, On extremes hath the plan of his universe built, On frailty perfection, and pardon on guilt; And through the short transience of death and of pain, Appoints human weakness to rise and to reign. CHORUS. 'Tis Virtue, 'tis Virtue, o'er grief and the grave, That rises secure, and sublime; The prize that Eternity watches to save From the wrecks and the ruins of time! END OF THE FOURTH ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT V. SCENE I. The Lists, between the Camp and the Town. Ivar and Hubba, with Danish Officers and Soldiers. Ivar. I see they do accept our summons.—Say, Are hostages exchanged? Officer. They are, my liege. Ivar. And all due ceremonials else performed? Officer. Duly performed. SCENE II. Enter Osric with British Lords and Officers. Osric. Princes of Denmark, hail!—I will not ask, Wherefore your warlike visitation—No— The mighty never want a cause for quarrel. I hold me to this question—do ye vouch The message of your herald? Ivar. Yes. Osric. Repeat it. Ivar. If Heaven shall bless our champion's arm with conquest, The gift of fair Northumbria's scepter, then, Is left at our dispose—If Denmark fall, We swear to abdicate your throne for ever, And leave your land in peace. Osric. We do accept you—but with this addition, That they whose champion falls this day in battle, That instant quit the field. Ivar. Agreed. Osric. Then let us march without the lists, and there Affirm the compact with our mutual sanction. Heralds, prepare the field—call in the champions, And hold them ready, at the trumpet's sound, To fix a nation's fate. [Exeunt. Enter Westmorland. West. If death should be no more than so—to loose The care-stretch'd rack of thought—to sink at once In sweet oblivion—'tis the hope—the Heaven, That Guilt sighs after!—Close these eyes—but shut Their living telescope—and all is darkness!— Let death but shut the world from every sense, The soul—what then of her?—when the hearing, Sight, touch, and taste, her wonted ministers Of light, of knowledge, and of action, perish; What is it then that wins yon distant worlds, And takes the rounds of varying nature in?— The eye?—O no—'tis dark amid the noon, Till the bright soul, its animating guest, Look from the lids, and waken to perception. It is the soul that sees, then—and this eye Is but her glass occasional, to view This outward world, perhaps not obvious else: But let her forth from this her prison house, She springs upon new worlds, whose light is life, To which the sun is darkness!—Then existence Is sure—but whether, or for bliss or woe?— Be it—Heaven's will is best—and bounty wide, Where there is least to merit. SCENE IV. Edwin enters on the other side: he walks slowly by, and looks stedfastly on Westmorland. West. Sweet youth!—Say, wherefore am I singled out, To stand within thy gaze? Edwin. Because, till now, I have scarce beheld the presence of a man; And joy that fame must wait upon my fall, When dignified by you. West. Good Heavens!—art thou, Art thou my fell antagonist?—Fair flower, Avoid my cruel frost!—Retire, my child, Nor break thy mother's heart! Edwin. Intend you this, In scorn, or in compassion? West. Both—but most In anger, that the British sons of war Should send their stripling, their Adonis forth, Where their best power would shrink. Edwin. Your cause is weak, Tho' strong your arm—so are we better weigh'd, Where justice, to my weaker arm, has join'd A cause invincible—My injured country Already fits triumphant on my sword; And lifts the last, the lowest of her sons, O'er thee, the first in Denmark! West. Child of glory! Happy the boastful climate of thy birth! And thy glad parents—thrice, thrice blest are those Of whom thou wert begotten!—Had'st thou, Heaven, Ordain'd a son, one son like this to Westmorland, His latest hour had blest thee, and been happy. Edwin. Have you no son? West. I have. Edwin. How blest were I, To be that child, and kneel to thee, my father! West. Reach me that valiant hand—Had fate not doom'd That one of us, this hour, must fall in battle; O, I had held thee at my heart, as near As is the blood that warms it.—Of Northumbria Art thou? Edwin. I am. West. I too am Britain-born. Enter an English and a Danish Herald. Eng. Her. The princes, valiant combatants, salute you; And round the panting barrier thousands wait, Whose fate receives decision from your arms. Dan. Her. Sound trumpets, sound the charge! [Exeunt Heralds—Trumpets sound—Edwin draws. Edwin. O, honour'd chief!—tho' my dear country lifts This sword impulsive on thee; yet, I feel, 'Twould be more grateful turn'd upon myself— Less wounding far, than pointed at thy bosom!— Come, come on! West. Soul truly noble!—This to prove thy force. [Fight. Edwin. Unworthy triumph—barbarous man!—that stroke You took defenceless!— West. It is accomplish'd!—Yes, thou glorious youth, We both have reach'd our wish—I came to die, And thou to conquer! Edwin. Ah, what mystery? West. But that the icey hand of death is on me, I could unfold—My friend will tell thee all, The noble Manchester— Edwin. Thy friend?—Great powers! West. Draw near—Thou hast a heart replete with greatness: If thou dost hope to wed some heavenly maid, To be as blest as once was Westmorland, Lay me, O lay me with the dear remains Of my loved angel, my triumphant wife, My deified Rowena!— Edwin. Thine! what—thine! West. Thou seem'st amazed. Edwin. If dead men rise to life, Thou art— West. Ha! what? Edwin. Thy son—his name was— West. Edwin. Edwin. My father!—O my father, my dear father!— Curs'd hour, curs'd hand!—O sir—O first of men! Give me that wound, if you would have me happy— Lost, ruin'd Edwin!—lost, undone for ever! West. Art thou my son, then?—my Rowena's child?— Thy goodness, Heaven! it is too mighty for me— Come to my arms—close—press into my heart!— [Embraces. Hold off, and let me gaze again upon thee! Thou art, thou art my son, my joy, my rapture, My better self—thy country's Westmorland!— Why dost thou weep?—by honour's holy bands, I swear I would not change this day for ages— This glorious day, wherein thy sire is made Triumphant o'er himself! Edwin. My father!—Oh— Those too kind words go pointed through my bosom— They reach at life; and sacred nature lies O'erthrown, and bleeds her last— West. Thy hand, young hero—child of honour, help me! [Sinks down. SCENE V. Enter Osric. Osric. Health to our champion! to his arm for ever, Success like this—and be his living name The first in Britain's story!—Silence!—tears!— Whence, wherefore? Edwin. O—touch not this parricide!— Your friend!—my father!—look, O look, where bleeds The lord of lost Rowena! Osric. Westmorland! What, Westmorland?—The powers! West. As I do think—my friend, The noble Manchester! Osric. Help there, in haste!—Fate, fate, thou art Almighty!— Strength, honour, prowess! what is now your boast, When prostrate thus your mighty one is fallen, When here lies Westmorland?—Help, bear him gently, [Soldiers bring in a chair. So—there—How fare you? West. As a lonely man, Unskill'd to steer his course, just launched from shore, And never to return.—O gentle Manchester, Through what a wondrous whirl of varying fortunes, Thy friend has past, this day—a lover blest— A captive—then a conqueror—then a king— And now, what thou beholdest here!—Ethelwald, My faithful Ethelwald will tell thee all— O, I have been to blame—too late, my brother, I saw, and would repeal—but deeds were done— And fate refused to cancel—What remain'd, But to atone in part?—The Dane was false— And thus, to bind his fate, I chose to perish, A victim to the land my life had injured!— My words grow painful—Noble, noble Manchester, Regard thy gracious son— No more—I faint!— Osric. Alas, my friend! Edwin. My father!— West. My spirit returns—the aspiring lamp of life Brightens its latest blaze—I see, they come, Again they come, the invaders of Northumbria! Treaties—leagues—what are ye?—O my country, How art thou waste!—Fair Albion, land of beauty! Owls build within thy lonely palaces, And weeds o'ergrow thy pavements!—Ha, he comes!— My child, the star of Britain, Edwin comes!— I see, like lightning, he divides the night— He darts, he rushes on them—Ho, for Freedom!— Down with the traitorous pair—the Magic Standard, Grasp it, 'tis thine!—Respiring Liberty, Justice, and golden Commerce, how ye walk, And brighten o'er the land!—Release me—oh!— Pardon I feel is past above—more—more— Wondrous, unspeakable!—I come—and leave This lesson to the world—that Heaven is all, And man is—nothing!—Oh! [Dies.</field>
   </doc>
</add>