<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Shirley, James, 1596-1666</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Shirley, James, 1596-1666</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">shirley james 1596 1666</field>
      <field name="author_text">Shirley, James, 1596-1666</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">17th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V1.0238.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1653</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:458994</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Cardinall</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 17th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 17th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Cardinall</field>
      <field name="title_facet">cardinall</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">cardinall</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Cardinall</field>
      <field name="year_display">1653</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1653</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1653</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:458994&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:458994&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Shirley, James, 1596-1666&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;shirley james 1596 1666&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Cardinall&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;cardinall&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1653&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1653&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Shirley, James&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1596&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1666&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Cardinall&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for Humphrey Robinson ... and Humphrey Moseley [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1653&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3871633-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv10238&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 17th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;17th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Cardinall&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 188 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted.&lt;lb/&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: The cardinal.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1653.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 1641 ?&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE CARDINAL, A TRAGEDIE</field>
      <field name="fulltext">To my worthily honored Friend G. B. Esq;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Prologue. The Cardinal, 'cause we express no scene, We doe believe most of you Gentlemen Are at this hour in France, and busie there, Though you vouchsafe to lend your bodies here; But keep your fancy active, till you know By th'progress of our Play, 'tis nothing so; A Poets art is to lead on your thought Through subtle paths and workings of a plot, And where your expectation does not thrive, If things fall better, yet you may forgive; I will say nothing positive, you may Think what you please, we call it but a Play, Whether the comick Muse, or Ladies love, Romance, or direfull Tragedy it prove, The Bill determines not; and would you be Perswaded, I would have't a Comedie, For all the purple in the name, and state Of him that owns it; but 'tis left to fate; Yet I will tell you e'r you see it plaid, What the Author, and he blusht too, when he said (Comparing with his own for't had been pride He thought, to build his wit a Pyramyde Vpon anothers wounded Fame,) this Play Might rivall with his best, and dar'd to say— Troth I am out; he said no more; you then, When'ts done, may say your pleasures Gentlemen.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">To the surviving Honour and Ornament of the English Scene, Iames Shirley. As Fate, which doth all human matters sway, Makes proudest things grow up into decay; And when they are to envyed greatness grown, She wantonly falls off, and throws them down: So, when our English Dramma was at hight, And shin'd, and rul'd with Majesty and might, A sudden whirlwind threw it from it seat, Deflowr'd the Groves, and quench'd the Muses heat. Yet as in Saints, and Martyr'd bodies, when They cannot call their blessed Souls agen To earth; Reliques, and ashes men preserve, And think they do, but what, blest they deserve: So I, by my devotion led, aspire To keep alive your noble Vestal fire, Honour this piece, which shews, Sir, you have been The last supporter of the dying Scene; And though I do not tell you, how you dress Virtue in gloryes, and bold vice depress; Nor celebrate your lovely Dutchess fall, Or the just ruine of your Cardinal; Yet this I dare assert, when men have nam'd Iohnson (the Nations Laureat,) the fam'd Beaumont, and Fletcher, he, that wo'not see Shirley, the fourth, must forfeit his best ey.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Persons. King of Navarre. Cardinal. Columbo, the Cardinals Nephew. Alvarez. Hernando, a Colonel. Alphonso. Lords. Secretary to the Dutchess. Colonels Antonelli, the Cardinals Servant. Surgion. Guard. Attendants, &amp;c. Dutchess Rosaura: Valeria, Lady. Celinda, Lady. Placentia, a Lady that waits upon the Dutchess.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Scene Navarre.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. Enter two Lords (at one door) Secretary (at the other.) 1 Lord. Who is that? 2 Lo. The Dutchess Secretary. 1 Lo. Signior. Secr. Your Lordships Servant. 1 Lo. How does her Grace since she left her mourning For the young Duke Mendoza, whose timeless death At Sea, left her a Virgin and a Widdow? 2 Lo. Shee's now inclining to a second Bride, When is the day of mighty mariage To our great Cardinals Nephew, Don Columbo? Secr. When they agree; they wo'not steal to Church, I guess the ceremonies will be loud, and publick. Your Lordships will excuse me. Exit. 1 Lo. When they agree? alas poor Lady, she Dotes not upon Columbo, when she thinks Of the young Count D'Alvarez, divorc'd from her By the Kings power. 2 Lo. And Counsell of the Cardinal to advance His Nephew to the Dutchess bed; 'tis not well. 1 Lo. Take heed, the Cardinal holds intelligence With every bird i'th' air. 2 Lo. Death on his purple pride, He governs all, and yet, Columbo is A gallant Gentleman. 1 Lo. The darling of the War, whom Victory Hath often courted; a man of daring And mostexalted spirit, pride in him Dwels like an ornament, where so much honour Secures his praise. 2 Lo. This is no argument He should usurp, and wear Alvarez title To the fair Dutchess, men of coarser blood Would not so tamely give this treasure up. 1 Lo. Although Columbos name is great in war, Whose glorious art and practice is above The greatness of Alvarez, yet he cannot Want soul, in whom alone survives the virtue Of many noble Ancestors, being the last Of his great family 2 Lo. 'Tis not safe, you'l say, to wrastle with the King. 1 Lo. More danger if the Cardinal be displeas'd, Who sits at helm of State; Count D'Alvarez Is wiser to obey the stream, than by Insisting on his privilege to her love, Put both their fates upon a storm. 2 Lo. If Wisdom, not inborn Fear make him compose, I like it; how does the Dutchess bear herself? 1 Lo. She moves by the rapture of another wheel That must be obey'd; like some sad passenger, That looks upon the coast his wishes fly to, But is transported by an adverse wind, sometimes A churlish Pilot. 2 Lo. She has a sweet and noble nature. 1 Lo. That commends Alvarez, Hymen cannot tie A knot of two more equall hearts and blood. Enter Alphonso. 2 Lo. Alphonso? Alph. My good Lord. 1 Lo. What great affair Hath brought you from the confines? Alp. Such as will Be worth your counsells, when the King hath read My Letters from the Governour; the Arragonians, Violating their confederate oath and league, Are now in arms; they have not yet marcht towards us, But 'tis not safe to expect if we may timely Prevent Invasion 2 Lo. Dare they be so insolent? 1 Lo. This storm I did foresee. 2 Lo. What have they, but the sweetness of the King, To make a crime? 1 Lo. But how appears the Cardinal At this news? Alp. Not pale, although He knows they have no cause to think him innocent, As by whose Counsell they were once surpriz'd. 1 Lo. There is more Than all our present art can fathome in This story, and I fear I may conclude, This flame has breath at home to cherish it; Ther's treason in some hearts, whose faces are Smooth to the State. Alp. My Lords, I take my leave. 2 Lo. Your friends good Captain. Exeunt. Enter Dutchess, Valeria, Celinda. Val. Sweet Madam be less thoughtfull, this obedience To passion, will destroy the noblest frame Of beauty that this Kingdom ever boasted. Cel. This sadness might become your other habit, And ceremonious black for him that died; The times of sorrow are expir'd, and all The joys that wait upon the Court, your birth, And a new Hymen that is coming towards you, Invite a change. Dut. Ladies, I thank you both, I pray excuse a little melancholy That is behind, my year of mourning hath not So cleer'd my account with sorrow, but there may Some dark thoughts stay, with sad reflections, Upon my heart for him I lost; even this New dress, and smiling garment, meant to shew A peace concluded twixt my grief and me, Is but a sad remembrance: but I resolve To entertain more pleasing thoughts, and if You wish me heartily to smile, you must Not mention grief, not in advice to leave it; Such Counsells open but afresh the wounds Ye would close up; and keep alive the cause, Whose bleeding you would cure; lets talk of something That may delight; you two are read in all The Histories of our Court; tell me Valeria, Who has thy vote for the most handsome man? Thus I must counterfeit a peace, when all Within me is at mutiny. Val. I have examin'd All that are Candidates for the praise of Ladies. But find—may I speak boldly to your Grace? And will you not return it in your mirth, To make me blush? Dut. No, no; speak freely. Val. I wo' not rack your patience Madam, but Were I a Princess, I should think Count D'Alvarez Had sweetness to deserve me from the world. Dut. Alvarez! shee's a spy upon my heart. Val. Hee's young, and active and compos'd most sweetly. Dut. I have seen a face more tempting. Val. It had then Too much of woman in't, his eys speak movingly Which may excuse his voice, and lead away All female pride his captive; His hair Black, Which naturally falling into curl's— Dut. Prethee no more, thou art in love with him. The man in your esteem Celinda now? Cel. Alvarez is (I must confess) a Gentleman Of handsome composition, but with His mind (the greater excellence) I think Another may delight a Lady more, If man be well considered, that's Columbo, Now, Madam, voted to be yours. Dut. My Torment! Val. She affects him not. Cel. He has person, and a bravely beyond All men that I observe. Val. He is a Souldier, A rough-hewn man, and may shew well at distance; His talk will fright a Lady; War, and grim- Fac'd-honor are his Mistrisses; he raves To hear a Lute; Love meant him not his Priest. Again your pardon Madam; we may talk, But you have art to choose and crown affection. Dut. What is it to be born above these Ladies And want their freedom? they are not constrain'd, Nor slav'd by their own greatness, or the Kings; But let their free hearts look abroad, and choose By their own eys to love; I must repair My poor afflicted bosome, and assume The privilege I was born with; which now prompts me To tell the King he hath no power nor art To steer a Lovers Soul. Enter Secretary. What says Count D'Alvares? Sec. Madam hee'l attend you. Dut. Wait you as I directed, when he comes Acquaint me privately. Sec. Madam, I have news, 'Tis now arriv'd the Court, we shall have wars. Dut. I find an Army here of killing thoughts. Sec. The King has chosen Don Columbo General, Who is immediately to take his leave. Dut. What flood is let into my heart! how far Is he to go? Sec. To Arragon. Dut. That's well At first, he should not want a pilgrimage To the unknown World, if my thoughts might convey him. Sec. Tis not impossible he may go thither. Dut. How? Sec. To the unknown other World, he goes to fight, That's in his way, such stories are in nature. Dut. Conceal this news. Sec. He wo'not be long absent; The affair will make him swift to kiss your Graces hand. Dut. He cannot flie With too much wing to take his leave; I must Be admitted to your conference; ye have Enlarg'd my spirits, they shall droop no more. Cel. We are happy, if we may advance one thought To your Graces pleasure. Val. Your ey before was in eclipse, these smiles Become you Madam. Dut. I have not skill to contain my self. Enter Placentia. Pla. The Cardinals Nephew, Madam, Don Columbo. Dut. Already? attend him. Ex. Plac. Val. Shall we take our leave? Dut. He shall not know Valeria how you prais'd him. Val. If He did, Madam, I should have the confidence To tell him my free thoughts. Enter Columbo. Dut. My Lord, while I'm in study to requite The Favour you ha' done me, you increase My debt to such a sum, still by a new honouring Your servant, I despair of my own freedom. Cel. Madam, he kisseth your white hand, that must Not surfet in this happiness—and Ladies, I take your smiles for my encouragement: I have not long to practise these Court tacticks. Cel. He has been taught to kiss. Dut. Ther's something, Sir, Upon your brow I did not read before. Col. Does the Character please you Madam? Dut. More, Because it speaks you cheerfull. Col. 'Tis for such Access of honour, as must make Columbo Worth all your love; the King is pleas'd to think Me fit to lead his Army. Dut. How, an Army? Col. We must not use the Priest, till I bring home Another triumph, that now staies for me To reap it in the purple field of glory. Dut. But do you mean to leave me, and expose Your self to the devouring war? no enemy Should Divide us; the King is not so cruell. Col. The King is honourable, and this grace More answers my ambition, than his gift Of thee, and all thy beauty, which I can Love, as becomes thy Souldier, and fight She weeps. To come agen, a conqueror of thee; Then I must chide this fondnesse. Enter Secretary. Sec. Madam, the King, and my Lord Cardinal. Enter King, Cardinall, and Lords. King. Madam, I come to call a Servant from you, And strengthen his excuse; the publick cause Will plead for your consent; at his return Your mariage shall receive triumphant ceremonies; Till then you must dispence. Card. She appears sad To part with him, I like it fairly Nephew. Val. Is not the General a gallant man? What Lady would deny him a small courtesie? Cel. Thou hast converted me, and I begin To wish it were no sin. Val. Leave that to narrow Consciences. Cel. You are pleasant. Val. But he would please one better. Do such men Lie with their Pages? Cel. Would'st thou make a shift? Val. He is going to a bloody business; 'Tis pity he should dye without some heir; That Lady were hard-hearted now that would Not help posterity, for the meer good O'th' King and Common-wealth. Cel. Thou art wild, we may be observ'd. Dut. Your will must guide me, happiness and conquest Be ever waiting on his sword. Col. Farewell. Ex. K. Col. Card Lo. Dut. Pray give leave to examine a few thoughts; Expect me in the Garden. Ladies We attend. Ex. Ladies. Dut. This is above all expectation happy; Forgive me virtue that I have dissembled, And witness with me, I have not a thought To tempt or to betray him, but secure The promise I first made to love and honour. Enter Secretary. Sec. The Count D'Alvarez Madam. Dut. Admit him, And let none enterrupt us; how shall I Behave my looks? the guilt of my neglect, Which had no seal from hence, will call up blood To write upon my cheeks the shame and story In some red Letter. Enter D'Alvarez. D'Alv. Madam, I present One that was glad to obey your Grace, and come To know what your commands are. Dut. Where I once Did promise love, a love that had the Power And office of a Priest to chain my heart To yours, it were injustice to command. D'Alv. But I can look upon you Madam, as Becomes a servant, with as much humility, (In tenderness of your honor and great fortune,) Give up, when you call back your bounty, all that Was mine, as I had pride to think them favours. Dut. Hath love taught thee no more assurance in Our mutuall vows, thou canst suspect it possible, I should revoke a promise made to heaven And thee so soon? this must arise from some Distrust of thy own Faith. D'Alv. Your Graces pardon To speak with freedom, I am not so old In cunning to betray, nor young in time Not to see when, and where I am at loss, And how to bear my fortune, and my wounds, Which if I look for health must still bleed inward, (A hard and desperate condition;) I am not ignorant your birth and greatness, Have plac'd you to grow up with the Kings grace, And jealousie, which to remove, his power Hath chosen a fit object for your beauty To shine upon, Columbo his great fvavorite; I am a man, on whom but late the King Has pleas'd to cast a beam, which was not meant To make me proud, but wisely to direct, And light me to my safety. Oh, Dear Madam! I will not call more witness of my love (If you will let me still give it that name) Than this, that I dare make my self a loser, And to your will give all my blessings up; Preserve your greatness and forget a trifle, That shall at best when you have drawn me up, But hang about you like a cloud, and dim The glories you are born to. Dut. Misery Of birth and state! that I could shift into A meaner blood, or find some art to purge That part which makes my veins unequall; yet Those nice distinctions have no place in us, Ther's but a shadow difference, a title, Thy stock partakes as much of noble sap As that which feeds the root of Kings, and he That writes a Lord, hath all the essence of Nobility. D'Alv. 'Tis not a name that makes Our separation, the Kings displeasure Hangs a portent to fright us, and the matter That feeds this exhalation is the Cardinals Plot to advance his Nephew; then Columbo, A man made up for some prodigious Act, Is fit to be considered; in all three There is no character you fix upon But has a form of ruine to us both. Dut. Then you do look on these with fear. D'Alv. With eys That should think tears a duty to lament Your least unkind fate; but my youth dares boldly Meet all the tyranny o'th' stars, whose black Malevolence but shoot my single tragedy; You are above the value of many worlds Peopled with such as I am. Dut. What if Columbo Engag'd to war, in his hot thirst of honor, Find out the Way to death? D'Alv. Tis possible. Dut. Or say, no matter by what art or motive He gives his title up, and leave me to My own Election? D'Alv. If I then be happy To have a name within your thought, there can Be nothing left to crown me with New blessing; But I dream thus of heaven, and wake to find My amorous soul a mockery; when the Priest Shall tie you to another, and the joys Of mariage leave no thought at leasure to Look back upon Alvarez, that must wither For loss of you, yet then I cannot lose So much of what I was, once in your favour, But in a sigh pray still you may live happy. Exit. Dut. My Heart is in a mist, some good star smile Upon my resolution, and direct Two lovers in their chast embrace to meet; Columbo's bed contains my winding sheet. Exit.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. Enter General Columbo, Hernando, two Colonels, Alphonso, two Captains, and other Officers, As at a Councell of War. Columbo. I see no face in all this Councell, that Hath one pale fear upon't though we arriv'd not So timely to secure the Town, which gives Our enemy such triumph. 1 Colo. 'Twas betraid Alp. The wealth of that one City Will make the enemy glorious. 1 Colo. They dare not plunder it. Alp. They give fair quarter yet, They only seal up mens Estates, and keep Possession for the Cities use, they take up No wares without security, and he Whose single credit will not pass, puts in Two leane comrades, upon whose bonds tis not Religion to deny 'em. Colu. To repair this With honour Gentlemen? Her. My opinion is To expect a while. Colu. Your reason? Her. Till their own Surfet betray 'em, for their Souldier Bred up with coarse and common bread, will shew Such appetites on the rich cates they find, They will spare our swords a victory, when their own Riot and Luxury destroys 'em. 1 Colo. That Will shew our patience too like a fear. With favour of his excellence I think, The spoil of Cities takes not off the courage, But doubles it on Souldiers; besides, While we have tameness to expect, the noise Of their success and plenty will encrease Their Army. Her. 'Tis considerable, we do not Exceed in Foot or Horse, our Muster not 'Bove sixteen thousand both; and the Infantry Raw, and not disciplin'd to act. Alp. Their hearts, But with a brave thought of their Countries honour, Will teach 'em how to fight, had they not seen A Sword; but we decline our own too much, The men are forward in their arms, and take The use with Avarice of Fame. [They rise and talk privately. Colu. Colonell. I do suspect you are a coward. Her. Sir. Colu. Or else a traytor, take your choice, no more, I calld you to a Councell Sir, of war, Yet keep your place. Her. I have worn other names. Colu. Deserve 'em, such Another were enough to unsoul an Army; Ignobly talk of patience till they drink And reel to death? we came to fight and force 'em To mend their pace; thou hast no honour in thee, Not enough noble blood to make a blush For thy tame Eloquence. Her. My Lord, I know My duty to a Generall, yet there are Some that have known me here; Sir, I desire To quit my regiment. Colu. You shall have licence. Ink and paper.— Enter with Paper and Standish. 1 Col. The General's displeas'd. 2 Colo. How is't Hernando? Her. The Generall has found out employment for me, He is writing Letters back. Al Cap. To his Mistress. Her. Pray do not trouble me, yet prethee speak, And flatter not thy friend, dost think I dare Not draw my sword, and use it, when cause With honour calls to action? Al. Colo. With the most valiant man alive. Her. You'l do me some displeasure in your loves, Pray to your places. Colu. So, Bear those Letters to the King, It speaks my resolution before Another Sun decline to charge the enemy. Her. A pretty Court way Of di missing an Officer, I obey; success Attend your Counsells. Exit. Colu. If here be any dare not look on danger, And meet it like a man with scorn of death, I beg his absence, and a cowards fear Consume him to a ghost. 1 Colo. None such here. Colu. Or if in all your Regiments you find One man that does not ask to bleed with honour, Give him a double pay to leave the Army; Ther's service to be done, will call the spirits And aid of Men. 1 Colo. You give us all new flame. Colu. I am confirm'd, and you must lose no time; The Souldier that was took last night, to me Discover'd their whole strength, and that we have A party in the town; the River that Opens the City to the West unguarded; We must this night use art and resolutions, We cannot fall ingloriously. 1 Capt. That voice is every mans. Enter Souldier, and Secretary With a Letter. Colu. What now? Soul. Letters. Colu. Whence? Soul. From the Dutchess. Colu. They are welcome; Meet at my Tent again this evening; yet stay, Some Wine—The Dutchess health— See it go round. Sec. It wo'not please his Excellence. 1 Colo. The Dutchess health. 2 Cap. To me! more wine. Sec. The Clouds are gathering, and his eys shoot fire; Observe what thunder follows. 2 Cap. The Generall has but ill news, I suspect The Dutchess sick, or else the King. 1 Cap. May be the Cardinal. 2 Cap. His soul has long been look'd for. Colu. She dares not be so insolent! it is The Dutchess hand; how am I shrunk in Fame To be thus plaid withall? she writes, and counsels, Under my hand to send her back a free Resigne of all my interest to her person, Promise, or love; that ther's no other way With safety of my honour to revisit her. The woman is possest with some bold Devil, And wants an exorcism; or I am grown A cheap, dull, phlegmatick fool, a Post that's carv'd I'th' common street, and holding out my forehead To every scurrill wit to pin disgrace And libells on't; did you bring this to me Sir? My thanks shall warm your heart. [Draws a Pistoll. Sec. Hold, hold, my Lord. I know not what provokes this tempest, but Her Grace ne'r shew'd more freedom from a storm When I receiv'd this paper; if you have A will to do an execution, Your looks without that engin, Sir, may serve. I did not like the employment. Colu. Ha, had she No symptome in her eye, or face, of anger When she gave this in charge? Sec. Serene, as I Have seen the morning rise upon the spring, No trouble in her breath, but such a wind As came to kiss and fan the smiling flowers. Colu. No Poetry. Sec. By all the truth in prose, By honesty, and your own honour Sir, I never saw her look more calm, and gentle. Colu. I am too passionate, you must forgive me; I have found it out, the Dutchess loves me dearly, She exprest a trouble in her when I took My leave, and chid me with a sullen ey; 'Tis a device to hasten my return; Love has a thousand arts; I'l answer it, Beyond her expectation, and put Her soul to a noble test; your patience Gentlemen; The Kings health will deserve a sacrifice of Wine. Sec. I am glad to see this change, and thank my wit For my redemption. 1 Col. Sir. The Souldiers curse on him loves not our Master. 2 Col. And they curse loud enough to be heard. 2 Cap. Their curse has the nature of Gunpowder. Sec. They do not pray with half the noise. 1 Col. Our Generall is not well mixt, He has too great a portion of fire. 2 Col. His Mistris cool him, her complexion Carries some phlegm, when they two meet in bed? 2 Cap. A third may follow. 1 Cap. 'Tis much pity. The young Duke liv'd not to take the virgin off. 1 Col. 'Twas the Kings act to match two Rabbet suckers. 2 Col. A common trick of State, The little great man marries, travells then Till both grow up; and dies when he should do The feat; these things are still unlucky On the male side. Colv. This to the Dutchess fair hand. Sec. She will think Time hath no wing, till I return. Colu. Gentlemen, Now each man to his quarter, and encourage The Souldier; I shall take a pride to know Your diligence, when I visit all your Severall commands. Omnes. We shall expect, 2 Col. And move by your directions. Colu. Y'are all noble. Exeunt. Enter Cardinal, Dutchess, Placentia. Card. I shall perform a visit dayly, Madam, In th'absence of my Nephew, and be happy If you accept my care. Dut. You have honour'd me, And if your entertainment have not been Worthy your Graces person, 'tis because Nothing can reach it in my power; but where There is no want of zeal, other defect Is only a fault to exercise your mercy. Card. You are bounteous in all; I take my leave; My fair Neece, shortly, when Columbo has Purchas'd more honours to prefer his name, And value to your noble thoughts; mean time Be confident you have a friend, whose Office, And favour with the King, shall be effectuall To serve your Grace. Dut. Your own good deeds reward you, Till mine rise equall to deserve their benefit. Exit Cardinal. Leave me a while. Exit Placen. Do not I walk upon the teeth of serpents; And, as I had a charm against their poyson, Play with their stings, the Cardinal is subtle? Whom tis not wisdom to incense, till I Hear to what destinie Columbo leaves me; May be the greatness of his soul will scorn To own what comes with murmur, If he can Interpret me so happily; art come? Enter Secretary with a Letter. Sec. His Excellence salutes your Grace. Dut. Thou hast A malencholy brow; how did he take my Letter? Sec. As he would take a blow, with so much sense Of anger, his whole soul boild in his face, And such prodigious flame in both his eys As they'd been th'only seat of fire; and at Each look a Salamander leaping forth, Not able to endure the Furnace. Dut. Ha! thou dost Describe him with some horror. Sec. Soon as he Had read again, and understood your meaning, His rage had shot me with a pistoll, had not I us'd some soft, and penitentiall language, To charm the Bullet. Dut. Wait at some more distance; My soul doth bath it self in a cold dew; Imagin, I am opening of a Tomb, Thus I throw off the Marble to discover, What antick posture death presents in this Pale monument to fright me— Reads. Ha? my heart that call'd my blood and spirits, to Defend it from the invasion of my fears, Must keep a guard about it still, lest this Strange and too mighty joy crush it to nothing. Antonio. Sec. Madam. Dut. Bid my Steward give thee Two thousand Ducates; art sure I am awake? Sec. I shall be able to resolve you, Madam, When he has paid the money. Dut. Columbo now is noble. Exit. Dut. Sec. This is better than I expected, if my Lady be Not mad, and live to justifie her bounty. Exit. Enter King, Alvarez, Hernando, Lords. King. The War is left to him. but we must have You reconcil'd, if that be all your difference. His rage flows like a torrent, when he meets With opposition, leave to wrastle with him, And his hot blood retreats into a calm, And then he chides his passion; you shall back With letters from us. Her. Your Commands, are not To be disputed. Kin. Alvarez. 1 Lo. Lose not Your self by cool submission, he will find His error, and the want of such a Souldier. 2 Lo. Have you seen the Cardinal? Her. Not yet. 1 Lo. He wants no plot— Her. The King I must obey; But let the purple Gownman place his engins I'th' dark that wounds me. 2 Lo. Be assur'd Of what we can to friend you, and the King Cannot forget your service. Her. I am sorry For that poor Gentleman. Alvar. I must confess, Sir, The Dutchess has been pleas'd to think me worthy Her favours, and in that degree of honour, That has oblig'd my life to make the best Return of service, which is not, with bold Affiance in her love, to interpose Against her happiness, and your election; I love so much her honour, I have quitted All my desires, yet would not shrink to bleed Out my warm stock of life, so the last drop Might benefit her wishes. Ki. I shall find A compensation for this act, Alvarez, It hath much pleased us. Enter Dutchess with a Letter, Gentleman Vsher. Dut. Sir, you are the King, And in that sacred title it were sin To doubt a justice, all that does concern My essence in this world, and a great part Of the other bliss, lives in you breath. Ki. What intends the Dutchess? Dut. That will instruct you, Sir, Columbo has Upon some better choice, or discontent, Set my poor soul at freedom. Ki. Tis his character— Reads. Madam, I easily discharge all my pretensions To your love, and person, I leave you to your Own choice, and in what you have obliged Your self to me, resume a power to cancell If you please. Columbo. This is strange. Dut. Now do an act to make Your Chronicle belov'd and read for ever. Ki. Express your self. Dut. Since by Divine infusion, For tis no art could force the Generall to This Change, second this justice and bestow The heart you would have given from me, by Your strict commands to love Columbo, where 'Twas meant by heaven, and let your breath return Whom you divorc'd, Alvarez, mine. Lords. This is but justice, Sir. Ki. It was decreed above, And since Columbo has releas'd his interest Which we had wrought him, not without some force Upon your will I give you your own wishes, Receive your own Alvarez, when you please To celebrate your Nuptial, I invite My self your guest. Dut. Eternall blessings Crown you. Omnes. And every joy your Mariage [Exit King, who meets the Cardinal, they confer. Alvar. I know not whether I shall wonder most Or joy to meet this happiness. Dut. Now the King hath planted us Methinks we grow already, and twist our loving souls Above the wrath of thunder to divide us. Alv. Ha? The Cardinal Has met the King, I do not like this conference; He looks with anger this way, I expect A tempest. Dut. Take no notice of his presence, Leave me to meet, and answer it, if the King Be firm in's Royall word, I fear no lightning; Expect me in the Garden. Alv. I obey, But fear a shipwrack on the coast. Exit. Card. Madam. Dut. My Lord. Car. The King speaks of a Letter that has brought A riddle in't. Dut. Tis easy to interpret. Car. From my Nephew? may I deserve the favour? Dut. He looks as though his eys would fire the paper. They are a pair of Burning glasses, and His envious blood doth give'em flame. Car. What lethargy could thus unspirit him? I am all wonder; do not believe Madam, But that Columbo's love is yet more Sacred, To honour, and your self, than thus to forfeit What I have heard him call the glorious wreath To all his merits, given him by the King, From whom he took you with more pride than ever He came from victory; his kisses hang Yet panting on your lips, and he but now Exchang'd religious farewell to return, But with more triumph to be yours. Dut. My Lord, You do believe your Nephews hand was not Surpriz'd or strain'd to this? Car. Strange arts and windings in the world, most dark, And subtill progresses; who brought this Letter? Dut. I enquir'd not his name, I thought it not Considerable to take such narrow knowledge. Car. Desert, and honour urg'd it here, nor can I blame you to be angry, yet his person Oblig'd, you should have given a nobler pause, Before you made your faith and change so violent From his known worth, I into the arms of one, How ever fashioned to your amorous wish, Not equall to his cheapest fame, with all The gloss of blood and merit. Dut. This comparison, My good Lord Cardinal, I cannot think, Flows from an even justice, it betrayes You partiall where your blood runs. Car. I fear Madam, Your own takes two much licence, and will soon, Fall to the censure of unruly tongues; Because Alvarez has a softer cheek, Can like a woman trim his wanton hair, Spend half a day with looking in the glass To find a posture to present himself, And bring more effeminacy than man, Or honour to your bed; must he supplant him? Take heed, the common murmur when it catches The sent of a lost Fame— Dut. My Fame Lord Cardinal? It stands upon an innocence as clear As the devotions you pay to heaven, I shall not urge my Lord your soft indulgence At my next shrift. Car. You are a fine Court Lady. Dut. And you should be a reverend Churchman. Car. One, that if you have not thrown off modesty. Would counsell you to leave Alvarez. Dut. Cause you dare do worse Than Mariage, must not I be admitted what The Church and Law allowes me? Car. Insolent? then you dare marry him? Dut. Dare? Let your contracted flame and malice, with Columbo's rage higher than that, meet us When we approach the holy place, clasp'd hand In hand, wee'l break through all your force and fix Our sacred vows together there. Car. I knew When with as chast a brow, you promis'd fair To another; you are no dissembling Lady. Dut. Would all your actions had no falser lights About 'em. Car. Ha? Dut. The people would not talk and curse so loud. Car. I'l have you chid into a blush for this. Dut. Begin at home great man, ther's cause enough, You turn the wrong end of the perspective Upon your crimes, to drive them to a far, And lesser sight, but let your eys look right What giants would your pride and surfeit seem? How gross your avarice, eating up whole families? How vast are your corruptions and abuse Of the Kings ear? at which you hang a pendent, Not to adorn, but ulcerate, while the honest Nobility, like pictures in the Arras, Serve only for Court-Ornament; if they speak, 'Tis when you set their tongues, which you wind up, Like clocks to strike at the just hour you please; Leave, leave, my Lord, these usurpations, And be what you were meant a man to cure, Not let in Agues to Religion; Look on the Churches wounds. Car. You dare presume In your rude spleen to me, to abuse the Church? Dut. Alas you give false aym, my Lord, 'tis your Ambition and Scarlet Sins that rob Her Altar of the glory, and leave wounds Upon her brow; which fetches grief, and paleness, Into her cheeks; Making her troubled bosome Pant with her groanes, and shroud her holy blushes Within your reverend purples. Car. Will you now take breath? Dut. In hope, my Lord, you will behold your self. In a true glass, and see those injust acts That so deform you, and by timely cure, Prevent a shame before the short hard men Do croud and call for justice. I take leave. Exit. Car. This woman has a spirit, that may rise To tame the Devils, ther's no dealing with Her angry tongue, 'tis action and revenge Must calm her fury; were Columbo here, I could resolve, but Letters shall be sent To th'Army which may wake him into sense Of his rash folly, or direct his spirit Some way to snatch his honour from this flame, All great men know, The soul of life is fame. Exit.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. Enter Valeria, Celinda. Valeria. I did not think Celinda when I prais'd Alvarez to the Dutchess, that things thus Would come about, what does your Ladiship Think of Columbo now? it staggers all The Court, he should forsake his Mistress, I Am lost with wonder yet. Celind. 'Tis very strange Without a spel; but ther's a fate in love, I like him ne'r the worse. Enter two Lords. 1 Lo. Nothing but mariages, and triumph now. Val. What new access of joy, makes you, my Lord, So pleasant? 1 Lo. Ther's a Packet come to Court Makes the King merry, we are all concernd in't? Columbo hath given the enemy a great, And glorious defeat, and is already Preparing to march home. Cel. He thriv'd the better for my prayers. 2 Lo. You have been his great admirer, Madam. 1 Lo. The King longs to see him. Val. This news exalts the Cardinal. Enter Cardinal. 1 Lo. He's here, He appears with discontent, the Mariage With Count D'Alvarez hath a bitter tast, And not worn off his palat; but let us leave him. Ladies. We'l to the Dutchess. Exeunt. manet Car. Card. He has not woon so much upon the Arragon As he has lost at home, and his neglect Of what my studies had contriv'd to adde More luster to our Family by the access Of the great Dutchess fortune, cools his triumph, And makes me wild. Enter Hernando. Her. My good Lord Cardinal. Car. You made complaint to th'King about your General. Her. Not a complaint my Lord, I did but satisfie Some questions o'the Kings. Car. You see he thrives Without your personal valour, or advice, Most grave and learned in the wars. Her. My Lord, I Envy not his fortune. Car. 'Tis above Your Malice, and your noise not worth his anger, 'Tis barking gainst the moon. Her. More temper would Become that habit. Car. The Military thing would shew some spleen; I'l blow an Army of such Wasps about The world; go look your sting you left i'th' Camp, Sir. Enter King, and Lords. Her. The King. Exit. This may be one day counted for. K. All things conspire my Lord to make you fortunate, Your Nephews glory— Car. 'Twas your cause and justice Made him victorious, had he been so valiant At home, he had had another conquest to Invite and bid her welcome to new wars. K. You must be reconcil'd to providence, my Lord; I heard you had a controvercy with The Dutchess, I will have you friends. Car. I am not Angry. K. For my sake then you shall be pleas'd, And with me grace the Mariage; A Churchman must shew Charity, and shine With first example, she's a woman. Car. You shall prescribe in all things; Sir, you cannot Accuse my love, if I still wish my Nephew Had been so happy to be constant to Your own, and my election; yet my brain Cannot reach how this comes about; I know My Nephew lov'd her with a near affection. Enter Hernando. K. He'l give you fair account at his return. Colonel, your Letters may be spar'd, the General Has finish'd, and is coming home. Her. I am glad on't, sir; my good Lord Cardinal 'Tis not impossible but some man provok'd, May have a precious mind to cut your throat. Car. You shall command me Noble Colonel; I know you wo'not fail to be at th'wedding. Her. 'Tis not Columbo that is maried Sir. Car. Go teach the postures of the Pike and Musket, Then dril your Mirmidons into a ditch, Where sterve, and stink in pickle, you shall find Me reasonable, you see the King expects me. Her. So does the Devill; some desperate hand May help you on your journey. Exeunt. Enter Secretary and Servants. Sec. Here this, I this will fit your part: you shall wear the Slashes because you are a Souldier; here's for the blue mute. 1 This doublet will never fit me, Pox ont', are these Breeches good enough for a Prince too? Pedro playes but a Lord, and he has two laces more in a seam. Sec. You must consider Pedro is a foolish Lord, he may wear what lace he please. 2 Does my beard fit my cloathes well Gentlemen? Sec. Pox o'your beard. 3 That will fright away the hair. 1 This fellow plays but a mute, &amp; he is so troublesome, and talks. 3 Mr. Secretary might have let Iaques play the soldier, He has a black patch already. 2 By your favour Mr. Secretary, I was ask'd who writ this play for us. Sec. For us? why art thou any more than a blew mute? 2 And by my troth, I said, I thought it was all your own. Sec. Away you Coxcomb. 4 Do'st think he has no more wit then to write a Comedy? my Ladies Chaplain made the Play, though he is content for the honour and trouble of the business, to be seen in't. 5 Did any body see my head Gentlemen 'twas here but now? I shall have never a head to play my part in. Sec. Is thy head gone? 'tis well thy part was not in't, Look, look about, has not Iaques it? 4 I his head? two'not come on upon my shoulders. Sec. Make hast Gentlemen I'l see whether the King has sup'd; Look every man to his wardrop and his part. Exit. 2 Is he gone? in my mind a masque had been fitter for a mariage. 4 Why mute? there was no time for't, and the scenes Are troublesome. 2 Half a score Deal tack'd together in the clouds, what's that? a Throne to come down and dance; all the properties have been paid forty times over, and are in the Court stock, but the Secretary must have a play to shew his wit. 4 Did not I tell thee twas the Chaplains? hold your tongue Mute. 1 Under the Rose and would this cloth of Silver doublet might never come off agen, if there be any more plot then you see in the back of my hand. 2 You talk of a plot, I'l not give this for the best Poets plot in the world and if it be not well carryed. 4 Well said Mute. 3 Ha, ha; Pedro since he put on his doublet, has repeated but three lines, and he has broke five butt ons. 2 I know not but by this false beard, and here's hair enough to hang a reasonable honest man, I do not remember to say a strong line indeed in the whole Comedy; but when the Chambermaid kisses the Captain. 3 Excellent mute. Enter another Servant. 5 They have almost sup'd, and I cannot find my head yet. 4 play in thine own. 5 Thank you for that, so I may have it made a property, if I have not a head found me, let Mr. Secretary play my part himself without it. Enter Secretary. Sec. Are you all ready my Masters? the King is coming through the Gallery, are the women drest? 1 Rogero wants a head. Sec. Here with a pox to you, take mine, you a player? You a puppy-dog is the Musick ready? Enter Gentleman-Vsher. Gent. Gentlemen, it is my Ladies pleasure that you expect till she call for you, there are a company of Cavaliers in gallant Equipage newly alighted, have offer'd to present their Revels in honour of this Hymen; and 'tis her Graces command, that you be silent till their Entertainment be over. 1 Gentlemen? 2 Affronted? 5 Mr. Secretary, ther's your head again; a man's a man; have I broken my sleep to study fifteen lines for an Ambassador, and after that a Constable, and is it come to this? Sec. Patience Gentlemen, be not so hot, tis but defer'd, and the play may do well enough cold. 4 If it be not presented, the Chaplain will have the greatest loss, he loses his wits. Hoboies. Sec. This Musick speaks the King upon entrance; retire, retire, and grumble not. Exeunt. Enter King, Cardinal, Alvarez, Dutchess, Celinda, Valeria, Placentia, Lords, Hernando; (they being set) Enter Columbo, and five more in rich habits Visarded; between every two a torch bearer: They Dance, and after beckon to Alvarez as desirous to speak with him. Alv. With me! [They Embrace and whisper. K. Do you know the Masquers Madam? Dut. Not I Sir. Car. Ther's one, but that my Nephew is abroad, And has more soul than thus to Jyg upon Their Hymenrall night, I should suspect 'Twere he. [The Masquers lead in Alvarez. Dut. Wher's my Lord D'Alvarez? [Recorders. K. Call in the Bridegroom. Enter Columbo, four Masquers, bring in Alvarez dead, in one of their habits, and having laid him down, Exeunt. Dut. What Mistery is this? Car. We want the Bridegroom still. K. Where is Alvarez [Columbo points to the body, they unvizard it, &amp; find Alvar. bleeding. Dut. Oh 'tis my Lord hee's murder'd. K. Who durst commit this horrid act? Col. I Sir. K. Columbo? ha! Col. Yes; Columbo that dares stay To justifie that act. Her. Most barbarous. Dut. Oh my dearest Lord! K. Our guard seize on them all, this sight doth shake All that is man within me; poor Alvarez Is this thy wedding day? Enter Guard. Dut. If you do think there is a heaven or pains, To punish such black crimes i'th' other world, Let me have swift, and such exemplar justice As shall become this great assasinate, You will take off our faith else, and if here Such innocence must bleed, and you look on, Poor men that call you Gods on earth, will doubt To obey your Laws, nay practise to be Devils, As fearing if such monstrous sins go on The Saints will not be safe in Heaven. K. You shall, You shall have justice. Car. Now to come off were brave. Enter Servant. Ser. The Masquers, Sir, are fled, their horse prepar'd At gate expected to receive 'em, where They quickly mounted, coming so like friends None could suspect their hast, which is secur'd By advantage of the night. Col. I answer for 'em all, 'tis stake enough For many lives, but if that poniard Had voice, it would convince they were but all Spectators of my act; and now if you Will give your judgments leave, though at the first Face of this object your cool bloods were frighted, I can excuse this deed and call it Justice; An act, your honours, and your office Sir, Is bound to build a Law upon, for others To Imitate; I have but took his life, And punish'd her with mercy, who had both Conspir'd to kill the soul of all my fame Read there,—and read an injury as deep In my dishonour, as the the Devill knew A Woman had capacity or malice To execute read there, how you were cozen'd Sir, Your power affronted, and my faith, her smiles A jugling witchcraft to betray and make My love her horse to stalk withall, and catch Her curled Minion. Car. Is it possible The Dutchess could dissemble so, and forfeit Her modesty with you, and to us all? Yet I must pity her; my Nephew has Been too severe, though this affront would call A dying man from prayers, and turn him Tiger, There being nothing dearer than our fame, Which, If a common man, whose blood has no Ingredient of honour, labour to Preserve, a Souldier (by his nearest tye To glory) is above all others, bound To vindicate; and yet it might have been less bloody. Her. Charitable Devill! K. Reads. I Pray, my Lord, release under your hand, what you dare challenge in my love or person, as a just forfeit to my self, this act will speak you honorable to my thoughts, and when you have conquered thus your self, you may proceed to many victories, and after, with safety of your fame visit again The lost Rosaura. To this your Answer was a free resign? Col. Flatter'd with great opinion of her faith, And my desert of her (with thought that she Who seem'd to weep and chide my easie will To part with her, could not be guilty of A treason, or Apostacy so soon, But rather meant this a device to make Me expedite the affairs of War) I sent That paper, which her wickedness not justice, Applied (what I meant tryall) her divorce; I lov'd her so, I dare call heaven to witness I knew not whether I lov'd most; while she, With him, whose crimson penitence I provok'd, Conspir'd my everlasting infamy; Examine but the circumstance. Car. 'Tis clear, This Match was made at home before she sent That cunning writ, in hope to take him off, As knowing his impatient Soul would scorn To own a blessing came on crutches to him; It was not well to raise his expectation, (Had you, Sir, no affront) to ruine him With so much scandall and contempt. K. We have Too plentifull a circumstance to accuse You Madam, as the cause of your own sorrows, But not without an accessary, more Than young Alvarez. Car. Any other instrument? K. Yes I am guilty, with her self, and Don Columbo, though our acts look'd severall waies, That thought a lover might so soon be ransom'd; And did exceed the office of a King To exercise dominion over hearts, That owe to the prerogative of heaven Their choice, or Separation; you must therefore, When you do kneel for Justice, and Revenge, Madam, consider me a laterall agent In poor Alvarez Tragedy. 1 Lo. It was your love to Don Columbo Sir. Her. So, so; the King is charm'd; do you observe, How to acquit Columbo, he would draw Himself into the plot; Heaven, is this Justice? Car. Your Judgment is divine in this. K. And yet, Columbo cannot be secure, and we Just in his pardon, that durst make so great, And insolent a breach of Law and Duty. 2. Lo. Ha, Will he turn agen? K. And should we leave This guilt of blood to Heaven, which cries, and strikes, With loud appeals the palace of eternity, Yet here is more to charge Columbo, than Alvarez blood, and bids me punish it, Or be no King. Her. 'Tis come about my Lords. K. And If I should forgive His timeless death, I cannot the offence, That with such boldness struck at me. Has my Indulgence to your merits which are great Made me so cheap, your rage could meet no time Nor place for your revenge, but where my eys Must be affrighted, and affronted with The bloody execution? This contempt Of Majesty transcends my power to pardon, And you shall feel my anger Sir. Her. Thou shalt have one short prayer more for that. Col. Have I i'th' progress of my life No actions to plead me up deserving, Against this ceremony? Car. Contain your self. Col. I must be dumb then; where is honour? And gratitude of Kings, when they forget Whose hand secur'd their greatness? take my head off, Examine then which of your silken Lords, As I have done, will throw himself on dangers; Like to a floting Iland move in blood; And where your great defence calls him to stand A Bullwark, upon his bold brest to take In death, that you may live: but Souldiers are Your valiant fools, whom when your own securities Are bleeding you can cherish, but when once Your state and nerves are knit, not thinking when To use their surgery again, you cast Them off, and let them hang in dusty armories, Or make it death to ask for pay. K. No more, We thought to have put your victory and merits In ballance with Alvarez death, which while Our mercy was to Iudge, had been your safety; But the affront to us, made greater by This boldness to upbraid our royall bounty, Shall tame or make you nothing. Lor. Excellent. Her. The Cardinal is not pleas'd. Car. Humble your self To th'King. Col. And beg my life? let cowards do't That dare not dy, I'l rather have no head Than owe it to his Charity. K. To th'Castle with him. Madam, I leave you to your grief, and what The King can recompence to your tears, or honor Of your dead Lord, expect. Dut. This shews like Iustice. Exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT IV. Enter two Lords, Hernando. 1 Lord. This is the age of wonders. 2 Lo. Wonderous mischiefs. Her. Among those guards which some call Tutelar Angels, Whose office is to govern Provinces, Is there not one will undertake Navarre? Hath heaven forsook us quite? 1 Columbo at large? 2 And grac'd now more than ever. 1 He was not pardon'd, That word was prejudiciall to his fame. Her. But as the murder done had been a dream Vanish'd to memory, he's courted as Preserver of his Country; with what chains Of Magick does this Cardinal hold the King? 2 What will you say my Lord if they inchant The Dutchess now; and by some impudent art, Advance a Mariage to Columbo yet? Her. Say? I'l say no woman can be sav'd, nor is't Fit, indeed, any should pretend to Heaven After one such impiety in their sex, And yet my faith has been so stager'd, since The King restor'd Columbo, I'l be now Of no Religion. 1 'Tis not possible She can forgive the murder, I observ'd Her tears. Her. Why so did I, my Lord, And if they be not honest, 'tis to be Half damn'd to look upon a woman weeping. When do you think the Cardinal said his prayers? 2 I know not. Her. Heaven forgive my want of charity But if I were to kill him, he should have No time to pray, his life could be no sacrifice, Unless his soul went too. 1 That were too much. Her. When you mean to dispatch him, you may give Time for Confession, they have injur'd me After another rate. 2 You are too passionate Cozen. Enter Columbo, Colonels, Alfonso, Courtiers, (they pass over the Stage.) Her. How the gay men do flutter to congratulate His Goal delivery? ther's one honest man, What pity 'tis a gallant fellow should Depend on knaves for his preferment. 1 Except this cruelty upon Alvarez, Columbo has no mighty stain upon him; But for his Uncle— Her. If I had a Son Of twelve years old, that would not fight with him, And stake his soul against his Cardinals Cap, I would dis-inherit him; Time has took a lease But for three lives I hope, a fourth may see Honesty walk without a crutch. 2 This is But Air and Wildness. Her. I'l see the Dutchess, You may do well to comfort her, 1 We must attend the King. Her. your pleasures. Exit Her. Enter King and Cardinal. 1 A Man of a brave soul. 2 The less his safety; The King and Cardinal in consult. K. Commend us to the Dutchess, and imploy What language you think fit, and powerfull To reconcile her to some peace. My Lords. Car. Sir, I possess all for your sacred uses. Exeunt Severally. Enter Secretary and Celinda. Sec. Madam, you are the welcom'st Lady living. Cel. To whom, Mr. Secretary? Sec. If you have mercy To pardon so much boldness, I durst say, To me—I am a Gentleman. Cel. And handsome. Sec. But my Lady has much wanted you. Cel. Why Mr. Secretary? Sec. You are the prettiest, Cel. So. Sec. The witiest, Cel. So. Sec. The merriest Lady i'th' Court. Cel. And I was wish'd to make the Dutchess pleasant. Sec. She never had so deep a cause of sorrow, Her Chamber's but a Coffin of a larger Volume, wherein she walks so like a Ghost, T'would make you pale to see her. Cel. Tell her Grace I attend here. Sec. I shall most willingly. A spirited Lady, would I had her in my closet, She is excellent company among the Lords, Sure she has an admirable treble—Madam. Exit. Cel. I do suspect this fellow would be nibling Like some whose narrow fortunes will not rise To wear things when the inventions rare, and new, But treading on the heel of pride, they hunt The fashion when tis crippled, like fell tyrants; I hope I am not old yet, I had the honour To be saluted by our Cardinals Nephew This Morning, ther's a man! Enter Secretary. Sec. I have prevail'd, Sweet Madam use what Eloquence you can Upon her, and if ever I be usefull To your Ladiships service, your least breath commands me. Enter Dutchess. Dut. Madam, I come to ask you but one question, If you were in my State, my state of grief, I mean an exile from all happiness, Of this world, and almost of heaven, for my Affliction is finding out despair, What would you think of Don Columbo? Cel. Madam? Dut. Whose Bloody hand wrought all this misery? Would you not weep as I do? and wish rather An everlasting spring of tears to drown Your sight, than let your eys be curst to see The murderer agen? and glorious? So careless of his sin, that he is made Fit for new Parricide, even while his soul Is purpled o'r, and reeks with innocent blood. But do not, do not answer me, I know You have so great a spirit, (which I want, The horrour of his fact surprising all My faculties) you would not let him live: But I, poor I, must suffer more, ther's not One little star in Heaven will look on me, Unless to choose me out the mark, on whom It may shoot down some angry influence. Enter Placentia. Pla. Madam, her's Don Columbo says he must Speak with your Grace. Dut. But he must not, I charge you. None else wait? Is this well done, To triumph in his Tyranny? speak Madam, Speak but your conscience. Enter Columbo, and Secretary. Sec. Sir, you must not see her. Col. Not see her? were she cabled up above The search of Bullet, or of Fire, were she Within her Grave, and that the toughest Mine That ever nature teem'd and groand withall, I would force some way to see her; do not fear I come to Court you Madam, y'are not worth The humblest of my kinder thoughts, I come To shew the man you have prokvo'd, and lost; And tell you what remains of my revenge. Live, but never presume again to marry, I'l kill the next at th'Altar, and quench all The smiling tapers with his blood; if after You dare provoke the Priest, and heaven so much, To take another, in thy bed I'l cut him from Thy warm embrace, and throw his heart to Ravens. Cel. This will appear an unexampled cruelty. Col. Your pardon Madam, rage, and my revenge Not perfect, took away my eys, you are A noble Lady, this, not worth your ey-beam, One of so slight a making, and so thin, An Autumn leaf is of too great a value To play, which shall be soonest lost i'th' Air; Be pleas'd to own me by some name, in your Assurance, I despise to be receiv'd There, let her witness that I call You Mistress; honour me to make these Pearls Your carkanet. Cel. My Lord, you are too humble in your thoughts. Col. Ther's no vexation too great to punish her. Exit. Enter Secretary. Sec. Now Nadam? Cel. Away you saucy fellow; Madam, I Must be excus'd, if I do think more honourably Than you have cause of this great Lord. Dut. Why is not All woman kind concern'd to hate what's impious? Cel. For my part— Dut. Antonio, is this a woman? Sec. I know not whether she be man or woman, I should be nimble to find out the Experiment, She look'd with less state, when Columbo came. Dut. Let me entreat your absence, I am cozen'd in her, I took you for a modest, honest Lady. Cel. Madam, I scorn any accuser, and Deducting the great title of a Dutchess, I shall not need one grain of your dear honour To make me full weight, if your Grace be jealous I can remove. Exit. Sec. She is gone. Dut. Prethee remove My fears of her return,—she is not worth Ex. Sec. Considering, my anger's mounted higher; He need not put in caution for my next Mariage, Alvarez, I must come to thee, Thy Virgin, Wife, and Widdow, but not till I ha' paid those Tragick duties to thy Herse, Become my piety and love, but how? Who shall instruct a way? Enter Placentia. Pla. Madam, Don Hernando much desires to speak with you. Dut. Will not thy own discretion think I am Unfit for visit. Pla. Please your Grace he brings Something he says imports your ear, and love Of the dead Lord Alvarez. Dut. Then admit him. Enter Hernando: Her. I would speak, Madam, to your self. Dut. Your absence. Her. I know not how you Grace wil censure so Much boldness, when you know the affairs I come for. Dut. My Servant has prepar'd me to receive it, If it concern my dead Lord. Her. Can you name So much of your Alvarez in a breath Without one word of your revenge? O Madam, I come to chide you, and repent my great Opinion of your virtue, that can walk, And spend so many hours in naked Solitude, As if you thought that no arrears were due To his death, when you had paid his Funerall charges, Made your eys red, and wept a handkercher; I come to tell you that I saw him bleed, I, that can challenge nothing in his name, And honour, saw his murder'd body warm, And panting with the labour of his spirits, Till my amaz'd Soul shrunk and hid it self, While barbarous Columbo grinning stood, And mock'd the weeping wounds; it is too much That you should keep your heart alive, so long After this spectacle, and not revenge it. Dut. You do not know the business of my heart, That censure me so rashly; yet I thank you, And if you be Alvarez friend, dare tell Your confidence, that I despise my life, But know not how to use it in a service, To speak me his revenger, this will need No other proof, than that to you, who may Be sent with cunning to betray me, I Have made this bold confession, I so much Desire to sacrifice to that hovering Ghost, Columbo's life, that I am not ambitious To keep my own two minutes after it. Her. If you will call me coward, which is equall To think I am a Traytor, I forgive it, For this brave resolution, which time And all the Destinies must aid, I beg That I may kiss your hand for this, and may The soul of angry honour guide it. Dut. Whither? Her. To Don Columbo's heart. Dut. It is too weak I fear alone. Her. Alone? are you in earnest? why? will it not Be a dishonour to your Justice, Madam, Another arm should interpose? but that It were a sawcy act to mingle with you, I durst, nay I am bound in the revenge Of him that's dead, (since the whole world has interest, In every goodmans loss) to offer it; Dare you command me, Madam? Dut. Not command, But I should more than honour such a truth In man, that durst against so mighty odds, Appear Alvarez friend and mine; the Cardinal— Her. Is for the second course, Columbo must Be first cut up, his Ghost must lead the dance. Let him dy first. Dut. But how? Her. How? with a Sword, and if I undertake it, I wo'not lose so much of my own honour, To kill him basely. Dut. How shall I reward This infinite service? 'tis not Modesty, While now my husband groanes beneath his tomb, And calls me to his marble bed, to promise What this great act might well deserve, my self If you survive the Victor, but if thus Alvarez ashes be appeas'd it must Deserve an honourable memory; And though Columbo (as he had all power, And grasp'd the fates) has vow'd to kill the man That shall succeed Alvarez— Her. Tyranny. Dut. Yet if ever, I entertain a thought of love hereafter, Hernando from the world shall challenge it, Till when, my Prayers, and fortune, shall wait on you. Her. This is too mighty recompence. Dut. 'Tis all just. Her. If I outlive Columbo I must not Expect security at home. Dut. Thou canst Not fly, where all my fortunes, and my love, Shall not attend to guard thee. Her. If I dye— Dut. Thy memory Shall have a shrine, the next within my heart To my Alvarez. Her. Once again your hand, Your cause is so religious you need Not strengthen it with your prayers, trust it to me. Enter Placentia, and Cardinal. Pla. Madam, the Cardinal. Dut. Will you appear? Her. And he had all the horror of the Devil In's face, I would not balk him. [He stares upon the Cardinal in his Exit. Car. What makes Hernando here? I do not like They should consult, I'l take no note; the King Fairly salutes your Grace, by whose command I am to tell you, though his will and actions Illimited, stoop not to satisfie The Vulgar inquisition, he is Yet willing to retain a just opinion, With those that are plac'd neer him, and although You look with Natures ey upon your self, Which needs no perspective to reach, nor art Of any optick to make greater, what Your narrow sense applies an injury, (Our selves still nearest to our selves) but ther's Another ey that looks abroad and walks In search of reason, and the weight of things, With which if you look on him, you will find His pardon to Columbo cannot be So much against his justice, as your erring Faith would perswade your anger. Dut. Good my Lord, Your phrase has too much landschape and I cannot Distinguish at this distance you present The figure perfect, but indeed my eys May pray your Lordship find excuse, for tears Have almost made them blind. Car. Fair, peace restore 'em! To bring the object nearer, the King says, He could not be severe to Don Columbo Without injustice to his other merits, Which call more loud for their reward and honour, Than you for your revenge; the Kingdom made Happy by those; you only by the last Uunfortunate, nor was it rationall, I speak the Kings own Language, he should dy For taking one mans breath, without whose valour None now had been alive, without dishonour. Dut. In my poor understanding, 'tis the Crown Of virtue to proceed in its own tract, Not deviate from honour, if you acquit A man of murder, 'cause he has done brave Things in the War, you will bring down his valour To a crime, nay to a baud, if it secure A rape, and but teach those that deserve well To sin with greater licence; but dispute Is now too late, my Lord, 'tis done, and you, By the good King, in tender of my sorrows, Sent to perswade me, 'tis unreasonable That Justice should repair me. Car. You mistake, For if Columbo's death could make Alvarez Live, the King had given him up to Law Your bleeding Sacrifice; but when his life Was but another treasure thrown away, To obey a clamorous Statute, it was wisdom To himself and common safety to take off This killing edge of Law, and keep Columbo To recompence the crime by noble acts, And sorrow, that in time might draw your pity. Dut. This is a greater tyranny, than that Columbo exercis'd, he kill'd my Lord, And you not have the charity to let Me think it worth a punishment, Car. To that In my own name, I answer; I condemn And urge the blody guilt against my Nephew, 'Twas violent, and cruell, a black deed, A deed whose memory doth make me shudder, An act that did betray a tyranous nature, Which he took up in War, the school of vengeance; And though the Kings compassion spare him here, Unless his heart Weep it self out in penitent tears. Dut. This sounds As you were now a good man. Car. Does your Grace Think I have conscience to allow the murder? Although when it was done, I did obey The stream of nature, as he was my Kinsman, To plead he might not pay his forfeit life, Could I do less for one so near my bloud? Consider Madam, and be charitable, Let not this wild injustice, make me lose The character I bear, and reverend habit. To make you full acquainted with my innocence, I challenge here my soul, and heaven to witness If I had any thought, or knowledge with My nephews plot, or person, when he came Under the smooth pretence of friend to violate Your hospitable laws, and do that act Whose frequent mention drawes this tear, a whirlwind Snatch me to endless flames. Dut. I must believe, And ask your Graces pardon, I confess I ha' not lov'd you since Alvarez death, Though we were reconcil'd. Car. I do not blame Your Jealousie, nor any zeal you had To prosecute revenge against me, Madam, As I then stood suspected, nor can yet Implore your mercy to Columbo, all I have to say is to retain my first Opinion and credit with your Grace, Which you may think I urge not out of fear Or ends upon you, (since, I thank the King, I stand firm on the base of royall favour) But for your own sake, and to shew I have Compassion of your sufferings. Dut. You have cleer'd A doubt my Lord, and by this fair remonstrance, Given my sorrow so much truce, to think That we may meet agen, and yet be friends. But be not angry, if I still remember By whom Alvarez dyed, and weep, and wake Another Iustice with my prayers, Car. All thoughts That may advance a better peace, dwell with you. Exit. Dut. How would this cozening Statesman bribe my Faith With flatteries to think him innocent? No, if his Nephew dy, this Cardinal must not Be long-liv'd; all the prayers of a wrong'd Widow Make firm Hernando's Sword, and my own hand Shall have some glory in the next revenge; I will pretend my brain with grief distracted, It may gain easy credit, and beside The taking off examination For great Columbo's death, it makes what act I do in that believ'd want of my reason, Appear no crime, but my defence; look down Soul of my Lord, from thy eternall shade, And unto all thy blest companions boast, Thy Dutchess busie to revenge thy Ghost. Exit. Enter Columbo, Hernando, Alfonso, Colonel. Col. Hernando, now I love thee, and do half Repent the affront my passion threw upon thee. Her. You wo'not be too prodigall o' your penitence. Colu. This makes good thy Nobility of birth, Thou mayst be worth my anger and my sword, If thou dost execute as daringly, As thou provok'st a quarrell, I did think Thy soul a starveling, or a sleep. Her. You'l find it Active enough to keep your spirit waking, Which to exasperate, for yet I think It is not high enough to meet my rage— D'ee smile? Col. This noise is worth it, Gentlemen; I'm sorry this great Soldier has engag'd Your travel, all his business is to talk. Her. A little of your Lordships patience, You shall have other sport, and swords that will Be as nimble 'bout your heart, as you can wish, 'Tis pity more than our two single lives Should be at stake. Colon. Make that no scruple Sir. Her. To him then that survives if fate allow That difference, I speak that he may tell The World, I came not hither on slight anger, But to revenge my honour stain'd, and trampled on By this proud man, when General, he commanded My absence from the field. Colu. I do remember, And I'l give your Soul now a discharge. Her. I come to meet it, if your courage be so fortunate. But there is more than my own injury You must account for Sir, if my sword prosper, Whose point and every edge is made more keen With young Alvarez blood, in which I had A Noble interest; does not that sin benum Thy Arteries, and turn the guilty flowings, To trembling gelly in thy veins? canst hear Me name that murder, and thy spirits not Struck into air, as thou wert shot by some Engin from heaven? Col. You are the Dutchess Champion; Thou hast given me a quarrell now; I grieve It is determin'd all must fight, and I Shall lose much honour in his fall. Her. That Dutchess (Whom but to mention with thy breath, is sacrilege) An Orphan of thy making, and condemn'd By thee to eternall solitude, I come To vindicate, and while I am killing thee, By virtue of her prayers sent up for justice, At the same time, in heaven I am pardon'd for't. Col. I cannot hear the Bravo. Her. Two words more And take your chance, before you all I must Pronounce that noble Lady, without knowledge, Or thought of what I undertake for her. Poor soul, Shees now at her Devotions, Busie with heaven, and wearing out the earth With her stiff Knees, and bribing her good Angel With treasures of her eys, to tell her Lord How much she longs to see him; my attempt Needs no commission from her, were I A stranger in Navarre, the inborn right Of every Gentleman to Alvarez loss, Is reason to engage their swords, and lives, Against the common enemy of virtue. Colu. Now have you finish'd? I have an instrument Shall cure this noise, and fly up to thy tongue, To murder all thy words. Her. One little knot Of phlegm that clogs my stomach, and I ha' done; You have an Uncle call'd a Cardinal Would he were lurking now about thy heart, That the same wounds might reach you both, and send Your reeling souls together. Now have at you. Alph. We must not Sir be idle. [They fight, Columbo's Second slain. Her. What think you now of praying? Colu. Time enough; [He kills Hernando's Second. Commend me to my friend; the scales are even, I would be mercifull, and give you time, Now to consider of the other World, You'l find your soul benighted presently. Her. I'l find my way i'th' dark. [They fight, and close, Columbo gets both the swords, and Hernando takes up the seconds weapon. Colu. A stumble's dangerous. Now ask thy life—Ha? Her. I despise to wear it, A gift from any but the first bestower. Col. I scorn a base advantage—ha. [Columbo throwes away one of the swords. They fight, Hernando wounds Columbo. Her. I am now Out of your debt. Col. Th'ast don't, and I forgive thee. Give me thy hand, when shall we meet again? Her. Never, I hope. Col. I feel life ebb apace, yet I'l look upwards, And shew my face to heaven. Her. The matters done. I must not stay to bury him. Exit.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT V. Enter two Lords. 1 Lord. Columbo's death doth much aflict the King. 2 Lo. I thought the Cardinal would have lost his wits At first, for's nephew, it drownes all the talk Of the other that were slain. 1 We are friends. I do suspect Hernando had some interest And knew how their wounds came. 2 His flight confirms it, For whom the Cardinal has spread his nets. 1 He is not so weak to trust himself at home To his Enemies gripe. 2 All strikes not me so much, As that the Dutchess, most oppressed Lady, Should be distracted, and before Columbo Was slain. 1 But that the Cardinal should be made Her Guardian, is to me above that wonder. 2 So it pleas'd the King, and she, with that small stock Of reason left her, is so kind, and smooth Upon him. 1 She's turn'd a child agen; a madness, That would ha' made her brain and blood boil high In which distemper she might ha' wrought something. 2 Had been to purpose. 1 The Cardinal is cunning, and how e'r His brow does smile, he does suspect Hernando Took fire from her, and waits a time to punish it. 2 But what a subject of disgrace, and mirth, Hath poor Celinda made herself by pride, In her belief Columbo was her servant. Her head hath stoop'd much since he died, and she Almost ridiculous at Court. Enter Cardinal, Antonelli, Servant. 1. The Cardinal Is come into the Garden, now— Car. Walk off, It troubles me the Dutchess by her loss Of brain is now beneath my great revenge, She is not capable to feel my anger, Which like to unregarded thunder spent In woods, and lightning aim'd at senseless trees, Must idly fall, and hurt her not, not to That sense her guilt deserves a fatall stroke, Without the knowledg for what crime to fright her, When she takes leave, and make her tug with death, Untill her soul sweat, is a Pidgeons torment, And she is sent a babe to the other World, Columbo's death will not be satisfied, And I but wound her with a two edg'd feather; I must do more, I have all opportunity, (She by the King now made my charge) but she's So much a turtle I shall lose by killing her, Perhaps do her a pleasure, and preferment; That must not be. Enter Celinda with a Parchment. Anto. Is not this she, that would be thought to have been Columbo's Mistress? Madam, his grace is private, And would not be disturb'd, you may displease him. Cel. What will your worship wager that he shall Be pleas'd again before we part. Ant. I'l lay this Diamond Madam, 'gainst a kiss, And trust your self to keep the stakes. Cel. 'Tis done. Ant. I have long had an appetite to this Lady, But the Lords keep her up so high—this toy May bring her on. Car. This interruption tasts not of good manners. Cel. But where necessity my Lord compells, The boldness may meet pardon, and when you Have found my purpose, I may less appear Unmannerly. Car. To th'business. Cel. It did please Your Nephew, Sir, before his death to credit me With so much honorable favour, I Am come to tender to his neer'st of blood, Your self, what does remain a debt to him. Not to delay your Grace with circumstance, That deed, if you accept, makes you my heir Of no contemptible estate—this way [He reads. Is only left to ty up scurrile tongues, And saucy men, that since Columbo's death Venture to Libell on my pride, and folly; His greatness, and this gift which I enjoy, Still for my life, beyond which term; a Kingdom's, Nothing, will curb the giddy spleens of men That live on impudent rime, and railing at Each wandering fame they catch. Car. Madam, this bounty Will bind my gratitude and care to serve you. Cel. I am your Graces Servant. Car. Antonelli, [Whisper. And when this noble Lady visits me Let her not wait. Cel. What think you my Officious, Sir; his grace Is pleas'd, you may conjecture? I may keep Your Gem, the kiss was never yours. Ant. Sweet Madam— Cel. Talk if you dare, you know I must not wait, And so farewell for this time. Car. 'Tis in my brain already, and it formes Apace, good, excellent revenge, and pleasant! She's now within my talons, 'tis too cheap A satisfaction for Columbo's death, Only to kill her by soft charm or force, I'l rifle first her darling chastity, 'Twill be after time enough to poyson her, And she to th'world be thought her own destroyer. As I will frame the circumstance, this night All may be finished; for the Colonel, Her agent in my Nephewes death (whom I Disturb'd at Counsell with her) I may reach him Hereafter, and be Master of his fate. We starve our Conscience when we thrive in State. Exeunt. Enter Secretary, and Placentia. Sec. Placentia, We two are only left Of my Ladies Servants, let us be true To her, and one another, and be sure When we are at prayers, to curse the Cardinal. Pla. I pity my sweet Lady. Sec. I pity her too, but am a little angry; She might have found another time to lose Her wits. Pla. That I were a man? Sec. What would'st thou do Placentia? Pla. I would revenge my Lady. Sec. 'Tis better being a woman, thou mayst do Things that may prosper better, and the fruit Be thy own another day. Pla. Your wit still loves To play the wanton. Sec. 'Tis a sad time Placentia, Some pleasure would do well, the truth is, I Am weary of my life, and I would have One fit of mirth before I leave the world. Pla. Do not you blush to talk thus wildly? Sec. 'Tis good manners To be a little mad after my Lady; But I ha' done; who is with her now? Pla. Madam Valeria. Sec. Not Celinda? Ther's a Lady for my humour, A pretty book of flesh and blood, and well Bound up, in a fair letter too; would I Had her with all the Errata. Pla. She has not An honorable Fame. Sec. Her Fame? that's nothing. A littie stain, her wealth will fetch again The colour, and bring honour into her cheeks As fresh; if she were mine, and I had her Exchequer. I know the way to make her honest, Honest to th'touch, the test, and the last tryall. Pla. How Prethee? Sec. Why, first I would marry her, that's a verb Materiall; Then I would Print her with an Index Expurgatorius, a table drawn Of her Court Heresies, and when she's read Cum Privilegio, who dares call her Whore? Pla. I'l leave you, if you talk thus. Sec. I ha' done, Placentia, thou may'st be better company After another progress; and now tell me, Did'st ever hear of such a patient madness As my Lady is possest with? she has rav'd But twice; and she would fright the Cardinall, Or at a supper if she did but poyson him, It were a phrensy I could bear withall; She calls him her dear Governour— Enter Hernando disguised having a Letter. Pla. Who is this? Her. Her Secretary? Sir, Here is a Letter if it may have so Much happiness to kiss her Graces hand. Sec. From whom? Her. That's not in your Commission Sir To ask, or mine to satisfie, she will want No understanding when she reads. Sec. Alas, Under your favour Sir, you are mistaken, Her Grace did never more want understanding. Her. How? Sec. Have you not heard, her scull is broken Sir And many pieces taken out, she's mad. Her. The sad fame of her distraction Has two much truth it seems. Pla. If please you Sir To expect a while, I will present the Letter. Her. Pray do Exit Placen. How long has she been thus Distemper'd Sir? Sec. Before the Cardinal came to govern here, Who for that reason by the King was made Her Guardian, we are now at his devotion. Her. A Lamb given up to a Tyger! may diseases Soon eat him through his heart! Sec. Your pardon Sir, I love that voice, I know it too, a little, Are not you? be not angry noble Sir, I can with ease be ignorant agen, And think you are another man, but if You be that valiant Gentleman they call— Her. Whom? What? Sec. That kill'd, I would not name him if I thought You were not pleas'd to be that very Gentleman. Her. Am I betraid? Sec. The Devil sha'not Betray you here, kill me, and I will take My death you are the Noble Colonel; We are all bound to you for the Generals death, Valiant Hernando? when my Lady knows You are here, I hope 'twil fetch her wits agen, But do not talk too loud, we are not all Honest i'th' house, some are the Cardinals creatures. Her. Thou wert faithfull to thy Lady, I am glad 'Tis night, but tell me how the Churchman uses The Dutchess? Enter Antonelli. Sec. He carries Angels in his tongue, and face, but I Suspect his heart, this is one of his spawns. Signior Antonelli. Ant. Honest Antonio. Sec. And how, and how—a friend of mine, where is The Cardinals Grace? Her. That will be never answered. Ant. He means to sup here with the Dutchess. Sec. Will he? Ant. We'l have the charming bottles at my chamber, Bring that Gentleman, we'l be mighty merry. Her. I may disturb your jollity. Ant. Farewell sweet— Sec. Dear Antonelli—a round Pox confound you. This is Court Retorick at the back stairs. Enter Placentia. Pla. Do you know this Gentleman? Sec. Not I. Pla. My Lady presently dismist Valeria, And bad me bring him to her bed-chamber. Sec. The Gentleman has an honest face. Pla. Her words fell from her with some evenness &amp; joy. Her Grace desires your presence. Her. I'l attend her. Exit. Sec. I would this Soldier had the Cardinal Upon a promontory, with what a spring The Churchman would leap down, it were a spectacle Most rare to see him topple from the precipice, And souse in the salt water with a noise To stun the fishes; and if he fell into A net, what wonder would the simple Sea-guls Have, to draw up the o'rgrown Lobster, So ready boild? he shall have my good wishes, This Colonels coming may be lucky, I Will be sure none shall interrupt 'em. Enter Celinda. Cel. Is her Grace at opportunity? Sec. No sweet Madam, She is a sleep, her Gentlewoman says. Cel. My business is but visit; I'l expect. Sec. That must not be, although I like your company. Cel. You are grown rich Mr. Secretary. Sec. I Madam, Alas! Cel. I hear you are upon another purchase. Sec. I upon a purchase? Cel. If you want any sum— Sec. If I could purchase your sweet favour Madam? Cel. You shall command me, and my fortune Sir. Sec. How's this? Cel. I have observ'd you Sir a staid, And prudent Gentleman—and I shall want— Sec. Not me? Cel. A Father for some Infant; he has credit [Aside. I'th' world; I am not the first cast Lady Has married a Secretary. Sec. Shall I wait upon you? Cel. Whither? Sec. Any whither. Cel. I may chance lead you then— Sec. I shall be honour'd to obey, my blood Is up, and in this humour I'm for any thing. Cel. Well Sir, I'l try your Manhood. Sec. 'Tis my happiness, You cannot please me better. Cel. This was struck I'th' opportunity. Sec. I am made for ever. Enter Hernando, and Dutchess. Her. Dear Madam, do not weep. Dut. Y'are very welcome, I ha done, I wo'not shed a tear more Till I meet Alvarez, then I'l weep for joy; He was a fine young Gentleman, and sung sweetly, And you had heard him but the night before We were married, you would ha' sworn he had been A Swan, and sung his own sad Epitaph; But we'l talk o'the Cardinal. Her. Would his death Might ransom your fair sense, he should not live To triumph in the loss, beshrow my manhood; But I begin to melt. Dut. I pray Sir tell me, For I can understand, although they say I have lost my wits; but they are safe enough, And I shall have 'em when the Cardinal dyes; Who had a Letter from his Nephew too Since he was slain. Her. From whence? Dut. I know not where he is? but in some Bower Within a Garden he is making Chaplets, And means to send me one, but I'l not take it, I have flowers enough I thank him while I live. Her. But do you love your Governour? Dut. Yes, but I'l never marry him, I am promis'd Already. Her. To whom Madam? Dut. Do not you Blush when you ask me that, must not you be My Husband? I know why, but that's a secret; Indeed if you believe me, I do love No man alive so well as you, the Cardinal Shall never know't, hee'l kill us both, and yet He says he loves me dearly, and has promis'd To make me well again, but I'm afraid, One time or other he will give me poyson. Her. Prevent him Madam, and take nothing from him. Dut. Why, do you think 'twil hurt me? Her. It will kill you. Dut. I shall but dye, and meet my dear lov'd Lord, Whom when I have kist, I'l come again, and work A bracelet of my hair for you to carry him, When you are going to heaven, the poesy shall Be my own name, in little tears, that I Will weep next winter, which congeal'd i'th' frost Will shew like seed-Pearl, you'l deliver it? I know he'l love, and wear it for my sake. Her. She is quite lost. Dut. I pray give me Sir, your pardon, I know I talk not wisely, but if you had The burthen of my sorrow, you would miss Sometimes your better reason; now I'm well, What will you do when the Cardinal comes? He must not see you for the world. Her. He sha'not, I'l take my leave before he come. Dut. Nay stay, I shall have no friend left me when you go, He will but sup, he sha'not stay to ly wi' me, I have the picture of my Lord abed, Three are to much this weather. Enter Placentia. Pla. Madam, the Cardinal. Her. He shall sup with the Devil. Dut. I dare not stay, The Red-cock will be angry, I'l come agen. Exeunt. Her. This sorrow is no fable, now I find My curiosity is sadly satisfied; Ha? if the Dutchess in her stragled wits, Let fall words to betray me to the Cardinal, The Panther will not leap more fierce to meet His prey, when a long want of food hath parch'd His starved maw, than he to print his rage And tear my heart-strings, every thing is fatall, And yet she talk'd sometimes with chain of sense, And said she lov'd me; ha, they come not yet; I have a sword about me, and I left My own security to visit death. Yet I may pause a little, and consider Which way does lead me to't most honorably; Does not the Chamber that I walk in tremble? What will become of her, and me, and all The world in one small hour? I do not think Ever to see the day agen, the wings Of night spread o'r me like a sable Herse-cloath, The Stars are all close mourners too; but I Must not alone to the cold silent grave, I must not; If thou canst Alvarez open That Ebon curtain, and behold the man, When the worlds justice fails shall right thy ashes, And feed their thirst with blood, thy Dutchess is Almost a Ghost already; and doth wear Her body like a useless upper garment, The trim and fashion of it lost. Ha? Enter Placentia. Pla. You need not doubt me, Sir, My Lady prays You would not think it long, she in my ear, Commanded me to tell you, that when last She drank, she had happy wishes to your health. Her. And did the Cardinal pledge it? Pla. He was not Invited to't nor must he know you are here. Her. What do they talk of prethee? Pla. His Grace is very pleasant [A Lute is heard. And kind to her, but her returns are after The sad condition of her sense, sometimes unjoynted. Her. They have Musick. Pla. A Lute only, His Grace prepard, they say, the best of Italy That waits upon my Lord. Her. He thinks the Dutchess Is stung with a Tarantula. Pla. Your pardon. My duty is expected. Exit Her. Gentle Lady,—a voice too? Song within. S. Come my Daphne, come away, We do wast the Crystal day; 'Tis Strephon calls. Da. What says my love? S. Come follow to the Mirtle Grove, Where Venus shall prepare New Chaplets for thy hair. D. Were I shut up within a Tree, I'd rend my bark to follow thee. S. My Shepherdess, make hast, The minutes slide too fast: D. In those cooler shades will I Blind, as Cupid, kiss thine ey. S. In thy bosome then I'l stay, In such warm Snow who would not lose his way. Chor. We'l laugh and leave the world behind, And Gods themselves that see, Shall envy thee, and me; But never find Such joys, when they embrace a Deity. If at this distance I distinguish, 'tis not Church musick, and the air's wanton, and no Anthem Sung to't, but some strange Ode of love, and kisses, What should this mean?—ha, he is coming hither, I am betraid, he marches in her hand, I'l trust a little more, mute as the Arras My sword and I here. [He observes Enter Cardinal, Dutchess, Antonelli, and Attendants. Car. Wait you in the first Chamber, and let none Presume to interrupt us. Ex. Serv. She is pleasant; now for some art to poyson all her innocence. Dut. I do not like the Cardinals humour, he Little suspects what guest is in my Chamber. Car. Now Madam you are safe. Dut. How means your Lordship? Car. Safe in my Arms, sweet Dutchess. Dut. Do not hurt me Car. Not for the treasures of the world, you are My pretty charge, had I as many lives As I have carefull thoughts, to do you service, I should think all a happy forfeit to Delight your Grace one minute; 'tis a heaven To see you smile. Dut. What kindness call you this? Car. It cannot want a name while you preserve So plentifull a sweetness, it is love. Dut. Of me? how shall I know't my Lord? Car. By this, and this, swift Messengers to whisper Our hearts to one another. [Kisses. Dut. Pray do you come a wooing? Car. Yes sweet Madam, You cannot be so cruell to deny me. Dut. What my Lord? Car. Another kiss. Dut. Can you Dispense with this my Lord? Alas I fear [Aside. Hernando is asleep, or vanish'd from me. Car. I have mock'd my blood into a flame, and what My angry soul had form'd for my revenge, Is now the object of my amorous sense, I have took a strong inchantment from her lips, And fear I shall forgive Columbo's death Is She consent to my embrace; come Madam. Dut. Whither my Lord? Car. But to your bed or couch, Where if you will be kind, and but allow Your self a knowledg, love whose shape and raptures Wise Poets have but glorified in dreams, Shall make your chamber his eternall Palace; And with such active and essentiall streams Of new delights glide o'r your bosome, you Shall wonder to what unknown world you are By some blest change translated; why d'e pause? And look so wild? will you deny your Governour? Dut. How came you by that Cloven foot? Car. Your fancy Would turn a traitour to your happiness; I am your friend, you must be kind. Dut. Unhand me, Or I'l cry out a rape. Car. You wo'not sure? Dut. I have been cozend with Hernando's shadow, Here's none but heaven to hear me, help, a rape. Car. Are you so good at understanding then, I must use other argument. [He forces her. Her. Go to, Cardinal. [Strikes him. Ex. Dut. Car. Hernando, Murder, Treason, help. Her. An army sha'not rescue thee, your blood Is much inflam'd, I have brought a Lancet wi'me, Shall open your hot veins, and cool your fever; To vex thy parting Soul, it was the same Engin that pinc'd Columbo's heart. Car. Help, Murder. Enter Antonelli and Servants. Anton. Some ring the bell, 'twil raise the Court, My Lord is murder'd, 'tis Hernando. The bell rings. Her. I'l make you all some sport,—So, now we are even, Where is the Dutchess, I would take my leave Of her, and then bequeath my curse among you. [Her. falls. Enter King, Dutchess, Valeria, Lords, Guard. K. How come these bloody objects? Her. With a trick my sword found out, I hope he's paid. 1 Lo. I hope so to; a Surgeon for my Lord Cardinal. K. Hernando? Dut. Iustice, Oh Iustice Sir, against a ravisher. Her. Sir I ha' done you service. K. A bloody service. Her. 'Tis pure Scarlet. Enter Surgeon. Car. After such care to perfect my revenge Thus banded out o'th' world by a womans plot? Her. I have preserv'd the Dutchess from a rape, Good-night to me and all the world for ever. [Dies. K. So impious. Dut. 'Tis most true, Alvarez blood Is now reveng'd, I find my brain return, And every stragling sense repairing home. Car. I have deserv'd you should turn from me Sir, My life hath been prodigiously wicked, My blood is now the Kingdoms balm; oh Sir, I have abus'd your ear, your trust, your people, And my own sacred Office, my conscience Feels now the sting, oh shew your charity, And with your pardon like a cool soft gale Fan my poor sweating soul; that wanders through Unhabitable climes, and parched deserts; But I am lost, if the great World forgive me, Unless I find your mercy for a crime You know not Madam, yet against your life. I must confess, more than my black intents Upon your honour, y'are already poyson'd. K. By whom? Car. By me, In the revenge I ow'd Columbo's loss, With your last meat was mixt a poyson that By subtle, and by sure degrees must let in death. K. Look to the Dutchess, our Physicians? Car. Stay, I will deserve her mercy, though I cannot Call back the deed, in proof of my repentance, If the last breath of a now dying man May gain your charity, and belief, receive This Ivory box in it an antidote 'Bove that they boast the great magistrall medicine, That pouder mixt with wine by a most rare And quick access to the heart will fortifie it Against the rage of the most nimble poyson, I am not worthy to present her with it, Oh take it and preserve her innocent life. 1. Lo. Strange, he should have a good thing in such readyness. Car. This that which in my jealousie and state Trusting to false predictions of my birth, That I sh dy by poyson, I preserv'd For my own safety, wonder not, I made, That my companion was to be my refuge. Enter Servant with a bowle of Wine. 1 Lo. Her's some touch of grace. Car. in greater proof of my pure thoughts I take This first, and with my dying breath confirm My penitence, it may benefit her life, But not my wounds; oh hasten to preserve her, And though I merit not her pardon, let not Her fair soul be divorc'd K. This is some charity, may it prosper Madam. Valeria. How does your grace? Dut. And must I owe my life to him whose death Was my ambition? take this free acknowledgment, I had intent this night with my own hand To be Alvarez Iusticer. K. You were mad, And thought past apprehension of revenge. Dut. That shape I did usurp, great Sir, to give My Art more freedom and defence, but when Hernando came to visit me, I thought I might defer my execution, Which his owe rage suppli'd without my guilt, And when his lust grew high, met with his blood. 2 Lo. The Cardial smiles. Car. Now my revenge has met With you my nimble Dutchess, I have took A shape to give my act more freedom too, And now I am sure she's poyson'd, with that doze I gave her last. K. Th'art not so horrid? Dut. Ha! some Cordiall. Car. Alas no preservative Hath wings to overtake it, were her heart Lock'd in a quarry, it would search, and kill Before the aids can reach it; I am sure You sha not now laugh at me. K. How came you by that poyson? Car. I prepar'd it, Resolving when I had enjoy'd her, which The Colonel prevented, by some art To make her take it, and by death conclude My last revenge; you have the fatal Story. K. This is so great a wickedness, it will Exceed belief. Car. I knew I could not live. Surgeon. Your wounds, Sir, were not desperate. Car. Not mortall? ha? were they not mortall? Surg. If I have skill in Surgery. Car. Then I have caught my self in my own Engin. 2 Lo. It was your fate you said to dy by poyson. Car. That was my own prediction to abuse Your faith, no humane art can now resist it, I feel it knocking at the seat of life, It must come in, I have wrackt all my own To try your charities, now it would be rare, If you but waft me with a little prayer, My wings that flag may catch the wind, but 'tis In vain, the mist is risen, and ther's none To stear my wandring bark. [Dyes. 1 Lo. He's dead? K. With him Dy all deceived trust. 2 Lo. This was a strange impiety. K. When men Of Gifts and sacred Function once decline From virtue, their ill deeds transcend example. Dut. The minute's come that I must take my leave too. Your hand great Sir, and though you be a King, We may exchange forgiveness, heaven forgive, And all the world. I come, I come Alvarez [Dyes. K. Dispose their bodies for becoming funeral; How much are Kings abus'd by those they take To royall grace? whom when they cherish most By nice indulgence, they doo often arm Against themselves: from whence this maxim springs, None have more need of Perspectives than Kings. Exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Epilogue. Within. Mr. Pollard, wher's Mr. Pollard for the Epilogue? He is thrust upon the Stage, and falls. Epilogue. I am coming to you Gentlemen, the Poet Has help'd me thus far on my way, but I'l Be even with him; the Play is a Tragedy, The first that ever he compos'd for us, Wherein he thinks he has done pretily, Enter Servant. And I am sensible; I prethee look Is nothing out of joynt? has he broke nothing? Serv. No Sir, I hope. Epi. Yes, he has broke his Epilogue all to peeces, Canst thou put it together agen? Ser. Not I Sir. Epi. Nor I, prethee be gone, hum? Mr. Poet, I have a teeming mind to be reveng'd. You may assist, and not be seen in't now. If you please Gentlemen, for I do know He listens to the issue of his cause, But blister not your hands in his applause, Your private smile, your nod, or hum, to tell My fellows, that you like the business well; And when without a clap you go away, I'l drink a small-bear health to his second day; And break his heart, or make him swear, and rage He'l write no more for the unhappy Stage; But that's too much, so we should lose; faith shew it; And if you like his play, 'ts as well, he knew it. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>