<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Duncombe, William, 1690-1769</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Duncombe, William, 1690-1769</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">duncombe william 1690 1769</field>
      <field name="author_text">Duncombe, William, 1690-1769</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">18th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1730's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V2.0879.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1735</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460399</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Junius Brutus ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Junius Brutus ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="title_facet">junius brutus</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">junius brutus</field>
      <field name="title_text">Junius Brutus ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="year_display">1735</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1735</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1735</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460399&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460399&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Duncombe, William, 1690-1769&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;duncombe william 1690 1769&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Junius Brutus ; A Tragedy&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;junius brutus&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1735&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1735&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Duncombe, William&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1690&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1769&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Junius Brutus&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed : And Sold by J. Roberts [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1735&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872711-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv20879&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 18th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;18th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Junius Brutus&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 159 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Junius Brutus.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1735.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 25 Nov 1734.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">JUNIUS BRUTUS, A TRAGEDY.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Consulis imperium hic primus, sævasque secures Accepit: natosque pater, nova bella moventes, Ad pœnam pulchrâ pro libertate vocavit, Infelix— Vincit amor patriæ, laudumque immensa cupido. Virgil.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">To the Right Honourable the Lord ?</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE PREFACE. I am to acquaint the Reader, that this Play is form'd on the Model of Mr. De Voltaire's excellent Tragedy, entitled, Brutus, tho' with considerable Alterations and Additions, especially in the Fifth Act. If with these it appears more agreeable to the English Taste, I shall have no Reason to think my Time ill-employ'd. Mr. De Voltaire says, in the Dedication to the French Tragedy, That it is surprising no English Poet ever writ a Play upon this Story, which he seems to think peculiarly adapted to the English Genius. But he was misinform'd in this Particular; for Mr. Lee writ a Tragedy on the same Subject in the Reign of King Charles the Second, entitled, Lucius Junius Brutus, Father of his Country; which, after it had been thrice acted, was forbid by the Lord Chamberlain Arlington, as an Antimonarchical Play: But, if it had been allow'd, it cou'd not, I believe, have succeeded, unless by the Force of Party and Prejudice; for, besides its being full of Rants, (which perhaps might be serviceable to it in the Representation,) the Character of Brutus is there so shockingly Severe, without any Softnings of Tenderness and Humanity, that (however vouch'd by History) it can scarce seem natural to a discerning Audience, much less agreeable to a polite one. The whole is conducted in so different a manner from this Play, that all the Use I have made of it was to borrow two Lines in the Fifth Act. I persuade myself, that the Reader will be pleased with the following Quotation from my Lord Lansdown's Preface to his Tragedy, entitled, Heroick Love. ‘When we observe (says that elegant Writer,) how little Notice is taken of the noble and sublime Thoughts and Expressions of Mr. Dryden in Oedipus, and what Applause is given to the Rants and the Fustian of Mr. Lee, what can we say, but that Madmen are only fit to write, when nothing is esteem'd Great and Heroic but what is unintelligible?’ I had, at the Instance of some learned Friends, prepared Choruses for this Play, after the manner of the Ancients; but finding no Disposition in the Managers of the Theatres to be at the Expence necessary for such an Undertaking, was oblig'd to drop that Design. I am inform'd, that Mr. Galliard has set to Musick the Choruses for the late Duke of Buckingham's Tragedy of Julius Cæsar, all writ by the Duke himself; and that Signior Bononcini has set those to his Grace's Tragedy of Marcus Brutus, writ by the Duke and Mr. Pope. Whenever they are perform'd, I doubt not but they will convince the Public, more effectually than any thing that I cou'd offer, how Subservient Musick might be made to the Drama. I cannot conclude without returning my humble and hearty Thanks to the Spectators, for their kind Reception of this Dramatick Essay.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PROLOGUE. Spoken by Mr. MILWARD. The Tragic Muse subdues relentless Hearts, Corrects light Mirth, and pleasing Woe imparts. Her soothing Strains with awful Pomp controul The Pride of Pow'r, and humanize the Soul; While guilty Mortals, with just Terror, view The Tortures that their daring Crimes pursue. Tho' lately banish'd from the British Stage, She boldly now resumes her gen'rous Rage. When Infant Rome, for warlike Arts renown'd, Began t'enlarge her Empire's narrow Bound, A Prince arose who by no Laws confin'd, Trampled on all the Rights of Humankind; With unrelenting Rage enslav'd the Land; The People groan'd beneath his cruel Hand: The Patriot-Citizens essay'd in vain, The Torrent of his Fury to restrain. Then Brutus, rais'd by Heav'n for Public Good, Himself descended from the Royal Blood, Stood forth t'assert the suff'ring Romans Cause, And vindicate their violated Laws. A foreign Bard these Scenes in Britain plann'd, Britain, dear Liberty! thy Darling Land. The Genius of our Isle here shines confest, Which warm'd with British Fire a Gallic Breast! Since, in Defiance of Despotic Sway, A Stranger durst such gen'rous Truths display, It were a Crime to doubt of Your Applause, Who are so happy to be rul'd by Laws.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE PROLOGUE. As it was writ Originally. When Infant Rome, for warlike Arts renown'd, Began t'enlarge her Empire's narrow Bound, A Prince arose who by no Laws confin'd, Trampled on all the Rights of Humankind; With unrelenting Rage enslav'd the Land; The People groan'd beneath his cruel Hand: The Patriot-Citizens essay'd in vain, The Torrent of his Fury to restrain. Then Brutus, rais'd by Heav'n for Public Good, Himself descended from the Royal Blood, Stood forth t'assert the suff'ring Romans Cause, And vindicate their violated Laws. Here, faintly sketch'd, the Warrior Prince you'll see, Who sav'd these Realms from double Tyranny. When pure Religion, drooping, hung her head, And frighted Justice from the Benches fled; When ev'ry Sacred Tye was wildly broke, And Britain bow'd beneath Oppression's Yoke; With just Resentment kindled by her Grief, The generous Heroe flew to her Relief, Redress'd her crying Wrongs, dissolv'd her Fears, And fixt her Liberties for Length of Years; The Night of Superstition chas'd away, And gave to View fair Truth's Meridian Ray! To Him we owe th'Illustrious Royal Race, Who with mild Sway the British Sceptre grace. Justice and Equity our Rights maintain, And, Uncontroul'd, with awful Splendor reign! Britons, with grateful Hearts your Freedom prize, And, as your Blessings, let your Joys arise! [The following Lines were inserted last Year, when his Highness the Prince of Orange was in England.] See! William's worthy Heir adorn our Isle, Whose Reverend Genius greets him with a Smile; Early he glows, in Arts and Arms to shine, Gracing with Native Worth his Ancient Line, While all the Muses their glad Aid impart, With Anna's Charms to fire his generous Heart.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Dramatis Personæ. MEN. Junius Brutus, Consul. Mr. Mills. Valerius Publicola, Consul. Mr. Berry. Titus, the Son of Brutus. Mr. Milward. Cælius, Ambassador from Porsenna, King of Tuscany. Mr. W. Mills. Messala, a Noble Roman, the Friend of Titus. Mr. Theo. Cibber. Silvius, Senator. Mr. Winstone. Rufus, Senator. Mr. Turbutt. Proculus, a Military Tribune. Mr. Woodbourne. Albinus, a Friend of Cælius. Mr. Hewit. WOMEN. Lucia, the Daughter of Lucius Tarquinius, commonly call'd Tarquin the Proud, the deposed King of Rome. Mrs. Heron. Hortensia, her Confident. Mrs. Pritchard. Senators, Lictors, Guards, &amp;c. SCENE, The Palace of the Consuls at Rome.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. SCENE I. SCENE, A Hall in the Palace of the Consuls, with a Prospect of the Capitol. The Senate are assembled before the Altar of Mars. Brutus and Valerius preside as Consuls. The Senators are ranged in a Semi-circle; and the Lictors, with their proper Ensigns, stand behind. BRUTUS. Ye brave Assertors of our Country's Freedom; The Tyrants Scourge; disdaining all Subjection But to the Gods, and Numa's sacred Laws; The great Porsenna, Tarquin's Tuscan Friend, Who covers with his Host the Banks of Tyber, And scornful threatned to chastise the Romans, At length begins to treat us with Respect. Dreading the Valour of a free-born People, He sues to Rome. Cælius, whom he deputes, Is just arriv'd, and asks immediate Audience. He waits the Senate's Answer. Fathers, Say, Shall we reject, or hear his Embassy? VALERIUS. However plausible the Terms he offers, Return him to his Lord without an Audience: This I declare my Sense. Henceforth let Rome Disdain to treat but with her vanquish'd Foes. Your Son, 'tis true, th'Avenger of his Country, Has twice repuls'd Porsenna's fierce Attacks. But this is not enough: Rome, still besieg'd, Beholds the Tuscan Camp spread round her Walls. Let banish'd Tarquin first retire; and then We'll weigh the Purport of his Embassy. Despairing to succeed by open Force, He now attempts to conquer us by Art. I view Ambassadors with jealous Eyes: Cælius is only sent to spy our Weakness, Or to seduce the Romans from their Duty. Hear not his soothing Words and subtle Glosses; Nor lose by Treaties, what you win by Arms!— Unskill'd in Fraud, O Rome! 'tis thine to fight.— To aid the just, and root out lawless Kings; To spare submissive Foes, and quell the Proud; Be these the Arts t'exalt thy rising Empire! BRUTUS. Rome knows, how dear I prize her Liberty; But tho' my Heart is fill'd with equal Ardour, In this Debate I differ from Valerius. I view this Embassy address'd from Kings, As the first Homage paid Rome's Citizens. Let us awhile permit the Pride of Monarchs, To treat with this Republick as their Equal; Till, prosper'd by the Gods, ere long we teach 'em, To own the Sovereign Pow'r of Rome as Vassals. Cælius, 'tis said, is sent to spy our Weakness; Why for that Reason let him be admitted; Allow this supple Slave of lawless Power, Here to converse for once at least with Men. Let him survey the Towers of Rome at leisure; In You he'll find our City's strongest Bulwark. [The Senators arise, and move towards the Consuls, to give their Votes. VALERIUS. Your Sense, I see, prevails. Rome and her Brutus Ordain his Audience: I yield, tho' with Regret. Lictors, conduct him in; and may our Country Have no Occasion to repent his Presence. [To Brutus.] On Thee alone the Eyes of all are fix'd; You rouz'd us first to break our slavish Bonds; Still vindicate the Cause of Liberty, And spread around the generous Principles, That warm and animate a Roman Breast! SCENE II. The Senate, Cælius, Albinus, and Attendants. Cælius enters, preceded by two Lictors and Albinus. He passes before the Consuls and the Senate, whom he salutes, and stands in the Front of the Theatre. CÆLIUS. Consuls and Senators— I give you Thanks for the distinguish'd Honour, Here to behold your Venerable Council, And to approach this awful Seat of Heroes; In Person to admire your shining Virtues, And hear the Soul of Rome in Brutus speak! Far from the Clamours of that barbarous Crowd, Whom a wild frantic Fury hurries on; Inconstant in their Love, as blind in Hate, Who threat and crouch, are Lords and cringing Slaves, All in a Day!—whose Insolence— BRUTUS. Hold, Cælius! There is no Slave in Rome. Know you must treat Her free-born Citizens with more Respect; It is the Senate's Pride to represent That virtuous People you so rashly censure. Your flatt'ring Arts will all be fruitless here. That Poison, which corrupts the Tuscan Court, Is yet unknown among the Roman Senate. Proceed. CÆLIUS. Unmov'd by these imperious Words, I look with Pity on your falling State, And mourn the Woes to which you are expos'd: I, as a Son of Rome, espouse her Cause. You see the dreadful Storm that low'rs around; Titus in vain averts th'impending Blow; His daring Hand (I speak it with Regret) Can only make your Ruin more Illustrious. His Victories unman your feeble Walls; The Blood of your own Soldiers fills your Trenches. Why will you then reject a Peace so needful? As you pretend t'assert the Cause of Rome, Porsenna is the Friend of injur'd Tarquin. Reflect, ye formidable Roman Sires! Sagacious Patrons of the People's Rights! You who judge Kings! Reflect, where now ye are! See there the Capitol, those very Altars, Where heretofore, attesting all the Gods, Ye swore Obedience to your banish'd King. These Eyes beheld you, prostrate at his Feet, With loyal Ardour plight your Faith to Tarquin. What Gods have then dissolv'd a Monarch's Right? What Pow'r can break a Tye, so strong and solemn? Who has releas'd you from your Oaths?— BRUTUS. Himself. Name not those Tyes, his flagrant Crimes have broke; His forfeit Title, and the Gods he mock'd! Mankind are all, by Nature, free and equal; 'Tis their Consent alone, gives just Dominion. With what Pretence of Right can Tarquin claim Respect and Reverence from the Roman State, Which he so boldly labour'd to subvert? Cælius, when we elected him our King, We vow'd Allegiance, but not Servitude! And since you call to mind, that in yon' Temple, You saw the Senate plight their Faith to Tarquin, Remember too, in the same sacred Place, In Presence of the Gods, before their Altars, He promis'd to maintain the Rights of Rome: This was the Bond between the King and People. Our Oaths are cancell'd by the Breach of His. By violating Laws Divine and Human, Tarquin alone rebells, and Rome is free! CÆLIUS. Should it alas! be true, that Sovereign Power Has tempted him beyond the Bounds of Reason; And that, deluded by this Siren's Wiles, He fondly stray'd from Virtue's fairer Paths; Where lives the Man, that does not sometimes err? Or where the King, exempt from Human Frailty? But how dare Subjects, form'd by Heav'n t'obey, Contend against th'Awards of Providence, And with high Hand call Monarchs to Account? What! shall a Son chastise a guilty Father? With silent Grief he only mourns his Crimes! And shall we pay less Reverence to Kings? We are their Sons, the Gods alone their Judges. If Jove sometimes deputes them in his Wrath, As Instruments to scourge a stubborn People, Provoke him not to send severer Judgments; Nor change the Regal Power for Anarchy, And by new-modelling the State, subvert it. By sage Affliction taught, (Man's best Instructer) Tarquin will more consult the Good of Rome. You may, in lasting Peace and Union join'd, Restore the Happiness of King and People; Then Liberty shall smile secure, and flourish, Protected by your Monarch's milder Sway. BRUTUS. 'Tis now too late: Each Country has its Laws, Which, uncontroul'd, it abrogates at Pleasure. The Tuscans, to their Kings and Priests enslav'd, Wish all Mankind as abject as themselves. The gen'rous Greeks, Patrons of Liberty, By Arts and Arms swell the loud Trump of Fame. The soft luxurious Race of rich Ionia Bow down their Necks to trampling Tyranny. The Kings of Rome were never Absolute. Numa, who gave us Laws, himself obey'd them. We share the Weight of the supreme Command. [He rises. Great Jove, thou Sov'reign Pow'r! forgive the Romans Their long Delay to pass the solemn Sentence, Against proud Tarquin and his impious Race, For ever to exclude them from the Throne! When, in Defiance of the Laws and Justice, He wantonly destroy'd his Subjects Lives, The Tyrant then depos'd the Legal King! The Romans, prest beneath his Iron Sceptre, By Sufferings rouz'd, resume their antient Courage, And with One Voice disclaim Despotic Sway. The Tuscans too, had they the Souls of Men, Might learn from Us t'expell licentious Tyrants! [The Consuls move towards the Altar, and the Senate rises. O Mars! thou Tutelary Pow'r of Rome, The Hero's Guardian, and the God of Battels! Receive our ardent Vows, on thy dread Altar, For this great Council, and the Roman People. Should there be found among the Sons of Rome A Soul so base, barely to wish for Bondage, Or harbour the least Thought to bring back Tarquin, May the perfidious Wretch expire in Tortures; And may his Ashes, scatter'd by the Winds, Leave nought beside a Name, still more accurst, If possible, than that of guilty Tarquin! CÆLIUS, moving towards the Altar. And I, on this same Altar you profane, Swear, in the Name of your deserted King, And in Porsenna's Name, his just Avenger, Eternal War to all the Roman Race! [The Senators move towards the Capitol. Stay, Senators; I have not yet complain'd Of all the Outrages I have in Charge. Is Tarquin's Daughter too, whom you detain, Design'd a Victim for the Roman Safety? Or do you load her Princely Hands with Chains, T'insult her Sire, and all the neighb'ring Kings? Is that Imperial Wealth, those ample Treasures, From whence his Donatives so largely flow'd, Now yours by Gift? or do you claim by Conquest? Well you dethrone the King to seize his Riches! Let Brutus, if he can, deny this Charge. BRUTUS, turning himself towards Cælius. Thou'rt yet a Stranger to the Roman Genius; We, and these Senators, Foes to Corruption, Have heap'd no Wealth, tho' hoary grown in Honours: Take then the Gold: Let Tarquin revel with it, Nor envy us our Poverty and Freedom.— Lucia, to Me entrusted by the Senate, Enjoys not here, indeed, that Royal Pomp, Those flatt'ring Honours and luxurious Pleasures, Whose Siren Charms corrupt the tender Heart; But all the kind Regard she has receiv'd, Due to her Sex, her Youth, and her Misfortunes. She is permitted to return with You. Henceforth may Nought in Rome belong to Tarquin, But Public Hate, and Vengeance of the Gods! To carry off th'Effects and Gold requir'd, You are allow'd a Day; That must suffice; In the mean while, my House is your Protection: Freely enjoy all Hospitable Rights. You have the Senate's final Resolution. Acquaint Porsenna with our fixt Decree, And bear to him from us War and Defiance! VALERIUS to the Senate. Proceed we now to crown the Capitol With Laurel Wreaths, that deck'd the Brows of Titus. There let us hang the Spoils and bloody Trophies, His happy Hands have ravish'd from the Tuscans. [To Brutus.] Thus may your late Descendants, with like Ardour, From Age to Age, Triumphant fight for Rome! BRUTUS. Ye righteous Pow'rs! continue still to bless The glorious Cause of Freedom with Success! [Exeunt all but Cælius and Albinus. SCENE III. Cælius, Albinus. CÆLIUS. Didst thou remark the Senate's stubborn Pride, Who vainly think themselves Invincible? They would be so indeed, were Time allow'd 'em, To cherish in their Sons this daring Spirit. Albinus, the fair Plan of Liberty, Which every Mortal secretly adores, Inspires the Soul with such a dauntless Courage, As they ne'er know, who feel the Weight of Bondage! In Tarquin's Reign a Flow of circling Joys, Unstrung their Nerves, and sunk their Martial Ardour. The King, employ'd in conquering his own Subjects, Permitted us t'enjoy the Sweets of Peace. But should the Roman Genius once awake; Should Rome be free; the Torrent of her Arms Will with wild Rage o'erwhelm the neighb'ring Nations. These Lions, which their Masters made so Tame, Will whet their Fangs, and spring upon their Foes! Then let us, by their Ruin, timely scatter The gathering Storms, which threaten all Hesperia, And may, ere long, disturb the World's Repose. For our own Safety, let us bind the Romans In the same Chains which they would fix on others. But will Messala come? May we confer? And will he dare— ALBINUS. This was the Place assign'd. He'll straight be here. Titus is his Support. CÆLIUS. But art thou well assur'd he may be trusted? ALBINUS. If right I know Messala, he conspires, Rather to change his own, than Tarquin's Fortune; And yet his Courage is as firm and dauntless, As if inspir'd by Thirst of jealous Honour. He's Master of himself, and of his Secrets, Impenetrably close, when most provok'd. CÆLIUS. In Tarquin's Reign, when last I was at Rome, I took him to be such as you describe, And since his Letters—But see! he here approaches. SCENE IV. Cælius, Messala, Albinus. CÆLIUS. Noble Messala, Hail! Thy Royal Master Accepts thy duteous Zeal with warm Affection, And bears a Heart that counts itself thy Debtor. What! nor Porsenna's Threats, nor Tarquin's Gold, Nor all th'alluring Charms a Court displays, Can move the Senate!—Are these Patricians Exempt from Hope and Fear, and every Passion? MESSALA. So they pretend; but their affected Justice, Their Scorn of Riches, and Contempt of Pleasures, Are nought but the prevailing Thirst of Power. On Crowns they trample with superior Pride. These strenuous Patrons of the Roman Rights, Banish their King, to Tyrannize themselves. Under the soft, seducing Name of Fathers, They haughtily affect the Pomp of Princes. Rome has but chang'd her Bonds; and for One King, Will in the Senate find a Hundred Tyrants! CÆLIUS. Are any of your Citizens so honest, As to detest this lowest Servitude? MESSALA. Few feel their Misery; their giddy Minds Are still transported with this sudden Change. The meanest Citizen, with Want oppress'd, Now swells with Pride, as equal to his King. Yet I've a Band select of faithful Friends, Who cannot brook the Yoke of these new Masters; Souls Resolute and Bold, whose Hands and Hearts Were form'd to shake, or change the Fate of Empires! CÆLIUS. Say, what may we expect from these brave Romans? Will they assist their King? MESSALA. Fearless of Danger, Their Lives and Fortunes are devoted to him. Yet think not they, with Enthusiastic Zeal, Will hazard All to serve ungrateful Masters. Tarquin, they know, is prodigal of Words, But when restor'd, they say, he'll soon forget, Or hate, perhaps, the generous Hands that sav'd him. They know the Great too well. When in Disgrace, Cringing they sooth the meanest of the Crowd; But soon as Fortune seats them high in Honour, They view with Scorn, at Night, the Darling Friend, That in the Morn was tenderly caress'd; And treat their Vassals, as mere Tools of State, Which, when their own ambitious Views are serv'd, They throw disdainfully away as Useless! Hear then the Terms, on which my Friends will aid you. They ask a Chief, whose well-establish'd Fame May win the Hearts of this inconstant People; A Chief so great, that should we prove victorious, He may oblige the King to keep his Faith; Or, if we fall, boldly revenge our Deaths. CÆLIUS. If I remember right, your Letters mention'd That Titus— MESSALA. Titus is Rome's chief Support, The very Life and Soul of all the Party! He is the Son of Brutus— And yet— CÆLIUS. How does he brook th'unjust Requital, He has receiv'd for all his gallant Actions? His single Hand sav'd Rome; and yet his Merit Could not procure a Consulship.— I know he was rejected— MESSALA. And, I know, he murmurs; His Blood boils high at this ungrateful Treatment. The Generous Senate gives him no Reward, Except the Noisy Honour of a Triumph. I've closely watch'd the Sallies of his Passions: He's yet a Novice in the Field of Glory, And may, by artful Management, be led. Impetuous Youth is wrought upon with Ease. But then maturely weigh, what Prejudices We have to conquer; Rome, a Father, a Consul, The tender Sense of Shame, and Fear to lose The Fame acquir'd by his illustrious Deeds. Therefore study Titus; read all his Soul, The Rage that swells, the Flame that melts his Heart. He dies for Lucia— CÆLIUS. Has Titus fix'd his Love on Tarquin's Daughter? MESSALA. I with much Labour wrung this Secret from him; He glows with Shame, and dares not own his Weakness. But among all the Passions that distract him, A Zeal for Liberty is most outragious. CÆLIUS. The Fate of Rome, in spight of my Endeavours, I see, depends upon this single Man, And varies with his fickle Gusts of Passion. But let us not despair. [To Albinus.] Do thou, Albinus, Prepare this Instant to return to Tarquin. [To Messala.] Let us attend the Princess: Some Experience Has open'd to my View the Human Heart. I'll pry into her Soul; and thence, perhaps, May weave a Snare to take the haughty Romans. Awhile the Lordly Lion scours the Plains, Mocks at the Spear, and terrifies the Swains; At length, entangled in the Hunter's Toils, With Fury roars, and drops th'untasted Spoils! End of the First Act.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. SCENE I. SCENE, An Apartment in the Palace of the Consuls. LUCIA, HORTENSIA. Hortensia. Lucia, you'll soon be seated on a Throne; Propitious Fate now offers to your Hands More than it ravish'd from your Father Tarquin. When wedded to Liguria's happy King, Subjects obsequious to their Prince's Will, Shall joyfully obey your mild Commands. But why, when Fortune thus relenting smiles, Swells your sad Heart, abandon'd to Despair? I've always shar'd the Sorrows you have known; If you love me, Oh! speak; What Grief devours you? Can you still languish for the Loss of Rome? LUCIA. Rome? the detested Seat of Blood and Slaughter! The Curse of Kings, and Source of all my Sorrows! The Place where I am yet detain'd a Prisoner! Rome!—Ah why was that accomplish'd Heroe, Why was the lovely Titus born a Roman? HORTENSIA. Is Titus then still Sovereign of your Heart? You have deceiv'd your too, too easy Friend! Did you not boast, that now you view'd him only, As Tarquin's Foe, and as the Son of Brutus? That you abhor'd his Name? LUCIA. I then believ'd it: Disdainful of my blind ill-fated Love, I labour'd to suppress the growing Flame, Nor thought my Passion was so deeply rooted. Indulging in thy Arms my boundless Grief, I sooth'd myself with Hope, I only mourn'd The King's Afflictions, and a Brother's Death. My foolish Heart, alas! deceiv'd itself, And from my View conceal'd the guilty Cause. To thee I'll own the Weakness of my Soul; Those Tears, a Brother's cruel Death demanded, Were drawn, I fear, by Love, and flow'd for Titus. But now, the Pain it gives me to depart, Tears from my Eyes the Veil that cover'd them. HORTENSIA. Then fly without Delay from these Usurpers, And cherish in your Breast the Scorn of Titus. Rome is too dangerous now for Tarquin's Daughter. LUCIA. Alas! my Infant Flame was free from Guilt. 'Twas you alone, displaying all his Virtues, Instructed first my yielding Heart to love him; Yet will I not upbraid thee, thoughtless Maid, Ev'n Thee, th'unhappy Cause of all my Anguish! You painted Titus, at my Father's Court, The Darling of the Senators and People, Gracing the Royal Blood from whence he sprung, Worthy my Father's Choice, more worthy Mine. But while your Tongue flow'd wanton in his Praise, A subtle Poison stole into my Heart. I rashly entertain'd a fruitless Hope; And thought I read in his respectful Eyes The Signs of growing Love, yet check'd with Awe. O fatal Error! now too late discover'd. HORTENSIA. Those were the Days of soft Tranquility, When Musick, Revelry, and costly Feasts, With all the Pomp of Tarquin's splendid Court, Invited sprightly Hopes, and gay Desires. But, Lucia, you forget your present State; How cruelly now Titus treats your Father; Has he not slain his Friends, repuls'd his Troops, And fortify'd the daring Hands of Rebels? He tramples under Foot the Royal Rights, And insolently Triumphs for his Treason! LUCIA. 'Tis kindly done to rouze my Indignation— [Huzza's without. Hear'st thou those Shouts in Honour of the Heroe? The Royal Spoils which deck the Capitol, The shatter'd Standards, all embru'd in Blood, The prancing Steeds, the Chariots, Crowns, and Incense, Proclaim his wide Renown, and my Disgrace! And yet my treacherous Heart (with Shame I own it) More fondly doats for what I ought t'abhor him. I see by Battels won against his King, How he would shine, if he had fought for me. The Lustre of his Deeds dazzles my Sight, At once displays his Fame, and hides his Guilt. HORTENSIA. Th'united Force of Absence and of Reason, With the gay Pleasures that attend a Court, To your disorder'd Mind will Peace restore. You'll speedily subdue this tender Passion. LUCIA. A just Disdain will drive it from my Heart! This daring Rebel, by Success elate, Beholds with Scorn the Daughter of his King.— On that illustrious Day to joyful Titus, (To Me, alas! the Source of Shame and Sorrow,) When first his Arms were crown'd with Victory, And Brutus welcom'd his Return with Transport; All bloody from the Slaughter of my Friends, He rush'd into my Presence!—I, struck with Horror And piercing Grief, charg'd him with falt'ring Tongue Never to see me more.— How punctually does he obey this Order! If he but chance to see me at a Distance, He starts, retires, and leaves me to my Woes! HORTENSIA. Behold! here comes—'Tis he himself, 'tis Titus! SCENE II. Titus, Lucia, Hortensia. LUCIA. I cannot fly, yet tremble at his Sight! TITUS. Princess, my Presence, I perceive, afflicts you, And calls forth Tears from your offended Eyes. In vain I try'd t'obey your rigid Order: But you are summon'd hence—Allow me therefore, Once more to see the loveliest of her Sex! Receive this last Adieu from wretched Titus, Who, for thy Sake, with Joy would Life resign, And prizes nought above thee but his Country. When call'd to Battel, in Defence of Rome, I hop'd, at least, to end my Life with Glory, Since it must still displease too cruel Lucia! LUCIA. Can You, the Leader of Rebellious Rome, And Son of Brutus, Author of my Woes, Oppress my Father, and yet pity Lucia? Loaded with Honours, See! the Heroe comes On his Triumphal Day, t'insult my Grief! Retire. That pompous Glory may suffice. TITUS. The Gods have stain'd the Lustre of its Charms; May the same Gods, henceforth more just to thee, For Sorrows past, double thy future Joys! You merited a Crown: A Crown they have bestow'd. Go then and reign: Enjoy at once the Throne, And raptur'd Heart of an enamour'd Monarch; Throughout the World he is the only King, Whose Happiness my jealous Heart could envy. LUCIA. Ah! wretched Lucia! check thy rising Tears! [Aside. TITUS. What secret Impulse urges me along? Lucia, I was thy Foe; but in Revenge, The Gods have made me now thy faithful Slave. This Flame, which I condemn, in Silence cherish'd, Increas'd by thy Disdain, in these last Moments, Impatient of Controul, bursts forth with Fury! With Wrath deserv'd chastise this rash Confession; Nor hope I Pardon, nor ev'n ask for Pity. LUCIA. Relentless Brutus, what a Load of Woes, Thou heap'st upon me! TITUS. Punish his guilty Son; 'Tho' Tarquin's Foe he doats on Lucia— LUCIA. Hold— You know my Birth, and that a Roman Subject Ought to show more Respect to Tarquin's Daughter; But I demand not from a Son of Brutus The Honours of a Rank, which he disclaims. I am at Rome, still here detain'd a Prisoner, And deeply share in all my Father's Woes. My Sorrows flow from You. I dare believe Your Soul too gen'rous to insult th'Afflicted. A Heroe train'd in Virtue's glorious Paths, Will scorn an easy and ignoble Conquest. But if a Roman Heart can yield Obedience; If I may yet command, then shun my Presence, Revere my Grief, and cease to load the Wretched! [Exeunt Lucia and Hortensia. SCENE III. TITUS alone. What have I said? or what did Lucia answer? Ah! whither has my Love transported me? Why, partial Gods, have ye conspir'd to make This glorious Day, a Day so full of Sorrow? SCENE IV. Titus, Messala. TITUS. O! my Messala, on thy friendly Bosom Let me unload my secret Cares and Anguish, The Grief that overwhelms my sinking Soul! MESSALA. The Senators, with overbearing Power, Delight to trample on distinguish'd Merit. TITUS. Love and the Senate both conspire my Ruin! The Senate scornfully rejects my Suit, Refusing me the Honour of a Rank, Won by my Arms, and purchas'd by my Blood. Before my Mind is cool from this Disgrace, Lucia, my Soul's Delight, is ravish'd from me. Ravish'd from me! alas! I've no Pretensions! And yet my Heart is rack'd with Jealousy.— Nay more, I've openly avow'd my Love; The Fire, which I had smother'd in my Breast, Broke forth at length, in spight of all Restraint. Could I have check'd its Rage but one Day more, I might have conquer'd this unmanly Passion, Nor languish'd Life away in shameful Bondage. But Heav'n has mark'd this Period to my Courage.— Shall Brutus' Son, a Soldier, and a Roman, Be now a Woman's Slave, the Slave of Tarquin's Daughter! Guilty to Rome, to Lucia, and Myself, Anger, Revenge, Disdain, Remorse and Love, By turns prevail, and shake my shatter'd Frame! MESSALA. Titus, will you indulge your faithful Friend, To offer his Advice with Confidence? TITUS. Thy Counsels have been ever kind and prudent; Speak then, and make me blush for these mad Transports. MESSALA. I both applaud your Love, and your Resentment. Shall Titus still uphold and countenance Th'unjust Authority of these Patricians, Who with the specious Plea of Liberty Fix on our Necks a heavier Yoke of Bondage? If you must blush, blush for this tame Submission! Shall I behold you pine away your Life, A Victim of the State, despis'd by Lucia? Are these the great Rewards of your high Actions? No doubt, a Heart like yours might still obtain A Conquest there, and humble the proud Senate. TITUS. How dar'st thou sooth me with such idle Hopes? Is not her Hate as strong as my Affection? Alas! dost thou not see the fatal Bars Between us fix'd by Duty and our Fathers? Must she then go, Messala? MESSALA. This very Day! TITUS. I ought not to complain. Heaven does her Justice. It form'd her for a Kingdom. MESSALA. Heaven, more propitious, Perhaps design'd her for a milder Sway. Forgive me, Sir; you know what was her Dower— Her Brother is no more. Rome was her Right— But I transgress—Yet if, to make you happy, To purchase your Repose, my Life could serve; Or if my Blood— TITUS. No more! my Duty conquers. The Soul of Man is free, that dares be so! Tho' Passion for a while obscur'd my Reason, A Soldier's Heart discards this idle Dotage; For Love is only strong by our Indulgence! MESSALA. Behold! th'Ambassador approaches— The Honour which he pays you— TITUS. O fatal Honour!— Th'Ambassador!—He bears away the Princess! 'Tis he who makes my Life a Scene of Woes! [Exit Messala. SCENE V. Titus, Cælius. CÆLIUS. Having in vain essay'd to move the Senate, To save their Country from impending Ruin, Permit me here (to Virtue paying Homage) With open Heart t'admire that generous Ardour, That happy Hand, which still maintains this City Against the fierce Attacks of her Assailants; Worthy a juster Cause, another Foe! Greater Regard, and more august Rewards! Monarchs there are (I here may safely speak it) Who would entrust their Empires to your Hands; Nor view with jealous Eyes those shining Virtues, Whose Lustre dazzles the disdainful Senate, Tho' Rome with Wonder and Delight beholds 'em. I pity your hard Lot to serve such Masters, Who, deaf to Merit, insolently spurn The valiant Friends that best deserve their Favour; And, born t'obey, yet take a cruel Pleasure In laying heavy Bonds on their Deliverers; Who, did they not usurp the Royal Rights, From You should take those Orders, which they give. TITUS. Cælius, I thank you for the kind Concern Which you express for me; nor will enquire Whether you seek by this Address so soothing, To take Advantage of my glowing Anger, And turn my Sword against my native Country. Lose not your Arts on this frank open Breast; My Heart is always naked: 'Tis true, the Senate Have us'd me ill, and I have Right to hate 'em; But still this Hand shall vindicate their Cause. When Rome calls forth her faithful Sons to Battel, They stifle in their Breasts domestic Wrongs; At such a time they know no private Foes. Thus I profess, and thus will ever practise. Be it or Honour, Pride, or Prejudice, Among the Romans born, for them I'll die! I am the Son of Brutus; Tyrants I detest; And on my Heart bear Liberty engrav'd! CÆLIUS. My Lord, you cheat yourself with specious Names. Tho' subject to a King, I prize the Charms Of Sacred Liberty, no less than You; Who, for the Substance, grasp an empty Shadow. Is not the Genius of a Commonwealth Far more Severe than Regal Government? Your boasted Laws are the most cruel Tyrants, Inflexible to Interest, Rank, or Merit. Survey a generous Prince's splendid Court! Honours unsought attend upon Desert; Pleasures, in circling Streams, there gaily flow; And Beauty crowns the Hero's glorious Toils!— They widely err, who brand, as Servitude, The Homage paid to an indulgent King; Since Liberty, protected by his Care, Distributes Joy and Plenty all around! Lov'd by your Prince, and cherish'd by his Smiles, You serve but One; all others are Your Servants. O! that a Soul, so greatly form'd by Heaven To shine in Camps, or grace a polish'd Court, Could taste th'endearing Charms of Tarquin's Friendship! With You he might have shar'd the Sovereign Power— Th'insulting Senate prostrate at your Feet— TITUS. No more—I've seen his Court, and I despise it. I might, perhaps, if I could stoop so low, Be his First Slave, and lord it over others. But I abhor such Baseness. Let me perish, If I be made the Tool of his Ambition! A Virtuous Heart can taste no Joy in Power Gain'd by the Ruin of a free-born People. Thanks be to Heav'n, I've no such abject Wishes; My Soul aspires at pure, unsullied Grandeur, By Honour won, and fix'd on stable Justice. I'll meet thy Kings in Battel. Thou, adore them! CÆLIUS. I must approve your firm and steady Conduct; Yet still remember, in your tender Years, Tarquin rejoic'd to strengthen and exalt Your rising Genius by the best Instruction. He never can forget you. Yester-morn, As he bewail'd his Son's untimely Death, “Titus (said he) might have sustain'd my Race; “His Virtues would have merited my Daughter— TITUS, turning himself away. His Daughter! Gods! Lucia? O hapless Vows! CÆLIUS, [Looking upon Titus.] I bear her to the King whom you renounce, At Distance far from Thee, and from her Country, She weds Liguria's Monarch. In the mean while, Thou may'st obey the Senate, oppress her Father, And ravage his Demesnes with Fire and Sword. But soon, I trust, yon' blazing Capitol, These lofty Roofs, and all your Towers in Flames, Shall serve as Torches to this happy Marriage, And Funeral-Piles for Citizens and Senate! [Exit Cælius. SCENE VI. TITUS alone. He's gone—But in what Anguish has he left me! Lucia might still be Mine! But on what Terms? It shocks my very Soul to think of them! This wily Orator came to discover The secret Flame that preys upon my Heart— It stands confest; my Looks, my every Action Betray'd the Force of my unbounded Love. He now returns triumphant to Porsenna, And mocks the Folly of my fond Desires— Still Lucia might be Mine! I might with Her Wear Life away in ravishing Delights! Great Gods! if this were true—What vain Delusions Dazzle my Senses, and distract my Thoughts! While here I wildly chase a fleeting Phantom, All Rome demands me at the Capitol. Th'impatient Multitude, in countless Numbers, Gather'd beneath the high Triumphal Arches, Echo my Name with joyful Acclamations, And call me to begin the solemn Oaths, Th'inviolable Pledges of our Freedom! I'll go—But there I shall behold the Senate, That Crowd of Kings, the Object of my Hatred— Unhappy Wretch! would they so much offend thee, Was not thy doating Mind enthrall'd to Lucia? Here every thing disgusts thy sickly Sense. Awake! awake! shake off this sluggish Softness! Ah! Titus, calm this Tempest of the Soul, That mocks thy Reason, and defies Controul: Quell thy Revenge; this Tenderness subdue; To Rome, to Brutus, and Thyself be true! O'er thy own Passions now the Conquest gain, Those Tyrants of the Mind, that rend this tortur'd Brain! End of the Second Act.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. SCENE I. CÆLIUS, ALBINUS, MESSALA. Cælius, with a Letter in his Hand. For this Dispatch, Albinus, I'm your Debtor. All answers to my Wish. Upon this Letter Depends the Destiny of Rome and Tarquin. Is the dread Hour agreed on in the Camp? Has the Quirinal Gate been view'd with Care? Say, will our Troops be ready for th'Assault, If by our Friends we cannot gain Admittance? Is Tarquin satisfy'd? Does he now think Rome will be ours? ALBINUS. He glories in your Counsels, To Him more prosperous than Porsenna's Arms.— At Dead of Night our Troops will be prepar'd. CÆLIUS. Either the Gods, Foes to this hapless Prince, Will blast Designs so great and well-concerted, Or Rome to Morrow will be subject to him: Perhaps with Slaughter drench'd, and laid in Ashes.— No matter.—Better a King should, on his Throne, In Peace profound govern the tame Remains, Than with precarious Power assert his Right Over a headstrong giddy Multitude, Prone to revolt from too much Liberty. [To Albinus.] Leave me, Albinus, I expect the Princess. [Exit Albinus. [To Mesalla, who offers to follow Albinus.] Messala, Stay. SCENE II. Cælius, Messala. CÆLIUS. Have thy Attempts succeeded? Will Titus join with the Confederate Kings? MESSALA. I've been, indeed, too sanguine in my Hopes; The Heart of Titus is inflexible. In every Act he fondly copies Brutus, And still harangues for Liberty and Laws. The Senate he abhors, and doats on Lucia; Ambition, Pride, Disdain, and Jealousy, Alternately inflame his lab'ring Breast; And yet the Love of Liberty prevails. At Tarquin's Name he starts into a Passion; And when I urg'd the Prospect of a Crown, With a fierce Look he broke abruptly from me. It had been dangerous to tempt him farther. CÆLIUS. So you despair of making Titus ours? MESSALA. It cost less Pains to bring his Brother over; I have engag'd, at least, one Son of Brutus. CÆLIUS. Is then Tiberius fix'd to us already? Say, by what happy Scheme didst thou succeed? MESSALA. Ambition was the Lure by which I took him; Long with a jealous Eye he has beheld The spreading Lustre of his Brother's Fame; Whose splendid Triumph stung him to the Heart; Tho' generous Titus, scorning all Suspicion, Stretch'd out his Arms from the Triumphal Chariot, And with a fond Embrace carest the Youth, Seeming to make him Partner of his Glory. I chose those lucky Moments to suggest, With what Contempt his Merits were receiv'd, While every Street rung with the Praise of Titus: I promis'd also, in the Name of Tarquin, Profuse Rewards, and all but Royal Honours; In short, this Bait has caught the greedy Prey; Firm to the King, he waits for your Instructions. CÆLIUS. Can he surrender the Quirinal Gate? MESSALA. Titus is posted there, whose dreadful Valour Has too much check'd the Progress of your Arms. He is the Guardian Genius of his Country. I dare not give my Voice for this Attack; Nor hope Success without his pow'rful Aid. CÆLIUS. But, since he was ambitious to be Consul, Can he resist the Offer of a Crown, His certain Dower, if he espouses Lucia? MESSALA. A Crown seems an Affront to his stern Virtue. CÆLIUS. But has not Lucia's Beauty touch'd his Heart? MESSALA. He doats upon her even to Distraction. The Flame suppress'd, with greater Fury burns; He hates the Father, yet adores the Daughter; He fears to speak to her, and sighs in secret: Now he retreats, then eagerly pursues. He yet knows nought of Love but its mad Transports. In the wild Hurry of this furious Tempest, A Moment may produce unlook'd-for Changes. The Soul of Titus, eager and impetuous, Flies out into Extremes of Love and Hatred. Should he but once engage to aid our Arms, 'Twill be impossible to check his Ardour. Ambition's smother'd Fire, that swells his Breast, Perhaps may kindle at the Torch of Love. No doubt he would be glad to see the Senate With abject Fear lie prostrate at his Feet. But I should flatter you, my Lord, to promise That his proud Heart will even yield to Love. Howe'er, I'll make another strenuous Effort. CÆLIUS. Since he loves Lucia, he may still be won. A tender Word, or one kind Look from her, Will more prevail to bend his stubborn Virtue, Than all the Schemes of the profoundest Statesmen— The Passions of Mankind are our best Servants; By those we turn, and wind them at our Pleasure. Lucia enters, Messala retires. SCENE III. Lucia, Cælius, Hortensia. CÆLIUS. I am commanded, Lucia, by your Father, To your own Hands to give this Letter. LUCIA. Ye Gods! prolong his Life; and change his Fate! [She reads.] “The King of Rome may reascend his Throne, “If his most gallant Foe shou'd prove his Friend. “Titus alone is able to restore “A Crown, which I consent with him to share. “Reject th'Addresses of Liguria's Monarch. “If you love Titus, Titus may be yours. “Remember, you receiv'd your Life from me. “On your Resolve depends the Fate of Tarquin. LUCIA. “On your Resolve depends the Fate of Tarquin— And—“Titus may be yours— Can this be possible? Will Tarquin stoop, Inflexible till now, in spight of Woes? Whence does he know, or how?—Ah! cruel Cælius, You only search the Secrets of my Heart! Show more Compassion to a wretched Princess, Nor with these Arts ensnare my heedless Youth! CÆLIUS. Indeed, you wrong me, Lucia, I but fulfill The Orders Tarquin gave, nor aim presumptuous, To pry into the Secrets of your Bosom. My Duty prompts me only to suggest, That Heav'n makes choice of You, to place the Crown Upon your Father's Head, and to restore This ravag'd Kingdom to its ancient Splendor. LUCIA. To serve my Father by joining Hands with Titus! Impossible! Explain this dark Ænigma. CÆLIUS. Trust me, this Heroe glows with secret Ardour Both for the King, and all the Royal Race. Th'Austerity of these Republicans Ill suits the Candor of his generous Heart. I don't pretend to penetrate his Breast; But since he knows the Merit of your Virtues, He must be proud to own himself your Servant. Who can behold so rich a Diadem Presented by your Hands, with double Lustre, And not transported bless the Royal Donor? One soothing Word from You will fix his Heart. Engage then Titus to your Father's Cause, Rome's chief Support, her Tutelary God! Deserve the happy Honour, you enjoy, To turn at Pleasure, and controul the Fate Of your great Sire, and of the Roman State! [Exit Cælius. SCENE IV. Lucia, Hortensia. LUCIA. Ye Pow'rs Supreme, what Incense can I offer? You smile relenting. Blest Reverse of Fortune! That Flame, for which I blush'd, now purely burns, And may with Honour be indulg'd and own'd. [To Hortensia.] Haste, dear Hortensia, and inform my Titus, He is allow'd to come into my Presence. Shall he, unconscious of his Happiness, Languish in Grief, while I exult with Joy? But don't I cherish a delusive Hope? Does Titus then, indeed, abhor the Senate? Alas! perhaps, I owe to his Resentment, That which I thought the sole Effect of Love! HORTENSIA. 'Tis true, the Senate has provok'd his Anger, And he's ambitious—Yet he dies for you! LUCIA. He loves, and will do every thing to serve me! Then fly without Delay— [Exit Hortensia. And yet this sudden Change, This Letter—What struggling Cares encounter Here!— Blaze forth, my Love, consistent now with Virtue! Honour, Reason, Duty, All command it! My Love will fix the Crown on Tarquin's Head! I shall unite brave Titus and my Father! The Happiness of Rome will flow from mine! O! Thou, the Object of my soft Desires! When shall I tell thee this amazing Change? When shall I, Titus, with transporting Pleasure, With thee converse, and hear thy tuneful Voice? Each anxious Care is fled! Rome, I forgive thee! With timely Tears appease thy injur'd Sovereign. Submit, ye Senate; you have lost your Champion! Titus is mine—with Fear obey your King! SCENE V. Titus, Lucia. TITUS. Princess, will you, indeed, vouchsafe to see A Man, whom you so justly may abhor? LUCIA. Titus, be now sincere, and own the Truth: Was that caressing Speech, you late address'd, The Dictate of your Heart, or meant to mock me? TITUS. Alas! this throbbing Breast too plainly shows My raging Flame, my Crime, and my Despair! The Graces of thy Sex, in thee display'd, Thy lovely Form, and still more lovely Mind, With pleasing Force subdue my ravish'd Soul!— You rule my Fate! LUCIA. Nay, mine depends on Thee! TITUS. On Me? My bounding Heart can scarce believe it. Am I not then the Object of your Hate? Princess, proceed; Say, what enchanting Hope Exalts me in a Moment to this Height Of too-transporting Joy? LUCIA, [Giving him the Letter.] Peruse this Letter— [While he is reading.] I then may hope—But whence that sullen Frown, That Air dejected, and that sudden Start? [Aside. TITUS. Of all Mankind, I am the most accurst! My Fate, whose Rigour weighs me to the Ground, Deludes me with a Glimpse of Happiness, Only to snatch the lovely Image from me: And, to compleat the Fulness of my Woes, I love, and may possess, and yet must lose thee! LUCIA. Lose me? TITUS. This Moment has condemn'd my Life To Sorrows most profound, or Infamy; I must be false to Rome or Thee—nor can Chuse aught but shocking Crimes, or dire Afflictions. LUCIA. How can you talk of Crimes and of Afflictions? T'expell thy King, and head a Band of Rebels; To grieve his Daughter, and reject her Love, These are thy shocking Crimes and dire Afflictions! A Father's Choice now justifies my Flame. I thought this Day the fairest of my Life, And yet the Moment, in which my ravish'd Soul May own, without a Blush, her Tenderness, That very Moment, you force me to repent! Open your Eyes, and weigh, in equal Balance, The envious Senate's unrelenting Rigour, Against the milder Sway of Regal Power. Chuse whether you'll obey, or dictate Laws; With Me command, or serve ungrateful Masters; And may the Gods direct your happy Choice! TITUS, [Returning the Letter.] My Choice is made. LUCIA. Then dare not you declare it? Say, What is thy Resolve? TITUS. To be worthy of thee, Worthy my Sire, and faithful to my Country; Tho' languishing for Thee, to fight for Rome; T'admire, and imitate thy shining Virtues; And, tho' I lose, deserve at least to gain thee! LUCIA. Must we then for ever— TITUS. No—Forgive me, Lucia, Forgive the Fury that distracts my Soul; Pity a Heart at Variance with itself; Now more accurst, than when it felt your Scorn. Or with thee, or without thee, I am wretched! O! let me rather die, than see thy Faith T'another plighted! LUCIA. It shall be ever thine! TITUS. If then you love me, let your Soul be Roman; Be more than Queen, and love the Commonwealth. Bring me for Dower, instead of Royal Titles, A Love and Reverence for the Roman Laws. Let Brutus be your Father, Rome your Mother, And her Deliverer your happy Consort: And let the Romans, vanquish'd by your Goodness, Receive their Liberties from Tarquin's Daughter. LUCIA. Should I betray the King that gave me Life? TITUS. Should I have less Regard for Rome and Brutus? LUCIA. Peace, busy Heart! no more betray thy Weakness For an ungrateful Man, who scorns thy Love! SCENE VI. Brutus, Cælius, Titus, Lucia, Messala, Albinus, Proculus, Lictors. BRUTUS, [to Lucia.] Lucia, the Hour is come for your Departure. In the first Fury of the Public Storm, Rome could not give you to your Houshold Gods. Tarquin himself, on fell Revenge employ'd, (His Thoughts entirely bent on our Destruction,) Seem'd for a while forgetful of his Daughter, And did not then demand you of the Romans. But I supply'd the Place of your lost Father— 'Tis with Reluctance that I call to Mind The Sorrows of that melancholy Day. Go, reign: And let unbiass'd Equity Be the firm Basis of your happy Throne. If You would be obey'd, Obey the Laws. Maturely weigh the arduous Task of Kings; If servile Sycophants, with soothing Voice, Should tempt you from the sacred Paths of Justice, Remember Tarquin's Fate, and think of Rome: His Fate, I trust, will stand on lasting Record, A dreadful Monument to future Tyrants! [To Cælius.] Cælius, we yield her to thee; Be it thy Care, To see her safe conducted to her Father. A Guard attends you to the Sacred Gate. [Exeunt Brutus and Lucia at different Doors. Titus, Cælius, and Messala stay. TITUS, [At a Distance.] O! the tormenting Anguish of Despair! [He goes towards Cælius.] She shall not go—Once more permit me, Cælius— Shall hopeless Love still prey upon my Life? [Aside. Allow me but a Word. CÆLIUS. The Time is urgent. Yet, for an Hour, I can protract her Stay; Beware, you do not seek my Aid too late. We may, without Reserve, in her Apartment, Deliberate on this important Crisis. Exit Cælius, following Lucia. SCENE VII. Titus, Messala. TITUS. Are we the Sport of Fortune? Did we meet Only to part for ever?— MESSALA. To see such Charms, with so much Virtue join'd, A Prey to Grief, and overwhelm'd with Woes, Afflicts my Soul, and melts me into Tears! None but a Heart like Hers, could merit Yours. TITUS. No, Messala; Lucia must ne'er be mine! MESSALA. Wherefore? What vain Surmises bar your Wishes? TITUS. The hated Terms impos'd by cruel Lucia!— Shall I obey the Tyrants I have conquer'd, And sacrifice the People I have sav'd? Shall Love, for six long Months oppos'd so firmly, Now, in an Hour, subdue my yielding Virtue? To Tyrants Rage shall I give up my Father? Such a Father? the Darling of his Country! A Pattern to Mankind! the best of Heroes! Who taught me to pursue his glorious Steps! MESSALA. Good Gods!—If Conquest had not crown'd his Cause, What were this Patriot, this mighty Heroe, Echo'd by Rome, as her Deliverer; I say, if Conquest had not crown'd his Cause, Won by your Hand, what were he but a Rebel? TITUS. How, Messala? a Rebel! My Father? To whom? MESSALA. Allow me but to speak. I had not finish'd. Compose yourself; I see you are disturb'd. TITUS. Disturb'd! Have I not Reason?—But go on. MESSALA. You may adorn the Name of Conqueror, With the more lovely Style of Mediator: The Virtues of a Roman Citizen Are seen in You, illustriously display'd; Now practise such as will become a Sovereign. Heaven puts into your Power, this happy Moment, The Object of your Vows, Revenge and Empire.— Bring back those Days, in which our Ancestors Weigh'd with impartial Hand, in equal Balance, Th'Authority of Kings, and Rights of Subjects. Rome may be reconcil'd to Monarchy, For Monarchy is no less amiable, Beneath the Conduct of a virtuous Prince, Than full of Horror, when a Tyrant reigns. Rome would almost adore a King like Titus.— TITUS. Presumptuous Man! thou surely hast forgot, That thou art talking to a Son of Brutus! Henceforth I must behold thee as a Traitor: To pardon Thee, wou'd be to share thy Crimes. MESSALA. Know then, that glorious Wreath, which You disdain, Is destin'd to adorn Another's Brow. What You dare not, Another will accomplish— TITUS. Another! hold—Gods! speak—Who? MESSALA. Your Brother— TITUS. My Brother!— MESSALA. Has pledg'd his Oath to Tarquin. TITUS. Will he betray Rome? MESSALA. He'll serve his King and Rome. Know, Tarquin is resolv'd to give his Daughter To that brave Roman, who restores his Crown. TITUS. Perfidious Wretch, attend!—Blind as I was, I did not see till now the Precipice, To which you artfully conducted me. You'd make me an Accomplice with my Brother, And stain my Soul with Treason's Crimson Dye. But first thy Blood shall answer— [Grasping his Sword. MESSALA. Here—strike this faithful Breast; I merit Death for lab'ring thus to serve you! Then plunge your Sword, yet reeking with my Blood, Into the Hearts of Lucia and your Brother, Lucia reserv'd for him, if you renounce her, The Spring and Life of the Conspiracy! And bearing on your Spear their Heads, as Trophies, Go pray the Senate for the Consulship, As a Reward for these Heroic Deeds; And be again with Scorn rejected by them!— SCENE VIII. Titus, Messala, Albinus. ALBINUS. My Lord, th'Ambassador, at Leisure now, Expects you in th'Apartment of the Princess— TITUS. Say, I'll attend him. [Exit Alb. O! had I never lov'd, I had been virtuous!— Why shou'd I sacrifice my Happiness To yon' imperious Senate?—Let us go— [To Messala.] Behold the Capitol grac'd with my Trophies. MESSALA. Do not unjust Patricians govern there? TITUS. Hush!—Hark!—Methinks I hear a Voice cry out, Forbear! Forbear! Wilt thou betray thy Country? Brutus, and Rome's great Genius cry, Forbear! [Raving. [After a Pause.] Yet free from Stain my Vital Current flows, And this stanch Heart no base Corruption knows! O! if by Heav'n my Ruin is decreed, May I, at least, a Spotless Victim bleed! Ye righteous Pow'rs! Whatever be My Fate, Protect Your Brutus, and the Roman State! End of the Third Act.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT IV. SCENE I. LUCIA, HORTENSIA. Lucia. Urge me no more—I will not see him! Shall I expose myself to new Affronts, And let him kindle in my lab'ring Breast, Th'alternate Flames of Love and Indignation?— Why did'st thou, treach'rous Cælius, thus delude me, And by thy wily Arts protract my Stay? HORTENSIA. You have forgot, that Cælius now expects you. LUCIA. I yet remain, and have no Power to quit This Seat of Woes, the Object of my Hatred! My Spirits are consum'd in vain Complaints! Wretch that I am! what Right have I to murmur? I! who degrading thus the Royal Blood, Have fix'd my Love upon a Rebel Subject; Who fond of Fame, and proud of his Exploits, Can taste no Charms, but Popular Applause. You saw, Hortensia, he would not follow me. HORTENSIA. Trust me, Lucia, Titus feels sharper Pangs Than you conceive. He labour'd to suppress His swelling Grief, that struggled for a Vent; Yet now and then a gushing Tear confess'd, What inward Anguish preys upon his Soul. You should excuse him: Can his generous Heart, More easily than yours, betray a Father? Do not You tremble for the Life of Tarquin? And can you blame his Filial Love of Brutus? Judge of his Pains by what you feel yourself. Then be not too severe in your Resentment, Nor grieve yourself, to grieve unhappy Titus. You also know, by what tremendous Oaths The Sons of Rome are bound to serve her Interest. This very Morn he swore Eternal Hatred To Tarquin's Family. What can he do?— LUCIA. 'Tis hard indeed, Hortensia; I pity him! Heav'n knows how deeply his Distress affects me; I'm almost overwhelm'd!—Why may not Titus Repent of those rash Oaths, unjustly taken, Return to his Allegiance, and to Me. Does not Tiberius, a Son of Brutus too, Assisted by the Noblest Roman Youths, Join to restore my Father to his Throne; Nor in the least pretend to merit Me? And shall Titus, to whom I've been so partial, To whom my Soul has overflow'd in Fondness, Shall he forsake me? HORTENSIA. In his divided Heart, You triumph over Rome and Liberty. LUCIA. Ah! guilty Liberty, a Rebel's Virtue!— I'll wait no more, but instantly depart; Depart without Regret—if possible.— What secret Horror thrills thro' all my Soul! Avert, avenging Gods, this dreadful Omen! I trembling view yon' tow'ring Capitol, And shudder for the Life of lovely Titus. Brutus appears, like some relentless God, With Fury arm'd to plunge us to Destruction. Grief, Anger, Love, and Fear distract my Thoughts! Let us be gone— SCENE II. Lucia, Hortensia, Titus. TITUS. Yet for a single Moment Let me intreat thy Stay— LUCIA. No, cruel Man, You think by soothing Words, and artful Glosses To gain upon me— TITUS. Alas! I know no Arts: My open Heart abhors Hypocrisy. Ev'n Reason now is fled. This fatal Day Bereaves me of the Power to rule my Actions. My Brain whirls round! my Thoughts are all confus'd! Guide thou my Steps, conduct me at thy Pleasure; Freely command me now to perpetrate The Crimes I most detest, Murder and Parricide! Rather than part with Thee, let raging Flames Lay level with the Ground the Towers of Rome; Her Citizens be buried in the Ruins; And let a Father, by his Son abandon'd, Beneath fierce Tarquin's Sword— LUCIA. The Gods forbid it! In Thee, the Voice of Nature pleads for Brutus. If I am Yours, your Father will be Mine, And shall by Me as Tarquin's self be honour'd. But tell me, Titus, can you then believe, That Brutus would repine to see his Son The glorious Sovereign of a willing People? He's King himself, tho' by another Title; His Reign, 'tis true, lasts but a Year at present; Yet soon perhaps—But what avail my Pleadings, If thy cold Heart's insensible to Love? I go—Then soon you will forget— TITUS. Forget thee, O! enchanting Excellence!— The Sun shall sooner cease his Daily Course, Than I can tear thy Image from my Breast! But then—to see the Romans made a Prey To wild Ambition, and to lawless Power, Those very Romans, whom my Hand has sav'd? My Soul starts back with Horror at the Thought!— LUCIA. Hear then my fix'd and final Resolution! My Heart shall witness by its Constancy, With what a mighty Force it would have lov'd thee. Think not that I will wander to Liguria, To wed a Monarch whom I never saw; No—Here in Presence of the Gods I swear, Whose vengeful Lightning blasts the perjur'd Wretch, Beneath these Walls, where reign'd my Ancestors, These Walls, which you defend against your King, By my own Hand to end my wretched Life! A just Reward for my presumptuous Folly, In doating on my Father's mortal Foe! I go— TITUS, [Holding her.] Yet stay, and hear me! It must be so—Thy Will shall be obey'd, Tho' my Soul shudders at the dire Resolve! I see the dreadful Gulph to which I'm plunging; I see, and I approve the Paths of Virtue, Yet, led by Love, pursue what I condemn! LUCIA. Ah! do not thus delude my ardent Passion! You mock the Fondness of my tender Heart. Yes, I confess, I live for Thee alone! Yet know, I'll sooner die than give my Hand To One, who wav'ring trembles to be Mine, Nor dare obey his King without Reluctance. The dreadful Moment's come, that must divide us. With Cælius I depart. Advise, consult; Weigh in thy Mind, how dear thou art to Lucia, And that all Rome may now be subject to thee. I go—but will with Tarquin soon return, To enter Queen, or perish in thy Sight! TITUS. Thou shalt not perish! I will— [Offering to follow her. LUCIA. Hold, Titus, You hazard Life, if you pursue me farther. Suspicion ever wakes—Resolve to be Or Tarquin's Friend, or Lucia's mortal Foe! [Exeunt Lucia and Hortensia. SCENE III. TITUS, Alone. O Lucia, thou hast conquer'd! Love prevails. I'll crown Thee Queen, or perish in th'Attempt. T'abandon and betray such matchless Charms, Were of all Crimes the most enormous! SCENE IV. Titus, Messala. TITUS. Welcome, my Friend. I long'd for thy Return. Forgive my late wild Transports. Follow me, And serve, at once, my Love and my Revenge! MESSALA. I shall with Joy obey your Will. My Cohorts Already arm'd on Mount Quirinus stand, To yield the Gate upon th'appointed Signal. Then lose no Time. Impenetrable Night With Wings propitious covers our Designs! TITUS, The Hour draws near. Lucia now counts the Moments.— Tarquin, to Thee my Vows were plighted first! The Dye is cast! [The Back Scene opens.] What do I see? My Father! SCENE V. Brutus, Titus, Messala, Lictors. BRUTUS. Haste, Titus, haste. Rome is expos'd to Danger. By Secret Means the Senate are inform'd, That we shall be attack'd at Dead of Night; And have, at my Request, made Choice of Thee To guard the City on this great Occasion. Away! if thou return with Conquest crown'd, Or fall in Fight, thy Name will be Immortal! TITUS. Heavens! BRUTUS. My Son— TITUS. Commit, I pray, to abler Hands The Senate's Favour, and the Fate of Rome. MESSALA. What dreadful Passions rend his struggling Soul! [Aside. BRUTUS. Can'st thou refuse the Honour they design thee? TITUS. I am unworthy of so high an Honour. BRUTUS. Thou art, indeed, unworthy!—Proud Ambition Still irritates thy Mind against the Senate, For their refusing thee the Consulship. But how unjust were all the Pleas you urg'd! How didst thou dare to stand a Candidate, Before the Age sour Sacred Laws prescribe? Is this a Time to cherish Civil Discord, Now Ruin and Destruction hover round us? Thou hast sav'd Rome; and canst thou yet repine? Will not the Fame of that Immortal Deed Content thy Heart?—Titus, I blush for thee!— Rejoice to hold a Soldier's Post of Honour, And pour the Torrent of thy Wrath on Tyrants. Offer thy Life for Rome without Reward. Be still a Heroe; nay, be more, a Patriot. For Me, my Son, my Race is almost finish'd; But when thy Hands have clos'd these languid Eyes, My Name shall ever flourish, rais'd on Thine. In Titus I shall live again for Rome! TITUS. Oh! Messala. Enter Valerius. VALERIUS. Let all retire. [Exeunt Titus, Messala, and the Lictors. SCENE VI. Brutus, Valerius. VALERIUS. Rome is betray'd! BRUTUS. Ha! VALERIUS. A dire Conspiracy is form'd against us. 'Tis past Dispute. I have not yet discover'd The Authors of this execrable Plot; But Tarquin's Name was mutter'd; and some base Degenerate Romans call'd for a Surrender. BRUTUS. Can Roman Citizens be fond of Chains? VALERIUS. At my Approach the guilty Dastards fled; By different Ways they closely are pursu'd. 'Tis thought that Lelius, Menas, and Vitellius, Those artful Advocates of Tarquin's Cause, Who spread around seditious Calumnies T'incense the Populace against the Senate, Have all conspir'd to aid Porsenna's Arms. Messala too would justly stand suspected, Were he not cherish'd as a Friend by Titus. 'Tis whisper'd, that he privately frequents The dark Cabals of these Conspirators. BRUTUS. Let us place Spies to watch their every Motion. The Laws and Rights, of which we are the Guardians, Restrain our Hands from Arbitrary Sway. T'arrest a Roman upon bare Surmise, Would be to act like that outrageous Tyrant Whom we renounce, and take up Arms t'expell. Mean while, let us go forth to rouze the Slothful, To chear the Weak, to animate the Virtuous, And terrify the Sons of Violence. Now let the awful Fathers of their Country, By their Example fire the Citizens. What Heart so cold, that will not be inflam'd To see the hoary Sires advance to Battel! SCENE VII. Brutus, Valerius, Proculus. PROCULUS. A Slave, my Lord, intreats immediate Audience. BRUTUS. What! in the Night? and at this lonely Hour? PROCULUS. He says, that his important Tidings Admit of no Delay. BRUTUS. The Fate of Rome, Perhaps, depends upon th'Advice he brings. He shall be instantly dispatch'd. [To Proculus.] Thou, Proculus, haste to the Roman Army, And charge my Sons from Me, to do their Duty. See the Quirinal Gate be well defended; Tell Titus, I entrust it to His Care. I'll follow strait, and by my own Example Will kindle in their Breasts a double Ardour; Conquest, or glorious Death, shall crown our Labours! The Eagle thus trains up her generous Brood, Provokes to Toils, and spirits them with Blood; This Line is taken from Mr. Hughes's Noble Ode, entitled, The Ecstacy. 'Till borne on Wings full-grown, and bold to rise, The Bird of Jove to Heav'n impetuous flies: By her fierce Talons his red Thunder's hurl'd, To punish, and reform a guilty World! End of the Fourth Act.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT V. SCENE I. SCENE, A Hall in the Palace of the Consuls. The Senate, Brutus, Silvius, Rufus, Proculus, Lictors, the Slave Vindex. BRUTUS. Yes; Mournful Rome must now have wept in Blood. Death would have march'd triumphant thro' the Gates, And heap'd the Streets with slaughter'd Citizens. This very Night, was Tarquin to have enter'd. Nor Sex, nor Age would have escap'd his Sword Keen with impetuous Rage, and fell Revenge. Then had our Liberties been lost for ever! This close-concerted Scheme, big with Destruction, Sprung from the fertile Brain of fraudful Cælius. In Rome were also found rebellious Sons, Who in Defiance of their solemn Oaths, And every Tye that binds the Heart of Man, Conspir'd with Tyrants to enslave their Country! The Captain of this Band was bold Messala. Lur'd with the Hopes of ample Wealth and Honours, He promis'd to betray our Gates to Tarquin. SILVIUS. You still maintain our Rights and Liberties With the same Zeal, as you at first redeem'd them. But Say, how was this subtle Plan detected? BRUTUS. The Power Supreme, with ever-waking Eye, Has watch'd for Rome, and guarded all our Lives. That Slave, unseen, hearing th'Intrigues of Cælius, [Pointing to Vindex. Open'd to Me this formidable Plot. Rouz'd by the pressing Danger of the Romans, I strait gave Orders for the Public Safety: The Ministers of Justice seiz'd Messala, And had receiv'd express Command from Me, To bring him instantly before the Senate. Encompass'd as he stood, he from his Bosom A secret Dagger snatch'd, and boldly cry'd, “The Man who dares conspire, must dare to die! Speaking, he fiercely plung'd it in his Breast. Th'astonish'd Lictors ran too late to save him. RUFUS. What Words can pay the Thanks we owe to Brutus, For his unwearied Toils to serve his Country? Too mild the Fate of this audacious Traytor!— For these perfidious Arts of smooth-tongu'd Cælius, Eternal Infamy shall brand his Name! Is he escap'd, rejoicing in his Crimes? BRUTUS. Cælius was far advanc'd. Our Troops pursu'd, And seiz'd him near the Tuscan Camp with Lucia. Doubt not, we soon shall dive into the Depth Of this Conspiracy. Active Valerius Is now employ'd in finding out the Authors. But when you know their Names, Fathers, beware Not to betray the State by ill-tim'd Mercy. Fulfill your Vows: Regard their Crimes alone. Let us be just to Rome, nor spare the Guilty, Tho' ev'n the dearest Friends, Brothers, or Sons. The Man who gives his Voice to pardon Treason, Should be esteem'd Accomplice with the Traytor. [To the Slave.] Vindex, to whom indulgent Heav'n has given A Dignity of Soul above thy Birth; Thou, who hast sav'd the Roman State from Bondage, Grateful Receive that Liberty we owe thee: Be Free, and Equal to the greatest Roman. [A Huzza without. What gives Occasion to this sudden Shout? PROCULUS. Cælius, conducted by a Guard, approaches. BRUTUS. Not all his Arts can cover, or disguise His flagrant Infamy.— SCENE II. The Senate, Brutus, Cælius, Lictors. CÆLIUS. O! frantic Romans, How dare you violate the Laws of Nations!— Your frontless Lictors insolently seiz'd me. What means this Outrage on my Character? BRUTUS. Thy Character does but enhance thy Guilt: No more appeal to a vain empty Title. CÆLIUS. A King's Ambassador— BRUTUS. Ambassador! Thou'rt but a dignify'd Conspirator, Presuming to commit the basest Crimes, Beneath the Sanction of a Sacred Name. The true Ambassador regards his Honour, Nor stains by Treachery his awful Trust: Promoting still Benevolence and Peace, He's every where receiv'd with Reverence. Try, if thy Actions suit this Character!— But know, the Roman State, tho' thus provok'd, Will faithfully obey the Laws of Nations; Nor farther Punishment on You inflict, Than to behold those perjur'd Parricides, Whom You seduc'd, suffer the Fate they merit. When that is past, go sooth Porsenna's Ear With the Success of this perfidious Scheme; And, in thy Person thus dismiss'd Untouch'd, Thro' all Hesperia's States at once display The Lenity of Rome and thy Disgrace. Lictors, conduct him hence. [Exit Cælius, attended by two Lictors. SCENE III. The Senate, Brutus, Valerius, Proculus. BRUTUS. Welcome, Valerius. Hast thou discover'd the Conspirators? But whence this Gloom? What means that downcast Look? You tremble. VALERIUS. Remember thou art Brutus. BRUTUS. Explain thyself. VALERIUS. My Tongue faulters. [He offers a Scroll to him. This secret Draught of the Conspiracy, In which the leading Rebels stand enroll'd, Was by the Lictors seiz'd upon Messala. BRUTUS, [Looking upon the Scroll.] Are not my Eyes deceiv'd? Detested Day! O wretched Father!—What! my Son Tiberius! Forgive me, Senators—Is he secur'd? [Returning the Scroll. VALERIUS. He stood on his Defence with two bold Traytors, Who rather chose to die, than to surrender; And, obstinately fighting, near them fell.— But there remains a heavier Weight of Grief; To Rome, to Thee, and Me, far more afflicting! BRUTUS. What do I hear? VALERIUS. Resume, and read again This dreadful List. BRUTUS. O Torture! Torture!—Titus!— [He falls into the Arms of Proculus. SILVIUS. What! Titus charg'd with practising Rebellion! After such glorious Deeds in our Defence, Can He, at last, be faithless to his Country? If his ingenuous Bosom harbours Treason, Where shall we seek for Honour, Truth, and Virtue? Who can be safe, when Titus is accus'd? RUFUS. I value and admire, no less than Silvius, Th'heroic Worth of your Illustrious Son. [To Brutus. But we're no Strangers to his headstrong Passions; We know to what Excess he was transported, When his ambitious Views were lately check'd. How far a blind Resentment may prevail, 'Tis hard to say. But if, which Heav'n avert! Th'unhappy Youth has been seduc'd by Cælius, I'll joyfully concur in any Measures To testify our Gratitude to Brutus. Perhaps Valerius can inform us farther. VALERIUS. I found him wand'ring in a lonely Place, Anxious, unarm'd, dismay'd, and full of Horror; His down-cast Eyes and folded Arms confess'd, Some mighty Woe sat heavy on his Soul. BRUTUS. Fathers, return without me to the Capitol; I ought not now to take a Seat among you. Justly exterminate my guilty Race: Nor will I there attend you, lest my Presence Shou'd seem design'd t'arrest your speedy Vengeance. [Exeunt Valerius and all the Senators. SCENE IV. BRUTUS. To Your Decrees, great Gods! I am resign'd. You, by my Hands, have rear'd this noble Fabrick Of Legal Power, and Public Liberty, Fix'd on the Basis of Eternal Justice, And promising to last a Length of Ages!— Yet in an Hour, my own unnatural Sons Would have destroy'd this fair and stately Structure, Had not just Heav'n blasted their impious Purpose.— O! Power Supreme!—Father of Men and Gods! Strengthen the generous Hands that fight for Freedom, And strike a Terror thro' the Foes of Rome!— Remov'd from Public View, I may discard The awful Rigour of a Roman Consul, And with Paternal Pity mourn my Sons, By too severe a Fate, at once cut off, In early Youth, with everlasting Shame, (O killing Thought!) as Traytors to their Country! That thou, Tiberius! hast conspir'd with Tyrants, To introduce Despotic Pow'r and Bondage, Nature recoils!—It sinks my Soul with Sorrow!— But then that Titus too, so brave a Roman, Who on this Day, distinguish'd by his Triumph, Was crown'd with Laurels in the Capitol By my own Hands, in Presence of the People, Hope of my Age, and Glory of his Country! That he should join in this Accursed Scheme!— O Titus! Titus! would the Gods permit me To offer up my Life to ransom thine, For Thee, my Son, I would contented die! But Honour, Virtue, Rome, all, all forbid it!— O Rome! thou little know'st, what Pangs I feel, To fix thy Rights, and make thee free and glorious! SCENE V. Brutus, Valerius, Proculus, Lictors. VALERIUS. Brutus, to Thee the Senate have transferr'd Their Right of Judgment on thy Son's Offence. BRUTUS. To Me? VALERIUS. To Thee alone.— BRUTUS. What of the rest? VALERIUS. Their Sentence is already past. Ev'n now perhaps the Lictor's dreaded Hand Cuts off their forfeit Lives. BRUTUS. Say'st thou the Senate have to Me referr'd The Fate of Titus? VALERIUS. Such is their Sovereign Will. They think You merit this distinguish'd Honour.— What Answer shall I bear? BRUTUS. That Brutus justly values this high Favour, Which tho' he did not seek, he'll aim at least By an impartial Conduct to deserve.— But did not Titus yield without Resistance, Who might—You will excuse my doubtful Heart— He was the Hope of Rome—I feel I love him— VALERIUS. Lucia— BRUTUS. Ha! VALERIUS. Lucia, this very Moment, Too far confirms his Guilt. BRUTUS. Confirms his Guilt! VALERIUS. No sooner she beheld the fatal Scaffolds, The gathering Crowd, the Lictors, and the Axes, But this unhappy Maid, with frantic Sorrow Tore her dishevell'd Hair, and raving cry'd, Is this the Royal Dower to Titus promis'd? Speaking she sunk, oppress'd with mighty Woe! The deadly Struggle o'er, and Life return'd, Her Servants seize this Interval of Reason, And with officious Care conduct her hither. BRUTUS. Just Gods! [After a Pause.] Lictors, bring in Titus. VALERIUS. A Father's Grief deserves to be rever'd. Rome will approve whatever You decree. [Exit. SCENE VI. Brutus, Proculus. BRUTUS. It cannot be.—The more I weigh the Crime, The more I am confirm'd he's Innocent. The Man who fought so bravely for his Country, Could ne'er conspire to aid the Foes of Rome; Nor from th'exalted Heights of Godlike Virtue, Sink down at once a most abandon'd Villain! PROCULUS. Perhaps Messala spread this false Report, To countenance his own destructive Scheme. BRUTUS. Would to the Gods it prove no more! PROCULUS. But if 'tis possible to think him guilty; Th'indulgent Senate still allows his Pardon. You may preserve this Heroe for the State. He's now your only Son. BRUTUS. I am a Roman Consul. SCENE VII. Brutus, Lucia with dishevell'd Hair, Attendants. Lucia runs, and throws herself on her Knees before Brutus. LUCIA. See, Brutus, See a Princess at thy Feet, To beg the Life of thy unhappy Son. O! let her not intreat in vain for Mercy! 'Twas I, 'twas I seduc'd th'unwary Youth; Mine was the Crime, be mine the Punishment! Pour all your Wrath on this devoted Head; I'll bear it all; but spare his Life more precious. I call great Jove, and ev'ry Power to witness, His only Fault was too much Love for Lucia! BRUTUS. O! born in evil Hour, t'afflict the Romans, Cease to inflame my Grief and Indignation!— Has Titus then conspir'd to aid Porsenna? If so, he must expect the just Reward, Due to the Guilt of his enormous Crimes. Therefore retire; sollicit me no more. I can no longer hear thy vain Petition. [Rising. For Thee, so fatally belov'd by Titus, Thou shalt be safe conducted to thy Father. [Exeunt Brutus and Proculus. LUCIA. No, cruel Man! unworthy such a Son, Deaf as the Winds, or raging Seas, to Pity, Lucia rejects with Scorn the Grace you offer! Tho' weak my Frame, yet still my Soul is Roman. Brutus and Rome shall see, this gallant Youth Plac'd not his Love upon a worthless Object. SCENE VIII. As Lucia, &amp;c. are going off the Stage, they meet Titus led in by the Lictors. Titus, Lucia, &amp;c. TITUS, starting Ha! Lucia here? LUCIA. O my much-injur'd Titus! In vain I have essay'd, with Pray'rs and Tears, To gain thy Pardon from relentless Brutus. His Heart is steel'd to ev'ry tender Passion. Hence he retir'd, to shun my hated Presence— Behold, just Heav'n!—This Father of his Country, So watchful to preserve the Roman Laws, Himself now violating those of Nature, With his Son's Blood pollutes his Savage Hands! TITUS. Blame not my Father. All the Guilt is mine! Those Sacred Laws I wildly have transgress'd, Extort the Sentence I so justly merit. I hasten to the Land of dark Oblivion, Where racking Thought shall torture me no more! LUCIA. Have I betray'd the best and bravest Roman, The Man for whom I wou'd have gladly dy'd? Unutterable Anguish overwhelms me!— TITUS. Forbear to pierce my Heart with thy Complainings!— My Soul was busied with the Thoughts of Death; Tempt me no more to wish for Life again! Nature's too weak to bear this dreadful Conflict! [Leaning upon her. [Recovering, after a Pause. May no Misfortunes grieve thy joyous Days; Yet deign sometimes to think on wretched Titus! Remember, with his dying Breath he blest thee! O! let me still indulge the pleasing Hope, That thou shalt live, live happy many Years, And Heav'n will crown thee with its choicest Gifts! Then shall I meet my Fate without Reluctance, Nor once repine against the Gods, or Brutus!— Thou fairest Pattern of transcendent Goodness, Farewell! Farewell!—for ever! [Embracing her. LUCIA. O! Farewell! Thou matchless Heroe! and too-generous Lover! If I cou'd cherish now One Thought of Life, I shou'd detest the Baseness of my Heart! Thy glorious Shade I'll meet in Realms below, Where thy fierce Father's Anger cannot reach us!— Nor Pain, nor Grief, our virtuous Souls shall know, But with Love's purest Flames for ever glow. Thy Fate, dear lovely Youth, with Joy I'll share, And thus escape from ev'ry racking Care! [Stabbing herself. TITUS, upon seeing Lucia kill herself, at first starts; and then stands awhile silent, as stupify'd with Grief. At last he breaks forth into this Exclamation. Break, stubborn Heart, and end my Miseries!— 'Tis done. The Pangs of Death, at length, are past! Heroic Maid!—thy great Example shows, With how much Ease a Mind resolv'd may die!— SCENE IX. Brutus, Titus, Proculus. PROCULUS, [coming up to Titus.] Behold, my Lord, Brutus approaches. TITUS. 'Tis my Father! O painful Moments! [Aside. PROCULUS, [seeing the dead Body.] Ha! Lucia slain? I tremble now for Titus. The Gods relentless punish Tarquin's Race! Lictors, remove the Body. TITUS. Open, thou Earth! beneath these stagg'ring Feet, And cover me with everlasting Night! BRUTUS. Of two beloved Sons, the Gift of Heaven, Tiberius is no more!—Now tell me, Titus, Have I One Son yet left? TITUS. You have No Son. BRUTUS. Then answer to thy Judge, Bane of my Life! [He sits down. Did'st thou resolve, in open Violation Of every Sacred Tye, to kill thy Father, And to betray the Liberties of Rome? TITUS. My self-divided Heart resolv'd on Nothing. A deadly Poyson prey'd upon my Soul; I was, and am a Stranger to myself: I wander in a Labyrinth of Crimes. My guilty Heart rebell'd a single Moment; That Moment stains the Lustre of my Actions; That Moment brands me with Eternal Shame; And makes ev'n Life itself a Burden to me. Rome, which looks up to Brutus as her Father, Unsettled Rome requires some great Example. By my just Punishment, then strike a Terror On all who meditate, like me, her Ruin, And would restore a Prince they have abjur'd. Pronounce my Doom, I stand prepar'd to hear it. Thus shall my Blood be never spilt in vain, But by my Death I shall preserve my Country. BRUTUS. Good Gods! such Courage with such Falshood join'd! How strangely are his Crimes and Virtues blended! [Aside. Amid thy Laurels and Triumphal Joys, And all th'illustrious Trophies of thy Arms, What jealous God, Foe to the Roman Name, Could prompt thy Soul to such a horrid Deed? TITUS. A cruel Train of complicated Passions; Ambition, Hate, Revenge, a sudden Frenzy— BRUTUS. Conclude, unhappy Wretch! TITUS. A guilty Flame, The torturing Source of all my dire Misfortunes. But 'tis too much—I shock your injur'd Patience By this Recital of my baneful Love— My frantic Rage and Woes are at the Height! Finish my Life, my Crimes, and my Despair, Your own Disgrace and mine!—But if this Hand E'er fought successfully for Rome and Freedom; If e'er I follow'd in the glorious Paths, Which You have trod, and panted after Virtue, And if my Death deserves a Father's Pity, [He throws himself on his Knees. Open your Arms to your relenting Son! Give him the Comfort of One kind Embrace, Before he is remov'd for Ever from thee! O! say at least, that Brutus does not hate him: These Words will save my Memory from Shame, And silence the Reproach of busy Tongues. 'Twill chear my Soul in its departing Moments, To think you pity, and forgive my Crime, That still you love, and own me for your Son! BRUTUS. His just Remorse with deeper Anguish wounds me! [Aside. These Two Lines are taken from Mr. Lee. “The violated Genius of thy Country “Rears his sad Head, and passes Sentence on thee. Go, Proculus, conduct him to his Fate.— [Brutus lifts him up in his Arms. Arise, thou piercing Object of my Sorrow! Delusive Hope of my declining Years! Embrace thy wretched Father!—May the Gods Arm thee with Patience to support thy Sufferings! The Sovereign Magistrate of injur'd Rome, Entrusted with the Care of Public Justice, Was bound by his high Office to condemn A Crime, the Father's bleeding Heart forgives! Go meet thy Fate with a more manly Courage, Than Grief will let me show in parting from thee! See! while I speak, my streaming Eyes confess, How dear thou art to this afflicted Breast, And how reluctantly I tear thee from it! Thou hast liv'd a Roman, like a Roman die; And, while she punishes, let Rome admire thee! TITUS. May Heav'n prolong th'important Life of Brutus! Worthy his Name, I now shall die content. [Exit Titus, guarded by the Lictors. BRUTUS. Farewell, thou much-belov'd ill-fated Youth! Tho' thou art snatch'd untimely from the Earth, My Misery is heavier far than thine; For all thy Pangs will in a Moment pass, But I am doom'd to bear a ling'ring Death; And to the Urn my hoary Head descends, Bow'd down with Grief, and never-ceasing Woes! How hard the Task, when partial Nature pleads, To yield the Father's, to the Patriot's Claim! SCENE X. Brutus, Valerius. VALERIUS. The Senators, with Sympathizing Sorrow, Condole with Brutus on this great Affliction. BRUTUS. I stand indebted to their Love—But now The threat'ning Dangers that surround the Romans, Claim all our Thoughts, and chace domestic Woes. Our Enemies prepare a fresh Attack; Then let us boldly meet them in the Field, Resigning to the Gods our righteous Cause. I look on all Rome's Citizens as Sons: It is their Duty now, with double Ardour, To emulate that Heroe's shining Virtues, Who, to preserve their Rights, was doom'd to die, While green in Youth, and deck'd with blooming Honours! O! may my Blood be spilt in their Defence, As poor deluded Titus shou'd have fall'n! SCENE the Last. Brutus, Valerius, Proculus. BRUTUS. Say, Proculus, what Tidings dost thou bring? PROCULUS. Your Son, my Lord, with dauntless Resolution— BRUTUS. Forbear! The Fatal Debt is paid to Justice, And Rome is free. Return we Thanks to Heav'n! Reason's just Laws with jealous Care obey, And never from the Paths of Virtue stray. It will be vain, illustrious Deeds to boast, When by One Crime, the Fame of All is lost. End of the Fifth Act.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">EPILOGUE. Spoken by Mrs. HERON. Our modest Bard, faithful to Virtue's Cause, Disdains by Ribaldry to court Applause.— You've seen unhappy Titus doom'd to prove The Axe's fatal Blow for too much Love. A Fault to which Forgiveness sure was due, If Tragic Poets any Mercy knew. But if his Punishment Severe should seem, And his High Virtues merit your Esteem, Your generous Approbation Fame shall give, And make him with Immortal Glory live!— The artless Thoughts of an enamour'd Maid Are in bright Lucia's Character display'd. Woes Undeserv'd, and Virtue in Despair, Justly affect the Sympathizing Fair. If then for Her, your tender Bosoms heave, Indulge the pleasing Pain, nor blush to grieve. By Feign'd Affliction mov'd, your Hearts confess, How great the Joy to aid Unfeign'd Distress! From Instincts so benevolent we find, How strong a Byas sways the Human Mind, To love whate'er is virtuous, kind, and true, And to Admire Heav'n's fairest Frame in You! FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>