<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Douglas, Evelyn</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Douglas, Evelyn</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">douglas evelyn</field>
      <field name="author_text">Douglas, Evelyn</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1880's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V3.0198.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1886</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460620</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Punchinello And His Wife Judith ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Punchinello And His Wife Judith ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="title_facet">punchinello and his wife judith</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">punchinello and his wife judith</field>
      <field name="title_text">Punchinello And His Wife Judith ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="year_display">1886</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1886</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1886</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460620&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460620&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Douglas, Evelyn&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;douglas evelyn&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Punchinello And His Wife Judith ; A Tragedy&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;punchinello and his wife judith&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1886&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1886&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Douglas, Evelyn&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Punchinello And His Wife Judith&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Chelmsford&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed At The "Essex Country Chronicle" Office&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1886&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3873325-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv30198&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Punchinello And His Wife Judith&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 117 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Punchinello and his wife Judith.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1886.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Unknown.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PUNCHINELLO AND HIS WIFE JUDITH. A TRAGEDY.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">TO MY FRIEND E. A. B., IN MEMORY OF COLLEGE DAYS. June, 1886.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PREFACE. The following dramatic poem, though complete in itself, is merely a sketch of a more elaborate work to follow in due course. The idea of the legend, the conception of a hardened criminal carried on prosperously in a career of uncompromising villainy, destroying all that stood in his way, even those dearest to him, turning the implements of his enemies against themselves, tolerated by God, eluding man, both lawyer and hangman, defying the spiritual world, jesting with the ghost of his murdered wife, but finally succumbing to the devil, has not been here fully worked out. Moreover, the grotesque element in the story has been too completely set aside. I do not make these remarks with a view to ‘forestalling criticism,’ still less as an apology for the present work, but simply to indicate the lines on which I purpose finally to work out the materials, and so to reserve the subject for myself. June 27th, 1886.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PERSONS REPRESENTED. IN THE PROLOGUE. Punch Judy The Dog Toby The Hangman The Ghost. IN THE PLAY. Punchinello, a young Venetian noble. Giuditta, his Wife. Orsino, Doge of Venice. Valeria, his Wife. Tobia Servant of Punchinello. Lurdo Servant of Punchinello. Paolo. Benedetta, Maid to Valeria. Laura, Maid to Giuditta. Felice, a Cardinal. Angelo Venetian Noble Eugenio Venetian Noble Marco, the new Doge on the death of Orsino. Dionysio, a Lawyer.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PROLOGUE. (Overture of drum and pan-pipe.) Enter Punch with his hump, long nose, and truncheon; Judy with her mutch, the dog Toby, and a Nurse bearing the Baby, also the Hangman. Punch. I scarcely knew, good wife, when swathed in flesh, How drenched in libel is our delicate world That hangs its purgéd conscience out to bleach, Each man conspicuously in his own back yard. Often, indeed, when you and I were here We heard unpleasing rumours of our deeds. Folks, in a whisper, called me murderer And much besides. They dared not openly. But never till to-day I groped my path Back to the world from my new place of lodgment (We will not talk of that) had I a thought How far their lies would strain. Judy. Nor I, good man. Walking abroad to-day I heard a screech Of a cracked pipe, and tapping of a drum To a most hideous tune. I looked and lo! Toward me came a model theatre With curtains of green baize, that seemed to walk Of its own will, and from within the screen Issued that sound. It stopped. A clustering throng Of children gaped around. The curtain rose And (dream my horror!) there, in mimic play, They acted a low farce of both our lives For the base vulgar eyes of all that crowd! Oh, had they come to Venice in our life, You would have bade a servant drench their drink With some sure opiate. But the worst of all Was that they dressed and painted me like this! Punch. And me like this. I saw it from a window. The bare idea goes nigh to make one mad. Judy. Yet in my youth I think I looked not thus, But my pure carmine cheek shone vivid and fresh Under the soft gold glory of my hair; My lips were things to gloat upon, you said, Drenched in a dew of sleep like opiate flowers, Two rich corn-roses for the bee to browse; My eyes were fluid globes of glamoured light, Lidded with waxen petals, fringed with silk; And all my bosom was a snowy field. Then, too, my dress was gorgeous gold brocade Lamping with jewels, my white shoulders swathed In dusky glories of the orient loom, Scarves shot with gold and coral, and my neck, My naked swan-white neck was clasped and locked In a rich carcanet of rubious fires. And gallants capped with bonnets of fair silk And plumed with ostrich feathers used to bow Before me where I went, and their white hands Were quick to snatch the jewel-studded hilt Of sword or dagger at my word, but I Had never cause to give it. I was chaste. Punch. Well, you have scarcely overdone your praise. The picture is a likeness, love, and I Wore nothing but black velvet and diamonds, And flatter me, that, with my jetty hair, My lofty stature, and blanched olive cheek Enchiselled like a sculptor's marble dream, I was the handsomest of Venetian nobles. Hangman. I, too, friends, have a small complaint to make. I who am called the hangman in your story, I was a cardinal! Ghost (appearing). Off, all of you! What are your grievances to mine. For I Who am dragged on wrapt up in a grave-cloth Like any vulgar churchyard-walking ghost To fright the crowd, I am the Devil himself. (Exeunt all shrieking).</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. SCENE I. —A balcony. Within through broad open windows is seen a brightly illuminated room crowded with dancers. In a dark corner of the balcony Punchinello is discovered seated. Punchinello. How dark a mystery this life of man! (Music strikes up within for the dance.) We are born, nursed, reared, buried among lies. First in the Stygian darkness of the womb We are conceived. None asks us would we live. Life is thrust on us. There we grope in gloom, Who shall recall in what ill-boding fears, What vague surmise of future formless woe? There in a sort of human Erebus We dumbly crave half-shuddering for the light, Till on a day desire sprouts forth in act, And we emerge, greeted with lying smiles And wailings real. “Bless his cherub face!” “So like his father!”—seeing perchance the while Some neighbour's image printed like a seal Indubitable on the fresh waxen face, Coined with his impress, milled, and superscribed— “This is my bastard by the grace of God!” (Music louder within.) Then in the cradle, while yet swathed in bands, Feeble and foolish, when we cry for food We are put off with tricks; and when our ears Are ripe for seed of words intelligible, They are sown full of threats of gnomes, and ghouls, Bugbears, hobgoblins, bogies, shapes of terror, Which, working in the black loam of our soul, Sprout up into our earliest dreams of God, The first rank harvest of all crops to come, Nurtured where growth is quickest, in the heat And putrefying ordure of a lie. (Music louder within.) Then we are taught—obedience first and last, Obedience sanctioned with the name of God, Obedience to the nurse, the pedagogue, But chiefly to the priest, God's terrible wrath Hanging the while, a Hell up in the air, A sheet of flame shaking above the clouds, We look to fall in fire—“Do this, do that. God loves not evil hearts.” Sweet childhood, see, The eternal prate of poets, painted true! Above, below, around, about us, lies. (Wilder music and whirl of dancers.) Next battling boyhood labouring earnest-eyed On pages crammed with lies from first to last, Still thwarted by some pedant's preference For shallower-witted curlier-pated brows. Then at the end, as though now surely freedom Were nigh at last, laden with love comes youth! (Music.) Truth, truth, we cry: we spurn and trample lies; Foul creeds are brushed like serpents from our path; We give our souls to high philosophy. In vain.—Fierce dogma scarce can pant out thick The paltry cries and watchwords of the schools, Until the curse of holy church, the kiss Of the blessèd inquisition, seems more mild Than a young mother's on her favourite babe As measured with the charity of the wise. “We are the sages; these are heretics. A crude materialist, a shallow slave, An egoist, utilitarian,” So snarls professor showing all his teeth, And “metaphysical dog, poor crack-brained dreamer, Old spider spinning systems from his guts,” Growls back the doctor. Then the youth goes forth Groping for some fair harlot in the streets In search of charitable sane society, And finds it not, but comes more near the goal. (Two of the dancers come out and whisper and kiss in the balcony, not seeing him. Then they return.) Then comes satiety: then he moulds his brows To look prim lies as others, and goes down, Cheating, and lying, and swindling, to the grave, And there he grovels with the worm, his kin. (Louder music.) But I, I was not made of the common flock, To browse and nibble on the verge of crime, And cower below the shepherd's outreached crook. For me the beckoning summit shines and lures To the high goal of all imaginable ill, If not of good; a bat-winged seraph I, An angel-stature of aspiring crime, Abaddon, Satan, old Apollyon, No half-way, groping, hovering doubter. See! Above me what a glory of gold cloud! What lurid fulvous tempest-hues entice To emerge upon the blazing citadels By fierce endeavour upward, till I rest Triumphant on the starry mountain peaks, On the last needled splint that cuts the sky, With all the quaking glories round about. There will I bathe me in the thunder-cloud And live in the blast and blaze of angry heaven. Oh, thou ineffable immensity, That shinest o'er me drenched in fluid flame Around the molten globe of the white moon! Ye fires that palpitate, ye burning eyes, Whose multitudinous coruscation fills All heaven's enubilous dome with astral grail! I feel a lust sublime that grows in me To issue among your choirs, an equal power, And find repose above the clash and throng Of earth's vile conflict and mean struggle, to bask In the pure light of evil or of good, A single spirit, an undivided will. But, for the goad of evil in my blood Will suffer me not be good and be at peace, I will not strain my nature nor make swerve From its own channel, but be evil pure, And crave no more for freedom, but be free! (Enter Valeria.) Valeria. Come, sir, you have not danced. You do us wrong; Many bright dames were happy of your hand To lead them through a measure. Punchinello. Noble lady, My mood is none of the merriest. See my wife! She makes amends. Valeria. Indeed she flaunts it bravely. Punchinello. One of them in a family is enough. I am not of her mood. Valeria. Can I not tempt you? Loose your eyes on the room, and let them browse All round the verges of this ample plain, On all the flowers. How like you them? Punchinello. They pass. Here a poor pretty lily of the vale, A modest daisy there with simple lure, This side a gorgeous-coated passion flower, Something too much of the hot-house in her hue, On the other an over-blown magnolia That goads with sickly wafts of odorous power, Nowhere a rose. Valeria. You are too hard to please. Punchinello. Not I, fair lady. Valeria. Will you take my hand? Punchinello. Seraph! you lift me through the poor bright stars To the pure empyrean, all one flame. Valeria. Nay through these trembling glories of the night I am your humble herald, Iris sent On a message to you from imperial Jove.— My husband— Punchinello. Ah, your husband! Valeria. Wherefore that? Punchinello. What said I? Valeria. Nothing. Do not crush my hand. Punchinello. Your pardon, queen. Valeria. Nay, drop it not like fire. I meant not that. It will not burn you, sir. It is a gentle little hand enough. Punchinello. It is a velvet flower-leaf to the touch, A vision to the soul. Valeria. A vision? Punchinello. Yes. Valeria. What is the vision? Punchinello. Opening Paradise, With all the houris thronging at the gate, The lipped corolla of a glorious flower. Valeria. The gate is open to the penitent soul: The flower is rich in honey for the bee. Punchinello. How sweet the calm of twilight in the skies, When, after strain and struggle of the day, The quiet lights of evening swathe in peace The weary soul that all subsides in dreams! Even such upon too craving hearts the dews And tints of mutual understanding fall. Here let me sit and hold your hand for ever. Valeria. Hush, hush, we shall be heard, and we must dance Or they will miss us. Punchinello. Yet a moment stay, For hearken, someone sings. (Song.) In aërial lands of tempest-girdled mountains, Full of fulvous torrents, dropping thunderous heights, From the tawny wells of amber-coloured fountains Throbbing hoarsely through the astral nights; In a sparry grotto, 'neath the boiling Of a white cascade, All her spires anguineal round her coiling, Sits Yarvade. To the leprous whiteness of her little bosom Close she strains the rosy body of a child, Squeezing the sweet perfume from the infant blossom, Making pure her flesh by leaving it defiled: And the torrent-bow flits flickering over Yellow braid on braid Of the coiled hair of the murderous lover— Pale Yarvade. Valeria. A song to make one shudder. Let us go. Punchinello (aside). The song is true. Such is the soul of man In the murderous clasp of sin. Each kiss of hers Turns him into her likeness, as the soul The man of Florence saw snake-bitten in Hell Turn to a snake.—Come, angel, lure me forth. (Exeunt within. Loud music and whirl of dancers.) Scene II. —Valeria's chamber. Moonlight. An open window. Valeria. I wonder will he come to-night. The stars, So undefiled, reproach me with bright eyes; The leaves are glossy in the moonshine clear; The spell of peace is hovering over me, But I feel none. The pure lights of my soul Are snared and caught in meshes of dark cloud, Funereal streaks of poisoned fog. The wind Of all my thought drones dismally and low Under that vaulted gloom my soul. Good God! Would he might come and soothe me, for I crave After the peace which dwells in every touch Of his strong hand. The goad of fierce desire Suffers me not to rest. Hark, hark, his voice. Punchinello (singing without) Where shall we make our bridal And strew the bride-bed where? By sea-waves never tidal In soft Aegean air? In glittering palm oases, That float o'er desert sands? Or in gorgeous tropic places Of roaring forest lands? Shall it be in some old manor Of oaken-panelled halls, Flaunting with many a banner On its castellated walls, Where classic sculptures harden Mid trees grotesquely hewn, And the dials in the garden Forever point to noon? Shall we dream of a grot of coral Under the southern sea, Far from the cold world's moral In a world of gramarye, In a mist of iris colour, Of fitful rainbow lights, Through green waves never duller Than the depth of moon-lit nights? And there mid sea-flower petals, Embathed in shattered rays, Sea-shells and unknown metals, Pass halcyonian days? And hear the passing thunder, And see the lightning gleam Of many a monstrous wonder Hurtling above our dream? Shall it be in a sparry palace Of frail green chrysolite, Enscrolled with fretted alleys Of living flowers of light, Where snakes of fire unravel Green coils from crystal stems, Poising o'er rubious gravel A roof of astral gems? Where glacial spires upspirted, Coruscant minarets, Keen stalactites inverted, Fine frozen fountain-jets, Where needly pointels bristle On blue lead gable-roofs, Sparry as splints of crystal That build the snow-flake woofs? Must I seat thee a sultana On carpets jewel-strown? Must I fix the vague morgana In a dwelling all thine own? Must I make of dreamland waking, And shrine thee in a dream? Or in the rose dawn-breaking? Or the pole's auroral beam? Valeria. Nay, love, not there. That is no scene to frame The picture of our loves, our dalliance. Punchinello. Where, then? Like you this better? Hearken, love. Nay in some dismal valley, Or forest of black pine, Some endless ebon alley Of a demon-tunnelled mine, Or 'neath the ocean's sobbing In a mountain's basalt keep, Hearing the fire-wells throbbing And the earthquakes mutter in sleep; Or on a plain of ashes By some mephitic lake, Where the baffled tempest lashes The wave that will not break, Where meteors rank illumine The sulphurous clouds that creep, Where 'neath the black bitumen The buried cities sleep; Or where old grey towers stand livid On sombre shadowy isles, Or burning towns flash vivid On mountain funeral-piles, Where the sunset's reeking slaughters Dye murky red the flood, And the dismal Stygian waters Blush with a blaze of blood. Valeria. Ay, better, but not good. My welcome friend, I have a language for your ears to-night Suits not with even this, a boon to crave Darker than night. I cannot share your love. Punchinello. Nay, better, in the charnel Twixt the living and the dead, Twixt the spiritual and carnal We'll strew our bridal bed, And dim sepulchral breathings Shall wed us in the tomb, And rue and rosemary wreathings Shall be our orange-bloom. Or rather let us madden In a terrible embrace Where the bat-wings of Abaddon Shadow the hopeless place, Where the gloomy waters gurgle Of all men's tears that fell, In the ninth most awful circle Of the hollow void of Hell. Valeria. Ay, that is best, but goad not my poor lips, Wavering o'er them like a butterfly But never tasting. Punchinello (climbing to the window). Thus we reach our aims By straining upward. That's a rotten branch, But the strong soul is not the pitiful slave To trips of circumstance. Thus we emerge Upon the pinnacles of our hopes, and thus Clasp them. Valeria. And thus divine success imprints Her sealing kiss upon the eyes of strength. Sit by me: let us talk awhile. Punchinello. Ay, love At your white feet. Valeria. That was a strange song. Punchinello. Strange? Liked it not you? Valeria. Ay, well. Punchinello. Then wherefore strange? Valeria. It struck an unison with one low sound Here in my secret bosom. Its key-note Was one with the deep key-note of my heart. Its tone and words alike funereal Fell on my purpose like a yew-shadow Upon a grave. Punchinello. A dismal metaphor. The scene closes. Scene III. Valeria's chamber. Valeria before the mirror. Valeria. Comb out my hair. (Looking in the glass.) How like a gold cascade Its torrents tumble through the ivory teeth, And curl in golden whirlpools on the floor. Methinks 'tis like a nebulous haze of stars, A hurricane of lightnings, sheet of flame, A golden-rippled sunset-lumined lake, A vein of dazzling ore in a deep grot, A sunlit rain, a revel of red waves. Benedetta. There is no hair in Venice like it, lady. Valeria. In Venice! Nay, I think not in the world. Benedetta. That's true. They say our gold Venetian hair Is the world's marvel. What, then, should thine be Which is the marvel of Venice? Valeria. True, girl, true. How shall we dress it? Fetch me a rope of pearls. Diamonds are but fit for negresses. They sparkle in their frizzled ebony curls, But my hair quenches them. In its golden cloud They are like stars caught in the glare of day, And cannot even twinkle. Benedetta. 'Tis indeed A flame-cloud, but I think not like the day. Rather 'tis like a torrent of falling stars, A deluge of wild meteors, like red tongues, That bacchanal across the fiery night Dazzled with sudden flame. Look at this coil, Is it not like a snake? a golden snake, His old skin newly cast, that wreathes and curls Sheathed in fresh glittering mail against the noon, His crest erect, so, and his flickering tongue— Aha! methinks this headless thing could bite, This blazing cobra somewhere hath a sting! Lady, it pricks my hand. Valeria. Beware of it, For it is as you say. Benedetta. 'Tis lightning, lady, Not sunlight. Ha! methinks it smells of sulphur. What fiend has laid his soft caress upon't In the dim night. Valeria. Apollyon, the king, Abaddon, the destroyer. Benedetta. Hence it got That trifling tint of blood under the gold. Hence it is shot with reeking red. Valeria. My mirror, My hand mirror to see its lines aslant! Ah, Benedetta, what dream had I last night? Benedetta. That all this venomed glory clung around Some one and burned him to the bone, a robe Dipped in the blood of Nessus? Valeria. Nay, not quite. I dreamed (and mark you this was but a dream) I lay all naked neath the moonlit sky, 'Mid purple heather-flowers, upon a robe Of crimson broidered with rich flowers of gold: Aspics and adders crawled in the short shrubs And moved the robe beneath me. My white limbs Shone with an ivory lustre; my fair hands Stroked them and smoothed them as a sculptor strokes His fairest statue. Then there came a man, Gods, what a man! his hair like ebony Hung over bronzy shoulders and swart brows; His deep eyes like a serpent's burned, his lithe And muscular limbs stood bold against the twilight, And o'er his head flickered the evening star. Then boldly as a hunter grasps his prey He seized me by the golden hair and tore Tiger-like, coiling it around his hand, And I was glad, and shrieked but clasped him close. Benedetta. I envy you your dream. Such visions, lady, Are rare and come not unto humble maids. They are but sent to princesses and queens. Valeria. But I dreamed more. Methought I wandered with him Beside the red wave of a hissing lake That washed with molten metal a hard shore Of adamant. He stood upon the brink And held me round the waist. His stature tall Emerged over my head; his iron chin Rested upon my hair. Just then there came Stalking across the livid air two forms, My husband and Giuditta. Each was swathed In the other's hair that burned like living flame, But they were not as lovers. Flank to flank They walked, but each one turned away the head. It was a common fate that linked them so. Then rose the man, and, with a seraph's stride But demon's look, seized them and crushed together, And hurled into the bubbling lurid surge. A candent crust of fiery surf rose up Like spray where they had vanished. Widening rings Of snowy ripple lapped the verge, and shone With a green iridescence, and then sank. Benedetta. That was the goodliest part of all the dream. Oh, to have seen them sinking! There are cups, Lady, and maddening drinks to brew in them That can make burning lakes of liquid lead Within the human body. There are plasters— Valeria. Keen-scented hound! Aha! on the right track? Benedetta. I snuff a crime not far off. Valeria. Hunt it down. Benedetta. See how it doubles. Through the brakes and briars I cannot turn so quickly. Valeria. Set your teeth And spring. Benedetta. At one bound I'll have it in my claws And then I'll rend it. Valeria. Now you are no hound? You speak this cat-like, and your fire-green eyes Have more of tigress than of hound in them. Benedetta. You speak well. I would play with what I kill Before I crush it. Valeria. Play me then with this. Benedetta. Ay, let me alone to waste him day by day. Will you have flowers my lady in your hair Valeria. Ay, lilies, girl, emblem of purity. One here. That's well. Nay tilt the mirror back. When to commence now that this cry is up? Benedetta. To-morrow. Let us lose no time. Valeria. Your price? Benedetta. The pleasure of the act. Valeria. No more.? Benedetta. Look you, The wreath is all awry, and this fair flower Has an edge faded. Valeria. Clip it with the scissors. Benedetta. How looks it now? Valeria. Well.—But your price? Benedetta. Five jewels Out of this coil of pearls. Valeria. A trifle. Benedetta. Ay. But I would do this work thrice o'er for them. But if I might ask— Valeria. What? Benedetta. Your gallant, lady, Is known no saint. He crops all flowers that grow. Valeria. I know it and I like him better. Benedetta. Then Let him crop me. My crude and virgin blossom Yet hangs upon the bough of maiden crime. He will not love you less. For, look on me. I am but fair. Valeria. You seek too much. And yet Who knows? I'll think on't. Benedetta. Oh, I'll dream such dreams Till then. Valeria. Dream on, your help weighs any price. And I must buy your faith or your help kills. Benedetta. Nay, lady, I threatened nought. Valeria. You were best not! I am not one to threaten.—All this white Shows sickly. Thrust me in one blood-red bloom Here on the right side. Benedetta. So. I will brew his drink Unto my lord the doge to-morrow. Valeria. Well, Spice it as daintily as you set that flower, And it will do. Benedetta. What on your neck? Valeria. Why nought. Tis better bare. I hate these jewels. Away, Brush them into the casket. I am fair, Fairer this night than ever. Hark ye, girl, I think it was the dark man's kiss last night, But seal your lips so, or I'll have them sealed. (Pinches Benedetta's lips savagely together.) Scene IV. —The Doge's state barge. In the background the scenery constantly changes, showing different parts of Venice. Small gondolas also pass. Orsino. Sit thou by me, my star-bright wife, and thou, Best of my nobles, sit thou at her side. We cannot honour thee too far. Punchinello Indeed, Thou canst not further honour me than thus: Not in the chariot where Apollo sits Is there a fairer place beside the god. Orsino. And thou, Giuditta, of Venetian women Next fairest after this my wife, sit here. Giuditta. My lord is pleased to honour me. Valeria (to Punchinello). Hark you, 'Tis working in his veins. See you his brow, How livid 'tis, how livid are his lips? His hand moves with a palsy. Punchinello (to Valeria). And mine shakes, But 'tis to feel you sitting at my side Shooting electric and delirious joy Through all my frame. Valeria. Believe me, I too tremble, But woman's blood is slower of its motion: It makes our breast heave and our cheek flush vivid, But seldom makes the hand to quake, as now Yours which I hold in mine, nor heart to bound, As I have felt yours bound what time you know. Orsino. Angelo, think you there are goodlier lips Than these two flowers of women. Angelo. Noble duke, Down in the grots of coral 'neath the sea, Where mermaids look upon their parted plaits Of braided hair in polished mother-o'-pearl Or crystal mirrors, singing sweet the while And combing with the teeth of saw-fishes Set in pure gold; or on the mountain peaks, Where oreads reach their hands up t'ward the stars, Dancing on needly pinnacles; or where, In tropic forests under tufted palms, While peacocks spread their pride and orchids burn, Clustering with scarlet blossoms on the trees, Beside some ivory palace, to a tank By steps of marble in a magic garden Some eastern queen in nakedness goes down, Followed by all her maids, each maid a rose: In such fair scenes such beauty may abide, But nowhere else, I think, on the wide earth. Punchinello (to Valeria). It is a picture makes one mad to dream of. Valeria. Sit closer to my side. Orsino. Now Angelo, Speak without fear:—which deem you of these twain, These rival pearls, the fairer? Angelo. Noble duke, The bright Giuditta is a moonlight fairy, Such as with gossamer iridescent wing Make little rainbows in the moonlit leas, And leave the flowers the fresher which they touch With the soft snow-fall of their flowery feet, But in the lightning's chariot and the car Of the eight-horsed whirlwind is not fit to ride— She cannot spread her wings out on the storm And visit howling caverns on the mountains. But fair Valeria skims the foaming sea And revels in the fulvous thunder cloud; Her golden hair swathes her like flames of hell In the agony of passion; her wild eyes Scorch where they fall; her devastating smile Is lovely as the earthquake or the red Swift over bubbling of valcano fires; Her white hands look as they could strangle doves; The flowers she touches with her candent feet That make bare patches in the swarthy heath All wither. Yet she is the lovelier, And were I great I would her trampling scorn Should rather stamp me into the black earth Than meet the fragrance of the other's kiss That seals the eyes with holy healing balm. Orsino. Canst thou devise a song to picture her. Angelo Ay, lord, I pray you listen:— She is paler than a rose-leaf and her brow is white and waxen, Flamy flakes of flowers about it drop like fire along the flaxen Wavings of her misty tresses. She is neither young nor olden: Myriad moons have waned and waxen, Since across her bosom folden First her white arms evanescence Mingled with the twilight golden In a rainbow iridescence. By the white cascade she glimmers and the belled spray writhes and shimmers Through her filmy form and falls on pale grass at her silver feet: Oh, her eyes are deep and cruel! In her cincture each red jewel Burns a living ember kindled with a preternatural heat— Burning clearly, burning densely, As her heart glows more intensely, Rubious fires that thrive and sicken As her pulses fall and quicken, Like red stars they burn and throb, Radiating fiery petals; She can shriek like fields of slaughter, And like hissing molten metals Is the echo of her sob, And her sigh like bubbling water! Valeria. I thank thee for the song, I like it well. Orsino. Nay, but I like not thou shouldst like it well; The poet colours with his lurid soul The likeness of thy beauty. He would fain, To more sublime it, liken thee to shapes Of glorious evil, and I praise the skill, Yet having ever found thee good and kind I would not have thee call the picture true. Punchinello (to Valeria). 'Tis true, howe'er he like. To paint thy face The threatening colour of the thunder-cloud Must mingle with the delicate red that speaks Of poison in the berry fruit and flower. Scene V. —Valeria's Chamber. Valeria. Ho, there, Benedetta. Benedetta. Did my lady call? Valeria. Call, yes, and often. Hast thou ears, girl? Benedetta. Ay, Ears far too sharp to catch my lady's sense, When some more timid would be deaf. Valeria. How now? Benedetta. My lady— Valeria. Silence. You grow strangely bold, And, hark ye, I mistrust you. Benedetta. But, dear lady— Valeria. Look to it. The Doge my lord yet lives. And you, When have you shown excuse? Benedetta. Hear me awhile, Valeria. I will not. Benedetta. Nay, but hear me, Valeria. Graceless girl, You have grown up beside me 'neath my eye. When have you lacked for aught that I could give? You have had jewels, silks, and costly things, Your pick of all my treasure. You have been The kernel of my mind, housed secretly In its securest inmost sanctuary, So that my soul and yours were like twin fruit, Two almonds in a shell. And for all this, When I but ask a little boon of you You make some hard condition, and delay Till I am tortured. Know you not, the life Of the poor grey-beard is my slow disease, And for each minute that he thrives I waste, And every breath he draws ebbs from my heart. Yes, on my heart I know that he is fed, And sucks my veins as vampires do, or as The sick and aged sleeping by the young Draw from their cheeks the bloom into their own And give instead their wrinkles and decay. Why will you let him live? Benedetta. Well, to be frank, I have not yet my stipulated wage. Am I not still a maid? Valeria. Ha, ha, you thought That I was earnest. How far will you go? How much will you presume? Benedetta. Presume! you promised. Valeria. And what, think you, are promises to me Who deal in murders? Shall I stick at treachery If I recoil not from blood-guilt? Shall I, Who for this man am murdering my husband, Submit him to your lewd embrace? Benedetta. What's that?— My lady, I am not mistress of myself. Permit me go. Valeria. Go! Think you me a fool? Yes, go, and tell the Doge! Most like! Think you That I would wake your poor malignity, The venom I have proved, and not make sure My path before me. Foolish girl. Yes, go, But further than you deem. What, are you pale? Benedetta. God, I am doomed. The wine you gave me now! Yes, yes, I have a pang here sharp as fire. Oh, God, time to repent! Kill not my soul. Lady—Oh God, I am fit for Hell, not Heaven. Save me but for an hour. You smile. She-devil, I will betray you yet. Help, ho! I die, Help, help, there! Valeria. Peace, fool. Benedetta. Help! My lord the Doge Is to be murdered by his— Valeria. Peace, I say, What, will you struggle? You are weak enough, That cup was stoutly dosed. There, swallow that, The silken thing I gave you, 'twill serve now To bind your tongue. Benedetta (breaking away). Out! God is on my side, Help! here is murder, treason, treason. (Falls.) Valeria. Die. What, are you silent? Nay, then, all is well, And yet I know not now whom I have left To dress my hair, for there was none like thee. Well, I must make some other serve as well.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. Scene: A Garden. Punchinello walking with Valeria. Valeria. Do you love flowers? Punchinello. Ay, wherefore ask you me? Valeria. I know not. Look you, do you love this thing, This drooping, white, pure, dainty little star, With sparry leaves spread out like rays, a heart Of gold, not flaming like a comet's core, Not burning like the nucleus of a sun, But modest, sprinkled o'er with powdery gloss, Glowing with constant light not over warm, A little jewel-stud set in the crown Of marriage? Punchinello. 'Tis a delicate flower enough, 'Twere pity of one to hurt it. Valeria. But I will: Look how I snap it off. The feeble sap Oozes like waterish blood. If you broke me You would find richer life. But look on this A heavy rose drenched in a maddening steam Of perfume, hanging down its gorgeous head, Each petal curled like proud voluptuous lips, Redder than blood of princes, swarthy crimson, A sunset streaked with night, a midnight black Carmined with conflagration, dusky-glowing Like a creole's peach-coloured cheek, or down Upon a splendid moth, a fulvous damask Like velvet to the fingers, dewy-rich With the heart's exuding moisture. From its presence An effluence of passion, waft of love, Sickens the soul as from a Maenad's body, Revelling in the tropic heat of woods Among the frantic satyrs—It has caught The fiery colour of their fox-red hides— Open it out, lay back the petalled plaits; What have we here? Another sort of heart From that poor daisy's. Spheric like a moon That coruscates under a thunder-cloud, But rather like a rubious fog-wrapt sun, A molten-metal ball, a candent globe. Now touch its many leaves of rusty red; Smell it and kiss it, and an essence keen Cleaves to the sense and lips. Which would you have, This florid flower, love, or that pale bloom Of married sanctity? Punchinello. I would have this flower. Valeria. See how I give it you.—But gently—First The pallid flower must die. Do you consent? Punchinello. You riddle darkly. Give it me. So now I set my foot on it and grind its hues Into the gravel. See the poor small thing, Some bruised white petals now no longer white Like crushed flies' wings, and a poor heart of gold Ground into sticky powder on the path. Valeria. Will you do this? (Punchinello kisses her hand.) Then you may have the rose; But stay, there are some clustering little blooms Around the daisy. We must not leave those Will you set foot on them too? Punchinello. Thus and thus. Valeria. Promise me this too. (Punchinello kisses her hand.) Why, then, take the rose. Now set your arm about me, hard against My beating side. Bruise it. You cannot clasp Too hard. I am no daisy, but a rose. Scene II. —Giuditta's Chamber. Giuditta in the Balcony. Giuditta. Give me my lute. Maid. Here lady, by your hand. Giuditta. He loved me once. Oh, sweet moon rising o'er The ebon tree-tops solemn, soft, and still, Shedding serene and silver influence About the misty marges of the air. Thou once wast like a music to my mind, And basking in thy dream-light after dusk, I softly closed my eyes and mused and mused, Repeating o'er and o'er within myself Three magic words,—He loves me, yes, he loves me. Now thou art no more dear. Thy mystic gaze Is grown an icy stare. Thy light is cold, There is no witchery in it. Maid. Lady, my lady, Why are you sad? You have not touched the lute. Giuditta. Take it again. I will not sing to-night. Scene III. A room in Punchinello's house. Punchinello discovered reading. Afterwards Giuditta enters. Punchinello (starting). Who's there? Aha! Giuditta. (Brushes away some papers from the table.) Giuditta. Gentle husband, Am I a spirit to scare you, that you start? And have I earned your hate that your voice jars In speaking to me? Methought you spoke those words As one who, dreaming mischief deeply, sees All of a sudden the object of his thought, His prey, his quarry. Say, what have I done That ever of late you treat me thus? I fear And yet I sorrow more to see it. Come, Ofttimes we have but one chance in our life To clear ill clouds of doubt and calumny. If such are on me, I do prophesy, And say this is that time; and never again, Never, I feel, shall such occasion more Be granted thee to learn my innocence, For death hangs like a shadow over me,— I feel its darkness to the core, I hear Its ominous thunder in your voice. Come speak. Be frank with me. Punchinello. What! Is the woman mad? Seek you some honest house-wife's work and keep These fancies from your brain. 'Tis idleness, 'Tis sloth and ill digestion make these vapours. Plague me no more with them. See you not these? I am busy. Leave me. Giuditta. Nay, I will not, lord. You cannot blind me with a wave of the hand; Have I not lived with you this year or two, And know I not when you are angered thus? Nay, tell the sea-man who lives on the deep And with the sky and stars, he but mistakes The threat of the north wind—Will he not laugh?— Or me, who know that thunder in your voice, That undertone of growling tiger-cats, That some one must not die for this. I know. Punchinello. Go to. Thou art a fool, and wilt be ever; Have I not bade thee leave me? Giuditta. Ay, my lord. Punchinello. And lingerest yet? By heaven, thou'lt have me wroth, And bring thy dream's fulfilment, if thou stay Tarrying and loitering when I bid thee go. Giuditta. My lord, be frank with me. Punchinello. Be frank with me. Doth not the Doge pay flattering compliments? Aha! Giuditta. My lord, it is not mine to appoint What the Doge shall or shall not speak. His tongue He ruleth and his counsel as seems best To his noble will, and who shall say him nay? Punchinello. His tongue, his counsel, and his noble will— What take you me for? Giuditta. For my noble lord. Punchinello. For one who will have kings put over him? Giuditta. A loyal servant of the Duke and Church. Punchinello. To tamper with the purity of his hearth— Giuditta. My lord! You mock the noble Doge and me. Punchinello. And will not raise a hand in self-defence— Giuditta. My lord, I pray you much, be disabused. Punchinello. To keep their lewd embraces from his bed? Giuditta. Oh, now I am sure some slanderer is at work. Punchinello. As every free Venetian noble should,— Giuditta. My lord, believe not slanderers. Guard your ears. Punchinello. And will not punish a light-minded girl Because it is a king or duke she chooses— Giuditta. My lord, I am most innocent, you deceived. Punchinello. To play the fool with, and no common man? Giuditta. Kill me, my lord, but guard your lips. Beware, For my sake, of loose speech, and dangerous treason. Punchinello. Then know you have mistook me, and be warned— Giuditta. My lord, I love you, I am innocent. Punchinello. To guard you for the future. Now be gone. (Exit Giuditta in tears). Scene IV. —Giuditta's chamber. Giuditta enters, staggers, and falls. Laura. Help, help, my lady is not well. Help, there! Giuditta. Call no one. I am faint. Set me a chair. Laura, I am not ill, but I must die. Laura. Die! Wherefore? Giuditta. Said I that? I meant it not. I am but faint. More air. Laura. You are dead white, You are afraid; you have been threatened. Giuditta. Hush. Who should dare threaten me? Impossible. Men fear my husband. Laura. Ay, but whom fears he? Giuditta. But whom fears he? What mean you? I am faint. Support my head. Laura. Now, if this thing be done 'Twill be a monstrous crime. Giuditta. Who spake of crime? I feel death near me. I must die. 'Tis fixed. Is it a crime to die? Laura. Nay, but to kill. Giuditta. You talk at random foolishly. My death Shall be from God—He only gave me life, And to his hands I yield it. Bear me hence. Scene V. —A dark room. Punchinello's voice. Valeria! (No answer. A long pause.) Punchinello's voice. Valeria! Valeria's voice. Hush. Punchinello. Is't thou? Where in this darkness art thou hid from me? I seem to grope for thee in Hell, among The spirits. Come, come quickly. Oh, 'tis gloom, Like a lost world. Valeria, it is done. Valeria. I knew it by the feel of thy hot hand, And heard it in the rhythmic dance of blood In all thy swollen veins. Poor hand, poor brow! Oh, Punchinello, you are damned for me. You are in pain. You totter. Help, I say! Nay, whom should I call hither? I am crazed To think of calling. Lean on me, sweet love, I love thee best thus hot with murderous fire. Punchinello. And I thee also. But 'twas terrible— I tell thee, sweet Valeria, 'twas a sight Too pitiful. I had not fathomed it, The anguish of the moment, till it came. Oh, I have wrought a crime on all things pure To kill so sweet a child. But thy fierce eyes Shone on me, and I grasped, I throttled her, Fancying I but kissed thee—a fierce delight Took hold of me. I know not: I have heard There is a lust of murder. Valeria. What? you learn This for the first time? What, you knew this not! I half begin to think you scarcely worth A crime. Nay, loose me. Punchinello. How, Valeria? Have I destroyed the life that grew with mine, Twined with my branches, nourished with my sap, To please you, and you now will cast me off? Oh, turn again. I perish. Valeria. Weakling. Punchinello. What! Speak that again, and as I throttled her, So will I wrench the life out of thy gorge. I am not safe to tamper with: the fire Is up. I know the blood-lust now. Valeria. Dear love, Do as thou wilt. Slay me. I am thine own To love or slay since now thou art thyself.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. Scene.—A grand banquet. The Doge. Councillors, senators, and friends, well met. And when shall we have better cause to feast? This day is like a jewel in the months And shines superior mid all other days, A peach of fruits, a rose of flowers, a white And lamping diamond of gems. For now, Some five and twenty refluent seasons past, Winter and summer, ebb and flood of the year, Our worthiest warrior, noble, scholar, friend Issued upon the light. Therefore be glad And drink to Punchinello. Punchinello. Gracious lord, You praise the lowliest of your following As generous natures will: and for return I'll pledge you in a draught your cellar's best, And you shall drink again a cup of mine Shall lift you into glory, and such joy, That you shall swear it is the mightiest wine Your lips e'er tasted. Ho, Tobia, fill The Doge's cup. Doge. How wild it bubbles and froths, As love or death were in it. On the level I see a creamy foam as of churned waves In a great tempest, cruel and white, but fair, And sweet as vintage of enchanted vines. Where got you such a nectar? Punchinello. Good, my lord, 'Tis not Italian grown. A dusky Moor Gave it to me in Spain. I tasted it. A mineral sweetness flew into my brain, And all my blood like lightning flashed and danced. The crystal half-sphere, whence my lips had drawn The rubious liquor, blue and silver shone, Until methought I gazed on the wan moon. Mine eyes were dazzled with delicious dreams, And my ears full of music. From that day I kept the flask, and once or twice at most Upon great feast days I have tasted it. This which you drink is the last precious drain Of the rare treasure. Doge. You have honoured me, I never drank such wine. Now health to you, Noble Eugenio, let me fill your cup Eugenio. And I'll fill yours. I have no magic wine, But bring my best. Doge. I shall not blame the cup When blessed by such a friend. And you, lord cardinal. Felice. I drink to you. Boy, fill the Doge's cup— Lacrima Christi from the Vatican. This wine the Pope sends to thee. Doge. It is sweet, But—hold me, I am ill. Angelo My lord, my lord. Punchinello. His lips are livid. Black, I say, quite black. Some wretch hath given him poison. Now by Heaven I like not this, Felice. Felice. Nay, nor I, Foul murderer, 'tis the summit of thy deeds. Punchinello. By God I'll teach thee call me murderer. Nay never hold the cross up, for by Heaven Though the Pope stood betwixt us, I would probe To find that toad thy heart.—Leave me, I say, I'll wrench his Latin-sputtering tongue from him. Felice. Unholy man, I leave thee to thy crime, And to the judgment of the citizens. Till then, farewell. Punchinello. Off hands. You sir, take that. Lie there. I'll after him, the lying priest. (Rushes to the door after the Cardinal, but is forced back by the guards.) Scene II. —A wood. Enter Valeria and Punchinello from opposite sides. Valeria. Well met. Punchinello. So we are free now. We have cleared Our love's great sombre temple of those poor swallows That chirped and fluttered in its sanctuary, Breaking the shade and silence. Now we stand In it alone, treading on graves, and girt With funeral tablets on the wall. Our eyes Fall everywhere upon some monument, Where child or wife weeps fallen on the urn. Come, should we not be solemn? Should we not Feel awful obligation in our vows, And deep religion, paid in such a place? You laugh. Have you no reverence? Valeria. Kiss me, Satan. I think the devil incarnate is in you, For sin becomes you like a gorgeous robe, And you look kingly, never kinglier Than when your hands are red. Punchinello. True, love, most true, It is the privilege of kings to kill, But I, I am no kinglet. Valeria. Well, 'tis good. Now you have earned me fairly. I am revered To think of it. Last night I had a dream. Methought you came and lay down at my side. The night was dark. I fed upon your lips, And you gave back my kisses hot and quick. Then I turned from you to take breath, and lo! A thin white beam of moonshine struck across The darkness of the chamber, straight on us. I turned round laughing t'ward you in the light, And blindly kissed the dead Doge in his shroud. Then oped my eyes full on the poisoned face, Blue in the dead white moonrays. Then I shrieked, And he clutched at me and held me, and I thought The poison entered foaming in my veins, And filled me with corruption of the grave, Yet living. Punchinello. You women have not our steadfastness; You have lost courage so to dream. Valeria. Not I, My courage is the main part of my soul After thy love, my own inalienable, And shall not leave me save with life. Punchinello. Well, well. What matters courage? You are wondrous fair, And I have yet to wear the gorgeous flower That I have won. To-night then shall it be? Valeria. To-night, and day is cursèd for thy sake For frightening off with gay and garish light The slow approach of those delicious hours. Farewell. Vunchinello. Farewell, Valeria, till to-night. Scene III. —A room in Punchinello's house. Tobia. You sent for me. Punchinello. Ay, did I. Tobia. Here, my lord. Punchinello. Go to, you know too much. Tobia. Too much, my lord! Punchinello. Ay, said I not ‘too much’? It is not safe That you should walk abroad. I'll have you muzzled. Tobia. My lord. Punchinello. Muzzled, or gagged, or silenced once for all. Tobia. I am discreet, no tale-teller. Punchinello. Thou beast, Thou hast already blabbed. Tobia. Blabbed! Punchinello. Ay, in thy cups, Thou drunken driveller—or worse, perchance, With dry lips thou hast half my secret told. Tobia. I! Punchinello. You. Tobia. Lord, spare me. I will guard my tongue. Look not so on me. I see in your eyes Death. I have seen it there before. That look Was always followed by a murder—Help! Punchinello. Silence, you dog. Tobia. I know that I am doomed. You mean to murder me. Oh, pardon, pardon. Have I not been a faithful, secret— Punchinello. —Slave. Tobia. Ay, lord, a slave, faithful and secret. Punchinello. Die, And keep my secrets with you in the tomb. (Stabs him). Under the floor I have a hole for you. Down to the pit, you offal! Panderer Of murder! You have had a scanty shrift. Now will I go and see the new Doge wed His bride, the sea. T'will show like innocence To put a bold face on the business. What? Art quiet? Farewell, honest slave of crime. To murder for another's pleasure thou Didst hold no fault. Now thou art gone before To be the Devil's pimp in Hell. Ha! ha! I feel my secret safe with thee at last Until the judgment day—the judgment day.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT IV. Scene I. —The court. The Doge sitting in state. Marco. Nobles, and men of Venice here assembled, Ye meet to-day to unravel back the web Of close-spun crime, and mid a myriad threads Of meshes finer than the spider weaves To seek the clue that goes right through the robe. Here Punchinello stands before our seat, Charged with no less a sin than murder, nay, Of treason to our city, in the person Of him who late sat here upon this throne, Your doge Orsino, a right valiant prince, Whom all men loved and honoured. Now attend, And, learned Dionysio, read the charge. Dionysio. Most noble Doge, and you, Venetian elders, I charge this Punchinello with the crime Now uttered, which my lips scarce dare to frame. And first I charge Paolo—the live weapon Wherewith the master-artist graved the metal Of his raw crime into the perfect shape. This man most clearly gave the good duke poison, Drenched in a cup of wine at the grand feast. For you, Pietro, you, as cup-bearer, Received the draught straight from Tobia's hand, And placed it in your lord's, who then fell back, And died with livid lips and seething throat. But for the object of this deed, that lies So near the frail flower of a lady's honour, That scarce I would uproot it. Yet I must. This Punchinello—devil in all crime, Aspired to the pure love of the chaste wife Of good Orsino, and to compass her, Who struck his base endeavour cowering back, Groping about for means, lit on this act Of double evil, which to hide when done He slew Tobia, one of his tools, outright, And would have sent Paolo after him, But the shrewd knave smelt blood, and to be avenged, Spake out the thing from starting post to goal, How he was sent with gold to lure the faith Of all the Doge's men, of whom alone Paolo took the bait, how at the feast Tobia and Paolo brewed the drink That made a furnace in Orsino's blood. What more have I to say? Is this not plain? Was ever crime more manifest? You two, Paolo and Pietro, will ye swear That every word is fact which I have breathed? Paolo and Pietro. We swear. Marco. Oh, lost and wicked man, have shame. Will your effrontery never be abashed? Or will you ope your lips? Punchinello. Ay, reverend sir. I do profess I am astounded. Knaves, Your lies shall take you and strangle you. I stand O'erwhelmed with horror and astonishment At such a crime imputed. Ay, we know Whence comes this stroke at my unguarded life. Not from these slaves be sure. Subtler the brains, Stronger the hands that dare to strike at me. Ay, we know well whence all my ills have come, From what foul fount all poisons issue here And threaten soon to flood the state. We know. This was a master stroke to lop two heads, Both held o'erproudly, blades that topped his own, And would not let his scarlet flower be seen By reason of our golden wheat. The priests, The priests, look you, are ever in these ills; They will have no one great save mother-church, That is themselves. Whose servant was Tobia Ere he was mine? His master loved me well! Oh, yes, we know, and loved Orsino too! What better than to compass death for him, At my hand as it should appear, and gain At once the goal of both his hates and of His lust of glory, scaling to that peak Whereof the stature beckoned from above To that whereon he stood, though high enough? Ay, ay, Felice, shake your blood-hued hat Over your hoary hair. Think you I fear you? You, cardinal, you murdered our good Doge; You bribed Tobia, once your faithful man, Entrusted with the errands of your crimes; You put suspicion on Valeria; And all to ruin me.—You see it all, Nobles of Venice. How it all grows light! You know the man's ambitions, know his hate Of me and of Orsino, who alone Had dared to check him, knew his subtle craft, His trust in his high office to conceal All crimes his doing. Look you to it well. For me, I will be silent, having spoken. Think you I fear you all? Dogs, let me die. My innocence goes with me: and I spurn you. Now I have finished. Marco. This shows very ill. Lord cardinal, we know your pride of heart, And this young noble's blameless life. 'Twere hard To deem that youthful breast so drenched with sin As so to play with murder. We are sad. We fain would see you clear yourself, my lord. Felice. I will not deign to speak. Ye have no power Upon me. I am in God's hand, his priest, A servant of his church, and to his throne On earth, the visible head of Christendom, My master, and his vicar, I appeal. Scene II. —A wood. Punchinello waiting for Valeria. Punchinello. Why comes she not? 'Tis strange. I have heard say It speaks love fading to be late at tryst; What should this mean? (Enter Valeria.) Valeria. Have you been waiting long? Punchinello. Ay, almost to heart-sickness. Valeria. Pardon me. In truth I almost thought to come no more. Oh, Punchinello, I have had such dreams; Their horror yet swims in my reeling brain Like the vague memory of some sin forgot Returning in the middle of the night Suddenly, in delirium, when the wall Seems miles away. Punchinello. Come hither, make your shrift, For I give ready absolution, And, being houselled, let it pass and rest. Valeria. I cannot. Do you know, last night, again, A dream I had once some while ere the things You wot of, and I cannot bear to name, Returned. 'Twas of Giuditta and the Doge Walking together by a burning lake Wherein you cast them—but ninefold more fell, Ninefold more hideous. Nay, the dim surmise Of having seen it all before, the sense Of recognition folded it like fire In a storm-cloud, more lurid for the shade Of a bewildered memory. How the surge Curdled about their bodies! Oh, his eyes, His eyes turned upward like a water-snake's Glaring out of the foam! They seemed to swim Upon the water like two burning balls, For I could see them only, not his face. Punchinello. You will go mad, sweet, if you think of it. Valeria. I care not greatly, so that right were done, And truth made manifest. Love, I am changed. Crime cannot long rest buried. The dumb corpse Of murder has an everlasting soul That leaves it and flies howling off to hell; And as a flower grows from an infant's tomb, So filthy fungus crusts the sepulchre, And sprouts out of the bones and mouldering flesh Of the unholy dead, and of their deeds. Oh, love, there is a God. Punchinello (aside). Why, here's a change! She is not safe to live. Love, be at ease. Valeria. Oh, never more. Punchinello. Come, kiss me, and forget. Valeria. No, no, it is too loathsome. Oh, keep back, You have the old man's lips. Bah! must I see These horrible visions? Oh, to close my eyes! The lids are powerless, for there is an eye Within the soul that God made without lids, For ever open, open, day and night, Oh God, my God! Punchinello. When I shut up my eyes I see but red light. Valeria. Ay, that's it—red, red. The very light is turned now into blood, Like Egypt's waters. Punchinello. Oh, Valeria! Valeria. Call me no more Valeria. Find some name That never can recall me to myself, For I must go hence and be no more seen, To a prison, or a convent, or— Punchinello. the grave. You were best there, not cloistered up with fools. Valeria. Fools, are they fools who live away from men? Oh, they are wise to shut them from the joys That lure to lust and murder. Oh, my love, For I have loved you, save your soul with me, Confess all, make your peace with Heaven. Punchinello. Great God! Is this Valeria? Valeria. Once more, no, for she Is dead. Punchinello. Ay, you say truly she is dead. She is writ down for death. Valeria. You scowl on me. Punchinello. 'Tis but a holy penitence thus draws My brow. Go to. If you must leave me, well. Here, take this ring, and when you tell your beads It shall remind you of a soul needs prayer Yet more than thine. Kiss it and pray for me. Valeria. Oh, blessèd change. Oh, I am happier now, Morning and noon with prayers and tears for thee My lips shall press it. Holy symbol, come Stay there and tell me of a penitent I hope to see in Heaven. I kiss thee, friend, Gift of a friend too dearly loved— Oh, fiend! You have poisoned me! Oh, monster! All my sins Cling round me like the clothes of drowning men And drag me down to hell. Oh, for some time To make my peace with God! It is too late. Then kiss me ere I go. Punchinello. You have betrayed me. Die unatoned, unkist, stranger alike To God and me, baffled of Heaven and love. So is it ever with the waverers. They will have all things and gain nothing. Go. Valeria. God pity me. Punchinello. Ay, as thou pitiedst me. Who was it made me kill my innocent wife, My babes, and all I might have loved? In sooth I had a taste to murder—but not these. And now you turn upon me. So may God Forget thee in His mercy. Nay, now, go, Make short work in the dying. Valeria. Lost, all lost! Alone, unreconciled, unpardoned, lost. Punchinello. She is quite dead. Well, after all, 'tis best, For I was tiring of her. Then heigh ho! The world is wide, and I am young: more miles, More years have I to travel and new joys, New crimes to prove before my journey's end, And then, why then, I shall have had my time, And for the rest care nothing. Come, the ring. (Takes the ring and exit.)</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT V. Scene: A forest. Enter Punchinello with Lurdo. Punchinello rides a black horse. He dismounts and hands the reins to Lurdo. Punchinello. Yonder afar I seem to see a light Across the valley, twinkling through the trees. Go, Lurdo, seek it out, and lead the horse, Perchance it is some convent of fat friars, Who burst their girdles upon vulgar dainties, And when they have been warmed with home-made wine Make rude advances to the country maids Whose coarse charms we have seen among these trees. Go, I will follow after. For some while I would be left alone. Why loiterest, slave? I have said, go. Lurdo. Master, I am afraid, The woods are full of brigands, ay, and worse, If folks say true. Last year one, Andrea, A muleteer who had drunken deep of wine, Was torn by devils. The monks found his limbs Scattered among the bushes. And young Marco, One of our town, who got his niece with child, Vanished just here and never was seen more. This is no place for sinful men. Punchinello. Go to, You grovelling slave. I have seen you crouch at mass; Will all that crawling not avail you now Against the terrors of your coward mind Which you call fiends? Have you not yet appeased The wrath of heaven with candles?—and for what? For kissing on the onion-smelling lips Some greasy tavern-maid, for eating flesh O' Fridays, and for bousing of sour wine! Go to, fat innocence, if this heart of mine Were clear as yours, I should die easier. Straight on before you. What, you want the spur; (Pricking him with his rapier) Ho, ho, my capering filly, on with you. (Exit Lurdo) Punchinello (sitting on the trunk of a tree) Sleep, sleep awhile you murderous rage within. You have tasted blood in torrents. Rest awhile Here in the ebon darkness of these trees. I like the gloom of the funereal firs, And the tall cypress, and this loamy soil Black as a churchyard, damp as the deep grave, Littered with mast and cones, which are the dead Of the forest, and are buried where they fall— But—not like human dead—to spring again. There goes the moon. The cloud has rolled away; It shines like silver through the black fir-spikes. Hulloa, what have we here? (Enter Brigands.) Brigand Chief. My dainty sir, We are come just in good time to help my lord Unrobe for bed. Charity, good friend. Feel in your pocket. We take only gold. (Punchinello stands up.) Punchinello. Hither, I pray, a word with you, good friend. An exile from my city, I would make One of your crew. A little more aside, I pray you,—I have somewhat for your ear I would not have all know. Lay your head close, My friend— Take that, and that. (Stabs him twice, then folds his cloak round his arm, and comes forward.) Good people all, Your chief is dead. Have me instead of him. I am fearless, bloody, and of noble birth. I might avail you much to buy off death From any whom the law should seize. Meanwhile I would make fair division of the spoils, And know where plenty lies. All. Save our new chief! Punchinello. Go quickly, half of you, and bear the news Back to your lair. The rest must be my guide. (Exeunt several.) Now, friends, here is a noble for you each, And next to prove submission to your chief, Lay down your arms. Lay down your arms, I say. (They look at each other.) Punchinello (to one). Dog, do you hold thus back when I command? That in your heart. (Stabs him.) Now come on all the rest. 'Tis one to three, but I have stood worse odds. (Disarms one, catches another's sword in his cloak, kills all.) So once again I have befooled the apes, My sweetest fellow creatures. I feel shame To call them fellows. 'Tis but that their form Is mimicked after mine, a copy spoilt, Distorted, counterfeit, that makes them kin. I have a mind above them and a heart Of trustier steel. Go up into thy sheath, My ancient friend, for thou hast done good work. (Sheathes his sword.) When Punchinello falls, if fall he must He shall not fall by man. What glistens there? (A spirit appears in likeness of Valeria.) Spirit. Thy time is come to fall, but not by man. Punchinello. Valeria! Spirit. Mock not so thyself and us, For though I wear her form I am not she. She was but as an effluence of my power. Wherever evil is and foul desire There am I, and to each man's eyes appear In different guise, in likeness of the lust That strongest burns within him. Unto thee I image all that can defile a man, Guile, cruelty, murder, rape, adultery. Thou hast done all these things. Now look on me. Punchinello. I cannot. Spirit. What, afraid! Is this the man Who loved crime for itself and mocked at God And dares not now look his own sin in the face? Punchinello. Thou liest. I dare, hell-hound, I dare do all. And wert thou God himself, I'd rip thee up, Here with my rapier. Spirit. Ignorant, frail man, Dost thou threat spirits with thy earth-forged steel, And hurl thy blasphemies even at God. Punchinello. Dastardly spirit. Take thou refuge then, In thy thin essence, which steel cannot pierce, But call not me a dastard. Here I stand. If I cannot pierce thee, yet thou canst me. Come, do thy worst. Thou saidst I dared not look Upon thee. I dare tell thee that thou liest, And I dare spit at thee. Spirit (assuming another and a horrible shape). And dar'st it now? Punchinello. Ay, now. Thou think'st to fright me by this form. Thine ugliness but makes me laugh. Foul thing, Learn this from me, a mortal. Beauty and power Are terribler than hideous impotence. Spirit (assumes a form of stern beauty). Punchinello. Now that is horrible in truth, and yet I fear thee not. I look thee in the eyes, And my soul feels thine equal. From the day When first I breathed my heart ne'er beat with fear, Nor does it now. I will go down to hell The equal of the devils or their chief. I do rejoice that I have made such wreck Of human hearts and lives. I would make more If I lived longer, for my whole delight Is to destroy. Come, let me grapple with thee, For thou may'st wreck and slay me, body and soul, But from these lips thou canst not wrench one cry. Spirit (assuming the shape of the chief of the devils) I, Satan, I, Abaddon, am thy chief, And shall reign o'er thee to eternity. Punchinello. Never, but to eternity we twain Shall wrestle for the empire till I win. Spirit. Poor worm. Punchinello. Ten thousand thousand years of pain Shall not subdue me. I will rise, and rise, Until I hurl thee from thy throne of flame, Or, if that may not be, yet will I rise Now and again, for ever. This I know, That you can never tame me. Spirit. Soon enough, Though thou wert tough as Cæsar, which I doubt. He sits there tame enough now. Feel my hand. Punchinello. It is all fire, and eats me to the bone. Yet see I look you in the eyes. Spirit. Lie there, A cinder, that your blasted corpse may be A warning to mankind. And, for your soul, I bid it join me ere the dawn in hell. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>