<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">, , Manley, (Mary de la Rivière), Mrs, 1663-1724</field>
      <field name="author_facet">, , Manley, (Mary de la Rivière), Mrs, 1663-1724</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">  manley mary de la rivire mrs 1663 1724</field>
      <field name="author_text">, , Manley, (Mary de la Rivière), Mrs, 1663-1724</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">17th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V2.0102.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240355</field>
      <field name="date_text">1696</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:459845</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Royal Mischief ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 17th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 17th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Royal Mischief ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="title_facet">royal mischief</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">royal mischief</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Royal Mischief ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="year_display">1696</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1696</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1696</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459845&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459845&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;, , Manley, (Mary de la Rivière), Mrs, 1663-1724&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt; manley mary de la rivière mrs 1663 1724&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Royal Mischief ; A Tragedy&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;royal mischief&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1696&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1696&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;, , Manley, (Mary de la Rivière), Mrs&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1663&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1724&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Royal Mischief&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for R. Bentley, F. Saunders, and J. Knapton&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1696&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872189-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv20102&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 17th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;17th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Royal Mischief&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 161 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: The royal mischief.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1696.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Apr 1696 ?&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE Royal Mischief. A TRAGEDY.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">To his Grace WILLIAM DUKE of Devonshire, &amp;c. Lord Steward of his Majesties Houshold, Knight of the Most Noble Order of the Garter, and one of his Majesties Most Honourable Privy-Council.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">To Mrs. Manley. By the Author of Agnes de Castro. Th'attempt was brave, how happy your success, The Men with shame our Sex with Pride confess; For us you've vanquisht, though the toyl was yours, You were our Champion, and the Glory ours. Well you've maintain'd our equal right in Fame, To which vain Man had quite engrost the claim: I knew my force too weak, and but assay'd The Borders of their Empire to invade, I incite a greater genius to my aid: The War begun you generously pursu'd, With double Arms you every way subdu'd; Our Title clear'd, nor can a doubt remain, Unless in which you'll greater Conquest gain, The Comick, or the loftier Tragick strain. The Men always o'ercome will quit the Field, Where they have lost their hearts, the Lawrel yield.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">To Mrs. Manley, upon her Tragedy call'd The Royal Mischief. As when some mighty Hero first appears, And in each act excells his wanting years; All Eyes are fixt on him, each busy Tongue Is employ'd in the triumphant Song: Even pale Envy hangs her dusky Wings, Or joins with brighter Fame, and hoarsly sings; So you the unequal'd wonder of the Age, Pride of our Sex, and Glory of the Stage; Have charm'd our hearts with your immortal lays, And tun'd us all with Everlasting Praise. You snatch Lawrels with undisputed right, And Conquer when you but begin to fight; Your infant strokes have such Herculean force, Your self must strive to keep the rapid course; Like Sappho Charming, like Afra Eloquent, Like Chast Orinda, sweetly Innocent: But no more, to stop the Reader were a sin, Whilst trifles keep from the rich store within. M. PIX.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">To Mrs. Manley, on her Tragedy call'd The Royal Mischief. Sent by an unknown hand. What, all our Sex in one sad hour undone, Lost are our Arts, our Learning, our Renown, Since Natures tide of Wit came rouling down. From you it flows with unresisted force, Nor can united Envy stop its course; Keen are your Eyes we know, and sure their Darts, Fire to our Soul they send, and Passions to our hearts; Needless was an addition to such arms, Where all Mankind are Vassals to your Charms; That hand but seen gives wonder and desire, Snow to our fight, but with its touches fire: You stroke our Souls, and all the Passions move, By fierce desires made fit for raging Love; Who sees thy yielding Queen, and woul'd not be On any terms the blest the Happy be Entranc'd, we fansie all his Ecstasy. Quote Ovid now no more ye amorous Swains; Delia, than Ovid has more moving Strains: Nature alone in her Exceeds all Art, And Nature sure does nearest touch the heart. O might I call the bright discoverer mine, The whole fair Sex unenvied I'd resign, Give all my happy hours to Delia's Charms, She who by writing thus our wishes warms, What Worlds of Love must Circle in her Arms.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PROLOGUE spoken by Mr. Betterton. Criticks, ye are grown so much unkind of late, Who dares to write runs on their certain Fate; If to Parnassus once they miss their way. Once chance to glimmer out a feeble ray, Condemn 'em always by such light to stray; That Poets floating betwixt hopes and fears, Now dread you more than Merchants Privateers. Fain ours wou'd bribe you high to let her live, At least mayn't mercy stretch to a reprieve; So may the Statesmans Policy increase, And Traders have their wisht desires for Peace; So may the Levite, with no doubts perplext, E'en as dear Interest leads, explain his Text; So may the Beans be sparkish as they can, All Wig and Dress, no matter for the Man; The Souldier paid his money without fighting, And Poets there's in that worse Combat, Writing: The Vizards Mask it to their Friends unknown, Fool most themselves in fooling of the Town: My last kind Wishes Ladies are for you, Espouse your Sexes Cause, and bravely too, So may you still be fair, your Lovers ever true.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Persons Represented. Levan Dadian, Prince of Colchis. Mr. Bowman. Prince of Libardian his Uncle, and Protector of his State. Mr. Kynaston. Osman, Chief Visier. Mr. Betterton. Ismael his Cousin, a Great Officer. Mr. Hudson. Acmat an Eunuch of Homais. Mr. Freeman. Officers of Camp, and State. WOMEN. Bassima, Princess of Colchis. Mrs. Bracegirdle. Homais, Princess of Libardian, desperately in love with Levan. Mrs. Barry. Selima, Sister to the Prince of Libardian, and Married to the Chief Visier. Mrs. Bowman. Ladies attending on the Princesses. Eunuchs. Slaves. Four Mutes. Guards.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE the Castle of Phasia in Libardian, and the Prince of Golchis's Camp before it.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. SCENE I. A Royal Appartment in the Castle of Phosia. Enter Homais and Acmat. Hom. 'Tis finisht, and a work speaks loud as Fame, Where Crowns and Scepters truckle to his Vertue. My Conquering Cousin has the War o'ercome, And now slowly returns, with Honour prest, As thickning Lawrels, sprung to stop his passage, And turn a necessary march to one Long solemn triumph. Acm. He brings the Princess with him, and sure Such Beauty should be tasted leisurely, Lest the rich Cordial prove too strong for Life, And ruin that which 'twas design'd to bless. Hom. Name her not, she's a Disease to all my hopes, Like early blasts upon too forward Blossoms, Reduces all into their former nothing: Acm. Might I but hope my long try'd service, And secrecy, the rarity of Courts, Which still where you're concern'd, bids me be dumb; Forget I've Life, and ranks me with the dead; Cou'd this and more deserve your Royal Ear, I would be bold to ask the Cause of your Disorder. Hom. Why thou my Acmat, who hast known my weakness, And markt the various changes of my temper, Shoudst know my Griefs can have no other rise But Loves Almighty Passion. Acm. My sense had toucht the mark, If that my Memory in all its search, Cou'd but have fixt your new disquiets on A Person fit to fill your Royal Breast; Osman the new made Visier you detest, His Cousin Ismael you have enjoy'd; (And sure such Fires did never wait possession) Since that, none has approacht your Royal sight, Fit to give Love, or to create desire, Or if there had, I soon had markt the Man; For love like yours, in absence may be hid, In presence never! Hom. Right thou has guest, And yet the wound is love, but such a love; So hopeless, so fantastick, all my stock, Of Youth, and Charms, cannot forbid despair. Acm. Impossible, you know not half your Power, Those Eyes did never vainly shoot a Dart, Such are their Fires, so sparkling, so attractive, So passionately, soft and tender, So full of that desire they give, as though The Glorious Heaven stood ready for Possession: You never look but to command our love, And give your Lover hope— Then how shou'd you despair. Hom. Had they inimitable luster, Were all my Charms unequall'd, like that bright Light above, superiour and alone, yet To the Man, who never either saw, or Heard their Power, my Sun-shine would be lost. Acm. Is there on Earth a Wretch so must unblest. Our Eastern World is full of Homais Beauty, And I am bold to think you have not lov'd beyond: No second Alexander fills the Globe, No Glorious busy Hero, to inslave Your heart at distance, and with unseen Fame, Make Conquest easy, name but the Happy Man, And I'll secure him yours. Hom. Dull, dull, Eunuch, What Lethargy has stole thy reason from thee, Cold through thy Reins, and mingled with thy blood, How far wouldst thou extend thy busy search, Hunt round the Globe for airy Heroes, When the realities at home—the Prince —The inimitable Prince of Colchis— Thou startst— Despair surround me, if thy Coward bloud Has not forsook thy ghastly Face, The gorgon Name has turn'd him to a Statue. Acm. My fears are yours, nor can I chuse but fear, When that must bring despair which causes love. Your Eyes in all their glorious course (and sure They are Omnipotent) cou'd not have shone Upon a soil so barren, no kindly hopes, No prospect of return, no flatt'ring gleams Of Sun-shine through the show'rs to make us Hope a calm, first here your Husbands Nephew's Just Marry'd to a young and beauteous Princess: Time has scarce lent a hand to pluck the fruit, Or say 'twere gather'd, yet the flavour lasts; Then he's a Prince so much renown'd for Vertue, So true a Copy of the long-past Heroes, As will serve for an original to Ages yet to come, But O that which concludes his Character, Destroys us more, abundant gratitude, And love to the Protector— 'Tis to your Lord he ows his Conquer'd Fields, Who gave his Lawrels growth, mixt with his own To make one lasting shade, which all your rays Can never penetrate. [She seems disorder'd during this Speech, and at length sinks down in a Chair. Hom. A heavy doom, Too strong for Life to bear. Acm. How lawless is a Woman's Love, The swelling current will admit no bounds; For if not gratify'd they die— [Within. Help there, the Princess sounds. [The Ladies appear. Hom. Bid 'em be gone, Alas it is not in their pow'r to help. This raging fire blazes to such a height, That till 'tis quencht, Life cannot come in doubt: I find, I feel, the burning at my heart, Which now, when thou hadst thought my reason lost, Shifted the Scene, and brought my anguish back. Acm. In all the course of Loves Tyrannick Power, I have not heard a Passion like to yours, Unsought, unseen, to throw your heart away; A Gem of that inestimable price, Shou'd be the blest reward of long paid service, And a flame, lasting and clear, as those bright Eyes, That lighted it. Hom. Thy vulgar Soul moves in the common road, Mine loaths the beaten path, and starts aside, To seek new Regions out, disgusted with the old, And now the rich discovery is made, I'll push the bold adventure on, And either die or Conquer. Acm. Change but the Climate and the Crown is yours, Survey the Globe, chuse where your Eyes wou'd reign; Or were it possible to mount the Skies, And wander through the starry Courts above, Not one bright dazling god but wou'd forgo His Heav'n for yours, and doat on the Exchange; Such magick's in your looks, none but The Prince of Colchis can resist them. Hom. How dares my Slave speak these uneasy truths, Thy barren Soul ne'er knew the growth of love, And wert not call'd to threaten but advise; No more expostulate a growing flame, More than Ambition bold, than anger fierce, Nor can but with possession be abas'd. My Life, my Soul, my All, is fixt upon Enjoyment, Resistance but augments desire: If thou wouldst live threaten no more despair, I've nam'd the Goal, lend me thy aid to reach it. Acm. If I have been displeasing to your Ear, Let my mistaken Zeal meet your forgiveness, For I have err'd to think of a defence When you prepare to arm; such Courage and Such Beauty must make the universal World your Slaves, nor will I more exempt the Prince, cou'd you but triumph there, the rest were Easy Conquest. Hom. Dost thou remember in my Virgin bloom, When time had scarce lent Colour to my Beauty, The Visier Osman made an interest here, My native Modesty taught long denyals, For 'tis but by degrees our Sex grow bold; Start at the name they after grow familiar with: Piqued with delays he urg'd his Sute no more, Nor took advantage of consenting Love, But left the bargain dead upon my hands, For which if ever I forgive the baulk, May lasting disappointments hunt me out, Watch all my steps and double as I turn; Dash the full Bowl when lifted to my Lips, And all the Senses eager for the taste. Acm. 'Twas then young Ismael return'd from travail, High in his youth, and with success made bold; He storm'd your heart, and took it by assault, Made himself Master of your richest treasure, For which the Visier drag'd him from your Arms; Sent him to Wars to disappoint you more, And wou'd have crost your Marriage with my Lord. Hom. But all those pangs which then thou saw'st me Suffer from Osman's scorn, and Ismael's loss, Were Minutes to the mighty Ages now; For had this hapned to an untry'd Courage, The weighty hand had sunk the novice down; Unable to support the pondrous blow. Acm. Yet e'er the Sun has gilded the Meridian, You may have hopes to see your Lover here: For so the Trumpet from my Lord reports, Last night they past the River Phasis, And pitcht their Camp along its swelling side; The Protector will undoubtedly be fond To entertain his Niece and Nephew here, And do them honour in his own Dominions; Now e'er the Princess treads her Colchian ground, Prepare your Charms, and let us see What Wounds your Eyes can make. Hom. They blaze with more than Comet Fires, The great and sure portents of following Fate; For Bassima or I must make the Prodigy. Trumpets, heark, they come—support— [Trumpets within. Me Acmat, or I shall sink with transport: Ay, now the fatal tryal's near, death or A heart more worth than thousand lives; Again they sound, feel but my throbbing heart How swift it plays, were it as low'd 'twould pay The Musick back, and speak both gratitude And love in strains unheard before. Enter a Slave. Slave. Madam, the Prince is enter'd. Hom. What Prince? Slave. The Prince, my Lord. Hom. Haste, and say I wait him here. [Exit Slave. What an unwholsome air that breath has cast, 'Tas dampt my Fires and almost put out life; My Senses turn and my chill'd bloud that ran In streams before, falls drop by drop as Frost Had numb'd the passage. Acm. Compose your self and meet my Lord with smiles, His jealous Age suspicious of a slight, Expects more wellcome than a youthful Lover, Wear close your thoughts, untold they are your own Nature has been so bounteous to our kind, Unless we lend the Clue they cannot reach our hearts. Hom. 'Tis most unlucky, thus to be deceived, Upon the first expectance. Oh thou Eternal Searcher of our hearts, that canst in thy large Book read our unhappy destinies, long Ages off, if I am doom'd a Martyr To my Love, shorten my pains, and let my Death be instant. Acm. Your Musick flourishes. My Lord is in the Lodgings, I hear him come; Shift swift your look, or you destroy us all. Enter the Prince of Libardian attended. Prince of Libar. O my fair Princess the joys of long past Life Are crowded in this moment, and a new Glittering store reveal'd to make me further Doat upon your Treasure. Hom. My Lord your Welcome— Prince of Libar. So cold, my Lord your welcome— Death meet my wishes, if this Minute, when I hug'd the dear Inchantress to my Bosom, That swell'd to meet the load, her snowy Arms, Kept not a most ingrateful distance, Nor Circled me, the least familiar welcome; And when I thought to mingle Kisses with her, She met my burning Lips with her cold Cheeks; Cover'd all o'er with a thick, damp sweat, Which nothing cou'd supply but strong aversion. Hom. Yet e'er my Lord you quarrel with my welcome, Allow me leave to say it was unkind To give the Stile and Dignity of Regent The empty name of Honour without Power, Whilst yon proud pamper'd Prelate bore the sway, Denied me leave to pass the Castle-Gates; And suffer'd none to have access, but just My Women, and my Slaves; hence 'twas I found My Servants were his Creatures, my Guards My Gaolers, and himself the Master Spy. Prince of Libar. O can you blame me to preserve a good On which the safety of my Life depends; Who but a Fool wou'd leave his wealth at large, To the uncertain Chance of Robbers hands, When by securing it 'tis sure his own. I am that Wretch undone, the moment, when I lose your treasure. Hom. 'Tis the Perogative of Age to talk, They dream broad wake, and then speak as they dream. Prince of Libar. Unequal nature, Why hast thou bestow'd A larger privilege of mind than body? For whilst we find and feel our Passions strong, We vainly hope the consequence as young; By Love made bold we hunt the beauteous Chace, Nor heed our lag of Body in the Race; Till taught too late in such ingrateful Arms, 'Tis Youth to Youth can only furnish Charms,; O cou'd I hide me ever from your Eyes, You shou'd no more my Love or Age despise. Hom. My Lord, you moralize too far, forgive My Sexes frailty, I'm a Woman, made Passionate by want of Liberty: I'll learn to wear my Fetters lighter, And if you please, will sute my wellcome to it. Prince of Libar. Wert thou but truly kind, What Worlds of bliss could'st thou not give? Thy Eye, thy Lips, thy thousand Beauties, Were too Divine a Feast for Mortal taste; O let me be but well dissembled with, And I will lie for ever in thy Arms, Nor never wake to find the fond illusion, But think it all substantial shining treasure. Hom. Well, now we are Friends— Let me like other Warriours Wives, First give a kiss, and then my dear, what News, How went the Battle, how the Peace, who wears The thickest Lawrel, and whose name sounds Sweetest in the mouth of Fame. Prince of Libar. Our Conquering Cousin, Young Levan Dadian, has out-stript my Age, Foil'd all my Glories by his rising splendour; For when the Battle hung in long suspence, And the nice Goddess wou'd be wooed by neither; Though each contending for the Lovers prize, Did things beyond a Lovers height; Till the young fiery Abean Prince, With a fresh Body of selected Horse, Broke in upon my Rear, my slaughter'd Men Supply'd the Luxury of Death, with a Full Feast, who did but taste before— Then young Levan flew to prevent the Inevitable stroke, which the up-lifted Hand of Fate stood ready to discharge: By Heav'n, it gave at once both spight and joy, To see this infant Eagle hatch underneath The cover of my Wings, now imp my flight, And far out-soar my height. Hom. But wheres this young Triumpher, shou'd we not Meet him now, with Io Pæans, and strow his Passage, with unfading Lawrels; do not All kneell to Heaven for benefits, why not To Heroes too, when they perform the work As well: I am indebted for a Husbands Life, And loath the stain of vulgar Souls Ingratitude; Lead me to pay the Tribute of my Thanks, For I, my Lord, am burthen'd with the weight. Prince of Libar. Incumbent duty has discharg'd your Debt, For when the fatal Circumstance Proclaim'd The Field our own, I ran to give him joy, He swore by all those hovering Ghosts just Then departed, that 'twas more satisfaction To preserve my Life, than find himself A Conquerour. Hom. But pray, my Lord, what of the Visier Osman, Has he deserv'd your mighty trust and favour, He cou'd not sure forsake in that Extremity A Prince who did him Honour. Prince of Libar. Why do you envy me, Inhuman Princess, That moments Peace our reconcilement brought? Or is't impossible my joys shou'd know thee Date of one small hour: but to retort that Poyson to your Heart with which you have Infected mine, know that your Minions lost For ever to your Charms. Hom. Not dead, my Lord. Prince of Libar. Then you avow him such, see if the bloud Has not forsook her Cheeks, and left her Beauties pale; I'll try if Jealousy, my Curst Tormentor, can have power to send the Roses back: Your Lover doats to death upon the Princess: I'm sorry for my Sisters sake, but Bassima's Bright Vertue leaves no suspicion of a stain; Like a Divinity, she teaches Fear And Reverence to all who worship her. Hom. May we not see this Goddess, will she not Deign, with the Divinity you mention, To Grace our little Court; or must I pay My Adorations at her own. Prince of Libar. No Homais, 'tis too dangerous a World, For Ladies of your Temper; I have declin'd Seeing my Nephew here, least the Court tide Of Liberty shou'd drown your Fame, where in The fatal Wreck, my Life cou'd never scape The Tempest. Hom. Then I'm it seems confin'd, till Age, or Grief Presents me Death, the work will not be long A doing: What signifies the Crown upon my head, When none can see how well the Circle sits, How rich and sparkling are the Diamonds, The Pearls how Orient; and how well such Glory sutes the wearers Face. Enter Selima attended. Sel. My only Brother, wellcome to my heart; I had much sooner ran to give you joy, And tell you mine, but that I know, when Lovers meet all other Visitants are But Intruders. Prince of Libar. My dearest Selima, I design'd this favour in your Lodgings, But every where from you 'tis wellcome. Sel. I am going on a Visit to the Camp, (The Visier sends he cannot leave the Prince) And hope, at my return, better to speak The transport of my Joy, for your Arrival. Prince of Libar. I'll wait you to your Chariot. Hom. Dull Princess. [Ex. leading. Thou art a Tool I must employ, to make The work, I labour with, compleat: Acmat Dost thou not think my Projects all aground, And my spent Vessel ready to be wreckt; But yet I'll not despair, Revenge does Aid my Love, and from within, I feel Undoubted Omens of success. In this Extremity all Aids I'll try, For he must either love, or I must die. [Exeunt omnes.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. SCENE I. A Pavillion Royal. Osman and Ismael. Osm. What boots it thus to drag a wretched being, A Lifeless lump, without one ray of hope; By Heav'n, I'll lay me down, and breath my Soul In sighs, at my too cruel Sovereigns feet; There grasp with my cold hands her flying Beauties, till I have urg'd her glorious Eyes To shed some pitying Tears. Ism. Rouse up your self, and bear you like a Man, The Lord of Womankind, born to Command That Sex which we intreat, but when we whine At your romantick rate, we move not love, But scorn, they like the forward and the bold, For Virtue in such Souls is like their form, Only exteriour Beauty, worn to deceive The credulous World, and buy Opinions From the common rout— But when they meet a Lover to their wish, They gladly throw the borrow'd Veil aside, And naked in his Arms disclose the cheat. Osm. You speak of common Women, are those fit To meet comparison with our blest Princess, Of whom 'tis Blasphemy to think her Mortal To any but our Lord the Prince. Ism. Fine stuff. What, do you doat upon a new found species? I thought you lov'd her; as she was a Woman, As nature bids us love, not with Platonick Nonsense; when you have reckon'd all her Beauties up, the Sex is lovelyest in her: Bate that Circumstance and a fair Picture Does the Work as well, if she be a Woman, Resolve to win her, and the work is done: Is she d'think the only frozen of Her Sex, whom the hot Sun of love cann't melt. Osm. Thou art a Libertine, and thinkst all Humankind As eager for enjoyments as thy self. Ism. I think you shou'd with such a prize in view, Or else forego your Title of a Man, Strip off those borrow'd Ornaments, and take An Eunuchs garb and rank; by Love the Universal Worlds great Lord, were I as her, I wou'd not give one smile to so much weakness. Osm. She has Commanded, on the forfeit of my Life, Not to presume to name my love again. Ism. She doubts the Consequence— Her Sexes frailty cann't resist the Battery, the next attempt lays all her Beauties prostrate. O Visier, had I but The prospect of thy Joys, to Morrows Sun Shou'd never touch the West, till I had Bath'd, nay wanton'd, in that Sea of Pleasure. Osm. Alas, I dare not raise my thoughts that way, For as I told you, when I urged my love, She chid me into everlasting silence; And on those hard conditions, gave her hand, In token of forgiveness. Ism. Her blest hand; By Heaven it was too mighty earnest, Her heart long since was yours, and the bright Body, next will follow. O I cou'd crush Thee now, with Envy at thy Joys; for though I wish thee happy, I shall die to know Thou art so; not that I love her more than As she is a Woman, the brightest of her kind, Next the Libardian Princess, whose Charms I never yet saw equall'd. Osm. Why Ismael, Because ye have enjoy'd, do you praise a Lady Guilty of all those Passions which a Womans Breast can breed; her Vertue, Senses, Fame, are All made Slaves to Luxury, lewd in her Nature, Gilting from her Cradle, void of Religion and Morality, she knows no Tie of Conscience, nor Affection, rather Than loose what her vile sense calls Pleasure. Murder and Incest wou'd be easy Crimes, Had she but power to act, as sure she Has the will, the Earth wou'd groan to bear her. Ism. I prais'd her not For any thing but Beauty, and what Eye So ever sees it, must allow her that. Osm. I grant her form is Excellent, but sure My Princess, does as much deserve our wonder. Hast thou forgot the time when thou didst play The Orator on her Perfections, and I cou'd scarce be heard, but as thy Echo. Ism. I am not at such odds with my remembrance, To need so strickt a reconcilement. Osm. Give me leave, 'tis the fond Lovers Pleasure, Still to be speaking of the thing they love: I'll pass the Circumstance of War, and lead You to that Scene where first we saw the Princess Retired, according to the Abcan Mode, To pass in Tents the raging Summers heat, Far as she thought, from the rude noise of War, Surrounded with a train of sixty Ladies, All bright as Stars, fit Nymphs for such a Goddess, Her self more than Diana fair, than Venus lovely; Drest with such negligence as left her swelling Snowy Breasts, and her white Arms, all naked To the gazers view; how often have I blest That friendly Planet, by whose officious heat Those dazling Beauties were reveal'd. Ism. You doat and yet want Courage for the joy, Our Sex can never bear themselves too bold, Provided still we lay the stress on love; For when we warmest urge our fierce desire, The self-conceited she mistakes the Cause; Nor nicely weighs the influence of temper, But thinks them all strong Arguments of Passion Which nothing but her Beauty cou'd inspire. Osm. I cannot think she loves me. Ism. Yet when we first surpriz'd her in the Forest, Our Warlike Party struck such terrour to Her Train, that not one Guard, nor Slave, but fled As fast, as their wild fear cou'd carry 'em; She stood alone unmov'd, and to my sense, Her darting looks spake much more love than fear; For at her Feet, when you had laid your Sword, She bad you take it up, and said, she did Not fear that hand wou'd ever ill imploy it. Osm. That minute look't my liberty away; For when my gracious Conqueress saw her self My Prisoner, she blush'd, confest her Quality, And said her Father wou'd not let her long Be such. I told her, I was more her Slave, And in that newness of my love, spoke things Which even thy boldness did condemn; At last I tore my self from this Inchantress, Nor took advantage of the Chance of War, But left her free, and at her own dispose, Which when she saw, she bow'd, and smiling said, She never shou'd forget her Conquerour. Ism. 'Twas well our Party knew her not, The Gallantry had cost you else your head. Osm. After Victory the Peace soon follow'd, And I was sent by Proxy to espouse her; Since that I have not dar'd to speak of love, Nor interrupt the joys our Sovereign gives, With my too fatal Melancholy Fate. Ism. Do you not see she's sullen at her Fortune, And smiles not on the Prince but with constraint; Her Eyes have lost that shining Power, with Which they darted on us in the Forest; She now appears musing, reserv'd, and sad, To me 'tis plain that he has not her heart. Press her again, and if she not avow It's yours, discard me from your Friendship. Osm. I will, for though she banish me for ever, I cannot be more wretched than I am, But O, I must not think on her high joys, Least I grow Giddy, with the distant prospect, And lag beneath, when Love calls on to climb. Enter a Slave. Slave. The Princess Selima allighted at your Tent, Osm. Tell her, I wait upon her instantly, How shall I look upon that injur'd Princess, When cold Civility, is all my treat, Undone by want, and yet have too much Love, But since no ill is such, to us till known, I'll keep the wounding secret from her Ear, And be unhappy to my self alone. [Exit Osm. Ism. This Visier stands betwixt me and the seals, His Death procur'd the Ministry were mine; No way so likely to remove him thence, As his mad doating Passion for the Princess, Which for that reason I incourage in him; To the Protector I have told the secret, Whose jealousy will never let it rest Till he has lodg'd it in bright Homais Breast, From whence her sure revenge will strike such fires, As well continued may the Hero send, To seek in unknown Worlds his Sorrows end. Enter Acmat. Acm. My Lord your'e welcome from the Wars in peace. Ism. Thou blest contriver of my highest joys, How fares my ever Charming Princess? Acm. O much more Beautiful than ever,—this Year has brought a wonderful addition, Each day discloses something new, though to Have seen the perfect Charmer, one wou'd have Thought long since 'twas an accomplish'd work, and Nature cou'd not add another Beauty. Ism. May I not visit her to night. Acm. Where is the Prince of Colchis. Ism. At Dinner with the Princess. Acm. Are we private. Ism. We are. Speak what thou hast to say and do not fear. Acm. My Lord, where Gratitude and Interest join, These we may hope to find fidelity; 'Tis on this Rock my Princess builds her hope, If they succeed the Visiers Seat is yours: But I have news will strike your heart with wonder, She loves your Prince, and much I fear will die If not belov'd again. Ism. Impossible. He knows her not, nor has she ever seen him. Acm. Love enters at the Ears as well as Eyes, His Fame has toucht her mind, his Form her heart, For though you had forsook her Arms for Glory, And left the beauteous Circle unemploy'd; The little God gave new desires, as loath To lose so bright a Vot'ry, and caused her Languish for a Prince unknown; my Lord, to Help the fatal mischief on, made her the Present of his Nephews Picture— By which she so indulg'd her fond desire. That soon her reason fled and left her heart A prey to Passion, nor cou'd her Stars resist it. Ism. Levan indeed by nature is so warm, So true a Lover of the charming Sex, That 'tis the only hint of humane Frailty in him, nor can his temper catch A blaze, from any other fire, though to his Wife, whom Policy made such; he seems To wear the effects of duty more than love. Acm. Therefore this Picture can create a new; Her Eyes have more than magick Art, to light 'em, Cou'd he but see 'em once, the work were done; Move him to view this wonder of her Sex, And raise his pity for her hard confinement; And if you find it proper move the love Which Osman bears his Princess, to Selima. I have dispatcht a Letter, the stile and Character, to her unknown, which brings the Fatal News, by which we have a perfect Spy upon them both; her Jealousy will Never let it rest till she has explor'd the Secret to our wish. Ism. I'll prove the chance, when Dinners done, He comes this way to lead the Princess To her private Lodgings, and there he leaves her To an hours repose; but say, I bring him Forth to view the Castle, the old Protector Will engross the visit, and Homais but Be satisfied in part. Acm. We have drencht him, With an Opiat draught, whose powerful Charms he'll not be able to throw off, till He has paid the Tribute of eight hours sleep; If our propitious Stars but join, there may Be wonders wrought e'er then to make you great, And Homais happy. Ism. To compass both, I'll Run the hazard of Levan's displeasure, And rather crush my Fortune than her hopes. A flourish of Musick, then enter Levan leading Bassima, the Ladies following, they pass over the Stage. Ism. Soft rest wait on your Majesty, Acmat. Withdraw, the Prince will instantly return; Occasion speaks, and we must haste to answer, The glowing Metals ready on the Anvil, And Fate calls on to strike. Enter Levan. Lev. I have a new-born dullness hangs upon me, A mighty heaviness, unknown till now; I fear my Fate is busy for some change, And this the sure Forerunner of the Tempest. Ism. Suppose you try the Princess Arms— Those mighty joys which she can give, Wou'd steal this heavy dullness from your heart, And send it to your Eyes in golden slumbers. Lev. I wou'd have staid—she seem'd averse— And I love nothing by constraint. Ism. How, refuse your Company, by Heaven I do not like the News, a Wife shou'd wake Her self to watch her Husbands slumbers. Lev. Is their such complaisance in Marriage. Ism. In love I'm sure there is—and unless you Will exclude that Passion from it— This and much more attends the Union. Lev. My Lord, you are experienc't in the Art, Describe me such a Woman whose cold Civility makes all her liking. Ism. In those who truly love they meet its joys, With as much eagerness as we can give 'em: Their glowing Lips, their sparkling dying Eyes Speaks rapture all; they grasp us close, and give Their Souls in kisses: words are too gross to Mingle with such Pleasures; the sacred Mystery transcends our sense, and better Sutes our wonder than description. Lev. This is not what I askt. Ism. This is the general Character, nature Has lent that common softness to the Sex; They're Lovers all, or else they are not Woman; Though I must own a Husband may not Always be the object of desire. Lev. What does the Woman then? Ism. She who likes her Lover more, Loaths the inclosure of her Husbands Arms, Coldly receives his Kisses and his Vows, And answers all his eager joys with sighs: But they are sighs of sorrow not of love, And when he urges her unkindness to her, She lays it on the coldness of her temper, Though to her Lover she's at hot as flames; The silly Husband must believe her Ice, Which nothing natural has pow'r to thaw But love, being the original of all; Nothing that's made by love can live without it. Lev. By Hell, thou hast described the Princess As right as if with me thou hadst shar'd her Arms. Ism. Sacred Sir, I must not mean her Majesty. Lev. I wish I cou'd not mean her neither— O Ismael, thou hast rais'd a Hell of doubts, Deep, horrid deep, ne'er to be fathom'd more: But by thy self, prove that she loves another, For 'tis most certain she is cold to me, As Marble Tombs, or Snow on tallest Hills; And I'll renounce at once her Love and Bed, Forsake the ungrateful Partner of my Throne, And give her Beauties up to strictest justice; But for her Minion who so e'er he be, That durst presume to mingle with my joys, And taste uncall'd, the Royal Feast of Kings; Though but in thought he had offended, yet His Guardian Angel shou'd not save his Head; The Minute, that I know the Wretch, he dies. Ism. To Morrows Sun shall bring you further News, Till then, conceal your doubts, and this discovery, And if I mark you not the Traytor plain, May all your indignation fall on me; And let me, meet that death which he deserves. Lev. Be sure thou dost it, for Royal anger Shou'd not be unjustly rais'd, the fatal Blaze burns all, it lightens on, and if not Kindled right, proves worse than lenity. I'le hug no more the Inchantress in my Arms, Nor give her cause to laugh at my Indulgence, Till I have prov'd her Vertue clear, if not, We part for ever. Ism. Suspend these troubled Thoughts, Unbend your Cares, and give your Eyes the leave, To view the only Miracle of Beauty, Your Uncle's Wife, has sure engross'd the Stile; But I'de forgot, an Eunuch waits without, Sent by her Orders; will you please to Admit him? Lev. From Homais! let him Enter. [Ismael goes out, and returns with Acmat. Acm. Long live the Glorious Prince of Colchis, For thus by me my Royal Mistress speaks; May all his Undertakings meet Success, Great as his Merits, equal to her Wishes; May Fortune in his Cause, change her Inconstancy, And lose for him, the Name of fickle Goddess. She wou'd have come her self to bind this Prayer, Had not her Inclinations been debarr'd: But those she never be so blest, to meet your Eyes; Tho Everlasting distance prove her Lot, Dividing what her strong Desires has join'd, She begs you keep this little Picture for her sake. Lev. My Lord, has not the Painter flatter'd her? Ism. Sir, I think he scarce can do her Justice, She has Charms, which Art can never copy. Lev. Then she is sure above all Mortal Frame, Her Eyes have Rays, her Face a Glory thro' The whole, that strikes full at my Heart; Now when I put the Colours to my Lips, My Heart flew at the touch, eager to meet Her Beauties; I'le gaze no more, there's Magick In the Circle. Acm. Sure there's a Sympathy between you, for Thus she bears her, when she sees your Picture, Which drawn at length, almost as Graceful as The Original, is the chief Ornament Of her Apartment, answering Exactly to her waking Curtains. How often have I seen this Lovely Venus, Naked, extended, in the gaudy Bed, Her snowy Breasts all panting with desire, With gazing, melting Eyes, survey your Form, And wish in vain, 't had Life to fill her Arms. Ism. The God of Love forbids you to deceive her. Such Cruelties can never suit the Brave, Courage and Clemency, are equal Vertues; A Hero shou'd extend to all his Mercy, But mostly sure, to those who Love, and Languish for him. Lev. I'le hear no more, y'are Charmers all, And I am to my self the worst deceiver. Acm. Then shall I tell the wretched Lady, You have refus'd her Love, nor dare I urge it more. Lev. Alas! I dye for that, as much as she, But our hard Fate has parted us for ever. Acm. Is this then, what your Majesty returns? Lev. Tell her, her Charms have wondrous Power, And were we both at liberty to choose, This Night shou'd see her mine, but there's a Noble Lord, the Partner of her Bed, Who I can never wrong. Acm. Nor cou'd you, tho' he found you there, 'tis none To take, what cannot fit anothers use; What boots the empty Name, without possession, The love of Nature has Divorc'd him from her, Her Beauty lies neglected by his side, Nor is he other than a Proxy sent, Sent to Espouse, but never Taste The Virgin Fruit, as yet remain untoucht, And if not pluck'd by you, must fall ungather'd. Ism. Are you a Man, and can resist this offer? Refuse her Love, and kill her with disdain; At least, in gratitude, you shou'd provide To make the Charmer easie in her Chains; 'Tis pity, that a Light, which might have cheer'd All Eyes, shou'd be it self condemn'd to darkness. Come, Sir, the Castle is in view— Or will you stay, and dally with a Wife That loaths your Arms, and sports in anothers. Lev. That Thought is Death, and every Place where she Has bin, is Hell to my sick Thoughts. Lead to the Castle, there my Fortune calls me, Be't good or ill, I'le now obey the Summons. Eunuch be gone, and tell her I am coming; But bid the Lovely Princess vail her Charms, In pity to my Fate, lest if they shine. Too bright, they dazle my weak sight for ever. [Ex. Acm. Ism. 'Twere not amiss, for fear this Visit, to Observing Eyes, shou'd seem particular, To give your Orders, that the Princess, when She wakes, attended by the Visier, may Meet us at the Castle. Lev. Then see it done, And yet methinks I wou'd avoid her sight, Till the great Tryal of her Vertue's past. O how unconstantly our Fortune turns, One Hour in Joy, the next with Sorrow mourns. [Exeunt Omnes.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. SCENE I. The Castle of Phasia. Enter Homais alone. Hom. He Sleeps as sound, as if he never were To wake again, now cou'd one ask him, what Avails his Prisons, Spies, and Jealousies, Wou'd he not say, a Woman's Wit Had made them fruitless all— Strickt silence fills the Lodgings, the Musick's placed, The Banquet's ready, and I more so than all, Will he not come, 'tis a long Parly: Methinks on such a Summons, he shou'd grow Fond of a Surrender; but hence be gone These Melancholy Doubts that loads my Thoughts, And turns them into Fears; the Fantoms Cannot stand, the day break off my Eyes; Ay, see they fly before this Lovely Face, [Looks in her Glass. My Hopes glow in my Cheeks and speak my Joy, My Eyes take fire at their own Luster, and All my Charms receive addition from themselves, Pleas'd at their own Perfection. Enter Acmat. Acm. The Prince is coming, he follows hard Upon the Scent, and soon the Royal Hunter Will press on to find your Charms at bay, He seems disgusted at the Princess; You have a Nobler Game to play, Let him not find you Vicious, and his Throne And Bed are surely yours for ever. Hom. What to conceal desire, when every Attom of me trembles with it, I'le strip My Passion naked of such Guile, lay it Undrest, and panting at his feet, then try If all his Temper can resist it. But heark the Sign, the Prince is coming, [Musick flourish. My Love distracts me, where shall I run, That I may gather Strength to stem this Tide Of Joy, shou'd he now take my Senses in Their hurry, the Rage my Passion gives, wou'd Make my Fate more sudden, than severest Disappointments: Coward Heart, dar'st thou not Stand the Enjoyment of thy own Desires; Must I then grant thee time, to Reason with. Thy weakness, be gone, and see thou do not Trifle Moments, more rich than all the Blooming Years thou hast past. [Goes in. Song and Musick, set by Mr. Eccles, and Sung by Mrs. Levercidge. Unguarded lies the wishing Maid, Distrusting not to be betraid; Ready to fall, with all her Charms, A shining Treasure to your Arms. Who hears this Story must believe, No Swain can truer Joy receive. Since to take Love, and give it too, Is all that Love for Hearts can do. Enter Levan and Ismael. Lev. Since I have enter'd this Inchanted Palace, And trod the ground where Homais dwells, Methinks I walk in Clouds, and breath the Air of Love; There's not a Strain the Musick gave, But melted part of my Resolves. Where's the Protector, my sinking Vertue Needs a Prop, it staggers far, and much I Doubt, will never recollect again. Ism. No matter, let the painted Idol fall, A Tomb so rich, as Homais's Arms, Wou'd make one fond of Fate—Look back to Ages Past, and say what Heroe thought not Love his Richest Purchase, that gave their Swords the Keenest edge, and sent them round the Universe, To hunt Applause from the fair Mouth of some Exalted Charmer. Lev. You speak of lawful Loves, were mine but such, I'de gladly lose the Rank of Kings, yet find More Joys than ever circled in a Monarch's Crown; But Incest shocks my Nature, blisters my Tongue, and carries Venome in it—Avant, Be gone, and do not crowd my Thoughts, I'de tear My Reason from its center, e're that shou'd Make it giddy; Divorce my Body from Its Life, rather than wallow in such Mud; And yet the gathering Cloud, looks monstrous black, Shou'd it once burst, 'twou'd surely scatter Fate. Ism. For shame, bely not thus our Sexes Courage, Forgive me, Sir, I'm zealous for your Joys, I'le fetch the Princess's Eyes, and try, if they'l Not make you blush your Cowardise away. [Goes in, and returns with Homais. Lev. By Heav'n, a greater Miracle than Heav'n can show, Not the bright Empress of the Sky Can boast such Majesty, no Artist cou'd Define such Beauty, see how the dazling Form gives on, she cuts the yielding Air, and Fills the space with Glory, Respect shou'd carry Me to Hers, but Admiration here has Fixt my Feet unable to remove. Hom. Where shall I turn my guilty Eyes— O! I cou'd call on Mountains now to sink my Shame, Or hide me in the clefts of untry'd Rocks, Where roaring Billows shou'd outbeat Remembrance. Love which gave Courage, till the Trial came, That led me on to this Extravagance, Proves much more Coward than the Heart he fills, And like false Friends in this Extremity, Thrusts me all Naked on to meet a Foe. Whose sight I have not Courage to abide. [Leans on Ismael, and bolds her Handkerchief to her Face. Lev. Permit me, take this envious Cloud away, That I may gaze on all the Wonders there; O do not close those Beautious Eyes, unless Indeed you think, there's nothing here deserves Their shining. Hom. The Light in yours, Eclipses mine, See they wink, and cannot bear your luster; O, cou'd I blush my Shame away, then I Wou'd say your Charms out-go my Wishes, And I'm undone by too much Excellence. Lev. As Strangers, a Salute is due, were the Protector here, he'd not refuse it. 'Tis Extasie and more—What have I done! Her Heart beats at her Lips, and mine flies up To meet it; see the Roses fade, her swimming Eyes give less'ning Light, and now they dart no more: She faints, by Heav'n, I've caught the Poyson Too, and grow unable to support her. [She sinks down in a Chair, he falls at her Feet. Acm. He's caught, as surely as we Live, Her Eyes have truer Magick, than a Phylter. We'll not intrude into a Monarch's Secrets, The God of Love himself is painted Blind; To teach all other Eyes they shou'd be vail'd Upon his Sacred Misteries. [Shuts the Scene. Ism. Whilst we were gaining of the Castle gates, He shew'd such fits and starts of Noble Temper, So much his Vertue strove to mount desire, That had I not bin there, the Holy Part Had surely Conquer'd. Acm. The Musick speaks, the Princesses approach. [Musick. Ism. Let us withdraw, and leave her to her Fate; The Visier, taught by me, will on the first Fair Minute, tempt her ruin; pity indeed, Such Innocence shou'd fall, but Interest Is a state much unacquainted with remorse. [Ex. omnes. Enter Selima alone. Sel. I have gain'd this place before them; Now if the fatal Letter ben't a Lyar, the Guilty Pair will take advantage of our Absence, and here employ swift time to the Worst Mischief, but shou'd I find it once, (For on surmise I never will condemn him) My Lord and I must part for evermore. They come—here I'le abscond me for the time; In Love all Stratagems are lawful, That serves to show, if what we Love deserves it. [Absconds. Enter the Princess Bassima, led by the Visier. Osm. Yet e're your Majesty removes, Be pleas'd to hear your wretched Lover speak, O do not turn that gracious Form away. There is no Spark of Ill attends my Flame, Refin'd by you, it lives without desire; Permission to explore my Wants, and tell My ungiving Goddess, I adore her, Cruel, discourteous, tho' she be, is the Extent of my Petition. Bass. Do you not know that I am fond of Glory? Am born a Noble, Vertuous Princess, Just Married to a Royal-Husband, Whose Love and yours admit of no compare; His like a lawful Household Flame, design'd For Use, not Mischief; gives moderate Warmth, and wholsome Heat; yours scorns the narrow Bounds, and soars aloft, where e're it touches It Consumes; with sure Destruction seizes All the Fabrick, lays waste the noble Pile, And of a goodly Building, makes an Heap of Ashes. Osm. No, let the Urn be only fill'd with mine; To those incendiary Eyes I'le offer Up their long'd for Sacrifice: No more will I offend your happy Lord, Your Royal Birth—nor Idol Honour— The Count's too large for my low state To Reckon with— This Hour I take me from your Eyes, Never to see 'em more— Nor will I ask the Tribute of your Tears, Tho' so severe a Fate might well deserve it: So true a Love, so Innocent a Flame; A Heart, which scorn'd by you— Disdains its Native Seat— Loaths the Anxiety it finds within, And tempts me beyond Life, to seek a better, Where no remembrance of your Scorn intrudes; For when the sick'ning Soul once takes her flight, Once rests her Wings on that Eternal Night, She bids an Everlasting, long adieu To all the World, and all she valu'd too. Bass. First stay, and hear a Wretch, more such than you, [Going. Methinks thus taught, I grow in love with Fate, And long to share in yours—But I shou'd speak No more, since speaking is a Crime—Go then, And leave me here to weep a Loss, that Will be truly mine. Osm. Rich Tears! What Power lies in those falling drops? They rivit me more fast than thousand Chains, And makes that Fate, which now appear'd so fair, Compar'd with that rich Life which you can give, Horrid, Deform'd, and Shocant; Such as my happier state would most avoid, Fit only to deceive despairing Mortals; Whose bitter Cups are brim full, running o're With the soft flatt'ring Tale, of lasting Rest From Pain, and thought of Pain. Bass. 'Tis I then that should seek that Land of Ease, For I am all which you have nam'd, Wretched, Forlorn, and desperate: O thou Eternal Power, that first made Fate; If I have sin'd, 'twas by your own Decree: Why send you Passions, of Desire and Joy, And then Command those Passions to destroy; When long foreseeing that we can't do so, Doom us Rewards of everlasting Woe? Where's then the kindness to their likeness shown, Cast in a Form, they vainly call their own? Fond Ignorance, for they are all Divine, Exempt from what unhappy Mortals fear; Nor can their Beings fail, like those who wander here: Hence then, thou false receiv'd Belief, be gone, And let us see, we're like our selves alone. Osm. Who gives my Princess Grief? Bass. You, only you. The Earth's united Hatred could not harm Me, equal to your Kindness; it strikes at Innocense and Fame, and lays, my Vertue Levels with the vilest, Makes Marriage an uneasie Bondage, And the Embraces of my Lord, a loathsom Pennance; what wou'd you more, the time is come That I must speak, to make my Ruin certain, Like some Prophetick Priestess, full of the God that rends her, must breath the baleful Oracle, or burst: My crowding Stars just Now appear to sight, and dart upon me With malignant Influence; nor can my Reason stop the dictates of my Heart; They Eccho from my Mouth in sounds of Love, But such a Love as never Woman knew: 'Twas sur'ly given by Fate, I would have said, From Heaven, but that inspires but good, And this is surely none. Osm. The good is all to come, the ill is past; Believe me, Madam, I who feel the Change, The Happy turn, your kind complaint has brought, Tho' I before, thought Life a worthless Rag, A Garment of too vile a price to wear, Wou'd not now change it for a Monarch's state. Bass. You draw too nigh— For fenc't about with Chastity and Glory, Which like a Magick Circle shall enfold me: You must not hope to pass the sacred round, Lest sure Destruction prove our Lot for ever. Osm. One splendid Day o're-rates a scanty Age, Who would not be ten Thousand Years a Wretch, To be one Hour a God!—So great a Blessing As your Love, was never meant a Curse; Or if it were, who would not be for ever Curst, to be but once so blest. Bass. You like a Lover entertain your Fancy; But I have still the fatal Land in view, Where Death of Honour waits on that of Life. Now let us part, lest we should meet on that; See, at your Feet I beg for Life and Fame: Nay, do not interrupt me, I'le not rise, Cou'd I have found Relief from Heaven, or hence, [Pointing to her breast. I had not kneel'd to you; My inauspicious Fate comes fast upon me. You, only you, can stop its headlong Course: I charge you then, by Honour, Glory, Fame, By Love, the mighty God that now torments me, You yield me not, a sinful Slave, to Death; Torn in my Conscience, mangled in my Vertue; But fly from hence, never to see me more; Or should you stay, dare not to meet my Eyes With yours, those tell-tales of your Passion, Lest I break rudely from my Husband's Arms, And fly to Death in yours. Osm. Can that be Death to you, which gives me Life? Now whilst I raise your Beauties from the Ground, I feel such Joys as Life knew not before. O! How can I, in one short moment, Lavish the Treasure of my Life away, At least allow me time for my undoing, For Death or Life were a more equal Choice. Permit me, to attend you to the Prince, And in your Ev'ning Walk I'le wait you With my last Resolves. Bass. See they agree with mine, And then in spight of Love, or Stars, or Fate, We will be guiltless, tho Unfortunate. [Exeunt. Re-enter Selima. Sel. Ah Syren, how she Sings my Lord to ruin; Ah Visier, am I thus repaid, I made Thy Fortune, but I cou'd not make thee Love: But oh my wrongs shou'd not admit Reflection, Revenge and Jealousie are enter'd here, They spread their Sails, and must my Fortunes steer. [Exit. SCENE draws, and discovers Levan and Homais, Ismael and Acmat, in waiting. Lev. Where has this Moments transport led me, To Joys untold, unprov'd, unthought till now? Thou Goddess, who has taught me best to Love, Receive my Thanks, for thy enlightning Power, Nor is there any due to my past Vertue, What Praise to stand, when no Temptation's near? No sooner had this Sun shone with full force, But that it burst the brittle Toy to pieces. Honour and Justice are low sounds, can scarce Be heard, when Love is named— Where's the Protector? I'le wait him on my Knees, And since he has not enjoy'd, urge him by all The Love he bears me, by that he Swore, my Dying Father, when to his Care he gave The Royal Trust, to bless my Youth, With what can never fit his Age. Ism. His Grant will in conjunction meet your Other Stars, for e're swift time has slipt o're Many Hours, you shall have Proof so plain. Of Bassimas's Injustice, that you shall think It none to part with her for ever, And with this brighter Constellation fill her room. Acm. The Princess waits you at the Banquet, When she returns, my Royal Mistress, If she pleases, must attend her, and e're Next rising Phœbus walks his Cirque, Your Joys shall be as Lawful, as they're Great. Hom. Impossible, for I've Embrac'd a God, No Mortal Sence can guess his Excellence, Where the Divine Impress has bin, A pleasing trickling cools through all my Veins, And tempers into Love, what else would be Distraction. A Dance, Performed by Indians. Lev. I minded not the Sports, you only fill My Sight, how cou'd I chuse but doat, Where Gratitude and Merit meet, to Grace Each other; one draws my Heart, the other Charms my Reason. Hom. Shew to the Banquet. Lev. In vain I go, Love has reduced my Senses all to one. And I can feast, on nothing else but you. [Exeunt Omnes.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT IV. SCENE I. The Curtain flies up, to the sound of Flutes, and Hoboys, and discovers the River Phasis, several little gilded Boats, with Musick in them; a walk of Trees, the length of the House; Lights fixed in Chrystal Candelsticks to the Branches; several Persons in the walk, as in Attention; Homais, and Ismael, come forwards to the front; the Camp is supposed to be near the Scene. Song, Set by Mr. Finger, and Sung by Mrs. Hudson. The sweets of Peace succeeds the Toyls of War, Unfading Beauty gilds our Hemisphere. Rewards with her the Conqueror's Toyls, No Joy so great as are her Smiles. No Dart so keen, as from her Eyes are cast, No Breath so sweet, as what with her is lost. Then all to Beauty bend their lowly Knee, And Worship as the Reigning Deity. The Souldier fill'd with Scars, boasts not a part So penetrable as the Warriour's Heart. Ungentle to his Friends, rough to his Foes, Beauty can all his Storms compose. Nor all the Honours of the dusky Field, Compar'd with her, can one rich Moment yield. Then all to Beauty, &amp;c. Grand Chorus. Then Crown her, Crown her, Crown her, straight, Crown this Goddess of our Fate; Adore, Adore, Adoring lye, She'le raise your Souls to Extasy: Come all to Beauty bend their lowly Knee, And worship as the reigning Deity. Ism. Well did I Prophecy, my conquering Goddess, When first you made me Slave to all your Charms; Joyn'd Extasie to Transport, and left me Panting with your Beauties, that they were call'd To better Fortune than my Arms—Not that My Prince can more Adore than I—But He wears Crowns, to make his Love more shining; O, I shall turn my dazled sight away, When I behold him Feasting on your Charms, And burn with Envy, more than he for Love. Hom. Late, when he urged me on the unwelcome Theam, If I was un-enjoy'd by the Protector, I Swore such things as set his doubts aside; Then seeking for what sweets my Lips cou'd give, My eager Arms unknowing prest him close, Forgetful of feign'd Vertue, or Ambition; This rais'd his Longings to their utmost height, That answering all my burning Looks with his, And intermingling fervent Sighs and Kisses, Not vast Imagination can define (Tho' boundless as luxurious Woman's wishes) Those Joys which dye upon my Breath unutterable. Ism. But must your first Adorer have no Favours? Will he not be allow'd sometimes a Taste, Some small remains of former Heavenly Bounty? Methinks you shou'd not sure so far forget Those Moments, Sacred to our Love and me, When close you graspt me, at your new found Joys; An Unbeliever till you prov'd the wonder, And felt the mighty Extasie approach; Then Swore, what ever Royal Lover shou'd Succeed, you never wou'd forget the first Discoverer. Hom. Nor do I, Ismael, for I'le serve your Fortunes, But for my Heart, the Prince is there already; Now in my Arms shou'd I receive another, The load wou'd be unpleasing. Ism. I'll give you leave to fancy I am him; For whilst I press you close, and feel your Charms, No Circumstance can make the joy uneasie. Hom. Oh, did you know the difference, Between a new born Passion, and a former, Nothing remains, but Memory and Wonder; Not the least warmth of kind desire or joy, Nay scarce can we believe, or make that Faith A Miracle, how we cou'd doat, as they reproach we did, How Love so much, that which at present seems unlovely. Ism. When Time has worn the gaudy gilding off, The Sacred Varnish that your liking gives; He then will seem forlorn and stale as me, An Object less for Love than Wonder. Hom. Impossible, he's here, for evermore, Fixt in my Heart immovable, immortally, The Lord of all its changes and desires, Nor can revolving time present my Eyes An Excellence, to tempt their Faith from him, The greatest Excellence. Ism. Madam, you speak, as eager Lovers use: Shew me but one, who tho' inconstant as The rising winds, or flowing Seas, still Swears not Fealty to the reigning Object, Nay fancies he shall surely keep it too, Tho' he has broke ten thousand Vows before; Took new Desires, new Faith, for every Fair, And loath'd as much as ever he had lik'd; 'Tis one great Point of Love, first to impose Upon our own Belief, so self deceiv'd, Are better sitted to deceive another. Enter Acmat. Hom. Wave we this Argument, till time decide it; 'Tis most remote and cross to our Affairs, That should not dally now, but execute; For e're your Stars begin to disappear, There must be Mischief wrought of such a hue, As, tho' black in it self, will brighten me. Acm. The Means is here, wisely you have conceiv'd, [Shews a Vial. Whilst Bassima has Life your Throne will be Unsetled, for tho' the Prince may wish her Death, Her Royal Birth will scarce permit it on Suspicion, and he wou'd cover all his Walks with Justice; but say that he should doom Her after, this makes but surer work. Hom. 'Till ten is all the time we can call ours, And there's but scanty Sand, 'till that Arrives The Opium's force will be expir'd by then, When he awakes, he will be seiz'd with Rage And Jealousy, to find me absent; nay, In the Camp too: What will he say? late, tho' It be, he'll venture here, and much I fear, Will seize his Right, to the Confusion of My hopes for ever. Acm. Nor has the Princess Selima, as yet, The Engine on which all our Mischief turns, Found a propitious Hour, to tell her Wrongs; Tho' now as I departed, your Lover stopt, And ask'd for Princess Homais; uneasily He cast his Eyes, in search of yours, and seems Unentertain'd, 'till he can meet them: Soon as your Charms appear, they'l make their Way, And draw him farther from the Clinging Croud; Then let your Sister lay that stamp, as sends Your Enemies to rest, and makes you rise a Queen. Hom. This asks more time than Fate will now allow; Draw near, my Lord, I would not speak too loud, The Walks of Kings are full of Ears and Eyes, The Princess falls my Victim to Ambition: The Visier to revenge and disappointment, And both are shuffled hence to make your part Of Greatness, I wou'd not shine without you, Could the Old Prince but keep 'em Company, Whil'st Acmat holds the Princess Cup. How easie 'twere to hush a sleeping Man, And send him to his Bed of Rest for ever. Acm. None but your self could have so well contriv'd; It saves a tedious, sure Expostulation, Between Levan and him—To you the shame And Dread of the Reproach, h'as plaid his part too long; 'Twere time he left the Stage to other Actors. Ism. Madam, I understand you well, but Swear First, if I do do this (for much it shocks my Soul, To be my self the Ruffian) Swear, Charmer, Swear by those bright Eyes that light me To my Ruin; thou that can'st damn the Race of Mankind with a Look, and make 'em start to Crimes they most detested—Swear by this Kiss, Which steals my Vertue from me—And turns thy Lover to a murdrous Villain— To bless my longing Arms with their first Joys, And let me find Reward and Heav'n in yours. Hom. I swear, my Love, by this repeated Kiss; But lose no time, an Old Man has Not Blood to spare, besides 'twould make a noise, His Breath but stopt, will do the Work and pass As a Lethargick Fit, to them who knew His Sleep, but not the Cause. Ism. I'le use the Prince's Name for my Admittance. When next you see me, know the Task is done, Your Eyes shall guide the way to him; Light in the Dark, and steel my fainting Arm: But go my Charmer, find your Monarch out, And set your Sisters Task—whilst I prepare for mine. [Exit. Hom. He's in the Walk, and see, he draws this way, My Sister with him too! Nay then the Ice Is broke, and I must venture over. Enter Levan and Selima, attended by a full Court. Lev. Said you, so kind to him, so cold to me; Her Marriage an uneasie Bondage, And my Embrace a loathsom Pennance: This Hour I cut the Gordian Knot asunder; Nor in my Arms will more enfold the Sorceress; O Woman fair, only to outward show. VVell have the Pens of Men and Angels Been employ'd to paint your Snares! Well, have the Saints and Fathers taught us to Beware those Shining Evils, and as we Love our Souls, avoid their Faithless Charms. Hom. You shou'd not sure, for one, condemn us all? For there are Women, who have Truth and Constancy, As bright and lasting as the noblest Male; And 'tis a Miracle to my Belief, How Princess Bassima cou'd break them both to you. Sel. Ay, Madam, there my Wonder meets with yours, How she could wrong a Prince of so much Worth, Were she not hotter than the Flames of Hell, Or the Infernal shee's that yell below; His Youth and Vigour might have quencht her Fever. Hom. But are you sure 'tis true, methinks I would Not willingly believe our Rank held one so bad. Sel. These Ears and Eyes beheld and heard them both; How after she had vomited her Black And Infamous assurances of Hatred To her Lord; he took the Adultress in his Arms: The Serpent, who unhissing, sought to sting him; And having prais'd, and kiss'd her Close, beg'd that This Evening Walk might fix their last Resolves. Lev. And so it shall, but Blood must be the Cement, I'le hear no more, reserve it for her Judges, And plead thou then, that they may find her guilty: My Rage is mounted to that height already, That should I hear it once again Repeated, Without their Aid, I should Condemn and Execute. My Lord, Assemble straight the Council, and say, I Will be instantly amongst them; [To one of the Courtiers, who goes out. Let the Ambassador from Abca, sit Upon the Bench, in Osman's room, he represents Her Father's Person, and shall not say she Fell without his Hearing. Hom. I've heard indeed, The Amorous Visier, e're the Battle past, Surpriz'd the Princess and her Court within A Forest, e're yet the chance of War was cast, Or fate determin'd; which to make the Vanquisht, All know the value of a Prize like that; The Only Daughter of our Monarch Foe; He weigh'd it too, but with the Lover's Reason, Which will have all things sacrific'd to Love, And therefore only made her Heart his Prize: In Gallantry he left her Person free, And promis'd soon to visit her in Abca, There to receive Reward for this important service. Lev. That Article alone will cost his Head: A Royal Prisoner should not be releast, But by a Nation's Voice, they both are doom'd; And if there be but Justice in our Land, He shall not live to see to Morrow's Sun. Sel. His Head, alas! said you, his Head, my Lord? No, let the Curst Adultress fall— The gaudy Bait that tempted his weak Faith, Proud to be made the Royal Eagle's prey; But do not take his Life, let him be banisht From all Eyes but mine: My Arms shall be the Chains to hold him close, That he may never trouble you no more. Lev. All that my Honour will permit, I'le do, 'Till then, prepare to meet the Council: Come Beautious Homais, this Hour is due to Justice; all the rest of Life to love. [Exeunt cum suis, manet Selima.] Sel. As her intents were ill, so be her Fate, I must not pity one that ruines me. But see my Traytor Husband coming here, This then's the Meeting Place, she'll not be Absent long, oh for the Bolts from Jupiter's High Hand, that I might strike their Infamy, And sink the Syren with unerring Thunder. Enter the Visier Osman. Osm. The Princess Homais settled in our Court, If not by Love undone, I shou'd by spight; Than Womans Malice, nothing is so sure: If we with disappointment meet their Charms, Once treat their proffer'd Love, with Cheapness, Or throw the melting Snow-Ball from our Hands, 'Till kindly warmth has turn'd it to a Thaw; Their Indignation falls like hail around us, Nor never cease the Storm, 'till Dearth ensue. This at another time would meet my Care, When Passion reign'd less Mistress of my Reason; Of Honour, and of all, now careless grown, Wounded by Love, no other Power I own; Thus blindly to my own Destruction run, Knowing those Ills, which yet I cannot shun, For with Loves Power, my wretched State's undone. Sel. Ah Traytor, thou art Blind indeed, not to Avoid the Person, thou like me hast injur'd. Osm. My dearest Selima, I saw you not. Sel. Trust me, I credit you in this; But where's the Princess, Traytor? Osm. What Princess, Madam? Sel. O! proper stuff to cheat a Womans Ear, But not a wrong'd one, steel'd like me To both your Ruins. Osm. These are Riddles—What, because you Heard me argue with my self concerning Princess Homais, your Jealousy's reviv'd; I tell you now, as I have often said, That of all Womenkind, she is the last And worst in my Esteem. Sel. O I see well the dark Confusion of thy Soul; How the Blood flushes to your guilty Face, Then sinks again, and leaves pale Fear behind. Dost thou not Curse a Wife's Prerogative, The hard Confinement which that Tie imposes, Where Law and Conscience speaks against Desire? Had I not Evidence too strong to be disprov'd, Your self would witness most against you. Osm. If I betray Surprize, 'tis that and absence, Long as mine, should not have cured Suspicion; When by our Nuptial Vow, I swear, I have Declin'd her Sight, because I wou'd your Jealousie. Sel. In this thou wrongst my Wit as well as Love: O for the Power of Heaven, to search thy Heart, Each guilty Corner of that faithless Breast; I wou'd to sight of all explore thy Fraud, Fix my avenging Hand upon thy baseness, And make thee stand their Object, as thou'rt mine. Osm. One of your Woman's fits, I'le leave you to them, When you're in better temper, I am for you, 'Till then Reason is lost, as well as Innocence. Sel. Take thy way, mine leads to death of Bassima; I go to plead my Wrongs, and her Adultery, Where if the Council find you not, doom both To suffer largely, as your Sins, yet Heaven's High hand, will surely search and Punish. Osm. I thought I heard you name her Majesty. Sel. Yes, Traytor; know I saw and heard thee all, When at the Castle thou didst break my Heart, In seeking hers, dy'd for her guilty Love, Whilst I am lost for thine. Osm. Then you have heard a most unhappy Pair; Much Innocent, and much Unfortunate; And well can tell your self, there's nothing past In wrong of those Embraces due to you. Sel. Traytor, the Treason's level'd at my Heart, Woud'st take me in thy Arms, and wish it her: Kiss me in Thought how much her Kiss exceeds; Absent to Love, tho' present to your sight: O the bare Name, wrackt me to that degree, That I will fly, to make her Judges strike. Osm. Stir not, I charge you, from this fatal place, For she is innocent as Angels are, [Kneels on her Robe. Free from the stain, or wish of Evil: I, only I, am Criminal— Wouldst thou have Vengeance, wreck it on thy Lord, But spare, O spare her inoffending Charms, And take thy Husband's Life. Sel. O Heaven, she comes! See, Gods, the guilty fair; Come to the Adult'rous Meeting with my Lord; My aking Senses wo'not bear the sight: Loose me, I will be gone, unless like Lightning I cou'd blast ye both, turn all her Beauties To that Monstrous Hue, as shou'd Bespeak her Fiend in Form, as well as Mind. [Exit. Enter the Princess Bassima attended. Bass. 'Tis an unusual Gallantry, my Lord, To find a Husband at his Lady's Feet: I fain would count it as a lucky Omen, Wou'd you but aid, as I design, we need Not fear no ill, leave this unhappy Land, And make the Abcan Court your own, My Father shall receive you next his Heart, And what his Kingdom can command, shall be At your dispose. Osm. O Fate, now are thy Ministers at work, That scatter Death, and Mischief round the Globe: Ah Princess, Guiltless as thou art Charming, These are not times for Vertue to succed; See how my Eyes rain Tears, to speak your Wrongs, My Wife, inrag'd with Jealousie, desires your Death, And now is parted to declare in Council, With unthought Aggravations, all the Story of our wretched Loves. Bass. My Destiny was striving hard for Light, And now it breaks upon us. Osm. But, Madam, there remains one means of safety, Whilst yet the Council are in close Debate, We'll get the start of time, and fly to Abca; My Horses, fleet as Wind, will reach that Court Before to Morrow setting Sun. Bass. What me, my Lord? Can you believe so poorly of me, To think that I would sell my Fame for Life, And fly with him, who they declare my Lover? No, were ten thousand Deaths now arm'd against me, Contending which should first present me Fate, I would sustain them all, or more, as far As Life and my Capacity extended, Rather than seek this guilty means of safety. Osm. Then fly without me, I'le procure a Servant, Diligent and faithful to attend you; Take any means, so you preserve your Life, Tho' I no more should prove so blest to see you: I'le to the Port, direct my utmost speed; Levan, both fears and owns the Ottoman Authority; if I ingage the Sultan On our side, you need not doubt the Arbitration. Bass. Still would they say, we were combin'd together, And tho' at present parted, knew to meet again. No, tho' unhappy, I will trust my Fate; She strikes but once, tho' she be ne're so sure, Death is the end, ordain'd for mortal Life; And if it meets us half upon the Road, It saves the labour of the rest. Enter the Prince of Libardion alone. P. of Li. Innocent and Wretched Lovers, I have Much to say, and narrow time to speak: Now in the Walk, thus muffl'd as you see, Unknown, I have attended Homais's steps; My leasure shall explain the rest, for now She prides it as she goes, and fancies all Our Heads beneath; your Majesty must take My Castle as your Refuge; a Chariot Waits not far, but whilst the weighty matter On the Bench, has drawn the Croud to leave the Walk thus empty: Aid me, my Lord, to seize My Wife by force; when she is taken from My Nephew's Eyes, he may to yours do justice. Osm. Ten thousand Blessings load your Age for this, I wait your Highness. [Exeunt P. of L. and Osman. Bass. Life, what art thou, that we are fond to keep Thee; the wretched, who do daily worse than Die, Yet would live worse, so they might still preserve thee? What we shall be, when dead, kills us whilst living: O unseen Destiny! What-e're thou art, Reveal thy self, and kill us not with doubts: [Shrieks within. Hark, they have got the Princess; must I go? How will the World Condemn thee for this flight, And yet I take it with my Husband's Unkle; One deeply wrong'd like me, the Cause is common: Now should I fall 'till time has clear'd my Vertue, My Fame must perish with me: The Standard Which the World condemns, or clears us by, Is not our Inocence, but our Success. Enter the Prince of Libardian. P. of Li. Madam, the Tray'tress is secur'd; Thus far Justice has met success, The Omen's good, be the event the same, And we will write my Honour and your Fame. [Exeunt omnes.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Song, Set by Mr. Finger, and Sung by Mrs. Hudson. The sweets of Peace succeeds the Toyls of War, Unfading Beauty gilds our Hemisphere. Rewards with her the Conqueror's Toyls, No Joy so great as are her Smiles. No Dart so keen, as from her Eyes are cast, No Breath so sweet, as what with her is lost. Then all to Beauty bend their lowly Knee, And Worship as the Reigning Deity. The Souldier fill'd with Scars, boasts not a part So penetrable as the Warriour's Heart. Ungentle to his Friends, rough to his Foes, Beauty can all his Storms compose. Nor all the Honours of the dusky Field, Compar'd with her, can one rich Moment yield. Then all to Beauty, &amp;c. Grand Chorus. Then Crown her, Crown her, Crown her, straight, Crown this Goddess of our Fate; Adore, Adore, Adoring lye, She'le raise your Souls to Extasy: Come all to Beauty bend their lowly Knee, And worship as the reigning Deity.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT V. SCENE I. The Royal Apartment in the Castle of Phasia, Homais is discover'd Bound: Then Enter four Mutes, three with Bow-strings, the other with a Bowl of Poison; they rank themselves in dumb show, on one side the Stage. Then Enter the Prince of Libardian. P. of Li. Our Castle is investing by Levan, Eager and swift, as Lovers to their Joys, He flies to his and my undoing; Yet e're we meet as Foes, And bring our Quarrel to the fatal Field, The Wretch that made us such, shall taste my Justice. See where she lies! O pity, Nature, thou So much should'st Err; so far bestow thy utmost Cost upon the Case, and leave the Building Empty; The lovely Frame exhausted all thy Store, And Beggar'd thee so far, thou could'st not look Within, to aid her Wants. Hence monstrous Forms, And unimagin'd Ills Inhabit there, But Death shall fright them thence: I will not stay to argue with my Wrongs, For fear her Eyes steal my complaints away. Be dumb her Charms, let me be Deaf and Blind, 'Till Fate has plaid the mighty part in hand. Hom. You need not bring your sight to urge my Faults, They stand full blown to my repenting Eyes; Sure there are Hours of Ill that wait us all, And Fate has made us subject to their call; Tho' some are blacker stain'd than others are, There's none can say, their Lives were ever fair: Then on our Guardian Gods be all the fault, Not having watcht our frailty as they ought; Back to themselves, I do retort the Blame, Who carelesly resign our trusted Fame. P. of Li. It is not wise to wrangle thus with whom You are to meet so soon. Behold the fatal Choice! would'st thou be Hours In dying, here is a Draught will give thee Time to ask Heaven pardon for thy Sins, Or if that thou hast fallen beyond its Mercy, And think'st within thy self, 'tis vain to ask it; Then here's the Bow-string will be sudden with you; Dispatch the doubtful Journey thou must take, And send thee to thy Home with smaller Cost; They're Cordials all, which but a Friend like me Cou'd minister to one so foul, so sick To Death, as thou—which shall the Garland wear, For having made the odious Homais fair. Hom. They are indeed rich Cordials all, which if Not urg'd by you, had met my Wishes: Swell'd with the fatal Draught, I shou'd have burst These Bonds, that now confine me close, and at Your Feet, in Flouds of Tears, and oft repeated Wishes for Forgiveness, have left my dying Breath. Now I shall part displeas'd to think that Love, Which oft you swore Proof against any Change, Cou'd not survive one Fault. P. of Li. O Women! exquisite in all that's Ill! Were they but wise to shun, as to excuse Their Faults, how perfect would they be! None that had sinn'd as high as thou— Cou'd once have thought my Justice too severe. But not to leave you matter for Dislike, Your Form I love, tho' I abhor your Faults. Did I once listen to what Passion speaks, Those lovely Eyes wou'd soon perswade my Heart, With all your Guilt, to doat upon their Shrine. Therefore no more, to dally with a Flame That may confound my Honour and my Reason. I will unloose your Bonds, And leave you to your self to chuse your Fate. [Unbinds her, and is going. Hom. O do not stir unless you wou'd forestall The use of these, and make Despair my Doom. Thus on my Knees, in Thanks for my Deliverance, I'll clasp your flying Feet, nor loose my hold, Till you've vouchsafed an Answer to my Prayer. P. of Li. We minutely expect a sharp Assault, Here my Revenge perform'd, I shall have time To argue with Levan of his Injustice, Force him recall that Sentence on his Wife, Who by his fawning Council stands convicted Of Adultery, banisht for ever all Her Husbands Territories, her Eyes put out; Those Lights, which dazled all the gazing Croud; Her Hands, her Nose, her Lips, to be cut off; Then thus exposed, thus branded, thus abused, Sent back with Ignominy to her Father; The Visier too, cramm'd in a Roaring Cannon, Discharg'd in Air, to expiate the Crime Of high-placed Love, my Sister Widow'd, and My self undone, are Ills your Eyes have caus'd: You Bow-string Mutes approach— And since she wo' not, I'll determin for her: Do your Office— Hom. Hold, hold, my Lord. Ah Wretch! thou art undone. Slaves! stay till I require your speed—See, see; He will not have you be so sudden. Give me but leave to speak this once, This only now—and I am dumb for ever. P. of Li. What canst thou urge of weight to recompense This Respite, which I borrow of Revenge. Hom. Nothing, nothing—I but move your Pity: O think, I charge you, by your own bless'd Soul, If thus you sink me now amidst my Sins, What will become of mine? Eternity, that never-ending Time, The Present and the Future all in One, That worse than deadliest Foes could ever think us; 'Tis but the uncharitable Voice of Hell, That wishes Pain, and Misery for ever, To give my Body, which you once thought beauteous, An endless Prey to those affrighting Fiends: This was your Love, and this your kind Revenge. P. of Li. Oh! I've a Sea of Tenderness within me; And thou hast mov'd my Tears by such a Spring, That now they flow to drown Revenge for ever. Hom. My dearest Lord, 'tis more than Safety to Believe, that yet you love me; to see those Falling Tears, to hear those rising Sighs, And know my Soul is precious in your Eyes. O let me live to make amends for this! Or else in Hell the Thoughts of my Ingratitude Will be my strongest Circumstance of Woe. P. of Li. O Homais! say that I should spare thy Life, And thou shouldst fall again—What Hell were then Sufficient for Revenge? Hom. None—None— Kill in my Sins, and may I burn for ever. P. of Li. 'Tis Grief for thy Immortal Part, that holds My Hands; and now I look again upon thee, That beauteous Frame, had it a Soul to suit Such Glory, when fading here, might rise an Ornament to all those shining Courts above. Heark! the Assault begins. [Trumpets, &amp;c. as to an Assault. Remember Homais, that thou bearst thee well, Or else thy Life's my certain Forfeit. Wait on the Princess, bring her Comfort in Her Sorrows, and say, I will expose my Life to serve her. [He leads Homais to the Scene, which opens to her, then closes again; the Prince returns, signs away the Mutes, and Exit. Then a long Alarm, repeated Shouts within, of Long live the Princess Homais. Long live the Prince of Colchis. Then Enter Homais and Acmat, with Officers, Guards, and Soldiers. Hom. Thanks worthy Soldiers, such are noble Sounds, That save at once our Lives and Fame from Ruine. My Lord, by those Designs which Acmat has Delivered, conspired the Fall of both: Now in a Civil War he fain would steep you, Defends the Adulterous Princess and her Minion Against her Godlike Lord, and my Protector: 'Tis to your timely Aid all owe our Safeties; And therefore, that Levan (who by your means I entring here) may praise your Diligence, Haste and secure the Visier from escaping. Offi. Now when the Gates were opened to the Prince, And Acmat had proclaim'd your Interest here, Osman retreated from the Walls in haste, Lowdly exclaimed against your Sacred Name, And with his Sword dividing all our Ranks, Open'd himself a Passage to the Palace, And took the way to Princess Bassima's Apartment. Hom. The Villain helps to shew himself. Secure the Avenues, let none escape, Till the victorious Prince arrives; And for that sawcy peremptory Priest, Who sent my Lord on Errand to the Camp, Secure him close, nor let him eat nor sleep, Till Death shall close his Eyes. He who durst wake His Prince, when I ordain'd him Rest, whilst he Himself has Life, shall never rest. Offi. Your Orders shall be straight obey'd. Hom. You're worth our Royal Care, and soon shall find The Effects of all my Promises to all. Till then my Thanks and Praises shall attend you. [Shout.] Long live the Princess Homais! Hom. Now to your several Posts, and guard the Palace, My own peculiar Guard attend without; After a Moments Conference with Acmat, I do my self intend to meet the Conqueror. Offi. Prosperity attend your Highness. [Exit. Manet Hom. Acm. Acm. I had forgot, the most important News, Relying on a better Star to govern here, Soon as the Princess was arriv'd, thirsty With Flight and Sorrow, I administer'd, According to our Yesternight's Resolves, In her Sherbet, the Cure of all her Ills. Hom. Done like a Princess Minister; now when I visited, I found her fainting; the Poyson and her Fears begin to operate, Nor can she long remain to cross our Hopes. Acm. That done, I made my Interest with the Officer (whose turn it was to guard the Gate) To admit the Prince, and set your Title up. Nor had my Lord escap'd, if in that Minute (Tho' ignorant of what I purposed to him) With a small Train he had not parted hence, Leaving the Visier to command the Castle; Himself, as they report, designs for Ablas, And in the Head of their united Force, Will soon return to try his Fate by Battel. Hom. Therefore, therefore—Whilst he's alive, how dare I think of any Crown but his? he who Has sworn my Death, will surely act it. Do thou make haste to Ismael— 'Tis but a Moment since they are departed, His Youth will soon o'retake their Speed. Tell him my Prayers and Vengeance shall go with him, And charge him strike, to save a thousand Lives, To rid my Heart of its worst Passion, Fear; That nothing may remain but Transport here. [Exeunt omnes. The Scene draws, and discovers the Princess Bassima fainting upon a Couch, the Visier Osman enters to her. Osm. Ah, Madam! We are lost! Betray'd to Ruine! The shameless Homais has undone us all: The Soldiers are revolted on her side, The Prince her Lord departed from the Castle, And ours Victorious now is entring here. Bass. Then Death's the Cure of all, And I am hastning to him. Since last we met I'm grown familiar with him, And we have now contracted such a Friendship, That I am certain nothing can disjoyn us. Osm. Therefore, my Princess, since your Fate and mine Are both so near, and there remains no means To save you; let us employ the time In kind Revenge, and Heavenly Joys. O do not banish me from Earth unblest! Send not your true Adorer hence Unrecompens'd for all his constant Love. Bass. There's none but you cou'd make me hear these Words; But by the eminent Disorder here, I now conjure you, Osman, not to name A Thought that may offend my Glory. Fain I would part at Peace with all, And something more, with you—But this is not the way. Osm. O do not argue thus, my Fair, with him, Who has not time to loose the Doors I've fasten'd All behind; they've five to force, before they Can disturb us; an Age if well employ'd. I count such vast Delight in your Embrace, That shou'd my Life exceed that charming Point, The Extasie would blunt the sharpest Sword, For I could feel no other Death but Joy. Bass. O Honour, Glory, guard me. Osm. They're all but empty, notionary Sounds; The World already does conclude me happy: Will you be more unkind than they? You, who of all the World can only make me blest. Alas! we have not time to lose— Already they wou'd force the Door that leads To this Apartment; your Joys, midst all this Noise and Horror, would prevent another thought. Show now that you have truly lik'd, and in This latest Hour of Life do not oppose A barren Shadow to my Love, unknown To any but our selves. Bass. Destroy me not, my Lord, by these Requests; For I forbid not only Hopes, but Wishes: That Faithfulness I owe my Royal Lord, That Veneration all must pay to Vertue, And a fair Conscience Peace, are more Than Force sufficient to repel your Suit. Then regulate your Flame by mine, and well Consider that a transitory Moment Ought to hold little weight, compared to Everlasting Life. Osm. Inhuman Princess! Bass. You ought not think me so; had I been such, Now in my Husband's Arms I'd flourisht fair, Not in a narrow Corner of the World, Hunted, detested by my greatest Friends, Am yet so far in Love with Misery, To court my Dying, since 'tis by your Love. O you know little! Not to know, 'tis much For Souls so truly wed to Vertue, To ballance with themselves as I have done, Which is the dearest to me, You or Glory. Osm. Did you but love like me, you wou'd by all Those Joys prevent the vulgar Road of Death; Or which is worse, that which will follow your Denial. Bass. I have a War within, which Death Can only conquer: None but my self can tell The wrecking Pains I bear; you see me Dying Eeither by Treason, or that time allotted To me. Cease then this most extravagant Request. Resign, like me, your Wishes and Desires. Scarce can we hear the Words we speak [A Noise at the Scene Door, For the rude Noise and Fury of our Foes. Heark! how they strive to bring us threatned Fate? Ah Heavens! Is this a time to deal for Guilt! When others would repent them of their Sins? VVe who have liv'd till now so void of Crimes, Let us not think it proper to begin 'em. Osm. Heavens! Is it possible you should permit This unexampled Vertue thus to fall! Have you not left one Means to save her? She who deserves a thousand Altars To her Name: Earth is indeed too vile to bear her; Above she'll shine, as in her proper Sphere. Forgive me, charming Excellence, I who Durst think you had a Mortal Part, with rude Unhollow'd Fires approacht such Sanctity, Now full of VVonder am convin'd, your Charms Are much too pure for ought, but his Omnipotence That framed them— Here the Door is forc'd open, Levan and Homais enter, with Officers, Guards, and Soldiers. Lev. Seize the Villain. I will remit of her Inhuman Sentence, Eternal Banishment be all her Doom. Grant her Repentance Heaven, for her dark Sin to me. My Lord, give present Orders to the Soldiers, [To one of the Court, who goes out. That they respect as mine my Uncles Person; My Quarrel never did extend to him. VVhen he returns my Arms are open to him, For I've a weighty Favour to request. Bass. By our unhappy Hymen, I conjure you, Spare Osman's Life; for all his Crime was mine. Osm. Believe her not, such VVhite cou'd know no stain, And 'tis my Curse, that I must speak her Innocent, Even whilst confessing Love was on her Lips, Her Cold, her Candid Virtue dampt the Sound, That but the Eccho only was enjoy'd. Hom. D'e stand unmov'd, before a Rival's Boasting; Go, bear him to immediate Execution, And in that way the Council has decreed. Lev. You've rous'd me up to noble Justice; Be sudden, as Revenge and Hate cou'd wish. Osm. Fare well, sweet Saint, 'till we shall meet above: Now Souldiers, to that Fate which none can shun. [Is taken and carried off.] Bass. Yet call your faithful Visier back; O send, and stop his way to Execution; Pity a most unhappy Bride, who e're She saw your Eyes, receiv'd a Wound from his; Love, has like Fate, its pointed Hour; And irresistible their Force, But made a wretched Victim to the State, VVith all this Languishment, this Love about me? My Royal Father gave me to your Arms; I strove to vanquish this uneasie Passion: Knew all your God-like Virtues, and ador'd them, But yet unaided, could not do you Iustice: To Osman I reveal'd the unhappy Flame, Conjur'd him, as my only cure, to take My Father's Court for ours; his Wife o're heard The fatal Dialect, and now for that he dies: The horrid Canon is discharg'd—I need no more: [A Gun shot off. Ah Heaven receive thee to its Joys. [Swouns in the Ladies arms. Lev. When Beauty pleads, what Rage can keep its height? And I am fram'd, by Nature, full of pity, But rival'd Love there's none should calmly bear. Enter an Officer. Offic. Your Orders, Sir, are punctually obey'd: The Visier went undaunted to his Fate, Nor at the horrid manner was concern'd, But cry'd, 'twas glorious all he underwent For Bassima, then as the Orders ran, Alive we cram'd him in the Fatal Canon, Which in a moment was discharg'd in Air, His Carcass shattering in a thousand pieces. New dread and Horrour fell on all the Crowd, At so unhear'd, and unimagin'd Death. Bass. The Vail of Death spreads o're my darken'd Sight; 'Twas kind who ever dealt this Mischief to me; They're much too exquisite for Nature's Pangs: Can you forgive the Errors of my Fate? I summon all my latest strength, thus low, To ask it of you—Farewell, my Lord—and O believe, Glory was still my darling Virtue. Nor did a Love, strong as my Amorous Stars cou'd give, once tempt me to forsake it: For you, who were too much Divine for me, I beg from Heaven a long and glorious Reign; My Stars shone sullenly upon my Birth; Let 'em not quench my Fame and Life together. [Dies. Lev. How calm she went! Should she be innocent, Eternal Grief and Horrour wou'd surround me: Nor cou'd the Globe afford my fellow Wretch. O Heavens! What state is mine, that I must hope My Wife was false? Hom. Drown all these Melancholy Thoughts in joy; Fortune has made our Victory compleat: The Storm that threaten'd black, is now o're-blown, And the bright shining Sun of Love appears, Unintermixt with any ill presage. Lev. By Heav'n, my Homais, I adore thee strangely; My Soul takes Fire at every glance of thine: So dear thou art to every Corner of me, So true a Mistress of my Thoughts and Person, That I will gaze my Miseries away, And in thy Arms remember naught but thee. [As Levan is Embracing of her, the Prince of Libardian Enters with his Sword drawn, runs at her, and Kills her. Hom. Ah Traytor, Hell-Hound, thou hast done thy worst. P. of L. Thus I've discharg'd the Debt I ow'd; Stretch Acmat's Tortures to their utmost length: Her Minion Ismael whom she sent to take my Life, Is by my Subjects packt to Hell before her. Room, ye Infernal Powers, for three more vile Then ever flam'd below. Hom. Thou Dotard, impotent in all but Mischief, How could'st thou hope, at, such an Age, to keep A Handsome Wife? Thy own, thy Devil will Tell thee 'tis impossible— Thus I dash thee with my gore, And may it scatter unthought Plagues around thee, Curses more numerous than the Ocean's Sand, Much more inveterate than Woman's Malice; And but with never ending time expiring. P. of L. Rail on, thou can'st deceive no more. Hom. O thou too fainly Lover! Canst thou hear him? That Coward Ismael too, who reapt my formost Joys; What an effeminate Troop have I to deal with? I'le meet and sink him in the hottest Lake; Nay, plunge to keep him down—O! I shall Reign A welcome Ghost; the Fiends will hugg my Royal Mischief. Grim Osman and his Princess grace my Train; One sent by Poison, t'other by new Fires. But thou, my Darling Evil, When Fate had nothing else to do but join us; When expectation beat the loudest March, And full blown Joys within an instant of us, 'Tis more than life can bear to be defeated: Be thou a shade, and let us mingle then; There feast at large, what we but tasted here: Thus with my utmost force I'le bear thee with me; Thus strangle thy lov'd Neck, thus die together; But O! a Curse on Fate and my exspiring strength. [Dies. P. of L. O Nephew! How wert thou mis-led, Thy noblest Nature turn'd to vilest Uses, Made Homais's Tool to hew Ambition, Murther, Incest, for her? I dare not tell Thee yet, how much to blame thou art. Enter an Officer. Offi. My Lord, the Princess Selima, dristracted With her Griefs, ranges the fatal Plain, Gathering the smoaking Relicks of her Lord, Which singes, as she grasps them; now on the Horrid Pile, her self had heap'd, I left her Stretcht along, bestowing burning Kisses And Embraces on every fatal piece. P. of L. Remove her, for your Life, with gentlest force, And then, with care, convey her to my Tent: I'me lost amidst this round of Fate, what Crimes Were ours, that you should thus severely blast The Royal Fame. Lev. And here stand I, the cursed Cause of all, As unconcern'd, as tho' the Beauteous pair That fell by me, were still alive; But mighty grief has stopt the passage up; Extreamest detestation of my self, Has left me means to speak no other way but thus. [Falls upon his Sword. P. of L. Add not new Crimes to the unhappy Count, Deluded Prince, this was no way to Expiate For thy faults; live to convince the World, By a more just and glorious Reign, That they were Fates, not yours. Lev. 'Tis past—Behold the Murderer of Bassima, Who took his Uncles Wife, and hug'd the Incest; And wou'd you wish me life? I wretch who gave Her up a Prey to her Avenger, prov'd In effect the Inhuman Butcherer Of Nature's fairest work. P. of L. Her two Extreams, So foul and yet so fair, she cannot paint again. O in a Cause so bad, to lose thee Thus, after all my ardent longings, And mighty strivings to advance your glory; Unwreath'd this Brow to place on yours the Lawrel, Show'd you to Conquer'd Nations, as my boasting Prov'd to be made your glories foil: My dearness to thee, more urges Tears of Grief Than Anger from me. Lev. By all your mighty Wrongs and my undoing, By Deaths inevitable Pangs that now assail me, I thought her un-enjoy'd— And Bassima that Monster she was made: O injur'd Saint, dart from thy Heaven upon me, And grant that Pardon which thou askt of me, To you, my Sins can never think forgiveness, Nor after Incest, cou'd I live to wear it. Beauty, Death's keenest Dart, More fruitful far than any other Fate. By whose Inchantments all my glories fade, And Innocence unwary is betray'd. [Dies. P. of Li. O horrour, horrour, horrour! What Mischief two fair Guilty Eyes have wrought; Let Lovers all look here, and shun the Dotage. To Heaven my dismal Thoughts shall straight be turn'd, And all these said Dissasters truly Mourn'd. [Exeunt omnes,</field>
      <field name="fulltext">EPILOGUE, Spoken by Miss Bradshaw. Our Poet tells me I am very pretty, Have Youth and Innocence to move your pity: A few Years hence perhaps you might be kind, The Tallest Trees bend so the rustling Wind; Then spare me for the good which I may do, Early bespeak me, either Friend or Foe: Nor think those Youthful Joys I have in store, Far distant Promises, unripen'd Oar, Meer Fairy Treasure, which you can't Explore: The Play-House is a Hot-Bed to young Plants, Early supples your Longings and your Wants. Then let your Sun-shine send such lively Heat, May stamp our Poet's work and Nature's too Compleat.</field>
   </doc>
</add>