<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Knowles, James Sheridan, 1784-1862</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Knowles, James Sheridan, 1784-1862</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">knowles james sheridan 1784 1862</field>
      <field name="author_text">Knowles, James Sheridan, 1784-1862</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1850's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V3.0294.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1859</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460694</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Love ; A Play In Five Acts</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Love ; A Play In Five Acts</field>
      <field name="title_facet">love</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">love</field>
      <field name="title_text">Love ; A Play In Five Acts</field>
      <field name="year_display">1859</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1859</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1859</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460694&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460694&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Knowles, James Sheridan, 1784-1862&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;knowles james sheridan 1784 1862&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Love ; A Play In Five Acts&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;love&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1859&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1859&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Knowles, James Sheridan&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1784&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1862&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Love&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Play In Five Acts&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London, New York&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Routledge, Warnes &amp;amp; Routledge&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1859&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3873210-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv30294&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Love&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Play In Five Acts&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 210 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted&lt;lb/&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;lb/&gt;Dedication included with Caius Gracchus.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Love.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Drama.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1840.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 4 Nov 1839.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">LOVE: A Play, IN FIVE ACTS.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">TO JAMES MUSPRATT, ESQ., OF LIVERPOOL. My dear Friend, A few honest words may convey a great deal. This Play is justly and joyfully dedicated to you. With affection and gratitude, Yours, JAMES SHERIDAN KNOWLES. November 1839.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHARACTERS. (AS ORIGINALLY PERFORMED AT COVENT GARDEN IN 1839.) Duke Mr. Cooper. Prince Frederick Mr. Selby. Ulrick Mr. Diddear. Sir Rupert Mr. J. Vining. Sir Otto Mr. Fitzjames. Sir Conrad Mr. Wigan. Huon Mr. Anderson. Nicholas Mr. Ayliffe. Stephen Mr. W. H. Payne. Falconer Mr. Collett. Herald Mr. C. J. Smith. Empress Mrs. Brougham. Countess Miss E. Tree. Catherine Madame Vestris. Christina Miss Lee.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. SCENE I. —A Room in Catherine's House. Enter Christina and Nicholas. Chris. As thou lov'st thine ease, Nicholas, restrain curiosity. It is a steed that runs away with a man, without his knowing it, until it has thrown him. The danger is never found out until the mischief is done. Besides, it is a woman's palfrey, which it befits not a man to ride. What signifies it to thee, who comes into the house, whatsoever be the hour, so it is I that let him in? Nic. Doubtless, Mistress Christina; yet a knock at the door at two o'clock in the morning—and the door opening at that hour, to let a man into the house—and that man a gay young spark—may make a body wonder, though he have no more than the ordinary stock of curiosity. Chris. Propriety, Nicholas, belongs to no one hour out of the twenty-four, more than to any other hour. It was fit that the young spark should come into the house, or I should not have let him in. And now mark what I say to you. Play not the house-dog any more. Do you mind? Let not your watchfulness interfere with your sleep; else, besides your sleep, it may peril your bed and board; but, if thou hearest a knock when thou liest on the weary side of thee, and wakest, draw thy nightcap over thine ears, and turn on the other side; and, so, to sleep again—yea, though it be four o'clock in the morning, good Nicholas! Nic. I shall mind. Chris. Do so, and be wise. Duty, that becomes a busybody, ever turns itself at last out of doors. Hast thou a good place, friend Nicholas? Nic. Not a better in all Germany! Chris. Then take my advice, and keep it. Nic. I will. Chris. Do! [Nicholas goes out.] My mistress will be discovered at last, well as she disguises herself, and plays the man. I wish she had not taken this fancy into her head; it may bring her into trouble. Ha! here she is; returned to her proper self. Who would believe that this was the spark I let into the house at two o'clock in the morning! Enter Catherine. Cath. [Speaking as she enters.] Christina! Chris. Madam! Cath. O, here you are! Was not Nicholas with you just now? Chris. Yes; he is only this moment gone. I have just been giving him a lesson. He saw you when you came home last night. Cath. Hush! Secrets should be dumb to very walls! A chink may change a nation's destinies, And where are walls without one—that have doors? Voice hath a giant's might, not a dwarf's bulk; It passeth where a tiny fly must stop; Conspiracy, that does not lock it out, Fastens the door in vain. Let's talk in whispers, And then with mouth to ear. 'Tis strange, Christina, So long I practise this deceit, and still Pass for the thing I am not—ne'er suspected The thing I am—'mongst those who know me best, too. Yet would that all dissemblers meant as fair! I play the cheat for very honesty, To find a worthy heart out and reward it. Far as the poles asunder are two things, Self-interest and undesigning love; Yet no two things more like, to see them smile. He is a conjurer, Christina, then, Can tell you which is which! Shall I be won Because I'm valued as a money-bag, For that I bring to him who winneth me? No!—Sooner matins, in a cloister, than Marriage, like that, in open church! 'Tis hard To find men out! They are such simple things! Heaven help you! they are mostly bird-catchers, That hold aloof until you're in their nets, And then they are down upon you and you're caged, Nor more your wings your own. I have scarcely slept! Chris. You run great risk, methinks, for doubtful gain. I wonder oft, when thus you play the man, You should escape offence; for men there are, By nature brawlers, and of stalwart limb, Who of their fellows take advantage, when Of slight and stinted frame; and, at the best, You make, in sooth, but a green and osier man! Cath. And there's a little airy, fairy thing, Call'd spirit, which makes equal statures, thews, Ay, between dwarfs and giants, my Christina; Whereof, although a woman, I have a share Which ekes out my dimensions, and defies Those to o'erbear me that o'ertower me. Besides, I have full pockets! That's enough! They call me “The young stranger,” and forbear All question, since I warn'd them 'twas my mood To see the world incognito; which I vouch'd With a free purse, that made the table ring As I cast it down; and startled some to see, As Fortune's loaded horn had leap'd among them. Chris. And think you none suspect your proper sex? Cath. Sure on't; for once suspected, 'twere found out. Chris. How do you hide the woman? Cath. With the man! It was my girlhood's study. Bless thee, child, Good shows beat, hollow, bad realities! When I have dress'd my brows, my upper lip And chin en cavalier, I make a vow, From such a time to such, I'll play the man. And so I am! One quarrell'd with me once— 'Twas when I first began this masquerade— “Look you,” quoth I, “I never quarrel but “To fight, nor fight except to kill; and so “I make my mind up, sir, to die myself; “So spare your carte and tierce.—Set points to hearts, “And at the signal, in!” His fire I quench'd, As water turneth iron cinder-black, In a white heat duck'd sudden into it! Chris. But of your lovers? Cath. Tell me who they are? Alas, to have a rival in one's gown! For 'tis the same thing—'tis your property! The fabric of the sempstress to outdo Heaven's fashioning—your body and your face; A piece of web, a needle and a thread, Give worth to them that lies not in themselves! Yet so it is with dames of noble birth, And how much more, then, with a wretched serf! For, though ten times enfranchised, such I am. But what my betters stoop to, day by day I spurn, Christina, spurn! nor deign to wed, Except the man that loves me for myself! Chris. And such a man, methinks, Sir Rupert seems. Cath. Ah! he is poor! Chris. And what of that? He is proud, And seems as jealous of his poverty Almost as you are. Cath. Yes! He makes no suit. He ever follows me, yet stands aloof; While others lay close siege. Chris. And of his rivals, Prefer you any? Cath. No. Have I not said, When tax'd with paying court to me, the rest— Yea one and all—instead of boasting me, My person, or my mind, for their excuse— Set forth my wealth; and ask if there's a man, Who would not wed a serf, with such a mine? Chris. Sir Rupert sins not thus. Cath. Sir Rupert? No! I bear him hard when I enact the man, Which yet he suffers for the sake of Catherine, My mad-cap cousin, as I call myself. He is jealous of me; eyes me as he might A spaniel like as soon to bite as fawn. He never speaks of me—I mean myself— Unless enforced; and then, to end the theme. “Sir Rupert,” said I to him once, with more Than wont civility—O, could you see What a fire-imp I am when I'm a man— “Sir Rupert,” said I to him once, “methinks “Your friends are sorry judges of good fruit; “And, for an apple, like to choose a crab. “Deal frankly with me. Kin, you know, are kin, “All the world over! now, a hug and kiss, “And boxing faces next! It follows not, “You know, since I am coz to Catherine, “Because she has the toothache, I have one! “So, tell me, fair Sir Rupert,—for, indeed, “Although a spoil'd boy, as 'tis lawful for “A mother's pet to be, I wish you well,— “What think you of my cousin Catherine?” And what was his reply? Beginning, middle, And end, as much as this,—“She is a woman.” But, sooth, the answer came in such a tone, Each single word might pass for a whole book. Chris. I am sure Sir Rupert loves you. He has all The signs of a lover. Cath. What are they? Chris. He sighs. Cath. Sighs! Listen to me! [Drawing a deep sigh.] There, girl! what think you now Of that, for a sigh! and say you I'm in love? I will coin sighs for you, fast as the mint Coins ducats. Shows are all uncertain things, Unless the cheek indeed grows lank and pale— Yet that may be with frequent lack of dinner. So, 'tis 'twixt the heart and appetite it lies! O for a sign that were infallible, And he to show it, whom I would see it on! Chris. Sir Rupert? Cath. What is that to you? Dear girl, Whoe'er it be, I pray that I may love him! The countess flies her hawk to-day. I'll make Essay of mine. Chris. A most strange lady, she! A form of flesh, and heart of ice. Cath. Not so. A heart, Christina, all possess'd of pride— That hath no place for any passion, else. Suitors pursue her, still she yields to none, But, hard requital! pays their love with scorn; That, out of troops, remains at last but one, The Prince of Milan. Chris. Will she ever love? Her heart is scarce the soil to root love's flower! Cath. No telling how love thrives! to what it comes! Whence grows! 'Tis e'en of as mysterious root, As the pine that makes its lodging of the rock: Yet there it lives, a huge tree, flourishing, Where you would think a blade of grass would die! What is love's poison, if it be not hate? Yet in that poison, oft is found love's food. Frowns that are clouds to us, are sun to him! He finds a music in a scornful tongue, That melts him more, than softest melody— Passion perverting all things to its mood, And, spite of nature, matching opposites! But, come, we must attire us for the field. The field!—the field!—Christina, were't to take The field in love!—a fair and honest fight! I wonder, be there one true man on the earth? But if there be, I one true woman know To match him—were he true as native gold. Chris. I think Sir Rupert one. Cath. Sir Rupert!—Umph! If he were rich, and I as poor as he, I'd tell you “yes,” or “no,” within a week. Heaven keep me from the proof!—I should not like To find Sir Rupert out! Come. Let me wed The man that loves me, or else die a maid! [They go out. SCENE II. —An Apartment in the Duke's Castle. The Countess—Huon reading to her. Countess. Give o'er! I hate the poet's argument! 'Tis falsehood—'Tis offence. A noble maid Stoop to a peasant!—Ancestry, sire, dam, Kindred and all, of perfect blood, despised For love! Huon. The peasant, though of humble stock, High nature had ennobled. Countess. What was that? Mean you to justify it? But, go on! Huon. Not to offend. Countess. Offend! No fear of that, I hope, 'twixt thee and me! I pray you, sir, To recollect yourself, and be at ease, And, as I bid you, do. Go on. Huon. Descent, You'll grant, is not alone nobility, Will you not? Never yet was line so long, But it beginning had; and that was found In rarity of nature, giving one Advantage over many—aptitude For arms, for counsel, so superlative As baffled all competitors, and made The many glad to follow him as guide Or safeguard; and with title to endow him, For his high honour or to gain some end Supposed propitious to the general weal, On those who should descend from him entail'd. Not in descent alone, then, lies degree, Which from descent to nature may be traced, Its proper fount! And that, which nature did, You'll grant she may be like to do, again; And in a very peasant, yea, a slave, Enlodge the worth that roots the noble tree. I trust I seem not bold, to argue so. Countess. Sir, when to me it matters what you seem, Make question on't. If you have more to say, Proceed—yet mark you how the poet mocks, Himself, your advocacy; in the sequel His hero is a hind in masquerade! He proves to be a lord! Huon. The poet sinn'd Against himself, in that! He should have known A better trick, who had at hand his own Excelling nature to admonish him, Than the low cunning of the common craft. A hind, his hero, won the lady's love. He had worth enough for that! Her heart was his. Wedlock joins nothing, if it joins not hearts. Marriage was never meant for coats of arms. Heraldry flourishes on metal, silk, Or wood. Examine as you will the blood, No painting on't is there!—As red, as warm, The peasant's as the noble's! Countess. Dost thou know Thou speak'st to me? Huon. 'Tis, therefore, so I speak. Countess. And know'st thy duty to me? Huon. Yes. Countess. And see'st My station, and thine own? Huon. I see my own. Countess. Not mine? Huon. I cannot, for the fair O'ertopping height before. Countess. What height? Huon. Thyself! That towerest 'bove thy station!—Pardon me! O, wouldst thou set thy rank before thyself? Wouldst thou be honour'd for thyself, or that? Rank that excels its wearer, but degrades him. Riches impoverish, that divide respect. O, to be cherish'd for oneself alone! To owe the love that cleaves to us to nought Which fortune's summer—winter—gives or takes! To know that, while we wear the heart and mind, Feature and form, high Heaven endow'd us with, Let the storm pelt us, or fair weather warm, We still are loved! Kings, from their thrones cast down, Have bless'd their fate, that they were valued for Themselves, and not their stations; when some knee, That hardly bow'd to them, before, Has kiss'd the dust before them, stripp'd of all. Countess [confused]. I nothing see that's relative in this, That bears upon the argument. Huon. O, much, Durst but my heart explain. Countess. Hast thou a heart? I thought thou wast a serf; and, as a serf, Hadst thought and will none other than thy lord's; And so no heart—that is, no heart of thine own. But since thou say'st thou hast a heart, 'tis well! Keep it a secret;—let me not suspect What, were it e'en suspicion, were thy death. Sir, did I name a banquet to thee now, Thou lookedst so? Huon. To die, for thee, were such. Countess. Sir! Huon. For his master oft a serf has died, And thought it sweet,—and may not, then, a serf Say for his mistress, it were bliss to die? Countess. Thou art presumptuous—very—so no wonder If I misunderstood thee. Thou'dst do well To be thyself, and nothing more. Huon. Myself— Countess. Why, art thou not a serf? What right hast thou To set thy person off with such a bearing? And move with such a gait?—to give thy brow The set of noble's, and thy tongue his phrase? Thy betters' clothes sit fairer upon thee Than on themselves, and they were made for them. I have no patience with thee!—can't abide thee! There are no bounds to thy ambition, none! How durst thou e'er adventure to bestride The war-horse—sitting him, that people say Thou, not the knight, appear'st his proper load? How durst thou touch the lance, the battle-axe, And wheel the flaming falchion round thy head, As thou wouldst blaze the sun of chivalry?— I know—my father found thy aptitude, And humour'd it, to boast thee off? He may chance To rue it; and no wonder if he should; If others' eyes see that they should not see, Directed by his own. Huon. O, lady— Countess. What? Huon. Heard I aright? Countess. Aright—what heard'st thou, then? I would not think thee so presumptuous, As, through thy pride, to misinterpret me. It were not for thy health!—Yea, for thy life! Beware, sir. It would set my quiet blood, On haste for mischief to thee, rushing through My veins, did I believe—! Thou art not mad; Knowing thy vanity, I aggravate it. Thou know'st 'twere shame, the lowest free-woman That follows in my train should think of thee? Huon. I know it, lady. Countess. That I meant to say, No more. Don't read such books to me again. I would you had not learn'd to read, so well, I had been spared your annotations. For the future, no reply, when I remark. Hear, but don't speak—unless you're told—and then No more than you're ask'd;—what makes the answer up, No syllable beyond. Enter Falconer with Hawk. My falconer! So. An hour I'll fly my hawk. Fal. A noble bird, My lady, knows his bells—is proud of them. Countess. They are no portion of his excellence; It is his own! 'Tis not by them he makes His ample wheel; mounts up, and up, and up, In spiry rings, piercing the firmament, Till he o'ertops his prey; then gives his stoop More fleet and sure than ever arrow sped! How nature fashion'd him for his bold trade! Gave him his stars of eyes to range abroad, His wings of glorious spread to mow the air, And breast of might to use them! I delight To fly my hawk. The hawk's a glorious bird; Obedient—yet a daring, dauntless bird! You may be useful, sir; so wait upon me! [They go out.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. SCENE I. —The Country. On one side a Ruin, on the other a clump of lofty Trees. Enter Prince Frederick and Ulrick. Fred. Now thou hast seen her, tell me what thou think'st. Has she a heart? Ulrick. I think her flesh and blood. Fred. Ay, most sweet flesh, and blood most rich! Ulrick. Then sure She has a heart. Fred. But where is it? None yet Have found it out. Ulrick. You mean a heart to love? Fred. Not such a heart, as well no heart at all! Ulrick. Men tell a mine a hundred fathoms deep, By certain signs that near the surface lie. Are flesh and blood more fallible than clay? Take but her face—There's not a feature on't, But vouches for the mood. Require you more? Her limbs and body give you proof on proof. If these convince you not, essay her voice; 'Tis of the stop befits the melting vein. There's nought without but with her sex consists, Pronouncing her its pattern, passing rich! And can she lack the heart, the want of which Would turn such affluence to poverty? Prove nature but a niggard, after all, Where she should seem to be most bountiful? She has a heart, sir; and a heart to love! Fred. How comes it, then, I plead a bootless suit, And not a boy at wooing? Had I chance, And were the heart, I sought, unoccupied, I never fail'd to gain some footing in it, If not instate myself;—with dames, I own, Of less degree, ay, and on lighter terms Than gift of hand for life. Why fail I here? Ulrick. Hast thou no rival? Fred. None. Ulrick. Thou art sure? Fred. I am. Dishearten'd at a race that hath no goal, Or one that seems to fly them, on approach, My rivals leave the field to me alone. Ulrick. Thou mayst have rivals whom thou know'st not of. Fred. No! I have press'd her father oft, thereon, And learn'd the history, beginning, close Of every siege of wooing; ending each In mortified retreat! Ulrick. You may have rivals Unknown to him. Love joys in mystery; And when you think it countless miles away, Is lurking close at hand. Fred. You are still at fault. She has no favour'd lover—cannot have. The thing is out of chance, impossible! Ulrick. Call nought impossible, till thou hast proved That passion hath essay'd it, and been foil'd; And set this down—nature is nature still, And, thought to swerve, is, at the bottom, true. Thy mistress is not stone, but flesh and blood, Wherein resides the juice of sympathy; Which, more refined in woman than in man, In woman sways measurably stronger! The essence of the sex is that, wherein They make a gift of their sweet forms and souls— The tenderness for some especial one, Who then, 'midst millions, they affect alone. High natures—and, of such, the highest, hers Rarely encounter their affinities, And, till they meet them, all approach repel. This holds with woman, most, if not alone. So, many live unwed, however woo'd; Hers has she found already; so you fail, Or it is yet to find, and lacks in you. Fred. She cannot love. As many streams will go To make one river up, one passion oft Predominant, all others will absorb. Ulrick. What passion, swoln in her, drinks up the rest? Fred. Pride. Ulrick. Of her beauty, or her rank, or what? Fred. Pride of herself! intolerant of all Equality—nor that its bounds alone— Oppressive to the thing that is beneath her. Say that she waives me off, when I advance, She spurns the serf that bows to her, at distance. Suitor and secretary fare alike! I woo for scorn, he for no better serves— Nay, rather worse comes off. Ulrick. Her secretary? Fred. The only one of all his wretched class Her presence brooks; for he is useful to her; Reads with a music, as a lute discoursed; Writes, as a graver the fair letters traced; Translates dark languages—for learning which She has a strange conceit; is wise in rare Philosophy; has mastery, besides, Of all sweet instruments that men essay— The hautboy, viol, lute. Ulrick. A useful man Your highness draws! What kind of thing is he To look upon? Fred. 'Faith, proper, sir, in trunk, Feature, and limb; to envy, though a serf. But, err I not, a most unhappy man, And for his service, weary of his life! Ulrick. O love, a wilful, wayward thing thou art! 'Twere strange! 'twere very strange! Fred. What?—What were strange? What saidst thou now, apostrophizing love? Ulrick. I said it was a wilful, wayward thing, And so it is—fantastic and perverse! Which makes its sport of persons and of seasons, Takes its own way, no matter right or wrong. It is the bee that finds the honey out, Where least you'd dream 'twould seek the nectarous store And 'tis an arrant masquer—this same love— That most outlandish, freakish faces wears, To hide its own! Looks a proud Spaniard now; Now a grave Turk; hot Ethiopian next; And then phlegmatic Englishman; and then Gay Frenchman; by-and-by, Italian, at All things a song; and in another skip, Gruff Dutchman;—still is love behind the masque! It is a hypocrite!—looks every way But that where lie its thoughts!—will openly Frown at the thing it smiles in secret on; Shows most like hate, e'en when it most is love; Would fain convince you it is very rock When it is water! ice when it is fire! Is oft its own dupe, like a thorough cheat; Persuades itself 'tis not the thing it is; Holds up its head, purses its brows, and looks Askant, with scornful lip, hugging itself, Enacting high disdain—till suddenly It falls on its knees, making most piteous suit With hail of tears, and hurricane of sighs, Calling on heaven and earth for witnesses That it is love, true love, nothing but love! Fred. You would not say the lady loves the serf? Ulrick. I would say nothing in particular, Save upon proof. Let me together note The serf and lady; I shall speak to the point, Or, baffled, hold my peace. Fred. To that intent I sent for thee,—for thou art keen of sight To pry into the inmost thoughts of men, And find the proper ends towards which they aim, Howe'er dissembled by assuméd purpose. Ulrick. Your pardon, sir; your father bade me come To warn you, in these times of turbulence, He means to stand aloof and take no part Between the barons and the Empress,—so Your course you know to shape. What company Is this? Fred. The countess flies her hawk to-day, And these are falconers in advance of her. Those nearest us, observe. The lady first, Is a rich serf, supposed love-daughter to The former duke, who left her well endow'd. Those with her are her suitors; but with none She'll mate, believing that her wealth is prized Beyond herself,—nor does she widely err Though some might think her beauty dower enough! There is one who follows her, indeed for love, A man of heart; a gentleman, but poor, Who his revenue spends upon his back; I say he follows her. He woos her not, Through pride, 'tis said, lest he be thought to hunt The dross so much he needs;—whence I esteem His chance the best. Mark! he is last of all. Let us retire a space; there's company Enough without us here. Some minutes yet Before the countess will alight, and then Remains the hill to climb. So bright a day, Methinks, will scarce go by without a frown. [They retire. Enter Catherine, Sir Conrad, Sir Otto, and Sir Rupert. Cath. Spy you my hawk? 'Twas here he struck his bird, And vanish'd from my sight. Sir Otto. Or I mistake, Or from his stoop he rose again and skimm'd The brow of yonder copse. Sir Con. I mark'd not if He soar'd a second time. Cath. Were I a man, And waited on a lady, used to hawk, I'd keep her bird in sight! Sir Rupert, what Say you? Where shall we go and seek my hawk, Or lurks he hereabouts? Sir Rup. I saw him not At all. Cath. Not see my hawk at all? You'll do For a falconer! So! Had I that boy, My hair-brain'd cousin, whom you say you know, And fair Sir Rupert hath such fancy for, He plays the wasp so well—a novel taste! As I can vouch he is indeed no bee, To pay you with his honey for his sting!— Had I that scape-grace with me, he would find My hawk, ere you began to look for it.— How loth these friends are to part company! Now will I scatter them. [Aside.] Who finds my hawk, Deserves to kiss my hand, and he shall do it. [Sir Otto and Sir Conrad run off. What! like you not my wages, sir, you stand Nor make a proffer of your services! Sir Rup. To kiss your hand would be most rich reward, If love's rich gift to him who sought your love; But, if love's gift, to one alone 'twere made, And not to any one! Cath. Love's gift!—What's that? Most thankless proffer made by empty hand! Give me bright diamonds, I shall have bright eyes. When fetch'd desert its value and was poor?— A hundred years ago?—but it was left A legacy, and then they found it out! The world they say is an old churl,—'Tis false. Can you afford to feast, you shall be feasted; You shall not dine at home one day out of three; Nay, you may shut up house, for bed and board. Sir Rup. You are a young ascetic. Cath. Am I so? Well, if I am, 'tis in the family— Witness my cousin, whom you love so well. A young ascetic say you? Sir, I am A young Diogenes in petticoats. I have strings of axioms. Here are more for you. They say that beauty needs not ornament; But sooth she fares the better having it, Although she keeps it in her drawer. Sir Rup. Indeed? Cath. Indeed, and very deed! For I have known Bracelets and rings do miracles, where nature Play'd niggard, and did nothing, or next to it; Beat lotions in improving of the skin, And mend a curve, the surgeon had given up As hopeless. Sir Rup. Nay, you speak in irony. Cath. I speak in truth, speaking in irony; For irony is but a laughing truth, Told of a worthless thing! Will you have more? You shall then. Have you never heard it said, Or never dream'd you such a thing as this— That fortune's children never yet lack'd wit, Virtue, grace, beauty—though it tax'd the owners To find them out? Once an exception chanced, I know not in what year or part of the world, But, while men stared at the anomaly, One parasite, less comet-struck than the rest, Turn'd up a heap of rubbish of all things Good men and wise and men of taste eschew, And found them underneath! Take this along though, The owner never knew their value, for He ne'er had need to go to market with them. Why, what a man you are, Sir Rupert! Fie! What! not a word to say? Let's change the theme then: The argument shall be, that you're in love; The which shall I affirm while you deny. I say you are in love. Come, prove me wrong! Sir Rup. I never argue only for the sake Of argument. Cath. Come, come, you have a tongue! You are in love—I'll prove it by fifty things. And first and foremost, you deny it, sir; A certain sign, with certain accidents— As dulness, moodiness, moroseness, shyness. I'd stake my credit on one single fact Thou bearest out to admiration— A lover is the dullest thing on earth! Who but a lover—or his antipode, A wise man—ever found out that the use Of his tongue was to hold it? Thou must be in love, And for one sovereign reason, after which I'll give no other—thou dost follow me! Sir Rup. Madam, although I may not use my tongue, I do my eyes and ears. Cath. But not your feet. Will you not seek my hawk, and run a chance To kiss my hand—or would it trouble you, In case you found my hawk, to use your lips? But I forget 'tis now your turn to speak, And prove my oaks of arguments are reeds. Have you no word?—or am not I worth one? Or must I take your side, and beat myself? I'll take your side, then. You are not in love, Loving yourself too well! Sir Rup. You wrong me there. Cath. Why, see what pains you take with your person! How You dress! Sir Rup. 'Tis not my vanity, but pride. I am far too poor to put mean habit on. Whose garments wither, shall meet faded smiles Even from the worthy, so example sways. So the plague poverty is loath'd; and shunn'd The luckless wight who wears her fatal spot! Want, but look full; else you may chance to starve— Unless you'll stoop to beg. You force me, lady, To make you my severe confessional. From such prostration never can I rise The thing I was before. Farewell! Cath. [Looks out.] Farewell! What! go not to fetch my hawk, and there He sits upon his quarry, new alit? Or want you earnest of your wages? Well, There, kiss my hand, and go and fetch my hawk, And then be paid in full. Sir Rup. If I could speak— Cath. My hawk were off again, ere you had done; So I would lose his service—thou my thanks! Sir Rup. Nay, I'll secure him straight. [Goes out. Cath. I gave him pain, Though he has borne it with a noble heart! I hope he will not make me weep in turn. Symptoms I feel of something like a shower— A slight one—but it must not fall. They are gone. A noble heart! a very noble heart! Enter Sir Rupert. Sir Rup. I have miss'd the hawk—he has taken wing again. Cath. 'Twas not your fault—you did the best you could. I am not angry. There's my hand for you. Mark'd you which course he took? Then, come along, We'll hunt for him together. Sir Rup. Stop—it lowers! There's shelter here. [Sir Ruppert and Catherine approach the Ruins— Enter the Countess and Huon, with Attendants— Prince Frederick and Ulrick come forward a little, but so as not to be noticed. Countess. [To Sir Rup..] Will there not be a storm? Huon. I am sure there will. Countess. I ask'd not you to speak! When you should speak, It shall be shown—it shall be plain. Be sure It is so, ere you give your counsel, sir. [Huon retires to the group of trees, and leans against one of them. Do you not think there's threatening of a storm? Sir Rup. Yes, lady. When the heavens look troubled thus, Earth can't be long at peace. Fred. The only man She brooketh speech from, with complacency. Observe her, now, when I accost her. Madam, Will't please you take my escort to your coach, At the hill-foot I see attending on you? Countess [haughtily.] The rain is on, sir; I am better here. Sir Otto and Sir Conrad enter in haste. Sir Otto. A storm! a storm! Those pitch-black clouds that speed In wild career to meet the sun, as though In envy of his light to blot him out, Come right against the wind—a token they Bring thunder! Sir Con. Yes; I saw a forkéd flash, And while I held my breath and listen'd, heard The distant clap. [To Sir Otto.] Avoid the trees; their tops With boastful towering, dare the threat'ning bolt To strike them! [Sir Otto and Sir Conrad approach the ruins. Ulrick. Do you note? She does not move— What keeps her there? Is that the scornéd serf, Leans drooping 'gainst the trunk of yonder tree, That lends him treacherous shelter?—Clear as day! Fred. 'Tis dark as night! Ulrick. What?—O, the storm! My lord, I meant not that—your doubts are clearing up. Look at the serf and lady! Cath. [To Sir Rup.] Pray you speak To the Countess—tell her she's in danger, there, Standing so near the trees. Sir Rup. Madam— Cath. Apace The storm comes on! 'Twill soon be overhead— Ay! there's the thunder now, and loud enough. She heard not! Call to her again! She bears That you accost her. Sir Rup. She is fond of you. Cath. Yes; but you mark'd her scorn of Huon, now! Sir Rup. Forgive me, madam! but—I pray you, madam! Come from beneath the trees. It lightens fast— A bold may strike you, madam! Countess. Sir, I hear you. Ulrick. The peril of the serf transfixes her! Her life, be sure, is only part of his! A common act of charity it were, Command him thence; but, conscious of the cause, Stronger than charity, that would prompt the act, And fearing to betray it worse than death; She perils her own life! It is not right To leave her there—go to her—take her thence! Fred. Your pardon, lady, but you must not brave The lightning. Come into the open space: There's shelter, with less chance of penalty, Beneath this time-worn ruin. [Thunder and lightning. Heavens, how near! Almost together came the clap and flash! The trees are all on fire—The serf is struck! [Huon staggers from the tree—the Countess rushes to him, clasping him. Countess. No! no!—O Heaven, he's dead! why would he stand Beneath the tree!—What, Huon!—Speak to me! Show me thou hear'st me! Let me see some signs Of life! Why, Huon! Huon! He is dead! Ulrick. Lady, he is not dead, but only stunn'd. 'Twas but a shock, although a powerful one. His colour comes—You see his eyelids ope— So please you, leave the charge of him to me. Countess. I thank you, sir—am sorry such a load Should burden you. Would some of my attendants Were here, to ease you on't. How dread a thing Is death, when sight on't makes one not oneself! Grows it not lighter, sirs?—Ay, there's the sky. Almost as soon as come, the storm is gone. Pray leave him to himself. 'Twas but a shock; It shames me, such a load should burthen you! Ulrick. As yet, he cannot stand. Countess. Indeed?—O!—ay!— It was a very heavy shock. I have a horror, And always had, of lightning. Do you know It takes away my wits? Did you not feel As I did, Catherine, when they thought the lightning Had kill'd the serf? A dreadful thing is death! And most of all, by lightning! Where is my hawk? O, they had charge to bring him after me, And here they come! Let's meet them, Catherine. [Going, stops and turns to look at Huon. Ulrick. He still grows better, madam. Countess. Who, sir?—O, The serf?—Why, Catherine, where's your hawk? Cath. I have lost him. Countess. I hope the lightning has not struck him. Come: We'll have fair weather yet. Enter two or three Attendants. Go, some of you, Relieve his lordship from his load. [Two of the Attendants take Huon, and lead him off, the Countess watching. Ulrick. You see He is unhurt. Countess. My lord?—I see.—You take Great interest in my serf. The sun is out; My hawk against the field! Come, Catherine. [All go out, except Frederick and Ulrick. Ulrick. You see, my lord; and seeing comprehend. Straight will I to the Duke, and freely tell him A kingdom to a hawk, she loves the serf! [They go out, severally.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. SCENE I. —A Chamber in the Castle. Enter Duke and Ulrick. Duke. She loves the serf? Impossible! Ulrick. My lord, 'Tis true. Duke. It cannot be! Her pride alone Forbids belief. More loftily, my lord, The stateliest of all her ancestors Ne'er wore his rank, than she. Ulrick. She loves the serf. Duke. Give me some reason stronger than averment. Ulrick. Such I have given already. What, my liege But love, such contradiction could beget? When did cold scorn look, speak, and act like love? Woman or man is known by fits and starts, More than by habits, which may be put on; For those so take the judgment off its guard, That inmost thoughts are shown. With care for him, She all forgot herself. Had doubt remain'd, It had vanish'd when assurance of his safety Restored collectedness, which brought with it Slight of the man that, but a moment gone, Seem'd essence of her being. Duke. You are right. 'Tis the solution of the mystery, That, with the progress of the season, comes not Fulfilment of its promises; and no sign Of blight or canker, but the blossom rich As ever knit into the perfect fruit! Her girlhood, longer past than some would own— Put forth a bloom like many another's prime, That often, then, I fancied love would come. When her prime came, nor love along with it, With many a suitor have I sigh'd to think Her breast was ne'er intended lodge for that It seem'd most fitted for, and little dream'd The guest we miss'd, already was within. Ulrick. And never fear'd the serf? Duke. No. Ulrick. Was't not strange? Duke. Not to consider him as I did; creature Made for her pride to vent its mood upon— Her pride insufferable—which alone Seem'd fruit of her capricious womanhood. Ulrick. That foil'd you. Duke. When the serf was but a boy— His mistress then an infant—taken with His forward parts, I put them to the test Of scholarship, which they robustly stood, A hundred-fold repaying cultivation; Nor stopp'd I there; but as he grew to manhood, Gave training to him in those exercises, Wherein our youths of gentle blood indulge— Preludes to feats in peace, and deeds in war— That I might boast a serf supreme in arms; As many a knight unwillingly has own'd, Accepting challenge to make proof of him. Ulrick. What didst propose him for? Duke. Instructor first, Then page and secretary to my child. Ulrick. Instructor, didst thou say? Companion of Her hours of privacy? Her age was then— Duke. Twelve, if I err not.—Yes; twelve times I then Had bless'd the day that gave my daughter birth. Ulrick. Her spring was mellowing into summer then, Young summer; at whose genial glow, the heart Finds wishes and affections shooting up, Known but by name before, and thrills and swells With rapture of the strange and plenteous verdure. She prosper'd with his aid? Duke. O, wondrously. Ulrick. And loved at first her tutor? Duke. Much: but soon A change, which grew with her, the nearer she Approach'd to womanhood. 'Twas distance first; Then sullenness; then scorn, which she gave sway to Incontinent, and chiefly of those feats Of high address wherein he match'd the noble, And which it seem'd her pastime he should practise For recompense of aggravated spite. Ulrick. Which he endured for love! Duke. He dies! That ends it. Ulrick. Yes; confirming it, Perhaps. Beware, sir, of a tragedy So deep! Her scorn may melt at it, and help Her tears to keep them flowing on until She weeps her life away. You must not play With a first passion, once it has taken root. For it strikes deep—to the foundations even Of the heart—entwining with the fibres there, Of life itself, that, pluck the other up, These, often, come along. Duke. He shall to exile, Thousands of miles away, 'midst snows and deserts! Ulrick. So may you tempt her, sir, with pity for him, To turn a pilgrim—take up staff and scrip, And follow him. She scorns him for the scorn Which others' eyes behold his station with. Removed from their regards, her rank unknown, For her rich charms were his embrace, a lodge She'd change your palace for. Duke. Impossible! Ulrick. O, never did achievement rival Love's, For daring enterprise and execution. It will do miracles; attempt such things As make ambition, fiery as it is, Dull plodding tameness, in comparison. Talk of the miser's passion for his store— 'Tis milk and water to the lover's, which Defies the mines of earth and caves of ocean To match its treasure! Talk of height, breadth, depth— There is no measure for the lover's passion, No bounds to what 'twill do! Duke. Advise me, then, What's best. Ulrick. Induce the serf to marry. That Were cure, in the end, for your fair daughter's passion; Whose wound were his desertion, so resentment Would blunt the edge of disappointed love. For, doubt not, though she ne'er espouses him, She trusts so far to keep him to herself, As that he ne'er shall pillow with another. Duke. 'Tis done. I have a bride for him, at once. One of his class, enfranchised by the will Of my cousin, who preceded me; indeed, Supposed love-daughter to him, and endow'd With wealth of his, that makes her coveted As fitting mate, by men of gentle blood. Her humour 'tis to keep her freedom still; But to my wish, as soon as known, she'll bend, Aware I may encoil her in the mesh My cousin's love or bounty freed her from. But say I wed the serf to Catherine, What profit then? My child may still persist To keep her virgin state. Ulrick. I should commit To Heaven the election of her husband;—let The tournament determine who shall wed her. Duke. Thereto I have made provision in my will; And further, sir, as I am due to death Now many a year, and momentarily Expect his summons, pray you keep by me The little space I have to tarry yet; For on your wisdom I have all reliance. Your prince, I know, will not gainsay me, here. And when it pleaseth Heaven to leave my body Without the breath, it has inherited So long; no minute lose, but take occasion Of the fresh flow of sorrow in my child— When her young heart is soften'd, and will mould Itself unto his will, who is no more— To break to her, on this particular head, My dying testament. Ulrick. I shall remember. Duke. So please you, I shall join you with the Empress, Liege lady and good cousin to my child, Executor. Ulrick. I shall discharge the trust. Duke. My lord, send Huon to me. Question not, Advise me not. He marries, or he dies. [Ulrick goes out. Life spent to waste! My pride become my shame! For this I rear'd her—rear'd to tow'ring thoughts. A gasp of being only left, and that To sigh that being has been spent in vain For her, last shoot of an illustrious tree! I loved my serf, was vain of him, and made My vanity to smile through his deserts; And now, their light is cloud to all my hopes. Through mine own pride my high aspirings fall. They shall not fall! Good-bye to ruth! He dares To love my child—to covet her, I grudged Surrender of to those could boast estate Equal to mine! Born at my very foot, How durst he lift his eyes so giddy high! He comes. I see! The passion never yet I dream'd of, stares upon me, in his look, His air, his gait. 'Tis dead—or he must die! Enter Huon. Huon! Huon. My lord? Duke. I have been thinking of thee. Huon. My lord is ever good. Duke. I have a notion 'Twould profit thee to marry. Huon. Marry! Duke. Yes. Huon. I first must love. Duke. And hast thou never loved? Why art thou silent? Wherefore holds thy tongue Its peace, and not thy cheek? Huon. My cheek! Duke. It talks! A flush pass'd o'er it, as I spoke to thee; And now it talks again—and on the ground Thou cast'st thine eye. “Thou first must love”—My friend, Thou art in love already! Art thou not? Art thou not, Huon?—Never mind, but keep Thy secret.—I have fix'd that thou shalt marry. Huon. My lord— Duke. [Interrupting him.] I know it will advantage thee, And I have look'd around my court to find A partner for thee, and have lit on one. Huon [more earnestly]. My lord— Duke. [Interrupting him again.] She has beauty, Huon, she has wealth; And that which qualifies her better still— As of unequal matches discords grow— She's of thy own class, Huon, she is a serf. Huon [impetuously]. My lord— Duke. [Interrupting, indignantly.] My serf!—How now?—Wouldst thou rebel? Huon. Rebel, my lord! Duke. I trust I was deceived! I did not see defiance in thine eye, And hear it on thy tongue? Thou wouldst not dare So much as harbour wish to thwart thy lord, Much less intent? Thou know'st him!—know'st thyself! Thou mayst have scruples—That thou canst not help; But thou canst help indulging them, in the face Of thy lord's will. And so, as 'tis my will Thou marry straight, and I have found thy match, I'll draw a paper up, where thou shalt make The proffer of thy hand to Catherine, And thou shalt sign it, Huon. [Writes. Huon. That I were dead! O, what is death, compared to slavery! Brutes may bear bondage—They were made for it, When Heaven set man above them; but no mark, Definite and indelible, it put Upon one man to mark him from another, That he should live his slave! O heavy curse! To have thought, reason, judgment, feelings, tastes, Passions, and conscience, like another man, And not have equal liberty to use them, But call his mood their master! Why was I born With passion to be free—with faculties To use enlargement—with desires that cleave To high achievements—and with sympathies Attracting me to objects fair and noble,— And, yet, with power over myself, as little, As any beast of burden? Why should I live? There are of brutes themselves that will not tame So high in them is nature;—whom, the spur And lash, instead of curbing, only chafe Into prouder mettle;—that will let you kill them, Ere they will suffer you to master them. I am a man, and live! Duke. Here, Huon, sign, And Catherine is your wife. Huon. I will not sign. Duke. How now, my serf! Huon. My lord, I am a man; And, as a man, owe duty, higher far Than that I owe to thee, which Heaven expects That I discharge. Didst thou command me murder, Steal, commit perjury, or even lie, Should I do it, though thy serf? No! To espouse her, Not loving her, were murder of her peace. I will not sign for that! With like default, To compass mastery of her effects, Were robbery. I will not sign for that! To swear, what I must swear, to make her mine, Were perjury at the very altar. Therefore I will not sign! To put forth plea of love, Which not a touch of love bears witness to, Were uttering a lie. And so, my lord, I will not sign at all!—O, good my liege, My lord, my master, ask me not to sign! My sweat, my blood, use without sparing; but Leave me my heart—a miserable one Although it be! Coerce me not in that, To make me do the thing my heart abhors! I beg no more! [The Duke draws his sword, and resolutely approaches Huon. At the same minute the Countess enters, unperceived, and stops short. Duke. Huon, I love thee, And would not do thee harm, unless compell'd. Thou shouldst not play with me, and shalt not. Take, Therefore, thy choice—death, or the paper. Huon. Death! Duke. Thou makest thy mind up quickly, in a strait. Huon. I do not wish to live. [Opens his vest, takes the point of the Duke's sword, and places it opposite his heart. Set here thy point; 'Tis right against my heart! Press firm and straight; The more, the kinder! [A pause. Duke. As thou wishest death, I will not kill thee for thy disobedience. An hour I grant for calm reflection. Use it. If, on the lapse of that brief space, I find The page without addition, thou mayst learn That even slavery hath its degrees, Which make it sometimes sweet! Our felons throng The galleys; but 'tis hard, or we shall find A bench and oar for thee! [He goes out. Huon. My lord, come back! My lord! What now my mind, be sure 'twill be At the end of the hour! of the day! of my life!—My lord! He does not hear, or will not. Most sweet cause Of most insufferable misery, Wouldst thou not weep at this? Couldst thou look on, And keep pride sitting in thy woman's eye— The proper throne of pity—which for me, The melting queen has yet refused to fill, But to a stern usurper all abandon'd!— Wouldst thou not weep? Or would my name alone— My sole condition set 'gainst all myself; The vivid thoughts, the feelings sensitive, The quick affections, passions of a man, Despite his misery of birthright; flesh, Warm, warm; of as high vitality as though His lot had been an heirdom to a throne— Would that, prevailing 'gainst such odds as these, Prevent thee? Yes! Thou wouldst not weep for me. O, knew I what would make thee! Would my corpse? Then to thy father! own my passion for thee, Tell him his serf aspires to love his daughter, Boasts of it, though he sends him to the galleys, Will glory in it, chain'd beside the felon, Ay, with the tasker's whip whirling above him, Reiterate it, when he threatens me, And when again he threatens, justify it, On the broad rights of common human nature, Till with his own hand he transfixes me! [Following the Duke. Countess. [Interposing.] Stop, Huon!—What's the matter? Huon. Huon—Huon! Didst thou say Huon—and with gentleness? Madam—my mistress—I am your slave!—I am nothing But the poor serf! Countess. See if that door is free From list'ners. Huon. [Going to the door.] There is no one here. Countess. Come in, And shut it again. Huon. 'Tis shut. Countess. Now, what's the matter With my father and you? Huon. He bade me sign that paper, And I refused. Countess. What is it? Let me see it. Huon. [Hands the paper, and watches the Countess while she reads.] How her eye fastens on the writing—seems To grasp it, as her hand the paper! What! Did she start? She did! O, wherefore?—What is this? Her sweet face, that just now was all a calm, Shows signs of brooding tempest! Yes, 'tis on— Lowers on her brow, and flashes on her cheek, Like cloud and lightning. How her bosom heaves! What makes it heave? She has let the paper drop, Yet there she stands as though she held it yet! And where, but now, all was astir—now, all Again is stillness! Dare I speak to her? She is not like to faint—no—no—she breathes! Her haughty spirit wakes in her again, Towering, alas! as ne'er it did before. Countess. [After a violent struggle, giving way.] Huon, I die! Huon. Heavens!—Mercy! Countess. [Bursting into tears.] It is over. Do not speak to me! Let my tears flow on! Huon. Flow they for me? Countess. I told you not to speak. Huon. Sweet Heaven! your voice is tears! Your looks are tears; your air, your motions, all Are tears! floods! floods! to those that course your cheeks, And fall more bright than diamonds on the hands Which now I clasp to thee in supplication, That thou wilt deign this once vouchsafe me audience, To give my fatal passion vent before thee— For years pent up within my wretched breast— And then I'm mute for ever! Countess. Huon, peace— I know thou lov'st me! Huon. Thou know'st it, dost thou? And sayest it!—and mildly sayest it! Not with a tone of scorn, not with a threat, Nor accent yet of cold indifference For the poor serf, who, body, soul, and all, Not being worth a tithe of thee, yet dares To love thee!—dares to wish for thee!—yes, wish, Although he knows thee out of reach of him, As the sun!—as the stars—a million, million times Beyond the sun! The poor despiséd serf, Despiséd of himself—of thee—of every one— Thou see'st he loves thee, and thou deign'st to say it! Say it with pity—with most tender pity! Behold'st him kneeling at thy feet, and know'st The passion throws him there, and suffer'st him To stay there!—Let him die there! Let him die At thy feet! [Falls at her feet. Countess. Rise, Huon!—Huon!—Hear'st thou me? And dost thou not obey me? Wilt thou not? Listen to me!—Lo, I entreat thee, Huon, By the love thou bear'st me, rise! Huon. [Rising to his knee.] Again! “By the love “Thou bear'st me, Huon!” And thy accents did sound Like those of one that love repaid with love! Thou start'st at that! and terror, all at once, Looks from the eyes, whence something look'd before I'd give the vision of my own to see there But for one other moment, so it set My soul a-blaze with hope!—Can I believe it, My arm encircles thee! Countess. [With forced dignity.] Remove it. Huon. Ah! Thou changest!—Yes!—Thou art returning fast To what thou wast before. Countess. No, Huon—but Obey me—kneel no longer at my feet, But rise. [He rises.] It pleaseth me thou dost my will. Huon, wilt do my will? Huon. Wilt do thy will? It is the nature of my blood as much As its colour—current! In thy every mood, I will obey thee, lady. Countess. Promise me Thou'lt do the thing I bid thee. Huon. What is it? Countess. Promise me first, and then I'll name it to thee. Huon, wilt do the thing I wish? Huon. I will. Countess. But swear thou'lt do it. Huon. Yes. What shall I swear by? Countess. Thy love for me! Huon. Then, by my love for thee, I'll do the thing thou bidd'st me. Countess. Sign the paper!— Thou art about to speak—but don't—don't, Huon, As thou wouldst not offend me; as 'twould grieve me— I won't say, anger me—that thou couldst offend me. Listen! I'll bear that thou shouldst love me, if Thou signest—else command thee ever from me. Wilt thou not? Speak not—give me acts, not words. Or sign it, or begone! Huon. I'll keep my word, And so do both. [Takes paper to table, and peruses it. Enter Attendant. Countess. [To Attendant.] Is Catherine in the castle If not, go to her house, and bring her hither. Attendant. She is in the castle. Now she enter'd it. Countess. Conduct her to my chamber. Stay. My chaplain— Tell him, and do it straight, to wait me in The chapel. Tarry. See that the chapel else Is clear—Make sure of it. That ascertain'd, Take post at the door, and mind that no one enter, Except the serf and the two ladies that Shall follow him. I shall be one. A mouse Besides, thou diest! [Attendant goes out. Huon. [Signs paper.] It is sign'd—Farewell! [Going. Countess. Stay!—To the full thou must redeem thy pledge. Unless thou marriest, it is not sign'd; The paper is but air, the ink but water, Without fulfilling of the written deed; And thou but jugglest with me, shamefully, Saying thou lovest me, and for thy oath Staking thy love, and leaving all undone As thou hadst sworn by nothing. Thou art bound To marry Catherine, failing which to do, Thou dost not love me,—thou art not a man. Huon. I am indifferent to what I do. All things of earth are now the same to me; Good, bad, love, hate, wrong, kindness, life, or death. What hour you please, I'll marry Catherine. [Going. Countess. Now! [Stopping him. This very moment! She will meet thee in The chapel, whither thou must straight repair. Thou wilt? Huon. I will. Countess. The chaplain thou wilt find Expecting thee—and, if he be not come Already, still he will be sure to come. Thou wilt not juggle with me? Huon. No. Countess. Thou darest not— I mean, thou darest not, as thou lovest me. Huon. I'll keep the oath, and then, farewell for ever! [Aside.—Goes out. Countess. 'Tis done! [Sinks into a chair. Enter Duke. Duke. Where's Huon? Countess. Gone to do thy will. Duke. Who work'd this miracle? I never dream'd He would conform to it! Who work'd it? Countess. I. Duke. Thou? Countess. [Giving him the paper.] There. Duke. My child! Thou art thy father's child, My proud child still! Where is he? Countess. In the chapel, By this. The chaplain waits upon him there. Catherine is in my room, expecting me. So please you, sir, since I have help'd the match Thus far, I'll e'en o'erlook the ceremony. Duke. Do so. My barque no more is fit for sea; A ripple threatens it with foundering, Almost 'tis founder'd now. Did Huon tell thee How he withstood me? Countess. All is known to me. But pray you, for the sake of Catherine, Grant him his freedom. 'Tis not meet her husband Should drag the chain, hath been unloosed from her. Duke. This document accomplishes your wish, E'en now prepared to win him to my purpose. I give it freely, for I love the boy; Ay, now entirely love him! See him married; And may he plight a happy, happy troth To her he weds! My child, I am failing fast. 'Tis time—don't heed!—go to the chapel—and My blessing on the errand takes thee thither. Enter Attendant. Ha!—you are come in time, sir! I shall need Your help to my chamber. Tell the boy, I bless him! Come hither, bless thee, too! And bless the work Thou goest to do! While I remember it, Regard Count Ulrick as thy father's friend, One of his household now, with sanction of The Prince of Milan. I am very feeble! Must to my chamber! Countess. [Rushing towards him, and kneeling.] Bless me again! my father! Duke. Again, my child?—Again! [Blessing her. Heaven bless thee! It is wiser—better knows Thy good—can better help thee to't—ay! Better than thy father! May it bless thee, then, And be its will, before thy father's, done! [Goes out. Countess. Now, fail not Catherine, and the die is cast! [Goes out. SCENE II. —The Corridor of the Castle. Enter Sir Conrad. Sir Con. What calls the chaplain to his sacred post, And why this privacy? About to pass The porch, I was admonish'd 'twas forbid To all to enter! 'Tis no day of fast, No hour of customary rites! 'Tis nought To me. I only wonder at its strangeness. Sir Rup. [Entering.] Where is the Prince of Milan? Sir Con. In the courtyard— Unless departed thence this moment. Sir Rup. Find him, And bring him to the chamber of the Duke. If on your way you meet the Duke's physician, In search of whom I go, he, too, is summon'd, And tell him so. Sir Con. Why, what's the matter? Sir Rup. Woe! The Duke!—the Duke!—No question, but away! SCENE III. —Chamber of the Countess. Enter Christina and the Countess's Maid. Chris. My mistress marry Huon? Maid. Even so! Now hand in hand with him before the priest; Unless the knot be tied already—said The blessing and amen. Chris. No bridemaid? Maid. Yes, My lady. Chris. What! the Countess! bridemaid she To Catherine that was before a serf! Yet she was ever fond of Catherine. Maid. You should have seen them both as forth they went, Like two sweet sisters for the altar veil'd. Chris. A sudden marriage this! Maid. And lonely, too; None but the principals admitted—friends Nor attendants! Chris. It is strange! Well. Huon gets A wealthy wife—a freewoman, to boot; And, sooth to say, a worthy husband, she— Ay, were she better still—for many a prince Looks not his rank so well as Huon would, Were he one. Softly—they return—yes. Maid. No; My mistress comes alone. How slow she moves! Enter the Countess faint; her Maid runs to support her. Countess. Help to unveil me, girl. I cannot lift My hand to my head—and I want air! Remove My veil. There! Now I breathe!—A minute only, And all the world seems changed. Is this my room? Art thou my waiting-maid?—Am I myself? Where is my father? Maid. In his chamber, lady. He is complaining. Countess. He is very old. His life spun out into a very film. I did not gainsay him! Thank Heaven for that! I would that I could go to him, but sooth My limbs have done their best to bring me hither. I am next to dead; almost dissolved to nothing. Is that Christina? Girl, what do you here? Home with all haste; your mistress there before you Waits your assistance with most instant need. Chris. It is all wonder. Countess. Art thou gone? Chris. I am! [Curtsies and goes out. Count Ulrick enters. Ulrick. Madam! Countess. Count Ulrick, is it you? I am glad To see you, sir; my father told me, or I dreamt it, he design'd to take you, sir, Into his service. If 'tis so, I'm glad of it. Ulrick. I grieve to think my office was a brief one! Countess. Your office was a brief one!—Speak!—alas! When silence is a substitute for speech, The heart must be o'er full of joy or pain! Enough. I read your errand-in your looks— I am an orphan. Ulrick. Madam, 'twas a debt Long due to nature. Countess. Still, sir, we must grieve To see it paid. At what a time to leave me! I cannot pay him half his due of sorrow. My heart is spent—benumb'd! this shaft of Fate Lights on a corpse!—a corpse! Alas, my father! [Weeps. [A pause—Enter Attendant, hastily. Atten. Madam! Ulrick. Keep silence! Do not interrupt The sacred flow of sorrow for the dead. Countess. No; let him speak; there's matter in his looks. Atten. The banquet, as you order'd, is prepared, But neither bride nor bridegroom can be found. Countess. You mean the bride cannot be found! Atten. Nor yet The bridegroom. Countess. Search for him, and you will find him— Must find him! [Attendant goes out. What a cross! at what a time! When all my thoughts should be with him that's gone! My father! I adored my father, sir: Indeed, I did! Ulrick. Then let me now fulfil His last behest, whereof the substance this, In full recorded here—which he enjoin'd You should be instantly possess'd of—proof Of his most fatherly regard and care. Of those who seek your hand you must make choice Of one to share the labours of the dukedom, Or else abide the issue of the lists— Your suitors summon'd to a tournament— When he who rests the victor wins your hand. Countess. I am content! I'll do my father's will, And bide the issue of the tournament, Or choose myself the man shall take my hand. Ulrick. Jointly the Empress and myself are named Executors, to give the will effect. Countess. It was not needed. It had been respected Without o'erlooking, how much less enforcement! My brain and heart are here and there! I haven't The use of them. Stop! [Thinks] Some one told me now Of something—What was it? Ulrick. One said the serf— Countess. Call him that name again!—Whom speak'st thou of? Huon? Atten. [Entering.] This letter is from Huon, madam. Mounted upon a steed, your father's gift, He threw it me, and fled. Countess. [Reading.] “Eternally “Farewell—Your will is done—I use my freedom. “Fortune my mistress hence—the richest boon “She can award me, death!—Once more, farewell!” O rashness most perverse and ruinous! Let them pursue him; and provide them with The fleetest of the stud, and gold beside, For new relays. If they o'ertake him—if?— They must!—'Tis an affair of life or death! They must not quit him, but return with him— Atten. The bride— Countess. No heed of her. Bring Huon back By fair means or by foul—persuasion vain, Let them resort to force—but not to harm A hair of his head. So be their numbers such As makes resistance idle. They are sure To track him, so they lose not time—and see They do not! If they waste a moment only. They answer for't. Stay, sir; a purse of gold To every one of them—of gold, you mark— So that they bring him back; and one for you In like event. A minute hence, observe, I look into the court-yard, and expect To see them in their saddles, and away! Upon their lives I charge them bring him back! [They go out.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT IV. SCENE I. —The Garden of the Castle. Enter Sir Rupert and Sir Conrad. Sir Rup. Time is the same. 'Tis our condition's changed. The hours hang weary heavy on our hands, We scarce could catch when Catherine was here; They went so fleetly by us. Then the death Of the Duke hath left a blank, which, while he lived, Light offices, with grateful tasks fill'd up, And kept our spirits from flagging. Sir Con. Eventful day, The day he died! Eventful day to us! Our Catherine married Huon then, and fled; And Huon fled, avoiding Catherine; Nor since of either tidings—though for him Almost the world was search'd. Strange, loathing him As she did, with hate almost unnatural, How much to heart the Countess took his flight. Sir Rup. Ay, as a gentle stream would take a rock, Suppose one cast sudden into it, Damming its channel up, and making foam, Where all before went crystal, without ripple, But such as noteth gliding. Yes, 'twas strange. Sir Con. 'Twas very strange. Sir Rup. 'Twas one of certain things We see, yet question that we see, yet there We know they are. Sir Con. She pines for loss of him. Sir Rup. No, sir; she takes to heart her father's will, Compelling her to choose a husband, or Accept of him the tournament may send her. And so, she keeps alone, to all forbidding Approach to her, except this youth, who sits In Huon's place, her secretary now, The forward cousin of fair Catherine. Sir Con. Strange, Catherine should fly, and Huon too! That each should purpose, what, if known to each, Had one accomplish'd, had sufficed for both— To shun the consummation of the rites! Strange, that the Duke that very day should die! Sir Rup. Untimely was the Duke's decease for us— Prevented by his death from profiting By the fair opening, which the turbulent And wild Bohemians for our lances made. We could not take the field; and, lo, the war, Ere well commenced, is done; concluded too By single combat, and the conqueror A knight unknown till now, whose championship Had graced the proudest days of chivalry: Of presence noble as his deeds are lofty, By that confirming what by these he won— The favour of the Empress. Yonder comes The secretary. Sir Con. Ay, 'tis he. Sir Rup. I fear He laughs at us, giving us hopes—as still You know he does—that one of us shall yet Make wife of Catherine. A forward spark! I hate a stripling that's so much the man; It shows like aping. He grows worse and worse, Since he hath got his office. For the sake Of Catherine, alone, I bear with him. Sir Con. He is like her; never brother more like sister. I have a word to say to you anon, Touching to-morrow, when the tournament Decides who weds the Countess; she declining To choose a mate herself. Cath. [without, very loud]. Ho! Holloa! Sir Rup. Ho! Catherine enters. Why call you, sir, so loud? Cath. To make you hear News, sirs, from Catherine! Shall I whisper it? She is coming! Sir Rup. So you told us months ago. Cath. Well, when she comes, she'll be the welcomer! Sir Con. I'll wait for her no longer. Cath. Wait for her? O! ay!—A man may wait, and wait in vain. I wait for a wife; though the odds are ten to one, As I'm a man, I die a bachelor. Do you know the signs of one? Sir Con. No; what are they? Cath. O, various; but the chief, a cautious eye, And calculating. He that scans a fence, But seldom makes a clever leap of it; Nine times in ten he balks his spring and falls, In the ditch; while he who takes it at a glance, Goes flying over. Women are shrewd imps! Behoves a man he thinks not of their pockets, When he is looking in their faces; for, Wear he his eye ever so languishingly, They'll find he's only busy at a sum In arithmetic! Sir Rupert, let me see Your face! Don't look so sullen at me. Who Can see the sun, if he's behind a cloud? That's right. I would not say, but when the woman Kind Heaven intends for wife to you shall come, You'll marry her. Sir Con. What say you of my face! Cath. The same I say of his. By my honour, sirs! Though I may pass for an astrologer, I never yet, believe me, made pretence To read the stars; nor am I adept, yet, In palmistry; nor have I studied signs As lucky or unlucky omens; yet Things can I tell before they come to pass. Sir Con. But shall I die a bachelor? Cath. You will, Unless it chance upon a certain day, In a certain month, in such or such a year— At present which is doubtful, but as sure As time runs on 'twill come—you get a wife! Now, there's a puzzle for you; make it out, And tell it me; and then I'll tell it you, If you are in the right. Your lot is cast In mystery; but for Sir Rupert, his Is plain. 'Tis right before me! I can tell The year, the month, the week, the day, almost The very hour, he will be married, or— Not married! yet am I no conjurer. Where is Sir Otto? Sir Con. We are going to him; He waits for us. Cath. I'll follow. News wait I From Catherine; I'll bring it, if it comes. Nay, sirs, beseech you, look not thus upon me With eyes of marvel. On my word! indeed, And, by my honour,—and, if nothing else Will satisfy you, though I have ta'en an oath 'Gainst swearing, I will give it on my oath— I am no conjurer! Another word: What I have told you, tell not, as you love me, Lest I should pay for it by flood or faggot! Upon my life, sirs, I am no conjurer! [They go out severally. SCENE II. —A Room in the Castle. Enter Ulrick. Ulrick. At length the day almost arrived that brings The tournament, whose issue brings to her A consort for her state—she yields me audience. Is it for loss of Huon she has pined, And kept herself forbiddingly alone? If so, why give his hand to Catherine? This is a mystery, the which the more I try to sound, deeper and deeper grows; While surmise after surmise rises, as Report succeeds report of high exploits Achieved by this unknown adventurer, Who now stands next the Empress, chief in place, That even he and Huon are the same! Should it be so, and he should come as well, What then the issue of her meeting with him? This I revolve, and with a troubled heart, That sees no end to its perplexity. [Looks off. How changed she is! Her fiery eye is quench'd! Her head its haughty carriage hath abated, Her cheek is beggar'd of its prideful flush. Enter Countess [a parchment in her hand]. Countess. I have perused the testament, my lord, Carefully, word for word, and see no mention, Either directly or by implication, Touching the quality of him may win me. Ulrick. No, none is made.—A slight omission only. Countess. Yet space enough to let my will creep through. You say, my lord, you have made proclamation Of this fair passage, far and wide? Ulrick. I have. Countess. And now expect the Empress? Ulrick. Yes. Countess. And with her? Ulrick. The noblest of her court; a glorious crowd; Among the rest her favourite; that youth With whose exploits the wondering realm resounds, Who, in so brief a space, without a name, Has made himself the noblest which the tongue Of high renown proclaims. Countess. That youth! what youth? Ulrick. A young adventurer, of whom it seems Fair fortune is enamour'd—gives him all He asks! Countess. I never heard of him, before. Ulrick. So please you, madam, you forget till now, Since that your father died and Huon fled, Save your new secretary, you have deign'd With none vouchsafe communing. Countess. You are right. I have forgot the world, time, everything! What is this favourite called? Ulrick. His titles change So fast—the former almost new as its Successor—scarce I know now his present style. Countess. His name I mean? Ulrick. His name I know not, madam. Countess. What moves my heart, so leaden-dull before? Why did it leap at mention of the stranger? [Aside. Has he been seen by any whom we know, Any of our vassals, chiefs, or friends? Ulrick. I have met With none, that yet have seen him. Countess [abstractedly]. Happy woman! Ulrick. Madam? Countess: The Empress is a happy woman. She can reward desert, ennoble it. Ulrick. So in this instance hath her highness done With such profusion of munificence, There are not wanting those who think she sees Less with an empress', than a woman's eyes; And means her bounties but as costly heralds, Poor to the costlier comer they forerun. Countess. What! means she to espouse him? Ulrick. 'Tis surmised. Matter to wonder at, yet justified. For they report him of a presence noble, As e'er bespoke a man to challenge honour. Countess. I never dreamt of an abyss so hideous— And to be standing on the very brink on't! Ulrick. [Alarmed at her vehemence.] Madam! Countess. Ay! what's the matter? [Aside.] I am frighten'd At myself! [Aloud.] My lord, my spirits are so dreamy, Things which are not, I see—which are, see not! Pray do not heed me. For this tournament, Thus near, without obstruction on my part, Hath it approach'd; but, pray you, keep in mind On what condition; that—at any time— The husband it awards, revolting to me, I am at liberty to make a choice Between the conqueror and the cloister. So! I'll read the will again. [Sits down and reads. Stephen. [Entering hastily.] News! news! my lord. Ulrick. What is it? Stephen. Huon! Countess. Ha! Well, what of Huon, is he found? Stephen. He is. Countess. Propitious Heaven, at what a time! Where is he? Stephen. In the suite of the Empress. Countess. Well?—Go on! Stephen. I saw him! More; that sun of chivalry, Hath blazed so suddenly forth in the brief war, So late gone by and dazzled friends and foes— The fav'rite of the Empress— Countess. Well? Go on! Stephen. Huon and he are one. Countess. I was sure of it! Send him away. [She staggers to a seat, Ulrick supports her. Ulrick. Hence, sir. [Stephen goes out. Countess. Don't wonder at me! Don't! Nor question me, whate'er I say or do! Listen and do my bidding. I prepare To give reception to the Empress,—thou See Huon. Tell him I would speak with him Soon as occasion serves; or let him make Occasion, and at once—at once, my lord! [Aside.] Where shall we meet? In the garden? No; the garden Is overlook'd. In the library? No; We may be subject to intrusion there. What should prevent his coming to my closet? What place so fit? Why think of any other? [Aloud.] My lord, bring Huon to my closet. Huon! The favourite of the Empress I should say. [The Countess and Ulrick go out severally. SCENE III. —Sir Otto's House. Enter Sir Otto, Sir Conrad, and Sir Rupert. Sir Otto. 'Tis slight of fortune not to take the chance She proffers; since the lists must open, sirs, To every lance, why not adventure ours, With such a prize? Wait you for Catherine. I'm for the tournament. Sir Con. And so am I. This secretary is a subtle spark. He has harp'd upon our suit to Catherine, Awaken'd hopes, we had given o'er as dead, And pledged himself with oaths she would return Free, as she ne'er had plighted troth to Huon; And, yet she comes not. What we take in earnest, Be sure he only gives in mockery. Sir Otto. I'm of your counsel, and shall break a lance To-morrow for the Countess. Sir Rup. Do so, sir. I break no lance except for Catherine. Catherine. [Entering disguised as a man.] Who talks of breaking lances? Sir Otto. Ha! our friend The Secretary. Sir Con. Well, sir, what's your news? Where's Catherine? Cath. Absorb'd in solving, sir, A knotty point. Sir Con. A knotty point; what is't? Cath. The measure of a lover's patience, sir. Sir Otto. Does she not come? Cath. Not till that point is solved. Now, could you solve it for her, she might come The sooner. Sir Otto. 'Tis an hour. Sir Con. A day. Sir Otto. A week. Sir Con. A month. Sir Otto. A year. Cath. [To Sir Rupert.] Will you not make a guess? Sir Rup. [Sighing.] It is a life! Cath. Can't you go further, sir? Try if you can. Lovers do miracles: 'Tis said they do, I never saw them, though, Nor met with those that did. Sir Otto. Where is our mistress? Cath. Here, Where'er she is; or nowhere, where you are. Have you a mistress, there your mistress is, Were she at one end of the world and you At the other. Sir Rup. Ay, were she in another world! Cath. Why what's the matter with Sir Rupert? Is The gentleman gone mad? I think myself A sterling lover, but I take no oath, Except to flesh and blood. Sir Rupert, what's Your thought of a mistress? Sir Rup. A vitality Precious, peculiar, not to be supplied; Once with your being join'd, a part of it For ever! Cath. Humph! and you believe, Sir Rupert, You have met with such a thing? Sir Rup. I have. Cath. And where? Sir Rup. In Catherine. Cath. Heaven help the man, he speaks As if he thought himself in earnest, sirs. Whom said he now he'd break a lance for? Sir Con. and Sir Otto. Her. Cath. For Catherine? poor man! Far better break A lance for the Countess; as the lists, they say, Are open to all challengers, that bear The rank of knighthood. Sir Otto. So they are, and we Design to try our fortune, and lament To find Sir Rupert not of the same mind. Cath. That mortifies you, does it? So, Sir Rupert, Will you make suit again to Catherine, Say she comes back again, released from her Enforcéd vow? Sir Rup. Will I make suit to her? My heart is ever lying at her feet. Cath. 'Tis neighbour, then, to an ungainly shoe. She has broken her ancle, and the awkward leech Who set it for her made a botch of it. Her foot's awry; she limps; her taper waist, So straight, before, when she moved, goes, zig-zag, now. Give your heart joy, sir, of its pleasant seat. Sir Rup. The gait and shape of gentle Catherine Are in her heart, no fracture—warping—there! Sir Otto. With what a serious face you play the cheat. Cath. Sir, I look serious at a serious thing. Sir Con. It is not as you say? Cath. Believe 'tis not; But take this with you, I should be more grieved Than you would, to disparage Catherine. Sir Otto. So the fair Catherine halts? Sir Con. Halts my love. Sir Otto. And so does mine. Cath. I have not told him all. Sir Otto. What, is there more to come? Cath. Listen—you'll hear. So, sir, you make retainers of your eyes, [To Sir Rupert. Nor feast at the same table, but eschew Their homely fare; though men, as noble, deem A well-turn'd leg a dainty! Let that pass; But give not me a mistress, with a fair Transparent skin, that you can see, beneath, Tracery costlier than veins of gold, Suppose they lay in bed of alabaster. It never stands the weather. Sir Otto. Is she changed In her complexion? Cath. Do not urge me, sir, To speak more than I would speak; speaking that With pain. Sir Con. What!—Has she turn'd from ivory to— Cath. Anything that you please. Sir Con. Mahogany? Cath. You say it for me, I'm beholden to you; 'Tis hard to speak unwelcome things of friends. Sir Otto. And hard to hear them too. Sir Rupert! Sir Rup. Well? Sir Otto. Hear ye? Sir Rup. I do. Sir Otto. And what resolve you? Sir Rup. What You heard me say before—to break no lance Except for Catherine. Her maiden thoughts— Sweet to the most tenacious mood of love— And generous affections, might unveil Themselves, without a blush, to modesty, Are Catherine's complexion! [Retires. Cath. He is mad! Isn't he, sir? Have twenty masses said, That you preserve your wits! seeing the thing, That turn'd his brain for him, you all affect; Think you 'twould bring him to his senses, sirs, To tell him she hath squander'd all her wealth? Sir Otto. Better she halted in her gait than that! Sir Con. Or cast her white skin for an Ethiop's! You do not tell us so? Cath. I'll tell it him. Sir Otto. But is it so? She was a prudent girl Before she went. Cath. Man, sir, is but a plant, Although he holds no rank in botany; And, as with change of climate, plants will change, Thrive more or less, or take no root at all; So man discovers strange diversity, Transferr'd to sun and soil, not native to him. Sir Otto. But are her riches dwindled? Sir Con. Has she shrunk, Indeed, from affluence to poverty? Cath. Sirs, you shall judge from one particular. From morn till night she lives in masquerade. You wouldn't know her, though you look'd upon her, Walk'd with her, talk'd with her. Can this be done At light expense? Moreover, sirs, she keeps Bad company; nor that of her own sex; Two arrant knaves especially, that stick Like leeches to her, and will ne'er fall off Long as she suffers them, while there's a drop To gorge. Sir Otto. She is ruin'd utterly. Sir Con. Undone, Beyond redemption. Look, Sir Rupert. Sir Rup. Well? Sir Con. Catherine's for hire; she must take service! All Her wealth is gone! Sir Rup. [cheerfully]. Is gone? Sir Con. It makes you glad! Sir Rup. Now could I woo her with the best of ye; Her match in fortune. I could praise her now, Dreading no charge of venal flattery. Fair sir, take pity on an honest heart And loving one, and as you know the haunt, This gentle fawn hath slunk to, tell it me, That I may trace her, straight, and make her mine. Sir Otto. Better you wait to-morrow's tournament, As we shall! Cath. Gentlemen, you do not know Your man! Tell me a linsey-woolsey maid, With halting gait, and saffron-colour'd skin, And not a doit to make a market with them, Could for a moment, in comparison, Stand with the Countess! Who could credit it? The simple truth is this, your friend lacks mettle. Sir Rup. Sir! Cath. He can bluster, that is evident. See what a giant!—He would eat me up If he could! but think you, sirs, I heed his club? Give me a straw, I'll face him. You mistake Your friend! his frame's robust enough, but, sooth, His spirit is a lank one. Sir Rup. 'Sdeath, sir! Cath. Ho! If you have sworn men into agues, sir, Don't try your skill on me! My parrot swears As well as you, and just as much I heed her. Sir Rup. [Drawing.] This passes all endurance—pshaw, a stripling! [Returning his sword. Cath. A stripling, sir, to make an oak afear'd. Sir Rup. [Again drawing.] Indeed! Cath. As I live, his sword is out again! But he's a spaniel, as I'll prove to you, Who thinks he bites by showing you his teeth. Here's for you, sir—[Draws]—but hold, what day is this? Sir Con. Friday. Cath. I never fight on Fridays, sirs. My killing days are all the rest of the week, E'en Sundays not excepted. Sirs, your friend Is a coward. [Coolly puts up her sword. Sir Rup. Furies! Cath. Fiends and all sorts of imps! Swearing won't save you, sir. I'll prove my words. I dare you, at the tournament to-morrow, To break a lance with me. Observe you, sirs, At the thought of it, he shakes, from head to foot, And thinks to pass it off with swaggering. He dares as soon confront stout Charlemagne, Were he alive, as me. I'll wager you My sword to your dagger, he takes flight to-day, And waits not for to-morrow. Sir Rup. Will I not! I will have satisfaction. I accept His challenge. I will have satisfaction, sirs. Cath. You shall, and have it to your heart's content! Take linsey-woolsey with a halt, and the skin Of a negro, rather than essay a tilt With chance to win a Countess! I could laugh To scorn the man that would believe him. Oh! He shall have satisfaction. I could beat him With a rush, in rest. He shall have satisfaction! Sirs, he will cower at very sight of me; Fall on his knees, and beg his life of me, With clasp'd hands. He shall have satisfaction! [They go out severally. SCENE IV. —A Room in the Castle. Enter Countess. Count. All is confirm'd—Each gives the same account His mistress sees her mate. Of all her court He is the only one, whose duties to her She takes as favours, not as things of course. He comes! Who stops him thus untimely? Oh, How changed he is!—The fiery hardihood Of the life he hath of late made consort of, Has given another spirit to his eyes. His face is cast anew, as circumstance Could alter Nature's modelling and work, Improving, on her mould. Is that the man, Was, once, my father's serf? whom once I scorn'd? Fell ever at my wayward frown that brow? Or stoop'd that knee, for me, to kiss the ground? Would it do it now? Fell ever at my feet That form, as prostrate as the hand of death Had struck it to the floor? 'Twould take that hand To lay it, now, there—and a wave of mine Had done it, once! If he confesses hold Of any other, never shall he learn His hold of me! If he bears me love, I bless my stars I have the 'vantage-ground. Huon enters, and remains standing at a distance, with his eyes on the ground. Countess. Is Huon here, and does not Huon speak? [Pauses. Absent so long, no greeting for a friend— [Pauses. A woman, too! [Pauses]—No salutation, kind, Prelude of happy news she'd joy to hear,— Relation of adventures she would thrill To listen to,—exploits she would wonder at, And the next moment at her wonder blush, Knowing whose arm achieved them! Huon. I am glad To find you well. Countess. You are glad to find me well? I hope you are! It were not saying much, I trust, to say I know you are! You are glad To find me well! Is that your news? If 'tis, 'tis very strange. Huon. You wish'd to see me, And I am here to learn your will. Countess. More news! You are a friend worth parting with, you bring Such marvels home with you. Some time methinks Since last we met together, and you are glad To find me well; and, as I wish'd to see you, You are here to learn my will! You were not here, then, Had not I sent for you. Huon. It would have been Presumptuous. Countess. Presumptuous! Huon. Yes, madam, In the serf. Countess. [With sudden indignation.] No, sir, not in the favourite Of the Empress!—Huon, this is not the way We ought to meet! It should not be in anger! You are come home, and you are welcome home. Requires my tongue a backer to get credence? Well! there's my hand beside. Do you not take My hand? Huon. You are a noble lady, madam, Whose father was my lord, by leave of whom, I thought and had a will—did what I did— Yea, kept the very blood within my veins. Behoves it I should take his daughter's hand? Countess. You mock me! Huon. Would I did, and 'twere a dream! But dreams are not repeated, day by day, And day by day reminds me of a time I was your father's serf. Countess. No more of this. Huon. Oh! would no more! The wounded body heals, The pain is over, all is sound again, A scar reminds you of it—nothing more! Not so the heart, you lacerate it once! Habit may dull, pursuit engross—divert— But never are you ransom'd from the throe! Live your meridian out, it comes again, Fresh as at first, to make you writhe anew. Countess. We do not meet to talk of grievances, Huon. I offer'd you my hand just now. Why do you weep? I did not give it you To kiss it with your tears! Huon. O, 'tis a hand Thou hast forbidden mine to meet. Countess. No, Huon, Not as a friend's!—[Recovering herself.]—I'll see him clearly first— [Aside. Sit down and let us talk. I have fifty things I want to say to you, yet know not which To begin with. Huon, do you like the Empress? Huon. Like her? Countess. Yes; like her,—that's the word I said. Perhaps it should be “love her?” Huon. Love her, madam!— Countess. [Interrupting him.] I see you do! Go on? What were you going To say? Huon. O contrast marvellous! beyond Belief of nature! Countess. Ay! 'twixt her and me! Go on! The contrast? Best we understand Each other! Well? The contrast? Huon. 'Twere as one Should find the sun by following the night! Should plunge into her regions, and for chill, And gloom, and sterileness, find light, and warmth, And verdure,—such as should belong to day! 'Twere as death own'd a heart, and life had none But with the shows of animation Harbour'd, within its breast, a core of stone, While the still ribs of death held throbs beneath them! Countess. Am I that day, that life, compared to which Death, night, are e'en so rich? Is she thou servest That death, that night, preferr'd to life and day? Huon. O, I did love thee to oblivion Of myself! What Nature gave me, to assert The man, neglecting, as despiséd things Compared to thee! That she intended me For deeds of nobleness, I may confess, Seeing that others own I have achieved them; Yet I abused her bounties,—and, for what? Scorns—wrongs—through love of thee, preferr'd them! And which I bore, until the cause itself, That made me bear them, thou wouldst make a means Of yet unknown oppression. That I bore! But, patience there gave up! Yes!—Not, until Coercéd there—where, spared, I were content To last the thrall of passion's lethargy— Did I rebel! But when I was struck down Prostrate, as, for the sake of flesh and blood, Behoves not slave to lie,—with marvel on't I waked to the sense of what I ought to be! Of what, against my will, 'twas past the sport Of power to change me from! A MAN!—and straight A man I started up! a man, resolved To use his attributes as fits a man; To vindicate the ancient, common birth-right, And answer the design of Him that framed him! Countess. So! You have register'd your debts to me, No item overlook'd thou knowest of. What, now, if I could name to thee one debt Would blot out all the rest?—not known to thee; A debt thy fairest dreams ne'er gave thee glimpse of, Howe'er they buoy'd thee up; when, cast away The clog that day put on, thou soar'dst as high As e'er ambition left at large could wing, Daring the eagle himself to follow thee! Huon. No debt that thou couldst name were gain to me. I keep no register of aught between us. Or, if I do, I never turn'd to it, Unless enforced, as now. Whate'er has pass'd, Is pass'd, and, profitless to memory, Were better be forgotten. Countess. Ay? Indeed! So easily done? Well, be it so! 'Tis past, And, so, should be forgotten. Please you now Turn to the Empress. You have painted me; Proceed to her. Come, let me see what hand You will make of her picture. When I ask'd you now If you liked her, you but echo'd me!—and then I ask'd you if you loved her, and again You echo'd me! I want an answer, not An echo! Well, sir? well? Huon. Madam, I love And honour her. [She starts from her seat; he rises also. Countess. Thou art rewarded, pride!— Meet'st thy deserts! Show thy high breeding now! Tread stately! throw thy spurning glances round! And talk as mighty things as though the earth Were made for thee alone! Where's thy domain? Gone! And thy palace, what is it? a ruin! And what art thou thyself? a beggar now! Huon, you loved me once! [Bursting into tears. Huon. I loved thee once! Oh, tell me, when it was I loved thee not? Was't in my childhood, boyhood, manhood? Oh! In all of them I loved thee? And were I now To live the span of my past life, twice told, And then to wither, thou surviving me, And yet I lived in thy sweet memory, Then mightst thou say of me, “He loved me once; But that was all his life!” Countess. 'Twas heart for heart! I loved thee ever! Yes! the love that now Thrills on the woman's tongue; the girl's had told thee, Had I been bold as fond; for, even then, I saw thy worth; but did not see thy station, Till others, not so well affected towards thee, Reveal'd it to me by their cold regards. I could not help my nature. From that time Two passions strove in my divided soul For mastery—scorn of thy station—love For thee—each feeding on the other's hate, And growing stronger, till I thought their strife Would shake my frame to dissolution! Yes! O, Huon! when my brow sat cloudy, oft, O'er my cold eye, that look'd askant at thee, Thou little thought'st what friend there was within Would make that brow clear as a summer sky, That eye bright, glowing as a summer's sun, To kindle thee—as they, their world, with life, And health, and wealth, and gladness! Huon. Say'st thou this To me? or do I dream I hear thee say it? Or is the past a dream? I did not yield At thy command, to marry Catherine? Thou didst not see me wed her? Fancy forged The ring I thought I put upon her finger? Thou wast not by at all? From first to last, Hadst not a hand in it? or, if thou hadst, Why, then, untimely this unfold to me? For well I know thee to be prime of all Proud honour's children! Art thou offspring prime Of cruelty as well? O, Heaven, to think She loved me, and could give me to another, Nor yet to her alone!—another!— Countess. Ha! Well? Huon. One who ne'er set eyes on me, until An outcast, by her deed of hate, who loved me! Saw me, a stranger, hunting after fortune, And gave her hand to me could help me up! Lavish'd her favours on me!—decorates With honours, till beside the bright themselves I lost no brightness! Countess. To the Empress? Huon. Yes! Thou lovest me?—O, fate! There was a time, 'Twere more than bliss, if more could be, to know it; But now 'tis misery! Countess. 'Tis misery! [Countess starts up again; Huon also rising. Art thou in such a strait indeed as that, To give my love for thee so harsh a name? What shall I call it then? Coin me a name Will stand for something worse than misery— Will paint the case of a high, noble maid, Who stoop'd to love a serf; nay, stopp'd not there, But told her passion to him—Misery! Huon. I am no more a serf. Countess. Thou art ennobled; Yet art thou still the same; thou hast won honours, Rewards of deeds, in spite of thy base blood Achieved by thee! Huon. Nay, madam, spare my blood, And pardon me, its owner, if I say It is not base. Countess. It is!—What should it be But base? A serf gave it to thee, a serf Gave him his blood! Trace back the current, sir, Far as you can, and you will find it base, Nothing but base! Huon. Madam, men's natures are Their blood; they have no other—high or low. If base the current hitherto of mine, It ceased with me. Born in thy father's house A serf, I left it one, to seek my fortune, Make it or mar it, for promotion having No other patron than my own right arm, And my own heart and head to guide and nerve it; And with their help, I see that house again, An independent, self-exalted man, While many a son, who left a noble home. With blood untainted for a thousand years, Returns to it no better than he left it. Is my blood base? Countess. No, Huon! mine was base To let me call it so. Alas! alas! And hast no better welcome for my love Than that sad word thou spok'st? Huon. What word so fit? What is it to a man condemn'd to die, To tell him of a treasure left to him? Shall he be glad and thank his lucky stars, Or shall not that, their bounty, aggravate The ruin, makes it vain! Countess. Condemn'd to die? Resemblest thou a man condemn'd to die? Huon. Why didst thou drive me from thee by that act? Countess. That act was nothing; 'twas thy flight, And that which follow'd it. Thou art entangled— And thank thy flight. Oh! Huon, were thy love In daring enterprise the tithe of mine, 'Twould attempt something to enlarge thee from The cause thou art prisoner to! Huon. It cannot cease, Except with life. Countess. The Empress loves thee, Huon! Huon. No. Countess. But she does. Thou art her favourite. She Hath chain'd thee to her throne. Huon. No. Countess. But she has! Thou hast made merchandise, Most shameful merchandise, of thy allegiance! Broken oaths as tiny shells, which at a touch, Will fall to powder! Huon. Broken oaths! Countess. Yes, oaths! Thy life was all one oath of love to me! Sworn to me daily, hourly, by thine eyes, Which, when they saw me, lighten'd up, as though An angel's presence had enhanced their vision, That I have seen their very colour change, Subliming into hues past earthliness. Talk of the adjuration of the tongue— Compare love's name, a sound which any lip May pipe! a breath!—with holy love itself! Thou'rt not forsworn, because thou took'st no oath? What were thy accents then? thy accents, Huon? Language that turn'd thy lightest words to oaths, Vouching the burden of a love-fraught soul! Telling a tale which my young nature caught With interest so deep, 'twas conn'd by heart Before I knew the fatal argument! Huon, I charge thee quit the service of The Empress! Huon. 'Twere against all honour. Countess. No! Give up her service! Huon. 'Twere ingratitude. Countess. Ingratitude for what! Huon. She has advanced me Past my deserts. Countess. No, I deny it! No! Not equal to them! No! Thy golden deeds She has repaid with tinsel! Ulrick. [Entering.] Please you, sir, The Empress summons you. Countess. You are not going? Huon. My presence is commanded. Countess. Are you going? Ulrick. My lord! Huon. I come. Countess. You are going, then? Huon. I must go. Countess. You must? Then go! Go, and farewell for ever! [They go out.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT V. SCENE I. —The Hall of the Castle. The Empress, Courtiers, Knights, Heralds, &amp;c., prepared to proceed to the Tournament. Enter Ulrick. Emp. [To Ulrick.] Why wait we for the Countess? What delays her? This day is dedicate to her; for her We are convened; and comes she last of all? Ulrick. Madam, she craves your favour for this pause. Believe 'tis not remissness, but mischance, Retards her. Doubtless she will come, anon. Emp. Anon, my lord! Anon is not our time For friends to greet us, when they summon us. [Enter three Attendants, the first bearing a coronet on a cushion, the second a pile of parchments, the third followed by Vassals, carrying money-coffers; last of all, the Countess, plainly attired, followed by her Women, in costly dresses. She stops before the Empress. Emp. Why, lady! what is this? Countess. My liege, receive This emblem of that pomp which I resign, Because 'tis adjunct to conditions, such As render it a burden to me, past The faculty of sufferance to bear. Emp. Lady! Countess. So please you, madam, give me leave, As joint executor with this worthy lord, Into your hands I also yield all right And title to this fair château, besides The lands and forests, its appendages, As well as vassals, natives of the soil. Emp. But, lady— Countess. Madam, suffer me conclude. These are the coffers which my father left, And, as he left them, render'd to your highness; And with them all resign'd, save such endowment As shall entitle me to that retreat, Holy and calm, wherein I mean to pass, I'll say, the remnant of my days, i' th' hope, Though few are past, still fewer are to come— Which option, as you know, my father's will Has left to me. Emp. Then will you not abide The cast of fate in the tournament? nor take The husband she may send—nor yet select Yourself? Countess. I cannot, madam. Emp. How? Countess. I am Forestall'd. Emp. By whom? Countess. By you! Emp. Let every one Repair to the tournament. Let it proceed, As we ourself were there. And you, my lord, [To Ulrick. Preside for us. It is our will the lists Be open'd straight. The Countess stays with me. [All go out, except the Empress and Countess. We are alone! Now, how am I a let To such espousals as your choice would make? Countess. Do you not know? Emp. Girl, be direct with me; Nor in the headlong passion of your soul, That seems to joy in strife and wrack, forget 'Tis your liege lady that vouchsafes you audience! Countess. That I forget, and everything beside, Except one thing, in still revolving which, The earth hath shrunk in estimation Into a grain—the sun into a spark! Nought hath kept substance but my desolation, Which seems to me to fill up space, itself, Till nothing else hath room. Emp. Thy desolation? Who made it for thee? Countess. Thou! Emp. In what regard? Countess. In thy attractive favour shown to Huon! Emp. I made thy desolation? Thou thyself Didst make it with thy pride, the greater, but Worse portion of thee! Countess. By my pride? Emp. Thy pride! Which, evil counsellor to thy love, advised it To blush with shame at homage, from the which It could not yet refrain, because 'twas due— Tribute to such desert, as far behind Left all desert beside, and might have won The subject's heart—whose mistress's it won!— Thy story—everything are known to me. Countess. Then thou confessest it! Emp. What? Countess. What? Emp. Beware! I brook not such a tone from thee. Countess. The heart Will speak, despite the checks of shows and forms, Shadows compared to its realities! Is it not so with thee?—e'er hast thou felt A pang?—and if thou hast, where, then, thy palace? Thy retinue?—thy guards?—thy empire?—Gone, With all their proud appurtenances, and No habitation left thee, but thy breast, The only house of happiness or woe! How shall it be with me then, with a heart, Madden'd with torture? Shall I cast about To furnish looks, and words, and tones for things, I have no interest in, and thou, that hast, In equal case wouldst give to disregard? Emp. Remember thou'rt a subject! Countess. So I will While thou'rt the empress; but when thou becomest A woman—a mere woman like myself— Stepp'st from the eminence that lifts thee 'bove me— Levell'st thee to me in one common nature— I deal with thee as woman deals with woman! I own thy power! I must and do! Thy breath Can doom me exile, bondage, what it will! There I submit! Thou art the empress there. But when thou thwart'st me in the interests Which are the right, not more of one than all— Trenchest upon my private peace—my love— Thou dost me wrong for which I challenge thee, As equal may an equal. Emp. Come! Thy challenge? What dost allege against me? Countess. That thou lov'st him! Emp. Ay, by my troth, as much as thou didst scorn him! Countess. Was't he accused me to thee? Emp. Wayward woman, He never spoke of thee except with love. Countess. How couldst thou love him then? How could thy greatness Forget itself to try and steal a heart, Thou knew'st to be another's? Emp. Steal! Countess. Ay, steal! Must we coin terms for those that are above us, To make offences gracious to their ears, When they commit them—which, by us enacted, They would blast with damning names! Emp. Thou hast a spirit! Countess. Thou knew'st he loved me, and didst covet him! Covet a heart at second-hand—an empress! Hear me that am a subject, and thy subject— His heart was mine, until thou robb'dst me of it— Not of it all, but of a part—though if A part be gone, go all!—Well, as I said, His heart was mine at first. 'Tis gone—My peace, Hopes, everything, along with it! What then? Would I have it back?—No!—I would sooner die! Its worth was its fidelity—That lost, All's lost. Thou covetedst a faithless heart! Emp. Didst thou deserve that heart? Countess. [Weeping.] I did!—I loved him Better than thou couldst do! Emp. I' faith, thou'rt brave! Thy love of him was persecution. Countess. [Weeping.] Yet I loved him! Emp. Loved him! It was tyranny, Enforced without the mercy of a pause. Countess. [Weeping still, and more bitterly.] The more I loved him! Emp. Loved him!—and constrainéd him To nuptials he abhorr'd. Countess. I did—and then [In an agony of tears. I loved him most! Emp. How had it fared with him, Hadst thou been I? Countess. Far differently. Emp. How? Countess. I then had been above rebuke or blame! I would have given his merits their fair field, Encouraged them to challenge their deserts, Rewarded them till they had lifted him So near equality to me, the seat I fill'd, he might have shared along with me. Emp. That field he found himself, without my aid! I saw him there, and challenged simple greatness, In spite of its disguise; desired it doff Its lowly suit and show the thing it was; Nor stopp'd till, step by step, I saw it climb To where it stands; nor mean I to stop there! Countess. How? Emp. I design him for the highest grace I can bestow. Countess. The highest! Emp. Yes, beyond His hopes, until to-day—Until to-day, Never divulged to him. Countess. He knows it, then? Emp. He does; and, till my promise is fulfill'd, With fears that shake him, spite of certainty Of his immeasurable happiness— For such he thinks it—wears a doubtful life. Countess. Thy hand! Emp. The hand of her, more proud to be The empress of his heart than of my realm. Countess. He shall not take it! Emp. Not? Countess. Thy power is huge, But there are bounds to it! Emp. What bounds? Countess. Right!—Law!— Imperial foot stops there.—It dares not cross, And if it dares, it shall not! Emp. Sooth, thou'rt brave! Countess. He shall not marry! Emp. No? Countess. No! Emp. She's a rock! She echoes me! Countess. He shall not marry! Emp. What! Again? Countess. Wast thou the empress of the world, I'd say to thee again—He shall not marry! Emp. Thou know'st a let? Countess. I do! Emp. The troth he pledged To Catherine—you see I am advised Of all! The marriage is annull'd. Countess. It is? Emp. It is! Countess. How? Emp. By the Church! Countess. The Church? And yet He shall not marry! Emp. What! Not marry thee? Countess. [Changing, and falling on her knees.] Madam! Emp. The hand that I design for him— Crown of my favour, his deserts—is thine, Not mine, my girl—the guerdon fair for which He would not take my empire in exchange— Ay, with my hand, to boot! Countess. My liege, my empress! Emp. My fiery queen, and have I tamed you now? Tamed you, so soon! I half repent me on't. Mine's the true spirit, namesake! It admires To see itself in others. 'Faith, my glass Never reflected me more honestly Than thou didst, even now. Listen to me. I am thy Huon's friend, and nothing more. Rise! Now we'll talk as sister does with sister. Hither thy Huon bears me company— Unwarn'd to what intent, until to-day. Until to-day, in darkness that the bar The Church, with thy fair aid, 'twixt him and thee Had set—the Church, at my persisting suit, Has quite annull'd; and now he's in the lists Striving to win thee! He that never yet, In strait of life or death, much less a tilt, Suffer'd defeat! [Trumpets.]—That flourish is the close. Smile at it, girl! It makes thee Huon's wife! Huon—no more the serf—but nobleman— Nor nobleman alone! This hour a prince, For thy fair sake! Countess [dejectedly to herself]. Would he were still the serf. Emp. Dejected, girl! Countess. Madam. Emp. They come! Come hither! Here take thy seat in the centre. Here thou art chief. We are but second! Smile—Thy Huon comes! [Music. Ulrick and the rest re-enter from the Tournament. The Empress anxiously surveys them. The Countess absent and dejected. Where is he? Countess. Madam? Emp. Which is Huon? [Aside to Countess. Countess. Which? Emp. [Aside to Countess.] Methinks he is not here. Canst make him out? Girl, tell me, is thy lover here or not? He seems not here, and yet he must be here. Herald. Madam, the lists are closed. The victor waits The prize which he has won. Shall he receive it? Emp. [Aside to Countess.] Shall I say yes? I must say yes. Thou smilest. I will say yes!—He shall receive the prize. [Aloud. Who is he that bows? Herald. The victor, madam. Emp. [To Countess.] Ha! Do you know him? Countess. Not with his visor; yet Methinks I ought to know him, were it he. Emp. Sir Knight, so please you, raise your visor. 'Tis The prince of Milan! Girl—what means thine eye To blaze with joy? It looks on thy despair! The prince of Milan 'tis that wins thy hand! Hear'st thou me? Know'st thou what I say? Countess. I do! Both hear and comprehend thee. Emp. Ay, and smile? Countess. And smile. Emp. Art thou thyself? Am I myself? I think myself the same! Where is Huon? Ulrick. Gone To take his armour off. Emp. How fared it with him? Ulrick. He enter'd first the lists, and one by one O'erthrew all comers, till the prince of Milan Unhorsed him. Countess. Is he hurt? Ulrick. No, madam. Countess. [Starting up.] Thanks! My Lord, bring Huon hither! Hither! Hie! Now all is as it should be. Emp. Should be, girl? Say rather should not be. Thy lover's foil'd. Where is the ashy cheek, that meets disaster, The brow that's like the wrack? the gusty breath? The quivering bloodless lip and quaking frame? These should be, and they are not! Where are they? Or rather, wherefore see I in their stead Things 'twould become to wait on holidays Rather than days of penance? Look not thus, Else thou wilt make me hate thee! Countess. Madam, madam, I tell thee, and believe me, all is well. Emp. [Indignantly.] Then let the prince of Milan take his prize. Fred. I claim it on my knee! [At the moment the Prince kneels, Huon led by Ulrick enters, and the Countess rushes towards him. Countess. How is it, Huon? Thou look'st as hurt. Huon. Sped in the spirit, lady. Forgetful of my charger, all unmindful, He lack'd my argument to hearten him, Bent on the most surpassing prize alone, I did not think to change him, and he fail'd me! Countess. Fortune, farewell! and pride go with thee! Go! Welcome adversity! Shake hands with me, Thou tester of true hearts! whose homely fare No flatterer sits down to—hollow friend— Foe, masking thoughts of scorn with smiling face;— But truth and honesty! affection stanch! That grasps the hand before it scans the sleeve, And greets the lowly portal with a grace More winning far than his, who thanks the gate That spreads with pride, to let a monarch in. Emp. Girl, I am loath to speak in terms of blame, But thou hast much offended courtesy: Not only slighting me, thy sov'reign lady, But him to whom thy fate awards thee bride. Countess. A wife must be a widow, ere a bride. Emp. A wife?—No wife art thou! Countess. I am a wife! Before this goodly presence I proclaim it. A wife by stealth, but still a wedded wife! Wedded for love, as fervent, durable, As ever led a woman to the altar! Emp. Where is thy husband? Hear'st thou—where is he? Countess. Where my remorse, contrition, deprecation, Homage, and love, now throw me! I am kneeling At his feet! [Kneels to Huon Huon. Thy husband, I? Countess. My husband, thou! Huon. Was I not wed to Catherine? Countess. Thou wast. My name is Catherine, as thou shouldst know, But, as thou knewest not, till now; the lips Pronounced that name in wedding thee—the hand Then given to thee—the troth then plighted thee— Were mine as truly as the breath that now Avows I am thy wife!—in debt to fate For baffling thee; for now she owns thee lord In thy adversity! Huon. Thou kneel'st to me! In marvel of thy words!—I overlook'd thee, Madam!—My wife, rise—pray you, rise!—my own, My dear liege lady ever! I am feeble In words; but oh! the strife is strong, within, Of wonder, gratitude, humility, Pride, honour, love, outdoing one another! Enter Catherine, disguised. Cath. Fair Empress, justice! justice! Emp. What comes now? Who asks for justice? Cath. One that is most wrong'd In his honour; cheated by a craven knight, Who promised him to give him meeting here; But hath broken his word—no doubt, through cowardice. Emp. What is his name? Cath. Sir Rupert. Sir Rup. [Stepping forward.] He speaks false! I am here to my appointment. Cath. Are you so? Have you not sprain'd your arm? Sir Rup. No! Cath. Nor your leg? Sir Rup. No! Cath. Nor your side, that you can't sit your horse? Sir Rup. No! Cath. Wonderful! Your spirit does not fail? Sir Rup. No! Cath. Yet more wonderful, you'll fight me? Sir Rup. Yes! Cath. You shall, but where I pray you are your friends? Sir Otto and Sir Conrad. [Coming forward.] Here! Cath. Gentlemen, I am sorry for the fall You got in tilting for the Countess; but 'Tis nothing to the one which he shall rue, As you shall see. Down on your knees and beg Your life. Sir Rup. And beg my life! Cath. Now what's the use Of pondering, on that which must be done? Do I not know, sir, that you have borne cuffs A thousand times, as well you know you have, And know you not, a bold face never yet Made a bold heart? Down on your knees at once! Valour won't come for stamping, sir! Entreat Your friends to hold you; that's a better way To pass for a brave man. Sir Rup. I'll smite thee. Cath. Do! If you dare! [Throwing off cloak. Ha! Have I brought you to thy knee at last, sir? Said I not truly, that I would bring you there? Beware I say not I shall keep you there! Sir Rup. What! Catherine? Countess. Yes, Catherine, Sir Rupert. Sir Rup. O happiness! Countess. Which thou hast well deserved. Sir Rup. Thou still wast gracious to me. Countess. For thy truth, Attested by thy jealous poverty. I saw thy honest love for Catherine, In secret cherish'd, as thou thought'st—as one Conceals a costly treasure he has found, And rightfully may keep, but, being poor, Fear to display it, through the world's charity. Thy Catherine, whom before thou fear'dst to woo, Now dares make suit to thee, and challenges thee, To make her thine. So, take her, if thou wilt, And with her honour, for thy honest love! Cath. O— Countess. Huon, my husband—Lord! canst thou forgive The scornful maid, for the devoted wife, Had cleaved to thee, though ne'er she own'd thee lord? Huon. I nothing see, except thy wondrous love. Countess. Madam, our happiness lifts up to thee Its eyes in penitence and gratitude! Thou, chief in station, first to give desert, Despite its lowliness, its lofty due! O, thou hast taught a lesson to all greatness, Whether of rank or wealth, that 'tis the roof Stately and broad which ne'er was meant to house Equality alone—whose porch is never So proud, as when it welcomes-in desert, That comes in its own fair simplicity. END OF LOVE.</field>
   </doc>
</add>