<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Wade, Thomas, 1805-1875</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Wade, Thomas, 1805-1875</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">wade thomas 1805 1875</field>
      <field name="author_text">Wade, Thomas, 1805-1875</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1830's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V3.0193.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1830</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460615</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Jew of Arragon ; Or, The Hebrew Queen ; A Tragedy, In Five Acts</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Jew of Arragon ; Or, The Hebrew Queen ; A Tragedy, In Five Acts</field>
      <field name="title_facet">jew of arragon or the hebrew queen</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">jew of arragon or the hebrew queen</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Jew of Arragon ; Or, The Hebrew Queen ; A Tragedy, In Five Acts</field>
      <field name="year_display">1830</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1830</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1830</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460615&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460615&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Wade, Thomas, 1805-1875&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;wade thomas 1805 1875&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Jew of Arragon ; Or, The Hebrew Queen ; A Tragedy, In Five Acts&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;jew of arragon or, the hebrew queen&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1830&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1830&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Wade, Thomas&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1805&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1875&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Jew of Arragon ; Or, The Hebrew Queen&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy, In Five Acts&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Smith, Elder And Co.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1830&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872971-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv30193&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Jew of Arragon ; Or, The Hebrew Queen&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy, In Five Acts&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 182 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: The Jew of Arragon.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1830.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 20 Oct 1830.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE JEW OF ARRAGON; OR, THE HEBREW QUEEN. A TRAGEDY, IN FIVE ACTS.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PREFACE. The events upon which the following tragedy is founded, are said to have occurred in Castile, at the commencement of the thirteenth century, in the reign of Alphonso VIII.: but, for metrical purposes, I have transferred the scene from Castile to Arragon; retaining, however, the name of the king, that of the cotemporary monarch of Arragon (Peter, I believe) not being sufficiently tragical—at least, for poetic ears: several matters and allusions will, thus, be found historically out of place; but I do not think I have any where exceeded the allowed license of the drama. In the construction of the tragedy (with the exception of the first and second acts, and the last scene of the fifth) I have availed myself of the Spanish play on the same subject, the Raquel of Vicente Garcia de la Huerta, prefixed to which is printed the following ‘argumento’: “Pues el Rey ovó pasados todos estos trabajos en el comienzo quando reynó, e fue casado, fuese para Toledo con su mujer Do?a Leonor, e estando y, pagóse mucho de una Judia que avie nombre Fermosa, e olvidó la mujer, e encerróse con ella gran tiempo, en guisa que non se podie partir de ella por ninguna manera, nin se pagaba tanto de cosa ninguna, e estubo encerrado con ella poco menos de siete a?os, que non se membraba de si, nin de su Reyno, nin de otra cosa ninguna. Estonce ovieron su acuerdo los omes buenos del Reyno, como pusiesen algun recando en aquel fecho tan malo e tan desaguisado: e acordaron, que la matasen: e que asi cobrarien a su Se?or, que tienen por perdido: e con este acuerdo fueronse para allá, e entraron al Rey diciendo que querian fabrar con el, e mientras los unos fabraron con el Rey, entraron otros donde estaba aquella Judia en muy nobles estrados, e degollaronla.”—Chrón. Gen. Of the Spanish play, the ‘personas’ are as follow: “Alfonso Octavo, Rey de Castilla. Raquel, Judia. Ruben, Confidente de Raquel. Hernan Garcia de Castro, Rico Hombre. Alvar Fa?ez, Rico Hombre. Garceran Manrique de Lara, Rico Hombre. Castellanos. Guardia del Rey. Acompa?amento de Judios y Judias.” From this, it will be seen that in the entire portraiture of Xavier, and, consequently, in the main design of the present tragedy, I stand not in the least in the shadow of my foreign predecessor, however I may be so placed in regard to many of its details. By the characters of Xavier and Rachel, the reader may be not unfrequently reminded of the origin of the “days of Purim,” which inspired for France one of the most forcible of the elegant dramatic poems of the classical Racine. Thus much as to the subject of the tragedy. Its failure on the stage only renders its publication the more imperative; as the few whose good opinion I covet, will, perhaps, be led by its perusal to think not unfavourably of the drama, in spite of the united outcry of the “critics;” some of whom, indeed, do me the justice first to misquote my lines, and then charitably load me with the burthen of their own stupidity: “Faciunt næ, intelligendo ut nihil intelligant.” Moreover, it has been asserted by certain of these benevolent men, that every passage at all worthy of notice in the tragedy, is derived from the pages of our glorious old dramatists: this is a direct falsehood, and they know it to be so; but who shall give the lie to the oracle, though a wooden god pronounce it? Amid the general cry of condemnation (the invariable portion of ill-success, merited or unmerited) which has of late been rung so cheerily and continually in my ears, and which might well dismay any but a mind predetermined to persevere and to succeed, some few journalists have ventured to speak of the tragedy with a little liberality and fairness; but one gentleman alone has stood aloof from the mob of critics, and gilded the storm about me with the radiance of encouraging criticism: I am a debtor to his justice for the remainder of my life. To confirm the opinion of two or three sensible people, that there is at least one superfluous office in the state, those ‘words and sentences’ which were struck by the Deputy Play-Licenser from the manuscript copy of the tragedy submitted to him for his approval, I have caused to be printed in capitals: the liberal reader will smile in perusing them; and deign, perhaps, to anticipate with some pleasure the speedy abolition of a childish tribunal. Of course, the revered name of the Deity, wherever it occurs, was erased by the great religious and moral pen of the licenser, and altogether abjured in stage-utterance: still, I have not hesitated to retain it in many places; having yet to learn, that it is not the part of the dramatist to make his characters speak as men speak; having yet to feel, that piety, or impiety, dwells rather in words, than thoughts—on the lips, than in the mind.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DEDICATION. TO THE JEWS OF ENGLAND.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PERSONS REPRESENTED. ALPHONSO, Mr. Warde. GARCIA, G. Bennett. ALVARO, Diddear. MANRIQUE, Abbott. XAVIER, the Jew of Arragon, C. Kemble. REUBEN, Egerton. SECRETARY TO XAVIER, F. Matthews. LOPEZ, Baker. FIRST LORD, Irwin. SECOND LORD, Henry. MESSENGER, Holl. ATTENDANT, Heath. ISABELLA, Miss Ellen Tree. RACHEL, the Hebrew Queen, Fanny Kemble. JEWESS, Phillips. Courtiers, Jews, Attendants, Citizens, Troops &amp;c. Scene:—Saragossa and its neighbourhood.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT THE FIRST. SCENE I. A Public Place. Enter Garcia and Alvaro. Gar. My Lord Alvaro! is 't six years, or seven, Since this our Arragon, Castile, Navarre, In triple league defensive, at Toloza Play'd havoc with the invasive infidels; And down a hundred thousand Moorish throats Cramm'd Christian steel; at which time, our changed King So dealt with war, that Spain saluted him The Mars of Arragon—Is 't six, or seven? Alv. Now seven, Lord Garcia. Gar. Seven, is it, Sir? Why, then, I say, the seventh solemnity, Which should to-morrow re-instate at full That great day in the public memory, Will lack its first-year lustre. Alv. Grievously: Changed King, indeed! and much-changed kingdom, too! Alphonso's grown a common reveller— Crows 'mid his women like a Musselman; And so disports him with his new-bought toy, This Bride elect (whose fate calls out on pity, That virtue, youth and beauty should be bound To such a mate) his glory seems a dream, Gilding the drowsy sleep of luxury. Gar. 'Twill be so, till a tempest waken him. The treasury is unlined: mere poverty Shall make the festival a threadbare show, With splendor of past years comparison'd; That victory from her faded celebration Shall turn, shame-blushingly. Alv. Would 'twere not so! Faugh! 'tis Manrique. Gar. I dislike the man; He is the merest trimmer of the court, And flatters low as fawning. What's the matter? Enter Manrique. Man. O, my sweet lords! upon a merry time Ye hang like sackcloth on a wanton nun: Dear lords! why frown ye? Alv. Sure, our faces are As much our own as is a paid-for vest? And that we wear so fashion'd as we will, Not being men o' the mode. Gar. What cause for smiling? Man. To-morrow's sun must teach ye, gentlemen: The festival and marriage of the King— Two suns at once in joy's meridian! Will wake high jubilee:—magnificence, By lighter graces temper'd, all past pomp Shall render vile and ugly; every veteran Shall fight Toloza's battle o'er again A thousand times i'the day, for valiant joy At its so worthy celebration, Made doubly glorious by god Hymen's torch, Lighting to heaven a royal votary! Gar. So! Are Saragossa's tradesmen liberal? Her artists, patriots? that they offer gratis Unto her glory's annual ordinance, Which hath been dwindling yearly, and tends fast Toward blank omission. Alv. Prithee, Lord, some light! Man. Gods! gentlemen, d'ye think his Majesty Hath no substantial subjects? faith, ye err. Lords, we're as full of Jews as Egypt was, Before the Red-Sea-miracle: these Hebrews Agree, by contribution voluntary, To patch the garment of to-morrow's state And tinsel it with golden novelty. Gar. What! more exaction? more oppression? more— O, O, these Jews have doff'd the spirits of men, And, beast-like, brook the pannier and the goad! Now, by heaven's God! altho' a Christian, I'd rather see Alphonso don the helm And draw the sword, to free Spain from her locusts, The swarthy Moors, than meanly persecute These unoffending Israelites at home— Altho' I love them not. Alv. A scourge upon them! I loath the thieves; and bless Necessity That grips them in her talons. Gar. You have cause. Shoot me this sparrow! Come, sir; we'll to court, Having to do with these solemnities. [Exeunt Garcia and Alvaro. Man. This they call manly breeding, bearded manners: Now the gods send them barbers! He hath cause? To hate Jews' flesh? What cause? I know the cause: He loved a Jewess better than a Jew; But she, sir, with her pretty Hebrew nails Writ her religion on his Christian skin In red-line characters; and since that hap, The Devil and a Jew are one to him. Enter Reuben. Where go'st thou, son of Israel? Reu. Mind thy ways! What's that to thee! Man. Reuben, hast heard the news? Reu. Ay; ay; a curse upon ye Christians!—ay: We toil and sweat, that ye may squander; fie! What are your triumphs and your ceremonies To us? What, what to us—that we must pay for 'em? We labour honestly, give no offence, And yet ye rob us; fie upon ye! fie; Man. Dog! mend thy manners, or we'll have thee whipp'd! Or closely pinion'd in a pillory— A scare-crow for all grumblers. Dog! I say. Reu. I meant no treason. Blotches foul ye all! The curse of fire consume ye!—O, these imposts! Man. What is thy errand, Jew?—I ask again. Reu. And I reply again—What's that to thee? Man. Thou trudgest vainly; I can tell thine errand; Thou go'st to Xavier's, to consult for means To 'scape the levy; for he's prince among ye. Reu. Ay, by the Sabbath! 'tis a princely Jew! Man. Thou tramp'st in vain: The state needs money, and must have supply. Go! go! get shaved; thy beard offendeth me. Reu. I do not keep it growing for thy pleasure. Man. Well, get to Xavier: should you see his daughter, Commend my Lord Alvaro to her nails. Have thy chest ready, Reuben; 'tis too full Get thee a sickle, Jew, and reap thy chin; Thou'dst look more like a Christian, would'st thou shave. [Exit. Reu. That honest men should labor, to feed flies!— And not their need, but waste!—It must not be: Five hundred thousand dollars to be raised— And all from Jews! I say, it must not be: I'll hear of Xavier—he is bold and wise. [Exit. SCENE II. An Apartment in Xavier's House. Enter Xavier and Lopez. Xav. So many of my friends call'd here to day! That's something strange: you should not have denied me. Lop. I but obey'd your own injunction, sir, Which did desire unbroken privacy. Xav. Spake they of aught? Lop. They were most urgent, sir, To be admitted, to have word with you, Concerning some new edict of the king, Bearing on our persuasion. Xav. So! An edict? Admit the next that calls. Wait at the door. An edict, did you say? Lop. Ay, sir. Xav. What now?— What does my daughter with her time to day? Lop. She's in the chamber, sir, which fronts the east, Reading that story of ambitious love, Written in Spanish, which you chide her for. Xav. God bless her—and forbid that I should chide! Yet should she love the language of her sires Before the modern jargon: in our Hebrew There's matter for all hearts. Well, get thee in! [Exit Lopez. An edict!—that's a word for, persecution; Edict and persecution—they're the same; And have been, since we wept at Babylon; And shall be, till we gather us again In the divine Jerusalem foretold. O, Judah! thou art gone out from thyself; My country! thou'rt the shadow of a name; In these amusing erasures, Mr. Colman had evidently the fear of the Jews before his eyes. My countrymen! ye're scatter'd o'er the earth, And feed on those that hate ye; yet ye prosper, And are a mighty people, strong in gold— The sceptre of all kingdoms! Were ye gather'd, O, were ye gather'd, ye were terrible Within the world—and holy, and set up 'Mid the prime potentates: the curse of Heaven That hangs so dark and heavily upon ye Cannot endure for ever; and ye shall be, Ye shall be a proud nation once again— And have your prophets, princes, and your rulers, As in the time of old:—it is decreed! In these amusing erasures, Mr. Colman had evidently the fear of the Jews before his eyes. But I, the rightful heir of your great kings (Whose just inheritance were camps and thrones) Must live a stranger to your renovation; In these amusing erasures, Mr. Colman had evidently the fear of the Jews before his eyes. Find all my glory on the abject mart, And die uncrown'd among ye! Yet I reign; Reign in your hearts—in thousands of your hearts! And so, I have a glory; and being great Amid the wreck of greatness, live content. I marvel no one knocks: this edict haunts me, Like the pale coming of a wonted ghost! Enter Reuben. Reu. Good greeting to the love of Israel! Xav. Ha! Reuben? I am passing glad to see you! What is this edict, Reuben? burning? flaying? Exile? extortion?—Let me hear it!—Come! Reu. You know to-morrow is the festival That doth commemorate the Christians' battle— And that Alphonso's marriage to the princess Goes hand-in-hand with't—a twin ceremony! Xav. I do; go on. Reu. 'Twill be a rare one, and The charge excessive: have you heart to pay for't? Xav. Name me the sum—I know the sum is named; They're ever quick to save us calculation. Reu. Five hundred thousand crowns! Is it enough? Xav. 'Tis not the sum, tho' that is vast enough; 'Tis not the sum, Reuben—'tis not the sum! It is the principle, the system, Reuben, In which consists the wickedness o'the act And our great wrong, which if we tamely stoop to, We build a precedent, whose after use Shall strip us even to rawness—Lopez, ho! Enter Lopez. Get my good vestments ready; make them neat, And hang them in my study—presently. [Exit Lopez. Reuben, I will to court. I hate the king, Despite his royal courtesy of speech And specious bearing to me: that estate I held at Borja was my daughter's pride; She seldom weeps—yet wept at leaving it: 'Twas princely tyranny that forced me sell! Reu. Ay, and for half its worth—the mischief on't! Your goodly citizen had given double. Xav. I hate him, Reuben; yet I will to court, To beg reversion of this ominous edict— Cloud-black with woe to our fraternity. I've done him golden service frequently; And 'twas in private—of no public note; So have I more than common privilege, And I will use it for our common good— And shrewdly too. Reu. Our prophet be your speed! Enter Lopez. Ser. Some twenty merchants, sir, stand in the hall, Waiting your leisure. Xav. I will come to them. [Exit Lopez. Go with me, Reuben; help me don my vest; Courts even from Jews crave courtly ceremony— I would be stately, tho' I go to sue. O, note in me our country's downfall, Reuben: The kings of Judah were not wont to beg! [Exeunt. SCENE III. A Chamber of State, in the Palace. Flourish. Enter Alphonso and Isabella, with Garcia, Alvaro, Manrique, and Lords and Ladies, in attendance. Alph. Now will we teach ye, dames and gentlemen, To keep the cup of pleasure ever full, And yet be ever drinking: jocund mirth, Being gay tenant of the monarch's heart, Should in each subject bosom property A joyous home—fulfilling loyalty! What says our future queen? Isa. That I am happy, sir, Even to the top of joy; and truth is, swim In the deep tide of my felicity So giddily, 'tis marvel I not drown. Man. O, warily! your grace: if you should sink, Mirth's self goes souse—and we are mourners all. Alph. Good my Lord Garcia, and my Lord Alvaro! There lives but little pleasure in your eyes, Howe'er attemper'd be your spirits within: What's with you, friends? Alv. So please your majesty! The dusky vision of a cloud of Moors, Dark'ning our Spanish earth, was on my soul; Which made me think, 'twere better to be winning Another battle, than defeating Time By idle celebration of one past— And better fighting, sire, than marrying. Gar. And I, all duty to your majesty Still jewell'd in the casket of my heart, Was making question of that policy Which lays a burthen on a peaceful people, Who pay all dues of custom to the state, Merely to fill the gap which unthrift makes In the state's means. Alph. We are not for schooling, lords: 'Twere best ill-humour knew to keep at home; For out-doors, she's a pest. Alv. Heaven save the king! Gar. And may no cares await his majesty! [Exeunt Garcia and Alvaro. Alph. But that the pure white pleasure of the time Must have no stain of discord, we could find A corner in our heart for passion now! Darkness flies light, and so these lords are gone. Lead to the banquet! and let music play, Sweet as the heart-sweet music in our souls! Enter an Attendant. Atten. Sire, the Jew Xavier craves an audience. Alph. He squanders labor; but we'll hear him, sir. [Exit Attendant. Tarry, princess! I'd have thee see this Jew: He's prince and prophet of our Israelites; And hath a bearing of some royalty, Which much confirms him in that eminence. Isa. I've heard our ladies word him handsomely, Praising the noble presence of the Jew. Alph. I pray thee, note him—thou'rt a judge of men. Man. He's coming now, my liege. Enter Xavier. Alph. Thou'rt welcome, Xavier. Xav. I'm not quite sure of that. I thank your highness. Alph. Jew! thou forget'st thy wonted courtesy, Paying no homage to a lady by; And she, the bride elect of Arragon: Hath she thy tribute? Xav. I do think her fair; But since my youth, I've found fair oft is foul, Which knowledge moderates doting. Isa. O, sir Jew, Must I then be the flatterer? Trust me, Xavier, Thou look'st a very King of Israel; And I could deem that, twenty years ago, Thou had'st a Christian power o'er Christain maids, Infecting them with Jewish honesty. Xav. They've Christians plenty, dame, to serve the turn You drive at. Lucky! Strange beasts couple not. Man. But now thou art a very scurvy fellow; Nothing but Jew—Jew all, from top to toe— That gazing on the beauty of a princess, Kneel'st not in worship; thou art stiff-neck'd, Jew; And I could wish we were well rid of thee: Thy presence does inflict a circumcision. Xav. Oh! check thee, Xavier! Shall a yelp draw thunder?— Your majesty keeps curs. Alph. What says the noble Jew? Xav. That if you highness needs must have a cur Still yelping at your postern, when a friend Comes to the gate (and you have call'd me, friend) It were best muzzled; tho' no harm, 'tis nuisance. Isa. No anger, prithee, Jew; we were but merry. Xav. Madam, I would not be your merriment. Thus stands it, King!—I would have speech with you: If that your majesty have private leisure, Let it be now; if not, soon as may be;— This known—my business is peremptory, And prays for swift despatch. Alph. Lords, by your leave: And gentle princess! bid the banquet wait, Until our audience with the Jew is done. [Exeunt Isabella and Courtiers. How can I serve thee, Xavier? Xav. Is it possible? That you, my liege—a king, for chivalry By fame high-trumpeted, and with a soul Hereto deem'd honest and right honorable In all the level and rough ways of life— Can, in the whole world's face, inflict a wrong On a great body of industrious men; And with the guilt thereof hot in your soul— Your fingers itching for that wrong's foul profit— Unto that body's representative, Coming to plead on justice' strict behalf For mercy that's mere right—say, with cold eye And ignorant tongue—How can I serve thee, sir? By Judah's God! my liege, it makes me mad, And underfoot beats reverence! Alph. Honest Xavier, We are too happy now to quarrel with thee; Be temperate, Jew: that edict must have force. For Arragon to duck her stately head, And underpace worse kingdoms, were to ink Our regal annals with a filthy blot, Mark for the eternal future's contumely; And that she should do, if her annual rite, To which the world's eye turneth commenting, Lacking its wont, made shew of poverty. The state doth lack five-hundred-thousand crowns, The which she deigns to borrow of your tribe. Xav. Borrow! and, borrow!—'tis the word in vogue; But, pay comes never in your memories: I'm sick of that word, borrow! Alph. More respect! The state accepts assistance in that sum— From those who owe her debts of gratitude, For shelter and all best indulgencies; 'Tis needful, Jew—and so, our edict's firm. Xav. The money may be needful—not the edict; Recall the edict—you shall have the money. Alphonso—my dread liege!—I've done you service, I should be vain to boast; I lent you gold When you had private need, and much did fear Lest naked kingship should be subjects' scorn; And when your choice did point at my estate, You had it freely, sire. Alph. We bought it freely; But it was sold us with reluctance, Jew. Xav. You had it—it suffices: for my service— And waiting service sure may beg a crumb— I this entreat—annul me this black edict, Which points at all my nation thro' the earth, As men fit to be robb'd by proclamation; As legal victims for illegal outrage; And gives the cue to all earth's sovereignties To plunder us by warrant of enaction, And stifle outcry with the gag of law: Annul the edict, gracious Arragon! And here I undertake—by that good trust And deference my brethren render me— To raise the sum in private, and unvoiced Place it within your royal treasury; So shall you still enjoy the benefit, And we not whipt in open market-place With lash unmerited of hangman law— I kneel till I am answer'd. Alph. Rise! at once: We honor thee with much regard, good Jew; But our decrees, like those of that great power We represent on earth, never know change: The edict must stand firm! Xav. Beseech thee, no! Alph. Thou kneel'st in vain—we are not to be moved. Xav. Am I refused? Alph. Ay; by my sceptre! Jew. Xav. Why, then—my curses on thee! wanton king— And know, I speak with the descended voice Of Judah's and of Israel's thousand kings! Compared with whom...Oh! with the least of whom... Alphonso's but a petty magistrate! They curse thee in my cursing: may'st thou riot, Till pleasure rot thee! and thy end, be this .. Exile and death by subjects' rebel hands! Know too, we will not yield to this oppression; But will resist your thievish officers, And struggle to the death, before give up Our share in man's eternal privilege Of mine and thine; thus, fast establishing A proud example unto scatter'd Jewry How she may yet be terrible and free! Alph. Fool! ye would sink in Christendom's great sea, Like a few scatter'd rain-drops—dost thou brave us? Not only will we have five hundred thousand, But twenty times five hundred thousand crowns, If so we need: look to your houses! Jew; If we but think them pleasant—they are ours: Look to your steeds and women!—they are ours, If we but find them mettled to our liking: The skin that covers ye is only your's So long as is our pleasure! Thou may'st writhe, Knowing our power still greater than our threats: After to-morrow must the sum be paid, By virtue of our edict, to the State; If not, King Xavier! let your subjects look to 't. Xav. O, my indignant heart! how canst thou hold? Why dost not break—and send thy royal spirit, I'll-placed on earth, to seek its throne in Heaven? 'Tis true; 'tis true: we are defenceless men, And outrage may do with us what she will! Alph. Jew! Xav. Christian! Alph. Slave! Xav. Ay—King. Alph. Thou'rt idle, Xavier.— Thou has a daughter; she is voiced for fair;— Thou understand'st me, Jew?—she might do much; But do not think to rail us from our purpose! [Exit. Xav. Daughter!—my daughter?—did he say it?—Daughter!— As well we might, hanging a veil i'the air, Think to secrete the fiery-beaming sun From the amorous earth, as by impediment Of fence and wall, keep beauty from men's note, Towards it for ever prying. She hath dwelt In solitude—to her no solitude, Seeing her mind fills all vacuity With notions and bright beings of its own;— Or only with the serious of my tribe, Who see no beauty save in holiness; Yet Christian Lords have thrust them impudently To her pure presence, shaming but themselves— Her honor excellent as her's for whom The Patriarch served a two-fold 'prenticeship: And now, a kingly curiosity, Smit with description, dotes on my pure child!— I am unhappy now. Thou hast a daughter— Thou understand'st me—and she might do much!— O, filthy beast! as if my Rachel were A courtezan, and lewd minx for the sport!— Why, would he force her—as the Roman did, I'd kill her by the shambles, rather than— What was't?—She might do much!—I'll muse on that: She might do much? 'tis not unlikely—much! She might aspire to crowns—a Christian crown!— She might be very Queen of Arragon!— For with that glorious beauty of her youth, And that high-pitch'd ambition she is full of, She might so queen it o'er the amorous King, As to thrust by the feeble Isabel, Make instant quash o' the edict, turn the streams Of power and greatness towards her countrymen— And Saragossa make Jerusalem! All this might be; and, oh!—if all this were! She loves her nation; is ambitious—well? And her ambition's but a slip of mine— Why should not Rachel be the Queen she looks? Well! well!—my thoughts are very conjurors now! Let Princess Isabel go home and weep— Rachel shall be the Bride of Arragon! Enter Reuben. Reu. Xavier, what news? we are impatient for't. Your name did lend me entrance; what's the sentence? Xav. Reuben, go thou unto my secretary, And bid him straight write letters circular, Warning our merchants to prepare the sum Which the state calls for; and immediately— For't must be paid; we have no remedy. Reu. My share of't will go nigh to bankrupt me: Beshrew the thieves! Xav. I'll pay thy portion, Reuben; So, get thee gone—and see the thing be done, As I have told thee. Reu. O, how well in this Is shown thy kingly nature, royal Xavier! Yet, 'tis extortion—well, my lord, I go: I'd give them drachms of poison—not of gold! [Exit. Xav. 'Tis fix'd! 'tis fix'd!—her aim shall be the crown— And may the Guide of Israel prosper us! Oh! well I know, she'll leap to my intent; For she hath dreams of glorious destiny— And I but hold a substance to her view, For their proud spirit to fill and animate: This deed's the child o'the time—and shall be done; A Hebrew Queen must rule in Arragon! [Exit.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT THE SECOND. SCENE I. An apartment in Xavier's house. Enter Xavier and a Secretary. Xav. Those letters have been sent to all the merchants? Sec. They have, sir. Xav. Very good: know you the hour, And that precisely, at which the procession Of Jubilee and Marriage—bless the Bride!— Moves to the Temple of the Dam of Christ? That is, sir—when begins our merriment? For we will call it ours, seeing we pay for't. Sec. 'Tis named for twelve, but I should argue one— Knowing these Christians to the hour do nothing, Unless 'tis sleep. Xav. And now it wants of ten? Sec. Half of the dial. Xav. I thank you, sir: you're free. You'll not forget to send my daughter to me. Sec. I'll tell her, as I pass her chamber-door. Xav. That means, 'tis not a secretary's office To do an errand to his master's child. Ho! very well, sir;—tell her as you pass. [Exit Secretary. It follow'd me to bed, and kept me waking; It crept into my sleep, and held me dreaming; It rose with me at dawn, since nought else thinking. And this day opes a page of destiny, The turning of whose leaf must make all clear. 'Tis Rachel's footstep: I do know the voice of't— Uneven and slow—a down-heart argument: Her spirit lacks excitement—and shall have it. Enter Rachel. Rach. What is your pleasure, sir? Xav. To see you happy, And therefore am I grieved to mark you sad; To see you good, and therefore am I wretched To think that goodness mounts not in this world; To see you great, and therefore am I pain'd To feel our greatness poor. Would'st thou be great? Would'st thou have power? Rach. Am I not Xavier's daughter? Would I have power? My Sire, I have a power I'm mistress of my soul—and she that is so Is queen of a rich empire. Xav. Then why sad? Rach. Can I be merry, when my kinsmen groan Under this new-awaken'd tyranny? Can joy burn brightly in affection's eye, When eyes she loves are tear-dropp'd with dull woe? Should daughters smile, when noble fathers grieve? Tell me that edict is annull'd, my sire; Tell me that prelude to destruction's hell Plays not for Judah's children—and my face Shall tempt my father's lip to bathe in smiles: My sorrow's but the shadow of your own— Remove the substance, and the shade goes with it. Xav. My precious Rachel! I do glory in thee More than the Prophet in his Prophetess: Thou art design'd for work miraculous; And in thine inborn royalty of soul And outward-worn nobility, I read Annihilation of the King's decree, Glory and power to Spanish Israel, And vengeance full for every Christian wrong Our patience hath bent down to. Rach. 'Tis my thought; But by what magic can he read my thought? Xav. Attend me, Rachel: yesterday, the King, Giving that flat denial to my prayer, Did leave me with—Thou hast a daughter, Xavier; Fame words her passing fair—she might do much; And ended thus—Thou understand'st me? Xavier. Rach. Well, sir: 'tis very strange! Did he say this? Xav. As I have said. Rach. And what should come of this? Xav. If thou hast no great monitor within That answers with a quick predominance To that slow question, there is no reply That could enhance conception. Rach. O, make none: Thou pluck'st the dream out from my inmost heart, And show'st it even to my material eyes! What? if my gifts of nature took Alphonso— Have I thy leave to be a monarch's thrall? Xav. I would rather kill thee—but, Thou hast—to be a monarch's wedded bride! Thou hast—to be the Queen of Arragon! Thou hast—to turn the axe from Jewry's neck! Thou hast—to raise thy fallen countrymen! Thou hast—to do that, which if left undone, 'Twere treason to thyself, thy sire, and country! Rach. Then, noble father! harken to me now: I love Alphonso. Xav. Love!—thou can'st not, dreamer: Thou can'st not love whom thou hast never seen? Rach. Sir, not long since, ere Isabel came hither, I saw him, after martial exercise, Returning to his palace; and his person, Renown'd for majesty—with that fame coupled Which showers thick laurels on his princely brow— Did so bewitch my fancy-nourish'd heart, That I have doated on his semblance since; And tho' 'tis maddest folly—his near marriage With foreign Isabella, grieveth me— As I were all defrauded of a hope, Wild-fixed on the possession of my king! Xav. In faith, dear daughter! some would think thee mad. I see thou hast adorn'd thy hair to-day, And that thou hast thy walking-mantle on— What's in the moon?—Art for the Jubilee? Rach. O, sir, decline not from that earnestness With which you first did greet me on this theme! The God of Judah in two kindred hearts Hath lit one resolution; and to mine Lent other feelings, to urge on resolve To its last limit. Fare thee well, my sire: This edict shall be void—and Israel free; Or I am not the daughter of my lord, But a base farmhouse trull, for nothing meet Save the day's drudgery. Xav. Yet, stay! my child: Thou look'st not gracious with that mantle on. Rach. O, sir, leave that to me. Ay, smile so still! That Rachel from the spirit of her sire May catch the very life of her attempt, And urge her fortune's crescent to the full. Xav. I'll see thee forth: our mutual heart is read. Thy proud eye shows me, in an hour to come, Jew Xavier's child a queen in Christendom! [Exeunt. SCENE II. A Public Way. Enter Manrique and Two Lords. Man. The Lord Alvaro, and his testy friend, The Garcia, letting their self-wilfulness Outstrip respect, have forfeited their place In this day's state; whereat his majesty Hath sent for your good honours, to fill up The gap made by defection of those lords, With nobler worthiness. 1st Lord. We are much honour'd. 2d Lord. And burn to show our duty to his Grace. [Flourish of music at some distance without. Man. They have left the palace, and are this way bent. Our time is brief, lords, will you straight along? [Exeunt. Enter Rachel, with veil and mantle. Rach. The Queen of Arragon!—that's a brave title; Alphonso's wife!—ay, there my heart were crown'd; Deliverer of my countrymen!—if countrymen I may call those who have been robb'd of country, And make their home o'er all the desert world— That were a glory of like eminence With the male deed of Judith. Bless me, Heaven! And make my hopes, in their accomplishment, Thine own and Israel's glory: if I fail— Take back the breath of life thy pleasure gave me, For Rachel then hath nought to do on earth. [Martial music approaching without. Hark! they draw near; and soon my tide of life Must either flood to power, or ebb to death: Hope's sun upon the dial of my days Shows his meridian now—or there 'tis midnight And unintelligible shadow all. [Music near. He comes! I see him move. O, regal grace, How well thou sit'st upon the front of kings, Picturing to earth a supreme majesty! And fullest on the brows of Arragon Thou glowest in thine excellence of pomp. Why should that dame be there? Why should she not? My head drowns in my heart, and reason gasps: She pranks it royally; and yet, methinks, I could outstate her, had I stately means. [Flourish of trumpets without. I'll shroud me, and stand by. Enter, in procession, King, Isabella, Manrique, Lords, Ladies &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c. Alph. O, good, my lords! Ye fill up worthily a worthy place, And bring no loss with change. On to the temple! To celebrate the present with the past! And praise and offerings accomplish'd there, Remembrance of Toloza's prodigy And expectation of sweet marriage-bliss Shall make the day and night triumphant reel, Till mortal hearts pant glory spiritual! Love plants a beauty in the heart of things, And Fame doth color fresh old Time's grey locks And make his wrinkle-covered forehead smooth! On to the temple, ho! Rachel, advancing and kneeling. Rach. Great Arragon! A suppliant damsel, on her duteous knee, Entreats a moment's passing audience: Her life doth hang upon it; sire—her life! Alph. Such urgency? Speak, lady; we attend: A weaker adjuration scarce had staid us. Rach. My liege, I am a maiden of that race, Upon whose means of life—and, therefore, life— Your edict shall to-morrow bear so hard; And if no royal feeling in your heart Crown Mercy with a power executive, The fortunes of my kindred and myself Go all to wrack. Have mercy, Arragon. Man. When do you Jews keep Sabbath? Rach. 'Tis to the king I speak. Alph. Such pleading well might win the thing it begs; But to your people's idol, the Jew Xavier, We have made final answer. Lead along. Rach. Nay, at your feet, O King! I beg for mercy. Alph. Lead on! I say. Rach. (starting up) A moment yet, my liege Beggars in humble vestments prosper ill, And mercy smiles on robes that frowns on rags— Wilt hear me now? [Throwing off her veil and mantle, and appearing in rich attire. Man. That, by the gods! he will: Xavier puts all his irons in the fire. Isa. Why do we stay, my lord? Shall we go on? King. Not yet—O, beauty!—grace unparallel'd!— If that thou be'st a Jewess, I will swear, Even by that mystery where our creeds divide, There is no Christian in my kingdom like thee! Rach. The edict, mighty king! Reverse the edict; And here I kneel your grateful servant ever. King. Nay—rather, sweet one! bid us kneel to thee. O, such a flower should never stoop to the earth, Save where she spreads her velvet lap to kiss it! Thy name, dear maid? Rach. 'Tis Rachel, sire—a plain one; Not so my parentage: 'tis Xavier's daughter That bends before the king—low as her sire. King. Xavier is wise. That fame which vouch'd thee fair Spoke with a common and a vulgar mouth! 'Tis marvel that so rare a sun so long Hath slept behind the cloud of privacy. Thy beauty henceforth must beam forth i'the air, And on the night of eyes rain heavenly day! Xavier is shrewd—is shrewd. Rach. Beseech your grace! Is my prayer heard? or must I profitless Get to my home, and cry, heartbrokenly— Alphonso has no mercy, O my father! King. Lead on! my lords. Thy hand, sweet Rachel, come: We'll hear of thy petition by the way. Manrique, lead the princess. Isa. Sir, I'll walk alone, Since that the king hath chosen his company: I marvel that your grace should think to wed, Seeing you make so light of ceremony. [Exit, with attendants. King. Thou art a dangerous suppliant. Rach. Nay, my lord. King. And yet, it scarce may be: let me hear more— [Exeunt King and Rachel, and all but Manrique. Man. O yes, my liege—it may be; all may be: Kings that make law, make lawful. So, so, so! I would not wager on these nuptials now, And least of all would stake my head upon't: Alphonso is a true man-weathercock. Enter Xavier behind. My court-wise cue shall forswear razors, faith! And bless the twice-six tribes of Israel. The bait is taken; if he gorge the hook, To which he's apt—O, ho! I know the man— I see small reason underneath the sun Why Rachel should not step in Isabel's shoe, And Xavier (bless us!) be first minister Xavier (advancing and tapping Manrique on the shoulder.) Suppose he should? Man. Is't you, sir; did you speak? Xav. Suppose he should be what you say, my lord (For you're a lord, sir—I believe, a lord) Do you not think he'd whisk the flies away That in the court's best sunshine make a pest? Would you begone, sir? Man. Sir, I serve the nuptial, And but neglect my duty, lingering: Pardon me, noble Xavier. Xav. Sure, my lord. [Exit Manrique. The fawning of this Christian argues well. 'Twas excellently done! she stood in clouds, And doff'd them like the Deity of Day, When he aspires to his meridian! I saw him grasp her hand: 'tis well; tis well.— I know Alphonso: he is ta'en by the eye, But scarcely held by the heart; yet much may come of't: My Rachel is his kingdom's paragon; And such as she build empires in men's breasts That grow convulsion-proof!—There's peril in't— But sooner shall the sun lack living warmth, Than Rachel the all-holy fire of virtue!— There is no canker in the healthy bud!— So, from such peril, if such safe things come As freedom, strength, power, retribution, Unto God's chosen thro' wide Arragon— Peril's more safe than safety.—Expectation! Thou broodest like an eagle in my heart, Ready to soar i'th sun.—Hush! here's a wave That frets at what it chafes on! this is joy. [Retires. Enter Garcia and Alvaro. Gar. My lord, the king is at his pranks again; Those ill demeanours which take awe from crowns: The Jewess stood beside him at the altar, Whilst at the holy Mary's sacred shrine He offer'd up six standards of the Moors, Won at Toloza; and so parley'd with her With the broad meaning of his libertine eye, That the indignant princess veil'd her state; And unperform'd the nuptial ceremony— She left the Temple, weeping. Alv. What! not married? The plighted honor of Alphonso's vows, Made to her royal sire's ambassadors— And the just dignity of Arragon, Damn'd by a vulgar Jewess!—Like you this? 'Twill not end here. Xav. (Apart.) It shall not, by my soul! Gar. Sir, I do not; and very joyful am I That we threw up our places when we did; Else had our honours suffer'd, in allowance Of the king's insult to grave decency In this proceeding, which shall outrage quite The intercourse of nations; and, 'tis like, Set Christian against Christian, whilst the Moors Yet triumph in our country—O, 'tis foul! Our glad successors will have little envy. Alv. Faith! none, for me; my life unto a dog's— That edict will not hold! Gar. Nor would I have it: 'tis a tyranny I never loved, to mulct particular men For a state's service—and in her endeavour Rachel is, so, praiseworthy. Alv. Tut! she's a strumpet! Xav. (Coming sternly forward) That's a foul lie! my lord—a filthy lie! Gar. Keep back your sword! wouldst draw it on a Jew? Xav. I say, a wicked lie! an abject lie!— Were all your honours ten times multiplied, Your titles swollen as an Eastern king's, Your riches vast as ocean's, and your power Next even to His that breathed the universe— I'd tell you, tis a lie!—my daughter's pure!— Not all the banded kings of Christendom Could o'erthrow the high empire of her virtue!— You know it, Lord Alvaro—you, you know it:— She spurn'd you when your lordly vanity Approach'd her with a coxcomb's confidence— And she had slain you, had you dared too far! You know you've spoke a lie!—a foul-mouth'd lie Alv. Had I my will, I'd make thee carrion, And give thy flesh to hogs. Xav. Thy house their sty? Look to your own flesh, lord; it may smart yet. Gar. Jew! thou dost wax surpassing insolent And I can somewhat see into thy soul; But if thou think'st, by thy fair daughter's means, To pave the way for Jewish influence And lord it o'er one inch of Christendom, I say to thee, beware!—the end is, blood! Alv. Ay, by the saints! [Exeunt Garcia and Alvaro. Xav. Why, then—blood let it be! A term of power is all that man can have, Let power be long as life. But—my sweet child? They would not tread to earth that blushing flower? They would not flaw that precious diamond? Not drag death's cloud athwart that living star?— 'Twould be a way to kill me; but, too cruel: No! rather than a Christian's hand should shed The royal current of her Jewish blood, My own should do't, tho' doing were perdition! Why do I tarry, when that bark's afloat Of which I must be pilot? Well? good Reuben. Enter Reuben. What wondrous devil of joy possesseth thee? Reu. Thou'rt Israel's saviour, Xavier; ay, her fence, Her prop, her staff, her rock of adamant! I'm drunk with joy, I'm foolish—mad with joy! Thy daughter hath obtain'd a full release; Jewry rings with it—the sore edict's null; 'Tis nought, 'tis quash'd—we've nought to pay at all! Xav. Praise be to God! deep-hearted praise to God! Not for the 'scape from impost—but, from shame. Enter a Messenger. Mess. The king salutes you. Here are papers, sir, With which I was proceeding to your house: And this he says; at your most speedy leisure, He would be pleased to see you at the court— From whence the lady Rachel greeteth you. Xav. I will come speedily: Heaven save you! sir. [Exit Messenger. It is the written cancel of the edict: Go with it, Reuben; get it multiplied; And let it have quick circulation Throughout all Saragossa—that our triumph Be read by every eye that conn'd our shame. Reu. That will I, straight. But this is joyful news! [Exit. Xav. (Kneels.) I thank thee, Israel's God that thou hast made me The guardian of the least part of thy people; And if thy pleasure will her rising now, In Jewry's greatness shall thy glory mount— Temples shall rise to thee, and Israel sing Her Alleluias, as she sang of yore!—(Rises) Back, soul! to earth: I must be courtier now: Alphonso yet shall have the sum he needs; Ay, and from Christian coffers. Nought's to fear: Her soul is arm'd in Virtue's adamant— That the most trenchant sword of giant Guilt, Daring to strike, breaks idly into splinters! Now, then, for policy!—Ay, it shall be— That foreign princess must not thwart my child: Ambition, take thy scope!—I'll hold nought done, Till Rachel be the Queen of Arragon! [Exit.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT THE THIRD. SCENE I. Near the Palace. Enter Garcia and Alvaro. Gar. This Hebrew madam makes our Arragon Her pleasure and her spoil: all bow before her; People and nobles lacquey her alike, And the mere crown is all she wants of Queen: Nay, men already name the Hebrew Queen, And Xavier sways the nation's ministry. Alphonso in his dotage is gone mad, And his proud kingdom uses as a toy To please a wench's fancy; yet she stands In honour unassailable—that the King's passion Must die, or end in marriage. Alv. Marriage! Gar. Ay: The lady Isabella is despised; As if she were a garment half outworn, And not a bridal robe, trimm'd for the wearing— But ne'er put on. Be joyful, Arragon! Your Queen's a Jewess. Alv. Would to Heaven's God! My feet were on the upstart Xavier's neck; His daughter in my arms—I'd teach them both What honour is! Gar. I thought them unoffending— Peaceful; but give them claws and fangs, I find They'll tear like other brutes: it shall not last! Jews shall no longer be the chiefs of state, And mock our Holy Faith with blasphemy! Alv. They shall not, by the Cross!—they shall not, dogs!— What! Jews make levy upon Christians? pluck Our fortunes from us—Now, by all the Saints!— Gar. What royal sorrow's this strikes pity mute With witchcraft of its tears? The beauteous princess? Enter Isabella. Isa. I can endure no more: I've suffer'd long; Letting the duteous heart of loyal love Beat 'gainst the sense of injury; and now— After calm brooking of so many wrongs, Now to be banish'd, now!—it breaks my heart. Gar. Banished! O, gracious madam, speak again The king is not so clutch'd in by the devil, As to do this? Isa. He frowns me from his presence; Xavier looks death upon me as I pass, And Rachel—there is poison in the name!— Insults me with the triumph of her smile. I'd rather live on roots i' the wild woods, Than thus beside a throne!—my honour'd lords, I here commend my fortunes to your care: Take me where'er you will—I reck not where;— Back to my father's court—to exile, death! No future sorrow can exceed the past! Gar. O, royal lady! your good cause is ours. We will avenge thee; and thy royal sire, Shall need to stir no foot in thy behalf. Be this your comfort, the Jew strikes himself And this presumptuous levy he hath dared To make on Saragossa's citizens, To serve his daughter's fast extravagance, Fells him to earth: resistance is on foot; Alphonso's troops are out against the Moors; The city shall rise arm'd within the hour— And her ten thousand voices thunder death To the proud Jewess and her upstart sire! Alv. Ay, and to every cursed Israelite That taints our kingdom's air with villainy: How the Jew dogs will howl!—I hear them now. Isa. Amaze and joy burn brightly in my heart, But apprehension's breath doth shake the flame. Gar. He shall be hurtless; and his dignity In our revenges will but rise renew'd From its long cloud of slumber: rest content! Please you await the issue, in my house Of this great blow for justice, to which shelter A troop of friends shall guard your royalty. Isa. Even be it so, my lords: what else should be? My bliss and greatness in their infancy Have sicken'd, at the least—and well may die; Would I might too!—death is not misery. [Exeunt. SCENE II. A room in Xavier's house. Enter Xavier and Reuben. Xav. The Christians rise against it, and my power Sits quailing now: that courier was despatch'd At sunrise, was he not? Reu. He was, sir; even at dawn. Xav. And with him bore that signet of the king I furnish'd stealthily? Reu. He has it with him. Xav. On that man's speed, the fortunes and the lives Of all of Israel that's in Arragon Hang as in agony. Swift be his horse! For tho' he do out-gallop the wild wind— Fly like a leaf along the hurricane, He shall not ride with that rapidity Our need cries out for. I've one more resource: The princess fled the palace; she's waylaid, And in an hour shall be my prisoner, Despite the guard of Garcia, unto whom I know she goes for refuge: then, my child Hath her life sure; or a fair princess bleeds for't. Reu. A bold manœuvre!—thou art ever sage. Xav. Summon a thousand of my well-arm'd Jews! Let them surround my house, that once encaged, The royal bird escape not: see it done! I'll to the palace, ere the storm comes on: The rabble will scarce dare molest their king? Reu. I'll have the thousand station'd in an hour. Xav. In less! in less!—an hour is half an age, When in an hour life with all time may part! [Exit Reuben. I've been too sudden: I had thought my power Grew with a deeper root, than thus to bend So crouchingly to the first storm that rises To threat its branching sovereignty. Awhile, And Rachel had been Queen of Arragon!— The very marriage-day was fixed in secret!— This hasty levy, by the king and her Urg'd 'gainst my better sense, looks perilous: God grant it prove not Israel's overthrow! Re-enter Reuben. Reu. Xavier, the multitude surround the palace, Headed by Garcia and Alvaro:—well?— Some cry Alphonso! Xavier! some—some, Rachel! Death to the Jews! shout some—(sharp plagues upon 'em!) O, we are lost; all our rich profits' gone: We shall be flay'd of our great fortunes now. Xav. Silence! base, bearded merchant: hast thou summon'd Some thousand friends, as I commanded thee? Reu. Ay; they are mustering now. Xav. Quick let them be! I'll seek no palace, then! but gaol a princess; And tho' a Rachel outweighs twenty such— One royal life may be the bond of her's. [Exeunt. SCENE III. A Chamber in the Palace. Tumult without. Enter Rachel, in dismay. Rach. Alphonso! Xavier!—O, my king! my sire! Haste! or your Rachel shall be trod upon By rebel lords and base mechanic churls. That fatal measure is the cause of this; And Xavier's wisdom augur'd prophet like.— Enter Manrique, hastily. Save me! Manrique; guard me! counsel me!— Is there no shelter from this hideous death? Man. Madam, I scarcely can advise myself: To your own prudence, therefore, I commend you; Which, if it save you, is miraculous. Rach. Out of my sight! thou shadow of a man: Thou art an arrant coward, Lord Manrique— And never coward was a woman's friend! Man. Call on the king—perhaps he'll serve you, Madam; For I must fortify your enemies. Rach. Away! thy weakness shames the weaker side. [Exit Manrique. They come! they come!—What ho!—Alphonso, ho!— The voice of Rachel can allure no more. Enter Garcia and Alvaro, followed by a crowd of citizens, with drawn swords. Gar. The king's secure: Alvaro, seek the Jew; And I will deal with this gay upstart here. Alv. I'll rest not, till he's shorter by the head! Rach. O, he is guarded by the omnipotent God! Thou durst not slay him, thou false Christian lord! [Exit Alvaro, with a party of Citizens. Gar. Jewess! repent thy sins, and pray to Christ, And make thy choosing between Heaven and Hell; For thou must die. Rach. 'Tis false; I must not die: Thou art too noble, Garcia, on my soul! To slay a woman that ne'er injured thee. Gar. Traitress! that art a curse to Christendom, Kneel to thy fate! Citizens (advancing) Strike down the traitress—strike— Alph. (rushing in) Villains! stand back: here, Rachel—in my arms!— [She struggles into his arms Use stronger bolts, Sirs, when ye'd gaol a king! Now, valiant gentlemen! now, loyal subjects! Strike your bold daggers to a woman's heart, Even thro' the breast of your anointed king! Enter a Lord. Lord Rescue, my lord; the royal Isabella Hath been waylaid and taken by the Jews: Such is the cry. Gar. Ha! Citizens (without) Slay him, spare him not! Enter Reuben, through the Citizens. Reub. I will come thro', though dagger-stuck!—a porcupine! Lay not a hand upon my master's daughter; Molest her not; harm not the pride of Judah! Your Isabel is fast in Xavier's hands, And dies, if one of you but touch his child! Rach. (breaking exultingly from the king) Who stirs, to stain him in that Isabel's blood? Rachel hath left her shelter; kill her now! O, my great father, how thy master-spirit Hath ta'en this giant danger by the throat, And laid it breathless! Christian gentlemen, What think ye of our Jewish policy? Your daggers! come, I will not flinch at all! Alph. (advancing, and taking Rachel by the hand) Be silent, Rachel; this cannot endure: I am awoke now from a perilous sleep, Which I have past in luxury of dreams, Neglecting the realities of life; Ever in absence from the battle-field, Where Christian glory springs from Infidel blood; And leaving Arragon to be controll'd By hands which, by her birthright, she abhors. List to me, boist'rous and rebellious men: By my great ancestor, The Battailer, Who on these towers install'd triumphantly The ever-blessed and eternal Cross, We swear ye shall have justice: sheath your swords. Gar. 'Tis all we seek, my liege: put up your weapons. [They sheath their swords. Rach. Parley with traitors? Is this King Alphonso? Alph. Be silent, Rachel: you have said too much; And that you utter'd 'tis resolves me now. We speak, Sirs, from our justice, not our fears: Our levy on your fortunes we recall; And henceforth your own loyal loves shall tax you, Unto our need's nought overstrain'd extent: We pardon your rebellion; and yet more, To show in all indulgent sovereignty, We banish from the soil of Arragon Xavier and all his Hebrew tributaries; Ay, every Jew and Jewess in the land; She not excepted, in whose banishment Our joys are exiles: Rachel, get thee gone! Gar. O, royal Arragon, we kneel before thee; And gratefully thus offer up our hearts Unto your majesty, for this free grace, Which so shall strengthen you in subjects' love, That all the world will cry of Arragon— Behold a king, now, fenced with adamant! Alph. Arise, my lords; there is no more to beg: But learn ye—not one drop of Hebrew blood, In execution of our stern decree, Must there be shed: this look to, on your lives! Gar. My liege, it shall be heeded faithfully; So flow in health the blood of Christendom! Alph. Go then, my lord, and hush the city's heart Before it heave to bursting; and take order, You and my lord Alvaro, both of whom We reinstate in your high offices, For the Jews' banishment. What is there more? Gar. All shall be done as you command, my liege! And from the Hebrews will we rescue her Who should be your throne's grace—the gentle princess. Alph. We did not speak of that; but do your will. Leave us; our word is past. Gar. Heaven keep your grace! [Exeunt Garcia and Citizens. Alph. From his own passions and you worthy monarchs; For now Alphonso is his subjects' subject: Where is Manrique? What dost stay for, Jew? Reub. To do my bidding to lord Xavier's daughter; And not for all the kings in Christendom Will Reuben budge a foot, till she desire. Alph. And art not gone? Why should'st thou tarry, Rachel? Rach. (waving Reuben off) [Exit Reuben. She that doth sleep in sunshine, amid flowers, Woke by the riot of the hurricane, Or the dread-volley'd thunder, shrinks within Her inmost self, and trembles; but not moves: 'Tis so with Rachel, sire. Alph. Oh! quit my sight: Thine eyes are treach'rous beacons, towards which steering, I, That am the royal pilot of the state, Do wreck the state, and all my freight of glory, And am nigh drowned in the perilous sea. Tempt me no more; but if Alphonso's fame, The quiet of the realm—nay, thine own life, With that of thine all-too-ambitious sire, Which falling in one scale, make love-griefs light i'the other, Have any heed from thee, forsake me now: Be to my eyes, as if thou ne'er hadst been; Or, at the most, a thought-made-visible dream Of some sweet past. Begone! speak not a word; Lest that thy witchcraft make a perjurer of me. Rach. Alphonso is a king. Alph. And being a king, Must look he forfeit not that loyalty Which holds him kingly. Rach. He is not a king That hath not the prerogative of kings. Alphonso hath not; every upstart subject Plants his base will above his sovereign's; Says thus and thus his pleasures shall be shaped— Thus shall he walk, eat, sleep, and thus be clothed; Thus shall he speak; thus see. Know this, O king! My father hath more royalty than thou; For many tremble at his beck and nod, And none dare dictate to his word, or deed. King. Our doting love for thee hath darken'd us, And set him shining in our cast-off state: Thou dost speak haughtily. Away! Rach. (falling at the King's feet) Never! By all thy vows of love, my royal lord, When thou hast named me thy soul's inner spirit; When thou hast call'd me thy dear Hebrew queen, And sworn thy state's crown, as thy life's, was mine! I do implore thee, drive not from their homes My ever-persecuted countrymen; O, scatter not those bees, hived in thy kingdom, Expelling them from all their labour'd store, To perish in the barren winter-air Of stranger lands—O, do not, gracious sire! I will go forth, the sacrifice for all; And in atonement for that envied little Of power which we poor outcasts have enjoy'd, I will die starving in some wilderness— Ay, in the worst of deserts—the drear waste Of all mankind's abandonment; but spare— O, spare my father and my countrymen! King. You rack my heart; Rachel, it cannot be: It is to save their lives I have done this, And thine—more dear to me than all. Away! Thou shalt hear of me, Rachel; do not fear it; And yet our marriage shall be solemnized! And thy pure, honor-guarded beauty shine The star of Arragon!—Yield to the time, And go at once: this passion tortures me! Rach. Yet hear me, sire: by thy own dignity! Alph. Tempter, away! I'm powerless; and my will Comes not within the account: I prithee, hence. Manrique, ho! Raph. Is't final? Am I spurn'd? King. O, get thee hence, sweet! and preserve thy life, And leave Alphonso of his love to die: 'Tis in our destiny; 'tis fix'd—go, go. Manrique! Rach. I will plead no further—no! Xavier, disdain not thy too grovelling child, That hath forgot her dignity and thine, By crouching to this Christian. Sir, I go; And leave thee to that lowest slavery Which the earth knows, the slavery of kings To their mechanic subjects. Never, perhaps, did the sub-licenser display his acute discernment to more advantage than in his expulsion of this passage: he is gifted with a miraculous tact in these matters. Thou hast kill'd me; Absence will be my death; and my wrong'd shade Shall haunt thee in thy camp and cabinet, In thy void state, and on thy slavish throne! I'm the world's exile, banish'd to the grave; Banish'd by thee, who vow'd to shelter me From all the plagues of body and of soul Engender'd by the elements and man. My grave shall give forth an eternal voice Of torture to thy heart! O, cruel king! Thus to turn from me: I can ne'er brook this. Come, welcome death! for nothing now is left To Rachel in this cold and desolate world. [Exit. King. She's gone; and my bow'd crown sits firmer here: Another breath of passionate entreaty Had made me violate my force-wrung oath, And bent my sceptre to the crack of breaking. Would I had left the Moors sans molestation, And kept my troops at home! Never let monarchy Forego its guard; power's slip is death to will: The lesson learn'd shall be remembered, And on the near'st occasion, practised too. Here again the licenser dazzles us. Manrique, ho! [Exit. SCENE IV. Within the grounds of Xavier's house. Enter Garcia, Alvaro and Citizens. Alv. No blood? Gar. Their banishment suffices; not a drop; I'm pledg'd for't to the king; nor break my oath, Come of't what may. Alv. I'll tell thee what will come of't: Xavier hath garrison'd his house with Jews; And we, in our attempt upon his life Have been defeated, wounded, driven back; And, look! the infuriate Hebrews are upon us! No blood, did'st say? Gar. No drop! I swear, my lord. Enter Xavier, followed by Reuben and other Jews, armed. Xav. Stand! till I bid thee strike—be not too hot. Out of my gates, ye Christian woman-slayers! On whose ferocious hearts, nor streaming locks, Lustrous as sun-set, nor heaven-kindred eyes, Nor dew'd-rose cheeks, nor beauty-breathing lips, Love-rounded bosom, nor the delicate hands Of ladies, clasp'd and trickling piteously, Washed by the tears of anguish; ye, whose hearts, All these—that well might move the brutes o' the wild— Move not at all—out, out of Xavier's gates! Or shall his garden-flowers drip with your blood? Alv. Thou damned Jew! thou royal, righteous dog! So perfectly I hate thee, were thy life Cased in by mine, I'd pierce it to come at thee! Down with him! citizens; set free the princess! Gar. Hold! by the virtue of mine office, hold! Xavier, thou know'st the sentence of the king: Thy servant, Reuben, will have told it thee. Xav. Sir, I know many things, which though unknown, My soul would not be more unalterable: Time must we have to move to banishment, Time must we have to render up the princess; And in the gap of time, oft chance is thrust, To prove fore-knowledge futile: where's my daughter? Gar. Safe, sir; for us. Xav. I thank my captive—safe: When she is in my arms, I'll talk of ransom. [Noise without. Enter Rachel. Rach. (As if speaking to the rabble without) Dare not to follow further, filthy scum! Ye common dirt! ye cannot soil me now: Lo! I take shelter in a father's arms. Xav. Go, drive them from my gates! [Exit part of the Jews. Here rest thee, child; And like a wild-flower, on this sheltering rock Smile at the storm! Rach. I do, my lord; I do. Gar. My Lord Alvaro, by my honor—no! I raise my sword against it; I have sworn. Alv. Turn Jew—I care not. Christians, rush upon'em There is no fence 'gainst charms, the witch alive— Kill her! and ye are safe. [They advance to kill Rachel—Garcia restrains them. Xav. Base blood-hounds, back! Molest her with a touch, a breath, a glance— If I but wave this hand to yonder point, Off goes your Isabel's head! Now; who will stir? [They fall back. Alv. Cowards! Gar. I thank ye, citizens: proud Jew! Now, hear the sentence; three days and their nights Are given ye to depart from Arragon, With all that ye possess; that time expired, If aught remains of Hebrew property, It falls to the state; and those that linger, die! And more, know this: if by to-morrow's sun-set The royal Isabel be not rendered up In health and safety, not a Jew shall live; For we will lead the banded citizens, With sword and fire, to slaughter and consume Ye and your habitations. Xav. If I yield her, 'Twill be in safety, Christian; but, for health, I cannot answer for her highness' health. Gar. Well, Jew; look to't: my deed pursues my word; And once again, I warn ye to beware, For ye stand verging on a bloody death! Lead hence, my friends. Alv. Garcia, attend my word— You'll grieve for this forbearance, speedily. Gar. Sir, I have sworn an oath. Lead hence, my friends. [Exeunt Garcia, Alvaro and Citizens. Xav. Follow them, Reuben; treble-bolt my gates; And there hold watchful sentry thro' the night. Reu. I will, I will: O, noble Xavier, trust me— Reuben could weep, could weep with very joy, To see thee and thy daughter still preserved To be the fence and pride of Israel! If but that messenger keep up the gallop, Our sun to-morrow may rise very cloudless; Let him ride so; and after, break his neck— He cannot live to do a better thing. Xav. Amen! good Reuben. Friends I thank ye all. [Exeunt Reuben and Jews. Rachel! Rach. My father? Xav. Come, arouse thee, daughter: Thou'rt very pale and very silent, Rachel; And I part fear the verdure of thy soul Hath been much blighted by one passing storm; That resolution in your woman's heart— By love and high ambition palaced there— Is somewhat reeling from her constancy: I should be loath to deem thee feeble, girl. Rach. I've been upon the dark brink of the grave; A hundred swords were thirsty for my blood— And death, think what we will, is terrible— I have been hurl'd from a most mountainous And giddy elevation of delight, To the low valley and drear depths of woe; Arragon's King and Rachel's high heart's god Hath shut me from his throne and from his heart; I look'd to wear a crown, where now are ashes— My father and my countrymen are doom'd To horrible exile; I'm in hourly fear Even for his honoured life, their lives—my own! O far from wondering to see me faint, Sire, thou should'st marvel that I live at all! Xav. Is this the fearless Rachel, Xavier's daughter? The pure descendant of great Israel's Kings? The chosen of Heaven to raise her countrymen? O, then, indeed! the time is come again When that our wives and daughters, cattle, homes, Our very skins, are Christian property— As once Alphonso said—for which I hate him! Hate him, as I would have thee hate him, Rachel— Thou should'st not love that foe of Israel. Rach. O, would I did not love him!—'tis my heart That, beating, shakes the fix'd strength of my soul. Xar. Daughter! bethink thee, how sublime we stand; The beacons whereby many thousand lives Direct their sail for safety, if we suffer Our light to be extinguished—O, bethink thee! The bark of Jewry will be wreck'd for ever. Rach. What should be done? Xav. This should be done, Blest Rachel; At early morn seek audience of the King; Kneeling, with tears and passionate entreaty, Made by thy beauty heavenly eloquent, Plead, till relenting he recalls his sentence Of banishment against us. Fear not; that Necessity of which he makes a merit And grants whate'er his riotous subjects would, I will subvert, if fortune wrong me not; And a most inwardly-prophetic spirit Tells me we triumph!—that the crown is thine, If thou dar'st snatch it!— Rach. It shall be attempted; And on the event hangs Rachel's life, or death. For, sire, she could not brook a second downfall— And such would failure be; I will attempt it! Xav. Ay; and if any virtue live in prayer, If any blessing in a righteous cause, The true sense of this passage might be thought “adapted to the meanest capacity,” did not the distinguished Lincenser's ominous veto clearly prove the contrary. Thou'lt issue from the attempt fair-garlanded With all the flowers of praise that crown success. Let not thy love aught blind thy patriotism; But gaze on Jewry with clear-seeing eye, Till she on thee doth glance triumphantly! Meantime, I hold the princess prisoner, For warrant of thy safety. Dear! let's in: We'll turn this banishment to firm estate, And the sweet bird of our prosperity Shall sing high songs again: the world shall know My Rachel doth but rise from overthrow! [Exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT THE FOURTH. SCENE I. A chamber in Xavier's house, with a casement, overlooking the Ebro. Enter Isabella and an attendant Jewess. Isa. Kind girl! thou cheer'st the sorrows of my prison; And of a princess hast the affections won, By delicate attentions—such as make Happiest life swifter, and sad days less slow; I'll think the better of thy race for this Long as I live; or Jew, or Christian— In the kind heart grows true fidelity; And amiable virtue has no creed And owns no sect. I thank thee, gentle girl. Jew. Madam, that service that rewards itself, Takes thanks, for bounty too superfluous: Would I could do your grace more benefit! Isa. And that thou may'st, perchance. Now, leave me, dear! For I have many thoughts that should be lonely. I'll call thee if I want thee: love me, girl. Jew. Tell me to love myself—there is like need. [Exit. Isa. I might not think, with Rachel's hated name, Form, voice and feature in my memory, I e'er could love a Jewess; but this maiden Hath so heart-dew'd my hours of solitude With tears and smiles of kindness, that my nature Turns answeringly to hers. O, much the need I yet may have of her sweet charity! The morn advances; and the Ebro glides Beneath my casement, free and happily; But, ah! not so the river of my life! How is't I still am here? close prisoner To the stern upstart of a race despised, When that the honor of the king and nobles Goes with my freedom? I imagine all things, And knowing nothing, am bewildered. Enter Xavier. Xav. Your pardon, madam; is your highness well? Isa. Impudent Hebrew! What's my health to thee? Xav. More than your grace would dream of, credit me; And so I have come early to enquire: Whene'er my daughter's safety ransoms thee, Lord Garcia the redemption sanctions not, If thou be sick: I pray your grace, keep well. Isa. Am I to be a base Jew's merriment? Xav. Madam, I once was yours; the wheel's gone round: But, did you know what news of life, or death Is moving toward me on the dial's hand, You'd wonder at my mirth. You're very fair: I marvel that Alphonso loves thee not;— But then, my daughter's beauty is a flower That outblows all Spain's garden. Yet, you're fair. Isa. How I despise thy vulgar triumph! Jew; Thee and thy daughter utterly despise! And the king's fault shows more unworthily In loving her, than in rejecting me. Take off thy rude glance from my person, Jew! And tell me how thou dar'st with thy vile hands Chain here a Christian princess! Xav. Indeed—'tis bold. Enter Reuben. Reu. The messenger is back; and at his heels Compliance with the mandate which he bore (By the king's signet witness'd from the king) Is moving rapidly. Xav. The passions'-plaything, Expecting life, or death—receiving life, As I do now, would laugh, weep, leap, fall down And rend the welkin with his ecstacy! But I will tarry till a silent hour; And then kneel down, and lift my joy in praise And prayer unto the king of Israel! Madam, I've that will carry me abroad; But this, my kinsman and my faithful servant, Will render thee all dues of ceremony, That may beseem your state. Reu. Madam, I will. Isa. I'd rather be attended by a bear, Or the most hideous ape that screams i' the wild, Than this thy vulgar, bearded infidel! I'm prisoner at the peril of thy life; And prayers for vengeance from a royal lip Rise not in vain to Heaven! I'd be alone: Thy death will free me—and my freedom's near. [Exit. Xav. Death being freedom, dame, it may be near. Reuben, be vigilant; she flatters thee— Let thy attentions mark thy gratitude. The city was most quiet thro' the night— Was it not, Reuben? Reu. Nought of tumult stirring; And not a Hebrew, nor a Hebrew's house Did suffer molestation. Xav. The more safe, Christians and Christian dwellings. Be thou watchful! Reu. If she escape from Reuben, I will forfeit That Reuben's life—his monies! which is more. [Exit. Xav. Now, I'll go haste my Rachel to the king: Those lords, I know, have had conditions drawn Of government, the which 'tis their intent To force Alphonso sign: this shall work well, And gall resentment; then my daughter comes— And that's approaching which shall lend him power To wreak his vengeance and his love to the height;— Then, where's the cloud that dare shut out my light? [Exit. SCENE II. A room of state in the palace, with throne &amp;c. Enter Alphonso and Manrique. Alph. Conditions! what conditions? Back! Manrique; Say that the king will seal to no conditions That chain the free hand of his government: We will not see them; we are busy—sick; Feign what excuse you will. Man. Your majesty But holds your greatness at a just account, Not to let subjects dictate: place is place; And those who know not, must be taught the rule Of each man in his sphere. I'll tell my lords Your majesty is indisposed to-day. Alph. Tell them, we will not listen—'twill suffice. [Exit Manrique. Oh! Rachel—thou wert born to be my curse, Even as my bliss—a honey that is poison; Thine absence weighs so heavy on my heart, That all cares else fall on me scarce perceived. O, for my troops! my troops!—Small ceremony, Enter Garcia and Alvaro. Insolent lords! Alv. Not hear thy ministers! My liege, 'tis needful, then, we force the leave! The tempest intermits—'tis not o'erpast. Gar. But in the grace of your great Majesty Lives that shall make it harmless: in this parchment There stand engross'd some small indulgences Of rule and privilege to lords and people— Subscribing which, restoring the wrong'd princess, And putting in full force the Hebrews' doom, My liege in the rich circle of his crown Resets the jewel of his people's love. Alph. Certes, 'tis fit the people be indulged: Perchance, they'd use our chambers and our gardens, To eat, and drink, and take their pleasures in? Be sure they shall; “indulgence” is the word: Trench'd they upon aristocratic power, What would my lords say then?—then would it be— ‘Vile herd,’ the ‘common nothing,’ ‘idiot brutes;’ Now 'tis ‘the people’—and, ‘their majesty’! Alv. Will't please your highness sign the instrument? Alph. Ay, without reading, sir—a royal custom. An evidence of the acute loyalty of the Deputy-Licenser! Gar. Not so, my liege; I do beseech thee, read; And seeing the great need and wisdom of't, You'll grant without ado. We'll leave you, Sire, And to your prescence render us anon, To know your further pleasure. Alph. As you will. [Exeunt Garcia and Alvaro. It is as if the oak bow'd to the bushes! There's not a slave in all my Arragon So slavish as the King of Arragon!— Let's see this instrument—Oh! flower-sweet Rachel, Would thou hadst pleaded more! then hadst thou triumph'd; And tho' thy triumph had been death to both, Still death is peace to this intense desire, Whose fire is its own fuel. O, come now! And snatch my sight from this vile document— Wherein I read the downfall of a king, Written by menial hands—to thy proud eyes, Wherein my soul hath ceaseless coronation! Rach. (Entering by a secret door) The spring is faithful of this secret door— And here I stand, like to a sudden spirit, Unheard—unseen. 'Tis he! I cannot speak. Alph. In thy full beauty glance before me now! Step like a seraph from the veil o' the air! And I will tread this parchment to the earth, And own no sovereign's sovereign but my love! Rach. At my lord's wish. Alph. I am a sorcerer! The spirit I invoked is conjured up!— Rachel, I see thee near, and love thee near; But yet this parchment falls not from my hand, And no excessive joy posseseth me: But grief, quick grief, and apprehension sad; For what can come of this, tho' thou be here? Rach. My liege! three days are given us to depart, And one is gone; that, two brief days are left For me to part with all that's dear on earth;— My native Arragon, to whose Christian soil My soul clings with a fondness that's religion; My cherish'd home; my morn and evening haunts, Where my ambition lit me to my love— My love to my ambition; and, oh! torture— From thee, the royal monarch of my heart, In whose most regal splendour I so bask'd, As to shine sovereignly with borrow'd light: Two little days!—Oh! let me use them, king; Else is no joy left in eternity. Alph. Thy sire goes with thee. Rach. Ay: heaven shield us both! O, my dear lord! upon thy lips but now Was heavenly music, that did utter love, Tranced to adoring, for unworthy me; Or else my ear was cheated; or my love, Pining into delirium, dream'd it heard; You call'd on me—I came—and sure, to stay? Alph. For ever! were Alphonso that he was; But all things meet to urge thy speedy flight From Arragon and death: what should I be— Rach. A king! sire; be a king! dare to assume That high prerogative of ample will, Which is a monarch's birthright; let not slaves Rebel not only 'gainst your hand, but heart; Hold your affections free; love whom you will; And wear again your exiled dignity, Redeeming her you love from banishment! Alph. Life of my heart! O, know you not, my word, My pledge, my truth—the honour of a king, Are seal'd upon the sentence? Dearer yet, Your safety and your life are centred in't. Rach. At length, I feel my pleading is in vain; Poor Rachel's heart may break—Alphonso cares not: Thus, then, I spend the value of my life— Come, death! but never, hideous banishment! [She draws a dagger, and offers to stab herself. Alph. Give me the dagger—desperate creature! give— Thou wouldst be Beauty's beauteous suicide. I will revoke the sentence, come what may! Oh! let my crown and sceptre rot i' the dust! I'll change them for a cap and simple staff; My robes for a grey vest, and my proud throne For the rush chair whereon the cottager Sits the most happy king of his own heart: There will I reign—and thou my empire, Rachel! Rach. To the most barren desert—the drear'st cave That foreshows hell's feign'd gloom upon the earth, I'll follow thee! if need; and thou shalt still Call me thy Hebrew queen. My heart's a spirit! King. What have I said? I am the woman here— And hold for real the sweet things I dream: It cannot be; the sentence must stand firm; Against the nobles and the people join'd, What power have I?—My troops are far away— [Martial music at a distance. Rach. Ha! King. Is't imagination?—God of War! Thou steel-invested and life-wasting Mars! Thy truant son bows homage at thy breath. Those trumpets thunder'd o'er Toloza's fight, When I from thee won high appellative!— [Music nearer. Is the sound spectred in the atmosphere?— Dream I?—It peals again! My troops are here! [March continues: part of the troops enter, pay homage, and line the apartment—then: Enter Xavier. He kneels, and places the King's signet and the mandate for their recall, in Alphonso's hands. Xav. Have I done well? King. Bold Jew! didst thou do this? Xav. Monarch! thy servant did: hath he done well? King. For which thou shalt have honour all thy life; Thou hast the art to make a king a king! If now our subjects feel the yoke of rule, Let them not wince—they've taught us tyranny. Call in our court!—We reinstate thee, Xavier, In thy high office; and our rebel nobles Cast to the dust! thy people we set free From doom of exile, and their wealth and persons Fence with protection of this warlike state. Xav. For which, their hearts shall bless Alphonso's name; Their hands speak thanks with deeds, when he commands— And heaven look down in grace on Arragon! Alph. (To Rachel.) Kneel not! for thou art greater than thy king. Enter Courtiers. Most welcome, each! Dearest, to your high place! [He leads her to the throne. Bear witness all! to Rachel we commit Our crown, and sceptre, and sway absolute; Whilst we take rest from cares of government: Obey her as ourself—thus on our seat Throned in the pomp of queenly majesty! And know 'tis our intent, in fitting time, To wed and crown her Queen of Arragon. Xav. First, let a father kneel!—not to his daughter— But to the delegated majesty Of this great kingdom: who dares otherwise? [Xavier and Courtiers kneel. Rach. Will you not sit, my lord? Alph. Nay; reign alone: Thou shalt be absolute! And now, fair queen! Power dominant of Arragon—to this, This parchment of conditions, this base clog— Meant to restrict the birthright of my crown— Fix thy disdain: the lords return anon; Give them such answer as befits the king Reigning in thee. Alphonso 'waits thee, Rachel: This is his heart's day of half shower, half sun; And thou its rainbow, that with glorious beauty Gives covenant of joy—sky-tinted hope, That lives in the sun of things.—Away! my lords: Take order for the chase!—Bird pleasure now Shall mark that sadness crawls, and wonder how. [Flourish; exeunt King and part of the Courtiers and Soldiers; the rest remaining, in attendance and guard, with Rachel. Xav. A silence, felt as that which broods i'the stars In moonless heaven, falls on my daughter's heart; A cloud of glory shades her. Ho! my lord. Enter Manrique. Man. Madam, my lords, the Garcia and Alvaro, Await the audience. Rach. Is't to me you speak? Who is't that speaks? O, I remember thee— And now my soul soars living to her place! Art thou not he, who when a woman cried On thee for succour, in an hour of need, Didst cowardly skulk aback?—Art thou not he? Xav. Sweet Rachel, sure not he?—he's very brave. Man. Madam, it was a fault; and all my life Hereafter dedicate to your sweet service, Must make amends for't: I am awed before you; And that divinity of nature in you Constrains me even to worship. Rach. Even so? Out of my sight! [Exit Manrique. Xav. They come! my enemies come! O, what a triumph sits wing'd upon my heart! Daughter, be all thyself—I'm at thy side. [Leans on the throne, at Rachel's righthand. Rach. Thy blood is in my veins; and a king's sceptre In my firm hand. Enter Alvaro and Citizens. Alv. Thy faithful subjects, sire— Now, God of Heaven! what infamy is this? Enter Garcia and other Citizens. Gar. Hath the king signed—O, Garcia's eyes are mock'd! His sight's the fool of fear. Rach. (Rising) What! are ye stone?— Do ye not know me?—I am Xavier's daughter— Rachel, the Jewess!—not your queen, but greater!— She that's omnipotent in Arragon!— Acts with Alphonso's power—speaks with his voice! Alvaro, look on Xavier!—thoud'st have slain him; Garcia, thy coward sword was at my heart; I fill a guarded and despotic throne— Do ye not quail with terror? Alv. Gods! gods! gods! Gar. That this should be! Rach. Ye are degraded, lords— Pull'd down from your high places!—And to this— This insolent-writ rebellion, this vile breath Raised 'gainst the sky of power, this petty scrawl— Thus I make answer as befits the king Whose greatness speaks by me; thus, in the dust! Low as ye shall be, Christian murderers! [Dashes the parchment at their feet. Now, get ye hence! and dread what is to come! [Descends the steps of the throne, as going. Xav. Most noble Christians! why, ye stand amazed! Three days ye gave us to depart, my lords; We had been ungrateful not to use them well: The princess I will not give up by sunset— That's she you'd have for queen—so, sword and fire And banded citizens must serve ye now, To kill poor Jews, and burn their silent homes: I prithee, set about it—and by times, Lest that ye lose the advantage—loftier necks Have crouch'd beneath the tread of Israel! Vengeance, long sleeping, shall now wake for ever— And shake her red locks in the face of wrong! Attend us, ho! My royal daughter, come! [Flourish; exeunt all in due array. Garcia, Alvaro, and Citizens remain, standing in wonder and confusion. Alv. Why do we stand like statue-gods in gardens, Stock and stone-still, as if we had not hearts! Gar. This master-policy of that Jew king— That plague of Arragon! whose ambition Climbs by the ladder of his daughter's beauty, Hath stricken me dumb with marvel: they must fall! We not believed the trumpet when it spoke— But, lo! the troops are come. They must both die! Alv. And quickly: let's about it!—matters now Come to this point—'tis Jew, or Christian! Enter Manrique, with a paper. Man. I grieve to be so black a messenger: This dooms my noble lords to banishment From ground of Arragon. Farewell, my lords: My prayers shall not be idle for your safety. Gar. You're a base lord. Alv. A Hebrew wench's lap dog! Man. 'Tis but a sweet variety of air! Mine is a surface from which rough things slip As well as gentle—save your courtesy! So I but prosper, and maintain my place (A touchy matter, as your lordships know) My heraldry's nought tarnish'd to the world. Ye're worthy nobles: may ye better know The gentle humour of prosperity! [Exit. Alv. Hang him! Gar. Let each man draw his sword—and here Kneel with the Garcia, and to righteous heaven Swear or to die, or cast out to the dogs The Hebrew and his daughter: kneel—and swear! [Drawing his sword and kneeling. Licenser's Note—“Omit this Swearing and Kneeling.” Alv. and Citizens (idem) We swear! Gar. Listen! Alphonso hunts, ere long, Some leagues from Saragossa, it is said: The soldiers (I did note it heedfully) Frown with a deep and sullen discontent, That scowls aversion to this Hebrew yoke: The king away, they're ours! Now, with the Jews Soon comes a day of highest festival; And to their temple one and all will throng— And Xavier, as their chieftain and high priest, With his proud daughter—even the Hebrew Queen— Be sure, will there make show of his stolen pomp, And vaunt the greatness of his ministry In (what he calls) the eyes of Israel. Alv. Our quick thoughts meet: we, with the citizens Will gird their temple, and destroy them all! Citz. All! Gar. Utterly! else not a Christian's safe; And we shall soon be butcher'd in our beds: This doom of exile is a speaking prelude. The princess' escape is plann'd; and sight of her Shall strike the people into phrensy! Come: Ere many suns shall set, we're dead—or free! [Exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT THE FIFTH. SCENE I. Isabella's apartment in Xavier's house. Isabella and the Jewess at the casement. Isa. Sweet wench! look down the stream—I would see hope Come toward me in the likeness of a boat, Mann'd by the Garcia and the Lord Alvaro And some half-score of loving citizens, That in my bondage feel themselves enslaved: Look down; for I have strain'd my eyes in vain, Even to the stretch of aching. Jewess. Nought see I, Madam. Isa. The letter you convey'd to me said six; That point the dial's shade past long ago— Ah! me—I fear things have gone contrary. Jewess. A speck flits in the distance, like a mote; A dark spot in the light—now light gleams on it; Now 'tis a flying thing, with oars for feathers! Isa. It is, it is the boat! the oars strike fast, But, oh! my heart strikes faster; and so fast, The rapid bark, shot faster every minute, Seems slower ever minute. O, sweet boat! 'Light 'neath this casement with a swallow's flight— And I'll dart down as with a merlin's wing! [Noise without. Keep the door fast! What's that? Jewess. Alas! dear lady, Your jailor's stirring, and the guards are roused. Isa. Keep the door fast!—The boat's a tortoise, sure: I'm seen; they doff their plumes in homage to me: It flashes nearer now;—and now—and now, They anchor close, and silently beneath:— I thank thee, God! [Noise without. Jewess. Haste, madam—haste Isa. God bless thee! Be sure that I will love thee, gentle Jewess, Ever for this; and place thee near myself— If ever I be queen. Jewess. Heaven guard thee, lady. O, haste! [Noise without. Isa. A kiss! farewell. A couch is spread— I cannot sure take hurt; and tho' I do, [She gets out of the casement. Worse harms are here; so, courage!—dear, farewell! [She drops outside from the casement. Knocking without. Jewess. Reuben is at the door:—she's safe! she's safe! And now the boat is struggling 'gainst the tide; They hoist a sail in the fresh-blowing wind— And now, it flies! it flies! [An alarm is given without. Knocking. Reu. (without) Open the door! what, ho! Jewess. The alarm is given—and all is doubtful yet: They'll slay me in their wrath; but welcome, death! so met! [Exit. Noise and knocking without. SCENE II. A Chamber in the Palace. Enter King and Rachel; he attended, as departing for the chase. Rach. Alphonso, I beseech thee, go not forth: To-morrow, if you will; but not to-day— O, not to-day! A dark, mysterious feeling Clouds o'er my heart; and even now I seem As I were standing on the hideous verge Of some deep, blood-wet grave: what 'tis, I know not— Or fear, or augury; but something 'tis That deep-pervades my being: do not go! King. Thou wert a dreamer ever, my fair Hebrew: The spirit of thy Prophet Ancestry Lives in their dear descendant. What's to fear? The rebels now are powerless and abash'd; Thy sire is with thee—and my faithful guards Hold thy throned greatness unassailable: 'Tis a rare morning for the gallant sport; And 'twill be pleasure to me; with me, the chace Is a mad passion—like my love for thee. Thy fears are folly, Rachel. Come, my lords— Thou'lt better keep thy Jewish festival; I should but drag thee from devotion, sweet! Rach. Upon my knees! upon my knees! dear lord. King. Nay, rise! my peerless Jewess: what's the fear? Rach. Those banish'd lords are mighty in the hearts Of the whole city: even Alphonso's guards Lower on his Rachel with a scowling eye; And if dark looks could do the deed of swords, She had been dead e'er now. And, oh! my king, My brain hath in the night been tortur'd By such a hideous real-seeming, dream, That, on my life! 'twas more than visionary. King. A dream! a dream! Why, now I mark thee, Rachel: Calphurnia had a dream— Rach. And Cæsar died! And Rachel had a dream—and Rachel dies, If thou, Alphonso, dost go forth to-day! Enter Manrique. Man. Your courser, my great liege! strikes up the ground, 'Till the air startles with an upward shower Of grass and dust: he stands magnificent! And with a tossing head, champing the bit, And his mane shaking like a cloud i' the wind, Reproaches royally his royal lord— Delaying high enthronement on his back: The dogs make music; and the huntsman's soul Frets in his eye!—Will 't please my liege to mount? King. You come in time, Manrique. All to horse! Sweet Rachel, we will hear thy dream to-night, And thou shalt laugh then at thy now affright. Come, come! [Exeunt all but Rachel. Rach. He's gone—and my misgiving heart Shakes with the palsy of some ominous fear: It is as he had left me to fall back Into my grave! Unlock my tears, dear God! That I may weep this burthen from my soul: I must behold my royal lord again? Enter Xavier. Xav. Why weeps my daughter in her pride of power? Why weeps the Hebrew queen of Arragon? Go, deck thee for our holy festival: Israel expects thee in her joyous temple, There to preside—her glory visible! What sorrow is the fountain of these waters? Tell me, my queen. Rach. 'Tis felt—not to be told. The king e'en now hath left me for the chase. Xav. That's leaden sorrow! You grow tame, proud lady. Rach. All brows bend on us with suppress'd disdain: The very soldiery, power's common tools, Scowl on thy daughter and her lofty sire— As they did wish their swords were in their hearts. Xav. A potent fear! were wishes sharp as swords: I do begin to weary of thy terrors; Thy love hath made thee very simple, Rachel. Rach. Sire! you have credence in the might of dreams; And of the mightiest, one hath shook my soul. Xav. Frail fret-work of the brain!—Yet I do listen. Rach. Thou stood'st before me in a cloud of fire— Which left thee; and all then seem'd black as night; But thou wert still most clearly visible: And then there came a dagger to thy hand, And thou withal didst pierce me thro' and thro'; Each stab was a life-losing agony!— That I did shriek, and shriek; and at my feet The king lay dead, as thou hadst murder'd him, Thro' wounding me: then rose the cloud again, In likeness of Alvaro—who did clasp And burn thee, till thou wither'dst into ashes; Which I fell down and kiss'd—and kiss'd; and waking, Did almost feel them on my feverish lips! Xav. I prithee, go; and in the inner chamber Of the great temple, 'wait thy father's coming. Rach. Sire, I would fain remain here in the palace: I have an ill-foreboding soul, that tells me There's danger in our going forth to-day. Xav. Not go? not worship?—Stay at home for fear? To Jewry—and more foul, to Christendom Make proclamation that our power is air? For fear, insult the God of Israel! And with neglect abuse his ordinance? Go!—that is well; else wert thou not my daughter. [Exit Rachel. Dreams have been warnings to our tribes for ever; But I were happy, if this dream were all: Those proud lords' banishment stands unenforced; There walks a lurking peril thro' the streets; Men's souls look thro' their eyes, and sullenly Speak of a deed to come. I've learn'd a truth: Our sun hath shone! the weight of the world's scorn Is heavy on us, that we cannot rise; Or rising for an instant, cannot stand:— And 'tis a truth that makes me wish to die. And yet, sweet Rachel! I would live for thee; Live to maintain thy greatness with that genius That's strong in Xavier's soul. Still have I power: Let citizen and soldier hate their fill!— They dare not strike, whilst at my dagger's point I hold this Christian princess. [Enter Reuben, bleeding and faint. The misery? Reu. My life and the small riches I possess Are forfeit all—my life's half gone already— Pluck out the rest!—the Christian is escaped. Xav. Death seize thee wholly! Dar'st thou say, the princess? Reu. Kill me! 'tis so. Xav. Now, Xavier's curse fall on thee! Thou wert concerting some low scheme of gain; She made a loophole of thine avarice! Hadst thou brought news that half the world was drown'd, 'Twere tidings of a jubilee, to this! The strong-hold of our power, our certain safety, Thy care hath turn'd to utter foolishness.— Get thee away! The curse of Israel on thee! Reu. I bleed, Sir; and had fought unto the death, Could it have aught avail'd—but she escaped: I slew the trait'rous wench that aided her! It chanced in this wise— Xav. Ay; it chanced: suffices; No need o' the history; 'twill mend no marring. Get to the temple! and there 'wait my coming. Reu. I'd to the surgeon's—but I'm fain to die. [Exit. Xav. Our downthrow is afoot—and that proud laurel I planted loftily, that it might spread Over a kingdom, withers with one leaf! But this, at least, shall be a day of glory And pomp and triumph to all Hebrew hearts: The troops shall gird the temple; and the king Be summon'd from the chase—or live, or die, The soul of Xavier fareth royally! [Exit. SCENE III. A Public Place of Assembly. Enter Garcia, Lords and Citizens. Gar. You left her highness safe? A Lord. In a good citizen's house, Recovering from the terror and fatigue Of the morn's perilous doings. Gar. At her sight The popular heart will throb exultingly, With uncontrollable passion—all must die! Enter Alvaro and others. Alv. All! all! Rachel is in the snare; and the cursed Jew, Clad in his priestly vestments, even now Enter'd the Temple: there the troops are placed; But, with a fierce reluctance, one and all Wince 'neath the gall of Hebrew government: By St. Iago! they'll not stir a man! Gar. Is the king forth? Alv. An hour ago. Gar. Enough! Quick; let the signal-bell of Mary's Church Peal death to every Jew in Arragon! [Exeunt some. Alv. Great glee, great glee is in Alvaro's heart! I long to grapple with these scoundrel Hebrews. Gar. My country! wipe the sorrow from thine eye; Mantle thy native cheek with native smiles— Blush out thy pleasure!—and from Jewish graves Start up again in Christian liberty! [Exeunt. SCENE IV. The Jews' Temple, with an Altar &amp;c. Rachel discovered, leaning on the Altar. Rach. There is a peace and holy quiet here, At variance with my spirit, which it lulls not: The shadow of some lowering ill falls on me, Arguing the substance nigh—O, what's to fear?— That horrible dream! 'tis on my vision now; And like the ghost o' the murder'd, will not vanish! Ha! [Confused noises in the distance. The signal-bell rings. That dull bell seems tolling for my death— There's tumult in the streets, and in the temple! What should the meaning be?—is the end come? [The bell ceases. Tumult within. Reuben staggers upon the Stage. Reu. Daughter of Xavier! fly—i' the instant, fly! The Christians are upon us, and the soldiers Join in the slaughter. Curses on my head! Ten thousand, thousand curses on my head! That let the princess 'scape: she stands on high, Setting their hearts on fire with gazing merely!— O, get thee from this place!— Rach. Whither? Oh! whither? Reu. I'm gashes; and my tears are drown'd in blood! Nay, they weep blood for thee—O, thou art lost!— Life and life's goods Are gone for ever—all is night with Reuben!— [Falls, so as to be concealed by the Altar. Rach. O, mercy! God of Israel—mercy! mercy! [Noise of a bolt falling. Enter Xavier, in his Priest's habit. Xav. 'Tis bolted; and a breathing space is left us. Rachel, our hour is come; think on thy soul, For it must straight to Heaven: this being fades— Even now the consciousness of life's half gone, And at the portal of Eternity Darkly we stand sublime. O, what a terror Stares in thine eye!—Scion of Israel's kings! Fear'st thou to die? I've heard thee speak of death As of a pleasing and an intricate maze, Leading in mystery to mystery, Even to be coveted: how is it now?— Thy soul is dead already! Rach. Horrible! horrible! My love hath made me coward—Oh!—'tis fearful: 'Tis cruel, now to die—in youth to die— Ere a grey hair is on my head, to die!— Is there no hope? Xav. In Christian daggers—Ay! Rach. The king? the king? Xav. A name—my child! come; come. [Noise at the door. Alv. (without) Break ope the door! I saw him enter here. Xav. Ay, bloodhounds!—here. Now, Xavier's royal daughter! Wilt thou be slaughtered by these Christian butchers— Be mangled by a pack of citizen dogs— Hold out thy throat to raging Garcia's sword— To base Alvaro, stung by loathed lust— Writhing with thy disdain, ope thy pure heart; Or wilt thou perish freely—like a queen— By thine own fearless deed? Rach. Give me the means!— And, oh! no blood—let it not be in blood! Xav. Men whom each hour may call upon to die Must wear strange armour: drink!—it is death's wine. [Gives Rachel a phial of poison. Battery without. Gar. (without) It will not ope; bring other instruments! Rach. Villains! I fear ye not: a desperation Makes me immortal! Sire, I drink to thee. [Drinks the poison. My dream! my dream!—O, speedy remedy!— I've dearly loved Alphonso, O, my father; And I do fear, with love that almost quench'd That higher love—my country; thine, my glory. We've reign'd! 'tis something: all is over now. Thou see'st how calmly I do bear this torture— Thou'lt follow—Oh!—so; so; past suffering— My soul's asleep—the king— [Dies. Xav. There Xavier's life Gasp'd into dumb oblivion! this rough frame Holds not his being; but in thee, thou fair And exquisite image of the living god! I refer the Licenser to Genesis—c. 1, v. 26 and 27. He breath'd, and moved, and joy'd. Cold! cold! my child; No fire is on the altar of thy beauty; Thy lips are idly ope, for balmy breath Of sighs, nor sweet word-music, ever more Shall pass from their deep-crimson—poison'd—pale; Thine eyes, that shone so gorgeous with rich light, Where the soul dwelt, a clear and visible thing, Are—my tears rise—I see not what they are. The holy pressure of a father's kiss Seal up thy lips!—their venom poisons not, O'ermatch'd with sweetness. Here, even here, dead saint!— Even at the altar's foot, sweet Hebrew Queen!— Lie tranquilly, and holy as itself— [He lies the body upon the altar-steps. And I'll kneel down, and pray. [Cries without—and noise as of the door bursting open. [Garcia, Alvaro, citizens and soldiers, with drawn swords, rush in: Xavier starts up. Ha! Murderers: Lo! ye are spared your honourable work; Great hearts have privilege to choose their death!— Now, bloodhounds! are ye happy? Look! look there!— What! naked weapons still?—ye'd slay a woman— And on the senseless flesh of the fair dead Would haply vent the manhood of your valour!— Out! ye are worms! Gar. The Jew hath kill'd his daughter! My soul is struck with pity: let him live— Live, to make legal answer for his deeds. Xav. Live! Alv. Drag him to a dungeon! he shall know What 'tis to rear a Hebrew commonweal!— He, the sole Jew that lives in Arragon! Xav. Stay! gentle Christians—even for charity; I'd once more kiss the dead lips of my child. [Kneels beside the body. Ye see—I weep; the Jew—the proud Jew weeps; See, that he feels almost as Christians do. God bless thee! and sweet peace attend thy soul! [Starts up. Now, ye inhuman dogs! leave ample space For the great exit of a mighty soul! [Draws a concealed dagger: they shrink back involuntarily. The last of all the race of Israel's kings Passes from earth to heaven—his passport, this! [Stabs himself, and falls on his daughter's body. Ye are baffled, dogs!—I'll die on thy hush'd heart, My gentle daughter. Faith! I once did dream Of building up a new Jerusalem Here in this Saragossa; and had visions Of Israel's resurrection: but, 'tis past— Yet will her full hour come—hear it! 'twill come. [Dies. Alv. A villain dead! Gar. A noble nature dead! The king! my lords, the king! Alv. Come! let's beg grace. [They all kneel. Enter Alphonso, Manrique and attendants, followed by Isabella and attendants. Alph. I come too late: ye shall all die for this! Oh! Rachel—my heart's life! What! dead? quite dead? All winter where I left a glorious spring? Here will I lie by thee, and rave for ever— King of no realm but sorrow! [Throws himself by Rachel's side. Isa. Methinks it were a happy lot to die, To be so mourn'd. My intercession, lords, Tho' weak, shall go between ye and the king, When this his fearful violence of grief Calms into tears. Here am I dedicate With patient love his lost peace to restore; Or, still disdain'd, I'll be as now are seen The Jew of Arragon—the Hebrew Queen. [The curtain falls. THE END.</field>
   </doc>
</add>