<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Tomkis, Thomas, 1604-1615</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Tomkis, Thomas, 1604-1615</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">tomkis thomas 1604 1615</field>
      <field name="author_text">Tomkis, Thomas, 1604-1615</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">17th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V1.0446.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1634</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:459177</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Albvmazar ; A Comedy</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 17th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 17th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Albvmazar ; A Comedy</field>
      <field name="title_facet">albvmazar</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">albvmazar</field>
      <field name="title_text">Albvmazar ; A Comedy</field>
      <field name="year_display">1634</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1634</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1634</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459177&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459177&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Tomkis, Thomas, fl. 1604-1615&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;tomkis thomas fl 1604 1615&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Albvmazar ; A Comedy&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;albvmazar&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1634&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1634&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Tomkis, Thomas&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1604&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1615&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Albvmazar&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Comedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed by Nicholas Okes&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1634&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3871799-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv10446&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 17th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;17th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Albvmazar&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Comedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 259 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Albumazar.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: University plays.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1615.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 9 Mar 1615.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ALBVMAZAR.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Dramatis Personæ. Albumazar. An Astrologer. Ronca. Thiefe. Harpax. Thiefe. Furbo. Thiefe. Pandolfo. An old Gentleman. Cricca. His servant. Trincalo. Pandolfo's Farmer. Armellina. Antonio's maide. Lelio. Antonio's Sonne. Eugenio. Pandolfo's Sonne. Flauia. Antonio's daughter. Sulpitia. Pandolfo's daughter. Bauilona. A Curtezen. Antonio. An old Gentleman.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Prologue. The brightnesse of so great and faire a Presence, They say, strikes cold amazement. But I feele Contrary effects. For from the gracious center O'th' Honourable assembly, some secret Power Inflames my Courage; and, me thinks I am growne Taller by th'vertue of this Audience. And yet thus rais'd, I feare there's no retiring. Ladies, whose beauties glad the whole Assembly: Vpon your favours I impose my businesse. If't be a fault to speake this Forraigne language, (For Latine is our mother tongue) I must intreat you To frame excuses for us; for whose sake We now speake English. All the rest we hope Come purposely to grace our poore endeavours; As we to please. In whose faire courtesie We trust; not in our weake ability.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Act. 1. Scen. 1. Enter Albumazar, Harpax, Ronca. Albumazar. Come brave Mercurials sublim'd in cheating. My deare companions, fellow-souldiers I'th watchfull exercise of Theevery: Shame not at your so large profession, No more then? at deep Astrologie. For in the dayes of old, Good morrow Thiefe, As welcome was receiv'd, as now Your Worship. The Spartans held it lawfull, and the Arabians, So grew Arabia, Fœlix, Sparta valiant. Ronc. Read on this Lecture, wise Albumazar. Alb. Your Patron Mercury in his mysterious character, Holds all the makes of the other wanderers, And with his subtill influence works in all, Filling their stories full of Robberies. Most Trades and Callings much participate Of yours; though smoothly gilt with th'honest title Of Merchant, Lawyer, or such like: the learned Onely excepted; and he's therefore poore. Harp. And yet he steals one Author from another. This Poet is that Poets Plagiary, And he a third's, till they end all in Homer. Albu. And Homer filtch't all from an Egyptian Priestesse. The worlds a Theater of theft. Great Rivers Rob smaller Brooks; and them the Ocean. And in this world of ours, this Microcosme, Guts from the stomack steale, and what they spare, The meseraicks filch, and lay't i'the liver: Where (least it should be found) turn'd to red Nectar, Tis by a thousand theevish veins conveyde And hid in flesh, nerves bones, muscles, and sinews, In tendons, skin, and haire, so that the property Thus altered, the theft can never be discovered. Now all these pilfries couch't and compos'd in order, Frame thee and me. Man's a quick masse of theevery. Ronc. Most Philosophicall Albumazar! Harp. I thought these parts had lent and borrowed mutuall. Albu. Say they do so: tis done with full intention Nere to restore, and that's flat robbery. Therefore go on, follow your vertues Lawes Your cardnall vertue, great necessity, Wait on her close, with all occasions. Be watchfull, have as many eyes as Heaven, And eares as Harvest: be resolv'd and impudent, Beleeve none, trust none: for in this City (As in a fought field Crowes and Carkasses) No dwellers are but Cheaters and Cheateez. Ronc. If all the houses in the town were prisons, The chambers cages, all the settles stocks, The broad-gates gallowses, and the whole people Justices, Juries, Constables, Keepers, and Hangmen, Ide practise spite of all, and leave behinde me A fruitfull Seminary of our profession, And call them by the name Albumazarians. Harp. And I no lesse, were all the City theeves As cunning as thy selfe. Albu. Why bravely spoken, Fitting such generous spirits: Ile make way To your great vertue with a deep resemblance Of high Astrologie. Harpax and Ronca. List to our profit: I have new lodg'd a prey Hard by, that taken is so fat and rich Twill make us leave off trading, and fall to purchase. Harp. Who is't? speak quickly. Ron. Where good Albumazar? Alb. Tis a rich Gentleman, as old as foolish. The poore remnant of whose brain that age had left him The doting love of a young Girle hath dried: And which concerns us most, he gives firme credit To Necromancie and Astrologie. Enter Furbo. Sending to me, as one that promise both. Pandolfo is the man. Har. What old Pandolfo? Alb. The same: but stay, yon's Furbo whose smoothest brow Shines with good news, and's visage promises Triumphs and Trophies to's Furbo playes. Ron. My life ha's learnt out all, I know't by's musick. Then Furbo sings this Song. Beare up thy learned brow Albumazar, Live long of all the world admir'd, For Art profound, and skill retir'd, To cheating by the height of stars: Hence Gypsies, hence, hence rogues of baser strain, That hazard life for little gain: Stand off and wonder, gape and gaze afar At the rare skill of great Albumazar. Furb. Albumazar. Spread out thy nets at large, here's fowle abundance: Pandolfo's ours, I understand his businesse Which I filcht closely from him, while he reveal'd This man, his purposes and projects. Alb. Excellent! Thanks to this instrument: for in pretence Of teaching yong Sulptia, th'old mans daughter, I got accesse to th'house, and while I waited Till she was ready, over-heard Pandolfo Open his secrets to his servant: thus tis, Antonio, Pandolfoes friend, and neighbour, Before he went to Barbary, agreed To give in marriage. Alb. Furbo, this no place Fit to consider curious points of businesse, Come let's away, Ile hear't at large above. Ronca, stay you below, and entertain him With a loud noise of my deep skill in Art, Thou know'st my Rosie modesty cannot do it. Harpax up you, and from my bed-chamber, Where all things for our purposes are ready, Second each beck, and nod, and word of ours. You know my meaning. Har. Yes, yes. Fur. Yes, sir. Furbo goes out singing, Fa la la Pandolfoes ours. SCEN. 2. Ronca, Pandolfo, Cricca. Ron. There's old Pandolfo, amorous as youthfull May, And gray as January. Ile attend him here. Pan. Cricca, I seek thy aid, not thy crosse counsell, I am mad in love with Flavia, and must have her: Thou spend'st thy reasons to the contrary, Like arrows 'gainst an Anvile: I love Flavia, And must have Flavia. Cric. Sir, you have no reason, Shee's a young girle of sixteen, you of sixty. Pan. I have no reason, nor spare room for any, Loves Herbinger hath chalk't upon my heart, And with a coale writ on my brain, for Flavia; This house is wholy taken up for Flavia. Let reason get a lodging with her wit: Vex me no more, I must have Flavia. Cric. But sir, her brother Lelio, under whose charge Shee's now after her fathers death, sware boldly Pandolfo never shall have Flavia. Pan. His father, ere he went to Barbary, Promis'd her me: who be he live or dead, Spight of a Last of Lelioes Pandolfo Shall enjoy Flavia. Cric. Sir, y'are too old. Pan. I must confesse in yeares about threescore, But in tuffe strength of body, foure and twenty, Or two months lesse. Love of young Flavia, More powerfull then Medea's drugs, renews All decay'd parts of man: my Arteries Blown full with youthfull spirits, move the bloud To a new businesse: my withered Nerves grow plumpe And strong, longing for action. Hence thou poore prop Of feeblenesse and age: walke with such sires As with cold Palfies shake away their strength. And loose their legs with curelesse gouts. Pandolfo New moulded is for Revels, Masks, and Musick. Cricca String my neglected Lute, and from my Armory Scoure my best sword, companion of my youth, Without which I seeme naked. Cric. Your love, sir, like strong water To a deplor'd sick man, quicks your feeble limbs For a poor moment. But after ones nights lodging You'l fall so dull and cold, that Flavia Will shrike and leape from bed as from a Sepulchre. Shall I speak plainer, sir? Sheele Cuckold you. Alas sheele Cuckold you. Pan. What me? a man of known discretion, Of riches, yeers, and this gray gravity? Ile satisfie'r with gold, rich cloaths and jewels. Cric. Wer't not farre fitter urge your sonne Eugenio To woo her for himselfe? Pan. Cricca be gone. Touch no more there: I will and must have Flavia, Tell Lelio, if he grant th'm his sister Flavia; Ile give my daughter to him in exchange. Be gone, and finde me here within this halfe houre. SCENE 3. Ronca. Pandolfo. Ron. Tis well that servant's gone: I shall the easier Winde up his master to my purposes. Pan. Sure this some novice of th'Artillery, That winks and shoots: sir, prime prime your peece a new, The powder's wet: tick, tock, tick, tock. Ron. A good ascendent blesse me: sir, are you frantick? Pan. Why frantick? are not knocks the lawfull courses To open doores and eares? Ron. Of vulgar men and houses. Pan. Whose lodgings this? is't not the Astrologers? Ron. His lodging? no: tis the learn'd Phrontisterion Of most divine Albumazar. Pan. Good sir, If the doore break, a better shall redeeme it. Ron. How! all your land sold at a hundred yeeres purchase Cannot repaire the damage of one poore rap, To thunder at the Phrontisterion Of great Albumazar? Pan. Why man? what harme? Ron. Sir, you must know my Masters heavenly brain, Pregnant with mysteries of Metaphysicks, Growes to an Embryo of rare contemplation, Which at full time brought forth, excels by far The armed fruit of Vulcans Midwifry That leapt from Iupiters mighty Cranium. Pan. What of all this? Ron. Thus one of your bold thunders may abortive And cause that birth miscarry, that might have prov'd An instrument of wonders greater and rarer Then Apollonius the Magitian wrought. Pan. Are you your Masters Countriman? Ron. Yes: why aske you? Pan. Then must I get an Interpreter for your language. Ron. You need not; with a wind instrument my Master made, In five dayes you may breath ten Languages As perfect as the Devill or himselfe. Pan. When may I speak with him? Ron. When't please the stars. He puls you not a haire, nor pares a naile, Nor stirs a foot without due figuring The Horoscope: sit downe awhile and't please you, I see the Heavens incline to his approach. Pan. Whats this I pray you? Ron. An Engine to catch stars, A Mase to arrest such Planets as have lurkt Foure thousannd yeers under protection Of Iupiter and Sol. Pan. Pray you speak English. Ron. Sir, tis a perspicill, the best under Heaven: With this Ile reade a leafe of that small Iliade That in a wall-nut-shell was deskt, as plainly Twelve long miles off, as you see Pauls from High-gate. Pan. Wonderfull workman of so rare an instrument! Ron. Twill draw the Moon so neer that you would sweare The bush of thorns in't prick your eyes: the Chrystall Of a large Arch, multiplies millions, Works more then by point blank: and by refractions Optick and strange, searcheth like the eye of truth, All closets that have windows. Have at Rome, I see the Pope, his Cardinals and his Mule, The English Colledge and the Iesuits, And what they write and do. Pan. Let me see too. Ron. So far you cannot: for this glasse is fram'd For eyes of thirty: you are nigh threescore. But for some fifty miles twill serve you, With help of a refractive glasse that's yonder. For triall sir: where are you now: Pan. In London. Ron. Ha you found the glasse within that chamber? Pan. Yes. Ron. What see you? Pan. Wonders, wonders: I see as in a Land-shappe An honourable throng of noble persons, As cleere as I were under the same roofe: Seems by their gracious browes, and courteous looks Something they see, which if it be indifferent They'l favourably accept: if otherwise They'l pardon: who or what they be, I know not. Ron. Why thats the court at Cambridge forty miles hence, what else? Pan. A Hall thrust full of bare-heads, some bald, some busht, Some bravely brancht. Ron. Thats the University Larded with Towns-men. Look you there: what now? Pan. Who? I see Dover Peere, a man now landing Attended by two Porters that seeme to grone Under the burthen of two loads of paper. Rom. That's Coriatus Persicus, and's observations Of Asia and Africk. Pan. The price. Ron. I dare not fel't. But here's another of another of a stranger vertue. The great Albumazar by wondrous Art, In imitation of this Perspicill, Hath fram'd an Instrument that multiplies Objects of hearing, as this doth of seeing, That you may know each whisper from Prester John Against the winde, as fresh as 'twere delivered Through a trunk, or Glosters listning wall. Pan. And may I see't sir? blesse me once more. Ron. 'Tis something ceremonious: but you shall try't. Stand thus. What heare you? Pan. Nothing. Ro. Set your hands thus That the vertex of the Orgon may perpendicularly Point out our Zenith. What heare you now? ha, ha, ha. Pan. A humming noise of laughter. Ro. Why that's the Court And University, that now are merry With an old Gentleman in a Comedy. What now? Pan. Celestiall musick, but it seems far off. List, list, 'tis neerer now. Ro. 'Tis musick 'twixt the Acts. What now Pan. Nothing. Ron. And now? Pan. Musick again, and strangely delicate, O most Angelicall! they sing! Ron. And now? Sing sweetly that our notes may cause The heavenly Orbes themselves to pause: And at our Musick stand as still As at Jove's amorous will. So now release them as before, Th'have waited long enough, no more. Pan. Tis gone, give me't again.—O do not so. Ron. What heare you now? Pan. No more then a dead Oister. O let me see this wondrous instrument. Ron. Sir, this is call'd an Otacousticon. Ban. A Cousticon? Why tis a paire of Asses eares, and large ones. Ron. True: for in such a forme the great Albumazar Hath fram'd it purposely, as fit'st receivers Of sounds, as spectacles like eyes for sight. Pan. What Gold will buy't? Ron. Ile felt you when tis finisht. As yet the Epiglottis is unperfect. Pan. 'Soone as you can, and here's ten crownes in earnest, For when tis done, and I have purchas'd it, I meane to entaile it on my heires male for ever. Spight of the ruptures of the common Law. Ron. Nay, rather giv't to Flavia for her joynture: For she that marries you, deserves it richly. SCEN. 4. Cricca, Pandolfo, Ronca. Cric. Sir, I have spoke with Lelio, and he answers. Pan. Hang Lelio, and his answers. Come hither Cricca. Wonder for me, admire, and be astonish'd, Marvaile thy selfe to Marble at these Engines, These strange Gorgonian instruments. Cric. At what? Pan. At this rare Perspicill and Otacousticon: For with these two Ile heare and see all secrets, Vndoe intelligencers. Pray let my man see What's done in Rome; his eyee are just as yours are. Ron. Pandolfo, are you mad? be wise and secret: See you the steepe danger you are tumbling in? Know you not that these instruments have power To unlocke the hidden'st closets of whole States? And you reveale such mysteries to a servant. Sir be advis'd, or else you learne no more Of our unknowne Philosophy. Pan. Enough. What newes from Lelio? shall I have his sister? Cric. He sweares and vowes he never will consent. She shall not play with worne Antiquities, Nor lye with Snow and Statutes; and such replies That I omit for reverence of your worship. Pan. Not haue his sister? Cricca I will have Flavia, Maugre his head: by meanes of this Astrologer Ile enjoy Flavia. Are the stars yet inclin'd To his divine approach? Ro. One minute brings him. Cri. What Strologer? Pan. The learned man I told thee, The high Almanack of Germany, an Indian Far beyond Trebesond and Tripoli, Close by the Worlds end a rare Conjurer, And great Astrologer. His name, pray sir? Ron. Albumazarro Meteoroscopico. Cri. A name of force to hang him without triall. Pan. As he excels in Science, so in Title. He tels of lost plate, horses, and strayd cattell Directly, as he had stolne them all himselfe. Cri. Or he, or some of his confederates. Pan. As thou respects thy life, look to thy tongue, Albumazar has an Otacousticon. Be silent, reverent, and admire his skill, See what a promising countenance appeares: Stand still and wonder, wonder and stand still. SCENE 5. Albumazar, Ronca, Pandolfo, Cricca. Alb. Ronca, the bunch of Planets new found out Hanging at the end of my best Perspicill, Send them to Galilæo at Padua; Let him bestow them where he please. But the stars Lately discovered twixt the horns of Aries, Are as a present for Pandolfoes marriage, And hence stil'd Sidera Pandolfæa. Pan. My marriage Cricca! he foresees my marriage: O most Celestiall Albumazar! Cri. And sends y' a present from the head of Aries. Alb. My Almanack made for the Meridian And height of Iapan, give't th'East Indy Company; There may they smell the price of Cloves and Pepper, Monkies and China-dishes five yeers ensuing, And know the successe of the voyage of Magores, For in the volume of the Firmament, We children of the stars read things to come, As clearely as poore mortalls stories past In Speed or Hollingshead. Ro. The perpetuall motion With a true larum in't to run twelve houres 'Fore Mahomets returne. Alb. Deliver it safe To a Turky Factor, bid him with care present it From me to the house of Ottoman. Ro. I will sir, Cric. Pray you stand here, and wonder now for me, Be astonish't at his Gorgon, for I cannot. Pan. Vpon my life he proves a meere imposture. Peace, not a word, be silent and admire. Alb. As for the issue of the next summers warre, Reveale't to none, keepe it to thy selfe in secret, As a touch-stone of my skill in prophesie. Begon. Ron. I go sir. Alb. Signior Pandolfo, I pray you pardon mee, Exoticall dispatches of great consequence Staid me; and casting the Nativity O'th' Cham of Tartary, and a private conference With a Mercuriall intelligence. Y'are welcome in a good houre, better minute, Best second, happiest third, fourth, fift, and scruple. Let the twelve houses of the Horoscope Be lodg'd with fortitudes, and fortunates, To make you blest in your designes Pandolfo. Pan. Wer't not much trouble to your starry imployments, I a poore mortall would intreat your furtherance In a terrestriall businesse. Alb. My Emphemeris lies, Or I foresee your errant: thus 'tis thus. You had a neighbour cal'd Antonio, A widdower like your selfe, whose onely daughter, Flavia you love, and he as much admir'd Your Child Sulpitia. Is not this right? Pan. Yes sir: O strange! Cricca admire in silence. Alb. You two decreed a counter-match betwixt you, And purpos'd to truck daughters. Is't not so? Pan. Iust as you say't. Cricca admire and wonder. Cric. This no such secret: looke to your selfe, he'le cheate you. Alb. Antonio after this match concluded, Having great summes of gold in Barbary, Desires of you before he consummate The Rites of Matrimony, he might goe thither, For three moneths; but as now 'tis three and three Since he imbarkt, and is not yet return'd. Now sir your businesse is to me, to know Whether Antonio be dead or living. Ile tell you instantly. Pan. Hast thou reveal'd it? I told it none but thee. Cric. Not I. Pan. Why stare you? Are you not well? Alb. I wander 'twixt the Poles And heavenly hinges, 'mongst excentricalls, Centers, concentrickes, circles, and epicycles, To hunt out an aspect fit for your businesse. Cric. Meane ostentation! for shame awake your selfe. Alb. And since the Lampe of Heaven is newly entred Into Cancer, old Antonio is starke dead, Drown'd in the Sea stone dead; for radius directorius In the sixt house; and th'waning Moone by Capricorne, He's dead, he's dead. Cric. 'Tis an ill time to marry. The Moone growes fork't, and walkes with Capricorne. Pan. Peace foole: these words are full of mysterie. Alb. What ominous face and dismall countenance. Mark't for disasters, hated of all the heavens, Is this that followes you. Pan. He is my servant, A plaine and honest speaker, but no harme in him. Cric. What see you in my face? Alb. Horrour and darknesse, death and gallowses: I'de sweare thou wert hang'd, stoodst thou but too foote higher: But now the Starres threaten a nearer death: Sir, send to toale his knell. Pan. What is he dead? Alb. He shall be by the dint of many stabs: Onely I spy a little hope of scaping Through the clouds, and foule aspects of death, Cric. Sir, pray give no credit to this cheater. Or with his words of Art he'le make you dote As much on his feign'd skill, as on faire Flavia. SCEE 6. Harpaz. Furbo. Album. Pandolfo. Cricca. Har. Stay villaine, stay, though safety't selfe defend thee Thou dyest. Fur. Come doe thy worst, thrust sure, or die. Cric. For heavens sake Gentlemen stay your hands, helpe, helpe. Helpe Albumazar. Harp. Thus to the hinderer Of my revenge. Cric. Save me Albumazar. Furb. And thus, and thus, and thus. Cric. Master, I dye, I dye. Harp. Fliest thou base coward? 'tis not thy heels can save thee. SCEN. 7. Album. Pand. Cric. Cric. Oh, oh! Pan. What ailes thee Cricca? Cri. I am dead, I am dead. Trouble your self no more. Pan. What dead &amp; speak'st? Cric. Onely there's left a litle breath to tell you. Pan. Why where art hurt? Cric. Stab'd with a thousand daggers My heart, my lights, my liver, and my skinne Pierst like a sive. Pan. Here's not a wound, stand up, 'Tis but thy feare. Cric. 'Tis but one wound all over: Softly, oh softly: you have lost the truest servant. Farewell I die. Alb. Live by my courtesie, stand up and breath. The dangerous and malignant influence is past; But thanke my charity that put by the blowes. The least of which threatned a dozen graves. Now learne to scoffe divine Astrology, And flight her servants. Cri. A Surgion, good sir, a Surgeon. Pan. Th'art well, th'art well. Cric. Now I perceive I am: I pray you pardon me Divine Astrologer. Alb. I doe, but hence-forth laugh at Astrology And call her servants Cheaters. Pan. Now to our businesse: on good Albumazar, Albu. Now since the moone passeth from Capricorne, Through Aquarius to the watry signe of Pisces, Antonio's drownd, and is devour'd by fishes. Pan. Is't certaine? Alb. Certaine. Pan. Then let my earnestnes Intreat your skill a favour. Alb. It shall, but first I'le tell you what you meane to aske me. Pan. Strange! Alb. Antonio dead that promised you his daughter, Your businesse is to entreat me raise his Ghost, And force it stay at home till it have perform'd The promise past, and so returne to rest. Pan. That, that, y'have hit it, most divine Albumazar. Alb. Tis a hard thing; for de privationa ad habit? non datur regressus: O what a businesse! what a Master piece 'Tis to raise up his Ghost whose body's eaten By fish. This worke desires a planetary intelligence Of Iupiter and Sol, and these great Spirits Are proud, phantasticall: It askes much charges, To entice them from the guiding of their Spheares To waite on mortalls. Pan. So I may have my purpose, spare for no cost. Alb. Sir, spare your purse, Ile do it an easier way; The worke shall cost you nothing. We have an Art is cald Præstigiatory, That deales with spirits and intelligences Of meaner office and condition, Whose service craves small charges: with one of these Ile change some servant or good friend of yours To the perfect shape of this Antonio: So like in face, behaviour, speech, and action, That all the Towne shall sweare Antonio lives. Pan. Most necromanticall Astrologer, Doe this, and take me for your servant ever. And for your paines, after the transformation This chaine is yours, it cost two hundred pound, Beside the Jewel. Al. After the worke is finish't, then how now? What lines are these that looke sanguineous? As if the stars conjur'd to do you mischiefe? Pan. How? mean you me? Alb. They're dusky marks of Saturne, It seems some stone shall fall upon your head, Threatning a fracture of the Pericranium. Pan. Cricca, come hither, fetch me my staffe again, Threescore and ten's return'd: A generall Palsie Shakes out the love of Flavia with a feare. Is thore no remedy? Alb. Nothing but patience. The Planet threatens so, whose prey you are. The Stars and Planets daily war together. Por should they stand at truce but one halfe houre This wondrous Machin of the world would ruine. Who can withstand their powerfull influence? Pan. You with your wisdome, good Albumazar. Alb. Indeed th'Egyptian Ptolomy the wise, Pronounc't it as an Oracle of truth; Sapiens dominabitur astris. Who's above there? Ronca bring down the cap Made in the point of Mercury being ascendent: Here put it on, and in your hand this Image, Fram'd on a Tuesday when the fierce of warre Mounted th'Horizon in the signe of Arries. With these walke as unwounded as Achilles, Dipt by his mother Thetis. Pan. You bind me to your service. Alb. Next get the man you purpose to transforme, And meet me here. Pan. I will not fail to finde you. Alb. Mean while with Sciofericall instrument, By way of Azimuth and Almicantarath Ile seek some happy point in Heven for you. Pan. I rest your servant sir. Al. Let all the Stars Guide you with most propitious influence. SCENE 8. Pandolfo. Cricca. Pan. Here's a strange man indeed, of skil profound? How right he knew my busines, 'fore he saw me? And how thou skoftst him when we talkt in private. Tis a brave instrument his Otacousticon. Cric. In earnest sir, I tooke him for a cheater: As many, under name of cunning men, With promise of Astrology, much abuse The gaping vulgar, wronging that sacred skill, That in the starres reads all our actions. Pan. Is there no Archers o're our heads? look Cricca. Cric. None but the Arch of heaven, that cannot fall. Pan. Is not that made of Marble? I have read A stone dropt from the Moone; and much I feare The fit should take her now, and voyd another. Cric. Feare nothing sir, this charmed Mercuriall cup Shields from the fall of mountaines: 'tis not a stone Can checke his Art, walke boldly. Pan. I doe, let's in. Finis Act. 1.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Act 2. Scœne 1. Trincalo, Armellina. Trincalo. He that saith I am not in love, he lyes De cap a pe; For I am idle, choicely neate in my cloathes, valiant, and extreame witty: My meditations are loaded with metaphors, and songs sonnets: Not a one shakes his tayle, but I sigh out a passion: thus doe I to my Mistris; but alas I kisse the dogge, and she kicks me. I never see a young wanton Filly, but say I, there goes Armellina; nor a lusty strong Asse, but I remember my selfe, and sit downe to consider what a goodly race of Mules would inherit, if she were willing: onely I want utterance, and that's a maine marke of love too. Arm. Trincalo, Trincalo. Trinc. O 'tis Armellina: now if she have the wit to beginne, as I meane she should, then will I confound her with complements drawn from the Playes I see at the Fortune, and Red Bull, where I learn all the words I spake and understand not. Arm. Trincalo, what price bears Wheat, and Saffron, that your band's so stiffe and yellow? not a word? why Trincalo! what businesse in Town? how do all at Totnam? grown mute? What do you bring from the Country? Trin. There 'tis. Now are my floud-gates drawn, and Ile surround her. What have I brought sweet bit of beauty? a hundred thousand salutations o'th'elder house to your most illustrious Honour and Worship. Arm. To me these Titles? is your basket full of nothing else? Trin. Full of the fruits of love, most resplendant Lady; a present to your worthinesse from your Worships poore vassall Trincalo. Arm. My life on't, he scrap't these complements from his Cart the last load hee carried for the Progresse. What ha you read that may you grow so eloquent? Trin. Sweet Madam, I read nothing but the lines of your Ladiships countenance, and desire onely to kisse the skirts of your garments, if you vouchsafe mee not the happinesse of your white hands. Arm. Come, gives your basket and take it. Tri. O sweet! now will I never wash my mouth after, nor breath, but at my nosthrils, lest I lose the taste of her fingers. Armellina, I must tell you a secret if you'le make much on't. Arm. As it deserves: what is't? Trin. I love you, dear morsell of modesty, I love: and so truly, that Ile make you Mistris of my thoughts, Lady of my revenews, and commit all my moveables into your hands, that is, I give you an earnest kisse in the high way of Matrimony. Arm. This is the end of all this businesse? Trin. Is this the end of all this businesse, most beautifull, and most worthy to be most beautifull Lady. Arm. Hence foole, hence. Trin. Why now she knows my meaning, let it work: She put up the fruit in her lap, and threw away the basket: Tis a plaine signe, she abhors the words, and embraces the meaning; O lips, no lips, but leaves besmeared with mel-dew! O dew no dew, but drops of Hony combs! O combs no combs, but fountains full of teares! O teares no teares, but— SCENE 2. Pandolfo. Trincalo. Pan. Cricca denyes me: no perswasions. Proffers, rewards, can work him to transform. Yonder's my Country Farmer Trincalo. Never in fitter time good Trincalo. Tri. Like a lean horse t'a fresh and lusty pasture. Pan. What rent dost pay me for thy Farm at Totnam? Tri. Ten pound; and find't too deare a peny-worth. Pan. My hand here: take it rent-free for three lives, To serve me in a businesse Ile employ thee. Tri. Serve you? Ile serve, reserve, conserve, preserve. Deserve you for th'one halfe. O Armellina, A joynture, hay a joynture! what's your employment? Pan. Heres an Astrologer has a wondrous secret To transforme men to other shapes, and persons. Trin. How? transform things to men? Ile bring nine Taylors Refus'd last Muster, shall give five Marks a piece To shape three men of service out of all, And grant him the remnant shreds above the bargain. Pan. Now if thou'lt let him change thee, take this lease; Drawn ready; put what lives thou pleasest. Tri. Stay, Sir. Say I am transformd; who shall enjoy the lease? I? or the person I must turn to. Pan. Thou, Thou. The resemblance lasts but one whole day: Then home true Farmer, as thou wert before. Trin. Where shall poor Trincalo be? how's this transformd? Transmuted? how? not I: I love my self Better then so: theres no lease. I'de not venter For the whole fee-simple. Pan. Tell me the difference Betwixt a fool and a wise man. As twixt your Worship and my self. Pan. A wise man Accepts all fair occasions of advancement, Flyes no commodity for feares of danger, Venters and gains, lives easily, drinks good wine, Fares neatly, 's richly cloath'd in worthiest company, While your poor Fool and Clown, for fear of perill, Sweats hourly for a dry brown crust to bedward, And wakes all night for want of moysture. Trin. Well, sir, I'de rather starve in this my loved Image, Then hazard thus my life, for others looks. Change is a kinde of death, I dare not try it. Pan. 'Tis not so dangerous as thou tak'st it, wee'l only Alter thy count'nance for a day. Imagine, Thy face mask't only: or that thou dream'st all night Thou wer't apparell'd in Antonio's form And waking find'st thy self true Trincalo. Trin. Antonio's forme? was not Antoniio a Gentleman? Pan. Yes, and a neighbour, that's his house. Trin. O ho! Now do I smell th'Astrologers trick: hee'l steep me In souldiers bloud; or boyle me in a Caldron Of Barbarous Law French: Or anoint me over With supply oile of great mens services. For these three means raise Yeomen to the Gentry. Pardon me sir: I hate those medicines. Fy! All my posterity will smell and tast on't Long as the house of Trincalo endures. Pan. There's no such businesse, thou shalt only seem so And this deceive Antonio's family. Trin. Are you assur'd? 'twould grieve me to be brayed In a huge mortar, wrought to paste, and moulded To this Antonioes mould: Grant I be turnd: what then? Pan. Enter his house, be reverenc'd by his servants, And give his daughter Flavia to me in marriage. The circumstances ile instruct thee after. Trin. Pray give me leave: this side sayes do't, this do not. Before I leave you Tom Trincalo take my counsell. Thy Mistris Armellina is Antonioes maid, And thou in his shape mayst possesse her. Turn. But if I be Antonio, then Antonio Enjoyes that happinesse, not Trincalo. A pretty trick to make my selfe a Cuckold. No, no; there, take your Lease. Ile hang first. Soft, Be not so cholerick Thomas: If I become Antonio, Then all his riches follow. This fair occasion Once vanish't, hope not the like; of astark Clown I shall appeare speck and span Gentleman. A pox of Ploughs, and Carts, and Whips and Horses. Then Armellina shall be given to Trincalo, Three hundred Crowns her portion: wee'le get a boy And call him Transformation Trincalo, Ile do't, sir. Pan. Art resolv'd? Trin. Resolv'd tis done: With this condition: after I have given your Worship My daughter Flavia, you shall then move my Worship And much intreat me to bestow my Maid Upon my selfe, I should say Trincalo. Pan. Content, and for thy sake will make her portion Two hundred Crowns. Trin. Now are you much deceiv'd: I never meant it. Pan. How? Tri. I did but jest. And yet my hand, Ile do't. For I am mutable, And therefore apt to change: Come, come sir, quickly, Lets to th'Astrologer, and there transforme, Reform, conform, deform me at your pleasure. I loath this Country countenance; dispatch: my skin Itches like Snaks in Aprill, to be stript off. Quickly, O quickly, as you love Flavia, quickly. SCEN. 3. Albumazar. Pandolfo. Ronca. Trinc. Alb. Signior Pandolfo, y'arrive in happiest houre If the seven Planets were your neerest kindred, And all the Constellations your allies: Were the twelve houses, and the Innes o'th' Zodiack Your own fee-simple; they could never have chosen A fitter place to favour your desires. For the great Luminaries look from Hilech, And midst of Heaven in Angels, conjunctions, And fortunate aspects, a Trine and Sextile, Ready to powre propitious influences. Pan. Thanks to your power, and court'sie that so plac'd them. That is the man that's ready for the businesse. Alb. Of a most happy count'nance and timber fit To square to th'Gentry: his looks as apt for changing, As he were cov'red with Camelions skins. Trin. Except my hands; and 'twill be troublesome To fit these fingers to Antonio's gloves. Pan. Pray let's about the work as soon as may be, Alb. First choose a large low room, whose door's full East, Or neer inclining: for th'Orientall quarter's Most bountifull of favours. Pan. I have a parler Of a great square and height, as you desire it. Alb. Southward must look a wide and spacious window: For howsoever Omar, Alchabitius, Hali, Albenezra, seem somthing to dissent: Yet Zoroastres, sonne of Oromasus, Hiarcha, Brachman, Thespion, Gymnosophist, Gebir, and Budda Babylonicus, With all the subtile Cabalists and Chaldees. Sweare the best influence: for our Metamorphosis Stoops from the South, or as some say, South-east. Pan. This room's, as fit as you had made it of purpose. Tri. Now do I feel the calf of my right leg Tingle, and dwindle to th'smalnesse of a bed-staffe. Such a speech more turns my high shooes strait boots. Ron. Nere were those Authors cited to better purpose, For through that window all Pandolfoes treasures Must take their flight and fall upon my shoulders. Alb. Now if this light Meridionall had a large casement That over-look't some unfrequented alley, Twere much more proper for th'Intelligences Are nice and coy, scorning to mixe their essence With throng'd disturbance of crosse multitudes. Ron. Spoken by art Albumazar, a provident setter, For so shall we receive what thou handst out Free from from discovery. But in my conscience All windows point full South for such a businesse. Pan. Go to my house, satisfie your curious choice, But credit me, this parler's fit, it neighbours To a blind alley, that in busiest Term-time Feels not the footing of one passenger: Alb. Now then declining from Theourgia, Artenosaria, Pharmacia, rejecting Necro-puro-geo-hydro-cheiro-coscinomancy, With other vain and superstitious Sciences, Wee'l anchor at the art Prestigiatory, That represents one figure for another, With smooth deceit abusing th'eyes of mortals. Tri. O my right arme! 'tis alter'd, and me thinks Longs for a sword: these words have slain a Plow-man. Alb. And since the Moon's the only Planet changing: For from the Neomenia in seven dayes To the Dicotima, in seven more to th'Pauselinum, And in as much from Plenilunium Thorow Dicotima to Neomenia, 'Tis she must help us in this operation. Tri. What Towns are these? the strangenesse of these names, Hath scal'd the marks of many a painfull harvest, And made my new pil'd finger itch for dice. Pan. Deeply considred wondrous Albumazar! O let me kisse those lips that flow with science. Alb. For by her various looks she intimates To understanding soules, that onely she Hath power t'effect a true formation. Cause then your parler to be kept carefully, Washt, rubb'd, perfum'd, hang'd round from top to bottome With pure white lunary Tapstry, or needle-work; But if 'twere cloth of silver, 'twere much better. Ron. Good good! a rich beginning: good! whats next? Alb. Spread all the floore with finest holland sheets, And over them faire damaske Table-cloaths, Above all these draw me chast Virgins aprons The room, the work, and workman must be pure. Trin. With Virgins aprons? the whole compasse of this City Can not afford a dozen. Ron. So, there's shirts And bands to furnish all on's for a twelve-moneth. Alb. An altar in the midst, loaded with plate Of silver Basons, Yewres, Cups, Candlesticks, Flaggons and Beakers, Salts, Chargers, Casting-bottles. Twere not amisse to mix some bowles of gold, So they be massie; the better to resemble The lovely brother-hood of Sol and Luna. Also some Diamonds for Iupiter. For by the whitenesse and bright sparkling lustres We allure th'Intelligences to descend. Ron. Furbo and I are those Intelligences That must attend upon the Magistery. Alb. Now for the ceremonious Sacrifice. Provide such creatures as the Moon delights in, Two sucking Lambs, white as the Alpine snow: Yet if they have a mole or two, twill passe. The Moon her self wants not her pots. Pan. Tis true. Ron. Were they hel-black, we'de make a shift to eat them. Alb. White Capons, Pheasants, Pigeons: one little Black-bird Would stain and spoyle the work. Get severall Wines To quench the holy embers: Rhenish, Greek wine, White Muskadell, Sherry, and rich Canary, So't be not grown too yellow: for the quicker, Brisker, and older, the better for these ceremonies. The more abundance, sooner shall we finish. For 'tis our rule in such like businesses, Who spares most, spends most: either this must doo't, Or th'resolution of five hundred yeers Cannot: so fit are all the Heavens to help us. Ron. A thousand thanks, thou'lt make a compleat cheat. Thus loaded with this treasure, cheer'd with wine, Strengthned with meat: wee'l carry thee in triumph, As the great Generall of our atchievement. Pan. Sir, for rich plate and jewels I have store, But know not how to furnish you with hangings. Alb. Cannot you borrow from the shops? foure houres Shall render all as fair as you receiv'd it. Pan. That can I easily do. Alb. And here you sit If you chance meet with boxes of white Comfits, Marchpane, and dry Sucket, Macarouns and Diet-bread, 'Twill help on well. Ronc. To furnish out our Banquet. Alb. I had clean forgot, we must have Amber-greece, The grayest can be found, some dozen ounces, Ile use but halfe a dram: but tis our fashion T'offer a little from a greater lumpe. Pan. All shall be done with expedition. Alb. And when your man's transform'd the chain you promisd, Pan. My hand: my deeds shall wait upon my promise: Alb. Lead then with happy foot to view the chamber. Pan. I go sir, Trincalo attend us here, And not a word on perill of thy life. Trin. Sir, if they kill me Ile not stir a foot, And if my tongue's puld out, not speak a word. SCENE. 4. Trincalo. Cricca. Trin. O what a businesse 'tis to be transform'd! My master talks of four and twenty houres, But if I misse these Flags of Yeomanry, Guild in the seat, and shine in the bloom of Gentry, Tis not their Strologie, nor Sacrifice, Shall force me cast that coat. Ile never part with't Till I be Shriefe of th'County, and in commission Of Peace and Quorum. Then will I get m'a Clarke, A practiz'd fellow, wiser then my Worship. And dominere amongst my fearefull neighbours, And feast them bountifully with their own bribes. Cri. Trincalo! Tri. 'Tweare a gold chaine at every quarter Sessions, Looke big, and grave, and speak not one wise word. Cri. Trincalo! Tri. Examine wenches got with child, and curiously Search all the circumstances: have blank Mittimusses Printed in readinesse; breath nought but Sirra, Rogue, ha? how? hum? Constable looke to your charge. Then vouch a Statute and a Latine Sentence, Wide from the matter. Cri. Trincalo. Tri. License all Alehouses, Match my Son Transformation t'a Knights daughter, And buy a bouncing Pedigree of a welch Herald: and then— Cri. What in such serious meditations? Tri. Faith no; but building Castles in the Ayre, While th'weathers fit: O Cricca, such a businesse! Cri. What is't? Tri. Nay soft, th'are secrets to my master; Lock'd in my brest: he has the key at's purse strings. Cri. My masters secret? keep it good Farmer, keep it, I would not lend an eare to't if thou didst hire me. Fare-well. Tri. O how it boyles and swels: if I keep't longer, 'Twill grow t'impostume in my brest, and choake me, Cricca. Cri. Adieu good Trincalo, the secrets of our betters Are dangerous, I dare not know't. Tri. But hear'st thou, Say I should tell, canst keep't as close as I doe? Cri. Yes: but I had rather want it. Adieu. Tri. Albumazar. Cri. Fare-well. Tri. Albumazar. Cri. Pre'thee Tr. Albumazar, Th'Astrologer hath undertooke to change me T'Antonio's shape: this done, must I give Flauia To my old master, and his maid to Trincalo. Cri. But where's Pandolfo and Albumazar? Tri. Gone newly home to choose a chamber fitting For transmutation: So now my heart's at ease. Cri. I feare the skill and cunning of Albumazar With his black Art, by whom Pandolfo seekes To compasse Flavia, spight of her brother Lelio, And his owne Son Eugenio that loves her dearely, I'le loose no time, but finde them and reveale The plot and work to crosse this accident. But Trincalo, art thou so rash and ventrous To be transform'd with hazard of thy life? Tri. What care I for a life, that have a Lease For three: But I am certain there's no danger in't. Cric. No danger, cut thy finger and that pains thee; Then what wilt do to shred and mince thy carkasse, Bury't in horse-dung, mould it new, and turn it T'Antonio: and when th'art chang'd, if Lelio Smell out your plot, what words of punishment Thou must endure, poore Trincalo! the desire Of gains abuses thee: be not transform'd. Trin. Cricca, thou understand est not: for Antonio Whom I resemble, suffers all: not I. Cri. Yonder they come, ile hence and haste to Lelio. SCENE 5. Albumazar. Pandolfo. Cricca. Alb. The Chamber's fit: provide the plate and hangings, And other necessaries: give strict order The Roome be cleans'd, perfum'd and hangd, mean while, With Astralobe, and Meteoroscope, Ile finde the Cuspe and Alfridaria, And know what Planet is in Cazimi. Pan. All shall be ready sir, as you command it. Trin. Doctor Albumazar, I have a vain of drinking, And artery of Leachery runs through my body: Pray when you turn me Gentleman, preserve Those two, if't may be done with Reputation. Alb. Feare not, ile only call the first, good fellowship, And th'other, civill Recreation. Tri. And when you come to th'heart, spoile not the love of Armellina And in my brain leave as much Discretion As may spy falshood in a Tavern reckoning; And let me alone for Bounty to wink and pay't. And if you change me perfectly, Ile bring y'a dozen Knights for customers. Alb. I warrant thee: sir, are you well instructed In all these necessaries? Pan. Th'are in my Table-book. Alb. Forget not clothes for th'new transform'd, and robes For me to sacrifice, you know the fashion. Ile rather change five, then apparell one: For men have living soules, clothes are unanimate. Pan. Here take this Ring, deliver it to my brother, An Officer in the Wardrobe, hee'l furnish you With Robes and Clothes of any stuffe or fashion. Alb. Almuten Alchochoden of the stars attend you. Pan. I kisse your hands divine Astrologer. SCENE 6. Pandolfo, Trincalo. Pan. Vp quickly Trincalo to my child Sulpitia, Bid her lay out my fairest Damaske Table-clothes, The fairest Holland sheets, all the silver Plate Two Gossips cups of gold: my greatest Diamonds: Make haste. Trin. As fast as Alchochoden and Almuten Can carry me: for sure these two are Devils. Pan. This is that blessed day I so much long'd for: Foure houres attentance, till my man be chang'd, Fast locks me in the lovely armes of Flavia. Away Trincalo. How slow the day slides on! When we desire Times haste, it seems to lose a match with Lobsters, And when we wish him stay, he imps his wings With feathers plum'd with thought. Why Trincalo! Trin. Here sir. Pan. Come let's away for cloth of silver, Wine and materials for the Sacrifice. SCEN. 7. Lelio. Eugenio. Cricca. Le. Eugenio, these words are wonders past belief. Is your old Father of so poore a judgement To think it in the power of man to turn One person to another. Eug. Lelio, his desire T'enjoy your sister Flavia, begets hope, Which like a waking dream, makes false apparence Lively as truth it selfe. Le. But who's the man That works these miracles? Eug. An Astrologer. Le. How deals Astrologie with transmutation? Cri. Under the vaile and colour of Astrologie, He clouds his hellish skill in Necromancy. Believe it, by some Art, or false imposture, Hee'l much disturbe your love, and yours, Eugenio. Le. Eugenio, tis high time for t'awake. And as you love our Flavia, and I Your sister faire Sulpitia; let's do something Worthy their beauties. Who fals into a Sea, Swolne big with tempest, but he boldly beares The waves with arms and legs, to save his Life. So let us strive 'gainst troublous storms of Love, With our best power, lest after we ascribe The losse to our dull negligence, not Fortune. Eug. Lelio, had I no interest in your sister, The holy League of friendship should command me, Besides the seconding Sulpitia's love, Who to your noblenesse commends her life. Le. She cannot out-love me, nor you out-friend me, For th'sacred name wherof, I have rejected Your fathers offers, importunities, Letters, Conditions, Servants, Friends, and lastly He's tender of Sulptia in Exchange For Flavia. But though I love your sister Like mine own soule; yet did the Laws of Friendship Master that strong affection; and denied him. Eug. Thanks ever, and as long shall my best service Wait on your will. Cricca our hope's in thee, Thou must instruct us. Cri. You must trust in Fortune That makes or mars the wisest purposes. Le. What sayst? what thinkst? Cri. Here's no great need of thinking Not speech; the oile of Scorpions cures their poyson. The thing it selfe that's bent to hurt and hinder you Offers a remedy: tis no sooner known But th'worst on't is prevented. Eug. How good Cricca? Cri. Soon as you see this false. Antonio Come neere your dores with speeches made of purpose, Full of humility and compassion: With long narrations how he scapt't from shipwrack And other faind inventions of his dangers: Bid him be gone; and if he presse to enter, Feare not the reverence of your fathers looks, Cudgell him thence. Le. But were't not better Cricca Keep him fast lockt, till his own shape return, And so by open course of Law correct him. Cri. No. For my master would conceive that counsell Sprung from my brains: and so should I repent it. Advise no more, but home and charge your people, That if Antonio come, they drive him thence With threatning words, and blows if need be. Lel. 'Tis done. I kisse your hands Eugenio. Eug. Your servant sir. SCENE. 8. Eugenio. Cricca. Flavia. Eug. Cricca commend my service to my Mistris. Cri. Commend it t'her your self. Mark't you not while We talk't, how through the window she attended, And fed her eyes on you there she's. Eug. 'True. And as from nights of Storms the glorious Sun Breaks from the East, and chaseth thence the Clouds That choakt the Ayre with horrour, so her beauty Dispels sad darknesse from my troubled thoughts, And cleers my heart. Fla. Life of my soule well met. Eug. How is't my dearest Flavia? Fla. Eugenio. As best becomes a woman, most unfortunate. That having lov'd so long, and been perswaded Her chast affection was by yours required. Have by delayes been famish'd. Had I conceal'd Those flames your vertue kindled, then y'had sued, Intreated, sworne, and vow'd, and long ere this Wrought all means possible to effect our marriage. But now. Eug. Sweet soule despaire not, weep not thus, Unlesse you wish my heart should life-blood drop. Fast as your eyes do teares. What is't you feare? Fla. First, that you love me not. Eug. Not love my Flavia? Wrong not your judgement: rip up this amorous brest And in that Temple see a heart that burnes I'th' Vestall sacrifice of chastest love, Before your beauties Deitie. Fla. If so, Whence grows this coldnesse in soliciting My brother to the match? Eug. Consider sweetest, I have a father Rivall in my love; And though no duty, reverence, nor respect Have power to change my thoughts: yet tis not comely With open violence to withstand his will; But by faire courses try to divert his minde From disproportioned affections. And if I cannot, then nor feare of anger, Nor life, nor lands, shall crosse our purposes. Comfort your selfe sweet Flavia: for your brother Seconds our hopes with his best services. Fla. But other feares oppresse me: me thinks I see Antonio my old father, new return'd, Whom all intelligence have drown'd this three moneths, Enforcing me to marry the foole Pandolfo, Thus to obtain Sulpitia for himselfe. And so last night I dream'd, and ever since Have been so scar'd, that if you haste not Expect my death. Eug. Dreams flow from thoughts of things we most desire, Or feare, and seldome prove true Prophets, would they did. Then were I now in full possession Of my best Flavia: as I hope I shall be. Cri. Sir, pray take your leave: this to no end, 'Twill but increase your griefe and hers. Eug. Farewell, Sweet Flavia, rest contented with assurance Of my best love and service. Fla. Farewell, Eugenio. SCENE. 9. Salpitia. Flavia. Sul. Flavia I kisse your hands. Fla. Sulpitia, I pray you pardon me, I saw you not. Sul. I faith you have some fixt thoughts draw your eyes inward when you see not your friends before you. Fla. True, and I think the same that trouble you. Sul. Then 'tis the love of a yong Gentleman, and bitter hatred of an old Dotard. Fla. Tis so, witnesse your brother Eugenio, and the rotten carkase of Pandolfo. Had I a hundred hearts, I should want roome to entertain his love, and the other's hate. Sul. I could say as much, were't not sinne to slander the dead. Miserable wenches, how have we offended our fathers, that they should make us the price of their dotage, the medcines of their griefs, that have more need of Physick our selves? I must be frostbitten with the cold of your Dads Winter, that mine may thaw his old Ice with the Spring of your sixteen. I thank my dead mother that left me a womans will in her last Testament: That's all the weapons wee poore Girles can use, and with that will I fight 'gainst father, friends, and kindred, and either enjoy Lelio, or die in the field in's quarrell. Fla. Sulpitia, you are happy that can withstand your fortune with so merry a resolution. Sul. Why? should I twine mine armes to cables, and sigh my soule to ayre? Sit up all night like a Watching Candle, and distill my brains through my eye-lids? your brother loves mee, and I love your brother; and where these two consent, I would faine see a third could hinder us. Fla. Alas, cur Sex is most wretched, nurst up from infancy in continuall slavery. No sooner able to pray for our selves, but they brayle and hud us so with sowre awe of parents, that we dare not offer to bate at our desires. And whereas it becomes men to vent their amorous passions at their pleasure; wee poore soules must take up our affections in the ashes of a burnt heart, not daring to sigh, without excuse of the spleen, or fit of the mother. Sul. I plainly will professe my love of Lelio, tis honest, chast, and stains not modesty. Shall I be married to Antonio, that hath been a soust Sea-fish, this three moneths! and if he be alive comes home with as many impaire, as a Hunting Gelding fal'ne Packhorse. No, no, Ile see him freeze to Christall first. In other things, good father, I am your most obedient daughter, but in this a pure woman. Tis your part to offer, mine to refuse if I like not. Lelio's a handsome Gentleman, yong, fresh, rich, and well fashioned, and him will Sulpitia have, or die a maid: And ifaith, the temper of my bloud tels mee I was never borne to so cold a misfortune. Fie Flavia, fie wench, no more with teares and sighs, cheere up, Eugenio to my knowledge loves you, and you shall have him: I say you shall have him. Fla. I doubt not of his love, but know no means how he dares worke against so great a Rivall: your father in a spleene may disinherit him. Sul. And give't to whom? has none but him and mee: What though he dote awhile upon your beauty; hee will not prove unnaturall to his sonne. Go to your chamber: my Genius whispers in my eare, and sweares this night we shall enjoy our loves, and with that hope farewell. Fla. Farewell Sulpitia. Finis Act. 2.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Act. 3. Scene 1. Pandolfo. Cricca. Pan. While the Astrologer hews out Trincalo, Squaring and framing him t'Antonio, Cricca Ile make thee partner of a thought That something trouble me. Cri. Say sir, what is't? Pan. I have no heart to give Albumazar The chain I promist him. Cri. Deliver it me And Ile present it to him in your name. Pan. 'Thas been an Aire loom to our house foure hundred yeers, And should I leave it now, I feare good fortune Would flie from us, and follow it. Cri. Then give him The price in gold. Pan. It comes to a hundred pounds. And how would that well husbanded grow in time? I was a foole to promise, I confesse it, I was too hot and forward in the businesse. Cri. Indeed I wondred that your wary thriftinesse Not wont to drop one peny in a quarter Idly, would part with such a summe so easily. Pan. My covetous thrift aymes at no other marke Then in fit time and place to shew my bounty. Who gives continually, may want at length Wherewith to feed his liberality. But for the love of my deare Flavia I would not spare my life, much lesse my treasure. Yet if with honour I can winne her cheaper, Why should I cast away so great summe? Cri. True: I have a trick now hatching in my brain How you may handsomely preserve your credit, And save the chain. Pan. I would gladly do it, But feare he understands us what we say. Cri. What can you lose to try't, if it take There's so much sav'd, if otherwise, nothing lost. Pan. What is't Good Cricca? Cri. Soon as Albumazar comes, loaded with news Of th'transmutation of your servant Trincalo, Ile entertain him here meanwhile steal you Closely into the Room, and quickly hide Some speciall piece of Plate: Then run out amaz'd, Roaring, that all the Street may know y'are rob'd. Next threaten to attach him and accuse him Before a Iustice, and in th'end agree If he restore the Plate, you'le give the Chain, Otherwise not. Pan. But if we be discov'red! For by his Instruments and Familiars He can do much. Cri. Lay all the fault on Trincalo. But here's the mayn point. If you can dissemble Cunningly, and frame your countenance to expresse Pitty and anger, that so learn'd a man Should use his friend so basely: if you can call An out-cry well, roare high and terrible. Pan. Ile fetch a cry from th'bottome of my heels But Ile roare loud enough; and thou must second me With wonder at the sudden accident. Cri. But yours is the mayn part, for as you play't You win or lose the chain. Pan. No more, no more, he comes. SCENE. 2. Albumazar, Pandolfo, Cricca. Alb. Signior Pandolfo, three quarters of an houre Renders your servant perfectly transform'd. Cri. Is he not wholy chang'd? what parts are wanting? Alb. Antonio's shape hath cloath'd his bulk and visage, Onely his hands and feet, so large and callous, Require more time to supple. Cri. Pray you sir How long shall he retain this Metamorphosis? Alb. The compleat circle of a naturall day. Cri. A naturall day? Are any days unnaturall? Alb. I mean the revolution o'th first mover, Iust twice twelve houres, in which period the rapt motion Rowles all the Orbs from East to Occident. Pan. Help, help, theeves, theeves, neighbours I am rob'd, theeves, theeves! Cri. What a noyse make you sir? Pan. Have I not reason That thus am rob'd, theeves, theeves, call Constables, The Watch and Serjeants, Friends, and Constables, Neighbours I am undone. Cri. This well begun So he hold out still with a higher strain. What ayles you sir? Pan. Cricca my chamber's spoild Of all my hangings, clothes, and silver plate. Cri. Why, this is bravely fain'd; continue sir. Pan. Lay all the Goldsmith, Keepers, Marshals, Bayliffes. Cri. Fie sir, your passion fals, cry louder, roare That all the Street may heare. Pan. Theeves, theeves, theeves! All that I had is gone, and more then all. Cri. Ha, ha, ha: hold out; lay out a Lyons throat, A little lowder. Pan. I can cry no longer, My throat's sore, I am rob'd, all's gone. Both my own treasure, and the things I borrow'd. Make thou an out-cry, I have lost my voyce: Cry fire, and then they'l heare thee. Cri. Good, good, theeves, What ha you lost? Pan. Wine, jewels, table-clothes, A Cup-board of rich plate. Cri. Fie, youle spoyle all. Now you out-do it. Say but a bowle or two. Pan. Villain, I say al's gone; the Room's as clean As a wipt looking glasse: oh me, oh me. Cri. What, in good earnest? Pan. Fool in accursed earnest. Cri. You gull me sure. Pan. The window towards the South stands ope, from whence went all my treasure. Where's the Astrologer? Alb. Here sir, and hardly can abstain from laughing To see you vex your selfe in vain. Pan. In vain Albumazar? I left my Plate with you, and tis all vanisht, And you shall answer it. Alb. O! were it possible By powre of Art, to check what Art hath done, Your man should nere be chang'd: to wrong me thus With foule suspition of flat Felony? Your Plate, your cloth of silver, wine, and jewels, Linnen, and all the rest, I gave to Trincalo, And for more safety, lockt them in the Lobby. Heel keep them carefully. But as you love your Mistris Disturbe him not this half houre, lest youle have him Like to a Centaure, halfe Clown, halfe Gentleman, Suffer his foot and hand that's yet untoucht, To be innobled like his other members. Pan. Albumazar, I pray you pard on me, Th'unlookd for barenesse of the Room amazd me. Alb. How? think you me so negligent to commit So rich a masse of treasure to th'open danger Of a large casement, and suspitious Alley? No sir, my sacrifice no sooner done But I wrapt all vp safe, and gaue it Trincalo. I could be angry, but that your suddain feare Excuses you. Fie, such a noise as this Halfe an houre past, had skar'd the intelligences, And spoyld the work, but no harm done, go walke Westward, directly westward, on halfe houre: Then turn back, and take your servant turnd t'Antonio. And as you like my skill, performe your promise. I mean the chain. Pan. Content, lets still go westward, Westward good Cricca, still directly westward. SCENE 3. Albumazar, Ronca, Harpax, Furbo. Alb. Fvrbo, Harpax, and Ronca, come out, al's cleere. Why hero's a noble prize worth ventring for. Is not this braver then sneak all night in danger, Picking of locks, or hooking clothes at windows? Here's plate and gold, and cloth, and meat and wine, All rich, and easily got. Ronca stay here about, And wait till Trincalo come forth: then call him With a low reverence Antonio, Give him this gold with thanks, tell him he lent it Before he went to Barbary. Ron. How lose ten peeces? Alb. There's a necessity in't, devise some course To get't again: if not, our gain's sufficient To beare that losse. Furbo finde out Bavilona The Curtezan, let her fain her selfe a Gentlewoman Inamored of Antonio, bid her invite him To banket with her, and by all means possible Force him stay there two houres. Har. Why two houres? Alb. That in that time thou mayst convey Our treasure to the Inne, and speak a Boat Ready for Gravesend, and provide a Supper: Where, with those precious liquors, and good meats, Wee'l cheere our selves; and thus well fed, and merry, Take Boat by night. Fur. And what will you do? Alb. First in and usher out our changeling Trincalo. Then finish up a businesse of great profit, Begun with a rich Merchant, that admires My skill in Alchymy. I must not lose it. Ron. Harpax bestow the plate, Furbo our beards, Black patches for our eyes, and other properties, And at the time and place meet all at Supper. SCENE. 9 Albumazar. Trincalo. Alb. Stand forth transform'd Antonio fully mued From brown soare feathers of dull yeomanry To th'glorious bloome of Gentry: prune your selfe, slick; Sweare boldly y'are the man you represent. To all that dare deny it. Tri. I finde my thoughts Most strangely altred, but me thinks, my face Feels still like Trincalo. Alb. You imagine so. Senses are oft deceiv'd. As an attentive Angler Fixing his steady eyes on the swift streams Of a steep tumbling torrent, no sooner turns His sight to Land, but giddy, thinks the firme banks And constant trees, move like the running waters: So you that thirty yeers have liv'd in Trincalo, Chang'd suddainly, think y'are so still; but instantly These thoughts will vanish. Tri. Give me a Looking-glasse To read your skill in these new Lineaments. Alb. I'rather give you poyson: for a glasse By secret power of crosse reflections, And Optick vertue, spoyls the wondrous work Of transformation, and in a moment turns you. Spight of my skill, to Trincalo as before, We reade that Apuleius by a Rose Chang'd from an Asse to Man: so by a mirrour, You'l loose this noble lustre, and turn Asse. I humbly take my leave; but still remember T'avoid the Devill and a Looking-glasse. New-born Antonio, I kisse your hands. Tri. Divine Albumazar, I kisse your hands. SCEN. 5. Trincalo. Ronca. Tri. Now I am grown a Gentleman, and a fine one, I know't by th'kissing of my hands so courtly, My courteous knees bend in so true distance As if my foot walkt in a frame of purpose. Thus I accost you: or thus sweet sir, your servant: Nay, more your servants servant: that's your grand-servant. I could descend from the top of Pauls to th'bottome, And on each step strew parting complements, Strive for a doore while a good Carpenter Might make a new one. I am your shadow sir, And bound to wait upon you yfaith I will not: pray sir, &amp;c. O brave Albumazar! Ron. Iust Æsops Crow, prink't up in borrowed feathers. Tri. My veins are fild with newnesse: O for a Chyrurgian To ope this arme, and view my gentle bloud, To try if't run two thousand pounds a yeere. I feele my understanding is inlarg'd With the rare knowledge of this latter age. A sacred fury over-swayes me. Prime! Deale quickly, play, discard, I set ten shillings six pence. You see't? my rest, five and a fifty. Boy, more Cards. And as thou go'st, lay out some roaring oaths For me; Ile pay thee again with interest. O brave Albumazar! Ron. How his imagination boyls, and works in all things He ever saw or heard! Tri. At Gleek? content. A mournnevall of Ases, Gleek of Knaves. Iust nine a piece. Sir, my gray Barbary 'Gainst your dun Cow, three train sents and th'course, For fifty pound; as I am a Gentleman Ile meet next Cocking, and bring a Haggard with me That stoops as free as lightning, strikes like thunder. I lye? my reputation you shall heare on't. O brave Albumazar! Ron. He'l grow stark mad I feare me. Tri. Now I know I am perfectly transform'd my minde incites me To challenge some brave fellow for my credit, And for more safety, get some friend in private To take the businesse up in peace and quiet. Ron. Signior Antonio? Tri. There's not a crum of Trincalo. In all this frame, but the love of Armellina: Wer't not for thee I'de travail, and home again As wise as I went over. Ron. Signior Antonio? welcome ten thousand times: Blest be the Heavens and Seas for your return. Tri. I thank you sir: Antonio is your servant, I am glad to see you well. Fie, I kisse your hands: and thus accost you. Ron. This three months all your kindred, friends, and children, Mourn'd for your death. Tri. And so they well might do, For five dayes I was under water; and at length Got up and spred my selfe upon a chest, Rowing with arms, and stearing with my feet; And thus in five dayes more got land: believe it I made a most incredible escape, And safe return from Barbary: at your service: Ron. Welcome ten thousand times from Barbary, No friend more glad to see Antonio Then I: nor am I thus for hope of gain; But that I finde occasion to be gratefull By your return. Do you remember sir, Before you went, as I was once arrested, And could not put in bayle; you passing by, Lent me ten pound, and so discharg'd the debt? Tri. Yes, yes, as well as 'twere but yesterday. Ron. Oft have I waited at your house with money, And many thanks: but you were still beyond Seas. Now am I happy of this faire occasion To testifie my honest care to pay you: For you may need it. Trin. Sir, I do indeed, Witnesse my treasure cast away by shipwrack. Ron. Here sir. Tri. Is the gold good, for mine was good I lent you: Ron. It was, and so is this. Signior Antonio, for this curtesie. Call me your servant. Tri. Farwell good servant, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha. I know not so much as his name! ten pounds? this change is better then my birth: for in all the yeers of my yeomanry I could never yoake two crownes, and now I have hoarded ten faire twenty shilling pieces. Now will I go to this Astrologer, and hire him turn my Cart to a Caroch, my foure Iades to two Dutch Mares, my Mistris Armellina to a Lady, my Plow-boy Dick to two guarded foot-men: then will I hurry my self into the Mercers Books, weare rich clothes, be call'd Tony by a great man, sell my lands, pay no debts, hate Citizens, and beat Serjants: and when all fails, sneake out of Antonio with a two-peny Looking-glasse, and turne as true Trincalo as ever. SCENE 6. Harpax, Trincalo. Har. Signior Antonio, welcome. Tri. My life here's ten pound more. I thank you heartily. Harp. Never in fitter season could I finde you. If you remember sir, before you went To Barbary, I lent you ten pound in gold. Tri. Faith I remember no such thing, excuse me. What may I call your name? Harp. My name is Harpax, Your friend and neighbour, of your old acquaintance. Tri. What Harpax? I am your servant, I kisse your hands? You must excuse me, you never lent me mony. Har. Sir, as I live, ten twentie shilling pieces. Tri. Dangers at Sea, I finde, have hurt my memory. Har. Why here's your own hand-writing: seal'd and sign'd, In presence of your cousen Julio. Tri. Tis true, tis true; but I sustaind great losses By reason of the shipwrack. Here's five pieces, Will that content you? and to morrow morning Come to my house and take the rest. Har. Well sir, Though my necessitie would importune you For all, yet on your Worships word, the rest Ile call for in the morning. Farewell Antonio. Tri. I see we Gentlemen can sometime borrow As well as lend, and are as loth to pay As meaner men. Ile home, lest other Creditors Call for the rest. SCENE. 7. Ronca. Trincalo. Ron. Signior Antonio: I saw you as I landed, And in great haste follow'd to congratulate Your safe return, with these most wisht embraces. Tri. And I accept your joy with like affection. How do you call your selfe? Ron. Have you forgot Your deare friend Ronca, whom you lov'd so well? Tri. O I remember now my deare friend Ronca. Ron. Thanks to the fortune of the Seas that sav'd you. Tri. I feare I owe him monie: how shall I shift him? How do's your body Ronca? Ron. My deare Antonio, Never so well as now I have the power Thus to embrace my friend, whom all th'Exchange Gave drown'd for three whole moneths. My deare Antonio. Tri. I thank you sir. Ron. I thank you. Tri. While my dear Ronca Clipt me, my purse shook dangerously; yet both his arms And hands embrac'd my neck: here's none behind me. How can this be? Ron. Most deare Antonio, Was not your passage dangerous from Barbary? We had great windes and tempests; and I feare me, You felt the force at Sea. Tri. Yes dearest Ronca. How's this? I see his hands, and yet my purse is gone. Ron. Signior Antonio, I see your mind's much troubled About affaires of worth; I take my leave: And kisse your hands of Liberalitie. Tri. And kisse my hands of Liberalitie? I gave him nothing: Oh my purse, my purse! Deare Master Ronca. Ron. Whats your pleasure sir? Tri. Shew me your hand. Ro. Here tis. Tr. But where's th'other? Ron. Why here. Tri. But I mean where's your other hand? Ron. Think you me the Gyant with a hundred hands? Tri. Give me your right. Ron. My right? Tri. Your left Ron. My left? Tri. Now both. Ron. There's both my deare Antonio: Keep your selfe dark, eat broth: your fearfull passage, And want of naturall rest, hath made you frantick. Tri. Villain, rogue, cut-purse, thief, dear Ronca stay: he's gone I'th'Devils name, how could this fellow do it? I felt his hands fast lockt about my neck; And still he spoake, it could not be his mouth: For that was full of deare Antonio: My life he stole't with his feet: such a trick more Will work worse with me then a Looking-glasse: To lose five pound in curt'sie, and the rest In salutation! Ron. Signior Antonio, What ails you? Tri. Ronca a Rogue, a Cut-purse Hath rob'd me of five twenty shilling pieces. Ron. What kind of man was he: something like me? Tri. Had such a thievish countenance as your own, But that he wore a black patch ore his eye. Ron. Met you with Ronca: tis the cunningst nimmer Of the whole company of Cut-purse hall: I am sorrie I was not here to warn you of him. SCENE 8. Furbo, Beuilona, Trincalo. Beu. Furbo no more, unlesse thy words were charms Of power to revive him: Antonio's dead. He's dead, and in his death hath buried All my delights: my eares are deafe to Musick That sounds of pleasure: sing then the dolefulst notes That e're were set by Melancholly: O Antonio! Furbio sings this Song: Flow streams of liquid salt from my sad eyes, To celebrate his mournfull Exequies. Antonio's dead, he's dead, and I remayn To draw my poor life in continuall pain, Till it have paid to his sad memory Duty of love: O then most willingly, Drown'd with my teares, as he with waves, I die: Beu. Break thy sad strings, and instrument: O strange! he's here. Signior Antonio! my hearts sweet content! My life and better portion of my soule! Are you return'd? and safe? for whose sad death I spent such streams of tears, and gusts of sighs? Or is't my love, that to my longing fancy Frames your desired shape, and mocks my senses? Tri. Whom do you talk withall faire Gentlewoman? Beu. With my best friend, commander of my life, My most beloved Antonio. Tri. With me? What's your desire with me sweet Lady? Beu. Sir, to command me, as you have done ever, To what you please: for all my liberty Lies in your service. Tri. Now I smell the businesse. This is some Gentlewoman enamoured With him whose shape I beare: Fie what an Asse Was I to strange my selfe, and lose the occasion Of a good banquet, and her company? Ile mend it as I can. Madam, I did but jest To try if absence caus'd you to forget A friend that lov'd you ever. Beu. Forget Antonio, Whose deare remembrance doth informe the soule Of your poore servant Bevilona? no, No, had you dy'd, it had not quencht't one spark Of th'sweet affection which your love hath kindled In this warme brest. Tri. Madam, the waves had drown'd mee, But that your love held up my chin. Beu. Wil't please you Enter, and rest your selfe, refresh the wearinesse Of your hard travaile; I have good wine and fruits, My Husband's out of town: you shall command My house, and all that's in't. Tri. Why are you married? Beu. Have you forgot my Husband: an angry roarer? Tri. O I remember him: but if he come. Beu. Whence grows this feare? how come you so respectfull? You were not wont be numb'd with such a coldnesse. Go in sweet life, go in. Tri. O I remember while I liv'd in Barbary A pretty Song the Moores sing to a Gridiron: Sweet Madam by your favour Ile sing't to this. Alcoch Dolash, &amp;c. Thus 'tis in English. My heart in flames doth fry, Of thy beauty, While I Die. Fie? And why Shouldst thou deny Me thy sweet company? My brains to teares do flow While all below Doth glow. O! Foe If so, How canst thou go About to say me no? This the Moores call two wings upon a Gridiron. But it goes sweeter far o'th'iron instrument. Ron. There's one within my Kitchin ready strung: go in. Tri. Sweet Lady pardon me, Ile follow you. Happy Antonio in so rare a Mistris! But happier I, that in his place enjoy her: I say still, ther's no pleasure like transforming. SCENE 9. Ronca. Bevil. Trincalo. Ron. Now is the Asse expecting of a banquet, Ready to court, embrace, and kisse his Mistris. But Ile soon stave him. Tick, tock, what ho! Beu. Who's that so boldly knocks? I am not within; Or busie: Why so importunate? who i'tt? Ron. Tis. Is Beu. Your name? Ron. Thomas up William, up Morgan, up Davy, up Roger, &amp;c. Tri. Spinola's Camp's broke loose: a troupe of Souldiers! si Beu. Oj me! my Husband! Oj me wretch, 'tis my Husband. Tri. One man, and weare so many names! Beu. O sir H'as more outragious Devils in his rage, Then names. As you respect your life, avoid him. Down at that window. Tri. Tis as high as Pauls. Open the Garden doore. Beu. He has the keyes. Down at some window, as you love your life, Tender my honour, and your safety. Ron. Bevilona? Down, or Ile break the doores, and with the splinters Beat all thy bones to pieces: Down you whore! Beu. Be patient but a little; I come instantly. Tri. Ha' you no trunk nor chest to hide me? Beu. None sir. Tri. Alas I am clean undone, it is my Husband. Ron. Doubtlesse, this whore hath some of her companions That wrong me thus. But if I catch the villain, Ile bath my hungry sword, and sharp revenge, In his heart-bloud. Come down. Beu. I cannot stay. There stands a empty Hogshead with a false bottom To ope and shut at pleasure; come hither, in, In as you love your life. Tri. But heare you Madam, Is there no Looking-glasse within't? for I hate glasses As naturally as some do Cats, or Cheese. Beu. In, in, there's none. Ron. Who now? Is the Asse past? Beu. I tunn'd him up, ha, ha, ha, I feare he'le fall a working. Ron. Second me handsomely, we'le entertain him An houre or two, and laugh and get his clothes To make our sport up. Wife where's the empty Hogshead That wont to stand under the staires? Beu. There still. Ron. Out with it quicly: I must have it fild. Beu. Not to day, good sir, to morrow will serve as well. Ron. I must ha't now. Beu. Tis more then I can carry. Ron. Ile help thee: so, so. Foh! this vessell's musty. Fetch out some water. Beu. Fetcht your selfe. Tri. Pox of all Transmutation, I am smother'd. Lady, as you love me, give the Hogshead vent. The beere that's in't will work and break the vessell. Beu. Signior Antonio, as you love your life Lie still and close, for if you stirre you die. Ron. So, so, now shake it, so, so. Tri. Oh I am drown'd, I drown! Ron. Whence comes this hollow sound? I drown, I smother! Ron. My life tis Trincalo, For I have heard that Coxcombe, That Asse, that Clown, seeks to corrupt my wife, Sending his fruit and dainties from the Country. O that 'twere he. How would I use the villain! First crop his eares, then slit his nose and geld him, And with a red hot iron seare his raw wounds; Then barrell him again, and send the Eunuch To the great Turk to keep his Concubines. Tick, tock, who's within heere? Beu. One that you dare not touch. Ron. One that I dare not? Out villain, out. Signior Antonio! Had it been any but your selfe, he dyed. But as you sav'd my life before you went, So now command mine in your services. I would have sworn y'had been drown'd in Barbary. Tri. 'Twas a hard passage: but not so dangerous As was this vessell. Pray you conceive no ill, I meant no harme, but call'd of your wife to know How my sonne Lelio did, and daughter Flavia. Ron. Sir I believe you. Tri. But I must tell you one thing, You must not be so jealous, on my honour She's very honest. Ron. For you I make no question. But there's a Rogue call'd Trincalo, whom if I catch. Ile teach him. Tri. Who, you mean Pandolfo's Farmer. Alas poore foole, he's a stark Asse, but harmlesse. And though she talk with him, tis but to laugh, As all the world do's at him: come be friends At my intreaty. Ron. Sir, for your sake. Ben. I thank you. Tri. Lets have a fire; and while I dry my self, Provide good wine and meat. Ile dine with you. I must not home thus wet. I am something bold with you. Ron. My house and self are at your service. Tri. Lead in. Alas, poore Trincalo, hadst thou been taken, Thou hadst been tunn'd for Turkie. Ha, ha, ha, ha, faire fall Antonio's shape. What a notorious Wittal's this! Ha, ha, ha. Finis. Act. 3.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Act. 4. Scene 1. Antonio. Thus by great favour of propitious Stars, From fearfull storms, shipwrack, and raging billows, Mercilesse jaws of Death, am I return'd To th'safe and quiet bosome of my Country, And wish'd embracements of my Friends and Kindred. The memory of these misfortunes past, Seasons the welcome, and augments the pleasure I shall receive of my sonne Lelio, And daughter Flavia. So doth alloy Make gold, that else were uselesse, serviceable. So the rugged forehead of a threatning Mountain, Threatens the smoothnesse of a smiling Valley. SCENE 2. Cricca, Antonio. Cri. What do I see? is not this Trincalo Transform'd t'Antonio? tis, and so perfectly That did the right Antonio now confront him, I'de sweare they both were true, or both were false. Ant. This man admires the unexpectednesse Of my return. Cri. O wondrous powre of Stars, And skil of Art t'apply't. You that are married May justly feare, lest this Astrologer Cloath your wives servants in your shape, and use you As Jupiter did Amphitrio. You that are rich, In your own forme may lose your gold. Ant. Tis Cricca. Cri. He seems so just the man he represents, That I dare hardly use him as I purposd. Ant. Cricca, well met, how fares my friend Pandolfo? Cri. Your friend Pandolfo? how are your means improv'd, To stile familiarly your Masters friend? Ant. What sayst thou? Cri. That I rejoyce your Worship's safe returnd From your late drowning. Th'Exchange hath giv'n you lost; And all your friends worn mourning three months past. Ant. The danger of the shipwrack I escapt, So desperate was, that I may truly say I am new born, not sav'd. Cri. Ha, ha, ha, through what a grace And goodly countenance the Rascall speaks: What a grave portance; could Antonio Himself out-do him? O you notorious villain! Who would have thought thou couldst have thus dissembled? Ant. How now: a servant thus familiar? Syrrha Use your companions so; more reverence Becomes you better. Cric. As though I understood not. The end of all this plot and goodly businesse? Come I know all, see! this untill'd clod of earth. Conceits his minde transform'd, as well as body. He wrings and bites his lips for feare of laughing. Ha, ha, ha! Ant. Why laugh you sirra? Cri. To see thee chang'd So strangely, that I cannot spy on inch Of thy old Clownish Carkas. Ha, ha. Ant. Laughter proceeds From absurd actions that are harmlesse. Cri. Ha, ha, ha, Sententious Block-head. Ant. And y'are all advis'd To jeast in stead of pitty. Alas! my miseries, Dangers of death, slav'ry of cruell Moores, And tedious journeys, might have easily altred A stronger body; much more this decay'd vessell, Out-worn with age, and broken by misfortunes. Cri. Leave your set speeches. Go to Antonio's house, Effect your businesse. For upon my credit Th'art so well turn'd, they dare not but accept thee. Ant. Where should I hope for welcome, if not there; From my own house, children and family? Cri. Is't possible this Coxcombe should conceive His minde transform'd? How gravely he continues The countenance he began? Ha, ha. Why Blockhead? Thinkst to deceive me too? Why Trincalo? Ant. I understand you not. Hands off. Cri. Art not thou Trincalo, Pandolfo's man? Ant. I not so much as know him. Cri. Dar'st thou deny't to me? Ant. I dare, and must To all the World, 'long as Antonio lives. Cri. You arrant Asse, have I not known thee serve My Master in his Farm this thirteen yeers? Ant. By all the oathes that binde mens consciences To truth, I am Antonio; and no other. SCENE. 3. Pandolfo, Cricca, Antonio. Pa. What means this noise? O Cricca! what's the matter? Cri. Sir, here's your Farmer Trincalo, transform'd So just, as he were melted, and new cast In the true mould of old Antonio. Pan. Th'right eye's no liker to the left, then he To my good neighbour. Divine Albumazar! How I admire thy skill! just so he look't, And thus he walkt; this is his face, his haire, His eyes and countenance; If his voyce be like, Then is th'Astrologer a wonder-worker. Ant. Signior Pandolfo, I thanke the heavens as much To finde you well, as for my owne returne. How does your daughter, and my love Sulpitia? Pan. Well, well sir. Cri. This is a good beginning, How naturally the rogue dissembles it? With what a gentle garbe, and civill grace He speakes and lookes: How cunningly Albumazar Hath for our purpose suted him in Barbary cloaths. Ile try him furthere: sir, We heard you were drownd, pray you, how scap't you shipwrak? Ant. No sooner was I shipt for Barbary, But faire winde follow'd, and faire weather led us. When entred in the Scraites of Gibralter; The heavens, and seas, and earth conspir'd against us, The tempest tore our helme, and rent our tackels, Broake the maine Mast, while all the sea about us Stood up in watry Mountaines to over-whelme us. And struck's against a Rocke, splitting the vessell T'a thousand splinters. I with two Marriners Swam to the Coast, where by the barbarous Moores We were surpriz'd, fetter'd and sold for slaves. Cri. This tale th'Astrologer pen'd, and he hath cond it. Ant. But by a Gentleman of Italy Whom I had knowne before. Pan. No more, this tast Proves thou canst play the rest. For this faire story; My hand I make thy ten pound, twenty Markes. Thou lookst and speakst so like Antonio. Ant. Whom should I looke and speake like, but my selfe? Cri. Good still! Pan. But now my honest Trincalo, Tell me where's all the Plate, the gold, and Iewels, That the Astrologer, when he had transformd thee Committed to thy charge? are they safe lockt? Ant. I understand you not. Pan. The jewels man, The plate and gold th'Arologer that chang'd thee Bad thee lay up? Ant. What plate? what gold? What jewels? what transformation? what Astrologer? Cri. Leave off Antonio now, and speak like Trincalo. An. Leave off your jesting; it neither fits your place Nor age, Pandolfo, to scoffe your ancient friend. I know not what you mean by gold and jewels, Nor by th'Arologer, nor Trincalo. Cri. Better and better still. Beleeve me sir, He thinks himselfe Antonio, and ever shall be. And so possesse your plate. Art thou not Trincalo My Masters Farmer? An. I am Antonio Your Masters friend, if he teach you no more manners. Pan. Humour of wiving's gone; farewell good Flavia. Three thousand pound must not be lost so slightly. Come sir, wee'l draw you to th'Astrologer, And turn you to your ragged bark of Yeomanry: An. To me these terms! Pan. Come ile not lose my plate. Cri. Stay, sir, and take my counsell. Let him still Firmly conceit himselfe the man he seems: Thus he himself deceiv'd, will farre more earnestly Effect your businesse, and deceive the rest. There's a mayn difference twixt a self-bred action And a forst carriage. Suffer him then to enter Antonio's house: and waite th'euent: for him He cannot scape: what you intend to do, Do't when 'has seru'd your turne. I see the maide, Lets hence lest they suspect our consultations. Pan. Thy counsels good: away! Cri. Looke Trincalo Yonder's your beauteous mistresse Armellina, And daughter Flauia. Courage, I warrant thee. An. Blest be the heav'ns? that rid me of this trouble. For with their Farmer and Astrologer, Plate, and gold, the 'aue almost madded me. SCENE. 4. Flavia, Armellina, Antonio. Fla. Armellina. Arm. Mistris. Fla. Is the dore fast? Ar. Yes, as an Usurers purse. Fla. Come hither wench Look here, there's Trincalo, Pandolfoes Farmer, Wrapt in my fathers shape: prithee come quickly, And help me to abuse him. Ar. Notorious Clown? An. These are my gates, and that's the Cabinet That keeps my jewels, Lelio, and his sister. Fla. Never was villany so personate In seemly properties of gravity. An. Tick, tock. Fla. Who is he that knocks so boldly? Ar. What want you, sir. An. O my faire daughter Flavia! Let all the Stars Powre down full blessings on thee: Ope the doores. Fla. Mark! his faire daughter Flavia, ha, ha, ha: Most shamelesse villain how he counterfeits! An. Know'st not thy father, old Antonio, Is all the world grown frantick? Fla. What Antonio? An. Thy loving father, Flavia. Fla. My father! Would thou wert in his place. Antonio's dead, Dead, under water was drownd. An. Then dead and drownd Am I. Fla. I love not to converse with dead men. An. Open the doore sweet Flavia. Fla. Sir, I am afeard; Horrour incloses me, my haire stands up, I sweat to heare a dead man speak, you smell Of putrifaction: fie! I feel't hither. An. Th'art much abus'd, I live: come down, and know me. Ar. Mistris let me have some sport too. Who's there? An. Let me come in. Ar. Soft, soft sir, y'are too hasty. An. Quickly, or else— Ar. Good word, good words, I pray In strangers houses! were the doores your own, You might be bolder. An. Ile beat the doores and windows About your eares. Ar. Are you so hot? wee'l coole you. Since your late drowning, your gray and reverent head Is smear'd with Oes, and stuck with Cockle-shels, This is to wash it. An. Impudent whore! Ar. Out Carter: Hence durty whipstock, hence you foule clown: be gone, Or all the water I can make, or borrow, Shall once more drown you. SCENE 5. Lelio, Antonio, Armellina. Le. Armellina; whom do you draw your t?gue upon so sharply? Ar. Sir tis your fathers ghost, that strives by force To break the doores and enter. Le. This his grave look! In every lineament himselfe no liker. Had I not haply been advertized, What could have forc'd me think 'twere Trincalo: Doubtlesse, th'Astrologer hath raisd a ghost That walks in th'reverend ghost of my dead father. An. These ghosts, these Trincalo's, and Astrologers, Strike me beside my selfe. Who will receive me When mine own sonne refuseth? Oh Antonio! Le. Infinite power of Art! who would believe The Planets influence could transforme a man To severall shapes: I could now beat him soundly? But that he weares the awfull countenance Of my dead father, whose memory I reverence. An. If I be chang'd beyond thy knowledge, sonne, Consider that th'excesse of heat in Barbary, The feare of shipwrack, and long tedious journies, Have tand my skin, and shrunk my eyes and cheeks; Yet still this face, though alterd, may be known. This skarre bears witnesse, twas the wound thou cur'dst With thine own hands. Le. He that chang'd Trincalo T'Antonio's figure, omitted not the skarre As a mayn character. An. I have no other marks Or reasons to perswade thee; me thinks, this word I am thy father, were argument sufficient To bend my knees, and creep to my embracements. Le. A sudden coldnesse strikes me, my tender heart Beats with compassion of I know not what. Sirra be gone, trusse up your goodly speeches, Sad shipwracks, and strange transformations. Your plot's discovered, 'twill not take: thy impudence For once I pardon. The pious reverence I owe to th'grave resemblance of my father Holds back my angry hands. Hence, if I catch you Haunting my doores again, ile bastinado you Out of Antonio's skin; away. An. I go sir, And yield to such crosse fortune as thus drives me. SCENE 6. Trincalo and Beuilona dressing him. Tri. When this transformed substance of my carcasse Did live imprison'd in a wanton hogshead, My name was Don Antonio, and that title Preserv'd my life, and chang'd my suite of clothes. How kindly the good Gentlewoman us'd me! with what Respect and carefull tendernesse! your Worship sir had ever a sickly constitution, and I feare much more now since your long travaile: as you love me, off with these wet things, and put on the suite you left with me before you went to Barbary. Good sir neglect not your health: for upon my Experience there is nothing worse for the Rheume, then to be drench't in a musty Hogshead. Pretty soul! such another speech would have drawn off my legs and arms, as easily as hose and doublet. Had I been Trincalo, I'de have sworn th'had cheated. But fie! tis base and clownish to suspect, and a Gentlemans freenesse to part with a cast suit. Now to the businesse: Ile in to my own house, and first bestow Armellina upon Trincalo, then try what can be done for Pandolfo: for tis a rule I wont t'observe. First, do your own affairs, and next your Masters. This word Master makes me doubt I am not charg'd as I should be. But al's one, Ile venter, and doe something worthy Antonios' name while I have it. SCEN. 7. Antonio, Trincalo. Ant. Wretched Antonio, hast been preserv'd so strangely From forraine miseries, to be wrong'd at home? Bar'd from thy house by the scorns of thine own children? Tri. Tick, tock. Ant. But stay, there's one knocks boldly 't may be some friend. Tri. Tick, tock. Ant. Dwell you here Gentleman? Tri. He cals me Gentleman, See th'vertue of good cloaths: all men salute, Honour, respect, and reverence us. Ant. Yong Gentleman, Let me without offence intreat your name, And why you knock. Tri. How sirra Sawce-box, my name? Or thou some stranger art, or grosly ignorant That knowst not me. Ha! what art thou that ask'st it? Ant. Be not in choler sir. Tri. Befits it me, A Gentleman of publick reputation, To stoop so low as satisfie the questions Of base and earthly pieces like thy selfe? What art thou? ha? Ant. Th'unfortunate possessor of this house. Tri. Thou ly'st base Sycophant, my Worship owes it. Ant. May be my sonne hath sold it in my absence, Thinking me dead. How long has't call'd your Master? Tri. 'Long as Antonio possest it. Ant. Which Antonio? Tri. Antonio, Anastasio. Ant. That Anastasio, That drown'd in Barbary? Tri. That Anastasio, That selfe same man am I: I scapt by swimming, And now return to keep my former promise Of Flavia to Pandolfo; and in exchange, To take Sulpitia to my wife. Ant. All this I intended 'fore I went: but sir, if I Can be no other then my selfe, and you Are that Antonio, you and I are one. Tri. How? one with thee? speak such another sillable, And by the terrour of this deadly steele, That nere saw light, but sent to endlesse darknesse All that durst stand before't: thou diest. Ant. Alas My weaknesse grown by age, and pains of travail, Disarms my courage to defend my selfe; I have no strength but patience. Tri. What art now? Ant. Peter, and Thomas, William, what you please. Tri. What boldnesse madded thee to steale my name? Ant. Sir, heat of wine. Tri. And when y'are drunk, Is there no person to put on but mine, To cover your intended villanies? Ant. But good sir, if I be not I, who am I? Tri. An Oxe, an Asse, a Dog. Ant. Strange negligence To lose my selfe! me thinks I live and move, Remember. Could the fearfull apprehension Of th'ugly feare of drowning so transforme me? Or did I die, and by Pythagoras rule, My soule is provided of another lodging? Tri. Be what thou wilt, except Antonio, 'Tis death to touch that name. Ant. Dangers at Sea Are pleasures, weigh'd with these home-injuries. Was ever man thus scar'd beside himselfe? O most unfortunate Antonio! At Sea thou suffredst shipwrack of thy goods, At land of thine own selfe. Antonio? Or what name else they please? flie, flie to Barbary, And rather there endure the forraigne crueltie Of fetters, whips, and Moores, then here at home Be wrong'd and baffled by thy friends and children. Tri. How? prating still? why Timothy begone, Or draw, and lay Antonio down betwixt us, Let fortune of the fight decide the question. Here's a brave Rogue, that in the Kings high-way Offers to rob me of my good name. Draw. Ant. These wrongs recall my strength, I am resolv'd, Better die once, then suffer always. Draw. Tri. Stay, understandst thou well nice points of duell? Art born of gentle bloud, and pure descent? Was none of all thy linage hangd or cuckold? Bastard, or bastinado'd? is thy pedigree As long, as wide as mine? For otherwise Thou wert most unworthy; and 'twere losse of honour In me to fight. More, I have drawn five teeth: If thine stand sound, the tearms are much unequall. And by strict laws of duell, I am excus'd To fight on disadvantage. Ant. This some Asse! Tri. If we concurre in all, write a formall Challenge, And bring thy Second: mean-while I make provision Of Calais sand to fight upon securely. Ha! SCENE 8. Lelio, Cricca, Trincalo, Antonio. Le. Am I awake? or do deceitfull dreams Present to my wild fancie things I see not? Cri. Sir, what amazement's this? why wonder you? Le. See'st thou not Trincalo and Antonio? Cri. O strange! th'are both here. Le. Didst not thou informe me That Trincalo was turnd to Antonio? Which I beleving like a cursed sonne, With most reproachfull threats, drove mine old Father From his own doores; and yet rest doubtfull, whether This be the true Antonio: may be th'Astrologer Hath chang'd some other, and not Trincalo. Cri. No, feare it not: tis plain: Albumazar Hath cheated my old master of his plate. For here's the Farmer, as like himselfe as euer; Onely his cloaths excepted, Trincalo! Tri. Cricca, where's Trincalo? doest see him here? Cri. Yes, and as rank an Asse as e're he was. Tri. Thou'rt much deceiv'd, thou neither see'st, nor know'st me. I am transformd, transformd. Cri. Th'art still thy self. Lelio, this Farmer's halfe a foole, halfe knave. And as Pandolfo did with much intreaty Perswade him to transforme, so as much labour Will hardly bring the Coxcombe to himselfe, That nere was out on't. Who art if not he? Tri. My name is Don Antonio, I am now going To mine own house, to give Pandolfo Flavia, And Armellina to his Farmer Trincalo. How dar'st thou Cricca, but a meaner servant, Resemble me a man of worth and worship, To such a Clown as Trincalo, a branded foole, An Asse, a laughing-stock to Town and Countrey? Art not asham'd to name him with Antonio? Le. Do not thy actions with thy rude behaviour, Proclaime thee what thou art? Cri. Notorious Clown! Tri. Villain, th'hast broke my shoulders. Le. O didst feel him? Tri. I with a pox. Le. Then th'art still Trincalo. For hadst thou been Antonio, he had smarted. Tri. I feele it as I am Antonio Cri. Foole! who loves Armellina? Tri. Tis I, tis I. Cri. Antonio never lov'd his Kitchin-maid. Tri. Well I was taken for Antonio, And in his name receiv'd ten pound in gold, Was by his Mistris entertain'd; but thou Envy'st my happinesse: if th'hast th'ambition To rise as I have done, go to Albumazar, And let him change thee to a Knight, or Lord. Cri. Note the strange power of strong imagination. Tri. A world of Engines cannot wrest my thoughts, From being a Gentleman: I am one, and will be: And though I be not, yet will think my selfe so: And scorn thee Cricca, as a slave and servant. SCENE 9. Cricca, Lelio, Antonio. Cri. Tis but lost labour to disswade his dulnesse, Believe me that's your father. Le. When I drove him hence, Spight of my bloud his reverent countenance Strook me t'a deep compassion. To cleere all, He aske one question. Signior Antonio, What money took you when you took your Voyage? Ant. As I remember, fourscore and fifteen pound In Barbary gold. Had Lucio kept his word I had carried just a hundred. Le. Pardon me father; 'Twas my blinde ignorance, not want of duty, That wrong'd you: all was intended for a Farmer, Whom an Astrologer, they said, transform'd. Ant. How an Astrologer? Le. When you parted hence It seems you promis'd Flavia to Pandolfo. News of your death arriving, th'old Gentleman Importunes me to second what you purpos'd. Consulting therefore with my friends and kindred, Loth my yong sister should be buried quick I'th' grave of threescore yeares: by their advice I fully did deny him. He chafes and storms, And findes at length a cunning man, that promisd To turn his Farmer to your shape: and thus Possesse your house, and give him Flavia. Whereof I warnd, wrongd you instead of Trincalo. Ant. Then hence it came they cald me Trincalo, And talkt of an Astrologer; which names Almost inrag'd me past my selfe and senses. 'Tis true I promisd, but have oft repented it. And much more since he goes about to cheat me. He must not have her, sir. Le. I am glad y'are so resolv'd. And since with us, you finde that match unequall, Let's all intreat you to bestow your daughter Upon his sonne Eugenio. Ant. Sonne at your pleasure Dispose of Flavia, with my full consent. Le. And as you judge him worthy your daughter Flavia, Think no lesse of his Sulpitia. An. I do: and ever had desire to match Into that family; and now I finde my selfe Old, weak, unfit for marriage, you shall enjoy her; If I can worke Pandolfo by intreaty. Cri. To deale with him with reason and intreaties, Is to perswade a mad-man: for his loue Wakes him no lesse. All speeches opposite T'his fixt desire, and loue-corrupted iudgment, Seeme extreame fooleries. Will he consent To giue his daughter to your sonne and you Deny him Flavia: Shall Eugenio Expect or land or loue from old Pandolfo, Being his open riuall; tis impossible. He sought to cosen you; therefore resolue To pay him in's owne money. Be but aduisd By my poore counsell, and one stroke shall cut The root of his designes, and with his arrows Strike his owne plot so dead, that Albumazar, With all his stars and instruments, shall neuer Give it fresh motion. Ant. Cricca, to thy direction We yeeld our selues, manage vs at thy pleasure. Le. Speake quickly Cricca. Cri. The ground of all this busines, Is to catch Trincalo, and locke him fast Till I release him: next, that no man whisper Th'least word of your return. Then will I home, And with a cheerfull look tell my old Master, That Trincalo—but stay, look where he comes, Let's in, and there at leasure ile informe you From point to point. Lelio, detain him here, Till I send Armellina down to second you. Crosse him in nothing, call him Antonio, And good enough. Le. Feare not, let me alone. SCENE. 10. Trincalo, Lelio. Tri. This rascall Cricca with his arguments Of malice, so disturbs my gentle thoughts, That I half doubt I am not what I seeme: But that will soon be cleer'd; if they receive me In at Antonioes house, I am Antonio. Lel. Signior Antonio my most loving father? Blest be the day and houre of your return. Tri. Sonne Lelio? a blessing on my child, I pray thee tell me, How fares my servant Armellina? well? Lel. Have you forgot my sister Flavia? Tri. What my deare daughter Flavia? no, but first Call Armellina: for this day wee'l celebrate A Gleek of Marriages: Pandolfo and Flavia, Sulpitia and my selfe, and Trincalo With Armellina. Call her, good Lelio, quickly. Lel. I will sir. Tri. So: this is well that Lelio Confesseth me his father. Now I am perfect, Perfect Antonio. SCENE. 11. Armellina, Trincalo. Arm. Signior Antonio! My long expected Master! Tri. O Armellina! Come let me kisse thy brow like my own daughter. Arm. Tis too great a favour. I kisse your foot. What faln? Alas! how feeble you are grown, With your long travell? Tri. True, and being drownd, Nothing so griv'd me, as to lose thy company. But since I am safe return'd, for thy good service Ile help thee to a husband. Arm. A husband, sir? Some young and lusty youth, or else ile none. Tri. To one that loves thee dearely, dearely wench: A goodly man, like me in limbs and fashion. Arm. Fie, an old man? how? cast my selfe away, And be no nurse but his? Tri. He's not like me In yeers and gravity, but fair proportion. A hansome well-set man as I. Arm. His name? Tri. Tis Tom Trincalo of Totnam. Arm. Signior Pandolfo's lusty Farmer? Tri. That's he. Arm. Most unexpected happinesse! tis the man, I more esteem then my own life: sweet Master Procure that match, and think me satisfied For all my former service without wages. But aj I feare you jest. My poore unworthinesse Hopes not so great a fortune as sweet Trincalo. No wretched Armellina, in and despaire: Back to thy mournfull Dresser; there lament Thy selfe to Kitchin-stuffe, and bones to ashes, Eor love of thy sweet Farmer. Tri. Alas poore soule, How prettily she weeps for me! Wilt see him? Arm. My soule waits in my eys, and leaves my body Senselesse. Tri. Then sweare to keep my counsell. Ar. I sweare By th'beauteous eys of Trincalo. Tri. Why I am Trincalo. Arm. Your worship sir! why do yon flout your servant, Right worshipfull Antonio, my reverend Master? Tri. Pox of Antonio, I am Tom Trincalo. Why laugh'st thou? Arm. Tis desire and joy, To see my sweetest. Tri. Look upon me and see him. Arm. I say see Antonio, and none other. Tri. I am within, thy love; without, thy Master. Th'Astrologer transformd me for a day. Arm. Mock not your poore Maid, pray you sir. Tri. I do not. Now would I break this head against the stones, To be unchang'd; fie on this Gentry, it sticks Like Bird-lime, or the Pox. I cannot part with't. Within, I am still thy Farmer Trincalo. Arm. Then must I wait, till old Antonio Be brought to bed of a faire Trincalo; Or flea you, and strip you to your self again. Tri. Carry me to your chamber. Try me there. Arm. O sir by no means: but with my lovely Farmer Ide stay all night and thank him. Tri. Crosse misfortune! Accurst Albumazar! and mad Pandolfo! To change me thus, that when I most desire To be my selfe, I cannot. Armellina Fetch me a Looking-glasse. Arm. To what end? Tri. Fetch one. Let my old Masters businesse sinke or swim, This sweet occasion must not be neglected. Now shall I know th'Astrologers skil: O wonderfull! Admir'd Albumazar in two transmutations: Here's my old Farmers face. How in an instant I am unchang'd that was so long a changing. Here's my flat nose again &amp;c. Now Armellina take thy lov'd Trincalo To thy desired embracements, use thy pleasure, Kisse thy belly full. Arm. Not here in publick. T'enjoy too soon what pleaseth, is upleasant: The World, would envy that my happinesse. Go in, ile follow you, and in my Bed-hamber Wee'l consummate the match in privacy. Tri. Was not the face I wore farre worse then this? But for thy comfort, Wench, Albumazar Hath died my thoughts so deep i'th' grain of Gentry, Tis not a glasse can rob me of my good fashion, And Gentlemanly garbe. Follow my deare. Arm. Ile follow you. So now y'are fast enough. Tri. Help Armellina, help, I am falne i'th' cellar: Bring a fresh Plantane leafe, I have broke my shin. Arm. Thus have I caught me a husband in a trap, An in good earnest meant to marry him. Tis a tough Clown and lusty: he works day and night; And rich enough for me, that have no portion But my poore service. Well she's something foolish; The better can I dominere, and rule him At pleasure. That's the marke and utmost height We women ayme at. I am resolv'd; Ile have him. SCENE. 12. Lelio. Cricca. Lel. In Armellina, lock up Trincalo. Arm. I will sir. Le. Cricca, for this thy counsell, if' succeed, Feare not thy Masters anger: Ile preferre thee And count thee as my Genius, or good fortune. Cri. It cannot chuse but take. I know his humour; And can at pleasure feather him with hopes, Making him flie what pitch I wish, and stoop When I shew fowle. Le. But for the suite of cloaths? Cri. Ile throw them o're your garden wall. Away. Haste to Eugenio and Sulpitia, Acquaint them with the businesse. Le. I go. SCENE. 13. Lelio. Sulpitia. Le. The hopefull issue of thy counsell, Cricca, Brightens this ev'ning, and makes it more excell The cleerest day, then a gray morning doth The blindest midnight, raising my amorous thoughts To such a pitch of joy, that riches, honour, And other pleasures, to Sulpitia's love, Appeare like Mole-hils to the Moon. Sul. Lelio? Le. O there's the voice that in one note contains All cords of Musick: how gladly shee'l imbrace The newes I give her, and the messenger. Sul. Soft, Soft y'are much mistaken; for in earnest, I am angry Lelio; and with you. Le. Sweetest, those flames Rise from the fire of love, and soon will quench I'th'welcome news I bring you. Sul. Stand still I charge you By th'vertue of my lips; speak not a sillable As you expect a kisse should close my choler. For I must chide you Le. O my Sulpitia, Were euery speech a pistoll chargd with death, I'de stand them all in hope of that condition. Sul. First, sir, I heare, you teach Eugenio Too graue a warinesse in your sisters loue, And kill his honest forwardnesse of affection With your far-fet respects, suspitious, feares: You haue your may-bee's; this is dangerous: That course were better: for if so, and yet Who knowes? the event is doubtfull; be advis'd, Tis a yong rashnesse: your father is your father: Take leisure to consider. Thus y'have considered Poore Flavia almost to her grave. Fye Lelio, Had this my smalnesse undertooke the businesse, And done no more in foure short winters daies Than you in foure months; I'de have vowed my maiden-head To the living Tombe of a sad Nunnery: Which for your sake I loath. Lel. Sweet by your favour. Sul. Peace, peace: now y'are so wise, as if ye had eaten Nothing but braines and marrow of Machiavell: You tip your speeches with Italian Motti, Spanish Refranes, and English Quoth Hee's. Beleeve me, There is not a Proverbe salts your tongue, but plants Whole colonies of white haires. O what a businesse These hands must have when you have married me? To picke out sentences that over-yeare you. Lel. Give me but leave. Sul. Have I a lip? and you Made Sonets on't? tis your fault, for otherwise Your sister and Eugenio had beene sure Long time ere this. Lel. But— Sul. Stay, your Qu's not come yet. I hate as perfectly this gray-greene of yours, As old Antonio's green-gray. Fy! Wise lovers, Are most absurd. Were I not full resolved, I should begin to coole mine owne affection. For shame consider well your sisters temper. Her melancholy may much hurt her. Respect her, Or spight of mine owne love, Ile make you stay Sixe months before you marry me. Lelio whispers. Sul. This your so happy newes? return'd, and safe? Antonio yet alive? Lelio whispers. Sul. And what then? Lelio whispers. Sul. Well; all your businesse must be compassed With winding plots, and cunning stratagems. Looke too't: For if we be not married ere next morning, By the great love that is hid in this small compasse, Flavia and my selfe will steale you both away To your eternall shame and soule discredit. Le. How prettily this lovely littlenesse, In her own breath pleads her own cause, and my sisters; Chides me, and loves. This is that pleasing temper I more admire, then a continued sweetnesse That over-satisfies: 'Tis salt I love, not sugar. Finis Act. 4.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Act. 5. Scœne. 1. Albumazar, Ronca, Furbo, Harpax. Alb. How? not a single share of this great prize, That have deserv'd the whole? was't not my plot, And pains, and you meere instruments and porters? Shall I have nothing? Ron. No, not a silver spoon. Fur. Nor cover of a Trencher-salt. Har. Nor Table-napkin. Alb. Friends, we have kept an honest trust and faith 'Long time amongst us: Break not that sacred league, By raising civill theft; turn not your furt 'Gainst your own bowels. Rob your carefull master! Are you not asham'd? Ron. 'Tis our profession, As yours Astrology. And in th'days of old, Good morrow Thiefe, as welcome was receiv'd, As now your Worship. Tis your own instruction. Furb. The Spartans held it lawfull and th'Arabians, So grew Arabia happy, Sparta valiant. Har. The World's a Theater of theft: great Rivers Rob smaller Brooks; and them the Ocean. Alb. Have not I wean'd you up from peti-larceny. Dangerous and poore? and nurst you to full strength Of safe and gainfull theft? By rules of Art And principles of cheating made you free From taking, as you went invisible; And doe yee thus requite mee; this the reward For all my watchfull care? Ron. We are your schollers, Made by your helpe, and our aptnesse, able To instruct others. Tis the Trade we liue by. You that are seruant to Diuine Astrology, Doe something worth her liuery. Cast Figures, Make Almanackes for all Meridians. Fur. Sell Perspicils, and instruments of hearing, Turne Clownes to Gentlemen; Buzzards to Falcons, Cur-dogs to Grey-hounds; Kitchen-maides to Ladies. Har. Discover more new Stars, and unknown planets: Vent them by dozens, stile them by the names Of men that buy such ware. Take lawfull courses, Rather then beg. Alb. Not keep your honest promise? Fur. Believe none, credit none: for in this City No dwellers are, but Cheaters and Cheateez Alb. You promis'd me the greatest share. Ron. Our promise! If honest men by Obligations, And instruments of Law are hardly constrain'd T'observe their word; Can we that make profession Of lawlesse courses, do't? Alb. Amongst our selves: Faulcons that tyrannize o're weaker fowle, Hold peace with their own feathers. Har. But when they counter Upon one quarry, break that league as we do, Alb. At least restore th'ten pound in gold I lent you. Ron. 'Twas lent in an ill Second, worser Third, And lucklesse Fourth: 'tis lost, Albumazar. Fur. Saturne was in Ascension. Mercury Was then combust when you delivered it. 'Twill never be restor'd, Ron. Hali, Abenezra, Hiarcha, Brachman, Budda Babylonicus, And all the Chaldes and the Cabalists, Affirme that sad aspect threats losse of debts. Har. Frame by your Azimut Almicantarat, An engine like a Mace, whose quality Of strange retractive vertue may recall Desperate debts, and with that undo Sergeants. Alb. Was ever man thus baited by's own whelps? Give me a slender portion for a stock To begin Trade again. Ron. Tis an ill course And full of feares. This treasure hath inricht us, And given us means to purchase and live quiet Of th'fruit of dangers past. When I us'd robbing. All blocks before me look't like Constables, And posts appear'd in shape of Gallowses. Therefore good Tutour take your Pupils counsell: Tis better beg then steale: Live in poore clothes, Then hang in Sattin. Alb. Villains, Ile be reveng'd, And reveale all the businesse to a Justice. Ron. Do, if thou longst to see thy own Anatomy. Alb. This treachery perswads me to turn honest. Fur. Search your Nativity: see if the Fortunates And Luminaries be in a good Aspect. And thank us for thy life. Had we done well, We had cut thy throat ere this. Alb. Albumazar, Trust not these Rogues; hence and revenge. Ron. Fellow away, here's company. Let's hence. Exeunt. SCENE. 2. Cricca. Pandolfo. Cric. Now Cricca, mask thy countenance in joy, Speak welcome language of good news, and move Thy Master, whose desires are credulous, To believe what thou giv'st him. If thy designe Land at the Haven tis bound for; then Lelio, Eugenio, and their Mistresses, are oblig'd By oath to assure a state of forty pounds Upon thee for thy life. Pan. I long to know, How my good Farmer speeds; how Trincalo Hath been deceiv'd by Lelio. Cri. Where shall I finde him? What we most seek, still flies us; what's avoided, Follows, or meets us full. I am embost With trotting all the streets to finde Pandolfo, And blesse him with good news. Pan. This haste of Cricca. Abodes some good; doubtlesse my Trincalo, Received for Antonio, hath given me Flavia. Cricca? Cri. Neither in Pauls, at home nor in the Exchange? Nor where he uses to converse? hee's lost: And must be cryed. Pan. Turn hither, Cricca, Cricca, See'st me not? Cri. Sir, the news, and haste to tell it. Had almost blinded me. Tis so fortunate, I dare not powre it all at once vpon you, Lest you should faint and swound away with ioy. Your transform'd Trincalo— Pan. what newes of him; Cri. Entred as owner in Antonio's house— Pan. On. Cri. Is acknowledg'd by his daughter Flavia, And Lelio for their father. Pan. Quickly good Cricca! Cri. And hath sent me in haste to bid you— Pan. What? Cri. Come with your sonne Eugenio— Pan. And then? Cri. That he may be witnesse of your marriage: But Sir, I see no signes of so large goodnesse As I expected, and this news deserv'd. Pan. Tis here, tis here, within. All outward symptomes And characters of joy, are poore expressions Of my inward happinesse: my heart's full, And cannot vent the passions. Run Cricca, run. Run as thou lov'st me call Eugenio, And work him to my purpose: thou canst do it: Haste, call him instantly. Cri. I flie sir. SCENE 3. Pandolfo. How shall I recompence this Astrologer? This great Albumazar? through whose learned hands, Fortune hath powr'd the effect of my best wishes, And crown'd my hopes. Give him this chain? alas! Tis a poore thanks, short by a thousand links Of his large merit. No he must live with me, And my sweet Flavia, at his ease and pleasure, Wanting for nothing. And this very night I'le get a boy, and he erect a figure To calculate his fortunes. So there's Trincalo Antoniated, or Antonio Intrinculate. SCENE. 4. Antonio. Pandolfo. Lelio. Eugenio. Ant. Signior Pandolfo! welcome. Lel. Your servant sir. Pan. Well met Antonio, my prayers and wishes Have waited on you ever. Ant. Thanks dearest friend. To speak my danger past, were to discourse Of dead men at a Feast. Such sad relations Become not marriages, Sir, I am here Return'd to do you service: where's your sonne? Pan. He'le wait upon you presently. Eug. Signior Antonio! Happily welcome. Ant. Thanks Eugenio, How think you Gentlemen? were it amisse To call down Flavia and Sulpitia, That what we do, may with a full consent Be entertain'd all? Pan. Tis well remembred. Eugenio, call your sister. Ant. Lelio, call your daughter. SCEN. 5. Pandolfo. Antonio. Pan. Wisely consider'd Trincalo: tis a faire Prologue To the Comædy ensuing. Now I confesse Albumazar had equall power to change, And mend thy understanding with thy body. Let me embrace and hug thee for this service. 'Tis a brave on set: ah my sweet Trincalo! Ant. How like you the beginning? Pan. Tis o'th'further side All expectation. Ant. Was't not right? and spoken Like old Antonio? Pan. 'Tis most admirable: Were't he himself that spake, he could not better't. And for thy sake, I wish Antonio's shape May ever be thy house, and 's wit thy In-mate. But where's my plate, and cloth of silver? Ant. Safe. Pan. They come: keep state, keep state, or al's discover'd. SCENE. 6. Antonio, Pandolfo, Eugenio, Lelio, Flavia, Sulpitia. Ant. Eugenio, Flavia, Lelio, Sulpitia; Marriages once confirm'd, and consummate, Admit of no repentance. Therefore 'tis fitting All parties with full freedome speak their pleasure, Before it be too late. Pan. Good! excellent! Ant. Speak boldly therefore: do you willingly Give full authority, and what I decree Touching these businesses, you'l all performe? Eug. I rest at your dispose: what you determine, With my best power I ratifie; and Sulpitia, I dare be bold to promise, says no lesse. Sul. What e're my father, brother, and your selfe Shall think convenient, pleaseth me. Le. In this, As in all other service, I commit my selfe To your commands; and so I hope, my sister. Fla. With all obedience: for dispose of me As of a childe, that judgeth nothing good But what you shall approve. Ant. And you Pandolfo? Pan. I most of all. And, for I know the mindes Of youth are apt to promise, and as prone To repent after; 'tis my advice they sweare T'observe without exception, your decree. Fla. Content. Sul. Content. Pan. By all the powers that heare Oaths, and raine vengeance upon broken faith, I promise to confirme and ratifie Your sentence. Le. Sir, I sweare no lesse. Eug. Nor I. Fla. The self-same oath bindes me. Sul. And me the same. Pan. Now Antonio, all our expectation Hangs at your mouth. None of us can appeale From you to higher Courts. Ant. First, for preparative Or slight Præludium to the greater matches; I must intreat you that my Armellina Be match't with Trincalo. Two hundred Crowns I give her for her portion. Pan. Tis done. Some reliques Of his old Clownery, and dregs o'th' Country, Dwell in him still: how carefull he provides For himself first! Content. And more, I grant him A lease for twenty pounds a yeare. Ant. I thank you. Gentlemen, since I feele my selfe much broken With age, and my late miseries, and too cold, To entertain new heat; I freely yield Sulpitia, whom I lov'd, to my sonne Lelio. Pan. How cunningly the Farmer hath provided T'observe the semblance of Antonio's person, And keep himselfe still free for Armellina! Ant. Signior Pandolfo, y'are wise, and understand How ill hot appetites of unbridled youth Become gray haires. How grave and honourable Wert for your age to be enamored With the fare shape of vertue, and the glory Of our Fore-fathers! Then would you blush to think How by this dotage, and unequall love, You stain their honour, and your own. Awake, Banish those wilde affections; and by my example Turn t'your reposed self. Pan. To what purpose, pray you, Serves this long proæme? on to th'sentence. Ant. Sir, Conformity of yeers, likenesse of manners, Are Gordian knots that binde up Matrimony. Now betwixt seventy Winters and sixteen, There's no proportion, nor least hope of love. Fie that a Gentleman of your discretion, Crownd with such reputation in your youth, Should in your Western days, lose th'good Opinion Of all your friends; and run to th'open danger Of closing the weak remnant of your days With discontentment unrecoverable. Pan. Wrack me no more; pray you let's heare the sentence: Note how the Asse would fright me, and endeare His service; intimating that his power May over-throw my hopes: Proceed to th'sentence. An. These things consider'd, I bestow my daughter Upon your sonne Eugenio; whose constant love With his so modest carriage, hath deserv'd her. And, that you freeze not for a bed-fellow, I marry you with Patience. Pan. Treacherous Villain! Accursed Trincalo! Ile—But this no place, He's too well backt. But shortly when the date Of his Antonioship's expir'd, revenge Shall sweeten this disgrace. Ant. Signior Pandolfo, When you recover yourselfe, lost desperately In disproportion'd dotage, then you'l thank me For this great favour: be not obstinate; Disquiet not your selfe. Pan. I thank you sir. SCENE. 7. Pandolfo. And that you freeze not for bad-fellow, I marry you with Patience. Traiterous villain! Is it not enough to wrong me, and betray me, But 't must be done with scoffs; accursed Trincalo: And me most miserable! I that when I thought T'imbrace young Flavia, see her before my face Bestowd upon my sonne! my sonne my Rivall! This is Eugenio's plot, and his friend Lelio's; Who, with my servant Cricca, have conspir'd, And suborn'd Trincalo to betray his Master. Why do I rage 'gainst any but my selfe, That have committed such a serious businesse To th'hands of a base Clown, and ignorant? I see mine errour, but no means to help it. Only the sweetnesse of revenge is left me, Which I must execute: th'houres of's Gentry Are now clean spent. Ile home, and there attend him. SCENE 8. Trincalo drunk, but something recovered. Welcome old trusty Trincalo, good Farmer welcome! give me thy hand, we must not part hereafter. Fie, what a trouble tis to be out of a mans self! If Gentlemen have no pleasure but what I felt to day; a team of horses shall not drag me out of my profession. There's nothing amongst them but borrowing, compounding for half their debts, and have their purse cut for the rest, coozned by whores, frighted with husbands, washt in wet hogsheads, cheated of their cloaths, and falling in cellars for conclusion. SCENE 9. Pandolfo at the window. Trincalo. Pan. O precious piece of villany! are you unchang'd? How confident the Rogue dares walk the streets! Tri. And then such quarrelling: never a suite I wore to day, but hath been soundly basted. Only this faithfull Country case scap't fist-free; and be it spoken in a good houre, was never beaten yet since it came from fulling! Pan. Tiff. toff. Base treacherous villain! toff. toff. toff. Tri. Is this the recompence of my days work? Pan. You marry me to patience? there's patience. She's a good bed-fellow; have patience. Tri. You'l beat me out on't sir: how have I wrong'd you? Pan. So, as deserves th'expression of my fury With th'cruelst tortures I can execute. Tri. You kill me sir. Pan. Have patience. Tri. Pray your sir! Pan. Seek not by humble penitence t'appease me. Nothing can satisfie. Tri. Farewell humility. Now I am beaten sober. (takes away Pandolfo's staffe.) Shall age and weaknesse master my youth and strength? Now speak your pleasure: what's my fault? Pan. Dar'st deny Thy own act done before so many witnesses? Suborn'd by others, and betray my confidence With such stony impudence? Tri. I have been faithfull In all you trusted me. Pan. To them; not me. O what a Proæme stuft with grave advice, And learned counsaile, you could showre upon me Before the thunder of your deadly sentence! And give away my Mistris with a scoffe! Tri. I give your Mistris? Pan. Didst not thou decree Contrary t'our compact, against my marriage? Tri. Why when was I your judge? Pan. Just now, here. Tri. See your errour! then was I fast lockt in Antonio's Cellar: Where making vertue of necessity, I drunk stark drunk; and waking, found my self cloth'd in this Farmers suit, as in th'morning. Pan. Didst not thou sweare t'enter Antonio's house, And give me Flavia for my wife? and after, Before my own face, gav'st her to my sonne? Tri. Ha, ha, ha! Pan. Canst thou deny't? Tri. Ha, ha, ha! Whilst Trincalo laughs, and falls the staffe, Pandolfo recovers it, and beats him. Have you got Mistris Patience? ha, ha, ha! Pan. Is not this true? Tri. Ha, ha, ha! Pan. Answer me. Tri. Ha, ha, ha, wan! Pan. Was't not thus? Tri. I answer. First, I never was transform'd, but guld, As you were by th'Astrologer, and those that cald me Antonio. To prove this true, the Gentleman you spoke with, was Antonio, The right Antonio, safely returnd from Barbary. Pan. Oh me; whats this? Tri. Truth it selfe. Pan. Was 't not thou that gav'st the sentence? Tri. Believe me no such matter: I nere was Gentleman, nor otherwise Then what I am, unlesse 'twere when I was drunk. Pan. How have I been deceiv'd? good Trincalo Pardon me. I have wrong'd thee. Tri. Pardon you? When you have beaten me to paste, good Trincalo, Pardon me? Pan. I am sorry for't; excuse me. Tri. I am sorry I must excuse you. But I pardon you. Pan. Now tell me where's the plate and cloth of silver, The gold and jewels that the Astrologer Committed to thy keeping? Tri. What plate, what jewels? He gave me none. But when he went to change me, After a thousand circles and ceremonies, He binds me fast upon a forme, and blindes me With a thick Table-napkin. Not long after Unbindes my head and feet, and gives me light: And then I plainly saw, that I saw nothing: The Parler was clean swept of all was in't. Pan. Oh me: Oh me! Tri. What ails you? Sir, what ails you? Pan. I am undone, I have lost my love, my plate, My whole estate, and with the rest my selfe. Tri. Lose not your patience too. Leave this lamenting, And lay the Town; you may recover it. Pan. Tis to small purpose. In and hold thy peace. SCEN. 10. Cricca. Pandolfo. Cri. Where shall I finde my Master to content him With welcome news? He's here; news, news! News of good fortune, joy, and happinesse! Pan. Cricca, my sadnesse is uncapable Of better tydings: I am undone most miserable! Cri. Offend not your good luck, y'are now more fortunate Then when you rose this morning: be merry, sir, Cheare up your selfe, y' have what you wisht, feare nothing. Pan. May be Antonio newly repents himselfe. With purpose to restore Flavia. Cricca, what ist? where's all this happinesse? Cri. Lockt in Antonio's closet. Pan. All alone? Sure that's Flavia. Is not Eugenio Suffred to enter? Cri. Antonio keeps the Key: No creature enters but himselfe; all's safe And shall be so restor'd. Pan. O my sweet Cricca! Cri. And they that wrong'd you, most extreamly sorry, Ready to yield you any satisfaction. Pan. Ist possible they should so soon repent them? That injur'd me so lately? tell me the manner That caus'd them see their Errour. Cri. Ile tell you, sir. Being just now at old Antonio's house, One thunders at th'back doore, enters, and presses To speak in private with yong Lelio; Was instantly admitted: and think you who? Twas your Astrologer Albumazar. When he had spoke a while; Lelio and Antonio In haste command me fetch a Constable. Pan. How can this Story touch my happinesse? Cri. I up and down through slimy Ale-houses, Cloudy Tobacco-shops, and vapouring Taverns: My mouth full of inquiry: at last found one. Pan. What of all this? ist possible a Constable Concerns my good? Cri. And following my directions, Went to a Tipling-house, where we took drinking Three handsome fellows with a great chest; attacht them, And brought all to Antonio. Pan. Well, what then? Cri. These were th'Astrologers intelligences, that Robd you through th'Southwindow. Pan. I thought th'hadst spoke Of Flavia's restoring. Cri. I mean your plate And treasure; pray you, sir, ist not great happinesse To re-obtain three thousand pounds in value, Desperatly lost? and you still dote and dream Of Flavia, who by your own consent And oath is promisd to your sonne Eugenio? Pan. Forward. Cri. Within this chest Antonio found your plate, Gold, jewels, cloth of silver, nothing perisht, But all safe lockt till you acknowledge it. And since Albumazar of his owne accord Frely confest, and safe restord your treasure: Since tis a day of Iubile and marriage: Antonio would intreat you to release And Pardon the Astrologer. Thanking your fortune That hath restord you to your wealth, and selfe. Both which were lost i'th'foolish loue of Flauia. Pan. Reason hath cleard my sight, and drawn the vaile Of dotage that so darkt my understanding. I clearely see the slavery of affections; And how vnsuitable my declining yeares Are for the dawning youth of Flavia. Let the best joys of Hymen compasse her, And her young husband, my Eugenio, With full content. And since Albumazar By accident, causd all this happinesse: I freely pardon him, and his companions: And haste to assist the Marriages and Feasts. Cri. Why now you shew your selfe a worthy Gentleman. SCEN. ult. Trincalo, Cricca. Tri. Cricca I over-heard your news: all parts are pleasd, Except my selfe: Is there no news for Trincalo? Cri. Knowst it not? in and see: Antonio Hath given thee Armellina with a portion, Two hundred Crowns; and old Pandolfo bound By oath t'assure thee twenty pounds a yeer, For three lives. Tri. Haj! Cri. Come in. Tri. Ile follow.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Epilogue. Two hundred Crowns? and twenty pound a yeare For three goodlives? Cargo! hai Trincalo! My wife's extreamly busie, dressing the supper For these great marriages; and I not idle, So that I cannot entertain you here As I would else-where, But if you come to Totnam Some foure daies hence, and aske for Trincalo At th'signe o'th' Hogshead; Ile morgage all my Lives To bid you welcome. You that love Trincalo And mean to meet, clap hands and mak't'a bargain. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>