<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Field, Michael</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Field, Michael</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">field michael</field>
      <field name="author_text">Field, Michael</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1910's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V3.0111.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1918</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460547</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Deirdre : A Sorrow of Story-Telling</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Deirdre : A Sorrow of Story-Telling</field>
      <field name="title_facet">deirdre a sorrow of story telling</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">deirdre a sorrow of story telling</field>
      <field name="title_text">Deirdre : A Sorrow of Story-Telling</field>
      <field name="year_display">1918</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1918</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1918</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460547&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460547&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Field, Michael&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;field michael&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Deirdre : A Sorrow of Story-Telling&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;deirdre a sorrow of story telling&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1918&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1918&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Field, Michael&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Deirdre : A Sorrow of Story-Telling&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;The Poetry Bookshop [etc.]&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1918&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872876-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv30111&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 20th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;20th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Deirdre : A Sorrow of Story-Telling&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 172 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Only verse drama included&lt;lb/&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Deirdre.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Drama.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1918.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Unknown.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DEIRDRE A SORROW OF STORY-TELLING</field>
      <field name="fulltext">“Nothing that is vast enters into the life of man without a curse.” —Antigone, 614.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PERSONS Conchobar King of Ulster (Ulla). Naisi the Son of Uisnech. Ainnle the Son of Uisnech. Ardan the Son of Uisnech. Cathfach the Druid. Eogan Prince of Fernmagh. Fergus Son of Ross. Fedlimid Son of Dall, Conchobar's Tale-teller. Fergna Conchobar's Charioteer. Deirdre Daughter of Fedlimid. Lebarcham a female satirist or wise woman. Medv Nurse to Deirdre.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PROLOGUE Scene: Emain, Ireland.—In Act II. Loch Etive, Scotland. The chief room of Fedlimid's house: at the back a wall pierced by windows through which gloomy night and trees can be seen; below the windows a table running the whole length of the wall and continued down the right side. In the left wall a closed door. The tables are lighted cheerfully and servants move about serving the guests. Fedlimid sits over against the wall at the right-hand table, Conchobar nearly opposite, his back to the centre of the room. Cathfach at the cross-table, also sits with his back to the room, facing the windows. FEDLIMID. [Rising.] O high king, welcome! Mighty Conchobar, Most valiant, most victorious over-king, Whose deeds my harp has fed, who deigns to honour His story-teller's feast of flesh and wine; All that I have I give you, all is yours That you can claim for pleasure or I offer, Here in your smooth Emain, O Light of Valour, To you who love my songs, my chaunts, my knowledge Of far-off wars, of genealogies. And be my witness, all who drink and banquet, How there is nothing I reserve my own That this enjoyer of my harp desires: For they who hear our music, they possess Our very selves, our substance, all we are And all we have.... A tumult at the portal! But yet the wind is down.... [Enter Medv.] A woman?—Medv, News of my lady? Is she labouring still? MEDV. Labour is over and a girl is born. FEDLIMID. The mother? MEDV. She has fallen asleep. FEDLIMID. The child? CATHFACH. [Rising, yet still facing the windows.] O voiceful dark, webbing the sky, Thick web about the earth and ash-tree boughs, And walls of this abode of men— What is your voice? The burthen, O the burthen, O the night! An impulse from the midnight comes upon me, Through the close silence from a far off silence, That sounds against my ears, Against my heart, A pain, a strength, and out of these a terror Until it cease to sound against my ears, To sound against my heart, Until it break on all men's hearing, Throb in their blood, Escape, as if by birth, escape a prophecy. [Calling aloud.] Woe, woe! [Facing the room.] The Woe—this child, this new-born girl, This sorrow of the name of Deirdre. FEDLIMID. Wizard, I have not named my daughter. CONCHOBAR [Turning on his stool and fixing his eyes on Cathfach.] Deirdre? CATHFACH. Yea! Ruin is born to-night: O Conchobar, thy madness and thy dying; O Ulla, loss of thee, Emain, of thee— Proud, white Emain, Emain, my city. A fire is lighted that will catch the hills, And spread from home to home, from hill to hill, From forest spread to forest, from the islands Of Ara to the ocean-stream of Moyle, And shores of far Manannan's ocean-streams. My wisdom has the voice Ye hear when in the forest's moon-filled clifts The Hidden People harp and sorcery Leads its own pulse through stillness: for my singing Is of the birth of Beauty. Ruin's flame Breaks from a silver form, And Ruin comes by glances of such eyes As charm with agony of ancient charms, Known first to sun and dew, to star and day spring; Yea, Ruin comes by golden, golden hair, Great net of fate; Comes by a thin, slow lip, A rose unfolding, First of all roses; It comes by laughter, Creeps on in smiles.... O lovely, dimpling silences of joy! It comes by loveliest speech, Soft in bright cadence—comes By heaving breasts of unbraved peerlessness, Swans on a silver that they own and heave. Fell Ruin passes, And Beauty passes.... Woe, woe, but Ulla Passes as they! CONCHOBAR. [To Cathfach.] Ruin—a flame! Thy face is but a dream; And we are dreaming as thy voice hath bidden. Do not yet break the sleep! FEDLIMID. You praise my child? AN OLD LORD OF THE RED BRANCH. More, wizard, for we drink. THE YOUNGEST LORD. O life, the singing! CATHFACH. Lords of our proud Red Branch, I see no more This Wonder of long hair of June-cloud whiteness, Whose eyelids dazzle and whose eyes undo, Robbing the souls of men as from the sea The brilliant sun above the sea drinks rain: No more presageful midnight Is blanched by her, nor loveable its doom— Behold, it swells and moves, Red it becomes, ah, red! A river washing Over Emain, over the fields, hills, valleys, Over the dwellings of our people, doom Blood-red, that from a river grows to flood, And ends a blood-red ocean. Faugh, the lives That make the carnage, make the lamentation. Woe to Emain, And woe to Ulla, And woe to Conchobar, the son of Fachtna, Woe to the proud Red Branch that perishes; To all who listen round me at this hour Mad fondness, hurt and harm, The smooth way lost, gloom and, where now the living Drink deep and take delight, the host of dead. AN OLD LORD. Avert the bloodshed, O avert the terror, The devastating doom; for if the child Of Fedlimid, new-born to-night, is destined To ruin all our pride and joy, our city Our province and our king, our Knightly Order, Our fortune and our feasting, let to-night Suck up the life it renders. ALL. Slay the child! ECHO. Slay, slay the child! FEDLIMID. O Conchobar, my king, O listener to my music, whom my stories Have raised to greatness from thy early years, Am I to be thy ruin? As a father, Am I, thy bard, to cherish in this earth What will undo the man I fire to glory By all the fires of verse born from my blood? Never believe it! Let my daughter die On her first breath, and let the beautiful, Soft flesh I have begotten grow as clay, For the dear sake of Conchobar, my idol, The lover of old music and great deeds. ALL. Minstrel, well said and bravely! FEDLIMID. For Emain Let my seed perish! CONCHOBAR. [Rising.] All that loveliness In tender shoot, ye gods, a moment's distance From yonder doorway and these weapons drawn Sharp pointed for its death!...Ye warriors, listen. O Fedlimid, O Father of the child! FEDLIMID. Our royal soldier lifts his loud king's voice. ALL. Peace, peace, attend! CONCHOBAR. And Cathfach—let him listen! Steel cannot slaughter destiny, transfixing The wide, inevitable wings that haunt The future with dark breezes. Son of Dall, Thy verse hath swept my heart. hath swept and passed: The offspring of thy loins within my heart Possesses life's endurance as her own; She stays where she is come, from out of the darkness, Of night and birth, a promise to desire, A habitant of vision. Song may thrill, Then wander from our pulses like a breath; But Beauty shall not leave us while we are: Its fiery being owns us, and our ashes Fall gray when it departs. FEDLIMID. Alas, my king, I shrivel, I grow shadowy. You requite My songs with this despair; a mortal creature, Begotten of my body for your ruin, Is valued as your life, and all the glory Of living that my music brought as health And sweet, abiding honour to your blood, Is cast away as hollow air, forgotten, And finds its end. CONCHOBAR. O Fedlimid, not so! Because I love your songs I am endowed To love your daughter in the prophecy That glows white with her dawn. I need no seeing, No touch and no mortality of sense To apprehend her. FEDLIMID. Of my song and music You are not taught this day of days. A VOICE. Emain! ANOTHER VOICE. Ulla! The land! ANOTHER VOICE. Your people! CONCHOBAR. Dear is Ulla, Most dear Emain, O warriors; and their safety Dear to their king. I free you from all doom, Ye, my green-sided hills, ye glens and harbours, And lonely places 'mid the idle swamps: I free you from all doom, fair-built Emain; And ye, my knights of the Red Branch, I free you, With my loved Ulla and Emain, from doom. The penalty be mine; upon my head I take it; to myself I take this child Of sorrow—for my sorrow; and her doom Be on me as my doom. THE OLD LORD. You heard the wizard! Will you be mad and perish? O relent And save yourself with us! Our swords are ready, And Fedlimid our friend. [Enter Lebarcham with the infant Deirdre.] See, Lebarcham, The wise-lipped, comely satirist herself Has brought the babe for slaughter. She is wise; She smiles. LEBARCHAM. Thy new-born, Fedlimid. ALL. Our foe! Quench the fresh curse! CONCHOBAR. [Parting their swords.] Amid your vassal-weapons I pass unheedful, minding but my promise, My troth plight to the child of Fedlimid— That she shall be my one own wife, her fate Be mine, my fate the current of her days, The waxing of her beauty. Lebarcham, Wisest of women, you and Medv the nurse Shall rear this babe to womanhood within A silent, strict enclosure, near my house, Fenced high with crimson planks of loftiest firs Making forbidden ground to any footstep Save yours, the nurse's, and, when hope becomes Too vernal-quick for patience, mine. The mother may but tarry for a month To milk her young; the father nevermore May look upon this bride that he hath yielded His king, till she is throned. [Bending over Deirdre] Small, gazing creature Amid thy covers, I have bidden a morrow Of sixteen years to rest from operation, Till thou art formed a loveliness to join me In doom, in joy superlative, imagined Against all words of woe. ALL. Alas, the frenzy! Alas, our fear! CONCHOBAR. But, by the law of Erin, I of free-will have sworn: the loss and sorrow Shall be on me, not you ... the flame and madness And bloodshed and the end that now begins. O Cathfach! [He bows his head within his hands.] CATHFACH. O uncompassable Law... What is to come, that cometh, and shall come!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I Scene: Sixteen years later. The enclosure where Deirdre lives. Outside the fir-palings, that cross the background, fir trees in a snow whitened ridge stretch along without break of line or substance. On each side are fir-palings. The enclosure is covered by snow, and a dead calf bleeds near the frozen well. Medv and Lebarcham are talking together. Deirdre stands apart, where the ground rises a little, and watches the sky gradually quicken with the light of the early year. MEDV. But look at her! LEBARCHAM. Ay, Medv, it is not for our eyes to look. The beauty! MEDV. She is dreaming. LEBARCHAM. She sees true; Therefore she is no poet. Gentle Medv, My sister with the mother-eyes that rest But when they rest on her, she is not ours, Nor fate's, nor any man's; for she will choose, Close prisoner as she is, her destiny, Choose for herself the havoc she will make, The tears that she will draw from other eyes, The tears that will burn through her, the delights That she will ravish from the world. She knows So definitely all she wants: such souls Attain. She is not dreaming; look at her! MEDV. She does not sigh as other maids kept close; She is soft as a wood-pigeon, but no crooning— And when I speak of love—King Conchobar To be her lord—she laughs. LEBARCHAM. A wanton laugh! MEDV. No, no! Dear heart, she has no wantonness; And yet I am afraid to hear her laughter, It is so low and sure. My maid, my maid! What shall I do that bitter day the King Tears her away from me? LEBARCHAM. Be comforted. She loves you, she will bless you all her years: But if she hate—I would not be the creature To cross her path, not if I were the chieftain Of Ulla, or of Alba, or the world. MEDV. She has no malice. Would you slander her? LEBARCHAM. I praise her! She can hate as only those Of highest race, without remorse, for ever. MEDV. Through generations? LEBARCHAM. She will hate but one With the hate of hate. A woman's enmity Is not a blood-feud: she may love her foe; But love the man who thwarts her who undoes The soft web of her nature!—Look again, Look at the thin, tight lips. MEDV. It is her doom Told her in every portent of the flame And crackle of the faggots, 'tis her lot To wed our Overlord. LEBARCHAM. Those starry eyes Are firm and quiet: all that they decree Will come to pass, however Erin murmur, Or you, or I, or Conchobar. MEDV. How fearful! Then she will suffer. LEBARCHAM. She will have her way. Therefore you shall not pity her, not pity Even the great, lone king, who gives me burthen Of all his passion, who refrains himself, And will not look on her; but asks me questions, Fast as a woman, of her body's fairness, The silver of her skin, her shape, her height. I do not pity him; he has his dream, He knows what he desires, his feet are sure. Such on the dizzy mountain-steps of life Will not be dashed to atoms. Look at her! I must report her fully grown and smiling With the May-sunshine's smile. Fie, Dierdre! Child, What is it you are staring at, as if There were a magic rune spelled on the floor? That foster-father should have killed a calf Is nothing wonderful. DEIRDRE. But come and see How the blood pours a draught upon the snow. LEBARCHAM. Ay, child! DEIRDRE. And pours and pours: the soak of rose Is wonderful ... A raven stoops to drink. Oh, look at him! The lustre of his feathers Is dull against the dazzle of the snow. Now listen, Lebarcham, For when I marry I will have a husband Of just these colours, scarlet on his cheek, His hair black as this plumage, and his forehead— There I shall kiss—pure crystal. Fetch him me! LEBARCHAM. Colour, child—it is the colour of a creature is its destiny and its lure. The dead are as white as you will. But this husband— The colour of the snow upon his skin, The calf's blood on his cheek, the raven's bloom On his black locks.... MEDV. Hush, hush! DEIRDRE. But fetch him me. LEBARCHAM. I have seen such in the house of Conchobar. Medv, you remember Naisi. MEDV. But the King Will wed my darling. DEIRDRE. Has he any blood Or change of skin like sunrise? I shall marry This piercing scarlet, and this black, not dull, But crisp and shining: I shall wed this snow. I will; it is my choice. LEBARCHAM. If you could see him, Our Naisi! MEDV. Hush, it is forbidden. Hush! O Deirdre, O my darling, would you look On the snow's whiteness, loose your bodice, child. There in the warmth! ... You have a cheek that glows Clear as the embers: you are beautiful. DEIRDRE. Sweet foster-mother! Ah, I think indeed You are the child: we shall change places soon. [Caressing her.] Get me the broth I love. MEDV. These hands are cold. Come in. DEIRDRE. No, not till dinner-time. [Exit Medv.] You said ... Say it again to me, for I am born To hear the story! 'tis about myself. O Lebarcham, I have heard many stories That have so tired me I have dropped to sleep; Of how one day I shall be made a queen, But by what means?—Not that some royal prince Shall win me by his sword; but Conchobar Shall marry me; and then they speak of joys And pomp and of my happiness. I knew It was their story of me, not my own. That we will make to-day. Stoop down to me... O Lebarcham, all I have learned I learned of you. LEBARCHAM. I have not married, child; I am a lonely satyrist. DEIRDRE. This body, You told me, is for love—a gift, and all My lover will have thought of in the world. I have remembered; I have cherished it; I have grown very beautiful. I kept My beauty close in hood and veil... but, see! I am white, not like the colour of the snow, But something warmer—not like Naisi's white; And then no rose at all, and golden hair; Nothing but very tender white and gold. But if you think that one so marvellous As Naisi is will take me as a cup To drink from, just a gold and silver cup, Then ... I will pour him wine; he will forget All else in drinking, if he stoop to drink. LEBARCHAM. You trouble me, my maid; I spoke too rashly. I am indeed a fool. For all the knights Of the Red Branch are comely. DEIRDRE. Not their king. LEBARCHAM. Yes, child; men say he is the goodliest man In Erin's Isle. DEIRDRE. But he is like the evening, He falls about me like a chill. 'Tis said I shall bring doom and ruin on his land. LEBARCHAM. No, child; you are his star. DEIRDRE. I softly laugh To hear these things decreed; for I am Deirdre, And I will wed no other in the world But this most bright one you have sung. LEBARCHAM. My maiden, I did but give his name. DEIRDRE. You sang of him; You set my breast afire. I cannot check The tide, nor stir these fences, nor remove The will that crushes me; I cannot climb, A bird, up in the air; but yet I feel Like a winged creature. I am so impatient ... LEBARCHAM. My child! My child! DEIRDRE. No more a child! How often you have told me I was a treasure wasted in the darkness, A jewel and unworn: fetch me the sunlight, And I will shine. My Naisi, give him me, And I will hang about his neck, till all The knights shall envy him. [She kneels.] [Lebarcham turns away and goes out.] She is not gone? It is this little space before, this torment, This agony, as all one's hopes danced down Like the sparkles on the waves to kiss one's feet. This waiting ... But he is not far away— No; he is close as springtide. I will sing Since when he comes I shall be mute for shame And terror of my longing. It is noon; The sun is breaking forth, blessed augury! Over the snow-clouds Softness of light, Outbreak of breezes, Magic of heaven! Wider, O sun-cleft, Open the sky! Never before Have I read the rune: Birth-song of springtide Now I discover, Sung of mute voices High in the clouds. Trembles the fir-bough Above the pale ... Glorious inrush! Magic of meeting! Mute in my bosom The name I hear. [Enter Conchobar from the fir forest.] CONCHOBAR. You were awaiting me? DEIRDRE. The fir-tree shook. CONCHOBAR. And you were singing. If I bid you sing The song again! DEIRDRE. You would not have it back. 'Tis they who set the song within the heart May hope to catch the tune. CONCHOBAR. You are the creature, O Deirdre, Deirdre—that in all the world Is surely mine. I may not be your lover, I dare not; I possessed you from your birth, I have owned you as a god. To-morrow, Deirdre, I come to make you fast my one, own wife, To rule a queen, to rule with me, your husband, Ever beside you. I shall give you power, And all my kingdom. DEIRDRE. It is prophesied I shall bring doom to Ulla. CONCHOBAR. Cathfach's fable. DEIRDRE. But Lebarcham's belief; the tale of Medv, My dream night after night. CONCHOBAR. No woman's dreams Are destiny: 'tis love alone, man's love Mows down the future of its springing corn. Away with omens! There is poetry Past speech in what you are, your womanhood, The blessings you confer, dear as the light, And dew and summer; and the solemn joys You will evoke in husband or in son Are nature's word to you of recompense. You touch but nature. DEIRDRE. I would have my freedom; You bring me chains. CONCHOBAR. Not so. You have no mother To speak of your espousals. Trust me, maiden, I love you, and that knowledge in fruition Will bring its witness to your cheek and soften The darkness in your eyes. You will be free, Beloved, when I have bound you fast my wife. DEIRDRE. I cannot ... I obeyed you as a child; I think my childhood must be past, because I can no more obey you: I defy. CONCHOBAR. O eyes, I have not seen in battle-light, How beautiful!—O violet levin-cloud! O brows that have been blank, and beauty rushing To cheek and forehead! In a moment, child, You have put on your fate. O rose, unfolding First of all roses—Deirdre! DEIRDRE. My dear Master, My guardian, hush! I cannot hear your words; They are as foreign speech to me: and yet They hurt me, like the harp. One cannot comfort The wild, lone music—for all music lives Away, in a far wilderness, alone. My spirit trembles on the open ground, And dares not ... I entreat you give me peace. I am too young to love you. CONCHOBAR. Still too young! The cry of every year for sixteen years. You are of age to be my wife, of beauty To crown my kingdom, and at last I snatch you From Time as once from Death. You are my own; And you will learn to love me as the herb Learns its first blossoming. DEIRDRE. I try to speak; I fear I am too young to speak to you. Be patient with me; for a little while, Let me have freedom. I have never gathered A wild wood-flower, nor seen the games nor prowess Of your warriors on their trial, nor been tossed On yonder moving sea ... and of all creatures I envy ships, more than the breeze-blown birds, More than the armies I have heard in passage Beyond the echoing fence and cried to follow Since they went forth abroad. CONCHOBAR. I make you queen, Have you forgotten that? I could not think That I your saviour, I your fosterer, Your hermit and the fellow of your doom Would ever have to woo you. O beloved, If you would hear your praises, of all living I could unveil them best: but do not think How much I know to praise in you, the compass Of my rose's beauty when there scarce was rose. Forget the evenings when you ran to meet me With prattle of the day, forget the kisses I gave you in your childhood, and the music I taught you on your little harp: remember Only the last time that I kissed your mouth, The last time that I kissed your forehead, child Because I felt you tremble like a lamb, And dared not kiss again. I only worship Your loveliness of this day's morn and noon. As any youth, I tell you that your eyes Are stars to me, your hair... DEIRDRE. As any youth? You say, you love me: in myself I feel That any youth would give me better praise Than you, praise from his golden lips, his lyre, Praise of the sudden wonder of my beauty, Flashed over him. You took me as a babe. CONCHOBAR. A babe ... You are a woman now, it seems; That in itself is doom. I have borne off So many captive women to my tent, Who cried to me: I did not know their speech, I did not heed their crying. Any youth, You say, would praise you better than your king. You in your turn, Shall be to me as any captive slave That I have had my will of. DEIRDRE. It may be ... You have the power. CONCHOBAR. So you resign yourself? DEIRDRE. Surely to Fate. Am I not Erin's child? For I shall suffer nothing but my doom, And that I can take silently. CONCHOBAR. Beloved, Close not your lips against me not from speech, Not with that rigid look as you were dead. O beloved, give me Some softness of your beauty! When you lay So shining and so small, I changed, I felt Great hollows in my heart—that is desire: It comes to women with their motherhood. Be patient, Fedlimid's sweet daughter, wait! DEIRDRE. [Closing her eyes.] If I were dead There would be music then that you would hear, More lonesome than the wind, more desolate Than the wan marshes when the moon is gone, For I should haunt you. CONCHOBAR. [Close to her.] Queen, Fiercer than any haunting ghost the steps Of a dogging husband. You will live imprisoned, In the open hall resplendent and unpraised. If any of my knights or bards—if Genan But venture on a stave, Aidall, Ferechne, Or of the Red Branch any sapling twig, Conall or Naisi ... you will snap their lives; So I will blight your springtide—it is little Your brief young spring-tide. So I hush the throats Of the nightingales that all would pipe for you, And sword-songs of one note. [She silently weeps.] These are the tears All maidens shed ere marriage. DEIRDRE. Conchobar, My king ... CONCHOBAR. O music! DEIRDRE. You have set my thoughts On the other happy maidens. Fetch my mother, Not Medv, but she who nursed me for a month; You tore me from her breast. CONCHOBAR. Bring Elva back! I have forgotten her; she may be dead, She may be living, DEIRDRE. You have given me At least her name that Medv would never say. Elva, my mother! CONCHOBAR. Peace! Is Lebarcham Within the cottage? DEIRDRE. No, she fetches me That I have need of. CONCHOBAR. I will wait for her.... [He stands considering Deirdre doubtfully: she smiles for the first time.] DEIRDRE. I shall not kill myself. How should one die With all the spring before... CONCHOBAR. One does not die with all the spring before, One cannot, Deirdre.... [With sudden resolution.] Wedded wives of Erin Have brought no ruin on their lovely land: They cannot, they are born too true. Farewell. [He kisses the hem of her veil and goes out into the firwood at the back.] DEIRDRE. If there were verity in that farewell, Farewell for ever! Elva, O sweet Elva, O Mother, bless my Naisi, bless the white And ruddy flower, the Bridegroom! I must tell you In secret of my Naisi, learn of you How I shall greet him. Mother, I shall die Except he bear me through the narrow strait. [On the left from below the cot enter Lebarcham and Naisi.] LEBARCHAM. She is gazing over the water—step gently; you shall look on her unseen. Alack! she is changed, she is pale. NAISI. She is white as the stars at dawning—she is white, who should be trembling gold. She is beautiful. Oh hide me before her! I am ashamed. You told me she was pining for me. Go to her. I have risked my life in her service. LEBARCHAM. [Calling.] Deirdre! But you do not answer? I have been on your errand; I have returned. [Deirdre trembles and turns to the cloaked figure.] I have never seen her frown before. Your disguise—the rough, gray cloak—take it off. [He throws his cloak back.] Now you may see her flush! Child, you are a princess. Naisi will think you ill-nurtured if you do not greet him. NAISI. Come to me, Deirdre. [She runs swiftly to him.] Ah, my fawn, My delicate, fleet-footed! [To Lebarcham.] Is she dumb? [To Deirdre.] She was not dumb a little while ago, Or this good gossip has a lying tongue. I heard that she would wed the snow and wed The rosy blood, and wed the raven hair. Since I am darkest, ruddiest and whitest Of Ulla's younger chiefs I braved the peril Of piercing your dark firs. No welcome, Deirdre? [She kisses him.] But is this wise? You will confuse the colours with this kissing— No snow beneath such lips as these! My Princess, 'Tis well the King must wed you presently, Well that he keeps you close! You see the Wonder. To-morrow it is gone! I have two brothers, Ainnle and Ardan; I am wedded to them In closest fellowship; we rove the world: And we this evening shall take ship to Alba, Alba with all its marvels, loveable, Sweet Eastern land.... Your touch is on my wrist. O Princess! [He pushes her hand away.] Quick farewell! For you are set aside to be my Queen; High doom is over you. I will not linger, I must not. I have given you your whim. The Knights of the Red Branch are terrible, And yet our Lord counts us the Lights of Valour— Ainnle and Ardan And Naisi—finds in me his one great want. Therefore, O maiden, do not lightly praise, If there be breath of song in you, my cheeks Or brow or dark-spread hair; praise my delight In the long oars, the dazzle of the sea, The long, black galleys and the bloody raid. DEIRDRE. But we shall never part again, O Naisi, Bear me away with you. I cannot speak, Not much, not anything to listen to, Yet I shall lie awake at night to ease The pain it is to think of you by thinking More constantly each moment. Bear me with you To Alba, to the loveable, soft land. [Naisi pauses stupefied; then turns away.] NAISI. But he has waited For sixteen years: I am his chosen knight: At dance, at feasting never has he turned His eyes on woman, or if idly turned An instant, he was back with Lebarcham Asking of thee, thy years. Where are you stepping? Your feet are toward the waves. DEIRDRE. For I shall travel Either across this narrow sea with you, Or else alone with the currents and the creatures That travel fleet and silent underneath. NAISI. O vehement, mad girl, it is for freedom That you would draw this ruin on us all, On the great King my Overlord, on Erin. It is not well. Women are ever captive In their spirits and their bodies: so the gods Have fashioned it and there is no escape. DEIRDRE. You will not give me love? NAISI. Your liberty I shall not give you, if I give you love. Love is the hardset bondage in the world. I would not put such chains on any woman To love me.... DEIRDRE. Let me be with you, the name Of being with you call it what you will— Bondage or freedom, I should still be happy, Yea, for a year, yea, for a brood of years. NAISI. Then you are mine for ever? I will lead you Over the narrow sea. We must not tarry. Heigh, Lebarcham! DEIRDRE. But I must kiss my Medv, My sweet, sweet foster-mother. NAISI. I forbid; She will betray us. DEIRDRE. Then with you, with you! [Exeunt Deirdre and Naisi.] LEBARCHAM. And Lebarcham, who has brought you this happiness, who would have you free, who is willing to put you out of her sight for ever that your beauty may not be blighted— Lebarcham is forgotten. The girl has never given me her heart. I do not make her suffer—that is the secret. For me no good-bye, only a softness for the milky heart of Medv. That is the way of beauty; I must be content to be beauty's friend. Ay me, but beauty can have no friend on the earth, only lovers! I will lie for her, I will ask no favour—And the King! I am a traitor—Naisi, he is a traitor too. I was not aware: But what names come on us in our misery, before we are aware. We are all traitors ... and the King!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II Loch Etive. To the right and left hunting-booths under fir-trees: at the back the curving silver water-side, and grass and grove full of branching garlic, white with flower. Mountains beyond in deep but silvery mist. Ardan and Ainnle by the hunting-booth on the left. ARDAN. It was an evil thing to do. AINNLE. Repented, Ardan, dear brother, it has lost its evil. I think she loves him more that he offended, And then so quickly sorrowed for her sorrow, And sought with vow forgiveness. ARDAN. She had never Come back to him if we had never followed And turned her flight! When first she heard her husband Had kissed the daughter of the Earl Dun-Thone In secret as they feasted, and had sent her A frisky doe, a fawn beside its foot, And after that had visited the girl, As he was marching home from Inverness, I saw our Deirdre shudder, fire, resolve— Alike to her was death or perishing; I saw her set her shallop on a wave; She floated forth, away from us. AINNLE. His beauty, His nature, and the freedom of his valour, Make him so meet for love he is beguiled To lightness and to dalliance: so I pleaded With lips that cannot lie. He never thought Of wrong to her. He drank a kiss like wine, Gave presents as a king his favouring grace. But when we brought her back again, he swore, Till he should leave her for the host of dead, He would not cause her gloom—then met her eyes, And there such mist and fire had wrought together It was creation of a world no mortal Could leave one instant of his life. But see her, Through the white branchlets of the garlic... [Enter Deirdre.] DEIRDRE. Ainnle And Ardan, I have slumbered Beneath a high rock yonder, while the daylight Went on with day about me. O the joys Of sleep below the fir-wood—swelling branches Attune their music to sweet recollection, That lives on through the swoon of weariness. To be a woman, Yet breathe the huntsman's and the warrior's life, Handle the leashes And keep the hounds myself, endure much hardship, Endure without a fire, never alone In any solitude, drinking the fountain, Fresh from the peats with you! ARDAN. O vehement, O sister that art fairer than the sun, You touch our days With newness wrought on their monotony As light on deserts. DEIRDRE. [Laughing.] Do I make Your bosoms simpler and your frames more placid To blast or sun-burn? This you do for me. And you have taught my womanhood the noble, Firm lenity of man, when I had almost Been hurried to destruction. ARDAN. See your hunter Leaping among the rocks. Look up! [Calling.] What sport? NAISI. [Afar.] The best, sweet boys; a deer, with three above The men shall carry down. [He enters.] My girl will banquet. ARDAN. And taste our spoil as well; we have been fishing Over the unsteady estuary: our nets Were loaded. DEIRDRE. Yesterday a badger-hunt! Fish, venison and badger's fat—no princess Is fed more daintily. NAISI. You are content? O Deirdre, O the wonder to behold This sparkling loveliness like dew that shoots Its scintillating arrows on the air. [He kisses her.] DEIRDRE. I fell asleep While you were on the hills, a daylight sleep, Beneath a forest-fir, mid garlic-stems, Their rank and sappy odour breathing up, Till mastered by the spices of the tree; And all their knots of stars mild in the noontide, While from a bending branch afar the cuckoo's Sweet voice came from the peak of Glen da Ruad, I lay and was made fresh, as gentlest nights Can never freshen. NAISI. You praise idleness, And I my exercise: we both are gay. Ainnle, take in this carcass and bring forth The draught-board—“Fairhead”—stolen from Conchobar. [Exit Ainnle into the right-hand booth.] Dear, you slept ill in bed. DEIRDRE. Dreams haunted me. [Re-enter Ainnle with the draught-board called “Fairhead.”] NAISI. Sit down and play as if for life. [They begin their game.] AINNLE. How lonesome. The wastes of air! No voice, nor eagle's barking, Nor fox's barking. ARDAN. I can hear the wavelets Tremble among the grasses.... [A voice over the water.] Sons of Uisnech! Heigh, heigh, ye sons of Uisnech! NAISI. [Starting.] Listen, listen! An Irishman is calling. DEIRDRE. Ah! [She rises as if in alarm, then sits down calmly.] Beloved, It is an error, and you break the game. NAISI. Pardon, my girl; I thought I heard an accent Sweet to the ear as raindrops after drought. My cast—no, yours! DEIRDRE. We are confused. 'Tis mine. AINNLE. It swept across the water. ARDAN. But a man Of Scotland must have raised it.... [A voice nearer the shore.] Sons of Uisnech, Heigh, heigh, ye sons of Uisnech! NAISI. [Starting up again.] Deirdre, listen. Again, again! It is an Irish cry. DEIRDRE. [Still sitting.] Ah!— NAISI. 'Tis an exile hears. DEIRDRE. But Erin's sons Shout not as Alba's. Ardan, Was that an Irish cry? ARDAN. It made me see My father's grave, and the green, green descent Down from his hill. [A voice from a moored ship.] Ye sons of Uisnech, Heigh, heigh, ye sons of Uisnech. NAISI. Fergus calls! ARDAN. Yea, it is Fergus. AINNLE. Fergus! NAISI. [To Ardan.] Run to him. [Ardan goes to the shore.] DEIRDRE. [Pressing them back.] I knew that first cry his, and if ye listen To any other words that voice shall speak— O, but I knew that voice, the voice of Fergus. NAISI. Why did my girl Conceal her recognition of the cry? DEIRDRE. Ay me, the greatest sorrow of all sorrows! In sleep, the tossing slumber of last night I saw three birds fly hither from Emain; They brought us sips of honey, and from us Bore in their cruel bills three drops of blood. NAISI. A foolish dream—confused. Interpret quickly. DEIRDRE. The signs were certain: Fergus and his sons Come offering peace, and the three drops of blood ... My darlings, long the lasting woe of it If ye receive his message. NAISI. Hasten down, Ainnle, and give him welcome; let us learn If there be substance in this dream. [Ainnle turns to follow Ardan.] DEIRDRE. But pause! You will not, you are dying, and I pray You will not die. But stay, but promise me Whatever Fergus asks you will deny ... How fast you fall back from me, like a tide Drawn deep into the sea.... Give me your promise, Give me your oath—then to the water-side. Naisi, beloved! NAISI. By Erin! DEIRDRE. Nay, by Alba, This gracious foster-land where I am queen, Queen to your kingship, Naisi. NAISI. Better death For Erin, for the laughter and the gloom Of the one isle in all the world, than peace And love and kisses in a foreign land, Even your kisses: but I do you wrong. Are you not Erin's child? DEIRDRE. Give me the promise, The promise with true lips. [Making a gesture of denial, Naisi joins Ainnle.] DEIRDRE. They are all gone, They cannot hear my dream. Alas, 'tis fatal To speak in prophecy from lips that love. They have no help of one another, none— I see ... but then to me his life is largest, It is his doom hangs on the air ... I see So very far, from verge to verge. But I must keep my vision to myself. When Naisi came, I put my dreams away, And simply lit my soul. All else estranges, All else is terror and makes variance. I should have learnt—I ever sung my staves To the dull hills in secret. Ah, they come. [The Chiefs return with Fergus.] NAISI. The king requires our arms. ARDAN. Our country is in peril. AINNLE. Conchobar bids us serve him with our swords. FERGUS. Lady, I am their surety; and they sail Under the safeguard of King Conchobar, Firm as the earth the covenant we offer, Children of Uisnech. NAISI. Verily, we knew It is most firm. DEIRDRE. [As in a dream.] Children of Uisnech, heroes Who can refuse no combats ... Without guile ... Branches of honour! [As if waking.] Naisi, will you listen? Far greater is your lordship here in Alba Than Conchobar's in Erin. Of your pride You will not stoop to serve him? NAISI. Better far Than any greatness is one's native land; No greatness can be excellent to him, Who may not see his country. FERGUS. Ah the deep Wave-voice of Naisi, dearer to our ears Than any other music. NAISI. [Vehemently to Deirdre.] Clear your face! Go, fetch my shield; you put me to this shame In presence of these heroes. Fetch my shield! DEIRDRE. [Motionless.] The waves are high; They rise to havoc—there is no contention, No clashing of the shields.... NAISI. You disobey? DEIRDRE. I am not Deirdre. Oh, the bitterness! I am no more your flower, my voice is freezing, My heart is freezing, and I feel a change Within me as when elves shrink up the form Of mortals to their stature. Pity me! I am become your curse, dear sons of Uisnech, I am become your doom.... You heed me not, You cannot. You must perish in the marsh As captives overcome. NAISI. So be it, girl. We three will never doubt the warranty. AINNLE. [Seizing her hand.] But you will come with us? DEIRDRE. ... To see your death! I have this song to sing, this bitter sorrow To tell the story of: it is not doomed, Surely it is not doomed I should be there! NAISI. Fergus, my oath to thee! ARDAN AND AINNLE. And ours, and ours! NAISI. I go to rouse my men with clarion-calls. Forgive, good Fergus, that I leave you here That raven on the bough. [Exit into left-hand tent. Deirdre remains where she is, but lifts her head to the hills as if listening.] FERGUS. She is your queen? She does not seem a mortal ... I can feel her Even in the little brook upon the shore, In the honey-suckle bushes, through the blowing Of the wild poppies, and I cannot speak. I am right glad she does not sail with us. ARDAN. She sails with us, you cannot doubt— FERGUS. The king Sent for the sons of Uisnech. In our land There is no name of Deirdre. AINNLE. They forget her? That cannot be. FERGUS. Nor have I ever said She is forgotten—it is worse, more fatal, As when they say an enemy is killed On the battle-field because he is not found Nor his bracelets, nor his armour. Through the court There is no mention of her: in the hall Her little harp hangs up; none touches it. There is a spider's web across. Take heed! I have told you truth, her name is never spoken By waking lips: but, in the summer nights, Those guarding the king's bed have heard her name With moans and sound of weeping. It were best She lingered in glen Etive. [Ardan comes to Deirdre and takes her hand.] DEIRDRE. [With a shriek.] Loose me, Ardan! The moving water hurts me: all these ripples Ripple to Ireland—loose me! I must listen For Naisi's bugle; I should surely die If it rang unawares ... A mottled, dusky, Round-bodied, wild-bee buzzes—beautiful And large ... O torture of the ear, deep wound To wait for Naisi's call. ARDAN. Is summer come, The harvest near in Erin? FERGUS. Neither corn, Nor grass, nor foliage grew this windy spring. There is a curse upon the land. ARDAN. The trees, Those oaks we planted on our father's grave— Have they been marred by failure? FERGUS. They were small Of leaf this year. ARDAN. Fergus, I sorrow yet After my father: like those dreaded waves That heave up from the bottom of the sea The hours when I lament him. FERGUS. Uisnech's children Not to the world's end may forget brave Uisnech, Not to the bosom of eternity. But here is Naisi. [He comes out of his tent and puts the bugle to his lips.] ARDAN. [Advancing.] Sister, you are pressing Your hands across your eyes. His heron-call! Look forth! DEIRDRE. [Removing her hands from her scared face.] These cloaks—all scarlet—everything Pressing so close down on me. NAISI. For Emain, Fergus, these sword-red heroes, quick for onset, Quick to break down great battles. MEN. For Emain! It calls us over sea—Emain, Emain! FERGUS. [To the Sons of Uisnech.] Fair Champions, hail. NAISI. [To Fergus.] Swiftly draw down the galleys. Weigh anchors up! [They rush from all sides to the tents and to the waterside Naisi passes in front of Deirdre defiantly.] NAISI. Girl, they are gathering; Once more my heron-cry among the hills! The muster will be full. [To Ainnle.] Bring down my gear, The king's good draught-board. Ah, it was a fault— To steal his “Fairhead”—All shall be restored. Go, I command you. Fetch her ornaments, Since it is vain to bid her do my will; Her brooches.... DEIRDRE. I shall hear your heron-cry Once more among the hills—O pity me! Let me not see you; but the long, long cry— Naisi, it may be I shall answer that, And follow you and walk as in a dream. I would not disobey. NAISI. Then fetch the gear, And meet me by the water. [He passes. Ainnle looks at Deirdre; then he goes to the tents and brings out weapons, jewels that he heaps on “Fairhead”—also Naisi's scarlet cloak.] DEIRDRE. [Fixing her eyes on it and shuddering.] Conchobar's Was a black cloak, pure raven. This is scarlet, And then his corse as white as the young snow. I shall not see it. AINNLE. Deirdre, sweetest sister! DEIRDRE. I cannot; in my heart it is forbidden. AINNLE. O Deirdre, sister! DEIRDRE. And the blood will pour; And suddenly ... it is not for these eyes To see it—suddenly... The roses know, The white-grass flowers, the wind. [To Ainnle.] Take down the board, Take all my jewels, and this little gorget He set about my throat. Let all be done Exactly as he wills it. AINNLE. Then, my own, Give me your hand, and by the water's brink Let Naisi find his wife. DEIRDRE. O cruel words, “It was a fault to steal!” I do not hear That heron-cry among the hills; I hear Only the hurry on the beach—this silence, And the thick crowd in front, the noise. [A horn call.] O Ainnle, If even now ... but fetch him back to me, Leave all, and bid him fetch me, if he cares To take back what he stole.... I am but raving; One must not give reproaches to the dead. AINNLE. Come to the water-brink, as he commanded. You will not? [Deirdre turns from him, and looks to the hills.] Then at least I must obey. [He goes to the shore. The tumult at the water-edge increases.] DEIRDRE. How piercing is the noise! I have no heart For any of their doings. They are strangers That land upon the shore, and strangers, strangers That drag the boats now down upon the beach. Naisi—the speeding foot—here was his track, The sea will cover it within an hour; Would that the sea could cover all! The harp is here, the little tent, the weapons, The fishing-rod, all the bright Eastern-land. [She suddenly starts up.] I think they are embarked, the moving oars— Naisi—his boat is deep within the creek, Or is it passed beyond? ... The winds are loosed, Strange little winds that know not where they go, Nor why they are—I know why they are loosed— Naisi is in his tomb. And this his praise Is like no praise that I have felt before, It falls so solitary on the earth. [She begins a dirge.] Long is the day without them, day of twilight, Long is the day, but I espouse their praise— Their singing-shields are silent; but my harp That has not been a stranger to their praises Sings me the spirit-chiefs. Their battle-fields Are with me in the air, their cradle-land, My lions of Lis Una. Long the days I live without them; but to sing their praises The time will be too short till day of doom; For I, as in a chariot, pass among The havoc of their arms. They mow, they reap, They toss the harvest; they hunt down their foes; Playing on breath above the horses' steam, They reach their spoil through drivings of sharp fire; Then they return— Oh, long will be the days Without them! O, my harp, thou must not wail! Give forth their melody. My eager heroes After their warriors' march are turning homeward, My brilliant ones,—and, with the light of valour Hovering over him, with ruddy cheeks Most beautiful, red lips ... But nevermore I shall await him; stronger than the waves That press up from their wave-beds is my grief. O Erin, O sweet rain-flowers in the grass, How heavy is my heart! [Re-enter Naisi behind her.] NAISI. There is no peril To lovers, save in parting. DEIRDRE. O most wise, Therefore you stay with me. NAISI. Infirm of heart, It is your purpose to remain behind? You prayed once, prayed through all your golden body To cross the sea with me; for you I crossed it; For you I was a traitor to my king, Conchobar, king of men; and he remembers Only my loyalty. I tell you, woman, His message is more poignant to my ear Than any call of love. DEIRDRE. [Pressing her cheek against Naisi's.] Upon the day Thou tookest me along with thee and over Assaroe of the oars, thou would'st not then Have been against me. This I say to thee, Naisi, beloved, I shall not be alive, Not after Naisi; soon my soul will leave me; My life will not be long. NAISI. What sunders us? If I be doomed to die—. DEIRDRE. Ah, were you dead, You were my own: then we are dead together, And secret evermore. Then you would listen; I should not make you gloomy with my songs. But now— My bridegroom, O my glory—white and red— O my belovèd, and your angry cheek! The haste as if for battle.... NAISI. You are false, You dare not see me die. But, if you loved me, You would drink up my blood while it was warm, Sooner than let it soak upon the earth. So women love in love's extremity. You darken, you grow red. Deirdre, that colour Of embers in your cheeks! My ruddy gold, You fire me with desire! What, leave this treasure, What, drag it down to doorways in the rocks Where Druids keep the keys!— [He seizes her.] DEIRDRE. But stay awhile. My sight is gone from me, and I must see. Oh, loose my hands, give freedom! NAISI. Then farewell. I leave you with your liberty: we sunder— DEIRDRE. Give me your hands again; I have no strength. Look there, The sun is setting! Etive of the loch, I think it is a cattlefold of sun, So glistening, so fair! NAISI. You sing of Alba, The music rushes to your face; you give me No word of parting. DEIRDRE. Naisi, look at it— Look at our land, how loveable it is, Look at the coast, the rushes. NAISI. See, the oars, The gallant colour of the cloaks. My men Flash from the creek in fair array. DEIRDRE. But look Once on that bending branch! 'Twas there the cuckoo Sang to us—there we listened. NAISI. Then; but now What matter—we are parting! DEIRDRE. Do not speak— But look a little with me down that straight, That fair-ridged glen. NAISI. You stay me— DEIRDRE. But a little; Yonder our home, belovèd; give me leave— Our first, fair home, the little copse behind. How short the time has been! NAISI. The time is short. DEIRDRE. [With sudden effort, after a pause.] O loveable, Pure sand that takes my foot-prints, limpid water, Take off your spell from me! NAISI. Why do you cling So strongly to my shoulder? Loose me, child: We part since you are fearful. DEIRDRE. Alba, Alba! It is for this:—I had not come away, As now I come away from you for ever, But that I part with my beloved. O Naisi, Turn once again! ... The loveable, dear land!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III Scene: A Hall in the House of Emain (similar to the Hall of Fedlimid in the Prologue—only where that had windows at the back, this has a great empty fireplace). Lebarcham is weaving: Cathfach is always at the chimney-nook reading one of his Fairy Books. [Enter Conchobar.] CONCHOBAR. Lebarcham, there is something wild and unnatural in this darkness. I am driven in by it. Over the forest there is a cloud like smoke. LEBARCHAM. It is in the house, too. People give it names, and then they are no longer afraid. They say it is insects in the air, or the shadow of a flock of birds. It does not stay me at my weaving. CONCHOBAR. If you know the secret of it, speak: for it spreads. And it lays hold of the leaves of the forest like a blight. I have been in the deep forest. The fir-spines dropt down. LEBARCHAM. I can interpret; but the legend is not of our gods. CONCHOBAR. It is not wholesome like the night; it is a blain on the air. To-day is the day of my birth. It should be auspicious. [To Cathfach.] I do not heed your prophecies; they are only music; they are doomful as the wind: but these auguries, these things that lie about one's feet!—Canker on the green leaves of the forest and on the day when a king was born to Emain! CATHFACH. [Pointing to Lebarcham.] Let her interpret. She has heard the story from the Druid who persuaded my child to be a Christian. There is no doom in it: it is something that happened on a yesterday long ago. CONCHOBAR. Was there darkness like this on my birthday long ago? Lebarcham, it is doom. LEBARCHAM. It is the doom of a god. I have often heard the fable from the lips of a woman. CATHFACH. From the lips of a girl—my daughter. It is no rune for a king. CONCHOBAR. I have noted this gray darkness on my birthday before, unseasonable, forbidding. Lebarcham, you are my gossip: give me the story. LEBARCHAM. It is the story of how a god met his death. He was young, he was radiant; he came from the Sun-God, bearing summer in his hands. They laid snares for him in secret ... CONCHOBAR. Then there was treachery? LEBARCHAM. [Wincing.] Ay, my king, they were traitors. But even the story-teller says they did not understand. Some of us are born to do these things, like children firing haystacks. They must be done; they are in the web. So his own people took him and nailed him to a tree. And the story-teller says he suffered it of his own will. There were two great armies marshalled in the air: but he would have no help of them. He died, he was betrayed—and he had never broken faith. The deed had to be covered, it was an infamy. CONCHOBAR. If I could avenge it, even now! And my shield has been singing to me. If I could avenge my God. He has been wailing to me through the fir-boughs. CATHFACH. He would not be avenged—he is no god. Have you not seen the image? He is a slave, and they are binding him to an altar. LEBARCHAM. No: in the legend he is not a slave: he was the most High God, the Creator of all men, the Creator of the heavens and the earth. He came to men to be their King— it was his last gift, for he had given them the seasons and the stars. CONCHOBAR. He was a King? LEBARCHAM. And they put away His majesty; they made light of Him. He was in the midst of His own people, giving them the grace of His lips, working wonders among them: the traitors hemmed Him round; they stripped Him as He had been a felon, and He let them do it, for He knew it was in the web. CONCHOBAR. It was an infamy! LEBARCHAM. But a great convulsion came over nature at the sight and the stars were in trouble, for He had fashioned them. It is a wild, strange story, but it holds my heart. One thought it was only women who must be patient and forgive: that Bound One, who could have drawn the far waves to His service, showed no anger. And He died on a great sigh as softly as a little child. CONCHOBAR. Hush, woman, for my heart is broken. Would I had been there, I who can deal division between hosts. I would have set the Bound One free. If I could avenge Him! CATHFACH. [Raising his eyes from his Fairy Book.] Are you become a Christian? CONCHOBAR. I am this—my heart is broken for my God. And they took Him unawares. CATHFACH. They defeated Him on the day of your birth. You were born under a curse. CONCHOBAR. And I took it to myself; I embraced it. So it must be with kings. Lebarcham, light a fire on the hearth. Let its embers blaze. LEBARCHAM. Is there a banquet to-night? CONCHOBAR. It is my birthday. LEBARCHAM. Beloved, O my king, I had not forgotten. But you would ever be alone on your birthday. CONCHOBAR. Ay, I would keep it with my Curse. Woman, would you question me? Light a fire—it is for my pleasure. Let it blaze as a beacon to those in the dark. To-night there is a banquet, and the Bards, not the Druids, must sing. Cathfach, bid Fedlimid unhang his great harp—it will learn a new theme at the king's feast. [Exit Cathfach.] And, Lebarcham, her bride-clothes ... They are laid in my chest. You shall remove them; they have use. LEBARCHAM. Master, must I put forth her raiment? The moth has wasted it, Time is in its folds. CONCHOBAR. I nursed her in her swaddling clothes, I chose the broidery of her maiden belt, her brooch, her wedding-dress. I have kept them smooth. There! [gives a key] you will find the pieces laid on each other as if there were a corpse beneath them. LEBARCHAM. She ... you have said no word ... is she coming alone? CONCHOBAR. I have been deserted by my Curse. Go, unlock the chest.... Her furs, that great bear-mantle, my gift. This is a wild evening; the sabled green is more mournful than snow. [Exit Lebarcham.] Never will I worship any lord save this king that stooped to cradle me in the hollow of His darkness; He that accepted His curse, for it was in the web; and knew no anger nor any vengeance. It has come to me what I must do. I have sent for my Naisi for Erin's sake, yea, for the want of him within my heart. I have not asked for Deirdre—yet if she should come, the fire is lit. I shall see her warming her beautiful, young hands. She is safe. I gave her her little harp—it was not well. I cared nothing for her music: she sang what she had never heard. But in the forest by the fort where I had guarded her, amid the deep trees.... And it is come to me, all the patience, the assuagement, all the smoothness of the road. She shall come back to me as the seasons, as the home-sailing of the far ships. [Enter Eogan.] EOGAN. They travel to Dundalk. It is reported Dierdre holds a Court among your vassals... CONCHOBAR. A Court? How?—Treason? EOGAN. Praying them to guard Naisi from the cruelty of your vengeance. CONCHOBAR. Report!—I will not doubt her, if report can make me my Naisi's murderer. EOGAN. It is said the Queen dropt tears as she drew near to Emain, but Naisi dashed them from her red cheeks with his kisses. CONCHOBAR. Then report says true, and that is Naisi's action. EOGAN. Your commands? CONCHOBAR. That you leave me. Begone! [Exit Eogan.] She said two armies were marshalled in the air about my God.... He did not beckon them. Oh, I have heard So great a rune I would give all my heart To its significance. Why did my God Mould me this body of my clay? What dealing Would He require of my right hand? A wroth Stirs in me deeper than can strike my foes, A call from Him, a call from the great darkness That now is vanishing and leaves the night. What should I do? I would fell all the forest All through the land if only I might learn What the great King requires of Conchobar. If I had ridden in a chariot There where the traitors grouped, I had arrested His cruel pain. O marvellous, my God! [Lebarcham returns and lays the fire.] I wonder—are you false? LEBARCHAM. The seasons change, And if one lives one must be false at whiles To memory or to hope. CONCHOBAR. The Heavens change, The skies, the state of man; there are some bosoms As rhythmic as the sea that has one burthen And grides upon the stones with one complaint, That never can forget nor need remember Because it does not weary. Light the fire, And let its flame spread out. LEBARCHAM. Your eyes are chill; I would put in them something of a flame. Besides, if one sit long and watch the fire, And fall to dreaming, one grows very soft, The years pass on before, the shining years, And one is with them.... [She grinds the flints together.] [Conchobar turns from her.] CONCHOBAR. It is raining fast. How wet her hair will be ... and he will wring it, And push it in her hood. She comes in rain, The Irish girl, in rain that makes her Irish— I love the dashing rain, with wind about! [Starting.] Red sunset on the floor! No, there is current And motion through the redness.... It is flame. [Re-enter Cathfach.] CATHFACH. [Drawing back from the hearth.] The fire is kindled. Would my children's children Might drop in darkness, perish one by one So Erin kept her green, her little shoots, The green, the beautiful young heads of grass: But lo, the fire is kindled that shall strew Her earth with ashes. There will be no spring-tide, No creeping out of verdure through the peats In Ulla any more. CONCHOBAR. What troubles you? The great feast-sign, the hospitality And the comfort of a fire? You will receive Your daughter's sons in safety, we shall quaff Great draughts.—To-morrow we shall forth to war, And, Cathfach, I shall leave with you.... To-night She sits by me at banquet. I shall lift Her hood and give her welcome... Then, O then.... Dash her to Faerie, that, if I must follow I follow as a madman, leaving Ulla To Naisi. Cathfach, you shall give me spell To follow her, if so I must. O Druid, When I lie down amid the forest-shadow, By the small fort she slumbered in, not daring Even to draw a deeper breath, the elves Gather around me in great woefulness, With solaces and charms. They hear between My breath—it shakes them in their slender land, That echo of no call. LEBARCHAM. [To Cathfach.] To see her face! But is the band approaching? Does she come? CATHFACH. I only see the far-away and mists Between—a heaving valley shut like death. CONCHOBAR. But they have passed Dundalk, across their journey Evening and night are mingled—Ochtree too ... Those hillocks on the sundown sever it Alone from our great plain. [Re-enter Eogan.] EOGAN. The Sons of Uisnech Are at your door. CONCHOBAR. At yonder door? EOGAN. The three, And Fergus.... CONCHOBAR. [In a whisper.] And the woman? EOGAN. Ay, my lord. CONCHOBAR. Lebarcham, you hear it. But I am not as that King whose death spread dust on my birthday. He was faint to dying when He did those deeds you tell of. I am not dying; I am not as that god. By my own vow.... EOGAN. You welcome them? CONCHOBAR. How stands The Red Branch Hostelry for food and drink? EOGAN. 'Tis well provisioned.... LEBARCHAM. Let me bid them hither, And bring them to you. CONCHOBAR. They shall rest awhile. Eogan, conduct them to the Hostelry ... Give them sweet-tasted viands and sweet drinks. Heap all the place with fuel. [With great effort.] Let the city Shout their return. [Exit Eogan.] CATHFACH. My king, O Conchobar, They come at their own peril, out of love, A contrite love.... CONCHOBAR. You mean the Sons of Uisnech Come thus? Of them I take no least account. If, at the time of harvest, summer dust Should raise itself, to him who owns the harvest What is the roadway's dust? If Uisnech's children Companion her who is my one concern, Let them have care! CATHFACH. The Curse, it is the Curse! Here at our very side, upon the lip I honour most.... CONCHOBAR. They come not of themselves. It was my warranty—They come to flourish Their triumph and their fame.... CATHFACH. The night is darker Each moment. O my king, not sad Emain, Not Erin, the fair-green, with her blond gales, Her flowers of bog-fir, fragrance of her earth, Her funeral mounds of heroes, the wild songs In the cluster of her rushes, call to me For succour now: it is the dead that call, It is the host of the wide Universe, The men of the whole world, all creatures sprung Of the free gods, who bear their wrong to me, Their wrong—ah, no, their terror, for the brave Tremble as women, they grow superstitious Lest— [Laying his hand on Conchobar.] But their fear is too quick-sprung; the glory Of earth shall not be blasted. Conchobar, Hear your old Druid speak, who ever after Will keep his voice as silent as the eve There on the edges of Emain. My dearest, A bond shall bind Like honeysuckle-bands that bind a tree. The pure and happy listen to this saying: The birds have heard it, it is with the hills; And all the seasons' flowing, all the glee, The happiness of all men, all their music Ceases, if once it should be found at fault. CONCHOBAR. Emain may soak in blood and Erin too, All lands, all kingdoms.... [Sharply to Lebarcham.] I would know your faith. Whose are you? Hers or mine? LEBARCHAM. O misery! CONCHOBAR. I need you for a messenger. LEBARCHAM. To see her, My fair? CONCHOBAR. It may be she has changed in fairness. And then—why, then she is not any more. There will be hospitality. Go forth, Report me of her beauty, of her shape. She did not love you; you are plain and wise And witty—and her love is stayed on fools But, Lebarcham, you love her. Quick, be quick. [Exit Lebarcham.] O Cathfach, are you there! CATHFACH. I look for grief— Since those of my own race, my Ailbhe's children, The props of Erin, have enlinked their lives With Deirdre, the destruction of their king, And of their country. Ye green-muffled rivers, With deep soil-sweetness in your waves, that chaplet Your brim with flowers, ye rivers of Emain, My heart is silent—it has heard you calling, My heart is silent, not with loneliness, But that it hears you calling.... CONCHOBAR. [Who has been pacing in reverie.] Tell me, prophet, Could she grow fairer? CATHFACH. I have never seen her, And none hath seen her—you forget. All beauty Is, till the noon abates it. CONCHOBAR. But at morning?— First of all roses—Deirdre! [Re-enter Lebarcham.] Lebarcham, Your breast is wet—your face. O Lebarcham, Death of my life ... it is not thus with her? LEBARCHAM. Ay, king, she is a weary woman, fallen From the fresh youth we sang of in Emain, Thin, with her cares upon her, with worn edges To eyes that have seen all things and then faded From wonder and their brightness. She is changed. My lord has all our Irish loveliness To choose from—with no foil. CONCHOBAR. Fill high a cup, And let me drain it to my liberty, My honour! Druid, see the Curse hath dwindled And died upon its ash. More wine, more wine! [His servants fill and bring a cup.] A banquet shall be spread and Naisi bring me This ruin of his love and my desire. To watch my gaze on his impoverishment Will chasten him.... LEBARCHAM. Forbear to feast to-night; The travellers can neither eat nor drink— CONCHOBAR. How do they pass their hours? LEBARCHAM. At draughts. CONCHOBAR. They play On my own draught-board “Fairhead” that they stole? LEBARCHAM. I cannot tell. But, Conchobar, henceforth Your enemies are as a bird-flock driven Before the Sons of Uisnech—the famed Three, Who have not lost their valour nor their strength, But show the best of manhood. [Re-enter Eogan.] CONCHOBAR. [To Eogan.] Chief, you know Who slew your father? EOGAN. How should I forget! I know that it was Naisi, son of Uisnech. CONCHOBAR. If so, then tell me—does the woman keep Such beauty as report of men and minstrels Spreads through the land? EOGAN. Who speaks of such a loss? She is supreme, and every rose of summer Poor tribute; every crown a bauble-speck On her apparent sovereignty: her form Is best in all the world, and Naisi, king Of all the world while she is left to him, For ownership and joy. CONCHOBAR. My wife is with him— He has ravished her—my wife! Her beauty mine! Fatherless, wifeless ... Eogan, you and I ... Call out my men In silence; whisper “Naisi, son of Uisnech, Is housing with the wife of Conchobar.” [Exit Eogan.] I took her from her mother, innocent, To be my troth-plight queen—and she is housing Stained and dishonoured, with a ravisher, Yet worthy of my capture. LEBARCHAM. Conchobar— CONCHOBAR. Silence! I will not listen To any word of yours. Hence to the chamber Where you have laid those garments of my wife, That have so long been ready. [Exit Lebarcham with a gesture of despair.] [To Cathfach.] Ha! No feast! Fools may foretell the future, but it takes Wisdom to bring fulfilment to its end— That is the great deed that I work to-night: For everything that happens is my will. CATHFACH. My prophecy! CONCHOBAR. Ah, not your will—your curse, Your terror! ... Had you never sung, the billows Would flow as they are flowing: you but sing them At ebb or flow—and call it prophecy. CATHFACH. [Facing him threateningly.] Erin, your country.... It was hidden from you, That you were drawing a great cloud of blood Across Emain: I broke upon the hills, I lifted and enlarged the air, I showed you How you would set a torch to your own city, To your own native land and all its host. CONCHOBAR. No power was in your murderous voice—the babe Fluttered a little, stretching forth a hand, The dark eyes wavered for a while uncertain, Then fixed on me—That, Cathfach, was my doom, And Erin's and the world's. But even beauty Must be subdued to pleasure of our will; Therefore there must be many evil deeds, Lustration, sorrow—there shall be lament. Music, and women's tears and women's voices ... They sometimes speak a little from that silence We feel along the shore and in the night. Ask not for tidings. [Eogan and Conchobar's followers enter stealthily with unlit torches.] [Whispering his war-cry] “Conchobar, And the Ultonians.” CATHFACH. But the safe-guard, king, Against you! CONCHOBAR. And your prophecies! Farewell! [He seizes a torch, lights it at the fire, and goes out. While Cathfach chants his old prophecy the men keep coming in, lighting torches, and then creeping out.] CATHFACH. A fire is lighted that will catch the hills, And spread from home to home, from hill to hill, From forest spread to forest, from the islands Of Ara, to the ocean-stream of Moyle, And shores of far Manannan's ocean-streams. Fell Ruin passes, And Beauty passes ... Woe, woe, but Ulla Passes as they. Black midnight changes, It swells and moves, Red it becomes, ah, red! A river washing Over Emain, over the fields, hills, valleys, Over the dwellings of our people, doom Blood-red, that from a river grows to flood, And ends a blood-red ocean. Faugh, the lives That make the carnage, make the lamentation! Woe to Emain, And woe to Ulla, And woe to Conchobar, the son of Fachtna, Woe to the proud Red Branch that perishes; To all who hasten yonder at this hour, Mad fondness, hurt and harm, The smooth way lost, gloom, and, where now the living Wave brands and troop to war, the host of dead. [Turning to the door.] I will avert the sorrow. Ailbhe, Ailbhe, For me now it is “Erin and Emain”— Not “Cathfach son of Maelchro of the Battle”— That is my cry! The torches slit the midnight; They glare on it and pass—they are all lighted. The flame of that rent darkness! I must call The waters of Manannan from their rock To whelm the Curse, to save my king, my country— To whelm my race ... for Erin and Emain! [Exit.]</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT IV Scene: A meadow outside the Hostel of the Red Branch. Moonlit night. In the centre of the meadow a knoll. The followers of the Children of Uisnech make a wall of shields round Deirdre, who is swept along by Naisi's arm. Ainnle and Ardan are close to her. NAISI. [To his men.] Extend your lines, shield touching shield, Wait the assault. There stand our countrymen, Our traitor-foemen, on the river margent; Yonder, behind us, is the blood-red fire. My Darling, The dew clouds all your hair—your eyes Burn staunch as planets. O the sorrow, Deirdre, That coming home we come to enemies! ARDAN. It might not be believed how stealthily The people built us in with forest-pine, How stealthily they built the wooden walls And prisoned us in smoke.... AINNLE. Deirdre, your nostrils opened, and you knew Destruction leapt in fire behind that smoke. ARDAN. Through swirls of conflagration how the traitors Were felled by us for fuel. NAISI. [To Deirdre.] In your hair The smoke lies sweet, dew-drenched—sweet, sweet! AINNLE. Sit here— But let me wipe the dew off with my hand. ARDAN. [Turning to the men.] Have patience to receive and break the onslaught, Break every onslaught, till the enemy Remembers we are kin. DEIRDRE. [Seated on the knoll.] It is so cool Here where no torrid winnowings of flame Flap us—so cool! so temperate your courage, So close and home-like is your love and mine In this blest moonlit midnight! The dark shamrock Swells 'neath my hand like down. How piercing happy To be with those more dear than life! NAISI. My Deirdre, Upon this smooth, mid-meadow fairies' knoll, I see you as I never saw before. With such deep cognisance of spell. DEIRDRE. A woman— Secure in this, that the soft air she breathes Is breathed by those she loves.... Soft dark, O air! AINNLE. A little night-cloud, like a heron, trails Across the East, the smoke has left unbleached. It trails, it trails.... ARDAN. The foemen keep their distance. DEIRDRE. Ardan, you swept the dew, yet both my feet Are chill. AINNLE. The dew has fallen again. My cloak To dry the ground— The cloak is drenched, the ground Remains as wet. 'Tis marshy where the shamrock Grows for your cushion. Deirdre!—but the sod Is flowing with a stream. NAISI. 'Tis meadow-land. Come higher up the knoll: there all is firm And warm to tread. [Helping her.] My darling! Earth or heaven Holds nothing for my joy, but only thee! ARDAN. The moon is on the meadow, white as frost. Where is the moon?—Half hidden! Yet so ghost-like The field becomes, so white with masking whiteness, The moon should be full-sail. AINNLE. O Naisi, see! The fields grow bright, it glitters, and the cloud, The little cloud, that like a heron trails Across the East, trails also on a mirror That cannot be of dew.... My mind misgives. CRIES. The meadow is a swamp. OTHER CRIES. A swamp—a pool—a flood! It rises. We are lost.... ARDAN. My ankles feel A clasp that bubbles past them... This is water That lifts and lifts itself, and now has wavelets And steals the least dull moonlight from the sky. Ah, we are caught—some treachery is spreading Its web of eddies round us, a meander Of death.... My knees are circled.... AINNLE. Climb up higher. CRIES. We sink—we perish.... Cursed be Emain! Our Curse on Conchobar! [The groans swell and die away.] NAISI. They have dammed up the river where we drank When we were children. We shall dream of childhood, They say, when we are drowning.... Ah, of youth! Deirdre, of our swift wooing, when the flower Of life but touched by your young finger opened Slick to the glow of noon, with no reproach. Let me behold our flight; the forest-slumber! When you lay peaceable with fringed cross-feet, While Love broke all my peace to watch you thus— My magical! a fugitive! and then Your curbing glory when the Scottish Lords Pressed you with too bold vehemence and Beauty Disclosed her goddess.... ARDAN. Naisi, all is silent, Unpeopled, weltering. The indraught buries Our company; the last accusing hand Sinks from the air. NAISI. My queen! AINNLE. Her robes are clammy: Brother, she is half-drowned against your breast: Lift her! The surge has dizzied you. She clings— Lift her above the surge. NAISI. A throne—thy throne! [He seats her on his shoulder.] DEIRDRE. O sheen of currents, White hue of Death's deep whirlpool, draw us, crystal, Down through the beating waves to happy plains Of friendliness and welcome! Oh, to reach them Before the rising of the sun! My Naisi, The pure, white-welling surge.... the happy plains! [She coils his head in her arms.] ARDAN. Farewell. I leave you, dear ones; the white silver Sinks me beneath it.... NAISI. Cling to me! ARDAN. No, never! Hold her aloft. I seek the gathering Where is no sorrow.... Deirdre! [He disappears.] DEIRDRE. But the sun Will rise before we sink ... AINNLE. My time is short. NAISI. Oh, press up on the knoll. AINNLE. Imperil you, While you can scarcely stand, but sway your burthen, Our Darling, in your struggle. What is this Floats up? The branches of an apple-tree, The ancient tree of marvellous white blossoms, On which the birds called to the hours together. [Lifting the branch to Deirdre.] Shake out their music—shake the silver branches Above my head and prophecy—a gift! [She catches it and he sinks.] DEIRDRE. [Waving the apple-boughs over the place where he sank.] They sing a strain to thee—it is not sad; The music swells with choruses of hundreds Who look not for unkindness, treachery, Nor hate, nor any wailing. O Emain, The marvel of such music in the ear! Its voice—I fall asleep on it—so sweet! NAISI. [His head backward in her arms.] Belovèd, in the world, with unfeared death A very short while from us, we have rapture Of such a freshness that I thought no clay Could, even with consummation of the grave, Encompass for a moment. Is there flux? A swish of hurry in the sea? An ebbing As if our joy sank from us? [Dawn breaks.] O beloved, Your feet are no more overflowed, your garments Are dropping thickly on you.... DEIRDRE. [Stretching out her hand to the waters.] Draw us down, Ye sinking rapids of the great-waved sea, And overwhelm us.... All is cruel anguish And foresight and frustration. The pure water, The whiteness! But the moonlight slides away With the ebb-tide.... Our very dead Forsake us, gathered to the channels. Naisi, Your sword is carried far from you. O Naisi, I see the dabbled meadow-bents, the yellow, Drenched tongue of land.... We shall be parted, Naisi! The vision happens, and against my ears, O loved One, laughter peals.... [Conchobar's followers advance, Naisi sets Deirdre down.] Until to-day I never was alone. My soul must leave me ... O loneliness! One bird's cry on a lake where two have harboured! I cannot be alone! Naisi! NAISI. You shall not. [Blinding Deirdre's eyes with his hand, he awaits Eogan, who rushes over the isthmus. Naisi receives a death-blow—his hand falls from Deirdre's eyes.] Beloved—no fear! And keep my smile! Beloved, A smile! A troth! [Deirdre kneels down by Naisi.] Ah, Conchobar, high King, those days, those days— [He dies before Eogan repeats the blow. Deirdre stretches her hand out to Eogan's sword.] EOGAN. No, I return you Fast bound where you belong. [He ties her hands together behind her back with his baldrick. She lifts her head and looks at him once.] DEIRDRE. I shall not live— Not without Naisi. [She stoops, presses her cheek against the body and breathes on it.] Cold!— So cold! And from thy mouth comes solitude. This is the loneliness. My sight is gone. [She swoons.] [Cathfach comes over the isthmus. Eogan stands above Deirdre with his drawn sword.] EOGAN. She is not dead. CATHFACH. Oh, then we may not touch her— I have called up the mighty Wave to whelm her, Cleena sped swift as breeze across the corn— The Wave ran swift, then dipped and crested high; It hid me from the host and from the hill; When it broke the host was scattered—her white raiment Was fluttering on the mound. The gods are nothing: Manhannan, the great Ocean-God, is nought! Something there is, an obstacle, a curse, A curse to be fulfilled. And those who are the first to reach the curse, And those who speak a little while before How it is surely wending on its way Are prophets, and their wailing prophecy. O fool, O sorrowful to love so sore! Emain, I have wrought ruin on thy children In my great energy to succour thee; Emain, the evil tarries— I but cursed; This is the curse. [He lifts Deirdre's head by the hair.] EOGAN. It was the king's command, At sight of, two, athwart the streaming ooze, Clasped in their love—“Dart over, stretch him dead.” CATHFACH. [With a cry.] Naisi! DEIRDRE. Unbind me! ... Cover me with stones From looking at them.... CATHFACH. Never Would I unbind you if I might unbind. But Conchobar Is here, and all his pleasure at his feet. [Conchobar advances.] DIERDRE. O Naisi, not thy lips—Naisi, thy wound! [She fastens her kiss on the wound. Cathfach shakes his hands in the wind and stands apart.] CONCHOBAR. [After a long silence.] Her hair—that bleeding And muddy woof! Cathfach, all here are dead? CATHFACH. She is not dead. CONCHOBAR. Then, Eogan, fetch a bier Of firwood planks ... The sun is coming up! Call Lebarcham. [Exit Eogan and three men.] She must be touched and sprinkled, Aroused—bend over her and lift her head, Cathfach. [The Druid turns sharply on the King, without touching Deirdre.] CATHFACH. Beneath her is a face you knew, And would not, if I bared it. CONCHOBAR. [Muttering to himself.] All is finished, Is past re-call, and never otherwise Can be but as it is.—For the gods' love, Touch her, arouse her, Cathfach. [Re-enter Eogan and men with trestles of charred wood.] Flames, the flood— Why then, the wreckage too! Remove the body. EOGAN. Her arms are bound, she cannot cling to it. CONCHOBAR. Go, lift her up. [Eogan separates Deirdre from Naisi's body. She stands as a statue. Conchobar gives a cry and holds out his raven cloak to Eogan.] EOGAN. The Cloak of Simon Magus! CONCHOBAR. Cover him With all the clouds! ... His bare, white face, The bare white of her face.... No woman, no! Nor child, nor girl—but the War-goddess gaping Red-wet where women smile. She gave no cry. Unbind her! [Eogan looses his baldrick.] [To Deirdre.] Both freed wrists For me, for me! [He takes possession, while Naisi on the bier is carried out.] Thou art raised, thy cheeks are red, Red as a bride's—thy starry eyes! O Deirdre, Speak to me, speak! Thy dumbness is my curse. Speak! ... Thou art striving ... I will let thee go Whither thou wilt, if thou wilt speak to me. Child, it is doom, this marriage ... Bleeding mouth— Wide rose, the autumn Dashes to scarlet rays.... [He draws back from her. Lebarcham enters.] There, Lebarcham! Your veil— [He seizes it and swathes Deirdre round in it.] You shall be hooded, child, and secret From all men's eyes, and secret from all shame, So you will speak.... [The colour fades from Deirdre. He covers her face with the veil and pushes her from him. She begins to walk along the way the bier went.] [To Lebarcham.] O woman, you said true, Not Eogan—she has lost her shape, her beauty. LEBARCHAM. But look at her, how she is drifting on, A corpse bound in the hollow of a wave, That travels on to ruin—see! She points the way to us—but why that way? CONCHOBAR. To sing him the lament—and she shall sing ... Then we shall hear her voice.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT V In the background the Palace of Emain, with fir-tree-tops enwoven above it, and over them the distant glowing of flame on the light of the air. In front the bowling-green, and, under a single bare fir-tree, a royal seat. To the right and left fir-trees, with a sudden break in the wood on the left. Conchobar sinks wearily on the seat. Across his brow there is the deep scar of a wound. Lebarcham is following him; Eogan stands behind the fir-stem. CONCHOBAR. I miss her, Lebarcham, I am missing her; I cannot bear her from my sight. I watch her as if I were watching the birds—the birds in summer-time when there is no song. Dierdre! LEBARCHAM. I will seek her presently. CONCHOBAR. Sometimes I hope, if I call very softly, That she will lift her head, I who have spoken hurriedly, in wrath, Or very sadly jesting, and she stirs not; Nor will she lift her head for any motion. She blooms, a flower beside me— Lebarcham, would she wither or grow old! ... Fairer she grows, more golden with desire; And sometimes when she wanders from the tomb A little smile has crept about her lips— I see it as a jewel that she wears, That is another's gift. Where is she now? Oh, answer not in words, but fetch her me. LEBARCHAM. Dear Master, if I take her from his tomb, She shrieks; I cannot. CONCHOBAR. I would hear her shriek. And if she wept. Does she weep, Lebarcham? [He rises to go out.] LEBARCHAM. [Intercepting him.] King, if you would not have her kill herself, You must not touch her there, nor take the path: There she must be alone. CONCHOBAR. Does she sing there? LEBARCHAM. Among the matted weeds, and roots of grass So stifled, the song rises from the earth, Like a young morning mist—it is not sound. CONCHOBAR. I ask you questions.... I have questioned you So often, when I should have learned myself. I am afraid.... If I could come to her, a bird, a falcon, That she could tame or handle! My approach Can never be in peace. She perishes. If I approach her. [Turning.] Lebarcham, persuade. [Lebarcham passes out, shaking her head and weeping.] [Sniffing the air.] How I rule! I am a tributary king now. Ulla is wrested from me, my Ulla, my land that is dearer than my breath! The curse should not fall on my land ... and my Cities are burning already, they are burning on the verge. But I am happy: I have never wandered from my doom. [Rising.] Cathfach! No, the Druid is not here; he is gone. [He gazes steadily at Eogan, standing where he looked for Cathfach.] Eogan, it is not my pleasure that to-day the great harper play to us. EOGAN. You would say it is not the queen's pleasure. CONCHOBAR. I wonder—it may that be that the sound of the harp would soothe the queen! EOGAN. It is not well that the queen should be soothed, she should be mastered.... King, would you yield her to me for a year, I would restore her to you, full of submission, knowing that she has her portion in the doom. We should have glory in Emain once more. There is no honour in the land where the women are silent. CONCHOBAR. Your harper shall play to us; it is my pleasure the queen shall listen and attend. [Enter Dierdre and Lebarcham.] Look, she is approaching with Lebarcham. She is a frail thing to master. These frail creatures! Eogan, there is spell upon her, she cannot speak to me. Bid your harper assuage her, bid him play softly; bid him sing of the fir-trees, for she grew up in their singing: bid him sing of the springtime that perishes, that she may weep and her tongue be loosed. EOGAN. [Scrutinizing Deirdre.] Lebarcham is trailing her as a prisoner. If I were her lord she would spring to my feet as a hound. You have not mastered a creature till you have set it free. I would so handle her—. CONCHOBAR. Peace, fetch your harper. Summon my men of the Red Branch; let there be a gathering of my people—those that remain. [Exit Eogan.] [Advancing towards Deirdre.] Deirdre, will you speak with me? Will you let me listen? LEBARCHAM. The queen would speak with you, my king; she craves to have speech with you. CONCHOBAR. [To Dierdre.] It is little to me what you utter, so I may hear your voice. Say what you will, as a rune, as a lay, O lips! DEIRDRE. High King—. CONCHOBAR. [Hurriedly.] I have a pleasure, I have a joy for thee, my queen. So long I have been seeking thee. There is a harper— You will listen to him, ay? He shall play all the tunes you bid him play. Tell me the tunes. [Taking her hands.] There is the tune Of the rock-doves, my Dierdre; and the tune Of the young elder-flowers— You sang that in the fortalice.... O Deirdre, Speak, for the voice is fading from your lips— ...... All is for you, That you may lift your head, and look at me. DEIRDRE. I can do nothing, nothing can I do, Except to die from you. I have a prayer— If you will hear my prayer, I will not die. [Drawing him slowly towards Naisi's tomb.] I will not die, I will flit up and down Among you: I will rise and fetch your shield; Flit up and down.... [Clasping his knees.] So you will bury me Breast-close beside my husband. CONCHOBAR. Ay—an oath! [Deirdre, in long breaths, as she divines Conchobar's meaning.] DEIRDRE. You purpose To creep into my grave; then I will live. And there are the famed harpers! [She points to the musicians and men of the Red Branch. Servants bring in rude benches, and the instruments, and rear up a little semi-circle about the throne.] CONCHOBAR. Child of Fedlimid, They shall sing all my woe and you shall listen. [Deirdre paces quietly beside him, giving him her hand.] DEIRDRE. My ears are open wide. You have the power. [Conchobar leads the Queen to the throne, and seats her there.] [He puts his own crown on her head, then he throws himself along the steps of the throne, and says to the harpers, without withdrawing his gaze from Deirdre.] Assuage the queen! [Eogan draws forth from the group the harper Ferechne, and whispers to him; the harper nods and begins singing the lay of “Cathal of the Woods.” 'Mid the forest and the forest-rocks, 'Mid the solitude where flowers are lonesome In their silent flocks, Cathal dwelt alone, yet in community: For such shapes as none may see, Who has not from all mortal kindred gone, Fairy-races of the leaf-green sap, Caught him to their quietness and their smiles, Drew him to the whortle-covert's lap, Or led through hovering miles Of the May-time leafage, crooned upon By the dove and murmured through by heaven. Low down many birds were singing clear; High above was the wood's rushing voice. Cathal lay, and tranquil to his bosom, Gliding with no fear, Came the leaf-green Princess of his choice. Close they breathed, and yet were wrapt away In their magic from all human day; Fresh their kisses fell, Cool with happiness, for happy things Freshen for their bliss, and may not dwell In the heat our carnal pleasure brings. Solemn rolled the breezes overhead, Dirge-like came the dove and nightingale Through the never-ending, solemn wail. Cathal could not hear the dole that spread Through the forest-ways; For like moss and briar He had now no life of fret or fire, Silent with the silent Fays, With the wind-flowers, with the sweet-fern shootlets, With the leaf-green presence of trees. [Deirdre has not listened; she has been looking out over the plain. Now she rises, with a motion of her hands towards Ferechne.] DEIRDRE. The harp! CONCHOBAR. Then she will sing to us her staves— Dierdre ... the sorrow is assuaged. O music! [Deirdre chaunts.] DEIRDRE. There is no tide in the river That keeps flood-tide, There are no weeds On the water-side; The water is all one web, At the flow and ebb. There is no tide in the river, Nor bank, nor shore; A stream there is, There was not before— And a stranger river Bubbles on for ever. The sweet waters! Sweet!—I am assuaged. [She remains quite still, her hands on the strings of the harp. Enter Cathfach.] CRIES. She is singing the great Wave Cleena. She will never forgive. She has the form of the great Wave; look at her! She is stronger than a wave; she has sung the deep, knotted flood. She will bring woe to us; let her be removed. Our king has called us to festivity: we are mocked. She has mocked the great harper. She has mocked our great harper; she is an evil spirit. CONCHOBAR. She shall be cast from us, my people. Deirdre—. DEIRDE. But I have sung my staves—so let me go! CONCHOBAR. Deirdre, tell me who is it that you hate most in all this company? Do you look round? DEIRDRE. I am looking for Eogan. It is Eogan I hate most in all the world. CONCHOBAR. Then you shall chaunt your hatred to him, you shall chaunt it. Fergna, my chariot!—I will set you in my chariot; you shall travel fast with your foe. You shall remain with him a year, you shall house with him. The chariot, quick! [Exit Fergna.] [To Cathfach.] Emain shall be delivered: There shall be no curse upon the land. O blessèd, there is a lightening of the air, And the boughs tremble as you break from Curse! [A chariot is brought in. Conchobar gives the reins to Eogan, then turns and lifts Deirdre to his side. He stands at a little distance, while Fergna mounts. As the wheels of the chariot begins to move, Deirdre, with a cry, stretches her arms towards Conchobar.] [He leaps behind her; the chariot disappears.] [Cathfach shields his eyes from the light and watches them silently.] LEBARCHAM. The end is come to us. O Druid Cathfach, An end that is an end. I shall not see her Again, and she has never looked behind. My Belovèd, when she started forth before, It was not in a car ... With bright-cheeked Naisi, Bright Flower of Erin— [Answering Cathfach's glance] Druid, I lament her, We, women, who choose happiness, choose tears, It is ever in the doom: and we choose parting, Quick death we chose, and the dew dashed from us— And sorrow for all faithful hearts for ever. I have fulfilled my darling's pleasure, prophet, But not fulfilled the curse. CATHFACH. Look forth! Look there! The fires are creeping nearer to the verge. That dusk upon the sky is of great armaments: Look forth! Have you the sight To watch the arming of the wind? The breezes Flock, as bright youths, and marshal to a band, Hostile and vehement, a scourge. LEBARCHAM. How little Is prophecy the hour it is fulfilled. It is the hour that covers everything, I shall never see her more, but of herself She knows the little secret way to death. If the king knew that way! [Wringing her hands] To have cast her off; Though I have heard the rune of all the winds Pass by on earth and leave behind them, never Had I conceived that moment Of the large chariot starting on its way. CATHFACH. The King will surely die, and of his curse. [Exit, with his face turned to the flames on the verge. Lebarcham sits down in the empty semi-circle: she starts suddenly, perceiving Fergna, who re-enters scared and breathless.] LEBARCHAM. Speak, Fergna! Are they dead? FERGNA. I scarce may say. The woman's shoulders panted on the rocks, And over her a struggle fiercely raged Of Conchobar with Eogan. LEBARCHAM. Fosterling, My Deirdre! Had they cast her from the car, That thus she lay on the sharp rocks of stone? FERGNA. None touched her. She had gazed on yonder mound, Setting her eyes on it, while car and horses Moved on, until the little crests at last Rose over it; then she awoke and swept One fierce glance over Eogan, set before, And slid one glance as fierce toward Conchobar, Behind her and more close! It was one hatred, The hatred of each glance. A shudder ran All through my body; and through all the air Ran laughter. LEBARCHAM. Hers?—her laughter? FERGNA. No, the king's. And then his words, the words of jest that followed! “Deirdre, the glance a ewe Would cast between two rams you cast on us, Eogan and me.” She started, and the horses. Started beneath my hand: I tightened rein, And the whole chariot shivered as she leapt Upon the rocks before her. Then those two Sprung to the place where she was dashed, their breath Whistled like winds: their crossing swords, with gnash Of hungry teeth, affrighted me, I fled, Leaving behind the chariot stopped by trees, Rock-rooted ... He returns— The king! He leads the horses of his car Slowly along. They come, but yet as night Comes by long twilight. LEBARCHAM. [Turning.] Lonely Conchobar! [Re-enter Conchobar solemnly leading the chariot.] O king.... CONCHOBAR. Your horses, Fergna! Take the reins. Lead them.... FERGNA. My lord, forgive me. I will lead them Back to their stable. LEBARCHAM. Deirdre? Where is Eogan? And Deirdre—where? CONCHOBAR. [With a hoarse laugh.] Ho, they have passed the borders, Passed from my realm. Nay, Fergna. Lead the great car, checking the horses' heads Beside yon barrow of a hero: there Unyoke them. Dig a neighbour sepulchre, And let the bases of each monument Touch where they spring. FERGNA. My lord ... and shall I seek Among the rocks? CONCHOBAR. You shall but lift its burthen Forth of the chariot to the hollowed grave. LEBARCHAM. O Dierdre! She is hidden by that cloak. O shattered loveliness of Erin, hidden From the ages, evermore! Thy Lebarcham Who saw thee come from hiding to our light, Will wend with thee along To thy last screening cover, to thy tomb. [Exit, following the chariot led by Fergna.] CONCHOBAR. The land! ... I wended hither: car and horses Are wending from me. Did I move like that, So solitary, dark above the grass?— But to no goal. In one of those near graves She will be with him, one of them will open; There can but be one tomb. The chariot lingers Its way in happy sloth: so wheat is carried Till night-fall to the barn.... [He remains watching in the silence.] The car Has turned the cromlech ... So wheat is carried. CURTAIN.</field>
   </doc>
</add>