<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Mitford, Mary Russell, 1787-1855</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Mitford, Mary Russell, 1787-1855</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">mitford mary russell 1787 1855</field>
      <field name="author_text">Mitford, Mary Russell, 1787-1855</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1820's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V3.0063.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1827</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460501</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Cunigunda's Vow</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Cunigunda's Vow</field>
      <field name="title_facet">cunigundas vow</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">cunigundas vow</field>
      <field name="title_text">Cunigunda's Vow</field>
      <field name="year_display">1827</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1827</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1827</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460501&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460501&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Mitford, Mary Russell, 1787-1855&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;mitford mary russell 1787 1855&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Cunigunda's Vow&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;cunigundas vow&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1827&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1827&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Mitford, Mary Russell&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1787&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1855&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Cunigunda's Vow&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Geo. B. Whittaker&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1827&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872841-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv30063&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Cunigunda's Vow&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 34 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Only verse drama included&lt;lb/&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;lb/&gt;Dedication included with Cunigunda's Vow&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Cunigunda's vow.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Drama.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1827.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Unknown.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CUNIGUNDA'S VOW. A DRAMATIC SCENE.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The story which forms the groundwork of the following short drama, will be found in Mr. Russell's delightful volumes on Germany; it has also given occasion to a very spirited ballad by Miss Landen, inserted, if I mistake not, in my friend Mr. Watts's Literary Souvenir for 1826.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">TO HER KIND AND EARLY FRIEND, WILLIAM CHAMBERLAYNE, ESQ. M.P. This Volume IS RESPECTFULLY INSCRIBED BY THE AUTHOR.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">CHARACTERS. Cunigunda, Lady of the Kienast. Sir Albert, a stranger Knight. Ernest, Cunigunda's aged Seneschal. Gertrude, Her waiting woman. Editha, Her waiting woman. Otto, her page. Squires, pages, grooms, and waiting women.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Scene, a hall in the Castle of the Kienast in Silesia.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Enter Ernest, to Gertrude and Editha. Ernest. Where is thy lady, Gertrude? Gertrude. On the turret Watching the first glimpse of the stranger knight Who comes to-day to attempt the perilous feat Ordained by her rash vow. Editha. Poor Cunigunda! Now pays she dearly the o'erweening pride Of haughty beauty. Love hath well avenged His martyred votaries. Ernest. Speak not with that tone Of pity, maiden! I'm an old retainer Of Cunigunda's house; have carried her A smiling child within mine arms; have loved her Even as a father, as a father gloried In her unparagoned charms. But her cold cruelty Doth fret my very heart-strings. Not enough For this proud beauty to reject all hearts Of knight, or count, or prince,—for princes sued At Cunigunda's feet—but she must tempt Each wooer to his death, grim ghastly death, Untimely bloody death, by that stern vow That he should win her, who should safely ride Around these Kienast walls,—the narrow walls, Of these steep mountain towers! She might as well Command them ride upon a falchion's edge, Or stand erect upon the topmost spray Of yon tall poplar. Many a gallant steed Lies whitening in the abyss, many a brave knight Hath perished in the rocky gulph;—and now Another victim comes! Editha. One—If he fall, The shades of all that for her sake have died, Were they as countless as the leaves that dance In Hirchsberg vale, would be avenged! She loves him, Believe it, Ernest, with the fervid love Of stern and haughty hearts. Ernest. Believe who will! She, thy proud mistress, love the falcon knight! Albert the falcon knight! A wandering stranger, Whose house, whose name she knows not. Tush! Editha. Yet Albert Is the sole name she speaks; the falcon crest Her only heraldry. Ernest. Princes have sighed For Cunigunda, and that she should sigh For this poor knight— Gertrude. She doth! Ernest. One all unapt To win a lady's eye! She that beheld Unmoved the gay Count Cassel, whose light step Came bounding like the roe, whose glance shot fire,— She that beheld unshaken his bright form Lie stiff and mute before her,—she that saw, Without a tear, the bleeding mangled corse Of Rudolf of Thuringia, blooming boy, Fair, slender, blue-eyed boy, whose nut-brown curls Clustered o'er his white brow, whose damask cheek, And coral lip, and brilliant smile, and round And joyous voice were redolent of youth, And hope, and life;—think'st thou that she, whom bloom And charms like these ne'er touched, can love yon sad And pallid stranger? Editha. With idolatry, Passing what hath been told or feigned of love In story or in song. Unapt to win A lady's eye! Ernest, thou hast been trained In courts, and camps, and battles; thou know'st well All that pertains to man, but woman's heart To thee is a sealed book. I tell thee, Ernest, Yon pallid stranger, with the serious grace Of his fine features, delicate yet full Of mild command; the dark locks closely shorn Around the noble head; the manly form Where grandeur blends with elegance; the voice Clear, deep, and ringing, fitting instrument Of lofty thought; the reverential port Majestically bending with a proud And prompt obedience, to the very name Of woman rendering homage;—such an one Might win— Gertrude. She comes! Enter Cunigunda and Otto. Cunigunda. Unbar the gates! Be quick, Unbar the gates! Why bide ye loitering here When ye should fly to bid the Castellan Give present entrance to the falcon knight— The valiant falcon knight? [Exit Ernest. Ye dally here, Whilst he stands waiting,—he! Why of themselves The Kienast gates should ope to him. Otto. He's here, Fair Madam. Enter Sir Albert and a Page. Cunigunda. Now, Sir Albert! Albert. Beauteous lady, I come to win thee.—Bid them lead my courser Round to the court of guard. Is't not the way That we must gain the ramparts? [Exit Page. Sweet, I come To win thee or to perish. Cunigunda. Oh, No! No! Albert. Why, thou shouldst arm me for this viewless peril As for some tourney fray. Why dost thou sigh? Why turn so deadly pale? Cunigunda. 'Tis a vast peril! Albert. 'Twas thine own vow imposed it; thine own choice; And now 'tis mine. I knew afore I saw thee What danger must be dared for Cunigunda, And knowing came. Thou wouldst not sure fright me With that same bugbear Peril? I'm a warrior Trained to defy, to seek each several form Of death in glorious battle. Wouldst thou teach me A cowardice now?—Farewell!—The sun shines bright On hill and valley; the soft breezes play O'er leaf and flower; over our heads the lark Chaunts his gay matins; Nature smiles on me And my high purpose;—for this deed is holy, Thrice holy, lady!—When I come again— Farewell! Cunigunda. Oh go not! go not! Albert. Cunigunda Hast thou not sworn to yield thy hand to none, Save him who rides unscathed around these steep And narrow walls? Is not that oath proclaimed On earth, and registered in heaven? Cunigunda. Alas! Albert. And I too have a vow recorded there To do this deed or perish. Cunigunda. Oh, go not! Not yet! not yet! Albert. Why should I dally? Cunigunda. Stay A month, a little month! Thou wilt not? Then A week, a day, an hour! Grant but such respite As the poor sentenced criminal may claim When he craves time for prayer.—Oh, go not yet! Not yet! not yet! Albert. Is this the soft relenting Of woman's tender heart to all whom pain Or danger threaten? Didst thou thus implore Henry of Cassel? or the gentle boy Young Rudolf of Thuringia? Cunigunda. No. Oh, frown not, Nor turn away thy head, nor snatch thy hand From mine! They knew the peril that they braved, And they would brave that peril. Canst thou blame me That I ne'er loved afore? that I love now? Oh, go not, Albert! Albert. Lady I am bound By a strong fettering vow.—If I return This hand is mine? Cunigunda. Ay, hand and heart. Yet go not! Beseech thee, stay with me! Albert. When I come back Thou art wholly mine? Cunigunda. Ay; ay. But go not yet! Albert. Mine to dispose even as I will? Cunigunda. Ay, dearest, Even as thou wilt. But stay with me awhile! Stay! stay! [Exit Albert. Editha. He's gone! Cunigunda. Oh, stop him! Say I beg! Say I command! Fly! fly! [Exit Otto. And yet my oath, My fatal, fatal oath! Without such trial We may not wed—But, oh, to see him dashed, As they have been, from off the wall and lain A pale disfigured corse—Oh horror! horror! Re-enter Otto. Stop him, I say; and if need be by force. Command him hither. Otto. Lady— Cunigunda. Dost thou hear? Where is the falcon knight? Am I not mistress Within these towers? Command him hither. Otto. Lady, Even as he left thee, at a bound he sprang On his proud steed, and scaled the rampart stairs; Ere now he's on the walls. Cunigunda. Oh save him! save him, Ye saints that watch o'er love! Go some of ye To the high turret that o'erhangs the Castle, And look ye send me blessed tidings—no! The truth! the very truth! Are ye not gone? [Exeunt Otto and Gertrude. Editha. Wilt thou not go thyself? 'Twere a less grief Than crouching there in that strong agony Of fear—thy head between thy hands, thy limbs Shivering, thy bosom panting. Go! Cunigunda. He'll die! He'll die! And how could I endure—He'll die For me! for me! Editha. Take comfort, lady. Cunigunda. Comfort! Who ever passed that dread abyss, where yawns The Hirschberg valley under the high rock Crowned with our frowning battlements, or dared The desperate leap from tower to tower, nor fell Crushed, breathless, motionless? Who e'er returned Alive?—Oh horror! horror! Edith, fly! Speed me some tidings. [Exit Editha. He must die; and I— I that so loved him, I that would have given My life a thousand fold to save him—I Shall be his murderess. Enter Ernest. Ernest. Nay, lady, nay, There's yet a hope. Cunigunda. Old man, art thou turned flatterer? He'll perish. Ernest. I beheld the manèged steed Ascend the steep and narrow stair; a steed Of Araby, light-limbed and fine, with eyes Of living fire half starting from his slim And veiny head; a hot and mettled steed; Yet trained to such obedience, that each motion Of the swift foot seemed guided by the will Of the bold rider, even as they had been One and incorporate. If man may atchieve This perilous deed, the falcon knight alone— Cunigunda. Ernest, thou shalt have lands enow to make Thyself a belted knight! Now blessings on thee That bring'st me hope!—But Edith, Gertrude, Otto, Why come they not? I could have won to Prague And back, in half the time. Why come they not? Good tidings find swift messengers. Alas! I fear; I fear. Ernest. Shall I go seek them? Cunigunda. No. The abyss, the dread abyss, where the old wall Shelving, and steep, and crumbling, overhangs The vale of Hirschberg from such dizzying height As never plummet fathomed;—that abyss— Henry of Cassel there, and the good knight Of Olmutz—Oh I have been cruel, Ernest, And for my sins he'll die! to punish me He'll die! he'll die! Enter Gertrude. Gertrude. Lady— Cunigunda. Why dost thou pause? Ernest. See how she pants! she's breathless. Cunigunda. Is there any Panting and breathless save myself? He's dead! I see it in her face. Gertrude. He hath safely passed The abyss. Cunigunda. Now thanks to Heaven! The dread abyss. He's safe! he's safe! Thou shalt be portioned, Gertrude. He's safe! Ernest. Yet that wide leap from tower to tower Where Rudolf of Thuringia— Cunigunda. Out on thee, Raven! Ernest. That fearful leap, with scarce a ledge Where steed— (Shouts without. Cunigunda. What means that cry? Re-enter Otto and Editha. Editha, Otto, What means that cry? Editha. He's safe! The leap is past; The falcon knight is safe! Ernest. Look to her! Cunigunda. Nay I'm well. Say o'er again! Editha. The leap is past. The falcon knight is safe. Cunigunda. My Editha, Ask what thou wilt of me. Was ever woman So blest before! The falcon knight is mine, Mine own, and I am his. Oh, thanks to Heaven! Now, ye that called my vow cruel and rash, What say ye now? Ernest. Alas, dear lady, still I grieve for them that— Cunigunda. Talk not of them. Think What were a thousand such as they, compared With the bold falcon knight!—Editha, Gertrude, Albert will come to claim his bride; wipe off These blistering tears, braid this dishevelled hair, Adjust my wimple and my veil;—my knight Will come to claim his bride. Enter Sir Albert and a Page. He comes! away! I was a fool to think of vanity; He will not love his Cunigunda less That she hath lain on the stone floor in prayer And tearful agony, whilst he hath dared This perilous deed.—Albert! Albert (to a page.) Lead Saladin Gently around the court. He trembles still At the o'ermastered danger. Cunigunda. Albert! Albert (still to the page.) Loosen The foaming bit. It is a matchless steed. Cunigunda. Oh matchless! matchless! I myself would be His groom. But Albert!— Albert. When he's cooler, bid Thy comrade, Jerome, ride him back to Prague. Bring thou another courser straight. The day Wears on. [Exit Page. Cunigunda. Sir Albert! Albert. Madam! Cunigunda. Hast thou not A word for Cunigunda? Dost thou stand There, like some breathing marble in thy cold Stern haughty beauty, mute and motionless, With arms close-folded and down-gazing eyes, No thought for Cunigunda, not a word For her whom thou hast won, not even a look? Dost thou not claim me, Albert? Albert. Lady, no; I have a wife—ay, start and tremble! turn As pale as winter snows! feel every pang That thou hast caused and scorned!—I have a wife, A sweet and gracious woman; beautiful Beyond all beauty, for the blush of love The smile of kindness, and the dancing light Of those joy-kindling eyes in whose bright play The innocent spirit revels, blend their spell With features delicate as lily bells, A shape more graceful than the clustering vine. Talk of thy stately charms! At Ida's side Thou would'st shew coarse and sunburnt, as the brown And rugged elm beside the shining beech.— Ay, shrink and tremble! hide thy burning cheeks Within thy quivering hands!—Wilt thou hear more?— This lovely loving wife, my three years' bride And twice a mother,—Oh none ever bent With such a grace as she o'er sleeping babes, Nor ever youthful mother bent o'er babes So like the Cherubim!—This wife, so fair, So sweet so womanly, whose pitying heart Would ache to see a sparrow die, this wife I love. Cunigunda. Why then—Oh cruel! Albert. Dar'st thou talk Of cruelty, proud murderess, whose meed For true-love hath been death? Whose sinful vow Slew the most gracious boy of all the earth, The hope and pride and joy of his high line Young Rudolf of Thuringia, my dear brother, My dear and only brother? Ernest. 'Tis Duke Albert! Yet pity her! See how she smites her brow, And tears her raven hair! Albert. Where was her pity When that fair boy—Murderess, 'tis Rudolf's brother That speaks to thee. When first I heard that tale, Several revenges, deadly, bloody, fierce, All that the body can endure of keen And lengthened agony, the rack, the wheel, The stake rushed through my brain, but they had been A poor and trivial vengeance, all unmeet For such o'erwhelming wrong; my cunning hate Hath found a more enduring curse. Thou lov'st me, Thou lov'st me, Cunigunda, with the hot Wild passion of thy nature, and I scorn thee! Thou art contemned and loathed by whom thou lov'st; Won and abandoned; spurned and thrown aside Like an infected garment. The plague spot Of sin is on thee, woman; blackest shame Shall follow like thy shadow. 'Twas for this I donned the mask of courtship; for this trained My faithful steed. Thy worthless hand is mine— Nay touch me not, hang not about my knees— Mine to bestow. Some horse-boy of my train Shall prove thy fitting partner. Editha. Oh for pity! For manly pity, good my lord, break not The bruised flower! Cunigunda. Be silent, Editha! I have deserved all evil. Deal with me Even as thou wilt, Duke Albert. I've deserved Thy hate—but soon my heart—my bursting heart— Deal with me as thou wilt. 'Twill not be long! Albert. Nay then—Rise, Cunigunda! Lift thy face From off the ground and listen. I'll not break The bruised flower. Live and repent. In prayer And pious penance live. The cloister cell Were thy meet refuge. By to-morrow's dawn Go join the Carmelites at Prague. For them Who died untimely, for thyself, for me And for my children, pray!—Now home, Sir Page! My steed! my steed! [Exeunt.</field>
   </doc>
</add>