<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Massinger, Philip, 1583-1640</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Massinger, Philip, 1583-1640</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">massinger philip 1583 1640</field>
      <field name="author_text">Massinger, Philip, 1583-1640</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">17th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V1.0144.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1632</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:458903</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Emperovr of the East ; A Tragae-Comoedie</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 17th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 17th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Emperovr of the East ; A Tragae-Comoedie</field>
      <field name="title_facet">emperovr of the east</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">emperovr of the east</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Emperovr of the East ; A Tragae-Comoedie</field>
      <field name="year_display">1632</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1632</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1632</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:458903&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:458903&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Massinger, Philip, 1583-1640&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;massinger philip 1583 1640&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Emperovr of the East ; A Tragae-Comoedie&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;emperovr of the east&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1632&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1632&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Massinger, Philip&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1583&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1640&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Emperovr of the East&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragae-Comoedie&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed by Thomas Harper, for Iohn Waterson&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1632&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3871558-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv10144&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 17th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;17th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Emperovr of the East&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragae-Comoedie&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 224 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: The emperour of the east.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragi-comedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1632.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 1631 ?&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE EMPEROVR OF THE EAST. A Tragæ-Comœdie.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Actors names. Thedosivs the younger. Paulinus, a Kinsman to the Emperour. Philanax, Captaine of the Guard. Timantus. Eunuch of the Emperours chamber. Chrysapius. Eunuch of the Emperours chamber. Gratianus. Eunuch of the Emperours chamber. Cleon, a trauailer, friend to Paulinus. Informer. Proiector. Master of the manners. Mignion of the suburbs. Countryman. Chirurgion. Emperick. Pulcheria, the protectresse. Athenais, a strange virgin, after the Empresse. Arcadia. a younger sister of the Emper. Flacilla. a younger sister of the Emper. Seruants. Mutes.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, AND MY especiall good Lord, Iohn Lord Mohvne, Baron of Okehampton, &amp;c.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">To my worthy Friend, Mr. Philip Massinger, vpon his Tragæ-Comœdie, call'd The Emperour of the East. Svffer, my friend, these lines to haue the grace, That they may bee a mole on Venus face. There is no fault about thy Booke, but this, And it will shew how faire thy Emperour is. Thou more then Poet, our Mercurie (that art Apollo's Messenger, and do'st impart His best expressions to our eares) liue long To purifie the slighted English tongue, That both the Nymphes of Tagus, and of Poe, May not henceforth despise our language so. Nor could they doe it, if they ere had seene The matchlesse features of the faerie Queene; Read Iohnson, Shakespeare, Beaumont, Fletcher, or Thy neat-limnd peeces, skilfull Massinger. Thou knowne, all the Castillians must confesse Vega de Carpio thy foile, and blesse His language can translate thee, and the fine Italian witts, yeeld to this worke of thine. Were old Pythagoras aliue againe, In thee hee might finde reason to maintaine His Paradox; that soules by transmigration In diuers bodies make their habitation, And more; that all Poetik soules yet knowne Are met in thee, vnited, and made one. This is a truth, not an applause. I am One that at farthest distance view thy flame, Yet may pronounce, that were Apollo dead, In thee his Poesie might all bee read. Forbeare thy modestie. Thy Emperours veine Shall liue admir'd, when Poets shall complaine. It is a patterne of too high a reach And what great Phœbus might the Muses teach. Let it liue therefore, and I dare bee bold To say, it with the world shall not grow old. Aston Cokaine:</field>
      <field name="fulltext">A friend to the Author, and well-wisher to the Reader. Who with a liberall hand, freely bestowes His bounty, on all commers, and yet knowes No ebbe, nor formall limits, but proceeds Continuing his hospitable deeds, With dayly welcome, shall aduance his name Beyond the art of flatterie: with such, fame May yours (deare friend) compare. Your muse hath bene Most bountifull, and I haue often seene The willing seates receaue such as haue fedd, And risen thankefull; yet were some mis-led By Nicetie, when this faire Banquet came (So I allude) their stomacks were to blame, Because that excellent sharpe, and poinant sauce Was wanting, they arose without due grace. Loe thus a second time hee doth inuite you: Bee your owne Caruers, and it may delight you. Iohn Clauell.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">To my true friend, and Kinsman: Philip Massinger. I take not vp on trust; nor am I lead By an implicit Faith: what I haue read With an impartiall censure I dare crowne With a deseru'd applause, how ere cri'd downe By such whose malice will not let 'em bee Equall to any peece limnd forth by thee. Contemne their poore detraction, and still write Poems like this, that can indure the light, And search of abler iudgements. This will raise Thy Name, the others Scandall is thy praise. This oft perus'd by graue witts, shall liue long, Not dye as soone, as pass'd the Actors tongue, (The fate of slighter toyes) And I must say 'Tis not enough to make a passing play, In a true Poet. Workes that should indure Must haue a Genius in em strong, as pure. And such is thine friend; nor shall time deuoure The well form'd features of thy Emperour. William Singleton.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Prologue at the Blackfriers. But that imperious custome warrants it, Our Author with much willingnes would omit This Preface to his new worke. Hee hath found (And suffer'd for't) many are apt to wound His credit in this kind: and whether hee, Expresse himselfe fearefull, or peremptorie, Hee cannot scape their censures who delight To misapplie what euer hee shall write. Tis his hard fate. And though hee will not sue, Or basely beg such suffrages, yet to you Free, and ingenious spirits, hee doth now, In mee present his seruice, with his vow Hee hath done his best, and though hee cannot glorie In his inuention, (this worke being a storie, Of reuerend Antiquitie) hee doth hope In the proportion of it, and the scope, You may obserue some peeces drawne like one Of a stedfast hand, and with the whiter stone To bee mark'd in your faire censures. More then this I am forbid to promise, and it is With the most 'till you confirme it: since wee know What ere the shaft bee, Archer, or the bow, From which 'tis sent, it cannot hit the white Vnlesse your approbation guide it right.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Prologue at Court. As euer (Sir) you lent a gratious eare To oppress'd innocence, now vouchsafe to heare A short petition. At your feete in mee The Poet kneeles, and to your Maiestie Appeales for iustice. What wee new present, When first conceiu'd, in his vote and intent, Was sacred to your pleasure; in each part With his best of fancie, iudgment, language, art, Fashiond, and form'd so, as might well, and may Deserue a wellcome, and no vulgar way. Hee durst not (Sir) at such a solemne feast Lard his graue matter with one scurrilous ieast, But labour'd that no passage might appeare, But what the Queene without a blush might heare. And yet this poore worke suffer'd by the rage, And enuie of some Catos of the stage: Yet still hee hopes, this Play which then was seene With sore eyes, and condemn'd out of their spleen, May bee by you, The supreme iudge, set free, And rais'd aboue the reach of calumnie.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Act 1. The Scæne Constantinople. Scæne 1. Paulinus. Cleon. Paul. In your six yeeres trauaile, friend, no doubt you haue met with Many, and rare aduentures, and obseru'd The wonders of each climate, varying in The manners, and the men, and so returne, For the future seruice of your prince and country, In your vnderstanding betterd. Cleon. Sir, I haue made oft The best vse in my power, and hope my gleanings, After the full crop others reapd before me, Shall not when I am call'd on, altogether Appeare vnprofitable: yet I left The miracle of miracles in our age At home behind me; euery where abroad Fame with a true, though prodigall voyce, deliuer'd Such wonders of Pulcheria the Princesse, To the amazement, nay astonishment rather Of such as heard it, that I found not one In all the States and Kingdomes that I pass'd through, Worthy to be her second. Paul. She indeed is A perfect Phœnix, and disdaynes a riuall. Her infant yeeres, as you know, promis'd much But growne to ripenesse shee transcendes, and makes Credulitie her debtor. I will tell you In my blunt way, to entertaine the time, Vntill you haue the happinesse to see her, How in your absence shee hath borne her selfe, And with all possible breuitie, though the subiect Is such a spatious field, as would require An abstract of the purest eloquence (Deriu'de from the most famous Orators The nurse of learning, Athens, shew'd the world) In that man, that should vndertake to bee Her true Historian. Cleon. In this you shall doe mee A speciall sauour. Paulinus. Since Arcadius death, Our late great Master, the protection of The Prince his Sonne, the second Theodosius, By a generall vote and suffrage of the people; Was to her charge assigned, with the disposure Of his so many Kingdomes. For his person Shee hath so train'd him vp in all those arts That are both great and good, and to be wished In an Imperiall Monarch, that the Mother Of the Gracchi, graue Cornelia (Rome still boasts of) The wise Pulcheria but nam'd, must be No more remembred. She by her example Hath made the court a kinde of Academy, In which true honour is both learnd, and practisd, Her priuate lodging's a chaste Nunnery, In which her sisters as probationers heare From her their soueraigne Abbesse, all the precepts Read in the schoole of vertue. Cleon. You amaze me. Paulinus. I shall ere I conclude. For heere the wonder Begins, not ends. Her soule is so immense, And her strong faculties so apprehensiue, To search into the depth of deepe designes, And of all natures, that the burthen which To many men were insupportable, To her is but a gentle exercise, Made by the frequent vse familiar to her: Cleon. With your good fauour let me interrupt you. Being as she is in euery part so perfect, Me thinkes that all kings of our Easterne world Should become riualls for her. Paulinus. So they haue, But to no purpose. She that knowes her strength To rule, and gouerne Monarchs, scornes to weare On her free necke the seruile yoke of marriage. And for one loose desire, enuie it selfe Dares not presume to taint her. Venus sonne Is blinde indeed, when he but gazes on her. Her chastity being a rocke of Diamonds, With which encountred his shafts flie in splinters, His flaming torches in the liuing spring Of her perfections, quench'd: and to crowne all; Shee's so impartiall when she sits vpon The high tribunall, neither swayd with piety, Nor awd by feare beyond her equall scale, That 'tis not superstition to beleeue Astrea once more liues vpon the earth, Pulcheriaes brest her temple. Cleon. You haue giuen her An admirable character. Paulinus. She deserues it, And such is the commanding power of vertue, That from her vitious enemies it compells Pæans of prayse as a due tribute to her. Solemne lowd musick: Cleon. What meanes this solemne musicke? Paulinus. It vshers The Emperours morning meditation, In which Pulcheria is more then assistant. Tis worth your obseruation, and you may Collect from her expence of time this day, How her howres for many yeeres haue beene dispos'd of. Cleon. I am all eyes and eares. Enter after a strayne of musicke, Philanax, Timantus, Patriarch, Theodosius, Pulcheria, Flaccilla, Arcadia, followed by Chrysapius and Gratianus, Informer, Seruants, Officers. Pulcheria, Your patience Sir. Let those corrupted ministers of the court, Which you complayne of, our deuotions ended, Be cited to appeare. For the Embassadours Who are importunate to haue audience, From me you may assure them, that to morrow They shall in publike kisse the Emperours robe, And we in priuate with our soonest leasure Will giue 'em hearing. Haue you especiall care too That free accesse be granted vnto all Petitioners. The morning weares. Pray you on Sir; Time lost is ne're recouerd. Exeunt Theodosius, Pulcheria, and the trayne. Paulinus. Did you note The maiesty she appeares in? Cleon. Yes my good Lord, I was rauish'd with it. Paulinus. And then with what speede Shee orders her dispatches, not one daring To interpose; the Emperour himselfe Without replie putting in act what euer Shee pleas'd to impose vpon him. Cleon. Yet there were some That in their sullen lookes rather confessed A forc'd constraint to serue her, then a will To bee at her deuotion, what are they? Paulin. Eunuchs of the Emperours chamber, that repine, The globe and awfull scepter should giue place Vnto the distaffe, for as such they whisper A womans gouernment, but dare not yet Expresse themselues. Cleon. From whence are the Embassadours To whom she promisde audience? Paulinus. They are Imployd by diuers Princes, who desire Alliance with our Emperour, whose yeeres now As you see, write him man. One would aduance A daughter to the honour of his bed, A second, his fayre sister: to instruct you In the particulars would aske longer time Then my owne designes giue way to. I haue letters From speciall friends of mine, that to my care Commend a stranger virgin, whom this morning I purpose to present before the Princesse, If you please, you may accompany me. Cleon. Ile wait on you. Exeunt. Scene 2. Informer, Officers bringing in the Proiector, the Suburbs Mignion, the Master of the habit and maners. Informer. Why should you droope, or hang your working heads? No danger is meant to you, pray beare vp, For ought I know you are cited to receiue Preferment due to your merits. Proiector. Very likely, In all the proiects I haue read and practisd I neuer found one man compeld to come Before the seat of iustice vnder guarde To receiue honour. Informer. No; it may be you are The first example. Men of qualities, As I haue deliuer'd you to the protectresse, Who knows how to aduance them, cannot conceiue A fitter place to haue their vertues publish'de, Then in open Court: could you hope that the Princesse Knowing your pretious merits, will reward 'em In a priuate corner? no, you know not yet How you may be exalted. Suburbs Minion. To the gallowes. Informer. Fy, Nor yet depressde to the Gallies; in your names You carry no such crimes: your specious titles Cannot but take her: President of the Proiectors! What a noyse it makes? The master of the habit, How proud would some one country be that I know To be your first pupill? Minion of the suburbs, And now and then admitted to the Court, And honor'd with the stile of Squire of Dames, What hurt is in it? One thing I must tell you, As I am the State scout, you may think me an informer. Master of the habit. They are Synonima. Informer. Conceale nothing from her Of your good parts, 'twill be the better for you, Or if you should, it matters not, she can coniure, And I am her vbiquitary spirit, Bound to obey her, you haue my instructions, Stand by, heeres better company. Enter Paulinus, Cleon, Athenais, with a Petition. Athenais. Can I hope, Sir, Oppressed innocence shall finde protection, And iustice among strangers, when my brothers, Brothers of one wombe, by one Sire begotten, Trample on my afflictions? Paulinus. Forget them, Remembering those may helpe you. Athenais. They haue robde mee Of all meanes to prefer my iust complaint With any promising hope to gaine a hearing, Much lesse redresse: petitions not sweetened With golde, are but vnsauorie, oft refused, Or if receau'd, are pocketted, not read. A suitors swelling teares by the glowing beames Of Cholerick authority are dri'd vp, Before they fall, or if seene neuer pittled, What will become of a forsaken maide? My flattering hopes are too weake to encounter With my stronge enemy, despaire, and 'tis In vaine to oppose her. Cleon. Cheere her vp, shee saints, Sir. Paulin. This argues weakenesse, thogh your brothers were Cruell beyond expression, and the iudges That sentenc'd you, corrupt, you shall finde heere One of your owne faine sexe to doe you right, Whose beames of iustice like the Sun extend Their light, and heate to strangers, and are not Municipall, or confinde. Athenais. Pray you doe not feede mee With aerie hopes, vnlesse you can assure mee The greate Pulcheria will descende to heare My miserable storie, it were better I died without her trouble. Paulinus. Shee is bound to it By the surest chaine, her naturall inclination To helpe th'afflicted, nor shall long delayes (More terrible to miserable suitors Then quicke denialls) grieue you; Drie your faire eyes, This roome will instantly bee sanctifi'd With her bless'd presence; to her ready hand Present your grieuances, and rest assur'd You shall depart contented. Athenais. You breath in mee A second life. Informer. Will your Lordship please to heare Your seruant a few words? Paulinus. Away you rascall, Did I euer keepe such seruants? Informer. If your honestie Would giue you leaue, it would bee for your profit. Paul. To make vse of an Informer? tell mee in what Can you aduantage mee? Informer. In the first tender Of a fresh suite neuer begd yet, Paulinus. Whats your suite Sir? Informer. 'Tis feasible, heere are three arrant knaues Discouerd by my Art: Paulinus. And thou the arch knaue, The greate deuoure the lesse: Informer. And with good reason, I must eate one a month, I cannot liue els. Paulinus. A notable canniball? but should I heare thee, In what doe your knaues concerne mee? Informer. In the begging Of their estates. Paulinus. Before they are condemned? Inf. Yes or arraigned, your Lordship may speake too late els. They are your owne, and I will bee content With the fift part of a share. Paulinus. Hence Rogue, Informer. Such Rogues In this kinde will be heard, and cherish'd too. Foole that I was to offer such a bargaine, To a spic'd conscience chapman, but I care not What hee disdaines to taste others will swallow. Lowde Mus. Enter Theodosius, Pulcheria, and the traine. Cleon. They are returned from the Temple. Paul. See, shee appeares, What thinke you now? Athenais. A cunning Painter thus Her vaile tane off and awfull sword and ballance Lay'd by woulde picture iustice. Pulcheria. When you please, You may intend those royall exercises Suiting your birth, and greatenesse: I will beare The burthen of your cares, and hauing purged The body of your empire of ill humors, Vpon my knees surrender it. Chrysapius. Will you euer Bee awde thus like a Boy? Gratianus. And kisse the rod Of a proude Mistrisse? Timantus. Bee what you were borne Sir. Philanax. Obedience and Maiestie neuer lodg'd In the same Inne. Theodosius. No more; hee neuer learned The right way to command, that stopp'd his eares To wise directions. Pulcheria. Reade ore the Papers I left vpon my cabinet, two hours hence I will examine you. Flaccilla. Wee spende our time well. Nothing but praying, and poring on a booke, It ill agrees with my constitution, sister. Arcadia. Would I had beene borne some masquing Ladies woman, Only to see strange sights, rather then liue thus. Flaccilla. We are gone forsooth, there is no remedy, sister: Exeunt Arcadia and Flaccilla. Gratianus. What hath his eye found out? Timantus. 'Tis fix'd vpon That stranger Lady. Chrysapius. I am glad yet, that Hee dares looke on a Woman. All this time the informer kneeling to Pulcheria, and deliuering papers. Theodos. Philanax, What is that comely stranger? Philanax. A Petitioner. Chrys. Will you heare her case, and dispatch her in your Chamber? Ile vndertake to bring her. Theod. Bring mee to Some place where I may looke on her demeaner 'Tis a louely creature? Exeunt Theodosius, Patriarck and the trayne. Chrys. Ther's some hope in this yet. Pulch. No you haue done your parts: Paul. Now opportunity courts you, Prefer your suite, Athenais. As low as miserie Can fall, for proofe of my humilitie, A poore distressed Virgin bowes her head, And layes hold on your goodnesse, the last altar Calamitie can flie to for protection. Great mindes erect their neuer falling trophees On the firme base of mercie; but to triumphe Ouer a suppliant by proud fortune captiued, Argues a Bastard conquest: 'tis to you I speake, to you the faire, and iust Pulcheria, The wonder of the age, your sexes honor, And as such daine to heare mee. As you haue A soule moulded from heauen, and doe desire To haue it made a star there, make the meanes Of your ascent to that celestiall height Vertue wing'd with braue action: they draw neer The nature, and the essence of the Gods, Who imitate their goodnesse. Fulcher. If you were A subiect of the Empire, which your habit In euery part denies. Athenais. O flie not to Such an euasion; what ere I am, Being a Woman, in humanitie You are bound to right mee, though the difference) Of my religion may seeme to exclude mee From your defence (which you would haue confinde) The morall vertue, which is generall, Must know no limits; by these blessed feete That pace the paths of equity, and tread boldly On the stiffe necke of tyrannous oppression, By these teares by which I bath 'em, I coniure you With pitty to looke on mee. Pulch. Pray your rise. And as you rise receiue this comfort from mee. Beauty set off with such sweete language neuer Can want an Aduocate, and you must bring More then a guiltie cause if you preuaile not. Some businesse long since thought vpon dispatched, You shall haue hearing, and as far as iustice Will warrant mee, my best aydes. Athen. I doe desire, No stronger garde, my equitie needs no fauour. Pulch. Are these the men? Proiector. Wee were, an't like your highnesse, The men, the men of eminence, and marke, And may continue so, if it please your grace. Master. This speech was well proiected. Pul. Does your conscience (I will begin with you) whisper vnto you What heere you stand accused of? are you named The President of Proiectors? Inform. Iustifie it man, And tell her in what thou art vsefull. Proiect. That is apparent, And if you please, aske some about the court, And they will tell you too my rare inuentions, They owe their brauerie, perhaps meanes to purchase, And cannot liue without mee. I alas Lende out my labouring braines to vse, and sometimes For a drachma in the pound, the more the pitty. I am all patience, and indure the curses Of many, for the profit of one patron. Pulcher. I do conceiue the rest. What is the second? Informer. The mignion of the suburbs. Pulcheria. What hath he To doe in Constantinople? Mign. I steale in now and then, As I am thought vsefull, marry there I am calde The Squire of Dames, or seruant of the sex, And by the allowance of some sportfull Ladies Honor'd with that title. Pulch. Spare your Character, You are heere desciphered; stand by with your compere. What is the third? a creature I ne're heard of; The master of the manners, and the habit, You haue a double office. Master. In my actions I make both good, for by my theoremes Which your polite, and terser gallants practise, I rerefine the court, and ciuilize Their barbarous natures: I haue in a table With curious punctualitie set downe To a haires breadth, how low a new stamp'd courtier May vaile to a country Gentleman, and by Gradation, to his marchant, mercer, draper, His linnen man, and taylor. Pulch. Pray you discouer This hidden mysterie. Master. If the foresayde courtier (As it may chance somtimes) find not his name Writ in the Citizens bookes, with a State hum He may salute 'em after three dayes wayting: But if he owe them money, that he may Preserue his credit, let him, in policy, neuer Appoint a day of payment, so they may hope still: But if he be to take vp more, his page May attend 'em at the gate, and vsher 'em Into his Cellar, and when they are warm'd with wine, Conduct 'em to his bedchamber, and though then He be vnder his Barbers hands, assoone as seene, He must start vp to embrace 'em, vayle thus low, Nay though he call'tm cosins, 'tis the better, His Dignity no way wrong'd in't. Paulinus. Here's a fire knaue. Pulch. Does this rule hold without exception sirrha For Courtiers in generall? Mast. No, deare madam, For one of the last edition, and for him I haue composde a Dictionary, in which He is instructed, how, when, and to whom To be proud or humble; at what times of the yeare He may do a good deed for it selfe, and that is Writ in Dominicall letters, all dayes else Are his owne, and of those dayes the seuerall houres Markt out, and to what vse. Pulch. Shew vs your method, I am strangely taken with it. Mast. Twill deserue A pension, I hope. First a strong cullise In his bed to heighten appetite: Shuttle-cock To keepe him in breath when he rises; Tennis Courts Are chargeable, and the riding of great horses Too boystrous for my yong Courtier, let the old ones I thinke not of, vse it; next his meditation How to court his Mistresse, and that he may seeme witty, Let him be furnish'd with confederate iests Between him and his friend, that on occasion They may vent em mutually: what his pace, and garbe Must be in the presence, then the length of his sword, The fashion of the hilt, what the blade is It matters not, 'twere barbarisme to vse it, Vnlesse to shew his strength vpon an andiron, So the sooner broke, the better. Pulch. How I abuse This pretious time! Proiector, I treat first Of you and your disciples; you roare out, All is the Kings, his will aboue his lawes: And that fit tributes are too gentle yokes For his poore subiects; whispering in his eare, If he would haue them feare, no man should dare To bring a sallad from his country garden, Without the paying gubell; kill a hen, Without excise: and that if he desire To haue his children, or his seruants weare Their heads vpon their shoulders, you affirme, In policy, tis fit the owner should Pay for'em by the pole; or if the Prince want A present summe, he may command a city Impossibilities, and for non-performance Compell it to submit to any fine His Officers shall impose: is this the way To make our Emperor happy? can the groanes Of his subiects yeeld him musick? must his thresholds Be wash'd with widdowes and wrong'd orphans teares, Or his power grow contemptible? Proiect. I begin To feele my selfe a rogue againe. Pulch. But you are The Squire of Dames, deuoted to the seruice Of gamesome Ladies, the hidden mystery Discouer'd, their close bawde; thy slauish breath Fanning the fires of lust, the Goe-between This female, and that wanton Sir, your art Can blinde a iealous husband, and disguisde Like a Millainer or Shoomaker, conuey A letter in a pantophle or gloue Without suspition, nay at his table In a case of picketo othes; you instruct 'em how To parley with their eyes, and make the temple A mart of loosenesse: to discouer all The subtile brokages, were to teach in publick, Those priuate practises which are, in iustice, Seuerely to bee punish'd. Mignion. I am cast, A iurie of my patronesses cannot quit mee. Pulcheria. You are master of the manners, and the habit, Rather the scorne of such as would liue men, And not like Apes with seruile imitation, Studie prodigious fashions. You keepe Intelligence abroad that may instruct, Our giddie youth at home what new found fashion Is now in vse, swearing hees most compleate That first turnes monster. Know villaines, I can thrust This arme into your hearts, strip off the flesh That couers your deformities, and shew you In your owne nakednesse. Now though the law Call not your follies death, you are for euer Banish'd my brothers court. Away with 'em. I will heare no reply. Exeunt Informer, Officers, Prisoners, the curtaines drawne aboue, Eunuches discouer'd. Paulinus. What thincke you now? Cleon. That I am in a dreame, or that I see A seconde Pallas. Pulch. These remou'd, to you I cleare my browe, speake without care sweete mayde, Since with a milde aspect and ready eare, I sit prepar'd to heare you. Athen. Know great Princesse, My father though a Pagan, was admir'd For his deepe serch into those hidden studies, Whose knowledge is deni'd to common men: The motion, with the diuers operations Of the superior bodies, by his long And carefull obseruation were made Familiar to him, all the secret virtues Of plants, and simples, and in what degree They were vsefull to mankinde, hee could discourse of. In a word conceiue him as a Prophet honourd In his owne countrie. But being borne a man, It lay not in him to defer the hower Of his approching death, though long foretold: In this so fatall hower hee call'd before him His two sonnes, and my selfe, the deerest pledges Lent him by nature, and with his right hand Blessing our seuerall heades, hee thus began; Chrys. Marke his attention. Phyl. Giue mee leaue to marke too. Athen. If I could leaue my vnderstanding to you, It were superfluous to make diuision Of whatsoeuer els I can bequeath you, But to auoide contention, I allot An equall portion of my possessions To you my sonnes: but vnto thee my daughter, My ioy, my darling (pardon mee though I Repeate his words) if my prophetick soule Ready to take her flight, can truely ghesse at Thy future fate, I leaue the strange assurance Of the greatenesse thou art borne to, vnto which Thy brothers shall be proud to pay their seruice, Paulinus. And all men els that honour beauty Theod. Nimph. Ath. Yet to prepare thee for that certaine fortune, And that I may from present wants defend thee, I leaue ten thousand crownes, which sayd, being call'd To the fellowship of our Deities, he expird, And with him all remembrance of the charge Concerning me, left by him to my brothers. Pulch. Did they deteyne your legacy? Athenais. And still do. His ashes were scarce quiet in his vrne, When in derision of my future greatnesse, They thrust me out of doores, denying me One short nights harbor. Pulch. Weepe not. Ath. I desire By your perswasion, or commanding power, The restitution of mine owne, or that To keepe my frailty from temptation, In your compassion of me, you would please I as a handmaid may be entertaind To do the meanest offices to all such As are honor'd in your seruice. Pulch. Thou art welcome. What is thy name? Ath. The forlorne Athenais. Takes her vp and kisses her. Pulch. The sweetnes of thy innocence strangely takes me Forget thy brothers wrongs, for I will be In my care a mother, in my loue a sister to thee; And were it possible thou could'st be wooned To be of our beleefe. Paulinus. May it please your excellence, That is an easie taske, I, though no schollar, Dare vndertake it; cleere truth cannot want Rhetoricall perswasions. Pulch. Tis a work, My Lord, will well become you; break vp the Court, May your endeuors prosper. Paulinus. Come my faire one, I hope my conuert. Ath. Neuer, I will die As I was borne. Paulinus. Better you nere had beene. Philanax. What does your maiesty think of? the maid's gone. Theod. She's wondrous faire, and in her speech appear'd Peeces of schollarship. Chrysap. Make vse of her learning And beauty together, on my life she will be proud To be so conuerted. Theod: From foule lust heauen guard me. Exeunt:</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Act. 2. Scæne 1. Philanax, Timantus, Chrysapius, Gratianus. Philanax. We only talk when we should do. Timantus: Ile second you, Begin, and when you please. Gratianus. Be constant in it. Chry. That resolution which growes cold to day, Will freeze to morrow. Gratianus. 'Slight, I think sheele keepe him Her ward for euer, to her selfe ingrossing The disposition of all the fauors And bounties of the Empire. Chrys. Wee that by The neerenesse of our seruice to his person, Should raise this man, or pull downe that, without Her licence hardly dare prefer a suit, Or if wee doe, 'tis cross'd. Philanax. You are troubled for Your proper ends, my aimes are high and honest The wrong that's done to Maiesty I repine at: I loue the Emperor, and 'tis my ambition To haue him know himselfe, and to that purpose Ile run the hazard of a check. Gratianus: And I The losse of my place: Timan. I will not come behinde, Fall what can fall. Chry. Let vs put on sad aspects To draw him on; charge home, weele fetch you off, Or ly dead by you. Enter Theodosius. Theod. How's this? clouds in the chamber, And the ayre cleere abroad. Phil. When you our Sunne Obscure your glorious beames, poore we that borrow Our little light from you, cannot but suffer A generall Eclipse. Timantus. Great Sir, 'tis true, For 'till you please to know, and be your selfe, And freely dare dispose of what's your owne Without a warrant; we are falling meteors; And not fixed starres. Chrys. The pale fac'd Moon that should Gouerne the night, vsurps the rule of day, And still is at the full in spite of nature, And will not know a change. Theod. Speak you in riddles? I am no Oedipus, but your Emperor, And as such would be instructed. Philanax. Your command Shall be obeyd, till now I neuer heard you Speak like your selfe; and may that power by which You are so, strike me dead, if what I shall Deliuer, as a faithfull subiect to you, Hath root, or growth from malice, or base enuy Of your Sisters greatnesse; I could honor in her A power subordinate to yours, but not As 'tis predominant. Timan. It it fit that she, In her birth your vassall, should command the knees Of such as should not bow but to your selfe? Grat. Shee with security walkes vpon the heads Of the nobility, the multitude As to a Deitie offring sacrifice, For her grace, and fauour. Chrys. Her proude feete euen wearied With the kisses of petitioners. Gratian, While you, To whom alone such reuerence is proper, Passe vnregarded by her, Timant. You haue not yet Bene Master of one houre of your whole life, Chrys. Your will and faculties kept in more awe, Then shee can doe her owne Philanax. And as a bondman, O let my zeale finde grace, and pardon from you, That I descende so low, you are designed To this or that imployment, suiting well A priuate man I grant, but not a Prince, To bee a perfit horseman, or to know The words of the chace, or a faire man of armes, Or to bee able to pierce to the depth, Or write a comment on th'obscurest Poets, I grant are ornaments, but your maine scope Should bee to gouerne men to guarde your owne, If not enlarge your empire. Chrys. You are built vp By the curious hand of nature to reuiue The memorie of Alexander, or by A prosperous successe in your braue actions To riuall Cæsar. Timant. Rouze your selfe, and let not Your pleasure bee a copye of her will Philan. Your pupill age is pass'd, and manly actions Are now expected from you. Grat. Doe not loose Your subiects heartes, Timant. What is't to haue the meanes To bee magnificent, and not exercise The boundlesse vertue? Grat. You confine your selfe To that which strict Philosophie allowes of, As if you were a priuate man. Tim. No pompe, Or glorious showes of royaltie, rendring it Both lou'd, and terrible. Grat. 'Slight you liue, as it Begets some doubt, whether you haue or not Th'abilities of a man. Chrys. The Firmament Hath not more starres then there are seuerall beauties Ambitious at the height to impart their deare, And sweetest fauours to you. Grat. Yet you haue not Made choice of one, of all the sex, to serue you, In a Physicall way of courtshippe. Theod. But that I would not Beginne the expression of my being a man, In blood, or staine the first white robe I weare Of absolute power, with a seruile imitation Of any tyrannous habit, my iust anger Prompts mee to make you in your suffrings feele, And not in words to instruct you, that the licence Of the loose, and saucie language you now practised, Hath forfeited your heades. Grut. How's this? Phil. I know not What the play may proue, but I assure you that I doe not like the prologue. Theod. O the miserable Condition of a Prince! who though hee varie More shapes then Proteus in his minde, and manners, Hee cannot winne an vniuersall suffrage, From the many-headed monster, Multitude. Like Æsops folish Frogges they trample on him, As a senselesse blocke, if his gouernement bee easie. And if hee proue a Storke, they croke, and rayle Against him as a tyranne. Ile put off That maiestie, of which you thinke I haue Nor vse, nor feeling, and in arguing with you, Conuince you with strong proofes of common reason, And not with absolute power, against which, wretches, You are not to dispute. Dare you that are My creatures, by my prodigall fauours fashion'd, Presuming on the neerenesse of your seruice, Set off with my familiar acceptance, Condemne my obsequiousnesse to the wise directions Of an incomparable Sister, whom all parts Of our world, that are made happy in knowledge Of her perfections, with wonder gaze on? And yet you that were only borne to eate The blessings of our mother earth, that are Distant but one degree from beasts (since slaues Can claime no larger priuiledge) that know No farther then your sensuall appetites, Or wanton lust haue taught you, vndertake To giue your soueraigne lawes to follow that Your ignorance markes out to him? Walkes by. Gratian. How were wee Abus'd in our opinion of his temper? Phil. Wee had forgot 'tis found in holy writ, That Kings hearts are inscrutable. Timantus. I ne're reade it, My studie lies not that way. Philan. By his lookes The tempest still increases. Theod. Am I growne So stupid in your iudgments, that you dare With such security offer violence To sacred maiestie? will you not know The Lyon is a Lyon, though he show not His rending pawes? or fill th'affrighted ayre With the thunder of his rorings? you bless'd Saints, How am I trenched on? is that temperance So famous in your cited Alexander, Or Roman Scipio a crime in mee? Cannot I bee an Emperour, vnlesse Your wiues, and daughters bow to my proud lusts? And cause I rauish not their fairest buildings And fruitfull vineyards, or what is dearest, From such as are my vassalls, must you conclude I doe not know the awfull power, and strength Of my prerogatiue? am I close handed Because I scatter not among you that I must not call mine owne. Know you court leeches, A Prince is neuer so magnificent, As when hee's sparing to inrich a few With th'iniuries of many; could your hopes So grossely flatter you, as to beleeue I was born and traind vp as an Emperour, only In my indulgence to giue sanctuarie, In their vniust proceedings, to the rapine And auarice of my groomes? Philar. In the true mirror Of your perfections, at length wee see Our owne deformities. Timant. And not once daring To look vpon that maiestie wee now sleighted, Chrys. With our faces thus glewd to the earth, wee beg Your gratious pardon. Grat. Offring our neckes To bee trod on, as a punishment for our late Presumption, and a willing testimony Of our subiection. Theod. Deserue our mercie In your better life heereafter, you shall finde, Though in my Fathers life I helde it madnesse, To vsurp his power, and in my youth disdainde not To learne from the instructions of my sister, Ile make it good to all the world, I am An Emperor; and euen this instant graspe The Scepter, my rich stock of maiesty Intire, no scruple wasted. Phila. If these teares I drop, proceed not from my ioy to heare this May my eye-bals follow 'em. Tim. I will shew my selfe By your suddain metamorphosis transform'd From what I was. Grat. And nere presume to aske What fits not you to giue. Theod. Moue in that sphere, And my light with full beames shall shine vpon you. Forbeare this slavish courtship, 'tis to me In a kinde idolatrous. Phil. Your gratious sister. Enter Pulcheria, Seruant. Pul. Has he conuerted her? Ser. And, as such, will Present her when you please. Pul. I am glad of it. Comand my Dresser to adorne her with The robes that I gaue order for. Mar. I shall. Pul. And let those pretious Iewels I tooke last Out of my Cabinet, if't be possible, Giue lustre to her beauties, and that done, Command her to be neere vs. Mar. Tis a prouince I willingly embrace, Exit Mart. Pul. O my deare Sir, You haue forgot your morning taske, and therefore With a mothers loue I come to reprehende you, But it shall bee gentlie. Theodos. 'T will become you, though, You said with reuerend duty. Know heereafter, If my mother liu'd in you, how ere her sonne, Like you shee were my subiect. Pulch. How? Theod. Put off Amazement, you will finde it. Yet Ile heare you At distance, as a sister, but no longer As a gouernesse, I assure you. Grat. This is put home, Timant. Beyond our hopes Philam. Shee stands as if his words Had powerfull magick in 'em. Theod. Will you haue mee Your pupill euer? the downe on my chinne Confirmes I am a man, a man of men, The Emperour, that knowes his strength. Pulcheria, Heauen grant You know it not too soone. Theod. Let it suffice My wardships out. If your designe concernes vs As a man, and not a boy, with our allowance You may deliuer it. Pulch. A strange alteration! But I will not contend. Bee, as you wish, Sir, Your owne disposer, vncompeld I cancell All bondes of my authority. Kneeles. Theod. You in this Pay your due homage, which perform'd, I thus Embrace you as a Sister. No way doubting Your vigilance for my safetie as my honor, And what you now come to impart, I rest Most confident, points at one of them. Pulch. At both, And not alone the present, but the future Tranquillity of your minde: since in the choice Of her, you are to heate with holy fires, And make the consort of your royall bed, The certaine meanes of glorious succession, With the true happinesse of our humane being, Are wholy comprehended. Theodosius. How? a wife? Shall I become a votarie to Hymen, Before my youth hath sacrific'd to Venus? 'Tis something with the soonest, yet to shew In things in different, I am not auerse To your wise counsailes, let mee first suruay Those beauties, that in being a Prince I know Are riualls for mee. You will not confine mee To your election, I must see deere sister With mine owne eyes. Pulcheria. 'Tis fit Sir, yet in this You may please to consider, absolute Princes Haue, or should haue, in Policie, lesse free will Then such as are their vassals. For, you must, As you are an Emperour, in this high businesse Waigh with due prouidence, with whom alliance May bee most vsefull for the preseruation Or your increase of Empire. Theod. I approue not Such compositions for our morall ends, In what is in it selfe diuine, nay more Decreed in heauen. Yet if our neighbour Princes, Ambitious of such neerenesse, shall present Their dearest pledges to mee (euer reseruing The caution of mine owne content) Ile not Contemne their courteous offers. Pulch. Bring in the pictures: 2. Pictures brought in. Theod. Must I then iudge the substances by the shadowes; The Painters are most enuious, if they want Good colours for preferment: virtuous Ladies Loue this way to bee flatterd, and accuse The Workeman of detraction, if he adde not Some grace they cannot truely call their owne. Is't not so Gratianus? you may challenge Some interest in the science. Grat. A pretender To the art I truely honor, and subscribe To your maiesties opinion. Theod. Let mee see, Cleanthe, daughter to the King of Epirus, Ætatis suæ, the fourteenth: ripe enough, And forward too, I assure you. Let me examine The Symmetries. If Statuaries could By the foote of Hercules set downe punctually His whole dimensions, and the countenance be The index of the minde, this may instruct me, With the aydes of that I haue read touching this subiect, What shee is inward: the colour of her haire, If it be, as this does promise, pale, and faint, And not a glistering white; Her brow, so so; The circles of her sight, too much contracted; Iuno's faire cowe eyes by old Homer are Commended to their merit, heeres a sharpe frost, In the tippe of her nose, which by the length assures mee Of stormes at midnight, if I faile to pay her The tribute she expects. I like her not: What is the other. Chrysapius. How hath hee commenc'd Doctor in this so sweete and secret art, Without our knowledge? Timantus. Some of his forward pages Haue rob'd vs of the honor. Philanax. No such matter, Hee has the theorie only, not the practick. Theod. Amasia, Sister to the Duke of Athens, Her age eighteen, descended lineally From Theseus, as by her pedegree Will be made apparent: Of his lustie kinred? And loose so much time! 'tis strange! as I liue, shee hath A Philosophicall aspect, there is More wit then beauty in her face, and when I court her, it must be in tropes, and figures, Or shee will crie absurd. Shee will haue her clenchs To cut off any fallacie I can hope To put vpon her, and expect I should Euer conclude in Syllogismes, and those true ones In parte &amp; toto, or sheele tire mee with Her tedious Elocutions in the praise Of the increase of generation, for which Alone the sport in her moralitie Is good and lawfull, and to bee often practis'd For feare of missing. Fy on't, let the race Of Theseus be match'd with Aristotles, Ile none of her. Pulcher. You are curious in your choice, Sir, And hard to please, yet if that your consent May giue authority to it, Ile present you With one, that if her birth, and fortunes answer The rarities of her body, and her mind', Detraction durst not tax her. Theod. Let me see her, Though wanting those additions, which we can Supplie from our owne store: it is in vs To make men rich, and noble, but to giue Legitimate shapes and virtues, does belong To the greate creator of 'em, to whose bounties Alone 'tis proper, and in this disdaines An Emperour for his riuall. Pulch. I applaud This fit acknowledgement, since Princes then Grow lesse then common men, when they contend With him, by whom they are so. Enter Paulinus, Cleon, Athenais newly habited. Theod. I confesse it. Pulcheria. Not to hold you in suspense, Behold the virgin Rich in her naturall beauties, no way borrowing Th'adulterate aydes of art. Peruse her better, Shee is worth your serious view. Phyl. I am amaz'd too. I neuer saw her equall. Gratian. How his eye Is fix'd vpon her! Timantus. And as shee were a fort, He would suddainly surprize, Hee measures her From the bases to the battlements. Chrys. Ha! now I view her better, I know her; 'tis the mayd that not long since Was a petitioner; her brauerie So alters her, I had forgot her face. Phil. So has the Emperour. Paulinus. Shee holdes out yet, And yeeldes not to th'assault. Cleon. Shee is strongly garded In her virgin blushes. Paulin. When you know, faire creature, It is the Emperour that honours you With such a strict suruay of your sweete parts, In thankefulnesse you cannot but returne Due reuerence for the fauour. Athenais. I was lost In my astonishment at the glorious obiect, And yet rest doubtfull whether he expects, Being more then man, my adoration, (Since sure there is diuinity about him,) Or will rest satisfi'd if my humble knees In duty thus bowe to him. Theod. Ha! it speakes. Pulch. Shee is no statue Sir, Theod. Suppose her one, And that shee had nor organs voice, nor heat, Most willingly I would resigne my Empire So it might be to after-times recorded That I was her Pigmalion, though, like him, I doted on my workmanship, without hope too Of hauing Cytherea so propitious To my vowes, or sacrifice, in her compassion To giue it life or motion. Pulch. Pray you be not rap'd so, Nor borrow from imaginary fiction Impossible aydes; she's flesh and blood, I assure you, And if you please to honor her in the triall, And be your owne security, as youle finde I fable not, she comes in a noble way To be at your deuotion. Chry. 'Tis the maid I offer'd to your highnesse, her chang'd shape Conceal'd her from you: Theod. At the first I knew her, And a second firebrand Cupid brings to kindle My flames almost put out: I am too cold, And play with opportunity. May I taste then The nectar of her lip? I do not giue it The praise it merits: antiquity is too poore To help me with a simile to expresse her. Let me drink often from this liuing spring, To nourish new inuention. Pulcheria. Do not surfet In ouer-greedily deuouring that Which may without satiety feast you often. From the moderation in receiuing them, The choysest viands do continue pleasing To the most curious palats; if you thinke her Worth your embraces, and the soueraigne title Of the Græcian Empresse, Theod. If? how much you sinne, Only to doubt it; the possession of her Makes all that was before most pretious to me, Common, and cheap: in this you haue shown your selfe A prouident Protectresse. I already Grow weary of the absolute command Of my so numerous subiects, and desire No soueraignty but here, and write downe gladly, A period to my wishes. Pulcher. Yet before It be too late, consider her condition, Her father was a Pagan, she her selfe A new conuerted Christian. Theod. Let me know The man to whose religious meanes I ow So great a debt. Paulinus. You are aduanc'd too high Sir, To acknowledge a beholdingnes, 'tis discharg'd, And I, beyond my hopes, rewarded, if My seruice please your Maiesty. Theod. Take this pledge Of our assured loue. Are there none here Haue suits to prefer? on such a day as this My bounty's without limit. O my dearest, I will not heare thee speak; what euer in Thy thoughts is apprehended, I grant freely: Thou would'st plead thy vnworthinesse, by thy self The magazine of felicity, in thy lownesse Our Eastern Queens at their full height bow to thee, And are in their best trim thy foyles and shadowes. Excuse the violence of my loue, which cannot Admit the least delay. Command the Patriarch With speed to do his holy office for vs, That when we are made one. Pulch. You must forbeare Sir, She is not yet baptiz'd. Theod. In the same houre In which she is confirmed in our faith, We mutually will giue away each other, And both be gainers; weele heare no reply That may diuert vs on. Pulch. You may hereafter Please to remember to whose furtherance You ow this height of happinesse. Ath. As I was Your creature when I first petition'd you, I will continue so, and you shall finde me, Though an Empresse, still your seruant. All go off but Philanax, Gratianus, and Timantus! Gratianus. Here's a marriage Made vp on the suddain! Philanax. I repine not at The faire maids fortune, though I feare the Princesse Had some peculiar end in't. Timantus. Who's so simple Only to doubt it? Gratianus. It is too apparent, She hath preferr'd a creature of her owne, By whose meanes she may still keepe to her selfe The gouernment of the Empire. Tim. Where as if The Emperor had espous'd some neighbour Queen, Pulcheria with all her wisdome could not Keepe her preheminence. Philanax. Be it as it will, 'Tis not now to be alter'd, heauen I say Turne all to the best. Gratianus. Are we come to praying againe? Phil. Leaue thy prophanenesse Gratian. Would it would leaue mee. I am sure I thriue not by it. Timant. Come to the Temple. Grat. Eu'n where you will, I know not what to think on't, The end of the second Acte.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Act. 3. Scæna 1. Paulinus, Philanax. Paulinus. Nor this, nor the age before vs euer look'd on The like solemnitie. Philan. A suddain feuer Kep'd mee at home. Pray you my Lord acquaint me With the particulars. Paul. You may presume No pompe, nor ceremony could be wanting, Where there was Priuiledge to command, and meanes To cherish rare inuentions. Phil. I beleeue it; But the summe of all in briefe. Paulinus. Pray you so take it; Faire Athenais not longe since a Suitor, And almost in her hopes forsaken, first Was Christned, and the Emperours mothers name Eudoxia, as hee will'd, impos'd vpon her: Pulcheria the euer matchlesse Princesse, Assisted by her reuerend Aunt Maria, Her God-mothers. Phil. And who the masculine witnesse? Paul. At the new empresse suite I had the honor. For which I must euer serue her. Phil. 'twas a grace, With iustice you may boaste of. Paul. The marriage followed, And as 'tis sayd, the Emperour made bold To turne the day to night, for, to bed they went Assoone as they had din'd, and there are wagers Lay'd by some merrye Lord's, hee hath already. Begot a boy vpon her. Phil. That is yet To be determin'd of; but I am certaine, A Prince so soone in his disposition alter'd, Was neuer heard nor reade of. Paul. But of late, Frugall and sparing, now nor boundes, nor limits To his magnificent bounties. Hee affirm'd, Hauing receiu'd more blessings by his empresse Then hee could hope, in thankefulnesse to heauen He cannot be to prodigall to others. What euer s'offer'd to his royall hand Hee signes without perusing it. Phil. I am heere Inioyned to free all such as lye for debt, The creditors to bee pay'd out of his coffers. Paul. And I all malefactors that are not Conuicted, or for treason or fowle murther, Such only are excepted; Phil. 'Tis a rare clemencie! Paul. Which wee must not dispute, but put in practise. Exeunt. Scæn. 2. Lowd Musick. Showtes within: Heauen preserue the Emperour, Heauen blesse the Empresse. Then in State, Chrysapius, Patriarch. Paulinus. Theodosius. Athenais. Pulcheria. Her two young Sisters bearing vp Athenais trayne. Followed, by Philanax. Gratianus. Timantus. Suitors, presenting petitions. The Emperour sealing them. Pulcheria appeares troubled. Pul. Sir by your owne rules of Philosophie You know things violent last not, royall bounties Are great, and gratious while they are dispens'd With moderation, but when their excesse In giuing gyant-bulkes to others, take from The Princes iust proportion, they loose The names of vertues, and, their natures chang'd, Grow the most dangerous vices Theod. In this, sister, Your wisdome is not circular; they that sowe In narrow boundes, cannot expect in reason A croppe beyond their ventures, what I doe Disperse, I lend, and will with vsury Returne vnto my heape: I only then Am rich, and happy, (though my coffers sound With emptinesse) when my glad subiects feele, Their plenty and felicitie is my gifte; And they will finde, when they with cheerefulnesse Supplie not my defectes, I being the stomacke To the politick body of the State, the limbes Grow suddainely faint, and feeble; I could vrge Proofes of more finenesse in their shape and language, But none of greater strength: dissuade mee not, What wee will, we will doe; yet to assure you, Your care does not offend vs, for an houre, Bee happy in the conuerse of my best And deerest comfort; may you please to licence My priuacie some few minutes? Athenais. Licence Sir, I haue no will, but is deriu'd from yours, And that still waites vpon you, nor can I Bee left with such security with any, As with the gratious Princesse, who receiues Addition, though shee bee all excellence, In being stilde your sister. Theod. O sweete creature! Let mee bee censur'd fond, and too indulgent, Nay though they say vxorious, I care not, Her loue, and sweete humility exact A tribute far beyond my power, to pay Her matchlesse goodnesse, Forward. Exeunt, Theodosius and the traine. Pulch. Now you finde Your dying fathers prophecie that foretolde Your present greatnesse, to the full accomplish'd. For the poore aides, and furtherance I lent you, I willingly forget. Ath. Eu'n that bindes me To a more strict remembrance of the fauor, Nor shall you from my foule ingratitude, In any circumstance euer finde cause T'upbraid me with your benefit, Pul. I beleeue so. Pray you giue vs leaue: what now I must deliuer Vnder the deepest scale of secrecy, Though it be for you good, will giue assurance Of what is look'd for, if you not alone Heare, but obey my counsels. Ath. They must be Of a strange nature, if with zealous speed I put 'em not in practice. Pul. 'Twere impertinence To dwell on circumstances, since the wound Requires a suddain cure, especially Since you that are the happy instrument Elected to it, though yong in your iudgement Write far aboue your yeeres, and may instruct Such as are more experienc'd. Ath. Good madam, In this I must oppose you, I am well Acquainted with my weaknesse, and it will not Become your wisdome, by which I am rais'd To this titulary height, that should correct The pride, and ouerweening of my fortune, To play the parasite to it, in ascribing That merit to me, vnto which I can Pretend no interest; pray you excuse My bold simplicity, and to my waight Designe me where you please, and you shall finde In my obedience, I am still your creature. Pul. 'Tis nobly answer'd, and I glory in The building I haue rais'd; go on, sweet Lady, In this your vertuous progresse but to the point, You know, nor do I enuy it, you haue Acquir'd that power, which, not long since, was mine, In gouerning the Emperor, and must vse The strength you hold in the heart of his affections, For his priuate, as the publique preseruation, To which there is no greater enemy, Then his exorbitant prodigality, How ere his sycophants, and flatterers call it. Royall magnificence, and though you may Vrge what's done for your honor, must not be Curb'd, or be controul'd by you, you cannot in Your wisdome but conceiue, if that the torrent Of his violent bounties be not stopp'd, or lessen'd, It will proue most pernitious. Therefore, Madam, Since 'tis your duty, as you are his wife, To giue him sauing counsells, and in being Almost his idoll, may command him to Take any shape you please, with a powerfull hand, To stop him in his precipice to ruine. Ath. Auert it heauen. Pul. Heauen is most gratious to you, madam, In choosing you to be the instrument Of such a pious work. You see he signes What suit soeuer is preferr'd, not once Inquiring what it is, yeelding himselfe A prey to all; I would therefore haue you, Lady, As I know you will to aduise him, or command him, As he would reap the plenty of your fauours, To vse more moderation in his bounties, And that before he giues, he would consider, The what, to whom, and wherefore. Ath. Do yo think Such arrogance, or vsurpation, rather, Of what is proper, and peculiar To euery priuate husband, and much more To him an Emperor, can ranck with th'obedience And duty of a wife? are we appointed In our creation (let me reason with you) To rule, or to obey? or 'cause he loues me With a kinde impotence, must I tyrannize Ouer his weaknesse? or abuse the strength With which he armes me to his wrong? or, like A prostituted creature, merchandize Our mutuall delight for hire? or to Serue mine owne sordid ends? in vulgar nuptials Priority is exploded, though there be A difference in the parties, and shall I, His vassall from obscurity rais'd by him To this so eminent light, presume to appoint him To do, or not to do this, or that: when wiues Are well aocommodated by their husbands With all things both for vse, and ornament, Let them fix there, and neuer dare to question Their wils or actions. For my selfe, I vow, Though now my Lord would rashly giue away His Scepter, and imperiall Diadem, Or if there could be any thing more pretious, I would not crosse it; but I know this is But a triall of my temper, and as such I do receiue it, or if't be otherwise, You are so subtill in your arguments, I dare not stay to heare them. Pulcher. Is't eu'n so? I haue power ore these yet, and command their stay, To hearken nearer to me. 1 Sister. We are charg'd By the Emperor, our brother, to attend The Empresse seruice. 2 Sister. You are too mortifi'd sister, (With reuerence I speak it) for yong Ladies To keepe you company. I am so tir'd With your tedious exhortations, doctrines, vses, Of your religious morality, That for my health sake, I must take the freedome To enioy a little of those pretty pleasures That I was borne to. 1 Sister. When I come to your yeeres, Ile do as you do, but till then, with your pardon, Ile lose no more time. I haue not learn't to dance yet, Nor sing, but holy hymnes, and those to vile tunes too; Nor to discourse, but of Schoolemens opinions. How shall I answer my sutors? since, I hope, Ere long I shall haue many, without practice To write, and speake somthing that's not deriu'd From the fathers of Philosophy. 2 Sister. We shall shame Our breeding Sister, if we should go on thus. 1 Sister. 'Tis for your credit, that we study How to conuerse with men; women with women Yeelds but a harren argument. 2 Sister. She frownes, But you'll protect vs Madam? Ath. Yes, and loue Your sweet simplicity. 1 Sister. All yong gyrles are so, Till they know the way of't. 2 Sister. But when we are enter'd, We shall on a good round pace, Ath. Ile leaue you Madam. 1 Sister. And we our duties with you. Exeunt Athenais and the yong Ladyes. Pul. On all hands Thus slighted? no way left? am I growne stupid In my inuention? can I make no vse Of the Emperors bounties? now 'tis thought: within there. Seruant. Madam. Enter a Seruant. Pul. It shall be so; neerer; your eare Draw a petition to this end. Seru. Besides The danger to prefer it, I beleeue Twill nere be granted. Pul. How's this? are you growne, From a seruant, my director? let me heare No more of this. Dispatch, Ile master him At his owne weapon. Exit Seruant. Enter Theodosius, Favorinus, Philanax, Timantus, Gratianus. Theod. Let me vnderstand it, If yet there be ought wanting that may perfect A generall happinesse. Fauor. The peoples ioy In seas of acclamations flow in To wait on yours. Philanax. Their loue with bounty leuied, Is a sure guard. Obedience forc'd from feare, Paper fortification, which in danger Will yeeld to the impression of a reed, Or of it selfe fall off. Theod. True, Philanax. And by that certain compasse we resolue To steere our Barque of gouernment. Enter Seruant with the petition. Pul. 'Tis well. The. My deerest, and my all-deseruing Sister, As a petitioner kneele? it must not bee, Pray you, rise, although your suite were halfe my Empire, 'Tis freely granted. Pulch. Your alacritie To giue hath made a begger; yet before My suite is by your sacred hand and seale Confirm'd, 'tis necessary you peruse The summe of my request. Theod. Wee will not wrong Your iudgement, in conceiuing what 'tis fit For you to aske, and vs to grant, so much, As to proceede with caution, giue mee my signet, With confidence I signe it, and heere vow. By my fathers soule, but with your free consent It is irreuocable. Timantus. What if shee now Calling to memorie, how often wee Haue cross'd her gouernment, in reuenge hath made Petition for our heads? Gratianus. They must euen off then, No ransone can redeeme vs. Theod. Let those iewells So highly rated by the Persian merchants Bee bought, and as a sacrifice from vs Presented to Eudoxa. Shee being only Worthy to weare 'em, I am angrie with The vnresistable necessitie. Of my occasions, and important cares That so long keepe mee from her. Exeunt Theodosius and the trayne. Pulcher. Goe to the Empresse, And tell her on the suddaine, I am sicke, And doe desire, the comfort of a visit, If shee please to vouchsafe it. From me vse Your humblest language: But when once I haue her In my possession, I will rise, and speake In a higher straine, say it raise stormes, no matter. Fooles iudge by the euent, my endes are honest. Exeunt. Scæne 3. Theodosius. Timantus. Philanax. Theod. What is become of her? can shee that carries Such glorious excellence, of light about her, Be any where conceal'd? Philanax. Wee haue sought her lodgings, And all we can learne from the seruants is, Shee by your maiesties sisters wayted on, (The attendance of her other officers By her expresse command deni'd,) Theod. Forbeare Impertinent circumstances, whither went shee? speake. Phil. As they ghesse, to the lawrell groue. Theod. So slightly garded! What an earth-quake I feele in mee! and but that Religion assures the contrarie, The Poets dreames of lustfull Fawnes, and Satyres, Would make me feare, I know not what. Enter Paulinus, Paul. I haue found her, And it please your Maiestie. Theod. Yes, it doth please mee. But why return'd without her? Paul. As shee made Her speediest approches to your presence, A seruant of the Princesses Pulcheria Encounterd her; what 'twas, he whisperd to her I am ignorant, but hearing it, she started, And will'd me to excuse her absence from you, The third part of an houre. The. In this she takes So much of my life from me; yet Ile beare it With what patience I may; since 'tis her pleasure. Go back, my good Paulinus, and intreat her Not to exceed a minute. Timant. Here's strange fondnesse! Exeunt. Scæne 4. Pulcheria. Seruants. Pul. You are certaine she will come? Ser. She is already Enter'd your outward lodgings. Pul. No traine with her? Ser. Your excellence sisters only. Pulch. 'Tis the better; See the doores strongly guarded, and deny Accesse to all, but with our speciall licence. Why dost thou stay? shew your obedience, Your wisdome now is vselesse. Exeunt Seruants. Enter Athenais, Arcadia, Flaccilla. Flac. She is sick sure, Or, in fit reuerence to your Maiesty, She had waited you at the doore. Ar. 'Twould hardly be Pulcheria walking by. Excus'd, in ciuill manners, to her equall, But with more difficulty to you, that are So far aboue her. Ath. Not in her opinion; She hath beene too long accustom'd to command T'acknowledge a superior. Ar. There she walks. Fla. If she be not sick of the sullens, I see not The least infirmity in her. Ath. This is strange! Ar. Open your eyes; the Empresse. Pul. Reach that chaire: Now sitting thus at distance, Ile vouchsafe To looke vpon her. Ar. How! sister: pray you awake, Are you in your wits? Fla. Grant heauen, your too much learning Does not conclude in madnesse. Ath. You intreated A visit from me. Pul. True, my seruant vs'd Such language, but now as a mistresse I Command your seruice. Ath. Seruice! Ar. She's stark mad, sure. Pul. Youle finde I can dispose of what's mine owne Without a guardian. Ath. Follow me. I will see you When your frantique fit is ore. I do begin To be of your beleefe. Pulch. It will deceiue you. Thou shalt not str from hence, thus as mine owne I seize vpon thee. Flac. Help, help, violence Offer'd to the Empresse person. Pulch. 'Tis in vaine: Shee was an Empresse once, but, by my gift, Which, being abus'd, I do recall my grant. You are read in story; call to remembrance, What the great Hectors mother Hecuba Was to Vlysses, Ilium sack'd. Ath. A slaue. Pulch. To me thou art so: Ath. Wonder and amazement Quite ouerwhelme me: how am I transform'd? How haue I lost my liberty? Knocking without: Enter Seruant. Pulcheria. Thou shall know Too soone, no doubt. Who's that with such rudenesse Beats at the doore? Ser. The Prince Paulinus, madam, Sent from the Emperor to attend vpon The gratious Empresse. Ar. And who is your slaue now? Fla. Sister, repent in time, and beg pardon For your presumption. Pulch. It is resolu'd: From me returne this answer to Paulinus; She shall not come; she's mine; the Emperor hath No interest in her. Exit Seruant. Ath. Whatsoere I am, You take not from your power ore me, to yeeld A reason for this vsage. Pulch. Though my will is Sufficient to ad to thy affliction, Know wretched thing, 'tis not thy fate, but folly Hath made thee what thou art: 'tis some delight To vrge my merits to one so vngratefull; Therefore with horror heare it. When thou wert Thrust as a stranger from thy fathers house, Expos'd to all calamities that want Could throw vpon thee, thine owne brothers scorne, And in thy hopes, as by the world forsaken, My pity, the last altar that was left thee, I heard thy Syren charmes, with feeling heard them, And my compassion made mine eyes vy teares With thine, dissembling Crocodile; and when Queenes Were emulous for thy imperiall bed, The garments of thy sorrowes cast aside, I put thee in a shape as would haue forc'd Enuy from Cleopatra, had she seene thee; Then, when I knew my brothers blood was warm'd With youthfull fires, I brought thee to his presence, And how my deepe designes, for thy good plotted, Succeeded to my wishes, is apparant, And needs no repetition. Ath. I am conscious Of your so many, and vnequall'd fauors, But finde not how I may accuse my selfe For any facts committed, that with iustice, Can raise your anger to this height against me. Pul. Pride and forgetfulnesse would not let thee see that, Against which now thou canst not close thine eyes. What iniury could be equall to thy late Contempt of my good counsell, when I vrg'd The Emperors prodigall bounties, and intreated That you would vse your power to giue 'em limits, Or, at the least, a due consideration Of such as su'd, and for what, ere he sign'd it? In opposition you brought against me Th'obedience of a wife, that Ladyes were not, Being well accommodated by their Lords, To question, but much lesse to crosse their pleasures; Nor would you, though the Emperor were resolu'd To giue away his Scepter, hinder it, Since 'twas done for your honor, couering with False colors of humility your ambition. Ath. And is this my offence? Pul. As wicked counsell Is still most hurtfull vnto those that giue it; Such as deny to follow what is good, In reason, are the first that must repent it. When I please you shall heare more, in the meane time Thank your owne wilfull follie that hath chang'd you From an Empresse to a bondewoman. Theod. Force the doores, Kill those that dare resist. Enter Theodosius. Paulinus. Philanax. Chrysapius. Gratianus. Ath. Deere Sir redeeme mee. Flaccilla. O suffer not, for your owne honors sake, The Empresse you so late lou'd to bee made A prisoner in the court. Arcad. Leape to his lippes, You'll finde them the best sanctuarie. Flaccilla. And trie then, What interest my reuerend Sister hath To force you from 'em. Theod. What strange may-game's this? Though done in sport, how ill this leuitie Becomes your wisdome? Pulch. I am serious Sir, And haue done nothing but what you in honor, And as you are your selfe an Emperour, Stand bound to iustifie. Theod. Take heed, put not these Strange trialls on my patience. Pulcher. Doe not you Sir, Denie your owne act; as you are a man, And stand on your owne bottomes, 'twill appeare A childish weakenes to make void a grant, Sign'd by your sacred hand, and seale, and strengthend With a religious oth, but with my licence, Neuer to be recall'd. For some few minutes, Let reason rule your passion, and in this, deliuers the deed. Bee pleas'd to reade my interest; you will finde there What you in me call violence, is iustice, And that I may make vse of what's mine owne, According to my will. 'tis your owne gift Sir, And what an Emperour giues, should stand as firme As the celestiall poles vpon the shoulders Of Atlas, or his successor in that office The greate Alcides. Theod. Miseries of more waight, Then 'tis faind they supported, fall vpon mee, What hath my rashnesse done? in this transaction Drawne, in expresse and formall termes I haue Giuen and consign'd into your handes, to vse And obserue, as you please, my deere Eudoxa. It is my deed, I doe confesse it is, And as I am my selfe, not to bee cancell'd: But yet you may shew mercie, and you will, When you consider that there is no beauty, So perfit in a creature, but is soilde With some vnbeseeming blemish; you haue labour'd To build mee vp a compleate Prince, 'tis granted, Yet as I am a man, like other Monarchs, I haue defects and frayleties, my facilitie, To send petitioners with pleas'd lookes from me, Is all I can be charg'd with, and it will Become your wisdome, (since 'tis in your power) In charitie to prouide, I fall no further Or in my oth, or honor. Pul. Royall Sir, This was the marke I aim'd at, and I glorie At the length, you so conceaue it. 'twas a weakenes To measure by your owne integritie The purposes of others. I haue showne you In a true mirror what fruite growes vpon The tree of hudwinckt bounty, and what dangers Precipitation in the managing Your great affaires produceth. Theod. I embrace it As a graue aduertisement, and vow heereafter Neuer to signe petitions at this rate. Pulch. For mine, see Sir, 'tis cancel'd, on my knees I redeliuer what I now beg'd from you. Teares the deed: Shee is my second gift. Theod. Which if I part from Till death diuorce vs. Kissing Athen. Athendis. So Sir, Theod. Nay sweete chide not I am punish'd in thy lookes, defer the rest, Till we are more priuate. Pulch. I aske pardon too If in my personated passion I Appeard to harshe, and rough. Ath. 'Twas gentle language, what I was then considerd Pulch. O deere Madame, It was decorum in the Scane: Athen. This triall, When I was Athenais, might haue pass'd, But as I am the Empresse. Theod. Nay no anger, Since all good was intended. Exeunt. Theodosius. Athenais. Arcadia. Flaccilla. Pulcheria. Building on, That certaine base, I feare not what can follow, Exit Pulch. Paulinus. These are strange deuices Philanax. Philan. True my Lord, May all turne to the best. Grat. The Emperours lookes Promis'd a calme. Chrysapius. But the vex'd Empresse frownes Presag'd a second storme. Paul. I am sure I feele one, In my legge already. Philan. Your old friend, the goute? Paul. My forc'd companion, Philanax. Chrys. To your rest: Paul. Rest and forbearing wine, with a temperate dyet, Though many Montebancks pretend the cure of't, I haue found my best Physitians, Phil. Ease to your Lordship. Exeunt. The ende of the third Act.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Actus 4. Scæn. 1. Athenais. Chrysapius. Ath. Make mee her propertie? Chrys. Your maiestie Hath iust cause of distant, and your resentment Of the affront in the point of honor cannot But meete a faire construction. Ath. I haue only The title of an Empresse, but the power Is, by her, rauish'd from me, shee suruayes My actions as a gouernesse, and calls My not obseruing all that shee directs Folly, and disobedience. Chrys. Vnder correction, With griefe I haue long obseru'd it, and if you Stand pleas'd to signe my warrant Ile deliuer In my vnfainde zeale, and desire to serue you, (Howere I run the hazard of my head fort Should it arriue at the knowledge of the Princesse,) Not alone, the reasons why things are thus carried, But giue into your hands the power to clippe The wings of her command. Ath. Your seruice this way Cannot offend mee. Chrys. Bee you pleas'd to know then But still with pardon, if I am too bold, Your too much sufferance impes the broken feathers Which carie her to this proude height, in which Shee with securitie, soares, and still towres ore you, But if you would imploy the strengths you hold In the Emperours affections, and remember The orbe you moue in should admit no star els, You neuer would confesse the managing Of state affaires to her alone are proper, And you sit by a looker on, Athenais. I would not, If it were possible I could attempt, Her diminution, without a taint Of foule ingratitude in my selfe. Chrysapius. In this The sweetenesse of your temper does abuse you, And you call that a benefit to your selfe Which shee for her owne endes conferr'd vpon you. 'Tis yeelded shee gaue way to your aduancement: But for what cause? that shee might still continue Her absolute sway, and swing ore the whole state, And that shee might to her admirers vaunt, The Empresse was her creature, and the giuer To bee preferr'd before the gift. Athenais. It may bee. Chrys. Nay 'tis most certaine: whereas would you please In a true glasse to looke vpon your selfe, And view without detraction your owne merits Which all men wonder at; you would find that fate, Without a second cause, appointed you To the supremest honor. For the Princesse, Shee hath raign'd long enough, and her remoue Will make your entrance free to the possession Of what you were borne to, &amp; but once resolue To build vpon her ruines, leaue the engines That must bee vs'd to vndermine her greatenes To my prouision. Ath. I thanke your care, But a designe of such waight must not be Rashly determin'd of, it will exact A long and serious consultation from mee. In the meane time Chrysapius rest assur'd I liue your thankefull Mistrisse. Exit Ath. Chrys. Is this all? Will the Physick that I minister'd worke no further? I haue playd the foole, and leauing a calme port Embarqu'd my selfe on a rough sea of danger. In her silence lies my safetie, which how can I Hope from a woman? but the die is throwne, And I must stand the hazard. Enter Theodosius. Philanax. Timantus. Gratianus. Huntsmen. Theod. Is Paulinus So tortur'd with his gowte? Phil. Most miserablie, And it ads much to his affliction, that The payne denies him power to waite vpon Your Maiestie. Theod. I pittie him: hee is A wondrous honest man, and what he suffers, I know will grieue my Empresse. Tim. Hee indeed is Much bound to her gratious fauour. Theod. Hee deserues it, Shee cannot finde a subiect vpon whom Shee better may confer it: is the stagge Safe lodg'd? Gratian. Yes Sir, and the houndes and huntsmen ready. Philan. Hee will make you royall sport. Hee is a deere Of ten at the least. Enter Countrieman with the apple. Gratianus. Whither will this clowne? Timant. Stand backe. Countrym. I would zee the Emperour, why should you Courtiers Scorne a poore Countryman! wee zweat at the Plough To vill your mouths, you and you curs might starue els. Wee prune the orchards, and you cranch the fruite; Yet still you are snarling at vs. Theod. What's the matter? Count. I would looke on thy sweete face. Timantus. Vnmannerly swaine. Count. Zwaine, though I am a zwaine, I haue a heart yet, As ready to doe seruice for my leege, As any Princox Peacock of you all. Zookers had I one of you zingle with this twigge, I would so veeze you. Timant. Will your Maiestie Heare his rude language? Theod. Yes, and hold it as An ornament, not a blendish. O Timantus! Since that drad power by whom we are, disdaines not With an open eare to heare petitions from vs, Easie accesse in vs his deputies, To the meanest of our subiects, is a debt, Which we stand bound to pay. Count. By my granams ghost 'Tis a holsome zaying, our vicar could not mend it In the pulpit on a Zunday. Theod. What's they suite friend? Count. Zute? I would laugh at that. Let the court begge from thee. What the poore countrie giues: I bring a present To thy good grace, which I can call mine owne, And looke not like these gay folke for a returne, Of what they venture. Haue I giuent you? ha, Chrys. A perillous knaue. Count. Zee heere a dainty Apple, Presents the Apple. Of mine owne graffing, zweete, and zownde I assure thee. Theod. It is the fairest fruite I euer saw. Those golden apples in the Hesperian orchardes So strangely guarded by the watchfull Dragon, As they requir'd greate Hercules to get 'em, Nor those with which Hippemenes deceiu'd, Swift footed Atalanta, when I looke On this, deserue no wonder. You behold The pooreman, and his present with contempt I to their value prize both; he that could So ayde weake nature, by his care, and labour, As to compell a crabtree stocke to beare A pretious fruite of this large size, and beauty, Would by his industrie change a pettie village Into a populous Citry, and from that Erecte a flourishing Kingdome. Giue the fellow For an encouragement to his future labours, Ten Attick talents. Countrym. I will wearie heauen With my prayers for your Maiestie. Exit Count. Theod. Philanax, From mee present this raritie to the rarest And best of women, when I th'nk vpon The boundlesse happinesse that from her flow to me In my imagination I am rap'd Beyond my selfe; but I forget our hunting, To the forrest for the exercise of my body, But for my mind, 'tis wholly taken vp, In the comtemplation of her matchlesse vertues. Exeunt. Scæna 2. Athenais. Pulcheria. Arcadia. Flaccilla. Ath. Yov shall know ther's a difference betweene vs. Pulch. There was I am certain not long since, when you Kneel'd a petitioner to me, then you were happy To bee neere my feete, and doe you hold it now As a disparagement that I side you Lady. Ath. Since you respect mee only as I was, What I am shall be remembered. Pul. Does the meanes, I practis'd to giue good, and sauing counsail's To the Emperour, and your new stamp'd maiestie Still sticke in your stomach? Ath. 'Tis not yet digested, In troth it is not, why good gouernesse, Though you are held for a grand Madam, and your selfe, The first that ouerprize it, I nere tooke Your words for Delphian oracles, nor your actions For such wonders as you make 'em, there is one When shee shall see her time, as fit and able To be made partner of the Emperours cares, As your wise selfe, and may with iustice challenge A neerer interest. You haue done your visit, So when you please, you may leaue me. Pul. Ile not bandye Words with your mightinesse, prow'd one, only this, You carrie to much saile for your small barke, And that when you least think vpon't may sincke you. Exit Pulch. Flacc. I am glad shee is gone. Arcadia. I feard shee would haue read A tedious lecture to vs. Enter Phil. with the apple. Philanax. From the Emperour, This rare fruite to the rarest. Ath. How my Lord? Philanax. I vse his language Madame, and that trust, Which hee impos'd on mee, discharg'd, his pleasure Commands my present seruice. Exit Philan. Ath. Haue you seene So faire an Apple? Flacc. Neuer. Arcad. If the taste Answer the beauty. Ath. Prettily beg'd, you should haue it, But that you eate too much cold fruite, and that Changes the fresh red in your cheekes to palenesse. Enter Seruant. I haue other danities for you; you come from Paulinus, how is't with that truely noble, And honest Lord? my witnesse at the fount; In a word the man to whose bless'd charity I owe my greatnesse. How is't with him? Seruant. Spiritely, In his minde, but by the raging of his goute In his body much distemper'd, that you pleas'd To inquire his health, tooke off much from his paine, His glad lookes did confirme it. Ath. Doe his Doctors Giue him no hope? Seru. Little, they rather feare, By his continuall burning, that hee stands In danger of a feuer. Ath. To him againe, And tell him that I heartely wish it lay In mee to ease him, and from me deliuer This choice fruite to him, you may say to that, I hope it will proue Physicall. Serv. The good Lord Will be oreioyde with the fauour. Ath. Hee deseru's more, Exeunt. Scæna 3. Paulinus brought in a chaire. Chirurgion. Chirurg. I haue done as much as art can doe, to stoppe The violent course of your fit, and I hope you feele it, How does your honor? Paul. At some ease, I thanke you, I would you could assure continuance of it, For the moyetie of my fortune. Chir. If I could cure, The gout my Lord, without the Philosophers stone I should soone purchase, it being a disease, In poore men very rare, and in the rich The cure impossible, your many bounties; Bid mee prepare you for a certaine truth, And to flatter you were dishonest. Paul. Your plaine dealing Deserues a fee. Would there were many more such Of your profession. Happy are pooremen, If sicke with the excesse of heate or cold, Caus'd by necessitous labour, not loose surfets They, when spare dyet, or kind nature faile, To perfit their recouery, soone arriue at Their rest in death, but on the contrarie The greate, and noble are expos'd as preyes To the rapine of Physitians, and they In lingring out what is remedilesse, Aime at their profit, not the patients health, A thousand trialls and experiments Haue bene put vpon mee, and I forc'd to pay deere For my vexation, but I am resolu'd, (I thanke your honest freedome) to be made A propertie no more for knaues to worke on. What haue you there? Enter Cleon with a parchement role. Cleon. The triumphes of an artsman O're all infirmities, made authenticall With the names of Princes, Kings and Emperours That were his patients. Paul. Some Empericke. Cleon. It may be so, but he sweares within three dayes He will grub vp your goute by the rootes, and make you able To march ten leagues a day in compleate armor, Paul. Impossible, Cleon. Or if you like not him Chirurg. Heare him, my Lord, for your mirth; I will take order, They shall not wrong you. Paul. Vsher in your monster. Cleon. He is at hand, march vp: now speak for your self? Enter Emperick. Emper. I come not (right honorable) to your presence, with any base and for did end of reward; the immortality of my fame is the white I shoote at, the charge of my most curious, and costly ingredients fraide, amounting to some seaventeene thousand crownes, a trifle in respect of health, writing your noble name in my Catalogue, I shall acknowledge my selfe amply satisfi'd. Chir. I beleeue so. Emper. For your owne sake I most heartily wish, that you had now all the diseases, maladies and infirmities vpon you, that were euer remembered by old Galen, Hippocrates, or the later, and more admitted Paracelsus. Paul. For your good wish, I thanke you. Emper. Take mee with you, I beseech your good Lordship, I vrg'd it that your ioy in being certainely: and suddainly freed from them, may be the greater, and my not to bee paralleld skill the more remarkable: the cure of the goute a toy, without boast bee it said, my cradle practise, the camer, the Fistula, the Dropsie, consumption of Lunges, and Kidnyes, hurts in the braine, heart, or liuer, are things worthy my opposition, but in the recouerie of my patients I euer ouercome them, but to your goute, Paul. I marry Sir, that cur'd I shall be apter To giue credit to the rest Emp. Suppose it done Sir, Chir. And the meanes, you vse I beseech you. Emper. I will doe it in the plainest language, and discouer my ingredients. First my boteni Terebinthina, of Cypris, my Manna, ros cœlo, coagulated with vetulos ouorum, vulgarly yelkes of Egges, with a little Cyath, or quantitie of my potable Elixir, with some few scruples of sassa-fras and Guacum, so taken euery morning and euening, in the space of three dayes, purgeth, clenseth, and dissipateth the inward causes of the virulent tumor. Paul. Why doe you smile? Chir. When hee hath done I will resolue you. Emper. For my exterior applications I haue these balsumunguentulums extracted from hearbes plants, rootes, seeds, gummes, and a million of other vegetables, the principall of which are Vlissipona, or Serpentaria, Sophia, or Herba consolidarum, Parthenium or commanilla Romana, Mumia transmarina, mixed with my plumbum Philosophorum, and mater metallorum, cum ossa paraleli, est vniuersale medicamentum in podagra. Cleon. A coniuring balsamum, Emp. This applied warme vpon the pained place, with a fether of Struthio cameli, or a bird of Paradise which is euery where to bee had, shall expulse this tartarous, viscous, anatheos, and malignant dolor. Char. An excellent receipt, but does your Lordship Know what it is good for? Paul. I would be instructed, Chir. For the gonorrhea, or if you will heare it In a plainer phrase, the pox. Emper. If it cure his Lordship Of that by the way, I hope Sir 'tis the better; My medicine serues for all things, and the pox Sir, Though falsely nam'd the Sciatica, or goute, Is the more Catholick sicknesse. Paul. Hence with the rascall. Yet hurt him not, he makes mee smile, and that Frees him from punishment. They thrust off the Emper. Chir. Such slaues as this Render our art contemptible, Enter Seruant Seru. My good Lord, Paul. So soone return'd? Seru. And with this present from Your greate, and gratious Mistrisse, with her wishes It may proue Physicall to you. Paul. In my heart I kneele, and thanke her bounty. deere friend Cleon Giue him the cupboorde of Plate in the next roome. For a reward. Exeunt Cleon and the Seruant. Most glorious fruite, but made More pretious by her grace, and loue that sent it. To touch it only comming from her hand Makes mee forget all paine. A Diamond Of this large size, though it would buy a Kingdome, Hew'd from the rocke, and lay'd downe at my seete, Nay though a Monarchs gift, will hold no value, Compar'd with this, and yet ere I presume To tast it, though sans question it is Some heauenly restoratiue, I in duty Stand bound to waigh my owne vnworthinesse: Ambrosia is foode only for the Gods; And not by humane lips to be prophan'd: I may adore it as some holy Relick, Deriu'de from thence, but impious to keepe it, In my possession; the Emperour only, Is worthy to inioy it goe good Cleon, Enter Cleon. (And cease this admiration at this obiect;) From mee present this to my royall master, I know it will amaze him, and excuse me That I am not my selfe the bearer of it. That I should bee lame now, when with wings of duty I should flye to the seruice of this Empresse, Nay no delayes good Cleon. Cleon. I am gone Sir. Exeunt. Scæne 4. Theodosius. Chrysapius. Timantus. Gratianus. Chrys. Are you not tir'd Sir? Theod. Tir'd? I must not say so Howeuer, though I rode hard; to a huntsman, His toyle is his delight, and to complaine Of wearinesse, would shew as poorely in him, As if a Generall should greiue for a wound, Receau'd vpon his forhead, or his brest, After a glorious victorie, lay by These accoutrements for the chase. Enter Pulch. Pulch. You are well return'd Sir, From your Princely exercise. Theod. Sister, to you I owe the freedome, and the vse of all The pleasures I enioy; your care prouides For my security, and the burthen which I should alone sustaine, you vndergoe, And by your painefull watchings, yeeld my sleepes Both sound, and sure. How happie am I in Your knowledge of the art of gouernement! And credit mee, I glorie to behold you Dispose of great designes, as if you were A partner, and no subiect of my Empire. Pulch. My vigilance, since it hath well succeeded. I am confident, you allow of, yet it is not Approu'd by all. Theod. Who dares repine at that, Which hath our suffrage? Pulch. One that too well knowes, The strength of her abilities can better My weake endeuours. Theod. In this you reflect Vpon my Empresse? Pul. True, for as shee is The consort of your bed, 'tis fit shee share in Your cares, and absolute power. Theod. You touch a string That sowndes but harshely to mee, and I must In a brothers loue aduise you that heereafter You would forbeare to moue it. Since shee is In her pure selfe a harmonie of such sweetenesse, Compos'd of dutie, chaste desires, her beautie (Though it might tempt a Hermit from his beades) The least of her endowments. I am sorrie Her holding the first place, since that the second Is proper to your selfe, calls on your enuie. Shee erre? it is impossible in a thought, And much more speake, or doe what may offend mee. In other things, I would beleeue you sister: But though the tongues of Saints, and Angells tax'd her Of any imperfection, I should be Incredulous. Pulcheria. Shee is yet a woman Sir. Theod. The abstract of what's excellent in the sex: But to their mulcts, and frayleties a meere stranger; Ile dye in this beleefe. Enter Cleon with the apple. Cleon. Your humblest seruant, The Lord Paulinus, as a witnesse of His zeale, and dutie to your Maiestie, Presents you with this iewell. Theod. Ha! Cleon. It is Preferr'd by him. Theod. Aboue his honor? Cleon. No Sir, I would haue said his patrimonie, Theod. 'Tis the same. Cleon. And he intreates, since lamenesse may excuse His not presenting it himselfe, from mee (Though far vnworthy to supplie his place) You would vouchsafe to accept it. Theod. Farther off, You haue told your tale. Stay you for a reward? Take that. Strikes him. Pulch. How's this? Chrys. I neuer saw him mou'd thus. Theo. Wee must not part so Sir, a guarde vpon him. Enter Garde. they all goe a side. Theod. May I not vent my sorrowes in the aire, Without discouerie? forbeare the roome, Yet be within call, what an earth-quake I feele in mee? And on the suddaine my whole fabrick totters. My blood within mee turnes, and through my vaines Parting with naturall rednesse I discerne it, Chang'd to a fatall yellow: what an army Of hellish furies in the horrid shapes Of doubts, and feares, charge on mee! rise to my rescue, Thou stout maintainer of a chaste wifes honor, The confidence of her vertues; bee not shaken With the wind of vaine surmises, much lesse suffer The diuell iealousie to whisper to mee My curious obseruation of that I must no more remember. Will it not bee? Thou vninuited ghest, ill mannerd monster, I charge thee leaue mee, wilt thou force mee to Giue fuell to that fire I would put out? The goodnesse of my memorie proues my mischiefe, And I would sell my Empire, could it purchase The dull art of forgetfulnesse. Who waites there? Timantus. Most sacred Sir. Theod. Sacred, as 'tis accurs'd Is proper to mee. Sirra, vpon your life, Without a word concerning this, command Exit Tim. Eudoxia to come to mee; would I had Nere knowne her by that name, my mothers name, Or that for her owne sake shee had continued Poore Athenais still.—No intermission? Wilt thou so soone torment mee? must I reade Writ in the table of my memorie, To warrant my suspition, how Paulinus (Though euer thought a man auerse to women) First gaue her entertainement? made her way For audience to my sister; then I did My selfe obserue how hee was rauish'd with The gratious deliuerie of her storie, (Which was I grant the bait that first took me too) Shee was his conuert, what the rethorick was Hee vs'd I know not, and since shee was mine, In priuate, as in publick, what a masse Of grace and fauours hath shee heap'd vpon him! And but to day this fatall fruite, Shee's come. Enter Timantus. Athenais. Flaccilla. Arcadia. Can shee bee guiltie? Ath. You seeme troubl'd Sir, My innocence makes mee bold to aske the cause That I may ease you of it, no salute After foure long houres absence? Theod. Prethee forgiue mee. Kisses her. Mee thanks I finde Paulinus on her lips, And the fresh Nectar that I drew from thence Is on the suddaine pal'd, how haue you spent Your hours since I last saw you? Ath. In the conuerse, Of your sweete sisters. Theod. Did not Philanax From mee deliuer you an apple? Ath. Yes Sir; Heauen! how you frowne! pray you talke of something els, Thinke not of such a trifle. Theod. How! a trifle? Does any toy from mee presented to you, Deserue to be so sleighted? doe you valewe What's sent, and not the sender? from a peasant It had deseru'd your thanks. Ath. And meetes from you Sir All possible respect. Theod. I priz'd it Lady At a higher rate then you beleeue, and would not Haue parted with it, but to one I did Prefer before my selfe. Ath. It was indeed The fairest that I euer saw. Theod. It was? And it had vertues in it, my Eudoxia Not visible to the eye. Ath. It may be so Sir, Theod. What did you with it, tell mee punctually; I looke for a strict accompt. Ath. What shall I answer? Theod. Doe you stagger? ha? Ath. No Sir, I haue eaten it. It had the pleasantest tast. I wonder that You found it not in my breath. Theod. I faith I did not, And it was wondrous strange. Ath: Pray you try againe. Theo. I find no scent of't heere. You play with me You haue it still? Ath. By your sacred life, and fortune, An oth I dare not breake, I haue eaten it. Theod. Doe you know how this oth binds? Ath. Too well, to breake it. Theod. That euer man to please his brutish sense Should slaue his vnderstanding to his passions, And taken with soone fading white and red Deliuer vp his credulous eares to heare The magick of a Siren, and from these Beleeue there euer was, is, or can bee More then a seeming honestie in bad woman Ath. This is strange language Sir. Theod. Who waites? come all. Nay sister not so neere, being of the sex, I feare you are infected to. Pulch. What meane you? Theod. To show you a miracle, a prodigie Which Affrick neuer: equall'd can you think This master peece of heauen, this pretious vellam, Of such a puritie, and virgin whitenesse, Could be design'd to haue periurie, and whoredome In capitall letters writ vpon't? Pulch. Deere Sir, Theod. Nay adde to this in impudence beyond All prostituted boldnesse. Art not dead yet? Will not the tempests in thy conscience rende thee As small as Atomes? that there may no signe Be left, thou euer wert so! wilt thou liue Till thou art blasted with the dreadfull lightning Of pregnant, and vnanswerable prooses, Of thy adulterous twines? dye yet that I With my honor may conceale it. Ath: Would long since, The Gorgon of your rage had turn'd mee marble, Or if I haue offended? Theod. If! good Angels! But I am tame: looke on this dombe accuser. Ath. O I am lost! Theod. Did euer cormorant Swollow his pray and then digest it whole As shee hath done this apple? Philanax, As 'tis, from me presented it. The good Lady Swore shee had eaten it; yet I know not how It came intire vnto Paulinus hands, And I from him receau'd it, sent in scorne Vpon my life to giue me a close touch, That he was wearie of thee. Was there nothing Left thee to see him, to giue satisfaction To thy infatiate lust, but what was sent As a deere fauour from mee? how haue I find In my dotage on this creature? but to her I haue liu'd, as I was borne, a perfit virgin. Nay more I thought it not enough to be True to her bed, but that I must feede high, To strengthen my abilities to cloye Her rauenous appetite, little suspecting Shee would desire a change. Ath. I neuer did Sir. Theod. Be dumbe, I will not waste my breath in taxing Thy base ingratitude. How I haue rais'd thee, Will by the world be to thy shame spoke often. But for that ribawd, who held in my Empire The next place to my selfe, so bound vnto me By all the tyes of duty, and allegeance Hee shall pay deere for't, and feele what it is In a wrong of such high consequence to pull downe, His Lords slow anger on him. Philanax, Hee's troubl'd with the goute, let him be cur'd With a violent death, and in the other world, Thanke his Physitian. Philanax. His cause vnheard Sir? Pulch. Take heede of rashnesse. Theod. Is what I command, To bee disputed? Philan. Your will shall bee done Sir: But that I am the instrument— Theod. Doe you murmur? Exit Phil with the gard: What couldst thou say if that my licence should, Giue liberty to this tongue? thou would'st dye? I am not Athen. kneeling, points to Theod. sword. So to bee reconcil'd, See mee no more. The sting of conscience euer gnawing on thee, A long life bee thy punishment. Exit Theod. Flacc. O sweete Lady How I could weepe for her! Arcad. Speake deare Madam, speake. Your tongue as you are a Woman, while you liue, Should bee euer mouing, at the least the last part That stirrs about you. Pul. Though I should sad Lady In pollicie reioyce, you as a riuall Of my greatenesse are remou'd, compassion, Since I beleeue you innocent, commands mee To mourne your fortune, credit mee I will vrge All arguments I can alleage that may Appease the Emperours furie. Arc. I will grow too, Vpon my knees, vnlesse hee bid mee rise, And sweare hee will forgiue you. Flacc. And repent too All this pother for an apple? Exeunt Pulcheria. Arcadia. Flaccilla. Chrys. Hope deare Madam, And yeeld not to despaire, I am still your seruant, And neuer will forsake you; though a while You leaue the court, and city, and giue way To the violent passions of the Emperour. Repentance in his want of you will soone finde him. In the meane time Ile dispose of you, and omit No opportunity that may inuite him To see his error. Athen. Oh! Wrangling her hands. Chrys. Forbeare for heau'ns sake: The ende of the fourth act.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Act. 5. Scæne 1. Philanac. Paulinus. Guard. Executioners. Paul. This is most barbarous! how haue you lost All feeling of humanity, as honor; In your consent alone to haue mee vs'd thus? But to bee as you are a looker on, Nay more a principall actor in't (the softnes Of your former life consider'd) almost turnes mee Into a senselesse statue. Philanax. Would long since Death by some other meanes had made you one, That you might bee lesse sensible of what You haue, or are to suffer. Paul. Am to suffer? Let such, whose happinesse, and heauen depend Vpon their present being feare to part with A fort they cannot long holde, mine to mee is A charge that I am wearie of, all defences By paine, and sickenesse batterd; Yet take heede, Take heede Lord Philanax, that for priuate spleene Or any false conceiued grudge against mee, (Since in one thought of wrong to you, I am Sincerely innocent) you doe not that My royall Master must in iustice punish, If you passe to your owne heart thorow mine The murther as it will come out discouer'd. Phil. I murther you my Lord? heau'n witnesse for mee With the restoring of your health, I wish you Long life, and happinesse: for my selfe I am Compell'd to put in execution that Which I would flie from, 'tis the Emperour, The high incensed Emperours will commands What I must see perform'd. Paul. The Emperour! Goodnesse, and innocence garde mee! wheeles, nor racks Can force into my memorie, the remembrance Of the least shadow of offence, with which I euer did prouoke him, though belou'd (And yet the peoples loue is short, and fatall) I neuer courted popular applause; Feasted the men of action, or labour'd By prodigall giftes to draw the needy souldier, The tribunes, or centurions to a faction, Of which I would rise vp the head against him. I hold no place of strength, fortresse, or castle In my command, that can giue sanctuarie To malecontents, or countenance rebellion. I haue built no palaces to face the court, Nor doe my followers brauerie shame his traine, And though I cannot blame my fate for want, My competent meanes of life deserues no enuie. In what then am I dangerous? Phil. His displeasure Reflects on none of those particulars, Which you haue mention'd, though some iealous Princes In a subiect cannot brooke 'em. Paul. None of these? In what then am I worthy his suspition? But it may, nay it must bee, some informer To whom my innocence appear d a crime, Hath poyson'd his late good opinion of mee. Tis not to dye, but in the censure of 'So good a Master guilty, that afflictes mee. Phil. There is no remedy. Paul. No, I haue a friend yet, Could the strictnesse of your warrant giue way to it, To whom the state I stand in now deliuer'd, That by faire intercession for mee would So far preuaile, that my defence vnheard I should not innocent, or guiltie suffer, Without a fit distinction. Phil. These false hopes My Lord abuse you. What man, when condemn'd, Did euer find a friend? or who dares lend An eye of pitty to that starcros'd subiect On whom his soueraigne frownes. Paul. Shee that dares plead For innocence without a fee, the Empresse, My greate, and gratious Mistrisse! Phil. There's your error. Her many fauours which you hop'd should make you, Proue your vndoing. Shee poore Lady is Bannish'd for euer from the Emperours presence, And his confirm'd suspition, to his wrong, That you haue bene ouer familiar with her, Doomes you to death. I know you vnderstand mee. Paul. Ouer familiar? Phil. In sharing with him, Those sweete and secret pleasures of his bed, Which can admit no partner. Paul. And is that The crime for which I am to dye? Of all My numerous sinnes, was there not one of waight Enough to sinke mee, if he borrow'd not The colour of a guilt I neuer saw, To paint my innocence, in a deform'd And monstrous shape? but that it were prophane To argue heauen of ignorance, or iniustice, I now should tax it. Had the stars that raign'd At my natiuity such cursed influence, As not alone to make mee miserable, But in the neighbourhood of her goodnesse to mee To force contagion vpon a Lady, Whose purer flames were not inferior, To theirs, when they shine brightest? to dye for her Compar'd with what shee suffers is a trifle. By her example warn'd, let all greate women Heereafter throw pride, and contempt on such As truely serue 'em, since a retribution In lawfull courtesies, is now stil'd lust, And to be thankfull to a seruants merits Is growne a vice, no vertue. Phil. These complaints Are to no purpose: think on the long flight, Your better part must make. Paul. Shee is prepar'd Nor can the freeing of an innocent From the Emperours furious iealousie hinder her. It shall out, 'tis resolu'd, but to bee whisper'd To you alone. What a solemne preparation Is made heere to put forth an inch of taper In it selfe almost extinguish'd? mortall poison? The hangmans sword, the halter? Phil. Tis left to you, To make choice of which you please. Paulinus. Any will serue, To take away my goute, and life together. I would not haue the Emperour imitate Romes Monster, Nero, in that cruell mercie Hee shew'd to Seneca; when you haue discharg'd What you are trusted with, and I haue giu'n you Reasons beyond all doubt, or disputation, Of the Empresses and my innocence, when I am dead, Since 'tis my Masters pleasure, and high treason In you not to obey it, I coniure you, By the hopes you haue of happinesse heereafter, Since mine in this world are now parting from mee, That you would win the young man to repentance Of the wrong done to his chaste wise Eudoxia, And if perchance hee shed a teare for what In his rashenesse hee impos'd on his true seruant, So it cure him of future iealousie, 'Twill proue a pretious balsamum, and finde mee When I am in my graue. Now when you please, For I am readie. Philanax. His words worke strangely on mee, And I would doe, but I know not what to thinke on't. Ex. Scæne 2. Pulcheria. Flaccilla. Arcadia. Timantus. Gratianus. Chrysapius. Pulch. Still in his sullen moo'd? no intermission Of his melancholy fit? Timantus. It rather Madam Increases, then grows lesse. Gratianus. In the next roome To his bed-chamber, wee watch'd, for hee by signes Gaue vs to vnderstand, hee would admit Nor company, nor conference. Pulch. Did hee take No rest as you could ghesse? Chrys. Not any Madam; Like a Numidian Lyon, by the cunning Of the desperate huntsman taken in a toyle, And forc'd into a spatious cage, hee walkes About his chamber, wee might heare him gnash His teeth in rage, which opend, hollow grones And murmurs issu'd from his lippes, like windes Imprison'd in the cauernes of the earth Striuing for liberty; and sometimes throwing His body on his bed, then on the ground, And with such violence, that wee more then fear'd And still doe, if the tempest of his passions By your wisdome bee not lay'd, hee will commit Some outrage on himselfe. Pulch. His better Angell, I hope will stay him from so foule a mischiefe, Nor shall my care bee wanting. Tim: Twice I heard him, Say false Eudoxia, how much art thou Vnworthy of these teares? then sigh'd, and straight Rores out Paulinus, was his goutie age To bee preferr'd before my strength and youth? Then groand againe, so many wayes expressing Th'afflictions of a tortur'd soule, that wee Who wept in vaine, for what wee could not helpe, Were sharers in his iuffrings. Pulch. Though your sorrow Is not to bee condemn'd, it takes not from The burthen of his miseries, wee must practise With some fresh obiect to diuert his thoughts From that they are wholly fix'd on. Chrys. Could I gaine The freedome of accesse, I would present him With this petition. Will your highnes please, A paper deliuer'd. To looke vpon it. You will soone finde there What my intents, and hopes are. Enter Theod. Gratianus. Hal 'tis hee. Pul. Stand close, And giue way to his passions, 'tis not safe To stoppe them in their violent course, before They haue spent themselues. Theod. I play the foole, and am Vnequall to my selfe, delinquents are To suffer, not the innocent. I haue done Nothing, which will not hold waight in the scale Of my impartiall iustice: neither feele The worme of conscience, vpbraiding mee For one blacke deed of tyranny; wherefore then Should I torment my selfe? great Iulius would not Rest satisfi'd that his wife was free from fact, But only for suspition of a crime S'ud a diuorce, nor was this Roman rigour Censur'd as cruell, and still the wise Italian, That knowes the honor of his family, Depends vpon the purity of his bed For a kisse, nay wanton looke, will plough vp mischiefe, And sowe the seedes of his reuenge in blood. And shall to whose power the law's a seruant, That stand accomptable to none, for what My will calls an offence, being compell'd, And on such grounds to raise an Altar to My anger, though I grant 'tis cemented With a loose strumpets and adulterers gore, Repent the iustice of my furie? no. I should not: yet still my excesse of loue Fed high in the remembrance of her choice And sweete embraces, would perswade mee that Conniuence, or remission of her fault, Made warrantable by her true submission For her offence, might bee excusable, Did not the crueltie of my wounded honor With an open mouth denie it. Pulch. I approue of Your good intention, and I hope 'twill prosper. Hee now seemes calme. Let vs vpon our knees Encompasse him. Most royall Sir, Flacc. Sweet brother. Arc. As you are our Soueraigne, by the tyes of nature You are bound to bee a Father in your care To vs poore Orphans. Timant. Shew compassion Sir, Vnto your selfe. Grat. The maiestie of your fortune Should flie aboue the reach of griefe. Chrys. And 'tis Impair'd, if you yeeld to it. Theod. Wherefore pay you This adoration to a sinfull creature? I am flesh, and blood as you are, sensible Of heat, and cold, as much a slaue vnto The tyrannie of my passions, as the meanest Of my poore subiects the proud attributes (By oil'd tongu'd flatterie impos'd vpon vs) As sacred, glorious, high, inuincible, The deputie of heauen, and in that Omnipotent, with all false titles els Coind to abuse our frailetie, though compounded, And by the breath of Sycophants appli'd, Cure not the least fit of an ague in vs. Wee may giue poore men riches; confer honors On vndeseruers; raise, or ruine such As are beneath vs, and with this puff'd vp, Ambition would perswade vs to forget That wee are men: but hee that sits aboue vs, And to whom, at our vtmost rate, wee are But pageant properties, derides our weakenesse. In mee to whom you kneele, 'tis most apparent. Can I call backe yesterday, with all their aides That bow vnto my scepter? or restore My minde to that tranquillitie, and peace It then inioy'd? can it make Eudoxia chaste? Or vile Paulinus honest? Pul. If I might Without offence, deliuer my opinion, Theod. What would you say? Pul. That on my soule the Empresse Is innocent. Chrys. The good Paulinus guiltlesse. Grat. And this should yeeld you comfort. Theod. In being guiltie Of an offence far, far transcending that They stand condemn'd for. Call you this a comfort? Suppose it could bee true? a corrasiue rather, Not to eate out dead flesh, but putrifie What yet is sown'd. was murther euer held A cure for iealousie? or the crying blood Of innocence, a balme to take away Her festring anguish? as you doe desire I should not doe a iustice on my selfe, Adde to the proofes by which Paulinus fell, And not take from 'em, in your charitie Sooner beleeue that they were false, then I Vnrighteous in my iudgement? subiects liues Are not their Princes tennisballs to bee banded In sport away, all that I can indure For them, if they were guilty, is an atome To the mountaine of affliction, I pull'd on mee, Should they proue innocent. Chrys. For your Maiesties peace I more then hope they were not; the false oth Tooke by the Empresse, and for which shee can Plead no excuse, conuicted her, and yeelds A sure defence for your suspition of her. And yet to be resolu'd, since strong doubts are More grieuous for the most part, then to know A certaine losse. Theod. 'Tis true Chrysapius, Were there a possible meanes. Chrys. 'Tis offer'd to you, If you please to embrace it. Some few minutes Make truce with passion, and but read, and follow What's there proiected, you shall finde a key, Will make your entrance easie to discouer Her secret thoughts, and then, as in your wisdome You shall thinke fit, you may determine of her, And rest confirm'd, whether Paulinus died A villaine or a Martyr. Theod. It may doe, Nay sure it must, yet howsoeuer it fall, I am most wretched which way in my wishes, I should fashion the euent, I am so distracted I cannot yet resolue of follow mee; Though in my name, all names are comprehended, I must haue witnesses, in what degree I haue done wrong, or suffer'd, Pulch. Hope the best Sir. Exeunt. Scæna 3. A sad song. Athenais in sackecloth. Her loose haire. Athen. VVhy art thou slow, thou rest of trouble, Death, To stoppe a wretches breath? That calls on thee, and offers her sad heart A prey unto thy dart. I am nor young, nor faire, bee therefore bold, Sorrow hath made mee old, Deform'd, and wrinkl'd, all that I can craue, Is quiet in my graue. Such as liue happy, hold long life a Iewell, But to mee thou art cruell: If thou end not my tedious miserie, And I soone cease to bee. Strike, and strike home then, pitty unto mee In one short hours delay is tyrannie. Thus like a dying Swan, to a sad tune I sing my owne dirg, would a requiem follow Which in my penitence, I despaire not of, This brittle glasse of life, already broken With misery, the long and quiet sleepe Of death would bee most welcome, yet before Wee end our pilgrimage, 'tis fit that wee Should leaue corruption, and foule sinnes behinde vs. But with wash'd feete, and hands, the Heathens dare not Enter their prophane temples; and for mee To hope my passage to eternitie Can bee made easie 'till I haue shooke of The burthen of my sinnes in free confession, Ayded with sorrow, and repentance for 'em, Is against reason. 'Tis not laying by My royall ornaments, or putting on This garment of humility, and contrition, The throwing dust, and ashes on my head; Long fasts to tame my proud flesh, that can make Attonement for my soule, that must be humbled, All outward signes of penitence, els are vselesse. Chrysapius did assure mee, hee would bring mee A holy man, from whom (hauing discouer'd My secret crying sinnes) I might receiue Full absolution, and hee keepes his word. Welcome most reuerend Sir, vpon my knees I entertaine you. Enter Theodosius, like a frier, with Chrysapius. Theod. Noble Sir forbeare, The place, the sacred office that I come for, Commandes all priuacie. My penitent daughter, Bee carefull, as you wish remission from mee, That in confession of your sinnes, you hide not One crime, whose ponderous waight, when you would make Your flights aboue the firmament, that may sincke you: A foolish modestie in concealing ought Is now far worse then impudence to professe, And iustifie your guilte, bee therefore free So may the gates of mercie open to you. Athenais. First then, I aske a pardon, for my being Ingratefull to heau'ns bountie. Theod. A good entrance. Ath. Greatenesse comes from aboue, and I rais'd to it From a low condition, sinfully forgot From whence it came, and looking on my selfe In the false glasse of flatterie, I receiu'd it As a debt due to my beautie, not a gift Or fauour from the Emperour. Theod. 'Twas not well. Ath. Pride wayted on vnthankfulnesse, and no more Remembring the compassion of the Princesse, And the meanes shee vs'd to make mee what I was, Contested with her, and with sore eyes seing Her greater light, as it dimm'd mine, I practis'd To haue it quite put out. Theod. A greate offence, But on repentance not vnpardonable. Forward. Athenais. O Father, what I now must vtter, I feare in the deliuerie will destroy mee, Before you haue absolu'd mee. Theod. Heau'n is gratious. Out with it. Athenais. Heau'n commands vs to tell truth. Yet I most sinfull wretch, forswore my selfe. Theod. On what occasion? Ath. Quite forgetting that An innocent truth can neuer stand in need Of a guiltie lye, being on the suddaine ask'd By the Emperour my husband, for an Apple Presented by him, I swore I had eaten it, When my grieu'd conscience too well knowes, I sent it To comfort sicke Paulinus, being a man, I truely lou'd and fauour'd. Theod. A cold sweate, Like the iuice of Hemlocke bathes mee. aside. Ath. And from this A furious iealousie getting possession Of the good Emperours heart, in his rage hee doom'd The innocent Lord to dye, my periurie The fatall cause of murther. Theod. Take heed daughter, You niggle not with your conscience, and religion, In stiling him an innocent from your feare, And shame to accuse your selfe. The Emperour Had many spies vpon you, saw such graces, Which vertue could not warrant, showr'd vpon him; Glances in publick, and more liberall fauours In your priuate chamber meetings, making way For foule adulterie; nor could hee bee But sensible of the compact pass'd betweene you, To the ruine of his honor. Ath. Heare mee Father, I look'd for comfort, but in this you come To adde to my afflictions. Theod. Cause not you Your owne damnation, in concealing that Which may in your discouerie finde forgiuenesse. Open your eyes, set heauen, or hell before you. In the reuealing of the truth, you shall Prepare a palace for your soule to dwell in, Stor'd with celestiall blessings; whereas if You palliate your crime, and dare beyond Playing with lightning, in concealing it, Expect a dreadfull dungeon, fill'd with horror, And neuer-ending torments. Ath. May they fall Eternally vpon mee, and increase, When that which wee call time hath lost its name; May lightning cleaue the centre of the earth, And I sinke quicke, before you haue absolu'd mee, Into the bottomlesse Abysse, I feuer In one vnchaste desire, nay in a thought I wrong'd the honor of the Emperours bed. I doe deserue, I grant, more then I suffer In that my feruor, and desire to please him, In my holy meditations press'd vpon me, And would not bee kept out, now to dissemble (When I shall suddainely bee insensible, Of what the world speaks of mee) were meere madnesse: And though you are incredulous, I presume, If as I kneele now, my eyes swolne with teares, My hands heaud vp thus, my stretch'd heartstrings ready To breake a sunder, my incensed Lord (His storme of iealousie blowne ore) should heare mee, Hee would beleeue I lied not. Theod. Rise, and see him, discouers himselfe. On his knees with ioy affirme it. Ath. Can this bee? Theod. My sisters, and the rest there, all beare witnesse. Enter Pulcheria, Arcadia. Flaccilla. Chrysapius. Gratianus. Timantus. In freeing this incomparable Lady From the suspition of guilt, I doe Accuse my selfe, and willingly submit To any penance, shee in iustice shall Please to impose vpon mee. Ath. Royall Sir, your ill opinion of mee's soone forgiuen. Pul. But how you can make satisfaction to The poore Paulinus, hee being dead, in reason You must conclude impossible. Theod. And in that I am most miserable; the Ocean Of ioy, which in your innocence flow'd high to mee, Ebb's in the thought of my vniust command, By which hee died. O Philanax (as thy name Interpreted speakes thee) thou hast euer bene A louer of the King, and thy whole life Can witnesse thy obedience to my will, In putting that in execution, which Was trusted to thee, say but yet this once Thou hast not done what rashly I commanded, And that Paulinus liues, and thy reward For not performing that which I inioin'd thee, Shall centuple what euer yet thy dutie, Or merit challeng'd from mee. Phil. 'Tis too late Sir. Hee's dead, and when you know hee was vnable To wrong you, in the way that you suspected, You'll wish it had bene otherwise. Theod. Vnable? Phil. I am sure hee was an Eunuch, and might safely Lye by a Virgins side, at foure yeares made one, Though to hold grace with Ladies hee conceald it. The circumstances, and the manner how You may heare at better leasure. Theod. How! an Eunuch? The more the proofes are, that are brought to cleare thee, My best Eudoxia, the more my sorrowes. Athen. That I am innocent? Theod. That I am guiltie Of murther, my Eudoxia. I will build A glorious monument to his memorie, And for my punishment liue, and dye vpon it, And neuer more conuerse with men. Enter Paulinus. Paulin. Liue long Sir, May I doe so to serue you, and if that I liue does not displease you, you owe for it To this good Lord. Theod. My selfe, and all that's mine. Philan. Your pardon is a payment. Theod. I am rap'd With ioy beyond my selfe. Now my Eudoxia My iealousie puff'd away thus, in this breath I scent the naturall sweetenesse. Kisses her. Arcad. Sacred Sir, I am happy to behold this, and presume, Now you are pleas'd, to moue a sute, in which My sister is ioyn'd with mee. Theod. Prethee speake it, For I haue vow'd to heare before I grant, I thanke your good instructions. Arc. 'Tis but this Sir, Wee haue obseru'd the falling out, and in, Betweene the husband and the wife showes rarely, Their iarres, and reconcilements strangely take vs. Flac. Anger and iealousie that conclude in kisses Is a sweete war in sooth. Arc. Wee therefore, brother Most humbly beg you would prouide vs husbands That wee may tast the pleasure of't. Flac. And with speede Sir, For so your fauour's doubl'd. Theod. Take my word, I will with all conuenience; and not blush Heereafter to bee guided by your counsailes. I will deserue your pardon. Philanax Shall bee remembred, and magnificent bounties Fall on Chrysapius. My grace on all. Let Cleon bee deliuer'd and rewarded, My grace on all, which as I len'd to you, Returne your vowes to heauen, that it may please (As it is gratious) to quench in mee All future sparkes of burning iealousie. THE END.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">EPILOGVE. Wee haue reason to be doubtfull, whether hee On whom (forc'd to it by necessitie) The maker did conferre his Emperours part Hath giuen you satisfaction, in his art Of action and deliuerie; 'tis sure truth The burden was too heauie for his youth To vndergoe: but in his will wee know Hee was not wanting, and shall euer owe With, his, our seruice, if your fauours daine To giue him strength, heereafter to sustaine A greater waight. It is your grace that can In your allowance of this write him man Before his time, which if you please to doe You make the Player, and the Poet too.</field>
   </doc>
</add>