<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">King, William, 1663-1712</field>
      <field name="author_facet">King, William, 1663-1712</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">king william 1663 1712</field>
      <field name="author_text">King, William, 1663-1712</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">18th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1710's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V2.0677.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1712</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460299</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Tragi-Comedy of Joan of Hedington</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Tragi-Comedy of Joan of Hedington</field>
      <field name="title_facet">tragi comedy of joan of hedington</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">tragi comedy of joan of hedington</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Tragi-Comedy of Joan of Hedington</field>
      <field name="year_display">1712</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1712</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1712</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460299&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460299&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;King, William, 1663-1712&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;king william 1663 1712&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Tragi-Comedy of Joan of Hedington&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;tragi comedy of joan of hedington&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1712&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1712&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;King, William&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1663&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1712&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Tragi-Comedy of Joan of Hedington&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for Bernard Lintott [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1712&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872617-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv20677&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 18th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;18th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Tragi-Comedy of Joan of Hedington&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 33 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Only verse drama included&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Joan of Hedington.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragi-comedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1712.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Unknown.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Tragi-Comedy of Joan of Hedington. In Imitation of Shakespear.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Dramatis Personæ. MEN. Mr. Pindar, a young Gentleman, and a great Disputant, who had made a Progress in Moral Philosophy, and has a Notion of Friendship, as an Heroic Virtue, and therefore is very faithful to Mr. Cole; but he has no great Insight into Casuistical Divinity, which makes him undertake a Murder to pleasure his Friend. Mr. Cole, a West-country Gentleman, who is of an Amorous Temper, and very easie Nature, as appears by the Indulgence he shews to Mrs. Frances, and the Tenderness he bears to her Mother. Father Clerkenwell and Mr. Atson, two North-Country brawny Fellows, very powerful at their Ale and Tobacco. The Church-warden, a considerate discreet Person, and very compassionate, though something negligent in not having presented the Enormities of the Persons living in his Parish. Persons mentioned. Mr. Warburton, a deceas'd Lover of Mrs. Frances Harris. Mr. Hopman, a fictitious Name. Crendon, a famous Bag-piper, not admitted. WOMEN. Mother Shephard, a prudent Person in her way of selling Ale, virtuously inclin'd, but suffering her Customers to run into Excess out of Hopes of her own Advantage. Mother Franklin, a Person that concerns her self with little but the Offices of her Function, which are Brewing and Bottling of Ale, and at the same time very Neighbourly. Joan of Hedington, a Country Woman, and an ancient Parishioner in Hedington, of a Calling which though discommendable, yet has been made use of in all Ages; she seems Spirituous, and, if her Employment would suffer her, not disinclinable to Virtuous Courses, at least she despises the more vile Practises of others of the same Profession. Mother Harris, one the same Calling with Joan, who though she pretends to more Gentility, yet has not the same Plainness and Sincerity as the former. Mrs. Frances Harris, a Jilt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE Hedington. Time of Action from bringing up Mr. Church-warden's Cows, to the end of Milking them.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The PROLOGUE. Gallants, we here present you with a Play, The Product of a Country Holiday. 'Tis usual now with Prologues to be Witty, But we are not; good Faith, the more the Pity! Our Play won't make ye Laugh, nor make ye Cry, For 'tis a perfect Tragi-comedy. We have no hopes for this our homely Treat, But that for being short you'll think it sweet.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. SCENE I. SCENE the High Street in Hedington. Enter Mother Shephard and the Church-warden. Mother Shephard. Indeed, Mr. Church-warden, as I was saying before, this same Joan of Hedington is a naughty Woman. Church-warden. I cannot help it, Neighbour. Mother Shephard. She does not keep a Civil House, and is a Disgrace to the Town, for Gentlemen dare not come to my House to drink, for fear they should be thought to go to Joan's. Church-w. Have you good Ale, Mother? Mother Shephard. Yes that I have marry. Church-w. Why then People will come for all Joan, I warrant you. But I must go fetch up the Cows. Ha! Here are Gentlemen a coming. Mother Shephard. He! A Pox on them. They are going to Franklin's. However, I have got some good North-Country Customers still; and here are two of them coming. SCENE II. Enter Father Clerkenwell and Mr. Atson. Mother Shephard. You are very welcom Masters, I am glad to see you. Father Clerkenwell. Have you got good ripe Ale, Mother? Mother Shephard. Yes indeed, Sir, but I have but a little. Atson. How much? Mother Shephard. A dozen and a half. Father Clerkenwell. What's that between us two? But come let's go in. Wash the Two-Quart Mug, for I am a-dry; two of them may quench my Thirst a little for the present. Stay, give us a Quarter of Tobacco. [Exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. SCENE I. SCENE the High Street. Enter Joan of Hedington and Mother Harris. Joan Hedington. Marry come up, you are so proud with your N. B. Joan wore a Hat, and Mother Harris a Hood. black Bag. Mother Harris. Well, 'twas none of your Mony paid for't. Joan Hedington. But your Daughter's did. You are so proud of that Minks, and think to spoil my Custom—But I would have you to know that I am sounder than e'er a Harris of you all. Mother Harris. You sounder! I'd have you to know I scorn to let such pitiful Rogues come into my House as you have to do with. Joan Hedington. I'd have you to know I have as good Customers come to my House as any Woman in Hedington, no Dsgrace to you, Goody Harris. Mother Harris. Sure you might have had a Mistress under your Girdle when you spoke to me, Hussey. Joan Hedington. Hussey me no Hussey, Mrs. Slopdawdry. I'll pull your black Bag for you. I am a better Woman than your self, I have been an old Parishioner here, and gone to Church and all the Town know I have been honest in my Calling; and to be abused by such a Gossip as you, that are come to put off your Pocky Ware in our Parish! Mother Harris. No more Pocky Ware than your self. Joan Hedington. You lye, you Whore, I'll tear your Eyes out. [Fall a fighting, Joan beats Mother Harris off the Stage, calling her Whore and Bitch, the other crying. SCENE II. The High-street. Joan of Hedington sola. Let's view the mighty Act which I have done: The thing is worthy Joan of Hedington. I that have favour'd Youngsters many a Score, Was ne'er affronted at this Rate before By such an Upstart, Tawdry, Pocky Whore; She from the Maggotty Pie away was sent, Because she had not Trade to pay her Rent. At Hinksey then they would not let her stay, Because she kept a Bawdy-house, they say; But now I think I have given the Whore her due. Shall I be hussied by a Bitch like you! No, I have beat her, and the Drab is gone, I will reign Mistress of this Place alone, And be the Topping Dame of Hedington. But I think I had best go home and drink a Dram of Brandy. [Exit Joan.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. SCENE I. SCENE Mother Harris's House. Enter Mother Harris, Frank Harris, and Mr. Cole. Frank Harris. This is intolerable, that my Mother should be abused by such a Drab as Joan of Hedington, I'll be revenged whatever it costs me. [Mother Harris groans. Mr. Cole. Alas, my Dear, torment thy self no more, And you, dear Mother, cease to Sob and Groan, For let me never more be happy made By the Enjoyment of my lovely Frances, If I don't satisfie your dire Revenge. Mother Harris. Ay Mr. Cole, nothing could oblige me and my Daughter more, than if you would revenge me on that Witch. Frank Harris. Ay, do my Dear, study how to revenge my Mother of that Witch; you're a Scholar, can't you Conjure? [Cole walks about Musing. Mr. Cole. I'll break her Windows; Windows she has none, And then her Lattice is not worth the breaking. I'll go and drink her Brandy, and not pay her; But not to pay for't would be Ungentile, And I can ne'er be guilty of a thing that does not favour of a Gentleman. But stay, I have a Friendship with a certain Man, Cunning and close, and trusty to his Friend, Pindar, my Eyes Delight, my other Self; He promis'd me that Disputations done He'd take a Walk, and meet me at this Place. Oh for his coming now when most I want him! He'll find a speedy Way to my Revenge, And gratifie my Mother and my Mistress. Two Heads are always wiser far than One, And when to mine his Counsels shall be joyn'd, We'll plague this Saucy Joan, with Force united. I believe, Mrs. Frances, 'twould do your Mother good to drink some of this warm Flip. Mother Harris. I can't drink Flip, if 'twas Flip of Gold, till I'm reveng'd. Frank Harris. Dear Mr. Cole, help my Mother but in this one Business, and I'll love you better than ever I did Mr. Warberton. Mr. Cole. Blessing attend you for this last Expression. O what a vast Reward is this you promise! Thy Love, for which I many a time would die, Is to be gain'd now upon Easie Terms. Were Joan on t'other side of Shotover, And all the Way stuck full of Bears and Lyons; Were Snakes and Camels there, and living Toads, I'd fetch her tho' six Giants stood to guard her. This I could do alone with single Strength, But when I shall have Pindar's Force and Council I'd dare—Indeed what would I not dare then. Mother Harris. I think you must carry me to the Bed, to lie down a little. Frank Harris. Pray Mother stay a little, here's Crendon the Bagpiper. Mother Harris. Musick encreases Melancholy Thoughts: But brings no Ease to Minds oppress'd with Grief. [They carry her off. SCENE II. Joan's House. Enter Father Clerkenwell and Atson. Father Clerkenwell. Here Who is within here! give me a Quartern of Brandy. Atson. And me another. Joan, we must go up the Stone Stairs. Joan Hedington. Hold, two Words to a Bargain, you owe me a Groat for last Time. Father Clerkenwell. Joan, where's your Helper? Joan Hedington. She is gone a Hay-making. Father Clerkenwell. Well then, I will go to Mother Harris. Joan Hedington. Rather than that I will do any thing, Wipe off old Scores, and let you run on new; I freely do forgive the Groat you owe me, But mention not, oh, speak not any more That odious, filthy, pocky Name of Harris; For when I hear it once, my curdled Blood Chills at my Heart, and trembles in my Veins. Be'nt so unkind, dear Clerky, to go thither; I vow you make me weep with your Unkindness. Father Clerkenwell. I be'nt unkind Joany, I vow you make me cry too. I wo'nt go Joany, I wo'nt. Atson. No, he shan't go. Come let's all three go up Stairs, and be Friends, and bid your Husband burn us a Pint of Brandy. [Exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT IV. SCENE I. SCENE A Field adjacent to Mother Harris her House. Enter Mr. Pindar and Mr. Cole. Mr. Pindar. I tell you Friend, from henceforth be at Ease, The Lovely Frances soon shall be your own, And Mother Harris have her wish'd Revenge. Mr. Cole. Thou best of Friends, let me embrace thee close; Let's both away and perfect thy Design. Mr. Pindar. Hold, you must stay behind; I'll act alone, To shew how much Pindar will do for Cole. You in my Absence comfort up your Mother, Put Sugar in her Ale, 'twill ease her Grief; And you and gentle Frances search the Henroost, That when I bring home News of your Revenge, With a large Dish you Lovers may be ready In Eggs and Bacon to proclaim my Welcome. But hold, I want a Rope. Mr. Cole. Here's one lies ready. Mr. Pindar. 'Tis well, Good-buy. [Exeunt. Mr. Cole. Now you propitious Stars be Guides to Pindar, For never Man so freely undertook To serve his Friend in such a Dangerous Moment. SCENE II. Mother Harris's Parlour. Enter Frank Harris leading Mother Harris, and Mr. Cole. Mother Harris. Lord Mr. Cole, that sugar'd Ale was very good, I did not care if we had the other Flaggon. Enter Mrs. Franklin. Mrs. Franklin. I'm sorry to see you so ill, Mrs. Harris; that same Joan's a sawcy Hussey, she beat me one Day too. Mr. Cole. Ah Mrs. Franklin, this is kindly done, to come to comfort us in our Distress. Mother Franklin. I am willing to do any Neighbourly Kindness; Lord forsooth you are black and blue, you must put on some wet Brown Paper. Mr. Cole. [Aside to Frank Harris.] This Mrs. Franklin is a very good Woman, she understands Chirurgery I see. Will you please to walk in and Drink, Mrs. Franklin? [Exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT V. SCENE I. SCENE Joan's House. Joan of Hedington, and Mr. Pindar. Joan. I'm glad they are gone, they were two swinging Fellows. Enter Mr. Cole. Mr. Cole. How do you do, Joan? Joan Hedington. Pretty well Sir; tho' I must beg your Pardon, I don't remember your Name. Mr. Cole. I believe not. I was never here before. But Mr. Hopman, of Cripsy, recommended me to you for a Gill of Brandy, and a Firk or two up the Stone Stairs, little Joan,—up the Stone Stairs, little Joan. Joan Hedington. Will you please, Sir, to have your Brandy before you go up, or burn'd against you come down? Mr. Cole. Against I come down, little Joan. SCENE II. Joan's Chamber. Mr. Cole and Joan of Hedington. Pind. solus.] I'll do it, and yet methinks my Heart relents. Why should I murder her that never hurt me? Not me indeed, but sure my Friend is me, And since this Joan has dar'd to be so bold To injure Cole, she must have injur'd Pindar. Hence then Compassion, and all tender Thoughts, For Mother Harris soon shall be reveng'd, And by this Hand of mine. Enter Joan. My Dear, come sit down upon the Bed little Joany. [As she is going to sit down he tosses the Noose of the Rope over her Head. Joan Hedington. What's this for? Mr. Cole. No hurt, little Joan! no hurt! [He pulls the Noose, and ties her up to the Beam. 'Tis done, and now I'll instantly to Cole, And bring him joyful News of his Revenge. [Ex. SCENE III. Mother Shephard's House. Mother Shephard, and the Church-warden. Church-warden. Lord, Mother, have you heard the News? Mother Shephard. No not I, what News? Church-warden. Why, there's such a Clutter about Joan's Door, you'd admire at it; poor Joan has been almost hang'd. A Scholar came and tied her up to a Beam in her Chamber, and if her Husband had not come and cut her down, she had been hanged by this time. Mother Shephard. Well, I always said she would come to a bad End; 'tis but what she deserves for being such a Whore. Church-warden. Well, I'm glad the poor Woman is not hanged for all that. Mother Shephard. Women whose Honour should be still their Guide, When once they give it up, and go aside, Into a numerous Maze of Mischiefs run, As may be seen by Joan of Hedington.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">EPILOGUE. Our Play is done, and if it chance to please, We shall be mighty glad, and much at Ease; But if it shou'd not please you, Sirs! what then! Why our young Poet ne'er will write again, For he's as Proud and Surly as old Ben.</field>
   </doc>
</add>