<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Daniel, George, 1789-1864</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Daniel, George, 1789-1864</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">daniel george 1789 1864</field>
      <field name="author_text">Daniel, George, 1789-1864</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1810's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V3.0144.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1818</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460575</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Doctor Bolus ; A Serio-Comic-Bombastick-Operatick Interlude</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Doctor Bolus ; A Serio-Comic-Bombastick-Operatick Interlude</field>
      <field name="title_facet">doctor bolus</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">doctor bolus</field>
      <field name="title_text">Doctor Bolus ; A Serio-Comic-Bombastick-Operatick Interlude</field>
      <field name="year_display">1818</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1818</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1818</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460575&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460575&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Daniel, George, 1789-1864&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;daniel george 1789 1864&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Doctor Bolus ; A Serio-Comic-Bombastick-Operatick Interlude&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;doctor bolus&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1818&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1818&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Daniel, George&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1789&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1864&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Doctor Bolus&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Serio-Comic-Bombastick-Operatick Interlude&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for W. and J. Lowndes [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1818&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872919-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv30144&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Doctor Bolus&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Serio-Comic-Bombastick-Operatick Interlude&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 52 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Doctor Bolus.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Burlesque.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1818.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 21 Jul 1818.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DOCTOR BOLUS; A SERIO-COMIC-BOMBASTICK-OPERATICK INTERLUDE</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DRAMATIS PERSONÆ. King Artipadiades Mr. Harley General Scaramoucho Mr. W. S. Chatterley Dillydundos, his Aid-de-camp Mr. Lancaster Doctor Bolus, the King's Physician Mr. Wilkinson Gaoler Mr. Salter Herald Mr. Richardson Fiddlers Messrs. Hart and Brown Ghost Mr. Huckel Queen Katalinda Miss Kelly Poggylina, Maid of Honour Miss J. Stevenson Mopsa, Maid of Honour Mrs. Pincott Mute Assistant Maid of Honour Miss Dennett. Courtiers, Soldiers, &amp;c.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE I. A Court-yard in the King's Palace.—Enter Doctor Bolus and Courtiers. AIR—Bolus and Courtiers. (Tune—“O dear! what can the matter be?”) O dear! what can the matter be! Dear, dear, what can the matter be! O dear, what can the matter be! Our Queen sure the ghost will give up. Here is a wretched, unfortunate pack of us— His Majesty will make an end, in a crack, of us; O 'twill be Dickey with ev'ry man Jack of us!— [The King appears at a window above. King. Zooks, what a noise you kick up! Bolus. Artipadiades! pray smooth your brow, Her Majesty, the Queen is— King. What's the row? Now, by my sword of vengeance, so much dreaded, You all of ye deserve to be beheaded! Bolus. My honour'd Liege, the Queen will die. King. Then let her! Bolus. She's got the cholic, Sire. King. So much the better! Bolus. She'll kick the bucket— King. Silence! prithee hush! My Lords, and Doctor B?, you'd better brush. [The King shuts the window. The Scene closes.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE II. An Apartment in the Palace—Enter the King, to soft music. King. Whether first nature, or long course of drinking, Has made me doat on brandy, I've been thinking; By punch inspir'd, the minutes quickly roll, It suits the jovial habit of my soul! But, ah! I feel a sort of flutt'ring here, I'm rather comical, and somewhat queer: See, Poggylina comes: ye Pow'rs above! I shouldn't be surpriz'd if I'm in love. Enter Poggylina. Poggy. Your Majesty will pardon this intrusion. King. What charming modesty! what sweet confusion! I'll tell her of my passion, try to carry her, And should the Queen pop off—egad I'll marry her! Fair Poggylina, upon such a thing dumb I cannot be; my heart's a little kingdom Wherein you reign;—in short, to drop all metaphor, You've gain'd my love, which you shall be the better for. Poggy. Be still, my heart! King. I've that within, sweet wench, Which not the Lunnun Water-works can quench; A raging fire, that burns me to a coal:— Mine is a desp'rate case, upon my soul! AIR—King. (Tune—“O no, my Love! no!”) What beautiful vision before me is bright'ning! My soul is in flames, and I glow with desire; Those eyes, so bewitching, are flashes of lightning, To set both my heart and my kingdom on fire. Then smile on my passion, nor cruelly mock it; Behold a poor King on his marrowbones fall! Here, take ev'ry farden I have in my pocket, My Crown, Star and Garter, my Sceptre and all! Poggy. I can hold out no longer—don't deceive me, For I shall cry my eyes out if you leave me. King. When I prove false, may pride forsake the flirt, Lawyers hate fees, and poets wear a shirt; On cabbage-stalks may honeysuckles grow— Enter Scaramoucho from behind. Scara. The King with Poggylina; there's a go! Poggy. And when I run your Majesty my rigs, May monkies play at cards, and sapient pigs, Like Toby, give their Converzationes, To entertain their fashionable cronies. King. Of this enough:—we'll some refreshment try; My joy is hungry, and my love is dry. Poggy. A good proposal! let us in to lunch. King. And wet our whistles with a glass of punch. [Exeunt King and Poggylina. Scaramoucho comes forward. Scara. I'll turn a rebel ere to-morrow's sun; The odds are in my favour, ten to one! I will dethrone this Monarch, trounce the jade, False Poggylina—dammee, who's afraid? AIR.—Scaramoucho. (Tune—“The Dandy, O!”) I'm a soldier ready made, and fighting is my trade, At rank and file, retreat and charge, quite handy, O; To Mars I am bound 'prentice, I kill my foes by twenties, And live on smoke, fire, gunpowder, and brandy, O! When standing with my hat off, I look like Hetman Platoff, Or some fierce, powder'd, whisker'd, German grandee, O; Geramb or Scheffenhausen, or wonderful Munchausen, Or Blucher, that old redoubtable dandy, O. Then, King, 'twixt you and I, I'd have you mind your eye, For, 'pon my word, I do not understand ye, O! And Poggylina you your coquetry shall rue, When I mill that royal lad o' wax, your dandy, O. [Exit.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE III. A Chamber—Queen Katalinda sitting in a pensive manner, with her Maids of Honour—Two Fiddlers attending. Queen. If music be the food of love, I crave, Good Gentlemen, the favour of a stave! [They play. That melancholy strain to heav'n would carry me: Play something soothing—“Nobody's coming to Marry Me.” [They play “Nobody's coming to Marry Me.” Enter King. King. Zounds! here's a pretty dust! a precious frolic! Madam, is this the way you cure the cholic? Queen. That air, methinks, it had a dying fall! King. Base Catgut Scrapers! Devil take ye all! [Kicks them out. Avaunt, and quit my sight! and you, too, ladies; I want to tell the Queen that she a jade is. [Exeunt Mopsa and Poggylina. DUET.—King and Queen. (Tune—“Madam Fig's Gala.”) King. Come, Queen, you had better be quiet, A truce to your airs and your graces; Don't breed in my palace a riot, Or I'll soon let you know whose the place is. Queen. I laugh at your threats full of spite, And them you shall see I'll be kind for; So, if you are willing to fight, Come, let us see what you've a mind for. Rum ti, &amp;c. &amp;c. King. Here's a virago! here's a shrew, beshrew me! Her pipe's so dev'lish shrill, it quite goes thro' me. Queen. You've grown a downright savage. King. Don't provoke me! Queen. A Hottentot, by Jingo! King. Rage will choak me! Soon, Madam, I will better manners teach you, Our Chancellor, Lord Wigsby, shall impeach you: The bus'ness shall be done as soon as said; You'll look quite comical without your head. Queen. I scorn your boasting threats, whate'er your rigs be, I'll more than prove a match for you and Wigsby; I know your pranks, I'm up to all your tricks: Does Poggylina still your passion fix? King. (Aside) I'm smok'd! I must dissemble.—Poggylina Has neither beauty, modesty, nor rhino; I hate the wench—she's no more like my love, Than a Pea-hen is like a Turtle-dove; A Cat a King, a Lord a Country Bumpkin; A Frog a Fly, a Pine-apple a Pumpkin! Queen. Celestial sounds! O let them mount the sky, And tell the Gods and Goddesses on high, Bacchus, Apollo, Jupiter, and Juno, The happiness, my Liege, that I and you know: Passion, avaunt!—no more I'll taste the cup Of jealousy:—let's kiss, and make it up. King. Agreed—(Aside.) We Monarchs, when our wives are civil, Must sometimes hold the candle to the Devil! DUET.—King and Queen. (Tune.—“Over the Water to Charley.”) Queen. My Daisy, my Darling, give over this snarling, I did not intend to ill use you; King. To chide me was cruel; come, kiss me, my Jewel: Queen. Here goes, for I cannot refuse you. In the best govern'd houses, some wives by their spouses Will never submit to be check'd, Love; And a dust now and then with the dearest of men— King. Is what married folks must expect, Love. [Enter a Herald with his Wig awry. King. Soul of a Grasshopper! wherefore those alarms? Herald. My Leige, brave Scaramoucho, is in arms; He vows destruction, swears he'll have your life, or Your Crown:—his Force, two Drummers and a Fifer; Some ten or twenty Soldiers ta'en at random, With a blind Sergeant Major to command 'em. King. Presumptuous slave! hie to my royal stud, And saddle Dobbin, that rare bit of blood! Fetch me my patent blunderbuss and spurs, That I may punish these rebellious curs; And, as for Scaramoucho, woe betide him! My soul is up in arms;—I long to hide him! [Exeunt King and Herald. Queen. Ah! cruel fate! [Enter Scaramoucho, disguised. What means that martial figure? 'Tis Scaramoucho's form, though rather bigger. [He throws off his disguise. 'Tis he! 'tis he!—I die—I swoon—I faint! Scara. She's dead as mutton—dammee if she an't! [Re-enter the King, unperceived. King. What noise was that? ha, ha! confound her mewing! Here's a fine dish of cuckoldom a brewing! To watch their pranks, my Kingship I'll deposit Ods blazes, squibs, and crackers! in this closet. [Goes into the closet. Scara. Look up, my Love. Queen. I'm something better now— O Scaramoucho, here's a pretty row! But ere we talk of bus'ness, answer, Dear, This question,—how the devil came you here? Scara. In this disguise, the outposts of the town I pass'd, and tipp'd the sentinels a crown; Next at the palace gate I bargain'd hard, It cost me one pound one to bribe the guard— But quickly let us fly—deuce take this reck'ning! Sly Cupid sits upon your shoulder beck'ning. Queen. I fear you gammon me. Scara. Hear this, great Mars, Juno and Jupiter, Sun, Moon and Stars! When Aldgate-pump shall stand in Paul's church-yard, And the King's Sceptre be a Tailor's Yard; When London-bridge shall come to Waterloo, Men walk on four legs, donkies walk on two; When in Fleet-ditch we catch Newcastle salmon, Then, Katalinda, you may say I gammon. DUET.—Queen and Scaramoucho. (Tune.—“When I was an Infant, the Gossips would say.”) Scara. Please your Majesty, let us away, Come, my Sweeting, Drums are beating, Cupid mocks our dull delay; So march along with your soldier. Queen. You'll persuade me, do what I can, How I could blush if I had my fan! O, what sport Will be at the court When they hear that the Queen run away with a Man! Both. All the world and his wife will be there, Jilting, vapouring, Grinning, capering, How the Lords and Ladies will stare, And envy me/you and my/your soldier. [Exeunt Queen and Scaramoucho, Maids of Honour following. King comes forward from the Closet. King. There needs no further proof—the murder's out! My horns begin to grow—I feel 'em sprout! To be, or not to be—aye, that's a puzzler! My Queen, heav'n bless her mug! has grown a guzzler: If I could pour within her royal throttle Of Cordial Balm of Gilead half a bottle, 'Twould do her bus'ness without fear or risk; Then hey for Poggylina and a frisk! AIR.—King. (Tune.—“Och, Whack! Cupid's a Manikin.”) Rogue, liar—vile Scaramoucho! He shall be dish'd, by Jupiter, an' he stir! Blood, fire—Pistol in pouch O— I'll rap his breadbasket, I'll crack his canister! For he's my rival, and basely cornutes me— A rascal obscene, Who gallants with my Queen; But if, as the devil would have it, he shoots me— From his shot, And what not, Let his Granny stir— Blood, fire—vile Scaramoucho, I'll rap your breadbasket, I'll crack your canister! Enter Doctor Bolus. Bolus. (Aside) The King is in a passion, singing solus. King. Thrice welcome to my presence, Doctor Bolus! Bolus. (Aside) His tone is alter'd—this some artful lure is. King. The Queen—perdition seize her—hell and furies! Death, fire and faggots! for my torment sent is. Bolus. My Leige, you're mad—that is, non compos mentis. King. Enough to drive one mad, to make a sot o'me. Bolus. We must phlebotomize. King. O hang Phlebotomy! Doctor, your ear—Gadzooks, you're mighty pale! You wear a wig—and thereby hangs a tale— [lays hold of Bolus's pigtail. You deal in physic—I abhor my Queen— You're up to snuff—can fathom what I mean— To men of your discernment, verbum sat— So, Bolus, you must finish her—that's flat. DUET.—King and Doctor Bolus. (Tune—“O what a monstrous gay day.”) King. O what a merry contrivance! The Queen shall go off in a huff; All her bad humours we'll drive hence, For she shall have physic enough! Bolus. Bolus, cathartic, elixir, Snug in her liquor I'll drop; If 'tis your pleasure I'll mix her All the contents of my shop. Both. Then hey for the pestle and mortar! And hey for th' infallible pills! No plan on earth can be shorter To cure our good Queen of her ills. [Exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE IV. A Tent—Scaramoucho discovered asleep—A Ghost rises up, and sings. Hey Scaramoucho! ho Scaramoucho! The trumpets they sound and the cannons they rattle; With a hey-day-diddle, the drum and the fiddle, The King and his Courtiers are coming to battle. [Ghost sinks. Scara. (In his sleep.) Charge, ev'ry mother's son! confound the laggers! Bring me another horse! mine's got the staggers! There scampers off the King!—my bow and arrow; I've wing'd him—down he tumbles like a sparrow! Enter Dillydundos. Dilly. There lies our Gen'ral sleeping—devil take him! I just will take the liberty to wake him. [Tweaks his nose. Scara. I'm wounded! mercy, ye inhuman crew! [Starting. Ha, little Dillydundos! is it you? Dilly. Gen'ral, our forces have been waiting long, We've muster'd more than five-and-twenty strong; They're all prepar'd for battle, arm'd in mail. Scara. Ere they begin, let half a pint of ale To each be given, with a mess of porridge, To warm their honest hearts and stir their courage. Now to your post—my soul their zeal partakes, And I'll be with you in a brace of shakes. [Exit Dillydundos. With doubt and fear my heart begins to knock, The Queen was to be here at two o'clock; How dreadful is the thought of fire and slaughter! Fly swift, ye minutes—still it wants a quarter— [looks at his watch. 'Twixt love and vengeance my poor brains are addled— I'm out of sorts to-day—Is Dobbin saddled? How hard my fate to lose the best of matches By this confounded King of Shreds and Patches! AIR.—Scaramoucho. (Tune—“Scots, wha hae wi' Wallace bled.”) Slave! when you my Squadrons spy, You'll have other fish to fry, Making love is all my eye Till the battle's done. When hot cannon-balls assail, Whizzing round your sconce like hail, You will tell another tale! Ah, you'll cut and run! Rage within my bosom stirs, By my whiskers, boots and spurs! Regimental coat of furs! And this martial frown. By my Charmer's peepers bright, Should I in th' approaching fight Catch this monarch—blow me tight! But I'll crack his crown! [Exit.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE V. A field of battle—King Artipadiades, Doctor Bolus, and soldiers. King. Thus have our arms with victory been crown'd, And sundry rebels, whom the devil confound, Have sorely been discomfited, or slain. Enter a Guard. Guard. My Leige, the Gen'ral Scaramoucho's ta'en. King. Rare news!—to night he shall with Pluto sup— Conduct him here, and let me—blow him up! [Exit guard. Bolus, is all prepared? Bolus. Quite snug and clean, Fair Mopsa, Maid of Honour to the Queen, Who with an eye of passion looks upon Your faithful subject, for she has but one, A pill dropp'd in her liquor, heav'n preserve us! Which Doctor Diddle'um calls Anti-nervous. King. You are the best of Doctors! by this light, And shall be well rewarded, honour bright! Enter Scaramoucho in chains, guarded. Ha, slave!— Scara. I scorn your words! behold these fetters, Usurper! King. Pray, be civil to your betters! I am the King, your master. Scara. What am I— A soldier— King. And a traitor— Scara. That's a lie! King. I cannot in my kingdom find his brother Rebel and raggamuffin— Scara. That's another! King. Prepare a dungeon—does the rascal mutter? As narrow as the Black Hole at Calcutta; There let him lie, depriv'd of light and air, A little bread and water be his fare; And, as he's whisper'd to our Queen some fine tales, First cool his courage with a cat-o'-nine-tails; Confine him close within our prison's borders, His jobbernowl shall wait for further orders. [Exeunt Scaramoucho and Guards. To feast were now the wisest plan, I think; Heroes, like us, should sometimes eat and drink: I'm grown quite sharp, no reason can be stronger; And see no fun in fasting any longer. [Exeunt omnes.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE VI. A Dungeon—Scaramoucho sitting in a melancholy Posture, with Pipes, Tobacco, a Bottle and a Glass upon a Table before him. Scara. O Scaramoucho, wretchedest of dogs! You've to a precious market brought your hogs! Alack! my heart is swelling with a big tale Of woe—let's see, I'll try a little pig-tail, [Takes some tobacco. Which the Queen sent me, with this fond request, That I would drink her health in Hodges' best. Sweet Love! may this cup be my poison, if I do not pledge thee! [drinks] Faith, 'tis plaguy stiff! “My spirits flag—I'll sing, to ease my pain, “A musical and melancholy strain. AIR.—Scaramoucho. (Tune—“The Thorn.”) “From a pot of mild ale my dear Susan requested “A swig, for the damsel was dry; “When I cried, My sweet Belle, come and drink, for you're welcome, “But don't think of giving the pot a black eye. “Then she took up the ale, toss'd it off like a new one, “And held up the vessel on high: “O, I cried, my sweet Susan, 'tis hard thus to use one; “Hang me, but you've given the pot a black eye.” Enter Gaoler. Gaoler. “An excellent good song! 'tis surely his'n, or [Pointing to Scaramoucho. “I'm much mistaken.” You are merry, Pris'ner. Scara. (Aside.) The Gaoler! to come over him I'll try. Your errand? Is't to summons me to die? You're married, friend! Ah, me! I smell a rat. Gaoler. There needs no ghost rise up to tell me that! Scara. What children have you? for the love of heav'n, Let me not die in ignorance! Gaoler. Eleven! Scara. You love them dearly: I have children, too! Fifteen, or twenty, which is more than you. You weep—although a Turnkey, you're a man. Gaoler. I can't help crying, dammee if I can! Scara. Here, take this purse, 'twill purchase my release. [Gives his purse. Gaoler. Three dollars, and an eighteen-penny piece! Scara. Now, Katalinda, to thine arms I'll rush! Gaoler. There is no time for talking; let us brush. [Exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE VII. An Apartment in the Palace—Enter Mopsa and Poggylina. Mopsa. The morn is overcast, the sun looks sad; It pours of rain—her Majesty is mad: She'll hop the twig. Poggy. 'Twere better that she should! 'Tis an ill wind that blows nobody good. Mopsa. Ill wind! what does my Poggylina mean? Poggy. That, Mopsa, I shall probably be queen! The King declar'd he'd wed me, could he doff her. Mopsa. Last Saturday he made me, too, an offer! Poggy. Faith, that's a good one! you have ta'en the wrong Beau. Mopsa. You, Poggylina, you have drawn the long bow. DUET.—Mopsa and Poggylina. (Tune—“Out of my Sight, or I'll box your Ears.”) Poggy. Out of my sight, or I'll box your ears! Mopsa. I'll fit you, Ma'am, for your gibes and jeers! Poggy. I'll cock my cap, for all you, at the King— Mopsa. Then I'll pull it off if you do such a thing. Poggy. I should like—Odd rat it! To catch you at it; I'd claw your cheeks, and I'd damage your paint! Mopsa. Tho' you look so demure, you are not quite a Saint, But a pert little Hussey, hang me if you an't! Enter King Artipadiades. King. To end this sad disturbance, on my oath, Should the Queen prove defunct, I'll wed ye both. Enter Queen Katalinda, mad. AIR.—Queen. (Tune—“Last Night, a little bowsy.”) Last night, while sitting solus, Of Scaramoucho thinking; Comes little Doctor Bolus, Who look'd as he'd been drinking; When down he knelt, My pulse he felt, Ah! little then a rat I smelt! He swore he rid Along, to bid Good morning to my Nightcap! Queen. I'm dead and buried, though they say I'm not; Poor Scaramoucho, too, he's gone to pot! You'll break my heart—peace, trembler!—how it jumps! I've shuffled—four by honours—spades are trumps! AIR.—Queen. (Tune.—“Jolly Dick, the Lamplighter.”) Peter Quill, the Scrivener, Whose Dad in Chancery pleads, Was shipp'd one day to Botany Bay, For forging title deeds. Queen. Poor fellow! he was comical and rum too: No matter; it is what we all must come to! Enter Scaramoucho. Scara. O piteous sight—speak, Katalinda fair! [She stares him full in the face. Mute as a mack'rel—mad as a March hare! King. This to my face! haste, you audacious brute O, To Styx! and give my compliments to Pluto. [Stabs Scaramoucho. Scara. I'm dish'd—O murder! Katalinda, fly! Oh! I can live no longer; so I'll die. [Dies. Queen. My Lover kill'd! my beautiful brave Lad! I'm craz'd already—soon I shall be mad! (Tune.—“For Robin, sweet Robin, was all my Joy”) For sweet Scaramoucho was all my joy. [Sings. In war how brave he was, in peace how gracious! Did ever hero boast such long mustachios? His martial beaver—now my phrenzy stirs! And—that way madness lies!—his boots and spurs! But now he's finish'd; thus I pay my thanks— Take that, my Maids of Honour, for your pranks! [Stabs Mopsa and Poggylina. Poggy. We die!— Mopsa. Tip it the Queen! King. Sweet maids, I will— A dagger's quicker med'cine than a pill. [Stabs the Queen. Queen. Ah! Who calls on Katalinda?—see, I'm beckon'd! I'll come, my Scaramoucho, in a second. It grows quite dark; my eyes are dim—good bye! Good riddance to bad rubbish. King. So say I! And now, to end the plot, as life's a bubble, I'll kill myself, to save all further trouble! [Stabs himself. Enter Doctor Bolus. Bolus. Death has been playing here a trick most scurvy: Kings, Queens, and Maids of Honour, topsy-turvy! [The King blows his nose. What noise was that?—ha, ha!—I see old Priam! Your Majesty is no more dead than I am! And you, Queen Katalinda, rise with speed, Poison in jest, I meant—I did indeed! I'll rouse these Maids of Honour, or belabour 'em; Mopsa and Poggylina, don't sham Abr'am! Brave Scaramoucho, stir your stumps, my hearty! We want your presence to complete the party. [They all rise. FINALE. (Tune.—“Never think of meeting Sorrow.”) King. Just escap'd from Charon's ferry, Anger's useless, bick'ring's vain; Let's be all alive and merry, Loudly chaunt a jovial strain! Singing Fal, lal, &amp;c. &amp;c. Queen. Spousy, with my Maids of Honour Don't be seen to toy and kiss; Poggylina, fie upon her! Mopsa, she's a romping miss! Singing Fal, lal, &amp;c. Poggy. Is it right, that, in a frolic, Pot should call the kettle black? Mopsa. Certain Queens, who've got the cholic, Should be mum, and hold their clack. Singing Fal, lal, &amp;c. Scara. Doctor Bolus, prithee stop, Sir; Do not on my manor poach. Bolus. Will you marry me, fair Mopsa? Answer, and I'll call a coach! Singing Fal, lal, &amp;c. The Piece concludes with a Dance.</field>
   </doc>
</add>