<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Printed by E.A. for Edward White</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Printed by E.A. for Edward White</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">printed by ea for edward white</field>
      <field name="author_text">Printed by E.A. for Edward White</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">16th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V1.0559.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1589</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:459276</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Rare Triumphes of Loue and Fortune</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- Early modern and Elizabethan, 1500-1600</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- Early modern and Elizabethan, 1500-1600</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Rare Triumphes of Loue and Fortune</field>
      <field name="title_facet">rare triumphes of loue and fortune</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">rare triumphes of loue and fortune</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Rare Triumphes of Loue and Fortune</field>
      <field name="year_display">1589</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1589</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1589</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459276&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459276&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Rare Triumphes of Loue and Fortune&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;rare triumphes of loue and fortune&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1589&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1589&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Rare Triumphes of Loue and Fortune&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed by E.A. for Edward White&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1589&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3873467-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv10559&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- Early modern and Elizabethan, 1500-1600&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;Early modern and Elizabethan, 1500-1600&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Rare Triumphes of Loue and Fortune&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1994&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1994 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 145 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Love and fortune.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Comedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1589.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 30 Dec 1582.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Rare Triumphes of Loue and Fortune</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The first Acte. Enter Mercury, then riseth a Furie: then enter the assembly of the Gods, Iupiter with Iuno, Apollo with Minerua, Mars and Saturne, after Uulcan with Uenus, the Fury sets debate amongst them, and after Iupiter speakes as followeth. Iupiter. Ye Gods and Goddesses, whence springes this strife of late? who are the authors of this mutenye? Or whence hath sprung this ciuill discorde here: which on the sodaine strook vs in this feare. If Gods that raigne in Skyes doo fall at warre, No meruaile then though mortall men doo iarre. But now I see the cause thou Fury fell, Bred in the dungeon of the deepest hell, Who causeth thee to shew thy selfe in light, and what thy message is, I charge thee tell vpright. Enter Tysiphone. Tisiphone. O Iupiter thou dreadfull king of Gods &amp; men the father hie, to whose commaund the heauens, the earth and lowest hell obey: Tysiphone the daughter of eternall night, Bred in the bottome of the deepest pit of hell: Brought vp in blood and cherisht with scrauling Snakes, tormenting therwithall the damned soules of them, Heer vpon earth that carelesse liue of thy commaundement. I am the same. I am the same whom both my lothsome sisters hate, whom hell it selfe complaines to keep within her race. Whom euery fearfull soule detesteth with a cursse, whom earth and Seas defie heauens lothing to beholde, I am the same. I am the same sent from thy brother Pluto now, Thy brother Pluto King of hell and golden mynes, Sent vnto thee and these thy fellow Gods I am, From him to thee from him by me, to tell thee to thy face, He hath been lately rubde and toucht perhaps too neere: which he ne can or will put vp without reuenge. If thou or any God the quarell dares defend. And this it is. Thy daughter Uenus thy proud daughter Uenus heere, Blabs it abroad and beareth all the world in hand, She must be thought the only Goddesse of the world: Exalting and suppressing whom she likes best, Defacing altogeather Lady Fortunes grace. Breaking her anckers downe, dishonouring her name, Whose gouernement thy selfe, thy selfe doost knowe. How saist thou, doost thou not? Her father therfore thy brother Pluto sendes, By me the messenger of discorde and debate: Commaunding or desiring, choose thou whether of both, Her honour still impire, she may maintaine: Els on thy daughter Uenus that lasciuious dame, Him selfe will wreak his high dispite on her. Iupiter. Departe foule feend vnto thy lothsome sell, where thou lamenting makes continuall mone: Goe tell my brother were it not for him, thou shouldst haue rude thy bolde presumption. Say thou thy message hath been largely heard, and bid him send his daughter Fortune now: whilst we are heere the matter may haue ende. Dispatch. Tisiphone. I goe. Giue place thou aire, open thou earth, gape hollow hell belowe, and vnto all that liue and breathe, I wishe a worlde of woe. Exit Tysiphone. Iupiter. Ye powers deuine be reconcilde againe, Departe from discorde and extreme debate: within your breasts let loue and peace remaine, A perfect patterne of your heauenly state. whilome a goe to hell condemning hate: Thus when the hier power is in one, Men vpon earth will flye contention. Mercury. Great God and father mine, your care and feare Of vs and eke of all the world beside, that restles rules in his continuall Sphere, wherby all thinges in perfect course abide: as one arayes an other forth to slide. And this example may preuaile for all, to woorke our willes according to your call: And I dare say presuming on the rest, the poyson of this rancour is supprest. Vulcan. How ye agree my maisters I cannot tell, But were we a bed, we two could agree well. Iupiter. Gramercy Mercury I know thy will Is euer prest to further my desire: in signe wherof to quiet all thinges well, and to surpresse betimes the secret fire, that I perceiue would break and mount vp hier. This to preuent content ye heere to staye, to marke a while what for themselues they say. And Uenus heere I charge thee on my grace, Not that I found thee heertofore vntrue: But for thine aduersarie is not yet in place, thou tell vprightly whence your quarrell grew: what woords betwixt you therof did ensue. Say louely daughter tell vs flat thy minde, they shalbe blamed on whom the fault we finde. Venus. O thou that gouernest euery thing that Gods &amp; men attempt, and with thy fearful thunderbolte their doings doost preu?t. what hath thy daughter so deserued? what doth she silly d?e: Before ye thus to be abused with vndeserued blame? Surely but that thy duety commaundes me now to speake, For such a trifling cause this way, my wrath I would not wreak. But she no meruaile though she seeke my seat thus to staine When otherwaies she connot tell, aduantage how to gain. But hence this hot dispight, Hinc illæ lacrimæ: Because I say she could not proue, her self of power with me For all you Godheads know, she paines but such as plesure knewe: She neuer greeues the groning minde, wher gladnes neuer grewe. She neuer ouerthrowes but at the top of ioy: For they that neuer tasted blisse, mislike not their anoye. But I torment the minde that neuer felt releefe, I plague the wretch that neuer thought on comfort in his greefe. That neuer had the hope of any happy chaunce: that neuer once so much as deem'd I would his state adu?ce. Thinke then which of vs both are of the greater power, Once in his life or not at all to graunt a lightning hower. I neede not stand to make rehearsall here of all, For Gods and ghosts, yea, men &amp; beasts vnto my power are thrall. I dare appeale to you if I should looke awry: Say father with your leaue, in heauen who dares my woord deny, And if I please to smile who will not laugh out right: Wherby my great omnipotence is knowne to euery wight. I make the noble loue the bastarde in degree: I tame and temper all the tunges, that raile &amp; scoffe at me. What bird, what beast, what worme, but feeleth my delight what liues or draweth breth, but I can plesure or despight. Yet diuers thinges there be that Fortune cannot tame, As are the riches of the minde, or else an honest name. Or a contented hart, still free from Fortunes power, But such as clime before they crale, must drink ye sweet with sower. Thy self O Iupiter didst graunt sometimes to me: Of all things heer beneath the Moone, I should the ruler be. Thou saist I did deserue the honor of that praise, thy selfe didst once deuise wherby my glory first to raise. Is this my soueraigntie, is this so glorious: Is this becomming thy renown, to quit thy daughter thus? Iupiter. Feare not faire Uenus, neither be dismaide, Repose thee on the warrant of my woord: What I haue promist doubt not to be perfourmed, the sparelesse destinies my will affoorde. Let this defend thee like a trusty Swoord. But Lady Fortune commeth now we see, Welcome faire dame, what is thy will with me? Fortune. Ye sacred powers deuine how should I now begin, Or which way should I couch my words your fauors for to win. I may poure out my plaint, but thou maist it redresse, My Father humbly praieth you to giue me leaue to speak, And pardon him yt in his wrath he did your quietnes break. I cannot but confesse dread Gods I am not she, that seekes with Uenus to compare in her supremecie. I am not of that power, yet am I of some might, which she vsurping chalengeth to keep me from my right. I graunt she may doo much with her aluring smiles, But soon your Godheads can perceiue her woords be full of wiles. What be ye tragedies, the terors that she makes? Lets see the mighty Monarcks the kingdomes yt she shakes. Poore soule she soundly liues with wanton sugred ioyes, triumphing in her own delight vpon her foolishe toyes. Sometime she flattereth it in pleasure mixt with paine, Like to a faire sunshine day ouercast with Clowds of raine But should I reckon vp what thinges I can confound, what is it then, or what hath been, or shall for aye be found. Is not the wonder of the World a woork that soon decayes: therfore ye see all earthly thinges, are wearing out alwaies As brittle as the glasse, vnconstant like the minde: as fickle as the whirling wheele, as wauering as the winde. Loe such am I that ouerthrowes the hiest reared tower: that changeth and supporteth Realmes in twinkling of an hower. And send th? hasty smart whom I deuise to spoyle: Not threatning or forewarning them but at a sodain smile. Where ioy dooth most abound there I doo sorrow place, and them I cheefely persecute that pleasure did embrace. what greater greefe can fall to man in all his life, then after sweet to taste the sower, in peace to be at strife. It is a biting thought that fretteth on the hart, to say the time was when I ioy'd, though now opprest with smart, If euer mightye King did scape vntoucht of me: if euery yeere, or moneth, or day, or if an hower might be. UUherin I haue not vs'd to practise some exchange, Perhaps for this authoritie I might he thought to range. Too farre beyond my right but euen the very starres, the Heauens, the Planets, and the Seas heare witnesse of my scarres. Venus. No more of that good dame you run too farre at rome, I'le take the paines to keep you short &amp; call you nerer home. I pray you whats your might when all are well belou'd? Fortune. The sweetest louers in distres ye sharper storms haue prou'd Venus. Perhaps for want of wealth but if their riches slack, Fortune. They are the very instrument wherby I woorke their woe, Venus. What if their freends abound, then can they neuer lacke? Fortune. The deerest freends are scattered when Fortune turns her toe. Venus. If they be noble borne or of a Princely blood: Fortune. UUhen Fortune frownes, that may procure more harme then doo them good. Venus. But wise men euermore vpon a Rocke are set: Fortune. Yet can they not escape a scourge for Fortune hath a net. Iupiter. I will not in till thinges be well discernde, Affection shall not marre a lawfull cause: By examples this may best be learnde, In elder ages led within your lawes. therfore a while heerof I meane to pause. And bring in Mercury in open view, the Ghosts of them that Loue and Fortune slue. Mercury. Thy woord my will. thou triple headed Cerberus giue place, And I commaund thee Caron with thy Ferry boate, Transporte the soules of such as may reporte, Fortune and Loue and not in open sorte. Let them appeere to vs in silent showe, to manifest a trueth that we must knowe. Strike with his Rod three times Vulcan. Are ye mad my Maisters, what a sturre haue we heere? Lord haue mercy vpon vs must the deuill appeare. Come away wife, when I pray thee come away, Downe on your knees my Maisters and pray. Musicke. Enter the show of Troylus and Cressida. Mercury. Beholde how Troylus and Cresseda, Cryes out on Loue that framed their decay. Vulcan. That was like the olde wife when her Ale would not come, thrust a fire brand in the groute and scratcht her bum. Musicke. Enter the shew of Alexander. Mercury. Alexander the great that all the world subdude, Curseth fell Fortune that did him delude. Vulcan. Tis an honest grim sire at his first comming out beleeue me, And ye had stood in the winde ye might haue smelt me. Musicke. Enter the show of Queene Dydo. Mercury. Queene Dydo that Aeneas could not moue, Stabbed her selfe and yeelded vnto loue. Vulcan. The more foole she and she were my owne brother, If my wife would not loue me must not I loue an other? Musicke. Enter the shewe of Pompey and Cæsar. Mercury. Pompey and Cæsar, the wonders of their time, By froward Fortune spoyled in their prime. Vulcan. They were serued well enough, why could not they be content, with a Roche and a red Herring in the holy time of Lent. Musicke. Enter the showe of Leander and Hero. Mercury. Leander presentes them very lothe: that felte the force of loue and fortune both. Fortune. Upon him I my soueraintie did showe, Venus. And thinke you dame my power she did not knowe. Fortune. But it was I that dashed their delight, Venus. After that I had proued my open might. Vulcan. UUhat a scolding is heere shall it euen thus be? You looke like an honest man in the Parrishe, I pray you make them agree. Iupiter. Content ye both I'le heare no more of this, and Mercury surcease call out no more: I haue bethought me how to woorke their wishe, as you haue often proou'd it heertofore. Heere in this land within that Princely bower, there is a Prince beloued of his loue? On whom I meane your souerainties to proue. Uenus, for that thy loue thy sweet delight, thou shalt endure to encrease their ioy: and Fortune thou to manifest thy might, their pleasures and their pastimes thou shalt destroye. Ouerthwarting them with newes of freshe anoye. And she that most can please them or dispight, I will confirme to be of greatest might. Venus. Your Godhead hath deuisde as I desire, and I am gladly therwithall content: Fortune. And I am prest to doo as you require. Now shall you see the proofe of my entent. Take vp your places heere to woorke your will, When you haue doon the rest I shall fulfill. Vulcan. They are set a sunning like a Crow in a gutter, what are they gone? And you will be quiet sirs, they will make ye good sport with their scolding anon. Are not these a sorte of good mannerly Gods to get them thus away: I must take the paines to ouertake them for I see they will not stay. Exit omnes. The ende of the firste Acte.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The second Acte. Enter Hermione and Fidelia. Hermione. Why then my deere what is the greatest price in loue? Fidelia. Absence of others greefs, the gretest yt louing harts c? proue. Hermione. But absence can not minishe loue or make it lesse in ought: Fidelia. Yet neuerthelesse it leaues a doubt within ye others thought Hermione. And what is that? Fidelia. Least change of ayre should change the absent minde, Hermione. That fault is proper but to th? whom ielouzy makes blinde. Fidelia. O pardon it for that the cause from whence it springes is such, Hermione. From whence is that? Fidelia. My mother sayes from louing ouer much. Hermione. Your author I will not admit, that restes as it to proue, Fidelia. But sure is it that ielousie, proceedes of feruent loue. Hermione. Can that be feruent loue wherin suspition leads the minde, Fidelia. Most feru?t loue wher so much loue doth make ye fancy blind Hermione. But faithfull loue can neuer be wherin suspect doth dwell, Fidelia. The faithfull louers doo suspect because they loue so well. Hermione. My deere Fidelia, as I thinke thy loue is such to me, So feruent, faithfull and vnstain'd, as purer none can be: Admit occasions fall out then, that I must parte from thee. tell me wilt thou meane space suspect inconstancie in me. Fidelia. If so I doo impute it to the force of louers lawes, that oftentimes are toucht with feare, wheras there is no cause. Armenio listning. Armenio. What haue I heard? what doo mine eyes beholde: Dishonour to the house from whence I came: Unshamefast girle, forgetfull, all to bolde, and thou false traitour author of the same. Sufferest not for guerdon of thy due, the King my Fathers gratious countenance: But must thou clime vngratefull and vntrue, these steps, at firste thine honour to aduance. Hath Fortune promiste so much hope at firste, to make thy conquest of a Princes childe: And should I stand to question how thou durst, to leaue to thinke she might be so beguilde. But woords may not suffice to wreak this wrong, Hid vnder cloake of ouer handy loue: thou vpstart fondling and forborne too long, to giue such cause thy Princes ire to moue. Fidelia. Nay nay good brother take it not so whot, the fault is mine, and I will beare the blame: And to returne you an answer well I wot, How to defend the honour of my name. But for my loue I am resolued in this, How euer you account of his defaultes. with vowed affection wholy to be his. As one in whome I spye more speciall partes, then fall in fondlings of the baser kindes: to haue a woord not squaring with the place. But measure men by their vnstained mindes. Let fortune be to vertue no disgrace, For fortune when and where it likes her maiestie: With cloudes can couer birth and highest degree. Armenio. What Dame, and are you shamelesse in your shame? No Mistresse, no, it will not so be let past: But wilfull Wench this new attempted game, Eare it be wun will aske another cast. And Lady, cloake his vertues as you will, Hee'le be but as I saide, a fondling still. Hermione. Earst had I thought my Lord a man so wise as you, Sonne to a Prince, Scholer to him that deepth of learning knewe. Among many lessons, none this rule could wisely finde, to haue the gouernement of wrath &amp; rancor of your minde. What hye offence is giuen vnto your fathers grace: I take it nothing needfull heer to reason of the case. But stand he lesse content, or pleased heere withall, My Lord, that thus you should mislike the cause is very small. The vnremoued loue I beare my Lady heere, Whose countenance my comfort is: that holdes my loue as deare. Commaunds me to disgest such hard and bitter woords, as not with credit of your state, your honor heer affords. Else Prince perswade thy selfe: my minde were not so base, to pocket, but for such respectes so hard and foule disgrace. And this Lady Hermione for ought that men doo know, By birth may be as nobly borne, as prince Armenio. Armenio. Traitour thru shalt not ioy that proud comparison, Fidelia. My good Hermione, come hence let him alone. Armenio. Nay Dame it likes me not that you should goe, Hermione. Whether thou wilt Armenio she shall, though thou say no. Armenio. What shall she villaine? Fidelia. Helpe, helpe alas. Enter Phizanties, a Lord, and Penulo. Phyzan. What sturre is heere? what meanes this broyle begun? Giue me to know the occasion of this strife, How falles it out? Armenio my Sonne Hath wound receiu'd by stroke of naked knife, Say to me straight: what one hath doone this deed: His blowes are big that makes a Prince to bleed. Fidelia. My soueraigne father, pardon his offence, whose greefe of minde is greater then his wound: My rightfull quarrell yeeldes me safe defence, and heere they stand that giltie must be found. Armenio, Traytor (O King) vnto your Maiesty, Whose proud attempt dooth touch your grace so neere: as what may be the greatest villanye, Upon recitall shall be opened heere. My sister and your farre vnwoorthy childe, Forgetting loue and feare of Gods and thee: and honor of her name is thus beguilde. To loue this Gentleman whom heere you see. Hermione whom for a Iewell of some price, Olde Hermet giue your highnesse long agoe: and for I gaue rebuke to your deuise, In gallant thought he would not take it so. But as it seemes to doo my body good, I thanke him dainde him self to let me blood. Phyzan. Hermione? and hast thou doone this deed? and couldst thou shrine such treason in thy thought? Armenio iest not with thy hurt take heed, and thou fond girle whose stained blood hath wrought, How hath mine age and honor been abusde? My princely care Hermione of thee? the fault so great it cannot be excusde. and you inforst the shame therof to see. But farre we feare some farther ill may fall: through loue and hate of one and of the other: Her foolishe loue I meane, and therwithall. The hot disdaine and stomacke of her brother, Hermione, way what our pleasure is. Whilome thou knowest we entertaine thee willingly: Now seeing thou hast doon so farre a misse, to reach aboue thy reach vnorderly. In milder woordes because we loue thee well, Loe, we discharge thee of our princely Court: thou maist no longer with Fidelia dwell, Forbidden to her presence to resorte. Holde my rewarde, that am no bitter Iudge, and wend thy way where ere thou likest to goe? this only way I take to ende the grudge, and stop the loue that eache to other owe. Among such haps as might my minde content, UUherof the gratious Gods haue giuen me store: I count this one if thus I might preuent, the furthest outrage of this swelling sore. Hermione. Alas, now haue I liued too long I see, Confounded so to yeeld to fortunes will: My soueraigne Prince offended thus with me, and I adiudg'd to death though liuing still. Ah my good Lord whom I haue honoured long, long may your highnesse ioy this highest place: thy selfe the roote and cause of mine owne wrong, But must I leaue to viewe my Ladies face? And banisht from my Princes royall Court, to wander as earst the vnhappy Oedipus: Whose paine my foes will make their cheefest sporte, My most vnhappy chaunce will haue it thus. Armenio. No force forsooth, vnpitied might he dye, that to his soueraigne meanes such villanye. Hermione. Such villany? who euer ment more good? Armenio. The venome of thy villany withstood. Hermione. Armenio, I forbeare thee heere for reuerence, Yet by my Princes leaue in my defence. I may alleadge I lou'd thy sister heere, which loue though I am like to buye full deere. Yet is her loue more precious then the price: But since hard hap preuents our late deuice. Long liue my Lord, long liue my Ladies grace, God send them freends as loyall in my place. And trust me then their fortune shalbe such, as not thy loue shall euer proue so much. Phyzan. Hermione, giue me thy hand, adewe, thinke this is doon to auoide a further ill, and double mischeife that might else insue, For my sake cease to loue Fidelia still. Unequall loue is enemie to rest, She is too yong to loue thee as she should: and thou Hermione canst conceiue the rest, My meaning is she loues not as we would. time may affoord to bothe your hartes desires: New choice to coole these newly kindled fiers. Fidelia. Neuer alas, neuer will be the day, that I shall leaue to loue Hermione: Sooner shall natures course quite altered be, then I shall leaue deere Knight to honor thee. Good Father let him stay, who if he parte, Gainst law is like to steale away my hart. Armenio. May it please your grace to keepe the body heere, It's like enough the hart will honor neere. Hermione. My Lord, laugh not oppressed soules to scorne, Loosers they say may easily be forborne. Phyzan. Forbeare these woordes and thou Fidelia, these misbeseeming foolishe passions stay. Let it suffise that thou shalt liue in Courte, Where if among the iolly braue resorte. Of sundry knightes of noble personage, Woorthy thy loue for giftes and parentage. thou shalt espye some such as we doo like, Our fauours shall not be to farre to seeke. Fidelia. Ah my Hermione. Hermione. Sweet Lady mine farwell. Farwell the curteoust Dame that on the earth doth dwell. Exit. Armenio. Sir now you are packing let me know your walke: For I haue that may not be past without some talke. Nor stands it with mine honour to let thee beare it cleere: But I will make thee know Armenios blood is deare. Hermione. My Lord, I make no chalenge with offence, But first I will prepare for my defence. Armenio. So sir, you are aforehand, keepe you so: and recken of Armenio for thy vowed foe. Goe wend thy wayes, obscurer then the night: and Fortune for reuenge plague thee with spite. Exit. Hermione. Farwell my cruell foe, not thou, nor Fortune may, ad more vnto the miseries that I haue felt to day. Nor but by safe restorde vnto this happy place, Can Gods or Fortune make amends in this distressed case. Then cease Hermione to vtter speach of this, Woords not suffise this endlesse woe, but death I wisse. and part thou from the place a dead and liuelesse man, Robd of thy sences and thy ioy, since first this stur began. Penulo. Ah my good Lord, my good Lord Hermione. Hermione. I am indeed as thou doost say Hermione. For that I am Hermione, I am the vnhappiest wight that euer hether came. Penulo. Ah my good Lord, would Gods poore Penulo, Might any way but mitigate this woe. and pleaseth it your honour to commaund, My seruice or the helpe of head or hand. Penulo my woorthy Lord would proue as iust, as he whom best your honour likes to trust. Say what it is wherin my secresie, May ayde your Lordship in this extremetie. Hermione. Penulo, since thou so freendly heere doost proffer me, the vttermost of ayde that lyes in thee. I doo remember that which brought to passe, Would make me halfe so happie as I was. Penulo. Say it my Lord, and constantly I vow it: It shall goe hard but Penulo will doo it. Hermione. Gramercy gentle freend: then thus it is, The Lady of my life Fidelia is. Of whome I am, I knowe belou'd no lesse, then she of me my gratious mistresse. Seuerde by Fortune and our cruell foe, My Lord her brother Prince Armenio. Now couldst thou Penulo thy selfe behaue, On trust to bring my Lady to the caue. Where whilome louers we were wont to meete, in secret sorte eche other for to greete. She wots it well and euery corner knowes, and euery vncouth step that thether goes. For what is not sharpe sighted louers see, this is the summe of my desire to thee. Accomplishe this, and this in silence doon, My happinesse wilbe againe begun. Penulo. My Lord I see wherunto this talke dooth tend, I haue this lesson at my fingers end. No more a doo: betake you to your flight, wee'le make a plaister for the sore eare night. But such a one as if it be applied, Shall doo more greefe then ease when it is tried. Hermione. Penulo I yeeld my life into thy handes, Penulo. Ye, doo sir, as now the matter standes, Hermione. Holde Penulo and I will looke for thee, Penulo. You will not looke for them that come with me. Hermione. I will be gone and liue to see my deere. Exit. Penulo. Doo so sir and perchaunce be neuer the neere. This is a step that firste we vse to clime, We that forsooth take holde on euery time: Men of all howers, whose credit such as spites, in heate forsooth hath calde vs Parasites. But let them spite and we will bite as fast, But Penulo thou spendest woordes in waste. A foole Hermione, that for hurting thee, One slender trust will giue a knaue his fee. Exit. Strike vp Fortunes triumphes with Drummes and Trumpets. Fortune. Beholde what Fortune if she list can doo, High mastris of the rowling wheele of chaunce: to ouerturne and who can doo therto, Or gratiously when please her to aduance. Loe Lordinges this is Fortunes Imperie, as in her pleasure to be changing still: Heerin consisteth Fortunes soueraintie, that Fortune can on earth doo what she will. When men haue builded on the surest grounds, their strong deuises Fortunes power confoundes. Venus. Not all in haste you doo not so intend, You haue begun but I must make an end.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The thirde Acte. Enter Bomelio solus like an Hermite. Bomelio. He that hath lost his hope and yet desires to liue, He that is ouerwhelmde with woe, and yet would counsell giue. He that delightes to sigh to walke abroad alone, to driue away the weary time with his lamenting mone. He that in his distresse dispaireth of releefe, Let him begin to tell his tale to rip vp all his greefe. And if that wretched man can more then I recite, Of fickle Fortunes froward checke and her continuall spite. Of her vnconstant change, of her discurtesie, I will be partner with that man to liue in miserie. When first my flowring yeeres began to bud their prime, Euen in the Aprill of mine age, and May month of my time UUhen like the tender Kid new weaned from the teat: In euery plesant springing Mead, I took my choice of meat. UUhen simple youth deuis'd to lengthen his delight: Euen then not dreaming I on her, she poured out her spite. Euen then she tooke her Keye, and turned all her stringes, to sing my woe, list Lordinges now my tragedie begins. Beholde me wretched man that seru'd his Prince wt paine, that in the honor of his praise esteemde my greatest gaine. Beholde me wretched man that for his publike weale, Refused not with thousand foes, in bloody warres to deale. Beholde me wretched man, whose trauell paine and toyle: was euer prest to saue my frends from force of forrain spoile. And see my iust rewarde, looke on my recompence: Beholde by this for labours past, what guerdon commeth thence. Not by my fearcest foes in doubtfull fight with vs, But by my fawning freendes, I was confounded thus. One woord of his dispite in question calde my name, two woordes of his vntrusty tung brought me to open shame Then was I banished the Citie, Court and towne: then euery hand that held me vp, began to pull me downe. O that the righteous Gods should euer graunt the power, that smoothest sandes and greenest bogs, should soonest me deuoure. Yet that I might discry the better their deuise, Heer haue I liu'd almost fiue yeeres disguisde in secret wise. And now somewat it is but what I cannot tell, prouokes me forward more th? wont to leaue my darksome sell. And in my crooked age in steed of mirth and ioy, with broken sighes in dolefull tunes to sing of mine annoy. Song. Goe walke the path of plaint, goe wander wretched now, In vncoth waies, blind corners fit for such a wretch as thou. there feede vpon thy woe, fresh thoughts shalbe thy fare, Musing shalbe thy waiting maide, thy caruer shalbe care. thy dainty dishe shalbe of fretting melancholie, and broken sobs with hollow sighes thy sauery sauce shalbe. But further ere I walke my seruant I will send, Into the towne to buy such thinges as now he can intend. UUhat Lentulo. Lentulo within. Lentulo. Anon forsooth. Bomelio. What Lentulo come foorth. Lentulo. Anon forsooth. Bomelio. Why when I say. Lentulo. Anon forsooth. Bomelio. You naughty loute, come out sir knaue, come away. Lentulo. Will you not giue one leaue to pull down his points, what and a should his breeches beray? Bomelio. Get you to the market and buy such thinges as needfull are for vs. Lentulo. Such things as needfull are for vs, &amp; what are those I pray? First there is needfull for vs a pot of porredg, for I had none this many a day: And then there are needfull for vs a featherbed, for I lye on a bottle of haye. And then there is most needfull for vs a prittie proper wench for and to laugh and play. Bomelio. Goe buy vs some victuailes and hye thee home. Exit. Lentulo. Now farwell Maister mine good gentle master mome. Haue you seene such a logger headded foole to say, Goe goe, good Lentulo, to buy my victuailes so, and giue me monie no. But for the names sake, swoundes I were as good serue a maister of clowtes: Hee'le doo nothing all day long but sit on his arse, as my mother did when she made powtes. And then a lookes a this fashion, and thus and thus againe, and then what doo ye? By my troth I stand euen thus at him and laugh at his simplismitie. Hath the best manners in the world to bid a man fall to his meat, And then I say, I thank you forsooth maister and I could tell what to eate. Wee two, looke you thats I and he, can lye a bed a whole night and a day: And we eate and we had it, it vattons a man looke on my cheekes els, are they not falne away? Well, I must iogge to the towne, and Ile tell you what shift I make there: Mary ye shall promise me not to steale it away. When I come to a rich mans gate, I make a low legge and then I knocke there. And then I begin to crye in at the Keye hole, that I may be sure they shall heare. God saue my good maister and my good mistresse, a poore boy a peece of bread and meate for Gods sake. Enter Penulo. Penulo. Heigh merely tricke, am I not a knaue for the nonce, That can dispatch two arrandes at once? I haue both tolde her euen as I should doo, And tolde my yong maister to meete with him too. Now he like a Gentleman for the vallour of his minde, Hath sworne by his honour not to stay long behinde. The desire of reuenge pricketh him forward so, That I am sure heele not let but to goe. And that with all haste possible he may: Then tantara tara we shall haue good play. I like such a knaue so can tickle them all, To set noble men at brabble and braule, Lentulo. Saue you sir yong maister and you be a gentleman, Penulo. Horeson pesant seest thou not what I am? Lentulo. Troth sir I see you haue a good dublet and a paire of hose But now a dayes there is so many goes So like Gentlemen, that such a poore fellow as I, Know not how a Gentleman from a knaue to spye. Penulo. Thou maist perceiue I am no such companion, I am a Gentleman, a Courtier, and a merry franke franion. Lentulo. Then thou merry companion, thou horson franke franion, Why hast thou abused the law: What goodman skipiack, in faith with thwick thwack your bones will I clawe. Come about sir knaue. Penulo. Cots my passion what a merry mate haue we heere? Lentulo. Giue me your hand sir, faith I was bolde to brushe the dust out of your geere. Pray sir tell me, they say in the Cuntry tis a common guise That Gentlemen now a daies cannot see with both eyes. Penulo. Its a lye knaue, I knowe few Gentlemen blinde: Lentulo. No sir what will you lay and I can finde, One with a wet finger that is starke blinde. Penulo. It may be so, but I thinke thou canst not, Lentulo. You will lay do wager on it. Penulo. What should I lay, Thou hast no monye I am sure to pay. Lentulo. No faith sir, but Ile tell you what our wager shalbe, Because I am not able to lay any monye. Ile lay three round rappes on the ribbes with my cudgell heere Penulo. Soft, let me looke first if there be no blinde man neere. Content I faith that bargaine shall stand: Lentulo. Then sir I must be so bolde as to search your purse out of hand. Penulo. My pursse sir wherfore? Lentulo. By my troth sir no more but to trie, if you be not as blinde a Gentleman in the purse as I. Penulo. I vse not to carry my monye in a pursse, All in a pocket, well neuer a whit the woorse. Lentulo. I must search your pocket. Penulo. UUhat if it be els where? Lentulo. UUhere soeuer it is I must seeke out this geere. Ile not loose my wager that's certaine: Uery well sir will you put me to paine. Penulo. Haue I neuer a weapon, Ile looke, I pray thee be content Lentulo. You shall haue your wager sir as it was ment. Penulo. Holde thy hands good fellow &amp; I'le doo any thing for thee: I perceiue a wise man of a foole ouertaken may be. Lentulo. Thou blinde Gentleman, vnlesse it be for my commodiositie, Ile teach thee to be blinde and goe so brauely. Penulo. Ile doo any thing for thee if thou strike me no more, Because I perceiue thou art almost as poore. As my selfe am and yet there is somewhat in thee, Ile preferre thee to a seruice in the Court presently. Lentulo. Ha wilt thou doo so? Penulo. That I will. Lentulo. Wilt thou doo so indeed, Sweare to me by thy ten commaundements in thy Creed. Penulo. I doo so. Lentulo. Troth then we are freendes, say nothing I pray: and you shall see me proue a rancke runaway. UUhy when a man may be a Courtier and liue at ease, Should a not leaue his olde maister to please. Sirra blinde gentleman, we too blinde gentlemen, and doo as thou promiste heere, Perchaunce I may be as good to thee as two pots of Beere, Ile goe with thee I faith, gaw lets be gone, Penulo. Soft tarry a while I'le goe with thee anon. Enter Armenio. Armenio. How thinkest thou Penulo, am I not prouided now? Lentulo. I warrant sir a shall haue a colde pull of you. And a begin to make an other brall, Armenio, Farewell when thou wilt, I trust I shall Meete with him: am I not almost at the tree, Penulo. That same is it sir. Lentulo. Sirra whats he? Penulo. UUhat carst thou, come gaw thou with me, UUhy I shall haue but an ill fauoured Courtier of yee. Lentulo. Now for a runaway God send vs good chaunce, Then maides at your mariage I meane me to daunce. Exit. Armenio. Now serues the time to wreak me of my foe, My dastard foe that to dishonour me: in priuie corners seekes to shame me so, that my discredit might his credit be. And hath my father from thy tender youth, Uouchsafe to bring thee vp? did I therfore Beleeue so earnestly thy periurde trueth, aduancing still thine honour euermore. That not contented with a common wrack, thou shouldst intend the ruine of vs all: And when thou seem'st afraide to turne thy back, to make a glory of our greater fall. Before thou triumphe in thy trechery, Before thou scape vntouched for thy sinne: Let neuer fates nor Fortune fauour me, But wretched let me liue and dye therin. Fewe woordes shall serue, my deedes shall proue it now: That ere I sleepe I meane to meete with you. Enter Fidelia. Fidelia. Beholde the shiftes that faithfull loue can make, See what I dare aduenture for thy sake: In case extreame make vertue of a neede, But hence the greefe which maketh my hart to bleede. My loue and life where euer that thou be, I am in dole constrainde to followe thee. Hence sprung the hell of my tormented minde, The feare of some misfortune yet behinde. If thou escape the perrill of distresse, My feare and care is twenty times more lesse. No reason tis that I should liue in ioy, When thou art wrapt in fetters of annoy. Nor to that end I sware to be thy wife, To liue in peace with thee and state of life. But as to dwell at ease in pleasures lap, Euen so to beare some parte of thy mishap. And so to draw in equall portion still, Of both our Fortunes either good or ill. And sith the lots of our vnconstant fate, Haue turnde our former blisse to wretched state, I am content to tread the wofull daunce, That soundes the measure of our haplesse chaunce. Ile waite thy comming, long thou wilt not stay, Hye Ioue defend and keepe thee in the way. Enter Bomelio. Bomelio. Now weary lay thee downe, thy fortune to fulfill, Goe yeeld thee captiue to thy care to saue thy life or spill. The pleasures of the feelde, the prospect of delight, The blooming trees, the chirping birdes are greeuous to thy sight. The hollow craggy rocke, the shriking Owle to see, To heare the noyse of serpentes hisse that is thy hermony. For as vnto the sicke all pleasure is in vaine, So mirth vnto the wounded minde, encreaseth but his pain. But heauens? what doo I see? thou Nymphe or Lady faire, Or else thou goddes of the groue, what makst thee to repaire. To this vnhaunted place thy presence heere vnfit, Fidelia. Ancient father let it not offend thee any whit. To finde me heere alone I am no Goddesse I, But a mortall maide subiect to miserie. And better that I might lament my heauy mone, I secret came abroad to recreate my selfe a while alone. Bomelio. Take comfort daughter mine for thou hast found him th? That is of others all that liue, the most accursedst man. O, I haue heard it saide our sorrowes are the lesse, If in our anguish we may finde a partner in distresse. Fidelia. O father but my greefe releeued cannot be, My hope is fled, my help in vaine, my hurt my death must be Yet not the common death of life that heere is led: But such a death as euer killes, and yet is neuer dead. Bomelio, Faire maide, I haue been well acquainted with that fit, Sometime iniured with the like, I learne to comfort it. Come rest thee heere with me within this hollow caue, There will I reckon vp at large the horrors that I haue. Fidelia. I thank you father but I must needs walk another way, Bomelio. Nay gentle damsell be content a while with me to stay. Fidelia. The longer that I stay with you, the greater is my greef. Bomelio. The longer that you stay with me, the sooner is releefe. Fidelia. I am prouided other waies, good father let me goe, Bomelio. To him that offreth thee no wrong, be not vncurteous so. Fidelia. Perhaps another time, ile come and visit thee, Bomelio. Both then &amp; now if so you please you shall right welcome be. Armenio. Shall she be welcome vnto thee olde wretch indeed, Ile welcome both of you come maid away with speed. Fidelia. O brother: Armenio, Brother peace. Fidelia. Good father helpe me now. Bomelio. Haue I no weapons wretch that I am? well youth, Ile meete with you. Armenio. Must you be gone? is this your meeting place? Come get you home and pack you sir apace. Weart not for reuerence of thine age I sweare, Thou shouldst accursse the time I met thee heere. But I faith sister my Father shall welcome you, Bomelio. Goe tell thine arrand if thou canst. Fidelia. Hermione adewe. Ten times adewe, farwell for euer now. Armenio. I thanke thee Fortune that thou didst this deed allowe. Exit. Bomelio. Thou Heauen and Earth, and ye eternall lampes, That restles keepe his course in order due: Thou Phœbo bright that scaterest the damps, Of darksome night, I make my plaints to you. And thou Alecto harken to my call, Let fall a Serpent from thy Snakye haire: Tisiphone, be swift to plague them all, That make a pastime of my care and feare. And thou O Ioue, that by thy great foresight, Rulest the earth, and raignst aboue the Skies: That wreakst the wronges of them that maister right, Against the wretches that thy name despise. And Rodomantes, thou Iudge of hatefull hell, UUhere damned ghostes continuall moning make: Send foorth a fury that may further well, the iust reuenge that heere I vndertake. Hence foorth accursed be thou euermore, Accursed all thou tak'st in hand to doo: The time, the day, accursed be the hower, the earth, the ayre, and all that long theretoo. Dole and dispaire hencefoorth be thy delight, UUrapped now in present, and in woes to come: To waile the day and weepe the weary night, And from this time hencefoorth I strike thee dumme. Think'st thou I knew thee not, yes well I wis, And that thy sister daughter to my Prince: Now brag abroad what thou hast got by this, So liue thou dumme, that be thy recompence. And when thy ghost forsakes thy body quite: Uengeance I wishe vpon thy soule to light. Enter Hermione. Hermione. Good euen good Father, pardon my rudenes heere: Bomelio, O ioy and greefe I will dissemble yet my cheare. Hermione, Good sir me thought I heard you speak of one right now Daughter vnto a Prince that made me bold to trouble you Bomelio. I spake of such a one in deed. Hermione. Why doo you knowe her name? Bomelio. Fidelia. Why doo you aske? what doo you know the same? Hermione. Yea father that I doo, I know, and knew her well, But did you wish those plagues to light on her I pray you tell. Bomelio. On her the Gods forbid, but on that wretched wight, Her brother that from hence right now perforce conuayde her quite. Hermione. Alas what doo I heare, good father tell me true. Hath she beene heere? Bomelio. She was. Hermione. She was? Where is she now? Bomelio. Gone back againe. Hermione. Gone back: with whome? Bomelio. Her brother. Hermione. Her brother: how? Bomelio. He secret watched heere, and when she should haue staide A while with me, he rushed out, and her from hence conuaid. Hermione. Confounded in my greefe and can it suffred be? And shall he make a brag at home of his dispite to me? First let me dye a thousand deaths, draw, runne and meete with him, Bomelio. Tarry my Sonne it is in vaine they are not at home I win. Let him alone, he wil not make great reckning of his gaine, Hermione. Wretch that thou art for lingering euerlasting shalbe thy paine. Continuall thy complaint, ay during still thy woe: Why madst thou not more haste to come and first of all to knowe. Bomelio. Content thy self my sonne, torment not so thy minde: Asswage the sorrowes of thy hart in hope some help to finde. Hermione. Some helpe, O Father, no all helpe comes too late, I am the only man aliue the most vnfortunate. I see thy loyaltie, I see thy faithfull loue, Els neuer durst thou this attempte aduentured to proue. Bomelio. Take comfort therby my sonne. Hermione. I am the man I say, That loue and Fortune once aduaunst, but now haue cast away. The ioy, the sweet delight, the rest I had before, Fell to my lot, that now the losse, my plague might be the more. O Fortune froward dame, wilt thou be neuer sure, Most constant in vnconstancie, I see thou wilt indure. Bomelio. Accuse not Fortune sonne, but blame thy loue therfore, For I perceiue thou art in loue, and th? thy trouble is more. Hermione. Father if this be loue to lead a life in thrall, To think the rankest poyson sweet to feed on hunny gall. To be at warre and peace, to be in ioy and greefe, then farthest from the hope of helpe, where neerest is releefe, To liue and dye, to freese and sweat, to melt &amp; not to moue, if it be this to liue in loue, father I am in loue. Bomelio. Why did you not possesse your Lady then at home, Hermione. At home, where is it sir? alas for I haue none. Brought vp I know not how, and borne I know not where, when I was in my childehood giuen vnto my Prince then heere. Of whom I can not tell, wherfore I little know, But now cast out to seeke my fate vnhappy where I goe. There dare I not be seene, heere must I not abide. Did euer more calameties vnto a man betide: Bomelio. My hart will burst if I forbeare amidst this misery, Beholde thy father thou hast found my sonne Hermione. Thy father thou hast found, thy father I am he, Hermione. But is it possible my father you should be. Bomelio. Euen from my first exile heere haue I liu'd forlorne, And once I gaue thee to my prince, for thou was noble born. And now he giues me thee, and welcome home againe, Hermione. This is my recompence for all my former paine. Deere father glad I am to finde you heere aliue, By your example I may learne wt froward chance to striue. Bomelio. Come sonne, content thee now, within a caue to dwell, I will prouide for thy redresse, and all thinges shalbe well. A darksome den must be thy lofty lodging now, Hermione. Father I am well content to take such parte as you. Here is a breathing pit after hard mischance, O gratious Uenus once vouchsafe thy seruants to aduance. Strike vp a noise of Viols, Venus triumphe. Venus. Beholde what loue can woork for their delight, That put affiance in her Deitie: Though heauen and earth against them bend their might, Yet in the end theirs is the victorie. I will in them and they triumphe in me, Let Fortune frowne I will vpholde their state, Yea seeme they neuer so vnfortunate. Fortune. Brag not too much, what thinkst thou I haue doon? Nay soft not yet, my sport is not begun. Musicke. Musick.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The fourth Acte. Enter Penulo and Lentulo. Penulo. Come away with thy basket thou loggerheadded iacke, I thinke thy basket be clouen to thy back. Lentulo. My backe and my basket, looke doost thou not see, When my basket is on my backe then my backe is vnder me. And oh this basket, wots thou wherfore I keepe it so close, For all the loue of my hart within this basket goes. Penulo. Thy loue with a wannion? are you in loue sir then with your leaue: Lentulo. What an asse art thou, couldst thou not all this time perceiue? That I neuer sleep but when I am not awake, And I eate and I eate till my belly would ake. And I fall away like a gammon of Bacon, Am I not in loue when I am in this tacon? Calst thou this the Court, would I had nere come thether, to be caught in Cupido, I faint I faint, oh gather me gather Penolo. Come vp and be hangde, alack poore Lentulo, Tell me with whome thou art in loue so. Lentulo. You kill me and you make me tell her name, no no, Oh terrible tormentes that trounce in my toe. Loue my Maisters is a parlous matter, how it runnes out of my nose, Its now in my back, now in my belly, oh now in the bottome of my hose. Penulo. The pestilence there, what is she my boy? ile make her loue thee againe be she neuer so coye. Lentulo. Wilt thou so? oh Gods of loue that woord pluckes vp my hart, Ile tell thee sirra euen as we two at ye Court gate did wait Didst thou not marke a goodly Lady, oh Lady, Lady, why should not I as well as he, my deare Lady. Didst thou not see her come in with a golden locke, She had a fine gown on her back and a passing netherstock. Penulo. Well sir proceed, I remember her very well, its the Dukes daughter the sot meanes I can tell. Lentulo. Now sirra there was a little dappard asse with her that went before, When I saw him I came in sneaking more and more. To haue heard them talke, ah croching on is good, For when he had talkt a while I had a come in, with I forsooth no forsooth that I wood. And she would haue lookte vpon me then more quaintaunce we should haue: Penulo. An excellent deuise, ah sirra you are an excellent knaue. Lentulo. Tu autem tum autem, I haue it in me, but sirra wots thou what now? As god iuggle me when I came neere them I tell thee true: The same squall did nothing but thus, I know whats what And I ran before him and did thus too. Penulo. A poxe on you what ment you by that? Lentulo. What meane I, mary sir he ment to giue her a box on the eare if she spake to me, And I ment to giue him another box on the eare sir he should see. Penulo. You should haue bestow'd it where you ment it then, Must you strike me and meane other men, Lentulo. Twas nothing fellowe but for samples sake, Penulo. Well sir I am content this once it to take. But sirra, you must know that squall is the Dukes sonne, That now by mischaunce is stroken starke dum. In fetching home his sister that ran away from hence: Lentulo. Is she then a runaway, oh passing wench. I thought as much, now good Lord to see, That she and I now a kin should be. Oh cuckally lucke, oh heauy chaunce ho: I runaway, she runaway, goe together goe. Pennulo. But all the Court lamentes and sore weepes for it: Lentulo. All the Court thou liest ye Court gate weepes not a whit. Enter Bomelio like a counterfeite phisition. Bomelio. Bien veneu chi diue ve mi nou intendite signeur no. I haue a peece of woorke in hand now that all the world must not know. Lentulo. Cocks nownes the deuill a gods name whats he: Penulo. Some Spaniard or forraine stranger he seemes to be. Bomelio. Dio vou salui signiore, e voutre gratio, pauero mouchato. Lentulo. I haue no pleasure in thee I pray thee get thee gon. Penulo. What would you sir? Bomelio. Mounsieur, par ma foy am one haue de grand knowledg in de skience of fiskicke, Can make dem hole haue been all life sicke. Can make te seco see, and te dum speake: Can make te lame goe and be neare so weake. Penulo. Can you so sir, what Cuntry man are you I pray? Bomelio. Ye be Italiane neopolitane, ye come a Uedice a toder daye, Lentulo. And you can speak any Pedlers French tell me what I say. Bomelio. No point intende Signiora. Lentulo. You are an Asse: I can spose him I, Bomelio. Mounsieur, parle petite ye heard now heerby. Deere be a nobell man dum, dat made me stay: If me no helpe him me carry no head away. Penulo. Will you venture your head to helpe him indeed: Well sir, Ile tell the Duke with all possible speed. Tarry me heere Ile returne by and by, Excellent luck, it fals out happely. Exit. Lentulo. Will you venture your head sirra blockhead you: Bomelio. You be de asse head me can tell dats true. Lentulo. Swoundes, oh but that I am in loue thou shouldst know UUhat twere to moue my vengeance so. Bomelio. Come heter sirra, me speak wit you, me can tell, You are de runaway from your matter, ah very well. Lentulo. You gods and deuils eke what doo you meane to doo, Shall I be knowne a runaway, for and to shame me too, I a runaway sirra, goe with your vplandishe goe, I am no runaway I would you should know. Bomelio. You no runaway from your mater in de wood, UUhen he send you to market ah no point good. Lentulo. Oh furies fell, and hagges of hell, with all that therin be, What doo ye mean to shame me clean, &amp; tell him thus of me. Heare you sirra you are no deuill, mas and I wist you were, I would lamback the deuill out of you for all your geare. Bomelio. Diauolo, ah fie fie me no diauolo me very fury, Letta me see your basket what meat you buye. Lentulo. Looke in my basket, oh villen rascall tarry, stay, Hath opened it: out alas my loue is quite flowne away. My loue is gone, my loue is gone out of the basket there, Prepare therfore to kil thy self, farwell my freendes so deere. Bomelio. Ah fatta you doo man. Lentulo. Uplandishe hence away, Bomelio, Fatta you doo man, no point your selfe to slay. Come de be hanga. Lentulo. Alas, oh my necke alas. Oh frying pan of my head vplandish now, cham woorse then euer was. Adewe farwell, farwell my loue. Bomelio. Your loue? if you be in loue den doo as I bid doo, And you slaue your loue away wit you too. Lentulo. Uplandish oh my freend if thou doo so for me, Hold heer my hand, thy fellow freend and partner will I be. Bomelio. Goe you ten and getta me some fine fine fine colosse, And wit te Marigole leaue all to mus your nose. Lentulo. Ah my nose my nose, oh God is my nose in my hand, Uplandish leaue your signes without th? I can vnderstand. Bomelio. And come a me heter wit a gold ring in your mouth fast, Ee make de Lady goe wit you weter list at last. Lentulo O let me brace thy cursed corpes, oh now I liue againe, I will goe get apparell straight, although be to my paine. Tis th'apparell, a Marigole and a ring, Bomelio. Noting els, and you tem bring. Lentulo. Bring them, yes I warrant thee, ile bring th? by and by, Now good man Uenus lend thy hand, and lady Uulcan hye. Exit. Bomelio. A good beginning I am not yet discride, They know not me but I know them too well: Disguised thus their counsells may be tride, And I may safe returne vnto my sell. UUhere I haue left my solitarye Sonne, Twixt hope and feare in doubt and danger too: Till I returne to tell him what is doon, which for his sake I haue deuisde to doo. Eternall Gods that know my true intent, And how vniustly wronged I haue been: Uouchsafe all secret dangers to preuent, And further me as yet you doo begin, Suffiseth you my trauell heretofore, My hunger, colde, and all my former paine, Heere make an end and plague me now no more. Contented then, at rest I will remaine: But harke some comes dissemble then againe. Enter the Duke, his Sonne, and Penulo. Penulo. My Lord yon is the man whom I haue tolde to you. Duke. My freend I am infourm'd that by thy woorthy skill, In Phisick thou art able to recouer at thy will. The strangest cures that be: if this be true indeed, As graunt the Gods it may, I pray thee then with speed, Prouide for our releefe, recouer this my sonne: Unto his speech, whom heere thou seest before vs to be dum. Bomelio. You no take care vor dat me nobell Prence, Me make him speak againe, or me nere come hence. Duke. Thrice welcome th? to vs dispatch it out of hand, And thou shalt blesse the time that ere thou cam'st vnto our land. Bomelio. Letta me see him, you heare me: Ah dat vel turne heter, no like it truely. Penulo. By the masse this Phisick is an excellent arte, It pickes such a deale of golde out of euery parte. Bomelio. Uell vell, me now see vat dis matter meane, Nobell Prence dis ting be done by Mashick cleane. Tis true dat me tell, me perceiue it plaine, No naturall pediment, but cunshering certaine. Duke. Oh dubble trebble woe, my sonne how commeth this? He saith by Magick it is wrought, vnnaturall it is. Doost thou remember ought that so it should appeere? Or canst thou any reason make it should be true we heare? What meanes he by these signes, can any one expresse, Penulo. If you giue me leaue sir to say as I gesse. Me thinkes he should meane there was some olde man, That threatned to be reuenged on him than. Tis so you may see, he confirmes it againe: Duke. Condemned be that man to euerlasting paine. Perpetuall his annoy, continuall his vnrest: O that I had him heere to plague as I thought best. But learned sir, is there no way is there no remedy: Can there be found out no deuise, the Charme to mollefie. Good sir, if any thing what euer that it be: Let spare no cost, my will is such I will allowe it thee. Bomelio. Indeed and by my trot, dar is othing, But me am vera lote de same to bring. Yit wit out dat me am seawer me tell, Your sonne againe be neuer more well. Duke. Good father tell it me, what euer should befall, Mine be the danger, mine the losse, you shalbe pleased for al. In any case expresse it then. Bomelio. Fat then me will, If you no haue your sonne be so dum still, You musse getta de grand enemy dat he now haue, and in de tenderest part his deerest blood craue. Derwit musse you wash his tung a string, Noting but dat will his speach bring. Duke. The deerest blood in the tenderest parte, Of his great enemy, oh greefe to my hart. Will nothing else cure his disease, Bomelio. Noting by my trot but doo as you please. Duke. My sonne, my wretched sonne, and whom doost thou suppose, Thy greatest enemy amongst thy Fathers foes. It is Hermione, tis he and none but he: He hath now prou'd him selfe indeed thy greatest enemie. Where liues the wretch? that he were tane and we reuenged be. Penulo. And must his deerest blood in his tenderest parte, Helpe him to his speech, thats an excellent arte. But what parte is that my maisters now about a man, That is the tenderest, gesse it and ye can. I can tell what parte a woman thinkes tenderest to be, and there is deere blood in it, but benedicitie. And doo you think sir there is none but he, That can be thought his greatest enemie? I haue heard it saide there is no hate, Like to a brother or a sisters if they fall at debate. I will not say but you may think it as well as I, If you marke since her comming home his sisters crueltie. And the continuall rancor she beareth vnto him: Bomelio. Is ten maide his sister, be Got den he say tim. Bin mine fat and trot ser, tis true dat he say, His sister be his greatest enemy to day. Duke. And must I kill my daughter to help my sonne to speeche, Ile neuer doo it. Penulo. See how a dooth beseech. I would all our beggers were of his qualitie, They should not brall with a man then so for his monye. Bomelio. You kill your Daughter fie no point suo, Her deerest blood in tenderest part me will showe. Tis in her pappes, her dugges vor der be de tenderest parte, And de blood de deerest, it comes from de hart. So she be prickt a little vnder de brest, And wash his tunga he speak wit de best. Duke. This thing is somwhat easier if she consent therto, If not, I can inforce and make her it to doo. Penulo, dispatch, and to my Marshall beare, This Sinet for a token, that he send her to vs heere. Penulo. I will my Lord. Exit. Duke. He that hath felt the zeale, the tender loue and care, The feare the greef that parents deer vnto their children bare He may, and only he conceiue mine inward woe, Distracted thus twixte two extreames that hale me to &amp; fro, Sometime mistrusting that, and then misliking this: Haue parents such a cause of ioy, or is it such a blisse. To see the ofspring of their seed in health before them now, O little know they what mishap awaites the death for you. But sonne, my deerest sonne, recomfort thou thy minde, Fight against fortune and thy fates, when they be most vnkinde, And since I vnderstand what may recouer thee, Make sure account of it: my selfe will doo it presently. But sir, I pray you least my daughter should by feare, Or flight of it be sore abasht, be alwaies ready heere. To stench her wound when you see good, Bomelio. Awe awe she lose but a little blood. Two or tree ounces sha be de very most. Yonder she come, is no she? Duke. The same is she. Enter Fidelia with Penulo. Fidelia. Father, they say you sent for me. Duke. Yea daughter I did so. And mark what I shall say to thee, the cause therof to show. Thou seest thy brother heere, Fidelia. In name but not in kinde, Duke. Well holde thy peace I say, and let me tell my minde. Thy brother heere I say thou seest him striken dumbe, And as this learned man declares, by magick it is doon. But yet there is a way, one thing he telleth me, that will restore him to his speech, that resteth inwardly. Which though I might commaund, yet I intreat to know, Be not so stubborne or vnkinde, thy furtherance to showe. Fidelia. Noble father you can not say, but hitherto I haue, Bin most obedient to your will in all things that you craue. But heerin pardon me, if this I doo deny, I neuer can be made to graunt helpe to mine enemye. My deadly enemy, woorse then my mortall foe, And such a one is he to me for I haue found him so. That laboured euermore to crosse me with despite, But I am glad I may so well his curtesie requite. Penulo A right woman, either loue like an Angell, Or hate like a Deuill, in extreames so to dwell. Duke. But daughter I commaund, and I thy Father too. Fidelia. And I your daughter any thing that lawfull is to doo. Duke. Is it not right and lawfull both, to helpe thy brothers woe? Fidelia. Its neither right nor lawfull sir to helpe my deadly foe. Duke. If he haue beene thy foe, he may become thy freend, Fidelia. And when I see that come to pass, I may some succour send. Duke. But wherfore shouldst thou be so cruell vnto him? Fidelia. Because vnto my deerest freend so spitefull he hath been. Duke. Nay stubborne girle, but then I will constraine thee I, Lay holde on her my selfe will then sith she dooth it deny. Fidelia. Assist me righteous Gods in this extreametie, Bomelio. Ah pardona, pardona, please you let me a while wit her alone, And me warrant me make her consent to you anon. Els me giue her a powder with a little drinke, Wish make her sleepe, and den when she noting tinke. Wit de sharp rasher me prick her by by, And stop it againe and she no feele why. Please you be gone and let vs too alone heere: Me make her consent you no point feare. Duke. Doo it Maister Doctor, and I am bound to you for aye, Ungratious girle that doost deny thy Father to obay. Look to her sir and send me woord when thou hast doon the deed. Bomelio. Awe awe, I fat I fat, me make her bleed. Fidelia. O wretched girle what hope remaines behinde, What comfort can recomfort now thy minde. Forsaken thus of Father and of freend, Why seek'st thou not to bring thy life to end. Can greater woes befall vnto thy share, Come Gentleman dispatch and doo not spare. If it be so his pleasure and thy will, I am content my deerest blood to spill. Deferre not then, holde take thine ayme at mee, And strike me through, for I desire to dye. Bomelio, The Heauens forbid, faire Mayden no not I: I am thy freend, I am no enemye. Feare not, stand vp it is only for thy sake, That I this toyle and trauell vndertake. Thy loue my Sonne is at my caue with me, Safe and in health long looking there for thee. Trust to my woordes faire maide for I am he, That ouertook thee in the wood last day: And till thy comming Hermione I say. Is in my caue. Fidelia. What ioyfull woordes be these, And is Hermione your sonne, doo then as you shall please. Beholde me ready prest to followe any way, Good father doo not thus delude, a simple maide I pray. I trust vnto your woordes, my life is in your power, And till I see Hermione, each minute is an hower. Bomelio. Daughter dismay no whit but trust to me, What I haue saide perfourmed thou shalt see. I haue dissembled with thy Father heere, The better that I might with thee conferre. And since thou art so faithfull to thy loue, As I may well reporte I did thee proue. Let vs be gon now closely as we may: Fidelia. Yea my good Father euen when you will I pray. Thrice blessed be the hower I met with you, My Father now and Brother both adewe. Unkinde to her, most kinde that you should be, I leaue them alll my deere to come to thee. Exeunt. Enter Hermione solus, with bookes vnder his arme. Hermione. O Gods that deepest greefes are felt in closest smart, That in the smiling countenance may lurk ye wounded hart. I see the noble minde can counterfaite a blisse, When ouerwhelmed with a care his soule perplexed is. It is for dastard Knightes that stretch on feather beds: Dispairing in aduersitie so lowe to hang their heads. The better borne the more his magnanimitie: The fearcer fight, the deeper wound, the more vndaunted he. So I perceiue it now, I well perceiue it heere: What I my selfe could not, I learne by thee my father deere. He that in golden age, I meane his lusty youth, Was thought to spend in pleasures lap, without regarde of ruth. He that had lost his time as brauely as the best: Onely deuising how to make his ioyes surmount the rest. Not in that wanton youth, not in that plesant mate: Could fortune with her ficklenesse his wonted minde abate. He rather challengeth to doo her very woorst, And makes a semblance of delight, although indeede accurst. My father therupon deuised how he might, Reuenge and wreak him self on her, that wrought him such dispite. And therfore I perceiue he strangely vseth it, Inchaunting and transfourming that his fancy did not fit. As I may see by these his vile blasphemous Bookes, My soule abhorres as often as mine eye vpon them lookes. What gaine can counteruaile the danger that they bring, For man to sell his soule to sinne, ist not a greeuous thing? To captiuate his minde and all the giftes therin, to that which is of others all the most vngratious sinne. Which so intangleth them that therunto apply: As at the last forsaketh them in their extremety. Such is this art, such is the studie of this skill, this supernaturall deuise, this Magicke such it will. In ransacking his Caue, these Bookes I lighted on: And with his leaue Ile be so bolde whilste he abroad is gon. To burne them all: for best that serueth for this stuffe, I doubt not but at his returne to please him well enough. And Gentlemen I pray, and so desire I shall, You would abhor this study, for it wil confound you all. Exit Enter Lentulo with a Ring in his mouth, a Marigolde in his hand, and a faire shute of apparell on his backe: after he hath a while made some dum shew, Penulo commeth running in with two or three other. Penulo. Runne for the loue of God, search villaines out of hand, Runne I say rascalles, look about ye how doo you stand. The Dukes daughter is gone againe, and all the Courte is in an vprore: A poxe on such a Phisition, he shall counsell her no more. Seriant. See you maister Penulo who is that yonder so braue, Penulo. Cocks blood you villaine what doo you heere you slaue? Swoundes hath rob'd the Duke of a shute of apparell, Why speak you not sirra? yea will you not tell? Lay him on my maisters, spare him not I say: Speak you by signes: one of you pull the Ring away. Seriant. Cocks blood my finger, a bites me, a pestilence there: Lentulo. What meane ye my maisters, what meane ye heere. Penulo. Haue you found your tung sir, oh very well, I pray you sir where had you this shute of apparell. Lentulo. This parell, what and I stole it, whats that to thee? Penulo Mary sir no more but that hang'd you shall be. Lentulo. Then all the world shall see there is somwhat in me, When I am hang'd, O I shall swing lustelye. Mas I shall doo him great credit that hanges me, But if I may be hanged by an Atturnye, I will desire thee the place to supplie. Penulo. Yes marry will I for curtesie sake, Come on your way sir the paines I will take. To bring you before the Duke that he may see, What a proper man in his apparell you be. Lentulo. Wilt thou faith, mas I thank thee hartely. But I must talke a little with our vplandishe heere, And then Ile goe with thee faith any where. Penulo. Uplandish you rascall, where is he now, Hees gone and stole away the Dukes daughter wt him too, Lentulo. Oh my hart, what doo you say? Penulo. Mary that togeather they be both run away. Lentulo Nay then haue after yee behinde Ile not stay, Lentulo. What no such haste with you sir I pray. Lentulo. And is my Lady gone and fled, oh take me vp for I am dead. Farwell my Marigolde, oh villaine Caitife he, By bones and stones, &amp; all the Moones, I will auenged be. Penulo. You shall be reuenged sir, that shall you presently, Away away with him to the Duke by and by. Lentulo. I can goe my selfe and you will let me alone: Now as I walke alas I make to me my mone. When I in prison strong poore soule shall liue and dye: Then will I make my louing song vpon mine own pigsnye. Penulo. Away with him sirs why doo ye tarry? Lentulo. And thou wert in my case thou wouldst not be so hastye. Exit. Penulo. Fie vpon it what a sturre haue we heere? Neuer was noble mans house in such feare. Such hurring, such sturring, such running euery way: Such howling, such crying, such accursing the day. That euer the villaine could counterfaite so, When we least thought of it away with her to goe. But the world is so full of knauery now, That we know not whom to trust I may say to you. If my wife fall sicke as she may, ile make a condition, She shall neuer take counsell of an vplandish Phisition. Hang them knaues, but what a prating keepe I? When I should haue been seuen miles of mine arrand, for why, I must goe set all the Cuntry vp in a watch, If it be possible this Phisition to catch. Enter Bomelio and Fidelia. Stay daughter stay, forbeare thy posting haste, Thou needst not feare, all perils now are past. Thankes to the Gods that such successe they gaue, Thus happely to bring vs to my caue. Fidelia. Oh Father still I feare mishap behinde, Suspect is naturall vnto our kinde. And perils that import a mans decay, Can neuer be estewed too soone they say. Had I a sight of mine Hermione, I care not then what did become of me. Bomelio. I will heerin accomplishe thy desire, So graunt the Gods the rest that I require. Hermione, Hermione, my Sonne I say, Come foorth and see thy freendes that for thee stay. Enter Hermione. Hermione. Welcome my Father but ten times welcome thou, The constant Lady mine that liueth now. Fidelia. And liues Hermione, liues my Hermione, What can be added more to my felicitie. Hermione. Thy life my life, such comfort doost thou giue, Fidelia. Happy my life, because I see thee liue. Bomelio. Whilste they recorde the sweetnesse of their blisse, I will apply to further as they wish. Their sweet delight by magickes cunning so, that happy they shall liue in spite of foe. Hermione. How doubtfull are the lets of loyall loue, Great be the dangers that true louers proue. But when the Sunne after a shower of raine, Breakes through the Clowdes, and shoes his might againe. More comfortable to his glory then, Because it was a while withheld of men. Peace after warre is plesanter we finde, A ioy differd is sweeter to the minde. So I. Fidelia. It hath been saide, that when Vlisses was, Ten yeeres at Troy, and ten yeeres more alas. UUandering abroad as chaunce and fortune lead, Penelope supposing him for dead. But he prouiding still for afterclaps, When he had scapte a thousand hard mishaps, It did him good to recken vp at last, Unto his wife his trauelles he had past. And sweetly then recording his distresse, To make the more account of happines. So I. Hermione. Then as the Turtle that hath found her mate, Forgets her former woes and wretched state. Renewing now her drowping hart againe, Because her pleasure ouercomes her paine. The same of thy desired sight I make, Whereon thy faith, thy hart and hand I take. Fidelia. And so I sweare to thee vnfeinedly, To liue thine owne, and eke thine owne to dye. Enter Bomelio. Bomelio. Gogs blood villins, the deuil is in the bed straw, wounds I haue been robd, robd, robd, where be the theeues, my books bookes did I not leaue thee with my bookes, where are my bookes, my bookes, where be my bookes villin, arrant villen. Hermione. O father my deere father harke. Bomelio. Father, my deere father, Soule giue me my Bookes, lets haue no more tarrying, the daye begins to be darke, it raines, it begins with tempestes, thunder and lightning, fire and brimstone, and all my bookes are gone, and I cannot helpe my selfe, nor my freendes, what a pestilence who came there. Hermione. Ile tell you father if you please to heare. Bomelio. What canst thou tel me, tel me of a turd, what and a come I coniure thee foule spirit down to hell, ho ho ho the deuil, the deuill, a coms, a coms, a coms vpon me and I lack my books. help, help, help, lend me a Swoord, a swoord, oh I am gone. Fidelia. Alas how fell he to this madding mood, Hermione. The heauens and earth deny to doo vs good. Fidelia. O father, my good father look on me. Bomelio. What ment I not to shut vp the doore, and take the keies with me, and put the books vnder the bed straw, out you hore, a hore, a hore, gogs blood Ile dresse you for a hore, I haue a cause to curse hores as long as I liue, come awaye come away, giue me my bookes, my bookes giue me, giue me, giue. Fidelia. Help, help me good Hermione. Exit. Hermione. I come of worldes of miserie. Confounded in the top of my delight, The Fates and Fortune thus against me fight. Exit. Fortunes Triumph, sound Trumpets, Drummes, Cornets and Gunnes. Fortune. See madam who can dashe your brauery, Euen at the pitch of your felicitie. When you assure that they shall stedfast stand. Euen then my power I suddeinly can showe, Transposing it, as it had neuer been so. Heerin I triumph, heerin I delight, Thus haue I manifested now my might. Heere Ladies learne to like of Venus lure, And me loue long your pleasures shall indure. Venus. Now thou hast doon euen what thou canst I see, They shall be once againe releeu'd by me. Musicke. Musick.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The fifth Acte. Mercury. Ye goddesses of this eternitie, To whom of right belonges each earthly thing. The King of Gods salutes ye both by me. And I beseech you marke the newes I bring. My father Iupiter perceiuing well, What hath heerin oft been doon by each of you: O how ye still indeuour to excell, Maintaining that wheron the quarrell grewe. That is the gouernment of this estate, And vnto whome the soueraintye shall fall: Heere therfore to conclude your long debate, Least your contention may be counted generall. Desires ye both, and so commaundes by me: Ye stand to his conclusion of the cause: How say you therfore will you now agree, that malice may no longer right delude. Venus. Brother Mercury, as I haue neuer been, So obstinate or bent so frowardly: But that I could some time relent the ill, A woman must a little haue her will. So am I now resolued for to doo, What so my Father shall intreate me too. Fortune. And all the world by me perceiueth well, Of course my fancy, my fauour and my skill. And when my cause a little course hath had, I am well pleased and no longer sad. Mercury. Then thus our Father Iupiter concludes, To stay the stroake of your vnceasing strife: As heeretofore betwixt these louers twaine, Ye haue exprest your powers vpon their life. So now he willes you to withholde your handes, Enough suffiseth to confirme your might: And to conioyne ye both in freendly bandes, Of faithfull loue wherin the Gods delight. His pleasure is, that Lady Uenus you, Shall be content neuer to hinder them: To whome Dame Fortune shall for freendship showe, Of wretched to procure them happy men, Ne shall you Fortune once presume to take, The credit of the honor in your hand: If Lady Uenus doo them quite forsake, You shall not seeme in her defence to stand. But whome soeuer one of you preferre, The other shall be subiect vnto her. For thus hath Iupiter determined now, Venus. I must and will subscribe my will to you. Fortune. And I most gladly therof doo allow. Venus. Whom Fortune fauours I will not dispise, Fortune. Whom loue reiectes by me shall neuer rise. Mercury, To this conclusion doo you both agree? Venus. For my parte. Fortune. And I most willingly. Mercury. Then let your vnion be confirmed againe, By proper course eche one in his discent: Ouer mortall men and worldly thinges to raine, By enterchange as Iupiter hath ment. Mercury. And freendly Fortune let me intreate alone, Sith by your meanes these louers hindred were: And now ye two are reconcilde in one, You graunt the grace their honour vp to reare. Venus. Sweet Mercury, I giue thee my consent, I will forthwith aduaunce them to renowne: And their destruction better to preuent, They shall releeue them that did throw them downe. Fortune. And I my gracious fauour will bestowe, Upon them all according to desarte: And I will helpe his fransie ere I goe, Mercury. That Beadlom vp and down he replaies his parte. Enter Bomelio with Hermione, and Fidelia, with a Cope and Dagger. Bomelio. Hots wounds ye here I am not for your diet, hang rascal make a leg to me, by Gogs blood Ile stab thee through, what the deuill the deuill and all my bookes be gon: O most accursed man Bomelio, goe hide thy selfe, goe hide thy selfe, goe hang thy selfe, goe hang. Ile hang the hore out of hand, and as for you villin, stand rascall stand. Fidelia. Good Father heare me, come take a little rest, Yea my sweet Father come sleepe vpon my brest. Bomelio. Hark y e hore, see what an impud?t hore it is, sleep you hore ile sleep with you anon, gogs blood you hore, ile hang you vp, Fidelia. Helpe helpe Hermione. Hermione. Good father let her alone, come let vs goe, Mercury. Now with my musick ile recure his woe. Play. Bomelio. Hark harke my hartes, Pipes, Fiddels, oh braue, I shall haue my bookes againe, daunce about, Robin Hood is a good knaue, come besse lets goe sleep, come besse together together Mercury. Now will I charme him that he shall not wake, Untill he be releeued in this place: Then take her blood and cast it on this brake. And therwithall besprinckle all his face. And he shall be restored to his sence, His health and memory as heeretofore: Doo this for I must now departe from hence, And so your sorrowes shall increase no more. Hermione. Fidelia, what hast thou heard my deere, O comfortable woordes were they but true: If any God or Goddesse be so neere, Uouchsafe of pitie on our paines to rue. Delude not with a fained phantasie: The wretched minde of men in miserie. Fidelia. Alas Hermione, let vs not feede And flatter our selues with my good surmise: We are too much accursed so to speed, Or any hope therof for to deuise. Resolue your selfe deere freend another way, And let vs neuer looke for happy day. Enter Phizantius, Armenio, Penulo, and Lentulo. Phyzan. When thirst of hot reuenge inflameth high desire, When malice blindeth so the minds of them yt would aspire. That to inlarge their names, they wreak not his dispite, That ouerseeeth all their woorkes, their dooinges to requite. Marke then what followeth when Princes ye prouoke, The deeper &amp; the larger wound when longest is the stroake. And this hath moued me to leaue my Court a while, To be content in sweat of browes, in trouble paine &amp; toyle. To seeke out wretches them that haue abus'd me so, And to rewarde their villany according ere we goe. Penulo. May it please your honour it is excellent doon, Gogs blood and I were a Prince and had such an noble Sonne. That should be so highly abused as he hath been, Would I put it vp? no by his wounds I would neuer lin. Till I had made such a mingle mangle vpon their nose, That their skin should serue to make me a dublet and a paire of hose. Lentulo. What you would not? I faith you look not with the face, Wh? you haue their skin sir, what wil you doo with the case? But maister Prince, since you are come to this trauelation, Ile bring you to mine olde maisters conuoculation. Where he hides him selfe when I ran away: Its not farre within these woods: how think you sir I pray? Phyzan. Lead on the way and I will follow thee, Lentulo. Why then come on my valiant harts, march on and followe me. But Ile make this bargaine first, heare you me what I say? When I come home you shall not let my maister beate me for running away. Phyzan. He shall not I warrant thee: Lentulo. UUhy then my noble youths of Oke pluck vp your harts with me. Wil you come sir, come on I faith keep in order you thereby: We shall finde her I faith maister Prince anon I know. And then Ile trounce him for running away with an other mans wife I trowe. Penulo. Stand sir, who lyes a sunning yonder can you tell? Lentulo. Its a Begger with a Roge. Phyzan. It is my daughter I see full well. Hermione. Fidelia be content, shrinke not at all, Phyzan. Strike not a stroke my sonne. Penulo. For helpe I shall goe run and call. Phyzan. And art thou found false traitour and vntrue: Traitour to him that delte so well with thee: Did I deuise to stop that would insue, And found my cares such issue as I see. I see I am abused too too much, And too much sufferance is cause of this abuse, This high abuse of yours as being such, Affordes no cloke nor colour of excuse. O where is thankfulnesse and loue become? UUhere is feare of Princes wrath exilde? Euen this is the vnhappinesse of some, To be of them they trusted moste beguilde, But sometime pardon breedes a second ill: Thou shamelesse wench, and thou false harted knight, By your vnhappy deedes I learne this skill. But yet I list not kill thee as I might, Her will I haue and keepe her as I may, On paine of death I charge thee hence away. Hermione. O Prince, this sentence hath his force and strength, And dead I am that heere appeer to liue: For how alas can this my life haue length, When she is hence that life and sence dooth giue. But since alas I must be only he, UUhom Fortune vowes to make a common game: Armenio my foe doo this for me, With thy reuenge to end my open shame. To helpe thee to disgest thine iniurie, Appease thee with Hermiones tragedie. Fidelia. Farre be the thought of that accursed deede, O sweete Hermione my sweet Hermione: Foule be his fall that makes thy body bleede, O sweete Hermione my sweete Hermione. And father this I vowe, forgiue it me, I will be sacrifice for this offence: And or I will haue my Hermione, My chosen loue: or neuer parte from hence. Him haue the destinies ordained mine: Most woorthy, me your daughter euery way: Nor he to any will his choice resigne. No more my troubled thoughts will let me say. Phyzan. What wilt thou foolishe girle and obstinate, Saist thou this treason is deuisde by fate. That shall we trie, dispatch her hence away, Lets see who dares our princely will gainsay. Penulo. Sir, and youle haue vs carry her, heere be them come of the carriers: Lentulo And youle haue vs marry her, heere be them come of the marriers. Penulo. Lord I maruell to whose share this Lady will fall, I am sure my parte in her wilbe least of all. Venus and Fortune shew themselues and speak to Phizantius, while Hermione standeth in a maze. Venus. Hye time it is that now we did appeare, If we desire to end their miserie: Fortune. Phizantius stay, and vnto vs giue eare, What thou determinest perfourmed cannot be. Phyzan. Dread goddesse, whatsoeuer of this place, If I heerin haue disobaied thy grace. Of fauour graunt for to remit the same, Let me not suffer vndeserued blame. Venus. Phizantius stand vp be of good cheere, None but thy freendes are met together heere. Thy freends though goddesses in other thinges, Yet enterchange an alteration bringes. And now wheras you seeke in what you can, To let your childe to marry with this man. Knowe that it is the pleasure of our will, That they together be conioyed still. For tis not so, he is not borne so base, As you esteeme, but of a noble race. His Father is the good Bomelio, That sleepeth heere opprest with woe. UUhom Phalaris thy father on a false reporte, In wrath and anger banished his Court. But this is he to whom thou wishest oft good, And this his Sonne borne of a noble blood. Thinke it no scorne to thee or thine heerafter, To haue his Sonne espoused to thy daughter. Phyzan, Right gracious Goddesse if this be true indeed, As I beleeue, because from you it dooth proceed. Then pardon me, for had I knowne it so, His Sonne had neuer tasted of this woe. Unwitting of his linage till this time, But I presumed sprung of a noble line. But hence and please your dieties my greefe, Because my Sonne is dumbe without releefe. Penulo. I faith sirra thou and I may holde our peace with their leaue, For none but wise men speak heere I perceiue. Lentulo. In some respectes so, in some respectes not, For a fooles bolte is soone enough shot. Fortune. Phizantius feare no longer his distresse, The gratious Gods prouide for his redresse. The shedding of thy daughters deerest blood, Shall both to him and to this man doo good. For let this Fearne be dipt in many a place, And as he sleepeth cast it in his face. And let his tung be washed there withall, And both of them releeued see you shall. Phizan. How say you daughter will you graunt therto, Fidelia. Most willing sir if you vouchsafe to doo. But this request which I most humbly pray, Then I may be Hermiones for aye. Phyzan. With all my hart heeron I giue my hand. Fidelia. I take it sir, and to your woord I stand. And for thy sake Hermione my deare, See what I doo, although it touch me neere. Now take thy fill and for his madnesse proue, Hermione. O sweet and fearefull sight the signe of loue. Lentulo. If it be any sweeter masters that runnes from you so. I pray you giue me some of your blessinges ere you goe. Armenio. I striue to speak and glad I finde my speeche, Forgiue Hermione, forgiue me I beseech. And you good sister pardon my freends too, Too rash in all I ventured to doo. See what proceedeth from vnstable youth, Shame to him selfe, and to his freendes a cause of ruthe. Hermione. Armenio long hath my end desired, To heare the proffer of this plesant peace: Which sith the Gods doo graunt as we require, Hence foorth let rancor and contention cease. And in our brest be knit for euer sure, The linkes of loue perpetuall to indure. Bomelio. What haue I heard? what is it that they say? Amazed quite, confounded euery way, My sonne Hermione, I know that is the same, And thats my Prince, now comes greefe and shame. Phizan. My Lord Bomelio shun not, I know you now, Forgiue the fact my Father did to you. And what he did impute it not to me, Thy former place I will restore to thee, In token of our faithfull amitie, UUe will be ioyned in neere affinitie. Bomelio. Long liue Phizantius, long liue in happy ease, The Gods be blest I liue this day to see: What please the one shall neuer me displease. Thrise happy now for all my misery. Penulo Why then sir, sith euery thing is come to so good an end, I hope my good master youle stand my good freend. And giue me but two or three thousand pound a yeere to liue on. Lentulo. Much in my nock Nicols you and I shal slaue it anon. Armenio. Assure thee Penulo thou shalt not want as long as I liue, Lentulo. Why then maister, mine olde Maister, I pray you forgiue, Your old runaway, twas for fashion sake, Ile doo so no more Bomelio. Look you doo not sirra and then I pardon you therfore. Venus. Thus euery thing vnited is by loue, Now Gods and men are reconcilde againe: On whome because I did my pleasure proue, I will reward you for your former paine. Receiue the fauours of our dietie, And sing the praise of Venus soueraintie. Fortune. And for I plaid my parte with Lady loue, While eche did striue for cheefe authoritie: Your good deserts dame Fortune so dooth moue, To giue these signes of liberalitie. Thus for amendes of this your late vnrest, By Loue and Fortune ye shall all be blest. And thus heerof this inward care I haue, That wisdome ruleth loue and Fortune both: Though riches faile and beauty seeme to saue, Yet wisdome forward still vnconquered goeth. This we beseech you take freendly in woorth. And sith by loue and fortune our troubles all doo cease, God saue her Maiestie that keepes vs all in peace. Now they and we doo all triumphe in ioy, And loue and fortune are linked sure freendes: All greefe is fled for your annoy. Fortune and loue makes all amendes. Let vs reioyce then for the same, And sing hye praises of their name. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>