<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Heraud, John A., (John Abraham), 1799-1887</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Heraud, John A., (John Abraham), 1799-1887</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">heraud john a john abraham 1799 1887</field>
      <field name="author_text">Heraud, John A., (John Abraham), 1799-1887</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1870's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V3.0656.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1877</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460985</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Uxmal ; An Antique Love Story</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Uxmal ; An Antique Love Story</field>
      <field name="title_facet">uxmal</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">uxmal</field>
      <field name="title_text">Uxmal ; An Antique Love Story</field>
      <field name="year_display">1877</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1877</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1877</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460985&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460985&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Heraud, John A., (John Abraham), 1799-1887&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;heraud john a john abraham 1799 1887&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Uxmal ; An Antique Love Story&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;uxmal&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1877&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1877&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Heraud, John A., (John Abraham)&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1799&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1887&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Uxmal&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;An Antique Love Story&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Simpkin, Marshall &amp;amp; Co.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1877&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3873321-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv30656&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Uxmal&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;An Antique Love Story&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 201 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted. Poetry omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Macee de Leodapart.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Drama.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1877.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Unknown.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">MACÉE DE LÉODEPART. An Historical Romance IN FIVE NUMBERS.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Persons Represented. Macée de Léodepart (Wife of Jacques Cœur). Jeanne de Vendôme (her Confident). Marie D'Anjou (Queen of Charles VII.). Agnes Sorel (her Maid of Honour). Charles VII. (King of France). Jacques Cœur (his Argentier). Jean du Village (Cœur's Steward). Alain Chartier (a Poet). Sieur de Giac (Courtier). Le Camus de Beaulieu (Courtier). George de la Trémouille (a Noble). Antoine de Chabannes, Comte de Dammartin (an Écorcheur). Ctto Castellani (Treasurer of Toulouse). Guillaume Gymart (Factor). Gaillardet (Factor). Mathieu D'Ecole (Abbot of the Convent of Cordeliers at Beaucaire). Duclere (Cordelier). Simonet (Cordelier). Michelet (a Captain). Legate from Pope Nicholas, Soldiers, Attendants, &amp;c.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Scene.—BOURGES—ROUEN—JUMIÈGES—MARSEILLES AND BEAUCAIRE. Period.—Fifteenth Century.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">For Costumes, vide “The Life of Jacques Cœur, the French Argonaut and his Times,” by Louisa Stuart Costello, 1847.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">I. The Court of Love. Scene—The Town Hall at Bourges, fitted up for “the Court of Love.” Alain Chartier and the Sieur de Giac. Giac. This hall is furnished for the Court of Love. Chartier. 'Tis fairly furnished. Giac. O mon Dieu!—and note, That there king Réne's sister will preside; Thence speak the sentence, in the suit between King Charles and our rich merchant. Chartier. But in the way Of gallantry, you guess—for both are married, Cæsar and Crœsus. Giac. Whose shall be the fair Agnes Sorel. Mon Dieu! King Réne's sister, Our Charles's queen, shall judge between the rivals! The merchant's spouse (beshrew her!) likes it not. Think you, king Réne would esteem this sport A fitting pastime? Chartier. Tush! tush! A merry suit— A very merry suit, and well designed To make the languid hours the king here spends, In forced seclusion, move with livelier speed. King Réne, royal troubadour, who sings Of love and love and love, his constant theme, Knows every mood of the platonic heart, Will, when he hears it, feel but one regret— That he was absent from the dainty show, And envy me, his rival in sweet song. Besides, to tell the truth, our Charles, from boyhood, Zealous and valiant, needs awakening, yet, By some device or other—for his spirit Affects a learned ease, and would forget He has a throne to win—that the town of Bourges Is not the city of Paris, nor this castle The palace of his fathers. To this end, The queen herself with the aforesaid Agnes, And rich Jacques Cœur, contrived this merry suit. Giac. O ciel! Who bears the cost? Chartier. Who but Jacques Cœur. Giac. What, he? Chartier. He, the king's king—whom wanting, were no king. Has the king gold, it was from the merchant's chest; Does the king feast, it is from the merchant's larder. In truth, our Charles were pauper but for Cœur, Here suffering disinherison in Bourges, While there in Paris, and the rest of France, The English and Burgundian sway the realm. But, soft! who comes in haste?—What storm's ahead? Le Camus de Beaulieu enters. Beaulieu. The king's insulted, and, for once, incensed. Chartier. By whom? Beaulieu. La Trémouille. Chartier. How?—when? Beaulieu. He met the king, This instant, coming hither; walked up to him, Looking defiance, then, with scoffing lip, Hailed him with, “King of Bourges! how goes the day?” As Bourges were all his sovereignty. Chartier. In sooth, A bitter jest! O crownéd poverty! For all thy crown, thou art not reverenced more Than the bare head, but, therefore rather scorned, And pitied less. Giac. The king resented it? Beaulieu. How, you may see; there come they. King Charles and suite with George De La Trémouille enter. Charles. Set him free. Now, by my chivalry, this is a knight, Affects the clown; that, when he doffs his smock, Surprise may quicken mirth. Trémouille. You say right well; A knight am I, one born of noble line; No man of the people, like your favourite Cœur, But courtly of the court, and loathing riches That grow on mean descent. Charles. Well, one like you Should know good manners. Why did you forget them? Trémouille. Because my king forgot that he was king, And let the ignoble sway him, to the wrong Of such as were his peers. Charles. Now, by the cross! Whom have I wronged? Trémouille. (smiting his breast). George de la Trémouille! Charles. I know thee now; thou hast pronounced thy name, And in that name thy condemnation, too. Now, hear me speak. Man, thou wouldst purchase lands, Broad lands, for twenty thousand golden crowns. The golden crowns thou hadst not, so the owner Sold them, instead, to him who had. Trémouille. Yes, to Jacques Cœur, Who now is lord of Toucy and Fargeau. Their ancient castles to plebeian rule Have thus been forced to bow. I plead my rights, My order's rights, against a merchant's coins. Charles. You have done so. Your suit was urged and heard, And the stern law has judged the lands are his. Trémouille. By undue means decision was obtained. Charles. On a king's honour, you mistake yourself, Your cause, the trial, and its righteous issue. No more!—begone!—you are pardoned! Trémouille. Maybe! Well— But never pardon I the wealthy upstart— Let him be lord of Toucy, or king of France; My vengeance, on the daïs or the throne, Spreads o'er him ruinous wings, and, vulture-like, With sudden swoop, shall fall. [Goes out. Charles. Alas, for state! When birth and merit strive for precedence. No choice for me. My gratitude, my love, This Cœur has nobly earned; he has them both, Is worth them—the magnanimous of soul Takes rank with monarchs. Go thy sordid way, Proud Trémouille; thou canst not match with Cœur. Now, to our queen. The hall is well prepared, Though o'er its morn, this churl has thrown a cloud, Our joyance shall, unchecked, shine out at noon. [Goes out, followed by his suite and the rest. Enter Macée de Léodepart and Jeanne De Vendôme, followed by La Trémouille. Trémouille. Your pardon, madam. Do I not address The wife of merchant Cœur. Macée (with dignity). You do. Your name? Trémouille. 'Tis one as proud. Macée. So, sir! my speech was civil. Trémouille. Yes; coldly civil; such as well befits The highborn to the mean. We must change places. Macée. Strange! but I have scanned him well. It must be he. None other were so rudely arrogant. La Trémouille, I guess? Trémouille. Right, madam! Macée. To My lord, then, bear thy plaints, strive thou with him. Shame to thy malice, that so low can stoop! Taunt unoffending woman—shame! shame! shame! Trémouille. True; the new gallantry might have taught me better; I knew not you were teacher in that school. You suffer wrong, I grant, yet not from me; True words are spoke in jest. This merry suit Has a pre-argument. Loves not your Cœur, In earnest sort, fair Agnes? Chance gives oft Proof vainly sought on purpose. In the question, Was late between us, when I met him once; Who sat within his chamber, cheek to cheek, Alone with him—familiar as twin doves? Agnes Sorel is charming—very charming. Another time— Macée. No other time. Nor that— Nor this! You know not Cœur. Be silent, sir! Here comes my lord—he'll better answer you. Jacques Cœur enters with a retinue. Trémouille. No! let him answer you; I have done with him. You are the daughter of a generous house; Much you forgot in yielding to his wooing; May, haply, all forget. The man is wealthy, And gold buys license. Heed you not? Macée. Cœur! husband! This man would to the mind of thy Macée, Suggest the yellow plague of jealousy; Of thee and thy high motives ignorant— This Trémouille. Cœur. Scorn him. Let him be sure, Before he judges us, he hath the skill. I've not yet heard the muses ever taught him, Song, legend, masque, love-lore, or any lore; So let him canker in his ignorance. What! moody? Macée. But a thought. Some other time. Cœur. Beloved Macée! I may not brook a doubt— I have a task that needs expediences, And least from you may meet impediment. Look up more clearly. Macée. Base suggestion, hence! I have no dread of thee, no doubt of thee; But much for thee I do both doubt and dread, Knowing that Mammon is a treacherous god, Expediency a quicksand. But, no more— I will perform my errand; then return. Come, Jeanne Vendôme. [Exeunt Macée and Vendôme. Cœur. La Trémouille! beware! You will do well in future to be guarded In uttering your shrewd guesses. Trémouille. Have a care More of your deeds than of my words. Cœur. My deeds? They're honour's! All my aims are acts—they're prudent, And in their wisdom prosper. Macée re-enters. Have you sped? Macée. Not well. But here comes he I sought. Trémouille. What Charles, Or Chartier? O, madam! keep you clear Of kings and minstrels, or your peace is wrecked. Macée. You're troublesome. Hail to your Majesty! Charles, Chartier, Beaulieu, and Giac re-enter. Charles. Madame Macée! you're well encountered where Our queen instructed our dull sense to find you. I come to plead with you in her behalf, And that of the fair Agnes. I myself To plead, in her majestic name, the cause Of gallantry—such innocence of sport, Has its one source in generous sentiment And sympathy of mind, alike commended By grave philosophy and pleasant song. Her great example should with thee prevail, To me conditioned, as thou art to him Thy wise and prudent lord. Macée. I do obey— And will take part in the day's show, convinced, By such authority, of a subject's duty. Charles. Then all here stay—anon, the court will form, Our queen will enter in her state; myself And my friend Cœur are suitors. Here stay we. You, Chartier, with song amuse the time. Song (By Alain Chartier). Upon these lips once kissed by thee, O princely Marguerite! Is sealed a spell that bides with me, And makes my lays so sweet; For still they sing of chivalry, And love, for nobles meet. The vulgar soul the tender charm Interprets, as it must; But genial hearts, with passion warm, Can yet be fond and just. Love only can with life inform And consecrate our dust! Queen Marie d'Anjou, with a numerous train of Ladies and Knights, here enters and assumes the throne. Queen. Ladies and knights! 'tis with unwonted pride, That, in your Court of Love, your queen accepts The honoured judgment-seat. Ill were the blood That was my sire's, transmitted to these veins, If I acknowledged not the noble impulse, Of men makes heroes and of women angels. What is the amorous suit? Charles. It touches one, Agnes Sorel, a maid belonging late To princess Isabella of Lorraine, Now to your majesty—therefore to me. Your's her good sense, fine wit and finer grace; And therefore mine! 'Twere waste for me to praise The fascination and the loveliness Of all acknowledged. Early seen by me, This heart platonic influence soon avowed, By you permitted. Queen. Is there nought else? Charles. This— A man we call and know to be our friend, With head more cool, but heart as warm as ours, Of fortune favoured more—no king in name, Yet king in means—consorts fair Agnes too, Is smiled upon by her, and holds her ear With soft persuasion, corresponds with her, Has daily, hourly intercourse—until, With fear our Agnes may prove infidel, Our jealous soul is troubled. Queen. Would ye, we Impose restraint on her, or him? You are not To learn, love will not be restrained. You're heard. What answers the defendant? Cœur. Queen of beauty, Fair arbitress of love! your majesty, Suffice it that I plead, the plaintiff is Disqualified—his love forepledged and wed. Queen. He has confessed as much. And is not yours? Cœur. Confession is not proof. Did I confess, There yet were needed witness. Queen. 'Tis at hand. Macée de Léodepart! come into court. Macée. Must I play such a part? Well! I submit. Here, royal mistress. Queen. You've heard the argument. Proceed. Macée. Belovèd queen! that I am wed to Cœur, Is known to all, and therewith satisfied I would conclude; but that most high example Might justify conjecture, I were fain To be content with a divided heart; Which is not so. Fidelity in mine, Would mirrored find itself in that deep sea; Even his, where all my treasures buried lie; Whereof bereavèd, abject poor were I! Cœur. A wife unparalleled—a priceless jewel! Talk you of treasures, girl? Why, all my wealth Were not of worth to buy such! Voyaged far Have I; seen heaps of gold and diamonds, And gorgeous works in colour and in stone, In Italy, and in the Oriënt— But never gem so whole, so pure, so stainless, As that true heart of thine! Queen. Such ecstacies Throw doubt upon the trial; cause the need Of Agnes' beauteous presence to be felt, To prove the merchant rival to the king. Cœur. Let her, I pray, be sent for. Queen. Be it so. Meanwhile, this lady may have proof to render. Macée. I would not, of my voluntary act, Abate the pleasure of the time and place; Yet not, for its promotion, would I wanton With my best feelings, and grow fabulous. Jacques Cœur has been to me a faithful lord, Honest and true, of the old-fashioned sort. —What, if on lady Agnes he has looked With a delightful eye; . . I know to him Fair things are pleasing:—What, though he have listened To the rich music of her speech; . . I know That hers floats wisdom on its melodies;— What, though he frequents her society; There are state reasons for it. The true wife Would not abridge her husband's liberty— Sure of his heart, he free may roam the world! Chartier. The lady Agnes comes. Agnes Sorel enters, attended. Queen. My royal lord! Madam Macée, methinks, hath read us both A lesson we should heed. Charles. Next, list to Agnes! Doubtless, we both shall ready quittance have. What saith the fair Sorel? What passages Of love 'twixt wealth and beauty have there been? Sorel. A pretty allegory you suggest, My sovereign liege—but one, methinks, so old, It well were obsolete; yet will not perish, While Jupiters descend in golden showers, The Danäes will prove mothers. Charles. Then, poor Charles To richer Cœur must yield. Queen. “Must”? “Must”—in love! Love's queen in me resists compulsion's law. The richer Cœur is barred by his chaste wife, Who here, in court, objects her prior claim: And we that prior claim now ratify. —But he, the royal plaintiff in love's suit, Hath now no wife, who can, before love's throne, Hold him in bar. Free privilege is his, To woo and win fair Agnes, if he may. But much I doubt her heart is turned away. Charles. Thanks for thy sentence, love's best arbitress! Left in the sole possession of the field, I were indeed weak warrior, should I yield. Queen (descending from the throne). Break up the court! Close our diversion here! Let us to graver duties. There is need! Macée. My royal mistress, and my loving lord! At your command, I have unbended me. —I trust, no slander touching on my husband May grow on my submission. Queen. Be of cheer! Macée. A merchant's credit is more capital, Than all the wealth he perils in adventure. Thus, for my happiness, his honour's pawned. But for his sake, even more than for my own, I hold it sacred. Queen. Nor shall it suffer. Sorel. It shall not! In proof, now heed my speech. Great king of France! I have a tale will witch you. Charles. Tell it, then. Sorel. The cunning man, without—(how name you him?) The astrologer, even now foretold my fortune. What think you 'tis? Charles. Make me not guess—but say. Sorel. This, then the sentence from the stars he brings:— I shall be nothing less than “the adored Of the most mighty monarch of the age!” Charles. Then, thou art mine! Sorel. What, thine? Nay, now thou dreamest. Henry of England, I am told, prepares To add thy crown to his. This granted, he Must be the greater, sure! Wherefore, I pray, Permit me passage to King Henry's court, That I may thus fulfil my destiny. Charles. Agnes! you mock me! Would you scorn me, Agnes? By heaven! my soul is fired! What! take my crown, Henry of England? First, thou takest my life! For, not without, will I surrender that Which makes its having other than a baseness! Cœur. Hail, king of France! there spake the monarch!—these, Thy words have made me jocund as with wine! Anon, shalt thou drive out from Normandy The intruding English! Nor despair of means, Leave them to me. Now, Charles is king of France. [All go out, except Sieur Giac, Beaulieu, and La Trémouille. Giac. Spare me a minute, good Beaulieu. Beaulieu. Ah! wherefore? Giac. No words. What you shall note will answer you. [Going over to La Trémouille. Giac. Now, are you edified? Trémouille. With what? Giac. With what? Mon Dieu! Trémouille. Go to! you are a fop;—and worse, an old one! An ancient ass, that thinks his braying music. Giac (with provoking coolness). Mon Dieu! I see you've not been edified. You know not, Charles of France has won the day, Has driven the English out, resumed his throne, Where Victory plumed sits with him, on the right! Trémouille. What do you mean? Giac. Why, that if I be fop, And at my years should ape a graver manner, You doubtless are the ass—and those long ears, Know not when they hear music. Beaulieu. Dear Giac! Nay, this is scarcely generous. Trémouille! He is but merry. Trémouille. Let me go! Hence with you! 'Tis you encourage Charles in wantonness, And trust to songs what should be done with swords; 'Tis you who flatter him, and aid their arts, Agnes Sorel and Cœur. Giac. Add, too, the queen; Whose influence is legitimate, I hope! They who, by this day's seeming simple sport, Have waked the soul of France in Charles's bosom, And roused her genius from the sleep of death! Now, know me better, sir! No fop am I— 'Tis but the slough the tailor makes for me. I doff my coat, and prove a warrior! Mistake me not again. And, for your carping, Learn rather from the manners you observe, Than act the censor on them. Ere long, you'll know, What now you've witnessed, and not understood, Was charged with glorious issues, wisely planned, In minds that by your own may not be scanned. Beaulieu. You have been too rash. Giac. Bah! He is too splenetic. [Goes out with Beaulieu. Trémouille (alone). Taunted—by him—the facile favourite:— Duped with a pageant; chid for ignorance;— Cheated of privilege;—deprived of lands;— And made the gibe—the sport of parvenus! Why! what new power is this, that vaunts such sway, By time unsanctioned, o'er time-sanctioned things? Let who will yield—I'll hold me yet erect! Adieu! fond Charles! I'll seek thy enemies! Agnes Sorel? The Dauphin struck the minx; Wherefore his angry father banished him To Dauphiné, to brood on his revenge. Where with intriguers he doth plot against The demoiselle of beauty. I'll to him! Not Charles, but Louis my allegiance claims.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">II. Rouen. Scene—Near the Gates of the Town. Otto Castellani and Jean du Village enter. Otto Castellani. Or I mistake, or you, my friend, are steward To the rich merchant, the king's argentier, The great Jacques Cœur. Village. Your memory is as true As dial to the sun. Otto. Your name is Jean Du Village. Village. Yours is Otto Castellani, The Florentine, the Treasurer of Toulouse. You owe the place unto my master's favour. Otto. Ha! well reminded!—(Aside) Smite him dumb for it, St. Zachary!—(Aloud) Shake hands! We both are leagued In the same purpose, as I guess. You come, To witness his triumphal entry? Village. Say, Rather, our good king Charles. Otto. Nay, be not modest— Charles were not king, but for his treasurer! 'Twas Jacques Cœur's gold that drove those English forth From Normandy. It makes me feel ambitious, Village, to be like Cœur in wealth and power, As in pursuit. A merchant prince, forsooth? A merchant KING is he! It makes us proud— It makes us hope—who are of the merchant-craft; It makes us equal with the lords o'th'soil. Village. Nay, Cœur is lord of many fine estates, In Bourges to wit, Montpellier and Fargeau; Not less than forty, as I reckon. Look! The crowd increases. Who comes hither? Joy! 'Tis Alain Chartier! Alain Chartier enters. Chartier. 'Tis I, Village! Ha! ha! They'll enter soon! Our good king Charles, With all his court and army, to possess His own good town of Rouen. Rejoice, kind Jean! Your master will be honoured. For his largess To the great cause of France, the grateful king Makes him conspicuous. Equally he rides With Count Dunois, Varenne and De Gaucourt, Alike each dressed, their steeds caparisoned. Our Charles himself precedes, armed at all points, His palfrey decked with azure, golden strewed, Attended by the King of Sicily, Counts, prelates, squires and priests. Here are the gates. You'll see them enter. Come with me along, Of special grace, I have gained you standing-room. [The procession passes over. Scene changes—Corridor of the Palace. Jacques Cœur and Antoine de Chabannes, Comte de Dammartin, enter. Chabannes. I've called you thus aside to buy your favour. I owe thee many sums of golden crowns— Yet, stung with spleen, have fallen from your cause, And joined the Dauphin's to despite king Charles. Cœur. It was an idle quarrel. Chabannes. Why, the king chid me For my écorcherie; he called it pillage— I was, forsooth, a “skinner,” écorcheur! Well, be it so! What wrong I did as such Was well redeemed. The power I wildly raised, I had wielded in his cause, and that of France. Cœur. Suffice it, there is one cool head i'th' realm. Um!—So you joined the Dauphin 'gainst the King. Evil the son that wars against his sire. Chabannes. Heaven has declared against the unnatural strife, Upheld the father, and depressed the son. There were small chance of my repaying you, Had I remained with Louis; . . hence, I am here. To Charles's fortune I'd myself ally, The which are you, unless I grossly err— To him in you I would be reconciled. Cœur. In Charles's name, Chabannes, I pardon you. The king has grown a warrior, as you know, And, plumed with conquest, can be generous. Still need you? Chabannes. Yes. Cœur. A thousand crowns, Chabannes, I'll lend you from my store. Will that content you? Chabannes. It will. Cœur. What more? Chabannes. La Trémouille, with me Revolted, would return to favour. Cœur. Ay! He did insult the “King of Bourges:”—the King Of France knows nothing of it. Would he guerdon, For his desertion of the Dauphin's cause? Chabannes. He asks but mercy. Cœur. Mercy he shall have. He need not fear—no more than we fear him. Chabannes. He has already made his peace, I find, With dame Sorel. Here, in her suite, he comes. Cœur. 'Twas overprudent. Still, perhaps, 'tis well. Agnes Sorel, Jeanne de Vendôme, Trémouille, Beaulieu, Giac, and Attendants, enter. Cœur. Welcome, Sorel! The soul you breathed in Charles Hath of a languid lover made a hero, Active and bold: he's quite a Mars in battles— In feats of personal prowess, an Achilles. France has her king and leader in the field. Sorel. France has what I have lost. Yet, willingly, Surrender I my happiness to hers. Here rests he now? Cœur. No rest as yet, for him Or me. We must pursue success, or lose it. Harfleur must yet be won, Caen, Cherbourg; Nor may we give advantage to the foe, Until the sea divides us from each other. Sorel. War has its charges. Is the cost defrayed? Cœur. There's not a month's arrear in all the army. For every soldier's need I have disbursed His punctual wages. 'Tis my proper service. Owe I not all unto the king and land, By whose protection I have won my wealth? Because I was a Frenchman, and his subject, The Soldan oft has granted me safe-conduct, For my stored galleys and my factors both, Exposed to peril both on sea and land. Whate'er I have belongs to France and Charles. Sorel. Whate'er I am belongs to both! Cœur. Most true. Our state-craft is believed in, now, by all. La Trémouille, even, is no sceptic. Trémouille. Sir! What said you? I was troubled! Pray you, pardon! Sorel. I'm glad he heard it not. I boast no craft: I make my heart a patriot offering— Nor more, nor less! Trémouille. There's witchcraft at the bottom. There's no resisting magic; so I yield! Cœur. And so do I, in such an argument. (To Jeanne de Vendôme.) Fair demoiselle! a word! [They retire. Sorel. Witchcraft and magic! La Trémouille! Trémouille. I charge not you. Sorel. Whom, then. Trémouille. There is a stone called the Philosopher's, Which whoso hath may have what else he would. It can transmute all metals into gold; And this, they say, Jacques Cœur has long possessed. And hence his wealth arises. Sorel. Trémouille! Who tell you so, abuse you. Not the stone, But the philosophy steads Cœur so well! His knowledge is the magic that he wields: He knows the markets of the world by rote, Has seen them with his eyes, and, from afar, Being absent from them, reaches them with ships. As many months as hath the year, so many Of his brave vessels sail upon the sea, Bound to the Levant; Egypt, that old power, Has commerce with him; while, at various ports, More than three centuries of his agents dwell, In Asia and in Europe. Wheresoe'er His navies travel, they command respect, Such homage as to sovran things pertains. From the remotest East; their ribs full-stuffed With silk, and cloths of gold, furs, spices, arms, Ingots of gold and silver; they return, Like jolly victors all whose triumphs had been Doubled by Bacchus. Trémouille. And Cœur's brain, methinks, Has caught the influence. Were he sane or sober, He would not shew his wealth to such excess. The proud, luxurious merchant! Why—his board Is more than royal; . . not a cup, nor bowl, No common platter, but of precious metal. His horses, even, they say, are shod with silver. Cœur (coming forward). I am vexed to hear my wife is discontent At our proceedings. I would know the cause. Pray you, step in—and say, I wait her here. [Exit Jeanne de Vendôme (Aside) Not naturally disposed, too stern of mind For weakness, yet by circumstance deceived, I fear, beloved Macée! doubt of my faith Hath, like an alien, in thy ample heart, Set up his tent, though not yet built his house. But I'll expel him from the soil! (Aloud) Fair dame, And nobles! Will it please you, be advised? The king expects you. Pardon me, Sorel! I may not be your usher—but Chabannes. Chabannes. O, willingly. Sorel. Chabannes can be gallant, But Cœur— Cœur. Lady, be counselled. Sorel. He is troubled! What means it? Ha! here comes his wedded pride! Enter Macée, attended by Jeanne de Vendôme. She passes by Agnes Sorel, with a marked and haughty gesture, almost of scorn or disdain. Pride? Something worse, methinks! Seek we the king. Cœur, Macée and Jeanne remain. Cœur. Is this our welcome? Then the forehead flushed Of conquest grows like fear's, and triumph's cheeks Are pallid as your own, as sunken wild, Two desert caves, that should be swollen puffed, The trumpet at her mouth. How now, dear wife? Macée. Am I yet dear?—your wife? Your widow, rather! Think not I envy France, or dread Bellona Hath been too much your bride:—so long divorced, I might have mourned the absent as the dead, Had none heard from you. But to me while few And frigid your replies, with trifles baited, Agnes Sorel received your soul in letters, Making her wise in every circumstance, Wherein myself was but an idiot. Cœur. Trust me, dear wife, such caution was required. Macée. Fine caution!—from a wife that would conceal, What to a mistress freely was avowed! Cœur. 'Tis you avow too freely what you should Give scarcely thought to, never words at all— Slandering the king, . . or me. 'Twere shame of you, To be the tongue of scandal. Macée. Shame not me— The honest blush not what they think to say, And truth, albeit called scandal, still is truth. Cœur. Truth may be spoke untruly. But your motives I trust are true; . . else were your words— Macée. What were they? Cœur. Nay—be not rash! Nor try too far my patience! A woman swears submission at the shrine, And, after marriage, 'tis the attribute That consecrates her most. Shall all my care, My labour in the service of the State, The ambition that on wealth should set the crown, Dissolve to vapour, become dreams again, Because a peevish will would dominate, And a proud wife direct a husband's course? Much as I love thee, let us henceforth meet Only to wrangle, as the vulgar do, Ere I yield aught in this. Macée. Cœur! I was born To at least equal privilege with you; And might, perhaps, in manners and in morals, Be your instructor. Cœur. Fond one! not in either. Macée. In both. Cœur. Nay, by your leave, in neither. Macée. You Too much concede to the gay law of the time, And countenance wandering appetite for love, That's only lawful, wedded. Cœur. Granted. Leave me. Macée. No more than this? Cœur. How now? my wayward sceptic! Must I explain my policy, ere you Confide in it? Has't been so little proved, That I must give my reasons, ere you trust me? Macée. Because I am your wife, I am your slave, And so but have to do with your commands;— Were I your mistress, I might share your counsels. Cœur. Nay, now, dear wife! you fret me! To thy soul, As to a temple, nought should enter in, But what is holy. We men in the world, Do that, in traffic, we'd ourselves not scan; Yet deem it not dishonour. Better, wives Should of such things be ignorant; seeing they Must of the laws that govern them be so. 'Troth, none can apprehend these matters, but The workers in them; and even they scant well; Where more of instinct and sagacity, Than reason guides. Be then, the mart the mart: Let home be home, and all be hallowed there! Macée. What words are these? What sin, what guilt define they? Dare I interpret? Cœur. Dare, but cannot. You, Who lack experience, talk of teaching manners? Modes of convention, creeds of right and wrong, That differ with the clime, the colour, age? Macée. You mock me, and, I think, insult me, too, Else wherefore should I tremble, as if conscience Were shaken on her throne? Cœur. Mock you? Not I! Macée. Not thus my father, in my childhood, taught me. Cœur. Good man! he had no knowledge of the world. Macée. How happy in his ignorance of evil! Cœur. It may be— Macée. Nay, he was: ... both wise and happy. Cœur. Not wise, though happy. You have granted it. Macée. No, Cœur! not so. Men may be largely wise, Whose evil knowledge is much circumscribed: Whereof who knows the least, the wisest he. Cœur. Be you content, and be the very wisest By knowing nought at all. But knowing nought, Think not to teach. Let ignorance be dumb! Yet let it learn! Learn you, to keep a secret. I wrote you one in my first letter to you; You told it to our Jeanne de Vendôme, here; She to Sorel—who thence conceived suspicion; I sported with her passion for King Charles, To my own profit. Heaven knows otherwise! It was for France! My influence, through hers, Half lost by your imprudence; . . first, I chid you, And next, resolved on silence. Macée. 'Twas no secret! Cœur. It was! Macée. Not marked as such. Jeanne was in fault, Repeating my discourse. O, Cœur!—O, husband!— Who would your wife should live in innocence, Yet blame her for that self-same innocence! Cœur. I had not spoke of it, had you not forced me. Macée. Have I grown hateful? Cœur. No!—more loved than ever! Macée. Then, you would trust me more! Cœur. 'Tis for your sake— Share you my triumphs. I would bear alone The troubles that lead to them. Macée. O, Cœur! Cœur! You love me not! you love me not, indeed! Alas! lost heart! I am no summer fly, That when the winter comes sleeps in the ingle. I'd bear the cold with thee—the heat with thee— Extremes of both! Ah! how can I be happy. Not knowing thou art so? Calamity May be this moment hovering o'er thy head, And I—thus blinded by thy wilful act— May play, sing, talk, and be most blithe of mood, While thou art on the torture! Cœur! Cœur! Cœur! I may no more be glad, not even gay, While this is possible. You break my heart. Cœur. Cheer up. There is no harm. Jeanne de Vendôme, Haste!—help your lady! See what you have done, In blabbing of her talk. I've served you well, You, and your family; . . thus you serve me! Beware how you transgress a second time!— —Cheer up, dear wife! Mere shadows of your fancy! My fortune's at the highest. Macée. Be it so! Would I had died, ere distance grew between us; Ere you had cause to chide, or put me off With trifles, like a girl too humoursome For confidence. Cœur. No more of this:—no more! Be calm. We've stayed too long. His majesty Will shew you in what favour we are held! Scene changes—State apartment, opening into a suite of apartments, illuminated for a ball. King Charles and his Queen, Agnes Sorel, Beaulieu, Giac, Chartier, Chabannes, Trémouille, Otto Castellani, Jean du Village, and numerous others, enter. Charles. Thanks, gracious queen. Such welcome puts the favour Of victory to the blush: . . She droops the head, In homage to your praises. Fair Sorel! Your counsel helped our arms, and now your smiles Enhance their lustre. Valour in our Court, May choose his mate of beauty. Queen. Still away, In chase of glory? May not I, nor Agnes, Keep you from Harfleur? Charles. Cœur shall answer you. Behold him, there, with his right noble lady. Sorel. Her brow at such a time might be less grave. Giac. Mon Dieu! methinks it might! Beaulieu. It were unseemly, Even were she Juno's self. Cœur, Macée, and Jeanne de Vendôme enter. Cœur presents Macée to Charles. Charles. A debt we owe, Thus honoured. Macée. Wherefore, sire? France in my bosom, As in my husband's, beats, instead of heart. His faithful wife is still your loyal subject, And Heaven, I hear, has sanctioned your great cause. A sainted maiden hath her mission proved, In her success, to rescue injured France. Charles. Meanst “La Pucelle”? fair dame. Macée. Jeanne d'Arc, my liege. Charles. Her inspiration, and your husband's gold, Fair lady, have indeed redeemed the land. Nor should we now forget to render thanks For the great gifts, good hands, and better hearts, That Providence has blessed our France withal. La Belle Agnes comes in for much of praise: Upon the altar of her country's cause, She laid her store of wealth—her gems, her plate, Setting ensample of like offerings To others richer still. Macée. Let me complete With her a little. To your righteous cause I give, what in my sense of all that's rich, I hold to be a gift unparallelled— My husband's love, his heart's entire devotion. Charles. Spoke like a wife, indeed! In grace whereof, Lead you the dance. Macée. Nay, let Sorel. She is Lighter of foot and heart. Charles. Then, be it so; Unless our Queen insist upon her right. [They withdraw into the suite of apartments. Dancers appear in the distance. Music. Trémouille enters, followed by Beaulieu, Giac and Chabannes. Giac. Nay, Trémouille! your hand. Trémouille. And why my hand? Giac. The issues of the sport disliked you once, Have been as stern as you would wish them be. You have returned to us. We should be friends. Trémouille. Yes, when we are equal. With our rhyming monarch, You have the advantage now. I am returned! What then? Your taunt was true: so are my blows! Chabannes! bear witness I throw down the gauntlet. This boaster may disdain to pick it up. Chabannes. Right willingly. Giac. St. Denis! not so willingly, As I now take it up. Enter Cœur, followed by Jean du Village, Otto, Macée and Jeanne Vendôme.—Macée remains behind. Cœur. A feud? What, now, When France needs both your helps? At such a time And in the midst of our festivity To forge a private quarrel? I forbid it! Giac. With all my heart. I came to be his friend. O ciel! his folly alters not my purpose. If he will be my foe, amen to that! Beaulieu, be witness, I accept his glove. We'll to the dance! [Beaulieu and Giac pass in. Trémouille. Scorn for his scorn! Chabannes, You saw my challenge. Chabannes. Yes, and well approve it! Cœur. Have I not said that I prohibit it? Chabannes. Are you the king, or even something more, That your imperative should carry it? What hinders that our swords should tilt at you? Cœur. Why, that which is far mightier than the sword— Your honour! and your interest, sirs, beside! My office, and the power that I could wield, And will, if needful—which my word alone, But whispered in my private steward's ear, Could put in act, and force you to submission! Chabannes. Is't possible? Mean you the debts I owe you Make me your bondsman? Trémouille. Nothing less he means. Chabannes. Take my defiance, then! Cœur. Rein in your wrath, Chabannes! Because Giac and he are angry, Should we, like schoolboys, fight? Trémouille. Chabannes, away! 'Tis manhood lost to listen to his words! [Dragging out Chabannes. Cœur. Here, Otto! Jean! There must be no delay! Now, mark me, Otto! You will buy the debt Of me, that's owing by Chabannes. Good Jean! He has my orders now to sell it you! That done, arrest Chabannes! I must not be As plaintiff in the suit: . . that you must be, Good Otto! I have served you in my time; Now, you serve me in this! I say, arrest him. So, in this challenge, can he lend no aid To Trémouille. For Trémouille himself, I have, unknown to him, bought up a debt He owed an armourer: . . that, too, is yours. Him, then, as well arrest! No feud shall be 'Twixt him and Giac—I'm resolved on it! Macée (coming forward). Cœur, list to me! Cœur. You, here? Macée. I have heard all! The orders you have given Village remand! The men you would coerce are noble men! O, play not you the merchant creditor. Is that a part to play at Court? A poor one! Rather the baron play, by conduct proved No less than patent made! Cœur. Now, is this well? Macée. Ay, Cœur! by all that's well! By what shall I Adjure thee to be prudent—thou who hast been In all thy dealings prudent? By thyself, And by my jealousy of thy dear honour! Let me speak loudly, Cœur, what men are whispering. They say, thou art their benefactor, from The king unto the peasant: this thou art; But thou art also from the throne to the settle The creditor of France! And worse—mark that!— The envious court are debtors to thy bounty, Mortgaged to thee for more than all are worth. Wouldst grow a terror to thy friends and foes? They say, thy benefits are gilded snares: Hence now thy wealth's a danger to thyself, Which, therefore, for thy safety, use as none. Still art thou stubborn? Then, behold, dear Cœur, Thy proud Macée doth bow the knee to earth; [Kneels Here, at thy feet, she makes her humble suit, And will not rise, till thou hast granted it! Cœur. Rise, then! Persuaded, not convinced, . . I grant it. [She rises. Jean! I revoke my orders. Castellani! You've lost percentage by it? (To Macée) Bravely spoken; Wisely, perhaps:—I am not assured of that! To threat is dangerous: to act were safe. The deed I have recalled—the words I cannot. It had been better I'd ne'er spoken them, Since, by your prohibition, they're no more. 'Tis thus, when women interfere with that Should be the business of man alone. Well, I forgive thee, wife. Thanks for that smile! There's nought I'd not surrender, dear Macée, To have you always smiling! Here's the king. Re-enter Charles and Court. Charles. We may not keep festivity up late, As if the wars were at an end. Full half Our victory's yet to come. To morrow morn, Must see us march for Harfleur. Up betimes! Till then, good night to all. Friend Cœur, a word!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">III. Jumièges. Scene—The Abbey Cloister. King Charles, Cœur, Jean du Village and Jeanne de Vendôme. Charles. How fares your patient, Jeanne? Vendôme. Still weak, and weaker. Charles. Now, by the Sanctities we worship here! I rather had lost Harfleur, than mishap Should come to Agnes. Perilous, say you? Vendôme. Most perilous, assuredly, her case; Perhaps, as certain mortal. Charles. Saints in heaven! And has it come to this? Cœur! be not silent! Recount once more the process. Cœur. Would the story Were nothing but the fable, there an end. But 'tis too sure a truth! From her retirement, Called by her Majesty's commands to Court, No sooner came Sorel, than, with that tact, Which serves her to unthread all policies, And ken what makes them, she detected there Conspiracy, foul spider! spinning webs Whose meshes were for us, but chief for thee. Instant, with express sanction of the queen, Hither to Jumièges, this Abbey here, Flew Agnes, like an angel, sent to warn Her monarch and her friend of coming doom. Charles. O lovely prophet! loving, faithful Agnes! How came she ill? Cœur. Of that same love, I guess— Of that same faith—to thee. That it should be so, Even on this day, when we a banquet hold For our success at Harfleur, grieves and irks me. My wife is now attendant on her couch; Already to her confessor has Agnes Her soul unburthened of its malady, Lamenting, in contrition most sincere; Her fate might have been happier but for that! Charles. Alas! What “might have been?” What could be—was! Cœur. You speak, as you were wounded by my words! Charles. Stabbed to the heart!—nay, more, sir! to the soul, O pang intolerable—immedicable— My spirit's wounded! Cœur! why were you rich, To make me so!—poor, I had not been tempted! 'Tis mammon bribes us with the means of guilt, So are we sold to sin! Wealth—Power and Sin! Of all the wine that most intoxicates, Power soonest maddens—fierceliest, blindliest rages, And murders or is murdered, as it may be! Cœur. Slain by a smile, or tortured by a tear! 'Tis ever thus. France must be thought of now! Jeanne, to your mistress. Bid her send us word Of any change in Agnes. Please you, sire, By this the captains wait us, in the camp. [Cœur conducts the King out. Village. A storm of passion now afflicts the king. Nor has our master much less cause of grief. The lady oft has by persuasion won, What his cool judgment would in vain enforce, And soothed to yielding mood the royal mind. Vendôme. Her influence with the king was great, indeed; And his with her:—'Tis therefore she is sick— Most hopeless sick. Village. What mean you, wench? Vendôme. Who tends her? Our master's wife? Note her distracted visage, Whose jealous soul turned pale, at Agnes' coming, On this so sudden errand. Now, Agnes is sick, Mysterious sick—and groweth still more sick. Village. Hush, wench! you speak in malice. Vendôme. Malice? psha! Wherefore should I bear malice? Once, indeed, My master chid me for my mistress' sake, Because to Agnes I betrayed her words, Whence strife arose between them: then, he said, I was ungrateful. Never so to him! 'Twere a good turn to free him from a shrew. 'Twere service he might thank me for, as much As he expects me to thank him for his. Village. Such speeches make you ugly as a witch, Like some malignant crone, or beldam wild, Swart imp, or dwarf misshapen. I have seen you Conversing oft with Otto Castellani, And other of my master's enemies, The agents of Chabannes and Trémouille, Who hate because they owe him love. His debtors, They are devising means (I know it well) Their debts to cancel even with his life. I know you, Jeanne! You have a wicked heart! Yes! hide your face for shame! Look not at me! But go your ways! Do that which you should do— Your duty to your mistress! There's your path. Begone! Adieu! Heaven send you better thoughts. Scene changes.—An Interior in the Abbey: An Oratory. Agnes Sorel (sleeping on a couch, a table or altar with a chalice by) and Macée de Léodepart. Macée (seated). She has made confession like a Magdalene, And been absolved. The priest, too, has departed And left me to my office. Cœur! blind Cœur! The sympathy between us, sure, is lost, Or thou wouldst purposely offend my pride, By dooming me to this. No confidence! I understand him not. For her he cares— But not for me. No!—nothing cares for me! Her judgment—beauty; nothing like to them. These must be cherished, failing him by me: I am his proxy, here. Perchance, he loves her Beyond what he would own to—not alone For that her wit and wisdom serve him well, But as he should love me. O agony! Burn on, my heart!—spontaneously ignite, And, like a willow, perish of combustion; Disdaining more to weep, consume with fire! Enter Jeanne de Vendôme. Who's there? What, Jeanne? Why creep you so on me? Vendôme. 'Tis at my lord's command, I should bring word Of lady Agnes' health from you. He'd know Each change that happens. Macée. 'Twere incredible! Tell him, she sleeps! Vendôme. She is not, then, yet dead? Macée. Dead? No! She rests with sleep, and not with death. Little we know of sleep, but nought of death. Nothing we know of death: too much of life, In that we live, self-conscious—still the same. Vendôme. There is no change, then? Macée. No!—no change. The fool Misunderstands my words. To her they seem (I note it well, and it has long been so) Strange and fantastic, as the ancient trunks Of olive trees in an Italian grove, Beheld by moonlight. Go, watch you the lady. [Jeanne de Vendôme goes to the couch. By the invincibility of death! And by the everlastingness of love! And the divineness of eternal truth! I feel as though I could speak oracles:— As I'd grown old at once, and should be held As reverend as the millenial pine, And tuneful as its music, heard at dusk. Vendôme. She wakes! Macée. Who shrieks so harshly? Vendôme. No one shrieks. Is it unwelcome news for you to hear, That lady Agnes wakes? Macée. Unwelcome? Yes! All is unwelcome now, that would disturb The dreamy slumber of my stagnant soul! Sorel (waking). Vendôme! is't you? Rest has not strengthened me: I need my cordial. Vendôme, give it me. I grow still weaker—weak, I fear, to death! Macée. What has she said? Vendôme. She doth desire her potion. Macée. 'Tis well! I will administer it myself. Vendôme (going to the table or altar, and looking into the chalice). I'd spare you trouble. Tell me where to find it. Macée. What asp is in your mind? What slimy worm, That creeps into the features of your face, And makes each line a poisonous reptile's lair? Hence, insolence!—nor question me again! Suspicion? ha!—straight bear my lord the tidings! [Exit Jeanne de Vendôme. (Rising) 'Tis more than her suggestion makes a void Where I would fain find substance: space is empty! Nay, space itself is gone!—Where is it hid? In time? Where time? In thee, eternity! Doomsday is every day, and, therefore, this. Sorel. I'm left to languish. Macée. I keep watch on you. Sorel. Is't you, most noble lady? I had dreamed 'Twas Vendôme watching by me. It befits not That you should have such labour. Macée. It befits A wife should be submissive. Sorel. This reply Comports not well with honour. Macée. How is that? Sorel. Thou art coerced to do what thou wouldst not. Macée. No! willingly I do what now I do. Sorel. Is't possible? Macée. Ay, very possible; And wherefore not? Art thou not worthiest? Sorel. Worthiest? Alas! Macée. Ay, worthiest. Sorel. Alas! 'Tis well if my contrition cleanse my sin! Macée. Can one so wise have sinned? Sorel. Oh, most of all— Against conviction, sinned! Macée. She owns it, too! Owns it to me—as if such wrong, to such An one, had small significance for any; Herself the doer!— Thou hast burthened conscience, Which now afflicts thee for it. What was the sin, That, in my presence, makes thee thus to writhe, As I had part in it? Why fall those tears, A shower, upon my hand? They make me pity, Where else I meant to punish. If 'twill ease thee, Unveil the mystery, that, perchance, is anguish Only unspoken. Speak—in accents dear, As native words heard in a foreign land! Sorel. I've still revered you. Macée. You revered me still? I've heard we best describe what we have lost, And honour most what ne'er we hope to gain. Our notions and our practice have so differed, I should have thought else, you had spurned the spurner. —If what you say be sooth, you're better fit For death than I. Sorel. Nay, you are every ready. The virtuous always are so. For Vendôme I am sorry her imprudence gave you cause Of grievance, touching me. Macée. She meant no harm. Sorel. 'Tis not by meaning harm that harm is done; The inconsiderate do the most. Macée. 'Tis true. We should think well, before we act at all. Sorel. Poor Jeanne Vendôme has still to learn that lesson. Macée. Let us, too, learn it—nor repent too late! Sorel. Prithee, my cordial. Macée (partly exhibiting the phial, from her bosom). Here it is—anon!— Were there a poison could annihilate, Not only kill!—Nay, 'twere too terrible!— Back to my bosom, asp!—I'll parley further! Yet without fear, she'll not herself convict. Thought hoarded long holds permanence for truth— Hath time's vouch for it—truth's discoverer! —(Pausing, then solemnly) Bethink yourself.—Is there no deeper wrong, That you have done me? Answer, as your soul Must shortly answer heaven's own Judge himself! Sorel. Why am I thus adjured? A deeper wrong, That I have done thee? Why, what deeper wrong? We all may do more wrong than all we know, From not reflecting duly. Where's the mortal That has not erred? Yet tax me not with guilt, Where I am only chargeable with error! I pray thee, do not! Macée. Pray not!—not to me! Unless you make confession! Your denial Brings back on me that unrelenting mood, Wherein I feel like some destroying angel, Commissioned to stern duty. I was melting— You make me granite. My heart grows, again, As hard as Pharaoh's! Sorel. O, beseech you, madam! Press not upon the fallen! Kill me not With words that fright me in this feeble state, Whereat my innocence trembles. Macée. Innocence! Sorel. Then, ignorance. Not knowing my offence, I feel as I were free. Macée. You will not know it— Albeit you shall! Sorel. I cannot know of that Whereof my sense is pure. Macée. Now, patience. Sorel. Pity! Beware thou slanderest not my memory With accusation false. When undeceived, Idle remorse will do the work of fiends, And, in his wanton mischief, make a sport Of thy condemnèd soul! Macée. O, wretched me! Sorel. To know that thou wert author of a lie, Were plague enough. But when to this we add, That, spite of thee, the lie is still believed, That rumour spreads, the echoes double it, And still for ever it exists apart, As it were consecrated unto hell! O, such remorse as helplessness begets, Is utter loss and absolute perdition! Macée. What! thinkst thou I would condescend to this? Or now have spoken without proof? Thinkst thou, That thou hast been so cunning with Jacques Cœur, That none your loves suspected? Am I blind, Fond, credulous, that no mutation shewed Itself to me, in my all-changèd lord? So dull of soul, so non-intelligent, That I should suffer not, yet suffer on, Having no more perception than a stone? Of me regardless, still regarding thee, Thy name aye on his lips, and never mine;— O, heaven and earth!—'twas orblike palpable! Firm as the centre, perfect as the arch! Sorel. What hear I now? Of me have you been jealous? Had I known that, how had I pitied you! Yet am I blessed in this,—weak as I am, That with my dying words. I may be potent To exorcise the fury, and set free Your soul from worse than madness. Fear you not! Your husband has been faithful. Love with me Was an ambition. Not the man alone, My heart might fill;—it was the crownèd king, Whose nothing less than adoration I Would fain secure—and did. Macée. But of my husband? Sorel. His wealth was needful to my royal lover, And so by me was worshipt:—in his turn, My aid was needful to the merchant's aims, And so by him was sanctioned. Macée. Nothing more? Sorel. Nor always sanctioned;—for of late has he Rebuked me for too much magnificence, As being of bad example to the king, And to the court, whose rude extravagance, In sooth, fell on himself, the creditor Of all. Macée. Did Cœur do this? Sorel. With reason,—for Hereof the danger grew that brought me here. His benefactions to uphold this State, Made foes—not friends. His debtors have conspired; They seek his ruin, and his king's with his, Unless he cast him off. Macée. Had I known this Before! O mockery! I knew it well! But passion buried knowledge—therewith hope— And near their grave I wander, spirit lost! Sorel. Hope yet! You may do much. Once, you restrained His anger wisely: . . Cœur himself confessed it. And since that time indeed, did they but know it, His enemies would know they need not fear. The debts, so much to them, are nought to him: And here, at court, the merchant he's no more, But all the noble you would have him be. Macée. What! thus has Cœur revered my counsel most, When least he seemed to do so! Wonder starks me! And thou— Sorel. Weak—weak—and weary! Macée. Swooning! Heaven!—The potion! [Disclosing the phial from her bosom. O most fatal substitute! [Casting it away. Not that! not that! There is no other here, And that were certain death! She's fainted! Well! There's hope from nature—only fear in that! —The terror of the dream that now hath past Still shakes me! (Sits.) I must sit. My limbs so tremble, 'Twere vain to think of their supporting me. Yet, hush! she, sure, is stirring. Grant, O God, She may be now reviving! (Rises.) Thought of it Renews my strength. Speak, Agnes! Sorel. I am dying! Farewell! I can no more! Exhausted—faint— Pray for, and pardon me! Macée. Another word!— No! not an accent! Crept a cold wind to her, That so she quivers? I'll wrap my mantle o'er her. Ha! now she's still:—so very still, she breathes not. Can she be dead? If so, 'tis terrible! 'Twere well that I should follow her—with means At hand, I'm strongly tempted! No! I've work— How much of work—to do! My lord's in peril— How much through me I scarcely dare reflect! She's surely dead! Let me becalm myself. I am not guilty, though I might have been, And cannot be too thankful; gracious heaven! —Something's to do! Yes—first, I'll hence for help: Thereafter to such meditations, as May make me wise for action. Who's there? Help! Scene changes.—The Abbey Cloister. Chabannes, Trémouille and Castellani. Chabannes. Your news is welcome. You have thriven apace. Giac—Beaulieu—both dead? Ye slew them both? Trémouille. Let Cœur now take it as he list! He would not The wont of chivalry should arbitrate. Be he content with rougher means! Chabannes. The manner? Trémouille. To Issoudun, at night, we sped in secret, Pierced to their chambers, took them from their beds, Placed them, ere dressed, upon two wretched steeds, And drove them to the fosse, and drowned them there. Chabannes. Summary executioners, indeed! 'Tis well! Now for the King and Argentier. Know, first, Agnes is dying. Castellani. May be, dead. Vendôme has her suspicions. Trémouille. Her suspicions? Castellani. The merchant's wife! Trémouille. Ha! ha! I know it all. A pact with you my friends. Vengeance on Cœur! The upstart! But Macée's of noble blood! 'Twas needful to our plans she should be piqued To desperate issues. Whatsoe'er her guilt, She is acquitted. Let the punishment On him alone descend! In this be just. Chabannes. Content! (To Castellani) Time is with you to meet Vendôme. At once we visit Agnes. (To Trémouille) Fare you well! [Exeunt Chabannes and Castellani. Trémouille (alone). I have wrought it, then to this. When first I dared To whisper danger, she disdained the thought; But she has heard it since from other lips, Which mine have tutored. Time's a wizard; makes, From smallest seed, things giant-like to teem By gradual change. Be absent but awhile, When we return—lo, what we left a mite Has grown a monster. Wonderful! she comes— She sees me, and approaches. On her brow A darkness lowers, yet luridly lit up, As something there were flashing in her eyes, Wherewith the brain was burning. Enter Macée. Macée (aside). Tempter!—Slanderer! Trémouille. Fair greeting, gentle dame. Macée. Gentle, forsooth— But for a certain sorrow and remorse, I might be gentle, now my mind is free From that most cruel yoke, which thou, and others, Had burthened it withal. Trémouille. What yoke, fair lady? Macée. Why dost thou question me, who wert the first So to corrupt the judgment of my sense, That whatsoever was most innocent, In Cœur, still seemed more cunning? Not again Can I be tempted, now, or he be slandered! Trémouille. You are, then, a happy wife? Macée. I might have been— What now may be I doubt. I will not doubt! But welcome faith reborn, and welcome hope, Welcome serenest thoughts, and that high love Which blesses whom it visits! Welcome home Ye sacred feelings, human sympathies, The heart's religion, the soul's confidence, The intuitions and the sentiments, That hovering wait upon fidelity, As she descends to earth! O welcome truth, Thus finding thee, I find myself again. The mourned-for exile is at length returned. Trémouille. A sudden change, indeed! Macée. Deride me not! But rather think how thou mayst prudently Atonement make to Cœur, ere I betray Thy baseness to him—think of it, betimes! Both for thyself and those who plot with thee;— 'Twere better done at once Trémouille. Such arrogance! Macée. Thou standst within his danger, . . if his wrath Be wakened, as it will be. Take good heed, Lest his resentment kindle. Trémouille. What do ye mean? Macée. Thou hast defamed the dead!—and wronged the living! Hence, fear to sleep; thou shalt be haunted for it. Dare scarce to breathe, for every word of thine Shall seem defiance and provoke revenge. Be humble, or my tongue shall ring a peal Fatal as thunder. Trémouille. To yourself or me? Where is your prudence . . reason . . self-respect? You better were a man! Make terms with thee? First, let me know the cause? Am I less brave, Than I was yesterday, or thou less weak? If 't please you to interpret, be it so; If not, to guess your mystery will content me! Macée. Then learn, Agnes is dead. Trémouille. No need to learn— I knew so, without teaching. Macée. Knew you, too, What of my Cœur she spake, and how her words, Her dying words, acquitted him of all You charged him with? Nay—now I come to terms— Will bribe you, if a man, to terms of peace. You have conspired against him, in your fears— (Would passion had not shut me from his counsel! But she was of it, knew his every purpose.) The debts ye owe him, all are gifts to you, And every courtier else who is his debtor. Thus Cœur forestalls your plots and grants their issue. Trémouille. Were you not blinded so with ignorance, You'd seen this were an insult, worse than all. Wouldst have us grateful? Macée. If ye would be noble. Trémouille. Would be! We are! 'Tis ours to give, not his. The privilege we inherit he usurps, And so must fall! Macée. Audacious! Fall? You dare. Trémouille. Be an historian, though perhaps no prophet. If I mistake not, here arrives my witness. Enter Castellani. Nay, start not, Castellani! There's Macée— 'Tis fit she hear what you would utter. Speak! But as I know the news must pain her much, And she will need sincerest pity, grant me To state beforehand, much as she may doubt it, We are her friends, and vow to help her through The straits of sudden peril. Now, say on Macée. What can have happened? Here stand I, like Death. Castellani. Chabannes went hence to visit Agnes, led By Jeanne Vendôme, he sought the Abbey-chamber. Alone, the lady rested on her couch, That was her bier: . . for she indeed was dead— Unwatched, untended; but beside her lay A phial, such as once her potion held, But which, for sundry reasons, raised suspicion. Chabannes seized on it, suddenly unsealed it, And poured the liquid down a mastiff's throat, The watch-dog of the Abbey;—the poor brute Died on the instant. Macée. Not more mortal, that, Than is thy tale to me! Trémouille. You know, then, of the draught? Macée. I scorn to lie. I do. Trémouille. Did Agnes taste it? Macée. Agnes did not: her death was uncompelled. Trémouille. Go on. The sequel? Castellani. Forth Chabannes and I Straight went to seek the King, at banquet with His Argentier. We found them not o'er merry: A gloom was on the monarch, and the merchant Anxiety o'ermastered. When we entered, “Agnes is dead!” he cried, expectantly. Macée. But in the course of nature—nothing more. Castellani. It might be so; but it seemed otherwise. Chabannes then told his tale, produced his proofs, Held up the phial in the sight of all, While pale Vendôme confessed her doubts and fears. Macée. Regarding me! Castellani. Ay, madame. But Chabannes Soon brought her to a pause. “'Twas Cœur,” he said, “Who needed Agnes' absence; and had charged His wife with deadly task and instrument, For his advantage; that he might enjoy That influence, undivided, o'er the king, Which erst he shared with Agnes.” Macée. But the king Believed not the false charge? Castellani. Indeed, he did. Conviction flashed across him, ere reflexion. A gush of tears relieved him; then, exclaiming, “O matchless traitor!” he the chamber fled. Macée. What then, did Cœur? Castellani. Surprised; enforced, surrendered To capture. Macée. What! dared they profane his person? Castellani. The accused must yield to legal violence. Macee. The crime of their unthankfulness ascend And drag the unwilling justice down. So, so! 'Tis true, that Cœur has fallen! Yet, Trémouille, Think not we're at thy mercy. No! I can Clear him by my confession. Trémouille. Humph! You can Convict yourself—but, as to clearing him, All you can say will strengthen proof against him. For a wife's faults the law still mulcts the husband. Macée. I know—I know. Still will I not despair. “Hope yet!” the dying said. “You can do much!” I will do all!—nay, more than can be done! Impossibility shall be a phrase, A vain articulation of the air, That has no potence in the life of things. I will save Cœur—'tis well that I should perish! To his redemption from this cursèd charge, I do devote myself—my life—my fame— Ay, honour's self, a sacrifice for him! Trémouille. This resolution we must needs approve. You know that Otto was your husband's friend, And said I not, anticipant of this, I had resolved on serving you? My reasons Are private, yet most cogent. We will help you. (Aside to Castellani) By humouring we may control her mood! Macée. What shall I do? Castellani. Vendôme's hard by. Till she's Consulted with, the merits are not known: What's to be done? What not? Moreover, Cœur Left her a message to be told to you. Macée. That word has charmed me forward. Sirs, conduct me! Trémouille. We're glad you yield to counsel. Macée. Not to your's. The wife, once rebel, now obeys her lord's. Scene changes.—Palatial Interior. Cœur, Chabannes and Jeanne de Village, Officers guarding Cœur. Cœur. Wait yet a little. Chartier soon will bring His answer. Enter Alain Chartier. Will King Charles grant me a hearing? Chartier. He will not, worthy Cœur. An apathy Has seized upon him with this sudden grief, Which will not be disturbed. Cœur. Ah, me! Of late, This weary mood, this listlessness of soul, Has grown upon him daily more and more. 'Twas born with him. Awhile the war's excitement Held in suspense the melancholy fiend; Then came reaction—and his sloth increases. For you, Chabannes! I think you've been ungrateful: Yet will I not rebuke you with my words. Rather my silence and my patience teach you What wrong from you I suffer. Chartier, My wife will doubtless seek me. Keep her back Until to-morrow. I'm angry with her now, And would not see her, till I am better tempered. I've bid Vendôme do this, and now bid you. Chartier. I will obey! Cœur. You'll see me, too, to-morrow. 'Till then, dear friend, adieu! My faithful steward, Good Jean! attend me to my prison gates, And take my last commands. Chartier (alone). Adieu, great soul! His resignation so exemplary Would soften hearts of marble. His foes have none, No hearts at all, whether of flesh or stone. —Here comes his raving wife. Enter Macée and Jeanne de Vendôme. Macée. Refuse to see me! Deny himself to me?—expel me from him. —To-morrow?—what's to-morrow? Still a debtor, To-day still puts off duty till to-morrow;— 'Tis not Cœur's wont thus to procrastinate, And I will not believe it, though you swear so. It is a thoughtless falsehood, an excuse To save yourself some trouble. I have pardoned, On your repentance, many a fault to you; And now this last, so big with fearful issue, Growing from your surmises. Add not to it. But, by confession, cheer me with the truth, That Cœur forthwith would have me visit him. Vendôme. Madame, indeed, I should be false to say so. Macée. Then all is false and contradictory. The beatings of the heart, the pulse of life, Ancient authority, and the dread oracles That, from ancestral urns, examples teach, Together with the starry dance in heaven, Which men have thought to be wise harmony; All these be discords, like the clank of chains! Cœur cast me off? A wife so true as I, Whose very error shewed how much she loved him. This is the mocking garland to my grief, A wreath of nettles but to sting my brows! Chartier. Madame, 'tis true; Cœur charged on me the same. Macée. Thou, Chartier!—whose lips are tuned to music, Whose numbers grow voluptuous in their sweetness;— What thou, O poet!—By thy cunning, swear, If this be theme for lyric ecstasy? O, I shall be an argument for song, Perhaps, for satire and the scurril jest? Hast thou no elegy on ruined hope, That will befit the state of my despair? Come, solemnize therein the wretched wife, Who, by too much of love, made desolate Herself and him she loved! Or are these sufferings, Beyond experience as I think they be, Too little pleasing for the pomp of verse? There is a penance of the human heart, Imagination never yet conceived; A state whereto poetic visitant Has ne'er descended, to set free the thought, Imprisoned in its self-created Hell! So leave me to that thought. All else be dumb! Chartier. See the king's chamber opens! Macée. Ha! the king! Cœur made him king. If he be king indeed, He'll not be thankless. Still his love for Agnes— I'm desperate!—and, as the wife of Cœur, Were she the queen, I were a match for her, And might command where yet I'll humbly sue! [Goes out hastily. Enter Trémouille. Chartier. You come from the king's chamber? Trémouille. Sir, I do. Chartier. Macée has entered? Trémouille. Sir, she has. With him, There let her plead, since she must plead in vain. Grief so has stunned his sense, that nought he hears, Nought answers:—he is but the log i'th' fable! 'Tis we now reign; not he, no more than Cœur! I seek Chabannes! Chartier. We follow her. Come on!</field>
      <field name="fulltext">IV. Marseilles and Beaucaire. Scene—An Apartment. Jeanne de Vendôme (seated). What, if I say 'twas not from thanklessness, But thoughtlessness, I wronged the merchant Cœur? To think not, is to thank not. Thought is memory Of the perpetual gifts that Time leaves with us. Yet thought I, too;—but, it would seem, not well. It is an art to think, as we should think; And to think well—is to think well of all, And without doubt—of nature, man, or God. Yet are the enemies of Cœur not men? And is not nature in their bosom human? Howbeit the Church—Heaven's representative, Has still defended Cœur, and censured them. Yet there were prelates 'mongst his debtors, too; Who were not the least rancorous! O this skein Unravels not itself for such as I —When comes Village? 'Tis past the day, the hour, Announced hereby—(showing a letter)—for his return [A bell sounds without. Ha! sure, 'Tis he—the honest steward! Here he is! [Rising Enter Jean du Village. Welcome, Village! Village. You're here, to welcome me? I am glad of that, at least. Vendôme. What fear had you, Here, in Marseilles, protected as we are By good King René? Village. Why—Provençe—. No more! I'll tell you, by and bye. First, tell you me, What, since I parted, chanced with Cœur? Distinctly! Nor care for repetition: ... for I seek To put some hints together, so to find Where now they hide him? Vendôme (greatly alarmed). Know you not? Good Heaven! Macée will, sure, go mad when hearing this! Village. We must be calm. I'll help you to begin. —At his desire, Cœur's last commands received, Ere he was dungeoned, I departed straight For Languedoc, commissioned in his name, There to take charge of stores of merchandize And vessels, which the harpies of the law, Their master absent, else had plundered. This I did. Not a bale 'scaped into their hands! Now—tell your story. Vendôme. All of it I cannot. For to imprison me, as well as Cœur, 'Twas needful held, on charge of Agnes' death. Whereof acquitting him, on my amende, Demanded and conceded, they released me: But to my utter wonder did not him. Village. Let's see!—let's see! I've correspondence, here, Upon that point—(seats himself at table, and takes out papers)—the strangest point of all; That most illegal of all stratagems. Something may come of that. Yes, Jeanne Vendôme! They wanted but excuse for capturing him; Which, having done, they added to that charge A thousand accusations, as more reasons For holding him still thralled. I have them, here. “He had sent armour to the Saracens, Been guilty of extortion”—and so forth— Which “the Grand Council should investigate!” So held they him confined, in Taillebourg, Transported thence to Lusignan, Maillé, And Tours;—thence whither I not know! One failed, Another—still they charged him with new crimes; Leze majesté, force and imprisonment, Public and private, without law in both. It had been vain, had Cœur pled to the facts; He therefore sought for refuge in the Church, Whereof he was a tonsured clerk, and pled His order's privilege. Her bishops urged it; His impious judges heeded not their voice, Nay, after months of false imprisonment, Sought to subdue their victim by the question. Vendôme. Tortures for him—for me, and for Macée! How she survived that anguish I can think not: 'Twas madness too sublime for life to hold! And she has since been rather like the dead Than living. Anon, came the last disgrace; When Cœur, condemned as worthy death, but pardoned Of the king's grace, . . his treasures confiscate, . . Was doomed, without or chaperon or girdle, In sign he was deprived of all his goods, To suffer penance in the public eye; The which he did, as purchase for his life, Bare life alone—and not his liberty!— Village. And this was royal gratitude! O Charles! Charles, king of France! thou needest honest hearts, Even now, to guard thee from the Dauphin's aims; Yet, by such foul ingratitude as this, Thou'dst lose them all! But, soft! Here comes the mourner, With Chartier, whom I met upon the threshold. Macée and Chartier enter. Macée. Gone from Tours?—taken thence? You know not whither? Chartier. Even so. Village. I, too, have vainly sought. Macée. You?—You? Then is the world as good as searched in vain! Nor need I argument for great despair, But find it in thy honesty writ large! Village. Still have I faith in Providence and Virtue. Macée. Think you, thereon I've never thought? Then, know, I number, 'mong my faults and errors, this:— That, ignorant and presumptuous, I still urged More holy motives, than were warranted By the world's market, on my husband, Cœur; Thinking that Merit ruled, not Destiny; Deeming the offspring of his own caprice, What were the Titan progeny of Time. The power he wielded was of recent growth, And had to combat ancient enmities, Which it must conquer, or be conquered by, And by his martyrdom will conquer yet. Now, would I take defiant attitude, And let blind Fate do what it list with me, Using my natural force to stead myself, Resenting the injustice, whosesoe'er, That mocks us with the shows of liberty, And cheats us with illusions into folly, Which needs must be, whether we act or no, Till death forecloses on our mortgaged hopes, And banquets bravely on our bankrupt hearts! Village. These words offend religion. Macée. May be. Earth! Were she a ship that blasphemy might sink! Who pilots her? What captains walk her deck, That have not merited anathema? Is't Charles of France? My curse on him was wordless! Not whispered!—the suggestion of my thought Was charged, yet as a cloud, and burst in silence! The miracle was signal. Puppet Charles! —My lord was king, not he: the puppet said. The jealous puppet smote its maker's pride! Then, was the puppet king? Vile, thankless slave! The slave of slaves more thankless and more vile! His arm was broken with the blow he dealt! And now the Dauphin strikes his pate across, With reckless insolence, in wanton sport! Chartier. True, madam! 'Tis not he that acts, but they— 'Tis not his act, the act that brought me here. Macée. We must remove? Nay, let me pause on that! From the false Government of France, you tell me, A requisition most peremptory Has reached king René, to withdraw his sanction For our remaining here; . . and the Provençal, Too weak for the French court, must hunt us forth. Where would they banish us? Where have they banished Him, for whose sake, they make us exiles, too? I'll be no more deceived, but rest at once On that which tramples hope! My Cœur's an exile! An exile from the world! Him whom they prisoned, Condemned unjustly, they've unjustly slain! Village. Nay, madam! We've no warrant to say that. Macée. Warrant! there's none for aught that we can say, But in our power to say it! Where's the warrant, For what, we know, they've done? What warrant need they, For what, we know, they may do? I have taken Counsel of wisdom, and am bid—“Despair!” By voices heard in Heaven . . among them, his: My Cœur speaks to me from his mansion there! There is an inspiration in the tone, Which can not be mistaken! [She sits. Here I'll sit! Famine, my guest! I love the specialty Of sunken cheeks, eyes rayless, bloodless veins, Of marrowless bones and juiceless ligatures, Until the skeleton scarce holds together. So long I've thought thereon, I am fascinate— I grow, with passionate love, into the image, And will from food and drink abstain, until This failing body free me to behold His form, as thus I hearken to his voice, That sweetly now invites me, haste to meet him! Chartier. O fearsome phrensy, madam! Macée. No word more! Village (to Jeanne de Vendôme). It must not be! 'Twas what I had to say— The thing that Chartier has informed her of— That we are hunted hence. I knew not how To say it! But this mood! It must not be! Jeanne. If she delays, thus obstinate, the hounds, That hence should hunt us, will be here! Chartier. Anon. Trust in my function. In such cases, learn, The bard is a physician. Go, make ready For your departure. Not a breath! [Exeunt. Meanwhile, I'm left to terror I'd not have them share, And would inspire the hope I cannot feel. [He contemplates Macée for some time, then gently approaches her. Madame!— [She gives him no answer. For shame!— [No recognition. Now, by the generous pride Of the Léodeparts!—Still no response! Macée!—or Cœur! Not even that loved name! What invocation, else? Ha! I hear footsteps! This must not be! Who're they that enter now? I fear some officers from René's court? Enter Guillaume Gymart and Gaillardet. —Whom seek ye, sirs? Gymart. Jean du Village, the steward, Late of the Merchant Cœur. Chartier. Ay, so I feared! Wait yet . . for see where sits the wife of Cœur, Fixed in the horror of a hopeless grief, We will depart anon. Gaillardet. Depart! I think, sir, You are the poet Chartier? Know us, then, We be two factors, late from Bourges, of Cœur. Chartier. Pri'thee, your pardon! Bring ye news of Cœur? Gymart (presenting tablets). Here, on these tablets, have we writings by him. Chartier. In his own hand? Is Cœur alive? Gaillardet. He was When last we left him. Chartier. At Tours? Gaillardet. No, at Beaucaire. Chartier. Cœur lives! Here is the proof! Wake up, Macée! Here, take his tablets in thy hands! Their touch, Having been felt by him, may thus inform thee, (Such sympathies are vouched for), that he lives. Cœur lives! Read—read what he has writ! Macée (slowly). It thrills! Something would make me feel! Disturb me not! The sun has died:—who'd live in darkness? O! Would I had not survived! Chartier. 'Tis daylight still! Hope's in the world! Cœur lives! Read—read, I say, His tablet's in thy hands. Macée (in a low tone). Where are my eyes? Can, then, my fingers see? (Shrieking) These? Ha! From Cœur?— You said, from Cœur? Chartier. His own handwriting. Macée. 'Tis! It is! It is! O, ne'er was scripture dearer. Yet, he is dead—and these are sent from heaven, By you, his angels. Chartier (to Gai. and Gymart). Step aside, awhile; And give her time for judgment. Macée (laughing hysterically). Ha! ha! ha! [She kisses the tablets, and then bursts into a flood of tears. Chartier. I pray thee, read the tablets. Macée. Wait!—I will! [Reads. “Beaucaire.” Describe what quarter of the skies, Beaucaire emparadises. More! (Reads) “The Convent Of Cordeliers.” That's earthy. Pah! (Reads) “The King.” What King? “King Charles.” It is King Charles of France. Ne'er thought I more to hear his name with joy, Or syllable it myself but with a curse!— (Reads) “Under his safeguard, prisoner at large; “Yet for the love of God and love of man, “Let not thy imprisoned master, faithful friend, “Pine in his bonds. Achieve his liberty!” Signed “Cœur.” 'Tis for Village. 'Tis not for me! Yet why should this rebuke me? Cœur is living. That is enough for me—should be enough! If love be dead in him, he's dead to love. O, cankerous doubt, that withers love's true rose! Come, famine! then. Chartier. Nay, this is wilful, lady. Cœur's motives are apparent. He is guarded With such strict charge, though in a convent, lady (As now I hear from these two honest factors), 'Twill need most perilous enterprise to free him. Macée. There's comfort in your news. Thanks, gentlemen! I'm glad of it. Fain would I venture death! Look, here's another tablet. (Reads) “Son,” he calls him— Entreating “instant action”—for, “I learn “My death is meditated by my foes.” —I knew 'twas so—that meditated death Cœur since has suffered; and again I yield, Myself to desolation. Chartier. Wife of Cœur! “Hope yet—thou canst do much!” Macée (abstractedly). So Agnes said— The dying prophet said it! Chartier. Where's the courage That once upheld thee in thy great resolve, To save him, spite all loss? Let not despair Baffle prophetic instinct—grant the danger, How imminent soever; speed may snatch The expected victim from the threatened snare. Macée (recovering). And, not the less for my despair will I Do this, and more—armed now for either issue. Let me see Cœur I would win back his love, His love I must win back; or myself perish, Though the work prosper which I go to do. Grant, heaven! some difficulty to surmount! O, let it be the wager of my life! I'll make such large atonement for my fault, Extreme devotion shall regain his love. (Calling) Village! Vendôme!—Come, we must speed away. I am as swift, now, in my new desire, As I of late was tardy! Gentlemen, We needs must leave Marseilles within an hour, But secretly, or we shall ne'er escape. We'll join our friends within. My mind grows clear. Take comfort, heart! Away with doubt or fear! Scene changes.—Exterior Collonade. Convent of the Cordeliers. Midnight. Matin music heard from the Chapel. Mathieu D'Ecole, Duclerc and Simonet enter. Mathieu D'Ecole. Keep ye good watch. Be ye not too secure. Ye have no common prisoner. Merchant Cœur Has head, and hands: is apt, and wise, and brave. He has had visitors. Duclerc. A brother or twain Of our own Order, from the opposite town Of Tarascon—no more. Mathieu D'Ecole. They should be faithful. Simonet. Are, doubtless. Easier to escape, Jacques Cœur Would find it, from a dungeon, than Beaucaire. 'Tis not alone the Convent's guarded strictly; The town is circled in by barrier-walls, Prohibiting attempt with silent scorn. Then there's the Rhone to cross. All these are bars Most formidable. Mathieu D'Ecole. I am satisfied. Simonet. The matins now are over, and Cœur comes forth For his accustomed meditation. We Respect his privacy. Mathieu D'Ecole. At such an hour, The sleeping world has nought to send us fear. Be vigilant. Duclerc and Simonet. We shall observe your orders. [Exeunt at different sides. Enter Jacques Cœur, alone. Cœur. Were I not strong in my integrity, Inconstant fortune! thou hadst broken me Upon thy treacherous wheel. O, thou hadst vaunted, How Cœur, in slavish bonds, thy triumph graced. But now, roll on thy chariot; still erect I walk apart, unconquered, unsubdued. The pious service of this midnight hour Sheds o'er my soul a customary peace, By repetition but more soothing made. And I to ye can upward look, O stars! Oblivious of ungrateful injury; Faith broken, lawless trial, doom unjust, And heartless cruelty sanctioned with the name Of royal privilege and grace unbought, The terrible compassions of the proud. One sorrow yet afflicts me, that, Macée!— That thou, Madonna of this living shrine,— That thou shouldst of this temple, where alone Thou wert adored, conceive so wrongfully And gender mischief in thy jealous soul; This pierces—this torments—this maddens me! Soft, footsteps! Enter Macée, disguised as a Cordelier. Ha! perhaps the friendly monk To whom, on his last visit, I confided My tablets to Village. That honest name The breath makes odorous that names it kindly. Macée. I never deemed that I should shrink away Into myself, and dread his near approach— Thus trembling! Cœur. Welcome, monk! Pray, do I know you? Are you from Tarascon? Macée. From Tarascon Cœur. That voice! 'Twas strangely like! From Tarascon! Instinct of love! I pierce through her disguise; But love offended mails itself in steel— No rock so hard—so sharp! What wouldst thou say? Macée. Does he not know—will he not know—my voice? Cœur (going). Thou art not the Cordelier I thought I knew? I thank thee, monk! I must beware espial. Macée (rushing up to him). Wouldst thou go hence? Dear Cœur! this must not be. Macée implores thee! Cœur (coldly). Wherefore seekst thou me? Macée. Whom should I seek but thee? Whom should the soul Seek but its God? Whom should Macée, but Cœur? Cœur. Macée! Here, kneeling?—weeping? Stand thou up! I have been humbled, and have drunk more tears Than I have shed. Therefore, stand up, Macée, Nor act the passion of a Niobe, Unless, like her, astonied; jealous heaven, Author alone of thy calamity! Macée. I've so charged heaven; . . but, then, thou wert not by To check the impious thought. Cœur. I check thy thought?— I know not when such mastery was mine. Macée. Thine? Ever, Cœur! Cœur. Most strangely manifest! In ever thinking, doing, what thou wouldst, Thy husband's ruler in his prosperous hour, And his main grief in this adversity. Macée. To heaven, and thee, I would acknowledge all— Be thou like that: . . absolve me from my sin! Thou wert a man, whose pardon still outran Offences, like the herald of good powers, On whose impassive essences serene No stain may fix, and no dishonour come. Unhappy me, the sole exception made! Cœur. Thou knowst the cause? Macée. I do. Not to extenuate The error of my love—for such it was— (Jealousies are to love as dreams to sleep) Nor tax thee with neglect—for none was thine— (Still rapt in trance broods creant enterprise)— I dare avouch, there ne'er was in my soul An impulse thou wert not the mover of Thy profit—credit—glory—pleasure—power— These were my inspirations; . . these the stars That shone upon me in my solitude; Whilst thou abroad wert doing, in the field Of life, the battle that the brave must dare, Even though they perish. These are thoughts of thine; They lived with me even when estrangement cast Its casual shadows 'twixt two anxious hearts, Perplexed with high responsibilities. And what if such were vexed, and one was wrecked, Judgment thrown overboard, and the poor barque Left to the mercy of the waves and winds. Is Cœur less merciful than they have proved, And the spent swimmer would forbid the shore? Cœur. 'Tis music such as this, the seas have solaced, When they were angry. Macée. Would my Cœur deny, When on the beach the breathless swimmer sank, The wine of comfort to the penitent? Cœur. I would not, and I will not! Dear Macée, Close to my heart! I, too, have been to blame! A faithful heart, like thine, should have been trusted; And what might not be so, been left undone. 'Twas a plain guide, but the trim voyager Would not consult it; . . So the vessel stranded! Macée. But I am vowed for its salvation, Cœur! Cœur. Thou, fond Macée? We'll talk less wildly now. Yet, saidst thou not, thou camest from Tarascon? Macée. Time wears: I'll tell thee all, without a pause! There are no listeners? Cœur. None. Macée. At Tarascon Thy friends assemble, led by Jean Village; The Convent of the Cordeliers his lodging; With him Gymart and Gillardet, assisted By a good score or two of armèd men, Soldiers in the late wars. At Tour de Boue, A galley of thy own lies ready; then At Nice another, which, with wind to serve, Will Pisa reach in safety: thence to Rome, Where good Pope Nicholas his palace gates Throws wide, for thy reception. Cœur. Cheering news! But how reach Tarascon? Macée. A hirèd boat Awaits thee, on the Rhone. The night's auspicious; Caution . . and silence . . and the river's crossed. Cœur. Impossible! The town is fenced with walls. Macée. Time has in one commenced a breach, which man Is even now enlarging, easy task, To let thee through. Cœur. Yet still impossible! At every avenue, by day and night, The Monks kept sentinel. I may not pass The Convent's bounds. Macée. They may be bribed, perchance. Cœur. I know them well, an incorruptible And pious brotherhood. There is no hope! Macée. “Hope yet,” said dying Agnes. By that name, I'll charm you yet to listen. Much to do Lies in my power—in mine, dear Cœur! And all, Nay, more than can be, I have sworn to do, By spiritual might! Prophetic words Were those she uttered. Be in me fulfilled Their purport; here devoted, lo, I stand For thy deliverance, Cœur; called to the work By sacred oracle, ordained, resolved! Cœur. What wonder, now, Macée? Thou art not phrenzied? Macée. List further, and then judge. I am prepared For what I came to do. Beneath this habit Lo, here my woman's gear. This habit take; And, in return, give me thy merchant's robe; In this same hood conceal thy visage, Cœur! And give me, for my brows, thy turban, Cœur! [Macée makes the exchange, while speaking:—he passively and abstractedly submits. Here will I stay. The distant sentinel Will mark me in the moonlight, sitting here, And thence have no suspicion. Meanwhile, thou, In this monk's garb, will pass securely by. 'Twill cost thee but a “Benedicite!” Cœur. But thee thy life! The Convent's laws are strict. Morn comes—thou are detected: this disguise Serving for proof, not shelter. No, Macée! I cannot do it. Macée. It is done without thee. Thou seemst to know not the exchange is made. Behold, thou art the monk, the merchant I. Cœur. Surprise had, surely, reft me of my functions. —Yet here stay I! Macée. And I—and thus attired! Hence, when discovered, they'll imprison both; And, for this cause, so thy confinement straighten, That thy resuscitate love for me again Will perish, when thou thinkst upon the fault, This new one I've trangressed in; like the rest, The child of a deep love, that no divorce Admits but death. Love and my life are one! Cœur. Be it even so. I shall not blame Macée. Macée. Thou wilt—thou must! I will not peril it. Or if thou do not, I am resolute To shut myself from pardon utterly. My own, and yours, and earth's, and Heaven's!—gaze on! I am become a mystery to myself, And capable of whatso most appals Good men and angels! I will do the deed, Shall make my soul an outcast! To my wish, Therefore, at once surrender! Morn soon dawns, And all this peril hastens. Yield at once! Cœur. Still thy imperative nature must prevail. Macée. Embrace me! Now, away! Cœur. Adieu! adieu! Yet still I turn me back, in hope to soothe thee. Thou lookest bravely in my turban, wife! No, by this starlight, thou art beautiful. I thank the moon for shining out so fair. By heaven! I will not leave thee to this peril! Give me again my garments! I will have them! Macée. I will not quit this gear, except by force; Which, if thou use, I'll sudden scream so loud, The Convent cells shall echo with my cry. Cœur. Thy will is dominant—thy mien commanding— Thou art imperial as imperious. I'm awed and spell-bound! I submit, constrained. To obey thee, is to please thee. Well, I go. And be the saints thy guardians! Macée. Hence! The Monk, Thy guard, impatient of our conference, comes. Away, or all is lost! Cœur. Adieu! adieu! [Macée sinks upon a seat.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">V. Beaucaire. Scene—Interior of Convent Chapel. Altar illuminated. Macée discovered by the altar-rail. Macée. I would my spirit should continue hushed, Grief quenched by the Immortal Sacrifice Which makes of none account all mortal loss. From midnight to the morn I matin keep, In silence, which, in solemn music, late Ascended high, and on the wing of sound Transported me to heaven: . . no prisoner, then; And now, if one, a temple, lo! my prison; And its celestial presences are set For comforters to those whom penance bows, The best physicians to the broken heart, That by self-immolation would make whole And be restored unto its perfect self. Here find I peace:—and if they take my life, To die were but as I should choose to sleep In some sweet bower of Paradise, where he I die for lies expecting me, awake! But better death like this—for absence is To loving bosoms nothing less than death!— Than that immortal widowhood of soul, Which, but for that I suffer now, had been Our lot eterne. Now, we shall meet again, Belovèd Cœur! if not on earth, in heaven! These tears anew baptize me, and the root Of life they water bears again the bloom Of love and hope. Enter Jeanne de Vendôme. Who's there?—Vendôme? Vendôme. Morn breaks. Macée. It grieves me much, Vendôme! your foolish faith Has made you prisoner with me. Vendôme. Scarcely so. You are alone in danger: I fear none. But as a witnesss here detained—no more— Charged, by Village, with letters from the Queen, That gave her royal sanction to your lord's Escape, from his malignant enemies; As what the King desired, though under influence, He had no power to order. These, produced To the good Abbot, might—so thought Village— Move him to set you free, to follow Cœur. Macée. Ye little knew L'Ecole. The father acts Solely by rule. To deed irregular, Even though an angel vouched it, nought might tempt him. The intervention of her majesty, Having no legal warrant, to his mind Was or impertinence or treason. Straight He sent, mark you, a messenger to court, And thus gave notice to my husband's foes. Hence have we here Trémouille, who breaths malign, Against me death and vengeance. I am doomed! Vendôme. Take counsel. Macée. Well rebuked. I shall do so. Trémouille, it seems, awaits the fierce Chabannes, Gone forth on expedition to Fargeau, And elsewhere—vehement to possess himself Of my dear lord's estates. Such impious haste Those cormorants make, to gorge them with the wealth That once their victim owned. What hear you, Jeanne? Vendôme. Not half an hour ago, a horseman came, The avant-courier of the so-feared Chabannes, Saying his master followed speedily, With an armed train, picked from the royal guard, Though for awhile detained by some strange news. Macée. Strange news? All news is strange! Vendôme. But this most strange. Macée. What is it? Vendôme. Something of the Dauphin. All I know not clearly. This alone I heard; That, taking 'vantage of these traitors' absence, Prince Louis' friends were Charles' attendants now, Who, shut up in the castle of Mehun, Suspecting poison, sustenance hath refused. Macée. That's news, indeed. This heavenly justice answers What suffering might pray for, and has virtue To make me strong to bear or to inflict. Mathieu D'Ecole, Duclerc, Simonet, Trémouille, and others enter. They come whom I must baffle or endure. D'Ecole. Here, daughter, watch ye? Macée. And protection seek. Trémouille. Protection, lady? Macée. From your malice, which You miscal justice. Trémouille. 'Tis justice, when the law's Insulted, to avenge it on the peccant. Macée. What seems may not be guilt; . . but circumstance May oft excuse an act, though not in rule: As when the innocent do hold the sword, That kills but murders not, in self defence, Or guards the old and feeble, or sets free The unjustly captive, though by mortal means. This last I did—the victim but myself! Force is repelled by force, and craft by craft. Trémouille. 'Twas legal force and authorizèd craft. Macée. Yes, legalized by robbers for their gain, And authorized by traitors for their safety; From whose insidious wiles or violence, All modes of quittance justice does permit. Trémouille. Robbers and traitors? Macée. Ay—no less! Trémouille. You rave. Heaven save your reason! Macée. So it will—it doth! 'Tis you are idiot . . blinded, by the veil Of custom, to those inner laws that, born With us, we may suppress, but not repeal: Not taught, derived, but living in our life Cogenial and inherent. By these laws, I judge your laws, and find that I have acted On the defensive only:—therefore am guiltless Of any act of treason against the State. So of this Abbot, here, I make demand, He set me straight at large. D'Ecole. I cannot, lady. My office is specific:—to the letter, I will perform its duties. Macée. Office!—duties!— O spiritless and most insensate clod! O tablet, for a cenotaph designed, But uninscribed as yet! O void of faith, Of charity, and yet ordained to both. Their minister, who shutst the gate of Hope On Hope herself, yet at the portal standst As if thou wert her guard, her servitor, But art her enemy, yet knowst it not, So brutal in thy pious ignorance, Thou slayest her on the threshold of her dwelling, Then claimest guerdon for defending her, Thy murdered mistress! Strip thee of thy office, And take to duties that befit thee better. These principalities become thee not;— Some servile task is more within thy scope! D'Ecole. Lady, you are too bold. Besides, you know not, 'Tis heresy you utter. Macée. Heresy! What, then, is truth, if this be heresy? Is it not truth for woman to be true To him she loved and wedded? Is it not truth, When on the judgment seat corruption sits, And by the altar ignorance adores, That to the sanctities which guard the hearth She should appeal, and worship? Or that barred, As mine is now from me, she should for truth Dig deep into her heart, and, in its promptings, Thus recognize the verities of Heaven! D'Ecole. Beware—lest, to the censure of the State You suffer now, you should provoke the Church To couple hers. Macée. Now, by these saintly shrines!— Now, by the awful holiness above!— That Providence which, though invisible, Watches o'er nations, and avenges wrongs, Public or private—plants, or else displants Altars and thrones!—speak your anathema! 'Tis not on me, but on yourselves, ye pour The dreadful burthen of your dolorous curse; Which, though it blast me standing in its way, Dismantles your own altars, overthrows Your rites, to pieces breaks your images, And shatters thrones! Poor wretches, blind to fate; Before the great emotions of the soul, Ye perish; like the idolatries of old Before the whirlwind of the wrath of God;— I scorn—despise; unpitied, pity you! [The Convent bell rings loudly. Trémouille. That is a peal indeed, bespeaks impatience. [Simonet goes out. Macée. It sounds as it would hurry on my doom! It sounds as 'twere indeed my passing-bell. Forgetting to be solemn, in the haste Of your desire to send my soul to bliss!— Ye would commit a murder—do it now! Simonet (returning). It is the Count Chabannes. Macée. I knew it was! Trémouille expects him, see you not he doth? I know he brings my sentence from the king, As men still call the puppet, Charles by name. These words are treasonous? I'd have them be so! Forms without power, shews that are substanceless— Away with them, or with ourselves away! Better annihilation, than to suffer The tyrannous yoke of mock authority That order turns to chaos! Trémouille. Here's Chabannes. D'Ecole. Lady, be silent now, and hear the Count. Macée. I shall, be sure! Enter Chabannes, attended with Guards. Chabannes. Hail, to the Consistory! I bear with me the rescript from king Charles, Touching this lady. Macée. Well—the matter? Chabannes. This. By the advice of the Grand Council, sitting Upon the trial of the Argentier, His Majesty pronounces that the guilty By his escape hath pardon forfeited, And merits death; . . but being now in Rome, And shielded by the Pope, cannot be reached. Yet, having left in pledge his wife, Macée, On her must fall the sentence due to him. Macée. You have made speed from Mehun to Fargeau; Maurice, besides:—thence, hither, to Beaucaire! Chabannes. I am not wont to loiter. Macée. 'Tis well known! Eager and rapid in all enterprise, No province, hardly kingdoms, could confine Chabannes' impetuosity, when moved! The écorcheur is still the écorcheur; Rapine and plunder, as of yore, his trade, And death the meed of whatsoe'er opposed. Death, too, his own, when justice overtakes. Chabannes. When overtaken, be it so with us! Behoves yourself regard your proper state! Macée. I'm past all fear. Do with me as you list. I plead not for your mercy. Spare me but Vain pageantry and hypocritic hymns;— No show—no pomp—no praise; unwailed, unwept; I would depart; seeing convention's self Has crumbled to its base, and faith on earth Has not a name to live! Chabannes. No more remains But in this holy Abbot's hands to place The mortal writ, under the royal seal. Macée. The royal seal? I do remember now; Among the charges brought against my lord, Was one most foul—that he had caused be made A forgèd seal with fleur de lis engraved, To serve his merchant gains with Saracens. Belike, 'tis such a counterfeit ye proffer;— Who bring such charges falsely, we may deem Willing, if safely, to incur the guilt. D'Ecole. If we thought so— Chabannes. Tush—tush! 'Tis the King's seal, As with my sword I'll answer! Who gainsays it? Trémouille. None but the prisoner. [Convent bell rings again. Simonet goes out. Macée. Some one else! He comes, By intuition to my soul foretold, In penitential prayer. Morn broke therewith; It was hope's day-spring! Simonet (returning). It is her lord, attended With a legate of the Pope, and divers soldiers, Who had forced their way with them within our walls, But that the royal escort, under orders Of Count Chabannes, prevented it. Chabannes. Meseems, A meet precaution I came guarded well. Simonet. Cœur and the Legate. Enter Cœur with the Legate. Cœur. Am I too late? Macée. No! No! Here is thy living—thy unburied wife! Now, living, though once dead to thee and love, Raised from the dead by love to welcome thee, Within these arms, now filled with love and thee! Cœur. My heart is full—amazed, enrapt, possessed With thy incredible fidelity, Divine Macée!—intrepid and devote— Thou hast as 'twere laid down thy life for me! —And now come I, to make like sacrifice, Unless these men be pitiful to both. Chabannes. You'd taken means to force us into pity. Your band of bravoes shewed no yielding mood! Cœur. You know, Chabannes, that you have troops without, Outnumbering my poor crew. Chabannes. I am safe in that! Nothing but magic had enabled yours To overmaster mine. Not being so, Thy pageant suite I scorn. Macée. I'll drop no tear— Nor shall irresolution mar a feature; And when I speak, my voice shall yet be firm. Chabannes. Sir, hear you me? Cœur. Right well, I thank thee. What! wouldst thou have me plead? Then look at me, Or her! If either flinch, contemn us! But If both be stedfast, then—thyself being brave— Respect in us the virtue thou hast shown. Who most excite compassion, most disdain: The gladiator who despises death, The gazing vulgar clamour for his life. Be not less generous than the herd thou leadest. Chabannes. Hast thou no more to urge? Cœur. No—not to thee! But with Mathieu D'Ecole, the Abbot here, The legate of his holiness the Pope Is charged to speak in his great master's name. D'Ecole. Say on, right reverend legate. Legate. I am bid By the most gracious Nicholas, to say, That the good merchant Cœur, a tonsured clerk, Has been unjustly, by the laic power, Condemned; yet being prisoner held within A convent's sacred walls, though innocent; The guilt of his escape, being such a clerk, Was greater made by that: ... in which same guilt, Both he who fled and she who stayed behind, Were subject unto censure. But his holiness, On the premise consulting, by the force Of apostolic mercy dealt to him, On their repentance, has absolved the twain; Commanding you by me, to let them go. D'Ecole. How shall I answer it to the King of France? Chabannes. Well said, D'Ecole! The King of France in us, Forbids this interference. Here's his warrant Upon the life of both. Trémouille. Foes of such craft Should have the speedier riddance. Cœur (passing over with Macée to Chabannes). Let us pass! Chabannes. You would not brawl within this holy place? Cœur. Therefore, I say, let us pass forth together! Your troops exceed in strength and number mine— The Church absolves, and gives us passage free— Let the State's quarrel be without decided; We'll prove the issue, when beyond these walls. It is a little grace, if you accord, May bring you larger gain. Chabannes. I'll not accord it. Poor trafficker in promises, who'd trade On credit now substantial means are gone! Cœur. For your own good be counselled. Macée. Dearest Cœur! Why supplicate you thus? Here we can die, As well as there! Let them accumulate Crime on their crime;—the sin of sacrilege Add to the number they commit in thought, As they already have that murder added To most unparalleled ingratitude! Chabannes. That word has stoned my heart! Thy debtor, Cœur, Is now thy creditor. What once was thine Is mine. For that arrest once meant for me, I can repay you now in kind. What shouts [Shouts heard without. Are those? Enter Michelet. Hoa, there! 'Tis Captain Michelet! Doubtless (to Cœur) he has seized upon your coward crew! (To Michelet) I saw you enter—you are vigilant! You've come in time, good Captain Michelet. Bring in your guard. Michelet. I was about to do so. [Exit, after speaking to Chabannes' guards. [Shouts again. Trémouille. Ha! that sounds well!—they're zealous in our cause. Macée (apart). Now I can smile at this. O, fondly thought— That to be virtuous was to be revered! And Cœur still thinks, as he has ever thought, 'Tis not ingratitude, but fear sins in them. 'Tis well the brave and wise for motive own Virtue, not guerdon. Well for me, I share The noble consciousness which now I note, From his calm brow, unflushed, unmovèd cheek, Supports his soul—that he no act hath done, But what partook of greatness—that to him, His country owes deliverance—that to him, His monarch was indebted for his crown— And not a citizen but benefits By his undaunted enterprize; whereby France has received new life-blood, vigour new, Power that was not, till Cœur created it. And if for this the lightning that destroys, But consecrates, strike him again; and now For ruin ultimate, without reprieve; Let it be so!—For glory shall descend, And fill the space should clip his statue in! [Shouts again heard without. Cœur. Fear not those shouts, Macée! Them, on sure grounds, I otherwise interpret than my foes. Jean du Village, Alain Chartier, Michelet, Troops and Monks enter. Chartier. Stay, Michelet! To all now present greeting, In me the bearer own of royal power. Chabannes, Trémouille, must both yield place to me. Chabannes. Not without further warrant. Chartier. Rightly pleaded. Then, Michelet, there are your prisoners! [Michelet arrests Chabannes and Trémouille. Chabannes. What mean you, captain? Trémouille. Take you us for them! [Pointing to Macée and Cœur. Michelet. In am no speaker, count. I but obey King Louis' orders. Macée. Louis, king? Chartier. He is. Self-starved, King Charles has died; and Louis reigns. Macée. O, mystery of justice! Yet instruct me— How bears it on Chabannes and on Trémouille? Chartier. Might they not better tell you? Chabannes. Not a word. Trémouille. Unless it were a wizard's spell, to harm! Macée. Their lips have not such music, Chartier! I should prefer their utterance to yours. Chartier. I'll speak, then. Louis, being king, will reign: And that he may do so, at once disgraces George la Trémouille and Antoine de Chabannes; For their offences proved against himself, Of every office that they once possessed They are deprived; and, in the Louvre, condemned, First to imprisonment:—next, banishment:— And confiscation absolute of all. Macée. And what for Cœur? Chartier. Ask of your faithful steward, Whose vigilance has brought much good about. Village. Most honoured lady, here is the decree, The letters-patent under Louis' hand: “That, on remonstrance made, his majesty, “Touching the life and welfare of Jacques Cœur, “Sometime his royal father's argentier, “Who, by the false reports of his ill-wishers, “Had been unrighteously despoiled of all; “To him just restitution should be made, “Both of the lands that De Chabannes had seized, “And other the estates whereof he was “Rightful possessor and true lord.” Cœur. Rejoice, Beloved Macee! Chartier. This Jean Village has done— And 'twas his speed kept measure with my own. So when arrived, I found him there before me, Even in the court of Louis, with credentials Won from the new-made king. To which credentials, Even now, the troops Chabannes brought hither yielding, At once allegiance swore to royal Louis. Doubtless, you heard their shouts. Cœur. Ay, did we, sir; As likewise did Chabannes, and you, Trémouille! —Unworthy men! had ye but shown remorse, How slight soever, for your cruelties, For your evasion means had I provided, Which now would come too late. Chartier. 'Tis better so. Captain! you have your orders: take your prisoners, And hold them in safe custody. [Chabannes and Trémouille are led out, guarded. Cœur. Their silence Bespeaks profound despair. Macée! beshrew me, Compassion for their doom, despite their guilt, Afflicts me more than I had thought it would. Macée. And I, too, may rejoice, but not exult. Sin leaves its scars upon the pardoned soul; Forgiveness woundeth more than punishment. Had I died for you, I had triumphed more, Than now I may. But this more sober joy Heals more than wilder transport. Death heals all! The bruisèd spirit which I bear within Is prescient of departure. Better, Cœur! A few few days of love and confidence, Than many years of jealousy and doubt. [Macée buries her face within Cœur's bosom. THE END.</field>
   </doc>
</add>