<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Southerne, Thomas, 1660-1746</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Southerne, Thomas, 1660-1746</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">southerne thomas 1660 1746</field>
      <field name="author_text">Southerne, Thomas, 1660-1746</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">18th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1710's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V2.0175.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240355</field>
      <field name="date_text">1719</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:459898</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Spartan Dame ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 18th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Spartan Dame ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="title_facet">spartan dame</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">spartan dame</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Spartan Dame ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="year_display">1719</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1719</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1719</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459898&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459898&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Southerne, Thomas, 1660-1746&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;southerne thomas 1660 1746&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Spartan Dame ; A Tragedy&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;spartan dame&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1719&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1719&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Southerne, Thomas&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1660&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1746&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Spartan Dame&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for W. Chetwood ... and T. Jauncy [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1719&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872234-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv20175&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 18th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;18th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Spartan Dame&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 192 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: The Spartan dame.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1719.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 11 Dec 1719.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE Spartan Dame. A TRAGEDY.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Pellex ego facta Sororis. Ovid. Meta. Lib. 6.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">To His Grace the Duke of ARGYLE and GREENWICH, &amp;c.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PROLOGUE By Mr. Fenton. Spoken by Mr. Cibber. When Realms are ravag'd with invasive Foes, Each Bosom with heroick Ardor glows; Old Chiefs, reflecting on their former Deeds, Disdain to rust with batter'd Invalides; But active in the foremost Ranks appear, And leave young smock-fac'd Beaux to guard the Rear. So, to repel the Vandals of the Stage, Our Vet'ran Bard resumes his Tragick Rage: He throws the Gauntlet Otway us'd to wield, And calls for Englishmen to judge the Field: Thus arm'd, to rescue Nature from Disgrace, Messieurs! lay down your Minstrells, and Grimace: The brawniest Youths of Troy the Combat fear'd, When old Entellus in the Lists appear'd. Yet what avails the Champion's Giant Size, When Pigmies are made Umpires of the Prize? Your Fathers (Men of Sense, and honest Bowlers) Disdain'd the Mummery of foreign Strollers: By their Examples wou'd you form your Taste, The present Age might emulate the past. We hop'd that Art and Genius had secur'd you; But soon facetious Harlequin allur'd you: The Muses blush'd, to see their Friends exalting Those elegant Delights of Jigg, and Vaulting: So charm'd you were, you ceas'd a while to doat On Nonsense, gargl'd in an Eunuch's Throat. All pleas'd to hear the chatt'ring Monsters speak. As old Wives wonder at the Parson's Greek. Such light Ragousts and Mushrooms may be good. To whet your Appetites for wholesome Food: But the bold Britton ne'er in earnest dines Without substantial Haunches, and Surloins. In Wit, as well as War, they give us Vigour; Cressy was lost by Kickshaws, and Soupe meagre. Instead of light Deserts, and luscious Froth, Our Poet treats to Night with Spartan Broth; To which, as well as all his former Feasts, The Ladies are the chief-invited Guests. Crown'd with a kind of Glassenbury Bays, That bloom amid the Winter of his Days; He comes, ambitious in his green Decline, To consecrate his Wreath at Beauty's Shrine. His Oronooko never fail'd to engage The radiant Circles of the former Age: Each Bosom heav'd, all Eyes were seen to flow, And sympathize with Isabella's Woe: But Fate reserv'd, to crown his elder Fame, The brightest Audience for the Spartan Dame.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Dramatis Personæ. Leonidas, A King of Sparta, driven out by the People. Mr. Mills. Cleombrotus, Attains the Kingdom by the Expulsion of Leonidas, marry'd to Celona, but in Love with her Sister Thelamia. Mr. Booth. Eurytion, Husband to Thelamia, of Leonidas's Party. Mr. Wilks. Agesilaus, The Ephorus, an Incendiary of the People against Leonidas, and fast to the Interest of Cleombrotus. Mr. Corey. Lysander, Sides, with Leonidas. Mr. Thurmond. Zenocles, Sides with Leonidas. Mr. Williams. Mandrocles, Sides with Cleombrotus. Mr. Will, Mills Thracion, Sides with Cleombrotus. Mr. Oates. Crites, Husband to Byzanthe. Mr. Cibher. Celona, Or Chelonis, marry'd to Cleombrotus. Mrs. Oldfield. Thelamia, Her Sister, Wife to Eurytion. Mrs. Porter. Euphemia, Another Sister in Diana's Temple. Mrs. Seal. Byzanthe, Wife to Crites. Mr. Garnet. Citizens, Guards, Gentlemen, and Attendants.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE Sparta.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. SCENE I. Agesilaus, Mandrocles, and Cleon. Ages. Propose 'em as the Business of the Day; They'll take up all our Time. Cleon. I wo'not fail. [Exit. Ages. Then he's a King. Mand. The Change will mend us all. Cleombrotus and Thracion to 'em. Cleom. The Harvest of our Hopes at last is come; Rich in a Crop that will reward the Toil; A plenteous Crop, to fill the Reaper's Hand, And with the Binder's Sheaves, load every Barn. Ages. Then let us not stand idle; Mandrocles And Thracion, you must to your several Posts. Cleom. Summon our Friends, and lead our Parties to The Hyppodrome: We shall have need of you. Thra. You sha'not want us long. Mand. We wo'not fail you. Ages. I am the Engineer to fire the Senate; The Flame must break out there. Cleom. I follow you! If we succeed, a King shall thank your Loves. [Exeunt. Celona to Cleombrotus. Cleom. Celona here! my Wife! Celo. Your loving Wife. Cleom. You'r early up to Day. Celo. My Bed, my Lord, Has no more Charms for me, when you are gone. Cleom. Dress'd sooner too than usual. Celo. My Beauties, Such as they are, are honest, and my own; They go to Bed with me, with me they rise, And need not many Hours in putting on. Besides, for me to court my Morning Glass, And practise Looks, were Loss of Time indeed. I am already what the Vanity Of a fond dressing Pride, in all its height, And Wantonness of Expectation, Can raise my Wishes to; I am your Wife, Most honour'd in that Title; and despise The Applause and Breath of any other Praise, Than of my Vertue, and Obedience now. Cleom. Hear this, you libelling Marriage-mortifiers! You unhous'd, lawless, rambling Libertines! Senseless of any Charms in Love, beyond The Prostitution of a common Bed, Lewdly enjoy'd, and loath'd: hear, hear, and kneel Before this Shrine, repent, and all get Wives; That from the healthy Constitution Of your own chaste Endearments, you may guess At what I feel, too mighty for my Tongue. Celo. O! stop not here, my list'ning Soul is charm'd Into my Ears, and dies upon the Sound Of ev'ry Word, soft as a Lover's Wish, And I cou'd hear you ever. Cleom. O my fair One! There is a Story, but I have not time Now to inform thee in it— Celo. O my Fears! Cleom. That will delight thee. Celo. Your Words always do. Cleom. Ay, but these Words carry strong Sense indeed, A sovereign Sense. Celo. The Meaning is too plain. Cleom. I won't anticipate the Happiness, By telling what you will so quickly find: But raise your Wishes high, mount your Desires On bold Ambition's Wing; whose airy Flight Shoots thro' the Clouds, to mingle with the Stars. When next we meet, I shall behold thee— Celo. A miserable Woman. [Going after him. Cleom. How, Celona! Celo. O my Cleombrotus! my Lord, my Life! What Furies urge you on this desp'rate Course, That leads to certain Ruin? Cleom. Whither wou'dst thou? Celo. I fear'd indeed before, but now I find The Ephori, those Fiends of popular Pow'r, By damning Spells have wrought upon your Soul, Seduc'd you into a Combination Of their black Plots against Leonidas: Why do you turn away? Cleom. O! I must leave you. Celo. I am your self, my Lord. Cleom. Pray let me go. Celo. Half of your self, your Wife. Cleom. You are my Wife Celo. And in that Right I speak, and shou'd be heard. My Fame must live but in your Chronicle: And as your Actions show to After-times, My Memory will be honour'd, or despis'd; Therefore I speak, and therefore must be heard. Cleom. Then I must hear you. Celo. Suffer not, my Lord, The industrious Malice of our Histories, To take the Advantage of a Crime like this, To stain the glorious Story of our Lives, And curse our Names to late Posterity. Cleom. Thou wou'dst not have me stand a Looker on, Behold the strongest Hand carry the Prize Of Empire from my Hopes? Celo. My Soul disdains The Weakness of that Thought: No, no, my Lord, I wou'd not have you tame at such a time, Boldly assert the Cause of Majesty; For yours is the Succession. Cleom. What I do Is to secure it mine. [A Servant enters. Serv. Crites, my Lord, attends you. [Goes out. Cleom. Pray retire, and in this Confidence, that all my Actions Shall wait upon my Honour. Celo. That's my Hope; Your Honour must engage you to the King: And in that Hope I leave you. [Exit. Cleom. Tender, and Chaste, and Fair! nay, she was once The boasted Pride, and Judgment of my Choice: So she was thought, and so I valu'd her: But she's my Wife—and nothing but a Wife, With all her Charms, cou'd have been stale so soon. [Crites enters behind him. O Curse of Marriage! Plenty makes its Wants; And what was meant Love's Food, starves all its Joys: The Feasts come quicker than our Appetites: Yet forcing Nature still, at last we cloy, And surfeit ev'n to loathing. Crit. My good Lord, Thelamia may restore— Cleom. My Health, my Life, She only can, my Crites, O that Sound! The very Mention of Thelamia's Name, Like a strong Philter, rages in my Veins, Shoots thro' the boiling Channels of my Blood, Up to my Heart; then with fresh Fury fed, Strikes at my Brain, where forming Fancy sits, Divining Pleasures in Thelamia's Arms; Which thou, and I, in all our Search of Love, And Riots in Experience of the Sex, Cou'd ne'er find out in any other Woman: O! she's excellent, and in that Thought, I must enjoy her. Crit. She's Eurytion's now. The Priest but Yesterday receiv'd their Vows, Their mutual Vows, bless'd 'em, and made 'em One. Cleom. How! made 'em One! O! that the cunning Priest Had conjur'd Us together, and made Us One! Incorporated Body, Blood, and Life, Our Spirits mix'd, and Love been all our Soul! Then I had been his Votary for ever. What's to be done? Speak thou who can'st advise. Crit. She's your Wife's Sister. Cleom. That's a Name indeed too distant from my Hopes. Crit. Then best forgotten. She knows your Love? Cleom. She must have known it long, but warily affects An Ignorance, that flies the Notice of it. Crit. She perhaps mistakes it only for a Brother's Love. Cleom. No, no, she knows me, and my Meaning well— Crit. And flies for Refuge to Eurytion's Arms. She must not 'scape you so. Eurytion, Fast to Leonidas, opposes you, and every Way— Cleom. His Virtue bluntly stands just in my Aim Of Empire, as of Love. Crit. Remove him then, And all your Plots fly sure, point blank, and level To the very White of your Designs. Cleom. Thelamia, and a Crown! Crit. They go together. Cleom. In that only Thought I'll conquer even Impossibilities: I know the Appearance Is to Reason, hard. But a King's Love Shou'd never know Despair. Crit. Despair! name not the Word. You know, my Lord, I'm fortunately for your Service, marry'd Into Eurytion's Family: My Wife Gives me a Title to their Confidence, Which I've improv'd, by a professing Zeal, To such a Reputation, that has been A Key to all their Counsels. I have serv'd Your politick Designs, and may assist your Love Affairs. Cleom. O! there is Life in thee. Crit. All, Sir, depends upon this very Day for the Success. [Shouts Hark, you are summon'd forth to head the Crowd. If your Ambition thrive, you have her in your Pow'r. Cleom. If that shou'd fail, I wo'not fail my self, Force shall prevail. [Exeunt. [Shouts, several running cross the Stage. Lysander and Zenocles enter. Lys. What's to be done? All's in a wild Combustion. Zen. The People, like a Torrent in its Fall, Disdaining Opposition, bear down all Before 'em: Ceremonies, Customs, Rites, Laws, human and divine; Orders, and Men Devoted to the Gods, profan'd, and scorn'd. Lys. All Quality, Distinction, and Degree Of Place, or Virtue, swept away, like Rubbish, By the vile Hands of popular Confusion. Zen. Our Party in the Senate-House, I thought, Was strong enough, concluding on those Fools Of Argument, and Noise, who roar'd for us: But when it came to Blows, our Orators, So famous for their Battles at the Bar, And Victory in Words, sneak'd from their Chairs, Stinted their Rhet'rick to a single Prayer, And wish'd us well. Lys. Slaves! who, but Minutes since, Drew down the Terror of loud Laws upon us, And spoke in Thunder; now, tho' they see the Rabble tossing Confusion about our Streets, Have not the Courage of a Lictor's Voice, To bid 'em keep the Peace. Zen. Eurytion yet stands firm, and constant. Lys. O'erpower'd by the Multitude, I saw him retreat towards Juno's Temple. Zen. There the Street is narrow, and may friend our Purpose well. Lys. The Example of his Bravery may steel us To the performance of some glorious Action, Great as our Cause, becoming honest Men, [Crites with Euphemia, enters to 'em. Zen. The fair Euphemia! Lys. O! thou Royal Maid! No Sanctuary left for Innocence! Euph. 'Tis fit my Father's Fortune shou'd be mine. Crit. I've snatch'd this Casket from the common Spoil, Worthy the Safeguard of the general Gods: And, as my Master's Heart is treasur'd here, Will place her in the Virgin Goddess' Shrine. Zen. The Gods, and good Mens Pray'rs must side with us. [Crites with Euphemia go out one way; Lysander and Zenocles another. Shouts, several Citizens enter. 1 Cit. Nay, better or worse, as time shall try; but so it is. Now we shall have the Laws for taking away our Debts, and dividing Lands. Lycurgus, as you have all heard, was a wise Man, and lov'd the People. In his Days we were all equal. 2 Cit. Equal! Neighbour, as how? How equal? pray? 1 Cit. How equal? why—equal in respect of Equality! How shou'd it be! that is, one Man as good as another. 2 Cit. Ay, those were Times indeed: but we, and our Fathers afore us, Now-a-days, are little better than Rascals, that's the Truth on't. [Trumpets flourish. 1 Cit. Stand aside: the new King is coming this Way; Let's see how his Majesty has alter'd him— The very same thing still for Courtesie.— See how he bows, and smiles on every Hand— Stand close, he'll speak anon. Cleombrotus attended. Agesilaus, Mandrocles, and Thracion, with Lysander, Zenocles, and Crites, Prisoners. Cleom. My Thanks among you, my most worthy Friends! This but begins, what a long happy Reign; (The Gods and you confirm it long, and happy,) Shall multiply in Blessings on you all. Not One of you, who has this Day appear'd In the Defence of Sparta, and her Laws, But Sparta here adopts among her Sons. Crit. The Sons of Sparta now are Slaves indeed. Cleom. And as her Sons, shall find a Parent's Care To make you happy, and secure you so, In all the common Goods of Government. Omnes. Liberty, Freedom; Liberty in Sparta. [Shouting. Cleom. Enough of this. I wou'd entreat you all To wait me to the Senate-House; there I Will give the Reasons of my Actions: Which, when our frighted Senators shall find Founded on no Designs, but what intend The publick Weal, our Liberties, and Laws, And the kind Care of all our People's Peace; How will they blush for so mistaking me! Ages. Mistaking you indeed, and all your Ends. Cleom. Agesilaus, you are the Ephorus, The People's first chief Magistrate in Sparta. Ages. But you their Champion and Deliverer. Mand. The Patron of the People's Liberties. Thras. Their Lives, and Freedoms, all redeem'd by you. Cleom. These are high sounding Titles, but the way To keep 'em mine? Ages. By passing of the Laws For cancelling Debts.— Cleom. And the dividing Lands. Ages. Sir, cancelling their Debts, at present will Content 'em: still keep something in your Hands; Dividing of the Lands may serve a Turn Another time, and make an After-Game. Cleom. I am advis'd: lead to the Senate-House. Ages. Yet e'er you go, begin a Justice here, Upon the People's, and your Enemies. Cleom. My Mercy had forgot 'em. Zenocles, And you Lysander, what you have advis'd, And acted against me, I freely pardon. But as you have betrayed the People's Trust, Being of the Ephorate, yet siding with Leonidas, against their Interest: I, in the People's Name, discard you Both From that high Office; which I will supply. With Men of worthier Note: You Mandrocles, And Thracion, shall fill up this Vacancy. Mand. and Thra. We are your Servants ever. Zen. We are doom'd. Lys. Is there ought else? Ages. Release 'em: You are free. But here's a Rogue Just ripe, and ready for the Hangman's Hands. Cleom. Thou Firebrand of Fools! what canst thou say To qualify thy Mischiefs by Excuse, in hopes of Pardon? Crit. What I did, I did in honest Earnest, and by open Day. In Duty to the Interest I serv'd: And now to stammer out a weak Defence, Can't make me innocent, but wou'd betray A Fear, that never shall be Part of me. Cleom. I know thee dangerous; yet since thou hast Some Virtues, which prefer and place thee near The Trust, and Bosom of a Man I love, And wou'd engage, I pardon all that's past, Eurytion pardons thee: but his Heart scorns To be oblig'd: and therefore we are forc'd Not to depend upon him. Forward, Friends. [Exeunt. Eurytion enters to Lysander, Zenocles, and Crites. Crit. Life is not yet become a Burden to me; Therefore I offer up, in thankfulness, To my Preserver, to Eurytion, My Days to come, and their best Services, to wait upon your Fortune. Eury. I accept them, and thy Love. Thou truly gallant Man! Come to my Arms: and O! embrace him all. This Spirit seems inspir'd to raise the Hopes of honest Men, And I obey the Call: no longer then Be our Hearts Strangers to each others Breasts: Fearless, and free, we'll interchange our Souls, Both of the past; and what we may expect from what's to come. Zen. What is there to expect? Lys. Or what can come? Eury. Let not the Carriage of Cleombrotus Lull us in a supine Security, Sooth our Credulity to the fond Thought, That he can pardon us. We are not safe, Till he be satisfied his Pow'r is so: And that can't be, but by the Fall of those Who have appear'd his Enemies. Crit. And how we stand in his Opinion, is well known. Eury. We are not Boys, nor is Cleombrotus; Whose quick Suspicion, as it will awake His Fears of us, so let our Reason too Provide against the Danger of those Fears, Which always end in Blood. Crit. For my own part, I value Life, but just as Life deserves. Eury. A sudden Thought, but hudled and confus'd, Unargu'd yet, inspires me with high Hopes, Which our united Counsels may digest To a maturity of Growth and Pow'r. Lys. This Place is much frequented, and too publick For our present Purpose. Eury. Pray withdraw with me, And you shall know the Ground I work upon. If then you find my Means sufficient To lead us on in this great Enterprize; Our Dangers, as our Hopes, will be the same, A Life with Honour, or a Death with Fame [Exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. SCENE I. Eurytion, with Crites and a Servant, gives a Letter to a Servant, who goes out. Eury. These must with Speed and Safety be convey'd. And, Crites, in these Tablets, you will find The Method I propose in my Design, Which you must be instructed in: You'll find Something concern my Wife; let that be kept A Treasure in thy Heart: for on that Trust Depends my All. Crit. I'll keep it as my Heart. Eury. Things thus dispos'd for our Intelligence, Nothing that in our Absence passes here, Can 'scape our quickest Notice. Crit. Nothing can: The distance of Tegæa from this Place, Favours our Posts, that may be hourly with you. Eury. My time grows short: I have a Word or two For my Thelamia's Ear: A farewell Kiss, Parting with such a Wife, may be allow'd, And not disgrace my Duty; that Rite pay'd, Thither I follow too. [Going. Crit. I know not what, My staying here behind methinks appears But an unactive, lasy— Eury. Pray, no more! Crit. I wou'd do something for him. Eury. Your staying here at this time, serves us best. Besides, Thelamia in my Absence may Need the Protection of thy friendly Care. Crit. Sir, I have done, and the Charge honours me. Eury. Pray Crites, tell my Wife—I'll go my self— But see she meets my way— The Graces all attending on her Steps— [Thelamia enters to him. I stood but now superior, and unmov'd, Ev'n in this Flesh, and Frailty of a Man, To all the Storms of this bad Under-world, But wonder at the Virtue of thy Love; Which, tho' worse Days were to succeed these bad, Might entertain me thro' long weary Years Of wretched Life: deceiving all my Cares In thy dear Arms; forgetting all for thee. Thel. O thou first Fondness of a Virgin Heart! How shall my untaught Innocence instruct me? How tell thee what my Heart wou'd have thee know? Eury. Thy Eyes inform me, their chaste Beams inspire And speak in Smiles the Language of thy Heart; Thy Heart, the Throne of Virtue! where my Peace, My Happiness, and Life must wait for ever. Crit. I may provide her better Company. [Aside. Eury. O let me thus transported, view thee still! Still thus transported touch thee! and each Touch, As ravishing, as was that furious First, That gave me the Possession of thy Love, And made thee mine for ever. Crit. He grows warm On the Imagination: I may cool you. [Aside. Thel. Cou'd this but last, my Lord. Eur. It ever shall. Thel. I fear the Gods are envious of our Joys. Eury. Thus thou hast often heard me: all my Words Thus charm'd, and fitted to thy tender Ear: As when I look upon thee, my fir'd Heart Must wanton in the Rapture of thy Praise. Thus thou hast always found me: but till now, Ne'er came prepar'd to leave thee. I have told thee The hard Necessity that presses me, And by my Absence best will be obey'd. Thel. Our Marriage sure was ominous: the Storms That threatned, and the Face of Things That frown'd upon its Birth, when we were join'd, Portend succeeding Mischiefs. Eury. Not to thee, My Love? They cannot mean thee any harm: Safe in thy Innocence, and Sister's Love, Thy Fears are vain: But I have done those things, Cleombrotus, tho' I were reconcil'd To all his Ills, can never pardon me. Therefore my Safety does advise my Absence now. Thel. O take me with you then! This is a World The Weak will suffer in: and who so weak, As Woman thus expos'd, thus naked left, Without the Care— Eury. Thou art my dearest Care. Thel. Yet I am left behind you— Eury. Not expos'd: O! think not so: my Crites here, my Friend, Whose Honesty, and faithful Services Have so renown'd, is thy Security, Thy Refuge from all Wrongs. Crit. Sir, I am bound the Servant of your Fortune. Thel. He indeed is truly honest: and 'tis some Relief Of my Misfortunes that he stays behind. Crit. My Life upon the Trust. Eury. I know thy Faith. And farther, Crites, let Bizanthe know Her near Relation to my Wife does claim Her, a Companion of this Solitude, during my Absence. Thel. Her kind Company will pass away the melancholy Hours. Crit. Madam, my Wife shall constantly attend you. Eury. Tho' I am forc'd thus to absent my self From all I love; I shall contrive some Means, Some friendly Intervals to visit thee: But then my Coming must be private, made A Secret, my own Servants not employ'd. Crites, who has my Reasons, will inform you, At better Leisure, why I thus proceed. Thel. I have sufficient Reasons in your Will, A Law to me, and shall be so obey'd. Eury. He shall be qualify'd from time to time, To let you know what happens. Thel. I must hear Hourly of your Health. I know not why, Altho' I know you safe in Crites' Faith, Yet still my Heart must tremble in its Fears. Eury. Only the Tenderness of parting Love Banish all Fears. [Exeunt. Crit. Ay, so says Crites too, Security will serve the Turn as well. Here he disposes in my Hand the Scheme Of their Designs—so much for State Affairs— Then he commits his Wife to the Protection of my Care, And certain Honesty. Why thus he spares My Pains, and plays the Game into my Hand. My Honesty! alas! that has long since Been brib'd by the Ambition of those Hopes, Cleombrotus must raise to Growth and Power. Therefore I am his Slave, and act all Parts, His Spy in Business, and in Love his—what? The Word indeed is coarse to dainty Ears. But he that makes his Fortune in this World, Must sometimes do what he wou'd blush to name. I wou'd not be observ'd—the Coast is clear— [Goes to the Door and returns. The Commerce of the World will have us save Th'Appearances, and Dress of Decency: We must put on those Forms, and Features, which Resemble, and come nearest our Design. All are not born with handsome Faces; then Mend 'em, the Ladies will advise, Paint to the fair Complexion of the Times, And hide the natural Deformity. Whom have we here? I wou'd observe unseen— Celona, enters with Mandrocles, and Thracion cringing to her. Celo. News of a Crown, and Royal Dignity, Is worth a Welcome sure from any Hand. But when such Men— Thra. The Servants of your Will. Celo. Such Friends— Man. Your honour'd, faithful Slaves. Celo. Such worthy Friends! Mand. Our Lives, and Interests Devoted to your Majesty's Command. Celo. When such as you are the kind Messengers, How can my Gratitude express my Thanks! Mand. Madam, the Honour of your Royal Hand— Thra. O'erpays our Hopes. [Offering to kiss her Hand, she puts 'em by. Cleo. You Brace of courteous, cringing Sycophants! You double hearted Slaves, and double tongu'd! Whose hollow Flatteries wou'd win me to Your rotten Sides, only to prop your Pride. Avaunt, be gone: But that I scorn, detest All the Advantages of Place, or Pow'r, Such despicable, wretched Instruments Can raise my Fortune to, you shou'd not scape The common Hangman's Hands—my Thoughts are bent On Matters more importing than your Death. But fly in time, hated, and curs'd be gone: For if you tempt me longer by your stay, This Dagger shall reward your Villanies. [Drives 'em off. How I abhor the odious sight of 'em! [Crites comes forward. But here comes one, an honest hearted Man, And welcome to my Eyes. Crit. Madam, you seem Disturb'd at something; what can be the Cause? Celo. A Trifle, Crites, at the first despis'd, But now forgot; My Sister is within? Pray let her know I'm here. Crit. I'm proud to serve you. [Exit. Celo. Oh! that I cou'd recall the Innocence Of yesterday: then there were Halcyon Calms! What a Tranquility, and Peace of Mind, Employ'd the Hours in Comforts on my Days! My full Content sate smiling on my Brow, And laughing in my Heart: now fled far off. Eurytion with Thelamia and Crites Eury. Once more farewell, 'tis hard to part with thee, But part we must: now, Crites, I am gone. [Exit with Crites. Celo. I did not think, Thelamia, that your Husband Cou'd pass thus coldly by: methought his Eyes Were cautious of me, and at distance held, Glanc'd on me the Suspicion of his Fears. Thel. Oh! do not blame Eurytion, tax not him Of any Fault, but charge it where it is. Celo. I bring along with me a Sister's Love; Wou'd have it so believ'd, and so return'd: No Spy upon his Actions. Thel. You are rais'd A Partner of that Power he has oppos'd. From that Reflection, Sister, you must find My Lord's Excuse; who, banish'd from himself, And driven from the Temper of his Soul, The natural Disposition of his Love, Compell'd and forc'd, appears thus chang'd and cold. Celo. Oh Sister! can a Lady show herself To more Advantage, than in pleading thus A Husband's Cause? Yet that I am deny'd. O! 'tis a Theme for the Athenian Song; And fits the Virtue of a Spartan Wife. Cleombrotus with Agesilaus to 'em. Thel. Here comes the King. Celo. Are you turn'd Courtier too? Ages. He must have chang'd his Purpose, else he had Faln into their Ambush. Cleom. I am pleas'd His Flight has scap'd 'em: to Tegæa I know he's gone, Some two Hours hence I shall have Business ripe For your Advice. Ages. My Duty shall attend your Majesty. [Exit. Thel. 'Tis fit I leave you. Celo. I wou'd have you stay. Cleom. Oh, Madam, are you found? This is a Place I'm pleas'd to find you in. Celo. I'm glad you're pleas'd. Cleom. I come, Thelamia, as a Brother ought to visit you. Thel. That Title of your Love makes all my Happiness. Cleom. I know your Heart is full of Fears, that your soft, gentle Sex, The Disposition of your Natures takes More dangerous Impressions of your Fears, Than Bodies stronger form'd; therefore I come— Celo. Like a kind Brother— Thel. Heaven grant he prove no more! Cleom. I know, in the Obligation of your Blood, And as becomes the Office of your Love, You have already told her— Celo. Told her, Sir! Cleom. Ay, given her all those kind Assurances— Celo. Of what, my Lord? Cleom. Of me and of my Fortune: Which, as my Friends shall still command she may Expect an ample Share in. Celo. That Subject, Sir, you best can speak upon. Cleom. You shou'd have done it. Celo. What Power had I? Cleom. You know my Power is yours: Besides, it must have been a grateful Theme. Celo. I thought not so. Cleom. How! 'twou'd have pleas'd you sure? Celo. Far otherwise. Cleom. I thought it might have pleas'd you. Celo. No, I do not understand it. Cleom. That is strange. Celo. Nor care to be instructed. Cleom. This proceeds from some more subtle Cause. Celo. From a plain Truth: Nor do I understand how I can give Her more Assurances, than I myself Can take from your new Fortune. Cleom. That indeed You cannot well; She has a Sister's Claim, But you're the Mistress of it, and my Queen. Come, come, no more of this Indifference, This Coldness misbecomes your present State, It looks like Envy of your Happiness, Which only Fools inflict upon themselves. Celo. All Arguments are unavailing now, Tedious and from the Purpose, and to ask Why you have thus proceeded, cannot change The Nature of the Action, or undo What is already done. Cleom. Grant that, and then We must look forward, where the opening Scene Discloses Nature, elegantly dress'd, To welcome us in her inviting Arms: We have that glorious Prospect now in view. To turn and wonder at the slippery Paths, The heavy Steps, the difficult Degrees, By which we rose, were to deny ourselves Those Pleasures, which invited first our Hopes, And wou'd reward our Pains No, Madam, no— Celo. Oh! Sister, witness to my Virtue now, Which tempted thus, thus courted to a Throne, And by the Man, who has all Charms for me, Stands yet resolv'd. Thel. Of what? Cleom. Resolv'd! Celo. Oh Sir, were it a Task for every common Strength To undertake, it were no Part for me: But loving as I do, and so belov'd! Prosperity inviting every Sense, With various Arts, to unprovide my Mind! What but a Spartan Spirit can sustain The Shock of such Temptations; thus resolve To leave the Comforts of your Bed and Throne, And live a Mourner for a Husband's Crimes? Cleom. How! How! Celona! wou'd Thelamia e'er Have us'd Eurytion thus? Celo: He never wou'd Have given her this Cause: my Life, my Love, My Fortune, my Obedience, all are yours; But of my eternal Part, my death less Fame, I am the Mistress, and must here command. True Sorrow only lives within the Heart, And in our Actions best is understood. Therefore my Virtue will allow no Mean— I must renounce your Power, or share your Crimes. Cleom. This Virtue which you senslesly affect, Is a Plebeian. Weakness in your Soul. A poor degenerate Fear of what may be, Which nobler Minds can never apprehend. Celo. My Lord! my Lord! I was not born to fear; My Country places me above my Sex: I am a Spartan born, can know no Fears But of Dishonour, and I wou'd be still A Coward in these Fears. Thel. Where will this end? Celo. But you are pleas'd to tax me, in your Phrase, Of a Plebeian Weakness: Sir, I scorn A groveling Soul; I have a Mind as high, As generously inspir'd with Royal Thoughts, As enterprizing, great, and glorious, As e'er Ambition prompted to a Crown. Cleom. Give me but a Proof of this. Celo. I will. Cleom. I ask no more. Celo. The highest Proof. Oh! were what you posses, A Fortune nobly rais'd in the Defence Of Rites insulted, or invaded Laws! Your Crown, the Thanks of a free'd Peoples Love! The Gift of vindicated Liberty! A Wreath of Triumph over Tyranny! The glorious Spoil of Arbitrary Power, Wrested and torn from an Oppressor's Hand! Oh! were it so deserv'd, and so bestow'd, How could I dress that Brow, and deck my own! What Plots, what Factions, what Conspiracies, What impudent Rebellion should oppose Your Title then! I have a Royal Soul Wou'd throw me on my Fate, never to rest, Till I were in the Grave, or on the Throne. Cleom. Exert that Royal Soul, let it still reign. Celo. I will, and as I wou'd all Dangers undertake, To share the Godlike Power of doing Good; So from that sacred Right of Sovereignty, I scorn the Privilege of doing Ill. No generous Motive from the Publick Cause, But an Impulse of impotent Desire, The wandring Lust of a licentious Will, Has hurry'd you, to violate all Laws, Which stood between you and your impious Ends, 'Tis therefore I abhor your Tyranny, That base-born Issue of unlawful Might! Begot upon the Fears of bad Mens Crimes, Or prostituted slavish Principles; Cradled in Infamy, and rear'd in Vice, Fatted with Feasts of undeserved Praise! Blown up with Flattery to a Giant Size Of Rapine, and oppressive Insolence, To trample down the Bounds of Property, And seize the common Birth-right, Liberty. This is the Monster Idol you set up, Which, in the Pride of Virtue, I despise, And in that Pride I go—But do not think You can be safe, you and your dark Designs Long cannot prosper; nay, by Hercules, The Father of our Empire, I hope they wo'not long: Nay, I myself will head my Country's Cause Against your Crimes—But Oh! the Conflict here! You judging Gods! whose Sentence has assign'd To wretched Mortals our proportion'd Share Of Labour, and our Recompence of Fame For Virtuous Actions, look in Pity on me: Compose this tost, this tempest-beaten Breast, With different Tides of swelling Woe oppress'd; By turns sustain the Daughter and the Wife, Or sink Celona in the glorious Strife. [Exit. Cleom. You wo' not leave me too? Thel. I'll follow her, and bring her back. Cleom. O! you may spare your pains. Her Fury must have way; shes best alone, And we as well without her. Thel. How, my Lord! You do not speak your Thoughts, you cannot mean— Cleom. I can mean only thee! All that thy Pray'rs Can ask of Heav'n, all that the Gods can grant In answer of thy Wishes, all be thine Eternal Youth, an Ever-rising Spring Of smiling Beauty, in its blushing Bloom, Make thee the Pride and Wish of Hearts and Eyes: All Joys, all Blessings, which long happy Years Of Empire can bestow, I mean to thee. Thel. Where wou'd this lead me? Cleom. O! thou canst not be So dull, Thelamia, not to apprehend What this intends: I wou'd prepare thee thus By soft degrees, gently engage thy Ear, In favour of a Cause, which I must plead, And thou must judge. Thel. My Sentence will be mild. Cleom. Indeed thy Looks are wondrous pitiful: Thy Heart's a-kin to 'em. Thel. I mean, my Lord, I may prove partial, and pronounce for you, As you're my King, and Brother. Cleom. O that Word! Wou'd I were more than that, or not so much. That Brother is too cold: canst thou not find A nearer Name? one nearer to thy Love, That better can bespeak thee. Thel. There is none; No Name, in the Relation of our Blood, Kindred, or Family, nearer ally'd To our Affections, than a Brother is; Husband is only more, Cleom. And yet you see I am forsaken: nay, Thelamia, you Ev'n you're abandon'd by a Husband too. Good Gods! what is this Marriage? that so soon Depraves our Appetites, that thus prefers Vile Things to pretious? It comes like Frost Upon a forward Spring: the Flower of Youth, Wanton in gay Desires, here nipt, shrinks in With all its Sweets, drooping the tender Head Upon its Stalk, no worthier than a Weed. Thel. You're merry, Sir, with our Condition. Cleom. Who but a Husband ever cou'd persuade His Heart to leave the Bosom of thy Love, For any phlegmatick Design of State, Of Life, or Fortune? But he's satisfied, And I shou'd not complain: his Absence makes Me room for my Desires— Thel. Desires, my Lord! Cleom. We are forsaken, but not quite forlorn; Not destitute of Comfort: there remains A Recompence— Thel. A Recompence! Cleom. Rich as my Hopes— Thel. What Hopes? Cleom. That seems intended by our very Fates, Designingly removing every Bar, To make our way to one another's Arms. Why do you fly me? Thel. O! I now perceive my Ruin plain. Cleom. What can you fear in me? Thel. I am most miserable. Cleom. How? Thel. No more; I've heard too much: it was too great a Wrong Ev'n to suspect my Virtue; but to explain Your guilty Thoughts, is such a Privilege Your high Place only gives you: and from this I fear a future Tyranny. Cleom. Away! My Thoughts, my every Word, my Actions, Are Slaves to the Obedience of thy Will, Nor can assume a Privilege from Pow'r Of violating thee: but Want will speak, And all my Want is Love. Thel. Call it not Love; Coming from you, it has another Name, Too horrid for the Ear. Were I that Wretch; Were ev'ry Light extinguish'd in the Mind, Which brightens Virtue, and shews Vice most foul; Were I forsaken of all Sense of Good, Abandon'd, and led captive to all Ill: One, whose experienc'd Wickedness cou'd prove Adultery no Sin: yet, ev'n there, Among the common Rout, you cou'd not hope: Tho' I were fear'd against all other Sins, Incest wou'd make me tremble: Sure it is On this Side Hell known only in the Name: A Reprobate so lost; there cannot be So damn'd a Reprobate to act it, sure! Cleom. Why, Madam, do you think I cou'd proceed Thus far, upon this Subject, without Thought, A serious judging Sense of Good and Ill? I have a Soul like you, a Conscience too, That apprehends the Terror of such Guilt; With Fears as nice as yours; and, but I know My loving you cannot be any Crime.— Thel. I have a Refuge yet, a Dagger here. [Aside. Cleom. Brother, and Sister, are but Terms of Art, Occasionally fashion'd to the Ends Of Government; as Marriage is no more Than a mere human Obligation; Of no more Force than is ordain'd by Pow'r; Which, as it ties the Knot, unties it too: And I ordain it shall no longer bind. Thel. O! Sir, consider.— Cleom. All that you can say, I have consider'd. I have curs'd my Fate, But how does that avail me? Curs'd my self, And the repented Rashness of my Youth, Whose unadvising Folly gave me to Your Sister's Bed, now surfeited and loath'd. Thel. Can you repent your Marriage? Cleom. Curses can't mend my Condition; yet I must curse Eurytion, all the World, that comes between Me and my Joys in thee. But this is wild, Quite from my Purpose, idly losing Time, Whose precious Minutes, as they pass along, May bring me Comforts: O! there can be none, But in thy Arms; there I must find my Joys, Or never find 'em.— [He pressing her, she draws a Dagger. Thel. Find 'em in the Grave. Cleom. A Dagger! arm'd against me! Thel. Stir not a Step: I wear it for my self, If you attempt me farther. Cleom. Have a Care; You wonnot wound yourself? Thel. A Thousand Wounds This, as the Guard of Virtue, shall bestow, Rather than leave me to your brutal Will, The Murder of my Fame. Cleom. This wonnot do: I must try other Means. [Aside. Thel. I know I'm within your Pow'r, expos'd to your wild Rage: But Death's a Sanctuary from all Wrongs, And that I can command. Cleom. O! only die The guilty Memory of what is past, My Sin, and now my Shame. Thel. Can you say so, and not repent? Cleom. But you cannot forgive: I can't forgive myself: I've done those Things Which Pardon cannot reach. Thel. If this be true— Cleom. I cannot look upon that injur'd Face— Now to dissemble well—without a Guilt, That quite confounds me. Thel. May the Gods, whom you Have injur'd most, forgive you. Cleom. I have wrong'd you. Thel. I freely pardon you. Cleom. How have I slept! your Virtue only cou'd Restore me to myself: I tremble, now, At the Apprehension of my Wickedness, Of monst'rous Size, and fearful to conceive. But my Repentance sets all right again. Sister, Farewel—this Victory is yours. [Leads her to the Door The next be mine, these Measures but begin, What Love by Stratagem, or Force, must win. [Exit The End of the Second ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Act III. Scene I. Agesilaus and Crites. Ages. That Way I have my Wish; but Celona! she Confounds my Policy: What can she mean? Crit. What can she mean? Why she speaks plain enough. Ages. I apprehend the fatal Consequence, Tho' the King won't. Crit. Alas, Sir, he's employ'd In other Fears: Love takes up all his Time: But the sole Ministry of his Affairs, The State, you rule. Ages. And I had fix'd it sure, Had not my Ambush for Leonidas been disappointed. Crit. I should think, indeed, his Death were well resolv'd. Ages. I have advis'd it often, but the King— Crit. Dont trouble him. When 'tis once done, he'll find that 'tis well done. Ages. 'Tis certainly most necessary. Crit. If it be necessary, it is just; And in just Things, sometimes to serve a Prince Against his Will, is the best Loyalty. Ages. Then 'tis our Duty, Crites? Crit. Without Doubt; And more than so, our own Security. Ages. What's to be done? There's nothing to be done Or thought on, where he is—cou'd we decoy Him here to Sparta— Crit. That's impossible. Ages. But how? What Means? What Arts? Crit. O! there are none. Ages. Then think not on't: He must live on, if tis impossible To bring him in our Pow'r. Crit. Not quite impossible, But very difficult. Ages. Suppose you, you, methinks, might quickly find Pretences probable in his Affair, to draw him here. Crit. What, Sir, if he were here? Ages. Here he shou'd stay, Murder'd as soon as enter'd. Crit. Here's a Letter Will speak what I have thought upon these Things. Ages. 'Tis to Leonidas. Crit. Pray read it. SIR, The Gods declare upon your Side, in their Inspiration of Celona, whose Virtue, confirm'd by me, has this Night resolv'd the Murder of the Tyrant. Pray fail not to head your Friends, who will be ready to serve you. Crites. Ages. This cannot fail: Her Carriage makes all easy to his Faith: He will believe, and come. Crit. Come! he will come: Not for those Reasons, which you apprehend, And might invite another. Ages. I cannot guess what you rely on— Crit. This. I know the Niceness of his Virtue such, That when the Letter tells him that his Daughter Intends her Husband's Murder, he will fly, To save her from the Sin. Ages. He may resolve To pardon her, and so not make such Haste. Crit. O! You are wide of him: Not this Earth's Rule Cou'd bribe him to consent to such a Crime, Tho' far remov'd, and distant from his Blood; But when so near him as a Daughter's Sin, You need not doubt his Coming. Ages. Have you said when he shou'd come? Crit. The Postscript says at Twelve. Ages. It does, and it appoints your House the Place: It is the fittest Place. Crit. I'm unsuspected: Give me but your Authority, and some Convenient Villains, who dare do the Deed, And he shall fall as soon as enter there. Ages. This Letter must be sent. Crit. Timæus will convey it speedily— He waits without— [Goes to the Door, Timæus takes the Letter.] Ages. So, this will make all sure. Crit. Fail not upon your Life. Tim. My Life upon't. [Exit. Crit. I've order'd him to stay, just 'till he sees Leonidas set forward, then to come With his best Speed, and bring me certain Word. Ages. You must attend— Crit. Only a Love Affair, Which happens luckily enough, and shall To-Night employ the King. Ages. That will allow Us Time for our Designs: I'm glad it thrives. Crit. O! all goes very well. Ages. He's coming forth: When you're at Leisure, I must speak with you. [Exit. Cleombrotus to Crites. Cleom. Thou art the Life of Counsel! It must be just as thou say'st. Crit. Indeed, I think it best. Cleom. Undoubtedly the best: And I must own Myself ith' Wrong, as Passion always is, So like a mad brain'd Boy, to think of Force. Crit. I must confess, a violent Remedy In some despairing Points does very well; When nothing else will do, 'tis well apply'd, And then a Rape is necessary. But Your Case is far from this: She's in your Pow'r, And cannot 'scape you: Nay, I say agen, She shannot, Sir; and when I thus declare, You shall enjoy her any Way you please, You wou'd not chuse a Violation. Cleom. Thou art my Guide of Love. Crit. This Way, that I propose, Shall introduce you for Eurytion, Give you a free Admission to her Bed, Which you may satisfy as well as he. Cleom. Then for his Care in coming unattended, in the Dark— Crit. Unknown of all but me, his faithful Friend. Cleom. Makes still for us. Crit. All Things must be remov'd, And silent to receive you. Cleom. If she discover me— Crit. Why, if she does— Cleom. Wou'd it were come to that. Crit. Sir, it shall come. Cleom. I am impatient. Crit. 'Tis too early, yet, and you must wait; there is no Remedy. Cleom. Then I must wait. Crit. The Hour will soon arrive. Cleom. Crites, withdraw with me—We must be nice In every Circumstance of Place, and Time: Those we'll agree within—This Service done, My Thanks in thy Reward shall follow soon. [Exeunt. SCENE II. A Bed-chamber. Thelamia and Byzanthe. Thel. I pity thee, Byzanthe; thy Gayety Has caught the Infection of my Company, And thou art melancholy too. Byz. I wish I cou'd divert you, Madam. Thel. I thank thy Love, my Friend; 'tis growing late; Yet, e'er I go to Bed, I'll try to read An Hour away; it may deceive the Time. Byz. Please you, I'll stay and wait. Thel. —O! by no means: I am too troublesome, but thou art kind. [Exit Byzanthe. Thelamia sits down at a Table, and opens a Book. Here I gave o'er—The Story seems distress'd: How will it end! (Reads) Tarquinius Sextus then, Pretending on a Journey, late at Night Came to Collatia, where Lucrece was; And breaking thro' all hospitable Laws, At Midnight ravish'd her—O Villainy! And most unhappy Lady! Collotine! Where was her Husband then?— Reads again— What do I read! a little farther on, My Author, in his Comment on the Fact, Says, 'twas her Husband's Absence ruin'd her. O fearful Apprehension! This is just The State of my Condition—The sad Tale May ominously represent my Fate In wrong'd Lucretia—I am helpless now, As she was then—My Husband absent too, As hers then was—nay, he has already dar'd To force the Modesty of my chaste Ears With the bold brutal Passion of his Love: And after that—But I have forgiv'n him that, And he repents—O! it is false and feign'd, Dissembled, to betray my Faith and me: Love never is repented, 'till enjoy'd— And he, perhaps, this Night, nay, now, resolves. He may be here already—Hark! Who's there? I dare not stay alone—Byzanthe! where, Where are you? Enter Byzanthe. Byz. You're disorder'd much. Thel. There's something in my Closet. [Byzanthe takes a Light, and examines. Byz. Nothing here. Thel. Pray, look again. Byz. Only your Fancy, Madam. Thel. I thought I heard a Noise. Byz. Nothing has stirr'd, Within your Hearing, since I left you last. Thel. Where is your Husband? Byz. Gone in some Affair relating to Eurytion. Thel. O! he is a faithful honest Friend, wou'd he were here; All our good Fortune does depend on him. Byz. I think I hear him, Madam— Thel. Welcome, welcome. Enter Crites. Crit. What, Madam, you have Leisure for a Book. Thel. O! Crites, I have met the saddest Tale, The Rape of Lucrece there— Crit. 'Tis famous in The Roman Story; Tarquin ravish'd her. Thel. The Circumstances are so near my Case— Crit. So near your Case! Thel. In all but the sad End. Crit. What can she mean! [Aside. Thel. Her Husband was from Home, As mine is now, the wretched Cause of all. Crit. Sure she suspects my Purpose. [Aside. Thel. When I think upon that Midnight Ravisher, I reflect Upon our Sex's Weakness, thus expos'd, How easily we are betray'd, or sold, by any one in Trust. Crit. There cannot be such Villainy in Men. Thel. There shou'd not, sure: Indeed, I was afraid; But now I think myself securely safe In thy kind Care. Crit. I'm glad you think you are. Byz. Have you no News for us? Crit. Faith, I have been In such a Conversation, scarce will please In Repetition—Marriage was the Theme, And my Companions its worst Enemies; They forc'd me to my Heels. Thel. What cou'd they say? Byz. No Matter what they say. Crit. By your good Leave, These Men will be our Judges—We must stand The Inquisition of their Raillery On our Condition—As, to speak the Truth, Nothing can 'scape their Jest: The Gods and Kings, Manners and Men, Laws human and divine, Must stand, or fall, just as they relish 'em. We must not think it hard. Thel. What do they say? Byz. We need not doubt but Marriage has its Load Of Scandal in the Lewdness of their Mirth. Crit. Why, first, they swear the Institution Was never made in Heav'n Thel. That strikes Home. Crit. That the malicious Roguery of Age, Impos'd it first, a Penance on the Pride Of lusty Youth, to keep their Bodies low, Dull, constant Slaves to one tir'd fulsom Bed. Byz. A Penance do they call it? Thel. Pray, Sir, on. Crit. That Love was ne'er consulted in the Law; But that it stands enacted, and ordain'd To these our Days, that only Interest Of Fortune, or of Friends, should join our Hands, No matter for our Hearts. Thel. Wicked and Base! Crit. Nay, when they once set out, they will go on. Byz. They have gone far enough. Thel. I'll hear no more. Crit. Faith, Madam, you may hear a little more, And not repent your Pains. Thel. How is the Night? Crit. Why there's a Question now that brings me Home Just to my Story's End. Thel. That Question! Why? Crit. 'Tis just about the Time. Thel. What Time? Perhaps you have some Tidings of my Lord. Crit. I have indeed. Thel. When will he come: I languish in the Thought Of his Approach: O! Why art thou so long In News so welcome? Prithee, tell me all; Say any Thing of him, that he is well; Say that he comes. Crit. If you would let me speak. Thel. 'Tis that I would entreat. Crit. Then he will come In half an Hour, so he sends me Word. You know his Pleasure is, his Coming shou'd Be private, his own Servants not employ'd. Thel. O! I obey in all. But how cou'dst thou So long delay the Comfort of thy News? But I forgive thee. Crit. Madam, I must wait Upon his Coming; you prepare for him, And I'll convey him to you [Exit. Thel. Byzanthe, I must require your Friendship: Pray dispose The Business of the Family, as you please, Out of the Way; I wou'd have all remov'd; He will observe our Care. Byz. Leave that to me. Thel. Whilst I prepare to entertain this Guest, Lodge him in his own Mansion of my Breast, And make him happy, as he makes me blest. [Exeunt. Scene changes to a Street. Crites alone. Crit. Thus far with Wind and Tide! Things are dispos'd Just to my Wish to carry on the Cheat. Where is my Lover now? 'Tis just his Time— He can't be far—I had forgot the Sign— Not answer me? Nay, then he is not come— Well, our Employment must have Patience. Enter Eurytion. Eury. What Sign was that? Crit. O! You are punctual, Sir. Eury. Rather before my Time. Crit. Eurytion here! [Aside. Indeed, my Lord, something before your Time: I did not look for you. Eury. How am I punctual then? Crit. Punctual, my Lord? Eury. Did you expect another? Crit. Yes, indeed, I did expect another, a good Friend, Not such a Friend: I have my Scouts abroad, And must be ready for 'em; yet you come As I cou'd wish, to warn you: Dangers, Sir, Are every where: This is no Place, retire, You may be seen. Eury. I'll follow thy Advice. Crit. Go not in there. Eury. My Safety must be here. [Exit. Crit. What shall I do? Death! Something must be done. [Exit. Cleombrotus enters. Cleom. The Servants still are stirring in the House; I heard 'em talk: I'll take another Turn. [Exit. Crites returns with Eurytion. Crit. This House, you may be sure, Sir, wonnot 'scape The strictest Search— Eury. Not if so general. Crit. Nor will be less suspected, being Yours. Eury. Much more suspected. Crites. But that Sign! What cou'd it mean? So late about my Doors, Just as I came to thee? Crit. I heard it too. Wou'd you were Safe. Eury. Well, Crites, I am gone. Crit. The King will soon be there. Eury. You'll follow me. [Exit. Crit. When I've secur'd all here— Unseasonable Husband! Fare thee well. Why! what a 'Scape was this? At the same Time, The very Place, so unexpectedly, And just upon my Summons of another! But he's remov'd—if he had seen his Wife, 'T had been impossible. That lucky Lye Has sent him to my House, to wait the King Leonidas—at Twelve I may expect him: 'Tis near Eleven now. Cleombrotus Won'not delay me long: For when he comes, My Office only guides him to the Door, And then to make all sure; I have prepar'd A hearty Welcome for the good old King. Enter Timæus. Tim. The good old King! Crit. Timæus, by thy Voice. Thou'rt come before thy Time. Tim. I come by your Command. Crit. I said at Twelve. Tim. You said that I should stay till he set forward. Crit. Is he coming then? Tim. I saw him mounted. Crit. How attended? Tim. Almost, Sir, alone. Crit. He must be near. Tim. He cannot be far off. Eurytion, Sir, already is arriv'd. Crit. Wait for me at my House. I'll follow thee. [Timæus Exit. This is unlucky—there's no pausing now. Thinking but loses Time: I must be gone. Love must attend the Leisure of the State: A single Fortune, this a Nation's Fate. [Going out, meets Cleombrotus. Cleom. Who's this. Crit. Cleombrotus! Cleom. Crites, I think. Crit. Still worse and worse [Aside. Cleom. Thou wert in Haste. Crit. Imagine, Sir, the Cause. [Going. Cleom. I know the Cause: I staid beyond my Time, and thou wert going To find me out, but I have spar'd thy Pains. This is the Door: Now, my Thelamia! What! Thou art uneasy still. Crit. I beg you wou'd Believe, that nothing, but a Certainty Of my best Service to you, cou'd perswade me To leave you now. Cleom. How? Crites! At this Time! and call it Service? Crit. Nay, my Duty, Sir. Cleom. No going, Man; thy Duty now lies here. Crit. To Morrow will convince you. Cleom. Thou art mad. Am I not at the Entrance of my Joys? Invited by thy own Appointment too? Crit. But Accidents— Cleom. There are in Fortune none: I conquer her in my Thelamia. Crit. To Morrow she shall be with Safety Yours. Cleom. I wonnot trust to Morrow: Now is mine. Crit. This will undo us all. [Aside. Cleom. No Words, but on. Crit. Let me but speak— Cleom. I will have no Excuse; show me the Way. Crit. Hear but my Reasons first— Cleom. Forward I say: Consider who I am. Crit. My royal Master. Cleom. Then thy King commands. Crit. I must be heard, and then— Cleom. Is this a Time, Thou sawcy Trifler, for Argument? [The two following Speeches are spoke together. Crit. This is the Time, or I must never speak— I wou'd conceal it from you, but there is Now a Necessity of telling you,— Your Life, your Crown; your Empire are at Stake: Leonidas, the banish'd King is now Within your Pow'r—If you wou'd save us all, This is your Time; an Opportunity Like this—you cannot hope— Cleom. When Expectation rages in my Blood, And shoots a thousand Fevers thro' my Veins?— Is this a Time, thou Prater!—hence, be gone;— Still he goes on, and louder in his Words!— Not let me speak! This is an Insolence, That never yet was offer'd to a King, And shou'd be answer'd by a Dagger, thus. [As Cleombrotus offers to stab him, Crites stops, and bows Cleom. Impudent Slave! Open thy Lips again Upon this Subject, this shall lock 'em fast, As close and silent as the Jaws of Death. Forward, and introduce me to her Arms, And on thy Life stir not till my Return. [Exeunt. Scene changes to Celona's Apartment. Celona, Servant, and Leonidas. Celo. One in Disguise! Some from Leonidas. Admit him: Leave the Room—'tis he himself! Thus on my Knees, thus let me thank the Gods, Who let me see you once again in Sparta. Leon. Celona, rise; the Posture is too humble, And misbecomes that haughty Excellence, Which knows to form new Virtue, and wou'd shine A Pattern to the uninstructed World. Celo. Indeed my Fate with intricate Misfortune Has compass'd round my Virtue. Wife and Daughter! Each different Duty shows a Precipice, Where-e'er I turn my Eyes: But yet my Honour, That steddily wou'd tread the narrow Path, Looks with Contempt upon the pageant Greatness, And most inclines where there is most Misfortune. Leon. It may incline too much. Celo. Too much it cannot. You seem'd, and yet I wou'd not think you did, You seem'd to tax the Conduct of my Virtue. But yet that Power, who places such as me In labouring Mazes of an anxious Fate, Who damps the Joys of all our present Hours, And pays us with the Promise of a Name, Shall see that I submit to his Decrees, (If I am mark'd for glorious Wretchedness) To shine the Pattern of a Spartan Daughter. Leon. That Fame's too narrow for a Spartan Princess, Celona too shou'd be a Spartan Wife. Celo. Have I offended then? Leon. Offended! O! Thou in a Moment wou'dst deface those Trophies, Which my laborious Ancestors, thro' Ages, Toyling for Fame, had pil'd up, Legacies To their succeeding Sons. Celo. High let 'em stand, Admir'd Examples to less generous Man, 'Till I by any Act disclaim their Blood. Leon. When Guilt is in its Blush of Infancy, It trembles in a Tenderness of Shame, And the first Eye that pierces thro' the Veil, That hides the Secret, brings it to the Face: But thine amazes me, and seems confirm'd, Beyond Confusion bold, and dares the Light, And the reproaching Horror of thy Father. Celo. Cleombrotus would speak more tenderly, And treat my Virtue, tho' his Enemy, In a more gentle Way. Leon. O! all you Ghosts! You injur'd Spirits of my Ancestors! Forbear a while to fire your tortur'd Son. By all your Acts, which form'd my Youth to Honour, You trust your Glory safely in my Hands; Nor shall my Loyns defile your sacred Blood: Give me but so much Respite in my Fury, To justify the Rage of my Revenge, To the Remains of Father in my Heart. First, she shall triumph in her Crime, and show A harden'd Soul, beyond forgiving damn'd, And take her then, she falls your Sacrifice. Celo. What dismal Resolution shakes you thus? When I believe I understand your Words, Some sudden Start, that contradicts my Thoughts, Throws me in wild Amazement. Leon. Ay, my Child! I will amaze thee, when I let thee know The tenderest Instance of a Father's Love: For I have sav'd thy generous Hand the Blow, A dangerous Task, and done the Work alone. Celo. Alas! What Work! What Blow! Leon. The giddy World, Unequal Judges of exalted Honour, Perhaps had blam'd thy Zeal: But now 'tis past: Nor shall thy Fame be trusted to the Crowd: Yet thou shalt triumph too: Thine was the Act, My Arm inspir'd by thee. Celo. What can you mean? Leon. Canst thou not guess? Celo. You more amaze me, Sir. Leon. I tell thee then, my Heroine! This Night, Pretending Secrets, and Intelligence, I gain'd Admission to Cleombrotus; Alone I found him, you may think the News— Celo. Wou'd I were past all Thought. [Aside. Leon. I sent this Steel with Tidings to his Heart. Nor parted thence, 'till with repeated Woulds I left the unpanting Villain on the Earth. Celo. And this must be my Triumph! Heav'n and Hell Are reconcil'd, and join contending Pow'rs To make my Ruin infamously sure. I strove to aid my King, and save my Lord, Yet now am call'd his Murderer, you Gods! And bid to triumph in my Husband's Blood. Leon. You seem disturb'd. Celo. Was it for this, you Pow'rs! I strove to keep the temperate Balance just, Between my different Duties? 'Twas too much: And you reserve those Heights of Excellence To your unrival'd Heaven: I shou'd have been Only a Wife, or Daughter: For you dash, With Jealousy, attempting Virtue down, That dares beyond your Limits to their Flesh. Leon. I thought you would have prais'd me. Celo. O, my Lord, I must not curse you. Leon. What! For an Act you wou'd have done yourself? Celo. I wou'd have done! Murder my Husband, Sir? Leon. This very Night you had design'd his Death: I know it all. Celo. And I too much: But cou'd you think me such: A Monster, Sir? But, Oh! I find you do. Leon. Why! Did he not deserve his Fate? Celo. O, Sir! I grant he has deserv'd from Heav'n, and you, And all good Men, worse than you can inflict: I have arraign'd and sentenc'd his Deserts: And I must think the Gods but justify'd, You honourably reveng'd, and good Mens Pray'rs But justly answer'd in a Tyrant's Fall: All this I think with you, and you were wrong'd: But how was I? How has he injur'd me, To make me capable of such a Sin, Barbarous, and yet without a Name in Hell, As you imagine, Sir, I had design'd? Is't not enough that I abhor his Crimes, But I must be his Murderer? If the Gods, And you, to clear my Fame, will have it so. If I must strike at him, it must be here— [Offers to stab herself. Leon. O Virtue! never to be found again! Thy Husband lives. Cleombrotus still lives. Forbear a Violence, that in thy Breast Wou'd wound me deeper than thy Ponyard there. I did but try thee: And in these Extreams I find thee still sincere to all my Hopes, Fixt to thy Virtue and thy Country's Fame, Thy Sexes Glory, and my Daughter still, A Spartan Daughter, and a Spartan Wife. Celo. Those Titles raise me. Leon. I have been abus'd, And thou art innocent: This Letter read At Leisure: Crites knows what it designs, He sent it, and I must suspect it now. O guard, you Gods of Greece! my faithful Friends From the destroying Arm of Treachery: Blunt the sharp Arrows which in Darkness fly: Disclose the Midnight Arts, and break the Snares Which fair fac'd Villany's false Heart prepares. If in the Courts above it be decreed A Sacrifice to Sparta's Peace should bleed, On me, great Jupiter, on me alone Hurl the collected Storm of Thunder down. Bur in your Anger, from your threatning Sky Regard me, cloath'd in decent Majesty, Submissive to your Will, and resolute to die. [Exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Act IV. Scene I. Enter Cleombrotus. Cleom. Thus far I'm undiscover'd. O frail Flesh! And Vanity of Fancy! My Desires, Which mounted me above my mortal State, Whose Rage, I thought, nothing but Age could tame, How have they droopt the Wing? How are they sunk Into the poor Concerns of Earth again? Now, Crites, I can hear thee. Sure there is Something extraordinary, as his Carriage was: He does not use to contradict me: And, If I remember right, I heard him speak Something abruptly of Leonidas. There may be Danger near: I must be gone: Thelamia takes me for her Husband still: I wonnot undeceive her, that may serve To morrow Night, and I can stay till then— Thelamia enters with a Light. A Light! She follows me. Thel. O! Do not find A Trouble in my Love, which thus attends In Duty now: Speak, and assure my Fears, You are not angry with me: O my Lord! I can forgive your stealing from my Bed, Your Silence there, but not this Silence now. What! Turn away! Nay, going from me too! That must not be: This Hand, my Lord, is mine, Nor can I part with it without a Look— [He turns to her, she drops his Hand, shows her Surprize, by standing stupidly still a while without speaking; he offering to speak, she snatches at his Sword, draws it half out; failing in that, she throws herself into a Chair, in the most violent Passion of Grief. Thel. The Gods refuse me their Assistance too. Here let me fall forgotten. Cleom. Let me raise you. Thel. Touch me not, Monster, thou hast sunk me down, And can'st not raise me— Cleom. To my Bed and Throne. Thel. Dishonour fill thy Bed, and Death thy Throne. Cleom. That's an unkind Return. Thel. Art thou not gone? Thou hast accomplish'd The fatal Ends of thy Design on me; What wou'dst thou more? Cleom. I wou'd bring Comfort to you. Thel. O thou Destroyer! Fly, fly from my Eyes: The sad Remains of my poor wretched Life I wou'd employ in Sorrow for my Fate, In Penitence, and Mercy to the World: But while thou stand'st in View, I cannot weep: My Eyes refuse the Comfort of their Tears To my Misfortunes: All their Moisture feeds The Passion in my Heart, which only can Be eas'd by Curses on thee. Cleom. Do not curse: Or if you must, think where you shou'd begin. Thel. O! where begin, indeed! All, all deserve Alike from me, the Gods and Fate, Crites and thou. Cleom. The Gods, for making you thus heavenly fair, And I, for loving you. Thel. Both have been my Curse. Cleom. Crites and Fate were but my Instruments; Those you have curs'd in me. Thel. That Crites! O! How was he trusted! how has he betray'd! But I myself am guilty of my Fall, By a fond, fatal Ignorance abus'd, And made th'Accomplice of my Ruin too. Cleom. That fatal Ignorance, then, is your Excuse. Thel. O! there is none in Nature, no Excuse For Crimes like mine: My Sister's Husband's—Oh! Cleom. Be patient, Madam, there's your Remedy, You have no other now. Thel. Yes, there is one Revenge that wonnot fail me—While I live, I must solicit that of Gods and Men; And Earth or Heav'n will do me Justice, sure. Cleom. I'll do you the best Justice; he advis'd, And hear me calmly—What is done, is past, Without your Crime: If it be any Crime, 'Tis so in me: But then 'tis such a Crime, The Purchase of my Peace, and so belov'd, I never can repent. Thel. O hardned Wretch! Cleom. 'Tis yet a Secret: While you keep it so, Your Husband is not wrong'd; or, if he be, He, who has done it; can maintain the Wrong: And then where's your Revenge! Thel. Art thou secure In Wickedness? That Fool's Security Shall be thy Ruin? When I have proclaim'd To all the World, as, while I have Life, I will Proclaim my Wrongs— Cleom. Your Shame, your Infamy: The World will call it so: And then you make A Monster of your Husband. Thel. O! Revenge, Revenge! thus, raving thro' the Streets, I'll cry for Vengeance on thee: All good Men, Fathers, and Husbands, Brothers, Spartan born, In the Defence and Cause of Chastity, Will arm to save their Daughters, Sisters, Wives, From my Dishonour in thy Tyranny; And, forwarding the Justice of the Gods, Will rise against thy execrable Deeds, Level their Thunder at thy Life and Crown, O'erturn thy Throne, and end thee in thy Crimes. Cleom. 'Tis possible your Story may do Harm, And therefore I'll prevent it. Thel. Only Death shall silence it. Cleom. Death silences at last. You see the Fortune of your present State, That 'tis not to be mended by Complaints, Yet you complain, and vow to be reveng'd. If you continue obstinate, resolv'd Not to be pacify'd, 'tis a hard Course, But Nature does oblige me to provide For my own Safety, and that is best secur'd By your Eurytion's Death. Thel. His Death! Cleom. I have vow'd his Death. Thel. What is his Crime? I do deserve to die. Cleom. 'Tis Crime enough to be your Husband now. I know his Disaffection only wants A Cause, like this, to animate the Crowd, And his Designs against my Reign, and me: But that he shannot have: Out of a Sense And Tenderness of you thus far I have Withheld my Justice, which now you enforce: Therefore resolve either to pardon me, Or doom Eurytion dead. Crites, you know, Can bring him in my Power: This is your Choice: Think well upon't, I will walk by awhile. Thel. Alas! what Choice! I have no Choice to make: My Ruin's certain: But Eurytion! Can I resolve his Death? he has been wrong'd Too much already: O! I never can Resolve his Death—there is no other Way— Let me dissemble for a Husband's Life, In such a Cause, in hopes of a Revenge. Cleom. I wait your Answer, Madam, if you have Consider'd well, I know you will forgive. Thel. If I should not, it will avail me little. Cleom. Little indeed avail. Thel. Then my Revenge, That will involve us all in other Crimes. Cleom. In Blood, and Murder: There must be the End. Thel. O fearful Sounds! I would not be the Cause Of Murder for this Earth. Cleom. Then no Revenge. Thel. Then no Revenge indeed. But O! my Shame, My Infamy! Cleom. That I'll secure you from: And I can keep a Secret, when engag'd By my own Interest; that's the certain Charm Upon Mens Tongues: So you are sure of Mine. Thel. I wish I could believe. Cleom. I wish you could: But to engage me deeper in my Trust, I swear— Thel. By what? Cleom. I would by this fair Hand. Thel. Well, well, I must believe you. Cleom. May I hope you have forgiven me? Thel. Hope is in your Power. Cleom. Say but you have. Thel. Not to say otherwise, is far enough at first. Cleom. You mean it then? Thel. You may interpret for me. Cleom. Then I say, you have, or shou'd forgive me. Thel. You may find my Meaning out hereafter: For this time I wou'd be private. Cleom. You will not say farewel? Thel. To be alone. Cleom. Then bid me go— Thel. Farewel. Cleom. That Farewel bids me stay: but I must go. [exit.] Thel. O! what a Part am I condemn'd to act, To save my Husband's Life! my Husband! Oh! I have no Husband: This foul Ravisher, This Villain, Tyrant, Author of all Ills, Divorces me for ever from my Lord: Has rob'd me of the Honour of a Wife: Nor am I worthy of that Title now, Or any Name, but—Oh! let me here Bury that Name, and all my Miseries: Sink down beneath the Burden of my Woes, Into my Grave, unmention'd, and unmourn'd, Ne'er be remembred in my Story more, To the Dishonour of my royal House, Or Shame of virtuous Wives. Celona and Byzanthe to her. Byz. What do I hear? Celo. Amazement of my Senses! can this be Thelamia on the Earth! these Sorrows hers! Byz. She minds you not. Celo. O! 'tis Celona speaks, thy tender, loving Sister. Byz. See, that Name raises her Head a little. Celo. Now thy Tears Flow faster than before. O you good Gods! Instruct me to redress, or comfort her. Nay, I intreat thee, do not smother thus Thy Griefs with Groans, but give thy Passion Words: They will unload the Burden of thy Heart, If they do nothing more: Byzanthe, help, Help me to raise her. Thel. O! you misemploy Your Charity on a Wretch, whom all the Gods Concurring in their Blessings, with your Means To bring me comfort, never can restore To Happiness. Celo. O you malicious Stars! I thought my Fortunes might have satisfied For our whole Family: You show'd your Pow'r Enough in me: You might have spar'd her Peace: But now where will you end? O! Sister, say, Speak to me, tell me, can there be a Cause Of this Distress? Thel. There is a wretched Cause: Believe it such, and seek to know no more. Celo. I'll help you to support— Thel. The Load will sink us both. Celo. Then we shall fall together. Come, the Cause? I have a Sister's Title, and a Friend's, That wonnot be deny'd—nay, no more Tears, But tell me. Thel. I can't speak— Celo. Away. Thel. To any but a Sister. Celo. Pray withdraw. [Byzanthe goes out] Now tell your Griefs, none but a Sister hears. Thel. And now I dare not: Oh! enquire no more: Tho' 'tis most fit my Griefs shou'd be reveal'd, 'Tis most unfit they be reveal'd to you. Celo. If they relate to me, I am prepar'd, Give 'em a Tongue. Thel. You'll curse it, when it speaks—Cleombrotus— Celo. My Husband? Thel. Monster of Men. Celo. Indeed his Practices have well deserv'd To be thus treated: But, Thelamia, I Have not deserv'd to hear you call him so. If he has made you wretched, I am made Unhappy too: If in a Husband's loss, I've lost him too: Equal in all your Griefs. Thel. O! yet there is a Grief beyond all these! A Loss, beyond my Father, Husband, Life: You wonnot understand— Celo. The Gods protect the Honour of our House. Thel. 'Tis faln in me: I am abus'd, dishonour'd, and undone! Celo. O! for a Thunder-bolt, the Arm of Jove To execute the Vengeance of my Heart Upon the Ravisher. Thel. Cleombrotus. Celo. Again Cleombrotus! O! have a care, This is a Subject, that concerns my Peace, Near as my Father's Cause: Therefore no more. I know thou hast been wrong'd, I see it plain: The Marks of Ruin blush upon thee still: And thy great Griefs perhaps have turn'd thy Brain: It must be so: For thou art mad indeed, To say Cleombrotus cou'd use thee thus. Thel. This only cou'd remain to make me yet More miserable: If my Injuries Be of that monstrous Growth above Belief, How shall I bear 'em? But they sink me down, And this must ease me. [Going to stab herself.] Celo. O! Sister, hold! Thel. I said before, you were Unfit to hear the Secret of my Fate: Yet you would hear, and wonnot now believe. Celo. Wou'd I cou'd not believe: but Oh! I find A Fear in every Thought, that makes me shake, In Apprehension of the fatal Truth: And now each trifling Circumstance appears In Evidence against him: O! 'tis plain: I had forgot I met him at the Door, Just as I enter'd here: There needs no Proof. Monster of Men indeed! and Tyrant now! Here I confess the Weakness of my Sex, Defenceless quite against a Stroak like this: And my full Heart can only speak in Tears. Leonidas enters to 'em. Leon. My Children weeping both! This is a Sight will make me old indeed. Speak one of you, inform me of the Cause: Celona, Oh! it must be bad indeed That thus can conquer thee. Thelamia, thou Art going: O! I dare not bid thee stay, Nor ask the Reason of thy parting thus: But thy Disorder and Confusion show Thee most concern'd. [Exit. Thelamia.] Celo. There is no saying who Is most concern'd: If I may judge the Cause, I'm injur'd most, tho' 'tis a Wrong to all; Nay, Sir, be you the Judge, but Age can't know The Pangs of slighted Love; therefore no Judge Of my Condition. O! to be despis'd! Is such a Thought! it strangles Patience. Leon. Why this is Madness, Child. Celo. What! at my Years forsaken! had I been Ugly or old, mismatcht to my Desires, My natural Defects had taught me then, In a tame Expectation of my Fate, To sat me down contented: But to be Thrown off, abandon'd, for a Sister too! O monstrous Love indeed! that such a Sin, As Incest could not tame. Leon. What say'st thou? ha! Celo. Thus violated, forc'd, and thus abus'd, She stands acquitted to the judging World, And Death, or a Revenge, redeems her Fame. But I must stand the Shot of every Tongue, The Censure and the Jest of laughing Fools: Be pointed at for the forsaken thing, Forsaken for a Sister! Leon. Yet again thy Sister! speak. Celo. O! yes, while I can speak. Leon. Thelamia forc'd! Celo. Forc'd by Cleombrotus. Leon. Incestuous Tyrant! Plagues of every kind, Long studied, and stor'd up by Wrath divine, For the Revenge, and Fate of such bad Men, Fall thick upon his Head: But O! he sins Beyond my Curses now, and only Hell, All Hell can do him Justice—Had the Gods Thought fit to exercise my Patience, Stript me of all the Comforts of this Life, My Friends, my Hopes, ev'n to my very self— But here my Age gives way, here I must own The Frailty of a Man surpriz'd, unarm'd, Unguarded, naked to this stunning Blow, That drives me to the Earth a weak old Man. Celo. O Misery on Misery! Leon. Away! Tears are thy Sexes Comforts, I must find Mine in Revenge. Celo. Revenge! Leon. Revenge for thee. Thy Sister, and us all. O! I have been Assisting to this Ruine: Had my Ears Been open to the Counsels of my Friends, This might have been undone. but it is done, And now must be reveng'd? Celo. O! Sir, forbear a while. Leon. No time so fit for my Designs. Celo. But hear me. Leon. Passion has no Ears. Or if I did, Words cannot alter me. [Exit.] Celo. Alas! my Woman's Weakness has undone All that my Virtue had so long preserv'd; Now I too late perceive the Consequence: How fatal this Discovery must be To my Cleombrotus! for he is mine, My Husband still, however base and false. Tho' I am wrong'd in the most tender Part, Most sensible of Pain, I am his Wife; That is the Character I must maintain: But to preserve it—something I must do, But what, or how, the Gods yet only know. [Exit.] She goes out, Crites passing over the Stage. Crit. All that I could of Moment I have learnt; But when the Husband follows at my Heels, 'Tis time to vanish: I have done my do At Chamber-practice, and must shift the Scene. He goes out, Eurytion enters. Eury. I meet with nothing but Distraction Thro' all the House; my Servants fly the Room Still as I enter it, as each were loth To be the first in some unwelcome News: Ev'n Crites shuns me too; something there is— I wonnot think the worst: Heav'n guard the King, And my Thelamia: if either be concern'd, 'Twill be too soon to know, when I must know; Till then I would not guess: But here's the King, And half my Fears are vain. Leonidas enters. Leon. The other half? who is your Fear? Eury. O! you may guess, my Wife. Leon. This is no time for Wives. Eury. No time, indeed, if your Employment call me. Leon. Then no time; For I have Business for thee. Eury. Sir, speak on. 'Tho' I should starve the Youth of my Desires, And come but old to her expecting Arms, The bare Reflection of my Loyalty Shall make amends for all my loss of Love. Leon. Have thy Reward, and hear me: thou art rash, And must be prefac'd into Government, And Temper of those Passions, which would rise Against my Reasons, and undo us all. Eury. Sir, I am calm. Leon. Then know I have this Night Resolv'd to undertake the publick Cause— Eury. Heav'n prosper the Resolve. Leon. What all my Friends With honest, weary Counsels cou'd not gain, The general Wrongs have forc'd. Eury. The general Wrongs are then our Friends— Leon. O! the worst Enemies to thee, and me: Thine is the general Wrong—Thelamia— Eury. My Wife! what, Sir, of her? Leon. Are you a Man? Eury. Talk'd you of Wrongs, and her? I am a Man indeed, to hear them join'd, Yet hold my Reason still: But, Sir, be quick, I cannot promise you, it can be long That I shall hear you; Madness will ensue The bare Imagination of her Wrongs, And hurry me upon some wild Attempt, Which my Repentance never can repair. O! therefore tell me all. Leon. Then hear me all—Cleombrotus— Eury. Cleombrotus! Leon. Soon as he found Your Absence, made his way, beyond all Sense Of Nature, Gods, or Men, in brutal Rage, Pursu'd Thelamia with his monstrous Love. Eury. My Wife! Leon. My Daughter, and thy virtuous Wife. Eury. Then she is virtuous. O! the infernal Fiend! It went no farther? ha! it cou'd not, Sir, For Crites was her Guard. Leon. He, he betray'd both her, and all: Eury. O Villain, bred in Hell! Has he betray'd us? But it ended there? O! answer the Impatience of my Fears: They cou'd not sure proceed? Leon. Still more resolv'd, and bolder still— Eury. Where will my hurrying Fate? Leon. Forsaken thus of every friendly Help, And nothing but her Virtue her Retreat, To save her from those savage, threatning Wrongs, She swallow'd Poison— Eury. O too cruel Gods! Leon. And so expir'd. Eury. 'Tis too much for Life. Eurytion seems stun'd, and dozes. Leon. Nay, then he is prepar'd to know the worst— Thelamia— Goes to the Door, and brings Thelamia in a Veil, by degrees, to the middle of the Stage. Eury. O! that Name! Leon. Come forth, my Child. Eury. Cou'd it awaken Death, as it does me, My Cheeks shou'd burst with the repeated Sound: O! how could I invoke the Rivers, Springs, Vallies, and Hills, Dales, Rocks, and vocal Groves, With all their splitting Echo's, to my aid? Nay, from the stormy Quarters of the Sky, Conjure the Winds, charm e'en the violent North, Who, in the tempest of his boistrous Voice, Should summon my Thelamia back again. But, oh! the Tyrant, deaf to all my Cries, Hears not my Summons, folds her beauteous Limbs In his cold Arms, as he wou'd grow one piece Of Earth with her, and I but rage in vain— Turning, he sees her, and starts. Have then the Gods restor'd her to my Prayers! It must be she—O! satisfy the Fears, If possible, of every Sense at once: I wou'd be all convinc'd. Leon. She lives in Death a Life of Misery. Eury. Not speak to me! what! not one Look! Leon. O! the black Hand of Fate Has drawn that Curtain to conceal her Wrongs— Eury. I find 'em now, worse than a thousand Deaths. Leon. But they will burst, like Lightning, from that Cloud, And blaze a Day of Horror in revenge. Eury. Speed it, you Gods! tho' it be Nature's last. Revenge her Wrongs! Here I devote my Days To Blood, and Vengeance. [Kneels.] Leon. Vengeance stays for us, Stalking impatient thro' our frighted Streets, Our Friends united too, to push it on. Eury. She's going. Leon. O! thou Captain of our Cause! We follow thee thro' all the Paths of Death. Eury. The Sword from thy foul Wrongs shall never part, Till stab'd, and bury'd in the Tyrant's Heart. [Exeunt.]</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT. V. SCENE I. The Outside of a Temple. Leonidas, Lysander, Zenocles, and People. Leon. The Gods propitious combate on our Side, The People animated in this Cause, To break their Yoke, and vindicate their Wrongs. Eurytion to them, with Gentlemen and Guards. Eury. Hither the Chace has led us: The vile herd Routed, and scatter'd. Leon. With the Morning-dawn They, and their Leaders fall into our Hands. Eury. Confounded in the Desert of the Night, Let 'em brood o're the Terrors of their Guilt, To wait the coming Vengeance of the Day. Zen. The Passes are secur'd. Lys. None can escape. Leon. Cleombrotus has here immur'd himself In Neptune's Temple— Lys. Garrison'd, and man'd, In bold Defiance of the Gods themselves. Cleombrotus and Crites on the Walls. Cleom. Who name the Gods, and yet with impious Hands Come arm'd against their Temple? Eury. Monster! thou, Thou hast polluted it into a Den Of foulest Villany, of Lust, and Blood. Cleom. Do not you make it so, it yet is pure. Eury. Art thou there, Crites? hang upon him still, And weigh him down to sure Perdition. Cleom. But who art thou? that I descend to thee: Leonidas I speak to, once a King. Thou dost usurp the Shadow of the Night, To pass thy faded Glory on the State, And hast surpiz'd a Midnight Victory O're frighted Citizens, and sleeping Laws; Which will awake, rouze, and exert their Force, In the Defence of their insulted King, To drive thee out again to Banishment. Leon. Mistaken Wretch! thy Subjects are no more: The Laws remain, and gladly live for thee, Their Tyrant once; they are thy Judges now: Therefore surrender up thy self to them, And save us from the Mischief of more Crimes. Lys. This is your last Retreat. Zen. Which will be forc'd. Cleom. Then here I stand my Fortune— Eury. Push it on. Leonidas, &amp;c. coming forwards on the Stage. Cleom. Now, Crites, now pursue thy own Advice. Thou tremblest! ha! thou shouldst have fear'd before, In time have fear'd, fear'd to have done the ill, Not fear to suffer for it, being done. Crit. If it should not succeed— Cleom. Why then thou feel'st The worst already that can follow it— Crites retires. All is at stake, but there is yet a Chance That promises, and may rise fair for us. Eury. While you prepare th'Attack upon the Gate, And keep 'em busie to defend this Side, I have my Pioneers at work unseen, To dig their Graves, and bury 'em in Ruin. Goes out; Leonidas, and his Party advance to the Gate, in order to break it open. Leon. Abandon'd of all Good! the Gods refuse Their Sanctuary to such Villanies, And give thee up devoted. Fall on then, And force the Gate. Cleom. Yet hold, Leonidas, Look up, I have an Offer yet to make— Leon. Be quick. Cleom. 'Tis this— Euphemia on the Walls. A Daughter to present to you. Leon. My Child! Euphemia! Cleom. Draw off your Men: For the first Violence to force the Gate, Shall send her to you from the Battlements. Leon. I plac'd thee in Diana's sacred Train, To shelter thee from my tempestuous Fate. Cleom. And I remov'd her, by the wise Advice Of honest Crites, my best Counsellor, To shelter me from this impending Storm. Leon. O! What is all our Foresight? You just Gods! Cleom. Nay, no Expostulations with the Gods: They have declared for us in the Success. Nor will a thundring Tale of Sacrilege Beat down these Walls, or gain an Outwork here. Therefore to cut off Time, you must resolve To give up all Advantages you've gain'd, Disperse your Faction, and withdraw your Friends, And you retire from Sparta instantly, Or see this Daughter of your Age, so lov'd, So innocent, first ravish'd by my Slaves, And murder'd next to close the guilty Scene. Leon. O you great Gods! determine for me now. Cleom. Do you determine, for the Choice is yours. Euph. O my Great Father! 'twere Impiety Beyond his Crimes, to think the heavenly Powers Can suffer what he only dares to name. Pursue your injur'd Cause, your just Revenge, Nor lose a Moment in the Dread of me. Therefore again resign me to the Gods, The tutelary Parents of the Weak, Who can disarm the Proud in his own Strength. There is a Hand unseen, a Shield to me. Cleom. Many I have to execute my Will. Leonidas, again I summon thee. What I have done, is a convincing Proof I will do more; that I am resolute To every Deed, my Safety, or Revenge Solicits me: And I will make short Work, Give her my Slaves, and drag her to her Fate. Leon. Hold, hold, the Gods dispose of me, and mine. The Father gives his all to save the Child: Unstain'd restore her to my trembling Hand, And I renounce my Pow'r, resign my Crown, Disband my Friends; or if you would have more, It shall be done: See, they are going, Sir. O my kind Friends! a long, a last farewel. Afford me but Euphemia, that Support Of my declining Age, and I am gone, Never, O! never to see Sparta more. Shouts in the Temple. Crit. What Shouts are those? Cleom. In thy cold Fit again. Lys. The Gods begin to thunder from their Shrines. Mandrocles above to Cleombrotus. Cleom. What is thy News? Man. The Temple is surpriz'd. Crit. Surpriz'd! Cleom. Impossible! Man. Eurytion is at the Head of the bold Enterprize, And is already enter'd. Cleom. Enter'd too? Zen. Our brave Deliverer! [Below.] Crit. What will become of me? Cleom. How got he Entrance? Man. Thro' Vaults, and secret Passes under Ground, Discover'd by the Priests. Cleom. I am betray'd. Man. They say you are betray'd, Betray'd by Crites. Cleom. How! Crit. Betray'd by me! Man. For there are Orders given to save his Life. Cleom. To save his Life! Man. The Priest, who does preside, Is of his Blood, and show'd your Foes the way, Upon that Promise. Cleom. Thus I make it good— Seizing Crites by the Throat. Villain! Betrayer! thou hast brought me here To the Gulph's Mouth, and dost thou plunge me down? But thou shalt try the Leap—'tis a just Thought— If thou hast kindred Devils in the Air To break thy Fall, the Priest may thank 'em for't. Seize him, take, hoist him up, break off his Hold, And toss him headlong from the Temple's Wall. Crit. O, save me, save me, kill me by the Sword. Crites thrown down, they gather about the Body, and drag it off. Cleom. Down with him, there he flies, I follow next, Upward, or downward, 'tis indifferent. [Exit] Leon. Drag off the Carcass, cast it out expos'd, The Food of Dogs— Zen. Vulturs, and Wolves his Grave. Shouts, and Noise of Fighting in the Temple. Leon. Hark, we are call'd. Lys. They are engag'd. Leon. Be quick. Fly, fly to the Assistance of our Friends: Employ your Crows of Iron, Leavers, Beams Against the Gate— They attack the Gate. Zen. Dig its Foundations up. Lys. Spare nothing in your way. Leon. With heaving Force, Wrench the compacted Joints of the strong Pile. O! for the battering Ram with armed Head To tumble down all Opposition. Zen. Bravely, bravely done. Lys. See, it gives way. Leon. Another Tug unlocks the griping Hinge. Lys. It bursts, it flies. Leon. Now follow for the Crown Of all your Pains. They force open the Gate, and enter. Shouts again, and noise of Fighting continued, till the Scene draws, and shows the inside of the Temple. Eurytion gives ground to Cleombrotus, and his Party, but is join'd by Leonidas, and his; then they drive Cleombrotus to the Front of the Stage, and take him. Prisoner, his Party fight off the Stage. Leon. Pursue, Eurytion, let 'em not have Breath To rally, but cut off their latest Hope. Eurytion goes out with his Party. After this Mercy of Deliverance, O! never may the Innocent despair! Lys. This Beast of Prey, this bloody Wolf at last Is hamper'd in the Toyl. Leon. Bring him along— Celona kneeling at the Door. Ha! is it thus, Celona, thou dost greet, Thus hail thy Father's Safety, and Success? Celo. O! for my Father's Safety, and Success, I kiss the Earth in Adoration Of the just Gods; dejected, humbled thus, In this poor suppliant State, they have beheld Me often on my weary'd Knees for you, And they have heard my Vows; left me no more To ask of them: They have preserv'd, preserv'd, And re-enthron'd you in their Mercy's Seat, Their great Vicegerent, now a God to me. Leon. Thy Father ever, rise, Celona, rise. Celo. 'Tis to that Father then I do appeal, Not to the Judge: O! I give up my Cause, Condemn'd, and sentenc'd; and I wonnot move A Word in the Defence of that bad Man, A Burthen to the Earth with all his Crimes. But O! remember, Sir, I am his Wife— Leon. Forget him, most unworthy of thy Care. Celo. Instructed in that Duty, taught by you, Ty'd to his Fortune, wedded to his Fate, To bear a Part in all his Weal, or Woe: O! therefore, if you would defend my Fame, My Virtue, which your Precepts first inspir'd, Let me not leave him in Extremity: If you wou'd save your sinking Daughter's Peace, Bestow her Husband's Life, grant it to me; Forfeited, dead already to the Laws, Sparta renounces him: Then drive him out To reprobated Exile round the World, A Cative, Vagabond, abhor'd, accurs'd, Most miserable in a hated Life. I ask but for a change of Punishment, More exquisite, and sharp: Revenge itself Should grant me that. O! only spare these Eyes The murd'ring Object of a Husband's Death. Leon. Defend me, shield me. See Thelamia comes— Thelamia enters on the other side, veil'd, with a Bowl in her Hand, as drank off. To tear me from thee— [Goes to her.] O! that Posture pleads More than a thousand Tongues: This fatal Bowl Is drein'd, and empty'd of its Poison now; A cordial Draught, and thou art happy, Child; The Gaul of Bitterness is left for me. 'Tis with the sharpest Conflict of my Soul My Bowels are distracted in the Love Of my unhappy Children. Eurytion enters. Eury. Your Enemies are prostrate at your Feet; And Mercy may become the Conqueror: But Vengeance is the injur'd Husband's Right, Thus with strong Hand I seize, and make it mine. [Stabs Cleombrotus.] Celo. He's gone. Leon. His Crimes be bury'd in his Death. Thel. The Voice of Vengeance in my dying Ear Is sweeter than the Songs of happy Life. Eury. Talk not of dying. Thel. O! I only liv'd To hear I am reveng'd, reveng'd by you. Eury. Look up, and feed thy famish'd Eyes with Blood. Leon. Remove the fatal Object from our Sight. Celo. And me for ever from a hated World. The Body carry'd off. Thel. Yes, once again I lift my faded Eyes For a last Look of my Eurytion, To feed 'em at the Fountain of thy Light, And fill me with thy Image, then to close 'em In lasting Night. Eury. Thou art going. Thel. Lead me hence From this infected Air My Spirit shrinks, And cannot mount in the same Sky with him. Let me not fall an Outcast of thy House, Nor in my Ruin lose the Name of Wife; Preserve Thelamia in thy Memory, Who liv'd for thee, and for thy Loss could die. Eurytion leads her off. Leon. The Dead are past our Care. Celo. Past all their Care. Leon. Be comforted, Celona. Celo. I was born To be unhappy, and I have my Lot, This is the Portion was reserv'd for me, Unhappy in the dearest Names of Love, A Wife, and Daughter, and I am past the Care, The miserable Care of Comfort now. Yet I will bear this wretched load of Life, But far remov'd, and shut out from the World, No more to be remember'd in my Wrongs. Leon. Thou wilt not leave thy Father? Celo. I am gone already, Sir. Leon. Forsake his hopeless Age? Celona goes to Euphemia, brings her forward to Leonidas. Celo. The Gods are present to you, and have sent This Blessing yet in store to raise your Hopes. Leon. My Child! I had forgot thee in the Crowd Of busy Fate. O! do I hold thee safe! The Gods have been thy Guard, and my Support. Celo. And be they ever so. The Winter's Rage, That tore your Branches from the bleeding Trunk, Is now succeeded by the healing Spring, To stanch its Wounds, and make it sprout anew. Receive her, as that welcome Spring of Life, Pregnant of future Blessings for the World, To rise in Comforts on a Father's Age. Her teeming Virtues shall enrich this Land, With the most worthy Progeny of Kings, A long Posterity of happy Times. Euphemia is the Promise of the Year, A golden Harvest rising to your Hopes: O! be that Promise every Year renew'd, And in its circling Plenty be fulfill'd! So shall her gentle Influence cheer Mankind, And ripen this into an Age of Gold. Saturnian Days may then again return, And e'en Celona's Griefs forget to mourn. Leon. The guilty Wretch so does the Thunder tear The Innocent, involv'd by being near, Are blasted, and the spreading Ruin share. FINIS.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">EPILOGUE, WRITTEN BY Major Richardson Pack. Our Author's Muse a num'rous Issue boasts, And many of the Daughters have been Toasts. She who now last appears upon the Stage, (The Hopes and Joy of his declining Age) With modest Fears, a cens'ring World to shun, Retir'd awhile, and liv'd conceal'd a Nun: At length, releas'd from that Restraint, the Dame Trusts to the Town her Fortune, and her Fame. Absence, and Time, have lost her many Friends, But this bright Circle makes her large Amends. To You, Fair Judges, she submits her Cause; Nor doubts, if You approve, the Mens Applause. Some sullen formal Rogue perhaps may lour, (Rebel to Female, as to Royal Pow'r) But all the Gay, the Gallant, and the Great, On Beauty's Standard with Ambition wait. Glory is vain, where Love has had no Part: The Post of Honour is a Woman's Heart. Ev'n Chains are Ornaments, that You bestow; The more your Slaves, the prouder still We grow. Man, a rough Creature, savage-form'd and rude, By You to gentler Manners is subdu'd: In the sweet Habitude we grow refin'd, And polish Strength with Elegance of Mind. Our Sex may represent the bolder Pow'rs; The Graces, Muses, and the Virtues, Yours. But ah! 'tis Pity, that for want of Care, Madmen and Fops your Bounty sometimes share, Wretches in Wit's Despight and Nature's born, Beneath your Favour, nay, below your Scorn. May poor Celona's Wrongs a Warning prove, And teach the Fair with Dignity to Love. Let Wealth ne'er tempt you to abandon Sense; Nor Knaves seduce you with their grave Pretence. Be vile Profaneness ever in Disgrace; And Vice abhor'd, as Treacherous, and Base. Revere Yourselves; and, Conscious of your Charms, Receive no Dæmon to an Angel's Arms. Success can then alone your Vows attend, When Worth's the Motive, Constancy the End.</field>
   </doc>
</add>