<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Cradock, Joseph, 1742-1826</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Cradock, Joseph, 1742-1826</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">cradock joseph 1742 1826</field>
      <field name="author_text">Cradock, Joseph, 1742-1826</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1820's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V2.0443.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1824</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460133</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Czar ; an historical tragedy</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Czar ; an historical tragedy</field>
      <field name="title_facet">czar</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">czar</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Czar ; an historical tragedy</field>
      <field name="year_display">1824</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1824</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1824</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460133&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460133&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Cradock, Joseph, 1742-1826&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;cradock joseph 1742 1826&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Czar ; an historical tragedy&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;czar&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1824&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1824&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Cradock, Joseph&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1742&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1826&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Czar&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;an historical tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;John Nichols and Son&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1824&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872456-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv20443&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Czar&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;an historical tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 120 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: The Czar.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1824.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Unknown.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE CZAR. AN HISTORICAL TRAGEDY.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">? Veris falsa remiscet. Hor.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PROLOGUE. Long have the heroes of the Roman age Blaz'd the bright meteors of the British Stage; So long their ensigns have been here unfurl'd, That yet they reign as sov'reigns of the world. Howe'er to-night we dare attention claim To Northern Genius, to aspiring fame, To Russian warriors, to barbaric fight, To empire bright'ning on the realms of night; Tho' less their annals, less their glories known, Yet Britain hails such glories as her own. Well might the nations with amazement gaze At the swift magic of their Monarch's days; To see from chaos light and order rise, And freighted navies streaming to the skies; The haughty Turk his dread commands obey, And Swedish Charles submissive to his sway. E'en Nature wonder'd at the sketch she drew, And held the boundless outline high to view; But to a Female did the task resign, To fix the State, and perfect each design. The Czar, long-toss'd in a tempestuous State, 'Gainst private woes was fortified by Fate; Passions, by turns, like storms o'erwhelm'd his mind; He govern'd—but he felt not for mankind; To noblest actions sudden rage succeeds, And in those transports Truth or Virtue bleeds. Such was our Hero;—Russia yet shall raise Her earliest tribute to her Founder's praise; Well-pleas'd shall trace, through each historic page, The bright examples of that warlike age; Britain transmit them to succeeding Time,— Valour, by her, is priz'd from every clime. But for our Author shall I nothing say, Who well may tremble at this bold essay? He asks no shelter, no protecting shield,— The Public is the Lion of the field, Views not from interest, seeks no private end, A generous Master, a discerning Friend; A thousand baneful passions vex the few,— Just is the sentence that is pass'd by you.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DRAMATIS PERSONÆ. The Czar. Alexis, his Son. Fedrowitz, Brother to Ottokesa. Artamon, Favourite of the Czar. Amgar, Friend to Fedrowitz. Orcan, Friend to Fedrowitz. Desna, Attached to Artamon. Theoroff, Attached to Artamon. Women. Ottokesa. Catharine. Olaria. English Ambassador; Boyars; Captain of the Guards; Officers; Attendants. Scene—Moscow.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. SCENE I. The Royal Palace at Moscow. Ottokesa and Olaria. OTTOKESA. Yes, my Olaria, this auspicious day Gives brightest lustre to the arms of Russia, Give to the wishing crowd their long-lost hero, And gives to Ottokesa All,—her Husband. OLARIA. Time, that with flagging wing awhile has droop'd, Now seems ambitious to adorn your prospects; Now to repay you for long-exil'd joys, And gild the scene with more than noontide brightness: This glorious conquest every hope renews, And love and empire court you to be happy. OTTOKESA. Think not that empire mixes with my thoughts; Oh no;—the Czar himself fills all the mind, And gems and diadems look dim before him. After a tedious absence now to view him, Once more to clasp him in these eager arms, Once more to share his ever-lov'd embrace, How, my Olaria, shall I speak the transports? OLARIA. Your looks proclaim your feelings,—this rich joy Sits smiling at your heart—nor is it strange Your cheeks should glow with animated beauties. OTTOKESA. 'Tis now ten years since first the Swedish arms Have kept me anxious for my hero's safety; Thou oft hast heard of each eventful change These lingering wars have wrought;—e'en on that day When Narva yielded to the fierce assault, While fortune varying held the doubtful conquest, His life was at a cast;—Oh! had I known His danger then, I had not sure surviv'd The dread suspense!—But lo! from fam'd Pultowa The Swedish Monarch bends his headlong course, And feels those arts of war he so much boasted, Redoubled now with direst horrors on him; Now, now he feels a people's ardour glows With ever-kindling fires, whose hopes elate, Whose wishes, wealth, whose every thirst of glory Concenter only in their monarch's heart. OLARIA. These wonders I could hear you oft relate, And still the theme delight me,—still should find My ear hang list'ning on the glorious sequel. OTTOKESA. That sequel, hoped for long, is now arriv'd, That sequel to my thoughts, my vows, my pray'rs,— I see the conqueror in his every step, Impatient to return to Ottokesa.— Why linger then my Train?—they feel not love, They feel not rapture, such as Ottokesa's, Else we had met him now;—return—return— They shall not be so dainty in the feast; Their musick speaks but artificial joy, Their garlands beam not, like a cheerful look, Like joy's fair votaries,—like joy itself, The trembling joy of an enraptur'd heart.— I will no longer wait. OLARIA. Madam, they're here, A brighter train ne'er grac'd a warrior's conquest, No brighter honours e'er a warrior crown'd Than these our triumph yields;—the pageant rare, The choice select, and dignified by you. OTTOKESA. Then let the Choir proceed;—each dulcet note Moscow will straight applaud, and raise a strain, Sacred to love, to gratitude, and peace. [The Scene withdraws, and discovers the Choir; having sung the following Song of Triumph, the Procession passes over the Stage. [Ottokesa retires. Chorus. Hail the mighty victor crown'd, Songs of triumph to him sing, Grateful let your praise resound, Every honour'd trophy bring. Air. Cease at length the dire alarms! Cease—the hostile clangour cease; Cease the boast of skill in arms, Half a world is hush'd to peace. Chorus repeated. Hail the mighty victor crown'd, Songs of triumph to him sing, Grateful let your praise resound, Every honour'd trophy bring. [Exeunt. Ottokesa returns meeting an Attendant. ATTENDANT. A warrior from the camp is just arriv'd, Who brings important news. OTTOKESA. Admit him straight; He comes but to reproach my long delay. ATTENDANT. Madam, he's here already. Enter Amgar. OTTOKESA. Welcome to Moscow, Welcome the tongue that speaks but of my husband; How did you leave the Czar? AMGAR. Madam, he's well. OTTOKESA. “Madam, he's well,”—have you no better answer? There is no pleasure in thy face;—why, man, Be warm and rapturous;—such a tameness Suits not thy grateful tidings.—Where is he? Is he not almost here? AMGAR. Alas! I fear— OTTOKESA. Talk not of fear.—This day to joy is sacred; Where did you leave the Czar? AMGAR. Near to the suburbs. OTTOKESA. Then, ere thou tell'st thy message, he is here; Thou art some loit'rer— AMGAR. On my knee your pardon! Would I had fall'n inglorious in the fight, Ere doom'd to utter my unwelcome tidings! OTTOKESA. Ha!—but there's more in this!—speak, quickly speak;— That shame, that downcast look, those sighs proclaim A message big with horror. AMGAR. Most gracious queen, I at the earnest suit of all your friends Have flown to give you notice— OTTOKESA. Notice of what? AMGAR. That ere I left the camp the cruel Czar Had issued orders to prevent your coming. OTTOKE Oh! is that all!—That only meant his care, But I will meet him straight;—my grateful heart O'erflows with rapture at his famed success. AMGAR. Pardon the freedom of my grief!—Were he as true, I should not say I'd rather die than speak. OTTOKESA. What dost thou mean? AMGAR. You judge him as he was; But absence may have worn out his affections. OTTOKESA. Some direful plot must then have burst the ties That twined our faithful hearts;—I was too blest, And heaven prepares this downfall to my joys. AMGAR. Madam, he's held in most ignoble chains;— But oh! forgive, if I again implore Both secrecy and pardon:—some toying she Has stopp'd his bright career in love and glory. OTTOKESA. How!—am I then deserted?—'tis impossible, I will not yet believe,—he is too great, Too noble,—oh! I throw away the thought; He cannot be the dupe of low deceit; Think'st thou the Czar untrue to all his vows; Think'st thou he e'er could wrong his Ottokesa, Whose life is wrapp'd in his, and who, he knows, Would die to save him from the least distress? AMGAR. Falshood like this destroys the bonds of love, And makes us almost doubt, in our weak state, Of just reward to ever-struggling virtue. OTTOKESA. I call high Heaven to witness,—from the hour Our hands at first were join'd,—I've ever been A true and faithful wife,—have known no wish But what his presence gave;—the day appear'd Too short to speak my bliss, and from the night, ('T'was all I could)—I've borrow'd countless hours, To pray for his success,—earnest have pray'd, That if there aught remain'd of treasur'd woe For future times, to pour it all on me, So I might still preserve his faith inviolate, And live the partner of unalter'd love; By him too I have borne a son, a matchless son, The model of our hopes. AMGAR. And yet that son— Is doom'd by him to banishment;—treason Is made the excuse of this inhuman sentence. OTTOKESA. If this be false—thou hast hazarded my life,— If true—why, take it! AMGAR. My life upon the truth! Your brother, ever anxious for your safety, Nor less in dire alarm for Prince Alexis, Compell'd this awful service. Ah! could you know the pungent pangs I 've felt Through every stage of this ill-fated journey, You then might judge aright. Who—who would willing bring such weighty ills, And risk the future frowns they oft occasion? Your lowliest servant is o'erwhelm'd with sorrow. OTTOKESA. Nay then my day is past,—night comes apace— Eternal night to all my full-blown hopes.— You may retire, for I can bear no more; Retire this instant, And leave me here a victim to my woe. [Exit Amgar. Enter Olaria. OLARIA. My Royal Mistress, lo! the Train await, Their mirth is chang'd to fear, their joy to doubt, The jarring minstrels mock the master's skill, Each note discordant uninspir'd by you. OTTOKESA. You may proceed, my friend;—but oh! your Queen Is chill'd to stone,—is speechless with her griefs,— She knows not what she is—unless distracted. OLARIA. For Heaven's sake speak your sorrows. OTTOKESA. I'm false; I've driven the Czar to seek a kinder home; I've made my son a traitor,—banish'd him; Have chang'd my bliss to woe, my joy to horror, And here stand fix'd the monster of creation! OLARIA. Why mystery is this? OTTOKESA. Do not dare to doubt, All this the Czar declares,—he cannot err,— His words are sure, and his decrees are fate. OLARIA. In pity speak more calmly to Olaria; You pierce her very soul. OTTOKESA. What can I speak? I've told thee all, my sentence soon will pass, And punishment await such dread offences. Enter Captain of the Guards, attended. CAPTAIN. Secure the Queen, the Czar has doom'd her straight To the Black Tower of Moscow. OTTOKESA. Then lead me, Sirs! CAPTAIN. Our Sov'reign having heard of divers plots, Hatch'd in his absence, thinks his State in danger; While others still of note more boldly say His bed has been usurp'd. OTTOKESA. Presuming slave! Stop that unhallow'd tongue;—I yet will teach— Oh! no, I am too weak—I sink already, I have no power to say—I'm innocent. There, take me,—lodge me in my gloomy cell; I will not plead my wrongs, tho' I can feel them. But where, oh! where's my son? GUARD. Now borne to exile. OTTOKESA. Alas! my boy!—how—how could he offend? By loyalty and truth!—to take him from me! Him, whom in infancy I 've often held, While prattling he beguil'd the weary hours The Czar was at the wars;—whose childhood charm'd, And whose well-temper'd mind, whose ripen'd years Would have rewarded all a mother's fondness! GUARD. We dare not disobey our orders. OTTOKESA. True, But had you, then, no better way to end me? Where are your ready daggers, speedy deaths? Had you no other means than stale pretence, Or ling'ring accusation? CAPTAIN. The Czar has cause— OTTOKESA. Ah! “Cause!” say that again,— “Cause,”—didst thou say? Not e'en the Czar himself, The pride, the awe of millions, shall attempt To prove the crimes alleg'd;— First let him break down altars, rifle shrines, And call the saints to wonder at his daring, Ere boldly venture at a thought so impious! CAPTAIN. We'll hear no more of this. OTTOKESA. Yes—I will make A last, a dread appeal:—If e'er in faith I've waver'd from the Czar, may Death o'ertake me;— But that would be a blessing;—then, let all ills, If greater ills are yet to be endur'd, Let guilt o'erwhelm my son,—let him be false, Let him become the traitor he is deem'd, Let him, in one vast ruin, crush the State, Whose pride of empire, whose increasing fame, Whose welfare still is dearer than my own! END OF THE FIRST ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. SCENE I. Apartment in the Palace. Fedrowitz and Orcan. FEDROWITZ. Such wrongs will force their way;—a sister's fame, The honour of her son,—all—all conspire, To pull down vengeance on him. ORCAN. Then do it bravely, Not hunt him tamely with a common fate, But front him in a war—proclaim his guilt, Urge, and avow it. FEDROWITZ. Was it for this, the queen Linger'd in absence,—yielded up her days A prey to solitude,—cloister'd her charms In barren expectation, cold suspense? This her reward!—are these the fruits of virtue? The Czar perhaps himself is nobly-minded, But favourites trample on the wisest laws, Whene'er ambition sets their wheels in motion; With basest arts can undermine a state, And pass those arts for virtues. ORCAN. Then you suspect This Artamon? FEDROWITZ. Suspect!—suspect dost say? I know and will unveil his dark designs; He is the cause of all these hell-born mischiefs. ORCAN. But sure the Czar— FEDROWITZ. Is of himself right-noble, But subject to the force of new impressions; This Artamon has laid a snare before him, And straight he's caught in the alluring toil. ORCAN. Who is this Artamon? FEDROWITZ. A Swedish captain, Who can instruct the Czar;—he's prompt to learn, Tho' oft from minds less-tutor'd than his own. ORCAN. 'Tis strange,—what could he learn from him? FEDROWITZ. Nothing, Unless by treachery to mine the strength He boldly should oppose;—during the war This Swede presented him a beauteous maid, So killing fair, if you'll believe report, That, like another Anthony, our Czar, E'en from the summit of imperial sway, Might wisely fall for love!—oh! such a maid That rapture, borne upon the Eagle's wing, Lags short of her perfections. ORCAN. What more of this? FEDROWITZ. This slave must blast the honour of my house, He makes quick room, he drags a queen to death, And dooms her son a captive. ORCAN. Where is the prince? FEDROWITZ. 'Tis said, he's closely guarded near the camp; But ere the Czar returns in triumph here, Is convoy'd into banishment. ORCAN. Unhappy youth! FEDROWITZ. No Pity now!—think'st thou we'll not revenge Such daring outrage? is there no fire, no zeal In Russia left?—are men now authorized To tread down truth and justice,—banish virtue, And build upon the ruin one great fabrick, And call that fabrick empire? ORCAN. And yet I fear There's danger in the attempt. FEDROWITZ. There is in all, And he, who rises not above his fears, Should bleed their victim. ORCAN. The Czar will be inform'd, And punish the deep arts of such a traitor. FEDROWITZ. Who can inform him?—is he not beset With sycophants, who strew his treacherous way With flowers for guilt to tread on?—dangerous baits; Where novelty gives relish to opinion. This woman's youthful charms from him conceals Vice in a snare, and ambush in endearment. ORCAN. But you impeach the Czar by these suspicions, And boldly frown on him who awes the world. FEDROWITZ. He awes not me:—I rise superior to him, And should there be no means to crush this slave, I'll shake the very throne;—I'll see the Queen, And if loud Fame not errs in the report, If by herself confirm'd, such wrongs assail, I'll fall or I'll redress them. ORCAN. Lead on, my friend, My hand, my heart is your's, and here I swear— FEDROWITZ. No oath! our cause be our best sacrament! There's truth and virtue in't, and honest men Will greatly dare for't. [Exeunt. SCENE II. A Prison. OTTOKESA. 'Tis well—this deep-felt gloom—this awful silence— This is sunk Melancholy's last abode, Here let my fancy rove! And here I'll picture unsubstantial forms To visit my sick dreams; There is a vault, where piteous infants oft Have smil'd in vain, and kiss'd the hands that bound them; There too their frantic mothers tore their hair, And wore their limbs along the flinty pavement, While some stern ruffians, by the place inspir'd, Murder'd their babes in luxury of guilt. Hail, dreadful mansion, hail!—here let me fix; While frequent list'ning to yon doleful bell, I lose myself in horrors,—till some lone owl, Waked by a groan more hideous than the rest, Echoes aloud the woes it cannot feel. Enter Fedrowitz, speaking to the Guard. FEDROWITZ. Lo! where she stands!—oh! what a sight is there? How can I bear to view that suff'ring virtue! OTTOKESA. Who art thou?—speak!—Ah!—my brother here! FEDROWITZ. Yes,— Thy kind brother, whose every sense is struck With grief at thy distress. OTTOKESA. You'll pity me; You'll not forsake me then, tho' all the world, That flutters only in the noontide beam, Declines my setting fate! FEDROWITZ. Forsake thee!—No! If yet there lives or power, or truth, or justice, I will redress thy wrongs. OTTOKESA. Never—oh! never; I'm but a speck on the expanse of empire, Made by a breath, and blighted. FEDROWITZ. Wrongs like your's Avenge themselves,—make red the front of war; Melt e'en the flinty frosts of Russian breasts, And make them pour their force. OTTOKESA. No,—tho' my woes Be past endurance,—yet my all-powerful love Protects and shields the Czar;—tho' here forsaken, Deserted as I stand, yet still I feel The bands that first entwin'd us;—time may do much; There yet may come an hour, when he shall hear How deep my wrongs!—He'll hear, and may redress them. FEDROWITZ. Were you alone to suffer, you might plead, To save his falsehood from the storm that gathers; You for yourself content might linger here, And live up to the summit of despair; But you have other claims;—a banish'd son, Whose very life even now— OTTOKESA. Aye—there I bleed, There you awaken all a mother's fondness; Let's see for speedy means,—a stricter guard May soon deprive me of a brother's counsel:— And yet there are no means,—the troops in arms Are ever guarded to the front of danger; My son might forfeit every darling hope, Nor we have power to save him. FEDROWITZ. What could he lose? The Czar already makes him sign his death, Or worse than death—a bar to his succession; This was enforc'd before I left the camp, And banishment for him was doom'd eternal. OTTOKESA. You kindle all my rage;—an act like this Nerves me with manly strength, and I methinks Could brave a field of foes;—this instant say Whence all our ills began. FEDROWITZ. The story's tedious; A Swedish knave, a favourite of the Czar's, Has rais'd this dire commotion in the State; Another Queen,—some strange all-conquering charm Has sprung to light through him. OTTOKESA (after a pause). Yet I forgive! And yield up every thought of due revenge; My darling son, the cause of all my cares, By this may breathe his last;—how could his frame Endure the bitter pangs of such keen misery! E'en now perhaps he calls on me for succour In hunger and disgrace,—in vain he calls To me for help, for shelter or redress, To wail his woes, or close his dying eyes. FEDROWITZ. Grief figures ills beyond the doom of fate; No time must now be lost,—I'll raise a war; There yet remain from bold Sophia's bands, Troops of no common force. OTTOKESA. I'll ne'er consent; I love the people, as I lov'd their monarch; What have they done, that they should suffer for me? Shall they who grateful bring their ready sheaves, The gleanings of their unremitting toil, Be murder'd for their pains? they now are happy; For me shall they give up their peaceful homes? Shall they leave all their little hives of sweets, And barter blessings for wide-wasting war? FEDROWITZ. 'Tis in the cause of justice.—Shall each man, In the extended scale of human being, Feel only for himself?—'tis public stock, And all must struggle in a common danger. OTTOKESA. I see rebellion in a murth'rous form, Stalking his guilty rounds, treading on the necks Of tenderest infants, calling aloud for mercy, While mothers, fond as I am, plead their woes, And plead those woes in vain;—yet do I swear, I would relinquish all;—give up the Czar, Give up myself to torture, shame, or death, So I might once again embrace my boy, And fold him in these arms. Enter Alexis, disguised. ALEXIS. Embrace him here. For lo! he comes to snatch thee from despair! FEDROWITZ. Ah! see, she faints!—this unexpected joy Bears down her languid soul!—help to support her! OTTOKESA. Say, who art thou, that from the dream of death Art come so like that form, that angel-form, That was my son? ALEXIS. Disguis'd I flew to see you. OTTOKESA. Speak, then, what art thou? ALEXIS. Your son, your darling boy, Now doom'd to exile, but who in this rude garb, Through friendly aid, before the Czar arrives, Has stol'n this anxious hour. OTTOKESA. And can it be? Welcome—oh! welcome, to my soul more dear Than any joy that Fancy could create! 'Tis he—'tis he himself—I hold him now— We never more will part,—I have him still,— Nor shall a cruel father tear him from me. ALEXIS. Alas! my time is short,—Olaria watches now The fleeting moment.—Should the Czar arrive Before I leave, my death would straight be sentenc'd. OTTOKESA. O fly this instant, then, and tho' the cord That holds my heart be sever'd at the stroke— Yet fly;—I charge thee, fly. ALEXIS. Our friends await, And will advise in time. FEDROWITZ. We'll think of aid; For if there be a power, whereon to hang The slightest hope, I will—I will avenge thee. ALEXIS. No hope remains for me, I've sign'd my death, My death to fame, to justice, and to empire. FEDROWITZ. Then let the Czar reverse the black decree! For such compulsion, such a daring outrage, His fame, his conquests—nay, his very life, Becomes too mean a sacrifice. OTTOKESA. Say not his life, O think of gentler means; for know the stroke That ends the Czar, will stab your Ottokesa. ALEXIS. Here in the awful sight of Heaven I swear, To give up all that's precious to my soul Rather than wound a father;—all—but thee, Whose virtue makes me straight recall my vow, Nerves me with strength, fans every fire within me, And instant I am arm'd a parricide. OTTOKESA. Too much, my boy,—this overwhelming kindness Is equal death.—See, the denouncer comes, And tolls the knell of Fate. Enter Olaria. OLARIA. Break off this instant, The Czar is at the gates,—your watchful guards, Trembling and anxious for your safety wait, Nor leave you time to take a last farewell. OTTOKESA. Now, now my soul, oh! summon all thy aid, Nor call to mind how dear, how lov'd he was! FEDROWITZ. Come, my brave youth, new prospects rise before us; Danger most threatens while we thus delay. OTTOKESA. O let me hear by every chance that offers, Where,—and how true you are. ALEXIS. My life to obey you! OTTOKESA. Thus then in one embrace take all my heart, And fly, ere I pronounce that word—Farewell! FEDROWITZ. We go together;—if victorious wreaths Shall crown our deeds but equal to our daring, When next we meet, that meeting shall be grateful. OTTOKESA. In mercy stop,—let me again repeat, Should any hand destroy my guilty Lord, Death ends your sister too. FEDROWITZ. Oh! dread it not. OTTOKESA. This one,—this last embrace! ill-omen'd fears Betray me now—I never more shall see thee, I never more shall hold thee in these arms; Fate will deprive thee of a mother's care, Ere the tomb yawn to close thee; oh! that thought Renews each trembling pang;—the little aid My hopes had gather'd for this mournful parting, Now fails me when I want it; there, take me, Heav'n! In this dire struggle of my soul—now, now I yield— I sink o'erwhelm'd with woe. [Faints into Olaria's arms. FEDROWITZ. This is the moment; Oh! seize it now, ere she again revive; Another pang would end her. ALEXIS. Farewell, farewell! Bright excellence!—and oh! Olaria! now, By every hope thou hast of future bliss, If e'er I shared your tenderest—least regard, If e'er my mother won you by her kindness, If pity pleads for wrongs beyond atonement, In this extreme of anguish shield and save her! END OF THE SECOND ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. SCENE I. A Colonade of the Palace. Amgar, Theoroff. Trumpets sound. THEOROFF. The hour at length is come; the all-conquering Czar Returns in triumph to the throne of Moscow; Let thronging crowds all hail the laurel'd hero, And nought be heard but minstrelsy and joy! AMGAR. The hour indeed is come; the cruel Czar Has given unjustly chains to Ottokesa, Has spread a gloom through all his thoughtful subjects, Who in his triumphs feel their helpless state. THEOROFF. The Queen, by dark conspiracy has form'd The dangers that surround her;—her lov'd son, By Artamon accus'd of rank rebellion, Submits to own the justice of his doom. AMGAR. The criminal, whose flesh is harrow'd up, Will oft acknowledge treasons not his own; By Artamon condemn'd, there's no appeal; His frown is censure, accusation, fate. What could a youth oppose to settled wiles? What could he urge against a father's act To bar him from succession?—to sign that act Is all the treason that Alexis knows. THEOROFF. The Czar will well approve himself a parent; E'en to the wildest Russian nature gives A fondness for its young,—a tender care To shelter and protect it;—shall then a mind, Tutor'd in all the arts of polish'd life, Feel less than a barbarian? AMGAR. The Czar is cruel, And though he rules a world with awful sway He cannot rule himself. THEOROFF. But sure the Queen Hath yielded up to others those rich charms The Czar so highly priz'd? AMGAR. Oh! never, never; She is as chaste as are our mountain snows Ere tasted by the sun;—December's ice Would sooner yield to any soft impression Than she to guilty love. THEOROFF. But for what end Should Artamon destroy the fame of her Who never wrong'd him? AMGAR. To rise upon her ruin; To make a Swedish dame our Empress now, Who will reward him largely with the spoils Of an ill-gotten throne. Theoroff. Perhaps you wrong her! Could she refuse?—She knows not Ottokesa. If she believes the son and mother guilty, Nor is herself the cause of their disgrace, Where is her fault? AMGAR. Her charms become her fault, Through them the monarch makes the crimes he wishes; But here I pause,—and hope that she'll approve Her innocence and worth;—if she's deceiv'd— And I'll take care she shall be soon inform'd, That every species of the vilest arts Have been employ'd to raise her to a throne; Let Artamon beware declining favour! Time yet may bring to light his dark designs, And pull down ruin on the head that form'd them. THEOROFF. But hark!—more trumpets sound! I'll hope the best, And meet the general joy. Amgar. And I meanwhile Will from the public take my devious track, And mourn for Ottokesa. [Exeunt. SCENE II. The Czar on the Throne. Artamon, Desna, Boyars, Guards, Attendants. Martial Music. Too long, alas! the God of War, His flaming wheels with furies hung, Has swept his desolating car, And thro' the air his clangors rung! But now he yields to softer strains; Peace waves the olive in her hand, Her plenteous joys shall fill the plains, And smile in blessings o'er the land. ARTAMON. Hail mighty Prince of this extended empire, Whose fame is spread o'er the admiring world, Let conquest wait thy will,— Till farthest India, till remotest climes, Partake the harvest of all bounteous sway, And the sun set not on your firm dominion! CZAR. Yes, I must own ambition fires my soul; The bright reward lights onward to my wishes, To banquet nobly on my people's welfare. DESNA. Your grateful subjects, with o'erflowing hearts, Can only pour the tribute of their thanks,— Entreat the Heavens in one rich shower of blessings, To make them worthy of their sovereign's love! CZAR. Enough of this; for other cares engage us;— What have you heard from England?—that proud people May feel perhaps the force of our resentment. 1ST BOYAR. Ambassadors from England are arriv'd, To greet your Majesty from Royal Anne. CZAR. 'Tis well they are, for 'tis of moment to them.— Know then, my faithful subjects, We, your Sov'reign, Have been ill-treated, E'en in the person of our great Ambassador; By some mistake—I think they call it there, This dread vice-gerent, this our other self, Has been imprison'd. 2D BOYAR. How, mighty Czar, imprison'd! CZAR. “Imprison'd,”—such an act, that Majesty Must blush but to announce it;—particulars Have yet scarce reach'd our ears; but know, my friends, Our lofty mind ill-brooks such studied insult. 1ST BOYAR. See the Ambassadors. Enter the Ambassadors. CZAR. Well, my Masters, Say, are you come to threaten us with war? To lay our towers and palaces in dust? Or more to gratify your stubborn hearts, Would you again behold our second-self Imprison'd, and in chains? AMBASSADOR. Letters, dread Sir, We bring from Royal Anne, our gracious mistress, Who bids us, with all due respect, present Her kindest wishes to the Emperor. CZAR. Wishes, ill-timed, are but repeated insults; Deep-sunk resentment fills our clouded brow. Say—have her officers as yet receiv'd The deaths they merited?—such stern order Admitted no delay. AMBASSADOR. 'Tis not her's to give,— She, mighty Sir, is not despotic there; Her Monarch is the Law. CZAR. Law!—Law is our Will; If the supreme has not a right to enforce The principles he forms,—where is his power? Is he not merely then a splendid gem, Set for a crowd to gaze at? AMBASSADOR. 'Tis your's to guard That bulwark you have rais'd;—our gracious Queen Receives her crown in trust, and tho' supreme, Makes but a part, tho' most important part, In our time-temper'd, free-born Constitution. (Czar reads the Letter.) She mentions here “Imprisonment for debt;” Were not the fame and glory of our State Pledges of weightiest trust? AMBASSADOR. All she could do She has complied with,—gain'd a ready Act, That no Ambassador from any Court Shall for the future, whatsoe'er his fault, Meet the like insult.—Weigh, then, dread Sir, The important reasons, that the Queen enforces, And once again with cordial love receive The friendship that she offers. CZAR. 'Tis somewhat strange, But I remember, when in a former reign I view'd your shipping and admir'd your arts, I wonder'd at your State, where I perceiv'd Your Heav'n-directed King, in making laws, Held conference with his people. AMBASSADOR. And then he ruled Full Sovereign in their hearts.—'Tis Britain's boast, No power despotic can destroy the work Her generous sons have wrought;—the people there Must join to crush the fabric that was rais'd By their renown'd forefathers.—Sacred trust! Their warlike force is clad in “righteous” armour; Their laws are founded on the rock of justice; Their throne and altars bid the world defiance; Britain—by Britain only can be conquer'd. CZAR. Your language is too bold;—howe'er, in pity, I will not pass my sentence on your laws; In pity to your Queen I'll meet her embassy With all free kindness, and return an answer That may renew all former ties.—Meanwhile We give you friendly welcome. [Exit Ambas. And now, my honor'd partners of the war, Thrice happy in the conquests ye have gain'd, Since by these means ye look to future times For blessings on your offspring,—sure to them As glorious to yourselves;—but hear your Monarch,— Tho' stubborn Charles has yielded to our arms, Tho' to the lost Augustus we restore The throne of Poland;—tho' laurel'd victory Smiles on our every step;—yet, know, my friends, I feel domestic war;—my once-lov'd Queen Has prov'd herself most base,—my darling son Become a traitor, and a war within— A war that preys upon our vitals—threatens The life-blood of our crown. ARTAMON. Whilst order rises, And arts and science flourish through the land; Whilst commerce here unfurls her freighted sails, And every treasure monarchs can bestow Is shower'd in blessings on us—shall the Czar— Shall the great founder of this mighty empire, Be troubled with a brawl?—shall not the wretch, The abettor of adultery, war, and treason, Be crush'd at once?—I'll speak more openly— The wily Fedrowitz, whose trait'rous arts Would curse this happy realm with civil broil, Instead of owning the attested crimes Of his insidious race, shows now his zeal In rescuing from banishment your son— CZAR. “Rescuing from banishment!”—you're misinform'd; Our Guards dare not betray us. ARTAMON. 'Tis too true; Nay more, I've learnt that, in disguise, the Prince Departed but ere now from Ottokesa. CZAR. Nay, if rebellion lurks so very near, We'll crush it in the bud. ARTAMON. No time to lose; If what I've heard be true;—Boyars of note Are deep in the revolt. CZAR. To thy care then, My faithful Artamon, I give the charge; Summon my troops as you shall see occasion, And tread down insurrection,—for through the cloud A dawn of light breaks in, and I must hail The glories of its rising. [Exit Artamon. (Noise without.) The Queen! the Queen! CZAR. Richer than all my gains, I now present The pride, the trophy of the war;—such a prize! Excelling fair!—form'd by the cunning'st hand Of pregnant fancy; upon her youthful brow Sits Majesty enshrin'd as on its native throne; To outward form she superadds a mind, Deck'd with the stores of her own softer sex, And manly strength of our's. 1ST BOYAR. See her approach. Enter Catharine, attended, the Czar introducing her. DESNA. Wonder indeed!—there all perfections meet, As in a sacred synod! (to the Boyars).—Oh! may you live (to the Queen), To bless the Czar, renew domestic joy, And flourish in the sunshine of his favour! CATHARINE. With fancied trophies my dread Sovereign decks “Her he delights to honour.”—All my merit Is to confess myself unworthy;—when I view The lofty summit of Imperial State I tremble at the height; but know, my people, However high your Monarch deigns to grace me, Next to my Czar's, I'll court his subjects' love. CZAR. I dare be sworn thou wilt;—thy love repays All the unkindness I've before receiv'd, Cares ill-return'd, and violated vows. CATHARINE. In love, great Prince, you triumph as in war, And conquer but to bless,—others make slaves, And read their safety in a nation's fears, But you gain willing empire o'er the mind. CZAR. Aye, should I not?—it is the sovereign's bliss; For where the heart accords not with the tongue, A people's homage is the worst of treasons. CATHARINE. Your power, supported with an equal justice, Has cull'd the flowery garden of the world, And thence has drawn, whate'er Italia's shores Have breath'd of softer elegance; what polish'd France Has taught in manners, and in maxims wise; Or what fair England's still more favour'd clime, Storehouse of genius, learning's best resort, In deep-read science, and improving arts, Has held in admiration,— All—all yourself has caught, and Russia now Bids fair to emulate their general fame. 1ST BOYAR. From this bright hour may Heav'n propitious smile, And shed its kindliest blessings on the head Of this most favour'd Queen, and may she crown, With joy's increase our Monarch's future days. CATHARINE. Oh! be those pray'rs prophetic! may I add Or peace or comfort to my Sovereign's life, 'Tis all I ask;— Empire compar'd with that appears a toy, And vanishes before me;—should I forget The gratitude I owe, you'll then proclaim, That fortune's gifts o'erturn the female brain, And I'm no more myself. CZAR. Enough, Enough,— And now receive her as your future Queen; And know, in honour of this glorious day, In honour of the Fair, we shall create An Order call'd St. Catharine's;—'tis for Merit, And giv'n to Merit only,—not bestow'd By partial favour on the half-deserving, Without inquiry after real worth; 'Tis for Pre-eminence;—who unwisely give Create a winter of desert around them; Neglect is then the honour;—but this shall be For kings to emulate;—'tis richly dyed With glory's tints, by every virtue won. But now retire, my friends;—fatigues to-day Demand our rest;—to-morrow we proclaim The Order of her Royal Coronation. DESNA. And from your loves may still new glories spring To guard the State you've rais'd. CZAR. Aye there, my friend, Thou pray'st aright, That never Sovereign may hereafter rise, To mar the wond'rous fabrick;— 'Tis built for ages, and I trust will last Till empires cease; till the sun's weary train Shall loiter in their courses;—the time may come Some abler hand shall take the extended reins, And keep the wheels in motion,—nurture the arts, Protect our commerce with unrival'd sway, Make this the envied seat of every grace, And kindred soil of honour;—and may that pow'r, Form'd to protect and shield this envied State, Be ever honour'd with my people's care, A future Catharine born to bless the world. END OF THE THIRD ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT IV. SCENE I. The Prison. Ottokesa. Olaria. OTTOKESA. That noise again!—look out, Olaria, straight; At length perhaps my son in triumph comes,— Or is he lost for ever?—yes—he is lost, And every hope is buried in his grave.— All righteous Power, who view'st my deep distress, Cut short the remnant of my wretched days, Or grant me some redress,—not ever thus Let anxious cares distract me! OLARIA. No plea alleg'd, No answer to your suit;—oh! may the Prince Gain all the scatter'd troops,—raise high the storm, And rush in terror on this guilty land. OTTOKESA. Yes, let him plead in arms!—till then I find In vain I sue to vindicate my fame. Grant me but that, kind Heaven!—I ask no more. Did Conquest spread her every gift before me, Had I the power to seize the Russian throne, To make the Czar submissive to my will, Here, here I swear, no other claim to make, Than to approve my wrongs, restore my son, The rightful heir of this unbounded empire. OLARIA. Hark!—sure the gates unbar!—a light appears, Some stranger from the field is now arriv'd, See—through the aisle he shoots, and lo! he comes, Your brother comes, to sooth your every care! Enter Fedrowitz. FEDROWITZ. All now is lost;—fortune, a foe to justice, Yields up her palm to infamy and fraud; The Guards, the pitying Guards, who brought the Prince To take a kind embrace—were all surpris'd,— The spies of Artamon had watch'd their way, And now they claim their lives. OTTOKESA. Ah!—where's my son? FEDROWITZ. Ill fated youth!—and do I live to speak it: E'en now he drags the chain,—unconquer'd yet, If minds can hold their freedom,—he, alas! This hour must take his trial. OTTOKESA. Then he must die. Do not say trial! For trial sure is condemnation here; Who will attempt to plead, defend my child, When lo! his father, his stern rigid judge, Deaf to his plaints, regardless of his suit, Will urge the cruel deed? FEDROWITZ. Yet will I plead, Tho' earth and Heaven oppose,— The Czar as potent as embattled Jove Shall not deter me;—thou, Artamon, be there! And if destruction can await thy wiles, If shame can rifle colour from thy cheeks, And plant detection there,—there, with bold truth, And conscious scorn I'll meet thee; Thy hour shall soon approach, thy sun shall set; Superior fate shall cast thee to the earth, And ring thy parting knell. OTTOKESA. Delay not then, Each moment's precious;—I'll to the tower's top, And catch from babbling winds each passing gale That breathes or death or freedom. [Exeunt. SCENE II. The Palace. Artamon and Desna. ARTAMON. All now succeeds, e'en to my utmost wish; Alexis seiz'd in the broad act of treason, The father hesitates no more on death; This clears us too of Ottokesa's vengeance, And fixes Catharine on the Russian throne. DESNA. The Czar, enamour'd of his blooming bride, Thinks not of Ottokesa;—in her dark cell She wails her woes to the relentless walls, And beats in vain the air. ARTAMON. Her date is short; The doom her son shall meet with soon will fix The period of her griefs. DESNA. Alas! poor Queen! Methinks I mourn her fate. ARTAMON. Dost thou relent? We've plung'd too far in guilt, and should thy tongue Proclaim the secret cause, reveal my shame, Her fate shall soon be thine. DESNA. I shrink not now, But on the wings of speed will force my way To execute your orders. ARTAMON. This moment, then; For see the Czar is hast'ning to the trial;— Catharine's meek nature must not guess our process;— In the short compass of this busy night Our all is at a stake;—straight to the prison; There use your utmost arts,—create delays To stop the Queen's arrival;—should she appear, Before her son receives his final doom, I know the Czar would waver;—fly, begone; Serve me but now, and fortune pants to yield Her every bright reward. [Exeunt. SCENE III. The Czar discovered on the Throne. On one side Artamon and his Abettors; on the other, Amgar and other Friends of the repudiated Queen and her Son. Boyars, Guards, Attendants. CZAR. From joyful triumph, and the dreams of bliss, Behold, my faithful friends, the sad reverse Of this inglorious hour;—here view at large A Monarch's cares, nor with the vulgar think That he who wears the glittering garb of State Can feel no pangs within. ARTAMON. Your subjects ever Must sure lament this most ungrateful cause Of your severe distress.—Affection, they may fear, Will plead too loudly for a darling son, Tho' your own life's at stake; facts already prov'd Leave little room for trial,—but to silence Those whom ambition prompts to seek their own More than their Sov'reign's good,—you still vouchsafe— Each witness to repeat what he has sworn, Should the bold Prince presume to allege before you, That tho' he levied troops and menac'd war, 'T was only to review your people's strength, And keep their arms in use. AMGAR. Forbear, Forbear! Nor urge in malice aught against the Prince, Whose griefs too much oppress him! ARTAMON. Was it for this, The Czar, victorious, led his powerful troops From fam'd Pultowa?—took from the vanquish'd Charles His very litter, and bore it in the triumph! Say,—has he trod the precipice of fate, To bring home laurels never gain'd before, Not e'en in ancient Rome,—not by great Alexander, Thus to be brav'd by boys? Guards without. Make Room,—the Prince! Enter Alexis in Chains,—Fedrowitz, &amp;c. CZAR. Give me some pause;—affection struggles yet, And almost threatens justice.—Well, my proud boy, Say—are your troops arrang'd?—all disciplin'd, To shake our very throne?—Time may do much; By proper exercise they'll gain such strength, Our life will be in danger. ALEXIS. Never—I swear, Could such a thought infect my loyal bosom, For loyal still it is. CZAR. What dare you urge In mitigation of your guilt—your trait'rous guilt, Wrought 'gainst a parent's love? ALEXIS. Nothing, dread Sire! CZAR. A fuller answer, boy, might please us better. ALEXIS. What can I plead in my defence?—Your frowns Already have condemned me;—else might I urge A mother's claims, a mother's matchless virtue, But there your ears are closed against me; there You most have been abus'd.—For me no more Ambition held its charms;—I had given up My hopes, my views to empire,—I had lost, Unknowingly alas! my father's love; That once removed, what then was left for me? 'Twas that I coveted in happier days; The world was all indifferent. ARTAMON. To the point, Prince! Did you not levy war against the head Of this all-righteous King?—speak to that point; That's an offence beyond the reach of mercy; But when I weigh— Who that King was, how tenderly allied, That all his glories were but heap'd for you, I'll think—but will not speak. FEDROWITZ. Restrain his malice; Let not his tainted tongue profane the air With plotted calumny,—let not such arts Plead against all affection,—affection, Which here has every claim;—I rais'd the war,— Nor can you wonder, when a sister's fame Was treated with such baseness. ARTAMON. The witnesses Will soon approve the truth of what I've utter'd, If proof shall still be wanting,—the Czar himself Will judge “the arts” I've us'd; “my tainted tongue” Shall still attest a duteous subject's zeal, Tho' check'd by proud rebellion. CZAR. No witnesses! The boy proclaims his guilt, and this proud traitor Shall meet the death he merits. FEDROWITZ. I embrace it; Worth lives with honour, or it dies with glory; But oh! in mercy to the noblest youth, In mercy to yourself, forbear to doom His guiltless life, lest you hereafter feel The keenest pangs, the bitterest remorse, E'er wreck'd a parent's peace. CZAR. I were unworthy To reign the guardian of my trusting people, If I could suffer any private interest To sway the public weal;—like the fam'd father Who doom'd his only son in ancient Rome, I'll triumph in my justice;—how shall we hold The sceptre of our State with honour'd rule, If we protect the first offender in it, In treason and aim'd parricide? FEDROWITZ. Ah! cruel Czar! The Prince had rival claims, a mother's wrongs; A mother's injur'd honour urg'd his vengeance; If he has been to blame, I was the cause, And yield my life the forfeit;—in time relent, Nor by attending to the forked tongues Of foulest slanderers, sign, in your once-lov'd son, Your own death-warrant. ARTAMON. If insurrection Shall thus destroy your power; if treason Unawed shall dare to take a father's life, I'll only thank high Heaven, in mercy to me, That I'm no parent. ALEXIS. I plead not for myself; I plead but to attest my mother's wrongs, And ask but to redress them;—shield her fame From the rude blast of envy, raise her up From the dark cell of sorrow, where she lies, And place her 'midst the stars;—her spotless faith Will show the fairer for its eminence; Angels will register the glorious act, And fix the seal of truth. CZAR. Think'st thou, base boy, I would in conquest's lap a serpent rear To prey upon my vitals, when I am sure— Nay—when conviction stares me in the face, Broader than glaring day?— ARTAMON. The Czar convinced!— There needs no further witness of the shame Of this once-honour'd Queen;—ere at Pultowa The Czar decreed her fate, he well examin'd The proofs of all her guilt:—guilt like this Shrinks from the public eye:—such adultery The mind recoils against;—the falt'ring tongue Almost is damn'd that names it. CZAR. Prove her guilt!— A thousand witnesses proclaim her crimes, But I will spare the repetition, lest her life Become the immediate forfeit, and her friends Experience every proof of lingering torture. ARTAMON. Had the Queen aught to have offer'd in excuse, Or for herself, or son, she had appear'd— She had permission for't. ALEXIS. She will not plead, To count out tedious hours in dread suspense, Or lingering expectation;— Thrice arm'd with innocence, she dares defy A host of viperous tongues, tho' darkly fraught With all the subtleties of hell;—she boldly asks For truth alone and justice; and for myself, No villain's guile shall shake my steady mind; If my stern father thinks I've made atonement, If yet he deigns to own that sacred name— In pity to my youth, he'll spare my life;— If not,—he'll take it! CZAR. Ah! so stubborn, boy, I will no longer pause—the traitor dies; My very throne would shake, my altars tremble, Nay more, I hazard all my people's love, Should I forbear the sentence;—to prison with him, And ere the second watch shall toll its knell, Thou, Artamon, proclaim his death. Enter Ottokesa, attended. OTTOKESA. Ah! Whither— Whither would you drag my child;—if he's condemn'd, O take his mother too;—I caus'd his crimes; In pity to my woes he took these steps, And levied war against you; but, oh! my wrongs, His mother's wrongs, might pull down fire from Heaven, Might rouse a world to arms;—my constant love— For here I will approve it,—here I swear, I will not leave, till you proclaim my truth, And save your guiltless son. CZAR. What woman's this? We thought to have call'd a culprit to the bar, And not a Queen to triumph. OTTOKESA. O spare those words! And say what fatal crime can so have wrought Your cruel heart to vengeance? CZAR. Adultery;— A thousand witnesses declare the shame; I've heard and I've determin'd. OTTOKESA. How easy 'tis for witnesses to swear What suits their monarch's will; there is a cause, A guilty cause, that makes you thus inhuman, To urge our timeless fates. CZAR. There is no cause But that of truth and justice;—hadst thou ne'er fall'n My love was once so rich, it was a cloud Against the beams of every other beauty. FEDROWITZ. Let my life be the atonement, spare your son, Your spotless once-lov'd wife; for oh! 'tis sure Some villain has traduc'd her, and when the fire Of present love abates, you then will feel, You then will own your guilt. ARTAMON. “Guilt!”—'tis blasphemy! Away with him this instant, and the Czar Will then proceed to sentence Ottokesa. OTTOKESA. I know my sentence well—I read it there. [To Art. But oh! by all the ties of deep affection,— Relent, and save your son. CZAR. 'Tis now too late; Here is the instrument, and here I swear, Unless he give up all that ever dared To further his rebellion—here I swear, No power shall make me yield,—not Jove himself Shall shield him from destruction! ALEXIS. Know, then, dread Sire, I boast that virtue in me that resists Such proffer'd pardon; think'st thou those gen'rous bands That bore me up in adverse fortune e'er Shall feel my accusation?—oh! no, by Heav'n! I here declare, I'll honour them till death, Will wear their friendship nearest to my soul, Till that soul take its flight! CZAR. Break up this instant! No more a war of words—the traitor dies. Tho' my heart burst with grief the traitor dies. OTTOKESA. Never by you,—for here I'll cling for ever,— Will not release,—no power shall drag me from you, I take his fate;—stop—murder me this moment, I'll say I'm guilty—swear I have offended, Be truly guilty then, so you will spare My dear, my only child. CZAR. Unloose her hold;— Guards seize them both, and bear them straight away,— Her to the Tower, the traitor-boy to fate. [Exit Czar attended. ARTAMON. Be speedy, Guards, and know your duty well. Your every hope depends on your obedience. ALEXIS. Let me embrace my mother ere we part! ARTAMON. 'Tis all too late; away with them this moment. OTTOKESA. Inhuman slaves! No mercy!—Vengeance, Heaven! [Exeunt. END OF THE FOURTH ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT V. SCENE I. The Prison. Ottokesa discovered in the Cell.—Olaria, on the front ground, with an Attendant. OLARIA. Alas! ill-fated Queen!—lo! where she lies In yon drear cell!—sad spectacle of woe! When will her sufferings cease? Sometimes I've hopes that a refreshing sleep Might yet alleviate,—and then again, When the wind murmurs through these hollow vaults, I think she has breathed her last.—What noise is that? Hark! sure some hasty steps!—my friend retire— And wait awhile without. Enter Catharine, veiled. Ah! who art thou, That look'st so like a sister of affliction? CATHARINE. A very wretch, who from the height of bliss Am plung'd into despair.—Where is the Queen? OLARIA. Behold her in yon dungeon!—Misery like hers Might force a tear from marble-hearted guilt, And make it own its crimes.—See her approach! OTTOKESA. Whence this intrusion?— I thought that sorrow's mansions were held sacred:— Indeed I'm wretched;—why at my last sad hour Com'st thou to eye my woes? CATHARINE. Not to eye alone; To feel, to share, to pity,—to redress them. OTTOKESA. That's now beyond the utmost reach of art; A few short moments bear my child to fate, Nor shall I long survive. CATHARINE. Perhaps not all Are deaf to your complaints;—declare to me Whom most you do suspect; I yet may clear Your injur'd innocence. OTTOKESA. A blooming bride, A fatal fair, who steals unwary hearts, Whose beauty makes my crimes, while a fell slave, To aggrandize himself, stamps deep the ruin. CATHARINE. Lives there a wretch so vile to forge such crimes, And brand a guiltless name? OTTOKESA. Yes,—Artamon. CATHARINE. Ah! say'st thou—Artamon? OTTOKESA. Yes, he alone Has blown these fires betwixt the Czar and me. CATHARINE. Could Artamon alone assert your guilt, Could Artamon destroy your spotless fame, Could he thus urge the bolts of angry Heaven, And stalk in stern defiance? OTTOKESA. Yes, he,—that wretch; He watches every weakness of the Czar; Guilt made by him is fate. CATHARINE. Could Artamon?— OTTOKESA. What means this iteration of his name? Ere from Pultowa's siege the credulous Czar Came flush'd with conquest,—then this serpent sow'd The seed of doubt in his once faithful breast; A fatal seed it is,—tho' small its birth, Yet in a fruitful soil it soon will spread, And poison all beneath its baneful branches. CATHARINE. You say that Artamon forced up this plant;— Excuse my freedom, Queen, but know hereafter This may unravel to the Czar a tale, A wondrous tale, That may redress and save you. OTTOKESA. Never! never! Love has escaped his breast,—I've wearied him; Another there has fix'd the seat of empire On Ottokesa's ruin. CATHARINE. But let me plead! OTTOKESA. I guess you come from Catharine;—tell the Queen I ask not for myself,—'tis now too late; But if she will entreat to save my child, I'll die, and yield forgiveness. CATHARINE. I seize the gift— A gift that Heaven imparts to cheer my soul In my life-weary path—important gift— I am—I am that Queen. [Kneels, and seizes Ottokesa's hand, throwing up her veil. OTTOKESA. You much amaze me. CATHARINE. Indeed I'm innocent of all your wrongs,— Indeed I am;—I cannot tell you now; Time presses on us, and your son's in danger;— Go to the Czar,—plead there your injur'd fame, Strain every power that may reclaim his heart, I'll fly before, and urge him to compliance;— Though death lay arm'd to bar me—I'll entreat,— I'll be myself the sacrifice, and cheerful take Your miseries on my head.—Follow, I say. [Exit Catharine. OTTOKESA. I fear I've been too hasty;—pardon, Heaven! Pardon, that lost in thy mysterious ways I've dared arraign thy justice,—perhaps e'en now, Tho' to the sickly eye of deep despair My woes were past redress,—e'en now perhaps Thy mercy meant to save me;—if 'twere so I've been indeed a wretch;—I then am guilty. SCENE II. The Palace. Czar, Artamon, Guards, Attendants. CZAR. How goes the hour?—the very watch of night Seems to betray me to prolong his life; Nay I betray myself; my heart relents To think I've doom'd a son. ARTAMON. Is not the Czar The father of his people? is one so dear To hazard all the flock,—to wake rebellion, And sanctify misrule? CZAR. Thou art no parent; THE CZAR, Else would'st thou plead for mercy, and nature here Would second all thy kindness;—but thou art rough, Bred up alone to war, and keenly feel'st The danger only of the public safety. ARTAMON. Your wrongs will justify my rugged zeal, And urge me on to vengeance. Did not a cloud of witnesses arise, Accusing Ottokesa?—you doubted there, Till the son's guilt confirm'd the mother's baseness. CZAR. No,—there I was always fix'd,—the traitress dies; Her shame would haunt me else in midnight dreams, And Catharine would have cause to doubt my love;— Hark! the dreadful bell!—'tis the first hour,— Again I'll see my boy;—ere the second watch Hath toll'd its knell we'll take off Ottokesa;— Guards, execute our will! Enter Catharine. CATHARINE. In pity stop, Or through this breast make out an easy way To rid me of my life! ARTAMON. Ah! what mean'st thou? What madness brings thee here at this late hour To stop the course of justice?—Hence I say! CATHARINE. I come to plead the cause of injur'd truth, To plead for innocence most basely wrong'd, To swear by every power, unless you spare The guiltless Queen, you shed your Catharine's blood. ARTAMON. Forbid her hence! Prosperity too great Hath overthrown her reason. CATHARINE. 'Tis reason prompts,— I speak the truth;—I here abjure the throne I never sought for;—happy in your love, [to the Czar. Happy alone with you, I could have shared The wintry blast, or brav'd the howling desert; But now another claims the rightful crown, And hurls me down a precipice of fate. CZAR. Never! I swear;—I would not part with thee For ocean's wealth, for the united sway Of the world's empire. CATHARINE. Too true, you must; You much have been abus'd—by one, I fear, Whom least you have suspected;—he—I say— ARTAMON. Now fly this instant, or by my daring soul This dagger ends thy life. [Half draws a dagger. CZAR. Seize him this moment! There's something more in this!—I stand amaz'd!— 'Tis more than honest rage that prompts such vengeance. ARTAMON. Zeal—zeal for my Sov'reign's safety,—zeal for him, Who rais'd this dross from the neglected mine, To glitter on his throne. CZAR. Such zeal betrays thee. CATHARINE. Oh! yes;—the tale I have to tell will chill, Will freeze thee into horror, curdle thy blood, And almost make thee curse that once bright hour That gave thee being. CZAR. Speak quickly all the truth. CATHARINE. Know, then, before that day, that fatal day, You took me for your bride, he did enjoin An awful secret,—so enforc'd its weight— ARTAMON. Nay, then there's nothing left but instant death; So take it!— CZAR. Ah! is it come to this?—Guards, Disarm the traitor! ARTAMON. By every power—she lies! CATHARINE. Before this fatal hour I never form'd The least surmise of Ottokesa's virtue. He told me she was sentenc'd by the laws, Or I had plung'd into the depths of fate, Ere lived to wound her peace. CZAR. I do believe thee. CATHARINE. Here then I quit your throne, and here I swear, I'll sooner wander o'er the earth forlorn, Than rise on guilty steps. CZAR. But yet, the secret! The secret!—speak; for still I'm on the rack! CATHARINE. Ambition prompted it,—that fatal flame Burnt up the seeds of virtue;—you he found Were apt to think what interest made him speak; You knew my birth was mean,—knew 'twas ignoble, But oh! you knew no then the guilty truth, He—he was my Father! CZAR. “Father!” dost thou say? Guards, bear him hence, drag him to instant tortures! CATHARINE. Oh stop—in mercy stop, and timely think He is my Father still,—and tho' his guilt Be past atonement;—tho' his boundless pride Made me the victim,—doom'd me to worse than death; Yet should they execute your dread command, His child becomes a parricide,—speak, great Prince, In pity speak, and say that you will save him. CZAR. Spare me that question now,—my heart's too full Of all his frauds, his artifice, and guilt, To think of ready mercy;—yet for thy sake Whom I must ever love— CATHARINE. Not as your Queen; The very throne would tremble, should I now Attempt the violation. CZAR. My dearest life, I cannot part with thee;—yet, Ottokesa— Oh! I am torn with fierce conflicting passions! I now believe her true; but that fell slave Impress'd my soul with doubt, Stung me with ceaseless irritating darts, And circled venom round the throne of bliss. CATHARINE. Hence let me fly,—there is no time to pause, For see, she comes to claim the awful power, Unknowing I've usurp'd. CZAR. Stay—I entreat. Instant remove this traitor. [Artamon led off. Enter Ottokesa attended. Most injur'd Queen! Come to my arms, tho' thou can'st ne'er forgive me; And yet upbraid me not!—This excellence— For such she is, who most might have betray'd thee, Has pluck'd the seal from off my dark'ned eyes, And gives me now again to Ottokesa; Let me renew my love, restore thy power, And ransack thought to recompense thy woes. OTTOKESA. Those words had once been dearer to my soul Than any boon that Heaven could have bestow'd; But now life ebbs,—yet I delight to view you; I could not bear to think of your unkindness, And when I found my son was doom'd to death, That you were fix'd—were deaf to all entreaties— The world had nothing left; I then had trod the precincts of the grave, And all beyond was harmony and peace. CZAR. Run! fly this instant to the prison,—say, the Czar Demands his much-lov'd son—restores his life, And will with transport clasp him in his arms. OTTOKESA. That is a dawn beyond my utmost hopes; Had I known that, I would indeed have liv'd, And blessed you for your kindness. CZAR. The thoughts of death Haunt thy sick fancy still. OTTOKESA. They do indeed; Your cruelty—but oh!— I meant not to upbraid;—my son's dire fate I could not live to hear;—there, there was the stroke That plung'd me down into the last despair, And then—I then drank poison. CZAR. Call for all help! The world, the world to save her! OTTOKESA. 'Tis now too late. CATHARINE. I hope not yet,—I here will give up all, Relinquish Russia straight,—pray for your safety, Nor shall poor Catharine e'er be heard of more. CZAR. Look down All-righteous Power, and here behold Distress in the extreme;—point me to act As best becomes your will;—I'll dedicate My every thought to you;—give up my life— Give up—if yet it be demanded of me, What's dearer far than life,—a warrior's fame, My darling thirst of empire. OTTOKESA. Live, I charge you, Live—and be happy in this generous bride, Whose virtues, spite of fate, compel my love; Take then this last farewell. CZAR. I cannot bear it; I'll try art to force thee home to joy, Nor ever quit thee— OTTOKESA. I sink,—the tyrant now Grasps my cold heart,—the threads of life give way, Nor can I longer hold you. [Falls into the Attendant's arms. CATHARINE. Here, dear Queen! Recline yourself on me! OTTOKESA. Say, then, who are you? [Wildly. I cannot know you now;—the poison works, And racks my feeble brain,—'beseech you not To leave me yet;—I will not long torment you. CZAR. O spare this killing language I entreat thee; Precipitate and rash, my sudden rage— ('Twas Nature's curse)—too oft, alas! prevail'd, And led me on to deeds my soul abhorr'd. OTTOKESA. 'Beseech you, then, to bless my dying son With one kind look!—You now restore him to me, I hold him tho' expiring;—oh! my dear boy! They cannot force you now;—stand off, ye Guards, Ye never more shall tear him from me;—see— The Czar himself protects him—yields him to me, And shelters him with care! CATHARINE. Alas! she raves! OTTOKESA. I do not rave—(hastily)—I have him all my own, I have a father's warrant;—share the throne, Thy mother leads thee to it;—crowds rejoice, And crowds all hail the glories of thy rising; Hark, how they shout and rend the ambient air! I too would triumph, but my strength decays, Too feeble for this joy. CZAR. Be calm awhile; He is not yet arriv'd. OTTOKESA. I had him then; (hastily) As now my tender Lord (turning to the Czar) I took him to me,— He wip'd away the tears from my sad eyes, I shed as he departed. CZAR. No more of this! For now indeed he comes,—the Guards approach; Your son returns again, returns in triumph, Returns to grace our throne. Enter Officer and Guards. OFFICER. Alas! he's dead; By Artamon suborn'd, the treacherous Guards Struck ere the sign was given. CZAR. Heav'ns: 'tis too much; Man cannot bear such quick successive torture. OTTOKESA (to the Officer.) Did you not say my child was dead?—I thank you, Yea kindly thank you;— I was just struggling on the fatal brink, And this last sentence ends me. [Dies. CZAR. Farewell, for ever;— There sunk a glorious fabrick;—my child too!— What would I not revenge on this curs'd Artamon, But for my Catharine's love! CATHARINE. No more I'll see him; On some lone beach I'll mourn my weary hours In penance for his guilt,—make reparation To Heaven's high throne for his unheard of crimes, If not fore-doom'd beyond the reach of mercy. CZAR. Never! thou perfect Being, thou'r't all the hold I've left me on my journey;—soon as we've paid Sepulchral honours to their injur'd shades, Deck'd their cold tombs with tributary tears, Which I will plenteous shed,—live then, my Queen; 'Tis your's alone to reign, and bless my people. CATHARINE. My cruel father!— CZAR. Shall be for life imprison'd; His conscience be his executioner! But oh! consent to rule the State I've rais'd, 'Tis now my only wish. Tho' blinded long, and by a villain lost, Yet in the bright career of boundless fame I leave an envied track;—my setting sun Eclips'd with guilt, almost beyond atonement, Shall end in clouds with Me; but rise again With renovated strength, new-kindled fires, To show my Catharine to a gazing world.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">EPILOGUE, IN THE CHARACTER OF CATHARINE. Well—I've said all I can—but 'tis the vogue, And, Ladies, I must speak some Epilogue; Must yield to custom's all controuling sway, And turn to jest some Heroine of the Play; Must “pluck bright Honour” from its throne and state, And sink Queen Catharine down to vulgar Kate. Yet say, ye Fair, have Titles then no charms? The very question female hearts alarms; Titles, for which we barter real sway, And deck December with the gifts of May; Titles, for which, each earthly bliss resign'd, We yield a willing empire o'er the mind. For these, the Maid, such is the modern rule, Fraught with sage maxims from a boarding-school, Is hawk'd about in Fashion's dull parade, From Church to Court, from Court to Masquerade: “Lord! how delicious! what a charming creature! “Such symmetry of limb, such grace, such feature, “E'en frozen age, such ripen'd charms must move,— “To gaze, is here, another phrase for Love.” Straight to the wish some Mummy Lord appears, Fraught with experience of full fourscore years; The Peer, 'tis true, has somewhat pass'd his prime, But Bath repairs the ravages of time; Relations then are summon'd, writings made, In all the unmeaning round of law-parade; The Title only Miss's doubts removes, Papa still hesitates—Mamma approves: At length vast Settlements secure her power, And Special License crowns the midnight hour. My Lord, whom youthful beauty still inspires, “For in his ashes live their wonted fires,” In whose enraptur'd breast the embers glow, Like Ætna glimmering through a shield of snow, Unable to repress the ardent flame, Using each soft, each sympathizing name, In extacy supreme, while Wits deride, Tottering and boastful, dares essay the Bride. Their happiness complete is then the boast, Till hints besiege each circulating post; “Pray have you heard?—the world does say it's so,” “Caught in her chamber,—nay, I do not know,” “Pistol and Thorax See School for Scandal.” then complete the blow. Such is the scene that gilds their married life, A nauseous fondness, and a peevish strife, Ills heap'd on ills, and force repell'd by force, Till a third winter crowns the wish'd divorce; The Brother Cuckolds the dead Lord deride, The living Fair one blooms again a Bride. Have Titles then no charms?—Must the Fair scorn them? Titles add lustre, when the Great adorn them.</field>
   </doc>
</add>