<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Hoole, John, 1727-1803</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Hoole, John, 1727-1803</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">hoole john 1727 1803</field>
      <field name="author_text">Hoole, John, 1727-1803</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1800's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V2.0888.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240355</field>
      <field name="date_text">1800</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460408</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Discovery of Joseph ; A Sacred Drama</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Discovery of Joseph ; A Sacred Drama</field>
      <field name="title_facet">discovery of joseph</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">discovery of joseph</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Discovery of Joseph ; A Sacred Drama</field>
      <field name="year_display">1800</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1800</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1800</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460408&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460408&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Hoole, John, 1727-1803&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;hoole john 1727 1803&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Discovery of Joseph ; A Sacred Drama&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;discovery of joseph&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1800&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1800&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Hoole, John&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1727&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1803&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Discovery of Joseph&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Sacred Drama&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for Otridge and Son ; R. Faulder [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1800&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872751-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv20888&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Discovery of Joseph&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Sacred Drama&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 55 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted&lt;lb/&gt;Poetry omitted&lt;lb/&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: The discovery of Joseph.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Drama.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1800.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Unknown.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE DISCOVERY OF JOSEPH: A SACRED DRAMA.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PERSONS OF THE DRAMA. Joseph. Benjamin, his Brother. Judah, his Brother. Simeon, his Brother. Asenetha, Wife to Joseph. Thanetes, Confidant of Joseph. Chorus of Jacob's Sons.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Scene, Memphis.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PART THE FIRST. Joseph, Thanetes. Jos. None of the Hebrew brethren yet return'd? Than. None yet, my lord. Jos. Hast thou dispatch'd, to explore The public ways? Than. I have; but sent in vain Full many a messenger. Jos. Yet not so far Is Mambre's valley from these regal walls, But since they parted hence, their tardy feet Might long ere this have measur'd back the way. Than. Forgive me, if I know not what to think Of such concern: a few poor simple shepherds Appear an object far beneath your care. Jos. [aside.] Thanetes little thinks these simple shepherds Are Joseph's brethren—[to him.]—I'm offended, friend, To find myself deceiv'd: to these I gave In charge to bring with them, at their return, Young Benjamin, old Jacob's latest born. Thou heard'st with what unwilling lips they vow'd To do my bidding. Than. But your wisdom well Secur'd compliance, by detaining one A hostage for their faith: if this should fail, The force of famine must again compel These Hebrews back. The barren provinces Yield not sufficient nurture to sustain The pale inhabitants: the blighted corn Dies in the blade, or shoots not from the soil. The feeble shepherd mourns his lessening flock, The famish'd cattle chew the unsavoury stubble Unmeet for nourishment: the husbandman, With trembling feet, each field explores in vain For life-sustaining food; while Memphis only (Such thanks to you we owe) abounds with plenty Of well-stor'd harvest, and the afflicted world To fly from famine, all repair to Egypt. Jos. If Benjamin, a victim to the rage Of envious brethren, should no longer live, What hopes to see him here? Than. And whence, my lord, Can such suspicions rise within your breast? Jos. The boy was Jacob's hope. Than. What then? Jos. Myself, Myself, like him, have known the calumny, The treacherous wiles of deep fraternal envy.— O! powerful King of Heaven! protect and save him. Than. What means this tenderness for one unknown? Jos. My life with Benjamin's is nearly pair'd, His fortune bids me recollect my own, By nature to compassion mov'd, We feel the griefs of those, Whose hapless destiny has prov'd The touch of kindred woes. A sympathy the heart constrains To pity the distrest; When, by our own, we judge the pains That rend another's breast. Than. And this, shall this suffice to make you wretched! Alas! how true, that here on earth is found No perfect happiness: for if to pass From life's worst evils to the highest rank Of human honours, be indeed a blessing, Who should like you rejoice? A slave, a stranger You came to Memphis; slander'd by a base Unhallow'd tongue and bound in cruel chains, Your life was forfeited, when righteous Heaven Declar'd itself for Joseph: future time Was open'd to your view: to one your words Greatness presag'd, to one they menac'd death. All Memphis heard your prophesies: the king Perplex'd recurr'd to you; your wisdom solv'd His anxious doubts; disclos'd the impending evils, And shew'd the remedies: th' event declar'd Your counsels just. Behold you now remov'd From prison to the palace; see your fetters Exchang'd for glittering gems and costly robes, Sublimely seated on the regal car, You pass those ways, which once your feet had trod A shackled prisoner; hear your name proclaim'd The SAVIOUR OF MANKIND. Now minister Of king and people, ripe with blooming honours, Rich in a beauteous offspring, blest by all The grateful world, and highly lov'd of Heaven, It seems that nought is wanting to your wishes; And yet amidst this unexampled flow Of earthly blessings, your inventive mind Can for itself create unthought-of evils. Did every outward feature show The inward pangs of secret woe, How oft would those our pity know, That now our envy move. 'Twould then be seen, in many a breast, What cruel foes their peace molest; And those, who seem to us so blest, As wretched then would prove. Jos. Thanetes, go—Asenetha approaches. Forget not my command: if Jacob's sons, If Benjamin should come, return with speed To welcome their arrival. Than. I obey. My gracious lord, henceforth be to yourself What you are still to others; every comfort You give to them, but to yourself distress, You heal another's pains, but feed your own. Asenetha, Joseph. Asen. My consort, is Asenetha permitted To ask a boon. Jos. The doubt, my love, offends me. Asen. Release the Hebrew prisoner from his bonds. Jos. Simeon? Asen. The same. Jos. But what excites thy pity For one thou know'st not? Asem. And what rigour, say, Has mov'd you to the punishment of one, Who ne'er to you was guilty? Jos. And how know'st thou That he is innocent? Asen. His crime I see not: His punishment is present to my sight. Jos. And is it less a crime because unknown? Asen. But yet it merits sure, forgive me Joseph, A judge more merciful. Jos. But not unjust. Asen. Alas! my lord, without the touch of pity, Justice were cruelty. Jos. And but for justice, Pity were weakness. Asen. Let us imitate The CAUSE of ALL, who sheds his kindly rain Alike on good and wicked: equal HE Wills that his blessed sun should shine on both. Jos. Who seeks to be like him, sometimes must scourge, For their correction, those whom most he loves. Asen. But what you feel for Simeon, pardon sir, By outward signs more hatred seems than love. Jos. Condemn me not too soon. How apt is man To judge of others harshly! Wretched fruit Of blind self-love! The blame we cast on others Is flattery to our pride: we seem to gain That which we take from them; and ever seek To find companions of our faults in others, Or faults which we have not; and hence it comes We change the names of things: fear, in ourselves, Is prudence call'd, and meanness, modesty. But seen in others, modesty is meanness, And prudence fear. 'Tis hence we ever prove So partial to ourselves; and hence it comes With slow belief we join the voice of praise, While censure ever finds our open ear. Ah! still with hasty judgment fear To view another's deed; For what may cruelty appear, From mercy may proceed. More cautious weigh whate'er can move Your thoughts to vain surmise: As cruelty may mercy prove, So mercy may chastise. Asen. If you refuse to set the prisoner free, At least consent to hear him: this, my lord, You will not sure deny. Jos. I grant thy suit: Bring Simeon hither. [to a servant] Little does she know The secret treason once employ'd against me; That Simeon is my brother and my foe. [aside. Asen. Thus by his speech, his action and his looks You may divine his innocence or guilt. Jos. Fallacious signs, Asenetha, are these. 'Tis not for us to penetrate the secrets That lurk within the heart: the mortal sight Views but the outward semblance: God alone Beholds the soul of man. Asen. But oft the soul That actuates life, impresses on the body Such strong emotions, that the passions lie Unveil'd, and looks and gestures speak the man. Each tree will by its aspect show Whate'er defect is hid below: By leaf and fruit and flower we know What from the eye the root conceals. In vain the face may features wear To veil the mind's corroding care; While borrow'd smiles would peace declare, A look the war within reveals. Joseph, Asenetha, Simeon. Jos. See, Simeon comes—[aside.] O! could he but divine That Joseph lives in me—Eternal Justice! Behold him in my power; behold him bound, Bound in a brother's chains whose life he sought! —Shepherd, draw near. Sim. Thus prostrate, mighty lord, Thus humbly at your feet— Jos. Rise. Sim. [aside.] Sure that voice— What means that likeness? Wherefore do I tremble? Why have I lost all courage? Asen. Speak. Sim. I dare not: I feel, I feel in presence of your lord A sudden coldness freezing at my heart. Jos. [aside.] Remorse has touch'd him, yet he knows not why. Jos. Shepherd, thy name— Sim. Thou know'st it well—'tis Simeon. Jos. Thy country? Sim. Carra. Jos. And thy father? Sim. Jacob. Jos. Thy mother? Sim. Leah. Jos. Who are those that came With thee companions at thy first arrival? Sim. My brethren. Jos. Was not Jacob then a father To more than these? Sim. Alas! alas! he was: The beauteous Rachael bore him other sons. Jos. Their names were? Say. Sim. Joseph and Benjamin. Jos. Why came not these with thee? Sim. The youngest stay'd To cheer his aged father. Jos. And the elder? Sim. O! powerful God!—the elder— Jos. Speak—what follows? Sim. I know not what befel— Jos. [aside.] But well I know. Asen. [aside.] The colour leaves his cheek. Jos. Tell me at least— Does Joseph live? Sim. His father mourns his death. Jos. Is he then dead? Sim. To us his fate's unknown. Jos. Thy words but ill agree. Sim. Yet truly spoken. Jos. But what was Joseph's fortune? Sim. Mighty lord, Speak not of Joseph more—his name alone Is tenfold anguish to the heart of Simeon. Jos. What crime has he committed? Sim. None—O! none. Jos. Perhaps, ungrateful to a tender father, False to his brethren's love, with impious guile He sought your lives, and merits now your hatred. Sim. O! he was innocent, was just to all— Ah! sir, what have you ask'd? How wak'd remembrance To dreadful images! Dismiss me hence; For pity's sake dismiss me to my dungeon: You know not how you rack me—O! that look Has wither'd all my strength, and every question Infixes in my breast a thousand stings. O! mighty God! I now behold The tears that down his features roll'd; The tears of innocence and truth. I hear his sighs, I hear him mourn, Thus from a fire's embraces torn, In all the bloom of early youth. Jos. [aside.] My soul is mov'd!—O! let me now, to give His sorrows ease, reveal the brother—no— Time is not yet mature—[to him] Thy doubtful words Increase my first suspicions; while to this Thy brethren's long delay— Joseph, Asenetha, Simeon, Thanetes. Than. His brethren, sir, Are now arriv'd. Jos. And Benjamin? Than. Behold him; Observe that stripling who with tardy steps Now lags behind the rest. Jos. [looking out.] O! powerful nature! How do I trace in him a mother's likeness! [aside. —Thanetes, go; prepare the friendly banquet: Let Simeon be releas'd from bonds, and you, Ye shepherds, now draw near—[aside.] Betray me not, My yearning heart! Joseph, Asenetha, Simeon, Thanetes, Judah, Benjamin, and the rest of Joseph's brethren. Judah. Our promise, mighty lord, Behold fulfill'd: behold us once again Thus prostrate at your feet: then cast aside Your former doubts, and now vouchsafe to take, With every zealous vow of grateful homage, These presents offer'd here. Jos. What presents? Say. Judah. Accept our humble tribute here, The balm of many an odorous tear Distilling from the Arabian tree: The liquor sweet, as crystal clear, The produce of the labouring bee. In gifts like these no wealth is shown; But what we give we boast our own, The fruits of simple industry. Jos. I take your offer'd presents: rise, my friends, Say, is your father well? The hoary Jacob Of whom ye spake, say does the good man live? Judah. He lives, your servant lives, but bow'd beneath The weight of years. Jos. And Benjamin, the youth Of whom ye spake? Judah. Behold him here. Jos. My son— [aside.] O! how his fight alone affects my soul! [to him.] Heaven! O my son, be watchful o'er thy days, And keep thee still.—[aside.] O God! what sudden tumult Of bursting passion! [to him] Still, my son, preserve— [aside.] My eyes o'erflow with tears—I can no longer Restrain their course—O! let me seek elsewhere To hide me from their presence. [retires with Thanetes. Judah, Simeon, Benjamin, and the rest of the brethren. Benj. Does he then Abruptly leave us thus? Judah. I know not, brethren, What mean those broken accents. Sim. Ah! too surely He has till now conceal'd, beneath the veil Of placid looks, the anger in his bosom. Judah. Who knows for us what Fate has next prepar'd? Benj. Whither, my brethren, would you lead me now? Sim. We merit all we feel: for Joseph's sufferings The Almighty now pursues us: prayers and tears Alas! avail'd not him. Judah. In vain I urg'd, Touch not the guiltless youth, and lo! from us His blood is now requir'd. Judah, Simeon, Benjamin, the rest of Joseph's brethren, Thanetes. Than. Shepherds, my lord Requires your presence; he would have you share With him the social banquet. Sim. Ah! some snare Is surely laid for our unhappy lives. Benj. O! what a day is this! Judah. O! fatal banquet! Than. Why loiter thus? Come shepherds, let us go. Judah, Simeon, Benjamin, and the rest of Joseph's brethren. All. Great God of Israel! hear; defend thy people. Chorus. Great God of Abraham! we confess our guilt, But we are still thy people: deal not then Thy judgments strictly; for before thy sight What living soul shall e'er be justify'd? And whither, whither shall we fly to shun A God incens'd but to a gracious God? Our hopes, our fears, on thee alike depend, On thee our Judge, our Father and our Friend! END OF THE FIRST PART.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PART THE SECOND. Joseph, Thanetes. Jos. Hast thou observ'd my bidding? Than. All is done. From me the Hebrew brethren have receiv'd The corn thou gav'st in charge, and in the portion Consign'd to Benjamin I have conceal'd The silver chalice, us'd by thee at banquets And solemn auguries; and this to them Unknown, the shepherds are with joy departed: But from amongst thy menials one at distance Pursued their steps; and scarce they shall have pass'd The city's gates, when he will seize and question Of their imputed theft, and then conduct them As criminals before thee. Jos. As I bade, Thou duly hast discharg'd—but whence the wonder Thy looks declare? Than. Who would not, gracious lord, But marvel at the strange discordant passions, Which I have mark'd in you? I've seen you lost In tender feelings and inflam'd with anger, All in the self-same moment. As a friend You welcome Jacob's sons, and then confus'd Abruptly leave them: to the festive banquet You bid them guests, and then with secret snares Would seem to seek their ruin. Benjamin You have distinguish'd by a thousand tokens Of tenderness and love; and yet on him Would fix the proof of this imagin'd crime. Jos. 'Tis not permitted thee, Thanetes, yet To fathom Joseph's thoughts. Go, bring once more These shepherds to my sight. Without enquiry To know my counsels, blindly thou obey My will unquestion'd, tho' obscure; nor think On thee my laws too rigidly impos'd. Each man, by social compact, must be subject To powers superior: these degrees are fram'd By God's high ordinance, and he whose will Resists his mightier's will, resists his God. Than. My zeal would not be rash, but when permitted Would humbly speak, or silently obey. Thy laws I honour, nor am yet to learn What duties suit the station of Thanetes. The servant ill his lord obeys, And forfeits all a servant's praise, Who each command presuming weighs, And first approves or blames. He slights th' eternal laws that bind The various stations of mankind, Who, mindless of his place assign'd, Himself a judge proclaims. Joseph alone. O! thou ETERNAL TRUTH! who read'st the secrets Of every heart, thou know'st if e'er I cherish'd Against my brethren aught of fell revenge. Almighty Power! for ever from my breast Avert such dire design, which still returns To plague its author; which employ'd on those Above our strength, is folly; on our equals, At least is dangerous: and on those beneath us, Is abject tyranny. The feign'd resentment My features wore, sought only from my brethren Repentance for the past: I only wish'd To set before them all the dreadful sufferings, To which the wicked tend, that thus the fear Of just reproach awaiting guilty deeds, Might henceforth teach them to abhor the crime. A mother such resentment wears, Soft pity in her eyes; Each moment threats, but still forbears Her darling to chastise. She lifts her hand, but lifts in vain, For ere her hand descends, In act to strike, her love restrains, And love the stroke suspends. Joseph, Asenetha. Asen. Alas! my lord, too truly have you spoken; I now reproach my own too easy faith. Jos. What since has chanc'd? Asen. 'Tis now a time for rigour. Thy guests ungrateful, who but late have left us, By fraud contriv'd to steal the sacred chalice Employ'd by thee to read events to come. Jos. What says Asenetha? Asen. I speak but truth. When by thy menials seiz'd, they firmly first Denied the charge. “Let him, whoe'er is guilty, Let him (they cry'd) be punish'd, let him die; And let the rest remain in Egypt slaves.” Thy ministers pursued their search, and found The unworthy theft conceal'd amid'st the corn Consign'd to Benjamin. The brethren then Lost all their courage: breathless, pale and silent, Without defence, they all with one accord Their vestures rent and wept in floods of anguish. Jos. Perhaps they are not guilty. Asen. Do my words Deserve so little faith? Jos. It was but now You thought them innocent, and now affirm That you were then deceiv'd. Who knows but soon You may, Asenetha, repeat the same, And call your present thought a new deception. Asen. Forgive me, consort, sure your frequent doubts Are carried to the extreme. Jos. And yet we never Exert sufficient caution: outward objects Are known but dimly by the soul, enclos'd “Within this wall of flesh.” Our partial knowledge The senses give, fallacious ministers! For these are ever subject to mistake: Yet, on their faith, we pardon or condemn With doubtful judgment. Asen. Ever must the soul Remain uncertain of the truth; and live Blind in her state of darkness? Jos. Yes, in vain We hope for light, unless in HIM we seek it, The sole, immutable, eternal fount Of light eternal! HIM the first, the greatest, The cause of every cause: in whom alone We move and live; who centers in himself Whate'er is good; light, spirit, peace and justice, And wisdom infinite, and truth and life! Asen. What heavenly splendor lightens in thy features! While, as thou speak'st, thine accents strike my sense With more than mortal sounds! I shake with awe To hear thy voice, and while thy soul seems rapt To God's high presence, here I lag below And feel the clog of this “sin-tainted mold.” As lost in gloomy woods I stray, I view beside me pale Dismay, Nor know what path must yet be tried. O! thou, my sun, reveal thy light; For who but thee can lead me right, My faithful counsellor and guide? Joseph, Asenetha, Thanetes, Judah, Simeon, Benjamin, and the rest of Joseph's brethren. Than. Behold the criminals. Asen. See where they lie, Stretch'd humbly at thy feet. Than. And not a tongue Dares break the solemn silence. Jos. Thoughtless men, What have ye done? Insensate! not to know My skill in divination. Judah. Mighty lord, How shall we answer? What can words avail? What plead in our behalf? Th' Eternal Power Too well remembers now our past offences— This day exacts the forfeit.—Mighty God! I feel thy hand avenging: well I see The secret workings of thy justice, arm'd Against the hidden deeds of sinful man. Behold the man with guilt opprest! By day, by night he mourns; By thee, his conscience, ne'er at rest, With flames unceasing burns, Till every treason in his breast Upon himself returns. Jos. Forbid it heaven, that Joseph e'er should take Such rigorous measures. No, the theft was prov'd On Benjamin: let him alone remain With me in servitude; and you, ye brethren, Return in freedom to your father's presence. Judah. How can we e'er return to Jacob's sight? Benj. Return, return! and I alone remain A slave in Egypt? Jos. Only thou: the rest This instant must depart. Benj. A little stay:— Ah! Judah, tell me, Judah, is it thus You keep your promise given? At least, my brethren, Refuse me not one tender last embrace. Alas! you all depart, and leave me here A guiltless prisoner! What will now become Of Jacob, aged Jacob, when he learns The fate of Benjamin his darling child? If yet your breasts compassion know, And feel a wretched brother's woe, For me to mourning Jacob go, And kiss for me a father's hand. Tell him his child alive remains, And still for him his love retains— But tell him not I live in chains, A slave, O! Heaven, in Egypt's land! Jos. [aside.] Be still my beating heart! Judah. And is there none, No hope to appease you? Jos. None: the word is given And must be now obey'd. Judah. Hear me at least Without resentment: hear me, gracious lord. Jos. What canst thou say? Dispatch. Judah. You well remember When first I came to Memphis. Jos. I remember I gave thee then in charge to bring before me Thy brother Benjamin: thou mad'st reply, His mourning father will not live, depriv'd Of him, his age's hope. I answer'd then: Think not without the child to see me more. Judah. On this condition we return'd to Jacob. Again he urg'd us to revisit Egypt: “In vain” (I cry'd) “our journey, if the youth, If Benjamin remain.” “And how (he said) Can Jacob live, depriv'd of all his sons? Alas! alas! I bore of Rachel's love Two pledges only: one, O! Heaven! the first, Was made to savage beasts a bleeding prey: You knew it well, for you, my sons, you brought The fatal tidings—him I saw no more! If now this second leave me, should some chance, Some dismal chance, o'ertake him on the way, You hasten to the grave my hoary age.” Meantime the famine now increas'd: what then, What then could wretched Jacob? If he still Retain'd his Benjamin, he died with want; And should he part from Benjamin, the grief Of such a parting kills him: “O! my father,” (I thus at length) “O! father most belov'd! To me instrust him: if I see thy face Without the child, to all succeeding time Impute to me the guilt.” He heard, believ'd My plighted faith. I parted and fulfill'd Your strict command. Now hear me, gracious lord; Thou art a father and hast been a son: O! for a moment to thyself transplant Thy servant's feelings: can I stand before My father's sight without his trusted pledge? Ah! no—O! then let Benjamin return To sorrowing Jacob; I, and I alone, Will here in servitude for him remain: Ah! rather let me suffer all, than witness The frantic ravings of paternal sorrow. Jos. [aside.] My heart is rent—I cannot bear— Judah. Ah! why, Why dost thou hide thy face? Alas! in pity, If not for me, yet sure a wretched father At least may claim it—O! my gracious lord, Had you been present at this cruel parting! It seem'd as if his life and darling son At once were ravish'd from his aged breast. “Farewell” (he cried) and once again embrac'd him; Again to this, to that he recommends The weeping innocent; then calls on Rachel, Then recollects his Joseph; finds them both Trac'd in the features of his Benjamin; And finds in them his every loss renew'd, All!—all!—you weep—what means this gracious sign? Our woes have touch'd your heart—O! mighty God? Improve those kindly tears. Jos. Enough, enough— I can no longer hold—my dearest brethren, Know your own blood—I here abandon all My late assum'd resentment—come, O! come, Come to your brother's bosom—I am Joseph. Judah. Joseph! Benj. Eternal God! Sim. Ah! wretched we, Where shall we hide us now? Than. O! strange events! Asen. Most wonderful! Jos. No, let not the remembrance Of Joseph sold to bondage now afflict you: To that event, both Egypt and yourselves Have ow'd your preservation: to this land God sent me first but to prepare your way. Return, return, my brethren, to your father, Tell him the greatness of his son, and tell him To haste and share it with me. Silent still? Perhaps you yet may doubt me? Answer, Judah. Simeon, be comforted: draw near, my brother, My Benjamin! Asen. Was ever seen, Thanetes, A spectacle like this? Observe how all The impatient brethren crowd around my lord, While mingled passions strive in every face Of fear and gladness; On his forehead one Imprints an eager kiss; that, on his hand; This on his cheek, and that his vest, whilst he With equal warmth would answer all their loves And give them all himself. Their tongues can find No words distinct, and in th' excess of joy, Instead of words, they mingle tender tears. How well those struggling passions show, What language scarce reveals: From such a silence well I know, Whate'er the breast conceals. A joy sincere requires not words Its feelings to disclose; And little aid the tongue affords When bliss the heart o'erflows. Judah. O! merciful as just! Sim. O! generous brother! Benj. O! happy Joseph! Judah. Lo! thy dreams are now At length fulfill'd. Sim. Eternal Providence! To thee all human wisdom is but folly. By us was Joseph sold lest future time Should see us subject to him; and behold The same unfeeling act that gave him bonds, Has brought us here to worship at his feet! Judah. So God, the great disposer of events, In wisdom plans, that they who most oppose, Fulfill his secret purpose. Jos. O! my brethren, The strange vicissitudes of Joseph's life Must veil some secret truths. To you I came In love sincere, commission'd from my father; You sought my death; you sold me for a price To rude barbarians: then, a slave in Egypt, Accus'd and innocent, I bore the shame Without defence, and suffer'd punishment Due to my false accuser: plac'd between Two hapless criminals; to one my lips Predicted death, to one a happier change. In friendship now with them, so late my foes, I minister'd the food of life to them Who sought my death. I heard myself proclaim'd The saviour of the earth. Am I the image Of one far greater? Sure some mighty work Is ripening now, and Joseph's life is given A type and shadow by mysterious Heaven. Chorus. Insenate he, whose impious folly dares Oppose his God: he falls into the snares He laid for others, that at last enclose The wisest with inextricable woes. True Virtue, like a palm, all force defies, And, more opprest, shall still more vigorous rise. END OF THE SECOND PART.</field>
   </doc>
</add>