<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Dallas, Robert Charles, 1754-1824</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Dallas, Robert Charles, 1754-1824</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">dallas robert charles 1754 1824</field>
      <field name="author_text">Dallas, Robert Charles, 1754-1824</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1820's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V3.0140.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1823</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460574</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Adrastus ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Adrastus ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="title_facet">adrastus</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">adrastus</field>
      <field name="title_text">Adrastus ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="year_display">1823</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1823</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1823</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460574&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460574&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Dallas, Robert Charles, 1754-1824&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;dallas robert charles 1754 1824&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Adrastus ; A Tragedy&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;adrastus&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1823&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1823&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Dallas, Robert Charles&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1754&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1824&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Adrastus&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for James Cawthorn [etc]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1823&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872917-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv30140&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Adrastus&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 176 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Only verse drama included&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Adrastus.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1823.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Unknown.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ADRASTUS, A TRAGEDY</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Frui paratis, et valido mihi, Latoë, dones, et præcor, integrâ Cum mente, nec turpem senectam Degere, nec citharâ carentem. Hor.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">INTRODUCTION TO ADRASTUS. The following Tragedy is partly historical, partly imaginary. In the historical part the Author has been more solicitous to mark character than to adhere to chronology, which he has endeavoured to make subservient to his object. The point of time taken is that in the life of Crœsus, the Lydian king, when his boasted and proud prosperity received its first blow by the death of his son Atys, accidentally slain by a young Phrygian prince, named Adrastus. The event, with its circumstances, is related by Herodotus, in the first book of his History, to which the reader is referred, should he wish to compare it. The story of Adrastus and Atys, however affecting in the narrative, is too scanty for dramatic effect. It was necessary to animate it with the assistance of more vehement passions than grief; the Author has therefore imagined a character, in which love and revenge are made to struggle violently, and has so connected it with the historical event as to concur in the unity of the action. This is the only imaginary addition to the history. With respect to the anachronisms occurring, they will be evidently seen to have been contemplated, for the purpose of giving prominence to the historical character of Crœsus. For instance: the answers of the Oracle introduced in the third act are long subsequent to the time of action in the Tragedy; so are Crœsus's last exclamations on Solon; but they are historical facts, and mark his character. The Author was desirous to adhere, as much as possible, to the Classical rules respecting the Unities; being of opinion that it is only owing to a very superior power of fascination in the action, and in the portraiture of character, that the neglect of those of time and place is unattended with disadvantage. Of that fascination the English Stage, even without referring to Shakspear, has innumerable instances: yet are the Unities, in spite of Dr. Johnson's masterly defence of our great Bard's “designed rejection or happy ignorance of them,” founded in sound criticism. For that of time, the Author has protracted the action a whole day of twenty-four hours, but with an intervening night. To preserve that of place he has taken the liberty of transferring the scene of the Boar-hunt from Mysia to the neighbourhood of Sardis. Every Act is restricted to one spot, except the fourth, which the Author attempted to mould also according to the rule, but, unable to succeed, without a cosiderable conversion of action into narration, he preferred transgressing in a few instances. The principal personages are characterized as follows: Crœsus: amiable, hospitable, virtuous, and brave: but vain of his wealth, elate with his prosperity, and self-glorious. Atys: frank, candid, highly susceptible of friendship and amiable feelings: not subject to painful passions. Adrastus: mild and susceptible, deeply suffering grief, virtuous, and noble-minded. Ada: of violent passions, but not abandoned. Although the Author trusts that the Tragedy does not need illustration in order to produce effect, yet he hopes that the subjoined Notes will not be displeasing to the classical reader, and they may be useful to others.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">PERSONS OF THE DRAMA. Crœsus. King of Lydia. Atys. His son, married to Ada. Adrastus. An unfortunate Phrygian Prince. Orontes. His Friend. Philon. Minister to Crœsus. Rhodius. Courtier. Diomed. Courtier. 1st, 2d, 3d Peasants. Officer. Ada. A Carian Princess, married to Atys; but in love with Adrastus. Aryenis. Daughter to Crœsus. Aspasia. Confidante to Ada. Singers, Messengers, Officers, Guards, Hunters, Attendants, Male and Female; &amp;c.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Scene—Sardis, and its Vicinity.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. Scene—Mount Tmolus, with the River Pactolus issuing from it. The mountain Tmolus, near Sardis, the capital of ancient Lydia, was noted for its salubrity, and the country round it was delightful, as it is to this day. The river Pactolus rises in Tmolus and falls into the Hermus below Sardis, through which it flows. It brought in its descent a quantity of gold-dust. Larcher says, it had ceased to do this in the time of Strabo, that is, in the age of Augustus. According to Pliny it was essential in the cure of various diseases, by bathing. Enter several Lydian Peasants. 1st Peasant. Didst mark him, boy? 2d Peasant. Ay, father: and such a monster never these eyes beheld before. 1st Peasant. 'Tis a famous beast. 3d Peasant. 'Tis a frightful one. I would he were destroyed! He hath ravaged far and near. Last night he visited our pastures. 1st Peasant. He shall not long annoy us. The King hath said the word; and when was ever the word of Crœsus forfeited? 3d Peasant. Know ye if the Prince will join the hunt? 1st Peasant. It hath not reached our ear. There was much talk of his desire, yesterday, in Sardis; and they say his bride supports him in it, and makes urgent entreaty for the King's consent. 2d Peasant. I wonder much he should refuse; and she's a gallant dame to back his suit. 1st Peasant. Know you not, boy, 'tis from excessive love? 2d Peasant. 'Tis strange love to stand between his son and pleasure! Such pleasure too!—Thou lovest me, father, yet thou sharest in very thought the pleasure I shall have in this hunt. 1st Peasant. In thought, lad! Ay, and shall in act. But there 's no fear in my mind, seeing thy agility— Now in the King's mind, they say, there is. 2d Peasant. Why, father! the Prince is more agile far than I am—and with what skill and force he darts a javelin! 1st Peasant. True, boy! but then the King hath had a dream. 2d Peasant. A dream! 1st Peasant. Ay! a vision in his sleep.—I know not clearly the matter of it—it imported danger to the Prince. 2d Peasant. A dream! a vision! psha! And a man is to be mewed up in a cage for a dream! I'd break my mew, that I would, and hunt in the teeth of a thousand dreams. 1st Peasant. I like thy boldness, my son—yet the feelings of a father—they are something for a son to think of—and, in my mind, it is a glory to Prince Atys that he considers them in the King.—Stand back; here are some of his officers. Enter Rhodius and Diomed. Rhodius. Good morrow, friends!—We seek the masters of the steeds left this morning in the stable at the foot of Tmolus—Have ye passed a youth of princely port in your early ramble? 1st Peasant. The melancholy stranger who hath been some time at the court of our King, with another stranger, whose face is new to us, went forth on foot this morning, to round the hill and view the Gygean lake and Alyattes' tomb. This tomb and lake are still remaining. Rhodius. Spoke ye with them? 2d Peasant. We did, Sir—And I at first made offer of my service as guide where the Pactolus might be crossed; but soon withdrew it as unnecessary, on remembering the person of the Prince Adrastus. Rhodius. Thanks! 'tis he we seek.—Good day! 1st Peasant. (The Peasants going, stop.) Sirs! continues the hunt fixed for to-morrow? Rhodius. It does. 2d Peasant. Go the Princes forth to the hunt? Rhodius. Prince Cyno goes. But respecting his brother, nothing is yet determined. Have ye seen the creature? 2d Peasant. Ay, Sir! and traced his haunt. I was on the farther brow of Tmolus with the dawn, and saw him at the foot, wheeling from the pasture grounds, and making for the wood, eastward of the mount. I marked the entrance which he took; and with the first order of the huntsman, the nets, now ready, shall all be placed in due directions. Rhodius. To Sardis, then, where we shall meet anon. [Exeunt Peasants. Diomed. How bold and ready for the manly sport Our hardy Lydians show. Rhodius. 'Tis time indeed This roving monster should be made to bleed; Since forest-haunts no longer bound his range, But issuing nightly to the champaign lands, He dares attack the cultivator's crops— He dies to-morrow. Diomed. So the order runs: But may the coming of the Phrygian Prince Not stay the death? He is not scared by dreams— Should he enforce the ardour of his friend, Would Crœsus yield forthwith? He builds a hope, Or I mistake, upon the mournful cast Of young Adrastus' mind, for prudence form'd, And therefore ventures to declare his voice May sway the issue to the Prince's wish. But, trust me, Sir, this may is mainly built Upon that hope.—The melancholy youth Will counsel Atys to forego the chace. Rhodius. You do him wrong. Himself woe-worn, Adrastus Promptly promotes the joy he cannot share, And owns a heart too large for self to fill. Know you the circumstances of his grief? Diomed. Precisely, no. When first he came to Sardis I was at Delphi with the votive treasure. Ere I return'd, his story lost its newness, And was but little talk'd of—soon it died Away. He slew his brother, as I heard, His elder brother; and 'twas roundly said, To open for himself a ready way To Phrygia's lofty throne. Rhodius. Believe it not. His suff'ring ill accords with that report, The prompt suggestion of malignity. No, Diomed—the sad and fatal act, If not sheer chance, was wholly void of will. Some warmth indeed between the brothers rose— Yet friends—Nor, since the constellated twins, Did e'er fraternal love more lovely grow. It was not passion's sway.—They bred their quails For sport, as was the fashion of the place, And train'd them up, with beak, and wing, and spur, To feather'd war and sportive glory. Now, Those of Adrastus ever beat his brother's; Quail fighting was a diversion among the ancients. “And his quails ever Beat mine.” —Shakspear. And still prevail'd when last they urged the strife. Provoked, Prince Agathon his temper lost; Photius, alluding to Ptolemæus, says: “He also relates that the name of the person who, in the first book of Herodotus, is said to have been killed by Adrastus, son of Gordius, was Agathon, and that it was in consequence of some dispute about a quail. When, darting on the victor bird, in haste He grasp'd his wing, and menaced instant death. With eager effort to relieve his quail, Adrastus dash'd his brother to the ground, From which he never rose; for as he fell, And sudden was the fall, his neck behind Was penetrated by an iron pin, Jutting unheeded on the area's rail. Diomed. It open'd still the channel to the throne. Rhodius. It did—but to be fill'd with bitter tears Of the successor to the regal hope, If hope may mingle sounds with deep despair. Adrastus fled reluctant—forced to fly By form and rule—for anxious he to meet A doom severer than the law inflicts, Beseeching death for death. By Gordius urged, His father and his king, he fled, and bent His steps despondent to the court of Crœsus: The King received him with a royal heart, Where all that 's good and great essential blend. Diomed. And thence his happiness. Rhodius. The lustral water purified the Prince Un homme absous d'un meurtre involontaire, doit s'absenter pendant une année entière, et ne revenir à Athènes, qu'après avoir donné des satisfactions aux parens du mort; qu'après s' être purifié par des cérémonies saintes. —(Anacharsis, vol. ii. p. 349.) Lorsque, par l'effet du hazard, d'une haine personelle, ou d'une defense legitime, les heros avoient donné la mort à quelq'un, ils frémissoient du sang qu'ils venoien de faire couler, et quittant leur trone ou leur patrie, ils alloient au loin mendier le secours de l'expiation. (Anacharsis, vol. ii. p. 56.) By Crœsus' hands. Since which protection, love, Whate'er the heart can wish, the head devise, Has been essay'd to chase Adrastus' grief;— Essay'd in vain. The atoning year is rounded, And still his heart, his eye, his vesture mourns. Diomed. Methinks his friendship with our Lydian Atys Might well have press'd upon his lip the smile Which rises from the heart to share the bliss Of those we love, the while these nuptials lasted. Rhodius. That fruitless effort he at once disclaim'd; And, that no gloom might lurk about his friend, Withdrew, with Crœsus' ready granted leave, From happy Sardis' walls. The nuptial moon In absence spent, he now returns to court. Diomed. And to a painful office—for 'tis clear, Both sire and son he cannot hope to please. But see! they wind around the mountain's base, And close upon us. Enter Adrastus, Orontes, and Attendants. Rhodius. Prince Adrastus, hail! Welcome again to Lydia's friendly soil. Adrastus. Thanks, Rhodius, thanks! and Diomed, I judge. Diomed. The same, my lord, who joins in cordial welcome. Adrastus. I thank thee, Sir. How fares the King, I pray? Rhodius. Well, joyous, happy in himself, in all: But most impatient to salute Adrastus, Whom, as appointed, he expects to-day; And waits his presence to decide a point, Now in suspense between the Prince and him. Adrastus. Atys? Sir. Rhodius. He, with more impatience still, Charged us to meet your Highness on the way, With message full of loving eagerness And vehement entreaty, to alight West of the palace, and ascend his stair. Adrastus. Know you the import of the royal question? Friendly, no doubt, and readily resolved. Rhodius. Oh! full of love, my lord; like all the rest That rise 'tween Crœsus and the duteous Prince. Your Highness is aware of Crœsus' dream? Adrastus. I am.—But tell it to my friend Orontes, Who now o'ertook me, as he journey'd hither From my father's capital. Rhodius. Sir, 'tis brief. Crœsus, surnamed the Happy—justly styled, Since years roll o'er him with success and joy— While sleeping on his couch, in vision saw His son stretch'd on the ground, his side transfix'd With a deadly spear, writhing in his gore. The impression left disturb'd the Monarch's mind, For Atys then a Lydian army led. A summons straight he sends, the Prince recals, And by a marriage fixes him at court: The nuptial festivals are scarcely over. Adrastus. How wears the bride her Lydian glories? Rhodius. Well: But rapt at times, as 'twere, to other scenes. I've known the King recal her wand'ring mind. Adrastus. 'Tis as I fear'd—(aside)—That, Sir, will mend with time. Proceed, good Rhodius. Orontes. Came he freely home? Report adorns his name with martial ardour. Rhodius. And justly, Sir—Yet freely he return'd. Valiant and gifted, and in arms accomplish'd, To glory he aspires: but selfih views Fade in the brightness of his filial glow: He lives in cherishing his father's smiles. Adrastus. How just!—But to the point to me referr'd. Rhodius. Scarce second to the celebrated monster Of Calydon, a huge, insatiate boar Roams through the land, a thing unknown before, Making waste nightly to our very gates. Adrastus. The rumour reach'd me e'en at Ephesus. Rhodius. The King, entreated by the husbandmen, To quell the savage in his wild career Grants them his Indian pack. Adrastus. The tiger dogs? These are mentioned by Herodotus as kept by Cyrus, not Crœsus—they were very celebrated Indian dogs, whose sires were said to be tigers. Diomed. You know them well, my lord—and these to press Upon to morrow's noble quarry fires The imagination and the blood of Atys. Adrastus. Most likely 'twould—The sequel I perceive— Crœsus, alarm'd, withholds consent, the while Prince Atys warmly pleads—Is it not so? Rhodius. Not with more warmth than doth his bride, fair Ada, To whom the wary King, in fondness, yields To be decided by Adrastus' voice. Adrastus. I trust he'll yield without the reference. (To an Attendant.) See to our steeds, and hold them ready, Sir. (To Rhodius and Diomed.) Now hie ye on to Sardis—Good day! Sirs— Say to the Prince we follow close your steps. Rhodius. My lord, good day! Diomed. Your Highness' slave! Adrastus. Adieu! [Exeunt Rhodius and Diomed. (To the remaining Attendant.) Follow thy comrade, and abide our coming. [Exit Attendant. Adrastus. Orontes! (leans on him.) Orontes. Rouse thee, Adrastus! Rouse from useless sorrow, And give thy noble mind to other transports. Adrastus. Is it, Orontes, in the power of man To move at will the springs of grief and joy? Could we but rule those springs, we should be gods. Orontes. Howe'er dependent on external causes, We are, believe me, to ourselves untrue, Untrue to nature, if, when motives weigh More in the cheerful scale than in the sad, We suffer not the balance to decide. Time hath wrought happy changes. Now, no more Is Phrygia shut: the people love their Prince, And loudly call for his return: Gordius, the venerable Gordius too, Enough hath mourn'd a son the gods have ta'en, And wants but thee to kindle joys anew— These of themselves are springs of bliss, my lord. And then, your natal town, Celene fair! And your Meander, lovely, wandering stream: Shall they not cope with images of woe? Adrastus. 'Tis true, my friend, the sun hath made his round, And smiles benign on Phrygia's fertile plains; O'er my devoted head his annual course Hath brought him to the period of the law That terminates a forceful exile, And leaves Celene open to my steps— But oh! how stain'd!—how stain'd with precious blood! Celene! blest Celene, till this arm, This fatal arm, involved thy walls in woe! Mine was a smiling infancy, Orontes, And followed by a youth of joy and glory, Till that black day—What daggers fill the thought! Would I had died that day! Oh, Agathon! Oh, my brother! Would I had died for thee! Would I had died for thee, my Agathon! (Much agitated.) Orontes. Forbear this grief. Adrastus. Thou know'st with what a love Our hearts thro' life were to each other bound: In peace or war inseparable found! The jocund paths of youth we trod together, Enlarging social pleasure: or, for glory, In battle urging, side by side, the foe— He was my father's joy! (Weeps.) Orontes. My lord! my lord! Adrastus. I slew them both! (Greatly agitated.) Orontes. Not yet, my dearest lord! I pray bethink thee, ere your words prove true: Gordius still lives— Adrastus. As I do—no more. Live! Call you it life to creep upon the earth, To breathe; the produce of the soil consume, And sink into a vivid sleep of horror? Orontes. Add friendship, Sir, the keen pursuit of knowledge, Taste that creates Elysium in the mind, The voice of Fame, the popular regard, The power of beneficence, and the sway A prince's virtues hold o'er ev'ry heart. Adrastus. They want their necessary relish, Peace: That peace of mind, which I no more shall know. Yet am I not insensible, Orontes, To friendship's all-pervading influence: To thine, to that of Crœsus and his son. It does revive me, comfort me, my friend: And not unfrequently exalts my spirits. But, like those anodynes and pungent aids, Which learned leeches use to soothe the nerves, Its influence o'er,—and, oh! 'tis o'er too soon— The malady returns with double force; Black images the clouded brain infest, Disturb the sanguine current in the veins, Clog as they flow, and overwhelm the breast. Orontes. Deem not I vainly hope, or lightly speak, When I advise another medicine, More potent still than friendship—think of love. Adrastus. (Gently starting.) Love! Orontes. Believe me, 'tis a sovereign charm, Adrastus; And Lydia's Monarch boasts a lovely daughter. Adrastus. Love! Aryenis!—No, Orontes, no! Once through my brain the ardent image sped, And only once—it never reach'd my heart;— Or if it did, 'twas but to show the wrong I would not do to so much loveliness. Mine is no breast to pillow such a cheek, Which smiles should animate, not tears bedew. Besides, Orontes, I have warn'd the maid To guard against that passion, and control, With Wisdom's rein, emotions that would rule Despotic, if not early train'd to obey. Orontes. Well flows instruction from such youthful lips! Oh! learn from her's to curb thy passion's sway; Become her scholar, and forego thy grief. If taught by thee no other loves to seek, Be sure, Adrastus, that she loves already. Adrastus. Misconstrue not the maiden's mild regard: So loves she Atys and young Cyno too; Her brothers, Crœsus' sons. For me, perhaps Something of gratitude may intermingle, For that I won her thoughts to lofty themes, And open'd Grecian treasures to her ken. Orontes. The meeter she to grace a lofty throne, And bless Celene with a race of kings. Adrastus. Her virtues and her matchless grace combine To win the soul, and seem almost divine. Such beauty and such worth would lustre shed O'er worlds, Orontes.—Oh! had Agathon— Accursed arm! See, see! 'tis stain'd with blood! Orontes. Recal your thoughts—You speak of Aryenis. Adrastus. Yes; and of Agathon. Oh! had he lived, Celene had been blest with such a queen! Orontes. And shall be still. Adrastus. Desist, my friend, I pray; Nor sow in Fancy's warm and fertile soil Seeds that can blossom but to poison. Orontes. Think of young Atys' happy lot. Adrastus. Oh!—Thou hast rais'd a hydra to my view. Think of my Atys!—Tell me how to think, To speak, to act, to look.—Was 't not enough, Ye gods! to shed, to see a brother's blood! Why am I doom'd to live in treachery, And veil my feelings from the man I love? If there 's a curse that falls more heavily, More poignantly than conscious parricide, 'Tis the withholding of the lip from truth, Equivocating to the ear of friendship, Wearing a seeming which the heart abhors. Why, what a mockery is the state of man! Whose very virtues are at war within, And in their conflicts bear each other down! We must away. Orontes. What shakes thee thus, my lord? Adrastus. We must away from Crœsus' court, Orontes. For 'tis infested by a fiend more fell Than the enchantress of the Euxine shore— Ada— Orontes. I fear the sequel of your tale. Adrastus. The bride of Atys is my deadly foe. Orontes. While on your Dorian visit did you chance To slight her charms, or feign yourself enamour'd? Adrastus. Enamour'd? well express'd!—the very word Which best expounds the feelings of the moment. I was enamour'd—ay, enamour'd, Sir, Like many more—for few the flame escap'd, Her beaming graces kindled all around. As if she singled me from out the crowd, She darted from her eye the love she sought: Mine drank of beauty to intoxication, And I grew giddy with her sparkling wit. But wit and beauty captivate, not bind: The heart requires a stronger chain than either, Which sense and virtue must conspire to weave. I did not feign—but neither did I say How much I was enamour'd: yet, awhile Warm'd with the charm of novel ecstasies, I almost thought it was the charm of love. Orontes. In truth 'twas like—and if you almost No wonder she should wholly judge it love. What sudden gust could chill your amorous fancy? Adrastus. Passion.—I shudder at the thought, Orontes.— Gusts of ungovern'd rage, at first conceal'd, Broke their restraint, and gave her to my view A very fury, whose distorted eye Darted far other fires than those of love. She first dismay'd me by a sudden scowl, Which her bent brow dared aim against her father. Transient was that, and quickly clear'd by smiles, Those needful guards of beauty and of love. Orontes. That shews at least that some command she held. Adrastus. Nature, howe'er expell'd, resumes her sway. One morn, with idle steps, I gaily roved Within the precincts of the royal grounds, And, unobserved, approach'd a portico, Which Ada paced with agitated gait. In sportive humour, meaning to surprise, I lurk'd beside a column's base Architecture had made little progress in the time of Crœsus. But for the purpose of sustaining the splendour and magnificence of such monarchs on the stage, this anachronism in the progress of the Arts will be readily overlooked by the dramatic critic.—But soon A female slave, with hurried steps, advanced, Eager to repair some slight mistake, The petty causer of a furious storm, That raged within her lady's lab'ring breast. Oh! what a change was there! what alter'd mien! Those lovely features hideous grew and wild. A crimson'd cheek, a glaring eye, bent brows, Distorted lips, and bristling hair ensued, And gave to life Medusa's frightful head: She waved it high, and all her frame deform'd, Raised her clench'd hand, and struck the maiden's face. With pain, and shame, “Oh Mistress!” cried the slave. Awed and submiss, 'twas all she said, the while Her ministry she anxiously pursued. Had Hercules's arm assail'd my breast, The blow had shook me less than that which came, Reverberated from her humble cheek, In echo to the little slender hand That struck it. And oh! my Orontes! mark How beauty is with moral sense entwined! For what the Princess lost the slave acquired. Orontes. What followed? Adrastus. I, undetected, from the scene withdrew, And, saved from Love, resolved to leave the court. She saw the change, and swore to be revenged. Something of this I hinted once to Atys: But he, by filial love supremely moved, Nobly intent to gratify his parent, Refused his ear, and she became his bride— Sweet word of love!—but big with horrors here— From Sardis must I fly—but whither fly? Orontes. To Gordius' arms—the sire expects his son; Wide stand Celene's portals for her Prince; Once nestled there, thy grief shall wear away: We will not leave thee leisure thus to pine. Adrastus. Alas! I must not, cannot see my father: No, spare me that, my friend—'twere death to both. I'll back to Ephesus: thence o'er th' Ægean Take ship for Attica. Solon, they say, Is now at Athens. If I live, I'll gain The arduous knowledge that empowers to reign. If aught this bleeding heart may heal, 'twill be The making Phrygia happy, great, and free. END OF THE FIRST ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. Scene—In the Palace of Crœsus. Ada, alone. Ada. Where art thou, wretched Ada? Whither bends Thy restless step? thy wand'ring guilty eye, Eager to see the man thy vengeance dooms?— Adrastus comes, the insulter of my youth, Rejector of my love. Already here, Within the palace walls, and with his friend, Unconscious, planning schemes of future pleasure. Atys his friend! my husband—Husband! hah! What have I done? Profaned thy altar, Hymen; Mingled with thy fires the fire of vengeance, Not the flame of Love; binding hands, not hearts; Espousing Atys to destroy Adrastus, The surer to transfix his heart, that heart That could belie a face where sparkled love With smiles perfidious as the Syren's song. Away remorse and pity from my breast! Ye gods! avengers of your slighted powers! Confirm in me an Amazonian mind! And ye, fell sisters, dire Eumenides! Visit my bosom; sweep away all shame, All weak compunction, and become my guides In the black purpose of my burning soul, To wreak a signal vengeance, come what may, Though Sardis groan, and farthest Lydia wail; Or e'en this wretched frame in pangs expire.— For disappointed love, though love return'd, The dame of Carthage braved the lighted pyre: A fiercer sting oft darts from love disdain'd, Nor leaves its hold within a female breast, Till soothed by Vengeance, or by death destroy'd. Now, Phrygian! now beware thy loving friend! For Atys' self shall strike th' avenging blow. Enter Aspasia. Ada. Well! my Aspasia, has thou seen the youth? Aspasia. The Princes have embraced, and now Remain conferring in my Lord's Museum. I saw them pass, but me they noted not. Methinks the Prince Adrastus alter'd much: His wonted smile is gone, his eyes no more Denote those playful sallies of the mind Which spread delight throughout your father's palace, During his sojourn at the Carian court. His features wear a settled melancholy; But fine, and noble still, replete with grace. Ada. Yes, yes, Aspasia, he could look, and speak, Delight and win—but never felt, himself; Save the mixt pleasure of a lively hour: Though to the eye and ear his mien and voice Proclaim'd him form'd for tenderness and love. 'Twas semblance all, and art, and conscious pride: He glow'd to win, and won but to disdain. Yet was it rumour'd at Halicarnassus, That, purified by Crœsus, he had learn'd To love the daughter of his purifier. Aspasia. Aryenis? Ada. The sister of my husband. The King and Atys say it is not so: Yet scruple not to wish it loudly. Well! Be their wishes gratified! Be her fate Involved in all the horrors of my own! Aspasia. Love unrequited— Ada. Sets the brain on fire, And flames the blood that gushes from a heart, Where hate contends with love for mastery. Aspasia. But Aryenis— Ada. Loves Adrastus. Aspasia. How is that known, since not reveal'd by her? Ada. Love is no flame within the soul confined And smother'd—All, all betray it—The eye, The voice, the curling of the silent lip— Oh! 'tis a fire that mocks concealment's power, And, shaded, burns with brighter blaze! Name but Adrastus, and these symptoms all Reveal the truth, without the aid of words. Aspasia. He is not worthy of a heart like thine: Call forth a noble pride, and scorn the man Whose tasteless eye on slighter beauty dwells. Ada. Pride!—'Tis the sport of Love to humble Pride. No! deadly Hate alone can cope with Love. No weaker passion satisfies the breast O'er which that tyrant god e'er bore control: Never can Scorn succeed, but Vengeance may. I've torn th' ungrateful monster from my heart, And with revenge the void he left is fill'd. Aspasia. With feelings such as these, how much, ye gods! Is poor unhappy Woman to be pitied! Ada. Pitied!—It may be. But, Aspasia, know, Still to be dreaded more. And, if there lurk Within the breast a spark of slighted love, 'Twill but augment the fiercer fire of hate.— Oh! what a conflict in my bosom rages! But hate, ever as pow'rful, now prevails, As he shall feel. But die he shall not—No! That were poor, common vengeance—He shall live: But live with blasted fame, while conscious virtue, Gnawing at his heart, shall greater pangs inflict Than Ada's dagger, or than Atys' sword. My thoughts confused o'er modes of vengeance range: In death is peace, in blasted life is woe. Aspasia. But think, whate'er the Phrygian Prince endure By Atys and by Crœsus will be felt. Ada. Atys and Crœsus both deserve their fate: Deserve my rage—Of this I well bethought— Did not their boastings reach my tortured ear, That Lydia's daughter should his peace restore? Time might have wrought a change—but in the heart Once love be fixed, its avenues are closed, And all attempts to win it are in vain. Aspasia. Would thou couldst quell these conflicts of thy soul! At least, my Princess, let them be conceal'd.— Some one approaches—Nay, resume thy looks, Unbend thy brows—It is my lord, Prince Atys. Enter Atys. Atys. Smile, Ada, smile—All nature smiles to-day. E'en my Adrastus smiled when first we met, Though Melancholy graced his lip the while. Ada. The Phrygian Prince is then arrived? Atys. I left him with a friend, preparing both To follow to the presence of the King, Whom now I seek to tell of his return. Ada. And talk'd he of the chace? And will he join To put to death this other Calydon? Atys. 'Twas our prime talk,—Crœsus will be convinced— But fain Adrastus would the chace avoid. Ada. The chace avoid! That's strange, methinks! Perhaps A nobler quarry in the palace lures. Did he of your sister speak? Atys. Yes, oh yes; And with an ardour whence a hope would spring, Had not his breast forsworn the power of love, That Aryenis might his grief dispel. Ada. Love, you imagine, then, may be forsworn? 'Tis idly said; for that despotic deity, Howe'er at common perjuries he smile, Brooks not derision of his proper power; The which nor men nor gods e'er yet forswore. May not his heart against her charms be guarded Even by Love itself, by other charms? Hath he ne'er thrill'd thy ear with Dorian beauty? Doris was part of Caria. There Halicarnassus was situated, at the top of the Ceramic bay. Atys. No—never talk'd he, Ada, save of thine; And then, methought, reluctantly, nor e'en To thine would pay the homage fully due. Ada. Yet deign'd he, Sir, before his homicide Much time to loiter at the Carian court. Doris was part of Caria. There Halicarnassus was situated, at the top of the Ceramic bay. Atys. I know it well. Why say it now, my love? And with such stress upon that loiter'd time? I must to Crœsus (going, returns.) Oh! be sure, my Ada, The sad distemper of Adrastus' heart Is unremitting, undermining grief, That mocks all moral aid, all other power; Yet mingles not amiss with heavenly friendship, That first of boons the gods on men bestow. Ada. The first of boons! And where ranks Love, I pray? Atys. Oh! second, Ada. (gaily.) Sometimes last, I fear— Sometimes no boon at all. Ada. Sometimes—a curse. Atys. Nay, clear that beauteous brow. I love thee, Ada— Excuse the candour of a soldier's speech— I love thee, Ada, as a soldier loves. Ada. Methinks, a soldier, Sir, should love like Mars; To whom we owe that deity himself. Atys. My Ada, so he should—and so he does. Soldiers are amorous, and few neglect Their vows at Venus' shrine—Yet friendship sways The hero's soul with unexampled force. Ada. Judge by the Phthyan hero. Ten long years His injured love suspended Ilion's fate. Atys. 'Twas rage, not love; 'twas pride, my fair one, pride So long withheld Achilles from the fray; Till wounded friendship set his soul on fire, And in its blaze involved the Dardan towers. But Love with Friendship never should contend— Atys is blest in both—his wife and friend. [Exit. Ada. What says Aspasia to this soldier's sense Of nature ruling in the human breast? Aspasia. If from myself a judgment I may form, I know no love exceeding that for you, And Friendship, Ada, holds superior sway: To judge by you, far diff'rent should I deem. Yet, ah! beware of Passion's dire extreme! It leads to misery— Ada. Passion is zest— When dull emotions stagnate in the breast, 'Tis living death, not life enjoy'd, Aspasia. Aspasia. Is stagnant all, if not in tumult driven? Recal the day, when, on the Ægean shore, We watch'd the gliding barks by zephyrs blown: Swiftly, though gently, each attain'd its goal. How sweet, and pleasant 'twas to view the scene! That very eve, within your father's palace, We gazed again upon our alter'd sea, Where zephyrs had resign'd their happy sway, Succeeded by the furious blasts of Auster, Which, sudden, with tremendous roar, o'ertook A large and strongly timber'd argosy, Quick steering for the port, then close before it. Methinks, I see it now—first, as in sport, It danced its playful bow to mock the wind, That, howling, threaded the Ceramic bay. Doris was part of Caria. There Halicarnassus was situated, at the top of the Ceramic bay. How proudly swell'd its milk-white sails! But soon Along the coast 'twas driven on its side, And dash'd upon the rocks—You heard the screams, Which, louder than the tempest's roar, assail'd The affrighted ear, and pierced the tortured soul With sympathetic terror—All were lost. So, Ada, act the passions of the breast! Gentle, they give to life its dearest joys; But uncontroll'd they goad and overwhelm. Oh! I beseech you, stop—forego revenge— The Phrygian Prince, who never knew to love, Is now absorb'd in grief—Atys is charming. Ada. As is the Parian stone: and with a heart Form'd for thy cold philosophy. The gods, Whose will the earth, the air, the sea obey, Have made me what I am—Infatuate wretch! Aspasia. But! mould thy soul by reason into peace. Ada. Reason is given to aid, not thwart their work: Away with Reason, then, that rebel grows! Fate rules Olympus, Fate the gods obey, And Nature ministers to Fate on earth. Thee friendship and a gentle mind it wills; To me a spirit glowing and resolved: Perhaps too much disclosed to thee, Aspasia! But well, my gentle friend, I know thou lovest me, And my swoln heart had burst, had I not pour'd Its overflowing feelings into thine. Aspasia. Ada, they come—Be calm. Ada. Again that step Vibrates melodious discord on my ear: Again conflicting passions shake my soul.— I'd see the Prince alone—remove his friend. Enter Adrastus and Orontes. Adrastus. Hah!—'Tis she! (aside.) Long life and joy attend the bride of Atys! Ada. 'Twere better wish'd with a less mournful brow— But, Prince, we'll teach you to dispel the cloud. Your friend— Adrastus. Orontes, Madam, from Celene, Bearing my father's mandate of return. Ada. You're welcome, Sir, to Sardis—But not so The mandate of the Phrygian King. We'll hope To send Adrastus home with gayer cheer. Orontes. I'm but the bearer, Madam, of the wish Of aged Gordius to embrace his son; And of warm congratulations to Crœsus, His son, and you, fair Princess, on your nuptials. Ada. We'll speak our thanks in time for your return.— Prince Adrastus— (Here Aspasia speaks in show to Orontes.) [Exeunt Aspasia and Orontes. (A pause.) Ada. Hath sorrow made thee dumb? Or time erased From memory thy Carian hours? Adrastus. Oh! Princess! I do beseech thee, bury in oblivion Those hours, and all, all else that may disturb Thy peace, or give a pang to Atys' heart; A heart of bliss so worthy and of love. Ada. Dost talk of bliss and love to me? Of peace, Which thou hast marr'd? Of love, which well thou know'st Is not at my command? A victim here At Hymen's shrine paternal power hath bound me: But what can bind imagination? Who Direct to petty channels of their own The mighty torrent of the love-swoln heart? Adrastus! thou hast dared to sport with mine— Alas! the time is past when, with fair fame, Thou might'st redeem thy pledge of winning smiles. But still 'tis unredeem'd, with me remains, And wretched Ada cannot throw it back. Adrastus. Madam! Ada. Madam!—Full of respect, forsooth! But Ada is my name—I'll have no other— 'Twas “Lovely Ada,” when that pledge was given. Adrastus. Reflect, I pray— Ada. Reflection is my curse.— I've done a deed that, as I look upon thee, Curdles my blood. Hadst thou deserved my love; Hadst thou not broken from my father's court, With alter'd visage, and with smiles of scorn, I ne'er the Lydian overture had favour'd. And, e'en when urged with all the force of duty, Or all a parent, all a king might claim, I ne'er had yielded to become another's: And sooner had they immolated Ada At any shrine than that by me insulted; The god of which a signal vengeance plans.— Of Love, disdain'd, Revenge usurp'd the place— No keener curse that passion could suggest, Than by this marriage, sought of policy, To make of Atys' wife Adrastus' foe. Adrastus. Alas! too well I know the spring—But, oh! In time bethink thee, ere, the curse fulfill'd, Involve in endless woe thy dearest friends. For me, could but my death thy wrath appease, I'd welcome it, with joy to me unknown— Give the command, and, Ada, I obey. Ada. Speak it again—say Ada once again— The sound is like enchantment in the air, And breathes a warmth to melt a harden'd heart. But no—It cannot—must not—I recal The wish—'tis Hate, not Love, now sways my breast. Adrastus. Oh! let not Hatred hold so dire a sway Where only Love should reign.—Be—be my friend— Friend to a wretched man, for mercy suing— My heart is broke—my fate already told To wither long, by moral lightning scathed; And all my years must pass in hopeless gloom. Some comfort yet this cheerless breast might know, Could I repair the heedless injury, Done in those giddy days of playful youth, When even smiles might be mista'en for love. Ada. Mista'en? Adrastus. If to admire, indeed, were love, 'Twere no mistake—To look on charms like thine, And not admire, were as impossible As gazing at the Sun to scorn his beams: Dazzled I was, but never spoke of love. Ada. Nor ever look'd it? Adrastus. That was not a crime. 'Twas homage, Ada, homage from the heart, Paid not alone by me, but all whose eye, Prompt to receive the soft impress of beauty, Convey'd its influence to the wond'ring soul. Ada. Such, enchanter! such were the magic sounds That tuned the voice of Love—thy voice!—Such still Their sweetness falls upon my ravish'd sense, Runs thro' my veins, and agitates my heart. Thou know'st 'twas love, Adrastus—'twas—'twas love. Adrastus. Oh! had I felt it then, in those gay hours, When peace and joy in Beauty's train were found, This breast had been a fit abode for Love: Alas! 'tis but a dreary ruin now, Suited alone to melancholy thoughts. Ada. No better antidote to grief than love. Adrastus. No antidote can operate 'gainst mine. Oh! hear me, cruel! Cruel to thyself! Hear me, nor be ungrateful to the gods! Welcome the bliss, by thee unsought, they give: Tho' vengeance urged the deed, let Love prevail! Never was man more form'd than Crœsus' son— Ada. Adrastus! hold—Crœsus expects thee now; Nor is there time for longer parley here. Vengeance I meant: but since I've seen thee, heard thee, This ardent brain, so german to my heart, Unfolds a milder project. Atys, full Of to-morrow's pleasure, meets the dawn, And therefore lodges in the outer court. I unobserved, when sleep the Palace holds, For all its ways I've learn'd, will leave my chamber, And seek thee— Adrastus. Princess!— Ada. Nay, never start. Adrastus. Not for my life— Ada. Oh monstrous! What vile degrading fancy soils thy brain? Am I awake? Think'st thou I proffer dalliance? Is 't come to this? Ye gods! is 't come to this? 'Tis shame enough when woman owns her love; But to be deem'd the wanton of an hour!— Now could I hate thee—but I've that to say, Which must be said; and which, when said, to both, If thou art wise, may bring relief and peace. Adrastus. Relief for me there's none. And as for peace, The quiet of the breast depends on honour. Ada. That we'll discuss at night—Expect me then. Adrastus. Princess, desist—I will not see you then. Ada. Not see me?—Madman! Yet more mad is she Whose insane visions lead her thus to trifle, And yield herself to scorn—But, Sir, I know The barrier to our conference—Know thou! The flame of vengeance shall that barrier fire. It is not Atys steels thy heart against me; But Atys' sister—Oh! thou canst not love! 'Tis grief absorbs Adrastus' soul—Now, mark me! For vengeance am I here, and vengeance shall be mine. [Exit. Adrastus. Oh! lost Adrastus!—Ho! Orontes! ho! [Exit. END OF THE SECOND ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. Scene—The Palace of Crœsus. A magnificent Apartment.—Crœsus and his Courtiers attending to Music, in which Flutes prevail. Flutes of different kinds were much used by the ancients, both on joyful and mournful occasions. Potter gives an account of the Lydian, Phrygian, Carian, &amp;c. In war, the Lacedemonians began their engagements with a concert of flutes. The manner is described by Plutarch in the Life of Lycurgus.—Crœsus seats himself.—Atys, Adrastus, Orontes, and Philon, arrange themselves by him, and the Act opens with the following Stanzas. The two first are sung alternately by Singers on the opposite sides of the Stage— the third by a single voice, in a solemn but not melancholy strain. As the voice of the Singer dies away, Crœsus speaks. 1. Crœsus, the happy! Lydia's king! Now let the roof with rapture ring! And Chorus loud with Crœsus' name, The Monarch's happiness proclaim. Happy Crœsus! Lydia's king! 2. Most happy he in wealth and power, With glories gilding ev'ry hour. Him nations hail, him children bless, Himself the source of happiness. Happy Crœsus! happy king! Solo. Call none happy ere he die: Fortune worldly gifts supply. Threescore years and ten we range, By a note of Mr. Beloe's, on the passage in Herodotus, a doubt is thrown on the accuracy of attributing the remark on the age of seventy years to Solon. The original text is said to have been altered. Fortune ev'ry hour may change: Goddess ever prompt to fly!— Call none happy ere he die. Crœsus. Such were the words of the wise man of Athens, Which we to Lydian measures have consign'd, To make Philosophy delight in song, And thus the crabbed saw disprove itself: For happiness belongs to life, not death. Who dreads to-morrow's pang must writhe to-day: While joy to-day is so far joy secure. Spite of the sophist's doctrine, this I feel, All Lydia is content, and Crœsus happy. If aught remain to gratify ambition, 'Tis to be sought beyond the gelid Halys, The river Halys was celebrated for its coolness. In regions where an empire seems to rise, Pregnant with rivalry to Lydia's throne.— Are the last Messengers to Delphi here? Philon. Arrived e'en now, they wait the King's command. Crœsus. Then bid them hither with their best despatch. (An Officer goes out.) The Oracular replies have all been good: But still the Pythoness I value most; And from Apollo's favour'd shrine I'd hear, Once more, the confirmation of my fortunes. Enter Officer and Messengers. Officer. So please the King, the Messengers from Delphi. Crœsus. Welcome to Sardis, Sirs. I long to know The new reply the Priestess hath vouchsafed. Messenger. Long life to Crœsus, Lydia's happy King! Thus did the Pythoness her answer give: “The Halys once by Lydia crost, A mighty empire will be lost.” Crœsus. That 's right! that 's right! We leave our kingdom safe, And penetrate the empire to be lost.— Philon! see that a hundred golden tiles Go with the Lion to the Delphic fane. What said the agitated Priestess more? Messenger. Urged on the fate of Crœsus, she replied: “When o'er the Medes an o'ergrown Mule Shall hold on high the sov'reign rule, Then, Lydian, over Hermus fly, Thy safety seek, and fear to die.” Crœsus. Most excellent! What can be more auspicious? When shall a brutal Mule ascend a throne? Or Crœsus' courage fail? Thanks to the god! Philon! Be added to our present offering The silver casks, and basons of pure gold: And to the Pythoness I'd have convey'd Those necklaces and zones of which I spoke; A treasure of themselves magnificent. Philon. Your Highness' orders straight shall be obey'd. Crœsus. We'll have a great and royal sacrifice. (To Philon.) A thousand chosen victims see collected; Herodotus says three thousand, the accuracy of which is doubted. Prepare a pyre of decorated couches, Goblets of gold, and costly purple vests. And let all Lydia follow our example, With proper objects, as by each possess'd. My Lords! these are great tidings! While, secure, Our Lydians in rejoicings fill their time, We'll meditate upon our future conquests.— But I see faces here, more eager far For present sport than future victory. Well! be it so. To-morrow, with the dawn, Our dogs shall rouse you with melodious noise. So now we'll separate. To each good day! (Rises and advances.) Choir. Now let the roofs with rapture ring! Crœsus is happy! Lydia's King! Happy Crœsus! happy King! (The Chorus is continued as the Stage is clearing, during which the principal personages advance.) Manent—Crœsus, Atys, Adrastus, and Orontes. Crœsus. Well, dear Adrastus! does your friend persist In his mad fondness for the chace to-morrow? Adrastus. If it so please your Highness. Crœsus. And can nought Divert thee, Atys, from this dangerous sport? Atys. Not much of danger, sure, my honour'd Lord. E'en if there were, think, oh! think, my father, How Lydians value courage and renown, Proved and obtain'd in war; or e'en, as now, In bold attacks upon the Forest tyrants. Will they not sneer at sloth and cowardice, In one averse to signalize himself? And he the very one on whom all eyes Turn for a chief to lead where danger threats? And what will Ada think, my lovely bride? My Lord! good my Lord! let me not lose opinion, That golden prize which weds esteem to love. Crœsus. My son! No coward ever sprung from Crœsus. What Lydian knows not of thy deeds in war? But oh! that vision!—that terrific vision! Which show'd thee prostrate with a spear transfix'd!— It is to you, my Atys, that I look For hope, in the succession to my realms; And for our Lydia a long race of kings. Cyno, your brother, amiable and brave, Mute left by Nature from his very birth, Can never fill the throne. Atys. My dearest father! Can I be senseless to your anxious care? Ah, no!—'tis full of love and wise intent. And little should I merit love like thine, Could I, in opposition to thy will, Enforce the wanton eagerness of youth. Repeat thy wish, and I forego the leave, Which so reluctantly has been accorded. But reason first upon this vision thus: It intimates the instrument of fate To be a spear. Where is the enemy? Boars wield no arms, present no deadly spear. Had the dire portent been a tusk, indeed, There had been ground perhaps for some debate— We go not to contend with men. I pray, Sir, Weigh the matter thus. Crœsus. Atys, you're right. My fears I own are idle. Thus convinced, I'll not retract my word, but joy to hear From your own lips the pleasant toils of sport, And all th' adventures of the bristled savage. You hunt, Orontes? Orontes. Sir, I count the hours. Crœsus. And you, Adrastus, must be early stirring. Adrastus. Alas! I've no excitement, Sir, to stir me: And would your Highness and the Prince excuse— Crœsus. Nay, my good friend, I would not for a kingdom But you were there. Adrastus, dear Adrastus! Think not I would remind you of your woes, To claim an int'rest for the expiation I once administer'd to your distress, Or make a debt of what has proved a gain: But if you feel that I have shown you love, Refuse not to accompany my Atys; To call forth prudence, and to guard his life. Wisdom and valour, those prime gifts of Heaven, Your family have long inherited, Nor have they fail'd in the descent to you: Where valour calls, Adrastus should be found. Adrastus. Oh! more than father to a wretched youth! Crœsus, enough! Thy slightest wish, believe me, Teems with excitement to my grateful thoughts. By such a dire calamity oppress'd, It ill becomes me with the gay to move: 'Tis not my nature, Sir; and you have seen How little given to revelry my heart: But gratitude excites, and I obey. I'll with the Prince to Tmolus in the morn, Wait on his steps, protect his precious life, And bring him back in safety to your arms. Crœsus. 'Tis nobly said. And now, my friend, beware The long indulgence of consuming grief: Let not our expiation lose its end. 'Tis time to soothe thy bosom; nay, to move Some powerful spring in favour of thy youth. Rouse, rouse thee, Boy! And know, that Lydia's King Would gladly make thee sharer of his joys.— Atys! you 'll find me with your Bride. [Exit with Attendants. (Adrastus muses, and speaks to himself, while Orontes and Atys eye him, and speak apart.) Adrastus. His joys! To move some powerful spring—powerful spring— The sharer of his joys—'twas strangely said— And with a smile that seem'd to bid me seek Some latent meaning in his words—Away! 'Tis folly and presumption—Yet 'twas so— What if it be, is mine a heart for love? Atys. He's wrapt in thought.—Mark'd you my father's smile? Orontes. I did. Atys. I trust 'twill work a charm upon his fancy! Adrastus. They heed me not—Say I could love—What then? Atys. Detain him here awhile—I'll soon return. It is a favourable moment, Sir, And must be seized, or lost, perhaps, for ever. [Exit. Adrastus. (Absorbed in thought.) Love should bring pleasure dancing in his train— If sorrow follow, let the gods look to 't,— 'Tis then their doing—But in woe to court, And crave of Beauty to participate A settled grief—and take a mourning suit To grace Love's nuptials—call it aught but Love. Except indeed it be the love of self— Self! that base instinct of the grovelling herd— Oh! never—never—never.—Atys gone? (To Orontes.) Orontes. He follow'd quick upon his father's steps, As if intent upon some plan. Adrastus. Orontes, I was thinking, and quite absorb'd you saw, That love can only dwell in generous minds: If self e'er mingle, 'tis no longer love. Orontes. At least 'tis not refined. Adrastus. Nay, but 'tis odious. Orontes. Not if it be natural. Adrastus. Nature, Orontes, True to herself, is always lovely—But She dwindles into ugliness, when false— E'en pity fails deformity of mind. Self is instinctive in the lower race; 'Tis man's prerogative to vanquish it, To live for others, die for others, love As he lives or dies, not for himself, But for the bliss of her his heart adopts. Orontes. I grant our nature may be thus ennobled. 'Tis not the glorious preference we give To others o'er ourselves, of which I doubt; But 'tis our judgment I suspect, my friend. We view of happiness our own creation, And think it that of others. But, Adrastus! Suppose the lovely Aryenis pined In poignant sadness, o'er some rooted grief; Were it not bliss, with mild affection's balm, To heal her wounded mind, and peace restore? Adrastus. 'Twere bliss indeed! Orontes. Imagine now 'twere hers To pour a balm into Adrastus' wounds— Adrastus. Dear, dear Orontes! cease this flatt'ring strain! So sweet your words, I half suspect I love. Orontes. So plain are yours, I know you wholly love. Adrastus. And would you have me kill the thing I love? Orontes. I'd have you take it to your bosom, man! And as it lies around your aching heart, 'Twill gradually extract the rankling sting, And give new life to you, and all who love you. Adrastus. Oh! rather say, this palsied heart would numb The vivifying principle, applied To lend to torpid powers new energy— I am not fit to live.—Would I were dead! Orontes. But Aryenis— Adrastus. Is lovely, most lovely! And all that beauty, all that virtue owns Would mix their essences, to form a charm Might rouse the dying to new life.—But I, My friend, am fated—not to peaceful death— Would that I were!—but life—and what a life! Could I forget this hand were stain'd with blood, And yield my heart, as it perhaps inclines, To a sweet hope in Aryenis' love, A direr woe threats my devoted head. Orontes. See where the Princess Aryenis comes. Enter Atys and Aryenis. Adrastus. Dear Aryenis! Aryenis. Welcome home, my Lord! My brother chides, and calls my welcome tardy. Atys. So brought her to deny the charge.—Orontes! (Atys and Orontes conversing apart, gradually withdraw.) Manent—Adrastus and Aryenis. Adrastus. 'Tis me he means to chide—but well he knows How idle is the charge. Aryenis. You smile, Adrastus! You shall go forth again to gather smiles. Adrastus. Say rather, shall return to find them here: Elsewhere they have not been observed, and this Is but the flutter of an anxious spirit, By nature tuned to joy, had not— Aryenis. Nay, nay! “Had not,” my Lord, hath had too long a sway. We must dethrone it now, and teach a heart That feels another's worth to know its own, And make its sorrow yield to friendship's joy. Adrastus. These are delightful words, my lovely pupil! And make me feel how fit thou art to teach. Aryenis. A little wisdom, dear my Lord, is worth A hundred times its weight of knowledge—And why? Because 'tis happiness a hundred fold. Knowledge ne'er banish'd grief—but Wisdom doth— Would I could teach you Wisdom's happiness! Adrastus. I know no lips so likely to succeed, Illustrating the rules themselves prescribe. Oh! Aryenis! were this mind at ease, And were it worthy of a heart like thine! (Sighs deeply.) Aryenis. My dear preceptor! What a sigh was that! Adrastus. Far, far too heavy for a sigh of love. Aryenis. Of love, Adrastus! Do you talk of love? Adrastus. It is not fit I should—And yet, methinks! If ever I could hope, 'twould be by love. Love rectifies the heart, aids all our virtues, And is the very wisdom you have counsell'd. Aryenis. My Lord! My Lord! I never counsell'd love. Adrastus. Then farewell hope! No other counsellor, No other counsel, e'er can heal this mind.— What am I doing? I forget myself.— Sweet maid! preserve your heart—'twas my advice, Amidst the studies that engaged our hours— Preserve it still—for love is dangerous; And must be bliss complete, or misery. Aryenis. Are not my brother and his Ada happy?— What sudden paleness seizes on your cheek? Adrastus. Nothing—It is— Aryenis. Adrastus! You are ill. (Anxiously.) Adrastus. Not ill—'Tis heat that penetrates the brain— Let us not talk of love—it fires the air: Failing to cure, it but confirms despair. We 'll in to Crœsus—He at least is blest Whom all men love, and whom no ills molest. END OF THE THIRD ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT IV. Scene—The Apartments of Adrastus. Ada and Aspasia. (Aspasia enters, after peeping through a secret door in the wall, and calls Ada, who follows.) Aspasia. Vacant, and silent all—fearless, advance. Ada. I would not here be seen.—Where is Adrastus? Aspasia. With the Prince Atys, in the King's apartment, Earnestly engaged in joyous foretaste Of the fulfilment of the Oracles, Which give to Crœsus Asia's inner realms. Ada. And where is Aryenis? Aspasia. Gone to rest. You seem but strange to these apartments, Princess, Nor found with ease the spring that free'd the door. Was it before unknown to you? Ada. This morn, Atys, unthinkingly, betray'd the secret, In anxious expectation of his friend, To whom th' apartments are appointed. Thence A private gallery leads to our range. As there we whiled some idle time, the Prince, In whom impatience overcame all caution, Touch'd on the spring, and vanish'd thro' the wall: But soon return'd. Unnoted, I observed The means he used for his admittance—Hark! (Goes to the spring door, and examines it.) Aspasia. No person comes—we are secure awhile. Hath Atys bid good night? Ada. He comes again:— But unapprized of what awaits his ear. And now let 's in—my object is obtain'd In being mistress of that spring—Yet stay— See whither leads that open door. Aspasia. (Looking in) —A couch, Beneath a Tyrian canopy outspread, Shows it prepared for sleep. A steady lamp Burns on a golden tripod. On the couch A handkerchief lies negligently left. Ada. A handkerchief! 'Tis an avenging charm! It was observed by a friend, that the use of a handkerchief by Ada to work upon the feelings of Atys might bring to mind Othello's napkin. If so, I can only say that it was not in mine, and that it does not appear to me to be of importance enough to change it for a less obvious instrument. The angry gods conspire to make it mine— This shall its place supply— (Exposes her handkerchief, goes in, and returns with another.) Mother of Love! I thank thee for this gift, the gift of vengeance! There 's in this 'kerchief more of eloquence Than any tongue in Attica can boast, And it will speak most forcibly to Atys. Away, away, Aspasia. [Exeunt through the secret door. Scene—The King's Apartment. Crœsus, Philon, Atys, Adrastus, Orentes, Rhodius, &amp;c. Crœsus. Truly, my friends, most prosperous our affairs! And whether I the past survey, enjoy The present, or anticipate the future, Glad Time presents exuberance of joy, The public glory, and domestic splendour. O'er our luxuriant plains and shaded vales Salubrious Tmolus sheds eternal health; And our Pactolus rolls his golden grains, In medicinal waters, See the first Note. to our hands. All, all is health, wealth, victory, and love! Then, let the snarling man of Athens boast Athenian Tellus, and the Argive brothers, Cleobis and Biton, The names of the persons adduced by Solon, as happy. happy in death, While we the happiness of life enjoy, Nor shrink from Fate, which oft our wisdom rules. Philon. Solon, my Liege, was not averse to joy; Nor held he Crœsus' happiness at nought: His doubt was of the fickle goddess, Fortune, Profuse of smiles, but sudden in her frowns. Crœsus. Why meet them, Philon? Or why, good Adrastus, Not combat with her woes, and dash them from us? Atys. My friend will combat with them, Sir.—Methinks, Already they oppress him less. And now Shall Lydian days, enforced with Beauty's smiles, Complete the cure, and make him blest as I am. Adrastus. Kind Atys! Crœsus. Come, Boy, smile—give wing to Hope— There's nothing you can ask that I'll refuse. Adrastus. Benignant Crœsus!—I will do my best. Crœsus. But do it soon, and be as Atys blest. We'll have our fill of sports, and then to war, To add new triumphs to the Lydian arms, And make the Asian Continent our own. To-morrow's chace will be but brief—By noon The Boar will be through Sardis proudly borne; And to complete the pleasures of the day, We'll make libations large to Cybele. Philon! direct the officer to raise An altar 'fore the Eastern Portico; Where, shielded from the ardent beams of Phebus, Zephyrs shall fan our hunters with their wings. And let the Corybantes join in dance, Clashing their cymbals wild, as to the ground We dash the gen'rous, undiluted wine. Philon. Your Highness' orders all shall be obey'd. Crœsus. Who hath e'er been among those Persian tribes, Which gathering into form acquire dominion? Rhodius. So please your Highness! I have been among them; And know those Persians well. Rough is their life; The account here given of the Persians in the time of Crœsus, is nearly the words of Sardanis, a Lydian, addressed to Crœsus, versified. Apparel they have none, save the fur skins Of which they plunder their poor fellow-brutes: Their lands but little owe to husbandry; They feed just as they can, not as they would: The grape they know not, water is their drink, Their only drink, and figs, the food of swine, A dainty held, forbid to vulgar palates. Atys. Far, far, ye gods! from Lydia keep these Persians! Should they once get a taste of Lydian dainties, By Hercules! they'd swarm the land like locusts: Dislodge them then who could.—'Twere better, Sir, Methinks, to leave them to their present diet, Than raise them such invincible allies As appetite and ease.—And, after all, What can we take from those who nothing have? Crœsus. Extended empire, Sir—the world, my Son. But, friends! of this hereafter—Night draws on: 'Tis time our hunters should repair to rest; And so, good-night!—To-morrow, friends, we meet, To pour libations, and to quaff the grape. [Exit with Atys. All go off severally, except Adrastus and Orontes. Orontes. The King is ever jocund—full of hope, As he were yet but in the spring of life. Adrastus. He hath its renovating source, a mind Replete with virtue, unassail'd by woe. Crœsus is great as well as blest, Orontes; And good as great—And, should the gods e'er try him, Would dignify adversity. Which proved to be the case, when a captive to Cyrus. Orontes. His heart Is noble—but it delights me most to see Its eagerness in your behalf. Adrastus. My friend, 'Tis manifest that his benevolence Would halt at nothing, that could bring me peace:— The more behoves it me to care for his. Orontes. He all but begs you to accept his daughter. Adrastus. Oh! Orontes. Aryenis— Adrastus. Hear me, kind Orontes! So much virtue with so much beauty join'd Would renovate, the sickliest heart, and mine Hath felt, and feels their power—I love—nay more— I think that love would work the charm you wish, And bring me by degrees to banish grief. But I, alas! am doom'd, deliver'd over To a Fury, and silent I must bear. I cannot open Atys' eyes—I cannot Poniard the man I love, whose zealous hand Is ever pouring balm into my wound. Ada to him may yet her heart incline; Me she devotes—one way alone remains To prop the hope new kindled in my breast: To-morrow's hunt once o'er, my leave I'll take, And for awhile to Sardis bid farewel. I go— Orontes. But not to Ephesus, I trust. Adrastus. Orontes, no.—To Gordius and Celene— So love directs—to expiate on the spot, Inure me to the objects that appal, Bless my dear father, and receive new life From him who gave the first—then hither send, And claim fair Aryenis for my bride— Shall it be thus? Orontes. Oh! joyous, joyous words! Gordius will then be happy—Adrastus Will be happy—all Phrygia will be happy! Adrastus. And now, let 's in—'tis time for rest—perhaps I'll hunt with better spirits than I thought— Yet there is something heavy, heavy here. [Exeunt. Scene—Ada's Apartment. Ada and Aspasia. Ada. In vain by pride you combat love, Aspasia! Vengeance alone the mastery may gain. Your counsel I respect, admire your virtue, And would the gods had bless'd me with your calm! How galls the yoke of disappointed love! Who that could throw it off would bear its weight? I know the folly, and despise myself; Know the best vengeance were to conquer it, And spurn the base deserter from my mind; But the malignant god defies contempt. Conquer I will—conquer I have—but how? By withering the heart that scathed my own; Making dishonour eat into its core. Aspasia. Both love and pity urge me to restrain The raging passion that inflames your soul, Since vengeance must recoil upon yourself. Oh! yet reflect, or ere you strike the blow. Already do the world respect his grief— Your deed once known, they 'll raise a general cry, Call thee infatuate, and lament his fate. Ada. And what imports to me that futile cry, If satiated hate relieve this breast, Which, unrevenged, with endless fury burns? Virtue, or rather character 's his idol:— To blast that character, to stamp him vile, Fix him the scorn of Atys and of Crœsus, Wring growing love from Aryenis' heart, Make the good shun him, and the world condemn, Is the fixt purpose of th' insulted Ada. Aspasia. How blind is rage!—I hear approaching steps. Ada. It is the Prince.—Expect me in my chamber. [Exit Aspasia. Enter Atys. Atys. Ada! the night is far advanced. Ere now I had been bound in life-restoring slumbers, But for the powerful charm that binds me ever, When Crœsus smiles, and talks of happiness. What buoyant spirits bless the dear old man! Oh! may his stream of life flow ever thus! Ada. The purest stream may be contaminated, And even joys become corrupt and choked, Mingling with muddy currents of the soul. Atys. Yes, but with such my father never mingles. Ada. Clear-sighted men may sometimes be deceived. Atys. Speak not in riddles, Ada, I beseech you: A soldier's ear loves a straight-forward speech. Ada. Be it not lost upon a soldier's ear— Adrastus— Atys. Still Adrastus! Ada. Yes, Adrastus— The muddy, foul, corrupt Adrastus— Atys. Ada! Such words make tumult in a soldier's veins. Prithee! unsay them, Love! He is my friend. Ada. And would be mine. Atys. That phrase insinuates still. I'll take it in its plain and simple sense, And plainly say, I would that you were his! And if you love me— Ada. Why, let Love submit To Friendship's higher claims. Be it so, my Lord— Good night! Atys. Not so, Ada.—I'll hear the rest. But speak direct, and let me know the whole. Ada. Direct! what means such insult, Prince? Direct! Atys. Be not offended—for you know my love. By habit frank—but insult is beneath me. There 's some mistake—Nay, Ada, I am sure— Give me your hand—Deem better of Adrastus, And hope to prove him worthy of your friendship. Ada. It is for those to deem who do not know; It is for those to hope who only doubt: But who can fashion thought in knowledge' spite, Or dream of hope when once the die is cast? Atys, you are deceived. Are you so frank To deem all men, like you, be what they seem? Have you ne'er met in life with specious villains, All sanctity without, deceit within? Who trick out Virtue in her best attire, The showy means to gain their selfish ends? Just such a villain is— Atys. Hold, Madam, hold! That epithet must never meet his name. Ada. Silenced again! Direct I must not speak— The whole you would not know— Atys. Princess, proceed. Ada. Nay, if my duty, Sir, offend, I'm dumb. Think not I seek protection from my Lord. Nor will I now proceed, save on condition You promise to be master of yourself, And make contempt, not anger, your revenge. Atys. Oh! 'tis a promise easy to be given: Contempt, not anger, were the just revenge. Ada. When at my father's Court he whiled his days, He ev'ry art essay'd to gain my love. The King encouraged rather than opposed His suit, leaving me mistress to decide. No feverish passion biassing my mind, I sought to know the youth who woo'd my hand: On which his vanity pronounced success. I let that pass, and gave him full career; Till noted he became for low intrigue; Injustice, falsehood, pride, and meannesses Innumerable. When, shock'd, I gently would dismiss his suit, He seized my hand, and swore 'twas coyness; swore That I loved him, and should alone be his. Atys. The picture 's overwrought— Ada. The picture 's just. Forced he withdrew; but never was convinced, So deeply rooted is his vanity. Why shunn'd he, Sir, our nuptials? Grief, you say— Then grief should teach him to command himself. Why did he strive to hinder them?—He did? Atys. I own I thought him strenuous on that point: But no such motive ever ruled his soul. I've listen'd, Ada, to your angry tale, And see the painful bias of your mind Against my friend. With beauty such as yours Virtue and gentleness should ever dwell, As ornaments essential to its charm. Yet, if offended Beauty stoop to rail, 'Tis privileged with lively rhetoric; And I'll excuse it in my lovely wife. Come, Ada, come! Adrastus has offended— Pardon the past—he'll not offend again— I hope to see him Aryenis' lord— Ada. Villain! Atys. By heaven! 'tis false—I think you crazed to say it: Honour ne'er brighter shone than in his breast. Ada. Never lived greater villain—Now, Sir, know, Save for your sister, here my lips were closed— Beware!—'Tis not for her he'll loiter here. Teach her to guard her heart, lest she repent— Your unsuspecting nature is abused. To-morrow's sport enjoyed, I prithee bear This kerchief to your honourable friend. Atys. What may it mean? Ada. Dishonour. Atys. Where was 't found? Ada. No farther, Sir, than on this bosom press'd, With hand more rude than ever honour used. Atys. Adrastus! Ada. He urged, my heart could never change, and tore In sport a kerchief from my struggling grasp, As a new pledge of future love. Atys. Adrastus! Ada. That pledge no doubt you will redeem. Atys. I will. Ada. Why stand you amazed? Why look as if— Atys. I will— Ada. What? Atys. Confound dishonour. Ada. But calm, and with no clash of words or arms— I claim your promise to despise the man. Atys. Never, never, never—And so good night! [Exit. Ada. What means he? Atys, return—My Lord! my Lord! Hah! and is it thus? Is this the bridal power? The sway of beauty, and the reign of love? On thee shall vengeance turn. Once more I'll try To win Adrastus to a Lover's flight: Failing, to Crœsus I'll appeal—At least, I'll blast the happiness I cannot share. [Exit. Scene—The Apartments of Adrastus. Adrastus alone. Adrastus. Immortal gods! how dark are your decrees, Where good and ill confusedly unite! Which render justice seemingly a chance, And virtue often but a sterile name! Celestial Virtue! who pursue thy steps Must look for rugged paths in this sad world; Must weep and bleed, be tortured and endure: Yet oft thy glowing rays thro' evils pierce, Soften misfortune and sustain the soul: Without thee, who could bear the stings of life? In Fortune's beams foul Crime may rear his head, But thou alone canst cheer the drooping breast. Sole moderator of the power of Fate! Oh! aid me, in my sad career, to bear, And stifle feelings that would wound my friend! Atys! (with surprise.) Enter Atys. I did not think to meet again, Till roused by echo, eager for the chace. Atys. Nor I, my friend; but so some god decreed. I could not sleep 'till I restored your kerchief— I ask not where you left it, for I know. Adrastus. But I do not—'tis odd—yet matters not— Except that you should bring it hither, Atys. Atys. I could not trust the message to another: And scarce can utter it myself, Adrastus— I have a wife whom much I wish to love— Adrastus. Whom much you love— Atys. I know not that. Adrastus. Not know? Atys. I did some minutes since; but am not sure If all my love hath not been sponged away By that same handkerchief. Adrastus. Oh! Atys! Atys! Atys. Tell me, Adrastus, have you one of Ada's? Adrastus. Can Atys ask that question of Adrastus? Atys. Ada has charms—Oh! start not, dear Adrastus, Nor think those sounds impute disloyalty To thee— Tmolus shall, melting, sink into a lake, Pactolus pile his limpid waters high, And stand a liquid Caucasus, or ere Atys degrade his soul to doubt Adrastus. (Embrace.) Ada has charms for me, my friend, and I, Crœsus' own son, am willing to be happy— But happy, how?—Not with disgrace—Ah! no. Beauty and wit awhile intoxicate, But constancy must give the zest to love. I'm full of doubt—the feeling's new and painful— I wake as from a sleep, and wondering trace, In my brief wedlock, striking absences Of Ada's mind—My friend!—she loves me not. Adrastus. (Aside.) Oh! what a moment! (To him) Prithee! think not so— Lose not conviction of the love you prize— Oh hold it fast, and Time may teem with proofs. Atys. You have no handkerchief of hers, you say? Adrastus. None, Atys, none—Shall I invoke the gods? Atys. For friendship's truth? Adrastus. Alas! Atys. But that, Adrastus, How came it into Ada's room, my friend? Adrastus. 'Tis hard to answer—Nay, I cannot answer— And vain the effort to dissemble, Atys, That well I know the Princess broods displeasure, And holds me for her foe. This seems to prove, She means to overwhelm me in her wrath. How she obtain'd it is unknown to me, Or where I left it—Stay—Is 't possible? Methinks I left it on my bed—a moment— These apartments may have been visited— (Goes into the chamber.) Atys. Dear, dear Adrastus! noble-minded youth! Adrastus (within.) Oh! Re-enter Adrastus. I cannot lie—I found it on my bed. (Presenting Ada's handkerchief.) Atys. Sink not—nor add to my calamity A proof that you can wrong your friend in thought, By fearing I should doubt Adrastus' honour. Adrastus. My godlike Atys! Oh! this heart will burst! 'Tis swoln too full, and can expand no more. Atys. But be composed—bear up,—rest, rest upon me. (Adrastus leans, weeping, on Atys.) Art a soldier? Adrastus. (Recovering.) 'Tis not a soldier's wound— Your generous friendship overcame me, Atys. Let us not yield, my friend, to circumstances, Nor sacrifice to passion better hopes— For I had learn'd to hope, and was prepared To talk of happiness, which now depends On your concurrence in my heart's design. Atys. Say on—I'll hear—Clear, if you can, our way: Make but my wife as lovely as I thought her, And I shall owe my happiness to you. Adrastus. Consent to let me bear the blame of this, As it is best I should.—A little time Spent with yourself and Crœsus shall effect All that your mind can wish, or love require. Atys. What could she mean? What cause for such revenge? Or how explain the changes of these things? How came this handkerchief disposed within? Adrastus. Explain I cannot—but I can account For her resentment, and this dire revenge. She thought her beauty slighted, and she knew I had opposed her marriage with my friend: Either enough to fire an ardent dame. Ardour is not a fault, if under rule: But rule the Princess never had been taught; And therefore 'twas that I opposed your union: Virtues she has, and you shall draw them forth. Atys. Beauty she has—we 'll think about her virtues.— Now, of yourself—for, if she e'er redeem This night's forfeit, 'twill be when you are happy— The very thought has predisposed my mind. Adrastus. My heart still bleeds;—but, Atys, I do own Your sister's charms have wrought some change, and if— Atys. Talk not of ifs—the lovely maid is yours— 'Tis Crœsus' wish; the gods themselves have will'd it; Nor can you doubt that Aryenis loves you. Adrastus. My friend! Atys. My brother!—Now let 's think of rest, For we have toils to undergo to—morrow. Adrastus. One favour yet remains.—As things now stand, I would absent myself awhile from Sardis: And 'tis but just I share my better state With a kind father, who has shared my worse.— After to-morrow's hunt I'm for Celene: Retard me not, and gain the leave of Crœsus. Atys. Your very errand shall preclude delay: And in your absence we will strive to impress The rule of happiness, that wisest rule, Upon poor Ada's mind. Good night! [Exit. Adrastus. Good night!— Oh! sacred friendship! powerful charm! In thy pure stream corruption cannot flow, And often evil is transform'd to good. (Sighs, and muses.) When uncheck'd passions sway the female breast, On what enormities do women rush! To what low means debase their troubled souls!— But these are rare—The greater part are honest, And blessings to the partners of their lot. Many excel—and some are paragons! Creatures almost divine! in whom unite Softness of symmetry with strength of mind, Alluring beauty with assuring truth, All-cheering speech, and never cloying love— And such a creature's image lies e'en here, And combats with the form of Agathon For full possession. Oh! my Agathon! Not e'en her smiles can generate a charm 'Gainst that red cloud which o'er my memory hangs. I'll now to bed.— (As he turns to go into his chamber, Ada, who has entered by the secret door, appears before him.) Adrastus and Ada. Adrastus. Heavens! Ada. Start not, Adrastus! Once more to thee my agitated soul Sues for release from ever-racking torture. Adrastus. Princess! Ada. First hear—my brain 's on fire, Adrastus, And cannot long sustain this cruel flame. I own I've done a wrong in plighting vows Where my heart felt it never could be true. The heart can love but once; all other loves, However named, are slight and playful fires, A sigh may kindle and a frown may quench: But that which only once the breast may know While life remains can never be extinguish'd. Thou know'st my heart was yielded first to thee. What tho' no tongue-tipp'd vows proclaim'd you mine! Love look'd it from your eye, and smiled it from your lip. Those looks, those smiles, were they not vows, Adrastus? Why raise an inextinguishable flame, And leave it to consume me? Still it burns: And mad revenge, despair's alternative, Is weak, compared, and vanishes before it.— Come, banish grief, forego all other passions, And fly with me—The deed is well exampled. My father 's old;—in Caria we may reign: Or, lead me to some desert isle, far off; Where, of thy heart secure, I'll glorious live, Nor change it for the empire of the world, Supreme in bliss to see and love thee there. Soon will resentment for the past expire— Say but the word and I forget it all. E'en now I am not angry—speak, Adrastus. Adrastus. Oh! thou hast blasted all remaining hope! Yet will I not, with harsh reproach, provoke New anger in thy agitated breast, Since I, however undesign'd, am still The unhappy cause of all your woe. Nor will I now attempt, with argument, To stem the torrent of delirious fancy; But only pray you to take time— Ada. To take time Were to lose time—Adrastus, no—this night Our fate must be decided.—Ay, this night Or hope must be new lighted in my soul, Or my resolve be executed.—Say! Canst thou on Ada yet bestow thy heart? Adrastus. Wretch that I am! I've none I can bestow. Ada. You own you love another, then? Adrastus. Oh! Princess! Ada. Well!—I consent—but first I stipulate, You do relieve this tortured heart—Behold! Stand off— (Shows a dagger.) Adrastus. On my knees— Ada. Rise! approach, and take it— Stop there—You 'll quickly plunge it in this breast? Adrastus. But give it me— Ada. You 'll do 't? Adrastus. Trust me— Ada. Swear! Not swear? Have you no oath that you can break? Not swear!—I know thee better than to trust thee— Nor is it meet that I should die alone— We die together— (Attempts to stab him, he secures the dagger.) Adrastus. Madness! Madness! Oh! Ada. Scorner! give me the dagger— Adrastus. Ada! Ada. Ay—Ada is my name. (Wildly.) Adrastus. This agony—hear— Oh hear—resume your mind—be noble, Ada! These pangs—hear me, I pray—awake a sense— Believe me, it is full of tenderness— Ada. Sir! You may keep the steel—I scorn to die— Love and self-murder is a tale for children. There is a loftier passion of the soul, Now hungering for a godlike feast—Revenge! Revenge more dainty than a foolish murder. You think me mad—not I—a heated brain Subjects our nerves to foolish pranks, but madness Knows not the thing it does—I am not mad. Adrastus. Oh! Ada! Spare me—spare yourself— Ada. Speak out! Spare Aryenis—spare my love.—Ay, Sir! We 'll spare our loves another day—and then— (A slight wild laugh.) Why then—Good night, said Atys—and Good night, Say I.—To-morrow, Sir, will tell you more. (Exit haughtily and wildly.) (Adrastus follows her to the secret door, returns musing, and sighs, looking at the dagger as he goes into his chamber.) Adrastus. Oh! END OF THE FOURTH ACT.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT V. Scene—A Portico and Area adjoining the Palace, with an ancient Altar—Couches here and there. Philon and an Officer. Philon. The morning air is cool and favourable. All 's right. See that the Choristers attend, Before the coming of the King and Nobles, Ready to greet the royal ear with glee. Officer. See yonder, Sir, his Highness with the Princess— A gloom unusual lowers upon his brow. Philon. Some serious talk, but soon that cloud will vanish. Health and the air have tempted him abroad. Let us retire. [Exeunt. (Crœsus and Ada, conversing earnestly, cross the portico—she goes off—he advances.) Crœsus alone. Crœsus. Somewhere there 's falsehood, faithlessness and treason. The Princess? Gods forbid!—Adrastus? No! Impossible! I cannot think him guilty. A mind like his, replete with lofty thoughts, Kind, candid, brave, and by affliction tried, Can never stoop to deeds corrupt and base. But Ada says it—and Ada must be base, If he be not.—On either side lie horrors. Would Atys were return'd!—What feeling 's this? Is 't fear?—Suspicion?—'Tis not happiness! Oh! man of Athens! at whom so late I scoff'd, Thy words come rushing on my memory: “Call no one happy ere he die”—Ah! Crœsus! Thou 'st made thy pride thy chief divinity, And deem'd thyself the ruler of thy fortunes— But now the gods assert their rights, to show They are the rulers o'er the affairs of men, And mock who solely on themselves rely. Philon! approach. Enter Philon. Philon. Your Highness has observed The preparations have been made. Crœsus. Good Philon! Far other thoughts engage my anxious mind. Philon. Anxious! Forbid it, heaven! Oh! may that word For ever be dismiss'd from Crœsus' lips! Crœsus. Philon! The man of Athens spoke the truth— Solon is wise, and Crœsus but a fool. Philon. Whate'er disturbs your Highness' mind, I trust Is but a slight and transient, airy, cloud, Dissolving as it forms. Crœsus. Judge of its weight By your amazement when I tell you, Philon, I wish to find a villain in—Adrastus. Philon. Your Highness does indeed amaze me—Gods! Can such a wish find place in Crœsus' mind? Crœsus. A dread alternative alone could raise it— A villain he, or Atys sacrificed! Bound in the dire chains of a new Medea! I know not what to think—Hast e'er observed Familiar gallantry, in look, or gest, That might denote him of licentious habits? Philon. Oh! never, Sir. Crœsus. Nor know you aught Might lead you to suspect he has designs Upon my son's bride? Philon. Good my Lord! Designs? Crœsus. You have not chanced to see them yet alone? Philon. Soon after the arrival of Adrastus, Passing the lobby of Prince Atys' rooms, I saw them in the gallery together, Alone and loud, and so absorb'd in talk I might have pass'd much nearer unperceived— Though nought they said distinctly reach'd my ear. But, gracious Sir, designs! Crœsus. Together! loud! By heaven! it is.—By heaven! it cannot be. E'en vice is neutralized by gratitude. Perdition! Yes, perdition's work begins— Philon. My King! my Master! be not thus moved, I pray. Crœsus. I'll tell thee, Philon.—Before his homicide, Adrastus was received by Ada's father, At Halicarnassus—But of this anon— For see who comes, all health and cheerful smiles! My sweet, my amiable Aryenis! Dear to my heart! thou daughter of my soul! (Embraces her.) Philon. How lovely nature shines In ties like theirs! [Exit Philon. Crœsus and Aryenis. Aryenis. My dear father!—It glads me, Sir, to see How much you relish the delights of others— Your morning thoughts are on our hunters turn'd, And bring you hither to anticipate. Crœsus. Trust me, my child, the habit is a good one. Who joy anticipates doth twice enjoy; And others' bliss is usury of bliss. Our sympathies have hitherto been joyous: But painful ones have far more pungent force. Aryenis. Far! far! as well I know, when for Adrastus I've felt the sympathy of grief. And yet The poignancy, I know not how, is soothed By some mysterious balm, self-minister'd. My father sighs—Sure, 'tis a new event! I scarce remember one so deep. Crœsus. Nor I.— You 've named Adrastus—tell me now, my child, Has he e'er spoke to you of love? Aryenis. He has— Oft has he warn'd me 'gainst its dangerous power: And with his mournful lips such lessons given, As would become the oldest sage of Greece. Crœsus. I own I thought him wise beyond his years— But has he made you offers of his love? Aryenis. Never.—But candidly to speak my thought, As I am used to thee, my dearest father, My ear deceived me, or he did last night. Yet 'twas so instantly recall'd, so soon Succeeded by deterring wisdom's counsel, That doubt I do not of my strange mistake. Crœsus. What think you of him? Aryenis. Dear Sir, as of one Whose virtues merit all the gods can grant. Crœsus. I think so too. Has Ada told you aught? Aryenis. Nought of Adrastus—Even now I met her; But stay'd her not—she frown'd and pass'd me by— What ails my father? Why so bent his brows? I never saw them thus before—Dear Sir! Your face no longer seems the face of Crœsus. Crœsus. Oh! how I love thee, Aryenis! How Throbs my fond heart with ever new delight When to this breast I press my virtuous child! Aryenis. Dear Sir! Crœsus. A cloud hangs over us, my daughter! Aryenis. When Crœsus talks of clouds, sure Nature 's changed. Crœsus. You know the love I cherish for your brother: You know in Atys centre all the hopes Of future heirs to Crœsus' throne and fortunes— What think you of your sister? Aryenis. Ada, Sir, Is eminent in beauty and in wit. Crœsus. Think you Adrastus is convinced of those? Aryenis. Sir!—who? Crœsus. Hath he discoursed her beauty to you? Aryenis. What means my father? Crœsus. Speaks he of her virtues? Aryenis. I rather think him niggard of his speech: He seldom mentions her, and never first. Last night, indeed—you bring it to my mind— Just when I thought he spoke of love to me, I mention'd Ada as a happy bride; When suddenly his cheeks their ruby lost, He mutter'd something of a heated brain, And most abruptly ended our discourse. Crœsus. Then! then, 'tis true—It must, it must be true. Aryenis. What must be true, my father? Crœsus. Oh! my child! Adrastus is—I cannot call him—villain. Aryenis. The gods forefend! 'Twere impious so to speak. Crœsus. With shameless love he persecutes your sister. Aryenis. Adrastus! 'Tis false! Believe it not. If ever heart of man was pure— Crœsus. Hark! (Noise at a distance.) The hunt is o'er—the hunters are returning. (A general scream near the palace.) What means that cry? (Persons enter, and hastily withdraw.) Come hither, Sir. (The person called, approaches uneasily, but passes and escapes.) Enter an Officer and Guards. Crœsus. What may this mean? Officer. My liege—Your Highness— Crœsus. Speak. Officer. The Prince your son— Crœsus. Where is he, Sir? Officer. My liege!—(Aside.)—I cannot speak. Crœsus. Call Atys in, I say— Why move ye not? (To the Guards.) Officer. Sir! collect yourself— Remember Crœsus is a King— Crœsus. Heaven! Lives my son? Officer. Would I could say he does! Aryenis. My brother dead?—Support—support the King. (Her father falls into her arms, the Officer helping—the Guards advance a couch.) My father! oh my father! Lifeless his hand—haste, haste for aid—fly, fly! [Exeunt Officer. He breathes not—Crœsus! king! father! awake! Enter Philon. (With Attendants—two Women go to Aryenis.) Philon. My king, my master, royal Crœsus! Oh! Aryenis. Life stirs not in him—Is my brother dead? (Philon makes a mournful sign.) Is there no hope from skill? Philon. Oh! Princess! none. Aryenis. He breathes—he moves—bear up, bear up, I pray. Crœsus. Oh!—Where? how?—where is my son? (Philon makes a mournful sign.) Where 's the corse? They shall answer it to me—Where 's the corse? Philon. Within the gates, upon the funeral car, Drawn by his mournful friends, approaching slow. Crœsus. You all shall answer it, all—Where's Adrastus? Philon. Lost youth! With heart dismay'd, and downcast eye, He follows close upon the car. Crœsus. But how? You answer not—What horror more awaits? How fell my son? Philon. Oh! King! Crœsus. I charge you, speak! Hide nought—my soul 's prepared to know the whole. Philon. The Prince—has perish'd—by Adrastus' hand. Crœsus. True at last! most monstrous! and most true! Oh! villain, villain, villain! Monster! monster! (Aryenis screams, falls into the arms of her Women, and is carried off.) Guards! seize, and drag him to my sight— (Some Guards go out.) He dies—slowly in flame expiring, dies. This intention of Crœsus to burn Adrastus, is historically true. —(Diodorus Siculus.) Now be his purifying fluid fire! So shall he expiate.—Command a stake (To Philon. Be here forthwith erected—And command Faggots, and blazing heath, and iron plates Susceptible of fire, to form a base, On which his tender soles may agonize. And, oh ye gods! invigorate sensation, To make his torture equal to his crimes! No fouler murder ever stain'd the earth! Oh! most licentious villain!—Ada! Ada! Thy truth I doubted—Philon, use despatch— Myself will tend the monster at the stake, And feast my grief upon the villain's pangs— And let the corse beside the stake be placed, That soul and body join to rack the wretch— Where is my daughter?—Gone!—Where 's Aryenis? Philon! despatch—Oh! Atys! Aryenis! Oh! my children! my children! [Exit. Philon. (To an Officer.) Sir, you have heard the royal orders given: See they be instantly obey'd.—Oh! Rhodius! Enter Rhodius. (During the following scene, the stake, faggots, &amp;c. are made ready.) Rhodius. A sad conclusion of our sport, good Philon! Oh! melancholy day!—How fares the King? Philon. As one bereft of hope, yet like a lion Chafed with his wound, regardless of despair— He dooms Adrastus to the flames. Rhodius. The flames! He wrongs himself—The hunters all proclaim Adrastus innocent, and I myself will vouch, For I was close upon the boar, The fault was more the Prince's than his friend's.— To save the Prince, on whom the monster brush'd, He aim'd his weapon at the foaming brute. Just as the shaft he hurl'd, back Atys leap'd, And met the point, which pierced him thro' the neck— When Atys sprung, Adrastus' lance was sped. The King must instant be inform'd of this. Philon. This truth, tho' proved, will little weigh, I fear, To change the purpose of the monarch's breast, Now pre-resolved by countervailing proof Of deeds atrocious, which confirm design.— Guards are despatch'd to seize him. Rhodius. That I know, For I was with the escort when they came, And hasten'd on to tell they are restrain'd, And by the Lydians kept from off the convoy. His new calamity is known to all: They grieve for Atys, but are just to him. [Exit. (Grave and solemn music, flutes prevailing —the procession—the car followed by Adrastus, &amp;c.—the car placed near the stake.) Adrastus, Orontes, Philon, Officers, &amp;c. Philon. Unhappy youth!—Oh! Sir, I cannot tell— (To an Officer.) Impart the royal sentence to the Prince. Officer. It is my duty, Sir, to speak— The King decrees your death. Adrastus. I welcome the decree. Officer. Permit—(Offering to bind him.) Adrastus. No bonds! I shall not shrink from pain. Orontes. How! Death? The stake! Monstrous! monstrous! it must not be. Where is the King?—The parent, Sir, may feel; The monarch must be just. Philon. Seek him, I pray. [Exit Orontes. Enter Ada. Philon. Madam! Madam! shun the car. Ada. Shun the car! Think'st thou that Ada faints at sight of death?— I'd speak in private with the Prince—fall back. (Philon and Attendants retire.) Ada. I know thy lofty and thy virtuous soul, Were it e'en tempted, pure of a design Which even love like mine could ne'er suggest: But let that pass—That love I come to prove— Nay, do not shudder—Hope hath left this breast— Thy new misfortune hath subdued my soul— And wrought a change unhoped, ineffable— I do repent me of the wrongs I 've done— With tears repent me of the wrongs I meant— Thy love I seek no more.—Oh! worthy youth! The gods do oft afflict whom most they love. Think of Alcides, When Hercules killed Iphitus he retired to Lydia, where he was long a slave to Omphale.—He was denied the necessary lustration by Neleus at Pylus—he obtained it from Deïphobus at Amyclæ. He applied to the Oracle at Delphi, and was answered, that he must spend three years in servitude to be effectually cured of a severe illness he had contracted on that occasion. —(Plutarch.) and support thy woes: Live to support them, so to please the heavens, Whose instrument thou art to punish Crœsus, Vainly elate with sublunary bliss. Adrastus. Now art thou lovely! Ada. The King believes thee false, And criminal—Forgive him this—'twas I— Another instrument of heavenly ire To punish royal pride and tutor princes— 'Twas I abused his ear. Adrastus. Oh! Ada. That groan Darts anguish with its keen reproach.—Adrastus, I come to disabuse the Parent's ear, Prove thee all virtue, and myself all guilt. Adrastus. Gods! what a mind has passion overthrown! Will you be now my friend? Ada. What would you? Speak. Adrastus. Conceal your error still—subdue all weakness, Establish firm your fame by virtuous deeds, Then by a glorious, as uncall'd, confession, Wipe off the stain from mine.—At present, oh! I 'm sick at heart, and long for death.—I pray, Do not, by sad and needless recantation, Deprive me of my only hope of rest. Ada (weeping.) Let my tears answer for my faulty soul:— Faulty it is indeed, but not ignoble. Adrastus. I meant not that—forgive—I meant— No matter— Enter Crœsus, Orontes, and Rhodius. Crœsus. Tell me not, Sir, of accident—Design Is clear at least in his licentious course— And see the Princess to confound him here. Thou murderer! Is this your gratitude? (In agony over the bier.) Where is my son?—Upon his bier—Yet, Prince! Had all been chance, had no foul passion sway'd, Justice had quell'd my rage. Adrastus. Crœsus! I 'm lost— I care not for my life.—I know the crime Of which you hold me guilty—Sir! Time was When Crœsus would have ask'd Adrastus kindly, “Is 't so?” and held his negative full proof— That time gone by, and this new horror fallen, I neither seek nor satisfy inquiry: I wish for death, and thank thee for my doom. Ada. Oh! wondrous virtue!—Crœsus! turn on me Those eyes of fire, and light round me the flames, Not to misfortune, but to falsehood due. Wretch that I am, I still must blush to own The sway which passion o'er this bosom bore. The Prince is innocent—I—I am guilty— Require no more—I speak before the gods. Crœsus. Amazement! Ada. Great King of Lydia! let not this amaze: But rather wonder heaven so long hath borne The impious vanity that swell'd thy mind In the proud course of thy prosperity. Now learn, that men—and kings are men—depend On heaven, whence joy and woe are dealt to earth. (Goes to the bier and weeps.) Atys! farewell! Accept a guiltless tear, In lieu of guilty smiles that mock'd thy faith— Friendship like thine deserved a better love. [Exit, weeping. Crœsus. The soul of Solon spoke in Ada's voice! Oh! Solon! Solon! When Crœsus was conquered by Cyrus, he was bound and about to be burned on a pile, when he remembered the words of Solon, and three times pronounced his name. The explanation, given at the request of Cyrus, preserved the life of Crœsus, and obtained him respect and honour with his conqueror. —(Plutarch's Life of Solon.)—Wretched, wretched youth! (To Adrastus.) Thy grief and voluntary condemnation Disarm my anger. Live, Adrastus, live. The immortal will 'tis fit I should obey— But oh! my children! my children! (Going.) Adrastus. Crœsus! stay. My second father! purifier! friend! Grant, grant thy pity to a wretch forlorn! One child remains to comfort yet thine age: Long may thy days fair Aryenis soothe! Thy grief from Nature flows: and Nature, kind, Knows how to heal the wound her hand inflicts: Horrors rouse mine:—Where'er I turn, is gore, Disaster, melancholy, black despair. Stain'd with a brother's blood, again this hand Hath plunged my benefactor into woe! Again deprived the man I loved of life! How can I live? Death is my sole resource— The history is, that Adrastus “retired at the dead of night to the place where Atys was buried, and confessing himself to be the most miserable of mankind, slew himself on the tomb.” And, Crœsus! thus I expiate the deed. (Stabs himself.) Crœsus. Hold! All. Oh! Adrastus. Atys! I come—Orontes! fare thee well! Say—say to Gordius—say to my dear father, I would—Agathon! Oh! (Dies.) END OF THE TRAGEDY.</field>
   </doc>
</add>