<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Cumberland, Richard, 1732-1811</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Cumberland, Richard, 1732-1811</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">cumberland richard 1732 1811</field>
      <field name="author_text">Cumberland, Richard, 1732-1811</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1810's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V2.0416.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1813</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:460117</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Torrendal ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Torrendal ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="title_facet">torrendal</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">torrendal</field>
      <field name="title_text">Torrendal ; A Tragedy</field>
      <field name="year_display">1813</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1813</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1813</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460117&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:460117&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;Cumberland, Richard, 1732-1811&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;cumberland richard 1732 1811&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Torrendal ; A Tragedy&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;torrendal&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1813&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1813&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Cumberland, Richard&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1732&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1811&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Torrendal&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed for G. and W. Nicol by W Bulmer and Co. [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1813&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872447-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv20416&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Torrendal&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A Tragedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 153 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Only verse drama included&lt;lb/&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Torrendal.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1813.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Unknown.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">TORRENDAL. A TRAGEDY.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">DRAMATIS PERSONÆ. Duke of Courland. Torrendal. Baron Vanhoven. Murinski. Lodowick. Adam. A Monk. Officer. Guards, &amp;c. &amp;c.—Servants of the Baron, &amp;c. Alicia, Countess Torrendal. Baroness Vanhoven. Marian, Wife to Lodowick.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">SCENE, Courland.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. Scene, the interior of a Cottage in Courland, belonging to Lodowick the Wood-cutter. He is sitting in his Chair dosing. Marian his Wife enters, and walking up to him, shakes him by the Shoulder. Lodowick, Marian. Mar. Rouse yourself Lodowick, you have dropt asleep, and your pipe is out. Lod. Aye, dame, 'tis dead, and turn'd to ashes. Mar. Shall I fill it afresh? Lod. No, let it be. Mar. Shall I fetch you something to wet your lips? You are weary, poor fellow. Lod. Not a drop. What's the hour? Mar. Past nine, and a dark night. Lod. Is Torrendal come in? Mar. No, he is yet out, wandering about the forest. I have set a candle in the upper window. Lod. You have done right. He must needs want a guide, whose senses are so totally astray, that when he is out of sight 'tis but a chance if ever he's seen more. Mar. Alas, poor man, if we can't cure him of these rambling fits, some night or other he'll be trapp'd by robbers, and leave his wretched bones in this wild forest. Lod. Robbers! who'll rob him? Every body flies him he's such a spectacle. Six months and more he has been feeding upon little else but sighs and groans for an abandon'd wife, not worth a thought. Mar. Ah, Lodowick, he cannot shake her from his thoughts. Some sorrows yield to time; his never will: body and mind they have destroy'd him wholly. Lod. Yes; sorrow is slow poison; he sinks under it. It grieves my heart to see him pine away day after day, and take no nourishment. If we set meat before him, he'll not touch it: the wild roots of the forest are his food, and better beverage than the brook affords ne'er moistens his parch'd lip. The time has been, when I remember him as fine a man as ever stepp'd the earth, —“the handsome Torrendal—the gallant Courlander,” so he was call'd. Mar. He was, he was. I never shall forget the day he enter'd Mittau with the troops that serv'd in Poland—you was in his train—aye, that you was—and rode a stately charger, though now you are fain to hoof it to the copse on your bare brogues, and labour for your living. Lod. Well, we must take what providence decrees; murmuring won't mend it. Count Torrendal was once a happy man; we liv'd with him, and led a happy life; now he is miserable, and lives with us.—So the world goes—and for myself, I care not; so let it go! I have nothing to complain of: I have my senses, and an honest wife; he has thrown his wits away upon a wanton. Mar. Aye, shame upon her! she is a wicked woman, that I will say—a base deceitful woman —is she not? when I reflect how happily they liv'd together, how good, how kind to her he ever was, I am astonish'd how she could be brought to abandon so excellent a husband, and become mistress to the Duke of Courland. Lod. Wife, 'tis a rule with me never to wonder at what a woman does. The Countess Torrendal has only shewn the world she had more vanity than virtue, and why her husband should, from that discovery, lose his reason, puzzles my wits as much as it does his—but hark! he's at the door. [A knocking is heard. Murinski calls from without. Mur. Within there—cottagers! Mar. That's not our master's voice. Do not go out unarm'd; take your sword with you! Lod. Pooh! what are you afraid of? Who's at the door? Mur. [from without] A traveller, that has lost his way and is benighted. Lod. Enter! [Opens the door and admits Murinski. Mur. I thank you. 'Twas a kindly deed, when moon and stars are wanting, to hang out that charitable light; it augurs well of your philanthropy. Lod. It augurs only that the night is dark, and we've a friend abroad in this wild place, whom we are expecting. Did you meet any person hereabouts? Mur. I met a man, who pointed out your cottage. Mar. Where have you left him? What have you done with him? Mur. Suspect me not, good dame. I am a gentleman, by name Murinski, in the especial service of the duke. Lod. Were you the duke himself, you should not stir out of these doors till I am satisfied my friend is safe. If, as you say, he pointed out the cottage, why did he not come with you? Mur. He did, till some few paces from your door he struck into the wood and disappear'd. I call'd to him, but to confess the truth, his gesture was so wild, his voice so stern, and his tall figure, through the misty gloom, so strikingly terrific, I was not over-anxious to detain him, he being arm'd withal, and I defenceless. Lod. You have seen enough to guess at his misfortune: he is derang'd in mind. Mur. I did suspect it. Nothing could I wring from him by the way, but broken murmurs in a hollow voice, and sighs between that seem'd to rend his breast. His step was slow and solemn, ill adapted to my impatience, and I own my heart shook with alarm, when, stopping on the sudden, he seiz'd my wrist, and in a tone, that seem'd more like the scream of pain than human speech, demanded—“Was I married?”—To which, when I gave answer I was not—“'Tis well for you,” he cried, “that you are not, else had I beat your brains out with this club, in very charity to save your wits.” Lod. Aye, that's the pinch; there is the point that wrings him—But hark! he is coming. [Torrendal strikes the door with his club-stick. Pray you, stand aside; wait, till we see what humour he is in. Marian will speak to him— [Marian opens the door, Torrendal enters. Mar. Oh welcome, welcome! we have been looking for you this long long hour. Where, in the name of wonder, have you been rambling at this time of night? Tor. Where the wolf rambles—up and down the forest. Night is my day; I walk not in the sun, For fear my shadow, falling on the bosom Of mother Earth, should turn her milk to gall. The tears I shed are cankerous as the drops Of rain distilling from that pois'nous tree, Beneath whose shade no vegetation lives. Here, Lody, put my staff into its place— I met a traveller—Hah! there he is— How fare you, sir? you journey in the dark. It is surprising, with how little light Some men will find their way through this blind world. Mur. What do I see? Can Torrendal be living? That voice, that air, that form—and yet how chang'd! Tor. Heaven keep your wits! what is that disturbs you? Do you see aught in me to move your wonder? Mur. Much to engage my pity. Tor. Why, what ails me? My wounds are out of sight. If I'd as many As there are stars, so they were in my flesh, I would not wince; but stab me in my spirit, Who can heal me? What say'st thou, Lodowick? Thou art a wood-cutter, the foe of nature, It is thy trade to murder vegetation; Didst ever know the tree that fail'd to die, When thy sharp axe had cut it to the heart? Lod. Come, sir, we'll call to mind the good old maxim—“Repeat no grievances”— Tor. Right! you are right; we'll hold to that good maxim, And make our griefs our sport: I'll be as merry As misery can make me. Tales of woe, That wring the whimpering tear from reason's eye, Madness shall laugh at. I'm in cue for mirth. Lod. Then happy be the hour! let us to supper! Our fare is homely, but our welcome's hearty: Marian has oaten cakes and roots on the fire; Shall we go set them out? Tor. By all means, Lody; set out what you have. Nature gives largely; we can spare a part. And harkye, my good wench, this man is weary; Spread him my bearskin for his bed to-night. I can read soldier in his face, and that's a billet For bed and board in every house he enters— Go; leave me with him! Mar. I will, I will. Heaven comfort your kind heart. [Exeunt Marian and Lodowick. Torrendal, Murinski. Tor. Ah, will that pray'r be heard? Now, sir, I know you. When I was Torrendal, and had a heart, I shar'd it with Murinski— Mur. Oh, my friend, If I have held that trust in happier days, 'Tis now, when Torrendal has need of comfort, I would fain share his heart and its afflictions. Tor. No, no, forget me; I am gone to ruin; I am as one that's dead and out of memory, And when I throw these wither'd arms about you, I press you to a cold and lifeless corpse, That chills you with its touch. [Embraces him. Mur. It warms, it cheers me, It gives a spring to all those tender cords, That early friendship twin'd about my heart. Tor. Do you still hold your station with the duke? Mur. I do. Tor. Then wherefore ask to know my sorrows? They are before you—every hour in sight— Each moment that you meet that shameless duke And my false wife must give them to your view. You best can witness how I lov'd Alicia, You then can best conjecture what I suffer. Mur. I hope you mean never to see her more. Tor. I see her every where, by night, by day, Sleeping or waking, still her vision haunts me; I saw her in the forest where you met me; She was then with me, walking by my side: There is no place secure; darkness can't hide her, Nor solitude, nor silence can exclude her. Mur. Do these good cottagers, with whom you harbour, Know you for Torrendal? Tor. They, and none else. I know there is a rumour of my death; I humour that report. You must be secret— Mur. As your own thoughts. Tor. What brings you to these parts? Mur. I'm sorry you inquire, for I must tell you. The Duke of Courland meditates a visit To the old baron of Vizinga castle. Tor. We shall be neighbours—Comes my misery with him? Yes, yes, she comes; I see her in his train: He travels in his proper state of splendour, With his full equipage of crimes about him. Now let Vanhoven conjure all his demons; And preternat'ral wonders aid the skill Of this far-fam'd magician. Mur. I have heard Most wond'rous fables told of this impostor. Tor. It is an age of wonders, and Vanhoven The wonder of the age. If you've a friend In t'other world, whom you would wish to see, Vanhoven is your man to call him up, Though he were bedded in the Baltic wave, And he shall come in person, or by proxy, No matter which—There is a curious fellow, Adam by name, an imp of the old wizzard, Who shall act Cæsar's ghost so like to Cæsar, That Brutus, were he living, should not know him From the true ghost, that met him at Philippi. Mur. How far from hence does this Vanhoven dwell? Tor. Scarce three bow-shots from hence his castle lies, A mould'ring monument of ancient days, Buried in swamps, through which no trodden path, No smoking chimney lures the traveller; His hall ne'er echoes with the festive song, But from the hollow tower the night-bird screams, And croaking ravens chorus to the yell Of the starv'd watch-dog howling to the moon: There, in his moated fortress deep entrench'd, In feudal state the musing baron sits, Whilst his torn banners, hanging by the wall, Recall, in retrospection, times foregone— Pondering his spells, he sits; at dead of night The neighb'ring peasant hears, or thinks he hears, Deep sighs and dismal groans of troubled ghosts Torn from their peaceful graves—Such is Vanhoven, Fit host, I ween, for his unholy guests. [Adam walks in cloked, and carrying a lantern, which he deliberately extinguishes, and puts by. Mur. Soft, who comes here? what solemn thing is this, That stalks in as by right, and gives no warning? Tor. This is the fellow that I told you of, Death's major-domo, he that keeps the key Of all the cells, charnels, and catacombs Where ghosts are quarter'd—How now, master Adam! What business brings you here, and why that lantern? Adam. My business is with Lodowick the woodman; And for the lantern, I must needs want light, When neither moon nor stars are in the skies. Tor. Can phosphorus want light? Let the stars go to bed; Let the good housewife Night put out her candles, You, and the self-illuminated owl, May travel without lanterns—Hoa! within there— [Calls for Lodowick. Mur. I understand, grave sir, that you belong To the great sage, whose fame the world resounds with, Baron Vanhoven— Adam. I'm his servant, sir. Mur. The wisdom that you carry in your looks, Shews you a servant worthy such a master. Adam. Sir, I'm not wise, not positively wise. Tor. No, but he follows wisdom at the heels, As a cur does a beggar; With the next turn he'll catch her by the skirts— This mummery disgusts me—Let us leave him— Here, Lodowick, where are you?—You are wanted— [Exeunt Torrendal and Murinski. [As Torrendal and Murinski are going out, they meet Lodowick, who comes from the inner room. Lodowick, Adam. Lod. Ah, master Adam, what is your good pleasure? Adam. Hear me, thou vassal of the great Vanhoven! The Duke of Courland and his peerless mistress are coming to Vizinga. You must up, and drive the forest by the peep of day. Lod. Why must I drive the forest? Adam. To kill him venison for his princely guest. Lod. I'll kill him a wild boar; methinks, friend Adam, the flesh of swine will better suit his highness, and breed a chyle more generous and congenial than flesh of timorous deer—What have those peaceful creatures done, that I should kill them? Adam. What have they done, that you should let them live? Lod. They are my friends; they visit me at my work, and when the echo of my hatchet lures their harmless curiosity, they come and stand, and gaze with such a listening look, that I can fancy myself another Orpheus, and my rude tool a lyre. Adam. Fancy yourself what you are, the vassal of the Lord Vanhoven, and let those friends of yours, that are so fond of music, dance into his kitchen, or, take my word, friend Orpheus, he'll make you dance out of this house to the tune of an ejectment. Lod. I hope he'll not do it; my father, and my father's father have held it for a pretty many years. Adam. If you had held it from the days of Noah, you will be ousted, so I tell you, friend, unless you stir betimes, and bring us something to set the spits a-turning. Lay down your hatchet, and take up your gun; that's music we have some ear for. What, what! princes must fare like princes; courtiers palates must be tickled with savoury sauces, and favourite ladies must have favourite bits—partridge or quail, or a nice thrush in vine-leaves must be serv'd up to the all-powerful countess. Lod. To her! to Courland's mistress! Let her fast, and physic her hot blood with such poor fare as may beget repentance, and atone to an unhappy husband, in whose heart her gross adulteries have planted daggers. Adam. What's that you talk of? Are you mad or drunk, or both at once, to give your tongue such license? Adulteress! she cannot be, for Torrendal is dead. Lod. Oh, is he so? It had escap'd my memory. Adam. If you escape the gallows, I shall wonder. Why, you are worse than your mad guest himself. I'll stay no longer in your company; I have given you your orders; so remember; I have done with you. Lod. Stop! you have drawn me unawares to say more than I ought in prudence to have said. If you are dispos'd to take advantage of it, I am at your mercy; you may cite me before the baron, and he may cite me before the duke, and there will be an end; your spite can go no further: the worst that can befall me, will be to suffer for my affection to a noble master, for such was the Count Torrendal to me. Adam. Well, well! that's some excuse: you lov'd your master, and resent his wrongs. I shan't betray you; but take better heed how you make other people's cause your own. And now I've often thought to ask you, Lodowick, who is this strange mysterious man, who has liv'd with you for months, and no one knows by his true name? Lod. Who is he? Adam. Aye, who is he, and how do you contrive to keep an idler at your cost, who strolls about, and never, as I am told, has turn'd his hand to any useful labour? Lod. He was not bred to labour, and, had he been, he is too ill to work. Adam. Then why do you maintain him? Lod. Because when I was poor, and he had plenty, I was maintain'd by him. As for who he is, and what he is, you will excuse me: he is an innocent man, and an injur'd man. Adam. A crazy one, I believe. Lod. The greater his misfortune; he thinks much, and is at times derang'd; but he is now calmer, and more compos'd than I have known him for months foregone. Adam. Well, I'll not trouble you with more questions—Give me your hand!—You have said enough. Good night! remember me to Marian. Lod. Thank you, friend Adam! I'll be with you early, and bring you something, if my gun don't fail me. Adam. Do so; it will be welcome, for we are unprovided: between you and me, honest Lodowick, in our castle the larder is the emptiest room in the house, and the kitchen is the coolest; the very rats are upon short allowance. Therefore bring something with you by all means —Come, you shall light my lantern at your candle, and then once more—Good night. [Exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. Scene, an Apartment in the Castle of Vizinga: the Style that of ancient Architecture. Baron Vanhoven and Baroness. Van. Here, madam, read this letter from the duke; read it, and see what honours he intends us. Bar. Excuse me: I am not gratified by his flattery; if you are, read it yourself. Van. Well, so I will; but why do you pronounce it to be flattery? Does not philosophy merit respect? Bar. Ah, my good baron, your philosophy is something so mysterious and so dark, that my common sense can't comprehend it—but read your letter, if you please—I'll hear it. Van. Do so! attend! 'Tis written all through with his highness's own hand— [Reads. To the Baron Vanhoven. [Secret and confidential.] “Learned Sir! “I am on my way to visit you, drawn by the report of your miraculous performances, to the castle of Vizinga, as suitors were of old to the Oracle of Delphi. I bring with me a fair client to your shrine, the relict of the deceased Count Torrendal. She has scruples of much moment to refer to you, the which if you can resolve to her satisfaction and repose, you will establish the fame of your philosophy in its fullest lustre, and shew yourself to be that illuminated sage, which some want faith to believe you are, but which I am willing to hope you will approve yourself to be. Yours, in all worthy service, Courland.” Well, baroness, what have you to say to this? Bar. Nothing, for I can discover nothing in that letter, but danger to you, and disappointment to the writer of it. Van. What danger do you apprehend to me? Explain yourself! Bar. I don't wish to explain myself; perhaps I cannot, at least to your satisfaction I am sure I cannot. There is so much credulity in mankind now towards things incredible, and so little faith in things worthy to be credited, that it is very possible they may expect of you something that you cannot perform, and ought not if you could. Van. What do you suppose it is they may expect of me? Bar. 'Tis hard to say what an imperious libertine, and an ambitious woman, may expect: one thing you are warn'd of—the lady has doubts; and well she may: conduct, like her's, will naturally entail some scruples on the conscience; these you are to have the honour of appeasing: I know not what resources you may have in your philosophy; but, for my part, I can't conceive what honour it will gain by finding salvos for adultery. Van. What do you know of my philosophy? Bar. But little, yet too much: this, however, I know, (and you who are a husband won't dispute it)—wives should be honest. Van. Yes, and those wives, whom nature stints in beauty, are honest by their fate. The Countess Torrendal can plead temptations, that few, if any, who arraign her conduct, would have withstood. Bar. Temptations! What should tempt her to abuse so excellent a husband? All the world pities him, and condemns her. Van. What does she care about the world's opinion, and how is he the better for its pity? The gentleman is dead. Bar. I understand that is not quite so certain; this may be amongst the lady's scruples, that she may think your art can ascertain. Van. Well, madam, if she does, I am prepar'd. Bar. Ah, baron, baron, 'tis a fatal omen for the world's peace, when men take up such arrogant opinions; and think themselves illuminated beings, when they have shut their eyes against that light, which heaven, in mercy, had reveal'd to save them. But I have done; thank heaven, my humble task is simply to prepare you food and lodging for your expected guests—the sooner that task is discharg'd, the better—so farewell. [Exit. Van. Well! Socrates was married, so am I. She has guess'd right, however, at the motives of Courland's visit; I shall be requir'd to raise the ghost of Torrendal— Adam appears. Van. Adam, come in! I have something to impart to you. Shut the door!—Adam, I have reason to suspect this visit of the Duke of Courland's, will call upon us to exert our art; if so, I would wish to set our mystery off in its best form. Adam. Well, sir, we have got a famous apparatus. Van. For common purposes we are provided, but not for all—Suppose I should be put to raise a certain ghost— Adam. We have shadows for the purpose. Van. But shadows should be like their substances. The death of Torrendal is yet in doubt —What if the duke command me to exhibit his apparition? I don't know his person; who will describe him to me? Adam. Lodowick, your vassal; the wood-cutter, that lives here in your forest: he was servant to the count for years. Van. Find out that Lodowick immediately, and send him to me. Adam. So please you, sir, he is gone out to shoot game for the castle—but his friend is here; the guest he harbours in his house is walking now hard by— Van. Well, if he is, what knows he of the matter? Adam. 'Tis hard to say, most venerable sir, what he does not know. Van. Indeed! I'm told he is unsound of mind. Adam. He may be so at times, or he may seem so to those who cannot rightly comprehend him. Van. That's true, that's true. Genius appears like madness to the vulgar. You have rais'd my curiosity to see him—Adam admit him instantly. [Exit Adam. Vanhoven alone. How many a man, in this misjudging world, By loftiness of thought, or depth of study In sciences abstruse, appears insane, Wild, and eccentric to the level eye Of common observation! One of these This man, perchance, may be—Hah! he appears— Torrendal enters. My servant tells me you attend to see me— Tor. I covet that high honour—Who does not, That has respect for science? Van. I'm told you dwell With Lodowick, my vassal— Tor. Sapient baron, Under your sage protection I am harbour'd, By your poor vassal in his humble cottage. I have known better days—but they are past. Van. Your phrase bespeaks you of no vulgar breeding, And what I had in mind to ask of him, You can perhaps resolve—It has been told me, This Lodowick, with whom you sojourn, liv'd And serv'd in Poland with Count Torrendal— Know you if this be so? Tor. Sir, so it is. Van. I never saw the person of the count: He could describe him to me. Tor. I should think so. Van. But can you say (for that imports me most), If Lodowick was with him when he died? Tor. Died!— Van. What alarms you? Torrendal is dead— Know you not that? Tor. Yes—Torrendal is dead— His nobler part is perish'd—He is dead. Van. You knew him, I should guess— Tor. I knew him once— No one could know him now—He's greatly chang'd— Van. All men are chang'd by death. Tor. And some by sorrow. Death cannot quench the soul as misery can; The worm preys only upon carcases: Misery can make the living man a corpse, And render frightful the fairest work of heav'n. Van. Do you now speak of Torrendal as living? Tor. No, no, I told you Torrendal is dead. Who ever lov'd as he did, and outliv'd The loss of what he lov'd? Is there in man That heart, which injuries deep as he has suffer'd, And fell ingratitude cannot destroy? Van. You're speaking of his wife— Tor. Aye, of his wife— Van. Of her, who now is Courland's reigning mistress— Tor. Of her—of her—of her. Van. You are much mov'd. Tor. Not much—not much. Dark deeds will come to light. For sure I am, lord baron, there is kept A register of every secret crime; That whatsoever we have lost on earth, By man's injustice, shall be found in heav'n; The injured husband's soul shall rest in peace. But for this woman— Van. You seem to know the tale So variously related; some acquit, And not a few condemn her. She is coming Here to Vizinga: 'tis a princely visit, Unsought and unexpected, for I give My thoughts to study. Tor. Yes, and wonderous things Are bruited of your studies: it is said That you unlock the graves, and, by your spells, Call up the spirits of departed men, Though buried fathoms deep at the sea-bottom. This is most wonderful—But, mighty seer, Are there no spirits, who resist your spells? Van. The spirits of the dead, as of the living, Are various in their kinds; some will oppose And mutiny against the potent spell, That in the end constrains them to appear. Tor. Of what degree are these? Van. I'll tell thou that—When injuries have been done To the deceas'd, and I call up their spirits In presence of the persons who have wrong'd them, So strong must be the charm, that shall enforce The angry and reluctant ghost to rise, And, when he comes, 'tis with threat'ning face, And yell so hideous, as must needs appall The stoutest heart with terror and amaze— For instance—in the dreadful case of murder, The scene is more than nature can abide. Tor. I can believe it: let me then suppose An injur'd husband rising from the grave Upon the call of his adulterous wife— Van. The adulterous wife might die upon the spot. Tor. She might—but would she? No, they do not die Of such slight cause; their consciences are sear'd, And 'tis not sounds or shadows can affright them. They only tremble at the living husband, The dead is out of thought. If your frail guest Would see the shadow of her injur'd lord, You need not tax your art to raise his ghost, Any stale mummery will pass on her, Who only wants to sanction her offence, And hold a show of conscience to the world. Van. Who you may be, I know not; your discourse Betokens observation, and a judgment That, little dazzled by exterior seeming, Looks deep into the heart—I now must leave you. To-morrow I would fain renew our talk, So each to other shall be better known. Tor. I'm yours, at any hour. Van. I'm with the sun; His orient beams ne'er find these eyelids clos'd In dull ignoble sleep. With the first dawn I will expect you at the castle gate; There shall be found, who will conduct you to me. Till then, farewell!— Tor. I humbly take my leave. [Exit. Van. Why do they say this man is craz'd? 'Tis false; His reason is disturb'd, but not destroy'd: As glass, when broken into fragments, seems More sparkling than when perfect and entire, So do his wits break out in brighter gleams, Wand'ring and wild, than when by judgment fixt. [Exit. Scene changes to another Apartment in the Castle of Vizinga. Baroness Vanhoven and a Monk. Bar. Father, I want your counsel how to act in a divided duty. The Duke of Courland is expected here, and brings his favourite mistress, Countess Torrendal. My honour and my conscience both revolt against the company of that bad woman. My husband mocks these scruples, and requires me to entertain her—Must I obey him? Monk. No, you must not: I warn you to beware: if he has made, as I suspect he has, an impious compact with the evil spirits, at his soul's peril, it cannot be for any worthy purpose that Courland brings his guilty mistress hither; therefore, daughter, separate yourself in time from their society, for, I predict, their witchcrafts and adulteries will draw some just and dreadful judgment down ere they depart. Bar. I fearfully expect it. Thanks, good father! give me your prayers, and take me to your peace. Let us withdraw: we fall on evil times. [Exeunt. Adam enters. Adam. The baron in his conjuring room, the baroness with her confessor, the Duke of Courland at the door, and nobody to receive him but I, Adam, and only I—Well, here he comes—a prince is but a man. Duke of Courland, Countess Torrendal, Attendants. Duke. At length we have conquer'd all our difficulties, and with much toil and labour, through ways so wild and rugged, as would have baffled travellers less zealous, reach'd the mansion of the omniscient sage—but where's our host to give us welcome? Does the baron know of our arrival? Adam. Most gracious prince, I have sent to give him notice. The baron occupies a distant quarter, and had withdrawn to study. Duke. We can excuse him, sir; he is a philosopher and not a courtier—but look! he comes— Vanhoven enters and makes a profound reverence. Baron Vanhoven, we are come thus far to lay a trouble on you; but as the feast we look for don't consist in table dainties, we have so contriv'd to take you by surprise, that we may levy simply a soldier's ration on your castle, and no more. Van. Your highness does me infinite grace, and I pray you to accept the homage of a poor hermit, who has nought to offer but cordial welcome to his homely cell. Duke. In point of solitude, it may resemble what you are pleased to style it; but, when found, it is a stately castle. Van. 'Tis like its owner, old and out of fashion. Count. It is the seat of science, and so far it may be said to be out of fashion. Duke. I once had wrote you letters, learned sir, inviting you to court; but, when I weigh'd the value of your time, I thought the sacrifice a public loss, and therefore came with this my fair companion, that I might have to say I had seen Vanhoven, the wonder of the age. Van. Your highness flatters your poor host too highly. Time, and a patient thought, will teach us something; and sages, who by study have discover'd the wond'rous powers and properties of nature, will do those things that make the vulgar stare, and set them down for sorcerers and magicians. Duke. This modest answer raises my high opinion of your great merits: I must now remind you, that all men, who possess superior talents, must pay a tax to curiosity, and you, of all men living in these times, stand at the highest rate in that assessment. Now, baron, you must know that I have vested all such my right and title in this lady, whom I shall leave with you to state her claims, and that your conference may not be disturb'd, be pleas'd to shew me where I may withdraw. Van. This door, sir, opens to a gallery—There's space at least, but little to amuse. Is it your pleasure to enter?—Your highness commands here: my duty is to obey. Duke. I leave my pledge with you. We shall soon meet again. [Exit with Attendants. Vanhoven, Countess Torrendal. Van. Now, lady, speak your pleasure! We are private. Count. It may be so; but there is nothing here, That marks the school of the philosopher; No mystic books, no symbols of your art: This is a room of state; it is not here That you perform those wonders, that excite The world's amazement, and my anxious hopes. Where is your place of study? Shew me that. Van. Instruction is not limited to place: Plato could teach in groves, and Socrates Could moralize even in the public streets. Count. But Socrates had private intimations From his familiar demon—So have you— Those awful visions, those mysterious meetings, There, there it is I am curious to be present. Van. That curiosity you might repent of. Count. I come to know my fate; disclose that to me, And in whatever terrors you may clothe The revelation, I am arm'd to meet them. Van. Then tell me what it is that you would know: Let me have clear perception of your wishes. Count. 'Tis said, that by your spells you can call up The spirits of the dead from out their graves, And shew them in their proper form and feature To such as you admit into your circle— I solemnly adjure you to declare If this, which I have heard, be true or false. Van. Excuse me, lady; these are mysteries I may not speak of: you must wave that question; You may proceed to others; well assur'd That what I shall attempt, I can perform. Count. Resolve me then if Torrendal be dead— Van. What proof do you require? Count. Ocular proof. Van. You're a bold woman. Would you see his ghost? Count. Stop! give me time: fix not your eyes upon me; You stagger my resolve. Van. What are these doubts? You know that he is dead; Why then disturb his spirit? Let him rest. Count. If I had peace, his spirit should have rest, But I am rack'd with terror and suspense. The man that brought me tidings of his death, Might be impos'd upon, might be suborn'd, He did not see him dead; no one is found To vouch that fact by evidence of sight. Van. But what is the report? Where did he die? Count. In Lithuania. Van. By what kind of death; Natural, or violent? Count. 'Tis said he sicken'd, And died by slow disease; but from the hour In which he left me, by the duke's command, To serve in Poland, not a word e'er reach'd me By letter, or by message, to relieve My anxious heart: twelve tedious months roll'd on, And all was silent, cruel, cold neglect; Can you then wonder if I fly to you, Whose spell the tenants of the grave obey, To call that awful apparition forth, And end at once my life or my suspense? Van. That spectre will be terrible to sight, The weakness of your sex may sink before it. Count. If you have look'd on spectres, and outliv'd it, Ev'n so may I; therefore prepare your spell, For I'm resolv'd. The peril of the act Be on my head! Van. Then let me warn the duke, And I no longer will oppose your wish. Count. So let it be! Where shall we meet, and when? Van. When darkness thickens, and the evening star Trims his pale lamp, will be the hour to meet: The place, my cell, beneath the western tower; There you must come in silence and alone, If come you will in spite of my protest; And when the ghost of him, that was your husband, Torn from the bowels of a distant grave, In shadowy terror stalks around the circle, Where you stand trembling— Count. Break off your description! Leave me to meditation— Van. Heaven direct That meditation, and divert your thoughts From this ill-omen'd enterprise!—Farewell! [Exit. Countess Torrendal. Why do I pause? There is no cure for conscience, Nothing to save my honour, and build up My fortune into greatness, but this ghost: Let me be once assur'd that he is dead, And I am Courland's consort, not his mistress: Ambition thus in me becomes a virtue; And what have I to fear from him when dead, Whom living I ne'er wrong'd, but truly lov'd, Till absent he forgot me? then, indeed, When I had lost his heart, I lost myself, And Courland triumph'd—Now, if some should ask What kind of spirits are they, good or evil, Which minister their aid to this magician, Is that for me to answer? No, for him. If, by his power, with these, to me unknown, He can compel my husband's ghost to rise, How terrible soever, let him come, 'Tis but his shade, and I will look upon him.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. Lodowick's Cottage. Torrendal sitting—Marian in attendance. Mar. Good master, you have slept. Tor. I have, good mistress; The humming of your wheel lull'd me to sleep. Mar. Marry, my wheel has wrought a blessed work, Heav'n's mercy heal you! Tor. If I am not heal'd, It was at least a merciful delusion, That led me to believe it. I have dreamt, And in my vision a wing'd cherub came, Who on my throbbing temples laid his hand, Moist with celestial dew; methought the touch Thrill'd every nerve, and to my brain so swift The magic virtue ran, that I was heal'd. Mar. Oh joyful hearing! as the truth is in me, I have not seen your features so compos'd This many and many a day. Tor. Be not deceiv'd; This visitation is not for my cure, But my correction: 'tis a quick'ning call, Rousing my torpid faculties to action, With reason lent me for a time to guide them. Mar. What do you mean? Tor. That I have now my senses But as a loan, which providence imparts To arm me for the task I have in hand. Mar. Ah, sir, sir, sir, do you relapse so soon? Have you forgot your dream? Your looks are chang'd; They terrify me now. Tor. Go, call your husband; Tell him I'd speak with him. Kind, friendly creature, I would not harm thee for the worth of worlds; But when the tempest tears the forest up, The shatter'd oak may fall, and in its wreck Whelm the poor lamb, that fled to it for shelter. Go, send your husband to me. [Exit Marian. Torrendal alone. What! shall adultery pass unreveng'd? Shall a man take my wife from me and live? I can bear poverty, and cold, and hunger, And be as patient as I ought to be; But, when a shameless villain stains my honour, Then to be tame, what is it but to abet The crime we dare not punish? I know there is a law for our redress, But when the culprit is above the law, A man's own spirit must be his avenger, And his own sword becomes the sword of justice. Lodowick enters. Lod. Now, my good master, what has pass'd with Marian To ruffle and disturb you? Let me hear it— Nay, if you chafe your forehead, I can guess How it is with you—Pray you now, sit down, And I'll sit by you. Tor. Lodowick! [They sit. Lod. Say on. I'm all attention. Tor. 'Tis not possible That I and Courland both survive this night: If I am lost, what will become of thee? Lod. Think not of me. I have made up my mind. Tor. Thou art a hero, Lodowick; I know it— But Marian, your poor Marian—Ah, that touches; That makes you shake your head—that sorrow sinks Deep in your heart, and brings the waters up— I would weep too, but that my brain on fire Dries up the fountain that should feed my eyes, And I can't shed one tear—Still I've a soul, That feelingly conceives all I should say At our last parting, but I cannot speak it— Here, take this casket! It will keep off want. Give it to Marian, and when night comes on, Fly, for your lives. Lod. No. Tor. What means no? Lod. I never can, I never will desert you: As for this casket, I'll place it, where I hope, with heav'n's permission, You may resort to find it. Tor. You are a strange being— Lod. I am an honest one. Say only, do you mean the duke should die? Tor. Wretch, monster, murderer of my bosom's peace! [Starts up. Lod. Think no more of him—He will hunt to day: I know each haunt and covert of the forest— Tor. What do you mean? you have once lent your bosom To the sword's point for me, but 'twas in battle, 'Twas when I thought myself the happy husband Of a beloved wife, and I forgave you; But, now, when I am weary of the world, There's no redemption left for me but death. To undermine the virgin's chastity, The parent's peace, the wife's fidelity, The husband's honour, these are modern arts, Events too trivial to create surprise, And crimes too common to extort a blush— I am not made for such a world as this. Lod. Then seek a better, sir, and let me follow you, For now I am convinc'd there is no hope To turn your thoughts from vengeance to contempt. Tor. No, no, contempt can film a shallow wound, Deep ones will rankle where it cannot reach. You know in what obscurity I found This false unfaithful woman—a poor orphan, One, who with beauty to inflame desire, Had poverty to expose her to seduction; I felt the passion, but disdain'd the crime. When I had put necessity aside, And she was free to choose, I made my suit; We married, and she knows not to this hour Whose hand it was that rescued her from want. Lod. That was indeed a gen'rous noble act. Tor. Three years she led a life without reproach; So fond was I, my very soul was love: At length the war in Poland call'd me from her; The Duke of Courland, with dissembled friendship, Profess'd to pity me, and at our parting Begg'd I would trust my wife to his protection: His age, his station, his imposing gravity, Conspir'd to blind me—I bequeath'd her to him, And mark what misery he has heap'd upon me! Marian enters hastily. Mar. Sir, sir, the baron—the great Lord Vanhoven— The Baron enters. Tor. Leave us! [Exeunt Lodowick and Marian. You're welcome, sir, to this poor cottage— It is a wholesome practice, now and then, To cast a look on humble poverty, And see how very little will suffice For simple nature, where contentment is. What is your pleasure? Van. First, accept this purse— Tor. Excuse me, sir; money I never lov'd, And since I have been taught to live without it, It would but trouble me. Van. Give me your hand! You are no common person, I perceive: You should be one of us— Tor. I shall be soon, when you and I are pent In the dark house together. Van. What d'ye mean? I am not dying. Tor. No, nor yet far off: As for myself, being a ghost already, You cannot keep me long out of my grave. Van. I understand you now, and you have struck Upon the very business brings me hither; The lady favourite will see her husband— Tor. Well, let her see him! Only let me be there, and she shall see him. Van. What do you mean? Are you of the illumin'd? Tor. Not I; not I—Only let me be there, I may help on the process. Van. How can that be, Seeing you know it not? Tor. Describe it to me! Van. Then mark me—When the chamber is prepar'd, And all my magic apparatus fixt, The parties enter—Silence is commanded, And I withdraw to pray— Tor. Whom do you pray to, And for what do you pray? Van. Be not curious. When incantations have arous'd the spirits, Their coming is announc'd by various sounds; The air is troubled, and the chamber shakes: With horrid yells the evil demons come; The good and friendly with harmonious strains, And voices sweet as the Æolian lyre— Tor. There is variety in that at least. Van. Hear me! for now the crisis is at hand; This is the shock—Cold sweat bedews my brow, My knees shake under me, and all my frame Is paralyz'd with horror; bars and bolts Cannot fence off the energetic spirits, Full of the spell; the chamber doors burst open, And the ghost enters— Tor. That will be a meeting Of flesh and spirit curious to behold. Where will this scene be acted? Van. In my cell, Under the western turret. Tor. At what hour? Van. An hour past midnight. Tor. May not I be present? Van. Can you be secret? Tor. As the grave—nay more— For you can open graves, but not one thought, That's buried in this bosom. Van. You may come; But come alone—Be faithful, and farewell! [Exit. Torrendal. Oh thou, that in my vision I beheld, Cherub divine, let fall one healing drop Of that sweet balm, in which thy wings are dipt, And touch these aching temples yet again With thy lethæan hand; strengthen my heart For this expected meeting; let not rage Possess me wholly, keep alive one spark Of pity and compassion, to remind me That even madness should respect a woman. [Exit. An Apartment in the Baron's Castle. Countess Torrendal alone. The evil that we feel, is but a feather, If weigh'd against the evil that we dread. Though 'tis beyond the compass of my reason To comprehend the power, by which this sorcerer Performs the feats, that are reported of him, Does that impeach his power? No, it does not: How many thousand wonders in creation Mock the philosophy of reasoning man! Put this into the number, and it adds No more than one drop to the boundless ocean. Duke of Courland enters. Duke. Now, by my life, Alicia, it repents me That we came hither; three times since the morning Have I surpris'd you thus alone, withdrawn From our society and wrapt in thought. Where are those smiles, that dimpled on your cheeks? Those eyes, whence ambush'd Cupids took their aim, And launch'd their arrows at beholders hearts? Let us begone at once. Count. Not for the world. Duke. Why? what good purpose can our stay effect? Why did we quit the pleasures of the court, To visit this old wizzard in his cell? Count. The pleasures of the court! No, call them rather The agonies, the torments—which to escape, Hither I come; and, rather than remain In painful ignorance of what I am, Urge on the revelation of my fate, With all its horrors—Is not this a cause? Duke. You thought it such, and therefore I embrac'd it; But first consider if you have need to fly To spells and charms, and next be well assur'd, Ere you proceed to drag the shrouded corpse Out of his grave, that you have nerves to meet him. I should have thought, convinc'd that he is dead, You might be well content to let him sleep. Count. If he is dead, we cannot harm his spirit, If he is living, I shall sleep no more. Duke. Why should you doubt against the evidence Of living witnesses, who, from all quarters, Confirm the death of Torrendal? Oh, why Ransack the graves, where dull oblivion sleeps, And fly to old Vanhoven and his magic, Only to puzzle that, which needs no proof? Count. Where are those witnesses, of whom you speak? I never saw them, never question'd them. You tell me he is dead; but conscience says I should have paus'd upon that information. Duke. Did you not pause? Yes, tantalizing fair one, How many sighs it cost me to persuade And soften that hard heart, yourself can witness. Count. Alas, how cheaply can seduction furnish Those feign'd unfeeling sighs, which only serve To flatter and betray! Such were your sighs— But what are those heart-rending agonies Your victim suffers, what those sighs she vents For ruin'd honour and lost peace of mind! Those, those are deep indeed. Duke. No more of this. Your conduct, my Alicia, needs no plea; And, if it did, your husband's gross neglect, The solemn promise of my hand in marriage, And your unshaken patience till his death, Must silence all reproach. Count. Here then we quit This painful and unprofitable subject— And look! Murinski comes to call you forth To your field sports— Murinski enters. Duke. I shall not hunt to-day. My spirits are opprest, I know not why, And at my heart I feel a sad foreboding, As if some dreadful thing were coming on. Count. If it will come, it will—What says Murinski? Mur. I'm no diviner, madam. Count. No, nor yet A lover of the chase, else, I should think, You'd recommend diversion of the spleen By cheering exercise, as nature's remedy. Mur. I am a soldier, and my course of life Has never given me leisure to seek out Other pursuits, than were impos'd upon me By duty and my calling. Count. I believe you, And say it to your face, You're a bad courtier. Duke. Then take him well to task, and teach him better— I leave him in your hands—and so farewell! [Exit Duke. Murinski, Countess. Count. Murinski, there is something at your heart, That lies too deep for my discovery. When I was simply a plain soldier's wife, We were the best of friends, what is the reason, When I have now some power, and much good will To serve your fortune, you stand off at distance, And seem to slight my favour? Mur. You have said it: I am a sorry courtier.— Count. Come, come, that general answer will not serve; You must be more explicit. Mur. I shan't please you. Count. You do not, when you practise these evasions. Tell me at once the cause of your reserve! Mur. Then I must fairly own myself unworthy Of your protection, for 'tis my misfortune To love the memory, and lament the fate Of an unhappy friend, whom you forget. Count. Do I forget? No, from the grave I call him: Hither I come—here, to the gates of death, To him, whose powerful spell can bid them open, And let the incarcerated spirit forth, Behold I come—If it is your misfortune To bear him in remembrance, it is mine Not to forget the agonies I suffer'd, When fatal proof that I was quite forsaken Rent my distracted heart, and with despair, Mingling revenge, compell'd me to accept Those guilty honours, which, whilst he surviv'd, Faithless although he was, I still withstood. Mur. To proofs, if proofs you have, I must submit; But to reports and tales, by which too many Contrive to damn the fame of absent men, I yield no credit—From his boyish days I knew your husband; honour rul'd his heart, And the whole tenor of his life was truth. Count. Go on, go on! for every word you utter Sinks deep into my heart. I never knew him But as the noblest, gentlest, best of men: But from the day he left me, to the hour Which clos'd his life, no word of kind remembrance, By letter or by message, ever reach'd me; So chang'd were his affections, he renounc'd me, Set me aside, revok'd his nuptial oath, And died the husband of another wife, Mur. Stop there! If those who tell you of his marriage, Tell of his death, I hold them false in both. You should have listen'd to those tales with caution: When you can give me proof of his decease, I have a certain record to produce, Which might, perhaps, awaken some sensations More to his honour than to your repose. Count. What record? Let me know it, I conjure you. Mur. The night before he went to join the army, He put a sealed paper in my hand, Of which the substance was a free bequest Of his whole property, without conditions, To you and your disposal—Of this trust I am the keeper—Wealthy he was not, For ere he married you, he had bestow'd Half of his property upon an orphan. Count. What do I hear? I tremble whilst I ask Who was that orphan? Mur. Need you to be told That orphan was yourself? Count. Oh, heaven and earth! Mur. He never told you this?— Count. Oh, never, never. Mur. Of this truth, I stand The living witness, for my hand convey'd The secret bounty, and my heart alone Was privy to the motive that inspir'd it: His generous mind disdain'd to court your praise, Or bribe your gratitude, whilst he aspir'd To merit your free choice. Count. Oh why, just Heaven, Did he conceal this from me, why did you? What guilt, what misery had I then escaped! Mur. If I could have suppos'd he had conceal'd it, I had not nam'd it now. Count. Lost, lost for ever! If any guardian spirit had but whisper'd This secret in my ear, I had been sav'd; If you, if Torrendal had but reveal'd it, I should not be the guilty thing I am: That gratitude, which now hath been my ruin, Would then have been my rescue—Wretched Alicia! Deluded, credulous woman, I'm betray'd, Lur'd into vice by what had been my virtue: That artful duke permitted me to thank him, To call him benefactor, friend, preserver, And in the grateful weakness of my heart Precipitate myself into his snares— Deceiv'd in this, I may be so in all; If more you know of my long-absent husband, Living or dead, declare it! Mur. I have done. What I have told incautiously escap'd me; When more you ask, I must decline to answer. [Exit. Countess Torrendal. Rise then, O Torrendal, rise from the grave, And let this awful night decide my doom! If with terrific mien and angry brow Threat'ning you come, the same mysterious power, That gives to incorporeal air a form, May also give a voice, and what the living Cannot, or will not tell, the dead may utter; Then with suspended breath, in mute attention, Lost to the sense of every other object, I'll stand and gaze, and listen to the tale, Till, when the sad recital you shall close, And vanish from my sight, my conscious heart Shall vent one dying groan, and burst asunder.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT IV. Lodowick's Cottage. Lodowick enters with his Gun, and is met by Marian. Mar. So, master, what have you been doing with your gun at this late hour? Lod. Nothing. I simply carry it for defence. Mar. I scarce believe you. Put it aside, however, and I'll talk to you. Lod. There—Now what would you? Mar. Count Torrendal is shut up in his chamber— Lod. Well! what of that? Mar. How quick you are. Don't think to blind me, Lodowick; I am sure there is some project in your head, when you go out at this time of the evening, arm'd with your gun. You have not struck a stroke of work this whole day, but have been prowling up and down the forest—I know you have. What have you been about? Lod. Beating the woods for game. Mar. Never tell me; your dogs have been tied up; I guess what game it is you have been beating for. You never kept a secret from me yet, and, as I hope, I never have betray'd one. Lod. No, no, my honest Marian, were all wives faithful to their trust as you are, I had not now gone arm'd, as you have seen me; Count Torrendal had kept his senses, that fine mind, so fraught with genius, had not been overthrown. Can you suppose that Courland shall escape us? Mar. Can I suppose that you will turn assassin? Lod. We kill things venomous, we crush the serpent, the watchful shepherd destroys the wolf that ravages his fold, and shall we spare this wretch? No, no, we will not—but look! our master comes—stand aside, Marian! He seems much disorder'd— Torrendal in his proper dress as the Count. Tor. There, there it is again! a floating ball Of vaporous fire, that dances in the air, And now 'tis seen no more— Ev'n so my senses come and go by fits; Sometimes a lucid gleam of light revives me, And then it vanishes, and all is dark— Oh, my distracted brain! It whirls, it wanders— Ah, Lody, art thou here? I'm much disturb'd— Lod. If there be any thing I can do for you, Behold me ready with my life to serve you. Tor. The killing recollection of the day, When last I wore this dress, was all too much: It was the day I parted from Alicia. Methought I felt her hanging on my neck In all the frenzy of dissembled woe; I look'd to see, if her false tears, that stream'd Upon my mantle, had not left behind Tracks of the scalding venom, that compos'd them: The faint remembrance of a certain pledge, Bestow'd at parting, struck upon my mind; I search'd, and found, appending to my robe, Her miniature enamell'd to the life— Heav'ns! what was then my agony! my eye Glanc'd on her image, and my brain caught fire, Frantic I rent the faithless bauble off, And dash'd it on the floor—Alas, alas! Time was I should have worshipp'd what I spurn'd. Mar. Ah, my good lord, indulge not these reflections; They are the food, that melancholy feeds on, Till, surfeited with sorrow, the heart sickens, And the soul dies within us. Tor. How is this, Lodowick? Did not I give you means for her escape? Why have you been thus careless of her safety? Send her away! Lod. Marian, you must withdraw— Mar. Now, in his utmost need, must I desert him? Lod. Only withdraw— Mar. Heav'n in its mercy save him! [Exit Marian. Tor. The evening star is up, and night comes on. I must away— Lod. Whither, and what to do? Tor. I have ask'd my heart that question; I have sought Counsel of heav'n by prayer—I have weigh'd Forbearance in one scale; revenge in the other— Mercy with justice, and the upshot is, Justice prevails—Lo! I am arm'd for vengeance! Lod. A dagger! put it up. No, no, my lord, We'll use no daggers: I have speedier means. He would not hunt to-day; I know not why: Had he once stept without the castle gates, I'd mark'd him for my own. Tor. You shall not do it: You have a virtuous wife, for whom to live; I've liv'd to see the wreck of every blessing, And having nothing left, can lose no more. Therefore no words—I go to meet the duke; My honour is engag'd to the magician; I've one ingredient more than he's aware of To mingle with his spell—a villain's blood— And doubt me not, but I will make a ghost Ere he can raise one—Silence! no opposing; Else will the storm, now lull'd, burst out afresh, And tear my brain to atoms. Lod. I have done. Tor. 'Tis well. Lod. Permit me only to attend you— Tor. Can you be firm? Can you possess your spirit, Nor let the horrors of the scene appall you, Though incantations shake the solid earth, And ghosts were rent from out their yawning graves With yells, that, echoing through the charmed air, Pluck the stars down upon you. Lod. Let them come! Fools gaze at falling stars, and, as for ghosts, Can I be scar'd with shadows of the dead, Who fear no living man? Doubt not of me; When you advance I will not lag behind. Tor. Then we're agreed. Now, vengeance, to thy work! [Exeunt. An Apartment in the Baron's Castle. Vanhoven, Baroness. Van. Now, madam, wherefore, and with whom, have you been closeted this many an hour? Bar. My confessor has been with me. Van. Oh, has he so? Women and monks keep the world still in dotage. The time will be, when our enlighten'd sect shall teach them better things. Bar. Heaven in its mercy keep that time at distance, Or take me from the world before it comes! Your sect indeed! we do not need their help To make that worse which is too bad already. Van. Speak reverently of my sect—you had best. Bar. I know my peril, and I know their power; But, notwithstanding, I am bold to tell you, You will repent the business of this night. Van. What know you of this night, or any night, Day, hour, or minute, that is yet to come, Blest or unblest? Can you expound the signs? Can you interpret the hermetic code, Cast horoscopes, or read the stars—Away! You are an idle woman: I predict This night will be auspicious to my fame. Go; leave the room. I have business with my servant. Adam enters. Bar. Infatuated man! will nothing warn you Till infamy and ruin burst upon you? Then you will rue this folly, then your spirit Will be as abject, as 'tis now presumptuous. [Exit. Vanhoven, Adam. Van. Well, Adam, is the laboratory ready, and all the apparatus set in order? Adam. All ready, and in order, potent sage. When ghosts obey you, how should I stand out? Van. This curious lady will not be content unless she sees the process. Adam. She shall see it, and hear it too. I have overhaul'd the machinery, and if it is your pleasure to be accompanied in your incantations with groanings and noises under ground— Van. Surely it is, when was it not my pleasure? Adam. Oh, then I'll do it to your heart's content in the true style of the infernal spirits; I have also music for the good ones: if fire and smoke are wanted, I have rosin, sulphur, and phosphorus—in short, the circle is chalk'd out, the black hangings are put up, the lamps lighted, the cauldron drugg'd, the green dragon display'd, and death drawn out of his case, a beautiful likeness, and what I dare say the company will see with as much satisfaction as they would the original itself. Van. All this is very well; but get back to your post as quickly as you can, for it is now the hour we should expect the lady—Away, away! The duke himself is coming. [Exit Adam. Duke of Courland enters. Duke. Vanhoven! Van. Sir. Duke. The countess has prevail'd; I've yielded my consent. Are you prepar'd To do the fearful thing that she requires? Van. I am prepar'd; but let it be remember'd I do not court the office, royal sir: I have your highness's command to obey her, And if she will persist to urge the spell, The spectre of her husband will appear. Duke. What shape will he assume? Van. Such as he was, Such he will be. Duke. I envy her not the interview; She's a bold woman, if she looks upon him. Van. Your highness then will not attend the process— Duke. Not present, but at hand. I've plac'd a guard Within your call, ready for all occasions; Give but the signal, I'll be instant with you. If, by your spell, you can return her to me, Convinc'd her husband Torrendal is dead, You'll do me noble service—so farewell! [Exeunt. Scene, without the Castle. Torrendal followed by Lodowick. Tor. Why do you follow me? Go home, go home! I cannot suffer it. I charge you, leave me. Lod. Well, if I must, I must—and yet 'tis hard, Having kept pace so far, I must now stop Short of the end, and part perhaps for ever. Tor. Give me thy hand! If, for the last time, now We part no more to meet in this bad world, 'Tis not for ever; where our finite ends Our infinite begins; there is to come That which shall never cease, that which no time, No thought of man can measure, or compute: There we may meet again—Therefore farewell, Thou honest heart—Peace! not a word—'Tis past. [Exit. Lodowick alone. Lod. Well, well, it must have way—I cannot help it. I knew that when the fatal moment came That we must part, I could not stand the shock: My heart gave warning as we walk'd together, And many a tear of sorrow by the way Fell unperceiv'd, but not a word had I To give one thought expression; he too held Obstinate silence till we reach'd this spot, The period of his journey—perchance his life. Officer and Guard of Soldiers enter and seize him. Offi. Who are you, friend, and what do you do here? Lod. Nothing. Offi. That answer won't suffice—Once more your name and business? Lod. My name is Lodowick; that is soon told; my business, being none, I cannot tell it. Now, who are you, that put these questions to me? Offi. We are the Duke of Courland's bodyguard; and you must go with us. Lod. Well; if I must, it will not be the first time I've march'd with soldiers. Shew me to the duke! Offi. Search him first; examine, if he has no secret weapons—His language is suspicious— And look! I've found this dagger in his bosom. Lod. Well, it was in my bosom, and you found it; where is the great discovery in that? Offi. Take him away, and hold him in safe keeping. [Exeunt. Scene, the western Tower of the Castle; Moonlight. Vanhoven enters alone. Van. Oh, Rabbi Abraham, Geber, Flamel, Behmen, Ye magic masters, now direct and guide me! Weak minister were I without your aid. Whence are these omens, that conspire to shake me? As I came forth, my wife, in wild amaze, Seizing my robe, and dropping on her knees, Conjur'd me to desist—I put her from me; Whereat she rose, and, with uplifted hands, Mad as the Pythian prophetess, exclaim'd— “Go, desperate man, this night your impious orgies “Shall draw a dreadful judgment on your house, “And bloody shall the consummation be”— I heard, but staid not; when, upon the instant, The night-bird scream'd amain, the watch-dog howl'd, And utter'd forth a yell, so like the wailings Of tortur'd spirits, that it chill'd my blood. [Clock strikes one. Hark! the clock warns me that my hour is come— Where is my proselyte? Where is the stranger, That promis'd to attend?—Adam, come forth! Adam comes forth. Adam. Master, what would you? From beneath the wings Of the all-potent dragon I come forth To know your pleasure—All things are prepar'd. Van. That's well, that's well. Adam. You tremble, mighty sir. Van. Do I? The night-air chills me through my mantle, And my flesh shivers—Let me have your arm— Now we will enter—Hark, I hear the steps Of one approaching—On, good Adam, on! [They enter the Tower, and the lights immediately appear in the windows of the Magic Chamber. Torrendal enters alone. Tor. The wizzard is at work. His lamps are burning, And his charm'd cauldron, fed with sulph'rous drugs, Makes foul the wholesome air, till the moon sickens With his accursed spell—Be firm, my heart! For now, (if such permission be to man) The evil spirits muster at his call, And hell-engender'd thoughts are wafted round By the contagious blasting of their breath. I will no longer bide within their sphere, Lest my weak brain should suck the poison in, And, on the sight of my adulterous wife, Tempt me to draw this murderous dagger forth, And plunge it in her heart—Oh save me heaven! In mercy save!—I turn to thy protection. [Exit. The Countess, as she enters, sees and watches Torrendal. Count. That—that—Oh, that is he!—The moonbeam now Strikes on his passing figure—'Tis no shadow— 'Tis he—'tis Torrendal; it is my husband, His form, his air, his slow and stately step— Oh turn, and, if thou'rt living, speak to me! If dead, the dead have spoken— Torrendal is seen again. Hah! he turns; My voice has reach'd him—Whatsoe'er thou art, Spirit or substance, of the air or earth, Real or spell-created, yet thou wear'st A form and feature awfully so like To what I lov'd and lost, that I will kneel And worship thee in sorrow— [She kneels—Torrendal approaches. Tor. Rise, Alicia! Him, that you seek, you see—your living husband. The heart, your cruelty has rent, yet beats, And reason, which at times forsakes me, serves Now to demand, what tempted you to wrong me; Why, when your bosom seem'd the native soil Of purity and truth, did you invite A devil to sow it with the rankest seeds Of treach'ry and pollution? Count. Strike, oh strike! That guilty bosom now invites your sword. Tor. No, not for worlds—I've pledg'd myself to heaven, And, what I've sworn to guard, will not destroy. Oh, faithless, cruel, and perfidious woman, What can you urge to palliate your offence? I never gave you cause to treat me thus; I never wrong'd you, my unbroken faith, Firm to this hour as truth itself, remains: In perfect love, through all vicissitudes Of good or adverse fortune, I preserv'd And treasur'd up your image in my heart; When in my tent, upon the eve of battle, I sought my God in pray'r, for you, my soul, Its first, most fervent aspirations breath'd; Nor in the fight, while death and slaughter rag'd, Nor after, when with shouts we rent the air For victory gain'd, did I forget Alicia. Count. Indeed! Is't possible? Have I been dup'd By the vile arts of an insidious villain, And lur'd to my destruction? I was taught To think you false, nor, from the hour we parted, To this sad moment, has a word e'er reach'd me, To tell me I was yet in your remembrance. Tor. In camp, in city, station'd, or on march, I seiz'd on every opportunity To write, remonstrate, and bewail your silence. At length, to all hope lost, my senses wand'ring, And my heart torn with anguish, I address'd A mournful letter, blotted with my tears, To that vile duke, imploring him to tell me What fatal chance— Count. Oh, infamy more base, Malice more black than ever yet was hatch'd In heart of demon! he suppress'd it all— Vanhoven comes forth. Tor. How now! Disturb us not— Van. Illustrious lady, The spell is cast. What stays you? Tor. Hence! be gone! Your spells and sorceries are not needed now. Van. Hah! is it you?—Behold, the duke approaches— I must escape in time— [Exit hastily. The Duke enters. Duke. What do I see? May I believe my eyes? It is the very form of Torrendal— Tor. Wretch, I am Torrendal. Duke. Where are my guards? [The Guards enter, the Duke shrinks back. Tor. Detected, trembling dastard, reptile-like, Do you shrink back and crouch into your shell, When challeng'd forth to meet an equal foe; One robb'd of more than half his natural powers By wrongs, by miseries you have pil'd upon him? What do you start from? Are you valiant only Against the feeble sex? Have you no weapons But slanders, perjuries, and lies to wound with? And are you leagued only to do the work, And learn the cozening tricks of petty devils? Duke. Can you hear this, and not avenge me, soldiers? Tor. If you are soldiers, give a soldier passage; Open your files, or, single as I am, I will assail him in the midst of you. Nay then—defend yourself— [He rushes upon the Guard, and strikes at the Duke, in which action he is disarmed by the Soldiers. Duke. Stop, stop his hand! Tor. Ye are not soldiers, ye are slaves. Duke. Out with your swords! Put him to instant death! Count. Oh, hold, hold, hold! The sword that pierces him, Shall pass through me. Duke. Alicia, are you mad? Would you protect a traitor, an assassin? Count. He, an assassin! No, 'tis you, 'tis I— We are assassins—Look at him, Oh look! How sunk his eyes, how ghastly wan his cheek! Famine and sorrow have consum'd his heart, And turn'd his brain—that noble mind is lost; He's not himself; how then can he be judg'd For actions not his own? Duke. Lo, where his dagger, Aim'd at my heart, and, only turn'd aside By this good friend, has rent and gash'd my robe— Do you not see it? Count. Yes, I see it clearly. He rent your garment, you have torn his heart. Duke. Take him away. Justice demands the traitor; And he shall die the death. Tor. Yes, you may now Enjoy the luxury of protracted vengeance, Load me with fetters, prison me in darkness, Arraign me as a traitor and assassin, And, to complete the mockery of justice, Pass sentence on my life: when you've done this, You have done all—there closes my account— Then be prepar'd, adulterer, for thine own. Duke. I'll hear no more. Away with him! he dies. Count. Stop yet a moment—Grant a moment's pause— Oh Torrendal, oh husband, turn not from me! Have pity for a sinful, suffering creature. I do not dare to raise my eyes for hope, And ask forgiveness, but I'll humbly kneel To beg you will not spurn my wretched corpse, When, on the bloody scaffold at your feet, Writhing in agonies of death I fall, And my soul sinks whilst yours ascends to heav'n. Tor. Live, and repent! I do not fear to die, For when the world has thrown aside all order, Heav'n lost its worship, guilt forgot its shame And man his nature, who would wish to live? [He is taken off by the Guard. Count. I'll follow him to death— Duke. Away! you're mad. [The Countess follows Torrendal, the Duke turns away, and departs with his Attendants on the opposite side.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT V. Duke of Courland, Murinski. Duke. Murinski, you amaze me: it should seem As if you thought my life might be attempted, And the assassin pardon'd—Here! behold, See where his poniard pass'd—Was not this stab Aim'd at the heart within? Mur. So it appears. Duke. Appears! it speaks, it marks the full intent Of a determin'd vengeful murderer; And shall he live? Why do you purse your brow, And shake your head, as if in discontent At what my justice dooms? Utter your thoughts; Keep not this sullen silence. Mur. I lament That you should not conceive it for your honour To judge the miseries of mankind with mercy, And take the plea of madness in excuse For what a madman does: there have been princes As sacred as yourself, who have endur'd The stab of phrenzy, and exacted nothing From justice, but security in future For others and themselves. Duke. You have said enough To raise my admiration of the virtues Both of the great example you refer to, And your own eloquence in the defence Of a convicted traitor. This might seem As if you lov'd the cause, which you espouse With so much warmth, but that I recollect You've been the bosom friend of Torrendal; Therefore whilst prejudice inspires your plea, Justice will bar my ears against the voice Of such an advocate. You have been heard; Your sentiments are known—you may withdraw. [Exit Murinski. Baroness Vanhoven enters, followed by the Baron. Bar. Hear me, my gracious lord— Duke. Ere I do that, Say, are you not the lady of that baron, Who stands abash'd behind you? Bar. Sir, I am. Duke. You may proceed. Bar. If I forbore to pay My thankful duty when your highness deign'd To visit this lone mansion, 'twas because My heart presag'd, with horror, the disgrace That would in time befal that impious sect, Of which my husband was, but is no longer, A much-deluded follower. My lord, His vanity misled him to affect Powers, which no mortal, but by heav'n's appointment, Yet ever did, or ever can possess. Duke. That he is innocent of all capacity To call up spirits and disturb the dead, I well believe; that he is quite as harmless In what regards the living, I must doubt, Till time discloses: all, that yet appears, Is, that his sovereign, underneath his roof, Has had his life attempted by a ruffian, Whom he employ'd and train'd to play the ghost In his mock magic. Van. No, upon my life: Heaven knows my heart, I harbour'd no offence Against your royal person, and the laws Of sacred hospitality—The man, Who now turns out to be Count Torrendal, Was only known to me as a craz'd fellow, Who sojourn'd with one Lodowick, a woodman. Duke. That Lodowick is seiz'd. Bring him before us! Van. I never knew Count Torrendal by person. This Lodowick, if he'll speak, can witness for me, And so can Torrendal, that I am clear Of all collusion in this black affair. Lodowick is brought in. Duke. Now, fellow; you are seiz'd as an accomplice; Your intercourse with Torrendal is known; If you would gain your pardon, make confession Of all you know touching this trait'rous plot. Lod. I've been a soldier, sir, and serv'd your highness In many an action: it was once my fortune, When Torrendal, my captain, was unhors'd, Wounded, and on the ground, to save his life, And cover him in battle; from that day He took me to himself, made me his servant, I had almost said his friend: after the war, Being disbanded, and the count in Poland, Hither I came, and having serv'd my country With my best strength, deem'd it my second duty To give the remnant to my aged parents: In this retreat my noble master sought me In his affliction—If your highness thinks It was a crime in me to give him shelter, It is a crime of which I can't repent— As for the baron here, I do believe, Nay, I am sure, he did not know the count. Duke. Baron and lady, I have done with you, You may retire. [Exeunt Vanhoven and Baroness. I've yet another question— And on your conscience answer it in truth! Do you conceive the countess was consenting, And party in the attempt upon my life! Lod. No, on my soul. I would she were as clear Of every other guilt. Duke. Why did you hide That dagger in your bosom? Lod. To defend, At my life's peril, my distracted master. Duke. You are a dangerous man. Lod. I have been, sir, When I have met your enemies in arms, And in my course of duty am not clear From shedding human blood; but never yet, Ev'n in the heat of battle, have I fail'd To spare the life of him, who ask'd it of me. Duke. You spoke but now of your distracted master— Why did you so? Is Torrendal insane? Lod. Oh yes, yes, yes. His mind is overthrown. Duke. How? by what means? Lod. When you ask that of me, A plain blunt soldier, you must hear the truth Boldly averr'd—You and his guilty wife Have wreck'd his senses, and destroy'd his peace. Duke. Hence from my sight! be gone; I'll hear no more! [Exit Lodowick with guard. And see, Alicia—Now, be firm my heart! Countess enters. Alicia, you have seen my life attempted, And, in the immediate terror of the moment, Have stood betwixt the assassin and my vengeance; It was a woman's fear, and I forgave it. Count. You're infinitely kind: I came to thank you. Duke. You answer calmly, and it much contents me. Count. Oh, I am very calm. Duke. Then, with like calmness, I will proceed to reason on th' events Of this disast'rous night: Vanhoven's magic Is, as you see, a despicable cheat; Yet has it serv'd to terminate those doubts That hung upon you, and obscur'd your hopes. Count. Yes, I can now unravel all the plan, Which, with unwearied pains, you have pursued To make me what I am. I find him living, Who you persuaded me to think was dead; I see that all his faithfulness, his truth, His untold bounties, shower'd in secret on me, Have either been distorted into crimes, Or else assum'd as merits of your own; And nothing now is wanting, but to take His forfeit life, and stamp a damning act, Devils would start from, with the name of justice. Duke. Why this is railing, madam, and not reason: You said you would be calm. Count. And I am calm. Duke. We have been friends— Count. Yes, yes, we have been friends, Close, conscious friends, that have conspir'd together, And know each other's hearts. I will not speak To you of mercy—You shall never name Peace, or a word of comfort more to me. Duke. Why this despair? You still preserve your place In my affections, and where love inhabits Why should you doubt if mercy may be found? Count. Where love inhabits?—Love! I thought that word Was sacred only to the hallow'd lips Of the chaste virgin and unblemish'd wife. There was a time I felt its influence here; Oh! that was happy! 'twas my fostering angel, And underneath its wings all, all was peace; But it is gone; a cruel falcon came And drove my dove away—'Tis gone for ever. [A Soldier enters, speaks apart to the Duke, whilst Alicia had withdrawn to the back part of the Stage. Duke. Say'st? 'Tis well—I'll see him once again— [Exit Guard. Now, my Alicia, now thy fortune hails thee Duchess of Courland—Torrendal is dying— Count. Dying! Eternal infamy light on thee; And as thou'st shut out mercy from thy heart, Heav'n, from all mercy, shuts out thee. Torrendal is led in between two of the Guard. Hah! 'tis my husband—Angels spread your wings To waft his spirit to those realms of glory, To which all earthly splendour, when compar'd, Is as a glow-worm to the mid-day sun. Tor. Peace, peace! Be silent! you, my Lord of Courland, You, that delight in blood, should entertain Assassins more expert; the coward stabber, You sent to murder me, has only mangled. Duke. Whether he struck by my command, or not, I am not careful how the world may judge; For, if he did, it is but blow for blow, And universal justice warrants that. Tor. Yes, for they tell me that my dagger's point, When levell'd at your heart, has rent your robe: 'Twas done in phrenzy, for the injury From you I had sustain'd; yet I am glad My hands are clear from spilling blood so foul; And though I have the melancholy plea Of a distracted brain for my acquittal, I leave it to the searcher of all hearts; I urge it not on you. When every conscience Shall give its secrets up, there stands a witness, Who must depose the truth. Count. Oh, hear me now, Whilst yet my senses hold, in pity hear me; For I have sinn'd in error, and been plung'd In this foul ruin more by others craft Than my own nature: when I fell from virtue, 'Twas not ambition, 'twas not vanity; A thousand thousand times unmov'd I saw That base seducer kneeling at my feet; My heart was still my husband's—Nay, when time Roll'd on in cold neglect, and not one line Of consolation ever reach'd my hand. Tor. Day after day I urg'd my fond complaints— Sir, what became of these? Oh, shame to honour! Count. Blush, blush, if shame can reach you! Even then Had any friend of honour interpos'd, I had not been the guilty thing I am: Then was the time Murinski should have urg'd The secret bounties, you had left untold, And he was privy to—Alas for me! I never knew the wond'rous debt I ow'd you. Oh, fatal ignorance! I suffer'd him To steal those praises, that were due to you, And, cheated into gratitude, was lost. Tor. Enough!—Oh, prince, are these the glorious acts, Which heav'n requires of those whom it appoints To be the friends and guardians of mankind? Look at the wreck of that once-beauteous creature, How sad, how wan, how chang'd from what she was— Be it your boast to have betray'd the friend, That trusted to you his heart's dearest treasure; 'Tis mine, that even now, whilst in my flesh I wear the stab you gave me, rack'd with pain, My senses wand'ring, and the ebbing stream Of my life-blood, cold, gathering at my heart, I yet survive to tell thee to thy face— Thou art a villain— Duke. Villain!—Stop his tongue; Away with him to death! He, that strikes short A second time, shall answer with his life. Be gone; depart; let none presume to speak. [Torrendal is taken off by the Soldiers. [The Countess remains. Duke. Why do you stay? Count. Mercy!— Duke. I'll hear no more. [Exit hastily. Count. Nor shall you—Aid me now, vindictive justice! And let this dagger plead, since mercy cannot. [She rushes out after him. [She returns holding the dagger. 'Tis done! he reel'd, he fell without a groan; There, where he fell, he lies—Go, get thee hence, Thou bleeding witness of a fearful deed! [Throws the dagger away. Oh, that I only could have kill'd his crimes, And spar'd him life to make his peace with heaven! Hark, what is that? What noise? And here comes one, A holy man—Make haste, make haste, good father! There's one within, if his soul is not fled, Has need enough of prayers—Go in, go in! [The Monk, who had entered during this speech, goes into the Duke's Apartment. The Scene changes. A gloomy Chamber or Prison, belonging to the Castle, Torrendal is discovered in the hands of the Soldiers. Tor. Why do you pause? Behold, I bare my bosom Already gash'd and bleeding: here beneath A heart yet beats, that panted once for glory, A soldier's heart—If thou hast been a soldier, Do thy work fitly, do it manfully; Strike at my heart, but strike me not in malice: I never did thee wrong— Murinski enters, followed by Lodowick. Mur. Break up your guard! Soldiers, your duke and sovereign is no more. I am your captain, and on me devolves To answer for your prisoner— [Soldiers withdraw. Oh, my friend, Heard you the welcome tidings that I bring? Courland is dead—I come to set you free. Tor. Your rescue comes too late; death sets me free, Lo, where his shaft has enter'd! Mur. No, my hero, You have stood many a ruder shock than this; We'll heal this gash—this is a shallow wound, Tor. 'Tis deeper than you think for. Ah! my friend, My honest Lody, hast thou found me out? Thy master's sorrows will be soon at rest. Lod. Oh, how this rends my heart! Come, let us bear you Into a fresher air—We may find help: Lean on my arm— Tor. It has already sav'd me; It can do so no more; yet, as it was My first support, so shall it be my last. [They lead him out. Scene changes to a Chamber, in which is a State-Bed, or Couch, and over it a Canopy with a Curtain drawn before it, concealing the Body of the Duke of Courland. The Countess discovered. Count. Either it is the error of my senses, And those, which I have look'd on, are but shadows, Or else some strange contagious horror strikes All that have life, and palsies every tongue. They come, they pass, and, in their passing, snatch A fearful glance at the blood-sprinkled corpse Of their dead prince; but no one stops to ask Who did the murderous deed. I saw the monk Stand by the body, muttering to himself His solemn offices for the soul's peace: He turn'd a look on me, and wav'd his head In silent reprobation, yet he spoke not: Murinski follow'd—him no horrors aw'd; Eager he gaz'd upon the prostrate corpse; Then stooping laid his hand upon the heart, To be resolv'd if life's last pulse had stopt; Whereof assur'd, he beckon'd to the guard To take the body up—then with the air And speedy step of one, who seem'd intent To spread some happy tidings, he departed. Baroness Vanhoven and Monk enter. Bar. Where is the desperate maniac, that has murder'd The Duke of Courland underneath my roof? Count. Oh, then I find it was not all a vision, For here is one at last has found a voice. But hush! be silent—Look, he comes, he comes! Torrendal led in by Murinski and Lodowick. Oh, pity me, my husband, turn your eyes In pity on a poor distracted creature! How now! what ails him? Why d'ye bear him up? Ah!—he is dying. Look! there's blood upon him! But I have slain the wolf that tore his flesh— There, there he lies!— [She runs, draws the curtain rapidly aside, and discovers the body of the Duke laid out on the bed or couch. Dead, dead—You see him dead; Touch him, he's cold—call him, he cannot hear— Accuse him, he can't answer—If you ask Who kill'd him, it was I—'twas I who did it— He had no mercy for my injur'd husband, I, I had none for him— Tor. Peace! Hear me speak! 'Tis with my dying voice I now appeal To Heaven's blest mercy, not for thee alone, (Thy phrenzy ev'n an earthly judge would spare) But also for the soul of that sad wretch, With whose dead corpse I bury all resentment, And so may Heaven to me like pardon deal, As I to him! Count. Oh, hast thou not a pardon Left to bestow on thy repentant wife? That I may lay it to my sinking heart, And at my death's hour meditate upon it. Tor. Oh, that these drops, which fond remembrance wrings From my now-closing eyes, had power to blanch Thy faded virtue, and restore it pure As from the Maker's hand! Now, bear me up! I yet would speak—Oh, ye frail, faithless wives, Let this sad story sink into your hearts, And leave an awful lesson to the world, What fools in nature, and what slaves to sin Those wretches are, who sacrifice their peace To a seducer, and then trust his honour To bear them up against the stings of conscience, The scorn of virtue, and the wrath of heaven. [Curtain falls.</field>
   </doc>
</add>