<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">fl. 1669</field>
      <field name="author_facet">fl. 1669</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">fl 1669</field>
      <field name="author_text">fl. 1669</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">17th Century</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V2.0086.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1671</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:459833</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="language_facet">Latin</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Womens Conquest ; A tragi-comedy</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 17th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 17th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Womens Conquest ; A tragi-comedy</field>
      <field name="title_facet">womens conquest</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">womens conquest</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Womens Conquest ; A tragi-comedy</field>
      <field name="year_display">1671</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1671</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1671</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459833&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459833&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent&gt;fl. 1669&lt;/displayAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent&gt;fl 1669&lt;/sortAgent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Womens Conquest ; A tragi-comedy&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;womens conquest&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1671&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1671&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="creator" form="persname" role="author"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;fl. 1669&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Womens Conquest&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A tragi-comedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Printed by J. M. for H. Herringman [etc.]&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1671&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3872177-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv20086&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;lat&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 17th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;17th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Womens Conquest&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;A tragi-comedy&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 274 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries and introductory matter omitted&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: The womens conquest.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: Tragi-comedy.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1671.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: Nov 1670 ?&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE Womens Conquest: A TRAGI-COMEDY.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Me lectori credere mallem, Quam spectatoris fastidia ferre superbi.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The First Prologue. Enter Angel and Underhill. Ang. Mr. Underhill—As I am a man of mirth, I am so overjoyed to day, that I could caper from one end of our Stage to the other. Und. I fear, Mr. Angel, you are too jocund before-hand; Wit is grown a ticklish thing of late, and how our Play will take, is some question. Ang. Take, why there's no doubt of it's taking,—To which purpose be it known to all here present, that we are to act a Farce to day, that hath sixteen Mimicks in it, several Jack-Puddings, and Punchinellos, never presented before, with two and thirty Dances and Jiggs a-la-mode besides. Und. A Farce to day, say you? Ang. Yes, &amp; I hope to morrow, and to morrow, and so to the end of our lives. Und. Must we still persist then to fool Wit out of countenance, and so bid farewel to good Plays and Comedy for ever? Ang. We must, as I take it, until there are Poets that can write them. Und. In the mean time, we are like to maintain a despicable Stage. Ang. And why so, Sir, ought not that which gets the most money, be held the best Wit? I suppose our Company are much of that opinion. Und. However, as I am an Actor, and bound to honour true Mirth and Comedy, I am so far concern'd, that I could wish the Scaramuchos, and Jack-Puddings were sent to their proper Stages, since Plays are now grown so greasie with French Lard, that an Actor do's not know how to handle them. Ang. My right reverend Comedian, you are not wise, and thus I demonstrate it—I will play a Farce ten to one against a Comedy, Tragi-comedy, or any Heroick Play whatsoever. Und. And be sure it will take? Ang. I told you before, that was no question—nay more, I can assure you, that many good Wits of the Town encourage it, who damn all Plays besides. Und. Perhaps in compassion to us Actors, or out of contempt to the Writers of this Age, whose Wit they judge cannot reach the elevation of their Brain. Ang. No matter whether it be from the Poles above, or the Poles below, I am sure they are better then Pole-stars to us, provided they dispense their influence often here. Und. And what shall become of the new Play, intended to have been this day presented? Ang. Why, our Actors have soberly resolved, it shall be deferr'd to some other time. Und. As I hope to act good part again, I am sorry for it; but is it certain? Ang. There is nothing certain in the world, though 'tis so concluded, unless some unexpected prohibition, or Fate hinder it—but 'tis almost time. Enter Noakes. We withdraw in order to our parts and properties—here comes Mr. Noakes ready drest. Und. Then I perceive we shall have a Farce to purpose, and 'tis odds, but he personates one beetle-brow'd Fellow or other. Ang. O Mr. Noaks, you have habited your self very properly. Noak. According to my best apprehension, Gentlemen. Und. But you should not have entred with your face grim'd, 'twill discover too much of our Farces plot before-hand. Noak. There's good design in it, I warrant you. Und. But what shall we do for a Prologue? Noak. Leave that to me, Sirs, I'le give u'm one a new way. Ang. Mark that, Mr. Underhill; and shall we have a novelty in our Prologue, Mr. Noakes? Noak. I have devised it purposely, because a new way is generally taking in what kind soever. Und. I am much of that opinion, since I have observed that new non-sense is valued more then old Wit. Noak. What think you then, if I speak to all the Judges in the Pit by looks and grimasks? Ang. A rare and prodigious thought! I have known a device like this, serve well in a Play. Und. And hath been thought a good Scene too. Noak. And first on you Criticks, I'le leer thus, like a Satyr; for the moderate Wits thus; for ho, ho, ho's, who laugh in such good earnest, when there is no Jest given them, comically thus. Enter Changling. Und. No more of your grimasks, good Mr. Noakes. Noak. And why so, Sir? Und. Because I have consider'd better, and since 'tis resolv'd, we shall have a Prologue to our Farce, here is one shall give it u'm the Farce way exactly. [To the Changling.] Ang. There's nothing better—the very Pudding of our Farce that must fill the Audience up to the throat with laughter. Noak. Since you will have it so, you shall find me reasonable; I confess 'tis a pretty toyish modish way. Und. And what is most extraordinary, he shall dance out a Prologue. Ang. A Prologue to be danced, aha, aha, Boys. [Angel leaps.] Noak. And I make Still-Musick with my mouth the whilst, shall I, Sirs? Und. 'Tis not amiss; come hither, Changling, and set your feet, and looks in order for the Prologue. Chang. Shall it be with my face, feet, and hands, tredoudling thus? Omnes. 'Tis very innocent and well. Chang. Il'e warrant you, I'le tredoudle it so, that it shall take to purpose. Omnes. Musick there for the Prologue. The Musick plays, he dances a while, then is heard a noise with Thunder and Lightning, at which time Ben. Johnson personated rises from below. Noak. Ha, Thunder and Lightning!—I hope the Madam Muses are not displeas'd with us. Ang. But what apparition is this moving towards us? Und. As I am an Actor, 'tis the Genius of the old Comick Poet Ben. Johnson, I know it by his Picture that hangs up in the Strand. Ang. Fly, fly, Associates, there's no being on the Stage longer, for us of the Farce party. [They go off several ways.] After which Ben. Johnson personated, goes up to the Audience, and speaks a Prologue.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Second Prologue personated like Ben Johnson rising from below. Behold I Ben appear, your Poet once, That living durst a vengeance here denounce On all the Stages Crimes, and Judges dare To make my Wit their sense, or else their fear; Thus have I left th'Elizium Shades and Groves, The sacred Mansions of the Muses Loves, Where I my Bays till now unwither'd saw In my immortal Plays, that here gave Law. But now provok'd, the Muses quarrel take, And from their call thus my appearance make; Did I instruct you (well ne're half an Age) To understand the Grandeur of the Stage, With the exactest Rules of Comedy, Yet now y'are pleased with Wits low frippery, Admitting Farce, the trifling mode of France, T'infect you with fantastick ignorance, Forgetting 'twas your glory to behold, Plays wisely form'd, such as I made of old; But by my Bays I swear, if you persist, And my Judicious Cautions hence resist, I'le next rise with the Furies from below, That scourge vile Poets there with Scorpions too, And with those circl'd, hiss at you, and them, Except the Scenes just Grandeur you redeem; Thus for your Crimes, but what this day will be, The fate and merit of the Play you'l see; I scarce divine, nor did its Author raise Me by a Poets charm to give him praise. I never had an Ear was sooth'd by Rhime, Or flatter'd to protect a Writers crime. And might this Authors modesty offend, Should my Encomium here his Play commend; Who now prevents it, whilest methinks I hear A whisper of his doubtings in my ear; His fears are many, there's such Fate in Wit, That Plays from fortune more then merit hit, Whose Muse would blush for such a guilty chance, Since 'twere the bounty of your ignorance. But though your crimes in judgment he forbears, Take heed, how Ben provok'd, once more appears.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Third Prologue. You see what little Arts w'are fain to try, To give a Prologue some variety; Wit you have had, perhaps, in many new, Though Farce, and Dance, (your much lov'd mirth) in few. But why Great Johnson's Ghost should thus appear, As if to hector Wits, and Criticks here, Who (if the Devil were Poet) would not fear? 'Twas a bold Fiction, and so let it go, Yet thus far 'tis instructive unto you; That should you recollect your Judging Crimes, The Ribaldry of Plays in Prose, and Rhimes, Johnson might rise indeed, and own it true. His Plays were Laws to Wit, and Plot well told, But such you slight, (though wise) because th'are old; And well it is for Writers, since that way You might expect from all who write a Play. True Comedy, the moral Mirth of Plays, Lives now the glory of dead Poets Bays, And like the Phœnix (though confess'd to be) Produces few of her Posterity. So rare a piece, our Poet dares not say You now shall see, but as weak Pencils may From Titian, or Vandike example take, And in their figures small resemblance make. So 'twas the business of our Authors Pen, To paint some life of Comedy agen, And like to such as would, but cannot Feast, Does wish your entertainment were the Best.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Persons Names. Tysamnes A Persian Prince Marry'd to the Queen of Scythia. Mr. Harris. Bassanes A General, and Prince of the Blood of Scythia. Mr. Young. Foscaris A Gentleman of Quality, who longs for his Wife after he has parted with her. Mr. Smith. Andrages Another Husband, who loves his Wife so well that he cannot part with her, though she seems to provoke him to it. Mr. Crosby. Toxaris Courtier to Parisatis Queen of Scythia. Mr. Standford. Alvanes Courtier to Parisatis Queen of Scythia. Mr. Cademan. Araxis Courtier to Parisatis Queen of Scythia. Mr. Norris. Draxanes Friend to Bassanes. Mr. Adams. Eumenes Friend to Bassanes. Mr. Westwood. Two Courtiers. Parisatis Queen of Scythia. Mrs. Betterton. Mandana A Queen of the Amazons. Mrs. Long. Statyra A great Persian Lady formerly belov'd by Tysamnes. Mrs. Johnson. Clarina Wife to Foscaris. Mrs. Shadwell. Melvissa Wife to Andrages. Mrs. Dixon. Four Court Ladies. Daranthe Chief Commandress of the Amazons. Mrs. Lee. Cydane Embassadress from the Queen Mandana. Mrs. Lilborne. Renone Embassadress from the Queen Mandana. Mrs. Wright. Masquers. Attendants. Guards.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">The Scene Scythia.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT I. SCENE I. Enter Toxaris, Alvanes, and Araxis. Tox. Well Mortals, if any live happy, 'Tis we Scythians at this day. Arax. And prethee why? Tox. Are not we Men? Arax. Yes, and Courtiers. Tox. And what's more, have our Amours unquestion'd By those meager sort of Females, Wives, whose entails We can cut off at pleasure, sometimes held necessary In case of Age, or accidental Ugliness; Is this no Felicity? Alva. A sign we had our Predecessors men. Tox. I, and such Souls of Matrimony, that Would be all in all in every Act and Concern of Woman; changing Wives at pleasure, Sometimes, as oft as Menial Servants how would The Wary Spaniard, the more Jealous Italian Glory, had they like priviledge? Alv. And yet, Methinks, this custom of our Nation In so absolute a dominion over That weaker sex, is not a little rigid. Tox. Prethee marry then, and if thou dost not Find it necessary; thou'lt be more easie Yok'd then most in Scythia. Alv. But our Queens marriage Is my wonder, with this Persian Prince Tysamnes. Arax. She is wise in all her Actions. Alva. Yet not by any priviledge exempted From this our Nations Law, though a Queen; 'Twere well, she had made it first, some Act of State. Arax. At least to exempt her self: Princes are But men, sometimes most various. Tox. It speaks her Confidence in her new made Husband. Arax. Or rather the strength of her own vertue, That dares trust her merit to embarque In any storm, should it arise from what ('Twere sin to think) Ingratitude. Alv. May they live great and prosp'rous. Arax. Tysamnes is a Prince endu'd with many Graces, Fam'd equal with the best Captains of our Times, In noble deeds of War; and though but younger Brother of the Persian Crown, against Natures act, deserves the first place in that Throne. Enter Foscaris. Alva. Here comes Foscaris, a Gentleman, that has Newly parted with his Wife, a fair one too. Arax. But that's a change in this part of Scythia, Few repent, where Women like to flowers, Are often plac'd in bosoms, but till Love Fades their sweetness—what Foscaris!— Fosc. The merry'st man 'twixt this and Babylon, Gentlemen. Tox. You have parted with your Wife. Fosc. And a fair riddance too; though as Women Go now, I think she was vertuous. Alva. Dost thou not therefore feel some regret For rejecting from thy embrace, so deserving a Lady? Fosc. No more then a child for throwing away A toy, when weary of the pastime. Alas, I have lain by her a whole Moon, Enjoy'd all her nights, and days varieties: Pass'd the beginning, the middle, and even The bottom of all can be call'd fruition; Which I confess was most delicious; But the heavy thought that this must prove In the end, but dull repetition, Did so cloy my appetite. Tox. Perhaps before it had taken a just fill. Alv. I confess, had I espous'd such a Lady I should have been content to have serv'd Love Two Apprentiships at least—But oh the wonders Of Matrimony! how soon has mankind Enough of the honey of Wedlock. Fosc. Nay, I dare commend her Graces, besides I think she lov'd me; and for her person Pigmalions Image might have been copy'd From her lineaments. A Face in ev'ry feature Pleasing: such an Eye! such a Lip! with a Cheek Jove ne're was fam'd a smoother to impress; With something yet, then all, more taking. Arax. And hadst thou not better have kept this delicate Food of Love, though thou hadst chang'd sometimes A meal; rather then thus utterly to forsake her? Fosc. Alas! I had my Surfeit, Gentlemen, and was So Wife-sick; she seem'd to me Loves potion. Tox. For my part, were I in thy case, and had A Face of Brass, I should go near to blush through't. Here comes the Lady— Enter Clarina. Clar. To be thus thrown from him without a cause, Or act of ill laid to my charge: on priviledge Of this our Countries ignominious usage; And by a man I lov'd so well? Vile, and inhumane custom! Tox. I hope her vertues, and thy crime will move thee To repentance: thou art else such a Tyrant-husband, as has no like, even In this hard-hearted Clime of ours. Fosc. Rather indulgent, that gave her means of Freedom: I open'd but the Cage, and Now Love may flye, as it lists. Clar. By my example— Let none be henceforth made a Bride in Scythia; Where sacred Tyes, and chastest Love Is no security. Tox. Though I am a true Scythian and partly Of thy humour, I could wish thee, (for this act,) Some fatal penitence. Fosc. Ha, ha, ha,—Is that Possible in a man of my complexion? Clar. He scarce vouchsafes a look on me; when but So late, each beam of mine was more Considerable then warmth of Sun-shine. Alv. We must now leave you to your better thoughts: The General Bassanes is arriv'd the Court. Our attendance is expected—pity Clarina has no kinder Husband. [Exeunt Alv. Tox. Araxis. Fosc. I'le wait on you Gentlemen: I serv'd But lately under his command— Clar. You have no pity left for me?— [Offers to go out, Clar. stays him. Fosc. A little somewhat; but thou seest I am now In haste. Clar. I'le be as brief; take me to thy embrace, My dear Foscaris: thou know'st I lov'd thee Vertuously and truly well: if I have done Amiss in any act unknown; I'le bend My knees for pardon. Fosc. Alas! I charge thee With no crime; but Marriage is such a mischief, It makes Friends sometimes differ, they know not why; For which I thank my Countries dispensation: Otherwise as a Mistress, I think no Lady In our Court deserves before thee. Clar. When e're you wed (as soon perhaps you may) May you espouse one far more beautiful And equal to my affection—so farewel— Fosc. Adieu—adieu: I'le not kiss her at parting, Lest I lick my self into Love again; And yet methinks I could almost be content: 'Tis a pretty black-ey'd rogue, and was so Amorous and Airy.—Heaven forbid I be not once more smitten, and so proceed To a second Wooing; but I hope I am arm'd— [Ex. Foscaris. Enter Melvissa. Clar. This unkindness grieves me. Melv. What! sad Clarina? Clar. I had ne're more cause, Madam—my Husband.— Melv. What of him? I dream't that he courted thee With more fire then ever; and my dreams I Can tell thee, hit unhappily sometimes. Clar. He is most unkind; a Husband of our cruel mode Perfectly, who having gather'd but so late My Virgin flower, has thrown me from his breast, As if already faded—and yet I needs must say, I love him still. Melv. Thence came thy mischief; The very spring of all thy Tears: we Wives Must use more dexterity in managing Of Husbands here; and that way, if possible, Get some hand on their Affections: nor should They bed with us; but when we please, Or when our healths require it: the soft and gentle Not seldom most slighted: The truth is, Marriage Amongst us is a most dang'rous food of Love: And therefore we must use more wit for sawce, Our men will be else so cloy'd, and cast us off With no more concern, then we give a dish Of meat after having well fed on't, to our Waiters. Clar. But I was so tender, In giving cause of separation— Melv. 'Thad fixt him surer to thee; nor is it hopeless, But the sense of thy Vertues and Beauty May work in him some thoughts of reconcilement: There have been (though rarely) such examples. Clar. Might I but live to be so happy!— Melv. Besides I have a means, if all fail To do thee service—thou dar'st confide in me?— Clar. With all assurance. Melv. You must be secret. Clar. As a thought within your breast. Melv. And mark me; if thou find'st this work him up To love again— Clar. I doubt the end will prove impossible. Melv. That's as the means are order'd: Love will find out Ways sometimes as extraordinary; which made A famous Poet write a Book of Lovers Arts, Not much inferiour to Medea's Charms:— And be sure when you see him next, let it Seem against thy will, as if thoud'st stand If possible, at like distance from him; As the sphere of fixed Stars: adding convenient Pride and scorn, no small artifice in our sex. Clar. Your Copies somewhat hard To be practis'd by a Lover. Melv. 'Tis but a just revenge in thy Case. Clar. I shall observe your fair instructions. Enter Andrages. Melv. See, here's my man of Venus; an example Of my skill and conduct—observe him well, And thou shalt see, I have an humble servant Instead of Lord and Master—is't not so, Andrages? Andra. Your will's a Law, Madam. Melv. In spight of our Nations custom, is it not? Andra. The same, Madam. Clar. This is a language, I have Not heard before from a Scythian Husband. Melv. And yet, I'le say thus much, for this thing Of my embrace: he dares vye with the best Of our Gallants; and cope with Mars himself If met in field; nor less would be concern'd For every frown of mine, with any he That durst despise e'm: Am I not right, Andrages? Andra. My life's at your command. Clar. You have a power I see indeed, and doubt not but you'l use it nobly. Melv. We must rule thus, or we are lost here: What's a Venus that cannot lead her Mars In triumph?—Andrages, perhaps I'le sleep With thee to night for this— Andra. You'l be most welcom Madam. Clar. This day some considerable of our Sex Join in a Petition to our Queen and New made King. Melv. 'Tis to abrogate their abuse, In the arbitrary rule of men. Clar. I hope 'twill prove a seasonable request, Since now the Queen has made her self a party; In taking of a Princely Husband. Melv. Thou hast eloquence, and shalt be one of Our fair Speakers in this Cause. Clar. You complement me Madam, Though I am oblig'd to serve the interest. Melv. We must appear with the fair number Who expect us to confer—Andrages— Wait my coming home about the hour of nine. [Ex. Melv. and Clarina. Andra. With all observance, Madam— Was ever Gentleman and Souldier thus hen-peck'd As I am? nay, against the priviledge of mankind Here, endure it? that can discharge a Wife With a breath: sure there's some extraordinary Magick in't; and I find by my inclinations, I am so unfortunate to love her at that rate, As I cannot rid my self of her, though I Suffer to death, or what's worse, the miseries Of a vexatious wedlock. Enter Foscaris. Fosc. What Andrages? heavy and drooping! Andr. Somewhat out of Tune. Fosc. Nay, then 'tis odds, but thou Art smitten, or at least ruminating On some new beauty. Andr. Would that were the worst. Fosc. The very best of our Banes, that have prov'd Wedlock—Come I'le sing thee a catch I have Made on this subject. He Sings. 1 What though her Eyes are black, And kisses with a knack, Natures best skill e're created? In time she may prove A surfeit to Love; And so deserve to be hated. 2 Love freed from this diet Is best kept at quiet, The wanton still longs for to range; Let's thank then our Laws In Wedlocks frail cause, Gave Husbands a License to change. Andr. This is all discord to my malady. Fosc. I took thee to have been longing after New flesh and blood, or rather sick of thy wife, Is not that it? Andr. Thou dost not mock me? Fosc. No, o' my life! Andr. Why then I'le tell thee, I love her a thousand times better, then When I long'd for her first enjoyment. Fosc. Is that possible in a man of thy Genius? Andr. Let me be punished else. Fosc. Alas! poor Souldier of Cupid: I have parted with a Wife fair enough To have figur'd Venus by, and for that only cause, Because a Wife: I'd fain see the power of Man, Or Angel, bring me again to the like dotage. Andr. Nay more, should she scratch me once a day, Or use me with that Amazonian confidence Practis'd in our neighbouring Scythia, where Her Sex has the supremacy, and are So many she Tyrants: I think I should Endure it, and love her: If this be not Magick, There's none betwixt us and the North Pole. Fosc. Visit her bed often; and if that does not do it, There's no surfeit in Wedlock. Andr. Alas! I have not leave to come there, but rarely, And on such terms of good behaviour, That I am almost in an Ague the while. Fosc. The very name of Humourist, methinks Should bid thee quit her, there's scarce a worse evil. Or if she be modish, and a wit, 'tis odds, But she makes it her luxury to abuse thee, And bite thee at every turn of thy tongue. If not, make any thing thy quarrel, to bid Adieu to her, thou'lt else shame thy Countries priviledge. Andr. But I am such a Dotard— Fosc. And yet i'th' Camp And Court, well knowing, as most of our Time; I pity thee— Enter Bassanes, Alvanes, Toxaris, Eumenes, and Draxanes. Andr. See the General Bassanes. Fosc. A Prince of high renown and vertue; Now return'd from ending our Tartarian War: We'll pay him our respects at time of fitter Opportunity— [Ex. Foscaris and Andrages. Alv. The Queen by us, my Lord, That have the honour to fore-speak her joys, Congratulates your Excellencies return. Bass. She is a gracious Lady; and though but late Made my Intelligence, has taken The Persian Prince, Tysamnes, for her Husband. Alv. A Prince that Court does loudly fame, surpassing All the race of the Arsacides, whence he derives His blood. Bass. Her vertue is a mate for his; Let it be great as e're did live upon the name Of mortal; but I that have a Souldiers plainness A little wonder, although her King I hold Of highest merit: since there is no act precedes To exempt her Royal Person, from that fate Of Marriage, the force of custom here May even inflict upon the greatest. Tox. It seem'd below her Soul and Love, to make That caution, some wise amongst us wish. Bass. Tysamnes! marry'd to the Queen! if I [Aside. Forget not I had Advertisement upon his first Arrival at her Court, and from a Persian hand Of trust, that he there lov'd a Lady; nay more, Was thought to have assur'd himself to her. Eum. The General's a little discompos'd. Drax. Perhaps some discontent relating to the Queens marriage. Bass. If this prove true, Heaven too soon may frown On all these joys—what are these Ladies? Enter Melvissa, Clarina, and four other Ladies, each with a Paper in her hand. Tox. They are come to wait upon the King and Queen This day of State, on some concern of their Sex. Bass. Tis well. Enter Araxis. Arax. The King and Queen are ready to come forth. Alv. We must attend—your Lordships pardon. Bass. I have some orders to dispatch unto The Camp, and then I'le wait their Majesties— [Exit Bassanes, &amp;c. Tox. Alv. Arax. another way, manent Mel. Clar. and four Ladies. Melv. It behoves us now Ladies, to weigh the force, And effect of those Arguments we have prepar'd To assail so formidable an enemy, as Men and Husbands, fortify'd With that so invincible Champion, Custom; I hope you are all well provided? 1 Lady. Doubt it not Madam, women seldom want wit To serve their desires and occasions. Melv. Well said pretty one, young and forward, And for Illustrations and Metaphors, of This hainous usage and tyranny of our Matrimonial Lords and Masters, such were to be wish'd, Are most pathetical and perswasive.— 1 Lady. I have taken mine, Madam, from The example of Socrates, that most grave Philosopher, who not only endur'd the ill Humour, but the supremacy of his Wife, As worthy of imitation. Melv. A famous president! 2 Lady. And I mine, Ladies, from that most dreadful Story of Andromeda, chain'd to a Rock; Which I hope I have apply'd with no small Flame 'gainst Husbands and their prerogatives. 3 Lady. Mine is from that of Ariadne, shewing The ingratitude of Theseus, with application To some such hideous presidents amongst us. 4 Lady. I have drest up mine out of Story, and the Grand Romance of our Times; from whence I have Drawn some noble examples of Love and Constancy. Clar. You are bold with the Poets and Romances Ladies. Melv. That's a pardonable fault, as the rate of wit Goes now; while some Poets have arriv'd to a Convenient reputation, yet play'd the Thieves, From Poems, Histories, and Romances; And ne'r durst trust themselves for a happy fiction— Clarina, I am sure you are well provided. Clar. I have an Argument at home, enough I hope To plead for all. Melv. Who has our petition? Clar. I have it Madam. Melv. 'Tis in a proper hand—the Queen. [Enter Parisatis the Queen led by Tysamnes, Andrages and Foscaris, Alv. Tox. Arax. Attendants and Guards: being sate Clarina delivers the Petition.] Tysam. We understand your fair desires, But you must in this case determine Dearest. Par. With your permission—where is your Speaker Ladies? a little fuller to explain your sense? Omn. All, all, all, speak. Fosc. How they muster tongues? Andr. Bating this presence, if they did not join Nails and scratch some of our foretops, I'd hang for't. Par. You can't be heard together, nor each in Several, 'twere tedious—name one your Speaker. Omn. Clarina, Clarina, Clarina! Melv. She shall perform. Clar. Since you impose it— Then thus Illustrious King and Queen; 'tis hop'd This day will prove a Mercy to the name Of Women here, that suffers by a too Injurious custom, now represented to your Royal hands for our just redress, And wants not many thousand hearts t'attest it. Par. Where had you leave to form this Strange request? does not the Law stand unrevok'd? Clar. But hop'd, that you our gracious Queen, would have Been Intercessor, for its Abrogation: That with your Love and Crown have given Such obligation to a husband, who must For your sake yield to make it ineffectual. Tox. Our Women press it home. Fosc. Have at us Husbands; They'r on a ticklish point. Par. Is this all Ladies? Clar. And but obtain'd, you'l difference the name Of wife from worst of slaves: restore the most Neglected, to the rights of Love, and live The blessing of your Sex; nor shall we want Expressions of our gratitude; our Gems Shall be our offerings to increase your Treasure, Which useless now, adorn our Beams, That every froward Husbands power (to cast us From his just embrace) must mourn. Par. I'le hear no more; yet pity those Whose Merits are regardless treated; Advising each to win the man they have lost By vertue and forgiveness: if the fault be his; And were I to be given again unto This Prince, or doubted of my happiness in him; I'de judge it sin to ask a Caution: And I dare be to all security, That our example will without a cancel Place a blush upon this Law, and no man hence Neglect a Wife deserving, when they shall Behold our mutual Loves their president; Is it not so, my dear Tysamnes? Tysam. Thou art above my wishes excellent. Arax. The Queen exprest her self most nobly. Tox. If not too confiding in her choice. Clar. We must submit. 1 Lady. Since there's no remedy. Melv. I'le serve thee yet Clarina! it shall go hard else. Enter Bassanes, Eumenes, and Draxanes. Par. Welcom, as I can express Bassanes— Thy Victories were early here on Rumors wing, Which made the grim-look'd Tartars beg a peace From us: and next my joys of love, completed here, [To Tys. I must rejoyce thy safe return, thou pillar Of thy Country, and glory of my Crown, To call thee both my Subject, and Alliance. Bass. My duty is best paid in the performance Of your services, which I shall ever study. Tysam. Let me embrace thee worthy man; The title which I have to thy brave merit, In my enjoyment of this beauteous Queen, Obliges me to hold thy vertues dear That bring'st me Triumph home, before I scarce Have warm'd this Throne. Arax. Our new King does caress him highly. Tox. His interest is great. Par. I understand You saw Mandana's Court, our neighbour Queen, on your return? Bass. I did Madam. Par. There Women govern all. Bass. To wonder, Madam— Make War, lead Armies, with all transactions Of the highest Magnitude in State, To whom the men are held subordinate. Par. Their Queen's a Lady, Fame reports Wise, Magnanimous, and no less Beautiful. Bass. I think all these may well be said to meet In her. Par. But the manner of her rule seems strange To me. Bass. If compar'd with ours here; but they Lay claim to that prerogative, from the Antient Amazons whence they derive descent. Par. 'Twas said Mandana did intend an Embassy Unto our Court in some short time. Bass. She gave me so to understand. Tysam. A beauteous one no doubt. Bass. They are Women, Sir. Tysam. We'll treat'm then as fairly. Par. But credit me, I should not like my reign So well, were my Sex here alike in power; Since nature and the worlds best Laws Have dignify'd the man superiour. Tysam. Spoke like my Parisatis—methinks we Are not chearful; I have joys enough to raise A man above the world, had he made forfeit Of his bliss—You told me of a masque, My Soul does want a little clearing up— [Aside. Par. I did appoint one. Tysam. By any means we'll have it. —Musick plays a while, after which the Masque begins; the Scene a Grove, in which Diana is beheld sleeping, having at one of the sides next the Stage a Rock, from which— Enters Arethusa habited like a Water-Nymph. Areth. Eccho! if thou dost visit this fair Grove, Where thou hast often mourn'd Narcissus love; At Arethusa's call appear. Eccho. Appear. Areth. Once more 'tis Arethusa calls thee here. Eccho within. Here! Areth. That's but thy voice, thy person I would see, Once known a Nymph of highest dignity. Enter Eccho as out of t'other side of the Grove. Eccho. Behold bright Arethusa I resume My long lost Figure, since Heavens fatal doom Depriv'd me of my dear Narcissus flames. Areth. I bear as great a grief confin'd to streams, Could never yet with lov'd Alpheus join; Think if thy loss can greater be then mine? Eccho. Fair Nymph, with yours I'le not compare my woe, Since with thy tears thy chrystal fountains flow; And by a wondrous constancy do glide Through veins of earth unmixt with other tide, Which Thetis for thy glory did decree, And great Diana Honours Constancy. Areth. I wait to see her bathe in my cool floods, Having a long chase follow'd in these Woods. Eccho. She in this Grove with her fair Nymphs does sleep, While with my wakeful voice her watch I keep; Lest Mortals here (Actæon like) should pry, And ravish blushes from her Deity.— Behold she wakes. [She wakes. The Song in the Masque. 1 Nym. See, see, our Goddess wakes, Whilst we harmonious notes prepare, Such as bright Phœbus makes, When to salute Aurora's ear, The Musick of his sphere he takes. 2 Nym. Or as before her Curtains drawn We welcom in the grey-ey'd dawn, When for the Chase Diana bends her matchless bow, And gives her self the first hollow. 1 Nym. Then through Plains, Lawns, and Woods, Over Mountains and Floods Nymphs trip it, Nymphs trip it apace. 2 Nym. Whilst the Hart, Deer, or Roe They swiftly pursue, Their Goddess best pleaseth to chase. 1 Nym. See she appears More bright then Hesperus does rise, Whose beams Stars borrow for their eyes. Diana rises and enters with her Nymphs. Dian. Belov'd of Nymphs whose chaste and constant stream, Shall give thy Love an everlasting name; More dear to me then Zanthus floods so bright; Or my own Cynthia's beams that guild the night; Art thou to tread a Chorus come with me, As once a Nymph of my society? Areth. Bless'd Goddess know from Thetis I am sent To wait thee first with her great Complement; Who, if not too much Neptunes Billows rave, Will soon pass hither in a Chrystal wave. Dian. She shall be welcom. But first Nymph on thee Diana, (to renown thy constancy) Does from her hand this pretious gift bestow, Sprung from the tree, whence grew her sacred bow; On which with finest silk my Nymphs have wove, The wondrous story of thy streams and love. [Puts on a Chaplet. Areth. This grace lov'd Goddess, I must ever own, While Arethusa by that name is known; But if I may thy Deity intreat, I'd gladly yet with my Alpheus meet. Dian. Thrice beauteous Nymph, thou su'st I fear in vain, But for thy merit if I can obtain, Or Cynthia's aid can help, she shall convey His gentle current where thy stream has way. Enter Thetis attended with several Sea-Nymphs. Omnes. For which let's all Diana's praises sing. Dian. Stay Nymphs, here comes the Queen to Seas great King. Thet. Chast Goddess, I am come to let thee know, What to thy Graces, Neptunes Queen does owe; And for this Nymph the honour of all floods, As these with thee make sacred groves and woods. For which to speak my thanks I'd gladly tread The stately Chorus, thy bright self does lead. Dian. Great Thetis know, no footsteps ever joyn'd With me a Chorus, but bear souls refin'd; For which I have deny'd some gods of late, Said to have fell from their celestial state. Thet. I once gave ear unto such tales like thee, But prov'd it soon my vain credulity; Nor on my waves did then rough Boreas blow, But I my Nymphs hid in deep Cells below. Since fame had told his strong arms did embrace The fair Orithia snatch't o're Seas to Thrace. Dian. Nor was it Thetis truth, Achilles came From great Peleus, and thy own soft flame. Thet. Such stories may relate as much of thee, Which tell the Moons sublime Divinity; Though thy chast brows her Heavenly figure wear, Did for Endymions love forsake her sphear: While such like Tales the guilty Poets sing, To feign their Hero's from the Gods did spring. Dian. Queen of the Seas my censure was too free, 'Twere sin to doubt truth in a Deity: Nor will I think that Goddess e're did burn, In such frail humane flames my chast thoughts mourn: But now behold with me this mortal Throne, Merits from our immortal powers renown. Thet. I do embrace the motion, since here's seen A Throne as bright as each of us sate Queen; May Love there find, serenest calms their days, Such as my Halcyons chuse that breed on Seas. Areth. Or as my streams no mingl'd currents own, So let their Loves be undivided known. Eccho. May Cupid else for ever loose his Bow. Omn. And for Loves Goddess none his Mother know. Thet. To honour whom, thy best known Chorus lead, And with the Oceans race like steps I'le tread. Dan. Then Nymphs express with mine your measures powers, As when we dance on tender grass and flowers: Leaving no signs our nimble footsteps show, Or as on Mountains tops, we tread on snow. [They Dance. Enter Cupid. Thet. Cupid, art thou come hither? Cup. I flew this way To meet my Mother, is she amongst ye pray? Dian. Away, thou amorous toy, dar'st thou be here, Where I to honour constant Love appear? Cup. I have a shaft here left within a Heart I'd fain withdraw. Dian. No more vile Boy, depart, Thy Mothers Arts and thine, I too well know. Cup. Then see I flye with an unbended Bow.— [Ex. Cupid. Dian. Thetis farewel! I'le to my Woods resort. Thet. But e're I hence return to Neptunes Court, Let's yet more honour Arethusa's name. Dian. This night I bathe my self in her clear stream. Thet. Where I'le attend thee with my watry race, And Nymphs, whose Songs shall there thy Chorus grace. Areth. For which my fountains clearest springs shall flow. Eccho. And my best Eccho's voice pay duty too. Dian. Till when farewel Seas Queen. Thet. Goddess adieu. [Exeunt Masques. Tysam. It seems a Moral. Par. And meant of constancy, I gave the Argument my self. Tysam. Most fit To entertain thy Vertue. What sight is that? Enter Statyra. Tox. The King seems troubl'd. Bass. My heart misgives me this is she. Par. How does my Love? Tysam. Your leave a while— Can'st thou forgive me fair Statyra?— [Goes aside, to Statyra. Stat. And wish you happy in your royal choice, She is a Princess far above my merit: Enough that I have seen your face and dye. Tysam. Thou had'st my promise first, Heaven is my witness, And give me but thy leave to expiate My crime, in due expression of my penitence, By some act unthought of; if possible, To win thy Loves forgiveness. Stat. 'Tis needless— Your leave that I return, I'le not ask So much as a farewel kiss— Tysam. I must oblige a while thy stay: Bassanes, Wait this Lady to my Garden lodgings With all observance— Bass. I shall Sir— [Ex. Bassanes and Statyra. Tysam. The ambition to possess a Crown has had too much The better of my Conscience—Come Parisatis. [Goes to Paris. Par. Your looks seem troubl'd. Tysam. A trivial thought I'm moving from my heart. Par. From mine, I'm sure, your love shall never part. [Exeunt Omnes.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT II. SCENE I. Enter Eumenes and Draxanes. Eumen. It seems the Ladies had but small success In their Petition. Drax. And yet they urg'd things Home and unhappily. Eumen. Women ne're want zeal, seldom wit To perfect their desires; but men have here So long had the Lee-ward point of love, as They must be content with the Weather Gage; Which casts not a few on the rocks of Wedlock. Drax. For my part I could wish, that Nature had Taken some other way for the procreation Of mankind; since both Sexes have so much ado To agree of the means—But we are Souldiers. Eum. And therefore have the less reason to blame Our Countries freedom, since 'tis odds, but we Take as much, if we make a true Muster Of our Mistresses. Drax. But the Queens opposing This desire seem'd to many unexpected. Eum. 'Twas to oblige the King no doubt; and by The prerogative of her vertues, live Above the Law, or whatsoe're could give a fate To her enjoyment. Drax. He's now more absolute Then e're was Soveraign that reign'd But in the right of Queen. His Creatures Dignify'd in Court and Camp; that almost 'Tis within his Will to rule alone, should He be guilty of that vile ambition. Eum. She has exprest in every act a kindness Most unparallel'd. Drax. I wish their Loves a peaceful happiness. Eum. 'Twas hop'd she might have respected our General Bassanes in her choice, a Prince Of Scythia's Royal blood, and favour'd In this Nation with an interest equal To his birth. Drax. But he it seems, as much in love With Mars, or paying duties to her service In the field, ne're rais'd his thoughts and merit To that fair ambition. Eum. We are his Creatures, And have serv'd his dangers. Enter Toxaris, Alvanes, and Araxis. Tox. Save ye Gentlemen; Your general thanks to his vertues, has given Our Crown at once both peace, and victory. Drax. His conduct did deserve no less. Alv. Had his return been sooner, perhaps 'thad Given some stay to the Queens Marriage— But that's between our selves. Eum. The news surpriz'd him, We must witness; as one was scarce consulted In that action. Alv. She was a little hasty in her choice. Arax. Though in her King, she seems to summe such joys As if she'd vye with Angels, as she shines, Espous'd on earth to his affection. Tox. Nor does the face o'th Court, sometimes the glass Of Princes, discover ought save joys, and smiles, A sign to us Courtiers, the Throne's no less serene. Eum. But in the midst of these methought the King Appear'd disturb'd at the presence of a Stranger Lady. Arax. But that soon vanish'd. Eum. Time will discover more. Alv. This day, Mandana's Embassy is expected; 'tis said, they are Women. Arax. Perhaps to complement our Queens Marriage; Or make some league betwixt their Amazonian State and us. Eum. But say they should provoke us To a War; we must bring strange arms into The Field to have the better of this Generation, That dare fight with men. Drax. I could methinks ee'n wish a War, To see how these the she Militants would Behave themselves; a home-charge with such Troops, Were winning of a field indeed Gentlemen. Enter Bassanes and Statyra. Eum. Here comes the General and that Lady I spake of. Arax. She's wondrous fair. Alv. May her beams give no dazle To our Kings affection; methought she mov'd Him strangely. Tox. Our way lies this way to the Court— [Ex. Tax. Alv. Arax. Drax. And our's here— [Ex. Drax. and Eumen. Bass. Madam, you highly honour me In this discovery, from which I find Your name and birth illustrious, as Persia knows. Stat. The acquaintance, Sir, I was oblig'd to make you, Since here my stay upon the Kings command, Might else have stain'd the honour of my blood With such a character as curious eyes in Courts Are but too apt to give the least of favours That a Prince vouchsafes a Lady. Bass. You are wise And noble: and give me your fair leave To ask a question, my intelligence Assur'd me most undoubted. Stat. If it be truth My Soul dares not deny it. Bass. Then thus most noble Lady; Did not the King once love you? Stat. I did not think Heaven had reveal'd what I had thought a secret— [Aside. To his heart and mine—suppose he did, and yet I blush to charge him with a guilty truth. Bass. It was my apprehension— Stat. And since 'tis made your knowledge, I must further say My wrongs are fit to be convey'd as far As the world has bounds, or fame can stretch Her wings to bear e'm. Bass. I fear too sadly— [Aside. But should you own this claim to his affection now. Stat. My love's a truth too dear to smother, nor Did I come, but arm'd with resolutions Worthy of my Soul. And 'tis my highest service To his Queen (whose vertues I much honour) If I reveal to her my claim, and thence Mark out her dangers in this man of falshood She enjoys. Bass. I know you would not charge Him with this crime, on purpose to create Repentance; or if you did, who knows What were your dangers (I speak it not to Fright you Madam) that here must look like some Prodigious Star on a great King, made now So fully happy in the bed and glories of a Queen— Which how he will resent— Stat. Let it be death, 'tis welcom from him. Bass. Heaven avert it, Madam; yet 'tis not safe To tempt a passion past recall, though I Want not a pity to your vertue. Stat. I thank your goodness. Bass. Or say you could attract his past affection; And in each beam of yours, more deeply wound His heart then ever (as you have all things Summ'd at Natures dearest cost, that can Inrich a Beauty) were it not glory To recede from such a Conquest. Stat. Your Counsel's noble I confess. Bass. Besides we have a custom here that does Impower each common man to loose the very Gordian knot of love in marriage, That other Countries hold inviolate: What may then a King do to enjoy So bright a Mistress as your self? Stat. I find the World in this degenerate Faithless age of man has yet one Worthy left: [Aside. Know then, most noble Prince, your Counsel does Conspire with the honour of Statyra's heart; And though I had a more superiour title To the Kings affection then the Queen can claim Though made his Consort; yet I for her sake now Forgive his breach of Faith; nay more, if 'twere Requir'd, would freely give my life, to see Their Loves most happy. Bass. Give me the honour Of your hand, to pay my humble adoration Of this vertue. Stat. My stay shall not be longer here Then taking leave, becomes me of the King. Bass. 'Twill speak your worth. Enter Tysamnes. The King—your pardon Madam— [Ex. Bassanes. Tysam. Statyra! how dost thou like thy welcom In our Court? Stat. As more then I intended to receive. Tysam. Thou can'st not soon be weary Of these shades, and pleasant walks, where Nightingales will meet, and sing New ravishments to entertain thy beauties: More glad to welcom thy appearance, then The morning joys, or evenings splendor that Invites their rest. I think thou might'st be well Content to live here still. Stat. My honour is no child To be deluded with such toys, though gay As Paradise when first it's sweetness bloom'd, While but a thought of crime does ripen near me. Tysam. Thou shal't be here as innocent as flowers That yield their smiles unto the distant Sun. You'l grant me sure, so much, Statyra? Stat. I'le rather welcom death then yield to stay A minute longer near your person. Tysam. I know thou art not so unkind. Stat. Alas I came without design of love, Though once your lover. Tysam. Statyra! hold, go not Too far in goodness, lest Heaven (to surprise My wonder) take thee hence, and place thee there A Star, or make me fall I know not whither. Stat. I have done Sir—nor shall my presence give you More concern; or further accent repetition Of your sin to Heaven and me; that in despight Of all the darts of Love (so late my wound) Can with this smiling ease and calm of soul Bid you farewel for ever.— [She offers to go, the King stays her. Tysam. You must not, Shall not leave me thus— Stat. You will not, Sir, detain me Here by force?—what will your Court then whisper, Or the bolder world convey to both our infamies? Enter Parisatis. I hope I have made enough expression Of my affection— Par. What do I hear? Tysam. 'Tis but to give thee more assurance Of my love, for which I dare adventure Life and Crown. Par. That word! oh my heart!— [Aside. Stat. Then know who 'tis you stay— And thus dare frown upon your will. Tysam. How's this? Stat. And what I thought this breast should have conceal'd, I'le utter with a boldness does become my honour— And when you know it, you'l perhaps, as soon Cherish a Tygress near your bosom— Know Sir—I came with full intent to kill you— Mark me well: to kill you—for your faithless promise; But that the vertues of your Queen with-held me, In whom I wish you ever bless'd: the whiteness Of whose Soul, I thought it sin to cloud (From act of mine) with sorrow. Par. Forgive me Heaven; This Woman is some Angel sure; I can No longer hold but pay my reverence. [Par. goes towards Stat. Tysam. We are interrupted—my Guard there!— Enter Captain of the Guard. Convey that Lady from my sight, and see Her safe confin'd within her lodgings. Par. Let me beg for her freedom, though I do it On my knees— Tysam. I must not grant it; she came To ruine my content, perhaps in thee; A Treason too she has confest against my life. Stat. Let me deserve your fair opinion, Madam, Though I dye. Tysam. Away with her—how does my Parisatis?— [Ex. Statyra with the Captain of the Guard. Par. Never better—this dissipates my fear. [Aside. Enter Bassanes. Bass. Embassadresses from The Queen Mandana are arriv'd. Tysam. See their reception want no state our Court Can give; they shall have Audience speedily. Some thoughts require me to my Closet first. [Ex. Tysamnes. Par. Bassanes, never so happy, as this minute In which I prov'd the fix'd assurance of My Kings affection. The Persian beauty Who but so late gave apprehensions to My love, is now no more my fear. Bass. She is a noble Lady, And gave me confirmation of her honour. Par. 'Tis most unquestion'd. Bass. She does intend suddenly To return back to Persia. Par. Alas! the King (To my great grief) in much displeasure Has restrain'd her. Bass. I hope she'l soon have liberty. Par. It shall not want my intercession. Bass. Pray Heav'n this be no Artifice. Par. True love is soon confirm'd; but in that Brest [Aside. Suspicion storms, it ne're can anchor'd rest. [Exeunt. Enter Clarina and Melvissa. Clar. Our Petition had but small success. Melv. No matter, as to thy case; did not I Promise to serve thee? Clar. But where's the faith Believes it possible? Melv. If it be next a Miracle, And do the feat, thou'lt welcom the effect? Clar. However, my obligement's great to your endeavours. Melv. What if a smile or look of thine, or a toy As inconsiderate as the least lock of thy hair, Produce his Loves return, as I apply it; Hast thou not reason to thank the means? Clar. 'Tis granted. Melv. Therefore believe well; rememb'ring that We are told, a dram of faith can do Far greater wonders. Clar. You shall confirm me, But I hope it is no Charm or Magick? I am strangely fearful of the Devil. Melv. Rather a means from Heaven! my Mother Left it as a Legacy to me. Clar. A Recipe most Wives may wish for here. Melv. I thought to have given it to the Queen, But that perhaps 'twere death to own, And this our custom unrevok'd. Clar. I hope her vertues ne're will want affection. Melv. As it effects, I'le tell thee more. Enter Foscaris. Here comes thy Husband, and I am prepar'd For him to purpose—thou must withdraw Till I give thee notice to appear. [Ex. Clarina. Fosc. Madam! your most humble servant. Melv. And I perhaps ten times more yours. Fosc. This sounds briskly. Melv. Not that I intend to instance, You have parted with a deserving Lady, And so press a reconciliation from The doctrine and uses of Love, as some Matrons Amongst us might perhaps ring in your ears In the like case. Fosc. Far be it from me to Think it, Madam; I know you are well bred, And must therefore understand what better Belongs to our Mode, and a Gentleman, then so. Melv. Well said Gallant—but I hope you'l not teach My Husband to follow your example; And like such a Buck as your self, break Through the toyl and bonds of Marriage; Though some of you allow it no more, then A State device to catch fools. Fosc. This is a Witty Rogue; a Wife that understands The intrigues of a Mistress. Melv. Then say, my husbands wife Should think you a fine Gentleman— Fosc. I understand you Madam. Melv. And were willing to bestow some affection On your worth.— Fosc. Go on Lady, go on; you are Coming to a point indeed. Melv. There it is, you have it to a hair— [Gives him a Bracelet inclos'd in a Paper. I hope you will keep Counsel— Fosc. O Madam! 'twere sin to doubt it. Melv. And wear it carefully, for the owners sake I mean, and so farewel kind Foscaris; If this fail, thou'rt proof above Mortal. [Aside. Now to be near and act further as occasion serves. [Ex. Melv. Fosc. What have I here? I'le open it carefully, And first taste it by the smell; it scents Most Lady-like, and amorous; methinks It moves too, I know not how: Oh these Women Are rare contrivers in these Scenes of Love— Now for the enclos'd— [Opens it. Ha, ha, ha, a Bracelet of a lock of Hair, In colour much resembling my Wives: but Such a trick on me, were to little purpose, I'le tangle no more there—but now I think on't, I have found the knack; as sure as I am made Of flesh and blood, 'tis Melvissa courts me For her self, for which purpose she handles Andrages, her husband, at that rate. 'Tis a witty-gay female, as most within Our Kingdom; and it seems the Rascal's Willing to graft his fore-head, and be beholding To his Friend for the Horn. In the mean time I'le pleasure her desire, and wear her favour. [Puts it on his arm. The Devil on't, it warms the vein that leads To the Heart strangely; and 'tis love I feel In abundance—I must vent it somewhere, Or I shall burn to ashes; 'tis most certain I am Charm'd to purpose, and 'tis odds but some evil spirit Waits at my elbow. Melv. within. None but thy better Genius— [Speaks altering of her voice. Fos. Ha! a voice too, then there is a Devil in the Case 'tis manifest—what art thou, and from whence? Melv. I am a Spirit belonging to the element of fire. Fosc. Thou hast some possession of me already then, Who am flame all over—what is thy business? Melv. Love, kindest Love. Fosc. The same is mine, and Since thou art a kind Familiar, I dare ask Thee a question—Art thou a Genius of Love at large According to our Gallantizing Mode? or art thou for A more peculiar Courtship? Melv. I incite Honourable, and Matrimonial Love. Fosc. A most Heroick Devil indeed; But take a care how thou dost otherwise appear to me, Lest my sword make bold with one of thy limbs, And it prove afterwards to belong to some Sorcerer, or Witch. Melv. You need not fear that. Fosc. Prethee avoid me then, I would not willingly be haunted By a Matrimonial Genius of all other. Melv. Your desire is granted— While only I'le thy heart incite To love thy fair deserted Wife, For whose sake, I am oblig'd thy sense to ply, Since on thy wrist thou didst a philter tye. And so farewel. [Ex. Melvissa. Fosc. Adieu, adieu! had ever man such a Dialogue As this? [He studies. Enter Clarina and Melvissa. Melv. Be confident I have perform'd to purpose. Clar. I warrant you. Melv. Nay more to his greater Terror, I withdrew here, and counterfeited my self A Spirit. Clar. Most excellent! Melv. And had Such pleasant discourse with him. Clar. You have done above my expectation. Melv. He comes on fiercely I warrant thee. Fosc. And yet I do not find my hair stares, or A cold sweat on me, enough to dissolve me to a gelly, Like some stories I have heard of this kind. Melv. See, he's here, observe a little—in the mean time I'le withdraw. [Ex. Melv. Fosc. Whilst I feel such a heat dispers'd through every vein Of my body, no man, or longing virgin ever felt The like in any burning wish, or actual enjoyment— Well Foscaris, thou hast got a tickling spirit in thee. Clar. I perceive it takes. Fosc. And yet methinks It should not be in the power of Magick to make Me affect my cast-off Wife; if it prove otherwise, What a confounded Lover am I then—she's here. [Observes her. Clar. Now I'le approach him. [Walks towards him. Fosc. As I am a man, 'tis she I long for, The very element of fire is met Within me, and my heart rises to my very lips At her appearance. [Gazes on her. Clar. The Physick works; now to handle this patient. [Aside. Fosc. Oh thou art bright indeed Clarina; Ariadnes Crown of Stars is Copper To thy Eyes, and in each look methinks thou Stain'st the evenings glory. Clar. Good kind Sir, keep off, 'tis towards bed-time. Fosc. 'Tis thither I would go with thee Love, and twine More happily then ever! Alas, I did but this To love thee ten times better then before; As men restrain themselves from food they like To make the next meal better. Clar. Keep your ground good Sir Amorous; You and I must not come to the close embrace So easily; and lest you should be boyst'rous, I'le be gone. Fosc. Stay but a twilights time longer— Clar. 'Tis more then I can well afford you. Enter Andrages. Fosc. Nay prethee let me beg it though I kneel. Clar. You deserve some penance; I'le not intreat you To be sparing. [Ex. Clarina. Andr. Foscaris kneeling! and to his own Wife? The world sure turns round, or Plato's year Is come about; if this Diamond he late Discarded should again be Trump?— What Foscaris! pensive? Fosc. Oh I am undone! And. What's the matter? Fosc. Nay, thou'lt laugh me into shame enough When thou know'st it. Andr. By no means. Fosc. Why, I am wounded by Cupid the wrong way? Andr. As how? Fosc. I scarce know how to tell thee. Andr. Nay prethee let me know. Fosc. Understand then I am in love With my own cast petticoat; if that be not A curse to a Scythian Husband, I'le Challenge fate to do worse if possible. Andr. Though I found thee on thy knees, I hope Thou dost not pray over love again to thy Wife. Fosc. But I do, and at such an intolerable rate, That were every sense of mine a several soul, She might command 'em all to express it. Andr. Is't possible?— Fosc. And more, look well to thy self, I fear thy Wife's an Inchantress. Andr. Ha, ha, ha— Fosc. If thou dost not see her flying steeple high, And thy self atop on her shortly, I'le hang As high for't. Andr. But you thought there was no such thing As Charm or Magick in Love, and that our Scythian Wives would have still continued such Tame things, as like bob'd Eyesses, they might Have been turn'd off; and took to hand at pleasure. Fosc. I have prov'd the Experiment dearly: Take care and mock not, lest thou art beheld Converted to a Cat, and cry Mew To keep her company. Andr. Is this the man That could defie Cupid and all his Arts? Nay shoot your Darts contrary to his, at A minutes warning—was it not so? Fosc. I thought I could, till more then mortal powers Conspir'd against me. Andr. And for a Wife, 'twas Such a potion, must have no more to do With your palate. Fosc. The very name of her Inflames me like fire. Andr. A little more to cool you And I have done; come I'le put you in mind, Of a Julip of your own composition; What though her Eyes are black, [Sings. And kisses with a knack, &amp;c. Fosc. No more, no more, though I deserve to be Bitten with a Satyr could sting worse then Scorpions. Andr. Well; I have done. Fosc. Let's shake hands then, And go thus postur'd to the Frantick Society here, Amongst which I'le dye, If e're there were two such Fanatick presidents Of Husbands as our selves: Oh 'twould make such a Novelty of distempers! Andr. And there endure a little of the twig, Shall we? Fosc. By any means; Thou for observing thy Wife with such a Fond affection, as I beyond dotage Long for mine again. Andr. Good Foscaris, Enough of this extravagancy: In the mean time I have so far the better of the malady, That I have no fear of thy relapse, And for a cure, let me advise one more gentle; Let's drink some Wine, and give it spirit In Clarina's health. Fosc. Oh that I could taste her lips once more— And mark me friend, 'tis odds as I am a Gentleman, But in spight of all prevention I shall Hang or drown my self for love, e're the next Moon. Andr. Come I'le take care of thee. [Exeunt. Enter Tysamnes, Parisatis, Bassanes, Clarina, Melvissa, Toxaris, Alvanes, and Araxis, &amp;c. Tysam. We understand Bassanes, that the Embassadresses From the Queen Mandana are arriv'd. Bass. They are, Sir. Tysam. Attend them to our presence. [Ex. Bassanes. An Embassy few Courts have seen before, Where Women bear their Princes Errands, And rule supreamly even our Sex. What think you Ladies, were your case alike With us? Clar. For mine I should not wish it, Sir, 'Twere too injurious to the right of men. Melv. You are a little of the kindest Lady— For my part, Sir, were I born under the like Favourable Aspect of Venus, 'tis odds but I Should wear a Bow and Quiver, to maintain The priviledge—you'l pardon, Sir, my freedom. Tysam. A witty sprightly Lady—and yet I dare believe There's none of all you Gentlemen, that has A Wife predominant, who does not own Submission to the custom here.— Tax. This touches home. Tysam. I am confirm'd, that were the case my consorts here, (So dear unto my soul) she would not claim Her self exempted. Alv. That parenthesis was odly plac'd. [Aside. Par. You know I am all obedience, Sir, And hope you'l now receive such offers, from This our neighbour-Queen, as will not give your thoughts The least disturbance; nor would I have a War Wherein my Sex should fight, were I made a party In the cause, or injury. Tysam. Thou art all Excellence. Enter Bassanes with Renone, and Cydane the Embassadresses. Now Ladies, your Queens pleasure. Renone. Who does by us, most Royal Sir, congratulate Your great accession to this Throne, and more, your joys In this your fair and vertuous Queen, who scarce Has equal in her Sex: to which (if possible) Her wishes do yet adde more happiness. Tysam. This is but usual form of State: proceed. Cyd. 'Tis what our Queen expects you'l welcom, Who waves dispute of Territories, The usual great concerns of Thrones; And has but one demand instead of all, To make your Greatness: whence may spring A lasting league betwixt her mighty Crown And yours. Tysam. Speak it then! Par. I hope 'twill find reception. Cyd. Then know, our Mighty Mistress does demand By us an Abrogation of that most Rigid usage here, from which the Husbands will Is too much Lord of love. Tysam. Sure, you mistake your Embassy? Ren. Nor can she reign without a blush must stain Her glories, should she not (if deny'd) Compel by arms her Sexes fair relief. Clar. Nobly urg'd. Melv. Methinks I could fight in this Cause my self. Arax. The King is mov'd. [Aside. Alv. Observe the Queen. Tysam. Your Queen's too bold with us in this demand; But she's a Woman. Cyd. And soon you'l find, she'l slight All dangers in this Cause: nor is the world Unknowing, that her arms (though guided By the conduct of our Sex) has oft gave Wars rough Laws to men. Par. Let me then intercede, my Royal Husband, I would not have a quarrel in this Cause, (Although I doubt not from your love security) The world I know would say you but defend A most unkind prerogative; and since 'tis thus, Bestow it as a bounty on the Sex for my sake. Tysam. Can this proceed from Parisatis? Par. As truly as I wish your peace and love. Tysam. Thou dost mistake in both— Par. Besides, what honour wer't in such a Cause To be a Conquerour? or on your Warlike Trophee to Inscribe, you did subdue the force of Women, Led by a neighbour Queen, whose bravery Of soul, deserves esteem and wonder— I know you'l condescend. Tysam. Away, thou dost abuse thy Love and me. Par. Is't possible? Tysam. Or else endeavour'st by compliance with This Embassy, to betray the honour of This Crown, and People; take which you like— And know thou hast forfeited thy Being In my soul. Par. Heaven defend. Tysam. And tell your Queen I'le reign [To the Embassadresses. A King of men in spight of all her power Of Spinsters: whose honour by this grant would be The mock of Women. Nor do I doubt their hearts And swords will join with mine to assert this Nations right. Tox. The King is much incens'd. [Aside. Alv. I hope 'twill not reflect upon the Queen. Tysam. And by my Act, to assure the world how much I'le own my Subjects priviledge, behold my Queen. Cyd. A Lady full of Grace and Vertue— Par. Oh my fears! Tysam. Who with no more concern I'le cast away, Then Indians do a Pearl, that ne're did know It's value; and from this hour no more my Wife. Par. Must it be so? Bass. Consider Sir, this Act May prove a rash one— Tysam. My resolution's fixt—nor do I fear What Law can act, though hence I reign not jointly With this Queen, while by the power I possess, I can create a right above it. Par. Nor shall I plead a word Against your Will, though it severely fall Upon my Love; or mention what should be Your gratitude to me, that gave you both My self and Crown, and yet will give my life, If your concern require it— You'l give me time convenient to withdraw. Tysam. Thou shalt to any place retire within My Crowns Dominion, where thou shalt live In state and greatness of a Queen— And so farewel. Par. Adieu, my dearest. Alv. This action of the King was unexpected. [Aside. Arax. Such as must breed some strange distemper here. Tox. I wish our Almanacks were all burnt else. Tysam. To morrow you shall have our Letters to your Queen. Renone. And as becomes her she'l resent this Act. Tysam. Bassanes— [Ex. Tysamnes and Bassanes. Cydan. Madam, you have our pity. [Ex. Embassadresses. Clar. The Queen deserves a sorrow From all Hearts. Melv. She has deeply mine. Par. Though life has many ways to lose it's comforts, Few hinder the distressed means of death: And let my sad example teach my Sex, That when they love embarque with men, 'tis like A vessel, that with guilded streamers sails On dangerous Seas, and in each calm must think This smooth-fac'd Ocean may their Barques soon sink. Exeunt.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT III. SCENE I. Enter Parisatis in a Mourning Vail led by Bassanes. Bass. I want no sense of your afflictions, Madam. Par. 'Tis like your worth. Bass. And dare express it more Then entertaining of your griefs by naked Accents, That were too low and common for Bassanes heart; Each vulgar ear that hears from rumours breath, Will do as much, and glory in the hope Of making stubborn Heaven bend to hear Your sufferings. Par. You are a Prince ally'd unto my Crown, Nor can I doubt, but every vein of yours Ha's many streams of honour— Bass. Know, Madam, Since you are pleas'd to call me worthy of Your great Alliance; I want no heart to tell The King, your Husband (though sitting on the Throne) His ingratitude. Par. I wish I had been truly charg'd with any crime That might have given his Act in my desertion, Some vizard to out-face the world: I dare believe The Law that first here gave this liberty to man, Did tacitely imply the Husband should Not be a lawless Tyrant to the Wife. Bass. The injustice is too palpable; and Fitter 'twere this Law had no more being, Or the Sex of women against Natures Made supreme, then thus to be imbitter'd 'Gainst your vertue, Though smooth'd and guilded over with pretexts, He calls State Policy, and Marriage Interest, But simply Artifice to bring another To his Throne and Bed. Par. I fear 'tis too much a truth. Bass. Statyra is no doubt design'd to shine In this Meridian, by your fair remove: But think not, Madam, that your Eclipse of Glory can pass without your Subjects due Remorse, and vindication: he is a King here But as you made him so, in giving him Your self a Queen; and from your love has only Title to your Subjects hearts. Par. And had the world Been mine in Kingdoms, with as many Hearts, My affection had dispos'd 'em all to him. Bass. You have given proof above parallel. Par. But this ingratitude does combate with my soul! Bass. Permit, I serve your Royal Vertue. Par. I know thou dar'st revenge my wrong, and hast An interest in thy blood and merits, that Can guide this Nations Arms, and raise a stream Of vulgar force, enough to sink Tysamnes Even to the depth of ruine, though fortify'd with All the power he now enjoys. Bass. I will imploy my utmost in your service. Par. I have I see a Subject great, brave, and faithful; In spight of all adversity—Bassanes Thou wilt obey me strictly? Bass. Be danger what it will; Nor need you question, but the arm I shall apply Is strong enough to right, or else revenge Your injuries: nor want I means prepar'd Even at this minute, that shall soon perform The least breath of your commands. Par. Then know, I do enjoin you all obedience To the King— Bass. How, Madam? Par. I mean Tysamnes, Who has thrown me from his heart, and that far More strict, if possible, then had he met My Love with equal constancy—I would Not live and underact the part of virtue. Bass. You oblige me now to be your enemy— Who knows how soon you may be taken from The world by him, that thus has cast you from His bosom? Par. 'Tis not inglorious if I die, Or split on any rock, This storm shall throw me on, If Innocence be my harbour. Bass. The Worm that's trod on, bows in some displeasure When it's griev'd; what should then do your Greatness? Par. But vertue's yet more gentle, whose value's Most refin'd by suffering—I know You will obey me. Bass. Since 'tis your pleasure. Par. And be sure give out 'twas Act of State, Or Crime in me, or any thing thou can'st devise Most plausible, to assure the people To Tysamnes. And more, that 'tis my strict Command, they obey him with all duty, As their King—this I command thee As thou art a Prince of worth, my Kinsman, And my best of Subjects. Bass. You shall have my obedience. Par. There's something further I must act— [Aside. I'le now consult my thoughts— Enter Tysamnes. Bass. Madam, the King. Par. Attend him— [Ex. Parisatis. Bass. Her worth does merit providence, To raise her triumph above all misfortune— [Aside. Tysam. Bassanes, thou'lt welcom War I know, when e're 'Tis made against our Crown. A Souldiers soul Is half asleep in peace; nor do I doubt But by my Arms and thine, to adde yet more Dominion Unto this. Bass. Your affairs (I judge) Are not so well compos'd at home, the face of things Has no kind prospect on your Greatness, If I can presage. Tysam. This looks not well, Or rather seems unmannerly and bold. Bass. My tongue is not so much a coward To my heart, but it dares speak you to the world unworthy, In the desertion of your vertuous Queen. Tysam. Dar'st thou own the name of Subject, And tempt my fury thus? Or stare me in the face, and ask me why I did an Act, reason of State, and the Prerogative of every vulgar man admits?— Bass. But forfeits all to honour when unjust; Nor can you truly call your self a Sovereign Here, since now turn'd Tyrant unto Love, which Rais'd you to this Throne. Tysam. I'le hear no more—my Guard there! Bass. Or mine that's nearer hand. Enter Eumenes and Draxanes. Tysam. How's this! treason? Bass. That word's too black for my intent; nor is There voice dares interrupt what I shall utter, Unless Heavens own, that perhaps will chide me, For appearing slow in doing justice On your self. Tysam. 'Tis not thy force, or death In all it's shapes of horror, threatn'd against My life, can move my soul.— Bass. I pity so much bravery in ill. Tysam. But that I find a pricking here— Bass. Such as will blisters raise upon your heart, And make it burst with burden of your crime; Nor must you think, that all the pendants Of your State and Glory (were you permitted Here to own 'em longer) will not fade and blast Themselves, worn thus inglorious. Tysam. Forgive me Heaven, as I repent; Bassanes, Thy loyalty has made me truly Convert; And could this Act but be recall'd— Bass. I dare pronounce you then my Sovereign, Though 'twill wound you yet more deeply, When you know this Royal Lady (injur'd Beyond thought) not only Ha's forgiven this Act, but by command On me and all her Subjects, made you absolute To Reign (if you dispense with the Ingratitude) without her. Tysam. What penance Is enough to expiate my Crime? though I should melt my heart in tears, and showre 'em As an offering at her feet— Call forth my Queen and best belov'd Parisatis. [Ex. Eum. and Drax. Bass. Let me now kiss your hand. Enter Eumenes and Draxanes. Eum. The Queen, Sir, is withdrawn. Tysam. How's that? Drax. Remov'd Sir, none knows whither. Tysam. I fear she has taken some precipitate resolve. Bass. The joys this news will bring, Must soon cause her appearance, Where e're she is retir'd. Tysam. Make strict and speedy search, He wants no wealth brings happy tidings first. Eum., Drax. We'll use all diligence. [Ex. Eum. Drax. Tysam. Bring forth Statyra. Bass. I'le wait her to you, Sir. [Ex. Bassanes. Tysam. 'Tis fit she know How much I have offended for her sake. Enter Bassanes and Statyra. Statyra, I must beg a pardon of thy vertue. Stat. Sir, you have prov'd I can forgive. Tysam. Thy goodness I have injur'd next my Queens, And I am making of my peace with Heaven And her. Stat. 'Tis worthy of your Soul— But you'l consider, Sir— Tysam. I do, that 'twas my sin of love to thee Which did induce this Act, to whom I first Dispos'd my heart: and would to Heaven I had Two souls, that I might give one to thy vertue, And make thee twin in my affection with my Queen; Excepting whom, the world and womankind Are but trifles to my heart. Stat. Mine is as truly yours; And let this blush excuse my boldness, If I claim you now my own. Tysam. How's this Statyra? Stat. You are made free by Law, (If such a one this Country owns) and can That less then plead for my enjoyment now, So much your Lover? Bass. I did not look for this. Aside. Tysam. Tempt me not fair Statyra, lest I fall Below the sin of the Apostate Angels; And call thy love my second crime. Stat. I did but mention mine to prove your constancy. May you for ever live most happy in Your Queen; and for your sake I'le beg of Heaven That she may late be taken thither. Tysam. Thou art a pattern of perfection— Stat. And since you now have made me free, I'le crave Your leave to respite my return, till I Congratulate your happy meeting with Your Queen, and so to Persia, where I'le Spread your joys. Bass. This centers with my wish. [Aside. Tysam. Each syllable of thine does give my soul new wonder. Since not alone, thou can'st my Crime forgive, But yield I may anothers Lover live. Ex. Tysamnes leading Statyra, Bassanes. Enter Melvissa with two Courtiers. Melv. You are pleas'd to like my entertainment Gentlemen; and I am apt enough to be Proud of your good opinion. 1 Court. You are all diversion, Madam, our Court Has not such another Lady. 2 Court. I hope you'l Give me leave to spend some hours with your converse. Melv. You may be welcom as I please Jointly, and severally. Both. We understand you, Madam. Melv. But methinks you are a little dull (though Courtly bred) since you speak praises of my Wit, But have little to say for my Beauty. 1 Court. Oh Madam! that's granted, the Court has no such Star, bating the Queen. 2 Court. Besides, your Ladyship Cannot so far mistake our inclinations, As to suppose we pay adorations To the ugly, though ne're so witty; They are only fit to eat with, provided They keep good Tables. Melv. Now I perceive you. 1 Court. But for you, Madam, (so perfectly taking) The day is too short to admire you, and The night to enjoy you. Melv. You aim well, and 'tis odds But I guess the mark you'd hit—pray sit a while; I can afford you some minutes— [They sit by her. 2 Court. There's no time Long enough, we are not in haste.— 1 Court. 'Tis fit we wait your leisure. Enter Andrages. Melv. I keep my lodgings free enough for entertainment, And live without the fear of Prying Watchers, or the Jealous Husbands eye. Andr. Oh my torment! she dares me to be jealous too. [Aside. 2 Court. I suppose, Madam, you allow the Gentleman His times of hawking and hunting, in order To your more private Recreations. 1 Court. Let me be so happy I beseech you, As to have notice when he is absent. 2 Court. Or I, Madam, I should endeavour to serve you. Andr. I'le try whether I have so much courage Left, as to mark these things (made up of perfumes [Draws his Sword. And Perriwigs) in the fore-head with a Jealous token of mine, e're I am convicted I wear a horn there my self—now Gentlemen— 1 Court. Your Husband, Madam—we are in haste— Melv. You need not make so much. 2 Court. Your Humble Servant, Sir.— 1 Court. The King expects me, Madam. Melv. You shall not part with any apprehension Hence—how now Sir Hot Spur? I must curb you I faith, if you offer to take such Careers as these. Andr. You may command me, Madam—a Lark is not So dar'd as I am by this Hobby of mine. [Aside. Melv. Put up your Tool, and remove; your appearance Was more unseasonable then I look'd for. Andr. Each word she speaks is a Charm; I have not So much valour in me as to oppose her tongue, What e're I have done, or dare do otherwise. [Ex. Andrages. Melv. You may now withdraw, Gentlemen, the King expects you. Both. Your Servant Lady. Melv. There is no need of the expression; I did but act a little of the most to show my prerogative; I hope you'l say there's one Woman amongst us Has wit enough to rule her Husband In spight of Law. Both. We'll witness it to wonder, Madam. [Exeunt. Enter Clarina hastily. Clar. Oh Madam! your experiment has done Wonders; my Husband— Melv. Loves thee now to purpose.— Clar. Beyond expression. Melv. My mother prov'd Such a like Artifice on my father, For securities sake, yet lov'd him dearly. Clar. You have given good proof in your own, And for mine, I believe he feels love. In every fiber of his heart; kneels to Adore me, compares me to Stars, and Vows that I am more fair then ever. Oh what a kissing time shall I have on't, If he and I meet in embrace again? Melv. Tantalize him well first. Clar. But to say truth, I long my self, and would willingly be—you guess— Enter Foscaris. Melv. He comes, withdraw a while— Ex. Clarina. Fosc. Oh Madam! you Have given me a present has had such Powerful operation on me. Melv. By this time You well understand the meaning on't I assure my self. Fosc. 'Tis love Madam, in extremity. Melv. Did I not tell you so? Fosc. I thought I had hit your sense To a hair indeed, while I conceiv'd you As Gentlemen should a Lady in the like case. Meiv. It means as good a thing I can assure you. Fosc. But I am doting on my Wife again, And must (in spight of flesh and blood) woo her 'Twice over. Melv. There 'tis—Alas good Sir, who could Have thought it in a man of your temper? Fosc. That same bewitching Bracelet you gave me, Which I am fain to kiss thus reverently Most minutes of the day, nay, sometimes pray to't; I can't blame your Husband For being such a strict Amorist; he Has had his philter I suppose. Melv. I never found it needful; if I had, Perhaps I should have endeavour'd much To preserve his love. Fosc. There's not a hair On thy head, but I dare say can do more Then all the Charms of Medea. Melv. Excuse me, Sir. Fosc. I should be loth to prove you guilty of Magick, though 'tis certain. Melv. Proceed, good Sir, And accuse me, because Heaven has brought Your affection back again to your Lady; 'Tis odds but I shall answer it. Fosc. Well, since 'tis thus, I forgive thee; and as you are a Woman, Speak a good word for me. Enter Clarina. Melv. That I assure you, And perhaps have taken more care for you Then you can imagine—here she comes, Apply your self first. [Ex. Melvissa. Fosc. And are we met thus? Clar. If not happily, you may remove me With the least breath of yours. Fosc. Nay, prethee stay, I love strangely to look on thee— O that Eye of thine!— Clar. And this Cheek, this Lip, (some think not ill) So often tasted by you, with other amorous Passages of ours: does this remembrance please you? Fosc. To miracle!— Clar. And do you truly repent My desertion, as you protested to me you did? Fosc. From the very bottom of my belly, sweetest. Clar. Had you said your heart, perhaps I had Took your word, and consented to have met Your desires on honourable terms. Fosc. This may be a device to bring my passion To some further mockery: (these she Serpents Want no wiles) I'le try whether or no I can dissemble mine, though against the Power of Magick. Clar. You dare trust my Love? Fosc. I could find in my heart— Clar. You seem'd of late To adore me so strangely, that I am oblig'd To take pity of you now for fear of your wits. Fosc. 'Tis certain she mocks me— [Aside. I confess I felt a kind flame, or so; But I did not intend to keep a perpetual Etna in my bosom, or such a Fevour Of Love, that will only admit of one Julip. Clar. Melvissa's Arts do fail I fear. Fosc. Besides, you Women are such nice things To handle, and as the world runs now, Have such superlative devices.— Clar. I can forgive you truly; by this [Points to his Picture by her side.] Image which ne're can hang too near my heart. Fosc. My Picture still there? better and better; [Aside. As sure as I live she's charm'd too. Melvissa I remember told me, that she had done Something extraordinary for me; I may Dissemble safely, and if need were, make her Long as much for me now; what a rare turn Of Love would that be? Clar. You then continue cruel still? Fosc. Alas my pretty fondling, I know thou Wer't ever kind and tender; but to say truth I did but counterfeit my passion, a little To comply with thine, and gave out I had Receiv'd I know not what charms of Venus, Supposing thou had'st more wit then to believe Such wonders. Clar. Is't possible? Fosc. Alas! what Could'st thou expect from a man of my complexion? Clar. I'le try my own Art a little then— [Aside. Oh my Foscaris!—behold I dye to shew Thee thy ingratitude [She makes as if she swounded. Enter Melvissa. Fosc. Help, help, help, my dearest thing of life, I love thee most outragiously. Clar. Are you in earnest? Fosc. Alas! I could even eat thee to express it. Clar. May I confide? Fosc. Besides, I'le tell thee more; I am charm'd to that purpose— Behold this Bracelet, there's ten thousand Spirits of Cupid in it. Clar. May I be certain? ha, ha, ha— Fosc. I'le swear it by a thousand Stars. Clar. Ha, ha, ha— Fosc. By this good light she jeers me. Melv. And acts her part unto my wish. Clar. Some other time you and I will dispute terms. [Ex. Clar. Fosc. Oh my folly! Melv. If you want an Advocate, Yet command me; in the mean time, I hope You'l make much of your favour, and so adieu. [Ex. Melv. Enter Andrages. Fosc. If I am not put in a Ballad, or Lampoon'd By some Scurrilous Poet before to morrow This time, there is no mischief in being a Subject of ridiculous wonder. Andr. What's the matter? Fosc. Ask me no questions— Andr. But I could tell thee Such a story of my Rancounters. Fosc. But pronounce not the name of Wife. Andr. I'le tell thee news then; 'tis said we shall have Wars with our Amazon neighbours. Fosc. Let it come, I have quarrel enough to the whole Sex For the sake of one. Andr. But if they have many Such Pentheselea's amongst 'em as my Wife, We are beaten into corners. Fosc. I am for any thing that's desperate, And if I do not cut as many of 'em Off at the waste, to be reveng'd of this Evil Genius of mine, let me dye By their Bodkins. [Exeunt. Enter Tysamnes, Alvanes, Araxis, Draxanes, Eumenes, and others. Tysam. Call in the Embassadresses. [Ex. Eum. Drax. Enter Bassanes with Renone and Cydane. Here are our Letters to your Queen.—We hear her Army Is advanc'd near upon our Confines. Renon. But first by us denounces War; Who scorns to gain a foot of earth, but what Her Sword shall fairly win. Tysam. We'll soon prepare to meet her. Cydan. And thus we take our leaves. King whispers Alv. &amp; Arax. Bassanes to the Embassadresses aside.] I hope your Queen, whose most Illustrious Person I admire, will grant me pardon, [Aside. If in my Countries Cause I serve a Souldier. Renon. She honours worth in all, amongst whom Your vertues have no small effects, Acknowledg'd by the world A worthy Captain. Bass. Your Servant Ladies. [Ex. Embassadresses. Enter Foscaris and Andrages. Tysam. You shall have all Commands become your valours; I know as men, you stand oblig'd to serve this Cause. Fosc. To a man, Sir. Andr. And I (excepting one Woman) Dare act as much against the Sex: but she I must confess, Sir, has the better on me In all Incounters. Tysam. Your Wife I guess; I am glad to hear I have a Subject who Is so kind a Husband—No news yet of our Queen? Bass. Not any, as the best of my Intelligence can learn. Tysam. My soul is on the torture. Enter Toxaris. Tox. I hope Sir, I have brought you happy tidings in this Letter. Tysam. 'Tis Parisatis hand. Tox. 'Twas given me From an unknown person, who would not stay To satisfie my further Queries. Tysam. reads. Let this assure you from Parisatis, That she is remov'd from this Life, before It meets your hand: The means I have Resolv'd on for my end, I will not give you the Grief to hear, or charge you guilty of my death, And to confirm you, this precedes my last being; I have sent you this Jewel, you must witness I vow'd should be kept to the death of Parisatis. Oh Heavens! my Parisatis dead! read Here Bassanes. [Bassanes reads. Bass. My tears are slow, but credit me, The death of Armies, and the groans of War When made from gasping Friends, just drowning Of their souls in streams of blood, ne're shook My heart like this. Tysam. Thy griefs are truly mine. Bass. But hope that providence, whose paths are Labyrinths, may yet— Enter Statyra. Tysam. She's dead, she's dead, too certain— Stat. The King's disturb'd. Tysam. Beyond expression; Parisatis my Queen— Stat. I hop'd was now return'd to your embrace. Tysam. The other world contains her vertues, she's dead. Stat. My eyes can ne're want streams to pour With yours for such a loss. Tysam. Mine are too guilty to partake With thine; and had I more then Niobe E're shed to drown my soul in; or turn'd To Marble at this news like her, 'twere but Too gentle to express my crime or grief. Stat. This passion's glorious. Tysam. What death can I devise, or torments Give my soul enough, that have at once To answer breach of faith to thee and death of her? Stat. Your stain is deep in both, though far more vile As you are a Prince who did unworthily Possess the love and glories Of so excellent a Queen; that no pretence Of Power, or Law, can expiate— But since by Heavens decree she's thus remov'd To Stars, for which did I but know her Urn, I'de visit it, and pay my tears as an Oblation to her memory— Yet now 'tis fit you live for my sake Tysam. Thou hast some justice to my life, But wilt not now oblige it? Stat. I do, and Claim it as the greatest blessing of my own. Tysam. There's nothing left me, but in thee, that can Invite a minutes breath. Stat. You had my first love Sir, So far you have an interest still. Tysam. And for thy sake I will admit to live; Nay more, I'le talk to thee of Love, and with What penitence thou shalt require, acknowledge My past vows to thee, besides the guilt of my Ingratitude unto my Parisatis. Stat. Heaven must absolve your crime to both, For this your noble sorrow. Tysam. Thy words are comforts to my soul; But this is such an hour the Stars must mourn, Or find new trepidations in their orbs To fright the earth with some calamity— Besides an Enemy does threaten now to invade Our Kingdom—Bassanes, you shall command As General. Bass. With my best duty Sir, and 'twas Your Queens command I should continue still your Faithful Subject. Tysam. I have no other title here to reign but from her love,— Admit I leave thee, fair Statyra, in some place Of best security. Stat. I am oblig'd to be companion in your dangers. Tysam. That were an endless peril, though thy vertue Be above what fate can injure. Stat. My heart were else not worth the owning yours. Tox. A brave and gracious Lady. Alv. The King 'tis sure affects her. [Aside. Tysam. I feel a cloud upon my soul, I know not when Or how 'twill vanish— Come Statyra, my Love and thine must wait The calmer hours of time and kinder fate. Ex. Omnes.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT IV. SCENE I. Enter Mandana, Daranthe, Cydane, Renone, and other Women. Mand. The King may soon repent he gave our Treaty Such neglect. Cyd. We doubt it not, most royal Madam— Mand. And for his Queen, whose fair desertion Has the first place in our quarrel, would she Were now alive, that we might with our arms Impose her on his Love. Daran. 'Twere to be wish'd. Mand. The proof we have now given by taking This strong City of Daxata on the River Volga, must make 'em know, their force Must yield unto our Sexes power, We lead—what thinks our chief Commandress? Daran. I judge that victory will soon Make offerings at your feet. Mand. This Pass we have Secur'd must prove considerable, since it Impedes all their recruits that way. Daran. And what's more, Hinders provision might else arrive Unto their Camp: nor can they forrage here Much longer, environ'd on each side with Mountains, where by your mighty conduct All the passages stand seiz'd by us. Mand. I think They dare not hope to force their passage. Daran. Our Womens hearts must fail 'em strangely then, And make your greatness wear a blush, To see them this day prove degenerate, Who from your conduct glory many Victories. Mand. Spoke like the blood of Amazons. Renon. Nor do we doubt the issue of this day Will make your Prowess far more fam'd Then brave Thalestris (stories tell) was from Great Alexander, (the Prince of Captains) Held in highest admiration. Mand. I see You are all resolv'd, as does become This Cause I fight, by which we'll force even Nature To confess she was a partial Mother To our Sex, when she made man First heir of Glory. Daran. Royal Madam— Mand. Enough, they serve Our drudgeries, our pleasures, or embraces, To create us Souldiers, that scorn their uses But for our heroick ends. Daran. Did but the Women Of this world besides hear this, they'd be asham'd, To think they had not broke the yoke of men, And such a fair and great Protectress in your self. Mand. An entertainment for our Greatness there, That this haughty Prince, Tysamnes, (who dares Make War against our Sex) may know that we In this strong City, forc'd from his bold powers, Keep our triumphant joys. Ren. Some Prisoners of War desire to present Your Majesty with a Dance, after the Manner of their Country. Man. We admit them. Musick and a Dance. Enter Messenger. Mess. A Moorish Lady desires admittance To your presence. Man. She has our leave. Enter Parisatis disguis'd like a Moor. Man. Your business Lady. Par. 'Tis such, most Royal Madam, must beg A pardon for my craving this access, Who have journy'd far to see the glory Of your Arms and Person, fam'd above all The antient Amazons so much renown'd. Mand. The ambition of this visit we can pardon; And glad we are our Actions have Oblig'd the world and fame. Par. But more your Sex in this Fair Cause your arms embrace. Mand. This language suits Our greatness— Par. And though our swarthy clime Cannot boast Natures Beauties in Rose And Lilly cheeks; that gives us there as Daughters Of the night; or that the kisses of the Sun Were so unkindly spent, as it alone Did darken us, and guild the world besides; Yet we have there bright souls of honour. Mand. I find thou hast, above what I in this Short view can read—thy Name? Par. Zeriffa, Madam— Mand. Thy extraction I need not ask, I know it must be great That represents thy self so full of noble grace Unto our presence. Par. Your great esteem is My ambition to improve, though with the Greatest hazard of my life. Mand. And dost thou then love Arms?— Par. So far, most Royal Madam, as I would Be glad to dye, though not so much as mention'd In the lowest place, among the Annals Of your fair Atchievments. Mand. I even dare Already boast I have a Souldier in thee, Worthy to lead with us, and these, whose veins Are warm'd with blood of Amazons, inciting Deeds, which but reported to the softer Of our Sex, give tremblings to their hearts. Par. I should be loth to lose my share in honour, Or miss the end I have design'd my life; Yet must avow I never yet have fought. Mand. Though thy Complexion above all my Sex, Nature has fitted most to deeds of War, In which the scars, and wounds of arms, cannot Dig furrows in the fair brow of Beauty, So dear unto the vainer of thy kind. Yet I must now require, whether no other Motive has produc'd this inclination? Par. I'le soon confess I have not liv'd so much Oblig'd by man, as that I may not justly Be concern'd in your great cause and quarrel To make an offering of my life. Mand. Thou hast won my confidence. Par. The command I ask from your great Majesty, Shall be but mean, such as your prudence best Will judge becomes a strangers trust. Mand. And thou shalt have it, worthy Moor. Par. But crave it may be hazardous and daring: Heaven knows how willing I am to be rid of life. [Aside. Mand. Thou shalt have fit employment for thy valour— And take care my valiant Women, that this Moor, who promises such wonders of her Faith And Vertue, does not in noble emulation Match your Prowess. Daran. The Queen's soon taken with this stranger. Cydan. She seems to promise much. Mand. A suit of our best Arms and Quiver For this Moor— Enter one with Arms and Quiver. Daranthe, and you Ladies, See her according to our warlike mode [They put 'em on. Invested; nor do I doubt thou'lt use 'em Nobly. Par. I should be else not worthy of that Soul I would be thought to bear. Enter Messenger. Mess. The Enemy prepares for Battel, Mighty Queen. Mand. We will prevent 'em giving the onset first— Mean while, let's hear a Martial Ode, The Harmony our Womens ears delight; While others of their Sex warble amorous Notes to entertain their Lovers. The Queen Mandana leads her Amazon Women in state round the Stage, making several pauses while the Ode is Singing; at the end of which they go off. The Amazons are suppos'd to sing the Martial Ode. To Arms, to Arms, the Warlike fare, As our Heroick Charms, With Martial Eccho's fill the Air, Inviting unto Arms. Our Women with their Bows and Darts, Dare Mans rough powers assail, And Conquer such unshaken Hearts To give Love laws as we prevail. Advance, advance, lest fortunes haste Our Onsets should delay, Obliging time that flies so fast, To curb his Steeds this day; And hand in hand with mighty fame, That wraps in Clouds her head, Her glorious daughters us proclaim, And first our stately Triumphs lead. We challenge Dian and her Host Of Nymph-like Archers all, Who from their Quivers glory boast, Or proud Acteons fall; If ever their bright eyes beheld, A Chorus like to ours; Or saw themselves so far excell'd By Womens more Heroick powers. [Exeunt. Enter Bassanes, Foscaris, Andrages, Eumenes and Draxanes. Bass. Be couragious Gentlemen, the straight we are in, I doubt not but my conduct with the Kings Will find some brave expedient to relieve. Omn. We'l all dye at your command. Bass. And for the Souldiers wants, our valours soon Shall feed, e're their pin'd bellies mutiny For bread; my presence is requir'd to see What order keeps our other wing. [Ex. Bassanes. Fosc. Well Lads, we must fight it out to purpose, I find there's no getting else a crum of sustenance. Andr. Or be made such drudges to these Amazonia Furies, their Camp has not the like. Drax. In our late skirmish methoughts they fought Like Dragons, and handl'd their Bows with more Dexterity then Parthians. Andr. There's at least A Legion of Women, or more Evil Spirits In any one of them. Eum. And should we fall Into their hands, what might they expect After that rate? Drax. As I am a Souldier, I think a Brigade of men would scarce do The bus'ness of one Woman of this Generation, If they have the same vivacity for Venus, As for Mars. Fosc. This morning I could have been contented To have broke my fast with one of the fair Centinels next me; 'twas such a pretty Hard-hearted Rogue. Drax. And if I starve for want Of Bread and Women, let me perish unpity'd. Eum. Nay, we must venture on their bodies some way Or other; there's not a passage left us else So wide as man enters the world. Drax. 'Tis said they hold Intelligence with our Scythian Women: and have made such furious resolves If we fall into their hands. Andr. And for us Husbands— If they Conquer— Fosc. Eunuch'd to a Man, Gentlemen— I look to carry my quill in my hat, To show I am wholly castrated; For the rest of our Troops, perhaps they'l give 'em Leave to spin in Boots, or serve their other occasions. Enter Tysamnes with Statyra, Bassanes, Alvanes, Toxaris and Araxis. Eum. Here comes the King; we now shall be for Action speedily. Andr. His looks seem troubl'd. Tysam. Our City taken on the Volga, and Our Provisions, the Sinews of our Armies strength Cut off before our eyes; nay more, inclos'd By female powers—Can you be men and live To this contempt? Bass. Spare your passion Sir. Tysam. I cannot, while I see I govern Souldiers Scarce deserve the name of men, more fit, By Heaven, to be converted to some other shape, Or serve as Chamber Eunuchs to this female kind Our Arms oppose. Bass. This stratagem of theirs Was unexpected; in all my time of war, I ne're was so surpriz'd. Tysam. Think, dear Bassanes, How we may redeem some part of this dishonour. Bass. I judge the way must be to attacque Their left wing with a brisk assault. Tysam. Be it thy command. Foscaris, Andrages, Draxanes and Eumenes, be you assisting In this enterprise with such Troops you lead. Omn. To our utmost, Royal Sir. Bass. And hope I shall soon give your Majesty A good account of this attempt—Madam, I have your happy wish. Stat. And more, my Prayers for your safety. Tysam. The other wing (my worthy Chiefs) I'le lead To assist your valours. Omn. We all are ready with our Duties. Tysam. And if our Swords cannot yet subdue these Women Warriours; let them triumph, And tell Dame Nature 'Twas her fond erroneous act, Entituled Man Superiour. Stat. Consider, Sir, For my sake, as you love Statyra's being, That have no small concern in every danger, Threatens you. Tysam. 'Tis for thy sake I'de only live To crown this day with victory. Stat. 'Twere too much hazard for my Love. Tysam. Thou would'st not have me tamely gaze upon These Foes, and see thee pine for food? Or yield our selves to this imperious womans will, That may, perhaps, give Laws unwelcom to Our Loves, or take thy Beauty Captive for Her slavish Handmaid, whom but to circle thus, Is joy to me above the world and conquest. Stat. Admit I intercede for some fair peace, She is a Woman fam'd of Royal worth, And cannot be so cruel you express. Tysam. I know thou would'st not save my life by Womans mercy; besides, 'twould fright thy gentle Person, to behold thy Sex in Armour, And their breasts (while thine's Loves tender sphere) Inclos'd in Ribs of Steel, with one cut off, More furiously to wield their Martial Bows, With other Warlike horrors to afflict thy eyes. Stat. I fear no danger, so I serve but yours. Tysam. Admit I leave thee in my Tent, Attended with my best reserves of Force— Enter an Officer. What news? Officer. Your Army, Sir, is in outragious Mutiny For Bread. Alvan. I look'd for this. Tox. I fear as much the Consequence. Tysam. A sign they are sons of Cowardise That cannot take it from their Women-foes, Or make them knead us more. Officer. Your presence, Sir, may possibly allay Their fierce disorder. Tysam. We'le see who dares not fight, Or starve if we command it—or else We'le look e'm dead—your hand my dearest— This Mutiny we'le soon compose— [Exeunt. He leads Statyra to his Tent, &amp; exit with the rest. Enter Foscaris, Andrages, Eumenes and Draxanes, disarm'd and led Prisoners by three Amazon Ladies and other Women holding their spears at 'em. Fosc. Nay, good Lady Errants some mercy— Eum. As we are Souldiers— 1 Lady. 'Tis below our Amazon honour to afford it To such Knights of Chivalry as you are. Andr. As we are Gentlemen of good Nature to your Sex. Drax. Or as you have had kindness to man. Fosc. Or for Loves sake, of which I have store at your Service. 2 Lady. You are Spirits indeed of Cupid. Fosc. I am more than an ordinary man that way, And have Venus about me in abundance. Enter Daranthe. 1 Lady. Here comes our General. 2 Lady. We must not further act without her. Daran. You have done bravely, valiant Ladies; But where's their General Bassanes, who Forc'd your Squadrons? the Queen would have been glad To have led in triumph such a famous Chief. 1 Lady. He fought his way with many wounds unto the Volga; in whose rough streams we judge him drown'd. Daran. The Queen will give his loss some pity— For you Gentlemen, who have not been Injurious to our Sex in practising Your Scythian custom; the Queen proclaims She'l think of mercy; and for such pris'ners Who have Wives— Fosc. What will be our Fate? [Aside. Daran. It is her Royal Pleasure They be surrender'd to their wills— I must attend and give her notice Of your brave success. [Ex. Daranthe. Fosc. 'Twere best to be afore-hand with this Act Of Grace—I humbly lay hold on your Queens mercy. And. And I, Madam. Eum. And I. Drax. And I. Enter Melvissa and Clarina. 2 Lad. Have none of you Wives in being, Gentlemen? What say you, Sir? Fosc. Who I, Madam? I would not be so unfortunate For a world; and would you But espouse us to some of your Masculine Generation, we'd get your Queen such Heroines. Melv. Dost hear how abominably these Creatures [To Clar. aside. Of our Loves dissemble? Clar. They are oblig'd, it seems, to Change the complexion of their hearts. Melv. Let it be for life's sake, or love's, I'le have My due acknowledgments— Andr. Do not own us, dear Wives, [Aside. We beseech you. Melv. How, not own our just proprieties? Fosc. As you are Women, and have mercy, We are coming off, and on the fairest terms Heart can wish—withdraw awhile, And we'll be with you in a trice, and Handle things kindly, as men and wives should do. Melv. You shall excuse us, we'll reprieve you Our own way now. Clar. And for you, Sir, whose Conversion, I hop'd, my better stars had wrought— Fosc. Alas! my sweetest, I love thee with a flame As warm as thou can'st wish; but was forc'd to Dissemble for some motives of danger, Which I know thoul't pardon. 1 Lad. 'Tis fit we understand Your business, Ladies. 2 Lad. You are not Spies.— Melv. By your fair leaves, We come to claim a pair of Husbands By vertue of your Queens Proclamation. Clar. Of which, one of them had the good manners To part with his Wife, witness my self.— Omn. How's this? Andr. What will become of us? Fosc. Or me, that have provok'd Fate and Woman together? Andr. I am like to suffer under both, that must again Endure the insupportable, and endless Civil war of wedlock. Fosc. O, the star of Venus has had a strange influence In our Horoscopes; there's no resisting destiny, And she the Ascendant. Andr. Might I chuse, I had rather once more charge the Amazonian Battel, and all the Viragoes Of woman-kind together. [The Ladies compass them in holding their Spears at them.] Both Lad. Shall we kill e'm to revenge your injuries? Clar. By no means, we beg their lives. Melv. And having thus cull'd out our Cocks, I doubt not, but we shall manage the game Advantagiously enough. 1 Lad. You have e'm at your mercy. Clar. Thanks to your Queens. Melv. She has mine likewise in abundance Ladies— But for you Husbands.— Fosc. Nay, prethee we'll compose differences as you please. Drax. Now for our Capitulations. [Drax. and Eum. aside. Eum. If we do not make fair ones for our selves With such Victors as these, We may curse our Nativities. Fosc. What terms of composition, good sweet Wife? Thou know'st I love thee above imagination. Clar. Perhaps I may give you fair quarter. Fosc. Let it be but in thine, and I will dye Upon the spot, e're part with thee again; I am thine now without a charm. Clar. I promise nothing, though you see I have took Some pains for your safety. Andr. What says my Spouse? Melv. 'Tis odds she'll proceed as occasion serves. Andr. Be not proud of thy victory, thou know'st I have been a most submissive Husband. Melv. You'l soon know my conditions— Andr. And if they prove but gentle, I am conquer'd happily— 1 Lad. You will not leave our Camp presently? Clar. Not till the issue of this day be past. 2 Lad. If you doubt obedience from your Husbands, Command a Guard from us. Fosc. By no means Ladies, We acknowledge an absolute Conquest. Melv. Otherwise, you know our Commission. Clar. Your servant, fair noble Warriours. [Ex. Fosc. Clar. Andr. Melv.] 1 Lad. The Queen. Enter Mandana with Cydane and Renone. Mand. You have taken those fierce Militants That did attempt to force their safeties In despight of our bold powers. 2 Lad. We have, most Royal Madam, And in obedience to your great commands, Have gratify'd two Ladies of the Enemies part, By surrendring of their Husbands to their wills. Mand. I am glad my victory Does give my name a Trophy in the Obligation of my Sex; these men we war, Have too injurious treated—But where's The Prince Bassanes, their General? 1 Lad. He forc'd his bold escape, if not drown'd In passing of the Volga. Mand. We could have Been content to have seen him made our Captive. Renon. And must have added Glory to your Victory. Cyd. He much exprest himself your great Admirer. Enter Messenger. Mess. Glad tidings, mighty Queen, the King and all His power is now surrender'd to your General. Mand. I knew the streight we had reduc'd 'em to, Would soon compel 'em— And where's his fair Persian Mistress, Statyra? Mess. She is, besides some Pris'ners of note Guarded by the valiant Moor. Mand. This Crowns our Conquest. Enter Daranthe and Parisatis, with Tysamnes and Statyra, Araxis, Toxaris and Alvanes. Daranthe, I must praise thy valour— And all you my Women Souldiers For this glorious day. Daran. We are honour'd that our duties Serv'd your Greatness. Mand. But thine, my valiant Moor, that gives Such noble emulation in thy worthy Deeds To all, I know not how enough to magnifie, But soon will raise thy merit to some higher Trust, shall speak our great esteem, both of thy Valour and fidelity. Par. You oblige the humblest of your Servants. Mand. The King's a gracious person. [Looking on Tysam. Par. I fear too taking. Mand. Now, Mighty Sir? Tysam. Your pleasure, Madam? Mand. Is it not just, that I, who am the Mighty Warriour, in my Sexes Cause, Should frown thee dead? Tysam. You cannot look me out of life, nor would I turn my head aside, though every beam Of yours, were Darts of Basilisks, that dare Behold you thus— Mand. You are resolute I find; And would to Heaven your Queen were yet in being, That she might witness my concern in her Fair Cause; or from my power Ask thee her Sacrifice, Since thou hast been so much her Tyrant Lover. Tysam. My ingratitude to her great vertue I acknowledge; though I meet all your rage In pouring of revenge for her sake on my head; And since she is no more, for which, Heaven knows, How true I grieve, I would not live, but for This Ladies sake. [Looking on Statyra. Mand. Your new made Mistress— Tysam. And just possessor of my heart. Mand. She has strange fascination in her eyes, [Aside. For which— Stat. If you pronounce me guilty, speak my death; Nay, I'le intreat it at your hand as royal mercy, So you'l spare the King, For whose great safety, Had I many thousand lives, I'd humbly Lay them, as my offering, at your feet. Daran. This Lady has a noble soul. Par. Too much the Kings I fear. [Aside. Mand. I have cause enough to bid thee dye, But will not cloud the glory of this day With Womans death; and wer't not for a sacred Resolution of my soul, perhaps would grant Thy Loves enjoyment; but I have now decreed— Tysam. If death, I am ready to embrace it. Stat. Oh speak some milder Accent! what can Become a Womans soul, like yours, so much As gracious mercy? Mand. My resolution's fixt irrevocable, As when by Heaven's o're-ruling will, we guide Our Justice: for know Tysamnes, I have vow'd Thy life a glorious victim of my Conquest; Nor has it been unusual in the Wars we make, For such a day as this, to grace our Altars With the best of Captives, of which I judge None worthy, like thy self. Stat. You will not be divinely cruel? Mand. I'le hear no more— Zeriffa—take these pris'ners to thy custody; Thy Complexion is most fit to serve this Trust; And be sure you have a watchful eye Upon this Lady; the rest, perhaps, Shall find our mercy. Par. I joy this trust. Tysam. Grieve not, Statyra, since I dye thy Lover. Stat. And might I bleed upon the Altar with you, 'Twere then my Loves true Sacrifice. Mand. Thus far this day propitious does appear, But from the end great Acts their Crowns must wear. [Ex. Omnes.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">ACT V. SCENE I. Enter Mandana and Parisatis. Mand. How bears Tysamnes his restraint, and our Declar'd resolves? I know they needs Must bow his lofty heart. Par. As unconcern'd as Infants sleep, Or as the Man you'd chuse the object of Your mercy ought to be—nay more.— Mand. What means that more? Par. You are a Woman. Mand. But a Conquerour. Par. Had I like power. Mand. What then? Par. I'd bid him live at least. Mand. Thou would'st not have me love him? Par. No by my life— Though 'twere a gracious Act to Heaven, if you Vouchsafe him mercy; since he's oblig'd to fair Statyra's Love; you else will kill two hearts at once. Mand. Away with this fond pity; I have fix't my Justice. Par. Your pleasure Madam. Mand. Bring forth the King, I'le make him know it. Par. I am all confusion. [Ex. Parisatis.] Mand. This Moor is brave and loyal; my Mother once Had such a Lady near her person, she Would commend above what Faith can reach. Enter Parisatis with Tysamnes. Zeriffa! admit none to our presence. Par. I shall not—but by your leave Queen, Will here observe— [Par. Stands aside. Mand. I hear, Tysamnes, You contemn the vow I've made, Nor does my eye Discern other then pleasing calms upon The brow you seem to wear. Tysam. Such as become a King, And every vulgar man, when made a Sacrifice To womans passion— Mand. Take heed, Sir, how You entertain a Summer in your hopes, Or slight the Justice I decree. Tysam. What mean you, Madam? Alas! I look'd to meet the Miter'd Priest, The Altar fixt, where I should bleed your Victim, And if you superscribe it With my crimes of Love, Which caus'd at once my Parisatis death, And fair Statyra's tears, I'le call it justice, And due expiation of my sins to Heaven. Mand. I'le soon my self convey you to the Altar I intend— Par. What means the Queen? [Aside. Mand. Or say I bid thee live? Tysam. 'Twere then a mercy greater then I crave, Or merit. Mand. I'd have thee judge it more. Par. 'Tis love most certain. [Aside. Mand. What think you of this look? [She smiles. Tysam. 'Tis somewhat gentler then I did expect. Mand. And what of this? [Smiles again. Tysam. It seems more kind then common smile. Mand. Is it not welcom to thy heart? Tysam. 'Twere too much to bestow such beams on me, And gives me greater wonder, then should Lights Orb Contract its glory to the Artick Pole, To quicken there some frozen spot of earth. Mand. He does perceive—thy pardon now is written In my heart—Zeriffa— Enter Parisatis. See thou respect Tysamnes Above observance of a Pris'ner; I have Some motives of a near concern require it. [Ex. Mandana. Par. Is this your vow, oh Parisatis? Didst thou walk as undiscern'd as Ghosts [Aside. That cloath themselves in bodies of the Air; This must affright thee more, then timorous hearts Scar'd with such pale horrors— Admit, Sir, I congratulate this Grace. Tysam. 'Twas unexpected— And I with glader eyes could have beheld Thee made my deaths black Hand-maid. Par. You do not slight the Queen, that with her Gracious beams of mercy quickens you to live? Nay more, if I discern that have some trust From her fair thoughts, is giving of her self A conquest to your Love—methinks This should awake your apprehension, Tysam. It does! but find my self Unshaken to Statyra, and could have wish'd Your Queens more rigid vow were unrepeal'd, That I might bleed her Sacrifice. Par. She is your Crime, And therefore does deserve to be your Fate, Or else embrace the same with her. Tysam. Though thy dark visage is most fit to be The messenger of death and all it's horrors, I may enquire what cause incites thee To appear thus cruel. Par. It breaks like clearest justice From my Soul, that am oblig'd to be Your Queens Revenger— Tysam. Thou art not sent from t'other world To be my Executioner, where she's adorn'd With Crowns and smiles of Angels, still interceding My forgiveness. Par. I have griev'd his Soul too much, [Aside. Pardon me, Sir, I was too bold to urge Your penitence. Tysam. It proves thee worthy. Par. One word and I have done; were your Queen living? Nay more, Sir, wer't soon as manifest, she Hazarded her life, repriev'd on purpose For your safety, would you receive her To your embrace and love? Tysam. She is too dear to Heaven To be given thence; and Stars which frown'd upon That fatal Act, already have enroll'd her In their first of bright Societies— But this is all thy dream. Par. Believe it such— Yet so far I dare represent her self, As to assure you, for her sake, I'le dye To purchase your just freedom— Let this tear confirm you, as 'twere shed from her. Enter Statyra. Statyra Sir. [Ex. Parisatis. Tysam. The carriage of this Moor Is honours riddle to my thoughts— Oh my Statyra! I have yet a hope of thy Enjoyment. Stat. Does the Queen Incline to mercy? Tysam. She has receded from her vow. Stat. That's happy— And more cruel in decree, seeks To divide my soul from thine— Thou understand'st me? Stat. I do too sadly— Tysam. But this Moor, employ'd by Heaven To be a Guardian of our Loves, or as The night, or Hymen gave her this complexion To be a sober guide unto his rights, Devotes herself to serve our safeties. Stat. This means of happiness was above my hope, While through each vein of mine, my blood had ebbings From my heart, in apprehension of your dangers; Nor did I view her with less horror, Conceiving her the Queens most cruel instrument. Tysam. I thought her so, but she has given me such Assurance of her Faith and Love, that had Thy beauteous figure took a veil like her, Or were my Parisatis Represented such, I would not have expected A more strict concern for me. Stat. It seems too much To credit from a stranger, or else 'tis but Loves kinder Labyrinth. Enter Parisatis. Tysam. She's here—salute her With thy kindest beams, she does deserve Our near regards. Stat. Madam, the King has given me such a character Of your worth, as I must beg to joyn Acknowledgments with his. Par. I'le venture all that's dear to serve him, And your vertue; but this is not a time For Words: Things call to action— Please you withdraw. [Ex. Tysam. Stat. Enter Draxanes. Draxanes come? Drax. I hope most happily. Par. And hast thou found him? Drax. Yes, Madam, and have brought him. Par. This place is safe from ears—wait him to me. [Ex. Drax. If fortune be not peevish now, the Scene I have laid shall Crown my Acts. Enter Bassanes disguis'd. I am wondrous glad to see thee live. Bass. And I like to some man that's Struck with Extasies of joy, Could even resign my soul, as thus I kiss the ground I tread, in adoration Of your being here, when fear'd beyond a doubt You had snatch'd your self away, to make its Bosom in your grave more sacred. Par. Draxanes told thee all? Bass. He did Madam, As I was levying of Recruits to free the King From this restraint he suffers here. Par. Then we'll spare further circumstance, And only know I have prepar'd to do him Signal service; for which end, I took this Cloud, Either to dye unknown, or live a means Of his lov'd preservation. Bass. This deed must ravish Men and Angels To express; who must admire at once Your most heroick constancy and vertue. Par. Enough Bassanes, and pardon me, that I Sent my summons to joyn thee as companion In the dangers I embrace. Bass. You shall command My utmost peril, though every man I meet Could look me into Atoms. Par. And know to my More cruel Fate, the King not only has A Mistress in Statyra, but the Queen Mandana, his fair Conquerour, has vow'd Him for her own enjoyment. Bass. What can be thought on To resist this high injustice? Par. I have resolv'd upon the means, in which I'le use thy Conduct, not more approv'd to act, Then sage in resolution; nor do I doubt The instruments we'll use, are less then cordial, To embrace the end we shall propose, which must Be swift in execution. Bass. I would not waste a minute e're I act to serve it. Par. The Guards are here at my devotion, besides A considerable number of our bravest Officers, By the Queen Mandana, set at liberty. Bass. They may be serviceable to your design. Par. The honour of their King obliges it— Within we'll debate more at large particulars. [Exeunt. Enter Toxaris, Alvanes, Araxis. Tox. Well Gallants, we are all Freemen now. Alv. 'Tis a seasonable mercy to us Courtiers, Not us'd to this kind of belly duty; We otherwise must have been living Anatomies By this time. Arax. And so perhaps Metamorphiz'd Into starv'd Ghosts, to walk with hideous Lamentations these Fields of Victory. Tox. I do not think All th'Infernal Region can fright these Victrices, should they appear in Arms, There's not an Image of Mars, but does raise Their fury above Miracle. Alv. And yet For all their being thus couragious and hardy (Which must be acknowledg'd more then wonder In their soft kind) they are refin'd as our Ladies Of the best converse; and as modishly witty As any she Platonick living— Arax. If Venus make no Captives in this shape Of Mars, may her Son ne're more wear Quiver. Enter Eumenes. Eum. Never men enfranchis'd on such terms As we are, for which this great and fair Warriour deserves a Jubilee. Tox. She's highly gracious. Eum. And like the Sun diffusive in her beams; I have been so Caress'd by our fair Conquerours, Under several Titles and Commands, as if they'd Invite us shortly to match by Regiments, And so at last joyn Armies! what a day Of Hymen would that be? Alv. Could but our King be freed On royal terms, 'twould adde yet Glory to this Queens great Acts. Eum. Some did interpret Favourably, when she late vow'd him To a sad destiny. Arax. As how? Eum. As men should construe in like case, a Womans vow. Tox. I am yet to learn, there's nothing but Riddle in the whole Sex. Eum. 'Tis said that Love's the Oedipus, And has resolv'd it, to whose soft Altars She has given the King some beams of invitation. Alv. But that may adde unto his greater peril, Being so much devoted to Statyra, That his heart is Ice to other flame. Arax. Heaven guide things for the best! Tox. Where did you leave Draxanes? He shares of this Grace I hope? Eum. Yes, and is advanc'd to no small favour.— Tox. Not with the Queen? Eum. No, but what's a step to't, He is deep in the Moors; I left him in close Conference with her. Alv. That Moor carries the stream indeed of Grace: Our King committed to her trust with his beauteous Mistriss. Arax. But what to judge her. Eum. She bears a Soul of brightest temperament; As if that providence had found a place Elsewhere for her Nativity; or as she wore An Ethiops Cloudy Veil, from Art, not Nature. Enter Foscaris leading Clarina, and Andrages, Melvissa. Tox. Foscaris and Andrages come off thus With their Wives! this must conclude A strange day of Womans Victory. Fosc. I have paid my Arrears Of Love, I hope to purpose; we are Reconcil'd, and have embrac'd, and so forth Gentlemen. Clar. You have so. Fosc. And can bill like Doves now. Clar. Not too much, I beseech you, lest you fall Into a surfeit of Love again; too much Of the honey of Wedlock is not good For your palate. Eum. We joy your Loves. Fosc. If any be unkind henceforth to his Spouse, May he suffer my penance; there's some Mystery behind, which you shall all know At leisure: in the Interim, I acknowledge My happiness, from you Lady. Melv. I am glad it was in my power to serve Your felicity in Clarina's. Andr. And I rejoyce a kind Wife too, Gentlemen. Melv. But take heed you don't presume; You know my power when I please. Tox. These Women Conquerours are strangely noble. Clar. We own our Husbands from their mercy. Andr. And we our freedoms. Fosc. Souldiers in every vein Gentlemen, And can drink a smart health or two as they Discourse of Arms—and would they yield Reasonable obedience to mankind, I'd wish You all to match amongst them, they'd spirit Flesh and blood indeed. Alv. I long to be doing. Arax. And I as much. Tox. Could but the King come off nobly. Fosc. He must, if the Queen do not once more Change her vow. Alv. No news yet of the General Bassanes? Eum. He vanish'd in a storm of darts! but what His fate is Heaven knows. Enter Draxanes. Drax. A word in private. [Whispers to Eumenes who deliver it to one another. Eum. Is't possible?— Drax. Rely your faiths on mine. Tox. We are confirm'd. Melv. You may admit us to Council, Wives should partake their Husbands secrets. Andr. You shall, you shall. Fosc. And know we have wondrous things in hand. Clar. If honourable, I'le venture all that's dear To serve it. Melv. And I as far engage. Fosc. Such as must fill your bosoms full of joy— Within more of particulars. [Ex. Omnes. Enter Mandana, Daranthe, Cydane, Renone, and others attending. Mand. We have given our mercy to the King. Daran. 'Twas gracious like your self.— Mand. Nor will I blush to own His Graces merit an esteem from us. Cyd. The Queen is surely smitten with her great Captive? Renon. Beyond a doubt. Mand. Bring forth the King Cydane. [Ex. Cydane. We'll treat him nobler yet, and make him joy This day of Womens conquest. Enter Cydane. Cyd. Madam! the King's withdrawn. Mand. How? Cyd. Or else escap'd. Mand. Blister'd be thy tongue That brings such tidings to my heart— Where is the Moor? Cyd. Not to be found. Enter Statyra. Mand. Her black Soul shall take a gloomy flight To the other world for this. Stat. I answer for her trust. Mand. Thy life shall bear hers company. Stat. I am glad To yield it up a Victim to your wrath, Since that must raise a Trophy to my Love; Where every Virgin of a faith like mine, Will drop a tear to give my memory A name, shall blast the glory of your Conquest. Mand. Away with this fond woman; it is an Ague To my blood to hear her reason thus. [As they offer to carry her off. Enter Bassanes disguis'd, with Foscaris, Andrages, Drax. Eum. Tox. Alv. Arax. and others arm'd. Bass. Hold and hear me first. Mand. How! men in Arms before our presence? Have we no Guard there?— Bass. None but what I have plac'd; And were your Women chang'd to Sons of Mars, Nay, Cadmus fiercer issue joyn'd to them, When ripen'd first to horror of mankind, As the earth trembling did contain their roots; This Sword of mine should mow 'em down To smooth the path I lead. Mand. A combination of these humane things So late our Arms reduc'd— Methinks they should convert to nothing From a look of mine; or I lose Majesty. Daran. This surprisal was beyond the reach of thought. Renon. 'Tis most ignoble. Mand. And thou that seem'st an object Fit to guide such base ingratitude, What shall I call thee? Traytor? Bass. A name that had an honour for your Soul, That fill'd no less the world with wonders; And lest your Womens frailty should stain The brightness of your noble Deeds, I thought it justice to resist your will, Though I met Seas of danger in the act. Mand. Bold and Impudent! Bass. I must be plainer, Do you not love the King? Mand. Suppose it granted— Bass. Heaven does not— And think not, Madam, that my blood, Though it bears fire of honour in each vein, But 'tis as cold to treachery; nor does the Cause That I maintain, less then command, without An arm of force— This Lady in her own fair right, methinks, [To Statyra. Should move you. Stat. May Heaven reward thy vertue! Mand. She is the Kings belov'd; but I have won Him mine by Arms. Bass. And therefore nobler conquest To subdue your self: The Bays you wear In triumph, else must wither on your brow, Where Majesty and Beauties lustre twine To make one Excellence. Stat. What providence has Blest me with this Advocate? Renon. I have seen a face resembles that. [Pulls off his Beard and Patches. Daran. The Queen a little alters. Mand. It must be he. Bass. Behold then, Royal Madam, this face Made but my own dark copy by disguise, Thus clear'd to own it's just original. Mand. Bassanes living? Bass. In which I wear A mirror of my heart, that does without A flattery express a Soul that highly Honours yours, though it has seem'd divested Of those Charms in making this reflection On your justice, which here is one most [To Parisatis. Powerful to incline. Enter Parisatis attended by Clarina and Melvissa. Mand. What is this Lady? Cyd. The Queen Parisatis, Madam. Mand. It cannot be; A meer imposture to abuse me. Renon. We must avow 'tis she. Mand. I am all wonder. Stat. And I no less rejoyce to see you live; I hope you'l pardon, that I claim'd an interest In your Kings affection, when 'twas assur'd You had no Being in the world. Par. And I more humbly begone here; Nor shall it e're be told that Parisatis Walk'd in that dark Cloud (though it vail'd her Actings for preservation of the life and love Of her Tysamnes) to live, your trust abus'd, Without a pardon from your lips. Daran. This Woman's brave. Par. Nor shall you loose, besides, One fruit of victory. Mand. You were the Moor then? Par. The same, most Royal Madam— And if you are my Subjects, prostrate Your selves and swords, with me, at these Majestick feet. [Kneels. Mand. This is a Conquest happier then all; Nor shall e're Woman boast she had the better Of Mandana's honour—Madam, you have [To Parisatis. Forgiveness—take up your weapons worthy Souldiers. Bass. You are highly gracious. Mand. Where is the King? Par. 'Twas but given out he had escap'd. Mand. Bassanes, you'l attend him to us. Enter Tysamnes whispering Bassanes, Foscaris, Andr. Tox. Alv. Arax. Drax. Eumenes. Tysam. Do I then live to be thus happy in Your grace and pardon? Mand. Your Queen has conquer'd me Tysamnes, After the power of your Arms was made My valour's glory; nor did the darts of Love, Which I confess, made some impression here, [Pointing to her breast. Leave wounds but to be heal'd more happily— I vow'd you, Sir, to love. Par. No change I hope. [Aside. Mand. And thus will make your offering here; She is a Jewel of a Crown indeed. [Presents him to the Queen. Tysam. I take her on my knees— She is too great a blessing, thus restor'd [Kneels. To my embrace, to be with less devotion own'd From Heaven, imploring (as I kneel) thy pardon. Par. You have it Sir, though not a gift, where you Command a duty; which when most passive In a Wife, does but refine the gold of Vertue. Tysam. Why didst thou take this Cloud? Par. To dye unknown, or serve your safety. Daran. A most heroick constancy. Tysam. Thy vertue's richer Then the world's vast globe, were it Converted to one purest Diamond. Mand. And does as far exceed what story can relate. Tysam. But I have yet a load of mercy here To beg, my crime of Love to thee Statyra, Which else must cloud this day of comforts, And bring eternal night upon my soul. Stat. Though I have lost an expectation of My greatest bliss in your enjoyment, That in warm sighs might soon dissolve A Virgins heart like mine, yet I can feel No want of happiness, since I behold Your Souls, that have already mingl'd joys, Meet thus, and kiss each other. Tysam. Heaven must reward thy goodness. Par. And my for ever obligation. Mand. This days example gives to Love Such brave repute, that I who both have fought, And men commanded, could even yield To hold my Scepter from obedience. Tysam. Here is a Prince within your eye (I hope More near your heart) that might deserve To rule a Throne like yours. Mand. I know him noble. Bass. And one, most Royal Madam, that owns A soul, you have an interest to command E're since I first beheld the glory of your charms: Pardon me, I now avow it, that rather To express my wonder of your vertue, Should by an humble distance still admire. Mand. 'Tis in my power to bring you nearer: Bassanes is a Prince may well become An Empress of the world's great choice; and were Mandana such, she would not think her Love Or Greatness stoop'd to match with thine. Bass. You make me more then happy. Mand. And I that honour Arms, and thy fam'd Deeds In War, will call it noblest triumph To yield thy Love a victory o're mine. Bass. This bounty stream's so powerful on my heart, That I may fear it's guide, in such a Sea Of joys you bring. Mand. I am yours for ever, dear Bassanes. Drax. This day surpasses wonder. Fosc. I knew it must conclude with some Extraordinary Love-miracle besides my own. [Aside. Mand. Daranthe! we must now no more make war, I have match'd a Souldier. Bass. One that will live and dye your just admirer. Mand. And Women, here divest Your selves of Arms with me. [They take off their Arms. Dar., Ren., Cyd. We all obey your Majesty. Mand. And let your conquests henceforth be to love, And give Men sole supremacy— I hope our Kingdoms shall unite in making [To Tysamnes. Laws may fit each Sexes duty. Tysam. I am oblig'd for Parisatis sake To make Decrees, no arbitrary will Of man shall henceforth e're reject a Wife. Mand. Our Crowns will have a blessed union then— What pattern shall we take? Tysam. Such as the world With best consent does practise. Bass. Or what's most Laudable, the form of happy England. Mand. It has been most approv'd. Par. Now Ladies, you are all well pleas'd to see This peace that smiles upon your Loves, and gives Both Sexes with our Crowns, such happiness. Clar. A welcom joy. Melv. We now can call our Husbands Ours by lawful duty. Andr. I am glad to hear that word. Fosc. And I to be secur'd thus; I was in no small Apprehension, this female victory Might have imporw'd them to part with us; What a mockery of Love's Magick had I been then? Mand. My Warriours, you will all take Husbands now? Here are men fit to match your spirits. Daran. Your great example must invite it. Tysam. What shall this day do for thee fair Statyra? The bounty of thy soul deserves a recompence Above what tongue can speak, that spreads A volume of thy goodness, fit only For the eye of Heaven to read. Stat. And thither I'le devote my love, Though while I live, no day shall pass without A contemplation of your happiness. Mand. You will not soon depart? Par. For Parisatis sake you must not. Stat. 'Tis my ambition first to fill an humble place In your bright train of triumphs. Tysam. For which thou dost deserve a Chariot Of Celestial substance, Mov'd by the wings of Seraphims; And every Virgin of most noble soul, Attending thee with Songs of Raptures; The Muses (as fair Hand-maids to thy vertue) Their best of Poets should inspire. Stat. You too much honour my small merits. Bass. This day does claim a glory from your worth, And next my just devotion here—my heart [To Mandana. Shall keep an Altar sacred to Parisatis Constant love and praise, with yours. Stat. And mine no less Shall speak Bassane's fame. Par. I'le be your Rival Madam, there— That am oblig'd unto this noble Prince [To Bassanes. By highest gratitude. Tysam. And I above expression thine. [To Bassanes. Mand. Tysamnes with your Queen must lead The way unto our joys— And Women hence from us this pattern take, Love, and obedience, your best conquests make. Ex. Omnes.</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Epilogue Spoken by the Queen of Amazon We Amazons did here unconquer'd yield, And nobly too, when Love had gain'd the Field, Against whose Darts, what Woman wears a shield? This War our Poet taught us by his Pen, But 'twas to be such Conqueresses then, As you ought, Ladies, when you Captive Men. Nor will we doubt if you protect our fear, Though 'gainst our Conquest Criticks shall make War, Such Foes no Amazons e're met with here. Besides the stratagems you Gallants know, Our Plays defeat and worse our Women too, A Miss that's fine we cannot keep for you. Then Gentlemen, since Love is much your way, Be well advis'd how y'are unkind to day, Lest we defie all such who damn our Play. Our Poet needs not apprehend what right You Wits will do him, or your factions spite, That's their concern who do for Money write. But with the Actors you may deal far worse, For if you damn this Play, 'tis half their Curse, Considering how its charge has plagu'd their Purse. Which if you do, I'le tell you what they say, They'l venture no more cost upon a Play, You shall have Farce good store a cheaper way. FINIS.</field>
   </doc>
</add>