<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Kegan Paul, Trench, Trübner &amp; Co.</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Kegan Paul, Trench, Trübner &amp; Co.</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">kegan paul trench trbner  co</field>
      <field name="author_text">Kegan Paul, Trench, Trübner &amp; Co.</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">19th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1890's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V1.1038.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1897</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:459667</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Una Pagina Pastorum</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 19th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Una Pagina Pastorum</field>
      <field name="title_facet">una pagina pastorum</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">una pagina pastorum</field>
      <field name="title_text">Una Pagina Pastorum</field>
      <field name="year_display">1897</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1897</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1897</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459667&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459667&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Una Pagina Pastorum&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;una pagina pastorum&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1897&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1897&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Una Pagina Pastorum&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;London&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Kegan Paul, Trench, Trübner &amp;amp; Co.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1897&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3873715-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv11038&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 19th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;19th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Una Pagina Pastorum&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 47 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Medieval verse drama.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries, introductory and editorial matter including introduction and notes omitted.&lt;lb/&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;lb/&gt;Dedication included with The Creation&lt;lb/&gt;Source texts incomplete&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Copyright (c) 1995 Boydell &amp;amp; Brewer Ltd. This text may not be reproduced, except for fair dealing purposes, without the express permission of Chadwyck-Healey and the copyright holder.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Una pagina pastorum.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: English mystery and miracle plays.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1450 ?</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 1390–1410 ?&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">[Una Pagina Pastorum] Incipit Pagina pastorum. Square brackets represent sections of text unclear or absent in the original and supplied by the current editor</field>
      <field name="fulltext">[Dramatis Personae. Primus Pastor. Secundus Pastor. Tercius Pastor. Iak Garcio. Angelus. Ihesus. Maria.]</field>
      <field name="fulltext">(1) Primus Pastor. Lord, what thay ar weyll that hens ar past! ffor thay noght feyll theym to downe cast. here is mekyll vnceyll and long has it last, Now in hart, now in heyll now in weytt, now in blast, Now in care, Now in comforth agane, Now is fayre, now is rane, Now in hart full fane, And after full sare. (2) Thus this Warld, as I say farys on ylk syde, ffor after oure play com sorows vnryde; ffor he that most may When he syttys in pryde, When it comys on assay is kesten downe wyde, This is seyn; When ryches is he, Then comys pouerte, hors-man Iak cope Walkys then, I weyn. (3) I thank it god hark ye what I mene, ffor euen or for od I haue mekyll tene; As heuy as a sod I grete with myn eene, When I nap on my cod for care that has bene, And sorow. All my shepe ar gone, I am not left oone, The rott has theym slone; Now beg I and borow. (4) My handys may I wryng and mowrnyng make, Bot if good will spryng the countre forsake; ffermes thyk ar comyng my purs is bot wake, I haue nerehand nothyng to pay nor to take; I may syng With purs penneles, That makys this heuynes, Wo is me this dystres! And has no helpyng. (5) Thus sett I my mynde truly to neuen, By my wytt to fynde to cast the warld in seuen; My shepe haue I tynde by the moren full euen; Now if hap will grynde god from his heuen Send grace. To the fare will I me, To by shepe, perde, And yit may I multyple, ffor all this hard case. (6) Secundus pastor. Benste, benste be vs emang, And saue all that I se here in this thrang, he saue you and me ouertwhart and endlang, That hang on a tre I say you no wrang; Cryst saue vs ffrom all myschefys, ffrom robers and thefys, ffrom those mens grefys, That oft ar agans vs. (7) Both bosters and bragers god kepe vs fro, That with thare long dagers dos mekyll wo; ffrom all byll hagers with colknyfys that go; Sich wryers and wragers gose to and fro ffor to crak. Who so says hym agane, were better be slane; Both ploghe and wane Amendys will not make. (8) he will make it as prowde a lord as he were, With a hede lyke a clowde ffelterd his here; he spekys on lowde with a grym bere, I wold not haue trowde so galy in gere As he glydys. I wote not the better, Nor wheder is gretter, The lad or the master, So stowtly he strydys. (9) If he hask me oght that he wold to his pay, fful dere bese it boght if I say nay; Bot god that all wroght to the now I say, help that thay were broght to a better way ffor thare sawlys; And send theym good mendyng With a short endyng, And with the to be lendyng When that thou callys. (10) how, gyb, goode morne wheder goys thou? Thou goys ouer the corne gyb, I say, how! primus pastor. Who is that? John horne I make god a vowe! I say not in skorne thom, how farys thou? Secundus pastor. hay, ha! Ar ye in this towne? primus pastor. yey, by my crowne. ijus pastor. I thoght by youre gowne This was youre aray. (11) primus pastor. I am euer elyke wote I neuer what it gars, Is none in this ryke a shepard farys wars. ijus pastor. poore men ar in the dyke and oft tyme mars, The warld is slyke also helpars Is none here. primus pastor. It is sayde full ryfe, “a man may not wyfe And also thryfe, And all in a yere.” (12) ijus pastor. ffyrst must vs crepe and sythen go. primus pastor. I go to by shepe. Secundus [pastor]. nay, not so; What, dreme ye or slepe? where shuld thay go? here shall thou none kepe. primus pastor. A, good sir, ho! Who am I? I wyll pasture my fe where so euer lykys me, here shall thou theym se. ijus pastor. Not so hardy! (13) Not oone shepe tayll shall thou bryng hedyr. primus pastor. I shall bryng, no fayll A hundreth togedyr. ijus pastor. What, art thou in ayll longys thou oght whedir? primus pastor. Thay shall go, saunce fayll go now, bell weder! ijus pastor. I say, tyr! primus pastor. I say, tyr, now agane! I say skyp ouer the plane. ijus pastor. wold thou neuer so fane, Tup, I say, whyr! (14) primus pastor. What, wyll thou not yit I say, let the shepe go? Whop! Secundus pastor. abyde yit. primus pastor. Will thou bot so? knafe, hens I byd flytt as good that thou do, Or I shall the hytt on thi pate, lo, shall thou reyll; I say, gyf the shepe space. ijus pastor. Syr, a letter of youre grace, here comys slaw-pase ffro the myln whele. (15) Tercius pastor. What a do, what a do is this you betweyn? A good day, thou, and thou. primus pastor. hark what I meyn You to say: I was bowne to by store, drofe my shepe me before, he says not oone hore shall pas by this way; (16) Bot and he were wood this way shall thay go. iijus pastor. yey, bot tell me, good where ar youre shepe, lo? ijus pastor. Now, sir, by my hode yit se I no mo, Not syn I here stode. iijus pastor. god gyf you wo and sorow! ye fysh before the nett, And stryfe on this bett, sich folys neuer I mett Evyn or at morow. (17) It is wonder to wyt where wytt shuld be fownde; here ar old knafys yit standys on this grownde, these wold by thare wytt make a shyp be drownde; he were well qwytt had sold for a pownde sich two. thay fyght and thay flyte ffor that at comys not tyte; It is far to byd hyte To an eg or it go. (18) Tytter want ye sowll then sorow I pray; Ye brayde of mowll that went by the way— Many shepe can she poll bot oone had she ay— Bot she happynyd full fowll hyr pycher, I say, Was broken; “ho, god,” she sayde, bot oone shepe yit she hade, The mylk pycher was layde, The skarthis was the tokyn. (19) Bot syn ye ar bare of wysdom to knawe, Take hede how I fare and lere at my lawe; ye nede not to care if ye folow my sawe; hold ye my mare this sek thou thrawe On my bak, Whylst I, with my hand, lawse the sek band; Com nar and by stand Both gyg and Iak; (20) Is not all shakyn owte and no meyll is therin? primus pastor. yey, that is no dowte. Tercius pastor. so is youre wyttys thyn. And ye look well abowte nawther more nor myn, So gose youre wyttys owte evyn as It com In: Geder vp And seke it agane. ijus pastor. May we not be fane! he has told vs full plane Wysdom to sup. (21) Iak garcio. Now god gyf you care foles all sam; Sagh I neuer none so fare bot the foles of gotham. Wo is hir that yow bare youre syre and youre dam, had she broght furth an hare a shepe, or a lam, had bene well. Of all the foles I can tell, ffrom heuen vnto hell, ye thre bere the bell; God gyf you vnceyll. (22) primus pastor. how pastures oure fee say me, good pen. Garcio. Thay ar gryssed to the kne. ijus pastor. fare fall the! Garcio. Amen! If ye will ye may se youre bestes ye ken. primus pastor. Sytt we downe all thre and drynk shall we then. iijus pastor. yey, torde! I am leuer ete; what is drynk withoute mete? Gett mete, gett, And sett vs a borde, (23) Then may we go dyne oure bellys to fyll. ijus pastor. Abyde vnto syne. iijus pastor. be god, sir, I nyll! I am worthy the wyne me thynk it good skyll; My seruyse I tyne I fare full yll, At youre mangere. primus pastor. Trus! go we to mete, It is best that we trete, I lyst not to plete To stand in thi dangere; (24) Thou has euer bene curst syn we met togeder. iijus pastor. Now in fayth, if I durst ye ar euen my broder. ijus pastor. Syrs, let vs cryb furst for oone thyng or oder, That thise wordis be purst and let vs go foder Oure mompyns; lay furth of oure store, lo, here! browne of a bore. primus pastor. Set mustard afore, oure mete now begyns; (25) here a foote of a cowe well sawsed, I wene, The pestell of a sowe that powderd has bene, Two blodyngis, I trow A leueryng betwene; Do gladly, syrs, now my breder bedene, With more. Both befe, and moton Of an ewe that was roton, Good mete for a gloton; Ete of this store. (26) ijus pastor. I haue here in my mayll sothen and rost, Euen of an ox tayll that wold not be lost; ha, ha, goderhayll! I let for no cost, A good py or we fayll this is good for the frost In a mornyng; And two swyne gronys, All a hare bot the lonys, we myster no sponys here, at oure mangyng. (27) iijus pastor. here is to recorde the leg of a goys, with chekyns endorde pork, partryk, to roys; A tart for a lorde how thynk ye this doys? A calf lyuer skorde with the veryose; Good sawse, This is a restorete To make a good appete. primus pastor. yee speke all by clerge[te], I here by your clause; (28) Cowth ye by youre gramery reche vs a drynk, I shuld be more mery ye wote What I thynk. ijus pastor. haue good ayll of hely bewar now, I wynk, ffor and thou drynk drely in thy poll wyll it synk. primus pastor. A, so; This is boyte of oure bayll, good holsom ayll. iijus pastor. ye hold long the skayll, Now lett me go to. (29) Secundus pastor. I shrew those lyppys bot thou leyff me som parte. primus pastor. be god, he bot syppys begylde thou art; Behold how he kyppys. Secundus pastor. I shrew you so smart, And me on my hyppys bot if I gart Abate. Be thou wyne, be thou ayll, bot if my brethe fayll, I shall sett the on sayll; God send the good gayte. (30) Tercius pastor. Be my dam saull, alyce It was sadly dronken. primus pastor. Now, as euer haue I blys to the bothom it is sonken. ijus pastor. yit a botell here is. Tercius pastor. that is well spoken! By my thryft we must kys. Secundus pastor. that had I forgoten. Bot hark! Who so can best syng Shall haue the begynnyng. primus pastor. Now prays at the partyng I shall sett you on warke; (31) We haue done oure parte and songyn right weyll, I drynk for my parte. ijus pastor. Abyde, lett cop reyll. primus pastor. Godys forbot, thou spart and thou drynk euery deyll. iijus pastor. Thou has dronken a quart therfor choke the the deyll. primus pastor. Thou rafys; And it were for a sogh Ther is drynk enogh. iijus pastor. I shrew the handys it drogh! ye be both knafys. (32) primus pastor. Nay! we knaues all thus thynk me best, so, sir, shuld ye call. ijus pastor. furth let it rest; we will not brall. primus pastor. then wold I we fest, This mete Who shall into panyere kest. iijus pastor. syrs, herys; ffor oure saules lett vs do Poore men gyf it to. primus pastor. Geder vp, lo, lo! ye hungre begers ffrerys! (33) ijus pastor. It draes nere nyght trus, go we to rest; I am euen redy dyght I thynk it the best. iijus pastor. ffor ferde we be fryght a crosse lett vs kest, Cryst crosse, benedyght eest and west, ffor drede. Ihesus. onazorus, Crucyefixus, Morcus, andreus, God be oure spede! (34) [They sleep.] Angelus. herkyn, hyrdes, awake! gyf louyng ye shall, he is borne for [y]oure sake lorde perpetuall; he is comen to take and rawnson you all, youre sorowe to slake kyng emperiall, he behestys; That chyld is borne At bethelem this morne, ye shall fynde hym beforne Betwix two bestys. (35) Primus Pastor. A, godys dere dominus! What was that sang? It was wonder curiose with small noytys emang; I pray to god saue vs now in this thrang; I am ferd, by ihesus somwhat be wrang; Me thoght, Oone scremyd on lowde; I suppose it was a clowde, In myn erys it sowde, By hym that me boght! (36) Secundus pastor. Nay, that may not be I say you certan, ffor he spake to vs thre as he had bene a man; When he lemyd on this lee my hart shakyd than, An angell was he tell you I can, No dowte. he spake of a barne, We must seke hym, I you warne, That betokyns yond starne, That standys yonder owte. (37) Tercius pastor. It was meruell to se so bright as it shone, I wold haue trowyd, veraly it had bene thoner flone, Bot I sagh with myn ee as I lenyd to this stone; It was a mery gle sich hard I neuer none, I recorde. As he sayde in a skreme, Or els that I dreme, we shuld go to bedleme, To wyrship that lorde. (38) primus pastor. That same childe is he that prophetys of told, Shuld make them fre that adam had sold. ijus pastor. Take tent vnto me this is inrold, By the wordys of Isae a prynce most bold shall he be, And kyng with crowne, Sett on dauid trone, Sich was neuer none, Seyn with oure ee. (39) iijus pastor. Also Isay says oure faders vs told That a vyrgyn shuld pas of Iesse, that wold Bryng furth, by grace a floure so bold; That vyrgyn now has these wordys vphold As ye se; Trust it now we may, he is borne this day, Exiet virga De radice iesse. (40) primus pastor. Of hym spake more Sybyll as I weyn, And nabugodhonosor from oure faythe alyene, In the fornace where thay wore thre childre sene, The fourt stode before godys son lyke to bene. ijus pastor. That fygure Was gyffen by reualacyon That god wold haue a son; This is a good lesson, Vs to consydure. (41) Tercius pastor. Of hym spake Ieromy and moyses also, Where he sagh hym by a bushe burnand, lo! when he cam to aspy if it were so, Vnburnyd was it truly at commyng therto, A wonder. primus pastor. That was for to se hir holy vyrgynyte, That she vnfylyd shuld be, Thus can I ponder, (42) And shuld haue a chyld sich was neuer sene. ijus pastor. pese, man, thou art begyld thou shall se hym with eene, Of a madyn so myld greatt meruell I mene; yee, and she vnfyld a virgyn clene, So soyne. primus pastor. Nothyng is inpossybyll sothly, that god wyll; It shalbe stabyll That god wyll haue done. (43) ijus pastor. Abacuc and ely prophesyde so, Elezabeth and zachare and many other mo, And dauid as veraly is witnes therto, Iohn Baptyste sewrly and daniel also. iijus pastor. So sayng, he is godys son alon, without hym shalbe none, his sete and his trone Shall euer be lastyng; (44) primus pastor. Virgill in his poetre sayde in his verse, Even thus by gramere as I shall reherse; “Iam noua progenies celo demittitur alto, Iam rediet virgo, redeunt saturnia regna.” ijus pastor. weme! tord! what speke ye here in myn eeres? Tell vs no clerge I hold you of the freres, ye preche; It semys by youre laton ye haue lerd youre caton. primus pastor. herk, syrs, ye fon, I shall you teche; (45) he sayde from heuen a new kynde is send, whom a vyrgyn to neuen, oure mys to amend, Shall conceyue, full euen thus make I an end; And yit more to neuen that samyne shall bend vnto vs, With peasse and plente, with ryches and menee, Good luf and charyte Blendyd amanges vs (46) Tercius pastor. And I hold it trew ffor ther shuld be, When that kyng commys new peasse by land and se. ijus pastor. Now brethere, adew! take tent vnto me; I wold that we knew of this song so fre Of the angell; I hard by hys steuen, he was send downe ffro heuen. primus pastor. It is trouth that ye neuen, I hard hym well spell. (47) ijus pastor. Now, by god that me boght it was a mery song; I dar say that he broght foure &amp; twenty to a long. iijus pastor. I wold it were soght that same vs emong. primus pastor. In fayth I trow noght so many he throng On a heppe; Thay were gentyll and small, And well tonyd with all. iijus pastor. yee, bot I can thaym all, Now lyst I lepe. (48) primus pastor. Brek outt youre voce let se as ye yelp. iijus pastor. I may not for the pose bot I haue help. secundus pastor. A, thy hart is in thy hose! primus pastor. now, in payn of a skelp This sang thou not lose. iijus pastor. thou art an yll qwelp ffor angre! secundus pastor. Go to now, begyn! primus pastor. he lyst not well ryn. iijus pastor. God lett vs neuer blyn; Take at my sangre. (49) primus pastor. Now an ende haue we doyn of oure song this tyde. ijus pastor. ffayr fall thi growne well has thou hyde. iijus pastor. Then furth lett vs ron I wyll not abyde. primus pastor. No lyght makethe mone that haue I asspyde; Neuer the les lett vs hold oure beheste. ijus pastor. That hold I best. iijus pastor. Then must we go eest, After my ges. (50) primus pastor. wold god that we myght this yong bab see! ijus pastor. Many prophetys that syght desyryd veralee to haue seen that bright. iijus pastor. and god so hee wold shew vs that Wyght we myght say, perde, We had sene That many sant desyryd, with prophetys inspyryd, If thay hym requyryd, yit I-closyd ar thare eene. (51) ijus pastor. God graunt vs that grace. Tercius pastor. god so do. primus pastor. Abyde, syrs, a space lo, yonder, lo! It commys on a rase yond sterne vs to. ijus pastor. It is a grete blase oure gate let vs go, here he is! [They go to Bethlehem.] iijus pastor. Who shall go in before? primus pastor. I ne rek, by my hore. ijus pastor. ye ar of the old store, It semys you, Iwys. [They enter the stable.] (52) primus pastor. hayll, kyng I the call! hayll, most of myght! hayll, the worthyst of all! hayll, duke! hayll, knyght! Of greatt and small thou art lorde by right; hayll, perpetuall! hayll, faryst wyght! here I offer! I pray the to take— If thou wold, for my sake, with this may thou lake,— This lytyll spruse cofer. (53) Secundus pastor. hayll, lytyll tyn mop rewarder of mede! hayll, bot oone drop of grace at my nede; hayll, lytyll mylk sop! hayll, dauid sede! Of oure crede thou art crop hayll, in god hede! This ball That thou wold resaue,— lytyll is that I haue, This wyll I vowche saue,— To play the with all. (54) iijus pastor. hayll, maker of man hayll, swetyng! hayll, so as I can hayll, praty mytyng! I cowche to the than for fayn nere gretyng; hayll, lord! here I ordan now at oure metyng, This botell— It is an old by-worde, It is a good bowrde, for to drynk of a gowrde,— It holdys a mett potell. (55) Maria. he that all myghtys may the makere of heuen, That is for to say my son that I neuen, Rewarde you this day as he sett all on seuen; he graunt you for ay his blys full euen Contynuyng; He gyf you good grace, Tell furth of this case, he spede youre pase, And graunt you good endyng. (56) primus pastor. ffare well, fare lorde! with thy moder also. ijus pastor. we shall this recorde where as we go. iijus pastor. we mon all be restorde god graunt it be so! primus pastor. Amen, to that worde syng we therto On hight; To Ioy all sam, With myrth and gam, To the lawde of this lam Syng we in syght. Explicit Vna pagina pastorum.</field>
   </doc>
</add>