<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">University Press</field>
      <field name="author_facet">University Press</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">university press</field>
      <field name="author_text">University Press</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1920's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V1.0678.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1927</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:459379</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">Edmond Ironside : or War Hath Made All Friends</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">Edmond Ironside : or War Hath Made All Friends</field>
      <field name="title_facet">edmond ironside or war hath made all friends</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">edmond ironside or war hath made all friends</field>
      <field name="title_text">Edmond Ironside : or War Hath Made All Friends</field>
      <field name="year_display">1927</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1927</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1927</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459379&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459379&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;Edmond Ironside : or War Hath Made All Friends&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;edmond ironside or war hath made all friends&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1927&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1927&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Edmond Ironside : or War Hath Made All Friends&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Oxford&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;University Press&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1927&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3873473-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv10678&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 20th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;20th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;Edmond Ironside : or War Hath Made All Friends&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 180 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Elizabethan verse drama.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries, introductory and editorial matter omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Copyright (c) 1972 The Malone Society. This text may not be reproduced, except for fair dealing purposes, without the express permission of Chadwyck-Healey and the copyright holder.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: Edmond Ironside.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: History.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1927.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 1590–1600 ?&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Square brackets represent sections of text which have been deleted or added at different stages in the evolution of the manuscript.&lt;lb/&gt;Angle brackets represent sections of text unclear in the original and supplied by the current editor.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Edmond Ironside The English King</field>
      <field name="fulltext">A trew Cronicle History called [Warr hath made all freindes:/] Enter Canutvs Archbishope of Canterbury Earle of South«am» Edricus Duke of Mercia Leofricke Earle of Chester Tu«rku» Duke of Norff' and Suff' Vskataulf and Swetho Da They sitt about a table: Canut?:/ Archbishope and you other English peeres I heare how Egleredus late your kinge my trybutary is departed life And how his sonne prince Edmond weares the Crowne wt hout the notice of yor free Consent [or] or homage vnto mee his Soueraigne yor selves lord? Spirituall and Temporall besides the due my ffathers Conquest Claymes have Chosen mee And by an vniversall sound decree have sollomly throughout this little world proclaymd mee heire aparant to the Crowne when [Egle] Egleredus livd[d] Then lett not this younge vpstart prince of prates hee ryse Curb yor proceeding? wt h vntutord woord? but fnish boldly what you have begu?e resist his pryvate Coronac?n and put not vppe this vild dishonor Done vnto you Cheife Comaunders of the Realme as though you weare not worth the sendinge for Arch B:/ Indeed his rashnes is importable and meerely nothinge but a proud contempt against vs of the Cleirgie and the rest that have for publique proffitt of the Realme for peace for quiet and vtilitie elected prince Canut? for our kinge whose vallor wee have provd[d] vnto our Cost whose love vnto the Church wee neede not doubt whose Care for all we may relye vppon and whose true bounty is soe notable that even his fooes admire and honor him When th'other what hee is I need not tell tis to well knowne I would I Could saye well./ But this I say and sweare weare I my self he ryseth./ profest a souldior or a man at armes as I am one deprived from the world [and from my Cradle Calld to serve the Lord] I would wt h launce approve his tytle naught and plead your Coronac?n wt h my sword Canut?:/ Stout harted Bishope spoken like a Mann would all the English lord? weare of thie minde South: Am I not redy to defend yor right wt h force of armes as doth become a knight Leofricke:/ I neare was slacke or hindmost of the rest but ever first and formost wt h the best Edricus/ Had I not bin a helpe vnto yor father when as [yo] he first arived in Albion you neare had stood in question for the Crowne nor had your fathers warrs so prospored Twas I that first did Councell Egelred to paye you trybute and to buye your league where by wee emptied all the treasurye and had not gould fayld you had neare bin kinge. I had a Navye once the tyme when twas in Egelredus daies your father lyveinge wt h wc h I should have mett you on the seae wt h in the straightes of England and I wis had then noe lytle vantage on yor shipes yet I as favoringe your party moste gave waye and lett you land wt h out resistance and for that fact rest foulye scandalizd. Was yt not I that gave intelligence of all the Councells of kinge Egelred vnto yor father, did not I I praye fayne sicknes, weaknes, Disadvantages whenas the kinge sent mee to fight wt h him was I not Causer of yor good successe in all yor acc?ns sence yor fathers death As Namely in that battale lately fought «et»wene yor self and Edmond Ironside where I fled from him and did succor you Then sence tho'nely ladder vppon wc h yor father Clymed to gett and you to hold this gotten kindome was my dilligence I hope you will not the least motion of an ill thought Creepe in to hinder mee nor doe I thinke you vsed this speech by mee Canut?:/ Whie what need all this repetic?n good fayth I meant noe harme in sayeinge soe whie should I doubt you, wherefore should I feare you never yet deceyved mee:/ I cannot speake but so?e or other straight misconsters mee whie by my troth my lord I meant not you but those that cleive to Edmond Ironside and hange in parte against my goverment calme yee therefore and bee not discontent South:/ In token then you meane as you have said honor my Castle wt h the name of Courte and take a subiect? welcome from [from] his harte to signifie you love my towne and mee Vskataulfe whispereth in Canut? eare Vskata:/ Whiy that? a tryfle mightie Soveraigne yeald vnto him in[gt] this petic?n yt will Conferme the peoples hart? to you and make him live and dye to honor you Canut?:/ I willingely dysscend to yor request and will this night bee wt h you at yor place South:/ Ile goe bee fore to Countenaunce yor grace Exit South:/ Enter a Companye of cuntrymen makeinge a noyse. Cuntrymen: Where is the kinge that hee may right or wronge Canut?/ The kinge is heere, whoe is yt Calls the kinge I am yor kinge, speake gentle Cuntrymen what laules hand hath Done you inivrye One of the Cuntry:/ Renownd Canut? wee are all Daines by birth the remnant of thie needye followers whoe when thie father lived, lived here secure and dwelt amongest the fatest of this land wee then did yoake the Saxons and Compeld theire [thei] stoborne neckes to eare the fallow feild? Wee then did force [vs] them honor vs as lord? and bee or slaves or drudges and or dogges But now I know not what the Cause shold bee vnles the instigac?n of theire prince younge Ironside, or ells theire stoborne nature They all rebell and wt h Conioyned force assault vs manly and from every ?te of this perturbed Iland banish vs [wee are not able to resist theire powers] [but fall like leaves before the Northen winde] [huge heapes of vs lye dead in every place] and wee vnles you healpe shall all bee slaine All Crye:/ Healpe, healpe Canutus healpe and sccor vs. Canutus:/ Good Cuntrymen Canut? will not see you wrongd for yet the spirrit of my father Swaine runes in theis vaines, wc h I will sheed even drope by drope eare I will see you harmd goe in good frind? and pacifie yor selves be Confident in mee, and yf I live I plant you in yor former quiet states Swetho looke to them they shalbee yor Care Exeunt Swetho wt h the poore Daines:/ Now lord? lett not this sodaine rumor daunte yor manly hartes though Edmond bee soe stronge wee are as stronge, and stronger farr then hee then tell mee shall wee now assayle him saye Vskataulf what is to bee don?e Vskataulf:/ You may my Lord, yet bee remembred now against what nac?n you are bound to warr a generac?n like the [Ch?s??I???s] Chosen Iewes stoborne vnwildye feirce and wild to tame skorninge to bee Compeld [ag?s?] against their wills abhoreinge servitude as haveinge felt the over lodinge burden of the same Edricus Indeed my Cuntrymen are faccous and must bee rayned wt h a markinge stall Curbe them my Lord and brydle but theire wills nd you shall find them mild and tractable Yf that you vse them as yor father did they dare not, nay they will not look awrye but serve you as your slaves by Conquest due But yf you lay the teame vppon theire neckes and lett them have but any scope to ru?e whye then bee sure, they'l gad as theyweare [gald] [glad] and neither know themselves nor yet yor grace for Lynitie doth Cause them to rebell Cause they are Ignorant of lyveinge well:/ Vskataulf:/ List how this flatteringe mate soothes vpp the kinge and doth abuse his gracious sufferance bace vild insinuatinge Sicophant Degenerat bastard falcely bred foule mother killinge Viper traytor slave the scume of vices all the ill that may bee. Whoe would excite the kinge to Tyranie against his Cuntrymen but onely hee I am a Daine renowned Soueraigne [you have experience of my loyaltie] [and that my Councell is not mercinary] yf I weare wise enough to give advice You should not prove a tyrant but a kinge A Tyrant is abhord of god and man when as a kinge loved and honored accomptest thou Edricus the Saxons fooles or rather hardy wisie and vallowrous theire names discover what theire natures are more hard then stones and yet not stones indeed In [ffyght] fight more then stones detesting flight in peace as soft as waxe wise provident witnes the manye Combat? they have fought Denmarke or Cuntryes losse by them and theires wt h manie other witnesses of worth [how often they have driven vs to or shiftes] [and made vs take the sea for our defence] [when wee in number have bin three to one] Oh you deceave yor self and eke the kinge in wishinge him soe much against himself recall the former perrills wee have past whose deere boughte tymes are freshly yet in minde The tyranny yor father Swanus vsed in tythinge peopele, killinge 9 of io what did ensue, whie lose of manye hold? bloodshed and warr, rebellion, sword, and fyer:/ for they are Englishmen, easye to rule wt h lynitie, soe they bee vsed like men patient of right, impatient of wronge brookeinge noe tyranie in anie sorte, But hateinge and revengeinge yt wt h death, therefore I Counsell you, yf yt might stand to wine theire hartes, not by severytie but by your favor love and lynitie Canut?:/ Good Vskataulf I alowe yor speech and prayse yor Counsell by my owne Consent I will indevor to suppresse my rage and quench the burninge Choller of my harte [wc h sometymes soe inflames my inward ?tes] [as I fall out wt h my best loved frind?] [I will therefore soe moderate my self] [as Englishmen shall thinke mee English borne] I wilbee mild and gentle to my foes yf gentlenes Cann winn theire stoborne hartes But lett vs hence my Lord? by this the Earle expect? vs at Southampton theire wele rest till we Consult yf peace or warr bee best Exeunt omnes Leofricke pulls Turkillus by the sleeve, as hee is goeinge and stayes him:/ Leofricke:/ A word my lord Turkillus:/ Soe you vse no bloes:/ «L»eofricke:/ I thinke you noble, vertuous, secret, wise ells would I not have opned my intent w«c»h doth soe much Conserne or privat good to you in privat soe yt is my lord I oft have noted yor discontented gate wc h measurd by my owne doe well declayre the mind that rules yor body is not pleased And sence soe sweete a Simphonie appeares:/ betwixt or bodyes, Discontent I Iudge or mind? disturbance to bee onely one Causd from the sadd neglect of theis strange Daies Oh what a greefe is yt to noble blood? to see each bace borne grome promoted vppe each dunghill brat arreard to dignitie each flatterer esteemed vertious When the true noble vertious gentlemen are scornd disgraced and held in obliqui[e] Bace Edricus a traytor to his kinge is held in honor, wee twoe trustye subiect? are feard, suspected and have libertye only to live, yet not in libertye for what is yt but prisonment or worse when as or Children blood of or owne blood are kept Close prisoners pledges for or faithes [King Edmond whoe indeed is or trew kinge] [for good regard of merrit and desarte] [for honor fame and true nobilitye] [ys rightly termd mirrour of maiestie] Canutus is a prudent noble prince and lves to heare him Cald soe too too much But I «will» tell you this as longe as wee take ?te against or Soueraigne Ironside wee are but traytor s therefore— Turkillus:/ Stay noble Chester for I spie yor drift to heape as manie tytles on yor head as you have pourd on mine, weare but yor d«ue» yet to Cutt off such troytinge theeves of tyme I saye Amen to yor intenc?n wc h is to leave Canutus and his Courte and fly to Edmond or true lawfull kinge But least you should suspect my secresie by beinge woone soe soone to yor Device:/ I here assure you that this very plott hath longe bine hameringe in my trobled braine and had not you prevented my intent I should eare longe have moved you heerein but what shall then become of our Two boyes whoe are our pledges they shall surely dye Leofricke:/ Tutt tis noe matter yf they dye they dye they Cannot suffer in a better tyme nor for a better Cause theire Cuntryes good wee gave them life for vs they sheed theire blood Turkullus:/ Hee that sent them Can send vs more againe then lett vs hence delaye of tyme is vaine Exeunt Enter Edricus solus:/ Edricus./ What shall I thinke of him that means to begg and Canne thvs finely live vppon his witt I was as meane as anie bace ly borne fye saye not soe yt will discreditt thee Tut noe man heeres mee I but thinke not soe for yt will make thie peacockes plumes fall downe yf one such abiect thought posse thie mind tis strange to see how I am favored posses thy duke dome and Canutus grace and am the Cheife of all his Counsellours when as my betters are exild the Courte being discountenancd and out of grace They Cannot so desemble as I Can Cloake, Cosen, Cogge and flatter wt h the kinge [Crouch and seeme Courtious promise and protest] saye much doe naught in all thinges vse decept tell troth to noe man Carry tailes abroad whisper Close secret? in the giddye ayre bee as a newes monger feed the kinge wt h soothes please all mens humors wt h humilitie wc h hee must doe that is a Courtier and mind? to keepe in favor wt h the kinge [hee that had hard my story from the eand] how manie treasons I have practised how manie vild thinges I have brought to passe and what great wonders have bin Compassed by this deepe reachinge pate would thincke I wis I had bine bound apprentice to deceipt and from my bearth daye studied villanie I vnderstand prince Edmond? vppe in armes layes hold vppon occac?ns sluggie locke And whilst Canutus here securely sleepes hee wines wt h ease what wee wt h paine have gott Mas yf hee doe and fortune favor him I will soe woorke as Ile bee in his grace and keepe my liveinge and my self vnhurte But yf Canutus Chaunce to gaine a gaine then I am his for I Can glose wt h all And yet indeed to saye the very troth rather of both I love Canutus best for Edmonds father first did raise mee vppe and from a Plowmans so?e promoted mee to be a duke for all my villanie [and soe as often as I looke on him] [I must remember what hee did for mee] [and whence I did decend, and what I am] wc h thoughtes abace my state most abiecly Therefore I hate him, and desire his death and will procure his end in what I cann But for Canutus hee doth honor mee becavse hee knowes not whence I did dissend Therefore of the Two I love Canutus best yet I Can play an Ambodexters parte and sweare I love, yet hate him wt h my harte Exit Enter Edmond and Alfricke the generall vnder the kinge:/ Edmond But are ye sure my Lo: that all is fitt are all my souldiers furnished for this warr what have they meate and drincke to theire Contente doe not the Capitaines pince them of theire paye Alfricke Assure yor Mat i e my Care is such as I doe daylie ouersee them all and Cause the meanest souldier to bee searved and have his fill of meate and drincke thats good wt h out Controulment Checke or menaces for th'only meanes to mare a souldiers fight pinch him of meate and paye and pinch his might Edmond Then doe yee well for I am of this minde hee that for private bace Comodetie will starve his souldiers or keepe backe theire paye hee that to decke himself in gorgious tire will see his men goe naked, dye for Cold ys a plaine Cutthroat to the Co?onwealth A worthie Capitaine seeinge a tall souldier march barefoote haultinge pluckt off his owne showes and gave them to the souldier, sayinge fellow when I want shooes, then give mee theis againe But Capitaines now a daies plucke offe theire souldiers shooes naye sell theire lives to make them ritch and gallant to the eie but soft what are yon Twoe strangers Enter Turkullus an Leofricke Turkullus:/ Wee are rebellious traytors to yor grace: they kneell borne Englishmen but strangers to or selves whoe in remorce of Consience knowinge well wee have in takeinge ?te wt h Danish Canutus deserved, death come of our owne free wills either to suffor for or hainous factes or elce imbrace or pardons wc h we crave even as hereafter wee shall merritt yt Edmond Rise vppe Turkullus, Leofricke arise give mee yor hands and wt h yor handes your hartes I more esteme the life of one Trew subiect then the distruction of a Thowsand foes One sheepe that was lost I more reioyce to find then Twenty other wc h I never mist A frinde of whose retorne I stood in doubt is more welcom to mee then ffortie other Oh that when Strangers cannot Conquer vs wee should Conspire wt h them against our selves [England yf ever warr thy face doth spoyle] [thancke not thy outward foe but inward frind] [for thou shalt never ?ishe tell that daye] [when thie right hand shall make thie harte awaye] goe in brave lords your sight doth mee more ioye then Agamemnon when hee Conqverd Troye Exeunt e?s</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Act 2d u s The Dru?e and Trumpetts sound Enter wt h a banquet: Then Enter Canutus South: Arch: Bish: Vskataulf and Swetho Edricus:/ Canutus: My lord My lo: you are to bountifull half this expence would well have satisfied the homely stomaches of our souldiers and entertaind our self right royally where is your Daughter South: Shee shall give attendance, to waight vppon your grace at diner tyme Canutus: Nay good my lord vnlesse you give her leaue to sitt at board and finde mee Table talke I shall not thincke my self awelco?e gueste uth: May I Crave pardon of your Mat i e my daughter beinge younge in yeares and maners is far vnfitt to keepe a Queenes estate Canutus: I faith my lo: you are to scrupulous to vnadvised to fearefull wt h out Cavse to stand vppon such nice excuses I love to see a Table furnished and sure I will not sitt tell shee Comes in South: Egina daughter Come awaye sweete gerle· Enter Egina the kinge will have thee dine wt h him to daye be not to coye, nor yet to flixable. yf chaunce hee proffer anie Curtesie behave your self in honorable sorte and answer him wt h modestie and mirth A meanes may bee to make thee Queene Canutus: What is yor daughter come, welcome faire ladye your presence is as welcom as the daye after A longe and weary watchfull night sitt downe faire ladie sitt downe noble lord fill mee a Cuppe of wine heeres to the health of Ironside and all his followers whoe will pledge me Egina:/ Pardon your hand maid and Egina will Canutus Wilt pledge me to the health of Ironside what reason moues you soe to fancy him Egina/ The good regard I beare your Maiestie for should hee die before theis warrs were done and you have ffinist strife through victory so?e other CADMVS bird worse then him self might happe to broch so?e new Co?otion and troble all the state wt h mutinies where yf hee lives tell you have Conquerd him none after him dares renovate the warres Canutus:/ Sweetely and wisely answerd noble Queene for by that name yf heaven and thou Consente by Su?e sett all the Campe shall wish thee health my lord what saye you to this moc?n South: As yt shall pleas your Royall Mat i e dispose of mee and what soere is mine Canutus:/ Madam pleaseth yt you to bee A Queene Egina/ What my dread Sou'aigne, and my father willes I dare not nay I will not Contradict Canutus: Then for a manuell seale receave this kisse he kesseth h the Cheife dumbe vtterer of the hartes intente [and noble father, now Ile Call you soe ] [yf this rash seemeinge match doe like you well ] [deliver mee possion presently ] [of this faire ladie, your beloved child ] and wee will straigh to church and Celebrate the duties wc h belonge to Marriadges Bishope of Caunterbury you will marie vs wt h out the sibert askeinge will ye not Arch: B:/ I am prepaird yf every ?te bee pleased Canutus:/ ffaith I am pleased Arch: B:/ But what saye you Egina:/ I saye a Woemans silence is Consente Canutus:/ Whie heers a match ex tempore small adoe a boute a waightie matter, so?e perhapes would have Consumed milions to effect what I by so?e spente breath have Compassed Lordes lett vs in for I intend to bee espoused to night wt h all solemnitie after our mariadge wee doe meane to goe to meete in open feild our open foe Exeunt omnes Enter Edricke a poore man his wife and Stich:/ Edricke:/ Naye Stich and you once see my so?e youle sweare hee is a bouncer, all in silkes and gold vengable rich Stich:/ How saye you that Wife:/ I Cann tell you, you may blesse the daye that euer you hapt in to his service, hee is a mann every haires bredth— a most vilde brave man yfaith:/ Stich:/ Then we shalbe well mett for I love braverye and clenlines out of all crye and indeed of all thinges I cannot brooke an ilfavord face hange him that want? a good face Edricke:/ you are of my minde we may saye a Poxe of all good faces and never hvrte our owne Stich:/ Wee may indeede god be praysd but what howse is this how far off are wee from Southampton:/ Wife:/ whie wee are in the Towne th kinge Canutus lies heere now, and my sonne is heere and all or neighbores wilbee heere to daye, at the bridall for almesse Enter Edricus Edricus:/ Whoe soe desires to mount a loftie pitch must beare himself against the stoborne winde and shu?e bace Common popularitie:/ Stich./ whoe is this: wife:/ Oh tis my so?e, make yee handsome, tie yor garters for shame wipe yor shooes, mend yor shirtband:/ Edricke:/ Oh lett mee goe to him first, God save yee sonne Edricus:/ A pox apon him tis the knave my father good fellow hast thou anie suite to vs deliver vppe thy Suplicac?n «Edr»icke:/ Oh Sr yee knowe mee well enough I am goodman Edricke your father «u»s: My father grout heade ser knave I saye you lye you horeso?e Cuckold you bace vacabond you slave you mungrell peasant doulte and foole, canst thou not knowe a Duke from co?on men Wife:/ By my troth I learnd him all theis names to call his father when hee was a child, and see yf hee can forgett them yet Oh hee is a wise man, for in faith my husband is none of his father, for indeed a souldier begott him of mee as I went once to a faire, But sonne knowe yee mee Edricus:/ Thee old hagge, witch, queane slutt drab, whore and theefe, how should I know the blacke Egiptian:/ Wife:/ This is his old trickes husband, Come, Come, so?e I am sure, yee know«m» Edricus:/ I yf not to well, wherefore comes yon sheepbiter, you sir knave you are my brother are yee not I praye Stich:/ Noe sir and yt like ye Edricus:/ It likes mee very well, what is yor name, wherefor Came ye heather: Wife:/ His name is Stich my sonne, wee Came wt h him to healpe him to your service Edricus:/ You [?swer] answer for him gossippe, wantes hee tongue Stich:/ Noe ser, I have tongve enough yf that bee good hee shewes his tongue Edricus:/ What Can yee doe Stich:/ Anie thinge, dresse a horse, scoure a Chamber pott, goe to plowe, Thrash, Dicke, and indeed what not:/ Edricus:/ Canst make cleane shooes Stich:/ Whoe I. yt is ?te of my occupac?n, you wine my harte. I am a Cobler for neede I Can peice a shooe as well as the best wipe a shooe looke you heere elce give mee your foote Edricus:/ Staye not soe hastie wee that by slie devices meane to mounte and creepe into opinion by decepte must not of all thinges have a scholler knowe or practices, wee must supprese good witts and keepe them vnder, wee must favor fooles And wt h promotions winn theire shallow pates [A Redie witt would quickly winde vs out] [and prie into or secrett trecharies] [and wade as deepe in pollecy as wee] [But such loose braind windy headed slaves] [such blockheades doltes, fooles, dunces, idiott?] [such loggerheaded rogues are best for vs] [for wee may woorke theire wills to what wee will] and winn theire hartes wt h gold to anie thinge Come hether Stich this villiane and this quean«e» that brought thee heither Clame an entrest in my nobilitie, when as god knowes my noble father died longe sence in warres beinge duke of Mercia then as I am now therefore, but first to Cutt of longe delayes I entertane the for my Chamberlaine and as thou shalt prove secret, trustie, trew I will reward thee wt h so?e higher place but first to trye thee fetch the Constable yet staye a while they would suspect the trewth Ile have thee when thou seest mee gon awaye beate theis Two beggers hence and teach them how they shall heereafter Chose a meaner sonne wilt thou bee trvsty, wilt thou Cudgell them: Stich: Never take Care for that Ile beate them they were neaver better beaten sence they weare borne Edricus:/ I doe soe, Stich I preethee beate them well harke yee? and see them whipt out of the Towne and yf they speake or prattle Cvrse or Rave for every woord give them Tenn blowes sweete slave exit Edricke:/ Oh sonne, sonne, staye Stich: Sonne Sonne wt h a pestelence, You are much like to bee his father and you his mother you brought mee hether Edricke:/ I Stich:/ And I must beate you hence, and yf you desire to [knw] knowe whie you must hereafter leare to finde ameaner mann for yor sonne then my lord is hee beates them about the stage Wife:/ Hee is my sonne. Oh: Oh: Oh good Stich hold thie hand Exeunt Enter Canutus [South:] Arch B: Edricus Vskataulf Swetho: Canutus: Then are they gon, tis Certaine they are fleed Turkullus and Leofricke whoe would have thought yt did not I vse them well, gave them good woordes Rewarded theire Indevors, and besides graced them as much as anie parson heere Edricus: You vsd them but to well and lett mee saye your linitie did Cavse them runne a waye Canutus: Have wee not pledges of theire loyaltie Edricus:/ yee haue my lord Canutus: Theire eldest sonnes I thincke Edricus: Trew but they know you are to mercifull Canutus: They are deceyved, for sence they have disturbd the settelled sollace of our marriadge daye and daunted or determind meriment? wt h Causeles flight, to plague theire fathers fact Ile laye the treason on their Childrens backe [and make theire gviltles shoulders beare the burthen] fetch mee the Pledges swetho, and wt h them some bloody varlett from the Danish hoast and lett him bringe an axe, a blocke &amp; knife alonge wt h him but doe yt quickly Sweth: Exet Swetho:/ and Come againe as fast Edricus: What doth your grace intend to doe wt h them Canutus Ile Cutt theire hand? and noses offe Edricus: Your Iudgment doth not far enough extend vnto the hight of runawaies desarte death is to light a punishment for traytor s and losse of hands and nose is [worse] lesse then death Vskata: If an honest mann had said soe I would have liked yt never the woorse Canutus:/ This punishment is worse then lose of life for yt is a stingeinge Corsive to theire sovles as often as they doe behold them selves lopt and bereft of those Two ornamentes wc h nessessary vse doth daily Crave [Againe yt giveth others daily cavse] [to thinke how trator s should bee handled wheras the memory of present death is quicly buried in oblivion [doeinge noe good but whilst yt is in doeinge] A trator maye be likened to a tree wc h beinge shred and topt when yt is greene doth for one twigge wc h from the same was cutt yeald Twenty armes yea twenty armes for one but beinge hackt and mangled wt h an Axe the Roote straight dies and [peecemele] peacemeale rots awaye Even soe of traytor s Cut mee off theire heades still moore out of the self same stocke will sprout but plauge them wt h the losse of nedfull members as Eies nose, hand?, eares, feete or anie such Oh theis are Cuttinge Cardes vnto theire soules [Eare marke to know a tratorous vilane by] [even as a brand is to discrie a theefe] [these desperate persons for examples sake] [these Ruffaines theis aldaringe lustie bloodes] [these Courte appendixes these madcape laddes] [these nothinge fearinge hotspures that attend] [or Royall Courte tell them of hanginge Cheare ] [theile saye yt is a tricke or two a boue ground ] [tell them of quarteringe or the heading Axe ] [theile sweare beheadinge is a gallant death ] [and hee is a dastard that doth feare to die ] [But saie to them, you shalbee branded] [or yor hands Cutt offe or you nostrilles slitt] Then shallow feare makes theire quireringe tongues to speake abruptly, rather lett vs dye then wee should suffer this vild Ignomie A valliant harte estemeth light of death but honorable mindes are Ielious of honorable names, then to bee mark«ed» wc h robbs them of theire honors likewise robbs theire hartes of Ioye, and like to irkesome owles they wilbee bashefull to bee seene a broad Vskataulf:/ Alas poore soules yt was against theire willes that theire hardharted fathers broake the league Edricus:/ Alas poore soules yt is against their willes that they must loose theire noses and theire hands Enter Swetho the Two Pledges and Stich wt h an Axe:/ Canutus:/ Come on Gentlemen Cause I have found your fathers trvstie as they promised vnto my father and to mee Therefore I meane to make you worthie men such as the world shall afterward reporte did suffer torments for theire Cuntries good [Come on I saye prepaire yor visadges] [to beare the tokens of eternitie] prepaire yor noses, bid yor hand? adue becavse your sires have proved themselves soe trew i Pledge:/ Rather then this Oh kill vs presently theis beinge gone wee doe abhore or lives [and haveinge theis wee loth to live accvrst] [accompted trator s to or native soyle] Suffer vs first to trye or striplinge force wt h anye Giant of your [Ciclo] Ciclopes Sise and lett or armes fight once before or deathes to reake theire mallice on theire maisters foes soe lett vs perishe like to Gentelemen like to our selves and like to Englishmen. Canutus:/ Looke how Cold water Cast on burn?ge Coles doth make the fier more fervently to flame Even so your teares doth adde vnto my rage and makes yt hotter when yt gines to Coole [tis not my pleasure you should suffer death] [Cavse I beleve twould ease your fathers greefes] [tis not my pleasure you should trye yor powers] [so I should give you honnors vndeseved] [and you perchaunce might soe reedeme yor selves] [But you shall see or Iudments straight performed] [doe execuc?n on them presently] Ile teach yor fathers yf they doe not knowe what tis to violate a lawfull othe I teach them what yt is to playe wt h kinges presuminge on theire mercy, Come I saye what trifle yee delaye noe more the tyme for you must suffer for yor fathers Cryme 2 Pledge:/ What ser must you Cutt offe my handes Stich:/ I and yor noses too, twere pittie in faith to marr two such faces Boyes will you Change beards wt h mee i Pledge:/ You shall not touch my nose wt h those bace hands by heaven Ile so?er Cutt yt offe myself Stich:/ You will thinke A worse paire then theis agood paire ere nig how theile looke when theire noses bee offe, every one wil«l» take them for ffrenchmen Canutus: dispatch I saie I must not staye soe longe the more you delaye the tyme the worse you speede i Pledge:/ Give mee the Axe Ile quicly execute this direfull Iudgment on my guiltles handes Stich:/ wt h all my harte you save mee a labor Canutus:/ Staye vnadvised vilaine hold thy hand or I will hacke the peacemeale wt h thy Axe whie art thou madd to give thie enimie an instrument to Kill thie self and mee Cutt offe his hand? first, then deliver yt him Hee cutts offe one hande Soe Cutt offe th'other. Hee Cutts offe the other hande now ser fight yor fill i Pledge:/ Lett theis my stumpes Crave vengance at thie hand? thou Iudge of Iudges and thou kinge of kinges Canutus: Cutt off his nose then lett him praye againe perchance his prayeinge metigates his paine Hee Cutts off his Nose i Pledge: Powre thie vengance on this bloody daine and lett him die some vnherd monstrous death Canutus: Make quick dispatch to execut the other I am sure you will not now bee pardoned 2 Pledge Not I thou Murtheringe stonie hated daine I am resolved to suffer this and more to doe my father or my Cuntry good they gave mee life for them Ile shed my blood Hee Cutts his hand? and Nose i Pledge: Now thou hast spitt thie venome bloody kinge wee doe retone defiance in thie face Canutus: Sers temper well yor tongues and bee advse«d» yf not Ile Cutt them shorter by an Inch remember that you both have lost yor hand? becavse your fathers did abuse theire tongues in periurye, goe quickly away and tell your tratrous fathes what I say 2 Pledge: Wee goe but to thie Cost proud Danish Canute throughout this Ile thie tiranie to brute i Pledge Wee goe thie Crewell butchery to Ringe oh England never trust a forraine kinge Exit Pledes Edricus: Ha. Ha. Ha Canutus: Whie laughest thou Edricus Edricus: I Cannot chuse to see the villaines rave Ent Mess nger «h»: And I must needes laugh to beare my Mr Companie Enter a messenger runinge Canutus: What newes wt h thee Messenger: Renownd Canutus thy forces in the North wc h thou didst send gainst Edmond Ironside are Cleene disperst and peecemeale overthrowne by him, as theis letters signifie. Canutus reades and then sayeth Canutus: Tis wonderfull what Twenty Thowsand slaine of Co?on souldiers this vnwelcome newes nipes like a hory frost our springeinge hopes and makes my fearefull souldiers hange theire head? [Come hether Edricus voyd the Companie] [that I and you may talke in secresie] Exeunt omnes Ah Edricus what had I best to doe to race out this dishonorable blott out of the brasse leaved booke of liveinge fame [shall yt be said heereafter when Report] [shall Celebrate my noble fathers actes] [that Canutus did lose, what noble Swanus gott] shall yt be said that Edmond Ironside vnfrinded poore forsaken desolate did ouerthrowe the power of mightie Canutus whose wealth was great, frindes more, but forces most Never sence Edmond was of force to beare a massey helmet and a [Cv] Curtlaxe Could I retorne a victor from the feild vnlesse as I remember thou betraydst the gallant striplinge once into or hands [then had not vallour hewed him throw or troopes] [that daye had made an end of all or greefes] But now what now, oh tell mee yf thou knowest how shall I extribute my stocke and name that after age may not reporte my shame «Ed»ricus: dispaire not noble kinge tyme Comes in tyme know yee not tis a deede of pollecye in fickell Chaunce to Crosse yor mightienesse [for elce in Tyme you might dismounte the Queene] [and throw her headlonge from her rowlinge stone] [and take her whele whirlinge wheele into your hand] I tell yor grace Chaunce ever envies wise men and favors fooles promotinge them aloft But as for this fleaspott of dishonor the greatest monarches have indured more even blinckeinge Phillipes sonne and manie more whose repitic?n weare needles to recyte Canutus: I preethee flatter still, on, on, what more speake wee of fortune honest Sicophante Chaunce favoreth not a foole in favoringe thee thy flatery is gracious in her eye [Come hether Edricus oh strange miracle] see you not in the heavens prodigious signes looke how the Sunne lookes paile the moone shines red The starres appeare in the ?turbed heven like little Comett? and not Twelve a Clocke what is the Cavse then that the starres are seene Edricus:/ I see them · well my lord: yett knowe noe cause vnles yet shewes the fall of Ironside Canutus:/ Shurely yt doth: looke now they all are gonne tis night, tis darke, beware ye stumble not lend mee yor hand, but first goe fetch a torch Exit Edricus to light mee to my tente. make hast I praye hees gonne to fetch a torch to light the daye Enter Edricus Edricus: My lord the mistie vapors weare soe thicke they almost quencht the torch Canutus:/ Trve as all the rest, I say thie witt is thicke grose flattery: all sothing Sicophant doth blind thie eies and will not lett thee see [that others see thou art a flatterer] [Amend, amend thie life learne to speake trewth] [for shame doe not in thie declineinge age] Children may see thie lies they are so plaine Oh whilst yee live from flattery refraine Edricus:: Yt standes not wt h my Zeale and plighted faith otherwise to saye then as yor hignes saith your grace is hable to give all theire due to make truth lye and likewise make lies true Canutus:/ I would Yt laye in mee to make thee true but whoe cann Change the Ethiophians hew</field>
      <field name="fulltext">[Act 3] Enter at one doore: ye Arch B: of Cauntery at th'other ye Arch B: of Yorke Caunterb: Whie bends not the presumptious knee of Yorke when Canter: speakes: Cannot the Curse of god and mee the metropolitan vnder the Pope of all Dominions wt hin this realme of England Cause thee feare prowd irreligious prelate know my power stretcheth beyond thie Compasse [ever] even as much as Rome doth mine then quiver when I Curse and like a Child indeed prostrate thie self before my feete that thy humilitie may move mee to absolve thie former sinnes and sett the free from Hells Damnac?n Yorke: Traytor to god and to thie lawfull kinge where thou dost blese I Cvrse where Cvrse I blesse as thou art Bishope my Co?ision stretcheth as farr as thine, and lett me saye ([[illeg.]] vnlese thou leave thy Contimulious threat?) further then mine Noe Canterbury noe I humble me to God and not to thee A traytor a betrayor of his kinge [A rebell a prophane preist a Pharesie] [A parrasite, an enimie to peace] A foe to trewth and to Religion I saye I will not bend myself to him and such a one arte thou and therefore heere vnles repentance bend thie stobborne harte I heere ?nounce the Curse of god and man vppon thie soule and soe farwell and [med] mend yorke offers to Departe Canter: Staye Yorke and heare me speake, thie puffie word? thie windie threates thie raylinge Cvrses light vppon thie stubborne necke vnles wt h speede thou dost forsake the parte of Ironside and cleave vnto Canutus, and more submit thie self to mee thie head and to or mother Church replie not Bishoppe for [th] I seale thie lipes wt h my Irrivocable bitter Curse yf one vntoward woord slipp from thie tongue Yorke So heapest thou Cole of fier vppon thie head and blessest mee wt h Cursing impious preist oh lett mee dye whenas I leave my kinge A trew borne prince for anie forriner Canter': Oh I Could eate thee, now my Crossier stafe longes to bee peltinge that old hory pate my hands doe quake wt h rage Yorke You are a Champion for the Devell and Canutus I flye not from thie Curses but thie strokes Exet Yorke Cant' Ile follow thee wt h Curses and wt h Clubbes Exit Cant' Enter Canuts South: Edricus Vskataulf Swetho Harrold at armes and souldiers Canuts. Goe to yon Citie wc h wee meane to sacke new Troy the state of Edmond Ironside Co?and a parley at the Cytie gates bid them Chuse whether they will lett vs in or els wt hstand the vtmost of or wrath and bee Consmed to ashes and to Coles wt h flayminge fyre which Whilom did distroy their mother Cytie Quandam Called Troy The Herrold departeth from the kinge to the walls soundinge his trumpit The Balifes appeare aboue Herrold:/ Canutus kinge of England prince of daines greetes you by mee his trustie messenger Comaundinge you to serve him as your lord biddinge you waite on him as on yor kinge [and you shalbee intreated loveingly] yf not hee is prepaird wt h fire and sword to race yor Cytie thus hee sendes you woord:/ 1 Balife Goe tell yor Master thus wee answer him may his shippes that proudly ride vppon the Thames shall anccor on the ground wher hee abides born by the bloodshed of or Carcases and wee Compeld by thirst to sucke the streame of this fair river drye, soe that his [mean] men may dryeshod march ouer the flottinge deepes ere wee will lett him enter in theis gattes [or ope or lipes to Call him soueraigne] [tell him wee are resolved to keepe him backe] Tell him wee are noe Traytors but are sworne to bee Kinge Edmonds leigemen while wee live and yf hee staye that shall hee soone perceve Harrold:/ Advise you Balifes what is best to doe incur[a] not danger wt h securetie Canutus is yor kinge then him obaye and to his gentle Mess[[illeg.]]age saye not naye Both Blifes:/ Wee are resolved to put Canutus backe he comes not heere his threates are spent in vaine Herrold:/ I feare your wills will put yor p wittes to paine and you repent yt when yt is to late i Balife:/ You haue yor answers soldiers gard the gatte[s] Balifes departe Herrold retvrneth:/ Herrold./ There answer good my Lord is negative full of haughtie Courage and disdainfull pride this little peace hath brought theire stomaches vppe wc h makes them to disdane yor princly mercy Canut?:/ And dare they thus refuse my proffred grace sett they soe light by my Co?aundement assault, the Cytie batter downe the walls [skale all the Turret?, rush the gatts assunder] whie slacke yee souldiers whoe is formost man to give a valiant onsett on the Towne:/ assayle the walls Enter a Messenger Messeng' Worthie Comaunder of theis Warlike troppes Edmond yor foe is cominge hetherward wt h a Choyce Companie of Armed men intendinge to supprice you svddenly Canutus:/ Hee is welcome though I hope vnto [yor] his Cost Wee are beholdinge to his exelence that hee voutsafe for safegard of his Towne to yeild himself wt hout Compulsion [Wee are as forward and as fitt as hee] [to give his force an equall Counterbvffe] [thoughe hee suppose to take vs vnawares] Now noble Lord? or neuer shew yor might to put his Men to sword and him to flight South: Hee that gives backe lett him be slaine by his next fellow that doth second him yf English men at first begin to flye Southampton willingly for them will dye Vska: This day shall manifestly be knowne how daines have better hartes then Englishmen and bodies answerable to the same elce lett them loose their everlastinge fame Edricus: The daye is yours before the fight begines great and renowned prince faire England? kinge for emulac?n wc h doth somtyme loose now doth assure you of the victory [See you not how the English Lords Contend] [Whoe should exell in feates of Chivaldry] [and Creepe vppe farthest in yor highnes grace./] [on thother syde, behold brave minded daines] [scorninge to ore match in feates of Armes] [strive whoe should Compas most by porer or witt] [to ampliefie your honorable fame] The souldiers are not slothfull in this sturr but redye, forward prompt, and fitt to fight expectinge gladly that delightsome hower When they shall grapple wt h theire enimies Then in assurance of this happie Daye arme to the fight yt is in vayne to staye Canutus:/ I doe presume on this to winne the feild but all my striveinge is to gett the Crowne Sound Dru? wt hin [Alarum] Soft what Churlish Dru?e doth ringe soe rude apeale wt hin the heareinge of our Armed troopes Tis Edmund stricke vppe drumes Enter Edmund wt h souldiers and trumpitt? sound Ile not delay my hopes wt h anie parley Alarum they fight Edmond drives Canutus offe the stage The dru?e soundes a farr offe Enter attired in blacke sayinge:/ Chorus: The fight is hott but Canutus is ore Come and Edmond huntes him out from place to place hee flyes to Worcester Edmond followes him the waye is longe and I am waxen faint I faine [I] would haue you vnderstand the truth and see the battailes Acted on the stage But that theire length wilbe to tedious then in dumbe shewes I will explaine at large theire fightes theire flightes and Edmonds victory ffor as they strivd to Conquer and to kill even soe we strive to purchase yor good will Alarum Enter Canutus flyinge Edmond followinge they fight The Two kinges parley sounde a Retreate and parte Chorus Canutus is beholdinge to the gracious su?e whoe greevd to see such heapes of Carcases lye mangled and besmered in theire gore made hast and went to rest before his tyme soe that the kinges for want of light agreed to [vntell] parte vntell Aurora raise the larke and now tis morninge and they ioyne to fight Alarum Enter Canutus at one dore and Edm«u» at the other they fight Canutus gives backe an«d» flies Enter the souldiers of Edmond persuing Canutus and his lords Edricus takes a dead «m» head vppon his swords poynt holdinge yt vppe Edmonds souldiers they flie Enter Edmond a Cheeringe them vp and makes Canutus flie:/ Chorus:/ Edricus perceavinge Canutus to have the worst and Edmond like to trivmph in theire fall out of the bowells of a Traytorous harte brought forth this subtell dangerous stratagem whilst the Two Battales dealt the dole of Death and Edmond in the forefront stoutly fought [wt h words encoraginge his souldiers] [and wt h rude stroakes discouraginge the Daines] Edricus tooke vppe an English dead mans head and stickinge yt vppon his bloody sword vnto the vanward of kinge Edmondes tropes held his dispightfull and most speedy Cource tellinge the souldiors Edmond Ironside was slaine, biddinge the souldiors yeald or flye the feild and trust vnto theire heeles The soldiors in a maze begane to flye then Edmond heareinge of this stratagem amongest the Thickest of his enimies gave notice that hee lived a conqueror his souldiors takeinge harte retorned and fought his enimies dispareinge Rune awaye Edmond returnes in tryumph [on] [in] [to] the [stage] [ffeild] But Canut? returnes in passion and in rage what after happens wt h your patience the entringe Actors gives intelligence Exit Enter Edmond Ironside wt h Lord? and souldiors:/ Edmond/ Praysd bee theternall bulwarke of this land the fortresse of my Crowne in whome I trust that hath thus discomfited my fooes by his omnipotent all Conquoringe arme And worthie Lordes tryumphant warriors [whose vallours eccho through the mouth of fame] [and writes you worthies in the booke of life] mauger the envie of detracc?n wee render hartie thanckes to each of you for fightinge in or rites wt h such bould spirites Continew to bee valliant, and yf god make vs once happie in a peacefull Raigne Ile guerdion every souldior bountiously that liftes a weapon to defend or rite Lett vs not loyter oppertunitie but follow danish Canute and force him flye One march afore, sound trumpittes stricke vppe drumes lett shrickinge fifes tell Canute that Edmond Comes The souldiors shout et exeunt Enter Canutus Edricus wt h other Lords and souldiers Canutus:/ A plague vppon you all for arrant Cowards looke how a dunghill Cocke, not rightly bred doth come into the pitt wt h greater grace brvslinge his feathers, settinge vppe his plumes Clappinge his winges and Crowinge lowder out then doth a cocke of game that meanes to fight Yett after when he feeles the spures to pricke crakes like a Craven and bewrayes himself Even soe my bigbond daines adrest to fight as though they meant to scale the Cope of heaven (and like the Giants graple wt h the god?) at first encounter rush vppon theire foes but straige retire? retire? nay runn a waye as men distraught wt h lightninge from aboue or Dastards feared wt h a sodaine fraye Edricus./ Renowned Soueraigne doe not fret yor self Fortune in turninge will exalt yor state and Change the Countenaunce of her Clowdy browe [now you must hope for better still and better] [and Edmond must expect still worse and worse] A lowringe morninge proves a fayer daye ffortunes ilfavord frowne shewes shee will smille on you and frowne on Ironside:/ Canutus: What telst thou mee of ffortune and her frownes of her sower visage and her rowlinge stone thy tongue rowles headlonge in to flattery [now by theis heavens aboue or wretched heades] [ye are but Cowards euery one of you] Edmond is blest, oh had I but his men I would not doute to Conquer all the world in shorter tyme the Alexander did But all my Daines are Braggadochios and I accurst to bee the generall of such A flocke of fearefull ru?awaies South:/ Remember you haue lost Tenn Thowsand men all English borne except a Thowsand Daines yor pensive lookes will kill them that survive yf thus to Choller you give libertie Canutus:/ It weare noe matter yf they all weare slaine then they should neaver runne awaye againe Vska:/ My noble lord or Cuntry men are safe in all theis broyles English gainst English fight the Daines or none or very few are slaine Turns towards Vskataul Canutus:/ It was a signe yee fled and did not fight Ist not a Dishonor vnto you to see a foraingne nation fight for mee whenas my homebred Cuntrymen doe run?e leaveinge theire kinge amongest his enimies Edricus:/ Give not such scoope to humorous discontent wee all are ?tners of yor privat greefes [Kinges are the head? and yf the head but ache] [the little finger is distempered] [wee greeve to se you greeved wc h hurteth vs] [and yet availes not to asswage your greefe] [You are the Sunne my lo: wee Marigold?] [whenas you shine wh wee spred or selves abroade] [and take or glory from yor influence] and [But] when you hide yor face or darken yt wt h th'least incounter of a Clowdy looke wee Close or eies as partners of yor woes Droopinge or heades as grasse downe waid wt h due Then Cleere ye vpp my lord [ad] and Cheere vpp vs for now or valours are extinguished and all or force lyes drownd in brinish teares as Iewells in the bottome of the sea I doe beseech yor grace to heare mee speake Edricus talkes to h«i» South: I doe [besch] not like this humor in my sonne twill quight discoradge all his followers Vska:/ Hee stopes his eares to all perswasions his Councell cannot bee admitted spech his father Swaine was much more patient and Could aswell brooke losse as victory Canut: Theis wordes proceede not from A shallow, braine Edricus Praise the event my lord the end is all in the meane tyme Ile goe write to Ironside craveinge forgiuenes and insinuate:/ his yealdinge favor, hee is pittifull and I am rare in moveinge passion [I knowe the prince will quickly Creditt mee] [and putt affiance in my smooth pretence] [but what soere hee doth or minds to doe] [you shalbe sure to haue intelligence] But good my Lord leave me a little while to privat Contemplac?n for my head swimes full of plotts and other stratagemes of great availe and I must emptie yt Canute: God prosper what thou dost intend Edricus:/ Praye to the divell god is not my frind Exeunt manet Edricus Stich, what Stich, Call in Stich Enter Stich Stich: Heeres a Stichinge indeed, you have made Stich have a stich in his side, wt h Cominge soe hastely after diner Edricus: Whie villaine darst thou eate meate in theis troblesome tymes Stich: Dare I eate meate I and eate tyme bee hee never so troblesome my lord weare Mars himself made of beefe and brewis I durst in this Chollericke stomache devour him quicke Edrick: Sure yeare a tall mann Stich:/ I sir at the end of a fraye, and begininge of a feast Edricus: well fetch me paper and a Cornegraph Stich: a hornegrafter whats that, sir? Edricus: Serra I meane an Inckhorne Stich: You meane well sir. A blackhorne, you haue dipt yor penne in manye amans Inckehorne besides yor owne exit Stich·/ Edricus My state may bee Compared vnto his that venters all his creditt and his wealth vppon the fickle hazard of a Dye the Crowne I levell at, I venter lyfe the Derest Iewell and of greatest price that anie mortall hath possession of my life is sweete yet will I venter yt at all or nothinge trust a mother witt Enter Stich wt h paper and an Inckehorne Stich: Heere ser I would never haue men that are vnmaried soe vnprouided as they should be compelled to borough hornes of younge men, Nor would I haue youngemen to boroughe Inhornes of married men Oh yt is perrilous when theire fore heades proves blushinge papers to bewraye younge buddes «d»ricus:/ Sirrah be gon but bee not farre from hence I presently shall haue occac?n to imploye you in some serious busnes Stich:/ I wilbe absent when you Call I warrant you Exit Stich Edricus sitts downe writteth and blotteth Edricus:/ Nay trye thie witt? thou writtest for awager tis not for gold, but grace, and for thie life A thinge that would putt spirrit in a blocke and bee a whetstone to a blunter head wt h what exordion shall I wine his harte how shall I tye his eares to my discourse A schole boye hath a redier witt then I I never tryed my barraine sconce tell now and now I see I am not Edricus but a most blockish and dulpated hinde [graveld at such an esie interprise] [What standest thou triflinge and delayinge tyme] fetch fyer from heaven and mix yt wt h thie incke gather Parassus due and writte wt h that plucke Cyllens feathers and make pens wt h them borrow the Muses ayd and lett them breath [some dulcet and melodious harmoney] some never hard of woord? into thie pate Hee writteth and blotteth Ah foole how hard yt is to writte for lyfe had I now written for my Mr i s love I could haue fild my pene, and raysed my spech vnto the highest stepp of flattery [had I now written for an other man] [to save his life or gett him into grace] [why all the world might have given place to mee] [for sugred lynes and phrases past Compaire] [had I bine now in favor wt h the kinge] [and had indevored to flatter him] [my pene would have distelled golden dropes] [and varied tearmes inchauntinge Cerberus] But now I knowe not how or what to writte to flatter weare to agravate my faulte for anger would sift out my vild intent Plainely to writte weare to accuse my self and bee a witnesse gainst my guiltie soule Yet writt I will and in the plainest sorte for that is Cosen German vnto truth Truth needes noe cullors though I meane to lye my simple writtinge shall deceave his eie Hee writteth and sayeth I soe, O rare Conceyted peece of worke how cuningly thou [Cast] canst convert thy shape into an Angell when thoudost intend to flatter the plaine honest meaninge kinge hee fouldes yt vppe Now for a swift winge footed messenger to flye in post that I might follow him [yt more behoofes mee to bee Cercumspect ] [and wt h my life to trust none but myself ] [swyfter then sure is noe good messenger ] And now I thincke ont oh tis exelent Ile for this once deliuer yt my self but in disigisement of my mans attyre soe may I safly goe and vnderstand how Edmond is adicted vnto mee and how all matters now are mannaged Stich: Stich: Enter Stich Stich. Yor will sir Edricus:/ My will is that you will vncase for I meane to Change apparell«.» Stich: whye sir you not turne wiseman will you Edricus: Yes foole for this once, Come I saye when Stich: Mary sir when I so?e boote Comeinge roundly from you for I «p» promise you I will not Change wt hout boote Edricus: But I will sirrah Come dispatch Stich:/ well sir sence their is shift but I must change shiftes I am contented They shifte apparell By my troth sir methinckes yare a properer man by od? in those the ye weare in theis, I would I Could perswade him to bee leue mee then yt should bee knowne by his aparell what a foole I haue made of him Sr shall wee change liveinge and lord shippe and name and all Edricus:/ I Stich for this once, thou shalt bee Lord Edricus and I Stich looke—you keepe in tell [you] I Come home Iadvise you and behaue yourself like a Lord Stich: I warant you good Stich Ile be lordly enough: farwell honest Stich, fawell foole Edricus: Now am I Edricus and Edricus man the secratary and the messenger All to effect wt h Counterfeytinge guile experiment? of matchles pollecye well this plaine suite doth now Contayne more witt then for soe meane a peece of Cloth is fitt Exit Edricus Enter Stich in his lord? attire wt h Blewcoates after him: Stich: Come on Yee blewcoated slaves, you that weare sattine doblets never but at good tymes, and weare a blew-coate buto once in a yeare, Come on I saye, ye trencher scrapeing cutters Yee Cloake bagge Cariers, ye sword and bucklere carriers ye rubbers of horse heles, ye Devourers of fatt oxen ye swillers of March beere, Come after mee I saye, take example after my vertue howe to mount, I proceedinge from the loynes of a man very littel better the a gentle man, am now by my vertue and good educc?n to bee yo r Master, yor vpholders, the staffe of yor lifes, and maintainer of yo r mastershipes, vncover Ye rouges. soe Cover. so. sirrah take my Cloake, beare yov my rapier, soe I am some what humerous and yt becomes mee, well, follow mee follow, How I can playe the lord? parte, oh what a foole is my m r to Change his nobillitie for my worshipe. Roger Blud sir, or sir Stich you must goe in heres a folloinge wee must waite on you must wee tich: Blud Sr you must goe in, Oh hould me hould me I am Collericke whye ye shakeragge · had ye never a lord vnder yor gerdell plaine Sr Stch wt h out welt or gard, whie howe now You malipert knave haue ye forgott all good manners Roger: Good manners bee yor speede: Stich: whie this tis to keepe familliar serveingman, As I am a Lord by my honnor I sweare, I will revenge yt, wt h puttinge you out of my howse, you fellowes take example by his punishment, follow me iust 3 foote behind not aboue nor beneth and Roger Rackehell for yor sawsines come you last Exeunt</field>
      <field name="fulltext">[Act 4] Enter Edmond Ironside Alfricke Goodwine Ayleward wt h Edricus disguised:/ Edm: What winde doth Cause yor Mr writte to vs all is not well I doute give mee the Letter The Letter:/ Prepaire Perillus Bull to punish mee or some new never-hard of torteringe paine to scourge me for my foule ingratitude Rumor did rayse suspition in my harte as yt hath lately done wt hin yor brest by some whoe envied my prosperitie my love and zeale vnto your Maiestie that you were doutefull of my spotles truth and meant to cutt mee of by Cuttinge shorte my headles body wt h a bloody Axe This on a sodaine cominge to my eare yt payrd my harte and strooke me to the quicke causeinge me flee the Courte to save my life as sadly as the late espoused man greeves to De?te from his new maried wife [how manie sighes[s] I fetched at my Departe] [how manie tymes I turnd to Come againe] [how oft I plaind how often[ddid] I [weepe] did weepe] [were too too longe to writte or you to reade] [But haveinge now Considred wt h myself] [my ouer light beleefe to Credulous] I come againe like to a strayed sheepe tainted god watt wt h naught but ignorance oh take mee to yor mercye, or yf not soe kill mee yor self death is the eand of woe finis Letter Edm: Heare ye my lord? this humble suplicac?n yor mr is become an Orrator but tell him Edmond is not lunaticke soe like a woeman to be wonne wt h woordes Edricus. This Cottnes accordinge to my minde the kinge is angrie see hee faceth me his collour comes and goes, I hold my life hee knowes mee, would I wer well away Edmond: Harke yee my lords what would you saye yf yon plaine fellow should bee Edricus Alfrick: I thinke not soe my Lord Edmond./ Ile quickly knowe co?e hether fellow tell thy mr thus:/ he pulls of the velvet patch of his what Edricus ist you I thought noe lesse you ment some good noe dout tell me the troth what was the reason you Came this disguisde Edricus:/ Now witt or never helpe, poore naked trewth hath taine awaye svspic?n of decept I neede noe arte, Art cannot helpe mee now then plainly thus renowned soveraigne I came thus plainely to yor maiestye disguised in clownes attire to sound the truth what oppinion yf good or bad You had of me, And yf I found yt good I had determied to bewray myself yf otherwise, I meant wt h secret speede to leave my native cuntry and to exile myself from England sayleinge into Spaine whereas I meant in Contemplac?n in pilgramage and prayers for yor grace to end my life. Enter a messenger runinge Messenger:/ Hast, hast, kinge Edmund to releeve thie land which is opprest by multitudes of Daines they swarme alonge thy Cost? like little gnates ouer a river in a Summers night [or like to bees when they begine to flight] [soe Comes theis Daines prepared fitt to fight] Theire Battaile mane of Threescore Thowsand men wt h bristle poynted speeres wc h vpright stand [shewes like a new shred grove of Ashes tall] [or elce a wood of pines and seaders tall small] Theire flagges and Banners yellow, blew and red resembles much the weed? in ripened Corne Theire Drumes and Trumpitt? wt h a dredfull sound of Clashinge armor and fyer brethinge steedes soundes like the fearefull Thunder sent from heaven mixt wt h Æolus boystrous northen breth They praye vppon thie subiects cruelly like hungry Tygers vppon silley kidds sparinge not Ancient men for reverence nor weomen for imbisillitie nor guiltles babes for their vnspoted life nor holy men theire maddnes is so rise Edmund:/ A sunne shine Daye is quicly ouercaste a springeinge budd is killed wt h a blast I see my state is fickell and vnsure there is nothinge in this world can fermly Dure yet corage Lord? we were and are the same or hartes are sound or bodies are not lame then lett not fear dismay yor warlike might god fightes for vs, god will defend the right Bace Edricus thou wert the fatall Crowe that by thie hored voyce this newes did showe thou camst to gaine wt h Cursed trechery the surname of vild inckname polecye/ [Right did I thinke whenas the fox did preach] [he ment to gett a goose wt hin his reach] [right did I Gesse when wt h thie oylie speech] [thou didest my pardon and my grace beseech] some mischife was a Broch but god a boue Doth alwais at a pinch my patron proue And wee have now learnd though to or laile not to beleeve each smooth face forged taile Edricus: Now my most gracious Lord as god shall helpe mee my cominge was onely for this intente to vnfould Canutus cominge and bewraye matters of secret to yor maiestye Counsells of great availe rare stratagemes plotted by Canutus wc h now shall dye wt h mee yf you seeme anie whitt suspicious Edmund I prethy harke, lett mee heare some of them Edrius talketh wt h Edmund secretly Alfricke pulls him backe Alfricke:/ Traytor darst thou presume to speake vnto thie soveraign? good my Lord as god shall healpe mee you wilbee in trapt Edricus: Traytor? remember this. malice hath a ?fect memory Edmund: Alfrick you are to blame you doe forgett yorself age makes yee dote, know I not what to doe wt h out yor tellinge, goe too hold yor peace A[yleward:] [Alfrick yor Combe is cutt yet will I speake] kinge I am sworne to Counsell thee aright and though I dye, I will not hold my tongue remember hee hath often broke his faith and fled awaye from you remember too hee Comes from Canut? thie vtter enimie remember he is a traytorous flatterer, A villaine &amp; a dambned hipocrite Edmund: Peace Ayleward, hold yor tongue my youth in som thinges ouerrunes yor age tis pollecy to graunte him audience naye further grace, naye further yf hee Craues perhapes the leadinge or armye too for thus I thinke yt stand? hee hath promised Canutus haveinge the leadinge of or forces to yeald to him seeminge as though compeld haveinge first givene an onsett on the foe for cullor s sake but wee will ouer match him for whilst the force of Canute on pollecye retyres by Edrick? drift, then wee will take the oppertunitie and rush wt h speed vppon his troopes whoe vnprepared to fight [and trustinge vppon Edrick? pollecye] shall all come pray vnto or souldior s how like you this: Alfrick: It cannot hape amis Edmund: Come hether Edricus: they whisper Edm. saith: I faith ye lye they whisper againe Tut, tut, yt cannot bee they whisper againe If this bee trew I pardon thee for all and will reward thee wt h diservd grace I will not dout yt, faith I think tis trew though yt weare not in hope thou wilt amend goe lett vs in and lett all quarrells end for now I meane indeed to Creditt thee by beinge captaine generall of my armie Edricus:/ Dutie and thankes I give tis all I have See what dessemulac?n bringes to passe howe quicly I Cann make the kinge an asse Exeunt· Enter Emma her Two sonnes Alphred and Edward in each hand Gunthranus goeinge before Emma: Sweete Boyes borne to be crost before yor tyme[s] oh lett mee kisse you ere you goe awaye curst bee the Cavse of [y]or departinge thus the ?sicution of theis bloody daines whose vnrelentinge eies delight to see the full conclusion of or tradegie Alphred:/ Good mothe sorrow not though wee de?te wee shalbee welcome to or vncle Richard and saffer there then in this trobled Ile wc h like the reelinge sea is tost wt h warr heere wee are ever in continuall broyles there in tranquillitie in peace and rest heere in the midest of vnknowne enimies there in the armes of true approved frind? here danger eminent doth Compasse vs there frinds and frindly Counsell shall defend vs Therefore reioyce wee are escaped the Daines whose greedy mawes devoures the Saxons blood like hungry lions, voyd of anie good Emma: Good boye in whome thie fathers feature lives though death hath seazd him in his wastefull armes if I could moderate my greeved minde wt hout remembrance what ere now I was then should my greefe deminish wt h my teares But memory the afflictor of the soule bides me remember how I was a Queene how Egelredus was my lawfull Lord how Normands Duke was my renowned syre how Englande was my pleasures paradice and how tyme was when tyme did waite on mee All theis are but Bellowes to the fyer to burne my harte, consumed afore wt h sighthes Alphred, Need is a childe thou arte of age to take example by my myserye not to beleve foule fortunes flatterye ward·/ Good mother weepe not, yf yee doe Ile crye Emma:/ Ah my prittie harte hast thou a feeleinge of my passion? then will I weepe the more to ease my harte Ile morne for thee, for him and for my self for England and for Edmund Ironside whose ?te god prosper, Heaven defend the right Gun: Madam yor healpeles teares are but a meanes to drawe more teares from vs to drowne or hartes Emma: Whie man I wep«e» to ease and not to load I trowe the more I shed, the lesse I have and as my teares wast soe my cares consume To dam my [harte] eies were bvt to drowne my harte like Hecuba the wofull Queene of Troye whoe haveinge noe avoydance for her grefe Rann madd for sorrow cause shee could not weepe But good Gunthranus to omit vaine talke sence I have heretofore aproved thy faith I make a Choyce of thee amongest the rest of manie frindes to guide my little Boyes and to conduct them into Normandye intreat my brother for to intreat them well they are his Nephewes and his sisters ioye if anie thinge amis should light on them the same on mee should bee redobled Gunthra: Madam even by the liveinge god I vowe I will attend and watch them as my soule knowinge duke Richard will accompt of them as nigh of blood unto his Royall self Emma:/ Then farwell boyes the Comofrt of my life they offer to de?te Yet Come againe yee shall not soe departe if that wee dye weile Choose to dye to geither. dyeinge or liveing wee wilbee to geither fonde woeman blesse them and then lett them goe that is the saffest waye to keepe them safe Then farwell once againe, god blesse you both they offer to de?te But Softe awhile I have not sayd my minde first lett me wash your face in mothers teares then sobb out sighthes to overload the earth [and cast a mistie fogge uppon the [w]ayre] Shee imbraceth them [that noe inquireinge foe may find you out] oh lett yor sanctuary bee my lappe She sitt? downe and settinge Edward on her knee a Alphred in her arme yor refuge, yor sepulchers, and your graves a Cradle fitt? you better then a shippe Gunthra: See see Dame Naturs operac?n what force yt breedes wt hin a mothers mind none feeles a mothes sorrow but a mother This Queene hath not her peere vppon [h]the earth for wisdome suffringe and for patience for Cloakeinge sorrow a desemblinge greefe and beareinge all thinges wt h a Constant minde yt can shee not conceale affection soe but that yt breaketh forth like hidden fyer Emma rise«t» Emma:/ ffye, fye, hid Natures found indulgencye de?te sweet Boyes, god keepe you in yor waye they offer Come hether Aphred, Ned I prethe staye I will goe wt h you to the foaminge haven and take my farwell of my darlinges there exeunt omnes Enter Canutus with a Letter in his hand and wt h him: Vskataulfe: Swethoe: Southampton: Archbishope of Caunterbury: Egina: wt h souldiers. Canutus:/ Coradge brave Captaines Conquest is at hand this letter comes from trustie Edricus and certifies mee that hee is in grace wt h Edmund Ironsid, and howe hee lead? the vantgarde of the princes armye now he assures mee of the victorye wt hout the losse of manie souldiors [for hee will disapoynt the warlike youth] [and flee to vs, leaveinge him desolate] where fore brave souldiors put forth all yor might to quaile theire stomaches at the first approch hee that doth take the prince in fight or flight shall have his ransome and dubd a knight 1 Soul: Ile venter hard to make Ioane my wif a Ladye 2 Soul: The king shall scape my fingers narrowly 3 Soul: Masse if I had steele sides as hee hath Ironsides I would gore him thim that I would 4 Soul: What yf misse the kinge, Ile have a Duke an Earle a Lord, a knight, or gentleman South: Or noebody and then youle hitt yt tell not yor chickens sires, ere they bee hatched perchaunce the egges are rotten in the nest then all yor broodinge hopes is cast awaye and you remaine as rich as new shorne sheepe I never loved to gaine by trechery for that againe was lost by trechery I doe remember hardy Hanniball: did vse theis woord? at wonne Tarentums losse Eadem arte qua prius cœpimus Tarentum amisimus ffraud woone Tarentum ffraud Tarentum lost soe Hanniball reapes his labor for his Cost The dru?s sound afar off Canutus: Soe Edmund so thou Comste vnto thie cost thy roreinge dru?e persageth thy mishape ringinge thie soules knell wt h a hollow voyce as thine doth mourne soe lett or Dru?e reioyce The Dru?e[s] sound Enter Edmond wt h Edricus other Lord? and souldiers they fight Canutus gives et exeunt Enter at one dore Canutus and at th'other Edricus «t»us:/ Edricus ricus/ My Lord: hye Cheere yor flyeinge troopes and bid them stay awhile for victory whenas you see mee lead my men aloofe then take occac?n and assaile the prince and Ile be absent when hee need? mee most and present for yor best availe, make hast Canutus:/ How much I love thee Edricus heavens doe knowe and I wt h guiftes one day will manifest Exit Canute Edricus./ Soe Edrick now thie plotforme is afoote and one shall dye yt skills noe matter wc h yf Edmund, Canute shall quickly follow him yf Canute, then Edmond shall not staye behinde whilst they wt h eger blowes assaile each other I heere remaine a newter free from feare not takeinge ?te wt h Canute nor Ironside before I see whoe gett? the victory Yet had I rather have Canutus Conquer and privilye will aid him wt h supplies rather then Edmund should escape the feild Alarum Enter Edmund chaseinge of Canutus Edricus backes Canutus Edmund flies: exeunt: and returne. Canutus wt h Edricus Canutus: Thanckes worthie Edricke for this victory this daye had made an end of me and mine hadst Thou not backed vs wt h thie warlike troopes know ye yf Edmond be escaped or noe? Edricus:/ Edmund is gon and I must after him to staye longe heere would breed suspition then mightie Canute live longe a Conquerer and when thou hast the Crowne remember mee Canutus:/ yf I forgett thee, god forgett my suite when like a sinner I doe humbly praye forgett the Edricke god aboue doth see how good a harte I ever bore to thee Edricus:/ Then noble Canutus, I pawne a souldiors faith by my best blood, and by my after hopes I will remaine to thee and to thy heires as trew, as falce to Edmund Ironside Lett vs not linger heere muster yor men and make them reddy for a new assault I will to Edmund and excuse my self and how I served him now Ile serve him then: exeunt</field>
      <field name="fulltext">Act 5 Enter Edmund Ironside Alfricke Vlfkettle Goodwine wt h others:/ Edmund: Vild Edricus all this proceed? from him I saved his life and hee doth thirst for mine vngratefull wretch, hellish incarnat divell [for sure noe man was ever soe vnkind] [vnto his kinge and loveinge Cuntryemen] disloyall and vnfaithfull Sicophant yt greeves my vexed soule to thinke on thee Alfricke:/ Lett yt not greeve you, rather ioye to thinke you are escaped from the hand? of him that sought like Iudas to betraye his Lord into the hand? of blood thirstye Daines Vlfkettle:/ Surely my Lord you are highly favord of god whoe sees each humaine acc?n that hee hath given you warninge wt h small losse of the contagious minde of Edricus:/ Enter Edricus wt h his hand in a skarfe, haultinge, with him Stich Stich:/ Mr I would not wishe you haulte Edricus:/ Whie soe Stich:/ Marry sir you know Alfricke is a cripple and the proverbe is tis ill haultinge before a cripple Heele perceve yt. Edricus had hee as manie bird? as Iunos birde or could peirce milstons wt h his searchinge sight hee (by his leave) should not my haultinge find I haulte not in the Thigh but in the mind All haile vnto my gracious Soveraigne Stich: Mr youle beraye yor self, doe you saye all haile, and yett beare yor arme in a Scarfe that? haile indeed Edricus:/ All haile vnto my gracious soueraigne [Edmund:/ Iudas thie next ?te is to kisse my Cheeke] [and then Co?itt mee vnto Cayphas:/] [Edricus:/ I vnderstand not what yor highnes meanes] Edmund:/ Oh heavens, oh impudent vngodly wretch Edricus:/ I hope yor grace doth not exclaine on mee Edmund:/ On thee, hence graceless wretch, grace mee noe more is there none heere that will laye hould on him? his sight, his breth, his fell infectious tongue is venumer then is the Basiliskes Edricus:/ Is this a [gerdion] guerdion for my skarrs and hurtes for all my bruses and my broken ioyntes Is this a hier for my hardines and valliant onsett on the enimies? are theis my wages wc h I woone wt h blood [blood of my self, and prowdest daine that fought] doth Edmund thus reward his followers that pawne theire lives for him and in his Cause then bootlesse haue I skirmished soe longe and sent soe many daines vnto theire graves [In vaine haue I lift vppe my wastinge arme] [and brandished my fawchion ore thie foes] [In vaine this curtelax was reared aloft] [wc h made a laine throughout thie foemens troopes] In vaine, my launce did ou'throw and spoyle Invaine I live to bee requited thus Stich:/ In vaine, what a vaine, vaine my Mr is in Edmund:/ Didst thou not flye vild traytor to my foe? Edricus:/ Whoe I? «Edmun»d:/ Even thou Edricus:/ Thus forward frindes are quited wt h suspect thus envye blast? the well deservinge wight thus the vnskillfull blames the warrour [thus thus Detracc?n hinders vertuous course] fleed I my Lord Canutus can reporte twas hee that should have fleed had succor Come [fleed I my Lord? yor eies were witnesses] [how farr my harte was free from Dastard flight] But this yt is to bee a man at armes when his desert is recompenced wt h hate and resoluc?n wrongd wt h ignorance for shame my Lord? spurne not against the trouth Thirst not to drinck the blood of inocent? Edmund:/ Whie Edricus canst thou denie thie flight Edricus:/ Noe gracious Lord I must confesse I fled forcd from Canutus not to him for aid and that tis true, I by yor graces leave will prove on him that dares affer?e a noe Edmund:/ I sawe thee flee myself wt h theis my eyes Vlfk: And I my Lord am witnes to the same Alf: [Goodw:] And I my Lord will proue yt by yor favor Edricus:/ I would the kinge would give mee leave [the] to speake Stich:/ And you will prove them blind I hould my life Edmund:/ I give the leave, speake for thyself and spare not Edricus:/ Seeinge yor grace soe forward to the fight vewinge the Daine to march soe [[illeg.]] bravely on prickd forth wt h shame I as the foremost man [(not suffringe the Daine to sett on vs] [or to approch yor grace wt h out a blowe)] stept forth intendinge to incounter them and to assaile the rereward wt h my band till you vppon the fore front held them playe But see how good intent? are ever thwarted ere I could gett the wind to Compasse them yor Dru?es reteate did Cause yor forces flee yet fleed not I a foote vntell such tyme as quight bereft of hope I was compeld witnes this arme this serviceable arme that in dispite of death did save my life witnes theis skares wc h yf yor grace will see theile tell my foes vnto theire face they lye. Stich:/ Oh horrible skarres, skares like blaseinge stares, well counterfeyted Master Edmund:/ yf this bee trew I was to Credulous Edricus: If yt bee true my Lord? assure yor self your grace was misinformd if otherwise and that my man can veryfie Stich:/ Take heed what ye saye Mr I can veryfie n thinge marry I can veryly anie thinge. yf youle saye soe Ile sweare [soe] to yt, [tth] that tis falce Imeane Edmu: Then Edricus twas I that wronged thee and I that will in all thinges make amen burye vnkines in oblivion and nere remember or suspition Edric? Twas not yor highnes but some fawninge mate that put mistrust in to yor graces head hopeinge by my dowfall to raise himself but heavens defend the wronged innocent Edmund:/ Lett this suffice thou hast confirmd or love and Edric? wee mind to honnor thee wt h publique notice of thie Loyaltie Edricus: See, See what witt and will can bringe aboute Canut? paies mee for my villaie and Edmund loves mee for my trecherye Stich:/ Give a man luck and cast him over the gallous exeunt omnes Enter Canutus readinge of letter wt h him Southampton Arch: of Canterburye Egina Vskataulf &amp; Swetho: wt h souldiers Canut?:/ My lorde my harte is firmly bond to you and I am prest to doe you anye seruyce But Edmund is growne strange to me of late and I am not familliar wt h his thougtes when I haue onc regaind oppinion I will not fayle to bee your faithfull agent In meane tyme make yee stronge to hould him playe for hee is cominge wt h a mightie power. Bireladye this goes hard, theis newes are naught is Edmund now growne wary, then I doute I nere shall see the daye I longe haue sought But I must beare a semblance of good newes least theis ?ceave our hopes to faulter and that would cleane discorage all theire hartes for all presume on Edrics pollecy: South: So?e ist good newes Canut?: My Lord exceedinge good Egina: Give me the Letter Canut?: Not for all the world I dare not trust myself wt h readeinge yt least I orecloyd wt h ioye should playe the blabe Lett this suffice I now am Confident [vppon sure grounded confirmac?ns] that Edmund is my owne, hee writtes to mee that hee is cominge wt h a mightie host but (saith hee) bee not you discomfited for were they millions, half should fight for you and turne their weapons vppon Ironside South: Tis strange the prince should bee soe Credulous The Dru?e soundes a far off Canut?. Yon Dru?e doth tell vs Edmund Ironside vnwittinge of his overthrough at hand comes gallantly attended on by troopes of horse and footemen to his funerall Oh that thou knewst thy dyeinge daye soe nigh hat thou mightest make the fitt to goe to god n faith yt greeves at the very harte o see him Come soe vnprepaird for death Enter Edmund, Emma, Arch: Yorke Edricus, Alfricke, Goodwine Ayleward Vlfkettle, Leofricke, and Turkillus Edmund: Behold where Canute: comes marchinge bravely on me thinkes yon sight would make a sickeman sound They march a longe the stage one an other «E»dmund: Canutus Canut?: Edmund Edmund: The ground thou standst vppon is Ironsides Canut?: The ground I stand on Edmund is myne owne fallen to mee not svccessively indeed but by forfeyture as Coppie hold rentrunn and wantinge reperac?ns falls to the Lord, Even soe thie ffathers Land for want of Trybute payeinge longe sence Due I Cease vppon as Lord to thee and that Edmu: But for thou shalt perceave that Edmund cann temper the vnrvlye stomach of his rage and moderate his lustie youthfull bloode wc h springes through every vayne to flye at thee Not half theis word? wt hout controleinge strokes should from thie lipes have vomited theire spleene [Oh how my harte beates muchadoe I have] [to make yt quiet tell I answer thee] [Art thou the Lord of me and of my Land] vncivell Canutus knowest thou to whome thou speakest? This harte skornes all subiecc?n and this head lookes 'ore the world, theis feete were made to tread ore kinges, Canutus over thee Nay storme not Canutus, learne how to mix thie speech wt h more beseemeinge tearmes, and gouern thou thie surly tearmes wt h reason not wt h rage I saye I am a kinge, soe arte not thou therefore I am thie better, I saye more I have a kingdome, this I stand vppon is mine, Thou standst vppon my ground I saye this Land is mine, Canutus yt is mine: Canut?: By vsurpac?n thine, by Conquest mine whoe knowes not conquest is inheritage Edmund: Soe rape and theft is true possessio yf malifactors goe vnpunnished Canut?: It seems indeed possession is of force for by possession you wt h hould my Crowne Edmund: Nay [Swaine and] you and Swaine yor griple minded Dad by treason not by force of valliant armes against all iustice, Lawe and equitie did first intrude yor selves, and then extrude or woefull subiectes from theire native home and that I Come to proue and there fore thus: he drawe«t» Canut?:/ Then to confute thie forged argument thus argue I, my sword is Resons proofe Hee Dr Edmund: That is of force to put backe reasons proofe wc h proues you like yor sword vnreasonable They trayne theire souldio the stage Edricus speake Edricus: Edmund is stronge, Canute is weake in p«o» Edmund gracious in the peoples eies Canutus is not soe, what had I best to doe [faine would I haue Canutus wine and hee is wea] [I would haue Edmund loose and hee is stronge ] oh gracious starrs in spire my nimble witt wt h some device, and as I ever have I will imploye yt to some villanie soft, lett mee see, oh it is exelent [fountaine of witt, the springe of pollecye ] [the flower of treason, and of villanie ] how much vndecent is yt that this cappe this homely Cape, should overload this Crowe when thou deservest a Crowne of beaten gold [but to the matter soe yt needes must fadge] [for can I bringe them to a single fight] hosoever hath the better yett shall I be gracious in his eie, as whoe should saye I was the Causer of his victory besides I shall insinuate my self into the bosome of opinion and beestemed my cuntries buckler well Ile about it. meaninge noe m? good but that my speech may sheed kinge Edmunds blood The Armies make towards one an other when Edricus standinge betwene sayeth Edricus: Renowned Edmond first I speake to thee lett theis my woord? proceedinge from true zeale begg at thy eares a little audience And worthie Canut? sheath vp thy slaughtringe sword tell I have spoke my mind that all may see my word? proceede from perfect pietie Edmond:/ Edricus bee breefe Canut?: Goe toe Ile staye a little, but be not tedious Alfricke:/ When the fox preaches then beware the geese Edricus: What strive you for Imperious Ironside? Renowned Canut? what doe you levell at? wee daylie to appease yor mortall warrs offer or slaughtred bodies to the sword yet neither of you haue the vpper hande [to daye hee that was foyld to morrow foyles] [Hee that even now did faintly sound retreate] [renewes againe the fight wt h doble force] [thus in quadryes hanges the victory] [and waveringe fortune frownes and smiles on both] Canut? is not to bee overcome because his Brother Swaine doth succor him and Edmond likewise is invinceable for force and vallour hewes him through his foes what then is thend, of this yor enles grudge none other but when all yor men bee slaine you then must fight alone or els accord and hee that then is kinge shall rule noe me? [nor governe nations, for consumeinge warr] [will quite devoure this solatary Ile] [not leaveinge anie over whome to rule] [r to resist forraine invac?ns] [yf love of kingedomes bee the cause of this] [supprese the boyleinge of yor haughtie mindes] [you haue approved yor souldiers forwardnesse] Then now at last shake hand? and ioyne in league agree like noble kinges and ?te the Land have now compassion of this little Ile whose soyle is manurd wt h Carkasses and made a sea wt h bloode of inocent? But yf yor emulac?n bee soe greate that either skornes to have competitors [and Brooke not equalls in yor d g dignities] fight then alone that would bee king? alone lett not all perish for the wills of Twoe but Lett yor sword? decid whose tytles best Edmond: Edricke thou hitst the marke I levell at thy Counsell cominge from a zelous harte fitt? in all poynt? our expectac?n Knowe I accept thereof, and offer heere to prove even hand in single fight wc h of vs Twoe shall weare the Diadem Canut?: Edmund Reporte shall never whett her tongue vppon Canut? to eternize thee I skorne to staine my reputac?n wt h abiect tytles of pale Cowardice to make the famous in opinions mouth I heere accept thie challenge and his speech glad of so fitt a tyme to bee revengd for all those foule dishonnors thou hast done [and glad for spareinge of that guiltles bloode] [wc h in or quarrells this daye had bine shed] Oh had this daye bine but a yeare agoe manie a tall man had bine now alive manie a salt teare had bine now vnshed by fathers for theire so?es vnhappie Deathes by mothers for theire Childrens wretched end? and widdowes for their husband? tyneles want But I am glad this longe expected hower at laste is Come Egina:/ My Lord you shall not fight Canut?:/ My Lady but I will, will you fight for me? give her my sword and sheild:/ Edm: and Emma talkes togeither, Edm: turnes a Emma:/ Yet heare mee good my Lord will you on whome the state doth sole depend or welfare, all the Realmes, yor frind? and kinsfolke hazard the lose of all vppon the Chaunce of fickell fortune, sence the better m? is soner killd by over hardinesse then an advised cowarde good my Lord yt is vndecent you should fight wt h him beinge noe kinge nor haveinge ought to loos«e» Edmond:/ Madam his life is even to him as deere as mine to mee, besides hee is a prince of noble blood and high resolved spritt and yf hee weare not, yet my Cause beinge «g» and Iustice on my side I would not feare [nay could not wt h my honnor but accept ] [the speech of Edricke and in single fight ] [approve my tytle lawfull good a right ] Then madam be content and you shall see the god in whome I trust will svccor mee [were hee Golias, I the little kinge ] [I would not feare, him on his knees to bringe ] [But hee hath rather Cause to doute of mee ] [I beinge bigge, and far more stronge then hee ] Egina talkes wt h Canut?, Canut? turnes away Canut?:/ I had rather fight wt h him then skould wt h you Egina:/ I cannot speake but straight you saye I skould Canut?:/ Then sweetinge you must learne yor tongue to hould nay now youle blubber 'goe too take this kisse and pray for mee, whie staye you Ironside Edmond: Beecause I thinke thou art not fitt to Dye but rather with Egina fitt to crye My Lord? I do Comaund you for yor lives none bee soe hardy as to svccor me or to approch vs eare the fight bee done but yf I dye to make my sepulcher even in the place where as I tooke my death settinge my Crowne vppon Canut? head and doe to him as to yor soueraigne Canut?: Even soe brave followers I will you doe to Edmond heere, yf Edmund Conquer mee sound Dru?s and Trumpitt? wt h yor warlike noyes either begine my ioye, or end my ioyes The Trumpitt? sound the Armies doe Compasse the Twoe king? in the middest, they fight Canut?: Staye: hould thie hand I prethee breth a while Edmond: Not tell thou yealdst or dies. Edm: drives: Canut? about Canut?: Staye Edm: tis not for I feare thie fortitud That thus I crave thee stay, but that I wante the vse of breth to prosecute the fight Edmond:/ Then breath awhile, I giv the leave torest Edrcus:/ I feeare Canut? wilbee ouercome then shall I wish my tongue the Cause thereof had bine cutt out when yt begane to speake for I desire to Drinke kinge Edmund? blood because hee ever sought to doe mee good South: Egina bee content I warrant you I Canut? will doe well inough «E»gina:/ I feare him much «E»dmond What are yee reddy Canut?: I to bee thie death they fight againe Edm: driues Canut? backe about the Stage anut?: Stay Edmond staye Canut? yeald? to thee icus: what will he bace'ly yeald the divell fore fend nut?: Take wc h of theis thou wilt my hand or sword my hand bringes frendshipe ferme immoveable my sword bringes enmitie irrivocable mond: Brave Canutus in yealdinge thou hast wone that wc h thie sword could never doe thy tongue hath brought to passe by gentle speech Canut? take my hand, heere lyes my sword Emond is thine, his thine, himself and all now lett vs strive whoe shall demerrit best by mutuall kindnes whoe shall be termd afrind anut?:/ How plesant are theis speeches to my eares Æolian musicke to my daunceinge harte Ambrosian dainties to my starved mawe [sweete passinge Nectar to my thirstie throate] [rare Culleasses to my sicke glvtted mide] [Refreshinge oyntment? to my wearied Limbes] and heavenly phisicke to my earth sicke soule wc h erst was surfited wt h woe and warr Edmond: Lett mee imbrace the warr begotten frinde They imbr«a» god graunte as broth«r»s wee may longe embrace and sweete Egina for thie husband? sake in signe of Love this kisse from Edmond take: Edm: kisses Eg But Lord? whie stand you still greeve you to see Canut? and your kinge soe well agree Alfricke:/ The inward sollace wc h or hartes conseave to see peace growe where foule debate was sowne to see sweete concord springe from Discord? wombe to see warr bringe forth love and amitye to see Two mortall foes prove faithfull frind? and Mars drincke milke in stead of purple blood doth force or tongues or hartes Cheife orrators to shewe wt h silence ioye vnspeake able yet Lord? behold even as you doe imbrace soe in dumbe shewes wee all vnite or hartes the Lord? imbrace Turkill?: Remember Leofricke or Childrens losse Leofricke: Turkillus I doe and must serve the tyme and waite vppon occasion for revenge a daye of mirth begines a woefull yeare as suddaine stormes doe follow sunne shine Cleare Edmond:/ Nowe noble Lords lett vs like frind? Consult vppon partic?n of this noble Ile yor self shall Choose wc h ?te you thinke is best the East or west, the Right hand or the left my Courte is yor s my Counsellers are yours my frindes yor frindes, thie foe my Enimie my people yor s my treasure and my self all are yor owne, for you shall all co?aund Canutus: Thankes noble brother and my second self in all thy art? thou dost excell thie self foule shame on them that are thie enimies and vengance light on them that thinke the ill Edricus:/ Bloode, Death and vengance light on both of Edmond./ Goe vnto or Cost? and feast vs there and there conclude an ever lastinge pea Sound Dru?es and Trumpitt? heere end? «w» thus hand in hand and harte in harte «w» Edricus:/ And I for one tis meete yt should bee «s» thus wise men can desemble what they th and till occa?on fitt? them sleepeinge win But I have sworne and I will keepe my vo by heaven Ile bee revengd on both of you They goe hande in hand out off th Edricus leadeinge the Dru?e Finis</field>
   </doc>
</add>