<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add>
   <doc>
      <field name="author_display">Oxford University Press</field>
      <field name="author_facet">Oxford University Press</field>
      <field name="author_sort_facet">oxford university press</field>
      <field name="author_text">Oxford University Press</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">20th Century</field>
      <field name="composition_era_facet">1970's</field>
      <field name="content_model_facet">text</field>
      <field name="content_type_facet">TEI</field>
      <field name="datafile_name_display">/FedoraRepo/text/chadwyck_evd/uvaGenText/tei/chevd_V1.0927.xml</field>
      <field name="date_indexed_facet">201909240354</field>
      <field name="date_text">1974</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">UVa Text Collection</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_facet">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="digital_collection_text">Chadwyck-Healey English Verse Drama</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Document</field>
      <field name="format_facet">Online</field>
      <field name="id">uva-lib:459557</field>
      <field name="language_facet">English</field>
      <field name="main_title_display">The Last Supper ; the Betrayal of Christ ; - The Bakers [Chester</field>
      <field name="repository_address_display">http://fedora-prod01.lib.virginia.edu:8080/fedora/get</field>
      <field name="shadowed_location_facet">VISIBLE</field>
      <field name="source_facet">Digital Library</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">English drama -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_facet">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="subject_text">English drama -- 20th century</field>
      <field name="subject_text">Verse drama, English</field>
      <field name="title_display">The Last Supper ; the Betrayal of Christ ; - The Bakers [Chester</field>
      <field name="title_facet">last supper the betrayal of christ</field>
      <field name="title_sort_facet">last supper the betrayal of christ</field>
      <field name="title_text">The Last Supper ; the Betrayal of Christ ; - The Bakers [Chester</field>
      <field name="year_display">1974</field>
      <field name="year_facet">1974</field>
      <field name="year_multisort_i">1974</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE adminmeta</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/admin/adminmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459557&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;access&gt;viva&lt;/access&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/policy&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminrights&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;character encoding="UTF-8"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;encoding label="xml" version="1.0"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;base label="TEI.2" type="DTD" version="P4" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.dtd" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;localmodification label="TEI.extensions.ent" href="http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/base&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/markup&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/text&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/technical&gt;</field>
      <field name="admin_meta_file_display">&lt;/adminmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;!DOCTYPE descmeta</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/descmeta/descmeta.dtd"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;pid&gt;uva-lib:459557&lt;/pid&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;form scheme="uva-form"&gt;monograph&lt;/form&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/mediatype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayAgent/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortAgent/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayTitle&gt;The Last Supper ; the Betrayal of Christ ; - The Bakers [Chester&lt;/displayTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortTitle&gt;last supper the betrayal of christ&lt;/sortTitle&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;displayDate&gt;1974&lt;/displayDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;sortDate&gt;1974&lt;/sortDate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/presentation&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Last Supper ; the Betrayal of Christ&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;- The Bakers [Chester]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;New York, Toronto&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Oxford University Press&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="publication"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1974&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Virgo ID"&gt;3873608-1001&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;identifier type="UVa Title Control Number"&gt;chv10927&lt;/identifier&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;authority scheme="http://www.loca.gov/standards/iso639-2/"&gt;ISO 639-2&lt;/authority&gt;eng&lt;/language&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;English drama -- 20th century&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;subject scheme="LCSH"&gt;Verse drama, English&lt;/subject&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;timeinterval&gt;20th century&lt;/timeinterval&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/covtime&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mediatype type="text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;mimetype&gt;text/xml&lt;/mimetype&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="main"&gt;The Last Supper ; the Betrayal of Christ&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;title type="sub"&gt;- The Bakers [Chester]&lt;/title&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;geogname&gt;Cambridge, England&lt;/geogname&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/place&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;agent type="provider" form="corpname" role="publisher"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;name&gt;Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.&lt;/name&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/agent&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;time type="creation"&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;date&gt;1995&lt;/date&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/time&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="copyright"&gt;Copyright©1995 Chadwyck-Healey Inc.&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;rights type="access"&gt;Accessible to VIVA community only&lt;/rights&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;physdesc type="extent"&gt;ca. 28 kilobytes&lt;/physdesc&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries omitted.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Medieval verse drama.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Preliminaries, introductory and editorial matter omitted&lt;lb/&gt;The following plays have been taken from this source:&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Copyright (c) 1974 Early English Text Society. This text may not be reproduced, except for fair dealing purposes, without the express permission of Chadwyck-Healey and the copyright holder.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Title: The last supper.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Genre: English mystery and miracle plays.</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first published: 1475 ?</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">Date first performed: 1377–1382 ?&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;description type="note"&gt;Square brackets represent sections of text which have been deleted or added at different stages in the evolution of the manuscript.&lt;/description&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/surrogate&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="UVA-LIB-Text"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;set code="CH-EnglVerseDrama"/&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/relationships&gt;</field>
      <field name="desc_meta_file_display">&lt;/descmeta&gt;</field>
      <field name="fulltext">THE BAKERS PLAYE Pagina Decima Quinta: De Caena Domini et de eius Proditione</field>
      <field name="fulltext">JESUS Brethren all, to me right deare, come hither to me and ye shall here. The feaste of Easter you knowe draweth neare and nowe yt is at hand. That feaste needes keepe must we with verye great solempnitie. The pascall lambe eaten must bee as the lawe doth commande. Therfore, Peter, looke that thou goe, and John with thee shalbe alsoe. Prepare all thinges that longeth therto acordinge to the lawe. PETRUS Lord, thy biddinges doe will we. But tell us first where yt shalbe and we shall doe yt speedelye, and thidder will we drawe. JESUS Goe into the cittie which yee doe see, and there a man meete shall yee with a water pott that beareth hee, for so you may him knowe. Into what house that hee shall goe, into the same [howse] enter ye alsoe and saye the maister send you too his message for to shewe. Saye ‘The maister to thee us sent to have a place convenient the pascall lambe to eate.’ There is my entent, with my disciples all. A fayre parlour hee will you shewe. There prepare all thinge dewe where I with my retynewe fulfill the lawe we shall. PETRUS All readye, lorde. Even thy will shortlye we two shall fulfill, and the fayre cittie we shall goe tyll as fast as we maye. Tunc Petrus et Johannis ibunt ac hominem vas aquae testaceum portantem alloquerentur. PETRUS All hayle, good fellowe, hartelye. To thy maisters house I praye thee hye; and wee must keepe thee companye our message for to saye. SERVUS Come on your waye and followe mee; my maisters house soone shall you see. Loe, here yt is, verelye. Saye nowe what yee will. Tunc domum intrant. PETRUS Syr, the maister saluteth thee and as messingers send we bee. Therfore we praye thee hartelye take heede us untill. The maister hath sent us to thee. A place preparde for him must bee; the pascall lambe there eate will hee with his disciples all. PATER FAMILIUS Loe, here a parloure all readye dight with paved flores and windowes bright. Make all thinges readye as you thinke right, and this have you shall. JOHANNIS Nowe, brother Peter, lett us hye the pascall lambe to make readye; and to our maister then will you and I as fast as we maye. Tunc adornent mensam et revertunt. PETRUS Thy commandment, lord, donne have wee. The pascall lambe is made readye. Therfore come on and you shall see, and we shall lead the waye. JESUS Nowe, brethren, goe to your seate; this pascall lambe nowe lett us eate, and then we shall of other thinges entreate that be of greater effecte. For knowe you nowe, the tyme is come that sygnes and shadowes be all donne. Therfore, make haste, that we maye soone all figures cleane rejecte. For nowe a newe lawe I will beginne to helpe mankynd owt of his sinne soe that hee may heaven wynne, the which for synne hee loste. And here, in presence of you all, another sacrifice beginne I shall, to bringe mankynd out of his thrall, for helpe him neade I muste. Tunc accumbet Jesus ac Johannis in gremio dormit. Brethren, I tell you bye and bye, with greate desyre desyred have I this Passeover to eate with you trulye before my Passion. For I saye to you syckerlye, my Fathers will allmightye I must fullfill meekelye, and ever to be bowne. Tunc Jesus accipiet panem, frangit, et discipulis suis dat, dicens: This bread I give here my blessinge. Takes, eate, brethren, at my byddinge, for, leeve you well, withowt leasinge, this is my bodye that shall dye for all mankynde in remission of there synne. This give I you on me to mynd aye after evermore. Tunc accipit calicem in manibus, oculis elevatis, dicens: Father of heaven, I thanke thee for all that ever thou doest to mee. Brethren, takes this with hart free; that is my blood that shalbe shedd on the tree. For more together drinke not wee in heaven-blys tyll that we bee to tast that ghostly foode. Tunc edit et bibit cum discipulis, et Judas Iscarioth habebit manum in patina. Brethren, forsooth I you saye, one of you shall me betraye that eatethe here with me todaye in this companye. PETRUS Alas, alas and weale-awaye! Whoe that may be, knowe I nay maye— for I yt is not, in good faye, that shall doe such anoye. ANDREAS Hard yt is for us all to whom this case shall befall. We be but twelve within this hall— lord, tell yf yt be I. JACOBUS Sorrowfull for these wordes be wee. Who ys yt? I cannot see. If this case shall fall to mee, lord, tell mee hastelye. Tunc Judas intingit in patinam. JESUS Through his deceipte I am but dead that in my cuppe weetes his bread. Mych woe for his wicked read that wretch must thole iwys. Well were him had hee binne unborne, for bodye and soule hee is forlorne that falselye soe hath donne beforne and yett in will hee ys. JUDAS Leeffe maister, ys yt not I that shall doe thee this villanye? JESUS Thou hast read, Judas, redealye, for sycker thou arte hee. That thou shalt doe, doe hastelye. JUDAS Farewell, all this companye, for on an errand I must hye; undonne hit may not bee. JESUS Brethren, take up this meate anon; to another worke we must gonne. Your feete shall washen be eychone to shewe all charitie. And first myselfe I wyll begynne and washe you all that be herein, one thys deede that you may mynne and meeker for to bee. Tunc Jesus precinget corpus lintheolo. PETRUS A, lord, shalt thou washe my feete? JESUS That doe I, Peeter, I thee beheight. The while more thou shalt not wytt, but thou shalt afterwarde. PETRUS Naye, lord, forsooth in no manere my feete shalt thou not washe here! JESUS But I washe thee, withowten were of joye gettes thou noe parte. PETRUS Naye, lord, my feete may well be layde; but wash my handes and my head. JESUS All ys cleane. Therfore doe I read thy feete shall washen bee and you cleane—but not all. PETRUS Lord, of wayle thou arte the wall, and, though yt not well befall, have here my feete to thee. Tunc lavabit pedes omnium singulatim et abstergit lintheo. JESUS My deare brethren, well wytt yee that lord and maister you call mee; and well you saye as should bee— I am, and have binne yore. Syth I have washen your feete here— lord and maister, in meeke manere— doe eychon to other in fere as I have done before. Tunc invicem omnes aliorum pedes lavant. My litle children and my brethren free, little while maye I with you bee, but thidder shall you not goe with mee as I am nowe in waye. But this soothly my biddinge: you love together in all thinge as I before, withowt fletchinge, have loved you trulye aye. Soe all men may knowe and see my disciples that you bee, falshood if you alwayes flee and loven well in feere. PETRUS Lord, whither arte thou in waye? JESUS Peter, thidder as I goe todaye come syckerlye thou ney maye this tyme in noe manere; but thou shalt thidder goe. PETRUS Whye shall yt not, lord, be soe? My lyffe I will put in woe and for thy sake be slayne. JESUS Peter, I saye thee syckerlye, or the cocke have crowen thrye thou shalt forsake my companye and take thy word agayne. Brethren, lett not your hartes be sore, but leeve in God evermore and in mee as you have before, and care not for this case. For in my Father house there is manye wonnynges of great blys, and thidder I will goe now, iwys, to purvaye you a place. And though I goe from you awaye to purvaye a place to your paye, I come agayne another daye and take you all with mee. THOMAS Lord, we wotte not, in good faye, what manere of gate thou wilt assaye. Tell us, that we knowe maye that gate and goe with thee. JESUS Thomas, I tell thee withowt stryfe, in me is waye, soothnes, and life, and to my Father no man ney wife may come withowt mee. And yf you knowe me verelye, my Father you might knowe in hye. From henceforth, I say you syckerlye, knowe him all shall yee. PHILLIPP Lord, lett us see thy Father anon and yt sufficeth us everychone. JESUS A longe tyme you have with me gonne, Phillipp; why sayest thou soe? Sickerlye, whoe seeth mee seeth my Father, I tell yt thee. Whye willest thou my Father to see while I with you goe? Phillipp, leeves thou not this: that my Father in mee ys, and I in him alsoe, iwys, and both we be one? The workes that I doe are his; for his helpe maye I not mys. Therfore, to wynne you heaven-blys, my deedes you leeve upon! Whatsoever ye aske my Father deare in my name in good manere, to fulfill yt I have power. All that ys to my paye, that my Father in majestie by mee glorified may bee; and eyther, as I saye to thee, for one have binne aye. Yf that you love mee hartfullye, keepe my biddinge truelye, and to my Father praye will I to send you the Holye Ghoste to abyde with you evermore— for the world knoweth not his lore, but you, that have knowen mee yore, in you he shall be most. Though I goe now to distresse, I will not leave you comfortles; but leeves this well and expresse, efte I will come agayne; and then your hartes on a rowe shall gladlye be, my blys to knowe, with joye noe man shall take you froo, would he never so fayne. Ryse up and goe heathen anon. To my prayer I must gone, but syt you styll everychwonne, my Father while I call. Wakes and have my benisonn for fallinge into temptation. The sprite aye to bale is bowne and the flesh readye to fall. Tunc it Jesus oratum, et discipuli pre dolore dormiunt. Father of heaven in majestie, glorifie, yf thy will bee, thy Sonne, that hee may glorifie thee, nowe or I heathen wend. In yearth thou hast given me postie, and I have donne with harte free the worke that thou charged mee and brought yt to an ende. Thy name have I made men to knowe and spared not thy will to showe to my disciples one a rowe that thou hast given mee. And nowe they knowe verelye that from the Father sent am I. Therfore, I pray thee especiallye, save them through thy mercye. Tunc venit ad discipulos et invenit eos dormientes, et dicit: What! Sleepe you, brethren all, here? Ryse up and make your prayer lest temptation have power to make you for to fall. The flesh is, as I sayd before, inclininge aye to synne sore, and ghooste occupyed evermore; therfore nowe wakes all! Tunc iterum ad orationem, et alta voce loquitur: My hart is in great mislikinge for death that is to me commynge. Father, if I dare aske this thinge, put this awaye froe mee. Eych thinge to thee possible is; neverthelesse, nowe in this at your will I am, iwys. As thou wilt, lett yt bee. Tunc redit ad discipulos iterum. You sleepen, brethren, yett, I see. Sleepes one nowe all yee. My tyme ys common taken to bee. From you I must awaye. He that hath betrayed mee, this night from him will I not flee. In sorye tyme borne was hee and soe he may well saye. Tunc Judas cum militum cohorte, laternis facibus et armis, venit illuc. JESUS You men I aske, whom seeke yee? MALCHUS Jesus of Nasareth, him seeke we. JESUS Here, all readye—I am hee. What have you for to saye? JUDAS A, sweete maister, kysse thou mee, for yt is longe syth I thee see, and togeather we will flee and steale from them awaye. JESUS What seeke you men with such a breath? PRIMUS JUDEUS Wee seeke Jesus of Nazareth. JESUS I saye yore, and yet I saye, I am hee, in good faye. Suffer these men to goe there waye and I am at your will. MALCHUS False theefe, thou shalt gone to bysshopp Cayphas, and that anon; or I shall breake thy bodye and bonne and thou be to late. PETRUS Theefe, and thou be so bould my maister soe for to hould, thou shalt be quytte an hundrethfould, and onward take thou that! Be thou so bould, as thrive I, to hould my maister here in hye, full deare thou shalt hit abye but thou thee heathen dight. Thy eare shall of, by Goddes grace, or thou passe from this place. Tunc extrahet gladium et abscindet auriculam Malchi. Goe playnt nowe to Cayphas and bydd him do the right. MALCHUS Owt! Alas, alas, alas! By cockes bones, my eare hee hase! Mee is betyde a hard case that ever I come here. JESUS Peeter, put up thy sword in hye. Whosoever with the sword smiteth gladlye with sword shall perish hastelye, I tell thee withowten were. Tunc Jesus tetigerit auriculam et sanabit. MALCHUS A, well is mee, well is mee! My eare is healed nowe, I see. So mercifull a man as ys hee knewe I never none. PRIMUS JUDEUS Yea, though hee have healed thee, shutt from us shall hee not bee, but to syr Cayphas, as mott I thee, with us shall hee goe. JESUS As to a theeffe you came here with sword and staves and armerye to take me in fowle manere and end your wicked will. In temple with you when I was aye, noe hand on mee would you laye, but nowe is common tyme and daye your talent to fulfill. PRIMUS JUDEUS Come, caytiffe, to Cayphas or thou shalt have a hard grace. Trott upon a prowder pase, thou vilde popelard. Though Belzebubb and Sathanas come to helpe thee in this case, both thy hand that thou hase shalbe bounden hard. Finis</field>
   </doc>
</add>